(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
for the first time from the new QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and here to cut the red ribbon
and officially open the new Fish podcasting headquarters
is the founder of QI himself, John Lloyd.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Andy.
My fact is that there was a job in medieval times
called the municipal swine herd
who was effectively a professional pig walker for city dwellers
who didn't want to walk their own pigs.
- Right.
(laughing)
- It's just a job that you used to be able to get.
Before we go any further, actually,
I should say this fact was sent in to us
at podcast@qi.com by a listener sent in by Andrew Salamone.
So thank you very much indeed for it, Andrew.
- Were they on leashes?
- No, I don't think they were.
- That's a more difficult job than I reckon
'cause you're corraling the pigs as well as walking them.
- It's difficult in that way,
but it's also very hard.
I imagine to keep a pig on a leash
if it doesn't want to be.
- Is it?
- Really?
The pigs are very strong.
- But they're also very intelligent and can be trained.
You can teach a pig to dance.
- No, you're right.
Well, yeah, I don't think they were.
This was in the middle ages.
- Sorry, John, can I just pick you up on,
you can teach a pig to dance?
- Yeah, well, they're very intelligent.
(laughing)
They're right at the top of the animal league,
smarter than dogs, sheep, and horses.
They can be house trained, taught to fetch, come to heal.
They can pull carts, they can sniff out landmines.
- But can I bring you back to the dancing point?
Pigs can dance.
- Apparently they can, yes.
- Were they sort of like vaudeville acts or?
- It's mainly flamenco dancing.
(laughing)
They'd click their little heels together like castanets.
- Brilliant.
- They like watching television.
They have their own favorite programs, pet pigs.
- Peppa Pig?
- I don't know if Peppa Pig can watch television.
- No, I was wondering if Peppa Pig
was one of their favorite TV shows.
- I'm sorry to be late to this,
but the Fox Trotter would be an example
of a dancer pig could do.
- And Southpawk would be a TV show they might like.
- There we go.
- Southpawk.
(laughing)
- Should we stragg us away from this one?
- Oh yeah, sorry, yeah, yeah.
Back into the middle late as we go, hooray.
So these are the first professional pig husbands,
I guess you would call them in Europe.
They were these village swine herds,
and it was in a time when everyone had their own pig.
A pig was an amazingly useful thing to have.
It was a waste disposal unit,
but it was a waste disposal unit made of pork.
What a delicious--
- Go into that a bit more?
- You feed it leftovers and scraps from the household,
and then when winter comes, you eat the pig.
- It's like if you can eat your wheely bin.
- Yeah, 'cause no, in the Flintstones,
that's what they, the trash is a dinosaur
that eats the trash sitting in a drawer.
So it's kind of like that.
- It's probably based on these academic studies
of medieval municipal swine herds, yeah.
And there was a pig daycare thing, though,
because you didn't want to look after your own pig all day,
being a busy middle-class peasant in the middle ages,
and you would have a village swine herd
who was rewarded with a sucking pig each year
and the entrails of any animal which had been slaughtered.
So--
- What did the sucking pig actually do,
or is that a vulgar question?
(laughing)
- You said they could be trained to do anything, John,
is that it?
(laughing)
- But they are party animals pigs.
Some pig farmers keep lights on in the sky at night.
When the farmers go home at the end of the day,
the pigs don't settle down,
they start eating, drinking, and having fun for small hours.
That's actually their favorite show this day at night.
(laughing)
Actually, I read one cool thing about lights in pigsties,
and that is to get rid of the smell in pigsties,
you can paint it with titanium oxide paint
and then fire UV light at the paint,
and that will somehow break down the chemicals,
which will stop it from smelling.
And it's even better if you put a disco ball
in the middle of the pigstie,
it will fire the UV light out in all different directions
and it will make it smell better more quickly.
- And you know why the disco ball's there
because of the dance?
- Yes, exactly.
(laughing)
- Medieval pigs don't look like our modern day pig,
and this is something that has led to a lot of annoyance
in the world of academia,
because a lot of medieval scholars
are constantly finding themselves,
I say constantly, it's one guy as far as I can find,
being pissed off by their representation
within video games these days.
So there's a lot of video games like Assassin's Creed,
Valhalla, there's Medieval Dynasty Foundation,
where they represent pigs as a modern day pig,
it's pink and it's hairless,
it looks nothing like the pig is today.
- Minecraft?
- Maybe in Minecraft.
- There are pigs in Minecraft?
- Minecraft, yeah.
(laughing)
And so actually of the time,
if we wanna picture an old pig,
it's a long legged, they're quite small, long snouts,
very lean figure, they had arch-crested backs,
and they had long curved tusks as well,
according to the academic.
- I suppose if you made them look like that
in the video game, people might not realise they were pigs.
- Yeah, and what you've described as a stalk, basically,
as far as I can tell.
(laughing)
- Wow, okay.
- But you mentioned Leeds,
did you know the thing about Gérard de Neval,
the 19th century French poet,
who had a pet lobster called Thibault,
which used to walk around Paris on a blue silk ribbon,
so he did have a lead for the lobster.
- He could walk on a lead.
- He was asked why he had a lobster as a pet,
and he said, "They are peaceful, serious creatures.
"They know the secrets of the sea, and they don't bark."
And it was a very--
- He know the secrets of the sea.
- It was a very sedate job, 'cause I checked this out.
In lab tests, the maximum recorded walking speed
of a lobster is 2.5 metres per minute,
or 144 metres an hour.
- That's a good easy job, a professional lobster walker.
- It feels like at some stage,
you would end up dragging a lobster more than walking it,
doesn't it?
- Maybe you got to get back for lobster dragging.
- I did the other day in a big railway station,
I saw someone who had a ferret on a lead.
That was nice. - Did you?
- Yeah, which you do see occasionally.
- Yeah. - You know,
'cause they don't need to be--
- So you pull it out of your trousers.
(all laughing)
- I got sent a picture from my friend Emi in Hong Kong
of someone walking a lizard on a lead.
- Really? - Like one of those big,
big lizards.
- What, like a commuter dragon?
- Yeah, exactly. - No.
- But not a commuter dragon.
No, no, no, but like sizeable.
- Did a real lizard or a shape-shifting lizard?
- It was, yeah, it was one of the members
of the Royal Family in Hong Kong.
- Monitor, I guess.
- Yeah, it could be.
Yeah.
- I went into my local,
sorry, no, just bragging about animals we've seen lately,
but I went into an aquarium shop the other day.
- Ah, yeah.
- I was trying to buy some--
- Fish.
- Sprintails, actually.
You know, sprintails, there's tiny insects.
- Yes. - Why do you buy those?
- I needed to fertilize some soil.
(all laughing)
I did a terrarium workshop and I made a terrarium.
Anyway, I went in there to get my sprintails,
which was very cheap,
three quid for a big box of sprintails.
Anyway, they had an axolotl in there.
- Oh, yeah. - I was staggered.
'Cause I thought, you know, they're very rare.
- Did you not buy it?
- No. - No.
- Really interesting. - I didn't know
where to put it.
And the guy who ran the aquarium shop was quite annoyed
'cause he said when he doesn't have an axolotl in,
people only ever say,
"Well, do you not have any axolotls?"
And then, when he does,
they just come in and look at the axolotl
and then don't buy it, you know.
They treat it like a zoo.
- That does feel like one person is going in there
every week as a joke and asking for axolotls.
(all laughing)
- Is an axolotl an amphibian?
- Yeah. - I think it is.
- Yeah, 'cause they're extinct in the wild, apparently.
Yes, they're only in two canals in Mexico City now.
Yeah, apart from zoos.
And the, because I ask amphibians
because another great medieval job was a frog stoner.
They used to hire people to throw pebbles into ponds,
shut the frogs up at night.
(all laughing)
- Partying as well.
- Yeah, the animal king was all parties.
But I did think it's a pretty boring job
for a pig walker in the middle ages,
a municipal swine herd.
And I thought we should come up with a better name.
So there's some great walking words.
Plutch, to flap the feet while walking like a seabird
from Shetland.
Prol, a short enjoyable walk that's from Kent.
Proper stroll, I should think it stands for.
Shove, to saunter with extreme laziness from East Anglia.
To spandle, to leave wet footprints on the floor.
Another Kentish stoner.
- So do you think swine spandler?
- I think it's exactly a hog-plutcher.
- Hog-plutcher. (all laughing)
- Now, what's this thing?
Like, so later on after the medieval pig thing,
urban pigs were a big deal.
Basically, in Manchester, everyone had their own pig.
And we know this partly 'cause of Friedrich Engels,
who was writing about the conditions
of the working class in England in the 1840s, 1845.
And he wrote that that was the case.
And another writer was describing North Kensington.
And in the mid-19th century, in North Kensington,
pigs outnumbered people three to one.
- Really?
- Quite a lot.
- There's more pigs in Spain now than humans.
- Really? - Yeah.
- Pigs in Spain.
In the 1820s, there were more pigs in Manhattan
than there are cars in New York today.
- Wow.
- Well, you know the movie, "The Wolf of Wall Street"?
- No, it was previously gonna be called
"The Three Little Pigs of Wall Street."
- It should have been called that as a prequel.
The prequel would have been that, exactly that,
because the wall of Wall Street initially was a wall, right?
This is when the Dutch were there.
- Oh, I see.
- And they built, yeah, they built this wall.
And this was during the 1600s, so 1653 to 1699.
As they were building the wall,
there was a picket fence that was there before.
- A picket fence.
- A picket fence, yeah.
And it kept getting knocked down by pigs.
So it was a huge problem.
And they brought in municipal swine herds
to try and curb it.
And that didn't happen.
So then they had to decree that you had to keep your pigs
at home until the construction of Wall Street was built.
- So the Dutch thing, New Amsterdam,
I happen to know that there's a Dutch word, Udvijn,
which means to take a bracing walk in the wind.
Isn't that a lovely thing to have a word for?
- Oh, that's good, yeah.
- And then the Dutch for pig is big.
- Is it really big?
- It's big, yeah.
- That's correct.
You're learning Dutch at the moment.
- I am, yes.
- What was the phrase you gave us just before the show started?
- (speaks in foreign language)
- Which translates as...
- How do we know if the animals in the zoo are happy?
- Great.
- They're philosophical people.
- Do you know truffle pigs?
You've heard of truffle pigs, right?
- Yeah, yeah.
- That hunt for truffles.
And in the Middle Ages,
they didn't, they did hunt for truffles,
but they ate them because nobody in the Middle Ages
ate truffles.
They thought that was weird.
- I agree.
- Foxes, badges, wolves, wild boar, pigs and rats ate truffles.
And they only came back into favor in the Renaissance.
So I got interested in truffles.
And Rossini, the composer,
called the truffle the Mozart of fungi,
which is rather nice, isn't it?
- Oh.
- And he claimed to have only cried three times
in his life, Rossini.
Once when his first opera was booed,
once when he had Paganini play the violin,
and once when he was picnic on a boat
and the truffle turkey fell overboard.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the comedian Bob Hope
was so reliant on his writers to come up with jokes for him,
he even had them provide bespoke one-liners
for his social life.
So we all know Bob Hope.
- A lot of people don't these days.
(laughing)
- Just in case, just in case.
- It fell on Stony Grandin.
Let's move on to the third fact.
(laughing)
- So Bob Hope.
- So you said comedian.
- Yeah.
- Bob Hope was possibly the biggest comedian in the world.
- He was huge.
He lived to 100 years old.
He hosted the Oscars 19 times.
He was a box office hit during the '40s.
Number one movie at one point in the '40s
was a Bob Hope movie.
He received its estimated 38,000 fan letters per week
during the 1940s.
This is how loved he was.
But he's the person who effectively created the idea
of the modern standup monologue
where he incorporated himself, the audience,
the situation around him, the topical news of the day.
And he used to hire so many writers.
He was the first person to acknowledge
he had writers as well, properly.
He would mention, hold the cue cards up higher
during his act, be quicker on that.
You wouldn't say that if my writers were here.
Those kind of lines.
And yeah, and so, so much was he reliant on it that,
as I say, even if he was going on like a golf game
and he knew that he had some powerful CEOs there
that he wanted to impress,
they would write these jokes for him
and he would memorize them and bust them out
as if they were ad libs.
- Great idea.
- Yeah.
- I'd love that.
- He'd gotten a lot of stick from other comedians.
The Lenny Bruce's and the growing world of comedians
who were auteur and wrote their own material
'cause they saw him as an actor as opposed to a comedian.
But I'm a big fan of the way that he led his life.
I think, and his comedy life particularly,
I think that he innovated so many things.
So if he was gonna play in a town,
he would send his writers ahead, days ahead,
and they would scope around the whole town.
They would look at the local shops.
They would meet the local people
and they would base the material they wrote for him on that.
- It would have been weird though,
if he's doing a joke about the local hardware shop.
- No, I think that's...
- Well, do you remember like when we went on tour,
we would do facts about the local town?
- Oh yeah, but that was good.
That was great.
That was, you know, that was a very different...
- John, did you ever meet Bob Hope?
- No, but I spoke to him.
- Really? - Yeah.
One Christmas Eve,
I used to produce a live radio two-show
called Late Night Extra when I was very, very young,
sort of 24 or something like that, 23 even.
And I was producing one on Christmas Eve
and I had the best address book in the world probably.
It was amazing.
Everybody's singing.
For some reason, I had Bob Hope's phone number,
so I phoned him up in California on Christmas Eve
and said, "Hey, Bob, how's it going?"
He goes, "Who is this? Who is this?"
I said, "It's the BBC in London, Mr. Hope."
He goes, "Oh, hi there. Hi, guy, how are you?"
He was great.
- Have you still got the number?
Let's call it now.
(laughing)
- He picks up.
- But he was interesting that his attitude to write,
he paid them very well.
He didn't acknowledge them,
but he didn't think the writing was the big deal.
He said creating the character was the thing
and the lines were just something that the character said.
- Yeah, weirdly, a lot of people in recent biographies
say that he was terrible at paying his writers.
That was sort of an idea that he was really good.
Jack Benny would pay two writers the same amount.
Jack Benny being another giant comedian of the day,
the same amount that Bob would pay 20 writers.
What he'd do is he'd find the young writers.
- Didn't you say that Jack Benny hated him
'cause he had writers?
- Not Jack Benny, no.
- Oh, I thought you said people like Jack Benny.
- Lenny Bruce.
Jack Benny and Lenny Bruce are both double first-namers.
Yeah, like Craig David or David Cameron.
Anyway.
- Do you know who Bob Hope's most famous writer
was the least the one I'd heard of?
- No.
- Larry Gelbart.
- Oh yeah, who's that?
- When he was very young.
He was the guy who wrote "Mash."
- Oh wow, okay.
- And Bob Hope, one of the things he used to do was tour.
He was basically, not only as you say it, Dan,
but he sort of invent stand-up comedy,
but the touring American forces in the '40s and '50s
was also a thing that was really,
nobody had ever thought of doing that before.
And he did a lot and Larry Gelbart worked for him
as a very young man and he was inspired by a tour
of the Far East to write "Mash."
- Yeah, Bob Hope famously used to do a Christmas show
that he would do from the front lines
of wherever a war might be going and after a war
while people were still stationed out there.
So most comedians and acts would go out
while it was wartime and he kind of continued on.
So he died age 100.
He did 48 Christmases out on the road.
So 48 of his Christmases were spent
in a different country performing to troops.
- And one of them speaking to John Lloyd.
- And one of them speaking to Lloyd.
- Yeah, in a way, like being in a war zone, you know.
- But you're, sorry.
- "Hope You Christmas" should have been the name of the show.
- "Hope You Christmas" doesn't get ever was.
- God, he had 48 goes to get that and you didn't.
- Never got that.
- Never got that, exactly.
- Hope is a first name, by the way.
- Is it?
- Yeah, it's a woman's name.
- Bob Hope joins the ranks of...
(laughing)
- But I was reading that about the wartime thing.
- Sorry, sorry, sorry.
- Jerry Lewis, two first names.
- Jerry Lewis, yeah.
- Dean Marden, two first names.
- Yeah.
- Did they all have first names?
- That's extraordinary.
- Frank Sinatra, no.
- But he's not a comedian.
- Great point, all right, on we go.
- The thing about his war shows.
- Andy Murray.
- Oh, that's good.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So it's not always comedians.
- John Lloyd.
(laughing)
- Yeah, fair enough, John Lloyd, yeah.
- I think John Lloyd and Andy Murray
are in those weird category of like Lloyd and Murray
are kind of first names and kind of surname.
You know, they can be both.
- Yeah.
- It's not the pure simplicity of it, Greg David.
- Agreed.
- Okay.
Did you have something come on?
- I did, I did.
- Well, no, I was just gonna say
what was particularly touching about the war shows
is that for a lot of parents, brothers and sisters,
whatever, friends at home,
this was the only time that they were able to see
possibly one of their family members
who was off at war on camera during Christmas time.
So a lot of the 38,000 letters that came to Bob Hope
was from people saying I got to see my boy
sitting there in the crowd laughing at your jokes
and he didn't make it.
He lost his life to the war.
Thank you for giving me that moment
where I could connect with him.
So they were really important shows
to America at the time.
- His last military gig was in 1990
when he went to the Gulf at the age of--
- '87.
- '87, yeah.
And lots of the troops in the crowd for his final gig,
they had fathers who had seen him in Vietnam
and some of them had grandfathers who had seen Bob Hope
in the second world war performing.
It's mad, the idea that you go to a gig
and your grandfather saw the same comedian.
- Yeah, I mean, lucky that you managed to get two generations
that they didn't die in the past.
- Yeah, that's true, yeah, that's true, yeah.
While reading about this,
I found my favorite new human.
Yeah, just like, it's an exciting character.
So this is to do with the writers and so on.
It's a guy called Barney McNulty.
Bob Hope used to bring him everywhere with him.
What do you think he did?
He was part of that team.
- So not a writer?
- Was he a boxer?
'Cause Bob Hope was a boxer before he was a comedian.
- He was, but no, he wasn't a boxer.
- Did he point out whenever he met anyone
who had two first names?
(laughing)
- No, this is--
- I could do with one of those guys, James.
- Yeah.
- I'd love that, yeah, yeah.
- I feel like you could be one of those guys, Andy.
- Oh, I dream, you know.
(laughing)
- What's, somewhat like a, just a personal, you know,
assistant, like a backburn or a--
- So what Barney McNulty was, was the Q-Card guy.
And everything was written on Q-Cards.
And Barney McNulty is acknowledged
with having invented Q-Cards, basically.
No one ever delivered monologues on TV before with Q-Cards.
And Barney McNulty was the guy to do this.
He said doing it was like, it was like a,
like handling snakes.
You had to work with the rhythm of the comedian.
You had to have the font big enough
and you're writing and so on.
- Like a snake.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
'Cause he said the comedians are wriggling around.
They're, they're improvising, they're changing.
You don't know where they're gonna go.
It's kind of--
- Like an auto-Q person.
- Yeah, like a modern day auto-Q person.
- So sometimes the auto-Q can be done too fast
or too slow and the presenter gets in a tangle
and then--
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, auto-Qs are boring then.
It should be called a McNulty, shouldn't it?
- Yes.
- The McNulty, yeah.
So McNulty was so important to him.
Steve Allen, who's another comedian of the time,
said that he was once at a barbecue.
- Steve Allen.
- Yep, Steve Allen.
- Oh, yeah!
(laughing)
- Oh, this is, you've uncovered a scene.
Once, the problem is once you start seeing them,
you can't stop.
- Yeah.
I've been this way for years.
(laughing)
So he was at a party at Barbecue with Bob Hope
and Bob came out and suddenly just did an improvised speech
to all the people, it's nighttime.
He's, "Yeah, thank you for coming."
And he's doing all these jokes.
And Steve said, he's hearing these jokes
and he's thinking, "This is a pretty worked out monologue,
but it's pretty topical."
Turns around, he says, "He notices sitting in the bushes
with a flashlight and some cue cards,
is McNulty hiding away, giving him the cue cards to do it."
- So I haven't really said very much in this part
because I don't really know anything about comedy,
but I do know a lot about golf.
(laughing)
And Bob Hope used to love golf.
And that's really kind of all I knew about him
is that he was a golfer.
I read that, you know, Alan Shepard, the astronaut,
yeah, he hit a golf ball on the moon.
And according to Bob Hope, it was his idea.
- No.
- Yeah, he said that he was once speaking to Alan Shepard
and he used to kind of always carry his golf clubs around him,
kind of just to--
- That was his thing, he would--
- Yeah, and he reckoned that Alan Shepard
got the inspiration by watching him
swing in his golf club.
He was on the Mike Douglas show
when Tiger Woods first appeared on television
when he was two years old.
So Tiger Woods was a little dot
and he was kind of hitting golf balls
and everyone was like, look how amazing
this little kid is at playing golf.
And Bob Hope was on the show when that happened.
So he's there for the start of Tiger Woods.
And apparently on his first date, he was so nervous,
he would just sit and draw golf holes on the tablecloth.
And he did it so much that they made him pay for the tablecloth
because he'd draw all these golf holes on it.
- Oh, that's so great.
- I certainly claim they were golf holes later on.
(all laughing)
- These, oh, they're--
- And Alan Shepard with, of course,
a job in the Middle Ages.
(all laughing)
- I thought that was your job on QI, John.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the unarmed stick insect
has an infinite number of arms.
(all laughing)
- Um, okay.
- So what?
- I'm not saying anything else, that's it.
- Why is it, that's it?
Does it play golf?
(all laughing)
Infinite is a big word.
- Yeah, that's a big word, I was gonna say that.
- It's a long word, yeah.
- It's a full eight letters.
- Don't you mean that?
(all laughing)
- It's, no, the thing is, I would say,
sticking sets can regrow their limbs.
- Yeah, right? - Theoretically.
- Theoretically.
- Theoretically, possibly forever.
You know, if you keep chopping them off,
they'll keep growing them.
- Yeah, the main body doesn't live forever,
does it, or does it?
- No, no, no.
I think probably we would reach a time limit.
The other thing--
- Like about a week?
- Well, 'cause they would die,
but the other problem is they can only do it
when they're young.
- Okay.
- But they could keep doing it and doing it and doing it
if you kept chopping off all the limbs.
- Yeah, hell of a shock to your juvenile stick insect.
The first time it chops an arm off
and it doesn't grow back, it thinks, oh no,
now I'm officially no longer a juvenile.
- Yeah, it must be.
- 'Cause you must get used to operating
with complete impunity.
- It's a real coming of age moment, isn't it?
- Yes, yeah.
- So they can keep regrowing their arms.
Another question is, do they have arms or are they legs?
(all laughing)
- It's called unarmed.
Is there a reason why it's called unarmed?
- Yeah, because it doesn't have defenses.
- Yes, it's armed as in weapons.
- Yeah, to be honest, it's just a silly thing
'cause I noticed it was called unarmed
and I remembered they could keep regrowing their arms.
- Yeah, that's so great.
- But I just thought let's talk about stick insects
'cause stick insects are awesome.
These ones, these unarmed stick insects
are the most common stick insects found in Britain.
- Are they?
- Oh, yes they are.
Because we have no native stick insects in this country,
but one of them accidentally got brought in some timber
from New Zealand in the 20s.
- Right.
- And they reproduce pathogenically
so they don't need more than one of them
to create more and more and more of them.
- It's really pleasing that it came over in some timber
disguised as a smaller stick in a load of larger sticks.
That's brilliant.
- There was probably a guy at the park
just counting all of these sticks
and go, we've got one too many.
(all laughing)
So these were discovered in New Zealand in 1955
by a man who also, like this misnamed animal,
is called John Salmon, not a fish.
- That's amazing.
- But he is responsible for discovering,
so there's a Wikipedia list of stick insects of New Zealand
of which there are 23.
John Salmon discovered nine of the stick insects of New Zealand.
- Oh yeah.
- You do find the same people come up again and again
when you look at all the different species
of stick insects, tends to be the same.
- It's almost if no one else is looking for stick insects,
right?
Or maybe they're specialized
'cause they're quite hard to see.
- They're so hard.
So I was reading about leaf insects,
which are similar, you know, they look,
and they are unbelievably realistic leaf insects.
As in they attach to a tree where they look exactly
like that leaf, and they have little bit and out edges.
So it looks like an insect.
- So amazing.
- But lots of experts on leaf and stick insects
have never seen them in the wild.
It's quite tragic really.
So there's a guy called Royce Cumming,
who's a world expert on leaf insects.
He's never seen one in the wild.
- That's amazing.
- Because what, you know, it's really hard for me.
- 'Cause you can't just check every leaf.
- Exactly, that's the problem.
That's exactly it.
- Yeah, it's a nightmare.
If you wanna get a new cell.
- Stupid, they should have gone for like.
- Yeah, elephants.
- Elephants, absolutely.
- Stick insects feature in Maori myth.
- Yes, right.
- Quite a few times.
And just something I just happened to know
about Maori, the language,
which is the Maori for nuclear warfare,
is umu pongi pongi.
- Right.
- You didn't think they would have a word for it,
but they do.
- Your duolingo is very bold.
You're like a far ranger.
- This is a dictionary.
This is not duolingo.
- Other language apps are available.
Memorise, et cetera.
- When stick insects feel under threat.
- Oh yeah.
- They will play dead.
Or be more like a stick than usual, basically.
And I found an insect owning website
which had a problem page.
And the problem was,
is my stick insect playing dead or has it died?
- Or is it in fact a twig?
- We used to have stick insects when I was a kid.
Pet and stick insects.
Yeah, yeah.
And it is, I mean, they did die,
I'm sorry to say, quite regularly.
They didn't live very long.
I hope that wasn't due to our bad husbandry, but.
- Or did they die very frequently?
- Maybe they were just trying to get themselves thrown out.
- We usually check, I don't know what your FAQs will say,
but for us it was usually when there weren't many poos
for a few days, that was a problem.
- What's a poo look like from a stick insect?
- It's just like a black dot.
- Right, nice.
- Yeah.
- Well, this is basically, if they're threatened,
they fold their legs up and they paralyze themselves
and they often fall off the branch to the foliage.
But that happens if they get surprised,
if they face any surprise until they're played dead.
So you either wait to see if the color has changed,
'cause that is a sign that they can't do that by themselves.
- Can the leaf insects change color in the autumn?
- I don't think so.
- Okay.
- And the other thing you can do,
there's just a bit of advice,
is to stimulate the insect's mouth palps,
which are these small organs near the mouth,
which are incredibly sensitive.
And if you stimulate those,
it will make a sudden movement, 'cause it hates that.
And if not, it has died.
I'm slightly moved by all these pets and things dying
because my dad was in the Navy, we never had pets.
So when the kids were small,
we won a goldfish at a fair in Chipping Norton,
who was called Chippy, the fish.
I love this little fish
and it got something wrong with it, swim bladder.
And I was really heartbroken.
I was very sort of, you know, anxious about it.
And so I used to take it to the local vet
in a bucket in Hammersmith.
And so I was sitting there in a bucket,
this little goldfish in a tiny little thing, fair goldfish.
- Was it on a lead?
No.
(all laughing)
- And all these people would be there with salukis
and parakeets and horses and things like that.
And the vet's assistant would come out and say,
"Mrs. Campbell Rouse and Montmorency, the third?"
(all laughing)
And so he would get up with an antelope or something.
They came to me and she'd go, "Mr. Lloyd and fish?"
(all laughing)
And after about four visits,
and what he used to do the vet was inject this goldfish
with something wrong with the swim bladder,
with the tiniest little hypotermics
that you've ever seen, about two inches long.
And after the fourth time he said,
"Mr. Lloyd, I'm afraid there's nothing more I can do for fish.
He's going to take his chances."
- Oh, 'cause that is a problem with goldfish, isn't it?
They get these swim bladder problems
and they'll kind of float to the surface
and sometimes they go upside down.
And people think that they're dead,
but actually they're not dead.
They can be, they can have their swim bladder pricked
and they'll come back. - Oh, you're joking.
- And so people flush the fish down the toilet,
but they're not actually dead.
They probably don't flush very well either
'cause they are quite buoyant that stage.
- Oh, no. - Yeah.
- That's terrible. - It's public service.
- Yeah.
- I was just thinking Mr. Lloyd and fish
is basically this episode, isn't it?
(all laughing)
- Very good.
Did you know that some children,
human children can regenerate fingertips.
Did you, I was astounded when I first--
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, I had heard that.
- And many doctors don't know that
so that they just grow back their fingertips
if you cut them off. - Yeah.
Up to a certain, it's kind of much like the stick insect.
You don't wanna, there's a cut off part, isn't it?
- And it's under a certain amount of the finger, I think.
It's not at the base, but it's the top joint.
- Yeah. - Or the fingernail.
If there's only a tiny bit of the fingernail left,
the whole rest of it can grow back.
- Well, so human children have infinite fingers.
- Yes.
- And it's another, don't try this at home, isn't it?
(all laughing)
- Speaking of children,
have you guys heard of John George Children?
(all laughing)
- No.
- He was a famous entomologist of the early 19th century.
And there's a stick insect called children's stick insect,
which is named after him.
- No. - Yeah.
He was a, as well as an entomologist,
he was a biologist.
And one amazing thing he did, in 1815,
he traveled to the battlefield of Waterloo
just after the battle.
And he purchased a tree
under which the Duke of Wellington had made his headquarters.
And so he, basically what had happened was,
the battle had happened and everyone had gone away
and loads of souvenir hunters were going in
and sort of chopping bits off this tree.
But he actually went and bought the entire tree
and had it made into furniture by Chippendale,
Thomas Chippendale.
- Wow. - Wow.
- Isn't that amazing?
- Was it called a Waterloo tree?
Was that, what is that thing?
- It was called the Elm, Waterloo Elm.
- Waterloo Elm. - Yeah.
- That is, wow.
- And I thought I'd see if John George Children
had any children and he did.
He had a daughter called Anna Atkins.
And she was the first person, we think, possibly,
to publish a book illustrated with photographic images.
She was a friend of Fox Talbot,
who made one of the first cameras.
And she made a book in 1843, which had photos in it.
Can you guess what the book was about?
First ever book with photos in it.
- Insects, the Battle of Waterloo.
- It's gonna be third of something.
- Something slow-moving, tortoises, twigs.
- Twigs.
- Children, children.
- Children, no, it was something very slow-moving.
- Oh, tortoises, tortoises.
- Rivers.
- It was very leisurely rivers.
- Meandering river.
- Yeah, something slow-moving, slugs.
- Smaller.
- The big book of slug photos.
Smaller than the slugs, lobsters.
No, no, that's not small.
- No, they're bigger than the slugs.
- Smaller than the slugs.
- Yeah, the rapids.
- The snail, is that smaller?
- That's about the same size.
- Oh, come on.
- I mean, much smaller than a slug.
- Oh, worms, tiny worms.
- Smaller.
- Smaller than the worms.
Parasitic wasps, they're tiny, tiny, tiny.
- I think a bit bigger than that.
I'll tell you.
- Well, there's water bears.
- Tartigrades.
- The big book of Tartigrade photos.
That was the first ever.
- Yeah, was of a Tartigrade.
No, it was of algae.
Her book was called Photographs of British Algae,
Cyanotype Impressions.
And it came out in October, 1843.
And that was the first ever book
illustrated with photographic images.
- It's very nice.
- I'm still recovering.
- Me too, I was about to say--
- It's still recovering from that thrilling--
- I was about to say, you look great.
- How these quizzes really get you
feeling like you're doing exercise.
- They pump me up.
These things are always so,
when you do these dives into things,
like regeneration, for example,
it's so miraculous, isn't it?
And all the creatures that can
axolotls and salamanders and sharks
regenerate teeth all the time.
And cockroaches can grow new legs.
Did you know that?
- No.
- And cockroaches have got a bigger genome than people.
- Okay.
- And they taste inside,
the innards of a cockroach.
Tastes like blue cheese.
- Really?
- Amazing, yeah.
And axolotls, they've got 30 billion base pairs
in their genome.
That's 10 times as much as we have.
- Wow.
- Do you think that guy who was selling axolotls
in your shop only had one of them?
And he kept selling it, but keeping a leg,
so that it would regenerate to a new one.
- What a brilliant business model.
- That's how I'm thinking.
- They're also, the axolotl gets its name
from the name of Quetzalcoatl's dog.
- Does it?
- Yeah, Quetzalcoatl had a dog called axolotl.
- Did he think when he went to the vet,
it was Quetzalcoatl and axolotl?
- Unarmed stick insects,
obviously a badly named insect.
- Oh, yeah.
- And I just want to mention one I found the other day,
which is the so-called whispering bat.
The so-called whispering bat's call
is as loud as a chainsaw or a leaf blower.
- Wow.
(all laughing)
- But the reason it's called the whispering bat
is because it's too high-pitched for us to hear.
Oh, thank God.
Other bats find it deafening.
- Yeah, right.
- That's funny.
- There's so many classic animals
that are completely misnamed.
So, a few that I found electric eel.
- Yes.
- Not an eel.
- No.
- It's a knife fish.
The horny toad.
- Yep, lizard.
- It's a lizard.
- Doesn't have much sex.
- Very sad.
- King Cobra's.
- Not.
- Not Royals.
(all laughing)
- Not Cobra's.
- No, really?
- Oh, Cobra's.
- Wow, skipjack tuner, not a tuner.
- Really?
- Is it really?
- That's the one that's always on all the tins, isn't it?
It's not tuner.
It's a completely different genus.
- Really?
Huh.
- Mountain goat?
Not a mountain.
No, not a goat.
- Really?
- What?
- No.
- The list goes on.
- Yeah, it does, actually.
Mantis shrimp, neither a shrimp nor a mantis.
American buffalo's not a buffalo but a bison.
Do you know the difference between a buffalo and a bison?
- No, I don't, Mr. Hope.
(all laughing)
- You can't wash your hands on a buffalo.
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is loedy.
So, I still have to decide which fact to give to you,
and I just want to give you some
that I didn't choose in the end.
(all laughing)
- That was a first.
- 'Cause I don't want to waste them.
To keep warm in the 16th and 17th centuries,
boys at British public schools burned the furniture.
Horrible, a bit like my school.
John Denver's wife, Annie,
claimed to have fallen in love with him
despite his songs, not because of them.
That's very sad.
And Toad Suck, Arkansas, recently won a survey
to find America's most unfortunate place name,
beating Belchartown, Massachusetts,
Climax, Georgia, Hooker, Oklahoma,
and Rochetown, Illinois.
- Well, I'm glad that you didn't do that low-brow one, John.
(all laughing)
What is your actual fact this week?
- My fact is, 45% of Britons do not know
where their rectum is.
(all laughing)
Now, this was according to a poll
of 2,000 British adults.
Commissioned by Powell Mell Medical Private Health Care
in January, 2023.
Only 55% of men and women in Britain
can confidently state where their rectum is.
And only 50% know where their reproductive organs are.
- No. - That is impossible.
Now, I can sort of understand why this might be
because they don't know what the words mean,
rectum and reproductive organs.
But according to the survey also,
an astonishing 37% of Brits
cannot say where either their heart or their brain is.
(all laughing)
- Well, my brain isn't my reproductive system.
- 'Cause there's that saying, isn't there?
He couldn't find his ass with both hands, yes.
And what we're saying is that 45% of British people
fall into that. - I don't think we're saying that
because to find your rectum with your hands
is quite an invasive thing.
(all laughing)
- Well, I did look it up because I thought,
okay, well, that's how ridiculous that is.
But I didn't know until yesterday
which part of the rectum is,
but you know, you've all looked that up.
So it's not actually what you think.
It's not the anus. - Not the heart.
- It's in, there's the anal canal with the anus on one end
and then the other end is the rectum,
which is basically the poo park
where the stuff that comes down the colon
is being digested all the way
and then it goes into the rectum,
which is exactly, it's the storage thing.
- Right. - Until--
- Is that a medical term, the poo park?
(all laughing)
- Yeah, same with vagina, I think, as well.
Like people think it's the opening,
but it's the tube. - Yes.
- So that's interesting.
I thought the rectum was connected
from sort of the bottom of the intestine
right to the opening. - No.
- I thought that whole thing--
- Okay, we've got this, we've covered them.
- Count me as one of the 55.
- The interesting thing about this survey was
it wasn't testing, can you find this?
It was saying, are you confident
that you could locate where organ X is?
- That's interesting.
So an 8% of people said they could confidently
identify none of them.
- None of them?
- They just said no, I couldn't identify any.
- But surely the brain, everybody must know.
- You would think so, yeah.
- That's just people with no confidence.
- Exactly. - Yeah, it's a confidence thing.
- Although we have said before
that there is this thing in,
is it called Lizardman's Constant or something like that,
where in any survey, you will get a percent
who will just give a ridiculous answer.
- I did wonder whether people,
because it was an online survey,
it wasn't a person asking my eye to eye.
So you wonder, people had a bit too much to drink,
they think, oh, I'll just put.
- Yeah.
- But there was another thing at the other end
of the spectrum on this survey,
'cause you know, people not identifying
where their brain is sounds mad.
I also would like to call a slight doubt
over the 24% of people, quite high,
who claimed they could confidently identify
where their pancreas was.
- Oh no. - And I think, come on.
- Like, I know it's in the middle section, but.
- Yeah, yeah, but where?
- Well, like the spleen, that was the one,
20% claimed to know where their spleen was.
I wouldn't have any idea, would give me a break.
- Yeah, 20% are not spleen doctors.
What's the term, I don't know.
- Splenologists?
- What's a speleologist?
- That's a screwdriver.
- Oh no, that's been a terrible mistake.
- Don't worry, he's gonna carry out the operation anyway.
He says it'll be just like a cave, probably.
- He's never been in an anal canal before.
- I tend to do a lot of these things now
when I'm trying to get access to a news article online.
- They often, a lot of websites will have like,
just fill this quick survey in quickly and.
- See the way your rectum is.
- Yeah.
- What kind of websites are you trying to get onto then?
- Please turn on your webcam.
Show us your rectum.
- I find it interesting that don't knows
in surveys as well.
And so YouGov always include their don't knows.
And there was an article about this in Wired
a few years ago by a writer called Amit Katwala.
And it's a great point 'cause YouGov
did a survey about surfing, right?
Have you ever been surfing or not?
In which 3% of people said, "I don't know."
And it's a big thing to not know if you've tried surfing.
2% don't know if they've lived in London.
(laughing)
- They could be on the outskirts.
- Possible, yeah, I guess, yeah.
- All born in London but left straight away.
Oh, I don't know if we've lived there for a couple of months.
- Okay, here's one from 2023.
Do you and your romantic partner each have your own side
of the bed that you sleep on, okay?
And if you don't currently have a partner,
please think about the last partner you have.
77% we each have our own side.
4% chaotic, we sleep on whichever side, absolutely insane.
But 6% don't know.
- Yeah.
- How do you not know?
- I would say it would be different depending
on which bed you're sleeping in.
Like in our home bed, we sleep on the same size.
But if you go to a hotel.
- Then it's anything goes.
Completely. - Exactly.
Well, it's not, it's whatever my wife wants to do.
(laughing)
- In 2017, a survey found that half of British gardeners
cannot name a single shrub.
And the next year in 2018, a poll found that 80% of Britons
couldn't pick out their own neighbors in a police lineup.
I thought that was quite strong.
- That's interesting.
- And how did they test that?
Did they do some lineups?
I'd like to know that, yes.
- That'd be great.
- It wasn't a Daily Mail, though, so maybe it's...
- Can you name a shrub?
'Cause I think shrub,
is that like a specific type of plant is a shrub?
- I agree, I mean, I garden, and you know.
- I have something that looks like a shrub,
which is Nazalia, is that a shrub?
- I don't know.
- Is it a little Leylandi bush, a shrub?
- A bush is a part of the body, isn't it?
I think that...
(laughing)
- Most people don't know why that is.
- I don't know where their bush is.
(laughing)
- Well, let's think of a shrub, it must be a shrub.
Is it a laurel, is that a tree?
- I think that's a shrub, is it?
- I think it's a size thing, isn't it?
Over a certain size, a shrub becomes a tree.
- I think we've shown that this is a very difficult thing
to know.
(laughing)
- We always jump when you're on the show,
we get into the deep questions.
(laughing)
- Can I do one more survey?
- Just this is a silly survey,
it's not really that much on topic,
but there was a poll quite recently
about what Britons aged 18 to 29,
so this is young people according to the survey.
What is the least cool hand gesture a person can make?
- Oh, that's great! - Just that it's a good quiz.
- Yeah, okay, cool.
- Okay, can I have a punt?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think the peace sign is not cool.
- Oh, do you know, I do that all the time.
- I do it all the time, but I just don't,
I don't think it's cool.
- Oh, okay.
- Possibly the horns, the rock horns.
- Oh, that's like a cuckold in Southern Europe.
- Oh, yeah.
(laughing)
- No, it's not that.
- Careful at Southern European Metallica gigs,
which I know you love to go to, Dan.
(laughing)
- The thumbs up.
- Thumbs up, that was in the poll.
It wasn't the worst,
but a lot of people thought it was quite cringe.
- A-okay.
- That was cringe, but not the worst.
- The phone, call me.
- In fact, the double A-okay
is one of the most cringe-worthy signs.
- Oh, air quotes!
Are they the--
- Yeah, that's pretty good.
- The most now.
- I actually think if anyone had thought of that,
they would have gone for it.
Hey, John, do you want to have a guess or?
- Wankings.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Sorry, Philippa Perry.
She basically answered the word "wank"
for every question we asked her as she came on the show.
(laughing)
It is, and this is 38% of people said this.
It's playing an air guitar.
- Oh!
- Like a Wild Stallions' Bill and Ted thing.
- That is pretty embarrassing.
- Oh, come on, it's cool.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- How old are you, Dad?
(laughing)
- The right age, to know that's cool.
Rectum?
- Okay, let's talk rectums.
The US Consumer Product Safety Commission every year
do a list of things that have been found
in people's orifices.
- Really?
- Yeah, the 2022 list include a monopoly piece,
a reusable ice pack, a fishing pole.
- No.
(laughing)
- It can't have been the entire pole.
- Well, they're collapsible, aren't they?
- They collapse, yeah.
- Oh, do they?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, okay, well, it could have been that.
And in other orifices, a golf ball in the vagina,
an expensive coin from a coin collection
in someone's throat and a USB card in someone's penis.
- Oh, a USB?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It's brilliant.
- You've got to make sure you put it in the right way round.
- Yeah, exactly.
Wow, that's brilliant.
Yeah, there was a guy also a 68-year-old man
with hemorrhoids in Hubei province in China
who had to have a 10-inch chopstick pulled out of his anus,
which he put up there.
He said, "Out of curiosity."
(laughing)
- Fair play, yeah.
- I haven't listened to the Museum of Curiosity this series.
John, is there?
(laughing)
- I'd like to donate this chopstick.
- And just while I was talking about emergency visits
in 2022, I found a list of quite a few here or some.
This is in the U.S.
"Pain after rubbing penis too hard with a loofah."
"Playing with pocket knife, accidentally stabbed penis.
"Closed penis in fridge door."
(laughing)
"And watched football, got excited when team scored
"and accidentally punched self in penis."
- Oh.
(laughing)
- Here are all ER visits in the U.S. last year.
- That's amazing.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland, James.
- @JamesHarkin.
- Andy.
- @AndrewHunterEb.
- And John.
- Ooh, @JohnLloydQI at Instagram.
- Oh, yeah, of course.
- I don't know, I didn't have a special account.
- Yeah, yeah, or @Quickipedia, I guess,
for like the total hub.
But yeah, find @Loydie on Instagram.
- But we do Instagrams.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, we've done that before.
- That's a good point.
Well, I'm on @Sriberland.
- I'm on no such thing as James Harkin.
- Mine is private, you'll never find it.
(laughing)
- And mine is @JohnLloydQI.
- All right, and we don't have a fish Instagram,
but we do have a fish Twitter account,
which is @NoSuchThing.
Or you can go to our website,
which is NoSuchThingasafish.com.
Do check it out, all the previous episodes are up there.
And that's it for now.
We'll be back again next week with another episode.
Thank you, John, for officially opening
the new QI offices and podcasting headquarters.
- That's an honor, Daniel.
- And yeah, we'll be back again next week
with another episode.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)