(man singing in foreign language)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing as a Fish"
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin, and Anna Chazinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that on their birthday,
every beef eater at the Tower of London
gets a gift of a free bottle of beef eater gin.
- On their birthday singular, so do they all do they all?
- They only hire people born on the 25th of September.
- They're like race horses.
They all get their new age on the 1st of January.
No, it's every beef eater on that particular person's birthday.
They get one bottle of gin.
And the beef eater gin brand
is nothing to do with the beef eaters.
But I went to the Tower of London this week,
and I spoke to my friend Andy the beef eater.
And he said that basically the beef eater gin brand
they've got so much out of the beef eaters over the years,
it's the least they can do to get them
a bottle of gin every year.
- Sorry, sweet.
So did you go to the beef eater pub?
- I went to the, it's called the Keys,
and it's the pub inside the Tower of London.
Yes, it had got there.
- That's very cool.
- That's cool.
Yeah, I was reading about it.
- A lot of pubs in the Tower of London.
This is the last remaining one.
- There's just one left, which means if you fall out
with any other beef eaters, if you have beef with them,
you have to go to the same pub all the time.
- That's terrible.
- But there's a sick calm.
- Sure, I would watch it.
In fact, there's a soap opera set in the Tower of London pub.
- You're right, you're right.
- Because they get up to quite bad behavior sometimes,
and they have done traditionally.
So I always thought of beef eaters as these sort of like,
eminent bastions of British stateliness,
in other words, like that.
- But actually, they were historically
used to kind of be drunkards, I think,
in the 18th century.
They were known for creating havoc
and for illegally subletting their rooms out to other people.
They would just randomly sell on the post of beef eater
to make a bit of extra cash whenever they wanted.
Yeah, they were known as scoundrels.
- You could only do that once.
Like once you sold it, it would belong to the other person
and then they might sell it on afterwards.
- Yeah, unless you stole it back from them in the night.
- Yeah, I'm not sure exactly how it worked.
I think you basically got money off them
and then they had the ceremony.
And the ceremony to become a beef eater,
you get a little kind of cup, a little pewter cup,
and you drink some part and you do a toast,
and then you're a beef eater, basically.
- Yeah.
Imagine if we could just sell our jobs to other people.
You can if you want.
- I mean, well, I'm in talks with a few guys in my case.
Alex Bell is pretty interesting.
- In the toast, it's a reference to that, isn't it?
'Cause they do the toast with a poor,
and then I think the thing they say
when they're toasting a new beef eater is,
is it may you never die a yeoman order?
So they're officially called yeoman orders.
And that's because the idea was,
if you made the mistake of dying in an office,
then you've been an idiot
'cause you hadn't sold it on in time
and made that extra cash.
- Yes, exactly.
It's like dying after, or not selling a house
in the years before you die.
And to go just on a rampage with the money.
- Is that what you're gonna do?
Considering you do have a son.
- Yeah, good point.
and they were really unpopular in loads of ways.
So as well as selling their jobs,
a writer historically said,
they have gradually assumed to themselves
the more lucrative occupation of stopping everybody
who wishes to visit these objects
of our national pride and glory
and forcing themselves upon them as their guides.
So the guards would just say,
hey, do you wanna guide a tour and pest you
until you gave in against the money?
- That's right, yeah.
- So Andy the beef eater gave us a guided tour this week.
And I gotta say, if you do go to the Tower of London,
do get a tour from their beef eater's,
'cause they are amazing.
And they know all sorts of stuff.
But you were duped into paying for a meal on your shirt.
It's a very easy job to eat.
(laughing)
- I read this thing about the beef eater's that.
So I think London, anyone coming here,
there's a famous fact about the cabbies,
the bike cab drivers having the knowledge.
It's one of those things.
They have to memorize every single road in London.
And that's a test they take.
There's a similar thing that happens with the beef eater's.
They have to memorize what's known as the story.
And it's 900 years of the Tower of London's history.
They need to know it word by word
within six months of passing their probation
after being sworn in.
- Yeah, but you now get these Uber beef eater's stuff
who come in and they just read the story
if they can not.
- I don't think we know why they're called beef eater's, do we?
There are lots of theories.
The story we were told on the tour was that
it was because they were paid in beef,
which they know definitely is true or paid in meat,
which they know definitely was true.
And that the people outside kind of thought,
I'll look at these guys eating all that meat.
And so it was like an insult kind of thing.
- It makes sense.
I mean, and they're part of the royal household.
They eat lots of meat, they eat lots of beef.
- I've seen other people poo pooing like crazy that story.
- That's just, all right.
- But it just makes so much sense.
It seems to be like one of those things
that you can't really poo poo.
It's like, yeah, they eat lots of beef
and they're called beef eater's.
- Do you have a better theory of red?
- I've read two or three.
There's one which is sort of it's from the French boufete,
which is a different word meaning something else.
- Yeah, that's clearly nonsense, isn't it?
- What? Why?
- Because that is such a convoluted way
to get to the word beef eater
rather than just they ate loads of beef.
- I think eating beef is--
- And we're paid in it.
- There's probably something--
- Who gets paid in the beef?
- But we know they were paid in it.
- They know that they were, yeah.
We know they were given a stipend of beef,
which most people were able to eat at the time.
- Oh, we know the people took the place out
of the royal household for having,
'cause they ate so much beef around that time.
- I think Andy's right, there's so many holes in this.
- Just can't see.
- I just don't believe it.
- I don't believe it.
- But it could be that it came from something else
and then it was helped by the fact they ate lots of beef.
- Yeah, exactly.
It could have come from Buffetay.
And then I'm not buying it.
- So what is Buffetay?
- But there are beef eaters today.
The Ravens eat raw beef.
- They get fed raw beef from Smithville, Marble.
- The beef eaters probably eat beef.
(all laughing)
- Wait, are you gonna explain
your definitely more plausible, weird, French origin
convoluted on?
- I did read this and I thought,
well, that's clearly bollocks for the fun.
- So the thing is that the beef eaters began,
they're called the Yomangard of the King of Queen, right?
Well, they're called the Yomang Waters,
which is part of a larger group called the Yomangard.
And they're kind of the bodyguard of the King of Queen.
But it started in the Battle of Bosworth in 1485,
when Henry VII won the crown
and all these guys who'd helped him,
who were from this Northern Regiment,
he brought them in and they became his bodyguard.
But Henry VII will have been an English-speaking king.
So if it was further back in Norman times,
you can kind of see where the French thing might have come from.
- Yeah. - That's a good point.
- Whereas Henry VII's actually hailed from Wales.
- Did he?
- Yeah, the tutors were all Welsh family.
- Is there any Welsh word
that sounds a bit like B-feeters?
- Tafferter?
(all laughing)
- It could have come from B-feeters.
Like B, what's the B-feet?
- You know a feat, like you accomplish a feat.
- With a B. - Yeah, with a B.
- B-racing or something.
- Exactly, so maybe they were famous for their B-racing
back in the day and they got known as the B-feeters.
- That's good.
- Maybe the Bs were the original Ravens, you think,
but they trained.
- Well, maybe there was originally another group
called the A-feeters who did lots of things.
- Exactly, yeah.
- And then they kind of died out
and then the B-feeters came in.
- Bingo.
- The less good featers we could never got into the '18.
- Maybe.
- I'm just saying, there's a lot of explanations.
- You're right.
Did you see, when you were in the pub, James,
I wonder if there's apparently a framed photo of Rudolf Hess.
- I took a photo of it.
- Did you?
- Yeah, of his signature as well.
- Wow.
- He sort of signed, they asked him for a pin-up photo, basically,
because he was a senior Nazi who was imprisoned there
briefly in 1941.
- I think he defected.
- Everyone else was taking photos of all the pictures
of B-feeters and stuff, but I clung to the signature
of Rudolf Hess and I got to get a photo of that.
- Well, you've got a large collection of Nazi signatures.
Instantly, you recognise that.
- I see that covenant behind the fake bookshelf in your house, right?
(laughing)
- Okay, that makes sense.
He did he defect, because it sounds like when he was there,
a lot of people collected his signature and that feels odd.
- I think he flew over with his family to Scotland, by and all of a sudden.
Yeah, I think he came out, I think, typically,
there weren't many Nazis arrested during the war in the German side.
- But he was prison, I wasn't he.
- He was prisoned, yeah.
- He was prisoned.
- He wasn't just drinking at the pub.
- Yeah, if you'd effect, they'd have to say,
"Oh, great, well, welcome to Britain, here's your home."
- Yeah, no, he was in jail.
- And they were under.
- And then they sort of asked you a few questions.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Are you sure you're Rudolf Hess, that kind of thing?
- But then he did get tried after the war,
didn't he and committed suicide in prison Hess?
- I'm not saying it's a happy ending to the story.
- Right.
(laughing)
- But also, let's not waste too much sympathy on the guy.
- So if you've got the Rudolf Hess,
everyone else is doing B-feeters.
- Did you see the framed photo of Bruce Willis?
- I didn't see that.
- Did you not?
- I saw a framed picture of the Duke of Edinburgh.
- Okay.
- I didn't see Bruce Willis.
- Well, it says, amongst the things that you'll find there,
there's a ceremonial ax, which is in the corner,
so that photos of guests like Bruce Willis and Tom Clancy,
the-- - I don't know what Tom Clancy looks like.
- No one does, so that could be--
- Does he look like a Duke of Edinburgh?
(laughing)
- That's true, and you've got Facebook, though, so actually--
- I would recognize Bruce Willis, perhaps.
- Right.
- If I was stuck next to someone who said,
"That's Bruce Willis, yeah."
(laughing)
No, I didn't see that, but I wouldn't,
you know, there's lots of pictures there.
- Yeah.
- Do they have pictures of their final prisoners?
'Cause they should do, and actually I didn't read that they did,
but their last prisoners were the Cray brothers, weren't they?
- Oh, were they the very last prisoners?
- Yeah. - Wow.
- I think this is so odd, there's such a weird coincidence.
- Well, it's because of their national service, right?
- Yes, no, I know, but it's odd that it's them.
- Yeah.
- They were famous, right?
- Yeah, exactly.
So this was in 1952 before they were famous,
and they had just--
- Where are they now?
(laughing)
- And they'd failed to report for national service,
and they'd been on the run for ages,
and then they'd been caught by a policeman
who was like, "You didn't report for national service,
"and I think they punched him."
- Yeah, but I think their regimen--
- Was based at the Tower of London.
- Yeah, which is bizarre.
- And Cray brothers, for any overseas listeners,
they're the very famous mob London gangsters.
They are Godfather's, basically.
- Made by Tom Hardy and Tom Hardy in that movie.
- That's right, yes.
- Yeah.
Here's a tenuous link.
You mentioned the Duke of Edinburgh just there.
- I did.
- So the Duke of Wellington--
- Okay.
- I completely different to you.
(laughing)
So the famous Duke of Wellington,
the one who won the Battle of Waterloo,
he was the Constable of the Tower for 26 years
after the Battle of Waterloo,
and he completely changed it.
So he did this huge reform program.
He stopped people selling their jobs as beef eaters,
and he drained the moat,
'cause lots of people were getting cholera, basically,
'cause it was so stagnant.
And he also closed the Royal Menagerie,
which used to be based at the Tower of London.
- Yeah.
- And it closed it,
because people kept being killed by the animals.
- Oh really?
- Really?
- Used to just be allowed into the monkey room.
There were no barriers.
- But the monkeys would eat you.
- But they?
- Well, they might--
- They might nibble on you.
- Well, that's kind of it.
And account, the account was that a monkey,
Toriboy's leg quotes in a dangerous manner.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
An assistant keeper accidentally let a lion
and two tigers into the same room,
and they started killing each other,
the wolves escaped and they ate a terrier.
Lots of just constant accidents happening,
'cause there were these wild animals there.
- Wow.
- And so when that guy came in,
that's basically when they count the beef eaters from,
really, beef eater number one was that guy,
and then beef eater number two was his mate,
and then so on and so on.
They don't really have records for the previous ones,
because they were so often sold between people.
But from that guy to the present day,
there have been about 400 beef eaters,
and that is fewer than people who have been in space.
- Wow.
- Have any beef eaters been in space?
- Not to my knowledge.
(laughing)
So the guy who was the constable,
he, historically, was allowed to keep all livestock
that fell from Tower Bridge into the river.
So anything that fell from the bridge into the river,
he was allowed to keep it.
- Again, that sitcom is gonna be a great episode
where the constable is trying to push livestock off.
(laughing)
- And for every foot of livestock
that stumbled into the Tower Moat,
he received one penny.
- Quite a lot to retrieve a cow from a moat,
I would have thought.
I think you've earned it if you do that.
- Wait, so if a donkey puts one foot into the moat,
you get one penny.
- One foot in the moat, it could be the neighborhood
of the sitcom.
(laughing)
- I believe that's right, yeah.
- You mentioned Ravens before,
the idea that they would be fed beef from,
and what was it, an East London--
- Smithfield Market.
- The Tower of London, one of the employees there,
and I'm not sure if he counts technically
as a yeoman wardo, but he's the Raven Master.
- Yes, he is a beef eater.
- So yeah, so they hire this guy who,
his whole family lives there, they have a house,
and he just has to look after these Ravens
because of an enduring myth
that if the Ravens left the Tower of London,
England would fall.
That's basically a ceremonial role just to fulfill
this little men.
And I've met him, he's a really cool guy.
I've done it and stand up with him.
- We did stand up with him.
- Yeah, Chris, he was really cool.
- He must have a lot of very relatable stories.
(laughing)
- Did he bring his Ravens?
'Cause Ravens are very good at talking.
- Are they?
- Yeah, COVIDs are famously the best birds
at kind of being able to form almost human sounding like words,
and they're extremely clever.
- Oh.
- And so he's trained them up to do some quite cool stuff.
- I thought he was getting bigger laughs than I was.
- Random table four.
- Yes, that's great!
(laughing)
- Then that's my bed!
- That was a genuine problem, wasn't it?
When the Royal Astronomer was stationed
at the Tower of London while they were waiting
for the Greenwich Observatory to be built.
And this was John Flamste, the first Royal Astronomer.
And while the Observatory was being built,
he was trying to do his astronomy at the Tower of London
and the Ravens kept pooing on the telescope.
And so he said, "Can you please remove all the Ravens?"
And King Charles was going to,
I think it was Charles II was going to,
and then said, "Oh no, I've heard that the crown will fall."
- But for him, it will have been quite close
to the last time the crown fell, right?
Charles II.
- Yeah, I suppose it was.
- So he's just come back, he's just restored the crown.
I can understand why he's worried.
- But he's worried. - That he's worried.
- You're right.
It's totally understandable.
- Like these days, I think no one seriously expects
if the Ravens go, and he's looking to be like he does.
- Well, this guy would be out of a house and a job.
Chris, if they can.
- Well, they do just be able to stand up
for a career to fall back.
I should add, it was a night of historical talks.
He happened to be very funny,
and it was mainly stand-ups doing it.
His talk was on Jack the Ripper.
So it was a bit dark, actually.
- Jack do all the Ripper more like.
- Yeah.
- He's in that sweat and crows.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for fact number two, and that is Andy.
My fact is that the economic activity of the Roman Empire
can be measured by studying thousand-year-old ice
in Greenland.
- Wow.
- That's amazing.
- Amazing.
- It's so cool.
Okay, so it takes a tiny bit of explaining.
So a group of scientists have released a new study,
which is all about measuring the Greenland ice sheet.
There's a miles thick ice sheet covering
a huge amount of Greenland.
And we know when ice forms, because we know how much snow falls
and it packs down and it becomes ice,
and it gradually gets deeper and deeper.
So the scientists have been studying the period
between 1,100 BC, 3,000 years ago, and 800 AD.
And they've been measuring the chemicals in there.
And one thing we know from that time in history
is that Rome was making lots of coins,
and the production of the coins, the coins were silver,
that they produced a lot of lead pollution,
'cause they were using all which contained lead.
That lead wafted all the way across the world.
It ended up in Greenland.
It gets rained down, packed into the ice.
And since 1999, scientists have been measuring
the lead level, corresponding with exact years in history,
and they can produce documents now showing that, for example,
when Rome devalued its currency in 64 AD,
there was less silver in each coin,
so there would have been less lead produced,
so there's less lead in the ice.
- Yeah.
- It's extraordinary. - It's nuts.
- It's really good.
It doesn't help people in ancient Rome
who want to know whether to invest in things.
- No, it doesn't.
- Sadly.
(laughing)
- But yeah, they follow, I think they've debunked
and thought that when the Roman Republic fell,
the economy was booming, and they've actually worked out
that when it came to the fall of the Republic,
the lead amounts in the ice actually show
that it was undergoing a bit of a recession.
And stuff like when Rome took Carthage,
they got all the Carthaginian mines,
so suddenly they were mining a hell of a lot more silver,
and you can see that exact year
of the Carthaginian invasion from looking at the ice.
- How far away is a distance that we're talking here
from the mines to the ice?
- It's thousands of miles.
- Thousands of miles.
It just shows you how strong wind is, doesn't it?
- That's my main takeaway.
- Well, I just, if you think about it, no.
- I tell you what's weird.
The prevailing wind in the world
goes from Greenland to the east because of the jet stream.
So how is it going?
It must be going all the way around the world.
- All the way around the world.
- I don't know about that, by the way.
- Wow.
- It makes sense, right?
- But it's like, you know how as well,
how there are sheep in whales
that have been affected by the Chernobyl radiation.
Like that's carried through the wind.
- That is the lake district.
- And the lake district is just winders, you know.
- And that got there even faster than this 2000 years.
- Wait a minute though, Chernobyl also to the east
of the lake districts and whales,
but that didn't go all the way around the world.
So maybe my jet stream theory.
- It feels like wind might be more complicated
than just the one big gust going around the world.
- Thank you so much.
- It might be a couple of different directions.
- I think this is very powerful flat earth evidence.
- Yes.
- I'll probably be shouting down in the comments about this.
- One explanation for it going the wrong way
is as one person pointed out,
this is the hypothesis at the moment,
but for instance, it ignores the fact
that China existed and was doing quite well
around that time.
- I think Western scientists and historians
always have a tendency to do.
And it could well be that China was just producing
massive amounts of silver or lead or whatever
that was influencing it.
- But we don't know, but it could be that
something was coming from the east to affect it.
- But it does seem to fit in with these things in Rome.
- Yeah.
- So for instance, there was a plague,
the Antonin plague, which they think,
they're not sure what caused it,
but lots of people died.
It might have been smallpox.
It might even have been Ebola.
And this was in between 250 and 262,
when 5,000 people a day were said to be dying.
And the amount of lead being produced then
obviously went down because people
had more pressing things on their minds.
But they assumed 250 AD, who was it?
Christians.
Assumed it was to do the Christians.
And so they basically sought out as many scapegoats
as they could and they kind of executed
a load of clergy and stuff like that.
- Wow.
- Did it work?
- Well, we no longer have Christianity.
(laughing)
- On that, a lot of people think
because it was so persecuted during this plague,
that kind of made Christianity a lot more solid
as a religion.
And that's kind of one of the main things
that made it such a worldwide religion in the end.
- Wow.
- There you go, bully someone and make them stronger.
- Yes.
No, don't bully someone.
But if you are being bullied, you'll come out of it stronger.
- Okay.
- Is that right?
- That's a healthier message here.
- So just quickly on this whole Greenland ice-led thing,
have you guys heard of Claire Patterson?
(laughing)
Does she, is she the Venn diagram?
- She is.
- All those words.
(laughing)
- She's a he actually.
He was a scientist.
- Ah, he was an amazing guy.
I wish we could do a whole podcast on him.
He was trying to find out how all the universe was
in the 1950s.
Okay, so that involves calculating
how fast uranium decays.
But he found massive lead contamination
everywhere he went.
And it drove him mad.
There was all this lead showing up
that shouldn't have been there.
He tried and tried and tried to build
this incredibly lead-free lamp, basically.
He scrubbed everything.
He cleaned everything for years.
He founded basically the first ever clean laboratory.
And he proved that lead in petrol was bad.
And that was, he-
- Ah, I saw him.
- Yeah, he was the guy who demonstrated later in his career
that modern Americans had 600 times as much lead
in their bodies as ancient Egyptians.
- Wow.
- All thanks to lead-ed petrol.
Yeah, and so as part of this research,
he went to remote spots in Greenland and Antarctica
and measured the lead much further down.
So this is one of the stories of the last two millennia
is massively increasing amounts of lead.
And that lead to all these efforts lead
to all the efforts to cut lead out of petrol, for example.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Because the person who invented putting lead in petrol
was Thomas Midgeley.
And that was a really good invention
'cause it stopped knocking and engines.
- Right.
- But when it first happened, everyone thought,
this is an amazing, oh, just putting lead in there
that solves this massive problem.
- Yeah, these to be all these little explosions
and the car engine basically is when you put kerosene in.
- Okay, and that's knocking.
- And there's good knocking.
And they try hundreds of different experiments
and chemicals to try and get rid of the knock.
And once it did, that was huge.
It made cars a real thing.
(laughing)
- Wow.
This guy sounds awesome.
- Yeah, he does.
- It was very bad for you.
We should say, lead is bad.
- Lead is bad.
- Well, isn't it true?
That the, a lot of people put the fall of the Roman Empire
down to lead in the pipes.
- I pointed it out.
- The plumbing was that.
- Yeah, the plumbing was made of lead.
And so they were lead poisoned
and that supposedly killed off a lot of the rich people.
- Don't know if that's true.
- Well, I've heard, so Roman miners,
they knew that lead was bad
'cause they shielded themselves
by covering their mouths with animal blood as incidentally.
So a lot of people knew that lead was bad for you,
but they still kept the pipes being out of lead.
I think some people said, even at the time,
are we sure about this lead stuff?
- Yeah, right.
- Everyone said no, no, no, it's fine.
- Would people at the time have died a sort of,
they would have just slowly got ill
and it would have looked like,
oh, you've got a flu and then it,
or would it be instant lead lead?
- Not sure what sentence of lead poisoning.
- Oh, yeah.
- Then you go a bit mad, didn't you?
- I just wonder how long it would take
if someone, sinister, had re-plumbed.
- Rudolf Hess for instance.
- Rudolf Hess re-plumbed the city of London
with lead piping.
(all laughing)
- Wow.
Super bellied blood.
- It's a subtly trade.
- Sutterly.
- Every single one.
- How long must be better ways?
- But how long before we would notice it?
- Just the fat bugs alone in the ice.
- It can be done.
- A supervillain that rises to prominence
in Thames water, right?
- Yes.
- And slowly start saying all the replacement pipes
have lead in them and then 40 years like,
no, it's really weird.
Your body thinks that lead is calcium.
It mistakes the two, chemically.
And it absolutely shreds you on the inside.
It gets in the way of all your neurotransmitters
and sends them crazy.
It weakens the blood brain barrier
so you're more vulnerable to,
it has about 30 different horrible effects on your body.
- Well, so your body tries to do the same stuff with it
as it does with calcium, like build your nails
and things like that.
- Yeah, do you have bones made of lead?
- I start drawing with our fingers.
(all laughing)
- There's no lead in pencil stuff.
- Okay, I'm not sure.
I don't know.
I don't know the full details, anyway.
- It wouldn't be super efficient though.
You couldn't guarantee to wipe everyone out.
- What an infrastructure-based bond movie
that would be over a period of several decades.
- I just wonder what point would someone know?
Like, hang on, I think what London is suffering from
is everyone's being poisoned by lead.
- I'm looking forward to this movie called "led finger."
(all laughing)
He does all this in London,
but also can write things when it's bigger.
(all laughing)
- I have a few things about great things found in ice.
So in Southern Yukon, they have had ice melting recently
and there's a big patch that's melted
and underneath it, they found all this caribou dung
that's been sitting there held in the ice.
Now, what's interesting is there is no caribou
that exists in Southern Yukon, but what it's done
is it's confirmed one of the oldest oral history stories
that have passed down from the First Nations people,
as it says in the article,
the First Nations people of the area
who claimed that the land used to be roamed by caribou.
So they did these tests on it
and they've discovered that some of them are hundreds of years old,
the dunks, some are thousands of years old.
So an oral history that's made it all the way through
that was thought to be wrong has been confirmed.
- Yeah.
Frozen deer in ice are actually a bit of a problem now though,
aren't they?
So there was that thing last year, I think,
which was about the permafrost melting in Siberia
and when the permafrost melts, then it starts to explode
and this is because of global warming,
it exposes the dead bodies of things
that have died of bad diseases.
And I think it exposed a reindeer who had anthrax poisoning
and it had anthrax poisoning in 1895,
but it released the anthrax back into the atmosphere
and I think someone died of anthrax poisoning actually.
- Really?
- Yeah, and now scientists are saying that, you know,
it's as it melts in global warming advances on us
and it's going to release all sorts of old stuff,
like bubonic plague is going to...
- I've heard smallpox.
- I've heard smallpox is going to come back, yeah.
- It's a good sequel for your movie, Dan.
- Yes.
- Next movie, "The Super Villain Mooster Siberia"
with a hair dryer.
(laughing)
- No, come on, just hair dryer in the world.
- No, he comes back here selling ice cubes
to everyone in London.
They melt in the house, and everyone dies
when they have a cup of water on us.
- Why do all these films set only in London?
(laughing)
- 'Cause he's James Bond, he's British, yeah.
- Yeah.
- I really like this fact, okay,
because it's sort of a historical thing
being revealed by science and it's kind of an exciting
crossing of those two academic worlds
and something quite similar to that,
was you know the saddle worth more fires this year.
- Yep.
- So that was in the Manchester area obviously.
One side effect of those fires is that it's going to release
all of this long lost pollutant from the industrial revolution
because it's, I know it's exciting.
(laughing)
We're all going to die in some way.
- I noticed the people in North Manchester.
- Yeah.
- Just my family really.
- Yeah, I'm really sorry about that, you should give them a call.
But the reason for this is that the peat
is an unbelievably good store.
So you know people talk about peat being a really good carbon store.
So it holds it for hundreds of years.
It's also a good store of other substances and pollutants.
And then the fires just set fire to it all
and release them all into the air.
So we're getting to now inhale that deliciously
smoggy stuff that the Victorians are doing.
- I want to kind of rain down, I guess, right?
- I don't think you'll be able to see
sort of bits of 19th century coal falling out of the sky.
- What?
- I mean, sometimes you get that.
- Don't you like when it's been, like it picks up sand
from the Sahara and it rains down in--
- Yeah, might get a bit more smoggy.
But you won't be able to tell it's 19th century coal,
particularly there won't be a top hat raining down
with it or a pipe.
Hey, that could be the third film you're trying to do then.
- Yes.
- Peat finger.
- Peat finger, yeah.
No, he's a sex offender from a nutshell, I think.
- Yeah.
- No, this, you would need the villain
to create a gust of wind that sends all the peat
from Manchester to London, but could we do this
with his giant hairdryer?
- Yes, okay, so all right.
So the villain of the second film we survived
into the third.
- 'Cause last week we did mention that they're looking
for a new director of the Bond films.
(laughing)
I think we're only cementing our pledge to become that.
(upbeat music)
- Time for fact number three, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the umlauts that are used
for the band Motley Crew are purely decorative.
They're not intended to have pronunciation.
However, when Motley Crew first performed in Germany,
the crowd didn't know that and chanted,
"Motley Krug!"
(laughing)
- This is fantastic.
Now this was tweeted by Quikipedia a couple of days ago
since we recorded, and we needed proper verification on it,
and we got it from Tommy Lee, the drummer of Motley Crew
or Motley Krug, who said, "Ha ha, Tra!"
Nick, to someone who asked him on behalf of us.
So yeah, we've got confirmation,
yeah, that they were Motley Krug.
It's very exciting 'cause the metal umlaut
is purely decorative.
Motohead had it as well.
Maximo Park, Maximo Park, and yeah, so that's very,
very exciting.
It's a proper verification from a real source,
which is also awesome.
I was looking into Tommy Lee if you don't know who he is.
So he is a drummer of Motley Crew.
- He's married to Pamela Anderson.
Responsible for the leaked porn video as well.
I don't know if he leaked it, but famously her porn video,
there are two, he is one.
- Oh, this is a real trip down memory lane.
- Yeah, yeah.
- She is a first celebrity story of the world.
- You were the boom operator for that film, didn't you?
- I thought of about 15 years that Tommy Lee
was the same person as Tommy Lee Jones.
- Yeah, and then I used to watch men in black
and be like, "I can't believe this guy."
- With family, yeah.
- He does have a surname, Tommy Lee.
But he doesn't use it.
And I only just learnt it before we started recording.
It's bass.
And I reckon he doesn't use it because he's the drummer.
So that would have just been confusing.
- Very, yeah.
Whereas just shoving umla, it was left right in center
that all the first three pronounce is absolutely fine.
- So it's just a convention in metal bands, right?
- Well, I guess not just metal bands,
'cause I just learnt as well that JZ used to have
an umla in his name.
- What?
- Yeah, he over, I guess, well, he doesn't specify.
He just said I used to have an umla.
And he uses punctuation quite oddly.
He had a hyphen to begin with.
He got rid of the hyphen.
His latest album came back.
He not only came back with a hyphen,
but in all caps as well.
So JZ is now shouting at you.
And he admitted that he used to have an umla out there.
- Do you know I think we should have an umla out in our name?
Or maybe some kind of punctuation?
- I think we definitely.
It seems like a supply way to make yourself sound hard, basically.
- No, no, such thing as a fish.
- No, 'cause then we sound like we're from Yorkshire.
(laughing)
- There's no such thing as a fish.
- It's fine line between heavy metal and Yorkshire.
(laughing)
- Has JZ ever done an autobiography?
- He has, yeah.
Is it called J2Z?
(laughing)
- It's not, and it should be, why is it not?
And I'm pretty sure it is an A to Z as well.
- You're kidding, yeah?
- No.
- I'm pretty sure.
- And who does a A to Z of their art and biography?
- It's quite a fun idea.
- Matt Lucas did it.
We should write an A to Z book.
- Yeah, but you do have some B is Bond,
but what do you do before that?
- Oh yeah.
Antenatal, I guess.
- Nice.
- Yeah.
- It's not as good as the movie ideas.
- Interesting.
(laughing)
- Stick to another sequel of those.
- So on the metal um-lout,
the first band to have a num-lout was called
Amon Dual, the second, that's A, M, O, N, D,
U, um-lout, U, um-lout, L, and then two eyes.
But that is fair enough because dual is a Turkish word
which has um-louts in it.
- Oh.
- And the first band to give itself a spurious
on-lout was Blue Eister cult.
- Oh yeah.
- Oh, of course.
- Yes, yeah.
- Over which?
- Lesson.
- Over the O in Eister.
- Mmm.
- And the longest continuous um-louted word
in the world is Ya, so J-A-A-A,
all of which have um-louts above are.
It's Estonian and it means the edge of the ice.
So when you get to the edge of the ice,
- Yeah.
- Oh, that was good.
- So yeah, punctuation.
- Yeah.
- So, I think we've covered before the intera bang,
maybe on QI, which was that was something
that actually appeared on typewriters in the '60s,
which was a question mark and an exclamation mark
that were elided, which means you're asking a question,
but like, oh, we're going to the cinema today
in a really excited way.
I had a really sad childhood.
I was the one who kind of think they got me excited.
But another thing that the language has always been
hunting for is ways to show irony, right?
So people have always been trying to invent bits of punctuation
that show you're being sarcastic.
And actually, the first person who suggested a way of doing that
was a guy called John Wilkins.
And do you remember John Wilkins?
- Nope, no.
- He is the guy who also was the first person
to plan to put a man on the moon and design a rocket
for it, Oliver Cromwell's brother.
- Yes.
- So was he suggesting that ironically?
- It was a one big joke.
(laughing)
Out of hand.
Yeah, his main thing was he wrote this huge book
on how to change the language.
And he said he should have an upside down exclamation mark
to show irony.
- Well, they call that the sarc mark, don't they?
- They do, yes.
- It's the sarcasm, yes.
- Just on another symbol that didn't kick off.
I read this fact, and it's hard actually to verify it.
So it'd be interested to know if anyone can get
to the bottom of this, but Hagrid Hawkes,
who's a fantastic Twitter account and has a few books,
he put this up saying that in 1580,
English printer Henry Denham,
proposed using a reverse question mark,
so a sort of mirror-imaged question mark
to indicate when a question was rhetorical,
which would be very useful if you were an author.
- Would it?
- Yeah, it would.
- No, no, no.
(laughing)
- So we think that this might,
we're not sure if this is true, right?
Because we've not found anything earlier than the 1990s,
of evidence for it, although Denham,
he did invent two different types of question mark.
One for yes, no questions,
and another one for questions that begin with WH,
like why were what?
So he had two different questions marks for those.
- What was that for?
Why do you need a special question mark
to let you know the question begins with WH?
'Cause--
- In case it's been such a long sentence,
you can't remember the word of the handle.
- I think the reason that we don't still have them
is because they're not that useful.
But he was the first person also to use semi-colons
with any kind of regularity.
He didn't invent them,
but he was the first one to use them regularly.
- Nice.
- And consistently.
He also invented the word parathesis for brackets
which later became parentheses.
- Oh, wow.
- Oh, he had a huge influence.
- Yeah, so he was a massive kind of punctuation, dude.
But huge in that world amongst all the greats.
- Well, semi-colons, I didn't realize,
some people really hate semi-colons, basically.
So George Orwell, he hated them so much
then he wrote a novel called "Coming Up for Air"
is one of his early ones, I think,
and he put no semi-colons in.
But then he was a bit worried that no one would notice
that he hadn't put any in.
So he wrote to his publisher, saying,
"I haven't put any semi-colons in here."
(laughing)
Oh, man.
- So childish.
- I know, one of the great writers.
- Yeah.
- Hemingway as well, very much.
So played with the rules of punctuation.
But he only did so with the claim that he knew it's so well
that he was able to go beyond the acceptable rules.
- I think that's quite normal.
- Yeah.
- I think that's quite standard, I would say people,
like Hillary Mantell and Rachel Cusk do that,
but it's because you can feel they've got such a good grasp of it
that they're mastering it rather than just spewing nonsense
onto a page and then going,
"Oh yeah, it's just so familiar with the art."
- Yeah, yeah.
So William Blake would sometimes put a full stop
in the middle of a word.
(laughing)
- What a maverick.
Is that because it was to be read and he wanted the punctuation
of a word to be broken up?
- I don't know, he also saw a lot of angels.
So, it might have been taking dictation from them.
- Guys, the punctuation point I need all the time
is a question mark colon.
And I can't believe this isn't a thing.
When you're writing an email and you're like,
"What about these points?"
And then you give a list and I always put a question mark
followed by a colon and it looks stupid.
It's, I think that's the most essential piece of punctuation
and no one's ever come up with one as far as I know.
- Yeah, so how are we gonna fix it?
- Is it a question mark with two dots at the bottom?
- Sideways, I'm allowed to at the bottom.
I have a second dot underneath the first dot.
So it's a way to start.
- Sideways, yeah, right.
- What about a second dot in the middle
of the round bit of the question mark?
Like an eyeball.
- Like an eyeball.
- Or a nipple?
Let's make the question mark a bit sexy.
- I think dots at the bottom makes more sense, doesn't it?
- We could call them question knocks.
- Okay, no.
- Oh god.
- Let's just send it.
That's actually being called a high brow point initially, I feel.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final step to the show
and that is Chazinski.
- My fact this week is that traditionally,
indigenous Hawaiians had personalized chance
for their genitals.
- That's unusual to be Hawaiians.
(laughing)
- This is so amazing.
All of this stuff about indigenous Hawaiians
and the what they associated with their genitals,
which I spent a lot of time reading about this week.
But I should say, I read it initially on the BBC
of such a cheat.
It was a series of amazing sex facts from around the world
and I saw that and I couldn't believe I hadn't heard it.
- That's not a cheat.
- This, is that not a cheat?
- No.
- I felt like a cheat.
- You're not allowed to get your facts from anywhere.
- I actually went to Hawaii to try and find something.
I didn't find anything.
- I went to Hawaii, you stood in the air pot
and did a chance about my genitals.
(laughing)
- Not allowed back in the United States.
This started being recorded from the 18th century
when cook and others went to Hawaii
and yeah, it turns out that indigenous Hawaiians
would give their genitals a name
or their parents would give their genitals a name
almost as soon as they were born
and they'd also design, they'd also write a song for them
and sort of have a story around their genitals
and it's called the Mille Mai, the genital chant
and it describes that individual's organ.
- So you had to, sorry, you had to name your child
and then you also had to name your child's genitals.
- It's hard enough to find a good name for your child, isn't it?
Have you reckon they had pucks?
(laughing)
The perfect name for your child's genitals.
I named my child's genitals after his grandpa's genitals.
(laughing)
- One example that I found was Queen Liliro Kulanis
Mille Mai was the story of her vagina
and it was called anapal, which meant frisky
and it was about her frolicing genitals
that went up and down apparently.
- Oh.
- So yeah, they used to frolic it.
- I think the source of the b-barticle
was this paper by a guy called Milton Diamond
who studied a lot of Hawaiian sexual traditions and culture
and things about nudity as well.
So this is really weird.
- Nudity was not sexual, in almost all contexts.
You only started wearing your clothes
over your genitals when you hit puberty
and that was out of respect for your genitals.
(laughing)
It's amazing.
But nudity for adults was symbolic of death
or punishment or lamentation.
And if you were seen nude outside a ritual context,
it was widely assumed that you had gone mad with grief.
- Yes.
- So it's not a sexy.
- It's really not.
- Nude speeches, three sad places in Hawaii.
- It could also be used as an appeal for forgiveness
this paper said.
So if someone's done you are wrong,
then the way you ask for their forgiveness
is by taking all your clothes off
and following them around until they forgive you.
- Turn up outside their house at three in the morning.
(laughing)
- Please forgive me.
Please take me back.
- I've done that actually.
(laughing)
- It's normally just my Hawaiian heritage.
- Is it, do we know if this is no longer being done?
Was this for traditional old indigenous?
- So what happened was when the Europeans came to Hawaii,
they saw all this stuff happening,
but then they soon cut it all out
because it wasn't very Christian.
- So there was a lot of taking over Hawaiian culture
and enforcing Western.
And then Hawaiian indigenous people have tried to take
a lot of it back, but I think it's obviously quite difficult
'cause it was lost for about 50 years.
- They said there was a basically where they go,
the penis chant, do we want that back here?
- I'm good I think.
- So like for instance, Hula dancing is probably
one of the most famous things in Hawaii
and Captain Cook said it was perfectly easy and graceful.
He thought it was amazing,
but when the missionaries arrived, it was officially suppressed.
- Have you heard of penis blowing?
- Yes.
(laughing)
- No, I don't think you have.
- I've seen that tummy leap in the eye.
(laughing)
- It's a signal to men in black.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- This is odd.
This was a daily ritual for Hawaiian infant,
which is where the members of the family would blow
on the penis, just with a stream of air,
just, and it was to prepare the foreskin
for a kind of micro-circumcidian ceremony,
and it would normally be an art or a grandmother
who did the blowing.
But lots of relatives were qualified to be the blower
if you didn't have any art, so that's fine.
- Wait, so what were they blowing onto it?
- Sort of Mike, or sort of a story of it?
- No, they just blow to protect it in their mythology.
- Yeah, okay.
- And this is a really common thing,
and there were lots of people even well into the 1980s,
for example, who had this done to them in their childhood.
- Yeah, in fact, there was a story, wasn't there,
about a man who was totally non-sexual, we should say.
- Yeah, completely.
There was a story about a man who was annoyed
because he'd married a Hawaiian woman,
and he left her mom to babysit their child,
and came back and found her doing this.
It was like, why are you blowing on my child's penis?
And apparently the mother-in-law was like,
well, I have to, otherwise it's very bad luck,
and was really worried about the baby's health if she didn't.
But it does, it seemed weird, actually,
if you haven't explained that before.
- Yes, yeah.
I like it's another gust of wind,
in fact, going into the,
(laughing)
'cause maybe it does have it.
Interestingly, you can tell the economic activity
of the Reven Empire from discarded foreskins
of Hawaiian children.
- Oh my God.
This, the author of this paper is called Milton Diamond,
as you mentioned before, and the only thing
that I could find of an interest outside
of him writing this paper.
So he wrote a lot about sex and gender, and so on.
He had a big feud with a man called Money,
so Diamond and Money had a big feud,
and they famously got into a punch-up
at a conference in Dubrovnik.
So Money had written a book called,
as nature made him the boy raised as a girl,
and mentions it in this book, this fight.
And there was a lot of chat about transgender at the time,
and so that's where they fell foul
of what they thought definitions were.
And yeah, there was a fight,
although Diamond claims he doesn't recall being punched.
But yeah, there's the only sort of thing.
- The thing is, with Diamond, he is really hard, isn't he?
(laughing)
- I have some stuff on chance.
- Right?
- So this, I just thought this was really interesting.
I'd never heard of it before,
but have you guys heard fruit singing?
- Oh, like Mongolian stuff, yeah.
- Yeah, so I didn't know that--
- Actually, I'm sorry.
- It sounded like that, but it's okay.
(laughing)
- It actually does sound a bit like that,
but I didn't realize that they're creating multiple notes.
- Yeah, they do harmonies, don't they?
- Yeah, with one throat.
So yeah, this is like Mongolians and some Inuits,
and it's called a two-tooth and overtone technique
when it's done in Mongolia,
and they can get up to six simultaneous notes
to come out of their mouth by doing this special fruit singing
technique, which I did not have time to look properly
into how exactly it works.
So all I can tell you is, it involves opening and closing
the vocal chords until harmonic resonances appear,
and I think if you go faster and faster,
different resonances come, and you make different noises,
but it's really cool.
And then there's this one other really cool way
of fruit singing, which is, this is an Inuit culture,
it's called the Katajak, and two women stand face to face,
but super close, so the lips almost touching each other,
and it's like a duel, a singing duel,
and so it goes really, really fast.
One woman says one note or throat noise,
and then the other one has to respond to it,
and it goes faster and faster,
and they use each other's mouths as kind of resonators,
basically, and it only ends when one of them
like collapses, laughing, or runs out of breath,
and they can go on for hours, and it looks so cool.
- It's like tooling banjos. - Yeah.
- But what you were saying is, so you got two people,
the mouths open, and I'm making good noise
into the other person's mouth, and because they've got a mouth,
there it's resonating the... - Exactly, and it makes a sound,
- but they're resonating in your mouth at the same time.
- Well straight after you, yeah, exactly. - Oh, right after you, right.
- So they're using your mouth as a musical instrument.
- That is so great. - That's weird.
- I know, it's fun, isn't it?
- Have you heard any? - Yeah.
- Wow. - It sounds cool.
- That sounds weird. - Yeah.
- It's not singing the normal stuff.
The Mongolian stuff sounds a bit like, did you reduce, doesn't it?
- It does, yes. - Yeah.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Who else? - Who else has got it?
(laughing)
- Six, no, six. - It's not doing that in my mouth, darling.
- Can I quickly mention, because naming of genitals
is a practice that still does go on.
There was a server that was done in 2015,
and it got reported in many places,
'cause it was a genuine survey,
and they found that 73% of men have given their penis a nickname.
- Is that right? - Yeah.
59% say that it was a woman who came up with their nickname
for them. - Oh.
- So the survey was commissioned by a men's retailer
called Jackamo, so this is a survey done through them.
So, okay, let's, a few nicknames.
- I can't think of anything that's not rude, Terry.
- So the top five. - Give us, what letter does it begin with?
- T for a... - I was a Terry.
(laughing)
- Is it one word? - It is one word.
- I think... - Terminator.
- I think sort of... - Terminator.
- Think what? - Gods.
- For? - No.
- No, 'cause that's just someone with a lisp.
- Sorry, I also have an aerial disease.
- I was trying not to. - My fetus is thought.
(laughing)
- Sorry, this isn't a god.
I was trying to put us in the ancient Greeks.
- All right, so what do you say that's a god?
- Oh, feces. - No, Troy.
So... - Troy?
- Yeah, yeah, weird.
- Doctor Doolittle, is that one?
- No, it's not. - That's shame.
- Russell the muscle is.
- Russell the muscle. - Yeah.
- It's not a muscle.
It's an organ.
- Oggons can have muscles in them.
Your heart's an organ, it's loads of muscle.
- Good point. - But there isn't a muscle in the penis.
- No, sir.
- Well, I'd be working out.
(laughing)
- I've also been kicked out of the chair yet.
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @tribaland, and my penis is on it.
(laughing)
- The table right now, damn.
- He stopped blowing on it.
(laughing)
- Andy?
- At Andrew Hunter M.
- James.
- At James Harkin.
- And Shazinsky.
- You can email podcast@QI.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @nosuchthing, or you can go to our Facebook page.
No such thing as a fish, or go to our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
As I said, last week we've redone it.
It looks really awesome.
It has everything up there from ticket links
to all of our previous episodes
to our new book that's coming out.
You can also get a behind-the-scenes documentary
that we made called Behind the Gills.
That's up there, link to that.
So go there, find everything.
And if you wanna hear us again,
we'll be back again next week.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)