Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode of No Such Things a Fish, which is the first
in our run of live summer shows at the Soho Theatre in London.
We have all sorts of amazing guests lined up for you for the rest of the summer.
I won't go into that now, because I really don't want to spoil it, especially for the
people who have tickets.
But what I can tell you is that in this week's show we were joined by Jamie Martin.
Now you will know Jamie if you listened to No Such Things a Fish before, because he has
been on quite a few shows, this is his third appearance, but of course he is most well
known for being one third of, let's be honest, the greatest British podcast of all time,
My Dad Rota Pono.
Now one important thing to say about that is that the My Dad Rota Pono team have chosen
some of their funniest moments from across the six season run, including some unheard
gems and they'll be releasing best off episodes once a month, starting on Monday the 31st
of June.
I absolutely can't wait for those best off shows, I'm sure you can't either, but in
the meantime, please do enjoy this week's episode of No Such Things a Fish with Jamie
Martin.
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Things a Fish, a weekly podcast this
week coming to you live from the Soho Theater in London.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray, James Harkin and
Jamie Morton and once again we have gathered round the microphones with our four favorite
facts from the last seven days and in no particular order here we go, starting with
fact number one and that is Jamie.
My fact this week, boys, is in 1782 a woman found a drag performance so hilarious that
she literally died of laughter.
Wow.
Probably not going to happen tonight, but not with me here for sure, but yeah, isn't
that mad?
Yeah, it's insane.
So this was an act, it was a play called Beggar's Opera and someone called Charles Bannister
who was playing a character called Polly Peacham and yeah, to give us a story.
Yeah, so Mrs Fitzherbert, suspiciously there's no first name, but she was a widow of a North
Hampton Shire clergyman, it was quite salacious that she was even at this kind of submersive
show and she found it so funny that this man came out and he was described as Lantern
jawed with five o'clock shadow and a double chin in a lovely pretty dress and she just
found it so funny she just didn't stop laughing for three days.
Oh wow.
That's the amazing thing, like she had to leave the theatre didn't she because she was laughing
so much but that's not when she died.
No.
The newspaper report said she couldn't get the figure from her memory so just every morning
she'd just wake up and go, "Ah!"
I mean what a sheltered fucking life, I'm sorry, like if that makes you laugh that much to
kill you.
Maybe it was a really good show.
Yeah, you know.
Well the Beggar's Opera.
It's a classic.
And the actor Bannister, he was one of the great actors of the day, he was very funny,
he was famous.
The good name too.
Charles Bannister.
Yeah, so John Gay, the Beggar's Opera actually, that was the first play which had songs in
it that were part of the narrative of the Beggar's Opera, it's pretty much the first musical
I would say.
Yeah.
So it was more popular, there was a thing called Beggar Mania and so you could go around,
you could buy matchboxes, fans, fireguards, everything with this show on.
Oh, it's like no such thing as a fish.
On your tables there is a merchandise leaflet, I think it's got a QR code but genuinely as
I can see it right there.
Go nuts!
Get us in with that merch.
Jamie, please, we rely on this, we rely on the merch, it's all that's keeping us going.
I was looking at people who had died on stage and I have a weird connection to one of these
people.
So Molière, very famous French playwright, actor, he collapsed on stage ironically playing
the lead in his final play called The Imaginary Invalid, so he literally died playing a hypochondriac.
Right.
And I have also played the lead in The Imaginary Invalid.
Really?
Yes.
Yes, I know.
That's cool.
In my youth, it's not that cool.
Thank you.
I sort of said that on autopilot Jamie, I wasn't actually thinking that is really cool, don't
care at all.
But back in my youth when I used to tread the boards, I didn't die obviously.
The thing about him actually is because he was an actor, in those days actors couldn't
go to heaven.
So if you, I'm not sure anyone could, let's not get into that, that's an actual medical
matter.
But like, so the thing was, if you're an actor, it was like, yeah, you had to renounce your
acting job before you died.
So on your death bed, you might say, oh, I was never really an actor or I wasn't a very
good one or whatever and then you would be allowed to go to heaven.
If you've said I'm really more of a playwright, I'm more of a sort of immersive media creator
really.
I facilitated the heathens, I wasn't one of them myself.
But yeah, and the thing was is that that meant that he was buried without, he wasn't allowed
to be buried in the churchyard or anything like that because he died so quickly after
this event.
Oh, wow, okay.
I wanted to see Molly I played a few years ago.
Starring Jamie Morton?
Yes.
No.
How was I?
Be kind.
It wasn't one with you in, but I did leave it halfway through.
Oh really?
Yeah.
In a sense, Molly died a second time that night.
Wow.
I'd say it's in the translation.
I think he's a fantastic playwright.
I'm sure he is.
There was a school party all around us.
It is.
It was tricky.
They were not having a good time and neither were we.
I've got a little quiz for you guys.
Oh, great.
All right.
So this is, I'm going to say a thing, right, an object and you have to say what it's used
for by the Royal Shakespeare Company as stage gore.
Okay.
Oh, great.
I love this game.
In 2010, for example.
Shakespeare specifically.
Yeah.
Okay.
Right.
These are all used by the RSC, right?
So in 2010, the Royal Shakespeare Company, they used three tins of lichies during their
summer season.
Bubos.
Not buboes.
Ibls.
It wasn't actually an everyone play game.
It was.
No.
That's school parties in again.
Yeah.
Please do.
No.
Just, wait for a second.
Just let them do it.
Ibls.
Yeah, that's it.
Yeah.
We can end that.
No.
Well done.
Well done to the people who knew it and thank you.
And yeah.
Ibls.
Okay.
That's the cause.
What scene?
Yeah.
Where they blind the Duke of Gloucester.
Okay.
Yeah.
He actually knew.
That's very impressive.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
Well, here's another one.
Yeah.
Chicken fillets.
Bubes for bras.
To pump up the bras.
Actual.
Well, that's a real thing.
No, it's not.
No.
Actual chicken fillets.
Well, I've got an Amazon delivery from my wife that she's going to be very confused
about.
Flapping skin and muscles.
Oh, nice.
Yeah.
No, it's...
Anyone?
Anyone in the audience?
Ears.
Tongues.
And finally, tinned pears.
Tinned pears.
Tennis book.
No.
What?
Nothing.
Tennis.
I didn't even say that.
I only said half of it and then I pulled back.
Yeah.
I think testicles is a good call.
Okay, testicles.
All right.
Idiot.
You complete full deck.
No, it's penises.
It's penises.
Tinned pears for penises.
Sorry?
What?
He's serious.
Yeah.
Don't...
Andy.
What?
Sorry, what's the question?
I've either been buying some really odd pears or I need to see a doctor.
I think they're shaped a little bit, but I think it's the consistency.
Consistency?
Consistency of a tinned pear.
Also, what are they doing with these fake penises that they need a good consistency?
Yeah.
I'm not sure I've seen that Shakespeare play where they all get their cocks out.
What?
Which one is that?
Yeah.
Is it measure for measure?
That's right.
Very good.
I don't actually...
Yeah.
That's amazing.
There we go.
They're real.
They have an amazing department.
Their fake blood is a...
Could it be that you put it in your stockings and it gives you a shape, maybe?
I think it was for some...
There's some horrible...
Titus Andronicus has lots of terrible torture and gore and all this stuff.
So they do like...
It's rare.
It's not across the canon that you need a tinned pear in the department.
But they've got these...
A tinned pear?
Their fake blood recipe is secret and they've got three different consistencies.
And there was an interview with Helen Hughes, who's one of their very senior prop and design people.
And she was being interviewed about fake blood.
And the interviewer asked her, like, what kind of...
What do you use for your fake blood?
And she said, what kind of blood?
There's venal blood, arterial blood, newly dry blood, crusty old blood.
They've got...
They can do all of it.
All the bloods.
She's an artist.
She knows her craft.
I know.
Yeah.
Helen.
There was a story which is...
Because you got this story from a Giles Brandrith anecdote book, didn't you?
Yeah, a theater anecdote book.
The word fact would be questionable.
But yes, I did.
But there was...
So there was a guy who was called William McCready.
And it was early 19th century Shakespearean plays that he was in.
And he forgot basically to put blood on his hand because he was in Macbeth and he needed blood on his hand.
And he went to the side of the stage and it wasn't there.
It wasn't on the side and he desperately needed it.
But there happened to be a bystander there.
So he punched him in the nose.
And he'll swipe the blood off his nose and ram back on.
Yeah.
According to Giles.
And that's where it falls down.
That's incredible.
But what happens when you die?
What do you mean?
What would happen to you as a person if you died?
What would you...
I think we...
What would you become?
A ghost.
I got so into theater ghosts.
Oh, right.
Researching this.
There are so many.
Yeah, yeah.
Some of them are really tragic.
So actually where this woman died of laughter at the Theatre Royal Jury Lane.
Yes.
They're kind of...
They've got...
I think it's the most haunted theatre in the world.
Or they claim that, you know.
And their kind of main event, their big star is the...
What's his name?
The man in grey.
Okay.
Who can be seen on like the upper circle, I think.
And he just like has a big cloak and is very menacing.
And it's actually founded in truth.
Because when it was being renovated in the 1800s,
they kind of found a bit of a fake bit of the wall.
And they looked into it and it was a little cubby hole.
And inside that cubby hole was a skeleton of a man with a dagger through his chest.
Wow.
And that's the exact place where this ghost has been spotted for centuries.
Very cool.
Dan believes it.
The theory of everything else.
I think I feel like that would be retroactively have been inserted into a wall in order to...
Really?
Yeah, I've got very skeptical recently.
Wow.
We need to move on, guys, to our next fact.
Well, laughter can be very dangerous, right?
Yeah.
So there was a study from the University of Birmingham.
It was a meta-analysis, so they looked at loads of papers.
And they found that laughter can cause abdominal hernia, dislocated jaw, incontinence, fainting,
infectious diseases, because when you laugh, you breathe in a lot and you get lots of germs
in your mouth.
Yeah?
Thanks for coming, everybody.
There's a thing called Bohava's syndrome, which is you laugh so much that you rupture
your esophagus.
That can happen.
But despite this, they have laughing contests.
And this is becoming quite common in America now.
Basically, you go in and you just try and make each other laugh.
And there's loads of different types of laugh.
Best giggle and best knee-slapping laugh and best belly laugh and stuff like that.
And apparently, the woman who won the American Championship last year, she didn't tell anyone
until afterwards, but she pissed her pants in the first round.
Oh.
Wow.
Is that an illegal move?
I...
It feels like it must be, right?
Yeah.
Wow.
It was only like a couple of years ago.
I pissed myself while laughing.
And it's honestly, it's one of those moments where it's not embarrassing.
It's great.
It's a really wonderful feeling.
You feel like you've done laughter next level.
You feel like you've...
What was it?
It was a late night.
I was quite drunk.
Someone said a joke.
And I just laughed so hard that I just...
And it wasn't even like a little bit of wee.
It was like...
Like, total flood.
And I...
Honestly, I did not apologise.
I was like, "Guys, you will need to try this.
I think we've forgotten how great this feels."
OK, well, we've got three more facts.
(LAUGHTER)
OK, it is time for fact number two.
And that is James.
My fact this week is that the first modern water bed
was filled with jelly rather than water.
The problem was that it was too heavy to move
and started to go rancid after a few weeks.
Isn't that incredible that it was jelly?
I find that one of the most astonishing facts.
Yeah, it makes sense, really, doesn't it?
If you want something nice and soft to lie on.
So was it the bed, like, kind of the mold?
The jelly mold, if you like, and you pour it in
and then it sets?
Oh, I see what you're saying.
Yeah, I guess it must have been, really,
because you'd be weird to just shove in solid jelly.
I'm not quite sure.
He also used cornstarch as well,
so cornstarch would be soft,
but then it's non-Newtonian,
so as you sort of push on it, it would get more solid.
But again, that went rancid as well.
What's a liquid that doesn't go rancid?
But he started it not as a bed, it started as a chair.
Yeah, so Charles Hall this is, right?
Yeah, Charles Hall.
So it was called the very first thing he invented.
It was called the incredibly horrible thing,
and it was a chair.
It weighed 300 pounds, it had liquid starch inside it,
and it had a vinyl skin.
And the point was that when you sat into it,
the chair would creep up around you,
because you were molding into it like that.
It sits on you?
Kind of.
Eventually, yeah.
Okay, so he made that,
but what he really, really wanted to do
was make an entire room that was a water bed/chair.
Oh, wow.
So it was almost like a bit like a padded cell, I suppose.
But you would walk in, close the door,
and wherever you were, you would just sort of sink into the wall
or sink into the floor.
Oh, my God.
But it was only because it was so expensive to make
that he decided to go for the water bed instead.
Gosh.
What was expensive,
manufacturing the jelly or the materials?
Well, the thing is, if you want to buy a room,
you kind of need to have to buy a house as well.
Do you know what I mean?
Yeah, good point.
Like, renovate your whole house to do that,
whereas if you just want to buy a bed or a chair,
you could rent.
Yes, you could.
Oh, but I don't think I'd want to rent a water bed.
No?
No, I mean you could rent a flat
and put your water bed in there.
Yeah, you could do that as well.
Have any of you ever slept on a water bed?
Yeah, my parents used to have one.
I don't think I have.
When I was a kid.
Really?
They're so uncomfortable.
Yeah.
Oh, are they?
They're horrible.
I've read about them and said they're amazing.
Like, they're the equivalent of pissing yourself while laughing.
But maybe mine was like, it was a friend's parents' bed
when I was a kid.
And it was like being seasick.
It would like move.
It was honestly vile.
Huh.
And it was really cold.
Like, they hadn't heated the water.
Oh, but you can get those now.
Oh, thank God.
Okay, well, that's all changed.
No, Charles Hall, these days, who invented this thing,
what, 50 years ago.
Yeah.
He now, he has two water beds now.
No, that doesn't sound very impressive,
but he's got, because they come in different,
it's different bladders.
So you can see how many bladders are there in your water bed.
So he's got one king-size single bladder.
Oh, wow.
But he's also...
If only you had a king-size bladder that night.
(LAUGHTER)
He's also got a, in his guest room,
he's got a double mattress which has adjacent double bladders,
so you can heat one if you want your bed a bit warmer
than whoever you're sleeping next to.
Oh, really?
Oh, that's excellent.
You can hot water bottle your...
Yeah.
Your bed is the hot water bottle.
Wow.
Oh, you're actually selling it.
Maybe we should look at one, guys.
That's incredible.
This first one was...
The one that Hall invented it, I think it was 1968, he invented it.
He called it the Pleasure Pit.
And we should probably talk about the slightly...
There was a slightly sexy reputation they had.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
One of the manufacturers in the early days was called Wet Dream.
(LAUGHTER)
There was an advert...
I don't know, it's not great advert,
but it said, "She'll admire you for your car.
"She'll respect you for your position,
"and she'll love you for your water bed."
So, it was a kind of...
Well, there was lots of...
Creepy.
He had that to begin with, so he had invented it.
He had patented it, but everyone just did sort of spin-off water beds.
And he said that there was one company he noticed that it was sort of sexy,
because, like, their other products were orgy butter and things like that, right?
(LAUGHTER)
And then, when you read into it...
Orgy butter?
And I did a lot of Googling.
I'm so sorry.
(LAUGHTER)
We had to switch to orgy marge because of the cost of living.
Sorry.
So, orgy butter was a thing.
And then, when you look into, as you say, the sexual connotations
about the early sales of the water bed.
So, a lot of it was that it was basically like having a threesome,
because the bed acted as the third person,
because it moulded around you as you...
It feels like a third person as part of the...
Hang on, buddy.
I'm sorry.
Just, like, let's just, like, zoom out on this.
Taking this, like, "I'm just telling you about my experiences."
Well, these are the facts.
Well, you're telling us a lot of stuff.
Your parents did have one, so you probably conceived in it, were you?
Probably.
Are you from a water bed?
Oh, God.
You're a water baby.
That's nice.
(LAUGHTER)
'Cause, like, I don't want to be, like, let's not get too graphic,
but, like, there's got to be a purchase problem.
Supposedly not.
Like, supposedly not.
It's a water bed.
Like, you're, like, sloshing around.
Apparently.
I mean, they were very popular.
I know they were popular.
At one point, I think a fifth of mattresses being sold
were water bed mattresses.
Yeah, I read that.
I thought that was...
In 1987, which is the year I was born.
Insane.
(LAUGHTER)
And Hugh Hefner famously bought one for the Playboy Mansion
that was upholstered in Tasmanian possum hair.
(LAUGHTER)
Isn't that the most disgusting thing you've ever...
Also, 'cause they're not...
Ever heard.
They're not very big.
So many Tasmanian possums has.
Yeah.
So it had this reputation for being very, kind of,
like, asexual aid.
'Cause, yeah, 'cause another tagline for it was,
"Two things are better on a water bed
than one of them's sleep."
Mmm.
I know.
Like, one in five kinky people are just, like,
getting off, well, your parents, one of them.
Yeah.
Two of them.
Two of them, yeah.
Getting off on water beds.
And honestly, it must have felt so sick.
'Cause it's the worst thing to sleep on.
Isn't there a point where you stop...
If you stop moving, the bed will eventually stop moving?
No. No, it keeps moving.
Oh, OK.
You're kind of like...
You're lost at sea.
It's an extraordinary experience.
I can't...
But that's another...
I could imagine you ringing up the Coast Guard.
(LAUGHTER)
Where are you?
Away from the sexual side,
it was also seen as quite therapeutic.
So, for example, the friends of Charles Hall,
when he first invented it, said,
"Well, you should name it 'The Bed Womb',"
because it feels womb-like.
It feels right to...
It's a good line.
Get a bed-womb for your bedroom.
Oh, call yourself a therapist.
That's...
And then there was, in 1988,
the American Journal of Disease of Children
published an article in which they said that
for infants that were born to drug-addicted mothers,
if you kept them on water beds rather than bassinets,
that would be better for them.
This sort of constant, womb-like movement.
Oh, right.
Going on as they sleep.
Yeah.
So, it was seen as therapeutic as well.
Well, the thing is that he did invent the modern water bed,
but actually there were earlier ones,
and they were used therapeutically.
So, they were used during the war to prevent bed sores.
These weren't like the ones that we had in the '80s,
but they were just kind of like...
I don't know, like, you know one of those blow-up mattresses
but with water inside of it?
Yeah.
Mark Twain wrote about them.
Elizabeth Gaskell wrote about them.
Charles Hall couldn't get a patent originally
because they'd been described by Robert A. Heinlein.
Quite a few of his books mentioned them.
And when he tried to get a patent, they went,
"Well, it's in all these science fiction books,
so you can't have invented it."
So, he had to change a few things to get that.
Oh, right.
But when they became quite lame, which was quite quickly,
so they were, like, massive in the early '80s, right?
And then by the late '80s, they were really passe,
like, no one really wanted them anymore.
And they had all these water beds.
They didn't know what to do with them.
And they gave them to dairy farmers,
and the cows would sit on them.
Oh, and that's all these films they still do.
The Queen's Cows.
They famously sleep on water beds.
The King's Cows.
Well, now the King's Cows, yeah.
Well, I don't know if he's changed it, though,
but, you know...
Sure, okay, all right.
I've been waiting 70 years to kick those cows off that bed.
My cows now.
That's what he was waiting for.
So, most, if you're...
They're so heavy. As you say, they're so heavy.
Like, a normal...
The most impractical thing ever in real life.
Like, a normal mattress is quite heavy, you know?
You fill it with water, you're joking, you know?
It's like...
So, some of them can weigh 900 kilos
if you've got a big double or a king's...
That's a lot.
And there's a concern in some buildings,
if you're in a flat or you're on an upper floor, obviously,
and, you know, they'll all go through the floor.
Yeah.
And most New York leases contain a standard clause,
which says no water beds.
Right.
Probably because of, like, it's a bit...
You know, maybe it's just bureaucracy, but...
But in California, on the other coast,
the civil code says landlords cannot discriminate
against people who own water beds...
No.
As long as they have taken out waterbed insurance.
Right.
The responsible thing to do.
It is.
Well, I quite like, as well, in 1990,
speaking of California,
the Compton Fire Department,
within their fire station,
changed all of the mattresses to water mattresses.
Not so that, like, if there was an emergency...
Just if they needed more water.
No.
No, no.
It was the effect on their back, apparently.
Someone had said, "I sleep better on a water bed,"
and so they all...
But that's all been disproven,
because it doesn't actually help,
because there's a lot of things that help, like,
your posture or, like, your joints.
That isn't true.
Really?
Okay.
Yeah.
Apparently it's not true.
Right.
I'm just obsessed that there was a waterbed magazine.
Oh, yeah, I know.
In the '80s.
I tried finding it today.
Yeah, so did I.
Oh, my God.
No, we need a soapy.
Cool.
Great.
Okay.
But...
Brilliant.
I bought us a lot of orgy butter.
Oh, great.
Okay, good.
Good.
Can I flip it over?
What?
I mean...
What other interpretation are you...
I was double-checking,
because I thought I might have heard you say,
"Flick your mattress," and I wasn't sure.
How often do you flick your mattress?
Twice a night.
No, how often do you flip it?
Well, this is what's amazing.
Not as often as I should, I'm sure.
And I was planning tomorrow to flip my mattress.
Get out of here.
No, get lost.
Yeah, absolutely, because both Vanella and I
are on the wrong sides at the moment.
It's gone soft on the sides.
On the outer edge?
Yeah, on the outer edge.
Why is it not soft on the outer edge?
That's not going to help, though,
because it's still going to be the outer edge.
I feel...
I feel like it's upside down anyway,
because I noticed recently I've been sleeping on a zip
the whole time,
and I'm pretty sure that's the wrong side.
Okay.
Some orgy butter.
We'll just sort that right out.
Just rub it in, you'll be fine.
Anyway, half Americans claim they flip it every six months,
and I just think half Americans are liars.
I think no one possibly does it that much.
But why should you flip?
I think...
I think it's...
So...
No, it's...
I can tell you exactly why.
You get soft on the outside,
and then you fall off the bed.
That's why we're doing it.
Is it not to try and air it out
a little bit or something?
I don't know.
So it's not the same bit of you
always hitting the same bit of the mattress?
Right, okay.
And so it refreshes it a bit,
it moves the scene around.
Because mattresses are disgusting,
because they're full of, like,
skin cells, sweat, like, bed bugs.
So I think this is the way
of just sort of redistributing
the skin cells and sweat.
You should really get rid...
They're so expensive, mattresses.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
They're, like, thousands of pounds.
You can't just...
Because you should really replace them regularly, I think,
but that's why you should get a waterbed.
Oh, yeah, because you just changed the water.
Well, not even, you know.
Because water doesn't go rancid.
Unlike jelly.
Yeah.
To bring us back to the start of the fact.
I need to move us on to our next fact, guys.
OK, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that there used to be a room
in the Pentagon where employees met specifically
to have Pokemon battles.
(LAUGHTER)
This is a discovery that was made back in 2016.
Was there a situation room elsewhere in the Pentagon
where other officials monitored the progress
of those Pokemon battles with big screens?
Do you think they have tables where they're pushing a Pikachu along?
Yeah, exactly, yeah.
(LAUGHTER)
That's the situation room. That's what it's for, yeah.
So this is Pokemon Go.
There was a huge craze, particularly about...
Still is.
Yeah, but there was a mo...
Well, James is...
What's that T-shirt you're wearing, James?
This is, I mean, this fact is up my street
because I do like Pokemon and changing regimes
in countries that I don't like, so...
Ah!
(LAUGHTER)
James loves...
Getting a bit political tonight?
Yeah.
James loves Pokemon Go so much.
I don't know if we've ever said this.
He likes it so much that when we went for a meeting,
for the first time ever, we were going to have
a Book of the Year, no such thing as a fish book,
and we were going to pitch it.
We ended up being a bit late to the meeting
because we were following James,
but it turned out James had spotted a very rare Pokemon
down the road from where we were,
and we just blindly followed him,
and then we were like, "Where are we?"
And he was like, "Yes! Snuffle off a gussle, whoever it is!"
(LAUGHTER)
When was that week they did a Sesame Street special,
wasn't it, of Pokemon Go?
OK, so here's the thing.
It's Pokemon Go, and Pokemon Go was the app,
and you would go and you would collect the Pokemons
in various different places.
You had to walk around, didn't you?
You would walk around, and yeah.
And then what they had as part of the app,
I've never personally played it,
so this is 101 for people that do.
You have gyms where you can take the Pokemon 2,
the Pokemon you have collected,
and they can train there,
but they can also battle for dominance of the gym,
and those would be plopped all over the world
in random spots,
and it just so happened that one was in the Pentagon,
and so anyone who was an employee there,
and it would be specifically employees,
because if you ever go on a tour of the Pentagon,
you have to leave your phone,
you're not allowed to bring your phone in with you,
so it was specifically employees
that were going to a very specific spot,
and then they'd battle each other for dominance of this gym,
and this was a huge problem
because the Pokemon app can track where people are going,
so their worry within the Pentagon
was that it shows the routes that people are taking,
so there were secret passages within the Pentagon,
or even just mapping out the general landscape.
That's something that the information
could possibly be hacked into and retrieved.
Someone might know that the Pentagon is pentagon-shaped.
I mean, that would be awful.
Do you imagine?
So they said, "No more Pokemon Go in the Pentagon."
Do you know why the Pentagon is pentagon-shaped?
I think this is amazing.
No.
It's because they were going to build it
on a pentagon-shaped piece of land,
and so they wanted the right shape of building
for that piece of land,
so it had to be a pentagon,
and then they decided to move it somewhere else,
and they thought,
"Well, we've gone so far with this shape.
We might as well keep it."
That's literally the only reason.
I mean, there's lots of good things about it being pentagon-shaped,
but the reason is just it was supposed to go on this bit of land.
That's incredible.
What are some of the good things?
Well, a circle is very good
because you can get from one bit of a circle
to another bit of a circle really quickly,
and a pentagon is a bit like a circle,
but it's got straight edges,
so it's easier to build the circle.
Yeah.
It's more of a circle than a square.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Less than a hexagon.
Oh, sure.
Food for thought tonight on...
And in the centre of the kind of circular pentagon
is a now-closed hotdog stand.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
During the Cold War,
the Russians always had at least two missiles
that seemed at this hotdog stand
because they thought that that was the pentagon's
most top-secret meeting place.
It was just where people got lunch,
but they were convinced that it was...
Was it because they saw people kind of congregate here?
Yeah.
And they'd be like, "That has to be the...
That's the heart of the pentagon,
when actually it was just a hotdog stand."
I know.
Was it part of the pentagon, this hotdog stand?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay. It was inside.
I still feel like if the missiles hit it,
the other bit of pentagon would suffer some damage.
Yeah.
They're not really so specific the missile that it's like...
No, true.
I mean, you know.
But it's fascinating, I think.
Did they know that, the hotdog owners at the time?
I think they did because everyone used to call it Ground Zero, didn't they?
That was the nickname for it.
The reason being that if the Russians hit,
it would become Ground Zero and become flattened.
Blimey.
Right.
I've read a thing that the pentagon own.
It's just their cool stuff division.
They own a laser, which that's not the cool bit,
which can analyse who you are based on your heartbeat alone.
Really?
So they'll...
You know, you have it...
All of our hearts have their unique cardiac signature,
how our hearts beat.
Yeah.
And they can point that laser at you from 200 metres away
and say, "There's Dan."
Or whatever it might be.
What if I've just gone up a flight of stairs or something?
Would it change my heartbeat or...?
It would change, wouldn't it?
But maybe it changes with the same...
But it's still recognisably you.
Yeah, they go, "That's James."
And he's very unfair.
There's a few flaws to this thing, though.
It's called Jetson, which is what they've developed.
And the flaws consist of the fact that,
A, we don't really have that bigger database
of people's unique heartbeats.
So when everyone's coming, they can go,
"Ah, no, no, I didn't do that. That's right."
And then the second flaw, and this is, you know,
200 metres away we can do this, is their claim.
The other problem is, yes, they can do it
if you're wearing a T-shirt, but if you're wearing a coat,
they can't get you.
Yeah, so it's half-useful.
Yeah, it's not as good as the fingerprint yet,
or the eyeball.
The lychee?
The lychee.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I was reading about the Pentagon generally,
about tour guides, because you can go there.
I imagine, Jamie, that's somewhere that you might have gone,
but maybe not yet.
I haven't.
But you love this kind of stuff, right?
Yeah, I actually have a friend that works at the Pentagon.
He didn't reply to my emails about fun facts about the Pentagon.
So the security is really high, guys.
We're safe, you know.
But one of the things is, there's stats
that you get told about the tour guides that work there,
and one of it is that they walk two to three miles per day,
but entirely backwards,
because when they're doing their tours,
they never turn around to lead,
because they always need eyes on the people
that they're taking on the tour guide.
So they guide themselves...
What?
Yeah, they guide themselves by landmarks.
So as they're walking back the go, there's the fire extinguisher.
That means, you know, ten steps until you get to the next corner,
then I can round it like that.
And so, yeah, every day, two to three miles of backward walking
is what they get.
And there's loads of ramps.
That's really quite impressive to walk down a ramp backwards.
You know, there's like no lift to the Pentagon.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It was built with one lift.
Yes.
Because it was built during...
Because it was made of concrete.
Yeah, it was made of concrete.
In fact, it's nicknamed the Concrete Cobweb, which is cool.
And it had one lift for 33,000 people in the early days,
because you can't make lifts out of concrete, I suppose.
Right.
And they were saving steel for the war efforts.
They didn't want to...
Yeah, yeah.
But they've now put some more in.
They've now got dozens and dozens.
I love the idea of you repeatedly emailing your friend,
who's in the middle of looking at a screen,
and there's like a bomb counter on it.
I know.
It's somewhere in Ulaanbaatar, but I don't know where.
Just ping, ping.
Hi, just wondering if you saw my previous...
I was like, fun fact, request email.
Is it true that they used to have office chair races down the ramps
in the Pentagon?
That's all I wanted to know.
I think what he's really going is,
"God damn it, snuffle-uffagus, come on, win this Pokemon battle!"
No, we can't, because they've banned the Pokemon.
Oh, yeah, of course.
They also banned...
Yeah, well, that was the whole thing,
that you aren't allowed it anymore, right?
Yeah, it's out, it's out.
Because they're banning things left and right at the Pentagon,
like TikTok's now banned at the Pentagon.
But they also banned Furbies.
Oh, yeah.
In 1999.
Because they record what you say?
Well, they don't, but they kind of marketed themselves as that...
It's like the thinking toy or the chatty toy or something.
I don't know.
And they were, like, concerned that it would be a security risk
that they would, like, yeah, record what you were saying
and then say it back to you.
That's so funny.
I think it's fair enough to ask people not to bring Furbies in.
It's a petty aspect or the spying thing.
It's weird having to bring your toy to work at the Pentagon.
Well, you say that.
The Pokemon Go is just as kind of...
Yeah?
...maybe childish, I don't want to, you know.
But the...
I think we say "for all ages", rather than...
Sure, sure.
I'm glad you made three in the end.
Three episodes of "No such thing as they say it".
Yeah.
Going on behind.
I know that Furbies was really interesting, wasn't it?
Because they...
The way they worked is they had a stock number of English words they had.
And they had a stock number of Furbies words.
They were just like...
All that kind of stuff.
Yeah.
And it started off, they could just say the Furbie words.
And then as you owned it for longer and longer,
it kind of put more and more of the English words into the vocabulary.
And so people thought that they were picking up words that you were saying to them.
But actually it was just programmed to do that.
But that's a bit like how it is with children, isn't it?
Yeah.
Like they start off talking complete nonsense,
and then by the end of their saying, like, "Nah, nah, or dog, or whatever."
Oh, no.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So that's kind of...
Maybe that's why they made the Furbie like that.
Yeah, I guess so.
Or maybe all children are actually fake.
Prove me wrong.
Which is more likely, Andy, I don't know.
But yeah, like the CEO of the company that made Furbies had to come out and say,
"This isn't true.
"Our Furbies actually aren't as clever as we've been lying about."
Wow.
And he also said, you know, there was a rumor that they could send...
They had enough technologies to send something into space.
And they said that one woman...
Wait, wait, wait, sorry.
Yeah.
Just break that down a bit.
Wait, what are the...
Somebody thought the Furbies had so much power
that they could send a rocket into space.
Are we talking about a complete Cape Canaveral setup?
Yes.
We can entirely start my Furbie.
I don't know, Furbies are all the deaths.
There's a Furbie in it with the briefcase going on to the ship.
Actually, if Elon Musk zips down his jacket,
it's just Furbies all the way up.
He is a Furbie.
What does that mean?
They could send a rocket to space.
It's the AI worry of its day, I guess, right?
Yeah, it wasn't true.
That's what he was saying.
'Cause he also said that there was a woman who was absolutely insistent
that her Furbie was singing Italian operas.
That also wasn't true.
Oh, my God.
But she was hearing...
She was convinced that she taught this Furbie an aria,
and she's like, 'My Furbie's really good at opera.'
And he's like, 'They literally don't have that capability.'
So they kind of had to backtrack on all of their marketing campaign.
Wow.
These were like, yeah, clever toys,
but they were actually all pre-programmed.
Oh, my God.
Scam, wasn't it?
It could be a haunted Furbie.
And that's a ghost, I will believe it.
Okay, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Imagine the next, like, crude moon mission
that gets there and finds they have built their own society.
Without us noticing.
The Furbies beat us to it.
Damn it.
The dark side of the moon is entirely Furbie.
Owned and operated now.
Have you heard of Tia Pikachu?
So she is a Chilean schoolteacher,
and they've had a load of protests in Chile against the government,
and she decided to go dressed as a giant Pikachu.
The reason being that her seven-year-old son
had maxed out her husband's credit card
buying Detective Pikachu merchandise.
They managed to send loads of it back,
but some of it they couldn't send back,
and this giant sort of inflatable Pikachu
they couldn't send back.
Okay, so then they have some protests in Chile,
and she decides, 'Well, I'm just going to go dressed as a Pikachu,
because why not, it's a protest.'
And she just became really, really, really famous,
because there was video of her being water,
like, fired with water.
Cannon?
Water cannon, yeah,
in a big Pikachu costume being forced back.
She was shot with rubber bullets,
dressed as Pikachu.
It's absolutely amazing,
but because she became so famous,
she is part of the team
who are writing the New Chilean Constitution.
So after the protest,
they decided that they were going to write a new constitution.
So every five clauses, it's just going to say,
'Pika, pika, pika!'
It is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that in 1972,
a family who had survived a shipwreck
kept themselves alive
by giving each other turtle blood enemas.
Guys, it's a light-hearted and funny fact.
I just imagine, like,
that family seeing each other at Christmas.
Yeah.
You know, they haven't said, 'Shall we talk about it?'
No, let's never talk about that again.
Never talk about it again.
No, go on.
Give us the context.
This comes from an amazing piece
that was in The Financial Times
by a writer called Kitty Drake,
and she was interviewing people
who had real knowledge of shipwreck
and being cast away.
And she spoke to a man called Douglas Robertson,
who was sailing around the world with his family,
his siblings and his parents.
He was 18 years old,
and their yacht was attacked by killer whales.
So they were halfway across the Pacific.
They completely battered the yacht.
The family all abandoned ship into a small dinghy
that was, I think there were seven people,
six or seven people in this dinghy
that was designed for one fewer
than the number of people who ended up in it.
They were 200 miles from the Galapagos,
and the wind was going in the wrong direction.
So they were really in trouble.
They spent 38 days stranded in the Pacific,
and they were sailing towards the doldrums.
They were trying to get weirdly to the doldrums
because there was a better chance of being spotted
and detected where they were heading to.
So the doldrums is where there's not as much wind or...
Exactly. Sorry.
Yeah, the region where there's no wind.
But it does get lots of rain.
So anyway, so they're in big trouble.
They did manage to get some turtles on board,
and they had to hunt the turtles that approached them,
and they used their blood as soup.
So that's a good thing.
Then, unfortunately, the water ran very low,
and they only had the old fish-polluted rainwater
in the bottom of their dinghy.
And it wasn't safe to drink.
But the mother of the family, Lynn, was a nurse,
and she realised you could absorb it safely
through your bottom.
And so everyone in the family got a rain...
Guys, this is funnier than we're...
I feel like there's tension in the room.
They all make it. They all made it, and they got picked up.
It was all right.
Oh, spoiler alert. Sorry.
They were all right.
Anyway, she worked out brilliant, an intuition,
that you could absorb it through your bottom.
So everyone in the family got a rain and turtle blood enema,
and it gets into your system,
but it doesn't go through your digestive system.
I'm getting confused when you say the enema bits.
What do you mean?
Up the bum. Squirt it up the bum.
Oh! What have you been researching?
What because I read? I read...
Oh!
Dan, Dan, Dan, Dan.
Just where does the orgy butter go?
Think in those terms.
That's way more disgusting than what I thought.
Yeah, it's horrible.
Cos that's the thing, like, it's not just turtle blood.
Anyways, it's disgusting.
Rain water, it's like infected fish guts.
Water, like, it's foul.
So the point is... But genius.
Yeah, it's genius. I mean, amazing.
If you drink this stuff, it's got all sorts of horrible things in it,
and it can make you really, really sick.
Now, if you go the other way... Yeah, yeah.
...then there's a way for the water to go into your body
through your rectum. Yeah.
But because you're already getting disgusting things
going down there anyway, your body is protected
against those disgusting things. Exactly.
So you can still get the water,
but it won't get the bacteria and all that.
So here's what I thought.
I thought they were removing the rectal membrane from the turtles
and using that as a bag to collect the water.
Genuinely, that's what I thought.
A bag to collect the water?
Well, you need to collect water to drink it through your fucking mouth.
It's your fucking mouth, right?
How much water are you collecting?
It's your fucking shell on it.
If you want to keep water...
If you ever get a turtle and you want to keep water,
don't take the little bag out of it, Tainus.
Just turn it upside down.
We've got to get to its asshole.
Jesus Christ. Wow.
Turns out it's Dan's last appearance on "Nose & Sins & Fish" as well.
I'd love to see you on, like, one of those reality shit-making shows.
Meanwhile, on Dan's Island,
I think it's up to God for a bad to worse.
Cool, that makes you...
Weirdly, I still think your one makes less sense.
Feeding water up your butt.
Incredibly clever.
Incredibly clever, and it is the thing that saved their lives.
They were really on the struggling.
And they all just trusted Lynn when she said that?
She's a nurse.
I get that, but how often are you...?
She's a nurse, though.
That's an off-common knowledge, I would say.
I don't know. Wow.
What's amazing is that there was the group...
There was the husband and the wife,
and I think they had...
Was it three or four kids?
It was three. There were four, but one of them got off
before this leg of the journey.
That was lucky. Fuck that.
It's cool. I'll die. I'll just die.
Someone up. So, in this family
of everyone putting stuff up their ass,
there was one guy who'd only just met them.
Did you read his name?
He was called Robin Williams, weirdly.
And he'd just taken a job on the boat
in return for his birth, and, you know, just...
Yeah.
It sounds like such a tough journey.
Oh, God. They had to spend six hours a day
just blowing the dinghy up, you know,
just because it was constantly losing air.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
What have they got to do, to be fair?
Well, you know, pass of the time.
And they eventually got back, didn't they?
They did. And then the husband and wife
just immediately divorced. No.
Really? Yeah, I'm afraid so.
So, the guy who was kind of
took them on this trip, Douglas,
he wrote a book
and went to live in the med.
And his wife became a farmer.
Oh, wow. Oh, because they were farmers before they said that.
They were, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, they completely, they split up, yeah.
Gosh. Oh, that's sad.
That is sad. Yeah, yeah.
Did you hear, there was a recent
someone stranded out in the ocean
and having to get by with what materials they had.
There was a guy called Elvis,
and he was found
120 nautical miles northwest
of Columbia's
Poreto Boliva. I don't know how to pronounce that.
Lovely. Yeah. And he survived.
He wrote help on the hull
of his sailboat, and so someone saw that.
But he was stuck out there for a long time.
And he was 24 days, I think,
he was out there and he survived almost
exclusively on tomato ketchup
from Heinz. Wow.
And so that became the story when he got back.
He found him after being missing all this time.
And then Heinz decided that they wanted
to give him a new boat because they thought this was amazing.
I thought you were about to say,
"Give him some more ketchup." Yeah, yeah.
No, that's a much better,
that's good PR by Heinz, yeah, yeah.
So, they've done it. They've done that.
Well, for ages, they couldn't find him.
So, he disappeared again, but just into his normal life
because he was, you know, he didn't make a big fuss of it.
So, there was a huge campaign to find
the missing boat guy who then,
and they found Elvis, basically.
Yeah, a hard hashtag to use,
but they found him
and he's now got his boat. That's great.
Tomato ketchup is exclusively, yeah,
what he was surviving on. Gosh.
You can, just a tip
for any of us who get shipwrecked,
do have a plastic bag if you can.
If you don't have a turtle to have.
Yes.
Why would that be? Well,
you use a bag of water.
What are you using this bag of water for, guys?
Drinking out of? Making fire.
You can make fire with a bag of water.
Oh, like a lens.
Like a lens. If it's a clear bag,
do make sure it's a clear bag.
Lot of caveats on this.
Not a bag for life.
Ironically, a bag for life wouldn't work.
That is.
And you'd be kicking yourself, wouldn't you?
Pay 30 papers.
No, a bog standard, like a clear plastic bag.
If you can make it into a round shape,
you can use that to focus the rays of the sun
onto your tinder.
And then, and it makes fire.
And if you don't have a plastic bag,
you can use a light bulb.
If you don't have a light bulb.
Just have an idea.
Excuse my ignorance.
Like, would it not
melt the plastic?
Or is that a stupid thing to ask?
It's not a stupid question, but I don't think it would.
I don't know why.
Oh, the point at which the rays focus
the hottest point, which is not on the surface of the bag.
It's on whatever you're pointing at.
Interesting.
I was reading some advice from a guy called Paul Hart,
who is the Royal Navy's...
He's a Lieutenant Commander for the Royal Navy.
And he was asked, if you get shipped wrecked on an island,
what should you be doing in order to survive?
So, he wrote this big list of stuff.
And so, here's the quiz-like
moment here.
So, your boat
has crashed on the shore,
or your airplane has crashed into
the ocean, and you've made it to shore.
What is the first thing
that you should be collecting in order to survive?
From the aircraft?
You're on an island, yeah. So, the food.
OK, so food would be a good...
Well, I would say the eight
single CDs that I carry
with me everywhere I go.
A copy of the Bible that you always have.
A copy of the Bible. And what would your luxury be?
A lovely bottle of Tabasco sauce.
Oh, lovely!
So, the answer is, he says...
No, no, no. A lifetime supplier of Marmite.
Sorry, sorry, sorry. Oh, OK.
Get that right, yeah.
Orgy butter if that's not available, yeah.
One of the same to him.
Life jacket. Life jacket, no.
The seats can be used as floatation devices.
I'm trying to remember what they've said to me.
Things that you're going to take from your wreckage,
or things that are on the island?
No, things that you take from the wreckage.
Something to... The radio from the...
A knife, no. Well, knife is, yes, it's up there.
But he says... A clear bag.
A clear plastic bag.
That's it, that's it.
He says Wellington boots.
Oh, OK. What? Sorry, when do you get on a plane?
Do they just hand you some Wellington boots?
He's saying any kind of...
A very strong footwear that you can have.
Right, OK. Because you're going to be going into the ocean a lot
in order to get food.
You're going to be travelling, and injury is the thing you need to avoid.
Most of all, and your feet are most likely to be getting injured.
That's really interesting. Because actually, on that Ryanair thing,
it tells you to take off your high heels
before you jump on the slide, doesn't it?
Yes. And you're saying...
You're saying keep them on?
Is that...?
No, so that's the biggest thing.
That's interesting, yeah.
Wellies, it is quite a niche thing,
as James just said, to have on that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It makes sense.
I would personally get a knife.
Because then you can fashion some sort of, like...
Fashion... Make some... Oh, come on, babe.
Not Wellies! Come on!
But you could, like, get, like...
Either you're going to carve your own...
Or you could cut your own way.
Do you know what I mean? Like, a knife surely is the most important thing,
because that can... That's very important.
Actually, you can use the, like, shoes to yourself.
You can tap the rubber tree, and then...
With a simple mould fashion from Bach...
LAUGHTER
You've got your own Wellie factory, then.
Look!
You could trade the knife for some Wellies
if there's some local Wellie owners.
There are local Wellie owners.
I don't think you need the Wellies.
You can just leave.
You're probably...
You're in North Devon.
LAUGHTER
Oh, my God. That's so funny.
I read the US Army Survival Manual.
Oh, yeah. Oh, of course you do.
To see if enemas were part of their...
Yeah. ...suggestion.
There is one mention of enemas
in the whole Survival Manual,
and the idea is to use warm water enemas
as a way to treat hypothermia.
Oh, OK. Yeah, apparently.
It's good because it warms you up from the inside,
if you think about that. Oh, right.
The thing that they said to drink
is the aqueous fluid
found along the spine and the eyes
of large fish. Right.
Oh, gosh. Is that interesting?
Is that because it's less salty than...?
Yeah, so everything else that's in the fish,
all the other Wellie fluids,
have got lots of protein, lots of fat,
so it's going to make you more thirsty.
But just the water around the eyes
and the water around the spinal fluid,
that stuff is just perfect.
I'm going to mention this guy, because one of the other things
at this Paul Hart that I was talking about,
the guy who said that Wellington boots
are what you need it. Oh, yeah.
One of the things that he said that was really important
was having positive mentality.
That's the main thing.
As soon as you crash, you go,
"Fantastic! This is great!"
And if you can keep that mindset, then you're going to be fine.
And that really kind of is...
That comes into play when you read about the story
of Jose Salvador Alvorenga,
who was a guy who was out at sea
with one other person for 438 days.
They were lost out at sea,
and it was a positive mentality that kept him going.
And when he was interviewed by a journalist
who wrote a book about it, he said,
"What's the thing that you remember most about it?"
And he said, "My imagination.
I imagine good food, and
I have the best sex in my life."
And he used to... So they used to...
The two guys used to see the planes that would fly over,
that would never see them,
and they would go, "What do you think they're eating up there?"
And they would picture the food that they were...
No, they never... They...
They both would then have...
Also, the best food of their lives on a plane.
Has he been on a plane?
(LAUGHTER)
Bit of stale bread, and something in a little
reheated tray. Yeah, great.
Better than whatever they were eating up
their assholes at that time.
It was that smell. They're on a dinghy.
And so... And yeah.
Diggy food is terrible, you know.
What's that all about? Yeah.
(LAUGHTER)
They used to... Both of them would do this.
They would sit, but him particularly,
he'd sit there every day, he'd close his eyes,
he'd imagine that they'd actually crashed onto a beach,
and there was a beautiful woman walking towards him,
and they would have sex, and he said every day
he just had amazing sex in his head,
and that kept him positive. Wow.
Yeah. The other guy died, right?
Did he? I think so, yeah.
(LAUGHTER)
He wasn't positive enough.
God's sake.
Unbelievable.
He was more positive
as he's throwing him off the edge of this dinghy.
(LAUGHTER)
I was going to ask, actually, who...
No, just quickly. Who out of...
Say the three of you got shipwrecked.
I'd die first. Who would you think would survive?
I would die first. The first.
Like, like... I'd die within 30 seconds.
Do you think... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I would start another day. I would start another day.
We're going to have to eat him. We're going to have to eat him.
There's a guy selling willing to do something.
No, no!
Cannibalism returned
to North Devon today.
(LAUGHTER)
Oh, God.
And Dan's probably the most positive, so I guess you win.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. Dan will be having fantastic sex.
(LAUGHTER)
And eating delicious plain food.
Oh, God. What a treat.
(LAUGHTER)
(UPBEAT MUSIC)
All right, we need to wrap up.
That is it. That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @sriviladjames.
@jamesharkin.
@andrewhunterm.
And Jamie. @uncleego.
Yep.
Or you can get us on our group account, which is @nosuchthing.
Or you can go to our website, nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
Do check it out, as well as Club Fish.
Very exciting place.
But that is all for tonight.
Thank God.
Putting an end to this.
Thank you so much, Soho.
That was awesome. Thank you for coming to our show tonight.
And we're going to be back again next week
with another episode, and we'll see you then.
Goodbye!
(CHEERING AND APPLAUSE)
(audience applauding)