(upbeat music)
- Speaking of things under the water, as we were,
and also kind of about space,
there is a guy called Avi Loeb
from the Harvard Smithsonian Center of Astrophysics,
and he's currently looking under the water for some aliens.
- So excited.
- I knew that Dan would like this.
So basically, do you remember there was this rock
that came from outside the solar system
when it was coming through?
It's like a long cigar-shaped rock,
and people thought it might have been an alien.
I think it's called Uma Mora or something.
- Uma Mora, yeah. - Yeah, something like that.
Anyway, there's been another one,
there was another previous one,
and it was coming probably from outside the solar system,
was going really, really fast,
and it actually crashed into the Earth's atmosphere
and went underwater.
And this guy, Avi Loeb, wants to go and find it,
ostensibly so he can study it
and see kind of what rocks it is
and what makes it up.
But then he also says it could be a technological object
created by aliens.
- He believes it might be a beacon
so that it's some sort of boop, boop, boop, boop.
- That's how the second one arrived.
- There you go.
- The second one was following the beacon of the first one.
- Oh, yeah.
- Saw the state of Earth.
I thought, "Oh, I'm actually just gonna pretend
to be a rock."
(all laughing)
- He's actually so cool.
- He's planning to go and find it.
He's got a ship lined up.
And one of the people who might be going on this trip is--
- Dan Shriver.
- I do a second podcast called The Cryptid Factor.
Buttons, who is on it, might become best mates.
Yeah, they hang out all the time.
Avi Loeb is a legit scientist.
This is a kind of him speculating
and going to that different kind of place.
But he's an interesting character.
- It's interesting because he is,
this is a proper scientific thing.
And his alma mater are giving him money for it
and all that kind of stuff.
And they're fine with it.
But every now and then he just keeps going,
it might be aliens or like, "Oh, for God's sake, Avi.
Leave it with the aliens thing.
Let's just talk about the other stuff."
- It gets attention though, doesn't it?
As a scientist, all you have to say,
it's like when we talked about finding like bits of stuff
in Loch Ness and looking for Nessie.
The scientists aren't actually looking for Nessie or aliens.
But if they say they are, that funding's gonna double.
- I think this guy does believe it though.
(all laughing)
I think so, yeah.
- Can I just tell you one really cute thing
about empathy in chimps?
In fact, chimps and bonobos are very similar.
Bonobos are called the pygmy chimp.
And Franz de Waal,
who's another amazing chimp researcher,
witnessed this and it was a bonobo called Cooney.
She was in a glass enclosure and a bird crashed into
the glass walls of her enclosure and fell to the ground.
And so she went up to this bird
and she sort of tried to prop it up right
to try and help it and it fell over again.
So then she picked it up and she threw it a little bit
and it fluttered a little bit, still couldn't fly.
So there's a pause.
Then she picked it up, climbed to the very top of a tree,
held onto the very top of this tree with her legs.
So she's carrying the bird in her hands.
She spread out the wings of the bird with her hands
and threw it off the top of the tree.
- Yeah, it plummeted to it's death.
- It did plummet to the ground.
- Oh no.
- But it was okay, it didn't die.
- She's sorry till then.
- So she did it again and again.
- She actually kept doing it and then she ate it.
No, then she went down and pray sensibly.
She thought, okay, not ready to fly yet.
And then she just guarded it until it was ready to fly again.
- Oh, okay.
- That's lovely.
- Isn't it?
- That's so nice.
- And did it eventually fly?
Do we know?
- Yeah, it eventually flew straight back
into the glass wall actually.
- Amazing.
I read one, 2017, 12 inmates in Alabama escaped a jail
when they tricked the prison guard to letting them outside
by smearing peanut butter on a sign above a door
that read exit so that he couldn't read the word
and said, "Can we go through there?"
And he said, "Sure."
(laughing)
And I have so many questions about this story
because how many jails just have a door
that just leads to a freedom?
- You need an emergency exit in any building, right?
- Yeah, I suppose so.
- Oh God, how do they do that in prisons
with emergency exits?
I've never considered that.
- They must have them.
- But the whole point of the prison is you can't.
- But it leads to the courtyard rather than to the--
- Right, yeah.
- Maybe to their outside area.
I mean, I'm just guessing, but.
- I mean, you get locked in your cell overnight
so they have to, I don't know how to--
- Maybe it's a loophole.
If you're in prison right now and listening,
find the emergency exit.
(laughing)
- There's one door, it's like, yeah, to freedom.
I think what this probably was was a courtyard
and then they had plans to scale the walls.
- Then you would be empty at that time or whatever.
- Yes, exactly, yeah.
- But also, yeah, why didn't you notice
the peanut butter smeared on the sign?
- How does he not know the schematics of the only door
that leads to freedom within his own prison?
- Yeah, it could have been--
- Often lots of questions.
- Secunded from another prison.
- And when it's your first day in the job,
you're grateful for any advice that you can get
from your colleagues as the prisoners will be.
- My colleagues?
(laughing)
- That's probably our now.
- I think of you all as my colleagues.
(laughing)
- I messaged you guys yesterday
because I found out that Tim Allen
was arrested in Kalamazoo Airport.
- Oh yeah.
- 'Cause we talked about Kalamazoo the other day.
I just thought it was--
- In the previous episode, yeah.
- It was interesting.
So he was arrested in Kalamazoo for possession of cocaine.
He provided the names of some other dealers
and got some time.
He went to prison,
but only for three to seven years,
not for a long amount of time.
But the interesting thing
and the reason I'm bringing it up again
is because his first film that he was in
was a film called Tropical Snow.
And it was about people who smuggled cocaine.
- Oh really?
- Yeah.
- Exactly 10 years after he was arrested,
he was in his first ever film about cocaine smuggling
and he was arrested for cocaine smuggling.
- Wow, so he did 10 years ago.
Did he go, no, no, I'm actually method acting.
(laughing)
Did that get him off?
- Yeah.
- So he started his acting career quite late.
Or he was smuggling cocaine aged 10.
- Yeah, I don't know when he was born.
So, yeah, I don't know.
- I wonder if, I read a story about Tim Allen
and that jail, particularly as well, Kalamazoo jail,
which is that they did a refurb of the whole jail
and they got rid of all of the beds.
But the one bed that they've kept,
which is a steel bed,
is the bed that Tim Allen slept in.
- Is that right?
- That's the story that I read.
- That's interesting.
- What do you mean they've got rid of all the beds?
- Well, they've replaced the beds.
- Oh, sir, I think, well, you said they got rid
of all the beds.
- But I said refurb.
Yeah, sorry, so I sort of implied.
- We're getting something new.
- It's an upgrade, a bit as more luxurious.
- It's only one bed now, but it belonged to Tim Allen.
So let's all hop in.
- You know, when he talked about crow's nest,
the first thing I think of is Captain Pugwash,
just because I associate Tom the Cabin Boy
was up in the crow's nest and--
- So that's a cartoon from the 80s?
- Yeah, well, it was 70s.
- But I never actually saw the cartoon, but books.
- And then cartoons.
- Oh, books then cartoons.
- I've read the books.
Oh, maybe the books are written after the cartoons.
I don't know, I wasn't asked to watch TV.
- Are these novelizations?
(laughing)
I love the Tom and Jerry novels, actually.
They're very gripping, pacey.
- Fan fiction, yeah.
So my mum used to read me the fan fiction.
So when I got distracted reading about Captain Pugwash
and I learned something I didn't know,
which is kind of sad, but quite funny.
You know the rumors about Pugwash?
- The Seaman Stains.
- Seaman Stains, exactly.
- Larger the Cabin Boy.
- Yeah.
- Those were characters and that they--
- All this stuff that we were told as kids.
- It was actually filth, yeah.
- And rude names, yeah.
- That it was all just a big cover
and it was a pornographic book.
And it was very easy to disprove.
Even as a six-year-old 'cause you were reading the books
and you were going, "Well, it's called Tom the Cabin Boy."
And there's no one called Seaman Stains.
My dad told me these rumors,
which seems very inappropriate for the age I must have been.
(laughing)
- Mid-read as a kid.
- Yeah, yeah, do you know what--
- Interesting fact, then.
- It says she's called Tom the Cabin Boy here.
But actually, if you watch the play,
which came before the book, which came before the cartoon.
- Anyway, these were all rumors
and they were started by a student newspaper in the 1970s.
But I was reading an interview with the daughter
of John Ryan who wrote Pugwash,
who said her dad was completely dramatized by them.
- Oh, no.
- So he was this really innocent, childlike guy, apparently.
And he, it was seriously upset.
And she said things like, "Yes, there was a pirate willy,
"but back at the time, people didn't think like that."
Back in what time did people not think like that?
- Was there a pirate willy?
- There was a pirate willy.
I bet that's where the students initially got the inspiration.
- I would kill to have been there the first time
he was told that someone had made the connection.
He's going, "Oh, I can't be that bad, can it?"
- Well, pirate willy is a bit of a,
"Oh, okay, but it's just pirate willy."
Well, actually Roger the Cabin Boy
is also a bit of an implicated name.
- But there's not a Roger the Cabin Boy.
It's Tom the Cabin Boy.
- Oh, right.
- So they're all fake.
They're all fake, apart from willy the pirate who's real.
- Yeah, yeah.
So the students could have made them up.
- Didn't realize that.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's all made up.
And there's the Pugwash being some kind of rude slang
for something.
None of that's true.
Master Bates didn't exist.
Master Mates did exist.
So you can see how they made the leap.
- They had a cult, didn't they,
one day when they were doing the show?
- Yeah.
- One thing annoys me,
which is that Listerine gets a lot of shit.
You know the history of Listerine?
- It was originally to clean floors.
- It was to clean floors or wallpaper or whatever, yeah.
And then people say Listerine made up.
- Some of them invented, yeah.
- Invented halitosis.
- Invented halitosis, yeah.
- Everyone had amazing breath before that.
- Yeah, it's like, what?
The halitosis is rank, bad breath.
You want to clear it up.
So yeah, there is this thing.
And they turned it into kind of a medical problem.
But halitosis is often caused by bacteria
and bad bacteria in your mouth.
So I always feel a bit bad for Listerine
because they did try to fix bad breath.
I'm not saying that mouthwash necessarily does.
And in fact, it can make bad breath worse.
And particularly mouthwash that contains alcohol.
- You know, most mouthwash does.
It contains about 25% alcohol.
People tend to think, why is that?
Why would you assume that was?
- Fun.
(laughing)
- You can have a good night in.
- I would say alcohol is antiseptic.
- Yeah.
- Bacteria.
- Yeah, yeah, exactly.
So you'd need about 60 to 90% concentration of alcohol.
So you'd need to be drinking very hardcore absinthe
to have any effect on bacteria.
- So I should do that every morning, shouldn't I?
(laughing)
- It's the right color, right?
Green absinthe.
- Yeah, same color.
- Perfect, yeah.
Swapping out for some very strong absinthe.
But yeah, the reason it's there
is basically sort of as an agent to dissolve other stuff.
But also 'cause it gives you that burning feeling
that makes you feel like it's being really effective.
And so it's actually worse
'cause alcohol dries your mouth out,
like stops you salivating as much.
And that makes a good environment for bacteria.
- What, a dry mouth?
- Yeah, weirdly, 'cause they like moisture,
but your saliva has an acidity level
which counterbalances what the bacteria want to live in.
- No, I do.
- Yeah.
- We have a mutual buddy
who I was out for a drink with a while ago.
And mid-drink, he pulled out a bottle of listerine,
took a shot of it and just drank it down and put it away.
- He's having a tough time at the moment.
(laughing)
- He said, yeah, you can drink it.
It's like, he was saying, he was using it for his breath.
He was using it to just have a nice swig
and reset his mouth, but--
- You can't drink it, yeah.
- Yeah, I didn't know that,
'cause I've been spitting it out this whole time.
- You're supposed to spit it out.
You were right to bring it up
as an unusual thing till it happened.
- I suppose if you're at the pub,
most people don't use listerine
when they're sitting in the pub with their mates.
If you're around the table,
you can't just spit on the floor, can you?
- No, I usually get a shot of listerine
and put it in some Red Bull.
(laughing)
- Do you want to hear something quite off-topic?
- Sure.
(laughing)
- Okay.
It is about things you have in your mouth.
- Okay, great.
- It's pretty on-topic, actually.
- Yeah, yeah.
Depends on where you go with it.
- Some fish are called mouth brooders, right?
- Oh, yeah.
- And they bring up their offspring,
their babies, in their mouths,
before eventually opening their mouths
when they're ready to go.
- So they're kind of safe to grow a little bit in there.
- Yeah, they're complete, exactly.
They're safe from predators.
That's the main thing.
Some fish, which are mouth brooders,
deal with the stress of parenthood
by eating their children.
(laughing)
- What, just have a quick swallow?
- Yeah.
- Right.
- Is it when their children are really, really naughty
or they're sleep deprived,
are they particularly prone to swallow their kids?
- It's when the mother,
'cause in the species it's the mother fish,
is stressed, she's more prone to swallowing.
So they've tried playing loud noises at the fish,
which stresses them out.
And then she'll swallow a few for children.
- Oh, God.
- I bet parents are empathizing
all over the country as they listen.
- It might mean that they get,
well, they get some nutrition for one thing,
which is helpful,
but also they might get some antioxidants.
- Some bloody piece of choir.
(laughing)
- The funny thing with extinction is,
is that, you know, it's not suddenly recorded on the spot.
It takes years to get to that decision where I think,
you know what, I haven't seen these things for quite a while.
How long's it been?
A couple of months, I'll give it another year.
Let's have another look at it.
You know, and then 30 years later,
like, I've got to be honest with you,
it's been 30 years now.
We probably,
should we write it down that they're gone?
And even then something will spring up.
Oh no, there they are.
Gosh, God, we shouldn't have written that down.
Did you write that down?
Yeah, it's been,
it's gone out in all the books.
Well, I've just seen one.
So, you know what I mean?
It's kind of like,
and that must happen quite often.
- It's hard to draw the line.
- Cecilia Kanth.
That was a long, long time, right?
How long was that?
- That was 65 million years, that one,
which was...
(laughing)
- Shall we wait 66 million years?
- Yes, let's wait 66 million years.
It's a nice round number.
And then we'll,
no, let's do it now.
- Let's publish the book.
- He definitely did box out, Dal.
Let's have a look and see what's did this year.
What?
The Cecilia Kanth.
I saw one this morning.
No, it's in there.
It's in there.
First page.
That's off.
I found one this morning.
All right, give 'em a call.
(laughing)
Hello?
Things are dead.
Yes, listen, mate.
Your latest edition.
The Cecilia Kanth.
Page one.
Court one this morning.
Oh, you're shitting me.
No, I'm so sorry.
Did you come around our area?
No, didn't bother with it.
(laughing)
So you never know.
That's just what I'm saying.
(laughing)
- You're not the first with this series
to sort of reinvigorate the name of Steve Bonnet.
2013, he was a character in Assassin's Creed.
- That's right.
- Which was, yeah.
And it was called Black Flag.
And it was a, yeah, 2013 game
in which there was a lot of pirates.
It was the fourth in the Assassin's Creed games.
And one really interesting detail about it
is how they promoted this whole game,
which was they decided,
like most people would be like,
"Let's get posters up everywhere
"or let's do some publicity in bringing a celebrity."
And they decided to exhume a dead pirate
from his grave to do DNA tests on him.
Yeah, so the company that makes Assassin's Creed,
they funded archeologists to go and find a pirate
who was known as Amaro Pargo.
This was a big mission where they had to remove
a giant slab of marble.
They assumed that they knew where he was buried
and they were correct in the end.
And they found this whole booty
of other dead people as well.
Like it wasn't just him.
It was like his nieces and nephews.
- Why are they doing this?
- Can I just say, I don't know if that's the right term,
a booty of dead people.
(laughing)
What's in your booty?
Dead people.
- That just sounds a bit piratey, I guess.
- But yeah, so they managed to find him.
They found all these details about him.
He was about five foot, four inches tall.
Yeah, he was quite a robust character.
- And then what purpose did they serve
except for like giving the makers nightmares?
Did they then base the character in Assassin's Creed
completely on this weird corpse that they'd found?
- What's weird is I don't think
he's in the game.
- No, 'cause you said it's just Steve in the game.
It's just weird.
- No, no, no, it's not Steve.
Steve's a character in the game.
There's lots of pirates
and there's lots of historical pirates.
And it was while they were doing the development,
they were researching the game
and they found this guy and they thought,
God, he's such an interesting character.
Why is he unknown?
And so they then got in touch
with this company of archeologists
and they said, would you dig him up for us?
I think they had plans probably to do that anyway.
- And they just wanted publicity.
- Yeah, they wanted publicity.
- They wanted people to talk about it on podcasts
10 years later.
- Exactly.
- You've fallen right into the trap
of this weird modern day Birkenhair freak.
- Do we keep doing this?
This will be a conversation piece, Trump.
We've got to keep doing this.
This will come up.
This will pop up.
There'll be something.
Someone will talk about it.
- I don't know.
It feels weird.
You get banana split eating contests.
- Oh yeah.
- Which I found underwhelming, if I'm honest.
And I thought maybe we could enter one.
- Okay.
- Great.
- You know, there's surveys where they ask a load of men
if they can beat Serena Williams in a tennis match.
- Oh yeah.
- And they all say they can.
I think this is the Anna equivalent of it.
It's like, I could beat anyone in an eating contest.
- An eating contest I see.
- You think we could win a banana split contest?
- Well, listen to this.
I was reading about the one that's held in Maryland
and it's an annual Jimmy Cone banana split eating contest.
And I was reading the report for the 2015 one.
I don't know how much people have improved since then.
But in the kids contest, it was won fittingly
by someone called Tommy Aites.
- Oh, brilliant.
- And he was 12 and he had 20 minutes
and he got through 2.5 banana splits.
- I think that if he was 12, this could be a kids thing.
- No, there is an adult round.
- Is there?
- I've kind of deep-raised this.
But the adult round.
- I've got to see Anna Hodlin into this kids contest.
I can bite the floor with a lot of you.
- I intend to try and enter the kids one first.
- Obviously, I'll wear some armbands or something.
The adult one, I think the winner got through
four banana splits in half an hour.
- Half an hour?
- I believe it was.
Isn't that so crap?
- That's four bananas and 12 scoops of ice cream.
- Yeah.
- In half an hour.
- In half an hour, yeah.
But no, I'm not saying it's a timing.
I'm saying it's a capacity thing.
That's a lot of...
- It certainly is capacity.
They say the best way to do it is to do it slowly
because everyone's vomiting.
In fact, Tommy, sweetly Tommy eights when he won,
he was interviewed and they were like,
"How was that, Tommy?"
And he said, "It was awesome."
And then immediately vomited into the bucket
that was provided.
- Disqualified.
- You know moon rock.
- Yeah, man.
- Yeah, it's from the moon.
- Rock from the moon.
So the Apollo 11 astronauts got a load of rocks down
when they came back from the moon.
And 7.5% of that rock was fed to animals.
- No!
- Yeah, 'cause they wanted to know what would happen
if you gave it to animals.
Would it, is it carcinogenic?
Would it make them sick?
All these different things.
So there was a woman called Marion Brooks
who worked at the University of St. Paul
and she was given all this stuff
and she gave it to oysters, shrimps, cockroaches, flies,
moths, fish, and just kept giving little bits.
And some of them were giving it to eat.
Some of them were inoculated with it.
Some of them were just allowed to crawl around it
and they wanted to see if they would die.
- That is incredible.
- Isn't that cool?
- And what happened?
- They were all fine 'cause it's just rock.
But some of the fish died.
But that's because someone dropped a bottle of sodium
hydrochloride next to where they lived
and so they died of the fumes.
And a couple of oysters died
because they pooed in their own water and they died.
But none of them died because of the rocks.
- I was gonna bid very recently
on a couple of cockroaches that were up for auction
that the moon dust was still inside.
- Oh wow.
- So you were getting the moon dust.
- Your children would have loved that.
- They would have loved it.
Unfortunately, NASA took it off the bidding
because they decided--
- 'Cause you're not allowed to sell that.
- You're not allowed to sell that, exactly.
- Even if they're inside a cockroach.
- Really?
- Even if they ground up dust in there.
- The cockroach is dead, right?
- Yeah, it's dead.
So this was back in the '60s, but they kept the cockroaches
and they had the moon dust still inside them.
- What kind of price would you have paid?
- Oh, you know, that was going for a good mill, I think.
So I would have been one of those just, you know,
token early voters.
- A lower bid, but with a lovely letter attached to it.
Saying this would really mean a lot to me.
- Yes, exactly.
- 'Cause sometimes auctioneers do take,
they look kindly on that, you know?
- Yeah, so I've got a bit of Berlin Wall
that would look nice next to that in the house.
- Wow, that's cool.
- Yeah, NASA are so pedantic, in my experience.
(laughing)
- Psycho.
- Yes, because you know that I have spoken
to a national on the International Space Station.
- Oh, who was that?
- I know this, yeah.
- Yeah, she's a fan of my dad, Brett Aporno,
and NASA astronauts are allowed a mental health call
every few weeks when they're up there.
She chose to speak to me.
- You.
- Honestly, she could have chosen anyone.
- That would surely trigger a bigger intervention
from the mental health team.
(laughing)
- Exactly, yeah.
- I'll speak to this guy.
(laughing)
- But I was like--
- Restrain her, restrain her now, put her in the brig.
- That was like NASA.
They're gonna have the most amazing like communication
and software, Microsoft Teams.
(laughing)
Is what I used to speak to space.
- Amazing.
- Yeah, insane.
And they were very, they were like,
you can't take any pictures,
you can't even do a screen grab.
- Wow.
- NASA was just so annoying.
- How did they know you hadn't done a screen grab?
- Well, this is the thing.
I was so paranoid that my whole computer's bugged.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- To my wifi connection, and so I didn't dare do one.
But so--
- Wow.
- Although I think I do have a photo of us.
- What did you talk about?
Was it her?
Who was asking who questions?
- Well, I think it was supposed to be her
asking us questions, but we just asked her
a million questions about being in space.
And she gave us a tour of the whole station.
It was incredible.
Showed us Earth from like the windows.
- That's so cool.
What was her name?
- I'm not sure if I can say the name,
just in case--
- Oh, really?
- Natter do get in, you know.
- If any astronauts are listening
and want to talk about rocks, Andy, you're--
- Oh my God, I'm so free.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Apparently they listened to a lot of podcasts up there.
So--
- Oh, okay, right.
- Edward Aporno.
- Right.
- It wasn't this, but, you know.
(laughing)
- I've got one more fact about tiny dust.
- Gosh, please.
- This is a really cool idea.
It's the idea that you can use crushed rocks
to fight climate change.
I think it's best to come across this.
So, basalt is a rock that's volcanic.
And when rain falls, so this is the problem.
Rain falls, it combines with carbon dioxide in the air,
becomes slightly acidic, right?
And the problem is obviously too much carbon dioxide
in the air, that's the main cause of climate change.
If that acidic rain hits particular rock types,
it can cause a chemical reaction which kind of locks up
the carbon dioxide, removes it from the atmosphere,
which is a good thing.
And if you spread basalt dust across a field,
just an ordinary field, you massively increase
the surface area, that reaction will happen,
like a hundred fold or more than that.
And that's the plan.
That carbon is captured, it washes down rivers,
animals like oysters might put it in their shells.
When they die, the shells fall to the bottom of the ocean.
That carbon is just sequestered indefinitely.
- Oh, that's a problem.
- Yeah, that's the problem.
- So that's the idea.
It's still in the research stage at the moment,
but it is, you know, that's a dream,
that it will be one of the methods
we could use to fight climate change.
It would use only 0.2% of UK electricity generation.
- You won't be able to grow stuff on those fields, right?
- I think you still can.
I think that's the point.
Yeah, yeah, it's just a very fine layer of dust.
In fact, it even increases crop yields in some cases.
- You could put it on golf courses,
couldn't you?
That might work.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's a green space.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
- That's really good.
- Yeah, that's the plan.
- So good news.
- We can all get planes again.
(all laughing)
- But the Muppet Show is sort of for adults
and for children, as in the original TV series,
as you know, and lots of the Muppets
have quite serious problems in their lives.
Gonzo is depressive, and Kermit is incredibly stressed,
and there's all sorts of stuff going on.
- That's not homeless.
- Oh, well, he's Sesame Street,
so he's different universe, but uh...
- 'Cause Sesame Street is for kids, right?
- Count on Count has erythomomania,
which is a mental illness
where you have a clouding obsession
with numbers and mathematical processes,
which interferes with your everyday life.
- That's...
Wait, hang on.
- There, hang on.
- You don't know about it, Andy.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
- I remember thinking 257,000 minutes ago.
(all laughing)
- But there's a thing about vampires.
There's a myth about vampires,
that if you throw grains of rice on the ground,
then they'll have to be obsessed with it.
So is that where the counting thing from?
- Well, we don't know for sure,
but it seems likely that that's where that comes from.
But yeah, obviously the erythomomania
is not necessarily that he suffers from that.
- Or is it 'cause he's called the Count?
- Yeah, it could be that.
- It's just, I think it's kind of worth it.
(all laughing)
- There was a complaint by a guy called Joseph B. Regoli
in 1979 that the Count von Counts
might mislead children into trusting Dracula
and possibly monsters in general.
- Because he was such a nice character.
- And everyone loved him, but actually he was a bad guy.
And maybe kids need to learn to not trust the bad guys.
- Not trust Dracula when he's not on your door.
Don't invite him in.
Keep the garlic safe.
- And the Sesame Street people replied saying
that we've tried to make it clear
that the Count is not a representative of evil.
(all laughing)
- God.
- Just on why things floating and things sinking.
- Yeah.
- There's been some new research done recently
into why some poo's float and some poo's sink.
- Okay.
- This is really exciting.
- This is very exciting.
- This is useful.
- So I think it's about 10 to 15% of people
that poo's always float.
And almost everyone else that poo's always sink.
So.
- Hang on, sorry, but most of us have
sometimes float, sometimes sink, right?
- Yeah.
But people have 10, people tend one way or the other.
- Okay, got it.
- Like some people, it's universal one way or the other.
And it's 10 to 15, it's sort of always,
they're always floating.
So, I know, and it's to do with,
you're not going to be staggered,
the gas content of the actual poo.
But there was a theory it was to do with fat content,
as in because the fat cells in the mud.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
And so the initial experiment was done by a scientist
called Michael Levitt and William Dwayne,
and this was in 1972.
And they were the ones who first showed
it was to do with gas.
I just loved this.
One of them said to the other,
my poo's always float.
And, oh, that's interesting, I wonder why.
And so they collected floaters
from 13 experimental subjects.
- Right.
- I had no idea how they opened those conversations.
And they increased the pressurization on the poo's
to remove the gas, and then they all sank.
And irrespective of the fat content.
So that's how they proved that.
The new research is from Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota.
And it's a scientist called Nagarajan Kanan and colleagues
who bred some mice with no gut bacteria.
And it means they always produce sinkers.
- Okay.
- It's gas from the gut microbes.
- Gas, how interesting.
- Yeah, it's normal mice, it's 50/50.
But these special GM--
- So if you're one of the 14%,
if you were to eat some yakult for a few days,
do you think your poo's would stop?
- I don't think that research has been done.
I think that's a great next journey for this experiment.
- The yakult actually increases good bacteria.
So I would have thought that makes it float.
- Well, it changes your microbiome, doesn't it?
- Changes, I wonder.
- What does it mean for Anna then, though, who's poo's?
(all laughing)
I would think Anna's.
- Anna's are shroding as poo's.
And you don't know whether they'll sink or float
until they're out.
- It's sort of both at the same time.
(all laughing)
- It's sort of listing.
- Yeah, you actually put armbands on them sometimes.
Get them back up to the surface.
- There's an episode where Fred is playing Scrabble.
And he's just trying to save face
'cause he doesn't know many words.
And so he makes up a word
to try and get some extra points.
And the word that they thought was made up,
which possibly was at the time--
- Brexit.
(all laughing)
- Was zarf.
- Oh, no way.
Oh my God.
- Zarf is an exciting word that I introduced
to our listeners and the fellow fishers.
A while ago, zarf is, do you know what it is?
- Yes, what?
- I love that episode.
(all laughing)
- God, what a chance.
- We probably don't need to go over it again.
- No, no, no, no, what was it?
- You know, when you go into a coffee shop
and you get a coffee and it's a bit too hot,
and they give you that little cardboard sleeve
that goes under it, that's a zarf.
- No.
- Yes.
So maybe the person who came up with the name of the zarf
had seen this episode of the Flintstones.
- And went, ooh, there's a word going for spare.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think the word zarf did exist before then
'cause I've since looked it up.
And a zarf in places like Russia and Turkey and stuff,
you have like a glass cup for coffee.
And then they have like a metal holder
that the glass goes in and that's known as a zarf.
- You're kidding.
- Oh my God.
- So it's a proper thing and then they use the word
to refer to the cardboard.
- That's what I've got.
That's really interesting.
- That's really cool.
- That's, yeah.
- Well, one of the videos I saw sort of screws up
because the tram has to go at quite a pace
to hit the inflatable ball.
And then the idea is that the ball rolls
into these giant inflatable skittles and knocks them down.
But the tram does struggle to slow down.
So what you see is a ball knocking into the skittles
and then immediately afterwards,
the tram mowing down all of the skittles.
- Oh, that's no point.
That's no point.
- That's no point.
- Just to break the forehand.
- As in bowling.
- I thought it looked, I think it looked good too.
- Wait, you're not allowed to chase your ball down the...
- Shit.
- I'm always getting lifted up by those claws at the end.
(laughing)
- Just rolling back up there.
- Popping out, someone puts his hand in your face.
- Two up the nose, one in the mouth.
(laughing)
Really to the go.
I'm a large size.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]