- Hey everybody, welcome to this week's episode of Fish.
We have a very exciting guest on this week.
- Yes, is it Andy?
- It's not Andy.
Yeah, no, Andy is still a guest.
We consider him a guest of the show.
But no, he was busy this week, so.
- I thought what I was saying is Andy isn't here.
- Yeah, that's effectively.
But I still, I feel the guest thing.
No, very excitingly, we have the founder of QI, John Lloyd himself.
He's been on a few times.
This is the guy who gave us not the nine o'clock news.
Black Adder, spitting image.
He helped create Mr. Bean, co-wrote to the original radio episodes
of Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy.
- Yes, he exact produced a short-lived television show.
Those things are the news.
- Which he says is the highlight of his career.
I don't know if he means the ending of it
or the experience itself, but he's now turned himself
into a music manager.
The band that he looks after is called Waiting for Smith.
And if you hang out, listener, to the end of this episode,
we're actually gonna play a track
from Waiting for Smith, their latest singer.
- You don't have to listen to it all.
You can fast forward the whole episode.
- It just gets straight to the song.
- No, no, experience the show without our guest Andy
and see how it feels and give us feedback of what you think.
Anyway, he was a fantastic guest.
It's always amazing to get loydy on the show
and have a listen at the end.
And yeah, enjoy the show.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Anna Chazinski
and Chief Nome John Lloyd.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, John.
- Right, my fact is that when the Greek government
put a tax on swimming pools in 2008,
only 324 Athenians admitted to having one.
A search by Google Earth Hava revealed the actual number,
16,974.
(laughing)
- It's incredible.
- It's bare face, isn't it?
According to the IMF, more than half of all Greek households
pay no income tax at all.
- Wow.
- And Greece has got the largest black market
in the whole Eurozone, accounting for 21.5% of its GDP.
There's a reason for this, I believe.
I was when I was in Greece last year.
Somebody explained why this is,
why the Greeks are so poor at playing their taxes.
Because for a thousand years,
they were part of the Ottoman Empire,
which they absolutely hated.
And it was considered a patriotic national duty,
not to pay your taxes.
- Well, and they just haven't caught up with the history
that the Ottoman Empire fell apart a hundred years ago.
- I think there are some traditions
that you really want to bring back immediately
and maybe pay in taxes not one of them.
It has a bit lower down on the list.
- You're right.
- I love these pools,
'cause it feels as if they were prepared
for this Google Earth search,
because they all hide them with camouflage.
- How do you hide a pool?
- Okay, so they have floating tiles
that they put on the top of their pool.
- Very clever.
- Yep, they have army nets,
so they camouflage it all together.
And some even paint the interior of their pools
to mimic grass.
- Wow.
- Oh, it's brilliant.
- It's extraordinary.
- So the first Google Earth search said no swimming pools,
but an extraordinary number of army nets
in people's garden with no apparent reason.
- The Greeks have a really good history of paying taxes,
'cause in ancient Greek,
they had a really good system of paying tax.
And that is that the assembly in Athens
would pick the richest people to pay tax.
The top 300 in some cases.
And they would just say you have to pay for this parade
and this battleship and this whatever.
- Really?
- And they all agreed.
They even competed to spend as much money as possible,
because it was a real kind of thing
where you would get respect from people and gratitude.
And if you were one of the people who paid tax,
it really increased your standing in the community.
And people really liked you for it.
So everyone wanted to pay tax.
- Okay.
- Everyone wanted to be in that 300.
- I wonder if you got your name stamped on the event
as well, like the liviest parade.
- You did?
Yeah, did you all you paid the more likely
you were to get your name on something?
- So this is kind of like those philanthropists who,
I don't know if you mentioned after Notre Dame burned down,
the philanthropists who really wanted to donate millions
and then it turned out they kind of only wanted to do it
if the bell was renamed, you know,
the ex-person, your name was Bell.
- Trump Bell.
- Yeah, Ikea, wing of Notre Dame.
They're not the worst taxpayers in the world, the Greeks, though.
The Chinese, only 2% of Chinese pay any income tax.
And in Pakistan, it's 1%.
I mean, you wonder how these countries operate?
- Especially China, which operates entirely as government, yeah.
I suppose it's just hard to get into those hard to reach spots,
isn't it?
We've all had that itch on our back.
It's kind of quite big, guys.
- I was kind of nervous researching this topic
'cause my Google searches were like amazing tax dodges
and we're coming up to the end of the tax year.
But I found tax dodges quite fun the way the people got--
- Again, researching them, right?
- Resurrecting them, just--
- Ah!
- That's my accountant there, Jimmy.
- Yeah, no, early England tax is like the 1700s.
So there's so many great ways that people try to get around
all the taxes that were being thrown at them.
So there was tax on bricks, for example, in houses.
So one of the dodges that they used to do was people
just used to use bigger bricks.
So you use less brick.
- Oh, really?
- Perhaps, yeah.
- Yeah, I did, you could just use four bricks, one for each wall.
- Exactly, and then they call onto that.
So they eventually taxed big bricks as well.
- Did it, by the way, that's actually a bit like with cheese.
You know the origin of big cheese wheels is based on the fact
that cheese used to be taxed by number of cheeses
in Switzerland, rather than by weight.
And so people would just make bigger and bigger giant cheeses.
And that's why we have them.
And now the average emmental is three feet diameter
and weighs 220 pounds.
And uses one and a half tons of milk
'cause it just gets the same amount of taxes.
And many one.
- That's a mini baby bell.
- And baby bell?
- Yeah.
- I was just looking at the quite famous case,
the jaffa cake case on tax.
So you know, there's always this debate over where
the cake, the cakes or biscuits debate.
And that originates in 1991.
I think it was, and it's because cakes are traditionally
in a lot of countries actually are not subject
to VAT sales tax, whereas biscuits with chocolate on our
'cause cakes were seen as a necessity
'cause it used to be, you know,
your working household would make a cake.
But yeah, in 1991, McVitties insisted jaffa cake was a cake.
And so they agreed it had biscuit tendencies,
but then had to argue overall that it had more cake elements.
And as part of the, like in court,
as part of the evidence for the fact that it was a cake,
McVitties baked a one foot diameter jaffa cake
to show this is actually a cake.
And the courts can cut.
And it's been a cake ever since.
- That's not cool.
- Yeah, it's amazing.
- Do you know the difference in cakes and biscuits?
How you tell?
- How you tell?
- Because when they go stale, biscuits go soft
and cakes go hard.
- Yeah.
- Oh, that's cool.
- But they didn't have the time to sit in the court
for sort of three weeks, watching the jaffa cake go stale.
This is also actually the case with gingerbread men.
So a gingerbread man counts as a cake
and counts as a biscuit that's exempt from tax
'cause it's got no chocolate on it.
Until it has a certain amount of chocolate.
So if you've got a gingerbread man just with eyes,
but naked, no tax on it.
But then it'll cost 20% more if it's got one button.
- No.
(laughing)
- One button on its shirt.
- Who in their right mind is adding that one button?
- No, I don't know.
These people are missing a trick.
- It's odd that the people who are best at paying taxes
are Americans strangely enough.
- Oh yeah.
- That's slightly surprising.
81 to 84% of Americans don't cheat on their taxes
compared to 68% of Germans and 62% of Italians.
- Are these self-reported figures?
(laughing)
- But it did really shocking actually how much
tax avoidance goes on, not just Apple and Amazon.
Amazon has not paid any federal taxes in America
even though it makes profits of billions.
And there's $8.7 trillion worth of the world's wealth
hidden away in tax havens by the rich.
That has a lot of money.
- Isn't it something like the fifth biggest country
in the world if it was a country, isn't it?
Something like that, I think, for the biggest in terms of income.
The tax haven country, whatever we're calling that.
- Where does that sounds great?
(laughing)
We know where it is.
- It's very wealthy.
It's wherever you want it to be, Dad.
- The UK is king of tax havens.
I mean, we don't have anyone else in the world.
- Yeah, exactly.
We talk about Greece and whoever,
but British, the Cayman Islands belongs to Britain,
the Virgin Islands belongs to Britain.
- Bermuda.
- Bermuda, yeah.
- I love man.
- Yeah.
- The Virgin Islands goes on on. - The Virgin Islands.
- The Virgin Islands. - The Virgin Islands.
- Did you realise you were taxis then?
- No, we're a bit like those villages in China.
It's very difficult for the tax ones to get down to Bolton.
- Tough itch to scratch, Bolton.
- So one of those honest Americans is Warren Buffett,
who's been paying income tax since he was 14.
- Wow.
- He had a paper round.
And in 1944, he paid tax of $7 on an income of $592,
which would be equivalent to about 8,000 pounds today.
He had a pretty enterprising 14-year-old.
- That's a lot of newspapers, isn't it?
- Yeah, another guy who paid £7 tax was the
longest-serving Prime Minister of Pakistan.
He was a guy called Noah's Sharif,
who was in office for nine years on three separate occasions.
At one point, he had a personal fortune of two billion pounds,
but over a period of several years,
paid only just seven pounds into tax.
- Wow, the same one.
- My wife and he bothers Bermuda.
It's like, yeah, this is it.
I'm fessing up here.
- It's your full seven-quid bag.
(all laughing)
- Shall we say something to stuff on swimming pools?
- Yeah, sure.
- Let's do that.
So, do you know, name something that you're not allowed
to do with a swimming pool?
- You already have a poo.
- Oh my, are there any signs on the walls
to say you can't do that?
- No, that's true, which is why I always challenge them.
(all laughing)
- On the attempt to kick me out.
- Okay, Dave, something that's explicitly told you
that's allowed to do on the wall, - Oh, petting.
- Petting, that's why I'm saying that.
- Not allowed?
- I mean, who uses that word anymore?
- Right, so why do they call it heavy petting
in these swimming pools?
- Yeah.
- Because surely it's just snogging or kissing or whatever,
right?
Well, the reason is, in the 1920s in America,
they had some things called petting parties,
and high school students would go to swimming pools,
and they would kind of kiss and cuddle and whatever.
They would never have sex in there,
but they would be getting very close.
And people disapproved, and so they would have signs
saying no petting on the swimming pools,
and that has kind of kept over for almost 100 years now,
and you still get heavy petting.
- Really?
- Signs even though you don't have these parties anymore.
- But you might have them if they took the signs away.
- I'm not saying, yeah.
- So, is that what a petting zoo is?
(all laughing)
- It is, I had a traumatic childhood, actually,
repeatedly taken to those places.
(all laughing)
- To a heavy petting zoo.
They were also these petting parties.
They were also known as necking parties,
mushing parties, fussing parties,
and snuggle-pupping parties.
- Snuggle-pupping.
- So, I really think it should sell the swimming pool.
No snuggle-puppings.
- No snuggle-puppings.
- Which they won't be,
'cause everyone will feel too sick
to pet anyone at the phrase snuggle-pupping.
- Because there are no signs actually saying no urinating.
(all laughing)
Public swimming pools contain up to 20 gallons of urine.
- Down.
- Enough to fill a dustbin.
- And the proportion in hotel jacuzzi
is up to three times worse.
- Wow.
- Why are people doing it more in a jacuzzi?
- I think it's the bubbles that you want to go, don't they?
- Do you think?
- Well, I think someone knows.
(all laughing)
- That study where they found out there was,
do you say 20 gallons of urine?
- Yes.
- It was really clever how they did it,
because it's quite difficult to work out
how much urine there is in a swimming pool,
'cause often the chlorine would change it
into other compounds or whatever.
But they found a compound in urine
that doesn't react with any other chemicals.
And that is called acesulfane potassium.
And it's a sweetener that you get in lots of like diet drinks
- Oh yeah.
- And if you urinate that into a swimming pool,
nothing can get rid of it, so it'll stay there.
And so they could take in the amount of water
and see how much of that was in,
and then work out the 20 gallons of urine from that.
- Hang on, are we all urinating this sweetener?
- I think they took an average of how much people would.
It's in a lot of foods, it's not just in soft drinks,
it's in a lot of stuff.
And that 20 gallons as well as being a dustbin,
it's approximately 121 bottles worth of urine in the swimming pool.
- In each swimming pool.
- And they sell it in Aldi, don't they?
(laughing)
That's a terrible slam.
Aldi has a really good wine selection, genuinely.
- They do, they do, they do.
- I'm sorry.
- They win Aldi Awards.
- Did you know this thing, another thing they could use,
and I think they do in some places,
silver has got the curious,
property of sterilizing water.
So they could use silver instead of chlorine.
- And only more expensive, though,
but you know, only tiny amounts,
you need only 10 parts per billion.
- Wow, 10.
- And it's completely safe.
- That's great.
So in the Olympics, whoever comes second
could jump in the pool out of the race
and then clean the pool for the next race.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- That's really good.
- You know, when you smell that really strong smell
of chlorine in a pool.
- Yeah, I like it actually.
- And you think, okay, and you get high off it maybe,
or you think there's too much chlorine in this pool.
Do you know what the problem actually is?
- My nose is too sad to serve.
(laughing)
- No, it's that there's not enough chlorine.
- Oh, yeah.
- So this is, I actually learned this from Dr. Colbert,
this in one of his books,
but if it smells too strongly of chlorine,
it means they haven't put enough in,
'cause the smell that you're smelling,
it's actually when the chlorine reacts with the nitrogen
from things like urine and sweat
and dead insects and bacteria and stuff.
It combines with it,
and it makes these chemicals called chloramines.
And the smell comes from this particular chemical
called tri-chloramine.
So that's very volatile, so you start smelling it.
If you add more chlorine,
then it keeps reacting,
and it moves on through the chemical process
and the tri-chloramine goes away.
- That's incredible.
- That's amazing.
- The smell that I really like
is actually dead insects and urine.
- That's correct, yes.
That seems true to form, no?
(laughing)
- Did you know that Clint Eastwood
used to dig swimming pools for a living?
- I think that was easy.
- Or was he a very enthusiastic grave digger?
(laughing)
He was quite successful, quite young,
and he was sacked by Universal Studios
because his Adam's apple was too big.
- What?
- What are you talking about?
- What do you mean?
(laughing)
- You're testing this now, aren't you?
That can't be true.
- Well, it is true.
It was on IMDB and on www.clinyswood.net.
- Oh, there you go.
- Where I also found the fact that his name is an anagram
of Old West Action.
That's quite good.
- That's really good.
- Wow.
Actually, I'm now thinking of Clint Eastwood,
and he has big Adam's apple.
- You can picture it.
- Big enough to stop him from digging holes.
- No, he wasn't sacked from the grave digging.
- I don't know, he was sacked from the movies.
- Oh, right.
- And then he had to get another job.
- You're gonna scare the mourners.
- It was swimming pools, it wasn't graves.
- He was so working.
- When did the Adam's apple thing come in?
- I'm sorry, I've lost it.
- In the '50s.
He was fired by Universal.
- That was at the start of his career all the time.
- Yeah, he'd been in a couple of sort of B movies,
and then the Adam's apple, they suddenly noticed,
"Hey, that guy there."
Oh my God, it was horrible.
- It was when they started having 3D movies, didn't it,
and people thought it was going to pop up in the eye.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for fact number two,
and that is Chazinski.
- My fact this week is that some terraces had heads
that were more than four times the length of their bodies.
- No.
- How big was that Adam's apple?
(laughing)
- They were such stupid looking creatures.
- So the terraces were tarot dactyl,
as often used as kind of a word for the tarot dactyl,
tarot dactyl actually not a thing,
the tarot dactyl lus was a type of tarot saw.
But yeah, they were the first flying species,
and they started off about 250 million years ago
with heads nearly as long as their bodies,
and they just extended and extended
until you got some terraces like the Ketsal coactless,
where the heads and the necks were at least triple
the length of the torso, so it took up over 75% of their bodies.
- It feels like if you're a flying animal,
having a massive head that's three times
big with everything else is probably going to be a problem.
- You just tip them out the sky all the time.
- You think so, right?
- It's been this real mystery about how they figured it out,
re-center of gravity, and generally their massive size.
And one of the ways that they did it
was by having a very light head.
So they had these openings in front of their eyes
in their skulls called the antorbital fenestra,
which is just the window in front of their eyes.
And we don't really know what was in it,
maybe a gland or muscle, it might've just been a big air cavity.
And this sometimes has huge hole in their skull,
was so big that it could, in some of them,
it could fit their entire torso through it.
Isn't they didn't put their torso through it?
- If they stopped too fast,
wouldn't it shoot out through it?
- Yes, exactly.
They literally turn inside out.
- Like a jumpy, you have to put back the right way around.
- Yeah, it's amazing.
And also one reason that we know they had very light heads
is because the bones were very light, right?
- Yes.
- But the bones were quite thick in places,
but there was a big gap of air in the middle,
and then the actual edges of the bone were like one millimeter thick.
And that means it's really hard for us to find
terrasaur fossils because they just kind of wash away
on the crumbalop.
There's hardly any of them in existence.
I read one article, I don't know if this is true
of all terrasars, but one person said
you could put all the fossil material of terrasars
that we've ever found in one handbag.
- No.
- If you were to crush it all up.
And that's because it's so thin,
and so we all had a nice, not that many of them as well.
It could be that they were talking about specific species
I couldn't quite tell from there.
- You could believe that though.
If you powder ill, put it in a blender.
- I've seen some big handbags.
- That's why they check your handbags
at the Natural History Museum when you're at it.
- That's why.
- Because it's a terrasaur, isn't it?
- Yeah, it's because we're serras.
This all of the fossils of terrasars
we've never found in history in the uphand bag.
- Oh, busted.
- Terrasars, not dinosaurs.
- No.
- I'm sure everyone around this table knew that,
but I didn't, so it's worth saying.
- It's weird.
- For the people at home.
Yeah, not dinosaurs.
- And also, birds didn't descend from them.
Which, again, I think everyone says,
birds descend from dinosaurs.
And you think, why it must be the flying type,
but yeah, not at all birds descended from things
that could not fly when the dinosaurs were around.
- It's really amazing that, isn't it?
And I read as well that the largest thing
which survived that attack from a meteorite,
not an attack, it wasn't a meteorite spot.
- It wasn't malicious, you make it sound deliberate.
- It was just flying through the universe
and the earth got in the way.
- Yeah.
- It's not the meteorite spot.
But the largest thing that would have survived
was around 44 pounds.
And that today would be about the size of an American beaver.
So anything bigger than a beaver would die.
Anything smaller than a beaver,
some would die, but some would survive.
And the things that turn into birds
were not just the small dinosaurs weirdly.
It was some of the medium ones that were eating seeds.
- Okay.
- Because when there's like a nuclear winter
because the meteor hits and nothing can grow,
the seeds can still live underground.
And so these little dinosaurs could go and still eat the seeds
until everything got better.
And they were the ones that survived.
- Wow.
- And I wonder if that's, I think that's why today
like birds, which are the things that survived
from there are the things that eat seeds.
- Okay, yeah, that's really cool.
One thing that's descended from those guys are woodpeckers.
- Oh, yeah.
- And those just found them, but what they do with their heads,
they bang their heads into trees at speeds of about 15 miles
an hour up to 12,000 times a day.
- Whoa.
- I mean, what must that be like?
- Yeah.
- I don't think they get headaches, it's just.
- We found this out for QI ones and it's...
- I never got a weird tongue, haven't they?
- Yeah.
- They're wrapped around their brains.
- I think they got thick skulls or some kind of padding skulls.
- They've got some kind of special brain casing.
- Yeah.
- It's sort of wobbles around in jelly.
- It is amazing though, isn't it?
- Another head banger is death watch beetles,
which repeatedly bang their heads on the floor
to attract mates.
- It's incredible.
- I tried that, doesn't it?
- Don't work.
- No, no.
- Death watch beetles, that's a metal band.
- Death watch beetles.
- Death watch beetles and a metal tribute beetles bag.
(laughing)
- I've got some, I decided to run a search for four times
to what things are four times as much as you do.
- Oh yeah.
- Oh yeah, yeah.
- So there's some quite good ones in here.
So spiders milk, but you didn't know there wasn't it,
but some spiders produce milk.
And spiders milk contains four times as much protein
as cow's milk.
- Oh, one more.
- And they're hard to milk though, aren't they?
I reckon like you get more from a cow's other
than you do from a spider's other.
- Just going to milk the spiders?
I'll be back in two months, when I've got enough.
- So, and chimpanzees expend four times as much energy
walking on either four or two legs than humans do.
- Wow.
- It's really hard for them walking.
- Wow, I wonder why that is.
- It's awesome, I don't know.
- They've got a huge upper bodies, haven't they?
That must be tiring.
- Yeah.
- The T genome is four times longer than the coffee genome.
So that's discovered by Chinese geneticists.
And this one is astonishing.
Almost four times as many people are murdered
as are killed in wars.
Isn't that a shock?
- Yeah, wow.
- Yeah.
- I mean, some of us would say that been killed
in a war is murder.
- All right, Jeremy Corbyn, okay.
(all laughing)
I'm gonna out.
- Well, we've had a lot of guests today,
Jimmy Carter, Jeremy Corbyn.
(all laughing)
- Actually, on tarot actials,
they wore a bit hairy, some of them.
They had what is called tarot fuzz in,
I found in an email thread that I sort of found
archive between paleontologists.
But yeah, they found hair fibers on some of them.
And they also think this might be
what helped them be able to fly to do with insulation.
But there was sort of fuzzy or fluffy.
- That's really cool.
- That's cool.
- It's quite cute.
But not on the wings, I think, just on the bod.
- Just that.
- Fuzzy bod, bat wings.
- They were also the babies.
You know what they call the baby tarot actal?
Or tarot sore?
- Um, no.
- Flap wings.
- Oh, yeah.
- Flap wings, nice little word.
And they were, so they were first identified
by a guy called George's Curvier.
- George Curvier?
- George.
- George Curvier.
- What stage reading that census did you realize
you were at George?
- You didn't even call him Gub.
(laughing)
- So.
- Sorry, who was George Curvier then?
- George's Curvier was a, he was a scientist.
And he was the person who discovered,
or firstly identified the flying terrasaur in 1809.
And he said that in 1812, he said
that they were unlikely, we as humans,
were ever unlikely to find any animal as large as that.
Then 10 years after he died, we discovered dinosaurs.
(laughing)
- Oh, what a shame.
He was the first person to say that they flew.
But the first person to describe them in any way scientifically
was Cosimo Collini.
And he was most famous for being Voltaire's secretary.
- Yeah.
- So it was.
- It was not cool, isn't it?
Such a weird two worlds colliding.
- Yeah.
- I wonder where he was secretary,
because Voltaire, just down the road from us in Comic Garden,
he used to live there.
- Oh, Voltaire.
- Yeah.
- I think probably in front of life.
- That's why he lived most of his life.
- Okay, cool.
- I think, you said 1809, I think it was 1801, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- And it's Curvier.
(laughing)
- He was also, I mean, not only did he see the baby,
he was also the person who was the foundation
of all Darwin's theories.
He was the person who realized
that animals could become extinct.
- I've one last thing before we move on,
which is, did you know that there were terraces
in the movie "Citizen Kane"?
(laughing)
- What?
- So this is really worth checking out.
So obviously "Citizen Kane" held up
as one of the greatest movies ever made, Orson Wells.
He had an incredible script, he had an incredible cast,
what he didn't have, was an incredible budget.
So for a lot of the movie, they had to reuse
certain things from other movies.
And there's a scene in the movie, and I've watched it,
where they're at some sort of party that's on a beach.
And in the background to show a sort of
jungly background, they had to borrow footage from King Kong,
or son of King Kong, because they couldn't afford
to do it themselves. - Oh my god.
- Yeah.
So in the background, you see these giant terraces
from the movie. - No way, no way.
- It's a spoiler alert, that's what Rosebud is.
- Yeah.
- The name of his pet, "Terrosa".
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for fact number three,
and that is James.
Okay, my fact this week is that the world's first casino
had a rule that you could only gamble
if you were wearing a tricon hat.
(laughing)
So, this was in Venice.
It was in 1638, and it was called Il Riddotto,
which means the private room.
And Riddotto was actually a word which was used for
like illegal gambling clubs at the time,
but they closed them all down,
and everyone was very upset about it,
but they said, "No, don't worry,
"we're gonna make an official one that you can all go to."
So, by the rules, everyone's allowed to go there,
you're all allowed to gamble here, don't worry,
you'll all be able to still gamble,
but if you do want to gamble,
you're gonna have to wear a tricon hat and a mask,
and tricon hats a mask, or it's extremely expensive,
and so actually the poor people couldn't do it anymore.
- So these were the kind of mask raid masks
that you would go and they-- - Yes, exactly.
- Really sorts out your poker face problem, doesn't it,
when you're gambling.
- It's pretty good, it's fine. - It's pretty good mask on.
How could they have called anything?
- I guess usually they don't cover the lips, do they?
They're sort of-- - So if your tail is a big pal.
- No, if your tail is a big pal.
- Because they normally do say,
but your tail isn't your eyes.
- Not like-- - Do they?
- Yeah, not pulling faces with your arm.
- But the masks, you can see out of the mask,
you can still see people's eyes.
- Yeah, you can see, well yeah,
I didn't know the eyes were the tail.
I've been looking in the wrong bit.
- Love you, look at that, the nose.
There's no one's how to move, it's still there.
- Talking about the casinos in Italy,
in 1963, Sean Connery, I just couldn't believe this fact,
but it's there.
He's successfully backed the number 17 three times running
at the St. Vincent Casino in Italy.
- Yeah, you heard that, sorry?
- Matt, yeah. - I have heard the story.
I know that to be true in a way,
but it did happen to be that there was a lot of press there.
It was basically a publicity something like that.
- No, you think it was a publicity stunt,
but I like to believe it. - I think it was.
- Yeah. - Although he did, he put it on 17 twice
beforehand and it didn't work, didn't he?
It still seemed like he was like,
"Oh, something's going wrong."
- Oh, no.
- But yeah, basically most people these days
think it was a publicity stunt,
because it happened to be the week before his movie came out
and he was with all the press and everything like that.
- I saw a bit of footage the other day,
totally unrelated to it, but to this fact,
so it just happened to be watching it.
I'm convinced it must be a publicity stunt,
but I can't see anyone that says it was.
- Muhammad Ali, when he was up against Sunny Liston,
he turned to get the fight and to really get at him.
He kept showing up at his house in a bus
and yelling through a megaphone at three o'clock in the morning,
getting a method that has just infuriating him.
And there's footage of Sunny Liston at a table
in a casino rolling dice.
And Muhammad Ali beside him, just yelling at him,
I'm gonna take you down doing all this Ali stuff.
And just out of nowhere, Sunny Liston pulls a gun
out of his pocket and he fires it at Muhammad Ali.
And you see footage of Ali running out
and everyone freaking out.
And it turns out that the gun only has blanks in it
and he fires a couple of shots into his jacket
and then just goes back to rolling dice.
And everyone's fine with it.
And it moves on.
He must have crapped himself.
(laughing)
- Found this great line from Stephen Wright about gambling.
In Vegas, I got into a long argument
with the man at the roulette wheel
over what I considered to be an odd number.
(laughing)
- Do you know that all, you know this,
you all know the fact that all the numbers
on a roulette wheel added up together.
- No.
- They add up to 666, do you know that?
- Yeah, it's a bad sign.
People should know not to enter casinos.
(laughing)
But I actually did some research on roulette
for this series, the R series.
And I was reading into the number zero, quite heavily.
And did you know that zero was banned on roulette tables
in this country?
In the, I think it was the late '60s?
- Fairly.
- Yeah, so.
This way is the odds too much in favor of the casino?
- Well, it's way the odds in favor of the casino at all,
basically.
So, like you'll know, if you go to a casino today,
they all have a zero and they absolutely have to.
Otherwise, a casino wouldn't be able to come off
making money because there are 36 numbers.
And you're given odds of one in 36.
But there's this zero on.
Sometimes there's a double zero or triple zero
if you're really being ripped off.
But yeah, in the '60s, in 1967,
the law laws, like the equivalent of the Supreme Court,
decided that they didn't approve of this.
They thought it was unfair that the casino would have any advantage
and they banned zeros from roulette tables.
- Wow.
- And Scotland, your policeman would go round casinos
and like check for zeros on tables
and then close them down if they had them.
- And how long did that last for?
- It lasted a year.
And then they realized that all casinos were saying,
well, we're not going to do business anymore.
And people like casinos.
- It's so interesting.
- And so they changed that law.
- Amazing.
I was reading a thing that apparently something
that's experienced by quite a few casino goers
if they sit down as a slot machine,
they'll sometimes sit on quite a damp chair.
And that's because very, very dedicated gamblers
who've been playing on a single slot machine for ages
and know that if they leave,
it might be the next one that wins.
Don't go to the toilet, they're just going their trousers.
It's a big thing.
Sort of urinated urine-covered seats.
There's a big problem in casinos.
- Is it really?
- Yeah, yeah.
It's certainly--
- Well, a big problem.
- Well, I never noticed it when I've been to casinos.
I must say, but I can believe that.
I think they were like adult diapers.
- Well, this is, yeah, there's new products
that have been made specifically for a casino goers.
It's called "Player's Advantage" and the idea is,
it's a diaper that gets you an additional 10 to 12 hours
of continuous play.
So you can put, you know.
- Well, you've got to take a long, hard look at your life
and then when you're buying.
And there's advantage or whatever.
- The roulette wheel, we don't really know who properly
invented the modern one, but a lot of people
think it was Blaze Pascale, who's the mathematician,
who's like the father of probability, really.
And the idea that a lot of places say, I don't know if this is true,
that he was trying to make a perpetual motion machine,
which would make it a really bad game of roulette, wouldn't it?
- Very dull.
- The ball just comes from never, and ever, and ever.
- Well, the diaper would come in handy in that case.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is to promote his new product,
the inventor of Vaseline, would demonstrate his invention
by dipping his hands in acid and then healing the burn wounds
with the balm.
- Dedicated to his product, I'd buy it after that.
- Yeah, well, how quickly does Vaseline work?
- So this is, okay, so we've mentioned this guy very briefly,
he just got on the podcast, his name is Robert Chesa-Brue,
which does--
- I call him Chisbrue.
- I really wanna call him Chisbrue,
and I googled how to pronounce his name a bunch of times,
and it came up with Chesa-Brue.
- Okay, let's call him Chisbrue.
- Chisbrue is way better.
So yeah, Robert Chisbrue, he patented the balm Vaseline in 1872.
So he had this new invention.
He'd spent 10 years experimenting on himself
to see that it would work.
But for the time, it was hard to convince people
that it had any practical use.
So he became one of those traveling salesmen,
and he went to department stores all over New York,
where he would arrive at the location and do a demonstration.
The demonstration consisted of him dipping his hand in acid,
or sometimes holding his hand over an open flame,
burning himself, and then putting the balm on,
and then showing his other hand
that he had done a demonstration on the day before,
and how it had healed it up.
Yeah, so it was one hand at a time.
- Oh, wow, so it was the blue Peter of his day.
- Exactly.
- So he was one I made earlier.
- Yeah, exactly.
- A lot of trust in that demonstration, though, isn't there?
- Yes, yeah.
- 'Cause it fit, I mean, you're trusting
that he had done that the day before,
and he's not just every single day putting his one
with a hand in it, and so that's it.
I bet it was his left hand always
that he put it in acid, isn't it?
- That's true.
- Yeah, but so he did that and used to travel all over.
It was real frontline salesmanship from Old Cheeseborough.
- He would, he had a horse and cart, didn't he?
And he would give away samples,
and apparently this is the first time
people gave away samples of any products.
- Wow, that's a very good one.
- I don't know if that's, it doesn't sound true, does it?
It sounds like someone else must have thought of it,
but this is the first example that we've found.
- So he used to, Chesaborough or Cheeseborough,
whatever his name is, he used to have a distilled
sperm whale oil business, so yeah,
and that started becoming redundant
because the oil industry became huge,
and he was basically going bust,
and he used his very last few dollars to go to Pennsylvania,
and he was going to get a job in the oil industry.
And he noticed all these oil workers were always complaining
about the stuff called Rodwax,
which is a black gunk that glued up the drill heads
and then came out and cleaned it off.
And he got curious about this,
and he took a bucket of it home and he thought,
because if they got wounds and burns and cuts and things,
they smeared on it, it seemed to get better.
I don't think it's got healing qualities, actually,
but what it does, it keeps the dirt out of it,
that's one reason it's good for you.
- Yeah, and keeps moisture in, doesn't it?
- He was fascinated by this.
He took this home and his dad said he spent years and years
experimenting to turn it from this black goo
into this very clear, almost translucent balm.
And did you know he was a Brit?
- No, I was a Brit.
- So he was American.
- No, he worked in America, but he was actually a Brit,
and Queen Victoria used Vaseline.
We don't know why, she was a big fan,
and she actually knighted him in 1883.
- But unfortunately, the sod slipped off his shell.
(laughing)
'Cause he did used to cover himself in it.
That's the one thing that we mentioned.
He thought that it was just this amazing thing
that would cure everything,
and he thought there was some special stuff in it
that would make him better.
And he got pleuricy and he covered his whole body in it,
and he did actually get better,
but probably not 'cause of that.
- Well, he lived in '96, and he got sick in his late '50s.
And he hired a private nurse who was instructed
to rub him down, whole body rubbed down in Vaseline every day.
- I can't matter that job.
- And he had just been full of it, literally every day,
and he attributed his longevity to exactly that.
- Yeah.
- I mean, you would if it's your big business, right?
- You would say that.
- He was secretly taking a lot of sort of morphine
and aracy to hold.
(laughing)
- But I dug out some other uses of Vaseline,
apart from the obvious.
- Oh yeah.
- So it has been smeared on fish hooks to lure trout,
treat nappy rash, and toenail fungus.
It's used for staunching nose bleeds,
removing ring marks from furniture.
It's dabbed on cheeks by actresses to simulate tears,
removing makeup, predicting gun barrels,
shining patent leather shoes,
lubricating slide rules.
That's a neat use.
(laughing)
- That's a use for this afraid or sex issue.
- And then the moustache wax, sunscreen,
anti-failing for boats.
It's used by ear, nose, and throat surgeons
to combat nasal crusting.
- Ooh!
- I don't want to get nasal crusting
when you're under the knife, do you know?
(laughing)
- I like the one I really like is,
it's supposedly used in boxing before a fight,
so that a punch doesn't quite land on your face
and sort of slips off as you are doing.
- You see them put it on the cheekbones, do you?
- Yeah, and they're not allowed to do it mid-fight,
and some people are caught doing it,
so the coaches will come over
and subtly Vaseline their face up.
- In American football, if you're trying to stop
someone from getting to your quarterback,
you're not allowed to hold them, that's a big thing.
You're allowed to block them,
but not hold them.
- Yeah.
- And so people would put Vaseline on their whole bodies
so that when you're putting your hands out
onto the chest to block them, they just slip away from you.
- Wow.
- But the defensive people, they kind of go against it
by putting like drawing pins in their gloves
and like thumbtacks in their gloves,
so they can grip on even better.
- Is that allowed?
- I don't think it is allowed.
It doesn't sound allowed,
but I think people still do it.
- Wow.
- There was John, you're a director,
you've done a lot of advert director.
- Yeah.
- So do you know about the fact that it's used as a technique
to make a sort of soft focus effect?
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- So they smear Vaseline on the lens of a camera.
- They'd say entry that put some Vaseline on the lens.
- Yeah, it's extraordinary.
It's used in a lot of soft core porn.
- You know, you get that sort of thing where it's like
a dreamy look around the face, the actress or whatever.
- You can imagine.
And I didn't know you had such a strong career
in the porn industry before.
- Yes, absolutely.
(laughing)
- It was lubricating slide rules before you.
- So they use it in Star Trek, for example.
Any time that Captain Kirk played by William Shatner
would see a girl that was gonna be the girl of the week
as it were.
They would use this soft focus on that girl.
- So he goes, "Mr. D.R."
- Yeah.
- It looks like he's gone, "Mr. D.R."
- So I think I saw a remember that in Star Trek.
- And Doris Day, the actress used to have in her contract
that close-ups when she got older all had to be done
in soft focus because she was too worried
about her, the lines on her face and so on.
- Really?
- Yeah, so there's movies with her in Rock Hudson,
where Rock Hudson is in clear shot
as a close-up cut to Doris Day.
She's in the street, and it looks really odd.
- That is so weird.
- Yeah.
- They also, I just found one use on smearing over glass.
One use for it related to that, if you're a burglar,
was uncovered in 2012 when someone went around
burglaring apartments.
And people realized that he was doing the same thing
every apartment he burgled, which was smearing Vaseline
over the opposite apartment's people.
So when they looked out of their people, they couldn't see him
and I don't know why he thought they couldn't open
their own doors.
- Or they thought, "Who's that dreamy guy?"
(all laughing)
- Burgling that house.
Harrison Ford would never rob a home.
(all laughing)
- And you should mention me in commercials
and Captain Kirk in the same paragraph.
Just two of the ads I shot were actually
with William Chatner.
- Oh really?
- Yeah, in LA for Kellogg's, yeah.
- Really?
- He was great, he was such a good guy.
I got really well with him.
Very, very funny.
- Really?
- Did he demand the Vaseline for every shot?
- No.
(all laughing)
- Oh, just one interesting thing about Vaseline,
something else that it was very important
in the invention of was mascara.
So modern mascara was invented when a woman
called Mabel Williams, this was in 1915,
she sort of singed her eyebrows and eyelashes
in a kitchen fire.
And she wanted to make her eyelashes look longer again.
And so she came up with this homemade technique
of mixing ash and coal with Vaseline.
And then she applied her eyelashes and did the trick.
Her brother Tom, weirdly watching her,
watching her, spying on her
and decided to try and recreate this and commercialize it.
So he used a friend's chemistry set,
mixed it all together, made modern mascara
and named it after her, named it Maybelline.
- No, that's Maybelline?
That's your own Maybelline.
- Maybelline.
- That's really good.
That's great.
- Very cool.
So speaking of burns, there is one thing
that's used for treating burns
and that is poo shakes and that is like a milkshake
but it's made with poo.
And this is in New South Wales
and it's the Pot Macarie Koala Hospital.
Obviously they had a lot of fires in Australia recently
and love the koala's got burned.
And they found that by feeding them these poo milkshakes,
the koalas are getting better a lot quicker.
And it's basically your old gut bacteria thing.
So when you're a baby koala, you eat pap,
which is a mixture of digested half digested food
and bacteria is created in the mother's gut
and comes out through the seacum and the joey eats it.
And so what they're doing is they're trying to come up
with a way of imitating this by making these poo milkshakes
and they give them to the koalas
and it just helps them to put on weight.
It just helps them to get generally better
and that makes the burns heal more quickly.
- Okay, because it sort of builds up their immune system
against the burns.
- That's treating burns from the inside,
which is such a cool.
- Inside out.
- Yeah.
- My favourite burns, burns related story is,
which is in the 1940s.
And scientists wanted to come up with a pain scale.
They wanted to create the pain unit, the dull law.
And they decided the way they were going to do this,
where they were going to measure pain
and work out the scale was by taking women in labor
and then burning them repeatedly.
And then asking them to compare the sensation
of being burned to being in labor.
And the women were keen to do, they were interested.
They tended to be the wives of the doctors and the nurses.
They were like, yeah, fine, I'm gonna be in pain anyway.
And so they have these women who were in labor
going through contractions.
And then they just like burn their finger with a lighter
and say, how bad is that compared to your contraction?
And they were gonna be like, yeah, it's about the same.
And then it got worse and worse.
And they found they said that the problem was
that as contractions progressed,
the women became less good at coherently describing
their feelings.
So the researchers had to make inferences
about their pain based on their behavior.
So I think when she told me to go fuck myself,
I'll put that down as a tab.
[LAUGHTER]
But that's amazing.
Is the idea a bit like how, you know, if you have a splinter
and then you break your ankle, you forget about the splinter.
Is it that kind of thing?
It's not that idea.
The idea was that they thought that going,
the peak of labor was maximum pain.
So that would be max on the scale.
And then they wanted the women to quantify, be like,
all that burn is about a tenth as bad as the labor pain I've just felt.
But women got less and less good at perfectly rationalizing that pain.
Do you know, before QI was a thing,
I saw a little email group, six of us, they were in the group.
And we said this thing called the quite boring challenge.
Do you know this story?
No.
And the idea was one of us would nominate every week
a subject about which nothing interesting was or could be known.
OK.
And I started an I nominated Chumford,
because I grew up from near Chumford.
And I spent a week researching Chumford.
It was a fascinating facts I came up with.
And one of them is this, is that largest burns unit in Europe is in Chumford, in S6.
And for 30 years, the Conservative MP for Chumford was Simon Burns.
Oh, great.
OK.
Yeah, he was knighted in 2015.
He's the second cousin of David Bowie, of Bizarre.
But because he was educated at Worcester College, Oxford, where he got a third,
he's known by his friends as third-degree burns.
No, it's amazing when those QI facts come together.
OK, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Streiberland, James.
Ah, James Harkin.
Anna.
You can email podcasts at QI.com.
Yep.
And John, you're not on it either.
I like Anna.
I'm in social media at all.
Yeah, you too.
Copycat.
You can go to our group account and no such thing, or you can go to our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
We have everything up there from all of our previous episodes.
We have links to our behind-the-scenes documentary.
And actually, before we go, we're going to play out with a nice little song,
because, John, you're now at the manager of a band waiting for Smith.
Yeah.
And we've got their single here.
So I am the manager.
My name is Brian Ego.
Lovely boy is very talented.
And their latest single is called "So Much Love".
OK.
Well, we'll see you all again next week.
And the player's out now.
It's waiting for Smith.
We're so much love.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC - "SO MUCH LOVE"]
[BLANK_AUDIO]