- We run it on QI a few years ago.
- Yeah.
- Which was, there's no such thing as a fish.
- And it's not such thing as a fish.
- No, seriously, it's in the Oxford Dictionary
of Underwater Life.
It says it right now, first paragraph.
No such thing as a fish.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Triber.
I'm sitting here with three other elves,
James Harkin, Alex Bell, and Anichezinski.
And once again, we've gathered around the microphone
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And here we go, in no particular order.
Here they are.
(upbeat music)
Okay, back number one, Alex.
- Okay, when he was bored, Calvin Coolidge
used to ring a bell to summon his bodyguards
and then hide from them under the oval office desk.
(laughing)
- Really?
- Yep.
- Just as a joke.
But I mean, presumably after the first time you've done that.
Or did they have to be like parents?
- It's too bad.
- It's too bad for your child.
- Oh, where does it be?
Oh no!
- Probably.
- Yeah, I wouldn't have much trust in them
if they were continually fooled by it every time.
- That would be the worst of it.
- You would fire your secret service straight away.
You'd be like, seriously, this is the second time you're done.
- Yeah.
- Well, actually speaking of firing people and hiding,
I found a completely sort of slightly related fact
as well, secondary fact.
- Herbert Hoover had a really strict privacy policy
to the point where whenever he or his wife were on the approach,
the White House staff would signal to each other
using the bell system in the White House
and then hide in a cupboard or behind bushes
or something like that,
because he hated seeing his stuff
and really liked his privacy.
And they risked being fired if they were seen.
So anytime he came into a room,
they would sort of have to scramble around
and try and hide somewhere.
They also used to doing this
that when Harry Truman took over the presidency,
moved into the White House, yes.
- He was like, "Where are all my stuff?"
Herbert Hoover invented Hoover Ball, didn't he?
Which was--
- Is it as soon as he gets the ball
or the other player's hide and cover it?
So he just gets the ball right to the ball line?
- Yeah.
- Even hides under a desk, yes.
- This is when we find them.
- That's Cool Ridge Ball.
- No, it was actually invented by his doctor to keep him fit.
And it's a cross between according to the government website,
tennis, volleyball, and medicine ball.
Which do you guys know what that is?
- Medicine ball, yeah.
It's a big ball that you use for exercise.
- Yeah. - That big and everything.
So it's basically like volleyball
with a unbelievably heavy ball about the weight
of a newborn baby
and you throw it over the net.
Calvin Coolidge liked to eat breakfast in bed
while having his head rubbed with Vaseline.
- Was he bald?
'Cause that is a recipe for greasy hair.
- No, no, that's really bad.
- You know the guy who invented Vaseline?
He was, I forgot his name,
cheeseburger or something like that.
He thought that Vaseline was like a big sort of cure all
and he used to eat it every single day
and he used to rub it on his body all the time
'cause he thought it would cure him of all illness.
- And did it?
- Well, he's dead.
- Okay.
So it didn't make him live forever.
- Yeah, okay, so it wasn't an elixir.
I can understand why he does that.
I once went on a date and I couldn't find any hair gel
and my hair was really all over the shop.
- If this is something about Mary's story,
can I stop you there?
- I put tiger balm in my hair
and my god, that was the most intense sensation
I've ever had.
It was like putting chilies all over my head.
It was just like on fire
and my head stunk like hell.
I got in the train and everyone was like,
what is that?
- Was that a successful date?
- It was 'cause in the end, I had to admit it.
I was like, by the way, the reason my head smells like this
is because I did tiger balm over my head
and she said, I really like smell.
- It is quite a nice smell and if you have a cold,
it's quite so maybe if she was a bit blocked up.
- Exactly.
- You would have really helped her out.
- Exactly, my sinuses were, I can credit all that.
My point is though, is that maybe the Vaseline on his head
while he's eating kind of gives a slight kind of
like putting Tabasco on your face?
- Maybe that's how he managed to get Mrs. Coolidge.
She was like, oh really?
- Yeah, it was a smell of Vaseline.
- Have you thought of tiger balm?
- There is a thing called the Coolidge effect.
Do you know that?
- No.
- The idea is that male animals prefer to have sex
with females they've never seen before
than females that they have seen before
and it's called the Coolidge effects
and it's named after Calvin Coolidge.
- Why?
- It's a story about him and his wife
who were being shown around the farm
and they got to a chicken yard
and Mrs. Coolidge noticed that the male chicken
was having sex a lot and she said to the guy,
does he do that a lot?
And he said, oh yeah, he has sex about 12 times a day
and she goes, well, you should tell that to my husband.
So then the guy went to Calvin Coolidge
and he said, oh, this chicken has sex 12 times a day
and your wife told me to tell you about it
and he said, oh, is it the same chicken every time
that you have sex with?
And this guy said, no, it's a different chicken every time
and said, well, tell that to my wife then.
- Just a chicken farm and named it then.
- It was named after that anecdote
which I guess probably didn't even happen.
- Yeah.
- But just to make this clear,
that is a really cruel thing he said.
So he did basically say the only reason
he wants to keep having sex is 'cause it's not
with my wife every time.
He's saying, if I was to have sex 12 times a day,
it wouldn't be with you.
- Yeah.
- To be fair, is a pretty soggy move on her part.
- That was the way it goes.
- No one comes across well in that anecdote at all
apart from the chicken.
(laughing)
- Do you know, I only found something the other day,
a weird number of presidents of one Grammy Awards
for spoken word albums.
- Really?
- So I stumbled upon this 'cause Hillary Clinton
did a spoken word album which was
some kind of, you know,
telling us how we should live better album in the '90s.
Obama's won two Grammys for spoken words.
- Oh, really spoken words.
- Oh, they are well spoken.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- True.
- Clinton's got won, both the Clinton's got won Jimmy Carter.
- To be a president.
- You have to be well spoken though, don't you?
You have to be good at doing speeches, so.
- Yeah.
- Not that surprised me.
- It makes total sense.
- Yeah.
- I wonder who didn't get one.
- Well, George Bush certainly didn't.
- Did he not?
- Yet.
- So, is there any night just full of presidents,
just waiting the best spoken word?
We've got Clinton, Obama.
- I think the presidents are the only ones
who are asked to make audio tapes.
- It would be like, the winner is Calvin Coolidge.
Has anyone seen Calvin Coolidge?
(laughing)
- I want to talk about hide and seek
'cause we were talking about hide and seek.
- Oh yeah, yeah.
- Coolidge playing hide and seek.
So, you know how refrigerators
have got this magnetic seal that keeps them closed?
- Yeah.
- Because of hide and seek.
In 1958, the decade up to 1958,
a load of kids have been killed playing hide and seek
and hidden inside refrigerators.
And so, the new law was brought in saying
that they had to be capable of being opened
with a 15 pound push from inside.
And as soon as that law came in,
they had to come up with a way of making sure
they stayed closed, but we're able to be open
from the inside.
- And that shouldn't mind.
- Should a kid push, because previous to that,
would it lock and then--
- Well, they used to have latches on them.
- So the kid would be stuck inside.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- That's interesting, because I only found out recently
that in back to the future, the time machine
was originally supposed to be a fridge.
And the reason it was changed was because of a fear
that kids would start trying to imitate them
and locking themselves in fridges.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
- Should we wrap up on this one or this one?
- No, go, go, go, go, it.
- I was just looking at things,
well, hobbies of presidents, which quite good
and related to hide and seek.
So, Woodrow Wilson made his secret service staff,
paint his golf balls black and wintered, didn't he,
so that he could still see them in the snow.
But, in more humorous news,
one of Einstein's favorite hobbies was sailing,
and he loved to sail even though he couldn't swim
and refuse to wear a life jacket.
And, at one point in his life,
he had to be pulled from the water by a teenager
who heard him crying out for help
and pulled Einstein out of the water.
And the teenager just disappeared,
so no one knows who that teenager was,
but Einstein's life saved by a teenager.
But, bizarrely, this year,
there's a fish called Einstein in black pool,
and it got a bladder infection,
which meant that it stopped being able to swim
and just sank to the bottom.
And so, the guy in black pool has designed
a tiny fish life jacket,
which the fish now uses to swim in.
So, unlike Einstein,
this poor Einstein fish has been forced into a life jacket
and given the chance to swim again.
I just think that's a really weird mirroring
of the real Einstein's life.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, time for fact number two.
And that's my facts.
My fact this week is that until 2011,
the sun was only in theory a sphere,
but it's now confirmed to be a sphere.
- Oh yeah, how have you confirmed that?
- NASA confirmed it.
- Oh, did they?
- Yes.
- How did they do that?
- So, NASA, basically,
and this was a headline that appeared
on NASA's official website on February the 6th, 2011.
It said, "It's official, the sun is a sphere."
And the idea was that NASA had two twin stereo probes.
They were called stereo,
and they went to either side of the sun
and took the first 3D photo.
Basically, they got to the dark side of the sun,
as it were.
They got to the side that we never see.
- Yeah, it's not dark as such, though.
- But just in terms of a badly chosen words,
it's the dark side of the sun.
- That would have been amazing if they got to the other side
and it turned out to be dark.
- Yeah, it would be amazing.
Or flat, or hologram, something awesome.
But anyway, I just find that amazing.
I find that we've gone all this time
and just assuming that scientists agree that it's a sphere.
And it's probably a bit tongue in cheek,
but I just like that is how far scientists do actually go.
- Might not be.
- That's what they say.
- It is amazingly spherical, the sun.
- Yeah, they don't understand why this is the case.
It was discovered only in 2012.
It's the most perfect sphere in nature by quite a long way.
And I think it's the second most perfect sphere
in the universe that we know of.
- What's the first?
- The first are the silicon balls
that have been used as a replacement for the kilogram.
So one incredible thing is that if you scale the sun
to the size of a beach ball,
it's bold, the biggest dip in it
would be less than the width of a human hair.
But even so, the biggest dip on the sun.
So the biggest difference between it's smallest diameter
and it's biggest is 10 kilometers.
And if my mass is right,
if you blew up this perfect sphere
that we've created to the size of the sun,
then the biggest dip in it would be about 120 centimeters.
- I know you always wanted to have a Guinness Book of Record done.
- Yes.
- One that you can't have is the record
for longest time spent staring at the sun,
because the Guinness Book of Records specifically
refuses to accept entries for that one.
- Ah.
- Why, because it's too dangerous?
- Because it's too dangerous.
Isaac Newton used to do experiments
where he would look at the sun for as long as possible.
And he did it one time for so long
that he had to shut himself up in a darkened room
and wait for his sight to return.
And it took three days for his sight to return.
- Not so smart, he's scientist.
Not so smart.
- In 1999, when there was no clips,
a lot of people were looking at the sun then.
And when people obviously damaged their eyesight
and they went to a hospital afterwards,
the doctors could tell exactly when they looked at the sun
by looking at the impression on the retinas.
So it was like a halfway through the eclipse,
it would have the half sickle of the sun.
- Wow.
- That's so cool.
- That's extraordinary.
- Although I don't know how anyone's eyes got damaged then,
because I remember it and it was so cloudy.
- So the original fact that we had here was how we didn't know
for sure that the sun was a sphere.
But people were pretty certain about it.
So Galileo, for instance, he could see the sunspots
going round the back and coming back again.
And so he postulated that it must be a sphere.
And there are lots of other reasons why we were pretty certain
it was a sphere.
But not 100%.
- Yes, exactly.
- I wrote a headline, which you guys are gonna hate.
- But.
- So the people listening to this podcast,
they must hear Dan about to say something
and then those are all groaning and wonder why we do it.
And it's, you know what, it's the luck on his face.
As soon as he's about to say something ridiculous,
he has this luck as if to say,
"I'm a naughty boy, you guys are all good, shout out me."
Anyway, go on.
- Okay, so the world almost ended in 2012.
But we survived by a week.
This is what happened.
The sun had a ginormous solar flare in 2012 around July.
And it shot out into one particular bit of space.
We were a week away from the end of the path of where it went out to.
And scientists have said that if we were in the path,
if we were a week ahead in time,
or if it happened a week later and we were in that path,
the size of the solar flare
would have knocked us basically back to the dark ages.
It was literally, we were that close to destruction.
- What, and if we'd just been a bit further ahead
in our rotation around the sun?
- Yes, we would have been in its path.
So it's just, we just happened to not be in its path.
- Wow.
- I am slightly terrified of the sun
because there is this massive risk of coronal mass ejections
just wiping out all technology on the planet,
which is just horrible at it.
There was a massive solar storm in 1859,
which is the storm that has had the biggest effect on Earth,
since records began on this.
And the biggest piece of technological infrastructure
that existed at that point was the telegraph network.
And it basically, all across Europe and US,
it basically shut down.
Everyone unplugged their machines,
but there were sparks flying off all the pylons.
And even if you turned off the transmitters,
they were still sending and receiving messages.
And all right, we're seen all over the world.
And in places like the Rocky Mountains,
it was so bright that the gold mine
has actually got up and started making breakfast
'cause they thought it was daytime.
- Wow.
- Wow, really.
- Yeah, Lloyd's of London, the insurance people.
In 2013, they did a study using the data
from 1859 to work out how much it would cost
if that kind of thing happened today.
And they estimated that in the US,
it could cost up to $3 trillion worth of damage,
even if it was just that strong.
So it could go so much worse than that.
- Very scary.
- Yeah.
- You were just saying about these guys
who woke up in the middle of the night
because they saw the corona.
- Earlier this week, there was an earthquake in California.
It was in the Napa Valley where they made wine.
And enough people around there have these,
you know, these exercise bands that are attached
to the internet and it can tell how many steps
you've done every day and how your heart rates doing
and such like that.
And they could work out who would woken up
at the same time as this earthquake went off.
And they found out that more than half of the people
who woke up during the earthquake stayed up
for the rest of the night,
even though it went off at 3 a.m.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, that's a great thing.
- Just a way that you can take information
that was for another thing and then work out
how humans react to something.
- Yeah.
- You mentioned California and the sun.
So, relatedly, there's a big solar plant in California
and when birds fly over the top of it,
often they catch fire because the sun's crazy,
so concentrated, so then they've called them streamers,
the guys who work there and these birds fly through
and cat ignites to spontaneously combust mid-flight.
- Wow.
- And set on fire.
It's really sad.
- Yeah, it's very sad.
They've got to freak out mid-flight.
Like, that's never happened before.
- Yeah.
- You're on fire.
- Oh, thank you.
No, no, you're on fire.
- You're on fire.
- Literally.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, time for fact number three.
And that is Chazzynstee.
- Yeah, my, in fact, is that there are some birds nest
that contain over a hundred rooms
and are so heavy that they cause trees to fall down.
- What?
- Yeah, so these are really cool.
This is my new favorite creature, I think,
the sociable weaver bird,
which you find in Southern Africa
and South Africa, Botswana, places like that.
And they are really sociable,
so they build these gigantic nests
where up to 400 birds will live in one nest
and they have loads and loads of different chambers.
And they're incredibly efficient
for a bunch of different reasons,
but they do weigh an enormous amount.
And so--
- Trees will collapse.
- Yeah, trees are tree-recently collapsed
under their weight, so they can weigh almost 1,000 kilograms,
which I think is about as much as 12 adult men.
So if you stick 12 adult men in a tree,
it's likely sometimes the branch is gonna break and it did.
The desert where most of these birds live
is obviously very hot in the daytime
and gets very cold at night.
And it's insulated so that if you go right into the middle
of this nest where they all roost together,
then it's much warmer at night,
like more than 10 degrees warmer than it is in the daytime.
And then in the daytime, if you hang out
in the outside chambers,
it's more than 10 degrees cooler than it is in the daytime
'cause it's so well-shaded.
- Wow.
- Do they have different rooms for different things?
Or do they have their own rooms and stuff?
- They all-- the pairs have their own rooms,
so each room will be a pair and sometimes they're offspring
and then in the center will be where they all sleep together.
- It's like a hotel.
- It really is, it's incredible.
It is like--
- Wow.
- And it's not just that.
- Is it the other birds live in there as well?
- Yes.
- I saw a list of some of the other birds
who live there, they include the familiar chat.
(laughing)
The ashy tit and the rosy faced love bird.
- Oh.
But yeah, they do, they let other birds live in them,
which I think is also great of these guys.
When they've got a spare room going,
they say to their mates,
"Hey, you can be asked to build a nest, don't worry."
- So they're like a hostel.
- Yeah.
- It's like Airbnb.
- Yeah exactly.
- Badgers do that as well, don't they?
- Today.
- Yeah, 'cause badgers have sort of like a very similar
to a rabbit hole, but it's,
'cause rabbits only let rabbits in,
but badgers are like, if they see a rabbit,
they'll be like, "Come on in mate, show us."
Yeah, yeah, and they let them live with them, yeah.
- Are you sure this isn't a watershed down?
Or might be windin' the willows of the birds, yeah.
Badger, they all wear tweed, right?
- Prairie dogs, we've done on QI as well,
quite sensibly, and they're quite similar to these birds,
and I also like them for it, aren't they?
'Cause they have enormous burrows, prairie towns,
I think they're called.
So they're smaller than they used to be,
'cause they're now more in danger.
But in 1900, a prairie town was found
that took up 25,000 square miles and housed
400 million prairie dogs.
But that's how many?
- 400 million.
(laughing)
- Are you hearing the number?
- That's like the population of America, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- So you've got--
- You've got prairie dogs in America, then, yeah.
- That's amazing.
In one house.
(laughing)
- It's in a book called Prairie Conservation,
preserving North America's most.
- Why do they need to go out of service?
(laughing)
- They need to go out of service.
- They need it in every single house.
- They're doing good.
(laughing)
- But they let other animals live in their homes as well,
so you get burrowing out.
- How is the ready room?
(laughing)
- Come on out, squeeze in.
- Let's go back to Nests.
- Yeah, sure.
- That was about Nests.
- You were talking about the temperature of the Nests,
how it flops you with?
- Yes.
- I found something great thing about temperature and Nests.
The sex of an alligator and some other reptiles,
like lizards and turtles,
is determined by how warm the nest is that they're laden.
So for alligators, if the egg is kept in a nest,
it turns out female, and if it's 34 degrees,
it turns out male.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- So in 2009, some researchers found a geofalcon nest
in the Arctic, and they did some radio carbon dating on it,
and they found that it'd been in use for 2,500 years.
So people have been living there since the Roman era,
or birds have been living there for the second time.
(laughing)
- First just outside and get out of my house.
- Wow, that's incredible.
- Yeah, Dan, you've been away at the Edinburgh Festival.
- Yes.
- While you're away, Gregg Jenna came in,
who was in one of our earlier podcasts.
He's a historian from Horrible Histories,
and we were talking about a human nest.
It was like a mattress inside a cave somewhere in Africa.
So this mattress was in use for 77,000 years.
- Wow.
- So many 7,000 years, I imagine how long that is.
Like 2,000 years was like when Jesus was around.
- When Jesus was around.
- It was 77,000 years.
- Is it still in use?
- It's mattress.
- Oh, no.
- Okay.
- I mean, we should keep the tradition going.
- That's true actually.
- Yeah, why do we stop?
- They used moss, and they would put it in this corner of a cave.
And then they'd use it for a while, for a while, for a while,
and then they would burn it and put more moss on top,
and then they would burn it and put more moss on top.
And this moss was particularly good,
because it would stop insects from being able to live there.
So it was a really good place to sleep.
- But also, so you're saying it's the exact same bed,
effectively?
- Because they just kept adding different bits of the mattress on top.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, wow.
- And they almost never changed the bedding.
We did ask about it.
It was only about every 2,000 years or something
that they bothered even changing the moss.
- Just on the subject of mattresses, I was reminded,
there's a trap door at the bottom of the blue whale
and the natural history is even London.
When they opened it up, they discovered a mattress in there.
And it was basically a time capsule inside the blue whale,
because it was when they were building it,
where all the workmen would sneak in.
So they found a bunch of magazines and newspapers
and empty wrappers, but also a mattress,
because apparently horny curators,
that used to be a top location.
- I can't believe they went to that sort of trouble.
- Think about it.
If you're someone who works at the Natural History Museum,
you're already quite a big dork.
And so the idea of sex inside a blue whale, yes please.
I mean, even I think that that's the best possible location.
- The problem with the mattress.
- I don't know why they need a trap door,
because a blue whale's vagina is large enough to walk through.
- That's such a good point.
- Maybe it's a male blue whale.
- Yeah.
- Oh, that's probably it.
- I was just gonna talk really quickly about the weaver birds,
just because they often now build their nests
on telegraph poles and pylons.
So you'd recognize their nests.
And anyway, this often causes power outages.
So I was looking at animals that cause power outages
and squirrels are always cutting off electricity.
So there are some electricity companies that say that
two-thirds of their electricity outages
just come from squirrels chewing through wire
or like linking up circuits by jumping from one bit to another.
And they've shut down the Nasdaq twice.
I think an estimated $20 million worth of shares
were not traded in that time.
- $20 million.
- Okay, guys, numbers can be big.
Let's get over that.
- Time for the final fact of the show, James.
- Okay, my fact is the worst baseball team in South Korea
has replaced its supporters with robots.
So these guys are called the Hanwai Eagles.
They've lost more than 400 games in the last five years.
They came bottom of the league in the last two years
and their opposition have started calling them
the Hanwai chickens because they don't put up any kind of fight.
What they do is they have these screens around the pitch
and you can, using your computer or your phone,
you can put your photo on the screens
and you can make the screens do Mexican waves
or do cheers or chants or whatever.
I just think that's quite a--
- That is cool.
- That's so sad, isn't it, though?
- I mean, so the players, and it's the idea
that the players are supposed to feel rejuvenated
at the site of automated things
which are being forced mechanically to cheer them on.
- Yeah, I think it's solving like that.
- Yeah.
- I think it's a bit demoralizing.
- It's solving the wrong problem.
Like it's, the problem is the bad team,
not that the fans are booing because they suck so much.
It's like, do you know what we got to solve about this?
Our fans, they're the problem.
- Let's invest all our money in futuristic robots.
- Let's invest all our money to cheer as we lose
again and again and again.
- Okay, so here's another way of using your fans,
maybe a slightly better way.
You guys don't like the robot thing.
- I like the robot thing.
I just think it's not solving an issue.
- Well, the Washington Bullets had this superfan
called Robin Ficker.
And what they would do with him is they'd let him sit
behind the opposing coach's bench
and they would give him a megaphone
and he would make fun of the opposing team
by shouting at them.
So he would make fun of the coach's outfits
or when the Chicago Bulls came to play,
he read the sex passages of the Bulls'
coach's autobiography.
- That's him, Jeremy and the game.
- Wow, he's distracting.
- I was looking up robots and death.
And I found out that Jeremy Clarkson
was really killed by a robot was.
Apparently one of the robots was fighting another robot
and a circular blade came loose and zoomed across the studio
and there you had it on film
and they played it back in slow motion
and it went across his head two inches above his scalp.
- Whoa, sorry, yeah.
- We actually know who the first person
would be killed by a robot.
And his name was--
- Robbie Williams. - Robbie Williams.
- Yeah.
- How was he killed by robot?
It was in a-- - He was in a calf factory
or something like that and he was in fog factory
and he was hit by a protruding arm
and he was killed by that.
- So it was like, 'cause it was an arm,
kind of was a robot.
- Yeah.
- Well, it was a big mechanical device.
It was for moving car parts from one end
to the factory together
and it just, he got hit on the head really hard to it.
The second guy who got killed by robot,
definitely got killed by a robot.
His name was Kenji Rada and that was two years later
and he got pushed into a grinding machine by a robot arm.
- Ooh. - Yeah.
- Like was it a malicious intent?
- So there's never been a malicious intent.
There is an innate human fear of robots.
The first use of the word robot was in a plague
by Czech playwright Carol Kappett
called Rosam's Universal Robots
and it was about robots trying to take over and kill people.
- 9% of Americans, when surveyed,
admit that they will have sex with a robot.
- I would have sex with a robot.
- So was that book called Sex and Robots,
which it's a guy who's a huge computer scientist
and chess champion saying that he thinks
will have sex with robots within 50 years?
- Well, he's one of the 9%.
- Yeah, definitely.
- They did have the first kissing robots in 2008.
They were made in Taiwan
and they performed as the stars in Phantom of the Opera.
They did an all robots cast for Phantom of the Opera
and these two robots kiss
and it's the worst kiss you've ever seen.
Their heads come together
and then they pause for 10 seconds
and their heads pull apart.
It's like at a 12 year old's disco.
- Empathetic robots are a thing
that just been experimented with
and they've sort of are claiming they've invented
where their robots that respond
to your own facial expressions
with matching facial expressions
and they're preparing, why are you smiling?
- It's really creepily.
- Sorry.
- Okay, I'm gonna start looking at you.
So they've come up with empathetic robots now
who's faces top of everybody.
They've come up with empathetic robots
who's faces mirror the facial expressions that humans have
in the hope that they can care
for lonely humans in future
but again, a bit like the fake cheering crowds in career.
It seems like a sad thing if you need a robot
to fake empathetic facial expressions
in order to feel okay.
- Our buddy, Leven Skyra,
who was on this podcast a few episodes ago,
just actually took part in the opposite version
of what we're talking about,
which was the World Robot Football Cup.
- Oh yeah.
- And he went out to Brazil, I think.
It was in Brazil. - Yeah, it wasn't Brazilian.
- And so it was robots playing against each other
at football and Leven was saying
that they've projected that within 50 years,
a robot football team will be able to beat
a human football team.
- Within two months they'll be able to beat Man United.
(laughing)
Did you see, so if you've seen this,
- No, I haven't.
- So we're recording this on Wednesday,
but on Tuesday, Man United played against MK Duns
who are lower in the third tier of English football
and they lost four nil.
- Whoa.
- And there was a great thing on Twitter.
There was a girl who'd got a free bet
from an online betting site
and she put two pound 50 on Man United to win four nil.
But it accidentally put two pound 50 on MK Duns
to win four nil at 500 to one.
- Wow.
- And she was like, "Oh my God, oh my God, oh my God,
"I've won over a thousand pounds."
- That's great.
- Anyway, let's talk about, oh, we'd like to talk about.
- I was gonna talk about sports fans
since we're on sports now.
So I was looking at generally sports fans,
one of them using things I like that's happened
in the past is that during baseball matches
until about a hundred years ago,
'cause the stadium was smaller.
If you hit the ball out of the stadium,
it would fall into the long grass
and the game had to stop for five minutes
and everyone, the fans and the players
had to spend five minutes searching for the ball
because they wouldn't have lots of spare balls.
I think now in baseball balls just get lost
and that's it, they have, they bring spare.
- People take them, don't they?
- Yeah.
- What do you get to, if it comes out and you catch it,
it's your ball.
- Yeah.
- That's how it works.
- It's another thing about old baseball games
where they didn't have as many umpires in those days.
And some of the umpires were allowed to,
if they weren't quite sure about a decision,
they're allowed to consult the audience,
consult the crowd.
- I can't want to be a millionaire.
- Yeah, exactly.
And see what the crowd thought
and then use their ideas if they couldn't really work it out.
- 92% of the audience thinks that that was a home run.
- God, must have sucked when you were playing away games.
- Yeah.
- If you plainly made it and you just missed it,
did you make it?
- No.
- Definitely not.
- So I think the angriest any sports fans
have ever been and James will know about this
and it must be during the Heidi game.
- Is that the Kevin Courage game?
(laughs)
- Heidi goes Seeky.
- Yeah.
- I don't think I know about the Heidi game.
- It's so good.
And it is frequently voted the most exciting game
for American football of all time.
It was Oakland Raiders versus New York Jets.
And it was really close.
The New York Jets were just ahead of the Oakland Raiders,
but it was obviously a really thrilling match.
It had about three minutes left.
And suddenly at the very last minute,
the Oakland Raiders overtook the New York Jets
and they won and it was a massive title
and it was a massive deal.
And NBC, the network that was broadcasting it,
as it had overrun by a couple of minutes past its three hours,
switched over automatically to show Heidi
for all the kids on the other channel.
Now, they didn't want to do this.
The NBC executive saw that it was a really thrilling match
and we're like, we've got to obviously keep this on the airwaves.
So they tried to call the studio to say,
obviously keep the match on, guys.
Look at this.
This is the biggest match ever.
But so many people, so many angry fans
were trying to call the studio to say,
I can't believe you're going to switch over to Heidi.
It's outrageous.
I want to watch the rest of the match.
That their phone lines broke down and the executives
couldn't get through to the studio to say, keep it on.
So in the great irony of fan complaints,
they caused Heidi to overtake the match
by calling breaking the phone lines and Heidi came on.
And then NBC managed to irritate people further,
I think, by during this episode of Heidi,
there was a really touching scene
where Heidi's disabled sister, I think, learns to walk
and they thought, what can we do to remedy this?
So they flashed up the score suddenly
for the fans in the middle of high school.
All these little kids suddenly tearing up at this scene.
And they say it sounds like an homestay to Fergie, bro.
My favorite baseball player, just before we finish,
is Joe Sprintz, OK?
And one of his rivals, another baseball catcher,
had caught a ball that had been dropped
from the top of a building.
And he got a world record for the highest catch
from a high point.
So he decided that he wanted to beat this record.
And so he got a friend to go up into a blimp.
And someone was going to drop the ball
from the top of this hot air balloon.
And he was going to catch it.
Oh, my God.
OK.
He caught it in the way that baseball players do
with his mitt directly above his face.
The ball hit his mitt.
The mitt hit his face.
And he fractured his jaw and lost five teeth.
And apparently, he dropped the ball.
Oh!
And someone alongside him just went, "Stop hitting yourself!"
"Stop hitting yourself!"
OK, that's it for this episode.
That's all our facts.
Thanks so much for listening.
If you want to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said during the course
of this episode, you can get us on our Twitter handles.
James, you're on Alex.
Alex, Alex, go under school.
I'm on @Triberland.
And Chazinski.
You can email podcast@keywire.com.
Still not on since I've been away.
Still hasn't happened.
OK.
And you can head over to nosuchthingasaffish.com,
which houses all of our previous episodes.
And we're going to be back again next week with another episode,
for more facts.
So stay tuned.
And we'll see you then.
Good luck.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(SINGING) We get together.
Sure we can do.
We'll hold on to you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[BLANK_AUDIO]