Hello, and welcome to another edition of "No Such Thing as a Fish Presents International
Fat Ball".
The only football podcast out there that makes absolutely no mention of football whatsoever
brought to you by VisitEngland.com.
We are the QI Elbs, my name is Dan, I'm sitting here with James, Andy, and Anna.
The match today is Columbia versus C么te d'Evoire, and we're about to find out who the most
interesting of those two are.
So let's begin.
Columbia.
Okay, a fact about Columbia.
Yeah.
Okay, Columbians traditionally drank Armadillo blood to treat asthma.
Wow.
Does it work?
I believe not.
Yeah.
And also, you get asthma quite a lot.
It's not like you just take a course of it and it's gone for the rest of you.
You need basically a live armadillo with a flesh wound.
Yeah, and treat it like an inhaler.
Yeah, exactly.
So people carry them around because you would be like, "In a handbag, you have an asthma
sufferant and she starts asking you, like, did you remember your armadillo?"
Yeah, sorry, can I borrow your armadillo?
I'm just feeling a bit...
One traditional snack in the Santander region of Columbia, which I did not know was a region,
is Hormigas culonas, which translates to ants with a big bum, because they are a kind
of ants that people like eating as a snack, and they're very rare and very valuable, because
they only come out of their nesting ground one or two days a year.
Sorry, do you mean rare as in undercooked, or...?
It has some great festivals, Columbia.
It's home to some of the various biggest festivals in the world, it's home to the biggest
theatre festival, as in, like, the highest number of people are ten, the biggest salsa festival,
biggest flower parade, and the biggest outdoor horse parade.
Oh, that's very good.
What's the biggest indoor horse parade?
I know of only one famous Colombian.
Okay, who's that?
Gabrielle Garcia Marquez, the fantastic, incredible author who passed away, sadly, this year.
And there's an interesting fact here, which I did not know is not on the blurb of his book.
His grandmother was a secret witch doctor, and his grandfather once killed a man in a duel.
Wow.
Yeah.
Pistols at dawn.
That's amazing.
Bring your armadillos.
He was really and wasn't he, Marquez.
He was married to his wife Mercedes for 55 years, and every day throughout those years,
she put a yellow rose on his desk in the morning.
For a reason?
To say hi.
Do you need a reason to present your wife with a flower?
Yeah.
Just for romantic, though.
I need a wife.
I need a wife first.
Well, Mercedes meant mercies, the plural of mercy.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
No, I didn't know that either.
You must have heard of another Colombian, Dan, Pablo Escobar?
Yeah.
The famous drug bar, and he was Colombian.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay.
He had a great big house where he kept loads of animals and stuff like that, and apparently
a lot of his hippos keep escaping from the house and terrorizing local towns.
Wasn't that, didn't that help the police find him?
Because hippos are not native to Colombia.
You will ask questions, wouldn't you?
Yeah, that's true.
In the 1990s, Escobar owned one of the best football teams in Colombia at Letico Nacional.
And their rivals, Millionarios, belong to a rival drug trafficker.
Wow.
Which is amazing.
He apparently used to have big parties.
Hey.
Escobar.
Yeah, yeah.
And at those parties, he would drown his enemies in the pool.
Is it kind of like two boroughs, one stone kind of thing?
Wow.
I don't want to just like do the dull stuff.
What?
That's a party and then we can have this happen back.
As one of his enemies, if you receive, with their people going, "I'm so surprised I'm
invited to Escobar's party.
He's never liked me, but I mean, I guess we should go, right?"
When he's going to say no to a pool party, he said it's a pool party, but he said I don't
need to bring trunks.
I don't understand.
Well, yeah.
Madeline's an interesting town.
They have a no-pants day as a protest against the government.
I have a no-pants day several times a week, not as a protest, just as a way of life.
Well, the many reasons we've changed the locks on this office, Andy, how did you get in today?
You mean no pants, you mean trousers?
Yes, I am.
American style pants.
Okay.
Well, I'm still having a no-pants day today.
Yeah, it's against freedom of expression, and so they walk around the town with no trousers
on.
I mean, sort of on the subject of this, there's a remote outpost in Colombia called it's
pronounced "loss penis", although it's not quite.
Nothing funny about that?
No, you're right.
Absolutely, no, it's just a way of expressing yourself.
And the guys who live there, it's separated from the nearest town by a ravine, and the Colombian
government's decided that it's too expensive, and there aren't enough people living there
to build a bridge over the ravine.
And so the nearest school, for instance, is in the nearest town, and all the kids have to
get there by ziplying across the ravine.
Oh, wow.
And as you can imagine, they're not the safety conscious zipliers at tourist, try when they pop
over to New Zealand.
You don't want to get your lost penis stuck in that ziplier.
Bogota also has a laziness museum, it's a museum in Bogota, which aims to make people think
about the social issues implied in taking a nap, in being jobless or in feeling that maybe
we are wasting our time.
Do you want to go to the laziness museum?
Yeah.
Imagine the staff behind the desk, yeah, just go in.
Why the no cards here, telling us what all these exhibits are, and actually, why the
no exhibits.
OK, now it's time for the halftime show, which is three QI questions brought to you by VisitingLin.com
and the three questions, with the answers being revealed at the end of this podcast are
James.
OK, my question is, how many lakes are there in the lake district?
Question number two, Andy.
Where is the southernmost point of the mainland in England?
OK.
Question number three from Anna, which world first was built outside the houses of commons
in 1868?
OK.
It's time for match to resume play and making their way onto the pitch.
It's Cote d'Ivoire.
So Cote d'Ivoire, who wants to go first?
OK.
Are we going to keep calling it Cote d'Ivoire or Ivory Coast?
Why, let's go for both.
Cote d'Ivoire is what most places in the world call it, but usually places in the UK call
it Ivory Coast, both are acceptable.
I prefer to call it Ivory Cote because it reminds me of my favourite item of clothing.
You've really got to hand that to a museum.
They've had a lot of problems in Ivory Coast over the last several years.
They've had a civil war and they've had a lot of domestic unrest.
So partly as a result of that, everyone's very young.
The average age is about 19 across the whole country and also wages are very low.
So someone earning as little as $100 per month is pacified as being middle class, officially.
Wow.
Yeah.
It is a troubled place we were saying that's quite hard to come up with more fun facts in the
Ivory Coast because there are a lot less fun facts.
As you say, Andy, it has been embroiled in civil war, basically since 1999 with a couple
of respites.
One of the major respites in the civil war was in 2006 during the World Cup and I know
we're not supposed to mention football, but the Ivory Coast football team was credited
with causing a truce because as soon as the Ivory Coast qualified for the World Cup,
the football team brought the boring parties together and made them sign a truce.
Because both sides were supporting the Ivory Coast and the World Cup, it brought them together
for a time.
I know an interesting fact about their independence day.
Go on.
Their independence day is the seventh of August.
Good one, Dan.
Doesn't really sound like much of a fact.
Yeah.
They celebrate it on December 7th.
Oh, that is good.
What really?
Why?
I think it's because by the time the harvests have been collected and sold, that's when they
get paid.
And so their independence day was set up on that, but they didn't actually have enough
money to have a proper celebration.
So it's just a better time of year.
A better time of year.
So they celebrate August the 7th Independence Day on December 7th.
We should celebrate Christmas in the summer when it's nice and sunny and not cold and
horrible.
One thing you were like, Dan, is that there is a group of people in the Ivory Coast
who are called the Dan.
Really?
And they specialize in doing stilt dances, dancing while on stilts.
And their main town is called Man.
So you could be Dan of Man.
Yeah.
I like it.
That's very cool.
Yeah.
There's another group of people, and I really like this.
They're called the Bowel people.
And they believe in another parallel world called Blolo.
And that means elsewhere.
So a man can have a Blolo Blah, which is another wife from the beyond.
And the female version of that is a Blolo Bianne, which is obviously a man for the wife.
But they tend to have a negative effect on this life, the other, the normal life, not
Blolo life marriage.
I've got a dance in Ivory Coast called the Fouca Fouca.
Oh, yeah.
Do you know of that?
No.
It's the dance that Didier Dropout used to do when he scored a goal.
I know we're going back to football again, sorry about that.
Yeah.
Oh, OK.
But it's called the Fouca Fouca.
What was it like?
Like a hip swivel.
Yeah, I see.
Well, the original twerking comes from the Ivory Coast as well.
Really?
There's a dance called them a Fouca dance, which is a traditional dance from the Ivory
Coast.
It's performed by women.
And another name for it is La Donce du Fessier, which means the dance of the behind.
In 1998, the government of the Ivory Coast prohibited its performance in public.
Wow.
And here's one more dance craze from the Ivory Coast.
Flap your arms and cluck like a dying chicken.
This was a bird flu dance that they did.
It was invented by a 21-year-old disc jockey, DJ Lewis, who invented a dance making light
of bird flu by imitating a chicken in its death rolls during a call.
Wow.
If they would bring that into British clubs, then I would definitely start going out on
the town again.
That's true.
Well, maybe we should go out tonight and try it.
Let's start the trend.
There is an absolutely amazing building in Cote d'Ivoire, which is, it's a basilica at,
and I'm going to say this wrong, Yamusukro.
And it's the tallest basilica in the world as in, it's taller than some Peters in Rome.
They built it slightly smaller than some Peters in Rome at the request of the Pope.
And then they put a massive gold cross on it to make it taller at the top, so it's sort
of cheated.
But a classic cheat for tall buildings around the world, always a large spike at the top.
Like the Empire State Building, the radio mask.
They didn't need that.
Yeah.
It's so big that a third of all the Catholics in Ivory Coast could worship there.
Wow.
And also, I read that it's got the largest air-conditioned space in the world.
That sounds nice.
That church does.
Yeah.
Let's go there, because I am bloody hot in this office today.
It is.
It is hot.
Okay, that's it.
That's full time.
That's the end of our match.
Before we find out who has won, we are going to quickly get the answers to our visitingland.com
quiz that was our halftime show.
Starting with the questions, James, what was the first?
Okay, the first question was, how many lakes are there in the lake district?
It was a bit of a trick question.
Most of them are mirrors or waters.
The only one that's actually called a lake is Bass and Thwite Lake.
So the answer is one.
One lake?
Yes.
I did not know that that was right.
Andrew Hunter Murray gets a point.
That's a nice Andy.
My question was, what's the southernmost point on the English mainland?
And if you were thinking it's landzend, it's not.
It's actually lizard point, which is not quite as far west, but it is a bit further south.
Okay.
And Anna, question number three?
Yeah.
So my question, which world first was erected outside the House of Commons in 1868?
The answer is the world's first traffic lights.
Traffic lights?
British first?
Yeah.
That is correct.
It had to be taken down pretty soon after it was built because it exploded in the face of
a policeman.
I thought you were going to say it was so successful they gave it the green light.
No.
Okay.
That's the end of the match.
And to decide who was the winner between Columbia and C么te d'Avoire, we are going to
go to James for the decision.
Oh, it's a tough one.
Let's go for the C么te d'Avoire.
Yeah.
I really love all those dance moves.
So let's go for that.
Yeah.
Great number of dance moves.
This match, if you want to chat to us about any of the things that we've said, you can get
us all on Twitter.
I'm on @Sriberland.
James.
At h-shaped.
Andy.
Right.
Andrew Hunter.
And Anna.
If you write to @cricapedia, the C么te d'Avoire might go back to you.
Yes, but we can't promise because Anna hates Twitter.
Okay.
That's it for the show.
Join us again tomorrow.
There's another match up in our World Cup of Facts.
And that is James.
That is the all-European counter between Switzerland and Italy.
Fighting.
Very cool.
Okay.
Well, we'll be back with that match tomorrow.
Until then.