(blues music)
Hello and welcome back to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the Kiwi offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Andrew Hunter Murray
and I'm sitting here with Anna Tijinsky,
Alex Bell and special guest Ed Brooke Hitching.
Once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, Ed.
- In 1875, the British Navy erased 123 islands
from their charts because they didn't exist.
- The British Navy didn't exist or the islands?
- Yeah, you were gonna do that.
No, it's, Phantom Islands were a huge problem
when we were sorting out our charts.
They were just, the maps were just cluttered with these things
and mainly caused by human error,
especially in a time before we could measure longitude,
you would estimate your position with dead reckoning.
And because of that, you had huge amounts
of wildly inaccurate coordinates
that would be fed back to cartographers,
painted on maps and presented as facts.
- So to be fair to them, they were often real islands.
They just weren't anywhere near the places
where they were told that they were.
- To what extent is an island in a different place
before it becomes a different island?
- I'll give them a hundred miles leeway
in any direction.
- Yeah, it's unbelievable.
They're doing a job half right as well.
You're giving them too much.
- You've gotta be loose with these poor charts.
They didn't have longitude.
- Okay.
- Were there sort of mirages and things
that meant people think they'd seen an island
and they hadn't?
- Yeah, there's a whole load of crazy natural phenomena
presumably still out there waiting for you to think
that you are seeing land when you're not.
I mean, we're talking icebergs,
but sometimes covered in dirt that can disguise them
as an island, surrounded by sea gals.
- Did somebody do that?
Did somebody go to an iceberg?
- It's put like a palm tree on it.
- The biggest prank of all time.
- America.
- The whole thing just made up just all the back of the iceberg.
- But there's also things like low-hanging clouds,
which doesn't sound like you would mistake the solid land,
but it's like this island, the fluffiest island
and the whole South Pacific.
- Is it still happening?
Do we ever get?
- Yes.
- There's one in 2012.
I was covered.
Sandy Island got undiscovered.
Yeah, it was in New Caledonia, just in Calsy.
- Yeah, the North East Coast of Australia.
- It was undiscovered then.
- So everyone thought it was there
and then eventually someone went there
and there was nothing there.
- Wow.
- It had been on maps for a hundred years
and it was discovered to be fake seven years
after you launched Google Maps.
- Yeah.
- So you could, to a time, find it on Google Maps
and you still can, but there's a little annotation saying,
it's not...
- It does not exist.
- It sees refreshable browser.
- How embarrassing, if you lived there,
and you found out it wasn't real.
- I feel like such an idiot.
- Do you think some people do still try to build houses, though?
You know, like if you go on a walk
and you are insisting that you're following a footpath
that you've obviously lost it,
but you just keep hacking through the undergrowth.
Doing there are people who are putting brick upon brick
on a cloud.
- On a cloud, yeah, yeah.
- There was a radio DJ in the '60s
who claimed to have broadcast a radio show
from a reef called the Maria Teresa Reef
that no one has ever been able to find.
And he swore to his friends that he was there
and the water was lapping up to his knees
and his deck chair was floating away.
- Maybe he just had a sound effect CD
and he was like, "Oh, the water's really close."
- He was in his mum's basement.
- Yeah, exactly.
- So three years ago, Pakistan got a new island,
completely new island.
They had an earthquake in the country
'cause they're quite a couple of tectonic plates
right up against each other there,
hence the Himalayas.
Anyway, after this earthquake,
it disturbed a pocket of pressurized gas.
And as a result, this entire section of the seabed
rose up to the surface and bobbed around for a bit
and until the gas underneath it was going to sort of collapse
or get pressurized and then it sank again.
But it was so unattractive as an island,
it was just mud and silt and it was covered in dead fish
which did not realize what was happening to it.
It's not the side of mystical land appearing
out of the sea that we all dream of.
- It was much of a stir.
- No wonder it sank.
It was so horrible to me.
- I think if I were a fish,
I would manage to swim into the water.
I mean, how quickly did this island pop up out of it?
- What if you're a flatfish?
And you're meant to be on this surface,
you might not notice as it was rising.
- Yeah, I see.
- It's like getting scurriedy close.
It's kind of like the fish's version of a tsunami.
- Yes.
- Do you know that there's no map containing the phrase
"Hibby Dragons"?
But there aren't two globes, ancient globes
which do have the phrase "Hibby Dragons"
or they have the Latin 'cause they were classy back then
which is Hick Sun to Draconis
and one of them is from 1510
and it's one of the first ever European globes
and one of them's from 1504
and it's from ostrich eggs.
That's what they made it out of.
Take two ostrich eggs, cut them in half,
glue them together, draw on globes.
- Oh wow, yeah.
- Do we think one day the sea will recede
to reveal that there are in fact dragons there?
- Wouldn't that be nice?
- Wouldn't it be?
- Well, you're getting island floating up
with the dragon's flopping around like fish.
(laughing)
- Well, a lot of these monsters,
they sort of they're painted on for stylistic flourishes
and sometimes it's just not a lot of information.
You've got to fill the blanks.
(laughing)
It's called horror vacuity.
You know, these cartographers,
they cannot ignore blank spaces.
They have to fill it in with something.
But there's one particular monster
you sometimes see drawn on maps
of South America in the Patagonian region
and it's a giant, a giant couple
and it usually says a Regium Gigantan region of the giants.
The weird thing is that wasn't just a stylistic flourish.
It got to the point in 18th century London
where they really believed there was a race of eight-foot giants
that stalked the landscape in Patagonia
and to the extent that I think Dr. Matthew Macy,
Secretary of the British Royal Society,
sent a letter to the French Academy of Sciences
saying the existence of giants here is confirmed.
- What?
- And when they printed their journal,
it came with a frontispiece illustration of one of the sailors
and British sailors at that time were about five at five.
One of the sailors giving them a biscuit.
- It's just going to piece off.
- So it was a massive bestseller.
People wanted to see it.
- Oh, wow.
- Maybe they only viewed them from a distance
and it was just that that area had slightly smaller trees.
- Well, the thing is, they reckon that it was a native tribe
that no longer exists of maybe six-foot tall men
that still to a very short Englishman
were laterifying.
- I'm distanced in an element of exaggeration going on there,
when a six-foot tall man morphs into a hereby giants type.
They had six-foot tall people.
And wasn't Washington older Lincoln six-foot?
- Abraham Lincoln was six-foot-four.
- I think that's with the hat, though.
- I think it was even bigger with the hat.
With the hat, he was about seven feet tall.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- They have a fully functional audio animatronic robot
of him in Disneyland.
- Is it fully functional?
- Yeah, fully functional.
- Does it emancipate slaves?
- No, it just stands up, makes a speech.
It's supposed to be exactly like him.
- They're all the presidents.
They're a whole hall for every single president of the United States
and they all get up and talk and make speeches.
- You watch Vida in YouTube, it's pretty weird and cool.
- And it's very passionate.
- Where is this?
- Disneyland.
- I'm sorry, when you said it,
I just had a vision of all of them in a hall
talking at the same time on their own.
And it's just the most frightening, weird, unsettling.
- They tag each other in, like restless.
- On Fictitious Islands, so you were saying
that there were various reasons that they got it wrong
and they put islands in the wrong places.
But they did also make them up, didn't they?
They, like you say, they wanted stuff to happen.
They didn't like empty space.
And so I was reading about Benjamin Morel,
who I assume you're a maps fan.
- Benjamin Morel, I just find historical liars fascinating.
- So what Benjamin Morel did is he made up
a whole bunch of places in Ireland.
So he made up this island called New South Greenland,
near Antarctica, which didn't exist.
And we thought it existed for a hundred years
until I think a Shackleton expedition undiscovered it
in between 1940 and 1917.
They went there and said, oh, that's not here.
But why did this guy do that?
- Well, this is, I mean, voyages at that time
and probably still are a business operation.
You need to raise funds and sponsorship to do it.
And people are more likely to give you money
if it's exciting, if you're often an adventure.
All he wanted to do was go and travel.
He just wanted to live at sea.
And so when he came back and he had a particularly
an eventful trip, he had to sex it up somehow.
So he invented as buyers island,
there's Morels Land, was one of his, he claimed.
- Oh, that's where the wheels started coming off
the way he was asked.
And what was the name of that that the locals had for it?
Oh, Morels Land.
- And so, yeah, that's how he secured funding.
And so he was known as the biggest lion Pacific
because of this tendency to just invent geography.
- So we should say the reason that Ed knows
so much about this is that you have written a book
on this very subject, haven't you Ed?
- Yeah, it's called the Phantom Atlas.
And it comes out in November 3rd.
And it's basically an Atlas of the world
as we believed it to be, rather than how it actually existed.
- There you go, Phantom Atlas, go and buy it.
Not on the second of November, but on the third.
'Cause on the second, it won't exist.
- Yes, you'll be a bit disappointed.
- Yeah.
There are, isn't there an island somewhere called
Disappointment Island?
- Maybe it was one that Morel bigged up
and then his son went and visited this paradise.
- I made it ice cream and it's easy to me to say.
- Turn out it's covered in dead fish.
- Disappointment islands.
One of the first Westerners to land there
was John Byron, who was grandfather of Lord Byron.
- I really though as well.
- The man who discovered the Patagonian Giants.
- Really? - Yeah.
- Was John Byron.
- Yeah, he was Captain of the Dolphin.
- Wow. - Oh, cool.
- And they called him Falweather Jack
'cause he had this amazing knack
of sailing always into enormous storms.
- I think we've met before. - Yes, we've told you.
- So the islands had already been called
the Unfortunate Islands 'cause they didn't have
a decent water supply on them.
And that was by Magellan.
- But they were called Disappointment Island
for a different reason.
It wasn't 'cause there wasn't any water.
It was because John Byron found that the people
who lived there were of a hostile disposition
and they didn't like him.
- That's a dick move.
They had to rename someone.
That's like, "You now live on bastard lanes."
- I would aggressive, isn't it?
- No, we were just a disappointment.
- Yeah, he didn't call them fierce or frightening,
which I think they would have been more flattered by
to call someone Disappointment.
- You've been a real disappointment.
Yeah, we were really expecting good things
from these islands and...
- I bet he was really nice to their face as well.
- It was really nice.
- Lovely time, guys.
- Thank you for the Candy Floss Brilliant Islands.
We'll definitely call it that when we get back.
(upbeat music)
Okay, time now for fact number two,
which is my fact this week is that the White House
only got the ability to print on double-sided paper
this year.
- And was that the staff weren't trained well enough
to understand?
- It's a very hard little clickbox to find.
- It's really easy.
- It's very hard.
- They've had the ability.
They just...
- No, this is the amazing thing
is that they have not had the ability.
It's incredible.
The White House has just had a huge technological overhaul,
which has meant that they can now print double-sided.
They can do color printing.
They don't all have to use blackberry phones.
It's incredibly difficult to upgrade any technology
in the White House, but partly because of security
and partly because it's very complicated,
but also there are four different offices
which look after White House tech.
So it's a complete nightmare.
It's the National Security Council,
Executive Office of the President,
the Secret Services and the White House Communications Agency.
And between them, nothing has been achieved for the last
- Even to eat all of that expertise.
They still can't get the opportunity to work.
No one's got any hope.
- No.
- And they even, one thing they did,
they had to remove lots of spare wiring
that was just left in the walls of the building
from previous systems that were no longer in use.
They removed 13,000 pounds of wiring.
So the White House has just lost 13,000 pounds in weight.
- So when they renovated the situation room in 2067,
up until that point, they were using cathode ray tube TV screens
and fax machines and photos from the 80s.
Like, you're absolutely right.
It was a completely diet situation.
And apparently it was a really disruptive overhaul.
They found bits of a windows
and the remains of a sunken courtyard
that had been left over by previous presidents.
They didn't know it was there.
- So I think Roosevelt built in the White House,
warm swimming pool and he used it
for therapeutic swimming for his polio.
So this was in the 1930s.
There was a big opening in 1933.
That was inside the White House.
Various other presidents used it
and then Nixon, fun lover that he was,
decided to cover it up and build the press.
- Classic Nixon.
(laughing)
- But he also installed the bowling alley there.
So you know, he's nice and all.
- That's true, yeah, yeah.
- So Nixon covered it up and typically
and he turned it into a press briefing room.
But we only realized quite recently
when they were excavating the White House
or doing some building work.
So the swimming pool is actually completely intact
underneath it.
So underneath this floor,
underneath where the main White House press secretary stands
is the deep end of the swimming pool
and then goes up to the shallow end underneath there.
- That's a fun metaphor for any of the secretary.
We're putting you in the deep end.
Presumably it's been drained.
- I think it has been drained, yes.
- Although Hillary Clinton expressed a while ago,
I think when Bill was president,
she expressed a desire to have that swimming pool back.
So you never know if she wins.
She might...
- Stop all press briefings.
- Stop the press briefings, get the pool back.
That's gonna be a campaign slogan.
- It's only we can have both
and you have inflatable floating chairs
for the press people.
- That is a good idea.
- And then to do length off and down there.
- And then the press secretary
can have a flamingo or something
an inflatable flamingo to be on
to show that position.
(laughing)
- You know, the secret service had to hide
the front doorbell on the north side
of the White House from Calvin Coolidge,
the president, because he would prank them.
And every time someone rang the doorbell
that wasn't expected, obviously the secret service
had to rush it.
We're talking 1929.
And he just loved doing it and then hiding in a bush
and watching them arrive and be completely confused.
(laughing)
So when they finally figured out what he was doing,
and this is from an article in Time.
I'm not pulling this completely out.
- Wow.
- They hid the doorbell from him,
so he couldn't do it again.
After that, he was leaving bags of flaming dog shit
on the doorbells.
(laughing)
- Of his own house.
- My partner still has a blackberry, doesn't he?
- But he really wants an iPhone.
- Does he?
- Yeah, he was saying, "Oh, it's a great phone,
"but it doesn't take pictures.
"You can't text, the phone doesn't work.
"You can't pay music on it."
And he's really jealous of his wife and kids
because they've got cool phones
and they can snap chat and stuff.
And he was complaining.
- That refers to sounds like a terrible phone
if it can't text, take pictures or doing else.
- That's actually the reason that he's not
completely tearing up the Constitution
and standing for a third term.
- He would, but he wants that iPhone.
- When you're the president,
you still can't get the model of phone that you want.
- Well, it's because it needs to be heavily modified,
doesn't it, by the secret service?
We'll have a phone, the president uses it.
I think this is why.
And so an iPhone is a little bit more difficult
for them to hack into, I think.
Or they've got to say much trouble
by the time they've modified his bloody blackberry
that when he comes back next year
and says I want an upgrade, they say, "Sorry mate."
- It's just the secret service.
They're always modifying things.
So we've talked before about the presidential cars
and how they're modified.
And I just get the idea of a blackberry,
which has got three inches of armour plating on the outside.
And there are seven decoys.
So whenever he goes, "Which one is my phone?"
- So another thing about early days of tech
in the White House, the first ever telephone
in the White House could only be used to call the treasury.
And if you wanted to ring the White House,
the treasury just had to pick up the phone and dial one.
- That's so cool.
- The phone number was one.
- So printing.
- Yes, printing.
Let's talk about that.
Did you know, you know heart, the Harold Angels thing?
- Yeah.
- The song.
Do you know what relation that has to printing?
- No.
- That Mendelssohn wrote that tune
to celebrate the 400th anniversary of the printing press.
- Wow.
- Yeah, isn't that weird?
It was for some celebrations in honour of Gutenberg.
And yeah.
- I didn't get that from the lyrics.
I've said, I always thought it was...
- Should have been called the Harold Angels print.
In glory to the newborn Canon H.B. laser jet.
(all laughing)
That is very cool.
- Yeah, so just to clarify,
aside from these guys silly jokes,
the lyrics were not the same at the time.
They were in fact lyrics suitable
to the celebration of Gutenberg.
- Well, really so.
- Yes.
- It's just the music that we're talking about.
- It was, yeah, so he wrote the tune
and then someone else wrote the lyrics about,
it was called the Gutenberg Cantata.
- Wow.
- And then later on it was repurposed.
- Well, do you guys know the expression to a T
when you're talking about knowing something very precisely
that you play the bank robbery into a T?
- Do you know what the T stands for?
- No.
- Tittle.
And Tittle is the official name for the dot
in a lowercase i that printers it.
- Ah, really?
- That is J.
So the original phrase was to a Tittle.
- So what's a jot thing?
'Cause I know the phrase jot and Tittle.
- Yeah, that's from the Bible.
- What?
- Yeah, to care not a jot or a Tittle.
- Well, they people, they sound like characters on the Bible.
- Oh, no, they won't be.
(all laughing)
- What kind of weird children's Bible are you reading?
- Jobs and Tittle. - Jobs and Tittle.
- And all these weird things.
- They could, actually they could catch on as fancy names.
Tittle, Tittle come and do your piano practice.
Jot, it's definitely Jot is a boy's name
and Tittle is a girl's name, I think.
- Well, she's gonna have a rough time at school.
- Did you know that on printing, publishing,
the illustrator of the first ever nursery rhyme book
was sued for selling porn?
This was a guy called George Bickham, Jr.
It was in the 1740s.
And the nursery rhyme book was three inches by 1.75 inches,
which is so sweet.
(all laughing)
I know, isn't that cool because it was a book for children,
so it was child size.
But then he went on to sell loads of porn,
which makes me really wonder what was for me illustrations.
- He put some saucy images in the first children's book.
- Well, maybe he did, but I don't think he did.
(all laughing)
- Have you heard of the smallest ever inkjet printed picture
this was done not so long ago?
It's 0.08 millimeters by one millimeter
and it's a picture of a few different tropical clownfish.
It's the same as Nemo, basically.
And it's unbelievable.
It's done with a thing called quantum dots.
The really weird thing is, the dots look
like a different color according to what size they are.
So obviously they're all absolutely tiny,
but the very, very smallest ones look blue.
There's slightly larger ones look green
and then the bigger ones look red.
So you can print different colors using the same ink.
- What?
- It's just using this, I think it's something to do with the light,
but I'm not completely sure.
- It's obviously, it's obviously something to do with light.
- That's on the press police.
(all laughing)
- It's on the press police for dummies.
(upbeat music)
- Time for fact number three now and that is Alex.
- My fact this week is that World War Two
Morse code operators could recognize each other's accents
over the line.
- They were speaking in Morse code at the time, presumably.
- Yes, yeah, so it's not even just World War Two operators.
There's all operators.
If you do Morse code a lot, if you're one of those kind of people,
it's known as your fist.
If you have a good fist or you have a poor fist,
that means you've got a very kind of sloppy,
bad way of typing in Morse code.
- It means a completely different thing actually
where I was brought up, but yeah.
(all laughing)
- And I grew up in a boxing community.
- All right, just to make that ultra clear,
go ahead and jump in, yeah.
(all laughing)
- Bit like, I guess it's like an antiation,
but for Morse code, if you have a good fist,
you Morse code very, exactly like I'm not doing now.
You code very, very good.
(all laughing)
- Particularly, it's the way that I can never remember.
- Just to be clear, is it the speed
with which people are typing the letters or is it?
- If you read it, it's everything.
It's the rhythm, which you type.
It's also, you would Morse differently depending
on the type of instrument you're using.
So there are different mechanisms in different things.
So you would get different rhythms
or different intonations of your Dawson dashes.
- Could British Morse code people
recognize individual German?
- Yeah.
- But it's not like, hello there.
(all laughing)
- It's a regional accent, yeah.
- No, it sounds like it's exactly the equivalent of that.
- Yeah, I know that there was,
the people in Bletchley monitoring spy codes
and speaking a lot with the same people
from a long way, they never met,
were able to recognize each other just from the Morse.
- I remember one story, a lady talking,
who worked at Bletchley, talking about it,
and she felt that she knew the person
who she was listening into so intimately
that she referred to her as, I think, Maria.
She gave her a name, and wow.
- Even though you only hear,
dot, dot, dash, dot, dash, dot, dot, wow.
- Classic Maria.
(all laughing)
- There's this story about Thomas Edison.
It's one of those probably apocryphal.
After he went deaf, that he and his wife
would communicate through Morse code.
And so when they went to the theater,
she would have his hand on his knee
and would tap out the lines as he was performed,
which, that would be pretty rapid
and quite irritating, yapping.
Especially for whoever's in the row in front of them.
- Yeah.
- Well, we sure she wasn't a Scotsie trying to say,
"Excuse me, do I need the toilet?"
Can you get up and let me know?
(all laughing)
- So on communicating in secret using Morse code,
here is a cool thing.
During the Second World War,
there was a British prisoner of war
who was imprisoned in Germany.
He was called Major Alexis Castelli,
and he was a sower.
So he would sove to pass the time,
very intricate, beautiful patterns,
and there are bits of cross stitch.
And there's one he did that's really nice.
It says, you know, this piece of work
was made by Major here at this castle on these dates.
But around the edges, there are two borders,
and they are little patterns of dots and dashes.
And one of them says, "God save the king in Morse code."
And the other one says, "Excuse my French, fuck Hitler."
(all laughing)
And it's amazing, and it was so nice and pretty
that he was allowed to hang it on the wall
at the prison camps.
He was in, and none of the German guards
ever spotted or deciphered that this was Morse code.
- So risky, 'cause so many of them
must have known Morse code.
It was wartime.
I thought everyone had to memorize it.
- Unbelievable.
- In 2010, members of the Colombian army
were being held hostage by the guerrilla army
in Gambia, the revolutionary armed forces of Colombia.
And so the Colombian army wanted to get a message to them,
and they decided the best way to do it
would be to commission a pop song,
which had Morse code hidden inside it,
and then find a way of getting it on air,
broadcast on radio, so that they could get a message
to their country.
So at the various points in the chorus,
they sing the words, "Listen to this message brother."
And then after that, the beat is built around a Morse code message
that says, "Nine people rescued your necks, don't lose hope."
And they got through it, isn't it?
- Wow.
- And then there's an interview with a guy who said,
"Yeah, I recognise you pretty much immediately,
'cause I was expecting Morse code,
and it was pretty blatant when I heard a,
"Listen to this message."
Yeah, it's amazing.
- And I knew your accent, obviously,
'cause of that extra long gap,
if you leave it between the ear and the L.
- It'd better be a good song as well.
Otherwise, you just turn the radio off.
- Yeah, that was the problem.
They had to make it good,
'cause they had to justify forcing radios,
like, as in they had to try and get it on radio stations,
so that it could be broadcast as a song on the radio.
So it couldn't be awful, otherwise,
people would get suspicious.
- Yeah, and you'd have to be like, you know,
Ken hates jazz.
We can't do that.
He will switch over immediately.
Actually, not that useful a message,
to be honest, if I were sitting there in prison
and I just finally decoded,
"Oh, how the, what's the key to how I get out?"
- We're on our way.
- I think I just hope you're well.
- At the moment, we're having a great time
recording a pop song, but we'll be there soon, yeah.
- There's Morse code on Mars.
Anyone?
- Yep.
The Curiosity Rover leaves tire tracks
and it has Morse code in those tire tracks.
This is JPL, but there's actually a practical use for it.
You're able to look at a picture
and they know how big the tire tracks are
because they design the wheels.
So then they can be like,
"Oh, okay, that's that much distance."
- So very efficient, dead reckoning.
- Yes, that's exactly what it is, yeah.
- We should say what JPL stands for
is the Jet Propulsion Laboratory,
which is NASA's the guys who built the rover, right?
- Yes.
- That's very cool.
Do you know what 21 means in Morse code?
- No.
- So you used to have all the letters, obviously,
but it's so, it's such a pain to type out every letter,
as Alex says.
So there are about 99 short codes,
which we're using the numbers from 1 to 99.
21 is stop for meal.
So that's why you're not getting a reply.
88 is love and kisses.
I really like 28, which is, "Do you get my writing?"
(laughing)
- Really insecure hips to do it.
- What are the themes that are emerging
in the last message I really want you to draw them out?
- In, I've just remembered this,
which is so related to the original fact,
but now we've slightly off topic,
but there were people in World War II
who claimed they could recognize a German accent
in a pigeon.
And these were experts,
'cause there were a lot of pigeon spies
that people thought were coming over here.
- Coming over here, taking our information,
going back to Germany.
- Exactly.
And so experts claimed that they could recognize
a German speaking Italian pigeon.
- This sounds to me like someone who knows his pigeons,
and he can tell by looking at them,
but he comes up with a really clever way
of sounding like he's the expert.
Like, just say cool again.
(laughing)
He just knows he's got brand dots, that's German,
but I'm not sure what's happening.
- Is it the ones which the German spies have a tube
on their leg, which has a message in it in German?
- They've got a little monochole.
(laughing)
A way that Moore's code has been used recently
is in a chess tournament last year,
and it was used by an Italian chess player to cheat,
but it was quite impressive, so it was one of the biggest,
I think it was the biggest chess tournament in Italy,
and this guy was ranked number 51,366 in the world,
and he got to the penultimate round,
so apparently the tournament organizers were,
but it's suspicious up to that point anyway.
And he kept on, he had his hand constantly under his armpit
while he was playing,
and he was blinking in a most unusual manner apparently.
(laughing)
- So he kept asking for the same song to be played
over and over again.
- So eventually people was a bit dodgy,
so they asked him to take off his shirt,
and understandably actually, he said he wouldn't.
And so then they put him for a metal detector,
and they found that there was a video camera
and a little pendant that he was wearing around his neck,
and then there was a box under his armpit
with a mass of wires going around his body,
and that was transmitting signals to him
from a computer or a friend who was telling him
- The friend who was only number 49,000 in the world.
(laughing)
- It's being cheating, there's a,
there's a spoke-or-vincan sport,
a sort of competitive bird tweeting,
where you have your bird in a box,
and they measure how many Cisco eats it produces.
- What's a modern amount of time?
- A Cisco eat is just the name of the note of a chip,
and if it goes a Cisco what, then it's a dud.
But they found, I think fairly recently there was a,
it's a competition.
- So you have a bird,
and you have to make your bird produce more.
- You have a bird in a box,
you don't do anything to make it,
you've just trained this bird to chirp.
- Okay.
- There's a huge amount of cheating
in the Vincan sport, Finch singing.
- Or Cheeping.
- To the point where one year they opened up a box,
'cause they noticed that his bird
cheaped the exact same number each time,
and they found a CD play.
(laughing)
- It hadn't struck the tournament organizers
to have sort of transparent boxes.
- That suspicion was a rouse when he asked
if he could plug in his Finch.
(laughing)
- Does anyone have anything else before we move on?
- Can we end this section with a stop?
- Since it's that one's code.
- Yeah, you know we can, Alex, just stop.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, time for our final fact this week,
which is Anna.
- My fact this week is that Brava Snails
have thicker shells.
- This is so good, I love this one.
- I like the snails, you have thicker.
- It's like a fridge magnet, saying.
- Yeah, it is, it's work up ages, what does it mean?
What are you trying to tell me?
- If something you tell your children
is not being bullied in the playground, I think.
- I can see, you're trying to work out.
- I'm just figuring out the wording,
so snails with thicker shells are Brava.
- What a great question, we don't know.
So it could be either way around.
This is a study last year that was published
in Biology Letters, which is the Royal Society
Science Journal, published last year,
and it found that risk taking fresh water snails
turned to have thicker, stronger, rounder shells.
But we don't actually know, so we can only hypothesize
as to whether they've developed stronger shells
because they're naturally very risk-taking,
and so they need to mitigate that risk of predation
by having a stronger shell,
or whether they had a stronger shell,
and so they went out and took more risks.
- I have never noticed a snail taking risks,
or being conspicuously brave, at burning buildings,
it's never a snail coming out
with the orphans over his shoulder.
- How do you define bravery in a snail?
Like, what kinds of things?
- Yeah, climbing up, saving children.
Yeah, so bolder snails are defined as snails
who, when you scared them, and they retract
to their neck back into their shell,
they then start their neck back out again
within 10 seconds, and the cowardly snails
with those who exceeded the 10 second limit
for sticking their neck back out again.
And also, I think the bolder snails
had a wider aperture, so they had a bigger front door,
essentially.
(laughing)
- That's really disgusting.
- That's snail, snails are amazing.
We've never really talked about snails before.
- That's unbelievable.
- That's who the snails go on.
- So, generally, in snails,
you can get a left hand of snails and right hand of snails,
in the sense that some snails have a left spiraling shell
and some snails have a right spiraling shell.
The first interesting thing is that,
in most places around the world,
the ratio of left spiraled to right spiraled snails
is roughly the same as ratio of left hand
of people to right hand people.
The reason that there aren't very many
left hand of snails in most parts of the world
is because it's very difficult for a left spiraled
and right to spiral to snails to have sex.
In Japan, there's a snail called the Satsuma snail.
And there are a lot more left spiraling snails
than right spiraling sounds there,
because they have a predator,
which is a snake that likes to eat them.
And it has real difficulty latching on and biting down
on snails with left spiraled shells.
- Wow.
- So they flourish.
- That is such a good example of natural selection.
- Yeah.
- Do you hear the story of in New Zealand,
they have a giant snails that can grow the size of Hamburg,
is it called the Puele Fanta?
- Oh.
- The Puele Fanta.
And in 2011, their habitat was on a particular,
I think, plateau that was due to be mined.
And so the government in a mass operation moved these,
I think something like 6,000 of these giant snails
into these high-tech cool rooms, temperature controlled.
You know what's coming next.
- Oh no, they died.
- There was a glitch and the temperature plummeted to zero,
but no one noticed for ages because they
didn't constantly check on the snails.
And half of the snails that hadn't been re-homed.
So I think something like 800 of 1,600 of these
very rare snails die.
They're all killed.
- Oh, that ate them.
- Oh, fuck up.
- Wow.
- Have you heard of the giant African land snail?
- No.
- This is an amazing snail.
It's massive.
And they're really popular for eating.
And people keep on smuggling them around the world.
It's about 15 centimeters long, normally.
It's just pretty long, but it gets really big.
In 2005, there was a passenger coming through Heathrow
who said she had something small to declare.
And she walked through the red line.
They looked in her luggage.
She had 104 kilos, 16 stone of snails in her luggage.
- 16 stone.
- Yeah, alive and with eggs all over the place.
Well, they're really popular to be eating.
One farmer in Austria sells snail caviar and snail livers.
And snail livers are also in spiral shapes.
- Are they amazing?
- Amazing.
Cool.
You know, speaking of smuggling snails, you know Patricia Heismith,
the novelist who wrote Tanda Mr. Ripley of those books.
She wrote strangers on a train
which was adapted into the Hitchcock film.
She hated people and loved snails at a snail obsession.
So she used to smuggle snails with her
and she kept about 300 snails as pets.
Took them with her wherever she went.
When she went to a dinner party,
she'd always have them in her handbag
and then she'd get bored.
Many, many, a good proportion.
And then she'd whip them out and put them on the table
and then she'd find the snails, right?
- The snails, yes.
- No wonder people didn't like it.
I know why she didn't like people.
- She hated people.
She sometimes apparently traveled around
with a snail under each breast.
(laughing)
- Why would you invite that person to a dinner party?
- There was a guy, I like this guy so much.
He was a charity director called Lloyd Scott.
And in 2011, he dressed up as a snail
to do the London marathon.
It took him 26 days.
He raised 20,000 pounds doing so.
One article wrote,
"He has crawled for 26 days across broken glass,
"nails, dog feces, enduring cramps, vomiting,
"and at least one trip to A&E."
He has said he was reluctant to repeat the experience.
Right, so he gets to the end of the course.
Took him 26 days.
- I know, and someone stepped on him and squashed him.
(laughing)
- He was in a nine foot long snail costume
dressed as Brian from the magic roundabout.
He was then sacked by the charity he worked for
because he hadn't raised enough money doing it.
- It's because he did cost more money to do it.
- Yeah, he'd incurred a loss, basically,
and not raised enough money, and that's a result.
Imagine just crawling slowly towards the P-45
at the other end of the way, it's so unkind.
Why wouldn't they sack him during it?
Why would they wait until you've done the whole thing?
- They do sound as sadistic people.
You're right, it's true.
- Just cheering him on all the way to the end.
- Snails, anuses, are...
(laughing)
- Got to talk about snails, anuses, for our snails.
Snails anuses are just above their heads.
- But they're not there for the whole lot?
- No, so they start out at the back of them,
and then they undergo the coiling process
like the rest of the body.
So I think the snail must be thrilled as it begins
an embryo that it is bummers all the way at the back of it,
doesn't have anything to do with it,
and it gradually grows up and around
until it's perched right above its eye.
- But it's a really weird thing that only happens
to specific type of invertebrates,
and it's basically a whole body just turns around.
- I'm unbelievably glad that only happens
to a certain type of invertebrates.
- Yeah, the ramifications of the cosmetic industry here
would be huge into having bum replacements,
so that you looked young and beautiful again,
'cause your bum was way your bummers.
Instead of on the back of your neck.
- That's a good point.
- Although you save an underpants, you just use a hat, right?
- Right, point, yeah, pants and hats dub up as one.
- That's a small advantage to many disadvantaged people.
- As true, as you get older,
you really want your ass to be as far away from you as possible.
- I was on pet snails.co.uk.
- I'm really confused with pet snails.
(laughing)
- But they have a list of problems
that your snail can have,
and the list of problems in killudes,
excessive mucous, swollen tentacles,
and sudden multiple death.
There's a page for what happens if I stepped on a snail.
What do I do?
How can I resuscitate it?
- What do you do?
- Well, the author then said,
"If you found a snail that looks really mangled,
or the internal organs sticking out of gaping cracks
in the shell, et cetera, please call 111,
but it's 999, it's over-stressed."
- I euthanase them by stamping on them.
It sounds horrible,
but it's far better than taking hours to dry out
and die from desiccation.
- All right, good advice.
- Probably worth clarifying,
'cause I always thought this is true,
and it's not true that snails are built into their shells.
They just live in their shells like a herb crab.
You don't turn into a slug if you take out a slug.
- How many snails did you remove?
- I've gone anywhere near them.
(laughing)
- Have you heard of semi slugs?
Does a slightly flaccid slug?
(laughing)
- I suppose that's what the permanently erect slugs
you normally get.
- Oh, they're always like that.
Oh, me, I'm just saying.
(laughing)
- You and Patricia Heismet, aren't they?
- Semi slugs, they're slugs,
which have got a shell on their back,
but it's not quite big enough for them
to fit the whole body into,
but it's not quite completely vestigial yet,
so they can kind of cram a bit of themselves into it.
(laughing)
- I'm definitely still a size eight.
I don't know, Boris, yeah.
House is looking pretty small these days.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you have enjoyed this podcast,
and you'd like to follow us on Twitter, you can do so.
I'm on @AndrewHunterM, Alex.
- @AlexBell_Ed.
- Ed @FoxTosser.
- Yeah.
- Which is a reference to Ed's previous book,
which is very good, either by that or the Phantom Atlas.
And Anna.
- You can email podcast@QI.com.
- There's also a group Twitter account,
which is @QIPodcast,
and if you want to listen to all our previous episodes
of no such thing as a fish,
you can go to our website,
which is qi.com/podcast.
Also, the first 52 episodes of fish
are now available to buy on iTunes,
and they are not available on the website,
so if you want to listen to them,
you've got to shell out, like a snail.
- Okay.
- See what you did, man.
- We'll be back again next week with another podcast.
Thank you so much for listening, and goodbye.
(upbeat music)