(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that if an eel
ends up in a predator's stomach,
it can reverse out through its gills.
- That's pretty amazing.
- This is Japanese eels.
And it's recently found out that they can get swallowed
by these sleeper fish, dark sleeper fish.
And then they go through the digestive tract,
but then they are just able to wibble their way back,
back out towards the gills and then slink out.
I think some slunk out through the mouth
and then some were able to slink their way out
actually through the slits that were the gills.
- Yeah, that's amazing.
I actually don't really have a good idea of fish anatomy.
I wouldn't have thought that the gills
would be attached to the digestive system.
- It does sound all hollow, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- We say that.
- Our gills, as people.
- Our lungs.
- Yeah, are sort of connected.
- You know, there's a bit where the pipe's branch, but--
- That's true.
It's like if you swallow a piece of apple
the wrong way it goes down towards your lungs.
- Exactly.
I mean, kind of sort of the same way
they're coming out of the bit.
We use the breathing.
- Yeah, you tend to take a few turns, probably.
- Yeah, yeah.
But it is mad.
- It is insane.
- And the scientists who did it,
I love it, it was a team at Nagasaki University.
And they filled the eels with the chemical
that meant they could be x-ray,
they could show up on an x-ray.
And then, it was really a bit mean,
they just introduced the eels to the dark sleeper fish,
which we're gonna be very hungry for them.
And one would get swallowed and then they'd just observe.
And about a third of the time, the eel escaped.
- That's interesting.
Do we think it happens in the wild, then?
- I think it definitely does.
- Yeah, it does, I think.
And they see that some make it halfway out,
some almost make it out,
but they get stuck with their heads.
It's not, yeah, it's not a foolproof process.
But what a weird thing to be the sleeper fish.
You eat your lunch.
- I know.
- And then it's sitting next to you a minute later.
- It does happen a bit in nature.
Doesn't it?
That things get eaten and then can escape.
- Yes.
- I reckon.
Like Jonah.
- Jonah?
- I think is one of them.
- Is that his nature?
- There's a snail called Tornatelides boiningi
that's also found in Japan.
And it's swallowed by this bird.
And 5% of them are able to escape out of the bum.
- Out of the bum?
- Out of the bum.
- Okay.
- That's all the way through.
That's very impressive, isn't it?
- That's a waiting game.
- Well, on the other hand, you don't have to reverse.
You just put your head down and go for it.
- I do.
- Yeah.
- But then 5% of them can get through and survive
for at least one week.
And actually quite often when they come out,
if it's a female who's pregnant,
they'll give birth straight afterwards.
And some people-
- That, as in like it brings on neighbor.
- Yeah.
- Wow, like eating a curry or something.
Maybe she did it on purpose.
She was so sick, big time.
- I don't think it's like in the Lansdale community,
they're like, oh, maybe if we have sex,
then the baby will come.
And they're like, yeah, but maybe if we get eaten
by a bird, it will come.
- That's just the inducing method.
Imagine that at hospitals,
if you have to be swallowed by an animal at all.
Baby needs to come early.
I found this great book called Eels by James Prosek.
It's one of those classic books that we love
where it's just the single subject,
the whole history of the animal.
And it's pretty fascinating.
We've spoken about before about how Eels,
they have the call,
which kind of brings them back to the ocean.
'Cause they are born in salt water
and they find river water in order to give birth.
And most animals do the opposite of that.
Salmon will do the opposite of that.
They're so mysterious.
And we've spoken about this.
They've never, we just never have seen
any pregnant Eels really or how they give birth.
But what's fascinating is how strong that call is.
So this guy, James Prosek,
he has some Eels in his house, in a tank.
And he said he woke up one morning
and they had busted through the top,
which was held down with rocks
and they were wriggling on the floor,
just trying to get out.
- You're joking.
- So then he reinforced it, he put them back in,
put the lid on and then he came down
and they were slamming their heads into the sea.
- They were constructing a rudimentary drill
from the stuff in their tank.
That was incredible.
- So basically some of them,
even like to the point of kill themselves,
but they were smacking their heads
so hard to try and get through this thing.
- Okay, I'm not going to say that that's not true,
but that's amazing.
- It's horror film.
- It's in his book and he's like a lead illness writer.
- I was implying, there's a subtext there that I think.
There is a thing that when they first realized
that there was a homininstinct in birds,
one of the experiments they did was,
they got the birds in a cage
and put little sort of ink on their feet
and then they would put paper on the floor of the cage
and then they could see that the birds
were trying to go in a certain direction.
- Right.
- God, it's so interesting.
- It is amazing 'cause they will often,
if there's a bit of damp ground in a field,
they will make their way out of their pond
or whatever bit of fresh water they're in
and they'll slither along
and start eating some farmland stuff and come back.
But when they want to go back to the ocean,
this is all true, James.
They can stay in wait.
They just wait and wait until the circumstances are right
to get them back to the ocean.
And then once they need to make that trip,
once a storm has come
and the water levels have risen a bit
and everything's wet,
they perform like ninja-like abilities.
So if they get to a hill,
they roll into a ball and roll down the hill.
- No way.
- Yeah, yeah.
They can climb up walls by braiding themselves
along the side of moths, walls, and it's extraordinary.
- Did you watch a cartoon?
- This is James Prasek, Eels.
- It is incredible.
Do you know where has an eel festival, by the way?
- Eely?
- Because, oh, Eely, yeah, Eely.
- Correct.
- Which one?
- Eely.
- Well, there we go.
- Not Eely, London.
- It wasn't a trick question.
It was actually just an on-the-nose.
- Because Eely is named after the eels, isn't it?
- I believe so.
But very sadly, the last eel catcher in Eely
retired 10 years ago.
Because they've had this terrible decline of population,
mostly due to humans.
But you know, there used to be a staple food in Cambridgeshire.
I just find that so bizarre.
- Yeah.
- You just, like, a thousand years ago,
you had a rock, you had an eel, effectively.
And the main thing to do now is removing barriers in rivers.
'Cause there are just so many
hundreds and thousands of these things.
And most of them are out at, like, a defunct.
They're like an old water mill.
- Yeah.
- You know, build a barrier across the river
'cause they needed to harness the power of--
- And locks and stuff.
Like, we've got quite a lot of eel,
we've got quite a lot of eel stares near us.
- Do you know?
- Which would like to go over locks,
'cause I live in the Fens,
which is where they used to be all over the stuff.
- Yes.
- Like your eel country.
- Were it?
Well, yeah, I'm really, yeah.
It's really hard to get an atlas of eel barriers
because the researchers looking at it found
there are 300 different words
which describe obstacles and rivers.
Which I find insane. - Really?
- You know, a sluice, or a lock, or a weir,
or, like, all of these things.
There are hundreds of terms, so you need to map them.
But there aren't, like, groups removing them slowly,
but surely, which is very cool.
- I think it's a bit mysterious
why their numbers have declined so rapidly, you know,
by 90% in the last 50 years.
But they're so sought after now.
- There are 350 million eels taken from Europe to Asia
every year.
- Is this legal or illegal?
- All illegal, very illegal.
- This is smug eel, smuggling?
- Yes, because they're very endangered now,
and so they're very protected.
You're only allowed to take certain ones and...
- I'd love if they get there,
and then they wake up the next morning
after having arrived,
all the eels have just migrated back.
(all laughing)
- Eel shape holes in all of the buildings.
- Which are just holes, aren't they?
(all laughing)
- Well, if they might go sideways through the wall.
Speaking of smuggling, or not speaking of smuggling,
but you'll see where the connection is.
Last year, there was doctors in Vietnam
who pulled out a two-foot eel from man's intestines
after he inserted it into his bottom.
- Oh, dear.
- And the problem was not so much putting the eel up there,
although that was quite bad,
but he'd also shoved a lemon up there
so that it couldn't escape.
- No, I don't believe this, James.
- Well, it's true, it's true.
- It sounds like he's trying to make a delicious meal
inside himself, a squeeze of lemon,
and then was it a sprinkle of salt?
- The man survived,
even though the eel had started biting
through his abdominal cavity.
- I don't think we can blame the eel a touch for that.
- No, no, I've not blamed the eel, I've not.
- I'm blaming you for raising this,
and I certainly, for one, I'm not finding it funny,
because I'm well aware that in 2013,
there was a similar, very serious incident,
and 33 people, staff at Auckland City Hospital,
were punished, and a few of them sacked
for looking at an x-ray unnecessarily
of a man who had an eel stuck
in the lowest parts of his digestive system.
- Well, you can get fired for looking at an x-ray?
- It was found that they did not need
to be looking at the x-ray, all his notes.
- Oh, I can see his notes. - Oh, come on.
- Maybe if it has incriminating--
- Down over here, speaking up for medical malpractice.
(all laughing)
If as long as it's funny.
- You have to learn.
- As a doctor, to see things you would not normally see.
- Exactly, what happens if then the next day,
someone else comes with an eagle up the bum,
but you don't recognize it?
- Yeah, sorry, I don't know what to do.
It was too funny, and I wasn't allowed to do it.
(all laughing)
- Do you know where European and American eels come from?
- European America?
- No, the ocean bits, where they're born, do you know?
- They haven't been said on the orders from the Sargasso Sea.
- Sargasso Sea, but do you know where the Sargasso Sea is?
- It's in the Atlantic. - Is it Bermuda?
- It's Bermuda. - Oh, God.
- Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
It is within the Triangle.
Let's head this off at the path.
- Is it within the Triangle?
- Well, the Triangle is an undefined border.
We don't really know how far the Triangle extends.
- Are we in the Triangle now?
- Technically, yes.
- I thought it went from Bermuda to the tip of Florida
to the tip of South America.
I thought it was defined, no.
- I don't know, I don't really know about this stuff.
(all laughing)
- It might be my area of interest.
It might be a lumpy triangle.
There might be a little bit of flexibility.
- I heard it on a podcast called The Crypto-Tactics.
They were very clear about the definitions.
- Oh, well, trust them, great show.
- What's your theory?
They're all getting started outside there.
- Just saying the mystery of them,
I can't believe that hasn't been folded in
as an extraordinary creation.
- If they're being called to a, let's say a mothership,
metaphorically speaking,
that's they're being drawn to a mothership, aren't they?
- And they talk about it.
They say the mystery of them being,
this calling to the Sargasso Sea.
They left as glass eggs, basically, in their look.
They get carried in the currents all over the world.
They end up in fresh water.
They live there up to a hundred years.
And then they somehow find their way back to the Sargasso.
- I suppose that is also true of many, many, many other species
that they managed to go back to their original breeding grounds.
- They are mysterious, aren't they?
They are kind of, it's incredible we haven't cracked it.
Even with all our knowledge.
You know, you can, all your computers and all of that
and all your internet and you still can't do it, can you?
- Can't crack the eels.
- Yeah, get on to it, eel on musk.
- Oh God.
- Well done, well done.
Let's distract them with that.
We've mostly been talking about,
yeah, European and European eels.
But conger eels, we have, and they're massive.
And they all hold on to each other.
- They all go back to the Sargasso Sea in one big line.
Apart from when one line of congery
is accidentally breaks off and goes to the wrong place.
- That's the European eel, the American eel.
- No, the conger eels, different spelling,
are, well, hunted all over British Isles,
particularly in Cornwall and the Isles of Silly.
And I just read in an old book,
and I can't find it anywhere else,
but the way to catch conger eels,
you know, sometimes you'll put a stick into a river
and the eels would wind around it and then you'd pull it up.
- Didn't know that, okay.
- I think that's what people did.
Well, apparently the traditional way to catch them
in the Isles of Silly is you suspend a small boy
upside down in front of the hole in which they live,
wait for the eel to wrap itself around him.
And these things can be up to three meters long.
And then you pull the boy up.
- Why does he need to be upside down?
- I think maybe he wants me to grab them.
- He would get ahead of it before too long, this boy.
- I think they come pretty fast.
- We don't seem to be concerned about his welfare,
so it's fine, but.
- He's happy to oblige.
He gets some of the jelly deal.
- Do you guys remember, I'm sure I pitched an eel fact
about six months ago and it didn't get any traction
with you guys.
- Oh, there we go.
- It was because in my local news agent,
they had a fisherman monthly magazine.
And it had a picture on the front of a guy
with the largest eel you've ever seen.
It was incredible.
- Yeah, but that's not a fact.
That's the thing.
You can't just say my fact this week
is you get really big eels.
- He'd broken the record for biggest eel caught in Britain.
I can't remember his name now.
I wrote it down at the time, but I've forgotten it.
- And what was the fact?
- It's just like the record for the largest eel
fished in Britain have been smashed by this guy.
But guys, honestly, it was like an elephant's trunk.
It was incredible.
- Yeah.
- It was a few feet long.
- I think this is maybe because this was this period
where all your facts were the most massive kettle
in just everything was an undefinable size.
You refused to tell us the measurements of.
- It was a trolley big eel.
Anyway, I bought that magazine and I think I'm sure
there's a fisherman near where I live
who's gone absolutely devastated
'cause he trots along to his news agent
for the one copy they stocked with this magazine.
It's not a big rack of them.
- Oh, he's missed the biggest eel news in the century.
- He's still living in a full paradise.
- He's done the time, Andy.
He owned that edition.
I feel like there's an elephant in the room
given that we're doing a fact about things
surviving being eaten.
In years to come, people will have forgotten this news story
that has been quite big this month
of the person who's been eaten by a whale.
- He was a kayaker, wasn't he, a Venezuelan guy?
- Did that happen?
'Cause I saw the headline, didn't read the article
and then saw a debunk and didn't read the article either.
- It did happen.
- The video is quite good.
- The video is amazing.
- How enticing does something have to be there
before you all click on it?
- I go through a lot of web pages every single day.
- I'm like, yeah, yeah, whatever.
- He got into the world's mouth
and then the world's matter of mouth.
- So he did go through into this.
- No, no, no.
There was no happening. - It was a few seconds later.
I actually, I heard about this story on a recent episode
of what was the show you were talking about?
Cryptid fact.
- They did a really good breakdown of that whole story.
- Did you go through that bit by bit?
- They did, yeah.
- Actually, that was the thing
where I saw the headline that just scrolled past it.
(all laughing)
- Very sensible.
- I saw the weird thing about it.
Well, there were two, there were two quite sweet things.
So they were going on a kayaking trip
for this guy's dad's birthday.
Initially, the headlines were like,
caught on camera by his dad.
And I thought, oh my God, this insensitive father's
filming the whole bloody thing.
But he did have a kayak mounted camera.
If that's what anyone else is worried about,
he wasn't holding the camera rather than saving his boy.
- Yeah, oh yeah, did you take the picture
of the insensitive dad on your show?
- I defended him because I think that if you know
the eating habits, you'd probably go,
he's not going to swallow him.
He'll be back in a second.
- That's about defense.
- And also, he was a distance away.
- Yeah.
- What are you going to do?
Swim over and have a word?
You just keep filming at that point.
- You're both fathers.
- Also, you'll need a crime reference number
from the police, so they need evidence.
Take it from me.
- I mean, I'm not normally on the side of this kind of thing,
but I've just been skiing with my three-year-old
for the number of times I've filmed her falling over
as opposed to going and helping her.
- Yeah.
- Right, you guys, social services are coming for everyone.
Imagine, this is all right.
I'm sure he'll come out with a mouth any time now.
So it was mounted on his kayak,
so the dad was not just holding a camera filming him,
but I thought the quite interesting thing
about human reactions is the dad didn't make a sound
when it happened, so he's seen what happens,
but he's so shocked.
And when the guy was then spat out of the whale's mouth,
the dad was like, mate, you're okay.
Shit, don't panic.
It's still there.
Get back in your kayak.
- But it's silent.
I see, what does his son get followed by a whale?
- Well, men don't like talking to each other.
What do you want?
(all laughing)
Unless it's in a podcast format.
- Even then, the only question is,
is that the new kayak that's just been...
(all laughing)
- I think we want to normalize this,
and we want to say to guys, if you're listening to this,
if your son has ever eaten by a whale,
then do try and talk about it.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, make yourself.
- Be a legend.
Have a chat.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that
Sweden's Minister for Equality
has a pathological fear of bananas.
- But all bananas equally.
(all laughing)
- Very nice.
- Yeah.
- This is incredible.
I mean, it really is a fear, isn't it?
- It's, well, yes, it is a fear.
It was in the newspapers quite recently,
especially in Sweden, unsurprisingly.
- That's where it started, didn't it?
- Yeah, "Sweet Afraid of Bananas."
- Oh, yeah.
- She herself is a vegetable, yes?
- I suppose so.
- Sweet, sweet.
- She, there was some leaked emails
to a tabloid newspaper called Expressen,
and they said that this lady,
who's called Paulina Brandberg,
has a strong allergy to bananas,
so we would appreciate it if there were no bananas
in the room where she'll be staying.
And the big scandal really is
that she isn't allergic to bananas.
She's just scared of them.
- Yes.
- And she said, like, they asked her,
they were like, "Are you really allergic to bananas?"
And she's like, "Well, it's sort of analogy, you could say.
It's something that I got professional help for."
And then eventually it came out
that she was just really hated them.
But, I mean, in fairness, you know, it's equally bad.
Is it equally bad?
Well, it depends how bad your allergy is.
- Yeah, I don't think it's, this is a big,
I don't think this is a big scandal.
There have been bigger in the world of politics.
- I know Sweden's politics are, you know, changing,
but it's still, guys,
if this is still what you're concerned with.
- And you know what?
Like, the opposition party,
they could have taken advantage of this
and maybe brought down the Swedish government.
But one of the opposition social democrats,
Teresa Carvalho said that she also has fear of bananas.
- I love that.
- And on this issue, we stand united
against a common enemy.
- Yeah.
- That's not plausible.
So I'll try to jump on the bandwagon.
- There can't be two, you're right.
- It's quite a rare phobia.
- Well, I think it's lovely.
And she, you know, she can't just spot a banana
and be alarmed by it.
She can smell bananas
or if someone has recently eaten a banana in the room,
she can truffle that out.
- You know why, speaking of truffles,
it's a bit like my severe hatred of mushrooms.
- Yeah.
- Isn't it?
Like, I can tell if there's a mushroom
in someone's eater mushrooms recently and stuff.
- You don't have a phobia of mushrooms.
- I think I do really, actually, yeah.
- I find them really disgusting,
but also if there's one growing in the corner,
I'll try not walk near it kind of thing.
- It's a stronger version to something
which actually is not gonna harm you.
- The Prime Minister backed her as well.
He sort of said, yeah.
So like, when he found out it was a phobia.
- What was the alternative to sack her, basically?
- I think she was getting mocked
and he said we shouldn't be mocking people
for their various little known phobias.
- Well, it's hard, isn't it?
'Cause loads of people have phobias
of things that are quite mainstream.
I mean, like, height, is that a phobia?
- It's a bit dangerous.
Spiders, some spiders are dangerous, you know.
- I would say these are phobias.
'Cause these are like, they're phobias of things
that aren't going to harm you.
A phobia of spiders in this country is totally rational.
- There is a theory that there's some kind of spider called,
I think it's called the six-eyed,
I can't remember, is it? - More spider.
- It's a bad one.
And it can be lethal if it bites a human.
And that lives in the plains of Africa,
which are the cradle of humanity.
So maybe there's something genetic going on there.
So that might be where spider fear comes from.
- Yeah, six-eyed, sound spider.
- And spider, there you go.
- And I think the problem, like,
the reason that the Prime Minister of Sweden
and the opposition sort of backed her on this
is, one, because it's ridiculous
that anyone should care about it.
But two, because it was kind of distracting
from the good work that this woman's doing
in her equality. - The famously unequal
country of Sweden. (laughing)
- It's not as obscure as you think.
It was an issue that was brought up on Loose Women
because one of the stars, Charlene White,
has a phobia of bananas as well.
- I don't know. - Yeah.
- It's common, all these people suddenly claiming.
- There is one person with a banana phobia
who is the most ironic person given the name.
- Oh. - Can you guess who it is?
- The guy who voiced Banana Man.
- No. - No.
- Banana Rama, the band? - Oh, the band.
I actually checked to see if they were allergic.
- The founder of the Big Yellow Storage Company.
- Oh, very good, but no.
So this person's surname is very related to bananas.
- John Peele.
- Very good, but no.
- Okay. - Oh.
- Monkey, something. - Famous types of banana.
- Oh, Cavendish, the Duke of Cavendish.
- Cyclist Mark Cavendish.
- Yes, sorry. - All right.
- We both know that it's the first Cavendish you think of.
- The first Cavendish that all of our listeners
will be thinking of when they hear that name,
the Duke of Cavendish.
No, Mark Cavendish, the cyclist,
he says even seeing someone eating a banana
gives him goosebumps and even thinking about it
makes him gag.
- That's incredible. - Wow.
- And he said it's the stringy bits on a banana
that he really hates.
- They're not the best bits, for sure.
- They're not the sweetest part.
- Well, he once won a bike race in Elania in Turkey
and he was given the world's biggest bunch of bananas
at price.
- Oh, God, that's terrible. - That's the scar of your fears.
And that's why it's bad having one of these niche phobias
because it's very hard to, like,
no one presents you with it like a bouquet of pigeons
at the end of it.
- Another person who has a fear of bananas,
Harriet Kemsley, the comedian.
- The comedian.
- Yeah, on another podcast called Off Menu,
which I've never heard of.
Have you guys heard of that?
- No, I think it's the cryptid factor,
I think the fans of it.
- Yeah, well, she was on that and she said,
she hates it when you throw a banana peel into a bin
and it doesn't go all the way in
so it looks like it's crawling out.
- Yeah, I can see that. - And I think I can see that,
actually. - Oh, gosh.
People have a lot of time to think, don't they?
(all laugh)
- Sorry, but just...
- I think it's instinct.
- I mean, really, non-intended, yeah.
Did we say that the Cavendish is named after,
the Cavendish banana is named after the Duke of Cavendish?
We'll just get emails otherwise.
- I think we have meant, I think, yeah.
- I think all of our listeners are very familiar
with the Duke of Cavendish, aren't they?
- Fears of bananas, the Guardian did a bit of digging
into this, I think, off the back of the Swedish politician.
They found a woman with a banana phobia who had it
pretty strongly, like, again, breaks out in a sweat,
can't bear being around them,
avoids them in the supermarket, that kind of thing.
She once was on a flight, quite a long-haul flight.
She woke up in the morning after everyone on the flight
had been asleep, and everyone around her
had been given their mid-morning snack, a banana.
I mean, just absolute nightmare territory.
- Imagine, you're in a plane.
- Banana's on a plane.
- It's basically...
- Yeah, motherfucking!
(all laugh)
- I was looking at kind of more common, uncommon phobias,
and bananas was a surprising one.
I didn't know that it was quite common
among the uncommon phobias,
but it does seem to be bananas,
Psydonglobophobia, which is an intense fear of cotton balls,
seems to be another one.
- Psydonglobophobia.
- That's surely more niche these days.
- Cotton balls?
- Are cotton balls still a big part of...
- I use them every day.
(all laugh)
- Okay, grandma.
- Actually, you know, Anna has an extremely common accent,
but she puts them in her cheeks and it makes her speak this way.
- Exactly.
- I've got a lovely glass antique container next to the bath
full of cotton balls.
- It doesn't surprise me as a leaf.
It doesn't surprise me.
Are they useful for washing things?
- Yeah, I actually do it to...
- Makeup removal.
- For women will be more I favor with cotton balls than men.
- I mean, I have more makeup in the time that you've known me.
- Okay.
(all laugh)
- It's washing food off a child's mouth.
- Yeah.
- Right, okay.
- Cleaning very, very young babies' bums,
you would use cotton balls.
- Yes.
- That's right.
- Whenever you wear makeup,
you basically continue to wear makeup
for the next two weeks until it goes off.
- Whenever we do a photo shoot every couple of years,
I look more and more like I've got black eyes.
(all laugh)
But another one is balloons.
I need some with a phobia of balloons.
- Oh yeah.
- And...
- Oprah Winfrey.
- Really?
- Yeah, she's got a fear of balloons.
The popping sound reminds her of a gunshot.
So apparently balloons are not allowed near Oprah,
in the same way bananas are not allowed near this Swedish...
- Well, there was one guy who has a phobia of balloons
who had to miss his brother's wedding
'cause his brother had balloons at the wedding.
And I just thought, as his brother,
are you gonna insist on balloons at your wedding
or let your brother come to your wedding?
- Good point.
I mean, balloons are not a big feature of a wedding
unless both parties are nine years old
and it's one of those European royal weddings.
- They always get balloons at weddings.
Every wedding that I've been to, I reckon.
- Excuse me, James, you're at my wedding.
I challenge you to spot a single balloon in there.
(all laugh)
- James brought me this over.
- I floated in on a wicker chair.
- Stop the wedding!
(all laugh)
It should have been me!
- But would you, if the groom had said,
"Listen, my brother has an extreme phobia of balloons
"and can't come if you have the balloons,"
would you have gone to the trouble
of taking the balloons away?
- That's such a good point.
Dodgy phobias, I just love this,
in 2014, a French government minister,
he had failed to pay his income tax for three years
and explained it was due to administrative phobia.
(James laughs)
- Which also meant he hadn't paid rent
on his flat in Paris for three years
and he also hadn't declared a company he owned.
- You know what?
I didn't read about that,
but I did read about a man in Sweden
who got a load of letters saying that he'd been speeding
but had a phobia of brown envelopes.
And he got off.
He said, "I thought I hadn't got any warnings
"because I hadn't read any of my things."
- No, come on.
- Well, and then I went onto the Oxford Dictionary
of National Biography
and looked if there was any weird phobias on there.
And I found someone called Gina Fratini,
who was a British fashion designer in the '70s.
And she also had a brown envelope phobia,
according to the ODMB.
- Really?
- So I think it is like this thing of,
you know, you think it's gonna be bad news all the time.
- Well, it is bad news.
(both laugh)
- It's the tax of writing.
- You're so scared of it
that you just won't open any of the envelopes.
- Yeah.
- I can kind of see what it comes from.
- You knew they'd arrived, hadn't you?
So you've seen that.
What did you think was in the brown envelope?
- Couple of other famous names who have phobias.
Macaulay Culkin, after making "Home Alone",
developed a phobia of leaving the house.
- Really?
- Yeah, he had agrophobia, and that was because
his life absolutely changed the paparazzi
everywhere, leaping out of bushes,
sort of following him in cars.
He got petrified, so he needed to stay at home.
He needed to be away from everyone.
- Pretty reasonable.
- Nile Horan from One Direction, the band,
petrified phobia of pigeons.
And when they're on tour,
they have people sweep the area for pigeons
if he's going to a venue.
- You would think he would just carry
like a sparrow hawk with him wherever he went.
- Or a duckstead.
- A sparrow hawk's better.
Sorry, that's more rock and roll.
Much more rock and roll.
I wasn't thinking about the optics.
- On agrophobia, as you mentioned,
I think that was the first ever modern recorded phobia,
really, when psychologists started talking about phobias.
And it was a guy called Westphal,
who was a psychologist in the 1870s.
But people were quite obsessed with it
in the late 19th century.
And Westphal described a patient who,
it basically was a fear of anything
that doesn't remind them of home.
So he'd be out in a big square
and he'd have to cling to the buildings
on the way around 'cause that reminds you
of being like surrounded by your awful walls.
And then he said, to get home,
if he has to get home and can't cling to the buildings,
then he'll either follow someone very, very closely.
So he's like, there's another human.
Or he'll acquaint himself with a lady of the night
and begin to talk to her until she realizes
that he's not trying to get any custom.
- Officer. (laughing)
Let me assure you, this is all a simple misunderstanding.
- Read Freud and he'll understand.
- Would he go to walk him home?
- He'd get a number of ladies of the night to walk him home.
So he'd go with a chain of things.
- Officer, officer.
- Me again.
- It's not an erotic conga, it's...
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that after Chernobyl,
nearby children were treated for potential radiation sickness
with compulsory hourly drinks of red wine.
So, yeah. - Very nice, yeah.
- This, I think, was sent in originally by Billy Vishen.
So thank you, Billy.
Chernobyl was in Soviet Union, now in Ukraine.
It was a nuclear reactor, it fell over in 1986,
had a big-- - Fell over.
- Well, it didn't, you know what I mean.
- It fell over. - It went badly wrong.
- It went bang.
- It went bang, it was a huge explosion,
and in the wake of it, obviously, lots of radiation,
which spread all the way across a big chunk of Europe.
- Including the UK.
And in the local area, there was a belief
that red wine was good for radiation sickness,
and doctors recommended it.
And there were numerous cases of children
who were hospitalized, not because of radiation sickness,
but because their parents have been giving them red wine
on the hour every day.
- It wasn't just around the areas
in the whole of the Soviet Union.
- Really, okay.
- So I spoke to my in-laws who were there at the time.
Apparently, it was common opinion
that alcohol helped radiation poisoning.
And they said that actually most people,
as opposed to red wine,
they would drink something called rectified spirit,
which is 97.2% alcohol.
- Oof, yeah.
- You can't actually kind of get by getting normal vodka,
and then distilling it, and distilling it,
and distilling it until it's really, really strong.
- Wow.
- Well, the red wine connection was,
there was a talk that went around at the time
that Soviet submarine sailors would have wine
with all of their dinner meals while they were down there,
and the idea was to clean the system of radiation
in the submarines.
- Wait, so were they actually doing that?
Oh, that was a rumor that they did that.
- They were definitely, I saw a menu
from a submarine, a Soviet submarine.
- I'm sorry.
- Incredible menu.
- Really?
- Yeah, I wasn't aware there were menus.
- Yeah.
- Okay, you're in it.
- As you sit down.
- Do you have anything a bit further away
from the reactor, please?
(all laughing)
- I ought to be ill, but it escaped.
- Wow.
- Yeah, and you would have a ration of red wine
for most dinner meals of most of the week.
So, yeah, so rumor went around that.
- And was that because of radiation?
- Who knows, but that was what, yeah,
according to people who lived in Chernobyl at the time,
who recounted stories.
- And of course, we now know that actually it does help.
- Yes, bizarrely, it seems to have been a study,
hasn't there, that sort of proved it.
- Yeah, a bit.
- A study from the University of Pittsburgh
School of Medicine in 2008 found that something called
resveratol, which is an antioxidant found in red wine,
may offer protection against radiation.
It helps cells, you got some cells in a Petri dish,
then it helps them against radiation,
but it didn't help mice when they tried it on mice.
- Oh, I thought we did help some of the mice.
- No, there was something called acetyl resveratol,
which is like the previous thing that I tried to pronounce,
but has got acetyl at the start of it,
and that does help mice.
- Right, okay.
- But the thing that you get in red wine on its own,
doesn't.
- And also, as they said, it was a really funny thing
to report because journalism is mad.
Every headline, red wine can be,
like the telegraph headline literally was,
red wine can protect against radiation.
Scientists may soon recommend that it is best you start
drinking heavily if exposed.
All of them saying it will protect you.
- The scientist who did the study was very clear.
He said that the dosage you would need to get enough
to help you with any kind of radiation sickness
would be 720 bottles of wine.
- Yeah, right.
- It's pretty amazing, all the stuff that happened
just after Chernobyl had the moment
where everyone in the government was trying to downplay it
within the Soviet Union, trying to say,
"Oh, it's not as bad as it seems."
So I've read this amazing article
by a lady called Natalia Charakova,
who spoke about being there and what it was like
and all the things that were being done.
She was saying that experts were going up onto TV
just saying, "You know what, actually,
"small doses of radiation are really beneficial
"we found in rat health."
And so actually, this is--
- God, it's like the study for a white, wow.
- So it's not actually gonna be too bad for you.
- Like that happened in the US as well
after the bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
There were 132 news items in the New York Times
about the bombings and not a single one
mentioned anything about the radiation.
And there were 15 articles in the 10 months
after the blast that mentioned radiation at all,
and they all said there are some medical
and biological benefits to be gained from radiation.
And the other thing is Oppenheimer said,
"There is every reason to believe
"that there was no appreciable radio activity
"on the ground in Hiroshima."
So he was just like, "Oh, no, it's all fine."
"Yeah, no, we just blew them up."
- Gosh, at Chernobyl when it happened,
they flew over in helicopters,
they dropped 5,000 tons of sand and lead and clay
on top of the fire to snuff it out, basically,
to stop the rest of it.
'Cause only a small amount of the radioactive material
in Chernobyl actually was in this explosion.
And so the impetus was to put out that fire,
which they managed to do.
'Cause if the rest of it had gone up,
Europe might've become uninhabitable, basically.
- Yeah, wow.
- Yeah, and it worked.
I mean, what they, you know.
- It worked eventually, although I didn't realize
that the sound, the dumping in the first three days
was almost completely ineffectual, the sound and boron.
So they dumped lots of sand to try and put out the fires
and the boron was to counteract the radioactivity.
But I read the opening in the roof
where they were trying to get it was really small
and basically all the sand missed it at first.
And also when you dump sand,
you picture it going down in a big lump.
I hadn't thought about it, but when you dump sand,
it all like scatters out in the air
and sort of ends up floating down.
- They should've put more water in it.
- Should've made wet sand, didn't they?
- Oh, big hourglass.
I'm sorry to have some creative thinking here,
but you know, that funnels it, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- Oh, you mean the top half of an hourglass?
- Yeah, I wouldn't have the whole hourglass.
- Yeah, it just goes up and down.
- Or gigantic sandcastle bucket
where you just lower the sand on top
and just build a lot of good solutions.
- The interesting thing about the hourglass
is you can have as big an hourglass as you want,
but the little funnel bit has to be the same size
'cause it has to be the size of a grain of sand.
So actually you're only gonna get a tiny trickle of sand.
- That's a good point, it will take a while.
- We're sitting in that helicopter day nine.
(both laughing)
Andy, are we sure about this?
- So then obviously you've got to cover this thing over.
So they built what they called a sarcophagus,
like this massive steel and concrete structure
to cover the reactor, what's left of the reactor.
And I find this amazing.
The crane operators who put that sarcophagus in place
did so without ever seeing what they were doing.
- What do you mean?
- Riddle me that.
- Okay.
- Okay, so they're in a crane
next to this thing that's happening.
- Yep.
- They would give them blindfolds
because they weren't allowed to know where it was
and they got led away.
- Any advance on that?
(both laughing)
- Not bad, not bad.
- Sorry, I was thinking.
- Official secrecy.
- Yeah, 'cause like, who's grave was it?
Were they blindfolded everyone?
- I feel like it was Genghis Khan.
- Yeah, or Attila, yeah.
- Yeah.
- It was nighttime.
- Oh, that's good, that's good thinking.
- That's actually the, did they just use a pencil?
- Yeah.
- Oh, I was gonna do that one, yeah.
- What it was is they were inside lead lined cabins
because the radio activity when this was being lowered
was more well known about and it was very high.
So they were following instructions over the radio.
They were basically doing pin the sarcophagus
on the reactor.
- Wow.
- Like they were getting instructions
from people who were observing from a long distance.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And they just were doing it blind.
- Left, left, no, mine left, no, mine left.
(both laughing)
- Okay, we're gonna need another sarcophagus now.
- Well, they did put a second one on in the end, didn't they?
- They did.
- In fact, this is something we talked about
on No. 6 Things in the News, our short-lived TV show.
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause I think it was around that time
when they put a new big bit of concrete over it
and it was like the biggest dome
that had ever been created.
- Is it concrete?
I thought it was, one of them was steel, right?
'Cause I felt like the first one was concrete
and that got dilapidated
and then they have now made this steel dome
which I think is gonna last 100 years-ish.
But it still feels like you're gonna have to set an alarm
for 100 years time when you've forgotten about it.
- It's just snoozing, isn't it, basically?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause it basically, it's Chernobyl turned into
basically a giant Russian doll.
- Oh.
- It's just bigger and bigger, yeah.
- Massive Ukrainian doll, we should say.
- Yeah, Ukrainian doll.
You can now, given that we're talking about alcohol
at Chernobyl, you can get a drink called Atomic
and I've ordered some of this, I love this.
It's harvested from apples from abandoned orchards
in the local area, all of which are now producing apples
which are very low in radiation.
So it's completely safe for consumption
and it goes to funding local bits of Ukraine
which have been, you know, severely hammered
not only by the nuclear reactor going off,
but also by the war.
And it's still being made and distributed, I believe, so.
- That's good, I know.
- I think it's you don't drink vodka, so.
- I'm gonna try.
- But good on you.
- I'm gonna have a bag of apples,
it might be more like snaps.
- It's exactly, I think it is actually.
I think it's basically snaps.
- Is it an apple sour?
- Yeah, it's an apple very sour, yeah.
- It's amazing the fallout, how far it did travel.
Like they have found a little layer
of radioactive materials at the bottom of Loch Ness,
for example, which has come.
- Here we go.
- Hey, listen, I can't.
- Did the Beatles find it?
My only chance.
- They were in a yellow submarine on the menu each night.
- But no, do you know what's interesting?
Talking earlier about the sort of the experts
coming on and trying to downplay it.
As a result, people sort of started thinking,
actually, this might not be true.
And according to Natalia,
whose article I read about the experience
of living there at the time,
she said everyone started experiencing radiophobia,
like her grandmother used to put iodine in her meals
just to make sure that, yeah.
Then also parents were just,
if they couldn't get out from where they were,
we're just putting their kids onto trains
with their names, and this is my name,
please look after me and just saying, go.
And they sent them out in further away,
in further away.
- 'Cause these weren't people in the exclusion zone,
'cause the exclusion zone was completely evacuated.
But people who were just close enough
that they thought, I'm really scared now.
- Yeah, it just spread around there.
Like how far did this travel?
- A lot of people in the UK were scared as well.
It's in all the newspapers.
I probably would have been quite scared, yeah.
- I got one of the letters that was sent out
to people living in the local area at the time.
It's really interesting the phrasing,
'cause they're trying to persuade people
to take some precautions,
but also trying to say, it's all fine.
So the letter begins, dear comrades, positive.
The result of detailed analysis showed
that living and working in your village
will cause no harm to adults or children.
Great news.
And then it said, we've got a few tips.
Do not eat berries and mushrooms gathered this year.
Children should not enter the forest.
Limit fresh greens.
Remove topsoil from the garden
and bury it in specially prepared graves
far from the village.
But apart from that, you're all fine.
- I think mushrooms like are particularly bad, aren't they?
'Cause they sort of get the nutrients from the soil
and they can't really.
- Now.
- Is that not true?
- Is this where your mushroom thing comes from?
- Oh, maybe.
- You look at a mushroom and you see radiation.
You were alive at the time.
It was in the news.
- It's true, it's true.
- There might have been a triggering incident.
- Could have been.
That's usually the case, isn't it?
That's what they all say,
that these people who are scared of bananas
must have had some terrible bananas.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- There was a woman who was electrocuted
while looking at a bowl of bananas.
Sorry, it's not funny.
It's not funny.
- No.
- Like, got an electric shock.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Electrocuted.
- Electrified.
- Well, she wasn't,
she didn't convert to run on electricity.
(laughing)
It's a word we haven't worked out yet.
- Have you guys heard about this?
Many things about this.
Samosally, they're the people who chose to return.
So about 1,200 people, after they're evacuated,
decided, you know what?
My home's Chernobyl or the surrounding area.
I'm going back.
And they went back and a couple of years that followed.
- Wow, like two, three years after.
- Like some of them went back months after.
A lot of them did.
And there are about 200 of them left.
And it's fascinating
'cause they're spread across about 164 villages.
So there were just over one person per village.
And they live extraordinary lives.
I was reading an interview with one called Ivan
who was remembering the time
and said that, you know, they weren't really scared.
He remembered going and handing alcohol
to everyone there 'cause they all knew it would cure them.
And he lives in a village with two other women.
The journalist said, do you ever see them?
And he said, no, we almost never socialize.
- I'm really sorry to say this, but sitcom?
I know I say it all the time
when something like this terrible thing happens.
- But you think this is the one?
- I mean, one guy and two women
living in a village on the road
and they never like to speak to each other.
- It's a recipe for comedy.
- Did you see Bionerd, 23?
- What's that?
- She's someone who had a YouTube channel
and she made over 60 videos of her
going in the exclusion zone.
And she would do things like pick apples off a tree
and take a bite into them.
But she was also a scientist.
And so she would show you that it was safe.
But she hasn't posted, I think, in about five years now.
And she never gave her name
and no one really knows who she is.
So we don't know what's happened to her.
But she's a legit sort of YouTuber from back in the day.
- A legit YouTuber, what is a legit YouTuber?
- Well, she was a scientist
who was trying to show you that it's changed.
- Yeah, legit.
- 'Cause a legit YouTuber is just someone
who has a camera on their phone.
- There it is, yeah.
- So everyone apart from you.
(all laughing)
There are a lot of dogs around Chernobyl today.
And they're genetically distinct from dogs
that are just about 10 or 20 miles away.
- Is that just they've mated with each other?
They've got their own clan.
And so they've become a little different.
- It honestly is that.
It's just they've kept themselves to themselves.
And the other dogs have kept themselves to themselves.
And they've lived apart for long enough
that they have genetic markers
that are different between the two dogs now.
- Do they?
- Wow, that's incredible.
- That's interesting.
'Cause they're basically survivors of the cull, aren't they?
When one of the less,
well, all the jobs are quite unpleasant after it,
but a specific police squad were sent in
to kill all the pets that were left in Chernobyl
so that they didn't go and spread.
- The idea is perhaps there was something about them
that made them able to survive the cull.
And that's like a slightly genetic difference
that has them, you know.
- Wow.
- The ability to hide under a sofa.
- But that's the same.
All the frogs around there are now black.
And this is very weird.
It's 'cause initially slightly darker frogs
were slightly likely to survive the radiation.
And this is how long ago, nearly 40 years now,
which is 10 to 15 frog generations.
So they have observed micro evolution even in this time.
And darker ones in the exclusion zone,
the frogs are all black now.
- I've read recently that gray squirrels are turning black.
- Is that so?
- We've got black squirrels around us.
And I always wonder what the hell they're doing there.
- Well, apparently they are more likely to survive
if they're dark because it means they can hide.
- I don't know what they blend in with.
- That's a bit depressing, isn't it?
- I read that in a study this week.
So actually, I just read the headline.
I haven't read the study yet.
- The hang on concrete is gray.
I would have thought gray squirrel or gray concrete
is perfect for them.
- And then you'll come, you get run over.
Black squirrel used to stand out.
- And is that why, do they want to stand out?
- I really wish I'd read this article now.
- No, it feels like it would have helped us a lot.
- That's just what you're like wildly,
it's what Dan's all the podcast is.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the song "Take Me Home Country Roads"
was written by three people who had never been
to West Virginia.
Take Me Out to the Ball Game was written by two people
who had never been to a ball game.
And the Pina Collada song was written by one person
who had never drunk one.
- Lovely.
- A lot of this makes sense.
I mean, the reason you want to be taken to a ball game
'cause you've never been to one.
- Oh, that's true.
- That holds together, doesn't it?
- But on the other hand, "Take Me Home"
to West Virginia. - Doesn't play, yeah.
- That's tougher.
- So that famously is a John Denver song written
by three people, Bill Danoff, Taffy Nivert and John Denver.
The first two were in a band before
and Danoff wrote that song "Afternoon Delight",
if you know that.
- My rock is in flight.
- Yeah, exactly.
If you've seen "Anchorman", you'll know that movie.
Sorry, you'll know that song.
But yeah, so they were riding around in their car
on Clopper Road in Montgomery County, Maryland.
And they had an idea for this song.
But it didn't scan.
- "Take Me Home", Clopper Road.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, it didn't scan.
And they were writing the lyrics one night
and John Denver happened to come over to their house
having busted his thumb
and gone to emergency hospital surgery.
He was sitting with them in their house early in the morning.
They'd planned to sell it to Johnny Cash.
And he started hearing the song.
He thought, "This is incredible."
And they stayed up all night writing the song.
And because none of them had been to West Virginia,
they got an encyclopedia down
and they had to look up all the details
in order to make the lyrics work.
- Is the rest of the song,
does it show an encyclopedic knowledge of West Virginia?
'Cause I've come over.
- Full violation, 384,000.
(all laughing)
- I heard that they basically liked the scanning
of Blue Ridge Mountains and Shenador River
and stuff like that.
They like these phrases.
And that's kind of why they went for West Virginia.
- 'Cause those are the famous bits.
If you just do the main population centers,
it's probably gonna be less romantic.
- Yeah, but also they were gonna use Massachusetts
'cause it's got four syllables as well.
Just looking for something with four syllables in it.
- Right, West Virginia, yeah, yeah, yeah.
What about this ball game thing?
- Oh, the ball game?
- Well, ball game, that was written in 1908
and that was written by a guy called Jack Norworth
and he wrote the lyrics and he brought the song,
the lyrics to this guy called Albert von Tilzer
and he put it to the tune that we now know it as.
Both of them had never been to a game before.
They would only go one of them 32 years later
after writing the song and then the other 20 years later
after writing the song, but it became popular
because it was an incredible announcer
for the Chicago White Sox.
He would announce their games called Harry Carrie.
Who used to sing it?
- We should just say that this is,
if you go to a baseball game,
they play it at every baseball game in America.
So that's why it's kind of famous.
- It's massive and they play it at the same point
as well as during the Seventh Innings.
- I don't think I know it.
Is it like the equivalent of like--
- I like thinking British people wouldn't know it.
- I don't know.
Take me out to the ball game
- Wow, really?
- British people would not know that song.
- It's just in so many American movies and--
- Is it the equivalent of the rare,
the referee, the wanker?
- That's it, yeah.
- It was their follow-up, it's just--
- That was actually written by a man
who had never masturbated.
(all laughing)
- A lot of people look back on this song now
because most people don't know the lyrics to the song,
certainly the first verse.
They just know "Take me out."
They know the main chorus, which is sung.
But it's pushed as a really progressive song
for women at the time.
And this was a result of he based it on,
he was having an affair at the time
with two vaudeville characters.
- His main girlfriend was someone called Trixie Fraganza,
who's also a bit--
- Sorry, Trixie, but not a real name.
- Before you say so, she was an outspoken suffragist
as well as a vaudeville.
- No good honest, incredible.
- Sounds like a suffragist's name,
doesn't it, Trixie Fraganza?
But she had, her most famous act was striptease,
where every time it looked like she was gonna take off
an item of clothing, she did,
but you never saw anything
'cause there was always more clothing underneath.
She would just keep going,
and there'd be more and more and more clothes.
- She's covered in layers of suffragist pamphlets.
- Yes.
- But it's pushed as a really progressive song
for women at the time.
And this was a result of him basing it on Trixie.
So the lyrics basically say she was baseball mad.
This was a time, 1908,
where women weren't going to baseball,
and it was, so it was a real push.
- Cool. - It was good.
- Go Trixie. - Aggressive.
- I won't hear a word against her.
- Okay, what was the last one?
- Oh, Pina Colada. - Pina Colada.
- Yeah, I love this.
- Yeah, well, do you wanna take over, Andy?
- Well, so Rupert Holmes from Northwich in Cheshire?
- Really? - Yeah.
- Who wrote the Pina Colada song?
- He wrote the Pina Colada song, Northwich.
- Lovely part of the world.
- Is it? I've never been.
- No.
- Well, it now has a Pina Colada festival every year.
- It does.
- And he had never had one.
And also it wasn't meant to be Pina Colada in the song.
Initially when he was writing it, it was Humphrey Bogart.
- Yeah.
- If you like Humphrey Bogart.
- Yeah, you would have to say Humphrey Bogart.
- No, I think you can go,
if you like Humphrey Bogart.
- No, guys, if you like Humphrey Bogart, that's easy.
- If you like Humphrey Bogart.
- But so yeah, he just thought,
what is a nice sounding drink?
He had never had it.
And the sales were terrible of the song at first,
despite the song being mega popular.
So it's a great, it's a brilliant song.
It's about this guy who's bored of his lady.
And he posts--
- Are you gonna spoil a Pina Colada song now?
- I think I am actually.
He reads an advert in the newspaper.
- If you're halfway through listening
to the Pina Colada song, just turn off now.
- He reads this advert in the newspaper saying,
if you like Pina Colada and getting caught in the rain,
if you blah, blah, blah, blah, then, you know,
let's get together.
And then he turns up and it's his wife.
They realize they did love each other.
They are compatible, but anyway, whatever.
- What a lovely story.
- And the thing is, come with me and escape.
And the song is called Escape.
And everyone was listening on the radio.
The radio fans were going nuts for it.
DJs were playing it all the time,
but no one was buying it 'cause they could not remember
the name of the song.
- Oh my God.
- It was what's that song?
It's the, oh, you know, the Pina Colada song.
And then his record label--
- How helpful were shopkeepers in those days?
If you went in and said, what's the song about Pina Colada?
And they're like, what's the seal?
- Nope, nope, never heard of that.
Nope.
- And his record label put,
his record label put on escape brackets of the Pina Colada song.
- I just love the idea of him saying,
unless you say the exact correct name,
I'm not gonna get it.
- A lot of record shots were starved
by Rumpelstiltskin in those days.
(both laughing)
But the record label added those brackets,
literally escape brackets, the Pina Colada song,
and it went quadruple platinum.
- Really? - It just went nuts, yeah, yeah.
- On sort of songs that don't fit their writers,
which I suppose is the topic of this,
a hard one to research.
But the famous one really is the Barry Manilow song,
I Write the Songs, which he didn't write.
It was actually written by Bruce Johnson of The Beach Boys.
- Wow. - Which I hadn't realized.
And Manilow did say at the time
that he knew that he would be in trouble
as soon as his producer handed it to him.
And he said, look, I know that I'm gonna get in shit
for this 'cause I didn't write it.
But have you ever heard the Barry Manilow song?
I really do write the songs.
- No. (both laughing)
- It's really good. - I love a song sequel.
- It's so good, so it's a spoof,
basically responding to all his critics who were saying,
but he didn't write, I write the songs.
And it's a manual for how to write a song.
So it has lyrics like, you start off with the verse,
and that's the part that tells you
what the song's gonna be about.
And you can talk about dope or death,
but love is probably the best.
It's better than this, the actual lyrics.
- It does sound like they have used
an encyclopedia entry for that one.
(both laughing)
- You know the thing with I Write the Songs?
He didn't want to sing it
because he wanted to write his own songs.
And he was presented with it by his producer.
And it's the singer of the song is the spirit of music.
It's actually from the perspective of music itself.
I write the songs, right?
Like I'm the inspiration for the channel.
But when he read the lyrics, he thought,
this just sounds like me, Barry Manilow,
singing I write the songs.
And that's what people interpret it as.
So I don't want to do that.
And Bruce Johnson said, no, this is God narrating the song.
- And it's gonna come off as much better
if you're speaking as God.
- Yeah, he really didn't want to sing it
until he was strong armed into it by his producer.
And then went to number one.
- I think he quite enjoyed it.
As in, I think now, like doing that piss take
that ends in the climax.
Sometimes I really do write the songs.
And he does refer to it.
I feel like he's taken it quite well.
You could have got quite pissed off about that tension.
I'm not like Frank Sinatra actually did a version,
which I didn't know.
And he insisted on changing the lyrics
to I sing the songs, which I think is a bit of a cop out.
- Yeah, it is.
- Do you guys know the song Girls Just Wanna Have Fun?
- Of course. - Love it.
Cindy Lauper.
- Well, she didn't write it.
It was written by a man called Robert Hazard.
And the amazing thing is not only did he write it,
he also sang it.
And he sang the same lyrics more or less.
It's slightly different, but they're more or less the same.
But when you listen to them, how he sang them,
it's got a really different meaning.
- I bet.
- So if you think about it, my daddy said,
"What are you gonna do with your life?
"You're not the fortunate one.
"Girls just wanna have fun."
What he's saying is,
"I'm not gonna care what I'm doing in my life.
"I'm going out and I'm gonna sleep with a load of women
"because they just wanna have fun."
- Fair enough.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But it's a different song.
- It's a very different song.
- It's a different tone, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, definitely.
- I think "I'm Every Woman"
was also largely written by a man.
- Was it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- What do you mean largely written?
Like, he wrote "I'm Every Man."
Someone had to do the WO.
- I think it was co-written,
but he wrote most of the lyrics.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, yeah.
- I do know that respect R-E-S-P-E-C-T.
Indeed, Ari Frankes,
which was a big feminist anthem, obviously,
and a civil rights anthem.
But that was originally written about a man
saying, "My wife's got to respect me
when I come home tired from work after a long, old day."
And yeah.
- Oh, wow.
- She just reclaimed it.
- One little tweak, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- My favorite one's always been that
the song "It Wasn't Me" by Shaggy.
15 years after the song was released,
he revealed that it was in fact him.
He was the cheater in the song.
- 'Cause it's about someone cheating.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's actually used legally now as the Shaggy defense.
- It's where you got irrefutable evidence
that you did something and you just say,
"No, I didn't do it."
- Exactly, yeah.
The Shaggy defense.
- The toddler defense.
- It's a bad defense.
- It's a Trump defense.
- Look at this, yeah.
- Toto, you can guess what I'm about to say about them.
- Africa, they've never been to Africa.
- Yeah, and this is David Page, who wrote,
I was reading about, I basically thought,
"I bet Toto had never been to Africa."
And I looked at Africa and they hadn't when they wrote it.
And the guy who wrote it was a member of the band
called David Page.
And he sounds quite arrogant.
He said he was humming the melody
and then the words came to him
and he thought to himself,
"Hang on, I'm a very talented songwriter,
"but even I'm not this talented,
"our higher power is writing through me."
- That God again.
- That bloody God he gets everywhere.
And he used descriptions that he'd read
in National Geographic.
And I think he'd read a biography of Dr. Livingston
to get his Africa...
- Okay, we'll just bang up to the minute
for the very latest news out of the continent.
- He'd basically been, I think we can say.
- Are there any brilliant Congress lyrics in the song?
I can't remember how it goes.
- There are a few.
- I hear the reins down in Africa, is that it?
- Yeah.
- The Serengeti is in the wrong place.
I can't remember what the lyric is.
Like something rises over,
a mountain rises over the Serengeti.
Kill the manjaro over the Serengeti, I think.
Which isn't...
- It's not too far away, isn't it?
- It's not too far away.
- Close enough.
It's all Africa.
Yeah, okay, got it.
- He didn't admit that he hadn't been.
And then he went in the late 1990s.
So he wrote it in 1982.
Then they toured in South Africa.
And apparently he said when he was touring South Africa,
all the South Africans ran up to him and said,
"Wow, so when were you in Africa?"
And when he said he wasn't, they said,
"But you described it so perfectly."
- The way that the pyramids reflect the beauties
of Johannesburg, it's incredible.
- The other toto.
Sorry, I've just got one more thing about the other toto.
- Yeah?
- The toto of the dog.
Wizard of Oz.
What's the famous song?
- We're off to see the wizard.
- Oh, sorry.
- Somewhere over the rainbow.
- Oh my God, the author had never seen a rainbow.
- I shouldn't have picked a film
which is banger after banger after banger.
Somewhere over the rainbow is the song I'm thinking of.
There were concerns about that song.
Can you guess why?
So it's an ecosystem based on selling sheet music.
Studio executives were very nervous about this song.
- Is it 'cause it's a set?
It's very short.
- It's because of the way the notes muck around.
There's an octave leap.
Somewhere.
And it's really, it's hard for amateur singers
to sing that well.
And the studio bosses were like,
"No one's going to buy the sheet music.
"This is junk, change it."
- 'Cause you can't sing along to it easily.
- Pretty much, yeah.
And so therefore that would damage their margins of the film.
- How interesting.
I think I should shout out to our colleague, James Rawson,
who I appealed to for this fact.
And he just really wants to air something
that's annoyed him for years,
which is the Alicia Keys debut album Songs in A Minor,
which was a great album.
(all laughing)
- Where's this going?
- You might remember.
- I'm not songs.
- They're all the A Minor, it's fine.
Yeah, there's only...
Well, the internet says there's only one song in A Minor
and I wasted quite a lot of time.
I'm not very good at the piano, putting Spotify on,
and then working out what key they're all in.
And I think there are two songs in A Minor on it,
but it's still not all of the songs.
It's only two out of 16.
So Alicia...
- That's great.
- Sort yourself out.
And then I learned you had a son called Egypt,
but he has been to Egypt.
(all laughing)
- But in fairness, she's called Alicia Keys.
So obviously it's going to be in different keys.
- Brilliant.
- That's a good point.
She's pulled it back.
(all laughing)
- Here's an interesting thing.
The song Ain't No Sunshine by Bill Withers.
- Yep. - Oh yeah.
- Is Unfinished.
- Is it? - Yeah.
- Really?
'Cause it just goes,
I know, I know, I know, I know, I know, I know
And I've never got to the end of that bit.
- That's the bit.
He got to the recording booth with the song Unfinished
and he just improvised,
I know, I know, I know, I know, I know
And he was like, "I'll do this later."
- It walked out the booth so it sounded like a fade.
(all laughing)
- Is that true?
- Yeah. - That's really funny.
- Well, thinking it'll come to me in the moment,
it's fine. - Yeah.
(all laughing)
- That's great.
- But yeah, if you listen long enough,
it goes, "No, I don't know."
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @Sriberland.
Andy. - On Blues Guy at Andrew Hunter M.
- James.
- I am on the artist's family known as Twitter,
@JamesHarkin.
- And if you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can find us on Instagram @NoSuchThingIsAfish
or on that Twitter place @NoSuchThing
or you can email our podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, or go to our website.
NoSuchThingIsAfish.com.
There is everything from upcoming gigs
that you can come and check out.
See if you want to see us live.
You can go check out Club Fish,
which is our secret members club.
We have lots of bonus items up there
going up every fortnight.
Really fun stuff, like answering your questions.
So do send them into podcast at qi.com, as Anna says.
Otherwise, just come back here
'cause we will be back with another episode
and we will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]