Hi everyone and welcome to episode
501 of no such thing as a fish. Well, what do we have for you this week?
We have finished our summer live shows and we have loads of extra bits that I couldn't fit into the normal
15 minute to an hour episode of fish
Usually what we would do with those is we'd make them into a compilation and they would go for our club fish members
That's where all the compilations go these days
But seeing as they were the live shows that were coming to the end of summer and that we're all sleeping off our hangovers from episode
500 we thought we would put this up on our main feed now the thing is about these episodes is if you like the
Facts on fish then these are some of the best episodes for you because they are super concentrated of little nuggets of information
But there's loads of fun silly stuff in there as well
I really hope you enjoy it if you like your compilations, then you can become a member of club fish
You will also get ad free episodes
You'll get other bonus contents such as drop as a line where we go through the mailbox and meet the elves where we meet some of our
Newer members of staff at QI. There's also stuff on there
It's well worth joining and you can join there by going to know such things the fish dot com forward slash apple or no such things
The fish dot com forward slash patreon anyway, I really hope you enjoy this week's show
We'll be back next week with a normal episode, but for now it's on with the podcast
Please welcome to stage our buddy loose Anders everybody
Please welcome to the stage Rachel Paris everybody
Sophie Duker everyone
Fry
You're joined by nerd royalty ladies and gentlemen welcome to the stage Susie Dent
He is of course Greg Jenner
Pariad Lloyd everybody, it's Jamie Morton everybody
Sally Phillips
Ella al-Shamahi everyone
It is Richard Osmar
Have you heard there's a great anecdote which I've been trying to prove but it's I don't think it's true. I was
Actually, it's not true, and it's not relevant. Let's move on
Well, we got a lot quicker than normal didn't we? It's great
Usually I waste all our time, but I'm learning
That's bullshit. That's one of your best stories done
Quickly tell you guys about Alain bombard. Oh, yeah
I was a French doctor and he is very unusual because he's one of the only people in history ever to shipwreck himself
Okay, so this is amazing
There were lots of people at the time being you know lots of shipwreck sailors who were dying each year
We're like when they're when their boats were shipwrecked and he wanted to prove that even if you had no food or water
There were there were ways you could survive so he set off from the canaries
With a sextant a tarpaulin a fishing rod and a sealed box of food and water which he was going to try really hard not to open
The self-control he must have had he suffered terribly like
Yeah, he had no rain for three weeks and then storms snapped the mast of his dinghy
Swordfish approached his rubber dinghy nose first
I know that's cool
53 days later he bumped into a ship and they said oh, yeah
You're still 600 miles off course for where you're going, right?
He had just become a father as well when he did this which I find
Like well at least some sleep
The length some people will go to
So anyway, but anyway, so he he then he got on board this ship which picked him up after 53 days
He had a small lunch of a fried egg
Then got back on his dinghy and kept sailing towards Barbados, right and he made it there in the end
He did it eventually, but yeah, I just think what a what a self-experiment to do that to yourself extraordinary, but why?
What's approved that apart from not to see your child and wife
I think they're taking 18 years to get
Yeah, I think it was to prove what you could survive on if you could survive on fish or plankton
Which you you can do and you can do that without actually doing it. You could just say oh, I might eat fish today
That's my self-control right there in a tin of food you can't open
Just out of curiosity have we have we been eating and drinking from the wrong end this whole time
Would there be would there be certain things?
Well
Because President Garfield was through his
Famously you've got a bit of your pipe left down
What better time to put it into practice a
Tutorial if you will I
Think if you have the option the mouth is a better option if we have no other option then the rectum is acceptable
Just fluids though, so I mean if you're trying to absorb lots of nutrients
Okay, then you want then you know your stomach and your upper digestive system will do all that work
So so it is a plan B very much so and I'll still try it
I was looking at people who
Died laughing this happened in 1920 and it was reported by an Australian newspaper called the Mudgee Guardian and Northwestern
Representative okay, do you know it? Yeah? Yeah, that's my
It's about a man called Arthur Cobcroft and I'm really I'm reading directly
So mr. Arthur Cobcroft died at his home in Lofter Street Saturday
He was reading at this 1920 he was reading an old newspaper of a 1915 date and was comparing the prices of various
Commodities with those of today
When he suddenly burst into laughter at the great difference he appeared to be unable to control himself and eventually collapsed and died
Commodity prices
They must have been so different
I'm laughing thinking about it now
It's amazing because I reckon the cost of living crisis isn't that funny today
No, but for him, but if I say to you are like a Freddo used to be 10p
Yeah, I
Was reading about when something goes wrong on stage
And so that got me into a whole territory of if someone is hurt as they're acting
What do you do and I found this thing that apparently it's a huge problem for paramedics when they're called to help someone
Who's really injured who's in a zombie movie because they arrive
They have no idea who the patient is because everyone is bleeding everyone's got
Even if they find the person who's really injured themselves
They just can't tell where the wound is because the amount of well
I broke a rib being chased by a zombie once did you yeah?
Yeah, I was in London like one of these things where you pay to be chased by zombies
Yeah
It does sound a bit like I
Was like watching a lot of American football at the time and the zombie was coming towards me
And I thought I'd do some amazing dodges past him
and I got nowhere near past him and he kind of tagged me and pushed me into a wall and I broke a rib and
They we had to go to like the A&E and there were quite a lot of people who'd had similar problems
And it was just like you say it was like being in mash
It's just people with arms hanging off. You didn't know what was real and what wasn't yeah
I found out that Bungay in East Anglia has the highest number of satanists in the UK. Oh
Today now I'd like to take issue with that would you because I think it's Bolsova in Derbyshire
How many has Bolsova got 17 17 17 17 in Bungay
Okay, but it might be relative to population. I don't know how big Bungay is sounds tiny
This Bolsova thing is from the census in 2011 when this was from the census. I bet it's is it later census mine
Maybe I don't know 20 21. Yeah, but the in Bolsova
It was only 17 people who wrote satanist as their religion, but that was the highest per person
But highest concentration even Bristol only had 34 people who wrote satanist, but Bristol's huge
So the Google article I saw said
Bungay in East Anglia and then the next one was Bronzebury
London which had 20 so the big gay be contingent of the alphabets
Beelzebub
The beast yeah
There was a footnote that said they thought Bungay my might been doing it as a kind of tourist attracting thing
Because they've got a big black dog. I can't know what it's called like a myth of a big black a satanic dog
I'm okay, man. Yeah, and they're trying to push that. It's worked. I mean, we're all talking about Bungay all the time
Or did you know there's a pantomime horse arrest in Tesco's
When it was when it was found that the Tesco's budget brand everyday value burgers contain 29% horse meat
Yeah, pantomime horse went to protest in Tesco's
Crying going mommy
And it was led away
And it was never seen
Here's a good quick little tip if you meet someone who's Dutch and they say to you I fuck horses
They don't
Not necessarily you've got it. Oh, I can't confirm for certain. Yeah, so is that Dutch does it sound okay means breeding?
Yeah, they breed horses. Yeah, and there supposedly was a story where the Dutch foreign minister was introduced to JFK
And he said hi how we knew so don't very good. Well, what are your hobbies? I fuck horses and
Why did he only say that one word in Dutch and the rest of it?
That's where I also questioned the anecdotes. Yeah, but it does stand I looked up the translation
Yeah, and fok is for breeding. So yeah, again, you'd never hear that in that kind unless horses
I didn't look up horses and look up if they say that in Dutch
Should we move on?
So one person who did slightly pioneer the idea of living underwater it was Jacques Cousteau Jacques Cousteau you all probably
Know him. He's he's had the calypso and he was one of the greatest ocean. Sorry. I don't you know the dance. No
You know the ice cream using it with a calypso. Yeah, he's one of the greatest
Oceanographers of all time and he kind of pioneered documentary making in the field of immersive and you follow a team and
The life aquatic by Wes Anderson is very much based on the story of Jacques Cousteau
But on a scientific level he also invented or co-invented the aqualung which is why we're able to go diving
So that was Jacques Cousteau and then one of the other things he did was this thing called the con shells
Which are the continental shells which were habitable zones down in the ocean and continental shelf to was this big looking starfish
kind of housing unit and
He lived in it with his crew for a number of days
They had a parrot that came down and lived with them as well because that in a sort of slightly dark sense
It was like the canary in the mountain. You know something was wrong with the levels of oxygen
Okay, parrot would know first and so they could get out of there
So he set a record for the longest anyone's been down there and then his son Fabian Cousteau
So he lived down there and held the record for the longest anyone's been under the ocean for quite a while
And then it got taken over by a professor and a student
But he invented a shark submarine. Have you seen this?
This is this is incredible. It's the submarine in the shape of a shark
So the idea is that he can observe sharks while being one of them. It's a one person submersible
No, he has to be in a diving suit while he's in it because water flows all the way through
He has to drive the submarine while laying down in the shark and his elbows are steering it as he goes
Why his elbows? What's he doing with the sun? Sorry, he's not his elbows steering with his hands
Okay, thank you
He has a needless layer of complication for an otherwise flawless idea. He's on his phone, isn't he and he's just like
I was looking at in British elections, you know, there's that thing of always on election night a general election night
There's a kind of who gets their their ballot counted first and it's which constituencies also
It's usually like Sunderland versus Newcastle Sunderland and Newcastle and you mean like a race to get
Yeah, I was reading about Sunderland's methods for ensuring they stay at the top of their game. Yeah, and they're amazing
So well we're going with it's kind of a tradition now and they've like they've done it
They've really gone into detail
So they hire bank tellers because they're very good at flipping through lots and lots of paper very quickly like individual bits of paper
They use lighter paper for their ballot sheets because it's slightly easier to count fast
So they switch from a hundred gsm to 80 gsm
Yeah, they do obviously they do practices like they practically dress rehearsals with the students who are running holding the ballot boxes
And they are like they say you're gonna be filmed. You're gonna be you need to be you know careful
you don't want to drop those that'll be a disaster and
They play but always wins in that constituency, right? I think they do I think they always win
I guess they would yeah, but you remember like I always watch the election night and they all the results come in and I
Only stay up for Sunderland the Newcastle a hundred percent labor and then I go to bed
Always slightly disappointed when I wake up. I get it. Yeah, you can get woolen coffins these days. I believe this is very
Little price for anyone who can guess the headline that was used on the story announcing us in 2011
Take your time that you're allowed woolen coffins now. Yeah as a cool woolen coffin that's been launched
Gonna have to hurry you
No, no, that's all no, that's all believe silent bits of podcasts a very popular anyone in the audience
This is too tough a quiz handy anyone
What was a burial was good famous phrase cozy bear went with
rest in fleece
Mine very nice, but lovely
Yeah, you can be you can be buried in it or it can be cremated
It's the same in the way you can get cardboard coffins wool coffins willow coffins banana leaf coffins
Or you can now be wrapped in a shroud as we used to be and there's a big movement a natural burial movement
Which is because there are so many
Horrible chemicals and a lot of funeral processes, especially if you are embalmed
It's very bad for the environment for your body to go into the ground full of chemicals
Right, so if you have a biodegradable coffin, then you can be buried in like what in a natural burial
It's basically a field that someone's agreed to have people buried in can you get wicker? Yeah wicker
Yeah, and you can also get one that's made of like a mushroom fungus that will start to decompose your body faster
That is cool, and so this is really important
I've talked before a big talk of planning your funeral and advance care planning is big thing that you should write this down now
Otherwise, you're gonna get wrapped in that wool suit. Right. I just like to put it that because this is being recorded and we'll go out
I do not want to be eaten by mushrooms when okay
Do you want banana leaves or wicker or wool? I'll be putting a big wicker cage and burned by some
And probably some people be dancing around in white in the situation. That's gonna be an amazing podcast when it comes out
One of the suffragettes this was Anne Hunt she walked into the National Portrait Gallery and
She stopped in front of a portrait of Thomas Carlisle who's one of the founders
Painted by Millay and she slashed it. It was a really famous thing that she did
There was only one member of staff who was suspicious. I was guy called David Wilson and the first time she walked in
He wasn't that suspicious. He thought she was American
Apparently he thought she was American because she was looking so closely at the pictures
Apparently that's what Americans do but then the second day she came back in again
And David Wilson said they she couldn't be American because no American would have paid the six pence entrance fee twice over
So it's like that must be someone that's up to no good
Was she coming back? Had she already slashed something? No the first time she went in was to kind of
Yeah, so there were lots of sort of famous incidents like particular flash points where for example
Mrs. Pankhurst was going to speak at an event and then and you know the police didn't want it to happen
And so that became a course celebrity. So there was an event called the Battle of Glasgow
The Mrs. Pankhurst was going to Glasgow to speak and the police did not want her to appear
They didn't want her to speak
There were 50 police constables in the basement of the building where she was billed to appear all the tickets have been sold
You know huge presence like people checking everyone on the door
Suddenly Mrs. Pankhurst appears on stage out of nowhere and it turns out she just come in as a punter with a ticket
Sat by the platform and then gets up and start speaking
So all the police start coming up from the basement because they're you know, they're activated
Meanwhile
25 of the suffragette bodyguards get their clubs out and start trying to beat the police up
Yeah, you know, so you've got 25 suffragettes with clubs 50 policemen with their truncheons
One of the suffragettes shot a policeman in the chest point blank with a blank bullet
So it wasn't it was just a kind of surprise rather than I
Hope she said that
And then playing clothes detectives tried to get onto the platform when Mrs. Pankhurst is still speaking at this point
Yeah, she's still delivering her speech the playing clothes detectives are trying to climb onto the platform
It turns out the floral garlands all the way around the platform are barbed wire. They've been disguised
There are old ladies now beating the police with their umbrellas as they're trying to fight the truncheon
We're like it just sounds like an insane scene. Who's listening to the speech at this point?
Weird moment today I was researching crisps and I found out in Japan at the moment
There's a trend that's going on and then it turns out this is going global now to eat crisps using chopsticks
So that you don't get the oil on your fingers as you are doing the other work that you're doing right if you're eating
So I was literally eating a bag of crisps as I was researching that fact and my fingers absolutely was sticky on the on the
The Mac sort of mouse bits, you know like keep all keep it. Yeah. Yeah, the keep that like the you know
The hand mouse thing the keypad. Yeah, well the keypads the mouse and the mean the mouse
The tracker the trackpad
The trackpad
Gosh, it's like living in the future, isn't it?
I found myself reading a piece about historical novels by a radical
James Forester, I just want to quote from this article. He wrote about ten years ago and listen to this
He was because he reads a lot and he I think he wrote historical novels, too
One highly acclaimed and commercially successful recent historical novel had on page three the statement that there were no priests within a three-day ride
Taking into consideration the time of year and the location of this statement. I calculated that there were between five and eight thousand priests
Within a three-day ride in that year. I could not carry on reading
Children are quite weirdly good at lying so or rather they're good
So adults are very bad at telling when children are like this is the thing and the reason for that they can only work
It out about the same as I'm guessing on at like a 54% of the time
So not much better than chance really and the reason for that there are lots of experiments and it's because adults assume that children
Lie like adults do and they assume that children's faces
Move in the same ways that adults do but basically there have been a load of experiments
Which assumed that children are not proficient liars and in fact the problem is that children just look guilty quite a lot of the time
Like because you talk to a young child though. They might divert their eyes. They might fidget. They might be incoherent
They look they look like they look like they're hiding something and that's so adults think they're lying when they may will not be so yeah
I think I look permanently guilty. It makes me a bad liar, but it also makes me a really bad truth teller
That's the problem because I look like I'm lying whatever so any lie I tell I'm gonna get cortex
I look like I'm lying and any time I tell the truth. No one believes me because I look like I'm lying
It's very difficult. That's why I have to have the computer in front of me on point this
One of the reasons that we have X as the X man and their
X-ray and stuff like that is because day car
Used X to mean an unknown in algebra. Yeah, wasn't it?
He decided to use X Y and Z and the story goes that the reason he did it is because the printer
Who was doing his books and I got loads of X's Y's and Z's left over because no words have
So I might as well use them
But it turns out that because he's French actually X is quite a common
Relatively common in French and it might have been because they just had lots of X's because X is quite common
But yeah, but without those without day car. We might not have the X man
We might have the a man or the other be man or whatever. Oh, wow. We wouldn't have the seaman
Probably not
So I was I was looking into things that are named after people and I was thinking I was reasoning that there must be something
Which is the most famous thing that people don't know is named after a person
So we've said before like shrapnel is named after a bloke who was called general Henry shrapnel
I think I said the nachos were named after a guy called
So we've done a few of these before and I the cardigan do people know it was named after the seventh Earl of cardigan
Okay, that is known because I read an article claiming that he was wearing one while he led the charge of the library cage
I thought that can't that can't be right there would have been a uniform because it feels too. Yeah, yeah
Well, like pushing his merch during war
Yeah, I mean, yeah, it is named after him, but yeah, I think and it was during the Battle of Balaclava
That's the thing that we don't know
Yeah, and then cravat go back to croats because croats were those yeah, and
Slaves were sloths. I mean, that's not quite eponyms
It's the kind of toponyms but and and I'm really sorry to always lower the tone
But I don't know that bugger is actually a riff on Bulgarian because there were these Bulgarian sects in the 11th
Sects in the 11th century there was supposed to get up to strange sex. So that's where bugger
Yeah, that's kind of topping in there wasn't it really not an eponym
Strictly speaking
In 1996 the Swedish Navy admitted that they had found a huge amount of evidence of Russian submarines operating in their waters
Right really serious, you know post-Cold War threatening security environment
And there had been six thousand incidents a huge number reported from 1981 to 1994
It turns out that what they had been hearing was largely
Otters splashing
Playful otters splashing in the water
There about one in a thousand claims would was likely to be a submarine and the rest was just random
They found out that it was farting fish as well, didn't they? Yeah, they communicate by farting
In fact, we have this fact so qi, which is herring communicate by farting
Yes, and we tweet it about once a year just so that everyone tweets Richard herring to go
Oh, I didn't know you
He hates us
I couldn't imagine so the thing I want to mention about protests is to do with another quiz show which is mastermind
And the first question ever was about protests and it was about a painting by Picasso
Which was a protest about the bombing by Spanish planes on a village and the question was
What year when the event took place was the inspiration for the painting?
The answer was 1937
The answer was 1937, but the question was about German planes not Spain
So the first ever question on mastermind was incorrect
Yeah
So how shit is mastermind
I just I just feel like it's qi and countdown on stage together. Let's shit on someone
What do you reckon soothe this shit? Yeah, let's get some headlines. That's it. Yes. Wait
Oh, I don't want to diss any other shit. Yeah, that was vicious. Um
Just on religion while we're there, um, there's been a few naked religions in the past
So the adomites
They were a sect in north Africa in the second third and fourth centuries
That used always worn no clothes during the religious ceremonies
The idea being that they were going back to the Garden of Eden before we had clothes
And this was the best way to get close to God
Now it became big again in the Czech Republic in Czechia in 14th century
And people who were adomites then would go naked through the towns and villages
So they would everyone take their clothes off and they would go through the town saying come and join our gang
You know, we're the we're the closest to Jesus. Conga basically you're describing a naked conga
Sure. Let's call it a naked. Well, they did do a lot of naked dances
They would have a fire and they would do naked dances around it and the idea was
That they rejected a lot of the things in the catholic church and a lot of people think that they were like the precursors to the Protestant revolution
So it was like, you know, they was with the first people really to kind of go against the church
And then it kind of built up and built up in central europe
But it carried all of the Cromwell trimmed a lot of that stuff away. Didn't he before it came up with puritanism
Yeah, sorry and then it carried on and in the early us
They had some adomites there and I was reading about one clergyman who was writing about them and he said um
About these people who were in church and were naked the whole time
If the planets of venus reigned in their lower parts making them swell for pride or rather for lust
Then the clerk with his long stick shall strike down the presumptuous flesh
So basically
If you yeah, you would yeah
And he said that on one occasion there was a woman who made a congregation member
Rise in such an unmeasurable manner that the old clerk was forced to use both hands to elate his courage
At which the prophesizer was in such pain that the whole house could not hold him and he said he would kill the clerk
And basically this guy just started whacking his genitals with his stick
He attacked that guy and basically they only just stopped him from killing the clerk
But this guy said he wasn't bothered because it was in church. God will look after him and it didn't matter if he killed the clerk
Because it was naked. It would all be fine
It feels like we feels like pants is just easier, isn't it?
So burrowing owls they have lots of piles of poo outside the nest and it's cow dung and bison dung and all of this
And then they just stand by the poo
And wait they just go into kind of sentry position and just stand there looking very still
And what scientists reckon is that they're fishing for dung beetles
Oh freshish dung and dung beetles are really interested in burrowing owls love eating the the dung beetles
And so they'll just stand and wait and let the dung beetles approach. Isn't that crazy? They're basically they're basically fishing
Like they're land fishing. Yeah. No, I got it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah
I try to find a uh, if there was another naughty barbie, you know
Kind of like the origins of barbie being a cool girl and I managed to find one which was the pole dancing barbie
This was a one-off because it was part of a thing in japan called hebo con which was you know, like robot wars
This was anti robot wars. This was a robot wars where everyone's specific negotiations. No, no
You you have to summit
robot model un
You had to bring a very bad robot basically it had to be terrible and so
The worse it was the better you got in the competition
Okay, you were so there were 31 entrants and barbie doll that was entered was a attacking
Through pole dancing barbie, but the other ones that it went up. How did she attack you with a pole dance?
Did she spin round and kick you in the head?
I think so because I couldn't find any photos because this was in 2013 and I think
So
No, so I but it's you know was a small thing that happened in japan the winner was a robot that was so sturdy
That no one could knock it over so it just stood so the other things walked into it
Okay, that's the best one was the uh the person who got a special acknowledgement
Was one person a lady who accidentally left her robot on the train and then just went for a beer instead
And they were like that level of shitness is so great. We want to
Commend you with a special honor there. That's awesome
But yeah pole dancing barbie the only one time in a anti robot war japanese competition hebo con very cool
Yeah, there is a thing called the bubble babba challenge. This is at the voxki river in russia
So it's near st. Petersburg. Uh, and it's a race
a
Kind of a rafting race, but instead of a raft you have a sex doll
Uh, it began in 2003
Anyone's allowed to enter but you have to have a compulsory alcohol test before you start
Oh, yeah, we don't want to we don't want to make this seem tawdry or unprofessional
And in 2006
That guy riding the sex doll down the river's had a shandy
The most exciting of the bubble babba challenge
Sex doll races was in 2006
So all the races jumped into the water
And there was a really really strong wind and that meant that almost all the sex dolls blew away
And so you've just got all these rushing mostly guys in the water just sort of without their sex dolls
And there was only one person the guy called osipov who reached the finish line
But he was disqualified
Because the jury had noticed signs of recent sexual activity on the doll
Which was very much banned
I've got another but we've got another barbie thing. Okay. Yeah barbie has uh, officially
Not part of any political party, right? So there's a
Various reasons for that. She's been a presidential candidate every election since 1992
Uh, much like hillary clinton
Um, not fair. Um, but she got in a she got in a beef with donald j trump bar barbie and donald j trump had a had a
Beef at the last election. Um, because donald j trump tweeted. There's a thing called voter barbie. And it's doing courage
What do you keep saying j in his name?
Oh, sorry. That's his junior. I'm talking about donald trump jr. Okay. I believe. Yeah. Yeah, okay. Can't be the senior
I mean, they're both such they're both such different. Yes
Well, I don't know who I don't know which of them said this. I think it was jr. But basically one of the trumps
Uh tweeted voter barbie must be a democrat because she's already wearing an i voted sticker
And yet she's got another ballot in her hand
And matel had to reply barbie is not and never has been affiliated with a political party
To an official statement saying she's not a democrat. Yeah. Yeah. Wow. I think she is though clearly clearly
Can I tell you one more dueling method that happened? Yeah
So basically the you know the thing about you turn back to back and then you walk and then you there are various different methods in different
Countries walk ten paces turn around shoot. Sorry. Yes. So the back. That's french basically
Um, and there is a much more fun variant which has another french name. It's called avalante
You face each other. Can we do the fun duel?
There was people really relished it, you know, a certain kind of person really seemed to enjoy it
So there's a variant called avalante where you face each other, right and you start walking towards each other
You can either of you can fire whenever you like but if you miss
You have to stand still and wait for the other
Guy to shoot right. I know and that feels tense
I thought you were going to say that you're standing right in front of each other and then you walk backwards away from each other
And then you're just hoping someone's not kneeling down behind you
That's amazing really
It used to be in the Olympics, didn't it pistol dueling? Yeah, 1906
It was one of the categories. It wasn't a medal one, but you would you would
So it was it was a thing that was done there because the winner would be dead. Yeah
Just pick him up. I'm gonna put a silver medal on
But that would be the there was like an intercalary games wasn't there in 1906
It wasn't the main game and they used wax bullets and the idea was you would just see who got hit first
And you had the sort of glass plate that was over your face and but it was done as a proper thing with spectators around and everything
Yeah, it was very exciting
Have we said before that I think nasa found the oldest known rock
The oldest known earth rock was on the moon and then brought back to earth. Yes
It was called big bertha was the name of the rock
Was it yeah, it was yeah, they named it after a I think a gun from the first world war
So they brought that back and it was the first earth meteorite ever found on another body as in the first
Like meteor out if you like, you know the first like bit of earth that it hit somewhere else
Wasn't that the moon created when uh an asteroid hit the earth and there's a little splash. So they say so they say yeah
No, I'm not sure I buy it. Yeah
Pixar didn't happen. There's actually a strong theory that it is hollow
So, uh
Is this the moon cave theory
Oh, yeah, I haven't heard it called that before but yeah, I suppose. Yeah, because supposedly when you hit it, it rings like a bell
So is it artificial? Is it real? Listen, you mean when a meteorite hits a knife? You just go
No, when they did drilling on the moon they they they specifically tried to find out because you can do
You can do well
You can do seismic tests on the moon to see what the composure is on the inside right and it was completely empty apparently and so
I'm joking. Hannah. I'm joking. I promise. Thank you. Yeah. Yeah. Thank you. Have you ever been in a diamond mine in your adventures, Hannah?
No, I haven't. I wonder what that's like. Hmm
I see we've run out of facts and entered speculation territory
God
And you've mentioned oscar the hypno dog before on the podcast. Can you remember what that was oscar the hypno dog was a
Labrador who was a hypnot who was hypnotically trained
And went and like went missing and there were signs put up all over the country saying do not look at this talk
Is that it? That's it. Yeah. Yeah. Basically
He's dangerous
We have mentioned that but what I'd never heard before was about puffy the hypno cat
Amazing. Uh puffy the hypno cat was in the 1940s in america
There was a guy who owned a bar and he said that puffy was sitting on the end of a nightclub bar
And a couple of girls came up to him and I didn't really pay attention what happened
But suddenly a girl was simply out on her feet. She simply wasn't from drinking
I'm something of a hypnotist myself
And I realized she was in a hypnotic trance and it turned out that this cat had been hypnotizing people
in this guy's bar
And he started then training the cats to stare at people really really fixedly to try and hypnotize them
And puffy became really really famous and in 1945 the american feline society called her the king of all cats
Um because she was bringing in money for war bonds
So you would go into the bar and you would pay some money to be hypnotized by the cat
And then you know, they get the money for the war
And by the end of her life, she was credited with hypnotizing over 300 people
Always for benign purposes. I just well I spent all my money on tinned tuner
It's so weird
Just left it open around the place probably probably nothing
And you Hannah you're such a skeptic you probably don't even believe that story's true
Actually that one I'm really behind
One of us on this panel might be slightly harder to hypnotize than the other three. Oh, okay, can we guess it?
um
Is it done because of his dubious questioning techniques? It's not done because of his dubious questioning techniques
I feel like Hannah with her skepticism. It's not Hannah with her dubious skepticism thing
Is it Andy with his lack of ability to talk to people at parties? It's not me
James for being so fucking judgmental about the other three people on the panel
It's james, but not for that reason not for that reason it's because so james you have aphantasia, right? Oh, right, okay
James can't you say what it is? I just can't picture things in my head can't picture things in your head
Yeah, and that might make it harder to hypnotize you. It's there was a well
This is from the uk hypnosis convention, which sounds amazing last year's events included recreational erotic hypnosis
Uh, and aphantasia. What is it and why should we even care slightly?
Slightly barbed
I don't know much time we got I got very deep in the weeds on people who want to be heroes and do bad stuff
Oh, yeah, yeah, go for it. Uh, have you heard of the hero complex? No. No, so it's not quite a psychological disorder
It's not in the diagnostic manuals, but it's like talked about by psychologists
It's a thing where it's sometimes known as a vanity crime where people are desperate to be the hero
So they'll do something bad so they can then rescue people
Like I'd mug you but then beat myself up. Yeah, exactly
Exactly that and hand yourself in I guess is the idea. Yeah, yeah, yeah, but I rough myself up a bit first
Why stop that a bit of a lifetime?
But like there's there's quite a lot of case studies the really famous one's 1984 an la pd
police officer called jimmy wade pierce and heroically discovered and diffused a pipe bomb
On an airport bus carrying the turkish olympic team in la
And people saw him running down like the airport holding a pipe bomb dismantling and throwing over his shoulder and shouting get out
You know like proper like bruce willis stuff and it turned out he had planted it there
Because he wanted to be the hero because he wanted to transfer into a different department and his boss hated him
And he thought the only way i'm getting out is if I get a commendation
And he failed the polygraph and he ended up with 1500 hours of community service and it became a bit of a thing
But everyone was like all right well no one was hurt fair enough, but then there's some really bad ones
So there's a thing called firefighter arson, which is a serious problem. Yeah, you heard of this. Yeah, yeah, yeah
There are a hundred firefighters every year arrested for arson
In america alone. There's a million firefighters. So it's a tiny statistic, but a hundred people
Most of them are young men age 16 to 30. I read a whole report issued in 2003 by the u.s. government's national fire administration
I got very deep
There are six primary motives excitement
Vandalism revenge profit political terrorism hiding evidence of a crime
And it's a really big problem for a small subset
And there's a guy who's a tenancy fire chief. He's set fire to his own fire station
Wow, he caused the three-quarters of a million dollars of damage and when released he then set fire to a car dealership
And he did it for the sexual thrill. This is why we need pawn hub
Yeah sexual sexual thrill he gay got off on the uniting the worst ones john or
He was from glendale fire service in california in 1991 was found to have planned eight arson attacks on shops
And was suspected of many more. He killed four people in these fires. It's really really horrible
His main job at the glendale service
Chief arson investigator
Wow
Hover story and so they tailed him for months and every time there was a fire investigating conference
There would be fires in the local area
And he was possibly alleged to have set 2000 fires
Making the most prolific american arsonist
Unrecord but one of the clues that they detected about him is that he had written a novel about a fireman who sets fires
It's like a serious thing and
I'm so sorry to get stuck on this, but I then watched fireman sam with my four-year-old dog
So, yeah, and I went does he do that? Hang on a second for sexual thrills. No
I work for cbbs. I don't want to get cancelled
But like I realized fireman sam he he's in charge of a tiny tiny village called ponty pandy
But he's got a fire truck a rescue tender a four-wheel drive suv within built animal rescuing crane
A quad bike an amphibious vehicle a hovercraft two helicopters and a mobile command center
This guy is playing the game like he's clearly set fires that get like a huge budget
Um, can I just say one thing about george banard short very quickly? Yeah, he he had you I'm saying it wrong am I? No
Like bernard is also in there. It's gay org. Yeah. Yeah
I've never heard it, but like george bernard. Yeah, oh george bernard. Sure. Yeah. Yeah. Okay, george. I'm cool. Whatever. Hey, it's all cool here
It's late night at the soho. Yeah, picking each other up on pronouncing. I'm gonna go home going god
There was this mad fucking fight about how to pronounce bernard. Oh man. You got to see fish live. Sorry. I'm sorry
Um, no, so, um, he used to have a riding shed which was amazing
He used to he lived in heritford sure and he had a riding shed which was basically on a lazy susan
He liked to chase the sun
So he would get in the sun would be beaming right in which was a big thing for him because he had specific glass
Which is in the shed windows that kind of beamed concentrated light in a way that it was meant to be healthy
It was thought to be a healthy. It was always on fire, wasn't it?
Bernhardt
Tell you a bit about milk floats. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah for one thing milk doesn't float
Oh, that's yeah
If it's food for thorns, isn't it? Yeah left on water. It will sink. So, um
Oh, but no, but if you mix it
It's oh if you mix it if you mix it. Yeah, that's yeah, that's not that wasn't the terms
I was anyway at the point milk floats to all UK has an FAQ page and it's one of the like it's a very it's a
Gorgeous website milk floats dot org dot uk. I cannot recommend it enough and the FAQ page begins
All right, maybe they are not exactly frequently asked, but
They might be the kind of questions people might ask given the opportunity
It's so nice. It's so good
Yeah, uh, you want to do a quick game of is it bigger in europe or america? Oh, yes, I do
Okay, what year?
2023. Oh, wow. Okay. So where would you find the world's biggest dump truck?
dump truck
USA america
That's that's a mark of pride. I'm afraid not it's in belleras in europe really
Yeah, the bell has 757 at 10 which can move the equivalent of 1000 whale testicles in one go
That's that's my comparison. That's not the advertising
That's how you measure trucks
I think we all know that
The world's largest log jam
So that's when you have a load of logs in a river and they get stuck and so where is it? Europe or america?
Oh america. Well, I was tricked last time. So I'll I'll say Europe this time. Well, you've been tricked again, andy
It's in none of us in canada
And the interesting thing about that is that it's about 20 square miles of log jam and it goes deep as well
And the logs store enough carbon to run 2.5 million cars for a year. Wow
That's interesting. Sorry. Is that a
Is a genuine question. Is that logs that have been cut by humans? No
It's they usually are like knocked down by wind and stuff like that and they fall into the river and they go down the river
And then there's like a little sort of point where they can't get out and then they just jam and jam and jam and jam
And it's a really good way of hiding carbon
And then finally the world's biggest barometer. Europe or america. Europe. I think I own I think I have that in my home
You've got a massive barometer andy. Yeah
Don't boast
It's a famous barometer. Is it? Oh god
It's one you see every day on tv on tv every day. Is there a barometer connected to big ben?
It's good. If there is I don't know about it. It's a clock, but secretly also a barometer. Oh, wow
But it is in europe. Uh, it is in europe. It is on shepherds bush roundabout
Uh, it's uh, oh, yes, we all tune it. Sorry. We all tune in every morning for five minutes
Just watch the live feed of shepherds bush roundabout
Let me get on with our day, don't we? You know
There's check what the pressure's like
What it's um, no, it's it's a huge barometer. It was built as a barometer. It no longer works as a barometer
It's currently covering up a big pipe
By um, london water, but it that building was what inspired the score column in the tv show pointless
Inspired by the world's biggest barometer
These are easy i'm surprised you haven't got any of these
Yeah, yeah, to barometers. Do they do they go up or down? I can't remember now turns which way you hold them
Yeah, okay, but they can go upright and what the weather's doing. Yeah. Yeah, it's just weird because when you said big ben
I suddenly had this image of the the um
The mercury going up in a barometer, right and it suddenly because I was at a fair the other week and my son did that strongman thing
Where you hit it has to hit the bell
Do you think there's anyone strong enough in the world that if that thing had to hit the bell of big ben that they could hit it hard enough?
No, so let's move on
One thing I do know about it is that um, there's a lot of rhesus stuff in there, right? Oh rhesus pieces
Rhesus pieces which is like an american candy, but it was huge for them
So the sales went up like 65 percent the next week just after it been in this movie
And the interesting thing about that is that they weren't the first choice if you look at the original scripts
All of the bits where it says rhesus pieces it was originally going to be m&m's
But apparently marz turned it down because they didn't want to be associated with aliens
They're called marz
I
I've got some stuff on dropping things from parachutes
Okay, this is about a place called franz star ranch and brothel in navada and i'm in
They had an idea of a an advertising campaign
Where they will put a mattress in the middle of an airfield
And if anyone could parachute to land on the mattress
Then they would have a chance to spend the evening with any of the women in the brothel
It didn't go very well
The problem was that all the women would stand near to the
Near to the place where people had to land right and the guy flying the airplane
Not that high could see everything that was happening and got completely distracted
There was also some sidewinds and
Long story short he crashed the plane
No
Everyone was fine. Oh no one died and the great
Great moral of the story in the end is the crash plane was so good for business
That they decided to leave it there and it's still there in navada if you ever see that crash plane next to the brothel
Is the what are you looking at me?
I've never been to navada
Well now I think you have
Wow, isn't that an amazing idea for advertising? Yeah. Yeah, it's an amazing idea. Sorry
How low was the plane when he got distracted? It was quite low, but high enough the parachutes would work
Yeah, so that's quite high for a pilot to be like
It's just like a little stick woman on the ground. Exactly check out the I think arms
On her maybe arms
No, it's a tree. That's a tree. Okay. Yeah, that's okay
Do you know that john major and tina turner were born on the same day?
Why?
Yeah, really that's cool. Yeah, if my memory is I didn't actually write that. Wow, that's not memory. That's not memory. Yeah
Wow, I once you hear that you're gonna forget that now hurry
You know everyone who was born on the same day as john major
classic Andy
In february 2020. Yeah, there was a poll by the center of public opinion
This is in the united states. It was ahead of the primary in new hampshire
And they asked a load of voters what they would rather and they found that 64 percent of democrats would rather see a giant meteor strike the earth
extinguishing all human life than see president trump reelected
You know, um, there's been a sequel to phantom of the opera andrew Lloyd Webber's phantom the opera. Okay. Um
Yeah, it was it was written by ben elton and it was music by
Andrew Lloyd Webber, but it was delayed for months in the writing process because of cats
The musical
His real-life cat he had a kitten who stood on his digital piano and wiped out all the music that he had done
In the writing of it, which just feels god bless that kitten
There was a group of secret operatives from britain called the choir boys
And they came up with a plan during world war two to drive hitler mad by eardropping huge amounts of pornography into his compound
Oh, wow
In the end they kind of slightly, you know, they came up with the idea
They started going for and they thought, you know, this is just stupid
And so they called off the whole whole idea
But not before and i quote the group had amassed an enormous collection of suitable material
Oh, I made an invention once talking of cars and weeing. Um
Wow, that is a hell of a vending diagram there. I don't think it's it's the it I've forgotten the name. It's a really good name
But basically you can piss and drive
Okay, it was all in the name, which I can't remember my great invention
Oh, yeah, what's wrong with the piss and drive?
It's not as romantic. No, let's see. Let's see. So it's the idea that you just you don't have to stop off
Yeah, if you can't um like I can't start my car a lot of the time
So it's annoying having to stop. It's brand new as well. It's an electrical fault. I think anyway, um
So I don't want to stop in case I can't start it again. So many people would get the electrical fault mended
But I I prefer what you've done engineering system where you never
Does the urine get utilized? I'm thinking screen wash. Oh, yeah, that would work. Well, what it's just what it's mostly water
I'm wondering if it's you pissing all over your electric. So there's stopping the car from functioning
to begin with
In norway if you are a fish
Um factory and you're kind of getting the whole the fillets out
What you'll do is you get the rest of the fish and you'll throw it away into a little area with all the heads and stuff like that
In that area children are allowed to go in and they cut out the little tongs of the cods
And they sell them for extra pocket money
And this is a really common thing in a place called lofferton
Um and from about six years until 17 you'll get loads of kids who'll just go in
Grab the fish and they'll cut out this little tongue in the back and apparently it's the tastiest part
And do you think they turn out to be psychopath like serial killers and psychopaths?
Yeah, unfortunately in that area there is a lot of debt. No, there isn't
Um, do you want to know some other things that people are scared of singers?
Yeah, sure. Yeah, I wrote some dance. I thought I'd do some work after you told me I was getting paid
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, I forgot to tell you that until yeah quite late in the day
Um, but thank you for bringing your one sheet of uh
It wasn't very much i'm getting paid so it is just fitting. Um, wait till you hear them
Adele is scared of seagulls. Who would have thought?
Oh, no, yeah, yeah, um, there's more
Rihanna's scared of fish
Okay, and Kylie Minogue is scared of coat hangers
She's scared of coat hangers. Yeah, Kylie Minogue and i'm scared of commitment
So we're all different aren't we how many different types of wrestling do you think there are in iceland one type of wrestling?
Unlucky, there are two types of wrestling, but they do have the same name so I can see why you got that
That's what I was thinking. Um, it's called glimmer and basically there's two types and they're quite similar
But one of them is a type of wrestling that you would do as a viking
If you came home after a long day doing whatever vikings do and you wanted to warm yourself up
They would just do some wrestling
Nice who with with another viking
It's wholesome right? Yeah, there was another one which was the dueling version
And it was quite similar, but it would take place in a field with a large flat stone known as the slaying slab
And that one you would try and slam your opponent onto the slab and break their back
Wow, and the amazing thing about this is they were going to have it in the 1912 stock home olympics
I think probably the first version not the second one and then the war happened and so the olympics got postponed
And in 1920 they were going to do it anyway, you know, they've decided okay
We'll keep all the same sports
But iceland decided that it only had a certain number of wrestlers
And it needed them to impress the king of demarc who was visiting at the same time as the olympic games
And so they decided we're not going to do this wrestling after all
We just want to
Impress the king of demarc
So it never became a worldwide sport that it might have done otherwise
And then in the end the king never came
There was a
Shanti not shanti but seesong when you were getting your grog
So you would get your the amount of alcohol you were allowed each day
They would give it you and they would sing while they were doing it and it was a song called Nancy Dawson
And it's the tune that we now know as here we go around the mulberry bush
But it was all about Nancy Dawson who was a stage sort of performer an actress possibly a prostitute
And the i'm not going to say what the words are to the navy song about her but they are
Are they rude they are very rude. I think they say sex worker now dear
Um, they're meant to be quite easy, weren't they because you couldn't like not a sex worker
No, no
I meant the songs to sing
Um, because like some people can't sing names of registered competitive roller derby players include
skate bush
venus thigh trap
And weird al spankabitch
I sort of thought what's like the rudest name that you can get to so I looked up the c-u-n-t word
And I was heading down that way, but on the way I discovered the c-l-i-t word
And again, do you know how to say that?
Go on go on Dan give us one clite, um
Okay, well in the c-l-i-t, uh, you've got uh catastrophe. Oh, yeah, please welcome to the ring clitosaurus rex
Clitler is about to enter the ring
And who's this coming up there a clitty clitty bang bang
That's really good
Oh
You
(upbeat music)