[phone ringing]
[indistinct chatter]
[music playing]
Hi, Andy.
Hi, guys.
We're all wearing coloured shirts today.
Finally, my memos have been listening to you.
[laughing]
Filming it has just changed us.
Honestly, it was the last shirt I had available.
Oh, okay.
Tomorrow, for me.
I'm down to three shirts because I jokingly sort of said.
Yeah, because I said I'm going to throw out my entire wardrobe and start again.
And Finella took that seriously.
And I came home a few days ago.
It was all over the lawn.
[laughing]
Did you cut through your ties as well?
It's something we're just happening.
Yeah.
Anyway, I'm staying down the road.
But it's down with that bitch.
[laughing]
Oh, my God.
Welcome to drop us in.
[laughing]
Welcome to drop us a line.
Our audience feedback show.
We've been receiving your emails.
And now we're going to give them back to you.
I've completely forgotten how to introduce this show.
This is the quickest time to cry.
Absolutely.
That you've achieved on this show.
No time to cry more.
Yeah, I cry with laughter in every episode.
If you're watching at home, you'll notice we've been able to see me crying with laughter.
So, apologies about that.
But now I've got it out of the way.
I'm sure it won't happen again.
Yeah.
We'll not be funny again.
Absolutely.
So, thank you so much for all your emails.
To podcast@QI.com.
The inbox is bulging.
And it's been a terrific fortnight in the inbox.
We've had some good stuff.
Great, great.
Yeah. Should we twoparl it?
Let's get in. Let's do it.
All right.
Andres Kut says,
"As an Estonian,
it's already going international.
Really exciting.
I was appalled by your blatant discussion of sounders
in episode 609.
Oh.
I'd imagine people in Finland throwing literal fits.
What was the context?
Pissing on the stones.
Okay, so this is Amy Gladhill.
Yep.
Came on the show.
And she said that on a sauna,
I think in Leeds,
there was a side saying,
"Do not piss on the coals."
Yes.
Yep.
Well, Andres says,
"Peeing on the stones,
brackets not the coals,
is one of the most awful things you could do in a sauna."
I think that's the point we were trying to get.
Yeah, we weren't saying it was a good idea.
Yeah.
I hope not.
I hope like everyone who listens to the show hasn't got away
and peed on the coals.
The only reason it's not a proverb is that it's too disgusting
of a thought to propagate.
It is by no means harmless.
The stench is awful
and you pretty much need to replace the stones.
Once it sets in the wood,
you kind of need to rep the whole thing down.
Oh, dear.
So, this is someone who's experienced.
Yeah, it feels like we've opened up something.
Yeah, absolutely.
So, I'm really sorry, Andres.
Thank you very much for telling us.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
No, absolutely.
Big sauna culture, isn't it?
It is.
Yeah, but he's from Estonia.
And I know Estonia and it has a synchia basically
a 200 yards away from each other,
but they're still there.
Estonia threw away, aren't they?
Brilliant.
Wow.
applause.
Let's stop the show.
See you next time.
Why?
There is short boat ride away from each other.
It's nice.
Yeah.
Okay. Brilliant.
Cool.
That's true.
Anyway, thank you, Andres.
Sorry to everyone in that region.
Let's keep going.
Hannah Bevan writes.
If you are actually choking,
it is an emergency.
Don't faff around calling 111.
This is a lighthearted comment I made
off the back of my suggestion
to yell into someone's mouth.
That's right.
Come out bone.
If you are a bone.
Yeah.
But good news from Hannah.
A fish bone in your esophagus is not choking.
Choking is an obstruction of the airway
and is an immediate threat to life.
Okay.
So you can't get oxygen.
So that's when you do the abdominal
or the heimlich and all of that.
If you can talk on the phone you want choking,
but if you have a stuckfish fish bone,
yes, see a doctor.
Okay.
I think don't come to us for medical advice.
Yeah.
Look just generally speaking.
I think that I would say the only piece
of medical advice that we've ever given
that is really solid.
If you have hiccups,
put your finger up your bum.
That's really the only one I stand by.
That's why I was a terrible GP.
You really got through those disposable gloves, don't you?
Drew Eustent.
Disposable.
Brilliant.
We've had word of,
I would say the fish messiah being born.
Right.
This is so exciting.
Okay.
What's that mean?
Well, James, you know how you're good
at dishing out harkinings and checking facts.
And you know, you're, I'd say,
the sort of most pure facty.
I hesitate to say so after I messed it up last time.
But yeah.
I do like to beautifully pick up people.
Well, there is another.
A child has been born.
Who I think might be the next generation.
Fish the next generation.
Okay.
It's my daughter.
It's not.
Literally as we were walking home the other day,
she was like, Danny, did you know that the moon is not a planet?
I was like, yeah, I did know that.
Did you know that the sun is not a planet?
Like, she's just got this, did you know?
I think going.
That's great.
I didn't think so.
It seems likely.
She's going to have a rough time growing up saying,
did you know to you?
Because you'll say every time, yes.
You won't, you won't, you won buckle.
Yeah, you won't.
Actually, when she said, did you know that the moon is not a planet?
I should have said, oh, really?
I was supposed to like, yeah.
Obviously I did.
That's a moon.
Don't ever bring these matters to me again.
Well, Aislin Fellow's rights.
I thought you may enjoy the attached PowerPoint presentation created
by my eight-year-old daughter, Cersha, for her teacher.
On the first day of their new topic, Vikings,
the teacher relayed the usual chat of Viking helmets having horns.
Oh, wow.
My daughter attempted to correct her.
The whole class and the teacher basically told her she was wrong.
She refused to let this stand.
And she put together an entire PowerPoint explaining that, no,
the teacher was wrong about this.
She sent it over.
It's a great PowerPoint.
I'll share a slide on the screen if Aislin doesn't mind.
We did ask her to remove the original last line of,
and this is why you're wrong.
So, she's been forced to wear helmets
with horns for a school assembly,
but she plans to display the helmet in her room with a plaque
describing that it's inaccurate.
So, you know, this is...
I know.
I mean, was that...
Would you have done something like that, do you think?
I don't think so.
Right.
Obviously, yes.
Anyway, congratulations, Aislin.
Lovely.
Very great stuff.
Yeah.
Wonderful.
Here's a little fact about us.
We've had a bit of audience research done,
which I really like.
Scott McKellen from St. Louis, Missouri,
has studied a sample of a hundred of our episodes.
Well, it's quite a big sample.
Yeah.
Notice of things that first shares an average of one sex fact
in 31% of episodes.
Brackets list-attached.
That's fewer than I would have thought.
I agree.
He's not counting penis mentions.
Presumably.
Arguably.
Arguably, that should be mentioned.
Yeah.
I presume that would just make it a hundred percent.
And it becomes an uninteresting study.
What period in our life are we talking about here?
The last 100.
The last 100 most recent.
My criteria was this is talking about a sexual position
or a breathing behavior.
But if I included every time a reproductive system was mentioned,
it would have topped 50%.
And there's a list of all the species we've talked about here.
A lot of them are water-based.
Orca, starfish.
Crocodiles.
And a fish.
Orpus.
Barnacles.
Good point.
Humans have come up a few times.
So to speak.
Wow.
The rough periwinkle snail.
Yeah.
If only we could tell it.
It had arrived in a list like this.
It only had the intelligence to understand.
Made it.
Made it, mum.
You're on a list with the Northern Giant mouse lemur.
Yeah.
Is there a conclusion about our interest?
Or is it just purely data?
It's purely data.
Yeah.
I always think if I go on mastermind and had a specialist subject,
animal sex would be right up there.
That's a good.
That's a good idea.
I feel like there's not much about animal sex
that I haven't come across over the years.
Other words better when you're on mastermind.
I've started self-finished.
And there we go.
That's why we'll keep this email in.
Brilliant.
Right.
We come to our radio climb of the week.
Okay.
But it's a really positive one actually this time.
We've had a lot of emails about climbing from climbers.
Oh, Alex Honald was our fact.
Let me guess because I've had quite a lot of people arguing
that he doesn't wear sticky shoes.
He wears climbing shoes.
Which I have to say I did know I was doing a bet.
Right.
I was saying that he wears sticky shoes.
I actually didn't know that climbers wore sticky shoes
until I researched it.
How sticky?
It's really interesting.
It's just like it's a kind of rubber,
which is particularly good at adhering surfaces.
It's not, it's got a very high coefficient of friction.
That's really interesting.
It doesn't leave a trail behind him.
It's not like a snail.
That's why I got alcapitan.
Okay.
Yeah, I got quite a lot of that on my own social medias.
We do.
We haven't had much of that.
You'll be relieved to hear it.
Because one or two did.
But Mike Robinson says there's a frozen waterfall in London
that you can ice climb.
Oh, wow.
What?
It's like I've been coven garden.
Yeah.
Not that mountain sharp that's near our old office.
I think it's the north face.
Because I've been upstairs and downstairs there.
And I don't.
I didn't see it.
No, there's a climbing place.
And they've got a frozen waterfall.
In coven garden.
I looked it up.
That's what it's seeing like.
Wow.
I know.
But there's no mention of where it is in this email.
He included a link, which I clicked.
Yeah.
How deep into the weasel we want to get on this one.
I think we're asking a basic question.
Where in coven garden is it?
Do you want me to Google it now?
We could do it after we could do it after.
We've got all day.
Yeah.
It's your own time.
You're wasted.
Or right in if you know where it is.
It's podcast at qi.com.
You can't hang that over my head.
You can't recognize this.
We can't weaponize this at all.
Okay.
Right.
Andrew says.
Just Andrew.
Do you want to guess what the screaming bar fees are when you're doing ice climbing?
He's an avid rock ice climber in western Canada.
We're such an international show.
Very cool.
Screaming the screaming bar fees.
It must be something to do with on it.
Oh, yeah.
Like bar.
Yeah.
It's something that makes you throw up when you're doing an ice climb.
Is it something to do with your ears not working?
So you get off balance.
So I was thinking like a wind, a type of wind that comes in through a crack.
I can't relay it around your head.
Quite.
I'll tell you what it is.
During a long cold climb, if you grip your ice axes too tight, your hands can go a little numb.
But if you lower your hands and relax, the blood quickly rushes in too fast.
And the pain in your hands is such that people will start either screaming or on occasion throwing up.
All this while partway up a frozen waterfall.
In Copenhagen.
It was in Canada.
But yeah, I mean, it's stunning.
Like, amazing what people do for fun, isn't it?
I just don't think it's a massively good idea.
I think if I was in TLC, I'd be singing "Don't Go Climbing Waterfalls".
That's really good.
Frozen or not?
Yeah.
Lovely.
We might need to stand up and sing National Anthem now, because we're going to House of Lords Corner.
Okay.
Lord Borwick of Hawkeshead writes, "Speakers' Corner".
You could call it.
Very good.
Yeah.
We've heard from a Lord.
This is huge.
Okay.
There's a lot of the rats.
There's a ton of them these days, aren't there?
Yeah, there's several hundred.
Yeah.
Does the Lord...
Does the Lord listen to drop us a line?
He listens to fish.
Right.
You don't get this on parenting, are you?
No.
Well, do you know?
I don't.
And I bet it's really good.
It is.
You got a top podcast.
They are.
The top podcast.
Yeah.
That's great.
Look, Lord Borwick of Hawkeshead writes, "Yes.
In episode four of Little Fish, you mentioned Daniel McClies, the Irish painter, and his connection
with William Sykes and Charles Dickens, and they...
Sykes was a wrongman whose wife had an affair with Daniel McClies.
Yes, it was your up-to-date hot gossip, wasn't it?
And then he uses Sykes in Oliver Twist for Bill Sykes, and there was problems.
There's an alternate story as to why the two fell out, which I have heard.
So Lord Borwick is also providing hot gossip.
Yeah.
Which is that.
Sykes, the Lord, was responsible for deciding the pay of painters in the rebuilt houses of Parliament.
He couldn't agree the price with the painter, McClies, who painted the enormous 50 by 20 foot frescoes
in the royal gallery of the House of Lords.
So, Daniel, the painter, painted lady Sykes into both paintings.
Oh.
So the wife of the guy who's paying him.
Yeah, the wife of the wrongman here.
Yeah.
She appears in the Trafalgar painting next to a shot Admiral Nelson, and she appears in the Battle of Waterloo,
standing there with a glass of wine in both.
Wow.
Really?
So that's a good sort of sick burn on someone you could do.
Is it?
Put your wife in something?
Yeah.
I'm not sure why it's a sick burn.
It's quite cool to immortalize your wife.
Ah, anyway, so thank you, my Lord.
Oh, yeah.
I don't know if that's the correct term of, um, probably is.
Hmm.
Thank you, Lord B of Hawkshead.
Never been to Hawkshead?
Anyone know where it is?
No.
Me neither.
Ian Halliday writes, "Did you know that you can drive from Moscow to California in just one hour?"
[laughs]
Which Moscow?
With the one in Erscher.
[laughs]
And California near Falkirk, both in Scotland.
I haven't heard of either of those.
Well, school or California?
Yeah.
So I'm not sure why this is interesting.
[laughs]
You've heard the place in Scotland, though.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Brilliant.
Um, Cath Kastner says, "I'm an artist and long time listener of the show.
And I just had to write him because I was so surprised to hear you mention the sci-fi initiative of the French army."
Oh, yes.
I mentioned that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, they basically had, as far as I can remember, a unit of sci-fi authors who were brought in to predict future warfare, predict, come up with ideas.
And that was just to them, personally.
Yeah.
Good idea.
But yeah, I don't remember much about it more than that.
Lots of much sci-ops as sci-fi-ops.
Mmm, lovely.
Well, Cath just answers the question that we raised in the episode, but I don't think we answered.
It's still very much a thing.
How is it?
That's cool.
I've changed their name from red team to radar, but Cath has been working for them, illustrating a book.
No.
Yeah, I couldn't write in straightaway as I signed an NDA for bidding me to talk about the project before the book came out.
But she's free now to talk about it and tell us that it's still going.
Interesting that they name themselves after quite an old bit of technology.
Good point.
You think they'd name themselves after something that's coming in 30 years?
Yes.
Yeah, you're right.
Or do they know something?
Oh, yeah.
And we're going to be reduced back to old technology.
Oh, no.
That's like that Einstein quotes.
You know, we said, "I don't know what World War III will be fought with, but I know World War IV will be fought with sticks and stones."
Yeah.
It makes me think.
She didn't tell us what the book is though.
She's not allowed to tell us that.
I think the book is out, so she probably is allowed, but she just didn't.
Okay.
So we don't know what the book is.
You didn't Google it?
I didn't Google it.
Can you Google it now?
Yeah, of course.
Unless you know at home.
In which case, email podcast at qi.com.
I do like receiving all the emails, so it's actually not a threat, guys.
He said, "I like having my head put down the toilet, actually."
So jokes on you, guys.
Let's go on to Mike Giggler of the week.
Yeah.
Gerard Pethabridge.
An unbelievably good name.
Let's have a moment for Gerard Pethabridge.
Pethabridge is wonderful.
Gerard Pethabridge.
It's like it should be Lord Gerard of Pethabridge.
It does, doesn't it?
Anyway, congratulations, Gerard.
You're going to the Lords.
And Gerard writes, "In the most recent episode where the group called Lily Allen,
the modern-day Lord Byron."
Oh, yeah.
"In the section where you were rattling off similarities."
Famous father and all that.
Someone asked, "Does she have a club foot?"
I think it was you, wasn't it?
Yeah, and the answer is, "No, Cassavian had a club putt."
Brilliant.
Well, Gerard is here to tell you she does.
In 2024, Lily started selling feet picks on only fans.
And much like clubfishes for fish fans,
Lily's feet fans must surely be her club foot.
Yes.
Lovely.
Very good.
I didn't know that about her.
Brilliant.
I've got an extra diesel, by the way, about Lily Allen,
which is relevant to the show.
Yeah.
So, do you remember how much have you spent on Lily Allen foot picks?
Signed.
Please.
So, this is why you read the premier in.
I don't mind you throwing my clothes on the lawn,
but please, just a misspeck.
So, the album was co-written.
This is a friend of the podcast.
This is a new album that's just come out.
Right.
The album is co-written and co-produced by a producer called Blue May.
Okay.
Blue May is a friend of mine.
He lived here in London.
He loved fish.
Okay.
Do you remember I told a story once.
I think James, you might have been off,
but I told a story once about a sausage dog that has such large dangling testicles.
That when it walked down the stairs, they banged down the stairs.
That dog belonged to Blue May, the producer of Lily Allen's album.
Does she mention it in any of the songs?
I think they're quite self-biographical.
They are.
I don't think Dave, the sausage dog, was around anymore by the time Lily came onto the scene.
Wow.
Yeah.
So, the producer of Lily Allen's album is a friend of the podcast by his dog.
Wow.
Well, that's...
Sometimes you don't realise you're famous, like mega-famous.
And then you just hear something and you realise, wow, we've come a long way.
We know a book.
He's got a sausage dog with big balls.
It's called Dave.
But he also produced Lily Allen's new albums.
Yeah.
Did he use any of the dog-stairball noises in the album?
What do you think is a high heart?
Is actually...
Well, thank you for that.
That's really cool.
Yeah.
Max Dweck says, "I have one request if at all possible."
This is about...
Max has become a friend of the podcast on Patreon, where you get to sponsor a fact.
I'm quite touched by this, so I just thought I mentioned it.
I know I must be very far down on the custodian fact list.
I really am sorry.
We've had a rush.
We're going to get you all your facts as soon as we can.
Yeah.
That's totally great.
But it would truly be an honour when it is my turn.
Could you please assign me not a headline fact.
But one of Andy's most boring side facts.
Like me.
And make it more specific, please.
Like maybe model railways using coal for coal.
I love Andy's boring side facts.
Nice.
So, thank you, Max.
I just...
I'm really touched by that.
Yeah.
So some people like them.
It's all I'm trying to say.
Yeah.
One person.
Thank you, Max.
Oh, we like them as well.
We love them.
Thank you.
That's why you're here.
And luckily, there will be plenty of headline facts that fill that criteria from Andy.
So...
It's not just the side facts.
It's not the side facts.
Sorry, Max.
Okay.
Luke McNeil writes.
Uh-huh.
In a recent Listen to Call in Episode.
Oh, so this was a drop as a line.
It might have been last drop as a line, but one.
Okay.
Andy mentioned his idea for a movie about a Ragtag group of world record holders defeating
criminals or terrorists.
And the final climactic moments depend on the Guinness record keepers stopwatch ability.
Yes.
Right?
Cast your minds back.
We've had some titles in.
Oh, great.
Because don't know.
Was the first suggestion.
Yeah.
Hall of oddities or holers, something like that was another one.
Something.
I don't really remember this very well.
Well, it was about the Guinness.
I was about...
You've explained what it is, but.
Andy's dream led to a plot that we hashed out on the show.
I woke up with an idea for a major franchise.
Yeah.
Well, Luke McNeil has the title.
It's second hand heroes.
This works on so many levels.
For one, the heroes in question are not exactly who you would think of as heroes.
Also, second hand obviously refers to the second hand of the stopwatch.
Oh.
Okay, I think it's just those two levels.
It's a good title though.
Nice.
Whereas Troy Holland.
A very amazing two place name.
A person name.
Only one of the mechston.
Yeah, true.
Troy Holland says, "I think the movie should be called Try Hard."
Which is not to die hard.
Because it's the plot of die hard, which we're being upfront about.
Right.
I like it.
And also, most Guinness world record holders surely try hard in their record attempts.
Oh, yeah.
I did get that from the first three minutes.
Sorry, I didn't.
Until I got to that sentence in the email.
If he ever writes a memoir, "Troy Hard" will be a great title.
Oh my god.
Yeah.
I love it.
I'm a university challenge when people get an answer right.
Do you know they often pick up a glass of water and just congratulate themselves.
I love how you just did that down after that joke.
I have to be careful because I'm running out of water.
These puns are not going to stop any time soon.
It's because you know the applause break.
It's coming.
Yeah, that's it, isn't it?
Yeah.
All right.
Let's have something about space now.
Okay.
The final frontier.
This is the log of Andrew Hunter Murray.
What we're doing, astronaut's logs actually.
Oh, no.
Because Aiden Kotter writes in with facts about astronauts going to the moon space.
Which we did on Little Fish, didn't we?
Yeah, we know.
Yes.
That's all right.
We were sent in a fact about the ISS having you're able to tell how much urine is in the urine tank.
The P-tank blue sky account.
That's right.
38 percent.
38.
Yes.
Well, Aiden's just following up with a little bit of information because there are some amazing
stuff about these missions.
So obviously it's, we is much easier to do with them poo.
Oh, yeah.
But where you can just put on some sauna calls.
Well, okay.
During the Apollo and Gemini missions, the NASA teams gave the first men on the moon bags
to go into.
Yeah.
They did know that.
But what I didn't know is that in zero gravity there is a problem with achieving separation.
Oh.
You see what I mean?
So the poo, you might, you might be pooing.
Oh, so it's like you know those plasticine things where you feed the plasticine in and it comes out in a shape.
Yeah.
And then you cut the plasticine off.
So you get your sausage.
You have to.
So the NASA designed bags with special finger compartments to allow.
Wow.
A astronauts in question two.
Does your Sphinx and I'll do that.
No.
I thought, yeah, can you not do a bum squeeze to finish it?
God.
I'm sorry.
I brought this up.
But it's, I think it doesn't flee.
It doesn't flee from you the way it normally does on Earth.
Oh, I see.
So it wasn't, it was cut.
But it wouldn't.
I'm afraid so.
You know, you know, it's not enough.
It's not enough push that when you get it out.
Sorry if you're eating.
It does feel like you would even because there's no friction in space.
One squeeze.
Yeah.
It would go away and then it would just continue on its way into deep space.
In space.
No one can hear you squeeze.
Yeah.
Or if it just hangs it, could you fart and the air propellate?
I wonder if it's strong enough to propel it.
A single fart because there is talk about astronauts farting to propel themselves.
That is not strong enough.
There is talk on the website that goes to.
What briefing paper stated this got to in NASA?
Is talk.
I love that.
Anyway.
So thank you, Aidan, for that disgusting fact.
That's great.
Yeah.
So, okay.
Two fingers as part of a plastic bag that you can thumb presumably.
I don't know if it's all fingers.
I haven't.
You might as well do.
There's no point having like mittens.
You might as well have all their fingers available.
Yeah.
Shittons, you could call them.
Yes.
Tag me your water.
Let's have some of the non-determ.
Oh.
Let's go to non-determ, Ali.
Kevin McGillivre says there is a 15 year old chess grandmaster from Iran whose name is
Sinah.
Move ahead.
He's a move ahead.
Sinah move ahead.
That's very good.
That's stunning.
Yeah.
That's good.
Never heard of him.
That's really.
That's quite creepy non-determinism.
Yeah.
That's.
Hang on.
Harry not writes in about Adele Acta.
Just wondering at what age Adele Acta realized he'd be an ideal actor.
He's an actor.
Yeah.
Incredible.
He's an actor.
Yep.
Great.
Ross Harvey says, the press secretary for the Reagan administration was named Larry Speaks.
Press secretary, which makes him both a sentence person and an example of nominative determinism.
Oh, that's good.
Yeah.
Is that brilliant?
We have to go back briefly to the nulla ball plane.
Oh, no.
In a section we're now calling nulla balls.
Can I say I think there's a chance one day we might go back to Australia for a tour.
Yeah.
If you guys want us to come, we'll come.
And I would love to do a gig, a gig in the nulla ball plane.
In the 500 miles of nothing in every direction.
I would be good.
That would be great.
I'm up for it.
That would be awesome.
Yeah.
Well, Mike Cowley is a former West Australian civil engineer and isn't writing about how you
say the word nulla ball.
He does include that as part of his email, but there's a thing amazing thing about road trains.
Right.
Which is this.
You know, you get a huge.
You've got a big semi on the front.
And you've got a lot of characters on the back.
Yeah.
Trailers and all that.
But this is a fantastic tiny extra bonus fact that I think probably only a former West Australian
civil engineer would know.
Okay.
So he's from Perth.
Like almost everyone in West Australia.
Geometric rose design is typically completed using the Ostrodes guide to road design part
three.
Okay.
You've already got Andy.
He's hooked.
You had me.
No design.
I'm flying a fighter jet right now.
I'm part of this process.
It's the calculation.
I promise this is good of the site stopping distances, which take into account vehicle speed road surface
road grade and reaction time.
Yeah, sure.
You had to learn that for your highway code in back in the day.
And the reaction time is selected by the engineer based on road conditions slash drivers circumstances.
So the engineer is building the road.
Maybe a Len B Del or similar.
You use either a reaction time of 1.5 seconds, two seconds or two and a half.
And there's this tiny note in Ostrodes guide to road design part three, which says reaction
time of 1.5 seconds, that's the fastest, cannot be used in Western Australia.
A 1.5 second reaction time is owned to be used in constrained situations where drivers will be alert.
The general minimum reaction time is two seconds.
And Mike writes, there is no reason Western Australia should be treated differently.
It's not regional Western Australia.
It's all of it.
The only conclusion I can fathom is we take just a fraction of a moment longer to do things over here.
It's just a slower pace of life.
Not because there is lots of featureless land.
And so you kind of kind of dose off a little bit and your reaction times are worse.
That's a very good theory.
It doesn't explain why.
It's maybe ungoogleable.
Thank you so much, Mike Cowley for that barnstormer of an email.
Great little spot of a tiny, tiny detail.
I think that's why I liked it so much.
I'm a former Western Australian road engineer.
That gets me going.
That pumps me up.
Should we have last one?
Last one.
Let's do it.
Dan, you like saying things about yourself on the show.
Okay.
You reveal things about yourself, don't you?
Yeah.
If I think of something that's relevant to the chat, I'll pop it in.
But you don't keep yourself secret.
No.
You know, I do.
I'm very private.
And you're much more open, I'd say.
Okay.
And James, you're somewhere in the middle.
Yeah.
I think, especially in the little fish, we're all revealing ourselves a little bit more.
That's true.
than we ever have before.
But what I do wonder is where the fuck you're going with this?
I can't think of where.
I'm not even playing at being innocent, I genuinely.
I don't know what you're trying to get.
We're such an unusual start to a bit.
I guess you're right.
It was weird.
It was weird of me to say.
Basically, we've had a fact from something we said on little fish about celebrities who give out
their personal phone number.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Patsy Clien.
At Laurel Hardy.
Yes.
Stan Laurel.
That's right.
And then about the former T-Shock of Ireland, Ender Kenny.
Oh, yeah.
Not that long ago though.
Not that long ago.
No.
Who was replaced by Leo Veracca and Olivia just right.
She remembers a conversation with her politics teacher where she was told Ender Kenny was so prone to giving out
his personal phone number to anyone who asked that two thirds of Kerry had him in their contacts.
And I just really like this.
So she tried to back it up.
She tried to do a bit more research.
Yeah.
She tried to Google it.
But it turns out that he has done this loads.
That's really great.
Ender Kenny.
And there's a news article she included the link to where Ender Kenny says his open invitation to global
business to call him anytime has had some unexpected consequences.
And he basically told the load of people.
Call me anytime.
And more or less put his number up on the screen.
And he then said, Christ, I'm getting phone calls from Adelaide and New Zealand and everywhere.
They're not all about industry.
That's really cool.
Oh, that's really cool.
Anyway, this is a nice little effect.
Yeah.
But Ender Kenny.
Who I think could be a friend of the podcast you never know with that kind of attitude.
Friend of Kenny.
Yeah.
Brilliant.
All right.
That's your lot.
Yeah.
Great.
Good stuff.
Always good stuff.
Yeah.
I would say at the moment, probably the inbox is a little bit gone.
The inbox is looking very hollow.
So what do we need?
We need emails.
I see what you're doing there.
You're helping me.
You have to be kidding out of this.
You do need a bit of that.
You've gone out of it.
We're bringing you back in.
Just what I think I'm out.
It will be right back in.
No, James is right.
We need emails.
We need them urgently.
If you are a former Western Australian road engineer and you've noticed something funny
in "Ost Roads" volume three.
If you're flying a fighter jet.
If you're flying a fighter jet, please send it.
I mean, I'll glance at it.
No, if you have anything to say about anything we've said on any of our 600 episodes,
40 on drop of the lines and a growing number of little fish, we'd love to hear it.
We'd love getting emails as we've mentioned once or twice before.
It's podcast@QI.com.
And we'll do another one of these in a couple of weeks.
But until then, it's by from these two.
Bye.
So long.
It's by from me.
Oh, I'm afraid it's too wrong.
There's no one else to say goodbye.
What about Little Andy?
What about me?
It's by quite fun, Governor.
He doesn't know how to fucking.
What about even smaller Andy?
What about me?
Why?
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC]