(bells ringing)
(speaking in foreign language)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast,
this week coming to you from Edinburgh!
(audience cheering)
My name is Dan Schreiber
and I am sitting here with Anna Chazinski,
Andrew Hunter-Marie and James Harkin,
and once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one,
and that's my fact this week,
my fact is unmarried people are more likely
to fall down stairs than married people.
(audience laughing)
And previously married people fall down more
than both of them.
(audience laughing)
- It does, it's not just 'cause they're like,
it's my phone's ringing, my phone's ringing,
get it, because you're single, you're kind of, you know.
- Yeah, you're ready for the thing.
- I don't think we know why, do we?
- We don't, so I read this in a Bill Bryson book
called At Home, which is a fantastic book
and he references in the chapter
which he writes about stairs that he read this one book,
the only book that is a sort of academic look at staircases
and it's by John Templer of MIT, it's called The Staircase,
Studies of Hazards Fall and Safe Designs.
- Yeah, and I have also read this book, there it is.
- That's it.
- It is the first theoretical,
historical and scientific analysis of the stair,
according to the blurb.
It is pretty hard going.
(audience laughing)
And actually that was a little joke
for you staircase enthusiasts out there
because the going is the width of a stair.
(audience laughing)
And all of my humour will be staircase based
for the rest of the show.
(audience laughing)
- John Templer's at home pissing himself
on the other end of that.
- I mean, there's diagrams as, you know,
loads of tables and stuff like this.
There's tables.
- What are tables doing in the book?
(audience laughing)
- There's like about three or four good facts
in the first four pages
and then the rest of it is just unbelievably tedious.
(audience laughing)
- Did he lead with the unmarried and married tables?
- Yeah, it's right near the start.
Another thing he says is that notable missteps
happen once every 2,222 stair uses.
Minor accidents happen every 63,000 uses.
Disabling accidents every 734,210 uses.
Hospital treatments every 3,616,667 uses.
And deaths every 513,947,300 uses.
And that was one of the least boring.
(audience laughing)
- Do you know why all these accidents happen?
- No, why?
- According to him, it's because every staircase
is a compromise between going up and going down.
- Yeah, so you can have staircases
which just for people going up, can't you?
- Oh no, that would be that would be decadent, wouldn't it?
(audience laughing)
- His point being that how would you get down again
as well, think of that.
- I'd have to in my house.
- Oh, I would have Harman's pole or a slide.
- Wait, so what do you mean by a compromise?
Who's compromising with whom?
Who's negotiating here?
- The perfect staircase would be a staircase
that would be able to adapt itself
to whether or not you were going up or down
for the length and the height and so on.
They're built in one way which plays advantage
to either going up or going down.
Very different skills going up and down a staircase.
- Very different.
- And actually in this book, there are figures
about how a staircase was if you're going up or down.
So if you're going up, there's a different
wearing out of the stair than if you're going down.
- But you would have thought the wearing would be the same
on all staircases unless you've just got a huge stockpile
of 10,000 people at the top of the stairs at some point.
At some point everyone who goes up stairs
does come down the stairs.
- I think there are a few like, for instance,
if you've got stairs coming up at a dock, say for instance,
people might use it for getting off the boat,
but to get on the boat they might use the pier.
- I see.
- So there are a few little things like that.
It's very interesting, actually, I don't know.
- And that's the origin of that saying, isn't it?
What goes up stairs must come down stairs.
- Women fall downstairs more often than men
or admit to falling downstairs more often than men.
So 38% of women, compared to 28% of men,
said they'd fallen downstairs or upstairs
or tripped on stairs in the last year.
And also weirdly, this was a study that was done
by the British Woodworking Federation
who relied on for all rigorous scientific studies.
And their study also found that the northeast of England,
so it was a study that discovered England,
the northeast is the most at risk of falling downstairs.
So 48% of people there said they'd done it in the last year,
whereas Yorkshire and Humber, directly next to the northeast region,
had the least incidences, 26%.
What's going on there?
It doesn't make any sense.
- I don't know, mate.
- I saw a really cool invention the other day
'cause a lot of people are trying to work out
how to stop people if they do fall over
from properly hurting themselves.
So there's this new invention that they're trialing
at the moment, which is like a big belt that you wear.
And it senses that you're falling over.
It's a sort of like, this is a movement
that's not being expected.
I've gone, as a belt, I've gone over that way.
And what it does is it inflates these massive airbags.
Speaking of stair-based inventions, that sounds awesome.
There are scientists at Georgia Tech
who have invented some stairs which walk you back.
- What, that doesn't make any sense?
- Well, I understand all those words, but.
- Well, I've tried to, I've tried to sex it up a bit,
and I don't think it's succeeded.
Basically, there are stairs which, as you walk on them,
they store your energy,
and then when you walk the other way,
so when you walk down the gravitational force
of you descending, stalls energy in the stair,
and then when you walk back up, it springs you up.
Every step you take, every move you make.
(audience laughing)
And when you go back up, it's 37% easier on your knee
than it would be normally, so that could be huge.
- Yeah, and there are shoes that have just been invented
to stop people from falling over,
which I think sound a bit less dramatic
than embarrassing than the air bag solution,
because they're just shoes with battery on the back of them
and a sensor, and they sense when you're starting
to have your body weight in the wrong position,
and they automatically start a little motor
that slides the shoes backwards,
so stops you falling over backwards.
- Like your moonwalking. - Wow.
- Exactly, like moonwalking,
but only if the option is falling over.
- That's amazing.
- And the person who invented them said,
"It's great because it's not as noticeable as having a stick
or a Zimmer frame, which some people don't want to have,
"because it makes them feel like they've lost their mobility."
And they just look like completely normal shoes,
which I watched the video,
and they've got a large motor on the back of each shoe.
(audience laughing)
- Can I just ask about the staircase giving you the lift again?
So presumably, if you were walking down,
it matches your body weight and type
for what the spring it gives you on the way back up, right?
So if I go down the staircase, but then my sun walks up it,
(audience laughing)
is he not gonna be lobbed to the feet?
- Because in 1948, an elephant climbed up the stairs
at the Eiffel Tower.
- No.
- And then climbed back down again, so imagine that.
- Are you serious? - Really?
- Wow.
- There used to be a thing that people did in the Eiffel Tower,
they used to just climb up the stairs in funny ways.
There was a guy who did it in Stilts,
quite famously, a baker.
And then when Hitler took over Paris in the war,
suddenly all of the lifts stopped working,
and they said, "Oh no, you're gonna have to walk up the stairs now."
And he was like, "Oh, I'm not gonna do it then."
- They were jeopardised, weren't they?
The resistance cut all the lift cables in the Eiffel Tower,
and there's someone who admitted to it,
and the end he wrote a book and said,
"It was me, I cut the cables in the Eiffel Tower
to make the Nazis look like idiots."
- But at the time they just said,
"Oh no, it's just not working."
And then the day after he left, they're like,
"Oh, it's working again."
(audience laughing)
- Jeremy Corbyn can climb four flights of stairs
faster than anyone else in the Labour Party.
(audience laughing)
- That's not true. - Proof me wrong.
- The fact that the Labour Party's wasting time
figuring this out doesn't go a long way to explain it.
- Why are you saying that?
I don't understand.
Is it a race they do?
- He's not saying it.
It's according to his deputy, Tom Watson.
- Yeah, Tom Watson can do it that fast, can he?
- No, but he didn't say it just,
he didn't say it was just faster than me, Tom Watson.
He said anyone else, I think in the parliamentary party,
not the 500,000-strong membership,
but maybe anyway.
(audience laughing)
- Do you know the most number of stairs
climbed on your head?
- What?
- Oh.
- So you're on your head, you're like doing a headstand.
- Yeah.
- And then you have to bounce off onto the next step
and you keep going up and how many can you do in a row
while someone will drag on?
- 15, 15, six.
- It's 36.
Do you know what the most stairs tumbled down
in a stunt fall is?
- Mm-hmm.
- Oh, cool.
- Do you reckon it's more or less than 36?
- It's more.
- I'll say it less.
- No, you were wrong to say that.
It was 134.
- Ooh.
- Yeah.
Do you know what the most consecutive stairs
climbed along Juggling the Footballers?
- Oh, Jesus.
- No.
- Are we to the part of the book
where it stopped being interesting now?
(audience laughing)
- It's 4,698.
- Sorry, that was the climbing stairs juggling a football.
But it's a bit of a cheat
'cause he just went of the same 18 stairs lots of times.
- Wait, Juggling a football?
- Yeah, with your feet.
- I can keep your feet.
- Oh, that, sorry.
I thought you meant he was juggling one football
with his hands.
(audience laughing)
I think I could do that.
- I don't think you could.
I don't think you could go at 4,600 steps.
No wonder what the football's doing.
(audience laughing)
And one more, most consecutive stairs climbed
while balancing a person on your head.
Ah.
So you're walking up and it's like
as if there's a mirror on your head
'cause there's another person directly above you.
- What is it?
- Are they standing on their head on your head?
- Yeah, their head is on your head.
- And they're upside down.
- All right.
- What's the number?
- 90.
- It's impressive.
- Yeah, yeah.
- More than the guy who just did it on his head.
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- I would say that is much easier.
They're still doing it on their feet.
- He has a man upside down on his head.
(audience laughing)
- Well, these, 'cause do you guys know
about competitive self-climing?
- No.
- Which is, this is a really a growing sport.
So it's like an official sport.
There's this global circuit of competitive stair climbers.
They call themselves the most difficult sport
that no one's ever heard of.
And it's basically they have these events all over the world
where they race up really tall buildings.
So the three main races are in the US,
the Empire State Building, Sears Tower and US Bank Tower.
And they have this big Facebook group
and they call each other step brothers and step sisters,
which is real clever.
But they take it super seriously.
So like the men shave their legs and shave their head.
So they're more streamlined going up the stairs.
They wear glasses.
- That can't make much of a difference, I'll cut it.
- 'Cause you're in a stairwell.
There's gonna be that much air resistance.
- I guess so.
- Yeah.
- There's still air, isn't there?
- There's still air.
- Although one thing they say is that
the air in stairwells is actually quite bad.
So you get this really bad smoke
as hacking cough as you're going up
because the air's really dry.
So they recommend that you suck on a fruit suite
or a lozenge as you're running up,
which I would have thought is a massive choking hazard
as your sprinting up says.
- You must be absolutely exhausted
by the time you get to the top.
- It's really tiring.
- That's true, a lot of spots so actually.
- Yeah.
- Like.
(audience laughs)
- But then at the end of this,
you've got to climb on top of another set of stairs.
- To podium.
- Yeah.
- Do you think some people kind of cheat
and at the end, they pretend they've come second
and then they race to the top one of the podium
in the last minute.
- Corribate?
(audience laughs)
- We need to move on to our next facts very soon.
You guys got anything before we do?
- This is massively off topic.
- Yeah.
- Just, I was reading about going upstairs two at a time
and there's a guardian.
- That's quite on topic actually.
- Just you wait.
(audience laughs)
- There's a guardian, notes and queries,
you know, where they get questions from the public
and they're really interesting questions.
And one of them was is taking the stairs two at a time.
Good for us.
And I looked up a few other notes and queries things.
One of them is, is it actually possible
to take a photograph of a river?
'Cause it moves, so, you know, what have you photographed?
Right?
(audience laughs)
- It's genius.
It's genius.
- That's not genius.
- It's never again.
That bit of water is never there again.
- But that's true of time.
Like, if I take a photo of you now,
then time has moved on and you're gonna be older
than you are.
- That's one of the most popular answers.
(audience laughs)
- Is it okay to do the crossword in the newspaper
for cafe customers?
Is it weird to be talking to myself so much?
(audience laughs)
And how many layers of paint would I need to apply
to make opposite walls touch?
(audience laughs)
- I think the last layer is gonna be quite hard to do, isn't it?
- Just paint to yourself, not into a car, no, but into it.
(audience laughs)
- All right, let's move on to our next bag.
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that there's a tanning salon
in St. Andrews called Sun Tandrews.
(audience laughs)
Now, don't get too excited, guys,
because when I say verse,
it's THERP apostrophe S, and it's short for there was,
(audience laughs)
because I check Google today,
and it's not there anymore.
- Wow.
- It's now a tanning salon called Abbott Hattan.
- What? - No, I don't get it.
A beta tan, a beta tan?
- Oh, a beta tan?
- A beta tan, yeah, a beta tan, actually.
It's still not great though, is it?
- No, it's no Sun Tandrews, which is genius.
- It is, but this is just a fact, this was told to me
by our colleague, Anne Miller,
who used to live up here,
used to live in St. Andrews,
and I just think it's awesome.
And I thought we could talk about maybe Sun Tans
and tanning salons and stuff like that.
- We should, although I think we should say for Anne Miller's sake,
that I don't think she's ever been in a tanning salon.
I don't want people to get the impression
that she was on the sunbed every day.
- She's got a life for a pun, hasn't she?
- She's got a life for a pun.
She's been in the punning salon, yeah.
(audience laughs)
- There's a cool pun one in Edinburgh,
and maybe you guys will know if this still exists,
but so there's a property shop,
and it's called the property shop,
and right next to it, someone set up a cafe
called the property shop, and so that just...
(audience laughs)
- It's the same company, it's in Stockbridge, isn't it?
It's the same, so it was a state agency,
and it was the same guy said, let's have a cafe.
- Oh really?
- It's cool. - It's hard of our thing, yeah.
- Okay, cool.
- On Sun Tans, I found out that,
so obviously getting a Sun Tant is bad for you,
in lots of ways, and there's no way of getting a tan
without doing damage to the skin,
as in the protection that you get in future,
is the damage that you do,
except that there is a team at Massachusetts General Hospital,
and they have invented a drug, which you can take,
which will give you a Sun Tant, with no Sun.
- Wow. - Nice.
- And this is amazing, it produces melanin,
which is the thing that protects you from skin cancer,
and it could provide the elixir of tanning a red-haired tan.
- Oh. - Yeah, you could have,
'cause people with red hair, they have a genetic mutation,
which disrupts the process,
and makes it very hard for people with red hair to tan,
this could create a big gray and...
- Oh, wow.
(audience laughs)
- That's very cool.
- Do you know, 'cause it is bad for you,
and there's been a lot of publicity,
now recently about it, you have to get your fingerprints checked
in a lot of tanning salons,
so like the tanning salon, the tanning shop,
which has a lot of branches over the UK,
you're fingerprinted, and if you've come in
and get before that day, they don't let you in.
- Oh, really? - Wow.
- Yeah. - That's quite good.
- These tanning salons and airports.
- But actually people didn't really care about,
like, Sun Tant's did they, for ages and ages and ages,
because basically having a Sun Tant meant that you were poor
and you worked outside, you were a labourer,
and so it was always thought that if you had light skin,
it was better.
But then Coco Chanel accidentally got tanned
when she went on a Mediterranean cruise in 1923,
and suddenly always everyone thought,
this is the thing that we all need to have now.
So it's quite a relatively new thing.
- Yeah.
- You know, when Sun Tant's got popular,
after the Coco Chanel incident,
then obviously a lot of kind of merchandise popped up
around them, and popular science wrote an article
about all the weird Sun Tanting technologies
that have been invented since kind of 1920s, 1930s,
and there were some crazy stuff people were doing.
So in 1938, it wrote about a rotating Sun tub,
which is basically a tent that you brought to the beach,
and it had like huge wooden kind of structure
that you had to bring to the beach, and you erected it,
and it followed the Sun's movements.
So you lay inside it and you had a little steering wheel,
and so you could steer the tent to point you
towards the Sun.
- That's a really good idea.
- It's incredible.
- So you're in the wooden structure,
but there's a gap of sunlight for your body.
- Exactly.
- But are you kind of steering it towards the Sun,
or does it do it automatically?
- You have to steer.
- But you've got to do something.
Otherwise, it's boring.
- Fair enough.
You can get bacon smelling sunscreen.
- Why would you want that?
- Well, because lots of people like bacon.
- Yeah.
- According to the website of this thing,
science has shown us that 10 out of 10 people
prefer the smell of bacon to coconut.
- Sorry.
(audience laughing)
- Can't argue with science, Andy.
- 10 out of 10, including vegetarian's and vegans.
- The smell, the smell of bacon.
- Is this another study done
by one of Jeremy Corbyn's Cabinet?
(audience laughing)
- Very questionable.
- Last year, KFC sold sunscreen which smelled of KFC.
- Oh, yeah.
- It would protect your skin while the real fried chicken scent
leaves you smelling delicious.
(audience laughing)
They had 3,000 tubes and everyone was disappointed
'cause they sold out in two hours.
But luckily, they learned the lesson
and that was the last time KFC ever ran out of anything.
Ever again.
(audience laughing)
- Speaking of artificial tanning,
sometimes people can overdo it.
I just wanted to share this headline from the mail.
A young mother claims she was housebound for a week
after a fake tan fail, left her looking,
like she'd bathed in chocolate spread,
with pals even mistaking her for a brown leather sofa.
(audience laughing)
- That is, I mean, what, like, guys, stop sitting on me.
What are you doing?
Did it change her whole body shape?
- I don't know.
- It's interesting, the methods that people used to go
about to try and get a tan back in the day.
And I read about one which I think people still occasionally
try, which is to use tea bags.
So, what you do is just put a lot of tea bags
into a hot bath, and you would get in the bath,
and you would allow that to cook you into a pot.
- Have you put the milk in first?
(audience laughing)
They didn't say in the article.
- I heard that that was done in the wall,
where women wanted a tan, but obviously,
there's no way of getting a tan,
'cause you can't go on holiday in Greece anymore.
- What's the big problem there are people
close to the Nazis?
- Oh, yeah.
(audience laughing)
- I knew I hated those guys.
But the thing I read is that, for people who try it these days,
when they do it in a bath, they come across the same problem,
which is how do you tan your face,
because that's above water.
And in order to tan it, you need to be underwater
for a long time.
So, a bunch of people bought snorkels, which they tried.
(audience laughing)
But, that was just weird then, when they put it.
- I think once you've got us far as getting in a bath
with a lot of tea bags, looking weird
with the snorkels, at least you.
- But I think it's always a point where you go
for no two-five, this is.
- And so, what did they work any for now in the end of,
they should not be able to do that?
- No, they'll just don't do it anymore.
- Well, the person in the article had a very white head
regretted the whole experience.
But yeah, you then just do it outside of the bath,
you just leave tea bags all over yourself.
(audience laughing)
- Of course.
- It's a thing, it's a thing, yeah.
- Well, they also used to have milk spray,
'cause people thought that milk could tan you better,
stop me from burning, but give you a really nice tan,
and there were motorized milk sprayers that, like,
groups of mainly women in the 1930s would carry
to wherever they wanted to tan on holiday,
and like it was this big engine,
and then you stood in front of it,
and it just showered you with milk.
And then you go on nice, even tan.
I like this, the Daily Mail, that spoke to some people
about how bad it is, but it's loved to get really burned,
and it found that eight, 10 million British people
said that they burned every time they went on holiday,
which is a large proportion of the population,
and the person the mail interviewed to talk about this
was a spokesman for Superdrug, chemist,
and he was called Martin Crisp.
(audience laughing)
- Hi.
- We're gonna have to move on to our next hack soon.
- There's a planet called Kepler-13AB,
where it rains sun cream.
- What?
- What brand?
(audience laughing)
- It's kind of a titanium oxide precipitation,
but it only falls on the dark side of the planet,
so it's completely useless.
(audience laughing)
- Just quickly, I was looking at some beauty salon stuff,
you know, tanning salons.
Do you guys know about snail salons?
- No.
- So snail slime is the new thing in beauty treatments.
It's really popular in, so places like Thailand
and Japan, in Italy it's popular,
and people who are running snail farms,
because snail is obviously eaten all over the world,
are diversifying their farms,
and they hand select a few snails on the farm
to be transferred to the salon,
and then you book a session in the salon as a woman,
you lie down, and you get a few snails on your face,
just crawling all over it,
and the claim is that it heals like your acne or scars
or it slows down aging.
- I've actually tried this.
- Have you really?
- It's good.
The service is unbelievably slow.
(audience laughing)
- All right, let's move on, let's move on to our next hack.
It's time for fact number three, and that is Andy.
- My fact is that during the second mobile,
the US government considered making all American shoes
deliberately ugly.
(audience laughing)
So, this is the thing to do with rationing.
They were very low on rubber, very low on leather,
and they thought, "Well, how are we gonna do this?"
Eventually, they decided to introduce shoe rationing.
They said, "Everybody can only have three pairs of shoes
"a year, and if you wanted that extra pair of shoes,
"you had to fill in a really long complicated form,
"saying why you want more shoes."
But you could only, as a manufacturer, make four colors,
and you could only have two different tones on a shoe.
So, rationing was introduced, but the alternative plan
that they did consider, I think, before rejecting it was,
let's just make shoes really, really horrible.
- Some people don't want to buy them.
- Exactly.
- And the four colors that they were allowed were
black, white, army, russet, and town, brown.
- Town. - Town, town, town.
Like a place where people live.
- Old tower.
- No, town, town. - No, town, town.
(audience laughing)
Town.
- You know, when people live in a tower.
(audience laughing)
- Sorry, I heard town, like the thing you rub yourself with.
- No, town. - Town, town.
- Town. - Town, yeah.
- Like a city without a cathedral?
- Yes. - Right.
(audience laughing)
- Oh, why didn't you say that?
- So, do you say that two tone colors on shoes weren't allowed?
- That was the maximum.
- Oh. - You couldn't have three tone shoes.
- Really, I saw that you could only have single tone,
you couldn't have double tone.
- Oh, maybe wrong.
- You weren't allowed boots taller than 10 inches
and you weren't allowed heels taller than two
and five eighths inches.
And you weren't allowed fancy tongues.
- Mm-hmm. - No.
- You also. - Tongs.
- Tongs. - Sorry.
- No. - Tongs?
- Sorry.
(audience laughing)
- Tung, like a tongue. - Tung, yeah.
Sorry, it's my accent.
I know I do say the word tongue wrong,
but it's the thing inside your mouth
that you lick stuff with.
(audience laughing)
- I don't know what I had to say this for everything now,
and I say from now on.
(audience laughing)
- Sorry, now it's a word that means you're not sure.
- But when you say tongues,
you are referring to the thing on your shoe.
- Sorry, yeah. - You're not saying
you're not allowed elaborate tongues in your mouth.
- That was the thing, they were rationed
during the second mobile, fancy tongues.
(audience laughing)
- There was another thing where you could get
a cheaper version of a shoe that would cost you less
of your ration coupons, your clothing coupons that you had.
And it was a shoe that was designed with a wooden sole.
So, the problem with that is you get no bend
as you're lifting up your foot,
like any shoe that anyone is wearing in this room has,
and so you would have to reinvent the way of how you walk
with your shoe to avoid--
- Okay, and the moment you're kind of
waddling left and right, is that how they did it?
- I mean, I'm putting myself into the place
of the person with the shoe, and that's how I feel.
- The shoes don't bend, is that the problem?
- Yeah. - 'Cause it's a wooden bottom.
- Just like a clog, I mean, with many with clogs.
Like a clog, thank you Anna, yeah.
- But people with clogs get around, okay, don't they?
Nope, what? (audience laughing)
What they then had to do is in order to make that
a bit more of a useful shoe, they then cut a bit
and they put a hinge in so that you could then walk,
and the hinge would allow you the bend.
The problem is, is that while you were walking,
the hinge would collect stones,
and so you would be stuck in the hinge position
in a sort of leaning forward position.
Like the Michael Jackson lean.
- Yeah, 'cause he invented shoes, didn't he,
that let him do that lean?
- He did. - And he owned a patent for those shoes.
- Yeah.
- And they were, they kind of, I think you're allowed to say,
they kind of, there was a bit in the stage,
and he kind of slotted them into the stage
so that he could lean right forward,
and he owned the patent for that thing.
- Which is weird, 'cause that's not really inventing a shoe,
that's inventing a strap on the floor of a stage
to put a shoe into. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I thought though it had weights in it as well,
I thought that it literally, you moved in a certain way,
it kicked in a weight into function
so that when you went forward, that would balance you as well.
- Yeah, might be.
- I don't, I've not followed the Michael Jackson shoe patent
paper close enough.
- Do you know you can get shoes for your shoes now?
- What?
- This has been shown off at, I think,
Paris Men's Fashion Week in the last couple of months.
Issues for your shoes have been designed.
They've been designed by a Chinese fashion designer
called Sanquans, and it sneakers
that then have kind of an outer layer, which is a sandal,
and you can velcro the sandal on and off.
And it's so that, you know, if you're going out on dirty street
and you've got new shoes, you don't have to get the shoes dirty.
- Yeah, but you just want about your outer shoes.
They're going to get dirty, I'm going to go through.
- The person did comment.
He said, we haven't got the triple layer stage yet,
but who knows what the future holds.
- Well, I could tell you what it holds,
the fourth layer of the triple layer.
(audience laughing)
- God, it's the branding.
- Well, so that's a big thing in Japan, isn't it?
So in Japan, it's very employed the way your shoes
into someone's house.
Everyone takes off their shoes as soon as you get to
a someone's house or a restaurant or whatever,
and they give you a pair of slippers.
And it's very nice, and you walk around the restaurant
in the slippers, and it's great, except that when you go
to the Lou in the restaurant, they have to take you
out of your normal slippers and put you
in special toilet slippers.
And there's a real risk of social embarrassment
that once you've been to the toilet,
you then forget to take off your toilet slippers.
- Ah!
- Because they're very different.
They look very different.
So one writer said, he walked back into a fancy restaurant
wearing a pair of bright yellow slippers
with a duck having a poo on the toes.
(audience laughing)
And that was the design.
- And that was a picture of a duck having a poo on the sole.
- Yeah, it was.
(audience laughing)
Yeah.
- In 13th century Italy.
So do you know my favorite fact about shoes?
I've said it loads of times.
And that is in the 14th century,
it was made explicitly illegal in France
to make shoes that were shaped like penises.
- Yes.
- Okay.
I found out quite recently that Queen Mary made it illegal
to make shoes shaped like vaginas.
- No way.
Oh my god, your two favorite facts can get married.
That's so nice.
(audience laughing)
Or at least have sex with each other.
- So in this all began in 13th century Italy
and there was a thing, it was the cult of the Virgin Mary
and basically everyone walked better
way to pay tribute to the Virgin Mary.
(audience laughing)
- Well, it wasn't like the Catholic church hated it,
basically, so it was like a cult.
It wasn't like a, it wasn't just a thing.
Everyone liked the Virgin Mary, it was a cult, you think.
And they suddenly became really paid a lot of attention
to the form of the perfect female body,
which was supposed to be what the Virgin Mary had.
And so they invented these shoes
and they were called duck spill shoes, they were really wide.
They were covered, they were heavily padded,
they were covered in hair like material
and they put slits in them
and you wore pink hosiery
and as you walked it was supposed to look like a vagina.
- Right.
- Wow.
- That is amazing.
- And this was high fashion in 13th century Italy.
- No.
- And then when Queen Mary came to the Crown in Britain,
she wanted to curry favor with the Pope
and so she banned them.
- I, it was supposed to look like a vagina.
- Yep.
- And the.
- Why?
(audience laughing)
- It was a hairy shoe that had a little slit
which like pink sometimes.
- So hang on.
- Were the...
(audience laughing)
- Were the shoes just an act to me, guys?
- Yeah, no, sure.
- So were the penis shoes a response to the vagina shoes?
People saying sort of as a prank, you know?
- No, no, no.
- My understanding is it's a complete coincidence
that these two things come into this.
- I believe so.
- That's amazing.
- The gender wall was fought in a very different way
in the Middle Ages.
- Some other World War II shoes that I found
is there's a shoe that they were sort of invented
to trick the enemy.
So the shoe would leave the footprints of the shoe
would leave a barefoot footprint.
So it looked as if one of the locals had been in the area
as opposed to a soldier who had a big boot.
So on the bottom of the boot was just the shape of a foot.
So we...
- But locals wore the shoes.
(audience laughing)
- This was Southeast Asia.
- Okay, yeah.
- I should have said the place.
- Did they make the footprints in the opposite direction
to where you were walking?
That would be clever.
- That would be very clever, yeah.
- We've said before some people did that
or supposedly Australian outlaws put their horses shoes
on backwards.
- You're right.
- So you don't think, oh, Nick Kelly's been through this way
or has actually, Nick Kelly had been through this way
but he was heading the other way.
But this is also in Bhutan, they say that yetis
have the ability to take their foot off
and put it on that way round.
(audience cheering)
That's an actual Yeti fact.
- Yeah.
- I do know the fact about animals in your shoes.
- Right, yeah, as a few years ago, scientists put boots
onto dung beetles to find out how they cope with heat.
This is so cool.
So dung beetles, they find a ball of poo
and they roll it around and every so often,
when it gets to the really hot bit of the day,
they climb up on top of the ball of poo
and then they rest there for a bit.
And scientists wondered, is that because it's really hot
on the scientific desert where they're walking around?
- Ah.
- So if you put boots on a dung beetle,
you will theoretically find out whether that's the reason.
- Ah, yeah.
- And the scientists put, I think it was
little silicon shoes on the dung beetles
and they said afterwards, turns out,
it's very, very, very difficult to shoe a dung beetle.
(audience laughing)
'Cause they did, they managed it.
They got the boots on them and it turns out, yes.
When you have boots on as a dung beetle,
you stop much less to climb onto your ball.
So that is why.
- Could it be that they don't want to get on their dung
in case they get shit on the shoes?
- Ah, yeah.
(audience laughing)
- They're actually working on a set of new outer shoes
for the dung beetles in a shoe.
(audience laughing)
I read that in plow.
There's a tradition of when people go into the reef
and they're going fishing and so on.
What they do is they take a sea sea cucumbers
and they squeeze the internals of the sea cucumber out
completely so the guts and everything go out
and then they wear the rubbery shell on the reef
so they don't cut their feet when they're in the reefs.
Improvised nature shoes.
- Why not just put some wetsuit feet on before you start diving?
- No, this is in plow where they don't have necessarily.
- Oh, they're just fishing and so on and so on.
- The sea cucumber can eviscerate its organs.
That's the thing that they do.
But they stay alive after they do that.
So this feels a bit...
- Oh god, I live while you're wearing them.
- What?
- Well, they can stay alive because they regrow them
and what they do is they kind of send out their organs
and then hopefully like the fish eats the organs
and they can swim away.
- Oh my god, can you imagine at the end of the day
being a sea cucumber going,
you're not going to believe what happens to me.
(audience laughing)
- But also the anus of the sea cucumber
which is where you're putting your foot.
- Yeah.
- Is they have fish living in those anuses.
So you might get fish in your feet as well.
- That's all right.
- You've caught a bit of the meal already then.
- I think if you've got your foot in a sea cucumber's anus,
the fact that there's another fish present there
adds very little to the overall horror of the situation.
(audience laughing)
- I could do it like, you know, in shopping centers
where the fish eat your...
- Oh yeah, exactly.
It's exfoliating as well as being protective.
- Yeah, that's great.
- I've had that once and all I could think
while I was having it was reincarnation
and just looking at the going,
what the fuck did you do in your last life
that you have come back to eat my feet?
- I had it once and I think I've told you guys this,
but I had it once in Cambodia and they had to ask me
to take my feet out of the pond
'cause you put your feet in with like five other people
and my feet are so disgusting
that they were all coming to my feet.
(audience laughing)
- No one else is getting their money's worth.
- It's real, real actually the low point pride wise me.
(audience laughing)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Chisinski.
- Yeah, my fact this week is that the etiquette experts
de Bretts run classes that teach five-year-olds
to have strong handshakes and navigate dinner parties.
(audience laughing)
And this is, so I don't know how many people know
about de Bretts, but they's basically a sort of guide
to being a posh person, I guess.
And they started publishing their etiquette guides in the 1700s
and they still go on today
and it's kind of teaching people how to perform well socially.
And they recently started doing these classes
which are called Signet Schools.
And it's for, it's meant to be for six to 12-year-olds I think,
but actually there's been such a lot of demand
that they're letting in five-year-olds.
And yeah, they teach them to do things like shake hands well
and perform well at dinner party and talk to grownups.
And it's to teach children of primary school age,
of early primary school age, social ease and confidence
and charisma and charm to guarantee
that they are both invited back to the next play date
and successful in interviews.
(audience laughing)
- Who's interviewing a five-year-old?
- You know, business is getting really desperate.
- Well, I've just opened another 19th century factory
that I need.
(audience laughing)
- Like school interviews.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, all right.
- So there was a report by one of the mothers
who sent her child on this.
And at the very end of the piece she wrote about it,
she gave her review of the whole experience.
She said, "The pleases and thank yous trip off the tongue
"and despite the occasional poop joke
"and a little light nose-picking,
"he's become really quite charming."
(audience laughing)
- But you do pay for it.
So I think it starts at about 650 pounds for two hours
to send your five-year-old to this.
But yeah, one woman who wrote a blog said,
"I think I'd have a really strong handshake at the end of that."
(audience laughing)
I've got a proper bone crusher.
- And that's just the start.
So the woman who wrote the blog paid 780 for two hours
to get her handshaking son back.
- They saw her coming, didn't they?
The normal price is 650 pounds to you, 780.
(audience laughing)
- You know, the depress, the depress offer advice
on eating bananas.
- Do they? - Do they?
- It turns out, I think we're all doing it wrong.
They're coming to the press.
Apparently, if you'll seated at the table,
the correct way to eat a banana is to peel it,
then use a fork to cut the flesh into bite-sized pieces.
In other, more informal situations,
we recommend peeling bit by bit
and breaking bite-sized bits of the banana off.
- That's not the way to do it, is it?
Do you always see on the internet
that you're supposed to eat bananas upside down, aren't you?
'Cause that's a way that monkeys do it or something like that.
I always break it, I always open it in the middle.
(audience laughing)
- Do you?
- I actually do do that.
I open it in the middle and then take the banana out
and then eat it without the skin.
- Right.
- You're a psychopath.
- I think.
(audience laughing)
Hang on, do you mean you snap it in too?
- No, no, no, you get the banana
and you kind of make a little hole in the middle of it
and then you open it up and then you pull the banana out
and you eat it.
- I'm sure there are other people who eat it.
- And then you reattach the skin
to make it look like a whole banana.
You put it back on the shelf
and then you leave the supermarket.
(audience laughing)
- There's actually, Debrez has a whole section
on difficult foods.
If you go to the website and enlist all the difficult foods
to eat and so one example is grapes,
which I always thought were quite an easy food,
but a grape show off.
- Yeah.
(audience laughing)
- No, they're very strict.
They say don't pick individual grapes from a bunch.
You have to remove a small bunch from the big bunch
and then eat from that using either your fingers
or grape scissors.
(audience laughing)
- Grape scissors, I've seen those.
I've been to a cutlery collecting man's house.
(audience laughing)
- Oh no.
- He showed me his grape scissors, they're really--
- Oh wow.
- How do they differ from normal scissors?
- They do not.
(audience laughing)
- Are they quite small or?
- They're quite, yeah, they're not massive shears.
You know, they're small, yeah.
- Why?
- I struggled anyway with the my stock.
- Did he have, 'cause Debrez also says that
if you're eating oranges, then if it's semi-difficult to peel,
you should cut it in half and eat it with a teaspoon,
which I'd never considered doing at all.
- I don't think anyone does any of this stuff,
do they really?
- No.
- I have eaten a banana with a knife in fork once
and it was actually very nice.
So.
- Yeah, but that wasn't because of the way you were eating it, though.
- You know, you would have tasted the same
if it had done my psychopath layer of eating it.
- No, I'd tell you what, it made me pace myself and enjoy it.
(audience laughing)
Was there a special reason that you decided to try that?
- Yeah, it was really odd.
I was on British Airways coming back from New York
and they came and they put a banana down
and a knife in fork and they walked away and...
(audience laughing)
It's so I thought I'd better challenge accepted.
So, de Bratz also do, they've got some rules
for polite social networking.
So, one they say is, this is I'm guessing for Facebook,
think before you poke.
That's a first suggestion.
(audience laughing)
Always wait 24 hours before accepting
or removing someone as a friend.
The delay will help you gather your thoughts,
which is just great philosophy, generally, isn't it?
- 750 quid for that one.
(audience laughing)
- No, that actually is a price.
- What?
- 750 quid and it's for 13 to 16 year olds.
- No way.
We're just giving it away for free right now.
As you have got lucky, this is an absolute bargain.
- The guy who started de Bratz was called John de Bratz
and he began his career with de Bratz Parridge,
which was a buck about lords and ladies and stuff like that.
But he got into a huge argument with a guy
who actually wrote it and he went bankrupt twice
and he only managed to survive thanks to taking
a huge amount of money from his wife.
- Really?
- Which they don't teach you that in de Bratz, do they?
- They do not.
- It's encouraged.
(audience laughing)
- They're very strong on Perridge, though,
and actually one of them is frequently asked questions.
One of the most frequent questions that's written
into de Bratz is like how to address the royal family
as if really anyone's coming up against them personally.
But they've got very detailed instructions
as to how you address them.
And apparently, if you're writing to,
so if you're writing to the queen,
then you have to open your letter with,
may it please your majesty,
and then you have to begin the next sentence
with with my humble duty.
But then if you're writing to other members,
it tells you all the initials
that have to come after everyone's name.
So let's say you're writing the Prince of Wales,
if you're writing to Prince Charles,
you have to say on the envelope to his,
that's her royal hyenas, and then on a new line,
you say, for example, the Prince of Wales,
and then these are the initials that offer's name,
KGKT, GCB, O-M-A-K-C-D-Q-S-O-P-C,
that's all the things he is.
It's so great. - Wow.
- GCB is, he's a great master in principal night
of the most honorable order of the bath,
and that's about how they used to bathe nights.
So when you were knighted in medieval times,
you had a bath first thing you did,
and then if you're a great master
of the most honorable order of the bath,
it's about bathing when you become a knight.
Isn't that cool? - That's very cool, yeah.
- He's the only great master.
- Good for him. - Well done.
(audience laughing)
- I was looking up general etiquette things.
- Yes, yes.
- There's a book by an author called Henry Hitchens,
and it's called Sorry,
and it's about English people and their manners,
and he just lists advice from throughout the ages
of etiquette varies, obviously,
depending on your society.
So, for example, in the 15th century,
the Duke of Gloucester's Usher advised
that one should not scratch one's codpiece in public.
(audience laughing)
I'm a sayingable.
Erasmus, the medieval writer,
advised that one should cough to disguise a fart.
(audience laughing)
- Erasmus actually, that book that he wrote,
it was about children's etiquette, wasn't it?
And it was the best-selling book in all of England
in the 16th century apart from the Bible.
- No way.
- And some of the other things he said was,
do not be afraid of vomiting.
It is not vomiting, but holding the vomiting
in your throat that is foul.
- I disagree strongly with that, actually.
(audience laughing)
- If you cannot swallow a piece of food,
turn around discreetly and throw it somewhere.
(audience laughing)
- Better don't teach that when you're 650 quink calls,
I don't know.
- Actually, weirdly, did Brett say the opposite
so how times have changed?
They say a dinner party,
when encountering an unexpected piece of gristle
or something that may be chewed to no avail,
it is polite to be brave and try and swallow it anyway.
(audience laughing)
- Children troke all things.
- Well, you know you got a suffer for etiquette.
- I'd love to see the difference between Erasmus
and the Brett's, that would be really awesome.
Another one, do not move back and forth on your chair.
Whoever does that gives the impression
of constantly breaking or trying to break wind.
(audience laughing)
- Well James.
- Hey, we need to wrap up very soon.
You guys got anything for you to do?
- In Victorian times, women were advised to pinch their fingers
so the ends would be nice and pointy.
(audience laughing)
- Do they have what their fingers made of a plasticine?
- I guess so.
- It was just a thought you meant to have nice pointy ends
to fingers, nice and tapering, not sort of flat cut off fingers.
And one writer said that if your fingers are bad,
your bad fingers, then just pinch them lots of times
all the time.
- Oh, I know.
- And women were advised, and this is a thing
that happens today, I believe, to fill all gloves with cream
and then put on the old gloves full of cream,
and then you get a bed at night.
And that's the thing that still happens.
- No, it doesn't happen now.
- No, does anyone hear it?
Someone said yes.
- Yeah, see all women's voices.
This is a conspiracy, there's a cap from men.
No men know about this.
- Guys, what kind of cream is it?
Like, I think just any double cream.
(all laughing)
This is a thing, I talk my girlfriend about this,
and she said, Andy, we all do this all the time.
You've never paid any attention to anything.
Why do you think the bed is full of cream every morning?
(all laughing)
- I've never heard of it, but I'd be so creeped out
if my partner was wearing gloves in bed, so.
- I was so weird.
I think they're just on a murder or something.
(all laughing)
- That is quite something, isn't it?
But then you're just gonna have nice hands,
but what about the rest of your body?
You should really be wearing a full body suit.
- Yes, I'm covering it all in cream.
- With a snorkel to keep you breathing.
(all laughing)
- Okay, that is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland.
Andy.
- @AndruhondaM.
- James.
- @JamesHarkin and Chazinski.
- You can email podcast@kyway.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is at @nosuchthing or you can go to our Facebook account
or nosuchthingasaffish.com.
It's our website.
We have everything up there from tickets for upcoming tour dates.
We have our book link and all previous episodes
that we've ever done.
And also, just quickly, we ask you guys in this audience tonight
to send us in your favorite fact.
We've picked a winner and the winner is gonna get a copy
of our cassette.
So we have the fact here.
- The fact is from Douglas Wood and the fact is this,
at the first robot Olympics held in 1990 in Glasgow,
the English competitor was disqualified from the climbing event
because of inappropriate behavior in front of children.
(audience laughing)
It tried to mount the Russian robot.
(audience cheering)
- So we're gonna be out of the back.
Come and say hi if you wanna cassette.
Please do get one.
That's all from us.
Thank you so much.
We'll be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you again.
Goodbye.
(audience cheering)
(upbeat music)