[music]
Hey everybody, Dan and Andy here.
Just wanted to let you know our special guest on this week's fish
is none other than old friend of the podcast,
your friend of mine, Alex Bell.
That's right, Alex has returned.
I mean he hasn't been on for ages,
but he has been there in the background the whole time.
Anytime you hear a song or a noise.
Shadowy, the spider master.
But now he's back, he's funnier than ever.
We can't wait for you to hear it.
He's brilliant, it's gonna be great.
So now I guess with no further ado,
let's get on with the only podcast
any of us has ever made or will ever make.
Right Dan?
Ah, actually I've got a bit of news.
What?
Yeah, I don't want this to be a shock,
but I've actually launched a new podcast.
Alright, what's it called?
It's called We Can Be Weirdos.
Oh, I see, and I guess it's just about solid facts though, right?
It's about stuff with a strong, evidential base.
Well, let's ignore that question quickly
and focus on what the show is about.
So it's a weekly show where I sit down with someone remarkable
and I try and find out all the weird stuff
that they believe in and all the weird stuff
they do in their life.
So it features everyone from British museum curators
like Irving Finkel who told me stuff about how he sits on buses
and stares at the back of people's head
trying to make them turn around.
It's got a Betsy Cameron who used to be a part
of the Children of God cult but who escaped
and wrote a fascinating memoir about it.
There's Steve Feltham who is the Guinness World Record
for the longest continuous search for the Loch Ness Monster.
Dan Aykroyd is coming on.
There's so many amazing guests
and it's a weekly show where I ask them to tell me
about every single weird belief that they have.
- That's right.
And guys, the rest of us know
how hard Dan's been working on this.
It sounds absolutely great.
It's called We Can Be Weirdos.
Give it a go wherever you get your podcasts now.
And we should say it's all based on Dan's book,
The Theory of Everything Else,
which is out now in the UK in paperback
and it's out in North America on the 27th of June.
Louis Theroux himself has called it
totally compelling and utterly bizarre.
- That's right.
- So it would mean the world to me
if you all fish listeners would subscribe to it,
follow it, give it a listen
and also pick up a copy of my book
and okay, okay, okay, back to the actual good podcast.
Here we go.
On with the show.
On with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of Know Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Alex Bell.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one and that is Alex.
- My fact this week is that when the founder
of the budget supermarket chain Aldi
was kidnapped in the 1970s,
he successfully negotiated a discount off his own ransom.
- Brilliant.
Did he claim that he was going off?
And that result, he had a yellow sticker on him, brilliant.
- Oh, he's such a good idea.
So this guy is called Theo Albrecht.
He founded Aldi with his brother Carl.
And they've got quite an interesting story
in how they founded the supermarket.
But in the 1970s, when he was one of the richest people
in the world, he was kidnapped at gunpoint
by a convicted burglar called Paul Cron.
- Diamond Paul. - Nick was Diamond, yeah.
And his crooked lawyer, apparently,
who had gambling debts called Heinz Joachim Ollenberg.
- Joachim. - Joachim Diamond Paul.
- Home alone, wet bandits, kind of duo.
- And yeah.
- They kidnapped him for 17 days and held him in an office.
- What, cupboard, wasn't he?
- Yeah, he was in a cupboard, he was in a cupboard.
And apparently his appearance was so nondescript
and he sort of wore quite kind of cheap suits
because he was as money pinching
as his discount supermarket reputation suggests.
They had to ask him for ID to check
that they definitely kidnapped a billionaire.
- The thing was that he didn't do any interviews,
did he, or anything like that, right?
He was really not very well known at the time.
I read a US newspaper article from the week
when he got kidnapped and they described him
as West Germany's least known millionaire.
- Yeah, wow. - So no one knew
what he looked like, he was just a name.
- So he was kept for 17 days.
He negotiates a cheaper ransom and they agreed to it.
A bishop comes and delivers it.
- The Bishop of Essen. - Yeah.
- Which is the city that they were from.
- Yeah. - I guess it's where
they lived at the time.
- But I didn't realize that was a bishop's responsibility
to do it. - He mediated.
Yeah, I mean, what a call to get as the bishop.
You must never get that.
- No.
- But then he was, isn't he the one who left the money?
- Yes. - The actual--
- Yeah, he did the handover.
He pays the cash. - Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
- But then, and I think Albrecht stayed with him
for 24 hours afterwards, stayed with the bishop.
- Why?
- Because the police were kept out of it completely
because the family didn't want the police involved
'cause they thought he might be in danger.
And the kidnappers said they wanted
the 24 hour period to get away.
And so they said, okay, well he'll stay with the bishop
for 24 hours and then after that time, we'll let him go
and he'll tell the police who he's seen and stuff.
- Okay, so he gets out, the bishop,
they get these 24 hours and--
- They catch them as well.
- And they catch them, yeah, that's right.
- And they only get half the money back.
- And to the dying day of the two guys,
they never recovered the missing 3.5 million.
- And they died within a month of each other.
- How weird is that?
'Cause they were about 20 years different in age.
- That's so romantic.
- No, it was within six years, I think.
- Within a decade, six, yeah.
- Oh, yep.
- Almost 87, the other was 93.
- But no, so after he gets let out,
Theo goes even more recluse.
He goes into total lockdown.
No photographs are gonna be taken of him evermore.
He is, every time he gets into a car,
it's an armored car.
A different route every single day
when he's going into his office.
If he's staying somewhere,
he goes and he finds the exits immediately.
So it's obviously a huge trauma on this experience.
- But he also--
- Sorry, I know one thing
that will make you interested in him, especially Dan,
which is that Forbes described the brothers,
the Old Brecht brothers, Theo and Carl,
who co-founded Aldi,
described them as more elusive than the Yeti.
- Ooh.
- I'm pretty sure like the Yeti doesn't have like a--
- An armored car.
- A business trail, like a paper trail.
He's not registered with the company's house.
(all laughing)
- Also, that doesn't make me more interested.
If he was a Yeti hunter, that's interesting.
Just saying the word Yeti in a sentence
doesn't immediately mean--
- You've got a higher threshold for interesting--
- I do. - Okay, okay.
- I think my favorite bit of this whole story
was that after the whole ordeal,
Alde Brecht went to court to try and claim the money
that was paid as the ransom
as a tax-aductible business expense,
which is brilliant.
I don't think he was successful,
but like, that's so cool.
- I think you can still do that, certainly in some places.
- If you have a good accountant,
'cause I think it's in America, it's been done.
- In America for sure, yeah, famously Yeti.
- I guess it's-- - John Paul Yeti.
- It is a business expense, isn't it?
- Yeah. - Well, or is it?
- If the person who is abducted
is the CEO of the company,
then it's to do with the company.
I think that's the argument.
- His brother Carl stumped up a lot of money
for that as well, the ransom.
He was part of it.
But yeah, I love how much the Alde Brecht brothers
were really sort of stingy with their cash.
- They're brilliant.
I think Theo was the one who,
they used to approve all the designs for all the shops,
and there was one where he was given the plans,
and he said, "The plans are fine,
"but the paper you printed on is too thick.
"Print it on thinner, cheaper paper."
- He used to famously use pencils right down to the end.
Like, when you see people with the pencil meets the rubber,
he would be using pencils like that,
and if he walked into the office of the Alde officers
and he saw that the lights were on,
but he could see that you could see
in a room without the lights,
he'd go around turning off all the lights.
- It's so screechy, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- I did read one article that said,
"He and his brother were the first people
"to ever turn off the lights in the room
"because they were worried that they were wasting electricity."
What a thing to invent.
- That's great.
- I thought I was thinking about the timing.
- Yeah, exactly.
- He invented being a dad.
- Yeah.
- The timing almost works.
- That's really funny.
I think the story is very interesting
'cause they founded it together, didn't they?
They founded Alde together.
- Yeah, their mother ran a shop, like, I mean,
like, so they took over the shop as part of their journey,
but she was the one who really started there.
I think she does a little bit of credit.
- Yeah, you're right, that's a good point.
And then actually they were dragoon into helping their mum
because their father, he's been a coal miner
and he got emphysema, so he couldn't really work,
so they had to support the family.
But anyway, they fell out
over whether or not they should sell cigarettes
in their shops, and I think Theo said we should
and Kyle said we shouldn't.
- And I think it was for shoplifting reasons.
- Yeah.
- I think, yeah, one thought that--
- They didn't care about the health reasons.
- It was its dinginess as well.
- Despite their father having emphysema,
they were, it was more about the deal.
- Is that so interesting?
Okay, and then they had this thing, the Alde Equator.
- Yeah, that's incredible.
- Where they divided Germany top to bottom
and north was Theo's territory.
- Not with any kind of wall, we should say, like--
- So many people died crossing the Alde Equator.
(all laughing)
- People were desperately trying to get to those.
- 'Cause they did, so this was 1961,
and they had about 300 Aldes all over the country,
and that's what got split up between them.
And if you look at the logos,
they are different colors across the Alde Equator,
and so they are definitely two different operations
that are going on.
- Ironically, if you were kidnapped in Germany,
you could use that to work out
which half of the country you were in.
- Yes!
- Oh my God, yeah.
- What a brilliant idea.
- There's still different companies now, aren't they?
- Mm-hmm.
- Alde Nord and Alde Sud.
- Yeah, that's right.
- And I think, which ones do we have?
We have Alde Nord.
- No, British Alde Sud.
- No, we have Alde Sud.
- British Alde Sud, yeah, yeah.
- And in America, they have them both,
but one of them's called Trader Joe's.
- Wow.
- Yeah, that's what Trader Joe is, I never realized, yeah.
And Alde itself is the name Alde that we said,
it's a poor mancher of Albrecht discount.
- Discount.
(all laughing)
- I was trying to remember what the German version was.
- His brother came up with that, didn't he?
(all laughing)
- Distingy cunt.
- The two of us is a real-called discount adaptor, right?
(all laughing)
- Imagine, like, big billboards with them kind of.
Over the border.
(all laughing)
- I'm with discount, I'm with discount, yeah.
- I think they liked each other.
I think they got on perfectly well.
They just disagreed over this.
- I think it was amicable, yeah, I think it was amicable, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- But I've never read into Alde before.
I've been to Alde many times.
God damn it, I love it so much.
I don't want to treat this as an advert,
but what an operation.
Well, okay, so for example,
they don't stock as many items as a regular supermarket will,
and they've never compromised on that.
It's grown ever so slightly,
but an average supermarket might have something
like 200,000 different items,
whereas they might have 2,000 items.
It has grown since the earlier days
when it came to Britain.
But one of the things was everyone who was working there
was required to memorize the price
of every single item in the shop, so every 2,000 item,
which meant that there was a thing that's known as Alde panic,
which is when you get to the checkout,
the panic is I can't pack my bags as quickly
as they're running the stuff through the till.
So you get a bit worried.
- And that's really common now,
'cause they're so fast at scanning.
- Well, here's the thing.
The reason they're so fast at scanning these days,
'cause this is another Alde innovation,
is if you buy a product from any supermarket,
you got a barcode, you get there,
the person's looking around for the barcode.
If you look on Alde products that are specifically Alde,
they print the barcode all over it,
so no matter where you turn the product,
it scans exactly, boop, and it's right through.
- Yeah, 'cause they also open, I think in the '50s,
the first self-service grocery store in Germany.
But in those days, self-service meant you go in
and get stuff off the shelves and bring it to the checkout,
as opposed to giving your list to a clerk
who were going to get it for you.
So that must have been a huge efficiency.
- And they brought in shopping trolleys.
And I think they were the first company
to bring in the shopping trolleys
where you had to put a coin in.
- That's what they say, yeah.
- I read an article with the communications director at Alde,
and he said, "We're always amazed
by the pay it forward spirit
that happens in our parking lots."
And apparently they reckon that in Germany, at least,
people will pay for the next person's trolley.
And I just, I've never seen that happen
in my entire life in the UK.
- I'd go around checking to see if anyone's left a quid.
I could lose an hour or two sometimes
if you've got a single, you know.
- I literally only have one quid that I keep in my car
for that thing,
as I don't really use cash these days, right?
- Yeah, right.
- Do you keep it on a string?
(all laughing)
'Cause you're sounding a bit like Theodore Albrecht.
- A bit like, I can't say.
- They got big in Germany
because they started looking at the models
of what was happening in America with grocery stores.
And so there was a Memphis grocer
that was called Pigley Wiggly.
So it was Pigley Wiggly, Hogley Wogley,
and Handy Andy was the last one.
These were all of the things going on
in America at the time.
And yeah, so they became Germany's--
- So Pigley Wiggly was famously the first place
that would let you take things off the shelves
and put them in your trolley
and then pay for them afterwards.
- Exactly.
- And I'm not sure if we said it here,
we might not have done,
but basically people didn't want to do it
'cause they felt like they were shoplifting.
- Well, I feel like that with the new Amazon fresh tools
when you walk in and you scan.
- Yeah, but you go and wear a motorbike helmet, don't you?
- You don't scan anything and you're shouting
and all of the baseball bat.
- I actually was gonna kidnap Jeff Bezos,
but he just walked into my house, into my cupboard.
Two weeks later, they put loads of money in my cupboard.
It was perfect.
- So when you go to Audi, there's always,
and I didn't realize this was a big thing,
but in the middle of Audi,
there's always this weird aisle
where it's just random stuff.
- The room of requirement is sort of like,
every time it's different.
It's huge. - It's so bizarre.
So the middle aisle and it's sort of famous
amongst online people.
There's Twitter accounts where what random thing
have you found in the middle aisle?
Yeah, it's massive.
Yeah, so everything from motion activated,
toilet bowl, night lights, you know,
it's just randomly to traffic cones.
- It feels like it fell off the back of the lorry,
kind of vibe.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Which definitely is not the case.
- Sorry, they definitely did do that, obviously.
- No, 'cause I remember like,
you would always get like a flyer through the post
and it would tell you what was gonna be
in the middle aisle in the next month or so.
- Oh, really?
- You know that there was gonna be a canoe there
and you'd be like, oh, shit, we gotta get there
on the second Tuesday.
Well, they only have a certain amount.
And so if it was something really cool,
everyone in the town would want to get there
as quickly as possible together.
- And they never restock ever, so it's just that.
It's like a one flash sale.
- It gets called the Isle of Shite.
- That's it.
(laughing)
- It's very good.
- Yeah, it's very good.
- One other thing on German kidnapping.
- Oh, yeah.
- I think German.
Do you know about the Pied Piper of Hamlin?
- Yeah.
- He famously kidnapped all the children of Hamlin.
- I never thought of it that way.
- Ah.
- I thought he got rid of the rats.
- And the parents didn't pay him?
- Yeah, so then he did the same thing.
He played his pipe and led them.
He basically hypnotized children to come with him.
- Oh, yeah.
- So there's a question of like consent, really.
- Yeah, it does sound like there is.
- There's no question.
There was no consent.
Like, basically he took all the children out of the town
'cause they didn't pay his bills.
- So he was fictional.
- Well, there was an entry in Hamlin town records
dating to 1384 that says that it is 100 years
since our children left.
And that fits in with the date of when people said
this happened which was in 1284.
And it supposedly happened on the 26th of June,
the day of St. John and St. Paul.
And 130 children in Hamlin disappeared.
And that's what the story is based on.
- Was there a day of St. George and St. Ringo as well?
(laughing)
- But we now have theories as to what the Pied Piper was.
So we think that possibly the Pied Piper story
is a fictional account of something that actually happened.
And the children did go missing
and did get taken by someone.
Can you guess what the actual job
of the real life Pied Piper probably was?
- Oh, okay.
- Are we gonna, is this guessable from?
- School bus driver.
- School bus, that's really good.
I mean, the dates don't quite work for school buses.
1284.
- I've got it, I've got it.
- It's called cart driver.
- Swine herd.
- Dresses the children up as pigs, really.
- No, that's not what the theory says.
- Okay, how was he one of the wiggles then?
(laughing)
- Aldi trolley manager at the Minwood Free Trollies.
- Well, according to most theories at the moment,
he could have been a recruitment consultant.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- I followed that in the street.
I find it so beguiling.
- These children were now working like Deloitte.
(laughing)
- There was an economic depression around that time
and a lot of the youth of various towns
were taken out of German sort of villages
and taken to the bigger areas of Western Europe.
And they had locators or recruiters
that would go around these towns
and try and bring the youth out there
to work in different places.
And so there's one possibility
that the Piper story is based on a recruitment consultant.
- Wow.
- Well, they all got sort of free mugs.
(laughing)
- Came back later with those cool wireless phone headsets.
- Pages.
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number two, that is Andy.
- My fact is that the world's largest collection
of model trains doesn't fit on standard model train tracks.
(laughing)
- I'm really pleased you added the word standard in there
'cause it's a big discussion.
- Yeah, we had a big email chat about this.
No, but I just got to say,
Alex has got in front of him actual like,
this is the weirdest bit of research I've seen ever said.
- I'm not going to go into it, don't worry.
- I'm going to say the basic fact
and then we'll have the argument.
- Yeah.
- By the way, thank you to Neil Gibson
who sent in this fact,
who didn't realize the chaos he was unleashing
in our previously happy team.
This is something that's from the National Rail Museum
in York.
They have a collection of 610 model railway vehicles
all made by the same man
who was called James Peale Richards, 1902 to '99.
And he was incredibly devoted to detail and accuracy
and he thought he could get his models more accurate
if you made them to a 33 millimeter gauge.
So the gauge is the distance between the two train tracks
and the normal gauge for model trains is 32 millimeters
and they're not compatible
with the vast majority of model railway lines
and even the National Rail Museum don't have a layout
where they can put these trains on a train track.
- Yeah.
- So I just think it's very sweet fact, I think.
- I don't want to make this fact even more contentious
but I have a feeling it was 612, not 610.
What did you guys read?
Did you maybe forgive me for a fractional rounding?
- The idea is a lot of these model trains,
you take anything that's one foot long
and you make it seven millimeters long
and you do the same for everything else
in all the trains, right?
Now, if you do that, then you get your gauge
to be exactly 33 millimeters to a 0.01 of a millimeter.
So it's pretty much 33 millimeters
but historically they've always had 32 millimeter gauges.
And so all the other trains that you would have
are slightly not exact.
- That's like the Hornby standard for example.
- The Hornby standard, yeah.
- The track you'll find is that width.
- A lot of them, it's called the O gauge.
But basically he decided,
well, I want mine to be exactly right
so I'm gonna get this one millimeter difference
even though I won't be able to go on hardly any tracks.
I'm gonna make it because I want it to be perfect.
- Yeah, he's a hero.
Did he make his own tracks?
He must have, right?
- I think as I went there and I had an amazing two days,
I stayed up at night.
(laughing)
- Did you, seriously?
- Was there a sleeper train in the...
(laughing)
- That was so great.
- Alex Krammick, one finger into the sleeper train.
(laughing)
- No, because they have actual other stuff,
they don't just have model,
they have actual trains there and all sorts of that.
No, it's an amazing, and I remember seeing them,
they've got this fantastic,
I think it's called an open archive
where they've got all this stuff that they can't,
they don't really have room to sort of display
in proper museum, just like thrown on the shelves
and sort of displays, you can see it.
And I remember also seeing they've got scale models
of the Queen Victoria's Royal train,
which is all sort of entirely plush inside
with a velvet upholstered toilet and things like that.
- In miniature?
- Yeah, yeah, this is all miniature.
When they were designing and building the train,
the actual full-on steam trains,
they used to make scale models of the steam trains
that are about, I'd say like a foot wide
and several feet long,
that were full-on working models to check that they worked
and they were all kind of the right size.
So they have these really stonking great models
of like working steam trains.
They've also got, you've mentioned it before on the podcast,
there's a massive train set
that was used to train signal operators.
So was the train set,
but the fun of the train set
was like all about the signals and not the trains.
- So can I ask, Alex,
did you see the entire collection
of J.P. Richards' trains when you were there?
- Well, I don't know because there's loads on the wall.
I remember them, they're all stacked up on the wall.
- You've seen them, 'cause they're all there.
- But I don't know if I saw 610.
- What's really interesting is that J.P. Richards
never saw the entire collection himself, we think.
And that's because he always kept them in his home
where most of them were in boxes.
So they were never all out at the same time.
And when he donated them to the museum,
he was really, really sick.
It was just before he died.
He was too ill to travel.
So when it was on display, he never got to see it.
So he actually never saw his entire collection on display.
- I'm really sad about that, 'cause what a hero,
what a great guy, I love it.
- The collection is still growing,
but actually I should quickly say thank you
to my friend Chris Valkoinen who is the associate archivist
at the National Rail Museum,
who sent me loads of stuff for this, absolutely brilliant.
But yeah, the collection is still growing
'cause a lot of his wagons weren't quite finished
when he got there.
So he left them to other people to finish them.
'Cause he wanted the entirety of the train system
of the London and Northwestern trains.
- Well, that's what we all wanna see, really, isn't it?
- Between 1902 and 1944.
So he wanted everything.
And they weren't all exactly done at that time.
So some people are still doing them now.
They're still kind of making them better and better.
- It is the most impressive thing
when you see the detail that someone goes into
to recreating an area, 'cause you make,
it's not, these aren't things you buy from the shop.
You create the buildings and you create,
and this is like when you're making a whole landscape,
so the tracks, the trees, the buildings around it.
I've only ever played with two model train sets before.
- Oh yeah.
- And they belonged to Eddie Izzard.
So.
- Plank.
- Plank drop.
- No, no, no.
- Trust you, you'd have a celebrity train set anecdote.
- This is not, it's not what it sounds like.
So every time we go to Bexhill on C,
which is, my family goes there a lot.
I always take my boys to the Bexhill Museum
and inside is Eddie Izzard's childhood model train set
that her father had built when Eddie's brother was born,
started building it then.
And then Eddie's mother got a bit ill
and eventually she passed away.
And part of the project of keeping themselves busy
from the sort of, you know, the horrible depression of it all
was to continue building this train set.
So you can go and press buttons
and it sends two trains around
and it's where Eddie's dad worked.
You can see the train he used to get into London
and it shows all the buildings around
and they've commissioned all of Bexhill on C
as a train set as well.
Eddie's kind of put money into that
and you press buttons and it goes around.
It snows.
- I love that.
- It's incredible.
Did you guys read about Simon George?
- No, no, no.
- Simon George is a model railway fan.
Currently, currently modeling and making huge sets.
So in 2021, he had just made a model railway
which was really big, was 61 meters.
And it was a model of a specific line
from where he'd grown up in the 80s.
It was the Calder Valley, lots of coal fired trains.
And it's one of Britain's biggest,
if not the biggest model trains set.
Really impressive.
Spent eight years working on it.
And he met someone.
He met his girlfriend while he was making it.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- That is amazing.
- This is the thing.
- Well, wait a minute.
Okay, fun.
- So he was interviewed about it.
And he said, when I first met her,
she didn't know I was building this.
And what had happened was
it wasn't in his home, this train that he was building.
He'd leased a mill
'cause it had this enormous basement, right?
- So, and he said, okay,
she knew I leased a mill with a huge basement, Simon said.
But I kind of led her to believe I was a wine merchant
because that sounded cooler than building a model railway.
- I'm just imagining the discussion that he had
when he said, now we've been getting on very well.
I think there could be something here.
I need to tell you that the basement in the mill,
I've not let you go in.
It's not a wine collection.
- What was she a thought?
- She turned up unannounced at his work one day.
She wanted to surprise him.
And she turned up to his wine merchant.
- Oh my God.
- What did he do?
- Don't come in, I'm whanking.
(all laughing)
There are loads of bodies down here, don't worry.
- This is where I keep a family locked up, come on.
(all laughing)
- He said, she wondered where all the wine was,
but actually she really appreciated the detail
and the artistic element.
- Very, very cool.
- Herman Gring, the Nazi, is also enthusiastic.
- Who's Herman Gring, not the Nazi?
(all laughing)
- I don't think there's any others out there.
He was an enthusiastic--
- No.
- Yeah, Nazis love trains.
They love models, obviously.
You know that famous big third Reich one.
But--
- No, sorry.
Again, Alex, you spent two days in the National Royal Museum.
- There's nothing to do with train models.
No, no, sorry.
That's a totally, totally off topic.
But--
- Did they have a big model?
- The Hitler commissioned a huge model
of what the center of Berlin was going to look like.
And it's a really horrible, scary model that still exists.
You can go see it there.
- Okay, right.
- And it's really bizarre and interesting.
But I think that whole element of control from afar,
you know the kind of--
- You're saying Gring did the trains.
- Gring had two train sets, just like Eddie is odd.
One in the, no, just like, you've seen trains.
Wait, you said you've seen two train sets in your life.
- No, played with it twice.
- Played with it twice.
- You played with it twice.
- Both of them were Eddie's, yeah.
- Right, so okay, so Herman Gring had one train set
in his attic and one in his basement.
- Oh, yeah.
- Okay.
- And there are pictures of it.
And they're really, it's pretty extensive,
is that he lived, he lives in a big old Nazi house
and had a huge attic and a massive basement.
And there's a rumor that you can sort of maybe
see evidence for in the pictures that there was,
there were wires that went over the one in the attic
that planes went across and you could drop little bombs
out of the planes.
- Okay, right.
- Which is good fun.
- Wow, they originated in Germany,
didn't they, model railways, basically.
There was a company called Marklin
and they'd be making toys and stuff.
But they mostly made dolls houses.
The idea is you make a doll's house
and you sell them the house.
And then they have to buy the dolls to go inside
and they have to buy the cookers and they have to buy
the chairs and they have to buy all the bits and pieces.
And they wanted something that boys would like.
- How are the dolls gonna get to work?
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- And they just thought, well, by doing the railways,
then we can sell the railway tracks,
but then we can sell the stock
and we can sell the little bushes that go,
I don't know, I've never played with them.
- There's another German connection,
which is maybe the earliest ever model train
belonged to the poet Goethe.
- Did it? - Wow.
- Clang yourself, mate.
(all laughing)
- This is from 1829, it's six years before Germany
had even a railway, a steam railway of its own.
- Wow.
- Some English well-wishers gave him a tiny, tiny model
of Stevenson's rocket, the earliest steam railway engine.
I think the earliest steam railway engine.
And it came with a set of wagons and rails
and Goethe put it on his desk.
I think he might have given it to his grandchildren
at the time, 'cause he was an old man by that point.
- Yeah, cool. - Wow.
Do you wanna hear an incredibly, well, so, okay.
Here's a fact about Moloroas.
I'm just gonna tell you what. - Right.
- Okay. - That's what we're all here for.
(both laughing)
- What a change of topic.
- I know what's about to happen.
- So, you know how you use different things to represent.
So you might use a coffee stirrer as a piece of fencing.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Like things from our world.
- Oh, okay, yeah. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I see, yeah. - Okay.
- You could use a marble as a boulder, for instance.
- Yeah, you paint it or whatever, yeah, yeah, exactly.
Okay, so do you know what they use to make coal?
- Okay, so it's gotta be something that looks like coal,
but is much smaller. - Yeah, mm.
But maybe it's not the same color,
but you could paint it black, right?
- Is it not just small bits of coal?
- They use coal. (both laughing)
- Oh my God.
- I hit it with a hammer and grinded it up small.
- What? (both laughing)
- Well, it's definitely a fact.
- Is this by any chance the fact
that you messaged us saying,
"I just told my wife a fact,"
and she said, "That's the dullest thing
"you've ever said in your life?"
- That's the fact.
She just said, "Stop talking."
(both laughing)
- We found it so interesting, and it's so boring.
- She took off her eye with this condition.
(both laughing)
- Amazing, Andy, great fact.
- Great fact. - Thank you.
Do you know the really tragic thing?
- We last talked about "Model Railways" four years ago.
I looked through my notes for that show.
It was in there. (both laughing)
- So, probably the most famous model railways in the world
have to be the ones that we see in "Thomas the Tank Engine."
"Thomas the Tank Engine."
I mean, that's globally the biggest, most famous,
and just a cool connection.
So, there is famously the Fat Controller,
who's now been renamed Sir Topham Hatt.
- He was always called. - He was always his real name.
- Yeah, but they kind of phased out the Fat Controller.
He's in the cartoons.
He's back to Sir Topham Hatt.
And we know someone who was the real-life Sir Topham Hatt.
- Sir Topham Hatt. - Yeah.
- What do you mean that's in the vice?
- No, so they used to have offices for "Thomas the Tank Engine."
When children wrote in,
they had an official Sir Topham Hatt,
who would write letters back to the children.
And we know that person.
They've been on "Fish," they've been on "Fish."
- Is it Craig Glenday? - Yes, Craig Glenday,
Editor-in-Chief for the Guinness World Records.
- Wow. - Okay, that's bizarre.
When I was tiny, I wrote to Sir Topham Hatt.
- No. - And I got a letter back.
- Did you? - Oh, him.
- It's just small coal.
You're a really annoying child.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is James.
Okay, my fact this week is that in 1760,
a book was publicly burned in Switzerland
because it claimed that William Tell did not exist.
- Is that a game? - Yeah.
- Ah. - 'Cause I sort of think he did.
I sort of think he did. - Oh, you're wrong.
- Well, yeah, yeah. - Is it?
- Well, publicly burned me then. - Is it like the Pied Piper,
and he was just like a management consultant?
- No, he's less historical than the Pied Piper, I would say.
He was part of the foundation myth
of the country of Switzerland, basically.
- Yeah, he's kind of Robin Hood-esque, right?
- Yeah, he is. - But in arrows to Dr. Power.
- You're spot on, you know, shot an apple off his son's head.
- That's the only thing I know.
It's the only thing, like, shot an apple off his son's head.
I didn't know any of the context.
I just knew I never questioned it.
- It was quite contrived, like, for some reason,
he ended up in a situation where they were like,
"Shoot it, or we'll kill you and your son,"
and then he did it, and then they were like,
"Well, how come you've got two arrows then?"
And he was like, "Well, if I accidentally killed my son,
"I was gonna shoot you."
- It was quite cool, wasn't it?
Because the reason this whole thing started
was he was going through this town,
which was called Altdorf, and he was...
There's a guy there who was a bailiff called Gessler,
and Gessler had this thing where he put a hat on a pole,
and it was in the center of the town,
and if you walked past the pole and you had a hat on,
you had to sort of take your hat off and be like,
"Hello, pole."
- And so we...
- I think we should say the pole represented
the immensely powerful Hapsburg Empire.
(all laughing)
- It's still weird, it's still weird.
So he goes past, doesn't take his hat off.
I guess Gessler, who's just happens to be monitoring
every passing by, sees that, says, "Hey, take your hat off."
He says, "No."
And then that's where this thing happens,
where he says, "You need to now shoot your son,"
or rather-- - Shoot the apple.
- "Shoot the apple."
(all laughing)
He says, "You gotta put your son,
"you gotta put an apple on his head,
"and you gotta shoot through it,
"and if you get it, then you guys can go free.
"If you miss, then I'm gonna kill you as well."
So it was a kind of big challenge.
- Perfectly fair challenge punishment.
- Fits the crime.
- It doesn't make any sense.
- It makes sense for someone who's put a hat on a pole
and made it so he had it up to it.
- Could he choose the apple, though?
Could he choose a very large apple, like a pink lady?
- Like the one I saw in "Me by any car dot com" that time.
(all laughing)
Honestly, I could have hit that for 200 yards.
- I know you've stopped listening, Alex,
but James has an anecdote
about this very, very big apple he once saw.
- It's actually, it's really weird to get bored
on a podcast that you're on.
You're not even listening to.
(all laughing)
- But if it had been that apple, yeah, you're right.
- Yeah, it'd be easy.
Anyway, look, like Dan said and Alex said,
"This is the story."
And then because he did the apple thing,
they said, "Okay, fine, Switzerland can exist."
And he became like the foundation myth of this country.
So everyone believed it and thought
that he was a real character.
And then there was a historian called Egidius Tudy,
and he found out that actually the earliest writing
of it was 250 years after the events.
And then they found the original Oath of Rutli,
which was for the foundation of Switzerland
for the early cantons all getting together.
And it named the three representatives
and none of them was called Tell.
None of them was called William Tell.
And so, and actually they got the date wrong as well
in the original, sort of the original story.
And so this guy called De Halle wrote a book
called William Tell at Danish Fable
and everyone in Switzerland thought this was outrageous
that he could put this in writing.
And the book was publicly burned in Altdorf Svr.
- Was he a Swiss author?
- He was a Swiss, yeah.
- And I, 'cause I sort of vaguely thought
of William Tell as a bit Robin Hoodish
as in somebody might have existed, but not really.
I didn't really think, oh, that doesn't seem
like a very significant thing to me.
But I read a piece about, it's from the Atlantic,
but it's from 1890.
And it said, just this line,
"To understand the commotion produced in Switzerland
"by cops expos, we must try to imagine
"what would be the result in the United States
"if George Washington was suddenly declared
"to be a legendary character."
- Yeah, it's a bit of that.
- It was a huge, huge moment to find out.
- It was a bit of that.
And then what happened was, everyone was like,
"Dahalla, what are you doing, this ridiculous?"
And so he said, "No, no, no, no, this was a literary exercise.
"I was just, it was just an essay I was writing
"to see if I could, it was like, you know,
"it's like coming up with two reasons,
"whether we should leave the EU or not leave the EU.
"And this was the one I decided to go with.
"It wasn't supposed to be taken seriously."
- This is the first, like, "Dude, it's a social experiment,
"like, no, you should."
- It sounds like he was petrified.
Like, it sounds like had he not renounced that,
it could have been like a Salman Rushdie kind of situation
where he might have gone into a, you know,
hiding in a cupboard kind of thing.
- They were absolutely furious.
But then obviously he'd opened the floodgates
and suddenly all the skeptics came in,
like skeptics do and said,
"Well, actually there was no organized uprising after all.
"And there's no evidence that anyone called William Tell
"had lived, let alone shot and pull off anyone's head."
And they concluded that he was probably a fictional character,
possibly based on a little bit of, you know, real life stuff.
And then someone found this old story
from the Danish sagas,
which is basically the entire story.
And that was written, you know,
hundreds and hundreds of years before William Tell
was supposed to have even existed.
And so it seems like they've taken an old story
from the sagas and they've kind of appropriated it.
- It was a story of Harold Bluetooth.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Veteran wireless technology, yeah.
Certainly the namesake of it.
Danish king of the 10th century.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And it is, like, I looked at it and it's identical.
- It is the same story.
- Yeah.
There was a play.
- Shiller.
- Shiller's play.
- Yeah.
- And then the play became an opera by Rossini
and it's just, it's such an international thing.
So it's an opera about a Swiss hero
by an Italian composer, Rossini,
based on a play by a German writer, Shiller,
which premiered in Paris.
- Brilliant.
- As in it's, all of Europe is involved in this, this, uh...
- And you know the, but you know the famous
William Tell Overture, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the.
- Yeah.
- Rossini didn't actually write that for the William Tell Opera.
- Get out.
- He was, like, running out of time
when he was writing the William Tell Opera.
(laughing)
- That's not how it works when you're running out of time,
writing music.
When it speeds up.
(laughing)
- No, he, he was running out of time
to finish the entire opera
and didn't have an Overture ready.
So he went and borrowed a pre-existing piece
from one of his earlier operas,
which was called Elizabeth, Queen of England.
So that was written almost 15 years beforehand.
- How interesting, because everything I can think of
about Elizabeth, the Queen of England,
none of the events in her life fit in with that music.
- No, it doesn't really work, does it?
Yeah.
- No, I mean, like, you can't imagine some Walter Raleigh
laying down his cloak and her going,
(humming)
- The opera was only performed in full three times.
- Yeah, 'cause it was five hours long.
- Five hours?
- Is that average time for an opera?
- No.
- No, really?
- That's very long.
- Definitely more than a few hours is fine,
but five hours is pretty long.
- Even three is.
- I've never been to one.
I always just always know that they're long.
- Especially given that some of the music was so fast.
Like, you would have thought the music would be slower
if he was gonna write it out.
- Yeah.
- There's a Herman Gring link.
I can't believe there's another Herman Gring
in the podcast.
The Nazi--
- Which Herman Gring, by the way?
- Sorry.
- The Nazi one.
- Okay, sorry, good.
Just got to clarify.
- The Nazi regime made a movie of William Tell,
and they treated the Tell story as a kind of Nazi myth,
'cause at that point, I think it was before the war,
they claimed they were liberating ethnic Germans
living in other countries who had been oppressed
by those countries, and Herman Gring's mistress
was cast in a leading role.
- Okay, right.
- That was based on Schiller's play, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- But then Hitler banned it later on,
because there was an assassination attempt on him
by a guy called Maurice Bavo, who was known
as the new William Tell.
- Yeah.
- And he thought, well, I better get rid
of all other William Tells.
- He was Swiss as well.
- Yeah.
- That's great.
- I've been in Switzerland for Swiss Independence Day
on the 1st of August.
- Oh, yeah.
- Which is when they have a lot of--
- What happened?
- It was sort of fireworks and stuff like that.
It was relatively low key.
- Lots of chocolate, probably cheese.
- Yeah, lots of chocolate.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Where did you go?
Like, specifically?
- A few different places.
- Oh.
- They sound great.
- Did you go to Bern?
I've been to Bern.
- I don't think I did go to Bern.
I was very young.
I didn't know where they got rid of all the books.
- Oh, my God.
- Brilliant.
Brilliant.
That was worth it.
- In the Bern, there's lots of, like, bears,
because a bear is the symbol of the city of Bern.
And the Appenzell Canton flag,
so the area of Switzerland called Appenzell,
has a flag which is a bear with an erection.
- Crikey.
- Yeah.
So if you look at it, it's only a tiny little red triangle.
If you can imagine, a bear rampant.
And then you've got a little red triangle
where his penis would be.
And there was a time when St. Gallen, this was in 1579.
So the Canton of St. Gallen had a printer,
and he did a calendar of all the Swiss Cantons.
And he did the Appenzell Canton flag,
but he didn't put the erection in the bear.
And this was, it kicked off.
It really, really kicked off.
They almost went to war
because they didn't have the penis on the bear.
And then it was only averted
when the printer offered abject apologies,
and St. Gallen agreed to destroy
every single copy of the calendar they could find.
- Wow.
- Again, lots of rounding things up and destroying them.
- Yeah.
- It's a very spicy time.
No wonder Switzerland is so determinedly neutral and calm today.
- Yeah, it's rewarding.
- They say they're for a very organized country.
They've got a really chaotic origin story.
- I think they've got it all out of their system.
They've only decided, I think, at a certain point.
No, we cannot stop rounding up and destroying calendars.
And things like that.
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that to make sure
that no one leaked the answer to who shot JR
on the TV show Dallas,
the production team had every main character
film a scene of them shooting JR, including JR.
It's an amazing thing.
So this is--
- We need to explain what Dallas is.
- Exactly.
So Dallas was a soap opera in America,
went on for a very long time in the 1980s it began.
And it was a show that kind of really transformed
the idea of soap having these dramatic plot twists.
And also cliffhangers and so on.
And it created the greatest cliffhanger
probably in TV history, certainly American TV history.
And it's about, it follows the escapades
of a wealthy oil tycoon's family in Dallas, Texas.
- It's the earliest succession.
- Early cheesy succession, really.
- It is.
It's about us Williamers, and the main character
is an anti-hero just like Logan Roy.
- I do think that succession is a very original idea.
And they definitely didn't rip off Dallas
in any way whatsoever, just as an ultimate opinion.
- I'm not so sure.
I think, no.
- So yeah, it's at the end of this third series,
it's the finale.
And JR, who is the character played by Larry Hagman,
is shot.
We don't know who's pulled the trigger.
And then there's a big break in the season.
And in that time, America goes slightly ballistic.
We're trying to work out.
- The world almost.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Who shot JR was basically the big question that everyone,
with t-shirts next to the, "I'm with this cunt."
- Who shot JR.
Politicians were referencing it.
- Yeah, everyone.
- And just a spoiler alert, it was Kristen.
There we go.
- What?
- But the thing is, the shooting of JR, this huge event,
maybe the biggest event in fictional TV history,
was not meant to be the end of the series.
They had already filmed an ending of the series.
And they'd had a load of events.
They'd had a deathbed murder confession.
They'd had the sectioning.
They had all sorts of, you know,
greatly written themselves into a corner kind of thing.
- Yeah.
And then they got told,
"Hey, great news. You've got four more episodes."
And they had to write four more episodes.
And then there was a big head-scratching thing
in the writer's room.
And someone said, "Why don't we just shoot the bastard?"
And then they all...
- 'Cause apparently a lot of the writers were comedians.
Or funny people at least.
Yeah, and this was, I read this in an interview
with Lorraine Desprez, who was one of the main writers.
And yeah, she said that these were really funny guys
who were trying to come up with ideas.
And almost let's shoot JR was one person going,
"Wouldn't it be funny if we did that?
'Cause wouldn't it fuck things up if we did that?"
And then they all went, "Oh, actually, that would be good."
- Well, that's...
I mean, a lot of the writers of succession
are very funny comic writers.
Jesse Armstrong, Lucy Crebel, Preble, sorry.
So, you know, it's another little link between the two, I'd say.
- But, you know, I mean, the world went crackers, didn't it?
- It did.
If you were on a plane going from Europe to America at the time,
if it was an Air France plane,
they said that they would tell anyone over the intercom
who'd shot JR, 'cause if you couldn't watch the show,
someone would radio up from the ground and say,
"It was Kristen."
And then they'd go, "We're flying at 40,000 feet."
And it was Kristen who shot JR.
- Oh, my God.
- Isn't that amazing?
- That is a huge spoiler.
There's no way of avoiding a plane-tannoy spoiler.
- That's true, although in those days,
you couldn't watch things on demand.
Like, you could have VHS'd it, or maybe...
- So, you actually kind of wanted to ask me to spoil it more.
- Actually, even in 1980, I guess,
you would have had VHS's, but only just.
- Yeah.
- Right.
- So, you had to watch it live.
If you didn't watch it live,
you were not gonna watch it.
- Exactly, you weren't gonna know.
- The Turkish parliament suspended a session
so that the legislators wouldn't be able to tune in
and wouldn't miss it.
- It really is.
- There was a really fantastic piece in Texas Monthly,
which if anyone's gonna cover who shot JR,
then you're off.
- Front page, surely.
- Absolutely.
But no, there is an amazing piece,
which is all about the madness that happened.
So, they shot at a real ranch.
You know, they shot some scenes at a real ranch,
so it was just shot in interior sets in Hollywood.
But the son of the guy who lived at the ranch,
they shot at, is called Joe Duncan.
And he says that they had people turning up
to take chips of the fence,
take pieces of rock.
- You know, they could have taken a chip of the fence
and used it as a tiny fence in a model railway.
- That's like relics.
That's mad.
- It is, yeah.
- He said, listen to this quote.
He said, "I was once 20 feet away from a guy
"who jumped to the fence and went out into the pasture
"to pick up a piece of horse manure to take home
"as a souvenir."
- That was a time before eBay.
- Yeah, as well.
- The name was Dad Shriver.
(all laughing)
- I read an article from, this was the day before
they were about to show who shot JR,
and this was in the Minneapolis Star.
And they asked some local celebs
who they thought had shot JR.
And like the head of the coach
of one of the local sports teams said,
"Oh, I don't know who shot JR,
"but there's a lot of agents of players
"who I'd like to shoot."
(all laughing)
And then, zing!
The police chief who's called Anthony Bouzard,
he said, "I'm happy to report that I've never seen
"a single minute of that goddamn program."
- Wow.
- And they asked the mayor, Don Fraser,
who's the mayor of Minneapolis.
And he said, "I haven't the foggiest who shot him.
"Are you serious?
"I've only seen one episode of that show
"and it was quite by accident."
- Wow.
- Sounds like a lifelong fan.
(all laughing)
- Just happily, they asked him.
Like, they asked someone and they got these answers
and they felt, "Well, we'll look back as well, print."
- Oh, yeah, yes, yeah, yes, that, yeah.
- The thing that I knew Dallas for,
'cause I'd never really seen it.
But I know it as a famous,
like a famous example of retconning,
where you retroactively change what happened.
So they wrote, filmed and shot and broadcast
an entire season in which a character, Bobby Ewing, died.
But this character was really popular
and they decided they wanted to spring him back.
So in order to do that, they retconned it
by the beginning of the next series.
They made the whole previous series of Dream Sequence.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- Which is hailed as one of the like,
the cheesiest and rubbish ways of like retconning.
But one of the weird continuity things was that
Dallas had a spin-off show called "Not's Landing"
that existed in the same universe.
But when they brought back Bobby Ewing
and was like, "Oh, this character never died,"
in "Not's Landing," they had referenced
the fact that Bobby had died.
So at that point, it's like a universe-splintering moment.
- It's like spider-verse into the multiverse.
- It is, yeah, exactly.
- But they were simultaneously taking into a,
like they were like keeping track of the different universes
while simultaneously wiping entire series off the face of the Earth.
- 'Cause you would think it would be easier to say,
"Oh, he didn't die, he faked his own death."
- Yes, exactly.
- Unless they showed, on camera, the funeral,
the like, open cast gear.
- I think it was like the main part
of a lot of the story of that season.
- They literally were like, "Forget that series happened."
- It's weird.
- Yeah.
- There was a real life Bobby Ewing
who lived in Texas and who owned an oil and cattle company.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
And so when this big sort of who shot JR thing was happening,
they really kind of cashed in
and you could buy JR Dolls, JR Cologne, JR Playing Cards.
And you could also buy fake certificates
for Ewing Land Oil and Cattle Company,
which was signed by Bobby Ewing, the fake Bobby Ewing.
But then the real Bobby Ewing, who lived in Texas,
sued them and said, "Well, you can't do this
'cause it makes it look like you're selling my company."
And I found out that it was settled in the end
and the real Bobby Ewing wasn't allowed
to sell any novelty items.
And it didn't say, but I assume he got a massive payout.
He must have done, right?
- Yeah, it's amazing.
- Larry Hagman, who played JR.
So obviously there's a big break for the,
when they're not shooting.
He hadn't signed his contract
when they started shooting the next series
and he held out for a long time.
- 'Cause he knows he's a star now, right?
- Yeah, everyone's talking about him.
- He wanted a huge pay rise.
He dispatched his agents to negotiate
wearing white stets and hats with the management of the show.
- And that was his kind of look, right?
- Sorry, yeah, that was his thing, yeah.
- I don't feel really stupid if I was as Asian
as I was told to do that.
- Well, they were like, "You're overreaching
with this negotiation and you want us
to go in fancy dress."
- It was worse when Mr. Blobby asked for a pay rise.
(all laughing)
- He wouldn't come in and be like, "Ah, Mr. Blobby."
- When they were trying to shoot the next series,
they had to start shooting,
but without JR being present
and having signed off his contract,
without having signed his contract.
So what they started doing,
they shot a couple of different versions.
One, they just shot JR from behind.
He just shot someone with the same hair,
which they could just like fill in later.
And then they also shot scenes
with a guy bandaged up like he did.
(all laughing)
And they said, "If we have to bring in another actor
to play JR, we can claim,
you had to have reconstructive surgery."
And now you're like, "This is so funny."
- The problem is JR was shot in the stomach.
(all laughing)
No reason.
- That's great.
Hagman, what an interesting kind of personality
he was generally.
He used to do a thing for many, many years
called "Silent Sundays."
He just didn't talk on Sundays.
- So funny.
- Yeah.
So what happened was is that--
- Religious?
Religious?
- No, no, it was part of,
he used to be on a different show called "I Dream a Genie,"
brilliant show, and during it, he had vocal problems.
And so he went to a doctor and the doctor said,
"Why don't you try not talking for a few days?"
And he thought not only did it work nicely,
but he really enjoyed the experience.
So every Sunday he thought,
"I'm just going to do this."
And didn't speak for decades.
- It's so good.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, he claimed that for 25 years,
he never spoke on a Sunday.
I think it's not 100% true.
I think he kind of cheated a fair amount, but--
- 'Cause Sunday's your birthday or--
- Yeah.
- A Lego.
- Sometimes he would go like four days in a row
without talking, wouldn't he?
And his family would hate him for it, and--
- Really?
- He kicked it, because he says that he started realizing
he was missing a lot of opportunities,
'cause he says in LA,
a lot of business is done on the weekends.
And so he said he couldn't call his agent.
He couldn't talk to them to say,
"Hey, get on the case of doing this," or--
- It's incredibly good negotiating to stay silent.
He probably should have done all this business on a Sunday.
Just sit there in silence while they just keep
upping the offer until the clock goes over to Monday.
- He's like, "Yeah, great."
- That's so funny.
- A Nazi who was a fan of Dallas?
- Great.
- Rudolph Hasse.
- Rudolph Hasse?
- No, he wasn't.
- Rudolph Hasse, yeah.
- Rudolph Hasse the Nazi?
- No, he sure was.
- Didn't we cover another person?
There was another,
there was genuinely another Rudolph Hasse.
- Really?
- Oh, he was called Rudolph Hasse,
the avocado man.
- Oh, the avocado guy.
- Yes, oh, unfortunately.
- The guy behind the house avocado was called Rudolph Hasse.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- This one was the Nazi,
and presumably train enthusiast.
- Was he still alive when--
- He watched, he's found out prison.
He used to watch it in East,
in Dallas and Dynasty with his two favorite TV shows.
- He did care.
- Did he?
- They were all bad.
(laughing)
- That is retcalling, Alex.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I am on @Sribeland, Andy--
- @AndrewHunterM.
- James.
- @JamesHarkin.
- And Alex.
- Oh, I've quit Twitter.
- Are you on, are you on Instagram?
- No.
- Are you on anything?
- Are you on Be Real?
- Be Real, no.
(laughing)
- That's good, that one.
- I'm still on Bebo.
(laughing)
- Are you on Master Done?
- No, don't be disgusting.
That sounds horrible.
What is that?
(laughing)
- Mafia-based porn sites.
- Yeah, or you can email us at podcast@Qi.com
or you can go to our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
Do check them out.
We'll be back again next week with another episode.
We will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]