[Bell]
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast this week coming to you live from Cardiff!
[Cheering]
My name is Dan Schreiber and I am sitting here with Anish Zenski, Andrew Hunter Murray and James Harkin
and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order, here we go
starting with you, James
Okay my fact this week is that the oldest football cup competition in Spain is the Coppa Del Rey
each year the winner gets the name engraved in the trophy in Comic Sans
The greatest font of them all
So I don't know if you know who invented Comic Sans, anyone? Vincent Kaner and he did it into me recently
and they asked him his favorite times at Comic Sans has been used so he said that it was in the Coppa Del Rey
in a photo album made by the Vatican and in the presentation by Surn to announce the discovery of the Higgs boson
Yes but it wasn't a Vatican, they didn't announce the new Pope in Comic Sans or anything
No, they still did that with the smoke
If you could do the smoke in Comic Sans
It was a lovely photo album that they gave to the Pope
So it was the Vatican's present to him and it was all the captions
The best way to caption a book, Comic Sans, there's no question
You know he's only ever used it once, he said it's Vincent Kaner
He said he's used Comic Sans once in his life
It was when I was having trouble changing my broadband to sky so I wrote the molestering Comic Sans complaining
saying I was disappointed, he got £10 refund
So he's sold
He's very bullish about it, he's done talks like a Ted talk or something saying
My name is Vincent Kaner and I've invented the best font in the world
And if people don't like it, he pushes back
So he said, if you love Comic Sans then you don't know anything about typography
But if you hate Comic Sans then you don't know anything about typography either
Where should you stand?
Unbiveness
I think so, yeah
And he also, he has a thing where he loves the hatred for Comic Sans as well
He really thrives off it and he collects examples of people's furies
So he was doing an interview again and he said, interesting fact
The main designer at Twitter tweeted that the most server space is used by complaints
First about airlines, second, Comic Sans, third, Justin Bieber
And then he says, so not even the Bieber can be Comic Sans
He's said it's like Bieber
He has said it's the Justin Bieber of fonts
Most people love him, but a lot of people wouldn't say it's the best music
It's fair enough, that's an controversial opinion here in Cardiff anyway
He said that he once went to the design museum in London and had to have a bodyguard
Did he help?
Well he said that, I don't know, he maybe he was joking
But just an interesting fact, his boss at Microsoft when he did that was Rob Norton
Who was the son of Mary Norton who wrote the borrower's
And also after he did Comic Sans he designed the Ministry of Sound logo
Yeah, a few minutes of trivia
There's this thing about Comic Sans that gets claimed which is that the reason it's used in schools and teachers like it is because it makes children read better
And it's very good for dyslexic children because partly because the writing is very slightly unclear
So it takes you longer to read it and the theory is that makes you remember it better
But that's been shown to be Bullocks
So teachers don't write in, there is a font called Sans Fogettica
And that was developed last year which tries to achieve what people claim Comic Sans does
And so that's the typeface, you should look at it, it's quite cool
That's quite difficult to read because it's got lots of gaps in the letters
And it just means it takes a bit more concentration to read it
But it is true that your retention of whatever's written there if it's in Sans Fogettica is much better
So is it that if you have something important you should write it in Sans Fogettica?
Yes
Because it feels like quite a risk if you're writing something important is something that people have to read like an emergency sign or an exit sign
And just saying you should write it with bits missing so people really focus on it
If it's something you have to remember in future, if it's something you need to know now then maybe just write it in Times New Roman
There's this thing just on that about how you read
So when you read I didn't know this, you're jumping all the time between the words
Otherwise when you read a story you just go once, once, once, once, once
Make the leap James, make it
Once upon, once upon, once upon
Okay, okay
No, I walked into that and that's fair
So you're doing these things called I think it's sacades or sacades
And fixations which is jumps and pauses
And if you're reading fluently, what you turns out you don't really look at the whole word when you read it
You look slightly to the left of the middle of the word you're reading
And you then sort of, you see the immediate letters around it
And then you kind of guess the other letters as you jump from one thing to another
That's so true, that is happening right now
This is live reading, welcome
Wow, yeah
So in the, in 2008, John McCain, when he was running for president, he chose Optimer as his font for his signs
Because it was the same typeface used on the Vietnam Veterans Memorial
Oh, that was his idea
Obama used Gotham, which has been described as friendly without being folksy, confident without being aloof
Wow
Which is crazy, because it's like a Gotham villain came into power right after him
Well, yeah, actually Trump's campaign font was called Accidents Grotesque
Honestly true
That's a designer having a laugh or something, isn't it? That's amazing
You know there are font detectives?
No, yeah
There are font detectives
Why? Well
So I'm looking at it as like we could possibly work out what that is
So if a font goes missing?
Yeah
If it sounds forgettiger, just completely disappeared
No, it's not quite that
It's people who determine whether documents are authentic by analyzing the fonts in them
So if the Dead Sea Scrolls are in Comic Sans, they're probably not
Exactly
So this guy Thomas Finney, he writes all these stories about his cases
And he writes them up like their Sherlock Holmes stories, it's pretty cool
So for example, in 1999, this lawyer got in touch with him because he was looking at a will
And he was trying to walk out, is this will real or hasn't been altered
And Finney discovered that the will was dated 1983, but it was printed by a high-res inkjet printer
Which wasn't on the market until 1988
Right
So, that's good
That's very good
But that's more like a printer detective, isn't it?
Yeah
Yeah, it was an extremely poor example from a wide-port photo of his career
On Dead People in France, one of the things that the campaign against Comic Sans hates the most
So this is a campaign that's set up by Holly and David Combs or Combs, so I think we've mentioned before
But they say it just doesn't look great in a lot of places
For instance, as David Combs, a place where it doesn't look great in my opinion is on a tombstone
And I have seen a number of those
So there are tombstones up there with Comic Sans?
There's actually a website you can go to called Comic Sans Criminal, where it sort of lists all of the most heinous crimes of Comic Sans
And it asks you, the reader, are you a criminal?
And it shows you examples, do you agree with this kind of thing?
And there was a, the opening hours for a sex offender's register office
Sorry, where's sex offender's register?
Yeah
Really?
Yeah, there was a defibrillator as well, which just looked really fun
There is a theory that this sort of, the whole reason that Comic Sans became huge
Is that it was a font that was launched, it was designed for this product called Microsoft Bob, which actually it ended up not being included with it
But it did get included as a package in Windows 95, I think
And this was the first time that all of us could do type setting
You know, before that you needed to go to a designer, and then this, and people have described this as a massive shift in power
You know, democratisation of type setting, it's basically like, what's his name?
Gutenberg?
Mmm
It's like the second print revolution
What you're saying is basically when you give people democratic choice, they end up doing something stupid
Well
You wouldn't have said that on our Sunderland gig, would you?
We're gonna have to move on to our next fac soon
A lot of couple of things about just other weird trophy decisions
There's a NASCAR sprint cup race that's in Mardensville, and their trophy that they give out is a grandfather clock
It's just a giant grandfather clock, that's what you win
And that started in 1964, it was given as a prize, everyone loved it so much
And it's a big thing, it's a big thing to get a grandfather clock, until you get too many
There was a guy called Dale Ehrenhardt, Jr, who took home six
Didn't really, I just kept winning and it got to the point where it's like
Do I just throw this one?
Now are you lifting that up?
Well you can't at the podium, yeah, it's a bit, it's a bit full on
I like, you know, there's a trophy that's given out, a ASCAR, ladies' day, to the owner of the winning race horse
Which is, it's like the main event, really, an ASCAR isn't it
And the trophy is presented by the queen
But that causes a problem when she wins it
So she has won it before, and Anne Prince Andrew did step in to play the role of the queen
Presenting it to the queen for that
But did he play, which queen did he play? Did he play the presenting queen?
He played the one giving the trophy, and then she played the one, well she was the one receiving the trophy
Just done a fonts, it's always good idea to choose the right fonts
Because there's a company called Bell Sheek
And they had a bag that said "My favourite colour is glitter"
But they chose the wrong fonts and it looked like "My favourite colour is Hitler"
Oh, as a couple of years ago, and then last Christmas, Iceland chose the wrong fonts and appeared to be selling ming pies
Okay, it's time for fact number two, and that is Andy
My fact is, the American product, "Trockful O Nuts" contains no nuts
It's a coffee product that the firm used to sell nuts, and then they sold nuts and coffee
And then they stopped selling the nuts, but they thought "Well the name is so good that we just have to keep the "Trockful O Nuts" name
Actually on the cans sometimes, some of the cans it says, "1920s, we sold nuts
1930s, we sold nuts and coffee. Now we don't sell nuts, we just sell coffee, but we like our name
And it has a massive disclaimer saying contains no nuts
And yet, every time the firm does any market research on why people might not buy it
People always say, "I was probably nuts at it, aren't they? It's probably nuts, this is "Trockful O Nuts"
But it's a New York product, isn't it? And if you said if there was a New Yorker near you, and you said "Trockful O Nuts"
They would say "Yeah, I know it has no nuts" and it's a big thing
It was as soon as they started going out into other cities and countries that became a problem for them
So they actually existed fine without putting it on
Yeah, they have a picture of the New York skyline as well on their packets
But they don't name it as the New York skyline
And their head of marketing said that it's nice, it worked perfectly for us
Because people in New York see the New York skyline and think this is for me
And then outside of New York, they have no idea what the New York skyline looks like
So they just think, "Yeah, fine"
And he's run focus groups all around America saying, "Would you object to something that said New York on it?"
And they all say "Yes" and then he says "Why?" and they say "Oh, I think it beats our sports teams"
And that's it, that's the reason they won't eat nuts
They're on any nuts in it
You're falling right into the gym
Have we said what it is? It's a coffee
So it started by a guy called William Black
He rented a little space under a staircase in New York
But it was underneath a drugstore
And he wasn't allowed to sell anything that was sold in the drugstore
So he didn't know what to sell, but there was a theatre opposite, so he decided to sell nuts
But then when the Great Depression struck, according to the website, nuts seemed too much of a luxury
And so he had to find something else
But he had a roasting machine for the nuts
And so he decided to go down to the docks by green coffee beans, roast them themselves and make coffee
And sandwiches, right?
And sandwiches, yes
And we spoke a few weeks ago about how sandwiches that no human-handed touched were a selling point
In those days, because it meant that it hadn't got any germs on it
And he used to sell his sandwiches, advertised as untouched by human hands
And even when they were making the sandwiches, they had to do it with tongs
So you had to spread the mayonnaise with one tong and put the ham on with another
And actually, they probably do that in cafes still, I don't know, I think, but hygiene
As I said it, I thought that doesn't sound that mad
So just sort of product names, basically
And this is a big thing, especially in America, so there's a cereal called fruit loops
But fruit is spelled F-R-O-O-T
And there's also cap and crunch with crunch berries
And these have been the subjects of repeated lawsuits from people who claimed I've been deceived
I thought this was full of fruit and really good for me
And the whole statement by judges saying things like, here's one from 2009
This court is not aware of nor has plaintiff alleged the existence of any actual fruit referred to as a crunch berry
Furthermore, the crunch berry is depicted on the box around crunchy brightly coloured cereal balls
So far as this court has been made aware, there is no such fruit growing in the wild or occurring naturally in any part of the world
You've got to be so careful though, because I red bull got sued in 2014 for the fact that they don't actually give you wings
There was a proper...
No, yeah, yeah, come on
It was a mixture of a... that was one guy who's part of the court case who said, I didn't actually grow any wings
The rest said it claims that it gives you this great energy and it gives you these boosts
And so they actually had to pay out a huge amount of money
Including $10 to every US consumer who'd bought the drinks since 2002 if they wrote in
Really, yeah
I remember though as once some sausages sold in Wales called dragon sausages that had to be taken off because they didn't contain any dragons
Is that true?
That's true, yeah
Very disappointing for the card of audience, thought you've been eating dragons all these years
There's a hair product in... I think in the US called Rogaine and it was originally called Regaine
And then the FDA, the Food and Drugs Administrator, next that, because they said you can't call it Regaine
Because obviously it doesn't work, because hair-regraith products don't work
So you don't have to change the vows
There was a tattoo artist in London whose salon was called Prick
He was called Henry Hate
And he tried to stop a nearby cactus shop from using the same name
And this guy, Henry Hate, is kind of semi-famous because he did a lot of Amy Winehouse's tattoos
And he thought that this person with a cactus shop was kind of passing off with his edgy rock and roll name
But then it went to court and court judge Melissa Clark said
"It is difficult to imagine two businesses with two less closely related activities
I think it's fair
I can imagine two things less similar than tattoos and cactuses
Like a waffle maker and then a sort of like a Rolls-Royce engine firm
And if I had a bit longer I could have come up with something really, really different
I guess they're both round, don't they? So it doesn't really work
Yeah
Well
Just on that very similar note, in 2018 rapper Dr. Dre lost a trademark case to another man called Dr. Dre
Who was written books including 20 things you might not know about the vagina
And the judge in that case said that confusion was unlikely as Dr. Dre is not a medical doctor
Nor is he qualified to provide any type of medical service
But they should get together because I would listen to a Dr. Dre rap about 20 things you might not know about
The vagina
To be honest, I think there's quite a lot of that in his rap
It's just on the famous names thing
They're in Australia at the moment, there's a pop-up burger place which a lot of people trying to not shut down but get them to change their name
They're called Pablo Escoburgers
And when you buy a burger from Pablo Escoburgers you get a fake line of white powder
It's like a garlic flower that's on top of the bun and then there's a rolled up $100 note next to it
Presumably a fake $100 note
No real?
It's real?
Yeah, fake, definitely fake
The passing off thing is quite, it's really well established, so for example, we've mentioned on the bogus before
The first ever self-service supermarket are you one way you get a basket and you go around or trolley and you go around putting things in
Going to a counter and handing over a list, the first ever of those in America was called Piggly Wiggly
And that was a fun novelty name
But it was immediately followed by another firm setting up called Hoggley Woggley
And then helpy selfie and then savey wavy
And these are all completely different firms
Do you know that the Food and Drugs Administration in America when people are coming up with names for new drugs
They run it through a whole bunch of handwriting tests, so they get those people in to write the drugs in certain types of hand-racing
To make sure that they can never be mistaken in certain handwriting for other drugs
Oh really?
That's really clever
Very clever
The letter Z appears in 18 times as often in drug names as it does in other English words
Wow
Yeah
Because it seems speedy and powerful and memorable because it's weird
So what's the drug that's got Z in it?
To Mazepam to Mazepam
Wow
You see?
Oh yeah
Well that's not really how I feel when I take it
Have you guys had a breakfast mates?
No
This was a product, this is actually just more a disastrous product than a bad name
So it was launched in 1998, it was Kellogg's breakfast mates
And it was an all-in-one package with one serving of cereal, one tiny tiny carton of milk and one plastic spoon
And it was designed for people who find normal cereal just too inconvenient and too much of a hassle in the morning
That does sound quite good idea
Yeah, so you get on the train with your breakfast mates and you just pour out your cereal into the bowl and then then...
Anyway, basically they had neglected to realise that cereal is one of the most easy things to prepare
And there was testing which went on and it showed that preparing cereal the traditional way took one second longer than breakfast mates
It adds up
Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is Chuzensky
My fact this week is that the scientist Robert Hook recorded in his diary every time he had an orgasm
So this is...
You might remember Robert Hook from school, you learn about Hook's law
I don't learn about this
Well, you actually do learn about Hook's law of elasticity which is a fail reference to this
He was a polymath, he was an unbelievably high-achieving scientist around at the same time as Newton
And he wrote extensive diaries where he recorded every detail of his life including his orgasms
And he had a sign for when he had an orgasm which was the sign of Pisces which is kind of sort of like a backward sea and then a sea back to back
And we actually are not 100% sure that it was all of them but we kind of assume people have used this as a basis of what his sex drive was
Yeah, so for instance in one of his diaries it says "played with Nell Pisces sign hurt small of back"
That could have been Twister, he was right
Another one went late to bed, Pisces sign in sleep, sweat much and disturbed
And then another one that made Wormwood wine, Pisces sign, Pisces sign
Oh!
Oh yeah, you're Robert
It's a good night
He's just bragging
Oh my goodness
But yeah, he was into it, he had a weird sex life actually, Hook
So he didn't really have relationships
It was kind of sad, he never had sex with someone who wasn't sort of financially dependent on him or dependent for a home
He used to have a lot of liaisons with servants and shagged them a lot like Nell
And then he had this weird relationship with Grace, his niece who was sent to live with him by his brother
Who was sent to live with him when she was 10 and then but she pretty much turned 16 and he was like
"Alright, you want to get off?"
"You want a Pisces sign?"
He was incredible, I mean he sort of, someone described him as Leonardo da Vinci but without the paintings
Yeah
Which sounds pretty crap doesn't it but it was, it sort of, he worked on all these different fields
Like he invented a microscope and he used that to draw incredibly tiny things no one had seen before
Or he designed the monitors or he came up with telescopes
So he invented the word "cell"
Do you mean a tiny cell in a body?
It's pretty cool
He saw them, didn't he?
He looked in his microscope at some car and he saw these little, he named them after the cells that monks lived in
But he didn't know that what they did he thought they was to send liquid around the body or something like that
So he didn't really know what they were but he did give the name which is quite good
He invented some flyer machines in his diaries, he drew them, he invented the first pressure cooker
Cool, that's very nice for stuff
He sort of claimed to have flown
He experimented with lots of flyer machines on the grounds of modern college where he went to uni with his friends
He built all these machines and then he did write in his diary in 1674
Told Sir Robert Sutherl, his friend, told him I could fly but I didn't tell him how
Ten cans of Red Bull
He was a proper scientist and he did a lot of measurements and stuff like that
And in those days it was long thought that masturbation was extremely bad for you
And so one reason that he always mentioned it in his diaries is because it was like an ongoing appraisal of his health
So he'll be able to see how often it had happened and then he'll be able to see how he was feeling
Because he was a hypokundriac as well
No, no, I'm just conducting an ongoing appraisal of my health
Sure
Mom
It's an experiment
When you say he's likely an order without the paintings, interestingly, we don't know what he looks like
We have no idea, there were no surviving paintings of Robert Hook and that is very surprising because he was such a prominent person
The Royal Society particularly loved him every all the scientists, they didn't like him as a person
But they respected the hell out of what he did
His books were admired by peeps through to all the top scientists
And there is a rumor and it's definitely a rumor that the rivalry that happened between him and Isaac Newton was so great
That when Isaac Newton became the president of the Royal Society and at this point Hook had died
That he slashed all of the paintings of Robert Hook to say this was not someone we need to...
I don't think it's a rumor
I think that's widely accepted to have happened
I think that he probably did it
Yeah, we don't have evidence, I think there was one painting and he and Newton hated each other
They had a massive rivalry and Newton did erase him from scientific history for a long time
We all think Newton is the good guy and then he became president of the Royal Society who happened to have this painting
Which has disappeared ever since
You raised him but all that survived were the orgasms
Poor guy
If you get a UV light in the Royal Society, you can't see the evidence
It's all that's left of him, it's so sad
He sort of proceeded Newton in a theory of gravity, which is a bit vague of the Newton's
But he said the planets were attracted to each other, the sun and the planets were attracted to each other
He said gravity was a universal force and Newton claimed credit
His diary is also chronicled his flatulence
And it was always in conjunction with the barometric pressure of the area
As he thought that the two might be connected in some way
So he thought if it was low pressure, today there's a storm coming in, everyone would be fasting a lot more
That makes so much sense
It does make sense
Does that?
Is it true?
Yeah, it does because if it's low pressure, you would have thought that your gas goes from an area of high pressure to an area of low pressure out for your rectum
I reckon it's true
I think I'm on the news going, well we've been getting a lot of reports of flatulence from the area of Cardiff
No, it's over to Anna with the weather
One long fart, take your own breath around today
I mean, he also wrote a lot about, he was a hyperchondriacum
He said that he suffered from giddiness, indigestion, flatulence, blockages of the sinuses, sore eyes, noises in the head, insomnia
And he took all these different medicines which he wrote all about as well
So he took steel, iron oxide, opium, amber, purgitives
And whenever his medicine gave him constipation, he said he was cheated of a shit
That's a great phrase
He was basically a drug addict though, wasn't he?
Yeah, he was so ill, he took all the drugs
And in those days medical drugs were basically all the illegal drugs now
Like opium and cannabis and lordinum and stuff like that
There's one other thing he took, because science was in its infancy
He believes that a lot of rather dubious stuff
So he noted down that a thing called stercus humanum was really good for removing films or myths from the eyes
And stercus humanum is dried and powdered human poo
Apparently you were meant to blow it into your eyes and this would heal your eyes
Does it work?
It doesn't work
Actually, I haven't even checked that but I just think it's important to say
I think this is the moment that don't try this at home as inventive of it
On putting stuff in your eye, Samuel Peeps, the world's most famous diarist
who was around at the same time and who in fact met Hook
He only wrote his diary for nine years
I had no idea, it's so weird because he's basically the main source for everything I've ever read about the 1600s
And he wrote his diary from 1660s to 1669
When he panicked that he was going blind because he'd been writing it too much
And he quit and he never wrote another word because he said I'm going blind
The good god prepare me for this awful affliction, I'm on my way out
And then he lived for the 34 years without going blind
Without going blind
Wow, that's amazing
He did write amazing so he was famous I guess for the sex stuff
Like if there's any time you think of Peeps it was he wrote very much about his sex life in it
But he was an entry that I read
So I to bed and in the night was mightily troubled with a looseness and feeling for a chamber pot there was none
I, having called the maid up out of her bed, she had forgotten supposed to put one there
So I was forced in this strange house to rise and shit in the chimney twice
And so to bed and was very well again
How I wish I had been cheated of a shit
Wow
You know you prefaced that by saying he was into the sex stuff
Yeah
Okay
I'm
Revealed a bit too much from my diary there
Okay, we need to move to our final fact of the show and that is my fact
My fact this week is that Warty comb jellies grow a brand new anus every time they need to defecate
How cool is that?
So a Wart comb jelly is like a jellyfish but not it's a different species
But they look very similar if you saw it in the ocean and for a very long time we assumed they had an anus
And it's only just recent
This is almost breaking news in science and very exciting news because what they learn is that when it goes the toilet
This was a guy called Sydney Tam who was studying them very closely with microscopes
Every time they needed the toilet basically the waste bit pushed towards the edge of their body on the inside
And this anus grew out of nowhere and then soon as it was out it closed up again and then they are anusless once again
And because they poo once virtually every hour they grow 24 anuses every day
It sounds like you're pitching to be the new David Attenborough
But this is very exciting in science because it's a transient anus
It's never before it's been seen in any of living species that we have
Well there are a few transient anuses actually
It's only one of a handful of
This is the first scientific observation of what that was
We know of a few because we have mentioned one on the podcast actually there's a jaw worm who has a transient anus called haplog nathia
And there's also a microscopic creature called Limnog nathia which lives in a hot springs on disco island in Greenland
Cool
Transient anus on disco island
Nice
The research we found this is really cool
He works at a lab called woods hole which is interesting and he watched individual water comb jellies for hours
And he marked the times of their defecations and then when the time was exactly right for the next one he zoomed in with a microscope
And he found that he saw the wormhole opening basically
Wormhole
What it is kind of like a wormhole is like a stargate
They call it the ring of fusion don't they?
That's the process behind it when the canal and basically the way they think it happens is that basically it's all fused up
And then your anal canal swells and swells and swells and presses against your skin tissue
And eventually it creates a little orifice that that dilates
And then it sucks itself back in again
Dan said that it's a bit like a jellyfish
It certainly looks like a jellyfish but it's not related to a jellyfish in any way really
It is less related to a jellyfish than we are to a worm
That's because about 550 million years ago
The types of animals in the world were worms, sponges, jellyfish and comb jellies which is this type of jelly
And worms kind of turn into all the different animals and mammals and birds and lizards and everything
And the jellyfish and the comb jellies had already split off way before that
It's as different from a jelly as a tattoo parlour is from a cactus imporium
They are amazing comb jellies
And like you should look them up because they're also kind of beautiful
But the way they move is they have sillier
So you may remember sillier from school as well
There's tiny hairs we have on our nose and our lungs
And they use sillier, these little hairs, as oars to propel them along
And they're the biggest things that use them for movement
They run in combs in eight rows on their body
And yeah, the largest animal has to do it and the main jelly is almost six feet wide
So some of them can get quite big
But mostly that under 16 inches quite small
The eating method is very cool
I think it's not exactly those ones but there are things called beroid comb jellies
Because there are whole family, there are different members of the family
And beroid comb jellies, they eat their food before they kill it
So they're just basically a bag floating in the ocean
And if they spot some prey, which is normally another jelly
They just swallow it hot, they just open the mouth of the bag, swallow their prey
And then they just keep their mouth shut for as long as they can
While they're pulling their prey apart on the inside
They actually have mouths that reseal that basically disappear
Like zippers, they're described as or it's like a zip, yeah
So they open their mouths, which their mouths are about half of their body
So it's like a plastic bag opening
And they engulf this other jelly, often bigger than they are
And then they zip it shut and they probably fuse their mouths back together again
Until they're ready to eat
Wow, that's amazing
But these particular jellies that we are talking about, the ones with the transcontainers
They're called nemiopsis lady
And they are also known as sea walnuts and a few other things
Now these guys, they eat by again opening their mouth
But then when they open it, it creates almost like a current
You know those rides when you're on like a donut and you're going really slowly down there
So they start that kind of current, but it's so, so slow
The things that get caught in this current don't even realize there's a current
And they're just suddenly slowly, slowly floating to this place
And before they know it, they're eating, almost like a conveyor belt
That the food just comes in them and it comes in them
And they can eat an unbelievable amount of stuff
They can eat ten times their body weight in a day
And so they end up basically taking over lakes
So there was some taken to the black sea by accident in some bilge water
And in less than a decade, the population in the black sea had gone, got a biomass of one billion tons
Which was ten times the weight of all the fish that were caught in the world that year
Wow, it's incredible, it's unbelievable
And weirdly we don't know a huge amount about them
And really we thought there were five US species in there until recently
And that's partly because they're really hard to study because the moment you attempt to pick them up, they fall apart
So there's, and genuinely they sort of melt in your hands
So I think there was a spotted cone jelly displayed in California's Monterey Bay Aquarium
And it was like literally water currents in the aquarium were just tear it into
So it's very difficult to collect
And this is actually, I was reading a piece about this Monterey Bay Aquarium
And the jellies that they collected, and the main marine biologists there was talking about them
And he was also saying that they shimmer
So when they have a light shone on them, then their little sillier break up the wavelengths of light
And they reflect them, so they're sort of all rainbow colours
And that actually wouldn't happen in the wild, but it does when we shine a light on them
But the marine biologist at the aquarium, who talked about that, it's called Steve Haddock
Nice! So lots of primitive life forms have only one hole in their bodies, and they have to eat through that, and excrete through that
And the reason that we are better than them, and I'm just going to say it, I think we are better than them
I'm sorry, I'm going to go to the aquarium, but I do think we've got them beat all right
So the reason that you need it is because if you have a through gut, which is what we've got
If you don't have that, then you can't eat anything until you've excreted your previous meal
So it's very inefficient system
So basically you can't have your lunch until you've pooed out your breakfast
Exactly!
Oh!
Exactly! Yes! I told you we were better than them
Just on sort of being able to regrow body parts
You know that we can regrow stuff, humans, we can regrow fingertips
And especially children can regrow huge chunks of their fingers
So children up to the age of ten can...
It's not an advert for cutting off the fingertips of children
It's not, don't try this at home, is it?
Well you know, if they've broken the TV curfew, what else can you do?
I suppose if you cut the fingertips off, they won't be able to use the remote control
Can't use the remote, exactly!
And if you can't off the fingertips, or if the fingertips of children under ten fall off, then...
As is very likely to happen to each other
As they do, it's a defence in court
And you don't sew them up
So what doctors tend to do is seal them up with flaps of skin
So you've just got to sure to finger at that point
But if you don't do that, then they'll tend to grow back
And interestingly, they grow back, but they don't have a fingerprint, oddly
And also the way they grow back, if there was any nail left at all, tiny bit of nail
It will grow back, but it will grow back square
Rather than over, which is how our nails grow
So it grows back, 20s back
Oh, I have that
I have a slightly square fingertip, and that's because my finger got shut in the door when I was a baby
Did you break the TV curfew?
I didn't break the TV curfew
I made sure to bring in all the tellies from the garden
Right on time
We're going to have to wrap up very soon
Just one more thing, I'm afraid this is about the word...
It's about the word in the fact
So there are old books, there are book scanners, which are designed to digitize very elderly books
Books from the 19th, 18th century, that kind of thing, which no one's read
And convert them into e-books, so they can be read
Unfortunately, there are some book scanners, which cannot tell the difference between the word "arms" and the word "anus"
And it literally can't tell it's asked from its elbow, isn't that pleasing?
So this does make a number of old books quite exciting
So, for example, Bertie, dear Bertie, will you not say goodnight to me?
Pleaded the sweet voice of Minnie Hamilton as she wound her anus affectionately around her brother's neck
When she spotted me, she flung her anus high in the air
Oh boy, she said, she grabbed my anus and positioned my body in the direction of the East Gallery
And we started walking
I'm on the reading the Book of Farewell to anus online, actually, and I've really enjoyed it
Brunbar comb jelly
Okay, that is all of our facts, thank you so much for listening
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have set over the course of this podcast
We can be found on our Twitter accounts
I'm on our Shriberland, Andy...
At Andrew Hunter M
James Harkin
And Chazinski
You can email podcast@QI.com
Or you can go to our group account, which is at "No Such Thing" or our website "No Such Thing" as a fish.com
We've got all of our previous episodes up there, links to our upcoming tour
Thank you so much, we'll see you again, goodbye!
(Applause)
(Music)
[ Cheers and applause ]
[MUSIC]