We run it on QI a few years ago. Yeah, um, which was there's no such thing as a fish
No, seriously, it's in the Oxford Dictionary of underwater life. He says it right that first paragraph. No such thing as a fish
Hello and welcome to no such thing as a fish. This is a QI elf podcast coming to you from our offices in Covenant Garden
My name is Dan Schreiber. I am sitting here with three other QILs James Harkin and Ange Zinsky and Andy Murray and once again
We're huddled around our microphone and these are the best facts that we found out from the last seven days
So in no particular order. Here we go
Okay, fact number one. We're going to start with you James
Okay, yeah, my fact this week is a computer game has been invented that takes more than a lifetime to complete
Is it digitized normally?
Oh, yeah, because remember that thing we found there was a computer simulation of monopoly and they found that something like 12% of all games will go on indefinitely
Which is not true because it's much more than that
What do you mean so with monopoly? How would it go on everyone with illness certain portion of the body?
Yeah, just keep going. Terry Pratchett has a computer game in his book, which is called Journey to Alpha Centauri
which takes over 3,000 years to play and
It's just you know the screen save the very old passion screen save with just the moving dots for a spaceship
It's that with a counter counting down for three thousand years and at the end the dot appears in the middle of the screen
It says welcome to Alpha Centauri now go home and someone has actually made that it's a very rough game
We're going to find out about this. No, we're talking about game. Okay, and this this came from the design museum
I went there this weekend
It's the design of the year 2014 is competition for all the best design things and this was that thing that I thought was most interesting
But the idea is it's kind of an art installation and they're asking questions like what happens to digital things after you die
If you die halfway through that game
Can you pass it on to another person to finish off the game is that possible or maybe this game is designed for mobile phones
What happens when mobile phones and obsolete will the game carry on and so they're asking those kind of questions
We're going to be dispiriting to you know to find out that your great uncle have bequeathed you his high score
So far in this game that you just had to keep on playing it for the rest of your life
To my first son I leave all the property and for my second son I leave this game
Hey, you guys know how many hours of games are played per week on earth by humans if you tallyed up over hours
I'll say a hundred million a hundred million hours. Yeah, I would say I'm gonna go for
Two billion. Okay, I'm gonna go for just 24 hours 24 hours. Yeah, and I think most of humanity's out on a walk
The answer is three billion hours
Oh, yes, I say I'm close, but actually I'm a billion out
Feels close. So gamers are supposed to be good at using drones aren't they for war? Yeah, and also
Searching a tree. Yeah, if they play computer games it's supposed to help them with keyhole surgery and stuff like this
There's a lot of job opportunities coming up for gamers now, which didn't exist before
When Robert Ballard discovered the record of Titanic probably in your head you have an image that he was in a submersible
But he wasn't a submarine, but they would send down drone submarines as it were and obviously you need someone to operate them
This this is a quote from he said I would not let an adult drive my robot. They don't have enough gaming experience
So with this game did you actually play it?
I I prodded at the screen a few times, but I couldn't really work out how to play it. Oh, okay. Maybe that's why it takes lifetimes the first
Just some of the other things of this design of the year they had the first car that's been able to drive
100 kilometers on one liter of petrol. It looks really cool
It's a bit like James Bond car. It's very sleek and in order to help their
Aerodynamics, they don't have wing mirrors and instead they have tiny cameras
They had talking lamp posts. Is that useful? They were popular stop that stop that bad dog
They were in Bristol last year of the year before I think and the idea is that say you had a rubbish bin and it was full
Then you would be able to talk to your rubbish bin and say you're a bit full and he got oh, sorry
I'll make sure I sought that out and then we get emptied
So it's a way of the community kind of dealing with stuff like that. Yes, it's really interesting thing, isn't it?
There's this guy and you guys heard of Demetri its cove. No, so he set up this thing called the 2045 initiative
Basically it's a Russian mogul who thinks that we who wants to remove our minds from our bodies essentially so our mind's gonna forever
Well, that's never gone wrong in any films
I think it seems very promising
So by 2045 he really thinks that we'll have our mind to do a couple from our bodies and he's gonna live forever
And he's a hundred percent certain of this and we'll have holograms and we'll be able to like
Shop in department stores for the body that we want that most suits our purposes and
Live for eternity and he met the Dalai Lama to discuss it
He apparently was really supportive according to their website
The thing is at the moment the computer capabilities isn't enough to simulate human brain is it? Yeah 2045 scenes
Ambitious so if I have something about things that run for longer than you'd expect
Okay, because off the back of the computer game
One of Norway's most popular recent TV shows has been a seven-hour train journey in real-time
across Norway
It might be quite beautiful actually. Yeah, it was and so they broadcasted in 2009 and over 20% of the population tuned in at some point at the show
Wow, I'm Britain. That would just be like 45 minutes of set outside Milton Keynes
I've watched that I've seen shots of the Norwegian one. It's gorgeous rolling countryside the snow in the first and it's all beautiful
And yeah, here would not be so and they keep doing this. They've done 18 hours of fishing for salmon
And then they had a 12-hour knitting night and my favorite is national firewood night which was in February last year
Which was inspired by a Norwegian book solid wood all about chopping drying and stacking wood which sold as many copies as 50 shades of gray in Norway
Oh, there are different kind of people
And the first four hours of national firewood night was a discussion of firewood
And then the next eight hours was shot was a live fireplace being filmed for eight hours and they had 60 complaints
Half were complaining that the bark had been put facing up and the other half of being complaining it was put facing down
Just picking up on this idea of things that go on for an extended amount of time
There's so there's obviously the game where it takes a lifetime or more than a lifetime to play
There's a lot of musical pieces that do exactly that as well John Cage famously has a piece
It's called Oregon squared slash ASL SP as a musical piece
Which was written in 1987 for an Oregon
The piece itself lasts 20 to 70 minutes
But it's gonna finish it's gonna go for about 639 years ending in the year
2640 and people you know the next note is gonna be played in a few years time and people will go and watch that note be played in this continuing piece
That sounds good. Yeah, they use John Cage to teach like beginners piano because a lot of his pieces are very easy
Technically speaking like piece number one don't play anything. Yeah, especially for minutes
That's one of the easiest things to play. There's a lot of people who accidentally play a note during that four-minute
See what you've gone wrong here
Classic mistake
Did you guys know that this game called ESP and I don't know if that's actually exists anymore
I couldn't get the website to open, but basically two people simultaneously like tag a picture with keywords
And if you tag it with the same word then you get a point and that's how they tied a whole bunch of Google images
Wow
I thought what you're gonna say is that people around the world are all playing this game
And they're gonna see if two people say the same thing at the same time and then see if there is actually ESP going up
I don't think it counts as ESP if you're both showing a picture of a table in both bright tables
Call me captain skeptic
Okay, let's move on to fact number two this one's my fact the fact is that
2013 was the first years since 1933 that there hasn't been a sighting of the Loch Ness monster
So there's huge worries in the Loch Ness monster community because they think Nessie's dead
Oh, it just learned to be a bit more surreptitious after hundreds of years of being constantly spotted
If I just stay underwater
No, I think they're worried. I think because they think Nessie's a friendly animal doesn't mind being spotted
People like Nessie very much so it's not an aggressive animal
It's never in fact in in 2005 there was a triathlon in Scotland
Where all of the athletes took a 1 million pound insurance deal out in case of being attacked by the Loch Ness monster when they were
Swimming across the Loch and the the community came out saying that's a ridiculous thing to do if anything she would join in
She would she would and she would beat them because she's a great swimmer
They're obviously saying that the Loch Ness monster is friendly because she hasn't killed anyone in the last 70 years
But there is a slight logic for her isn't it maybe she only needs to eat once a century?
No, I'm saying she doesn't exist every year William Hill the bookies. They do an actual competition
It's a photo competition where they award money to the winner who's provided the best photographic evidence of Loch Ness monster
And this is the first year where they haven't given the head to disqualify all three entries. The first one was obviously a duck
The second one was a wave and the third one a closer inspection just wasn't even the Loch
It was just another body of water
So I have a theory of what's happened to Nessie. Oh, yeah
Well, it's not my theory. This is the theory by Britain's high priest of White Witches Kevin Carlyon and he says
I personally believe Nessie is a ghost of a dinosaur who has been regularly seen in the Loch
But the spirit of the creature has been so exploited in recent years
I decided to carry out an exorcism hence no sightings of the monster
So he's saying that he has personally killed off Nessie
Yeah, he just thinks that people have been
Yeah, people have been messing around with this spirit of a dinosaur and he wanted to set it free
I really like the mythical creatures that we come up with there are so many of them in Britain
I don't really know if other countries have them to the same extent
But my favourite I came across in I'm reading our mutual friend at the moment
And I've decided to read all of the footnotes and if you're ever reading I think Dickens especially but like read all the footnotes
They're so interesting one of them made reference to the done cow this
Vicious beast that was slain by Guy Earl of Warwick who was one of these like pre-medieval British heroes
And yeah, it was just this cow and it produced an everlasting supply of milk and eventually got annoyed that people were like
Milking it and milking it and milking it and ran away from its farm in Shropshire
And eventually Guy Earl of Warwick who seems like a sort of St. George of the 10th century
Went out and had to slay the cow
Yeah, you say St. George but slaying a cow is not quite as impressive as slaying a dragon
Although he did also slay a dragon which was it must have seemed like a step down
It's not that difficult
Did that old second monster syndrome in the game?
If you go to Warwick Castle so until the 90s I'm not sure if it's still there because I haven't seen it
You can see the rib of the done cow
And that the king ordered would should be like put in Warwick Castle
Is it big? They're getting all cow rib?
Yes, it is bigger they think that it's actually an elephant tusk
I mean skeptics think that it might not be the rib of the giant done cow
That's even cooler though if this was found in Gloss the Chirin of Fear
Why is no instead of saying oh it's a great crazy magical cow
Why is this elephant been there?
Maybe that's what they meant by a giant cow
Because you know that the initial photo taken in 1933 of the Loch Ness monster
The very famous photo they think that that's an elephant
No, in the lake
Just to justify you that there was a circus in town at the time
Elephants as we've seen in David Attenborough documentaries do go swimming
And when they do they use their trunks as snorkels
And if you look at the photo it looks exactly like an elephant trunk
Do you guys remember that story in 2011 where police in Southampton went on the alert
Because there was a tiger sighting in one of the fields
And then there was a gust of wind that blew it over and it was a cuddly toy
There was a lion's skirt in the 70s in Britain which turned out to be a paper bag
Well there was a lion's skirt on the last year that turned out to be a large cat
So I mean you were saying you're not sure if other countries have similar kind of monster time to do
So I have one or two here
So the lake Okanagan in Canada they have a monster which is very similar to Nessie
And every year they give a $50 prize to anyone who can shout loud enough to wake the beast up
So everyone stands on the side of the lake, yells, wake up, wake up
And if anyone can wake them up they get $50
And they go home with the same $50, don't they?
And yet no winners I think
Isn't there a fact, you told me years ago I was saying to remember that there was an animal similar to the Loch Ness Monster that had protection policy on it in a different country?
Yeah, in Sweden that was, it was the Storcio monster I think you pronounce it
And it was classified as an endangered species in the 80s or sometime like that
Yeah, because as a result of that, a direct result of that
The factory government actually put the Loch Ness Monster on the animal protection
Oh really?
Yeah, they were going to do exactly the same, they were going to do what Sweden did but they decided that that was one step too far
So they would just put in, they were actually there was a document that was put in front of thatcher or thatcher's main people
Which they wanted to bring to Blue Nose dolphins over from America to search for the Loch Ness monster
Really?
Yeah, it never got passed but this was the Tory government that said
What would happen when the dolphins find, is it like Flipper?
They'll come back and go
I'd like to, yeah, what's that? What's that? What's that?
We're speaking of Hollywood people, what about Charlie Sheen? He went looking for the Loch Ness Monster to see him
You know what? You know you're saying that there's this guy who exercise the ghost in there
Charlie Sheen's getting a lot of stick from the Loch Ness Monster community, so they think
The Loch Ness Monster doesn't like two and a half men or maybe they don't have been used together
He went into the Loch Ness with a fishing hook and he attached the leg of lamb to a fishing rod
And tried to catch it, I an old wooden boat
You know what? Call me Captain Skeptical
But I don't think that's any less sensible than trying to exercise its ghost
Oh, look for it in the first place
Okay, time for fact number three, this is your fact, Anna
Yep, so my fact is that the French government forced Madame Tussaud to make models of her friends decapitated hence
Yeah, poor old Madame, it's kind of like how her career started
Is that during the revolution?
Oh exactly, yeah, it was during the terror
And the story goes that she actually had her head shaved and everything and they were ready to
to capitate her as well because she was friends with the royal family and she had like
there is mates in high places and she'd made wax models of a lot of them
And just before they dropped the guillotine they were like actually, you come in handy
because we want to make these death masks of our victims
And so she writes in her memoirs about having to sift through these piles of heads
Decapitated heads, pick them up, have them on her lap and making models of them
Yeah, I read an account of it and I kind of got the impression that it turned into something she really enjoyed
Yeah, I mean she had no choice but you know when you kind of just get used to something
You know it's your job, you know, you now waxing heads for a living
It was like a treasure hunt effectively, it was going like oh this is the bloke who was in the paper last week
Isn't he? Mary Antoinette, it's like nothing coming on in these direct hunt reviews
If you just get used to it, you're already into it
She was madamsu's father, the only wax workperson at the time
I don't think so, I think she just made, so I've been going on for hundreds of years
I think she was just very much a self-made woman
Well, my understanding of madamsu's father is that she was an apprentice to a doctor
And he would make wax bits of internal organs
Was that right? Oh yeah, I mean
Was his name Cateus? Yes, Cateus
But there's a theory that he may have been her father
Her biological father, yes
I know, her mother's husband was killed two months before she was madamsu's born
But there is a theory that he was her natural father
Because I heard about this guy that he made most of his money making erotic wax miniatures
Is that true? I don't know
I didn't see that, really
That cast kind of an odd light on him having this 15-year-old girl making wax models for him in his little office
Creepy
She was obviously talented though, when she was 16 I think she made models of Rousseau and Voltaire
I love Voltaire because Voltaire had a statistician friend who figured out that this lottery that the French government was proposing
As a way of it making money, actually if you bought up all the tickets of it you were guaranteed to win more money than you'd spent buying the tickets
So Voltaire bought up all the tickets offered in this French lottery and became the equivalent of a millionaire today
And never had to work again
I don't know if this is completely true but with Madame to source these days when they do a wax work of someone
There's no contracts for anything and technically I think people could request for it to be taken away
They could say I'm not, I don't want to be done as a wax work
But everyone just finds it's such an honour that they're fine for it to be done
Yeah I think you worked, wouldn't you?
Some people put a few clauses with it so Tom Cruise and Mel Gibson have both said you can do me
and it's fine and people can take photos but no press are allowed to take photos of the wax work
Because then they'll start using that as press shots and so they're good
They're good but they're not that good
Yeah
Tom Cruise bought it again in Madame to source wax work of music and he just loves that thing
I found it very interesting who they pick, who the pool of people is
Because now it's almost all celebrities
Although every monarch since George III has had a wax work made of them
So every king of Queen of England
Off the top of my head, Ian Duncan Smith is the only leader of the Conservative Party not to have had a wax work
Oh no that's because he's the most likely isn't it?
Well it takes a while as well to make the wax work and he wasn't leader for very long
So I mentioned by the time they'd booked the appointments he was out
Do you know Jenny Ryan who works on QI a few years ago
Well and she had to ring up Madame to source for another reason to find out
Which was the most groped wax work at Madame to source
And she found out that it was Brad Pitt
And the way they find out is they work it out by
Which is the one that's taken in for maintenance of the most knowledge
Because presumably he would have had to have been taken in for maintenance constantly
They had Hitler in a glass box didn't they because they were worried that he was going to be
Repeatedly attacked and in fact he was and he was beheaded in fact
Yeah someone ripped his head off, was that before or after or when was that 2008?
2008, it's not lunatics who have made one during the war I suppose
I think he had his maiden in 1930s, that's not really
And then gradually they moved it from, you know, honored place with other states
Men went to the ground floor to the Chamber of Commons
They don't actually in the Lou or something like that
There's also there was a rumor going around that
Gary Borolo it was melted down into Britney Spears
So it was so great that he was curious but it turned out that wasn't true
He was taken away, he was taken out after take that had finished
But he was brought back when Robbie Williams and take that got back together
But it meant that he's kept an aware house in the interim
And apparently there's a warehouse with all these fallen wax works
Yeah which is kind of it's like the like the end of Raiders of the Lost Ark
And I don't know who we're in there
That is the stuff of Nightmares, I really think
Imagine being locked in that warehouse
It's just going to be all people from the 80s isn't it?
Yeah vanilla rice is in there
I read as well that some people is so enthusiastic about being turned into a wax work
That they just do as much as they can to help out with the authenticity of
Oh yeah
And Boris Johnson when he was turned into a wax work
He gave on the spot after they measured him the clothes that he was wearing
And he left it all to me
Oh yeah
That was his excuse for why he was found wandering the streets of the naked
But if you visit Boris Johnson at Madame Two Swords
Have a look at the bottom of his trousers because you'll notice that there's a rip
And that's a rip from a bike chain from when he was riding over to be measured
Oh, yeah so there's a little bit of PR stunt
Even as I love cycling at
That is the best cockney rhyming slang I've ever heard PR stunt
Boris Johnson is a complete PR stunt
Apparently in the past five years 123 pairs of false teeth
And one false leg have been left behind in Madame Two Swords
One set of ones to claim
Who leaves their teeth?
I don't know, 123 pairs, five years a lot isn't it?
One last fact about wax works and wax in general
It's possible to fire lasers at a fly's brain and make it have sex with a ball of wax
Not only possible, it's great fun
For the fly or for you
I suppose the fly, if the fly doesn't know that it's having sex with a ball of wax
So there will feel stupid afterwards
Yeah
We've all been there
*laughs*
Okay, final fact of the show
And we come to you, Andy
My fact is that during the Normandy landings the Allied forces dropped dogs by parachute onto
Why are they able to do that?
The UK deployed parachute dogs in the Second World War
Which we used to identify minefields and to keep watch and to warn of enemies
Yeah, you know when you say identify minefields
Does that basically mean wander over a minefield?
*laughs*
There was a snippet, a snippet dance
Yeah, they could smell them
And they, so yeah, there were three, initially just three, sent over
Brian, Monty and Rene
And Rene, I think, was the only female parachuteist in the British army during the war
And they were sent in with the 13th Lancashire Paris
And then one of the articles I read it said they were called "Paradox"
"Breakets short for parachuting dogs"
*laughs*
Which I love
But the more office have made radio appeals in 1941 for people to give up their dogs for the war movement
And basically lots of people used it as an opportunity to just get rid of their dogs
Oh
So they, they have thousands sent in and lots of them weren't suitable
So were they trained to, like, pull the parachute cord at the right time?
I think the parachutes opened automatically
And they were, because they were the right shape and size
They were given the same parachutes that the parachute was used to drop bicycles over the battlefield
Which they all, sorry Addy, are you saying a dog is the same shape as a bicycle?
And size, and you can, if you peddle it right, they're the same effect
*laughs*
That's a very good point
Um, yeah
The first training was to jump out of the plane with a bit of meat
In your pocket
*laughs*
And then I think...
And then I think for someone else to throw the dog out of the plane
No, no, no, no, it's actually slightly cooler than that
They used to starve the dogs
Um, and so what they would do is they would hold the meat outside the plane
So the dogs would leave for, yeah, yeah, yeah
And how else are you going to get a dog out other than throwing it?
Yeah, but they're not cruel
I think, I think, I think, eventually they got used to it though, didn't they?
You didn't get used to it though
I watched them watching a really interesting documentary a while back about um
I think it was 12 paratroopers from the Second World War
Who, they did their first parachute jump and they were obviously terrified
As you are when you threw yourself out of a plane for the first time
Really, really nervous
And then obviously they did it for the subsequent five years
Got really used to it, not to get it all
Didn't parachute for 50 years
And this documentary picked up on them when they were in their 70s and 80s
And said, "Jonna do a parachute jump again, let's see how it is"
Now to 50 years, not a trace of fear in them
And it's like this thing where the way to get over a phobia permanently
Is to do it repeatedly
And you're cured for life
So 50 years they didn't parachute and they all just blazing up in the plane
You're, when you're looking for illustrious, decapitated heads
You're used to it
So I have something else about people dropping stuff by parachute during the war
And during Mussolini's invasion of Ethiopia
And they dropped sheep and bulls by parachute
And the reason was, and they needed food
They were in the desert
And what's the best way of doing it?
You can drop meat down, that's very enough
Or you can drop live animals
And then they can butcher themselves whenever they need the meat
And so that's what they did
They dropped their bulls on the sheep
They attached them to modified harnesses
And parachuted them down to the soldiers
That is a main style
Yeah
That must be the biggest thing that's ever been parachuted
A bull
I read that in parachutes, actually, during war times
People, as well as, you know, you'd look out for it because of enemy
But you would also be looking out for it because parachutes, the material
Was such a collectible
There was a thing that everyone, yeah, yeah
Like apparently if it was a silk one, that would be the common little triangles
And you would turn them into underwear
That's true
Otherwise they had no underwear
Like a new meaning to go and commando
I love, have you guys seen the footage of friends
Oh yeah
Rachel, yeah, were you watching that poor guy
Who developed a parachute suit, I think, starting in 1910
And I just love the fact that he saw he made this parachute suit
Which he decided was going to be useful, effective, and work
And it just didn't work consistently, didn't
And he threw various dummies wearing it off from various heights
And they all just plummeted to the ground and died of dummy death
And then he tried to throw himself off there, like 10 meters high, sort of levels, um, fell, broke his leg
And so he thought, well, this has gone well
I'm gonna ask if I can throw myself off the Eiffel Tower wearing it
And so, yeah, he did and died
And you can watch it
You can watch it on YouTube, it's an extraordinary bit of footage
That's amazing, I didn't realise that it had gone so badly before he decided to jump off the Eiffel Tower
Just to get, just to give him the benefit of the doubt
Isn't, did he jump off the viewing platform at the Eiffel Tower?
Yeah, because he saw no platform
And that's quite low, isn't it?
Yep, but I wouldn't be surprised if, maybe if he jumped from higher, it might have worked
That was what some people said
Some people claim that his parachute looked like his parachute suit suddenly blossomed
At the last moment, the last split second
But I actually can't, I've watched the footage
That sounds like a wily coyote and roach run a thing, doesn't it?
He splatts down and then the parachute opens just to be run
Yeah, he's the most amazing one stars though, I wondered why the most stars didn't save him with the air resistance, it's so good
One of my favourite facts about D-Day landings is that 4% of the sand on the beach today in Normandy
Is made up of tiny metal particles left over from artillery explosions during the attack
No, 4%? That's a lot, isn't it?
Yeah
Did you guys read it in the 2000, or someone tried to replicate it in our adventures?
Who is one of the first people to design a parachute?
Yeah, it was like a triangle or what was it?
Yeah, it was, I think it was a bunch of triangles
And anyway, it definitely had wood in full
So in his design, it was like some sort of cloth
And wooden things holding it together, wooden plank, holding it together
So someone tried to recreate this in the 2000, but using modern materials and said it worked
And it was this, like, it was all over the news saying they didn't know to venture to design
Works, this guy survived, but he used cloth and modern materials
I feel like if he built a parachute out of wood
It would never have worked, would it?
I don't think it would work
That would never have worked
I think the official, I guess, first parachute jump
As far as we know, the first public one
So it was done by Luis Sebastian Lennemond in Montpellier in France
And his very first jump was off a tree holding two umbrellas
Cool
That was the very first parachute jump
So, do we not counter the Monsbury Monk Ilmer of Monsbury
Who was the 11th century monk who flew 200 meters
When he jumped off the top of Monsbury Abbey
He was airborne for 15 seconds, they've worked out
Because they know where he landed
And where he took off from and how high it was
And he just made a bunch of wings for himself on his feet and his pants
And he said if he'd remembered to make himself a tail
Then he would have been arm-harmed
And that actually seems to be true
Because it, like, gives you an equilibrium and means that
You're giving me a really good look at him
I think that sounds very true
And people would have thought him a fool when he did that
And yet, a few hundred years later
We are throwing dogs out of planes
To help identify mines
Still doing it, 2010
German shepherds were being flown in
And dropped over Taliban regions
It was just fine on the Taliban
It's a spy
Yeah, they had little cameras on them
Wow
Yeah, German shepherds
I like the fact that in the war it was German shepherds
That the British were dropping on Germany
I mean, they're not so strong
You treading
That reminded me that there's always countries that
Find an animal and then arrest it for spying
But after the whole time, isn't it?
Yes
Was it Saudi Arabia?
I'm making this up
Saudi Arabia that arrested a coconut for spying
I remember that
How was it?
I don't know
I think it's amazing
I find you guilty of spying
You have to be broken up and put in cocktails
There was a bounty on his head
[Laughter]
Okay, that's all that there is for this week
There's of our facts
Thanks so much for listening everyone
If you want to get in contact with us
You can do so by going to our Twitter handles
I'm on @SriberlandAndy
@AndreyHunterM
Gent
I am @Xshaped
And still not on Twitter
But do you know what, let's get you on this week
Otherwise, you can get Anna in the meantime on @Quikipedia
Please do go if you enjoyed this podcast to our ki.com/podcastpage
Anna and Alex have been putting together these amazing pages
They have all the links to the stuff that we're talking about
Videos that go with what we're talking about
It's a great page
Goes away
And we'll see you again next week
So thanks everyone for listening
And we'll catch you again
Bye
You hold on to me
I'm holding on to you
(Music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]