(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski.
Once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts of the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that some planes
are specifically built to carry other planes' wings.
How degrading.
- Is it?
- I think it's a bit degrading for those planes.
Just, you know, you're the--
- Oh, I think they're the king planes.
- Well, the wing was that, do you?
- Yeah, I think they're the planes
without which other planes cannot be.
- I think they're more like a wingman.
- Very nice. - Nice.
Well, whatever their social hierarchical status
in plane community, these are really cool looking planes.
So I was just reading about plane construction,
how planes are put together.
And it was saying how all the different bits
are made in different places.
And I was thinking how on Earth they get them
to where they're assembled.
And for Airbus, which is the world's biggest aircraft maker,
they use this thing called Beluga XL,
which looks just like a Beluga whale,
which is quite cool.
It's got the big, we've talked about melons, haven't we,
on the podcast for their big foreheads.
James is looking skeptical.
It doesn't look exactly like a Beluga whale.
You wouldn't confuse it with one.
- I've seen the image.
I think they look a bit like them.
I'm just trying to think if the average listener
is gonna know what a Beluga looks like.
- Maybe a dolphin, I think a picture of dolphin.
- A dolphin with a big melon on its head.
- Big bulbous head, yeah.
And they paint them to look like Beluga whales.
They paint the smile on to make them look friendly.
- They're very charming looking planes.
And they are amazing.
So they are as long as two blue whales,
just to continue the whale analogy.
- Yeah, they're the biggest whale in the world
as a result, aren't they?
(laughing)
- Oh, nice.
- And they're designed,
they can carry two wings for an Airbus A350,
which is itself a really big plane.
And they were designed, I think specifically,
to carry two of those, to fit them in,
because those wings are massive.
And the whole face of the whale comes off.
So you don't load them in the back.
You just pull off the whale's head.
- Well, it sort of lifts up, it lifts up, doesn't it?
- So do the wings go on the inside?
- Yeah, yes.
- Did you not just attach them to the actual wings?
- But then how do you fly back when you get there?
- No, double wings, get them there faster.
- Oh, like a biplane.
- A biplane.
- I don't know why they haven't thought of that.
- Yes.
But the Beluga is one of the smallest whales in the world.
So actually, it should be a very small plane.
- Yeah.
- That is poorly named.
- Yeah, yeah, silly.
- You know it's crazy as well.
So the Beluga XL is a more recent innovation
from the original Beluga.
The number of staff on the plane at any one time
on the original Belugas, it's just two.
- Really?
- That's it.
You put the wings in.
- Pilot, co-pilot.
- I assume not like two flight attendants.
(all laughing)
- But now the XL has a third member, the load master.
- Oh, cool.
- Suggested one person's loading the wings on.
- She is quite wild.
- Is it to make sure I suppose that they stay strapped down
during the flight?
- Yeah.
- It's all right.
I got it.
- That's a pretty sexy job title.
- Yeah, load master.
- What are you?
Oh, I'm a load master.
- Oh yeah, and what do you do?
- I watch small piece of Velcro in terror,
fearing it's gonna come undone.
- Cool, cool.
I'm gonna speak to this person over here now.
(all laughing)
They didn't always use aeroplanes
to get these things around.
The Airbus A380, they used to move everything around
using something called the Itinerair, a grand gabarit.
And that is a water and road route
that was created just to move pieces
of this aeroplane around Europe.
- No way.
- So cool.
- They dig sort of giant canals across Europe
that we didn't notice.
- Well, I think they more used existing canals
and made them a bit wider.
- Cool.
- And also use existing roads
and made them a bit stronger.
But basically they were put together in Toulouse,
but the bits were made in France, Germany, Spain,
United Kingdom even.
And so they had to bring all the bits together to Toulouse
so they could make them.
But they had to reinforce everything
because they're so big.
- Right.
- And they would always travel at night time.
- That's so cool.
- So they'd park up in some lay by during the day.
And then at night time, they'd drive around with these.
- They do all these big load people,
largely 'cause it's a real inconvenience in the day,
but that makes it sound sexy as well.
- Oh, it sounds covert, yeah.
- When it's the only travel at night.
- I'm a night load mask.
- Yeah, I don't normally come to these parties
because I'm a bit of a night load mask.
(all laughing)
- On that, James.
So you know how NASA gets its rockets around?
- I do actually.
- Okay.
Well, can you pretend you don't for them?
- No, do they attach balloons to it and float it around?
- No, they use barges.
They have a barge called Pegasus.
And they load the rocket on,
'cause it's from the assembly factories in Louisiana.
And they need to get it
to the Kennedy Space Center in Florida.
And it's 100 meters long
and they just load the rocket on.
And then it doesn't have an engine.
The tugs have to just tug it all the way.
- How far are those two places apart?
- They're quite far.
- From where to where, sorry?
- From Louisiana to the Cape Battle,
it's probably about 400 miles, I'd say.
- Yeah, you wouldn't walk it at a gas.
- So I think that's weird, isn't it?
- It's weird because the word barge is so,
yeah, you picture it's like toad in the hole or something.
- We're in Venice.
- Yeah, all Venice.
- If you go to Venice with your wife,
are you saying, "Hey, let's get a barge."
(all laughing)
- Darling.
- You've got us the most amazing deal.
(all laughing)
- Now there will only be three staff on the barge.
- But we will velcro you down.
Now, yeah, what I found interesting about that NASA barge
is actually it's only about 50% longer
and wider than a standard canal boat.
'Cause canal boats are quite long, aren't they?
- Wow.
- I mean, having stayed on a canal boat for a week,
it doesn't feel spacious.
- Maybe not a narrow boat, like the tiny narrow boats.
'Cause those are--
- Oh, I'm not talking about a rising-gym style narrow boat.
- It's 310 by 50 feet.
So I'm pretty sure that that's not,
it's only, it's not twice as big as a normal canal boat.
It's pretty amazing, isn't it?
- It is amazing.
- But they have got another way of doing it, haven't they?
They use a thing called the pregnant guppy.
- Oh!
- Which is a modified Boeing 377.
- Yes, and this was at the start,
well, they made their first pregnant guppy
start of the space race.
So I think then they went back to barges for a while
'cause this was in the '60s
and it was a massive problem.
'Cause at that time, they were made on the West Coast
and then had to be taken to Cape Canaveral.
And yeah, it was just taking forever
and they had to go through the Panama Canal and--
- So far.
- It took about a couple of days.
- You mean the America Canal?
- Sorry, sorry, yes.
And they took the transport time from 25 to 35 days
down to 18 hours, but it was,
that's what inspired the Beluga designs.
'Cause if you look at them, they look kind of similar,
don't they?
- They really do, yeah.
- The pregnant guppy, the pregnant guppy inspired them.
- Yeah, absolutely, they're all nautical,
or they're all sea creatures, guppies and belugas.
- Yeah, I think that's a good thing.
The beluga was a nod to the guppy.
- 'Cause the guy who created the guppy
was a guy called John M. Conroy
and he also came up with a plane
called the Conroy Sky Monster, cool.
Just such great names these planes have, so cool.
Hey, this is pretty cool, the Beluga XL,
it doesn't just take wings.
It often gets, well, sometimes gets asked
to bring a few other things.
And at one time in 1999,
it carried the liberty leading the people painting.
So this is that French painting by Eugene Deliffoy.
- And the things you make when you say that,
it's such a shame the listener can't see it.
- It's why I'm not allowed to go to France.
And yeah, so that's very famous, isn't it?
- It's a massive campus.
- Like one of them's holding a big flag.
- Yeah, there's a lady in a bit of a state of undress.
She's definitely in an emotional state.
- Yeah, yeah.
- She's got the flag.
- One of the buttons has fallen off.
- Yes.
- And she'll be livid when she finds out
someone was painting that scene.
(all laughing)
It was learned from Paris to Tokyo.
And so they needed to get it over there.
It's too large to fit in what was, I guess,
the biggest transport plane at the time, Boeing 747.
So they needed to use a Beluga in order to do it.
It is a 9.8 feet tall and 11.8 feet long.
- That is small.
- I feel like I've been in a Boeing 747.
- That's about the same size as this wall, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- It's a bit smaller.
- It's a bit taller and a bit smaller.
- But you've got to package it up
and you need to make sure it's really good packaging, right?
So that's going to add exercise.
I mean, have you ever, tons of bubble wrap?
You know, in your order for, like a, you know,
sometimes you order just like a lipstick from Amazon.
- Always, yeah.
- Yeah, it comes in a giant box.
- I was on a flight last week and I bought a bag of crisps.
And then I forgot about it.
And then halfway through the flight, I went,
"Oh, I'll have that bag of crisps."
I went to my bag and the bag of crisps was enormous.
Like, 'cause the pressure changed, right?
- Oh, right.
- Okay, so it would like, okay.
So I wondered if you had an enormous bubble wrap
around your painting,
where the whole thing would just balloon
to like 10 times the size.
- So it looks small when you put it in
and everyone's going, "That could fit on a seven,
"fourth sense level, you wait 'til we get in the air."
- But yeah, they had to put it in a vertical position.
There was a special pressurized container
so it didn't get damaged on the way.
And they had these anti-vibration devices
that were in it as well.
Yeah.
- I feel like this is missing flow.
- Just in case the load master got excited.
(all laughing)
- Loopy plates.
- Okay.
- So various countries have really led the field in this.
I think the Germans had a pretty good record for a while.
Did you hear about the Blohmann Ross BV-141?
(all laughing)
- I'm just gonna go speak to this guy now.
- This is so amazing.
So picture a classic, let's say a bomber plane from the war.
You know, you've got the main fuselage in the middle,
you've got the wings on either side
and you've got an engine on each wing
and maybe the propeller on each.
- Got it.
- Classic engine.
- Yeah, classic plane.
- Maybe next time just say picture a plane.
(all laughing)
- Picture a plane, you're ahead of the top.
- Second one, more plane.
- Second one, more style bomber, right?
This was a plane which had the fuselage, sure,
but that's not in the middle.
- Uh-huh.
- So there's a wing, then there's a fuselage,
then there's a separate wing
and the crew are sitting in a little pod
halfway along that wing.
- Oh, cool.
- It is the weirdest looking thing.
- But what's the reason?
- Reconnaissance.
- So it gave a better view for reconnaissance photos
to have you not being in the main bit of the plane.
- Okay, well, 'cause the wing doesn't get in the way maybe.
I always think the wing gets in the way of the view a bit
when you look out the wings.
- Yeah.
- And that's actually invented a wingless plane
which they flew called the flying bathtub.
(all laughing)
And it was in the 1960s, they're experimenting.
If you look at a photo of it,
it literally, it looks like just the plane, no wings,
and it managed to take off and they used to-
- And what's giving it the lift?
- You have to roll it down a hill
with three yorks and another.
(all laughing)
- It's a lot for the older generations.
- I think it's playing it, don't explain it.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, what was the actual answer, please?
- I was sort of hoping James's joke
would make us run past that.
- I'll always wait out the joke.
Turn to the answer, thank you very much.
So we don't have a flu, we have a flu.
- You have a high flu.
- A flu.
- Do you wanna hear a plane we never got?
The Lockheed flatbed.
- Okay.
- This is bananas.
- Okay, so what's the thing about planes?
So you got your two wings.
- You're gonna have an engine underneath each one.
- Okay, but you put everything you got in your plane, right?
Or your people in their bags.
There's still a load of space above them, isn't there?
- Yeah.
- There's still a load of head room
that is unnecessary wasting of that tube of the plane.
- Oh yeah.
- So one of you had a plane which had the wings
and it's got the head and the tail,
but then it's just like a flatbed truck in the middle.
It's not a tube.
- Okay.
- Do the people have to lie down in it?
- It's not for people.
- Oh, it's for people.
- It's just for paintings by Delacroix.
- It's for like, I don't know,
like a big lorry or a tank or whatever,
like something you need to move by air that just goes
in an open top sandwich.
- No, it's a convertible plane.
- Stunt that down, convertible plane.
- Cool.
- And that was designed and tragically it was,
I don't think it was built, it was designed in the 80s.
The pilots get to sit in a compartment,
but mostly it's open.
- Yeah, otherwise your hair would get completely messed up,
isn't it? - That's true.
- Do you guys know about the X planes?
- Yes, where have they gone?
They were meant to be the future.
- Well. - What it is,
it's how the X men get around.
- Yes, exactly.
They are the future.
And basically we only learn about them
after they've been declassified.
So, you know, there might be still some X planes being made,
but we don't know about them yet, right?
But we know about the ones which have been made
and weren't useful.
A lot of them were missiles.
There was one called the stiletto,
which looks like basically the bottom of a shoe,
of a women's shoe, extremely thin aeroplane.
They thought it might be able to go really, really fast.
- Who's making all these X planes?
- This is the US.
- Okay. - Yeah.
- And what's their category?
Their secret until they're released?
- Secret until they're released, yeah.
So if you're making a secret sort of wacky plane
and you're in the American military,
dick dastardly is in charge,
then you give them an X designation.
- I see. - And then eventually
some of them cloud.
The X 43 was in 2004 and it flew at Mach 9.6.
So at 9.6 times the speed of sound,
it was about 7,000 miles per hour.
- No.
- But the engine only was able to run for 10 seconds.
(all laughing)
So they got that fast, but they couldn't do it for very long.
- You still popped Paris, couldn't you?
- That was great.
- Can I tell you guys one really amazing thing
about moving big stuff around?
- Yeah.
- Wind turbines, those big sort of arms of wind turbines,
you have to basically make them in one piece
and then get them to where they need to go.
You can't make them and then stick them together
'cause they need to be really strong.
And so they put them on enormous flatbed trucks, right?
But sometimes the place where you need to put your
wind turbine is in the countryside.
How do you get through a little town
with these massive wind turbine trucks?
- Do you have to just take everything down basically?
Like anything that goes over the street,
any wires or anything?
- Sometimes that would happen.
Yeah, in the past that's had to happen
or they've had to like make roads way wider.
They've had to pave over the top of roundabouts
because they can't go roundabouts.
But they've invented a new class of vehicle
called the self-propelled rotor blade adapter.
And this is amazing.
So you drive your truck and it's on a flatbed
and then the rotor blade of the wind turbine
can move upwards so that it's perpendicular to the ground,
which means you can drive it much better
around like tight corners.
- It does mean you've got the biggest sale known to man.
(all laughing)
- They would only do it at nighttime
and everything's really quiet.
But otherwise, you're knocking down like trees and.
- I've actually seen,
I think they sometimes don't do it at night
'cause there's a really good video.
Someone drive, I think it's in Hull,
a really good video of a truck,
which looks microscopic when you put a 100 meter,
like wind turbines might get up to 100 meters long.
I think this one's 70 meter long turbine blade on it
sticking up like James says in the air.
And then behind it,
there's one guy walking in fluorescent gear
with a hard hat on.
- He's the load master.
(all laughing)
- Come on and go hearty together.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is Andy.
My fact is that Japan has just experienced
its maximum ever number of traffic lights.
(all laughing)
- Is this by Royal Decree?
- It's, yeah, it's an imperial thing.
They've decided they're just too darn many.
- No, why is this?
Like, how can you be sure that they're not gonna add more?
- I'm not positive,
but barring surprising demographic shifts.
- I see.
- Which aren't unheard of,
Japan will never have as many traffic lights
as it does now.
- Is your fact that Japan's population is going down?
- No, that's, no, it's closely related to that fact.
- Okay.
- I'll grant you that.
- Just joking.
- This was a piece in the FT
about the fact that Japan's population is going down.
(all laughing)
- But if you've got fewer people,
you need fewer traffic lights.
- It's basically, do you remember
we did the thing about conveyor belts,
that man Japanese scheme to have conveyor belts
instead of freight lorries, you know,
in rural bits of the country.
Basically, many traffic lights are quite old now
and roads in rural areas are emptying of traffic.
So the police have just announced
from this year more traffic lights
will be decommissioned than newly installed.
So the total number's going down demographics.
It's called the 2025 problem actually in Japan,
which is where this massive baby boomer generation,
they are moving from early old to old old.
They're over 75 now.
So they're moving into more of the,
and that's not advanced old age,
but you know what I mean, they're getting older.
And that just means big changes, man.
This is one of them, yeah?
- Is it that they don't know how to use traffic lights
anymore 'cause they're getting older?
- No, it's more like that will lead to lots of shifts
in terms of the amount of social care you need for people.
If you have a big cohort of society
who are no longer in early old age,
but in older old age, that will lead to big things.
And that's why they're experimenting with lots of things
like robots in care homes and things like this.
They're trying to solve it
with a combination of robotics and other things.
Mostly robots 'cause it's Japan.
- It's not just depopulation.
It's the fact that the traffic lights themselves,
they have a life expectancy of 19 years.
And so if you wanna redo them up,
it costs about 6,000 pounds
in order to do each traffic light.
And they just saying, actually, let's just take them down.
It's depopulation and old age of the lights themselves.
- So as to your question, James,
if Japan suddenly goes on the bonkathon of the century
and suddenly the population is gonna double,
then they might consider Japanese bonkathon.
- I love it.
You mentioned robots.
Robot is what a traffic light is in South Africa.
- Beautiful.
- What does that mean?
- That's what they call them.
Robots. - Really?
- Yeah, yeah.
- What are they called robots?
(all laughing)
- I think you can have the same name for two things.
- I don't think so.
- It might get confusing though.
- It might be.
They were originally called that.
So in Johannesburg, the first one came in 1927
and they were called robots and they still are,
but they're quite unreliable in Joburg
and people knock them over quite a lot.
The Johannesburg drivers damage 81 robots a month
and they have to replace them
and they often replace them with quite high-tech things
and those high-tech things often get stolen
'cause they have lots of metal in the cables
and stuff like that.
They fitted loads of them with a monitoring system,
but the monitoring system had SIM cards in
and people realized they could just steal the SIM cards
and use them in their phones and make free calls.
- Wait, what?
- And the problem is so bad that in some cases,
jail sentences or attacking robots can be as high
as they are for murder in Johannesburg.
- Wow.
- Because they decided we're gonna stop this
so we're gonna make the punishments really high.
- That's wow.
- Yeah, big problem.
- That is a big problem.
Singapore's got an interesting thing with its traffic lights.
Depending on who's crossing the road,
you might be stuck at a red light in your car longer
than if someone else was crossing the road.
Is this a riddle?
Yeah, go for it.
- Is it that they've got sensors to tell if it's someone
in a wheelchair or an elderly person
who takes longer to cross?
- So yeah, but it's not sensors.
This is a new thing which they're gonna slowly spread out
through all of Singapore,
which is if an elderly person is trying to cross the road,
they have a car, which is kind of like a pensioner's card,
which they tap onto the side,
which tells the signal that there's an old person crossing
and they get an additional 13 seconds to cross the road.
- I think that's such a good idea.
I spend a lot of time with pedestrian crossings thinking,
this is way too little time if you're really old.
Sometimes I can even only just get across.
And especially if you're not there at the very start.
- Yeah.
- If you're an older person, you're like,
I'm not gonna start unless I was there at the beginning.
- Yeah.
- Some of the roads in Singapore quite long as well.
- Yeah, quite wide.
- They're quite wide.
Yeah, they have lots of lanes.
Like almost as wide as Amosways,
but they're just normal A roads.
- God imagine getting to sort of the middle
of a 12-lane road,
realizing and looking behind and in front and thinking,
- Surely tap my car.
- Did you tap my car?
- Did you tap, darling?
I thought you tapped.
- You did have to.
- People in wheelchairs are much likely
to be in traffic-related accidents,
partly 'cause they might take a bit longer to cross,
but also partly because they're way less visible
'cause you're at a lower height.
So in Vienna, the cameras can detect that
and they sort of work out with 99% accuracy
whether you want to cross the road or not.
- How cool is that?
- I honestly thought we had similar things in London,
I must say.
Like there's one near our house
which gets you across to the park.
And I swear when people are slowly going across it,
it stays on for longer.
- Oh, really?
- You've got to get out there with your stopwatch, right?
- I know, I'm gonna get out.
- Did you know, outrage of outrage that,
well, first of all, I've always been fascinated
by traffic-like technology.
And I've like Googled this loads before,
like how they're all coordinated,
how many lights are rigged up to the same system.
'Cause you know, they all seem to change
in coordination with each other.
You have something called a green wave.
Do you know what green wave is?
- Well, I came back from the airport the other day
and I was driving from Stanstead into central London
and it felt like every single light was on green.
I just got so lucky.
- That's 'cause you'd had your crisps
that you were in a good mood.
(all laughing)
- But what I thought is, if you hit one green,
does that mean you're gonna hit all the greens?
'Cause you're just going at the right pace.
- Well, it usually depends on whether
you're in a row of traffic.
- Well, no one was there.
It's the middle of the night.
- Okay, well, that's very weird.
And you just got lucky, I think.
(all laughing)
- Well, if it was the middle of the light,
they'd just have them on green
unless another car comes.
But the green wave is basically-
- Well, you're driving a wind turbine blade at the time.
(all laughing)
- This is when loads of lights along the same route,
along the same straight stretch of road
are coordinated to go green one after the other
to stop cars stopping.
Now, usually it only works if you're in a row of traffic
because environmentally it's much more friendly
to not have lots of cars stopping and starting
'cause when engines stop and start,
that's worse for the environment.
So, people say that if you are in a green wave,
if you catch a green wave,
then a bit like getting in a slipstream,
you've got to stay close to the car in front.
Not too close, but close enough
that you don't break the green wave
so that you can get through all the greens.
'Cause if suddenly you let enough distance
between you and the car in front happen,
then the light will go red.
- Okay.
- So-
- So is everyone on board?
Are you in the car going,
"Oh my God, we're in a green wave."
- You should be, yeah.
- Right, and then you will-
- Then you will think to each other.
- Conger it along, yeah, that's pretty cool.
- London has a thing called Scoot,
which is smart traffic lights.
And they can let certain cars and trucks
and people go through depending on
what's best for the environment.
So if there's like some really big, heavy goods vehicles
that are gonna go through London,
they think we don't want to stay in central London
and clogging up the air.
So we're gonna kind of give them a bit of a free run
on the green lights.
And that's using smart cameras
and all that kind of stuff that they can do that.
- That's so cool.
- I know, and they have a similar one in Amsterdam,
which can talk to your phone.
They can give cyclist priority when it's raining.
- Wow.
- That's so amazing, yeah.
- The Dutch are so far ahead of the day.
- They're kind of thinking to stop this.
In fact, they might have recently stopped it
because they hadn't really thought about the privacy risks
of being able to see where everyone's going all the time.
- What's the harm?
- A few people have complained about it.
So I'm not sure if it's still going,
but for a while that was definitely the case.
- There's people who were cycling home from their lover's house.
And that's how they got busted.
- I don't know from the big Dutch bonkathon.
- Well, I just wonder if that's,
if there's a hidden sort of like air traffic control system
that's used for say like,
if there's a major incident
and you need ambulances to get through.
- In America they have that.
But in the UK, we don't have it
because ambulances just go through red lights.
So we don't need it.
- But there is, again, in the Netherlands,
there's a traffic light system in,
oh gosh, I can pronounce it wrong,
Hertogenbosch, which has all these detection loops
like plugged into the whole town software.
So all the city buses have these transponders on
which talk to the junctions.
If the bus is running on time,
the light works as normal.
If the bus is running late,
the lights change to give the bus priority.
And if the bus is early, the light says,
yeah, you can hold on.
- The light just stops the bus for the sake of it.
- It stops the bus and lets the other traffic through first.
- Well, this is the explosive thing.
I realized about this country,
is that, yeah, we don't have it with emergency vehicles,
whereas America does, which, and I should say,
'cause I read so many forums with ambulance people saying,
we never go through red lights unless it's safe.
So, you know, it was really nilly.
- Of course we don't.
- But, no, no, of course not.
- We're gonna need a few more ambulances out there.
We've got them in great time, but.
- We have left a trail of destruction.
But, you know, who can't override red lights
whenever they want, the buses in this country
- It's so cool.
- What?
- So, if a bus has the appropriate technology,
which is the bus radio link.
- I think you're thinking of cyclists.
(laughing)
You're always hopping on the back of passing cyclists
and tapping them with your oyster card
but staying on until you've reached your destination.
- This is true.
They have certain different bits of tech that come to it,
but one of them is bus priority radio link,
which communicates with traffic lights.
So, if you're on the bus, you have this radio link
that says, I'm coming along, I'm a bus,
let the light stay green for me
and the light will stay green for the bus.
'Cause again, it's better because buses are more efficient,
they're carrying more people,
bad for the environment for them to stop and start.
Sometimes you'll see,
and I really want to see one of these now,
a sensor on the road before traffic lights
and it's a bus sensor.
And I think they're often at the bus stop
just before the lights on the bus stop
and it senses that a bus has gone past
and it relays information to the traffic light saying,
if you're on green, stay on green for a bit longer
'cause bus is coming, let him through.
These buses are getting away with murder.
Police cars are there, sitting in it for lights.
- Such a miserable response.
I am being cheated here by this bus
getting through efficiently.
- My Ferrari, happy to see it idling.
- Okay, which is better?
Reversing into a parking space or going in face first?
- I have this argument with my husband all the time.
- I always go in face first.
- I was reverse, I wonder if it's a gender thing.
- I don't believe it's easier to reverse into any spot.
- All right, you're doing the challenge.
- Because then I reverse coming out, don't I?
- We both have to reverse at some stage.
Although my dream is I drive in straight
and then the person in front of me
and the other parking spot leaves
and I can just go straight through the parking spots.
- That's a great day when that happens.
I knew this would be a hot button topic.
And if you're listening at home
and you've got opinions about whether you reverse
it or go face first.
- Okay, here's another reason why you should do
what Anna does.
Reversing out of a parking space is more dangerous
because there are people walking around there.
- Bingo.
- Whereas it's unlikely there's someone walking
in your parking spot.
- Exactly that.
So there is a writer called Tom Vanderbilt
who's an American traffic writer.
And basically, particularly in America,
which is where he's focused on,
there are loads of crashes, you know,
some of them fatal in car parks.
And it's because people,
and it's also because American cars
are way bigger than European ones.
People just get in, they reverse out,
visibility's much reduced.
However, there are some places where it is illegal
in America to reverse into a parking space.
- Really?
- What?
- I know.
- There's a city in California called San Luis Obispo,
I'm sure I'm saying that wrong too,
which has made it illegal to reverse into a space.
I don't know.
- Everyone who lives there is a woman
in a 1950s sexist joke, aren't they?
So it's just chaos.
- It's clearly safer to do the opposite
of the law in this place, which is nuts.
- It must be the fights, right?
Because you, in order to reverse it,
you have to pass the spot.
And then it's like you've changed your mind,
they're going, actually, I'm gonna,
and they're going, no, I'm a front parker.
Yeah, I think that's probably it.
- Can I say one last thing
about an effect of traffic changes?
So, New York City has just a little bit of glamour,
has just introduced a congestion charge.
- Okay.
- Yeah, very late.
London had it about, what, 15, 20 years ago, you know?
- Well, Durham had it before that.
So, yeah. - Did it?
Oh, nice, okay.
Well, New York has finally caught up
with Swing and Durham
and brought in a congestion charge.
And it's like, it's only a month or two in,
and it's, you know, politically sort of much vexed
'cause some people are saying,
"Oh, it's terrible, it's woke, blah, blah, blah."
But it's cut down traffic a massive amount.
Like, it's just journeys are much smoother now.
But the other weird effect it's had,
it's cut down another thing that's common in New York.
What's it called then? - Honking.
- Honking.
- Oh, very good. - Okay.
Honk-related complaints are down 70%.
- Oh, really? - 70%.
- Wow. - Is that just car honking?
Or is it also people pretending
to grab people's breasts?
(laughing)
- Well, no, actually, those are up hugely, sadly.
I also load the number of instances of people saying,
"I'm walking here."
- Oh, that's to cars?
- That's tragically down, 94%, really sad.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that bacteria eat clouds.
(laughing)
So it turns out, up in the sky,
there's a lot of stuff living up there, lots of stuff.
And a lot of it is very small.
So, you know, fungal spores, viruses, and bacteria.
And the bacteria, how they can live up there for so long
is that they get their energy from the little bits
that make clouds.
So, if you think about it, a cloud is made out of water,
right? - Mm-hmm.
- But the water can't just stay up there by itself.
It needs to get around something.
So there's little bits of dust.
There might be little bits of dead animals up there,
little bits of, you know, dead fungal spores,
something like that.
- Little bits of dead animals,
like the leg of a rabbit.
(laughing)
- The roadkill that the planes hit on there up there.
- Tiny cellular.
- I meant tiny cellular things, yeah,
as opposed to a trunk of an elephant.
But yeah, so that stuff might be made of carbon,
and the bacteria can use this carbon
to make a molecule called adenosine triphosphate, or ATP,
which is basically what we all use,
what all living-- - How mitochondria?
- Yeah, all living things use it to create energy,
and they get theirs from this stuff that's in clouds.
- Yeah, cool. - It's sort of,
I always thought these are nucleators,
the little bits that clouds gather around it.
I always thought they were mainly dust and bits of earth,
and basically water attaches them,
forms ice around them, and that's clouds.
But actually, up to 100% of them in some places,
and the vast majority are biological.
So it's largely the corpses of other bacteria
that bacteria are eating.
- Yeah, and a lot of dust is, like,
comes from bacteria or-- - Yeah, used to be alive.
- It's wild to think, though, that when it rains,
there's an estimate that says a single square meter
of ground gets pelted with 100 million bacteria
during every hour of rainstorm.
- Yeah, I-- - So you're being rained
on by bacteria. - 'Cause I don't really like
using umbrellas, 'cause I feel like it's a bit soft,
and so I can always go out in the rain,
and I'm just kind of happy to get wet,
and also, 'cause I'm from Bolton,
I feel like it reminds me of home when it rains.
- Yeah, right. - But now that I know
all that bacteria is coming down as well,
I feel like I might have to use an umbrella.
- Oh, you're being mad at me. - But now you know
you're being bombarded with fungal spores.
- I know. - Yeah.
- Yeah, you've got a real two mixed signals coming in there.
That's so huge, James.
I recently considered buying a second umbrella stand.
(laughing)
- Honestly, if anyone listening wants to know
the difference between me and Abby,
that pretty much sums us up.
(laughing)
- It's pretty wild, though, that it's not just the rain,
that I grew up by the beaches in Australia.
Every crashing wave was pumping bacteria into my face.
I just didn't know that. - It's crazy, 'cause I always go
swimming completely naked, 'cause I think if you wear
a swimsuit, that's soft. (laughing)
- Now you're burkini, aren't you?
- I read a piece, which I'm sure you guys all did,
which was printed in microbiology today in 2005.
- I'd read it before. (laughing)
I'm really visited.
- This was a fantastic, I just wanted to give a shout out
to Dale Griffin.
I don't know if he's still training or still listening,
but it's about soil moving across the earth every year.
I just want to read you the quote.
The current estimate of the soil moving some distance
in the earth's atmosphere each year
is approximately three billion metric tons.
If that was converted into 1964 Volkswagen Beetles,
based on weight and dimensions,
there would be enough beetles to create
a 42 kilometer tall tower with base area equivalent
to the walled city of Chester, UK.
- Oh my God. (laughing)
- Mate. - So, hang on.
- So think about that. (laughing)
- I'm struggling to pick that. - So the amount of soil--
- Did we need the beetles in there?
Couldn't we just have the soil making the tower?
- No, no, no, because the soil is denser than beetles.
The soil is converted, three billion tons of soil,
converting to three billion tons of Volkswagen Beetles.
You can't stay inside of a Volkswagen Beetle
is not full of soil.
- No, not unless you've been doing
some very heavy driving. (laughing)
- Interesting, okay, well, I say interesting.
It's a cool tower, yeah. (laughing)
- Do we need Chester any more?
Wouldn't it be better to have a 42 kilometer tall tower?
- Tea hailstorms, you know about these?
- No. - Tea plantations?
- Yes. - Oh.
- They're more common hailstorms over tea plantations.
And it was this really big mystery in 1979.
There was a scientist in Kenya
who was aware that the world record of hailstorms
was on Kenyan tea plantations.
They got 132 days of them a year.
- Wow.
- Which is a lot of hail and didn't know why.
And it turns out it's all the tea pickers fault.
Basically, as they walk through the tea plantation
picking the tea, they kick up bits of leaf,
bits of dead tea leaf into the air.
And there's a bacteria in tea leaf
that attaches itself to the leaves as they rot
and they're flawless hail nucleators.
So, as you kick up the tea leaves into the air,
you free up these bacteria,
they go straight up into the air,
and they hail down again.
- Incredible. - Does it damage the tea?
- Must do, right?
- It seems like it would,
but it's not like they're constantly having
to move the tea plantations to escape the hailstorms, so.
- There's a scientist writer called,
I think he's called Zimmer,
who's writing a lot about- - Kazema.
- Kazema, and he writes a lot about these things
which are collectively aeroplankton is the term for them.
And it contributes a huge amount to the circle of life.
So, there's a bacteria called Pseudomonas,
and it's very good at turning water to ice
or helping water turn to ice.
And so, when a plant is covered in this stuff on the ground
with these bacteria and rain lands,
the Pseudomonas bacteria turn the water twice,
the leaf cracks open,
and the bacteria can then get inside the leaf,
which is what it's trying to do,
it's trying to feed on the leaf.
So, that's what the bacteria's function is,
and it sort of damages the plant.
But, clouds containing those bacteria rain more,
and it might be that that helps plants grow
because plants need rain to grow.
So, actually, everyone's helping everyone in this world.
- So, they're kind of happy to have this little bacteria
cracking open their leaves,
'cause they know by doing that,
they're gonna get more rain.
- Exactly.
And so, the thing is,
there are these kind of bacteria motorways in the sky,
which is mapped.
These kind of-
- They're traffic light controlled,
or is it like a roundabout way system?
- Well, there's this thing,
the environment is called the Aerobiome.
Like, outdoor above us is the Aerobiome.
So, in cities, the Aerobiome is less diverse,
and there are fewer microbes,
and then the countryside loads more microbes
in the countryside,
and maybe this affects whether you get asthma,
you know, the environment you live in,
whether you breathe in more or fewer,
all different kinds of these things sort of affects that.
But, some scientists think that the 2001
foot and mouth outbreak in the UK,
which was cattle, livestock foot and mouth, not human one,
they think it might've been due to a storm in North Africa,
which may have carried spores north,
because a week after that storm,
cases of foot and mouth started happening.
So-
- How interesting.
- Could be that.
- And that's the Sahara, I think, wasn't it?
Which gets blamed for a lot of stuff being carried.
I think it was from there that they thought
it might have come.
'Cause similarly, I think we've talked before
about how a lot of the sand in the Caribbean
is blown over from the Sahara,
and there was this major coral disease in 1999,
which killed off loads of Caribbean coral.
It was a fungus called Aspergillus sidae,
and it happened to coincide with all these dust storms
in the Sahara, and this fungus lived in the Sahara Desert,
been picked up, blown all the way over to the Caribbean,
killed a bunch of coral, bloody Sahara Desert.
- I read something about this,
which I don't have in my notes, 'cause it was years ago,
but I think there's an underwater cave in the Caribbean,
which is one of the best places to study old sand
from the Sahara, because it flies over there.
It hits the water, it goes down, it gets into this cave,
and it's kind of stuck there,
and no one can contaminate it or anything,
and I think it's called the Dam Cave.
- Oh, wow.
- I think, from memory.
- That feels like an enterprising scientist has said,
"Well, I need to study the Sahara,
"but I'm going to need to study from the Caribbean."
(laughing)
And that's incredible.
- I think that's true.
- That is so good.
- The Dam Cave sounds like something
so much more disgusting than that, actually.
- It's like a man cave.
- No offense.
- It's weird.
I always think you're like superhero back cave.
- That's where I went.
- You went straight for the Dirty Magazines.
- Yeah.
- I was actually thinking of rotting Nessie corpses and stuff.
(laughing)
- With me just wanking in the corner.
- There's no need for that.
- That's what my wife said.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that number one selling singer,
Sabrina Carpenter,
is the niece of another number one selling singer,
Bart Simpson.
- Wow.
- It's a confusing fact, 'cause much like me,
none of you would have heard of this Sabrina Carpenter,
and you won't know the Bart Simpson,
who's the leading singer.
- Who's the Bart Simpson fellow?
(laughing)
Okay, so a lot of people will know
that Sabrina Carpenter is one of the biggest pop stars
in the world right now,
and she has had a bunch of singles
that have gone to number one.
Mia Espresso, for example, is one,
and it turns out that her auntie is Nancy Cartwright,
the voice of Bart Simpson,
who herself had a number one hit,
would do the Bartman.
- Can I just say, I read someone on Reddit,
someone called Blamennixson,
saying that that makes Nancy Cartwright a carpenter aunt.
(laughing)
- 'Cause she's called Sabrina Carpenter.
- And Carpenter aunties, and David for Species of Ant.
- Nice, that's good.
- That's pretty good.
- Oh, and Anne is a Northern pronunciation of aunt.
- Yes. - Yes.
- Got it, thank you.
That was the missing link I needed.
- I just thought it was a good joke,
but not good enough that I was gonna claim it myself.
(laughing)
- You thought you'd buy the kite.
You could always edit out the Reddit bit
if it goes really well.
- Are you a fan of Sabrina Carpenter?
- Huge fan.
- I thought you would be,
'cause she's a big fan of Moss.
(gasping)
The album cover of her last but one album,
"Email So I Can't Send,"
was inspired by old photos of Kate Moss.
(laughing)
- So who was it, was it someone from Reddit as well?
- It's old mine.
(laughing)
- Well, you have me going there.
- I really like Sabrina Carpenter.
- I think she's great as well.
- I actually think you would like her,
'cause who was the person we spoke about who sang--
- Oh, it's my party.
- It's my party. - It's Leslie Gore.
- Yeah, I think of her as a modern day Leslie Gore.
- Oh, wow. - Her song, "Please, Peace, Please,"
I reckon is pretty much the modern version of that song.
- I'm always open to new talent.
- I'll give this girl a go.
I'll give her a go and see if maybe we can help her.
- Apparently she's doing fine without me.
She's doing okay.
- So was she the only one of the Carpenter's
who had a career after--
- Oh, she's not current Carpenter's sister.
- Yeah, she's not related to the Carpenter's.
She, what we've got here is two people
who live in the modern world and they've got me and Anna.
- Well, let me give you a bit of background
about Sabrina Carpenter.
So Nancy Cartwright's step-brother is David Carpenter,
who is Sabrina Carpenter's dad.
He is an x-ray servicing company member.
His-- - Sorry?
- Sorry?
- David Carpenter works--
- He's an x-ray servicing company member.
- Yeah, it doesn't feel very important.
That fact is not real.
- Well, I mean, you said it in the same way
that you would say, "He's a teacher."
Or, "Oh, he's a doctor."
He's an x-ray servicing company member.
Company member, right, okay.
- If you ever meet someone like that at a party,
again, you're moving on to the next person.
- Do you have my friend, Andy?
- I'm going home with the lobe muffler, that's the point.
(all laughing)
Get your big trunk, you pulled.
Her mum is a chiropractor.
The reason I mentioned these two things,
the reason I mentioned it,
is because outside of Nancy Cartwright,
there's no connection to the world of entertainment.
- She's not a depot baby, right?
- Exactly, she's often accused of that
as a result of that connection,
but they don't seem to be that.
She started her freaking,
she can get all the x-rays she wants.
(all laughing)
Anytime she likes.
- Need your back clicked, you are in luck, my friend.
- She released her first single,
which was called, "Can't Blame a Girl for Trying,"
one week after fish started.
So she is as old as fish for one week.
Yeah, March 14th, 2014.
- We should get a watch,
we could have a joint birthday party.
- Yeah, she's still got a week
to catch up and be as big as us.
Is that what I'm saying?
(all laughing)
- She started off, she did a Miley Cyrus singing competition
when she was 10 years old.
And she's-- - We're gonna have
to explain to her.
- Oh my God.
- She know Billy Ray Cyrus, her dad was Billy Ray Cyrus.
- Right.
- Who worked in the musicals.
- He was an x-ray guy.
- That's right.
But it was like a competition
for Miley Cyrus fan club members,
but it was kind of voted for by people,
it was one of those early internet things.
And it was mentioned in loads of her local newspapers.
And they basically said vote for her, vote for her, vote for her.
So she got down to the final, like three or four people.
And she was only 10 years old
and everyone else was like older teenagers doing it.
- So was that when she started out,
when fish was--
- Yeah, well actually-- - That would be earlier.
- Oh, okay.
- Yeah, that was earlier.
And then she went on to YouTube
'cause she got big on this competition
and put a load of songs on YouTube
and then got massive on YouTube.
Then she got picked up by the Disney club or someone.
- Yeah, she did a show called Girl Meets World,
which I think was a reboot of Boy Meets World,
which is a big show when I was a teenager.
She was cast as the lead character,
the Lindsay Lohan character
and the mean girl's musical that Tina Fey did on stage.
So she had a bit of a career ahead of it.
And then she did this.
- A lot of slogging away before you're an overnight success.
- Exactly.
- That's what we felt.
- Is this like an ad crossover swap
is she gonna release a song about no such thing as a bitch?
And that's saying for this party.
- Yeah, I gotta say.
- Come on, it's like,
we're not expecting any publicity back
from the traffic lights into Shaggy.
(all laughing)
- Nancy Cartwright.
- Oh yeah.
- Is this disappointing or am I being judgmental?
She's big on Scientology.
I know they all are, but she's really big.
- What do you mean they all are?
- All the famous people.
(all laughing)
- Have you not seen the roof of Mo's cavern?
It's one of those big pyramid wire things that you wear.
- She, Cartwright was awarded in 2023,
the status of patron Excalibur with honors
by the Church of Scientology,
which she called the most beautiful acknowledgement
I've ever received in my life,
which I think is really weird to appreciate that.
'Cause the reason she's got it,
I assume is that she's donated $20 million
to the Church of Scientology.
- So where the Simpsons money goes?
- That's where it's going.
- Well, there's a lot of Simpsons money, isn't it?
- Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, this album that you're talking about down,
this was The Simpsons Sing the Blues released in 1990.
- This is the, Nancy Cartwright.
- Oh, I'm sorry.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I threw the Batman on it.
- Exactly, that was the first track.
And that sold in the UK, it's on 400,000 copies.
- Yeah, I remember it was absolutely Monday.
- Yeah, well, yeah, it went to number one here,
but it didn't in America, oddly.
And what's weird is it was only played on Sky One
at this point, The Simpsons in the UK.
So for overseas listeners, that's a sort of,
what do you call that?
- You have to pay for it.
- Yeah, it's a pay for channel, so quite wild.
- The album sounds very good.
It's got lots of great musicians on it.
BB King, Dr. John, DJ Jazzy Jeff.
I mean, these are my people, I don't know if they're with.
- It was listed that Michael Jackson
was the composer of Do The Batman,
which I think we might've said on this show,
and I believe that's not actually true.
- Yes.
- A guy called Brian, Brian Lauren.
But it got sold two million copies in the USA.
I mean, it was a really,
I think people forget how massive The Simpsons was.
- Yeah.
- The biggest cartoon ever.
- Well, until the new Chinese movie, "Nasia."
- I can't take another pop-cotch reference.
(all laughing)
- It's just there's a new animated movie,
which is the biggest animated movie of all time.
It literally came out this week.
That's it.
- Oh, wow.
- Will that be The Simpsons movie?
- Yeah.
- Probably, yeah.
- Nancy Korrow, by the way, before she was Bart,
she did various different roles.
So she did, in my little pony,
she did a voice that was quite similar to Bart Simpson.
But probably for me, most iconically,
she did the voice of, if you remember who framed Roger Rabbit,
there's a moment where there is a shoe being dipped
into a vat of acid.
That's her.
- Brilliant.
- That's Nancy Korrow.
- It's quite a seminal bit of that movie.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I don't think that's even on a Wikipedia page.
You need to get that up there.
(all laughing)
- That's funny.
- Guys, who's the main creator of The Simpsons
that comes up?
- Matt Groening.
- Groening.
- Not him.
- Sorry, it is.
I just can't believe I've been saying Groening all these years.
You see that name so much.
You think Groening is Groening.
- Groening.
- Do you know what his parents called?
- Oh, it'll be.
- Mr. and Mrs. Groening.
- Wouldn't it be like Homer and Marge?
- It's Homer and Marge.
- Is it? - Yeah, yeah.
- His dad's a consultant radiology company member,
isn't he?
(all laughing)
Yeah.
The effects it had in the early years was brilliant.
I just love all the things.
'Cause there was a time where The Simpsons
was really big in the news.
And I know they're still making it now,
but there was a time where like it prompted big headlines.
So in 1996, The New York Times reported
that there was a mega glut of saxophony
happening in America.
All children wanted to learn the saxophone
because of Lisa Simpson.
- Yeah, makes sense.
- Sax teachers said, they interviewed the sax teachers
who said, this is just, you know, it's a nightmare.
They would have a whole band of saxophone students.
- This is like, who are we talking about last week,
the farmers who complain when they get too big a yield?
- The saffron.
- Yeah, the saffron farmers,
bloody saxophone teacher, Killjoy.
- Sorry, band leaders were furious about this
'cause they, you know, they desperately needed a piccolo
and all they got was a thousand saxophones.
- Ah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, that makes sense.
- And they interviewed one who said,
also due to the fact that if you go to the movies,
it's always the sax playing the steamy part
when there's something interesting going on on the screen.
- Saxy.
- Saxy stuff.
- That's very cool.
- Also Bill Clinton and Kenny G.
- Oh, yes.
- Oh, gosh.
- The two sexiest men ever to live, sex.
- So the reason I said Homer and Marsh before
is 'cause I do know that fact that he named all the characters
after his family except for Bart,
which was an anagram of brat
and he sort of came up with it in the moment.
But I was reading up on his sister, Lisa,
Grainning, and she...
- Scraining.
- Grainning, she married a man called Craig Bartlett.
- Which part of the radiology department?
- Craig Bartlett is the creator of another show
that's called Hey Arnold, which is a massive show.
- I love Hey Arnold.
- Yeah, and Dinosaur Train was a more recent one,
which my son grew up on.
But yeah, so that is a real powerhouse of a family.
A cartoon connection.
- He also named a lot of characters in The Simpsons
after places he knew about.
So he grew up in Portland, in Oregon.
And streets where he grew up,
and where he grew up included Flanders Street,
a Simpsons character.
Lovejoy Street, Reverend Lovejoy.
And there was Burnside Street in Montgomery Park
next to each other, which is Montgomery Burns.
And then Portland also has Ter Williger Boulevard.
And of course, the real name of sideshow Bob
is Robert Underdunk Ter Williger.
But he didn't name him after it.
- No.
- Completely different person.
They were interviewed once, and they named sideshow Bob
after a character from the film, The 5,000 Fingers of Tea,
who was called Dr. Ter Williger.
And it has nothing to do with the fact
that also in Portland, Oregon,
there's a street called Ter Williger Boulevard.
- That's a total coincidence.
- It's apparently so.
- Maggie Simpson is the baby.
Her first word was Daddy.
And it was said by friend of the podcast, Elizabeth Taylor.
- Oh.
- They got lots of famous people voicing it, don't they?
But she had to do six takes.
Because every time she did it, it came out too sexy.
(all laughing)
- Oh, God.
- According to producer Mike Reese,
he said we had to keep reminding Elizabeth Taylor
that she was a baby talking to her father,
not hitting on him.
(all laughing)
- Do you know who voices Maggie?
So, Maggie is, we just, we get the dummy sucking.
- So you mean who does the dummy sucking?
- Yeah.
- Who does the dummy sucking?
- Is it also Lisa, Nancy Cartwright?
- Nancy Cartwright.
- No, no.
- Is it Matt Groening?
- It's Matt Groening.
- Is it?
- Yeah.
- It's like it's an easy way to make a lot of money, isn't it?
- I think it's like when we talked about Simon Cowell
doing the cowbell just to get the credit.
- It's like, I'm just going to get a credit on this.
- He can't need more.
- It can't be the producer of the show.
It can't be the difference between him.
- 100% he'll get paid for that.
- Yeah.
- That's very funny.
- I'm going to say that's James's opinion
as to why he's doing it.
- I don't believe that's his motivation.
- That's why I coffin these shows sometimes
is to get a little extra on the back end.
- I'd love to start a feud with The Simpsons
and then maybe they'll put us in The Simpsons
as some evil, I mean, no one watches that anymore.
So it doesn't really matter, but there you go.
There's your feud.
- Cool.
- That would be, yeah, yeah.
- They used to get into great beef with people all the time
and they recently have had a bit.
They've had a bit with Morrissey.
- Okay.
- Oh yeah.
- He hates beef.
(laughing)
- They parodied him in an episode called
Panic on the Streets of Springfield.
They had a singer who had a quiff and was a vegan
and you know, they just took the Mickey a bit.
That was pretty gentle.
And Morrissey complained,
"You are especially despised if your music
affects people in a strong and beautiful way.
In fact, the worst thing you can do in 2021
is lend a bit of strength to the lives of others.
There is no place in modern music
for anyone with strong emotions.
In a world obsessed with hate laws,
there are none that protect me."
- Hang on, was this targeted at The Simpsons?
- Yes!
- Okay, so the story just sounds like a generic statement.
- It was a statement to The Simpsons.
- It was to Dear Simpsons.
And there he is.
- They've had high profile beef with world leaders.
So they had Barbara Bush called them out saying
that it wasn't a show you should watch
and Marge Simpson wrote a letter
to Barbara Bush in response saying
that she actually thinks her family is a good family.
They've had episodes where,
'cause obviously it's a global product.
And so there's a lot of references
that are gonna be not suitable for certain countries.
So in China, for example, there was one episode
they had to remove the line about Mao Zedong
being a little angel who killed 50 million people.
They thought that wasn't appropriate in Japan.
- Can you cut after angels too?
(all laughing)
- Japan, there was an episode where they had to lose a bit
because--
- They mentioned the massive Japanese bogathon.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, Hobotoss is the Japanese emperor
into a sumo thong dumpster.
So in fact, that whole episode was banned.
- Right.
- Okay, do you think that Marge should dump Homer?
- Not after all this time.
I think--
- Oh, really?
- Well, I just think once you've been in a relationship
for, when was my marriage?
Once you've been in the marriage for at least 12 years,
you shouldn't dump your husband.
- I think, yeah.
I think once the kids are grown up and out of home,
unfortunately, that's never happening.
- Okay, I only ask because you, Gov,
asked their long suffering test audiences.
This is 2018, yeah, all right.
- I think 20 people trapped in a room.
(all laughing)
- What did they say, the prisoners?
- So thank you for asking.
So 14% of women said Marge should dump Homer.
Only 8% of men said that,
so men being a bit more forgiving.
- Can't believe so few of either, though.
- Well, you go--
- He's not a good husband.
- I just want to say what you've said.
When asked, the majority, 52% of Simpsons fans
consider Homer a man who frequently strangles his son,
has framed Marge for drink driving,
committed bigamy, caused his father's kidneys to fail,
has worked for a terrorist organization,
and is frequently asleep or absent in his role overseeing
safety at a nuclear power plant to be a good person.
- Has he not also, like, he's definitely been to space.
You must have, I bet he saved the world
like three or four times.
- Yeah, he probably has.
- You're saying you take the rough with this move.
- Yeah.
- All right, so by contrast,
Bart, who's escapades are far more child-like
and consequence-like, is almost twice as likely
to be seen as a bad person at 22%,
yet Maggie, who shot Mr. Burns,
is only seen as a bad person by 4%.
- 4%.
- Sorry.
- That was a big deal, wasn't it,
when it was who shot Mr. Burns?
Were you guys the right age for that?
- I remember it was, exactly.
It was like Dallas, yeah, JR.
- Well, you guys weren't old enough for Dallas.
- No, no, no, no.
But yeah, I was there for it.
I remember it.
Apparently only, they had lots of forums at the time
saying, can you guess who it is?
And the show writers said only one person got that it was--
- I remember you could bet on it.
And I remember, I don't think even,
it was one of the options.
- Wow.
- But you weren't old enough to bet at that this time.
But this was going on.
- When did it happen?
- He had a fake ID on 990 at the end of six.
- I don't know, mid-90s?
- Well, I was born in '78.
- Okay, so it's possible.
- So I was able to, in '96, I could--
- I'm just picturing the scene in the betting shop.
Like, a load of jaded regulars gathered around
the horse racing screen and a load of, like,
nerds in the other corner watching the Simpsons.
(all laughing)
And it comes in this, Maggie.
Oh!
(all laughing)
Get her out of your ticket.
One guy goes to the counter, pulls out the stacks
and stacks of cash.
(all laughing)
- Isn't that Matt Groening?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @Sriberland.
Andy.
- I'm on Blue Sky at @andrewhunderem.
- James.
- My Instagram is @no such thing as James Harkin.
- And if you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can find us on @nosuchthing on Twitter
or @nosuchthingasafish on Instagram
or email podcast at qi.com.
- Yeah, do send in some emails
because they will make their way,
hopefully, to our bonus episode that happens in Club Fish.
Club Fish is our secret members' club
that you can find at nosuchthingasafish.com.
We do a show called Drop Us a Line
where we go through the mail bag
and answer all of your questions.
You can also find all of our previous episodes
on that website.
There's Merchandise, there's an upcoming live show
at the Crossed Wires Festival in Sheffield
that's happening in July.
Check that out and come see us live if you're around.
Otherwise, come back next week.
We'll be back with another episode
and we'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]