(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of No Such Things as a Fish.
We are slap bang in the middle of our tour right now
and that means that you yourself can come and see us live.
- Yes, you can.
We love doing the tours.
We're having a great time this time around.
We record a new podcast every time we do a show
and we have lots of little nerdy,
extra never before seen bits in between
and we are going to be in Cardiff, in London Town
and in Manchester very soon.
So we are in Cardiff on the 16th of October,
London on the 23rd and the 24th
and Manchester on the 27th.
- That is correct.
And one of the places we will be very soon is Gothenburg.
We will be in Gothenburg on the 27th of September.
That's a week on Friday
and we will be doing a live episode of the podcast there.
So do come along, search for the Gothenburg Book Festival
and you'll see all the details about that.
- And of course you can get tickets to that
and all the others by going to No Such Things
as a Fish dot com slash live.
- Okay, I don't know, I think it's time to sound check.
We better get on with it.
- Let's get on with the show.
- On with the podcast.
(beeping)
(speaking in foreign language)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast this week coming to you live from Bristol.
(crowd cheering)
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
- My fact is that the unauthorized release of beavers
into British waterways is known as beaver bombing.
(crowd laughing)
- That's exerting.
- Yeah, this has been covered recently.
They're all over the place now
and they've been making their way back.
So the river Otter is now full of beavers and--
- Confusingly.
- Very confusing.
- Which pisses off the otters in the river Otter,
as I suspect.
- Are there otters in the river Otter?
- There are otters in the river Otter.
And I did read that someone was saying the Camel River
is another good place to introduce them,
which I imagine will piss off the camels
in the Camel River.
- And there are hundreds of them out there now.
- Is that really in the UK?
- In the UK, yeah, yeah.
In researching this fact, I spoke to someone who said,
very secretively, they were related to someone
who knew a thing or two about reintroducing secret beavers.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, sort of gorilla, confusingly.
(crowd laughing)
- The gorillas are furious.
- Yeah, and so I've read an interview as well
with a guy called Simon.
Basically, it takes a lot of time and paperwork
to release a beaver outside an enclosure.
You need to do an impact assessment.
Sometimes on the Isle of Wight,
you have to do 100,000 words of impact assessment.
100,000 words, that's a novel, that's a full novel.
- Yeah, and people are objecting, aren't they?
'Cause no one's got time to read that many words.
- But why do we want beavers anyway?
- Well, because they build dams, don't they?
And it creates this lovely kind of ecosystem
for lots of other things to exist.
They're like engineers.
So there are these people, and it's such an exciting world.
If you want to get into crime,
but feel like you're doing kind of a good thing,
I think beaver bombing is the way.
- Interesting.
- There's a guy called Olivier Rubbers.
Did you read about him?
He was one of the originals.
He was in 1998, he just heard someone mention
the reintroduction of beavers and he decided,
I'm gonna do that, borrowed his dad's car,
and he drove to Germany.
I think he lived in Belgium, drove to Germany,
picked up some beavers, crossed the border,
back into Belgium, dropped them in a river,
went so well, he repeated it with 97 more beavers.
(laughing)
- Why?
- He did 97 different journeys,
or did he go, all right, lads, in the car?
- Yeah, it's like that riddle.
You're not allowed to take a beaver with another beaver,
otherwise they eat each other.
- Right, that's crazy.
Hey, do you know, if you let a beaver into your lounge room,
it will rearrange all your furniture.
Isn't that amazing?
- Oh, that's nice.
- That's lovely, along Feng Shui principles.
- No, this is a thing that was noticed by someone
who wrote a lot about beavers back in the day.
She was sort of a conservationist who wanted to raise
the idea that they're intelligent animals
that they're interesting to look at.
She was called Dorothy Richards,
and she was looking after beavers,
and they came into her house,
and as soon as they walked in, they were like,
no, let's put the chair over there,
let's get that over there.
And apparently, according to her,
they are the only animals apart from humans
that radically transform their environment.
So it's all about safety.
They want the room perfect.
So if you put a beaver in your room, it will be different.
- And it will flood the room.
- Yes.
- Crucially.
- What they do is they build the dams
where they hear the water the most, right?
'Cause they wanna find the narrow part of the river
where the water's really flowing.
So they listen out for loud water.
When they find the loud water,
that's where they build their dams.
But if you get a tape recorder
and put it in the middle of the room,
and put a beaver in there,
they'll go around finding any bits and pieces in the room
and then just put it all on top of the tape recorder.
- Yeah, that's cool. - That's very cool.
So they make dams,
and this can help to clean the water,
can it, in rivers.
The ones in the River Otter,
they store 24 million liters of water,
which is the equivalent of 10 Olympic-sized swimming pools.
And they reckon it could help our bills, our water bills,
because they clean it,
that means the water companies don't have to.
(audience laughing)
'Cause I did find that between November 2019
and February 2020,
sewage treatment works near Stoke illegally release sewage
equivalent to 10 Olympic-sized swimming pools.
So basically all those beavers
just did the right amount of work
to help that one sewage leak.
- That's great.
So they're the sort of water company's friend?
- Yeah. - That's nice.
I don't like them as much now.
(audience laughing)
- Do you know what a beaver deceiver is?
- Um, is that like catfishing?
- Is it like a...
(audience laughing)
Oh yeah.
- So it's someone who tricks a beaver in some way
into building them a dam for their own use though.
- Basically you've got an area where you want to have beavers,
but you don't want the area to be flooded.
And so you allow them to build their dam,
but then you might put a little pipe in it
so the water can still go through,
but they can still do their dam.
And that's called a beaver deceiver.
It's just nice to say.
- Yeah.
Was there ever a dog that was a beaver retriever?
(audience laughing)
I don't know.
- Hey, I read a sentence about beavers
and I wasn't able to find anything more out about it.
So I'm just saying it in case you guys did,
but it was such a mysterious sentence in a review
about a book on beavers.
It said, "Beavers never walked backwards."
(audience laughing)
- Okay.
- Did you read the next sentence in the review?
- They eat their food twice.
(audience laughing)
- They do do that.
- They cannot doggy paddle.
They have ever growing orange teeth
with which to gnaw woody plants.
- Is this book review 10 weird facts about beavers?
(audience laughing)
- No, it's an amazing book about the point being made
that beavers, actually, they don't only make dams,
but they made America, effectively.
America's fortunes were effectively down to beavers.
And it was fur trading.
Beavers were virtually extinct over here, right?
Because they'd been hunted down, we'd used all the fur.
And then we found out that in North America,
there were all these beavers there.
So all the ships went over and started hunting them down.
And then you ended up with billionaires of beaver fur.
And it made America.
- I read that it literally created Canada,
beaver trade, basically.
'Cause you had all the people on the East Coast,
and they needed to find more and more beavers.
And so they had to go inland and inland,
and they set up all these kind of trading posts
between all of the First Nations people.
And all those trading posts that came because of beaver pelts
was what became Canada in the end.
- Yeah, it's very hard to underestimate
how totally essential they were.
But when New York was sold to the Dutch
by the Native Americans,
I read that actually it was mostly beaver pelts
that were sold.
And New York was like a little bonus.
They were like, "We'll sell you 2,000 beaver pelts.
And also we've got Manhattan as well.
Do you want this one too?"
And they were like, "Yeah, okay, toss it in."
But yeah, crucial.
And historically, it seems someone fair
for such a crucial animal
that the main thing they're famous for
is taking off their testicles.
If you Google beavers, and their name--
- What?
- If you Google beavers with your safe search off.
You do get a lot of testicles that give you that.
- You wouldn't think testicles were the first thing.
- How did they take them off?
- Well, I mean, they didn't take them off at all.
But since ancient Greek, since Esop's fables,
there was this idea that beaver testicles
were very sought after, which they were,
for their medicinal qualities, which didn't exist.
And beavers figured out that if they tore off the testicles,
threw them at the hunter,
the hunter wouldn't chase after the beavers anymore.
The reason this came about is because they hide their testicles
behind this fleshy flap, the male beavers.
- Lovely.
- So, yes, I think fleshy flap is the term.
And so, people were like, where are their testicles?
They must have torn them off because of this reason.
But it's where the name comes from.
So castorium is the stuff they secrete.
Their name is castor in the Latin name.
And that's from castrated, same origin.
'Cause the idea was they ripped off their testicles.
- When I was kid in Bolton,
we used to shout beaver in the streets.
If we ever saw anyone with a beard, you did beavering.
- This is so exciting.
- Literally, we would walk down the road
and there was someone with a beard
and the first person to spot them would shout beaver.
- Right.
- I read that this was a game popular
in the 1910s and 1920s.
(audience laughing)
- I believe that is the case in the rest of the country.
- What would beavering survive?
- What would the beaver do, what would they say?
- Well, they would be confused.
They would be like, that game hasn't been popular
since the 1920s and were there variations for you?
- I can't remember.
I was really young when it happened.
It wasn't literally in the 1920s,
but yeah, I was really young when it happened.
- 'Cause supposedly there were things like
if someone had a beard and a moustache,
that was a royal beaver or there was a king beaver,
which is a red, whiskered policeman
riding a green bicycle.
(audience laughing)
And I just wondered if you knew the--
- No, I didn't know the nose.
But my theory is that the use of beaver
for women's genitals is from that game.
I'm pretty sure it is.
Because the first citation of that is from 1927.
And the citation in the Oxford English Dictionary says
she took off her clothes from her head to her toes
and the voice at the keyhole yelled beaver.
- Right.
- So it genuinely seems like that might be it.
- Yeah.
Well, I'll tell you what, Canada in 1920,
that was the year that what is now
their second oldest magazine ever was founded.
It was called The Beaver.
And it lasted all the way until 2010
until it needed to change its name,
which they've just changed to Canada's history.
And it was largely because none of their emails
were getting through to anyone
because they were being filtered out by foreign filters.
(audience laughing)
So all of their emails, all their newsletters,
nothing reaching it.
People were confused anyway about it.
- Same as Beaver College in Pennsylvania.
- Really?
- They changed their name because, again,
that no one could get to their website.
- Plus the applicants they got were questionable,
to say the least.
(laughing)
- So there wasn't an attempt before now
to reintroduce beavers to the UK
'cause I think there were some hundreds of thousands
in the Middle Ages.
Europe had about between 60 and 400 million beavers.
So I think that's a sign that no one really knows
how many there were.
But there were attempts to reintroduce them
'cause they clung on a few,
and like really far Eastern sort of like central Asian step
that there were a few beavers knocking around.
- Right.
- And in the 1860s, there wasn't an attempt
to re-beaver in Suffolk and--
- Is that the technical term?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- To re-beaver.
- Re-beaver, yeah, yeah.
But they were de-beavered, they were destroyed.
(laughing)
And the very final ones, I just like this,
were sent to London to be stuffed by Lady Gooch.
(laughing)
- That sounds like another euphemism, doesn't it?
- How was that not your headline fact?
(laughing)
Beavers used to be stuffed by Lady Gooch.
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number two, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in the 1600s,
the Spanish ambassador to England had a specially made chair
with a hole in the bottom to accommodate his anal fistula.
(laughing)
- Wow, hmm.
- Yeah, this is such a good article that I read.
It was on history today, and it was about a play
called A Game at Chess, which is the most popular play
of the 1600s.
Most of you won't remember it.
The main--
- Still big in Bolton.
(laughing)
- The main villain in it is a guy called Diego Sarmiento
de Acuña, or Count Gondemar, who was the Spanish ambassador
to England between 1613 and 1622,
and he had an anal fistula that was very famous.
And I just think if you've got an anal fistula,
you don't want it to be famous.
It impacted his movement, and--
- It's hard to say how famous it was, isn't it?
- Right, literally everyone in the country knew about it.
- Their posters on their bedroom wall, it was--
- But how many people can even name
the Spanish ambassador now?
It's a job that has undergone a huge decline in prestige
in the last 400 years.
- Right.
- Yeah, it's since we weren't at war with Spain anymore.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- Exactly, but I just think that's really tragic.
I looked up the current--
- We're not at war with Spain anymore?
(laughing)
- I'm willing to say, "Wow, come and have a go."
Well, no, I just think it's as in,
I looked up the Spanish ambassador to the UK earlier.
I've forgotten his name.
- Right, yeah.
- It's definitely Spanish, but I just mean--
- Yeah, yeah.
- I think it's a shame for him.
And when you say an anal fistula,
I actually would like a quick sense check on what that is,
because I like the way you said in your fact,
his chair had a hole in the bottom,
because as far as I can tell,
that is what one of those is, right?
(laughing)
But it's a sort of extra hole in the bottom.
- Yeah, it's one too many.
- Right.
- A fistula is a hole basically between two tubes.
- Yeah.
- It's a gap where there shouldn't be a gap.
- The hole in the bottom of the chair
was not 'cause he had something hanging out
that had to drop through it,
which is kind of what you assume, I think,
when you hear me say that.
It's because it would be so sensitive and painful.
And he also had to be carried through the streets
of London on a sedan chair,
'cause everyone hated him so much
that they would attack him if he was carried,
you know, if he walked.
- Really?
- Plus it was quite hard to walk with a fistula.
- Well, like kick him in the bum kind of thing, as a--
- I think that would probably be one of the tactics, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Surely something to make you less likable
is having yourself carried through the streets of London
in a sedan chair.
- Surely just wear a hat and go out and just...
- When you say it doesn't, a secret...
- No.
- Well, it does.
I mean, it does, and it is an unpleasant condition.
- But not feces, it doesn't act as a second bum hole.
It acts as a second bum hole.
- Yeah, yeah, of course.
Because basically it's caused by some sort of infection.
Sorry for the gory details,
but it's important to know if you have one.
An infection somewhere in the anal tract,
and there's a bunch of pus builds up,
and then when it goes away, it leaves a little tunnel
that goes from the anal tract out of the sort of button.
Right near the bum hole,
and so it will leak things from your bow.
- Most of my stuff is about Spanish foreign policy.
- Right.
(audience laughing)
- Do you guys remember when my wife, Fenella,
thought that my oldest son, Will, had a second bum hole?
(audience laughing)
- No.
It was in the first few weeks after he had been born.
It was our first child,
and you have to change the nappy every few hours, right?
So you're getting up at like two a.m., four a.m.
I got up at like two or four,
and I was going to change the nappy,
and Fenella said to me,
"Don't forget to wipe a second bum."
And I said, "Excuse me?"
And she said, "His second bum hole, don't forget so,
"because it could get infected if you don't wipe it properly."
And I said, "What do you mean?"
And basically newborn babies,
they have a little dent that's right at the top,
but she thought that that was an actual other bum hole.
This is how tired and sleep deprived she was.
- What did she think was going to happen to this
in the fullness of time?
Does she think there are people walking
among us who have this?
- I said to her, I was like,
"How did you think that was possible?"
And she was like, "I don't know how boys work.
"I don't know what you have."
(audience laughing)
- That's fair.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So the Spanish in the 1600s,
(audience laughing)
they had been at war with Britain,
or with England, I should say.
And this guy, Gondama, who was the ambassador,
he'd come to the English court
and he'd become really best friends with King James.
They were super close.
And because they were so close,
he started making James do lots of policies
that were very pro-Spanish.
And it eventually came to the extent
where he forced James to execute Walter Raleigh,
because so Walter Raleigh had been a pirate
and attacking some Spanish ships.
And he said, "Well, we're gonna go to war
"unless you execute him."
James first said, "Okay, fine, you're my best mate.
"I will do it."
And then obviously, everyone hated him
from that moment.
- It's just incredible.
- Yeah, the Spanish ambassador has the power
to ask the king.
- Well, we don't know that he did.
- Imagine if King Charles executed Alan Titchmarsh
on the orders of whoever the Spanish ambassador is now.
I was just trying to think of a beloved national figure,
like a national figurehead.
- Alan Titchmarsh isn't attacking Spanish possessions.
At most, he's buying up some Spanish plants.
- Okay, it's a bad example.
- Did you guys read the account
of the execution of Walter Raleigh?
- No.
- That's sort of alluded to.
He was incredibly popular.
He was like the fanciable, you know,
Clive Owen or whatever of his day.
And PR-wise, he nailed the execution.
So it was pretty dodgy grounds
on which he was sentenced to death for treason.
The morning of his execution,
he had this huge breakfast.
He was puffing on his pipe.
He had a glass of wine.
He made a joke about it.
He went up to the scaffold and he said,
"Sorry, do you mind if I just say a few words
"at the scaffold?"
He made a 25-minute speech.
Full of sort of charm and laughs and warmth.
At one point, he sensed that the nobles on the balcony
couldn't hear him properly.
And so he invited them all onto the scaffold with him
and started the speech again.
So that they could hear it properly.
And he shook all of their hands, saying,
"Hello, how are you, how's your wife?"
All of that.
At one point, the sheriff said,
"Do you want to come and warm yourself by the fire
"while you give this speech?"
And he said, "No, I'm getting a bit sick,
"so I want to get this over with before I get ill again."
And then he apologized to his executioner
for going on so long.
And then popped his head under the ax and went.
- Really? - Which, you know,
if you're going to go and style.
- It does feel like he was leading up
to something incredibly clever.
- That's the shame of it.
- You know, one person who, I was trying to,
I was really hoping there was a Wikipedia article
which was notable people with anal fistulas.
And it wasn't, it wasn't there.
It's kind of the thing Wiki sometimes has.
But one person, if the page did exist,
that would belong on there, is Charles Dickens.
- Oh.
- Dickens had a fistula.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, and he had it very early on in his career.
And there's an argument that had it not
had been sorted out by a pioneering doctor at the time,
who was called Frederick Salmon,
then we might not have had all the subsequent books
that he wrote because he was so debilitated by it.
He used to have to dictate to his then wife
and she would write down.
But he couldn't, he just couldn't think properly
with all that going on.
So this guy, Frederick Salmon,
because it was a dangerous operation back in the day.
This guy was amazing.
He set up his hospital, which was called
the Infirmary for Relief of the Poor,
afflicted with fistulas and the diseases of the rectum.
It was called that until someone said,
why don't we just call it St. Mark's?
They changed it to that.
(audience laughing)
And he carried out over 3,500 operations,
one of which was Dickens.
And as a result, he was fixed.
And then he went on to being able to sit down
and write his book.
- That's great.
- And Dickens, in those days, no NHS.
So he had to pay for his operation.
And he paid for his operation
with several autographed copies of the Pickwick papers.
- Hmm, they've not accepted
impossible things as payment at my private doctors.
- The most famous surgeon of fistulas
in the 18th century was Martin Van Butchel.
He was--
- That's very, very disconcerting for the patients.
- Well, he would put loads of adverts on.
He had amazing advertising.
He was most famous 'cause he enjoyed riding
around Hyde Park on a white pony,
which he often painted purple.
- Oh.
(audience laughing)
- And he had a really long beard
and he always carried a large white bone around with him.
- Bone?
- Bone.
You know, like Fred Flintstone might.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And his wife died.
She was killed by the Nazis, actually.
Well, she died in 1775.
- Yeah.
- And Butchel asked his friend, John Hunter,
to preserve the body.
And then he put the body on display
as kind of advertising for his fistula company.
- Lot of questionable decisions being made in this.
- The body was described soon afterwards
as a repulsive looking object.
And eventually he had to get rid of it
when his second wife objected.
- Oh, that is fussy.
(audience laughing)
- His wife's preserved corpse was on display
in the college in Lincoln's Infields
until 1941 when it was bombed by the Nazis.
- Ah.
- It was not the target.
(audience laughing)
- It's too creepy.
Get rid of it.
- This play, by the way, is so fascinating
because it was 1600s.
This was performed at the Globe.
Like this was the original Shakespearean theater.
And the play itself, the plot is amazing.
It was literally as if you were watching
a live game of chess, right?
- Yeah, and the play, this is the play
that took the piss out of Condomard.
- Yes, exactly.
And so when the play started,
people very quickly realized that this was a satire
of the ambassador.
And so they had to get word to the king
in order to ban it.
And they specifically put this play on at a point
when the king went away.
So it took about nine days to get to him.
So multiple performances were happening.
They couldn't stop it from happening.
So it was such a hit job
and it was done in Shakespeare's Globe.
- And it was massively popular.
It's mad.
- Everyone got the allegory.
A seventh of the population of London
saw it in nine days.
The chess piece, which I think was the Black Knight
who represented Condomard,
was referred to as the fistula of Europe
during the play.
And 50 years later, in the 1660s or 1670s,
people were still referring to the fistula of Europe
and everyone knew what they meant.
- Right.
- Imagine that.
- Did he see it?
Was he there?
- I don't think he was.
I think he had retired as ambassador by that point.
It was his successor as ambassador,
who was a guy called Coloma who complained about it.
The play has a lot of scatological humor
and it has a lot of rude, wind-based puns.
And I was reading an article analyzing the play
in a book called "Theatre in Post-Reformation London."
And I just want to read you this sentence,
which I just really liked,
to adapt Anton, oh, so by the way,
they bring on his fake seat.
They bring on the fistula seat,
which looks exactly like a loose seat.
That's the thing.
Here's the line.
To adapt Anton Chekhov's maxim
that when a gun is introduced into a play, it must be fired.
I propose that when a toilet is brought on stage,
there must be farts.
(audience laughing)
- Lovely.
- Who would've thought?
He sounds very sinister, Condomar.
He does, I mean, in all, you know,
it would like titch my stuff aside.
I think he does sound, he tried to intimidate people.
He had himself painted as Machiavelli.
- But apparently Machiavellian wasn't a word
that was used to describe someone
who was Machiavellian until him.
So that got applied to him.
And then everyone was like, that's a great term.
- We use that for other things now.
So he's done good things as well, right?
- He married his niece.
He's done great things, as one tried to say.
He married his niece and then his cousin.
He definitely had a type.
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, that's terrible.
- No, that's not that close.
- His niece?
- His niece is pretty close, I know.
- It was the 1500s, if you do 1600s,
if you didn't marry a niece, you're a weirdo.
- How is your uncle, by the way?
(audience laughing)
- My four-legged child is doing very well as well.
Thank you.
(audience laughing)
- Bubbles from here to breakfast.
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number three, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 1930s Canada,
the Mounties dealt with illegal nudists
by covering them in itching powder.
That is a very, how did they get close enough to apply,
as in the Mounties or on horseback, I think of them as?
- That's the Mountie part of them, the Mounted.
- Did they just scatter it?
- Yeah, I think they threw it.
This was the Dukobas who were a group of 7,500 Russians
who arrived in Canada 'cause they'd been persecuted
in Russia, and there was a small group of them
who insisted on going naked all the time,
kind of for their religion.
They kind of thought it was getting closer
to Adam and Eve and all that kind of stuff,
and going naked was also a way to protest,
so they didn't really want their children
to go to the state schools, but they were forced to do so,
and so they went naked.
- Obviously, the obvious protest against not wanting
your children to go to the state school,
they wanted to keep in their communal living,
they didn't want to be forced into state housing,
so they went naked, and even if their own leaders
did things that they didn't really like, they went naked.
And the Canadian government decided this is not a good idea,
so not only did they do this thing with the itching powder,
but eventually, just due to what was happening here,
the Canadian parliament outlawed public nudity in 1932
as a result of the Dukobas.
- Yeah, right.
- Itching powder is more of a schoolboy 1940s prank thing
than a kind of legally imposed thing.
Do we know what the itching powder was?
Was it the old rose hips?
- Yeah, I don't know which one it was.
I suspect it was rose hips,
just thinking about where they are.
- 'Cause it's not that bad a punishment, is it?
Especially if you're naked.
I think the worst is when it gets in your clothes.
- Well, you're just trying to deter people, right?
Like, we've spoken about this on the podcast before,
where it was used by Churchill's brain box
where they were coming.
You know, all these amazing ideas they were coming up with
that would subtly get to the Nazis,
they were putting it in their clothes,
they were putting it in their condoms,
they were just itching powder.
- These were things that were tried in the Second World War.
- Yeah, exactly.
Like, it's just, it's a deterrent, isn't it?
And...
- That's why we won the war.
Itching powder in the condoms.
- The condom thing is quite clever, isn't it?
Because you put your itching powder in the condoms
and they get itchy down below
and they think, well, I must have lice
or I must have an STD or something like that.
And quite often, if a lot of people in a platoon
got an STD,
then they were all kind of taken away from the front.
- Really?
- So I did read, I was on the website powderbolksolids.com,
which is a great guide to historical powders.
And they mentioned especially the itching powder
was smuggled into Germany
and particularly into the uniforms of the German army.
So, particularly the Navy as well.
So there was at least one U-boat
had to turn around and come home
because everyone on board was just itching so much.
- And again, they just assumed it was fleas.
- Yeah, of course.
- So you're in a submarine, you're itching so much,
you think we must have a flea outbreak here,
we're gonna have to go back to land,
clean all our clothes, but actually it was itching powder.
- Oh, there was itching powder for trains as well
in the Second World War.
That was the thing you could do.
- So what would you do?
- It was a special powder called carburandum.
It was incredibly fine.
And if you mix it with lubricating oil,
it basically gums up an entire engine.
It's a really, really effective way
of just jamming a machine to a stop, effectively.
- Is that itching?
How is that itching?
- Well, it's, you know, I imagine the trains,
I imagine the train would feel pretty itchy after that.
- That's the train equivalent of itching.
- It's the train equivalent of itching, that's so fascinating.
- Yeah, all right.
But that was done in 1944 in June.
Two teenage French sisters applied a load
of carburandum powder to a train
that gummed up the tank supply to Normandy.
- Wow.
- So it's quite, that was an incredibly effective maneuver
at that time, yeah, yeah.
- It was also important in the Second World War
because of where it comes from.
So rose hips are the standard itching powder, right?
When I was a kid, it was always like, you know,
you should spread the seeds on someone from a rose hip
and it'll be very, very itchy.
That's what most itching powder is made out of.
Did you guys used to do that?
- I never did.
- No.
- Oh, Andy, you had it done to you.
(audience laughs)
And you thought you had fleas, all of your teenagers.
- Oh, the drugs on them, 'cause I also had fleas.
(audience laughs)
- But they're also an incredibly good source of vitamin C.
So I love, they're one of the few things you can eat
and we're just coming up to rose hip season.
It's in winter.
How many berries can you eat in winter?
And you squeeze the, you know, the red juice out
and it's delicious.
But it has 20 times more vitamin C than oranges.
And in World War II, oranges in short supply
because we couldn't import many things.
And so the government ran this huge rose hip collection
campaign and they organized whole days
when they sent out Boy Scouts and school children
and WI people to go and collect rose hips
and turn it into syrup.
And I think they collected 134 million hips.
- Wow, that's great.
- Not around here though, I don't think,
'cause they had ribena, right?
'Cause wasn't ribena invented in Bristol?
Yeah.
And I think they, it was invented here for World War II
because there weren't many oranges,
just as a vitamin C thing.
And I think they gave it free to kids.
- Wow, did they?
- Ribena, yeah.
- That's great.
- Wow, that's awesome.
The Duk Horvos of Canada.
So those who left Russia and they set up this,
this basically thing, that word is basically,
it kind of means spirit wrestlers.
It was the idea that people didn't believe
just in the word of the Bible.
They thought personal revelation was very important.
So they wrestled with what the Bible was telling them
and that set them up as their own thing.
They moved over to Canada.
And the people that we're talking about
who largely were dealing with the Mounties,
dealing with protests and so on,
they were kind of a splinter group of them.
They were called the Sons of Freedom.
And effectively what they liked to mix
was nudism and arson.
And this was in their own communities as well.
They thought materialism was too much
and that needed to be done by.
So I was reading this article about a guy
called J.J. Virgin who said when he was a kid,
he used to come home and there would be some naked old lady
trying to burn his house down.
And they'd have to go get out of here.
Like they were rats.
- I think he's the leader of the group now.
- Yeah, exactly.
- So his great, great, great, great, great grandfather
was Peter Virgin, who all of these people must have had,
I'm not surprised they didn't want to go to school
because they would have had a--
- Because they were virgins.
- They would have had a hard, hard time.
Just, that's a tailor-made nickname.
So Peter Virgin was, he was killed on a train
in British Columbia.
He was blown up.
And his followers then set their houses on fire in protest
and then stood around them naked.
This was part of, it was just part of the society.
- But they only burned their own stuff.
And to be fair, we should say,
'cause they're still out there, the duke of balls.
The vast majority, not nudists,
very embarrassed by this weird nudist sect,
like an embarrassing uncle,
getting naked, setting fire to stuff.
- The vast majority were just,
their motto was, "Toyle and a peaceful life."
What a depressing way to live, but you know.
- It's not depressing though.
Peter Virgin, he founded a town called Brilliant.
- Yes, I love it.
- Yeah.
- Such a good PR.
'Cause everything you build there can be called,
oh, the Brilliant Cafe.
- Absolutely, there's a Brilliant Bridge,
a Brilliant Power Station,
a Brilliant Jam Factory, and a Brilliant Cemetery.
- Actually, to be fair, I think the Brilliant Jam Factory
was one of the things that was burned down.
- It was, yeah, it's not there anymore.
- But Tolstoy was the one who facilitated their emigration.
They're persecuted in Russia,
because they refuse to do anything the czar says.
And Tolstoy's like, "Hey, I love people
"who deny themselves all the fun stuff in life."
You know.
- Like people who read my novels.
(laughing)
- Exactly.
And so he raised the money,
actually out of the proceeds of resurrection,
his third, less well-read novel.
He paid for them to get to Canada.
- Yeah, yeah, cool.
- And they put up a statue to them in return.
- Yes.
- Nude protest has been a thing for centuries,
as the Dukubos kind of show.
But there are recent examples too.
So in 2020, French dentists launched a nude protest
to protest the lack of PPE in their sector.
- No. - They did.
They took a series of reasonably erotic shots of themselves.
- Open wide.
(laughing)
- You could have said spit.
Yeah, okay, anyway.
(laughing)
No, they took photos of themselves nude in their surgeries
to say, "Look, we're being hung out to dry here.
"We don't have any PPE."
So I think that's great. - Right, wow.
- German doctors did the same thing.
- Wow.
- In 2022, a Somerset woman called Jill White
did a fantastic nude protest on the A358 in Somerset.
Right, she's in a wheelchair.
And the council had let the pavement
by the side of this road get completely overgrown.
She could not get along it in her wheelchair.
I mean, to see the photos is ridiculous.
No one could be a pedestrian on this road,
and especially not if you're in a chair.
So she posed naked along the roadside
with protest signs aimed at the council
saying, "I've trimmed my bush.
"Now highways trim yours."
- Oh, wow.
Yeah.
- Super.
- Awesome.
- She'd been complaining for two years,
getting no results.
As soon as she started taking off her clothes,
they acted and they trimmed it and they dealt with it.
- Wow.
- Really good.
- In Christianity, it is often a thing, isn't it?
Trying to be like Adam and Eve.
- Yeah.
- And the nudist, I quite like, are the ranters.
I didn't, have you heard of the ranters?
- Are they like Ramblers or?
- Was it someone called Clarkson?
Was it a cadre of the ranters?
I think he actually was.
- I think it was.
- Oh, genuinely.
- All right.
- There was basically, this was during the English Civil War
when lots of Quakers and Shakers and Weird Sex popped up
and the ranters are one of them.
And they were the best
'cause they basically didn't really have any leader,
didn't really have any beliefs
except to eat good meat, drink loads of alcohol,
swear loads in pubs, embrace sex, and cause havoc.
And be naked.
- So it does sound like Clarkson would have been.
- It does sound like Clarkson would have been.
- Yeah, yeah.
- This is the greatest religious grouping in the world.
- Yeah.
- And then he gets naked and everyone leaves it.
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number four
and that is my fact.
My fact is that the world of statistical analysis
was changed forever
because of a woman called Dr. Myriel Bristol
who is most famous for being able to tell
whether a cup of tea was poured milk first or tea first.
- The controversial topic in the room apparently.
- Yeah.
- Do you all think you could tell?
- I think I could tell personally.
- Do you?
- I'm confident I could tell.
- Wow, okay.
- I'm certain.
- I am as well actually and which do you prefer?
- Oh, well, I mean, tea and first.
- Yeah.
- Because--
- Let's hear it for milk and first.
- Okay, can I just call nonsense
on that milk and first crowd, right?
- Right.
- 96% of tea is made by people putting a bag in a mug,
single serving of tea, pouring hot water on the bag.
There's nobody alive in the world who puts a milk in a mug
and puts the bag in the milk.
- I think though, 'cause this was in the 1920s,
I think more people were doing it in those days.
- It was the time of--
- Tea pots.
- It was big teapots.
It was the golden age of the teapot.
- But how did statistics change then?
- Oh, okay, well, this is amazing.
So Muriel Bristol was a phycologist, not a psychologist.
There's a very distinct difference.
You don't wanna be telling your woes to a moss expert,
an algae expert.
- Don't you?
(laughing)
- So one day she was in a common room
where a lot of scientists were at Romestead
and there was a guy there called Ronald Fisher.
He offers her a cup of tea and he's making her the tea
and she declines it because she prefers it
when the milk was poured into the cup before the tea.
So she's one of the people who are in the minority here
and he was like, "Well, don't be ridiculous.
"You can't taste that."
And she said, "Well, absolutely I can taste that."
And so the story goes is that eight cups of tea were made,
four with milk poured in first
and then four with the milk in afterwards.
And he developed a hypothesis basically
on how this is applicable to statistics generally
and it has become quite a bedrock of statistics as a result.
- Yeah, so we should say Fisher was not that...
I don't think he gave a shit about milk in first
and tea in first, to be very honest.
- No, no, of course.
- He didn't mind whether she knew,
but it was about developing the kind of moment
at which you agree that if someone's claimed
they can do something, that has been kind of proven.
So he decided that after she said correctly eight times,
whether the milk was in first or the tea was in first,
there's a one in 70 chance that she'd get that correct.
That's probably about right.
- It's sort of the...
This was the birth of the randomized controlled trial.
- Yeah.
- Which is the gold standard of all scientific trials today.
The tea cups are presented, yeah.
The tea cups were presented in a random order.
She would, I think the odds of her knowing,
did you say it?
It was one in 70. - Yeah, one in 70.
- Yeah, just there was no way.
Well, there was a 1.4% chance of her getting it exactly right.
- And these statistical tests are still used
if you've got something where you're only doing a few tests,
you can't do it a billion times
and see whether she gets it right a billion times.
You only do it eight or nine times
and you see what the chances are.
- Yeah, so there's a popular science writer
called Karl Zimmer and he wrote in his article
"Why We Can't Rule Out Bigfoot".
He said...
- Incredible.
- He said that this method has become an important tool
for scientific discovery.
You find the test in every branch of science
from psychology to virology to cosmology
and scientists have followed it using his threshold method.
So it's hugely important.
- Although his threshold was incorrect
to what statisticians do today, I think,
which is long actually, he didn't need
to make eight cups of tea.
I think he could have only made six
'cause I think mostly if you show that something
only has a 5% chance of happening in statistics,
then you've decided that's fine, that's legit,
that this, therefore, is a real thing.
So two useless cups of tea that wasted, I think.
But I think what's quite nice about this
is that if you've studied statistics ever,
Lady Tasting Tea is like the bedrock.
It's the most famous thing.
But who knows that it's this random algae expert
and most sweetly, the reason it happened was, I think,
'cause of a bit of flirting
because basically she was with this, you know,
very big deal mathematician, Ronald Fisher,
and she claimed this about the milk and tea.
But the person who said, I bet you don't know
where the milk's gone in first or tea's gone in first,
was another guy in the room, a biochemist called William Roach.
And he was like, go on, let's test her.
Let's see if she does know.
And William Roach went on to marry her.
And if that's not some kind of like saddle
across the lab flirting, go on, let's test her.
- It's very sweet.
- Do you wanna hear a bit more of lab flirting from history?
- Yeah.
- So is anyone here familiar with the Bristol stool chart?
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, it's a big deal over here.
You're all checking your poos every day
and checking whether they're sausage-shaped but lumpy
or soft blobs with a clear-cut edge.
- James, I think you promised flirting
and I'm not currently seeing any.
- This was invented by a guy called Dr. Ken Heaton.
And when he was at university,
he was asked by one of his lecturers
to examine the ankle of a fellow student
who was called Susan O'Connor.
And the ankle examination went so well
that they got married.
- Wow, that is very good.
- Did he fall in love with the ankles?
Do we know?
- Yeah, and worked his way up.
- Yeah. - Maybe.
- She was very cool, Muriel Bristol.
She worked at this place, Dan described,
Rothamsted Experimental Station.
- Yeah.
- And one of the things they had,
they had soil that was collected in 1846, right?
And at the time, she was studying the same soil,
the same sample in 1919.
And she found that if you feed it little solution
of minerals, then life appears.
I tried to find out interesting people
who would span the dates 1846 to 1919
very few really interesting people.
- Okay.
- Who have you got?
- Well, 1919 JD Salinger was born,
catcher in the rye.
He's pretty cool.
You know, I like him.
- He was drinking his own urine by the end,
which was really interesting.
- Wow, that's incredibly depressing.
Do you wanna hear the 1846?
- Sure.
- I'd really tried to find people who died in 1846
who were of interest to us.
Have you heard of John Ainsworth Horrocks?
- Yeah, he was killed by his own camel or something, right?
- Bingo.
Well, I remembered.
Yeah.
- What's he?
- He was one of the early Europeans
to go very deep into Australia
and he was shot by his own camel.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- And how is he associated with this?
- He died in 1846,
which is the year that the soil sample was collected.
- Oh.
- That Muriel Bristol then studied in 1919.
- And did she collect it from Australia?
- No.
No, no one.
No.
- It's serious, isn't it?
- Thanks.
- I was looking at other,
cool statistical stuff that's named after randomers
who don't know anything about the statistics,
which she didn't.
She knew about algae.
And do you guys know about the Will Rogers paradox?
- The comedian in America.
- Of course you know who Will Rogers is.
The vaudeville 1930s comedian.
Does anyone else know who Will Rogers is?
Brilliant, Anne.
You are so, so good and so niche.
- Can you imagine the only person in the room
who knew him is sat right next to you.
(laughing)
- So he had a joke
which had them rolling in the arse in the 30s
at a time when during the Great Depression
and a lot of people from Oklahoma had left
and moved to California
'cause they were very poor.
They wanted to make a life elsewhere.
And they were called Okeys.
And he had a joke which went,
"Hey, when the Okeys left Oklahoma and moved to California,
"they raised the average intelligence level in both states."
Yeah.
Still, it still gets a few of them going.
- Yeah.
- So that's basically saying,
"Hey, these guys are so thick
"that once they leave Oklahoma,
"Oklahoma gets smarter."
But Californians are so thick
that once they enter California,
they'll make California smarter.
The weird thing about this is, right,
you've made, that is statistically possible,
if that were true.
You've made the average intelligence of both places higher.
But of course, you've only involved the same people.
So you haven't made the overall average intelligence higher.
How is this possible?
And it is possible 'cause it's all about weighted averages
and we don't need to go into that.
(laughing)
I think that's a really cool paradox.
I'm made up by a comedian who made a silly joke in the 30s
who didn't know that his name would be placed
in mathematical history.
- Yeah, very cool.
- A good match. - Very cool.
- I heard two of you saying...
- Oh, I know if milk's been poured into the tea
beforehand or not.
(audience laughing)
- Well, we've got four cups of tea here.
- Oh, piss off.
(audience laughing)
- It's James Lee, everyone, our tour manager.
(audience applauding)
- Here we go.
Two have had milk poured in to begin with
and two have had them in afterwards.
Now, have a taste test and let's see if you can...
- This is for me and Anna.
- Yeah. - Okay.
- That one's tea first.
- Okay.
- Milk first.
- Oh, God, it's so sweet.
- This is captivating, God, yeah.
(audience laughing)
- These are both tea first.
- You have two tea first.
- Yeah, I definitely.
- Okay, Andy, what are you gonna say then?
- I think one of mine is milk first.
- Okay. - It's a lot milkier.
I'll tell you that much.
- Yeah.
- So one of you has to be wrong, right?
Because there's two and two of each,
but you've picked two for yourself.
So, James, which one?
- Look at the wrong saucer! - Look at the wrong saucer!
- This is so exciting for us.
Milk, M for milk first.
Bullshit, you've put it on the wrong...
Put it on the wrong saucer, mate.
Another M.
- You've had two.
- Both of us, neither of us got it right.
I got one right and one wrong.
- You're no Mario Bristol.
- Oh, man.
- Well, look.
That's it for our show tonight.
Thank you so much for everyone for being here.
Bristol, that was awesome.
We'll see you again soon.
We'll be back again next week
for another episode.
Goodbye!
(audience cheering)
(upbeat music)
[MUSIC PLAYING]