I am really happy in the middle bit
between Christmas and New Year.
Ooh, very nice.
Thank you very much.
I'm trying to get a range of greeting cards out.
Going very soon.
No, was to buy greetings cards after Christmas, very weird.
- Yeah, Dan and Andy here.
We just want to quickly let you know
what you're about to listen to.
This is a compilation of all the outtakes
from the whole of 2017.
Every podcast, we always chop away a lot of stuff
and James has been secretly collecting it
to put together for this big bumper addition,
78-minute-long episode.
- 78 minutes.
- 78 minutes of outtake.
- I could watch a short children's film.
We're a very, very long episode of Frazier in that time.
Frazier made 78-minute-long episodes.
- I don't believe so, but it was the,
the only thing I can think of that's shorter than 78 minutes.
So what we're saying is, please do enjoy it
unless there's a weird Frazier marathon on,
in which case we give you a license to go
and watch that instead.
We hope you enjoy this.
Have a wonderful New Year.
When it comes, I will see you then.
- All right, on with the outtakes.
- I'm off to watch Frazier.
(upbeat music)
- Did you guys know that anteaters,
who have obviously famously long tongues,
have got very, very few taste buds?
- Really?
- Yeah.
- What does one taste but every middle, eh?
- They can hardly taste what they're eating.
- Well, they're eating shitty ants and you know,
termites and stuff.
- They're eating ants and they occasionally swallow dirt
as well as the other thing.
- Yeah, really?
- So it may be an advantage.
- You don't need to be a,
'cause all ants are gonna taste the same, right?
They're gonna taste vinegary.
- Oh.
- Yeah, they are.
- No. - 'Cause they're full of formic acid.
- That's so antists.
- Disagree.
- 100% disagree.
'Cause there are some of those ants,
and they do remember, they swallow honey
and they hang upside down,
and they're sort of honey repositories.
- Imagine how much you must think you've locked out
when you get the odd honey tasting ants.
Such a relief.
They have, well, pangolins, which look quite similar,
have their tongues attached to their pelvis.
I don't know if I'm using the same thing,
'cause they have such long tongues,
when they start their pelvis.
So I think their tongues are.
- So they're attached at the back.
- They don't.
- They don't, they don't.
- They're on the inside of them.
They're the way their tongue comes out
and then sweeps around.
- That's what I was thinking.
Yeah. - Hang on.
- Yeah.
- It can't be all tongue all the way back.
It's to all tongue, all the way back into a pangolin.
Their tongues are longer than their bodies are.
- What's the point of that?
- So you can, I guess, maneuver it all the way down the tongue.
And once it's back at the pelvis,
the food's practically there.
The belly need a digestive system.
I don't know, they've just tested for the truth.
- That's amazing.
- Isn't it true that I think woodpeckers
have them all the way through back into the skull
and they wind around the skull?
I've seen like an X-ray of them, right?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- And that helps cushion their skull
when they're pecking, doesn't it?
- As well as being a useful place to store their tongue.
- Do you know what the longest tongue is?
And this is relation to body size.
- It must be this pangolin.
I think, no, go on.
- Go for it, no, have a bat.
- Is it a bat?
- Yes, it is, yeah, it's the tube-lipped nectar bat.
And its tongue can go to 1.5 times the length
of its actual body.
- Wow.
So that's the longest tongue in proportion to body size.
- Exactly, in an animal.
- I know the length of that bat.
- Oh do you?
Nora fist you later.
- How on earth did you remember that?
- It's weird that with it having such a massive tongue
and a tongue being 1.5 times bigger than the whole thing
that they choose to name it after the lip.
- Yes, that's true.
- But maybe they didn't see the tongue for a long time.
Maybe they're like, well, look at that lip.
- Almost no one had ever seen the tongue
because it's always in these massively long flower nose.
- What am I saying now?
- The flower nose.
- The trumpet of a flower.
- Did they think that the bat's face was a flower?
(laughing)
That's got the head of a flower.
- It's really weird.
- Do you know when an elephant's charging you
when you should be nervous?
- It's running towards you very fast.
- Is it only about 30 centimeters
for a hit to you, you panic?
(laughing)
- It's not that.
If an elephant has its trunk out, this is according to.
- Whoa, what is it?
How can it have its trunk in?
- If it's up its bum.
(laughing)
- If it's like coiled up, I guess.
I'm like not in use.
- Yeah, if it's trunk is like, that is facing downwards
or coiled up or it's relaxed.
- It's always out, that was it.
- It is always out, so it's never sucked into its face.
- Yeah.
- It's just like lifting up and it's doing like,
one of those like, charge the light brigade
like fanfares out of it.
Like, and charging at you, that's when you know
it's going to attack.
- No, it's not going to attack then
when it's doing the charge of the light brigade.
So when it's got its trunk protruding out towards you,
you can absolutely relax.
You're going to be fine.
Apparently, that's a bluff.
And it's when the trunk's down and relax
that they're doing a proper job.
- I've never seen an elephant
with its trunk straight out like a...
- Well, that's because they genuinely want
to trample you down, James.
- Have you seen that that I've never even seen
a picture of that?
- I haven't really.
- I'm running with your fist out.
- Ready to hit someone.
- Yeah.
- But you very rarely get to photograph
an elephant charging from the side on.
Don't you?
Normally, a human elephant contact is rare enough,
especially in Safari,
that there wouldn't be another group of people
photographing the elephant from the side.
- So you're saying he saw it face on
and it just looked like an elephant without a trunk.
- It's pointing straight out of his.
- I do see that.
But I'm just surprised I've never come across a picture
like that.
- I think something that happens.
- I'm surprised I didn't look at Google images
as soon as I read the facts.
- So what's going to happen if the trunk is stretched
down and it's bluffing?
Will it just get up to you and then they're just being
awkward?
- Get up to you and then noddle you, friend.
In a friendly manner.
- Shove is shrunken your mouth.
- Just thinks you're stressed.
It's just to scare you away.
- Oh, okay.
I think it would work for me.
- Even if I remember this conversation and thought,
Hannah said that that's not gonna hurt me.
- Imagine if I've got this the wrong way around
and how guilty I'm gonna feel.
- Well, I always forget the numbers.
I always think 99% of elephant charges of bluffs.
And then I think, or is that 99% of shark attacks?
- Yeah.
- And actually, only 4% of elephant charges of bluffs.
(laughing)
- But then it's also like, but the black bear
and the brown bear.
But then brown bears can be black.
And then which one is way...
- It's the nightmare.
- Yeah.
- Just run away from them all.
I think it's what I was saying.
Just live in a city.
(laughing)
- Have you heard of Hobart's funnies?
- No.
- Good, great.
So these were tanks that were used in D-Day.
And there was this whole range.
Like a range of superheroes, basically.
They all each had their own special superpower.
- Were they named funnies because they're unusual?
- Yeah, pretty much.
- That was a sort of nickname they were given.
There was one whose sole job was
to carry massive bundles of sticks.
- Ah, fash skis.
- Fash skis, exactly.
It was called the faskine carrier.
And it basically, if you came to a ramp
that was too steep or a hole in the ground
that you needed to fill in,
it just dropped a few massive bundles of,
and these were enormous bundles of sticks.
- And that's where the name fashism comes from.
- Exactly.
So it was using the faskine carrier to defeat fashism.
- Yeah.
- Ah.
- They were the first ones actually.
The first armoured vehicle launch bridges,
were the ones that just carried a big bunch of sticks
and then tip them into a ditch.
- It can't assume very scary.
If those were the first things
the Germans saw on the horizon.
(laughing)
- The least scary robot was robots.
- Yeah.
- But you would think that the like in the end of Macbeth,
spoiler alert, trees, the trees are coming towards you.
- Oh yeah, that's true.
Yeah, I guess any German soldiers
who had done the English PTSD wouldn't be frightened.
- Did you guys know that,
and I'm not sure that this is true.
So I'm sort of asking, as well as saying,
that in France, Camembert is the translated equivalent
of our pie chart.
- It is.
- Is it?
- Camembert.
- Camembert charts.
- Let's take a look at this Camembert for a pie chart.
- That's awesome.
- Yeah, and that's because the correct way to eat
Camembert is to slice it into pie shapes, really.
- And then the people who think trees
may be a better prime minister,
get one bit of the cheese.
- They got tiny little slither of cheese.
(laughing)
And they don't know who's just getting massive of the cheese.
And actually on Reddit, I think it was this year,
or it was late last year, they had a big argument
where somebody showed a picture of a Camembert
that their mum had cut.
And their mum had cut it in not a slicey way.
And this was a French lady,
and they were all saying she should be kicked out
the country for that.
- I've got to say, I wouldn't cross my mind
not to slice it up like a pie.
Who's doing it in a slicey way?
That's insane.
- This lady.
- Well, this lady.
- We would have a kicked out.
- Well, they didn't kick her out.
I don't think in the end.
But someone said, oh, there's a cause
for loss of nationality.
And another commenter said,
"Take her to the British border immediately."
(laughing)
- I actually cut off the top of the Camembert,
the whole thing.
- Just the mold.
- I just eat that.
- 'Cause that is just solid bacteria, isn't it?
Basically, I think so.
- The rind of the Camembert, the edible liquid.
A solid mat of mold.
- And then the bacteria is a little brownie bits,
and you should have some brown bits on it,
but not too much.
- Like a banana?
- Yes, like a banana.
That depends what you like in a banana.
- That also probably depends what you like in a Camembert.
- No, this is objective facts.
(laughing)
- So I've been to Pompeii.
I went last year, and there was a lot of brothels there
that they found which were still standing.
In particular, there's one called Lupinar,
and the Latin for that is she-wolf,
which was slang for prostitutes.
And it was two levels, had five rooms,
and you know that it's a brothel because on the walls,
there was still depictions of people in various positions,
having sex, and they think the idea behind that
was it was almost like porn material to be watching
while you were having sex.
It was the equivalent of having a pornographic movie
on in the background for them.
Isn't that weird?
They had porn on their walls in the brothel.
- It might have been like one of those menus,
where if you don't speak the language,
you just point at the thing you want.
But yeah, no, it's an extraordinary place.
Highly recommend, if you go there.
- They also, one of the things I find amazing about Pompeii,
it might be Herculenium, which was the place
nearby, the same thing happened to it,
is the scrolls that were found.
So 800 scrolls were found, perfectly preserved,
as everything there was.
And it's, you know, one of the ancient world's
best surviving libraries, most extensive surviving libraries,
and we can't read it, or we can't read a huge amount of it,
because they're in such a delicate state
that we can't touch them.
So we've got all these rolled up scrolls,
and we don't know what they say,
and they're sitting in museums and stuff,
and we're just developing the X-ray technology
to try and read bits of them, and they've just found out
that they use lead sometimes in the ink,
and now X-rays can see what the lead shapes are,
and work out what they read.
But how annoying is that?
Wouldn't you just, if I saw that, I'd try an Unreal one.
- Is that case? - Oh, well, they did try,
but every time they tried, they would just fall apart.
- Oh, so they did sample that for the time. - Yeah, they tried it,
and they'd fall apart, and then I read an article,
I don't know how this would work, but one time they said,
they tried to open it and explode it.
- Wow. - Can I just open it and explode?
That don't know how that works. - Wow.
But yeah, this X-ray stuff is really interesting, isn't it?
Because they convertually unroll scrolls,
which is just unbelievable. - It's so cool.
- So they kind of get the X-ray scan of it,
and then they go, okay, now we're gonna take off the first layer,
and they can unroll it, and they can see what's on the next layer,
which is just outrageous. - Yeah, that's super cool.
- Amazing. - How many scrolls do you think they ruined
that turned a dust in their hand before they went,
"You know what, this isn't working?"
- I would have stopped after about 50.
- I simply... (laughing)
- In the 1930s, sociologist Norbert Elias walked around Europe
with his shoelaces on tie to see what people would say to him.
- No. - He did.
- What was his real name, though?
(laughing)
- Oh, very good. - Yeah.
- That sounds like alias.
(laughing)
- That's good.
He found that in England, most old men won that he might fall over.
When he was in Germany, the old men would look at him with contempt.
- Wow. - And he was walking around
a Spanish fishing village with his shoelaces untied,
and he felt that he was being warned that his laces were untied,
but he felt that it was helping him to be included
in the village community.
- Really? - Yeah, I think I read about this guy.
There's something about, I don't know what country he was walking,
and a bunch of girls were giggling at him,
little girls were giggling at him because of the untying
of the shoelaces, and then he tied them up,
and that really transformed how he felt about his connection
to the places that he was in, when he realized who he was, yeah.
- That's weird because if I saw someone walking around
with the shoelaces untied, I think my instinct would be
to go and try and step on one and to trip them over.
So you not find that, happened a lot?
(laughing)
- Or to wait until they stop and then to tie them together.
- Yeah, definitely. - Oh, wow, yeah.
- If you've got enough time for that, that's the dream.
(laughing)
- Do you guys know about the orangutan that can tie knots,
and we don't know why, and this sounds like a,
it's a bullshit animal fact,
but it's genuinely true and it's bizarre.
So there's this orangutan called Watana.
She was born, I think it's a she.
Yeah, she was born in 1995 in Belgium,
and this guy called Chris Hertz,
who's written a book about her,
but she ties knots and no one's ever taught her to do it,
and she just finds two threads or two finds or whatever,
then she ties them together.
- I think she's trying to escape.
(laughing)
- Is she kept in a very high zoo?
- She's, she's never tried to climb up out of them
or hand herself from them.
- She's.
- Sorry.
(laughing)
- Are you hosting her?
- That got dark, very quickly.
(laughing)
- That was my instinct when he said she was trying to escape,
and I realized that I'd got it wrong.
- Escape from the monotony of life.
(laughing)
- There was an article in The New York Times from 1976,
which reports an occasion where there was an exhibition game
of football between a team from China and a team from Athens,
and over the loudspeaker, a tune started blaring,
and both teams stood up and put hands on hearts,
because you know, they seemed it was the other ones,
national hook of them, and it turned out it was a toothpaste
advert.
(laughing)
Everyone, the stadium stood up, and respectfully.
- That was amazing.
That's really good.
- Do you know what the rules are about singing the anthem?
The government have said that you should dress appropriately.
- Right.
- Also that you should stand still.
- And that you should be full of energy.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- That's interesting.
- Yeah.
- Stand still, so you're ready to go, basically.
- Yeah, I think you have to be quivering, basically.
(laughing)
- That's not still.
- No, you're right, you're right.
I don't know how do you say that.
- As soon as they finish, everyone's just gonna explode
in some kind of--
- Yeah, and you're not allowed to whisper during it.
You're not allowed to talk on the phone during it.
- But lots of countries have weird rules, don't they?
- That's true.
- I think Philippines, in the Philippines,
their national anthem has to be between 120 beats per minute.
The Star Spangled Banner, when that was first written,
it was supposed to be Conspirito, which means with spirit.
- Oh, I thought you meant it was meant to be called?
- No.
- Conspirito.
- It sounds like a magician.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- And also, the God saved the Queen.
George the Fifth, he thought he was an expert
'cause he'd listened to it so many times.
And he said.
(laughing)
- It was called God Save the King then as well.
- Yeah.
- He was desperate pleading for some kind of skill.
How many times have you listened to it?
(laughing)
- If that is for, he is like,
I'm the person who has to hear this more than any of you.
- That's true.
- Please, can you sing it right?
- But if he sings it, it's called God Save Me.
- I'm sorry, that doesn't scam.
- God save our gracious me.
It was like Prince Philip's joke.
He jokes that he's the world's best plaque on Vaila.
- Oh yeah.
- And there's a great cut of him saying it repeatedly.
- It's still a good joke.
- Anyway, he said that the opening section,
you should set your metronome to 60.
And then later on it goes down to 52.
Well, that's pretty slow, that.
(laughing)
- What sort of as everyone loses energy?
- No, no, that's always a big ending
of an American national anthem.
- No, you're talking about God Save Me.
- I'm talking about God Save the King.
- I'm sorry, I'm talking about God Save the King.
- So the American national anthem was supposed to be quite,
you know, conspirator with spirit
was supposed to be kind of quite upbeat
and whatever.
Of course, these days, if you watch the Super Bowl,
you can bet on how long it's gonna be
and the average is usually about one minute,
50 or something I think.
- Is that slow?
- Yeah.
So they put loads of extra notes in like,
they're on American Idol, don't they?
(laughing)
- Other things that are being played at the wrong tempo?
- Oh yeah.
- A lot of bait hoven.
So this is a theory that bait hoven's metronome
was broken.
(laughing)
- That just says like a sick bird from the review.
I just, wait, so he wrote his songs at the wrong tempo?
- No, he wrote them at the wrong tempo
'cause his metronome was wrong.
So this is some research that's been done by...
- He's been by Brahms.
(laughing)
- Because he has...
- He's not playing like, whoa, this is fast.
- No, no, no, no, that's not...
So he played it at a tempo that doesn't sound fast.
But he ever went through a phase of writing
pieces of music that are unplayably fast.
So between 1850 and 1820, the timing that he writes,
the time he says he should play it in
is like unplayably fast, it's impossible.
So no one plays it at that tempo
and everyone thinks, well, why not, that he write this?
It sounds awful.
It's frantic and mad.
And it turns out this guy called Peter Stadlin,
who's a pianist, did some in-depth research
and some mathematical analysis
and worked out that the metronome he had
was weighted slightly wrong.
So Beethoven was just writing down the wrong stuff
because his metronome was ticking wrong.
So when his metronome was saying,
yeah, you're playing a 60 beats a minute,
he was actually playing at 90 beats a minute.
- That is brilliant.
- That's amazing to know he wrote to a metronome.
I'd never...
- Well, he actually owned the first ever metronome, I think,
or he owned a metronome that was made
by the inventor of the metronome.
He was really excited by this new technology.
Turns out it wasn't actually quite developed for the end.
- I suppose it's plausible that you could have a pianist
who writes music and all of his keys are out of tune
and then when he writes it down,
it's just a completely different tune
to what he thought it was.
Like every single time Beethoven thought
he was writing Happy Birthday or something,
but then his keys just kept going out of tune.
- Do you think Beethoven's 9th is actually Happy Birthday?
- Yeah.
- Miss Written.
- I don't really think that.
- There's a really creepy ant colony
that they've just discovered in Poland,
which lives in old Soviet nuclear bunker.
And basically, there's this Anson S on top of a ventilation pipe
outlet that comes up from the nuclear bunker,
but a lot of ants are falling through this ventilation pipe
and they're falling into the bunker below,
which is about three meters underground,
and then they can't get out,
so they can't climb up the walls and get back out.
And they do what ants do, so they build nests
and they operate as ants, but they have no food, obviously,
so they die eventually, but they constantly are being replenished.
So there's this deadly community where new ants keep falling
down onto what is now about a few centimeters thick layer
of their dead comrades, and then they just keep working
and building at their nests, and they die,
and then their stock is replenished.
- Oh my god, that's like six sci-fi films.
- It is, isn't it?
- It sounds like a metaphor for the Soviet times.
(laughs)
- It does.
I was thinking it's kind of like a metaphor for life, isn't it?
- Yeah. - That's really just what we're doing.
- Yeah, just falling into a life and dying
on top of our dead comrades.
- And on that note.
(laughs)
- In 1850, there's an article that I found it
in the English Civil Engineer and Architects Journal,
and it states that the Academy of Sciences in France
was considering an idea for a suspension bridge
between England and France, so going from Dove to Calais.
Four barges would be sunk at equal distances
apart across the channel, and then they'd have chains
going up from the barges to the surface,
and then the chains would be fixed to the bridge,
which would run from England to France,
and then above the bridge would be these huge balloons.
It describes them as giant balloons of elliptical form
and firmly secured, which would support in the air
the extremity of these chains.
In my head, I'm imagining it like the big red balls
in total wipeout, and you could just bounce from balloon
to balloon.
- Now, I can see that working.
What I think about those big plastic balls
is they're in South America somewhere, aren't they?
If mankind kind of collapses quite soon,
and then all of the world just kind of becomes grown over
by plants and stuff like that,
they're made of plastic, so they won't really buy or degrade.
So if aliens come along, all they'll see
really is these big plastic things around.
- No, no, I don't think that's true.
- No, I think that's true.
- If they landed in South America,
all of the concrete and stuff would go before the plastic,
surely.
- But we've got a lot more plastic than just the balls
that are used in this weird TV show.
- Sure, sure, sure.
But they'd probably think that that was the center
of human civilization or something.
This is where they built their greatest table.
- Exactly, you were probably looking at it,
and they probably, there may be north-south aligned
or something like that, or they'd probably work out
that they're aligned with the sun or something,
and they think that it was a temple.
- Yeah, although they think it's a model of the planners,
they think it's an early human attempt
to understand the solar system,
and that the different sizes represent the different things.
- They're all the same size, though.
So they'd be like, you idiotic humans.
- They thought that Mars and Jupiter were the same size.
- Actually, James, you make a very compelling argument.
Think of all the temples, the step pyramids in South America.
Think of what game show they probably were.
(all laughing)
- And we're in Gladiators, they used to have a thing
where you had to climb up a pyramid.
- That was probably it.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- You get to the top and at the top.
You're sacrifice.
(all laughing)
- I think we all know that they'll assume
the Disney plastic castle in Paris is our ultimate temple.
- That's true.
- We're gonna lose such a weird stuff behind it.
I was reading an article the other day,
about what happens first,
when if all humans disappeared,
the rough running order of how things wind down.
(all laughing)
It's fascinating,
'cause it was talking about actually concrete
last a lot less time than you would think,
because freezing and thawing in, let's say, New York,
actually in about 10 years,
lots of plants will have grown
in between the cracks in the concrete
and it'll all be working loose.
And actually, it's quite quickly that you end up with.
- In 10 years?
(all laughing)
- It's like a bit more than that.
- Well, I did think so.
- 'Cause you know, just rebuild New York every 10 years today.
- If I mean, if this is predicting the apocalypse
and they're like, well, the concrete's gonna disappear
in 10 years, that shouldn't have been headline.
I can't believe they buried the news.
- But it is a fair point, perhaps,
that in 1,500 years or 2,000 years,
that only the Disney Tower in Paris,
the one in Disneyland, the one in Disney World,
these are gonna be the only buildings left,
'cause they made a plastic.
- Yeah.
- Are they made a plastic?
(all laughing)
- We assume.
- Or just Wendy Houses.
(all laughing)
- Big wheel lift.
- A tiny race of polypockets.
(all laughing)
- All the exhibits in their museums
will be, you know, little Play-Mobile dolls and Lego people.
(all laughing)
We think that these were the life forms themselves
frozen when they disaster came.
- What are we talking about bridges?
- You don't know.
- Absolutely, you lost it.
How does Dan keep this thing together?
- So hard to know.
- So much fun when teachers away.
(all laughing)
- They used to, in the medieval times,
draw elephants with actual trumpets for trunks.
- Did they?
- Yeah.
So the idea they think is not that they actually thought
this was the case, but it was kind of an allegorical way
of drawing.
- It would be very weird if they thought
it was like, if they'd seen an elephant
and they saw a trumpet.
- And the idea being that they did make loud noises
and they thought their noises came from the trunks
and the only way you can show them on a picture is
by showing the trunk as natural trumpet.
- Oh, cool.
- And they think maybe a lot of medieval pictures
are like this.
They're more allegorical than actually literal.
- Oh, that's kind of what I said,
whenever you put anything that has notes coming out of it.
Like, to symbolize music.
- Yeah.
- Like, a bit like that, yeah.
- It's not a notation, it's not actually, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Wait, you said they thought that the noise came out
of the trunks.
- It does, doesn't it?
- I don't know.
- Yeah, they do.
- It sounds very nasal, the noise.
I think it comes out of the trunk.
- Sure.
- You're basing this off your own...
- I just tried doing it, yeah.
- And it sounded very elephant time
when I did it out of the nose.
- I think you're right.
(laughing)
- And now with the mouth?
- Ha!
It's not the same.
- Actually, did you read about that woman?
I think it was in this country.
This week or last week, who ordered a takeaway,
and she put a note on the takeaway,
when it said, "Are there any delivery instructions?"
Saying, "I feel so ill, I've got terrible flu.
"Can't get out of bed, please.
"Could you stop there chemist on the way
"and bring me some Benadryl?
"I don't even want the takeaway.
"I'm only ordering this, so you can do that."
(laughing)
And so this restaurant brought her her medication.
- There was a Chinese restaurant near me
that used to deliver cigarettes as well.
So people just used to order a bag of prawn crackers
and tin boxes of cigarettes.
(laughing)
I've got a whole business school who did a study
and came up with this thing called the Ikea effect,
which is that you place more value on Ikea
for self-assembled furniture, which is what Ikea furniture used for you.
- Yeah, because you made it yourself.
- Yeah, and you kind of get attached to it
and fall in love with it as you're building.
And then by the end of it, you've got a shitty book,
so it doesn't really stand out right, but you use yours.
- But you fall in love with it.
Is that, I think that's--
- He said fall in love with those at his will, that's not why.
- All right, okay.
Because that would be like a good argument
in favor of a robotic wife, for instance, that you build yourself--
- Oh, yeah.
- Or a Lego wife.
- Yeah, either of those.
- But she's too tiny for you.
- She will be tiny.
(laughing)
- You get massive Lego people, though, don't you?
- Do you?
- Yeah, Lego Latin, Lego Latin.
- Not like a Lego Latin.
- But you'd have to get married at Lego Latin, wouldn't you?
But I think if you're going as far as getting a Lego wife,
I think that's probably not an issue.
- No, it's gonna be like, no, it's not really my scene.
(laughing)
- You've put on a lot of bricks since we married.
- Have you guys ever heard of the National Fruit Collection?
- No.
- I saw this, I was reading about apples, and I just saw it.
And I've never heard of it, so I don't know anything about it,
apart from what I saw in this article.
But apparently it's in Brockdale in Kent,
and they have a living collection of apples,
presumably old trees.
They have 2,300 traditional varieties of apple.
- Wow.
- Really?
- Apparently they get 40,000 visitors a year.
- That's so cool.
So you get a chance to taste all those varieties
that have gone out of public use.
- Isn't that the name of said you can eat them?
- Yeah, I know, I'm not sure if you're allowed to eat them.
(laughing)
- I don't know.
- I'm assuming it's like anything in a museum.
- The National Fruit Collection was demolishing this scene.
(laughing)
- It's not hearing, there's a zoo,
with the most rare and fun-looking animals in all the world.
And you can try all of them in our restaurant.
- You're the reason they don't have the,
please don't eat the penguins I know.
(laughing)
- Yeah, but isn't that cool?
Apparently it's been this, it's 1952,
and I've never heard of it.
- I really want to go and visit that, that sounds so fun.
- I found it, I think we should visit actually.
- Yeah, let's go.
- Let's go.
- Cool.
- If you're listening to this and you work
at the National Fruit Collection,
why not invite us?
(laughing)
- Give us a discount.
- Do you know what was the company that was a huge boon
for Apple eating in the world over the last 15 years?
- Strong boon.
- Close, but they're major in Apple drinking.
- Apple eating, is it an Apple Tart company?
- Like Mr. Kippling.
- It is not Mr. Kippling.
The answer is, oh, I think we can get it.
- I know, I know.
- So I'll give you some clues.
- I can lolly company, it was like a flavoring thing.
- Smoothie makers.
- I'll give you some clues.
- I will give you some clues.
- So, basically, when sliced apples started being a thing,
consumption suddenly went massively up.
- Sorry, I missed that memo.
- That sliced apples are fake.
- I have one of my lunch box.
Pretty much every day of school.
- I'm still stuck on avocado toast.
(laughing)
- You know, when you buy Apple in the supermarket,
some people do, and it's sliced, and it's in a packet.
- I didn't know of that, no.
- Have you never seen those in the food section?
- I have seen that.
I think it's very weird.
- I've never met anyone who's done this,
but you can go to McDonald's and exchange your fries
for sliced apples or carrots.
- Oh, those.
- That's right, why?
- You can't see that.
- It's the McDonald's, Emma.
- There you go.
(laughing)
- I can't even, I wasn't told you, I get points.
There are no points.
- Well, I'm gonna wear this out, what you just said.
(laughing)
- It is McDonald's, so they introduced sliced apples
in the 1980s into their restaurant fair.
I think it was the 1980s.
And overall, Apple consumption tripled within 10 years.
And it's because children, especially,
but all of us, we are more willing to eat more of an apple.
If it's sliced, it's just easier to eat.
And Apple consumption shoots up.
And it's also really helped in schools across Britain.
- People before that were just having
one bite of an apple and throwing it away, weren't they?
- But I think it's also, as I'm partly to the,
just the size of McDonald's as a franchise,
because when they started giving away free books
on in Happy Meals one year,
they became the largest literary producer
in the world for a lifetime.
- Literacy tripled in America.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so it's 10% of apples sold in the US
are of sliced apples sold in the US up from McDonald's.
- But exactly the same thing happened in the UK
when they introduced them into schools.
Then Apple consumption went up by almost 100%.
- Wow, easy in schools though,
'cause they can just make you eat stuff.
- Oh, sorry.
- But they tried to make you eat full apples
and it didn't work.
And then when you get sliced apples.
- I had an apple this morning.
- Did you?
- And I'm amazed at my bravery in getting through it
without having it sliced for me.
(laughing)
James has an apple peeling machine by his desk.
- I do, I've never used it.
I bought it for QI because for the opening show,
I was gonna put it in there as a weird opening thing
and then I bought it and everyone went,
"That's not weird."
- Everyone has one of those.
- I think you can have one.
- What the hell?
I've never heard of that.
Does it actually work?
- It looks like a little torture device.
It's made of metal and you basically skewer the apple
and you put it on a skewer and then you turn it
so it's being like spit roasted, essentially.
And then there's a kind of little arm that comes down
with a little knife on it and you sort of turn it
and it peels it off the, it takes off the peel
like a little big, big little spiral.
- It's also for oranges.
- I only really like an apple on a skewer
when it's got a suckling pig wrapped around it.
(laughing)
- So there is a shaving brush manufacturer
around at the moment called Penn Halligan's.
I think they're quite an old,
an old one with a lot of history.
On their website, they're asked,
"Do you use badger hair on your shaving brushes?"
And they say, "Yes, we do."
But they take them from parts of the world
where badgers are not endangered
and in fact are primarily farmed for their meat.
- Wow, that's good.
- And I don't know where that is
'cause I can't see really many places in the world
where they farm badgers for meat.
(laughing)
But presumably they must do.
- Well, I was on a forum.
I think it was a Gillette forum about whether the badger hair
on brushes was ethically farmed
and they got theirs from China.
So I think it was Gillette wrote a really good email
saying, "You know, we make sure that we source
only the most ethical badger hair."
- So do you think they farm badger for meat in China?
Maybe they do. - Maybe.
- They used to eat badger in Europe
and old European recipes for badger would tell you
to lay it in running water for several days
to get rid of its rink of flavor.
- Several days.
(laughing)
- You just have to tie it up in the river, I guess.
- Yeah.
- But rink flavor is a lot of the most.
(laughing)
Or just eat beef.
- Well badgers, they don't make a noise though.
Do they?
- Do they not?
- Well, do they?
- They must.
- Yeah, depending on what you do to them.
(laughing)
- Old McDonald had a badger, EIO.
- Yes. - With a...
- What?
- Do they?
- I don't know, do they fuff like ferrets do?
Like fuff?
- Maybe. - I don't like that.
I imagine squealing.
I reckon they squeal if you run away.
(laughing)
- That'd be a great quiz, by the way.
Just sing the old McDonald's song
and put in a new animal and the person has to respond
and if they're wrong, they're out of the quiz.
- That is good.
- How many animals can you get down the line?
- Big ships.
- Yeah.
- The sea-wise giant is pretty much the biggest ship.
I think it is the biggest.
It's longer than the Empire State Building is tall.
- Wow.
- It goes at about 16.5 knots, which is about 30 kilometers an hour
and it's stopping distance is nine kilometers.
- Nine kilometers?
- Wow.
- If it's going at that speed.
And it's turning circle in clear weather is three kilometers.
- So that's like, imagine we're standing outside our office
facing south and we wanted to face north.
We had to go all the way around to around
where Madame Tussauds is, before we were facing north.
- Wow.
We're like quite close to Trafalgar Square, aren't we?
- Imagine in an emergency, like in the way you would in a car
hitting the brakes on a boat, but nine kilometers away.
Because if you did it just one kilometer too late,
you'd be like, we're screwed.
- We just have to watch ourselves plow into this island.
- I have a fact about banning songs and rude songs.
- Okay.
- So it's about parental advisory lyrics.
You know that sticker that you see on albums?
Do you know who those are partly thanks to?
You may do.
- Can I actually have a genuine guest?
- Cypress Hill, or now one of the early people to have it.
- Okay, that's not what I've got, although that might be part of the NWA.
- Is it a rap group?
- It's Al Gore's wife.
(laughing)
- I thought you were close.
- Is she part of a rap group?
- Yeah, she is, yeah.
No, she was listening to Prince with her young daughter.
And she heard some very explicit lyrics.
They were things like, I guess you could say she was a sex fiend.
I met her in a hotel lobby masturbating with a magazine.
And she was very angry about this because she was listening
with her daughter and she thought it was very inappropriate.
So she wrote a book called Raising PG Kids in an X-rated Society.
And as part of this drive, she set up the parents music
that was all sent to.
And they released the list of artists called The Filthy 15.
So this contributed to the rise of the parental advisory.
- Filthy 15 is a great name.
- Yeah, it's equal to the dirty dozen.
(laughing)
- But there was an album once that got a parental advisory label
in spite of the fact that it was completely instrumental.
- Why?
- Did it have sex noises?
- No, it didn't, no, it was completely instrumental.
It's by Frank Zapper, it's a Frank Zapper album.
It was called G-Spot tornado.
(laughing)
- What are the other bits of trivia from the movie Twister?
It was because there's a cow which goes through at some point.
- Yeah.
- That was a sort of early CGI cow.
- Supposedly, I haven't backed this up yet though.
Supposedly, that cow was originally one of the zebras
from Jumanji.
(laughing)
- That's quite a career change, is there?
I tried to be typecast it as a zebra.
(laughing)
- I also like that you say I haven't backed this up yet.
Like, as soon as we stop this podcast,
you're gonna be out there.
- I think this zebra's CV, it says,
oh, it says here you can also do cow.
(laughing)
- You need two zebra's, one in the front
and one in the back of the cow.
(laughing)
Yeah, no, you're right.
After every podcast and I go through verifying everything.
(laughing)
- What did they, what do you mean by that?
Did they paint the stripes off the zebra
or did they paint stripes onto a zebra for Jumanji?
- I think maybe, 'cause Jumanji came out first,
maybe they had the design of a zebra going round
in a tornado.
- Yeah, and so they just use that footage,
not the footage, but you don't, I mean,
that little computer generator thing to be the cow.
I don't, as I say, have them backed it up yet.
Gonna do it as soon as the podcast ends.
- So my friend, Dan, who works in CGI,
told me he, a fact, he learned to London film school.
And again, I haven't been able to back this up.
So possibly if someone CGI is listening,
- If you guys have thought of your research
before the podcast, I'm pretty sure that would be ideal.
- No, but this is, it's one of those things
where it's been said, but don't know where the proof is.
Any time CGI's been used, I don't know if it's now,
but let's say movies of the last 10 years,
roughly the last, maybe five years predominantly,
CGI has been using, if they have a person in it,
they've been using Brad Pitt.
Because when Benjamin Button was made,
they made a full DNA, as it were,
CGI of Brad Pitt, the full motion of him.
And rather than needing to replicate that,
you just use that.
So the company that built that sells Brad Pitt
to all these different movies that need a body.
- That's cool, CGI.
- You can use all the different ages of man as well.
- Exactly.
So theoretically, in World War Z, the zombie film,
would all the zombies that they used
have also been Brad Pitt.
- Wow.
- I hope they paid him well for that.
(all laughing)
- I bet they did.
- What if someone really overweight or something?
Was there a bit in Benjamin Buttonway,
put on lots of weight?
- Two Brad Pitt's.
- One of the proofs, what in the back?
(all laughing)
Have you seen the new thing that Ikea is doing
where they're using augmented reality?
This is pretty cool.
So if you wanna get, let's say you wanna get a sofa
and you wanna have it in your front room,
but you wanna know what it looks like,
they've got a new app where you can take a photo of your room,
and then you can kind of augment a sofa
in the place where it would be.
So you can see what the room would look like
with that sofa.
- That is so cool.
- That's amazing.
- Clever, isn't it?
- 'Cause they already had, they had like,
a build your own kitchen in your website.
It was like a budget version of the Sims
but without the people in it, which had hours of fun.
- We did that for our new house, it was amazing.
- Yeah, yeah.
- We didn't go with them at the end.
- But we've got pictures of what it might've looked like.
- This thing, you've got a happy ending
if you think it's public kitchen,
whereas I'm just like, well, I can't do this.
(all laughing)
- Don't ask the owner anywhere for the kitchen to see.
- Ah, but there is a video game as well.
You'll love this then.
It's basically a, it simulates you building Ikea furniture
but on a computer and there's no end to it.
You know, you don't win.
- No, you just, you don't even end up with the furniture.
- No, yeah, and the idea is that it basically simulates
the frustration of what it's like to build Ikea furniture
and you can do it with up to four friends.
It's a game called Home Improvisation.
So Home Improvisation.
(all laughing)
- Thanks for the translation, dad.
- What language are you from?
- I googled that, turns out it translates as Home Improvisation.
And it lets you, yeah, basically through virtual reality,
exactly what you're doing, Alex.
So if you want to build stuff outside of kitchens,
that's there for you.
- That's fine.
- There is a thing that's happening at the moment.
People keep having sleepovers in Ikea shops and Ikea.
I'm not relaxed about it.
They are really annoying.
- Well, surely they could just stop people
like as in kick them out.
- Well, people go in and they hide in cupboards at the end.
- So they can't go through at the end of every working day
checking every cupboard in the shop.
- There's an old status and there's something like,
it might be 1% as well of people in Europe
were conceived in an Ikea bed.
- So you're one in ten.
- One in ten is it, wow.
And were they all in the shop?
(laughing)
- Somebody filmed the soap opera set entirely in Ikea
and they did it without Ikea's knowledge
and yeah, it was a web series.
Yeah.
- That's amazing.
- That's awesome.
So they were in the physical shop
that they just never staffed, never called onto.
They were always filming with sort of handheld cameras
and things and presumably they must have got asked
to leave a few times,
but isn't they filmed in an entire web series?
And you know, it was just they were just like living
in the holes and so on.
- Oh, 'cause yeah, 'cause if it's a kitchen set,
yeah, they're like doing a set.
- I think the only other thing is that in every scene
you've got random people walking around your house
and just like, you're picking up your kids
and you're tensed up and taking them away.
- So the whole concept of the sitcom
has to be about a place where you live
where there's a lot of burglars.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Do you know if we ever said that when Nelson died
and he famously had a hardy next to him
and cradling him and his arms
and the person who wrote the account
who was there at the time said that,
Nelson said kiss me hardy and then hardy kissed him.
And then we ever mentioned that for about 80 years
during the Victorian era, that story was changed
so that he said kiss me hardy
because they were too squeamish
about the idea of two men kissing each other
and kiss me was a Turkish for fate.
And so they said that he'd said kiss me hardy.
And this guy must have misheard it.
No one would have said kiss me hardy.
- Why do you say kiss me hardy?
Isn't that?
(laughing)
'Cause he wasn't a fake pirate.
- Right.
- It's a missed opportunity, I think.
- I bet hardy got a load of those jokes
all the way through his name.
- Yeah.
- But if the story was that Nelson said kiss me hardy,
how do they explain away the bit where hardy
then kisses me?
(laughing)
Do they say, oh Nelson said, oh get off me you weirdo.
- Can I throw in one Nixon fact before we move on?
Can anyone tell me what Richard Nixon's middle name
is Mill House?
- Yeah, it's a Mill House.
- Yeah, so it is Mill House.
However, I'm gonna put forward the reviewed fact
that it's in fact a double barrel surname.
- Okay.
- Because it is his mother's maiden name.
Mill House was his mum.
- Okay.
- So he took that on and I would say that that's not a--
- That's quite, so my brother has the same thing
with my mother's maiden name.
That's quite common.
And I would say that's not double barrelled
because it's not the mother's name anymore, is it?
- Well, it can still be her name.
She might, yeah.
- What's her name still Mill House?
- I don't know, but it's taken
because it's his mother's maiden name.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, I just, I didn't know that connection in any case.
- It's a huge, huge news if true though,
that Richard Nixon's middle name isn't Mill House.
It might just be a part of it, sir.
- Yeah, well that's what I'm trying to put forward here, yeah.
- It is a relatively common thing.
I think especially in Scotland, they do that a lot, don't they?
- They use mothers maiden name for middle names.
- I don't.
- If that is took correct,
then there will presumably a lot of times
his name has been carved into stone,
but they're gonna have to go back
and do a really botched squeeze
of the word Mill House into it.
I don't know how many times his name's been written in stone.
(laughing)
- Yeah, that's true.
- I mean, he's not, I don't think he's one
of Mount Rushmar, is he Nixon?
(laughing)
- No, no.
- But it should be a shit rush more with Andrew Jackson
and Nixon and you know--
- Calvin Coolidge.
- Calvin Coolidge, Trump, yeah.
- That's just another thing about his name.
He was named after a British king.
So there's a thought that his family tree actually goes back
and he descends from King Edward III of England.
That's a sort of an idea that was put out there.
But he's named after Richard the Lionheart
and he is one of four brothers
and all of them also carry English king names.
- Really?
- Yeah. - What do you have the names?
- Well, there are only about three other names.
- Sorry, sorry, three of them carried it
and then there was Francis who was name of his dad,
who carried his dad's name.
- Isn't rich the Lionheart far back enough
that everyone is directly descended from him?
I think he is.
I think Edward III is.
So everyone on earth is directly descended.
- What?
- 'Cause everyone in Britain,
everyone pretty much everyone in Western Europe's.
- But everyone in America as well, 'cause--
- But Danny Dyer did who do you think you are
and they found that he is related to Edward III
and it's this huge story.
And actually, the odds of him not being related,
it would have been an amazing new story
if he had not been related to Edward III.
- I don't think that's gonna sell many papers, is it?
- Danny Dyer, they're not related to it.
- By the odds, the odds are that 99% of everyone
is related to Edward III.
It's suddenly a very interesting story.
- I see that, but then people don't usually go
much past their headlines, are they?
- And if their headline is Danny Dyer,
isn't related to Edward III.
But that's an interesting story
because the odds of 99% that he would be.
I'm my newspaper, it's gonna have very long headlines
that are really short articles.
- Country music has the most intelligent lyrics, apparently,
because one of the measures,
which sounds like not a great measure,
is the number of syllables in words.
And it doesn't have filler words,
so you don't get a lot of, oh yeah, yeah, oh,
you know, that kind of stuff you get.
- I see what you mean.
- But if you say that the most advanced songs,
are the ones with more syllables,
then the most advanced song in history
is Supercalifragilistique Spialidosius.
- Yeah, it takes years of study to understand that.
(laughing)
The study example the study used was,
country music uses more syllables,
using words such as cigarettes,
tackle box and hillbilly.
- tackle box.
(laughing)
- Apparently.
So that's too advanced for an eight-year-old, obviously.
- Yeah, fair enough.
- Also on Too Big To Fit,
I googled Too Big To Fit and Dwayne, The Rock Johnson,
is Too Big To Fit in a lot of the cars
in the latest Fast and the Furious.
- Wow.
- So there is an interview with him
and they're asking him why you always in trucks
not in the little cars,
and he's like, "I'm too big to fit in there."
- Oh my God.
- Wow.
- That makes sense, yeah.
- You should drill a hole in the ceiling or something.
Is he too tall or too?
- He's very muscular.
- He's muscular, yeah.
- But that is extraordinary.
- He's good that, isn't it?
- Could they have an adapted one
where he's just got one seat in the middle,
so there's not a two-seater?
- I guess they could, although they'd have to write that
into the story line of the film.
- Yeah.
- What story line there is in the film?
(laughing)
If you wanna collect semen from Macax, it's quite hard.
- Macax.
- Macax, little primates, little monkey things.
- Oh yeah.
- What they used to do is they would stimulate
their genitals with electricity.
Sometimes a little weak jolt,
but it would make them ejaculate.
But one researcher realized that actually
they were ejaculating quite a lot anyway,
because they do it like four times an hour
or something like that.
- Wow.
- Yeah, they average four times an hour ejaculating
when they're just having fun and just on their own.
- Watch all the time.
- Not for the rest of the time.
- But whether it's sleep now, it just keeps going.
(laughing)
But do they ejaculate 40 times a day?
You know?
- Yeah, I think they do.
- I'm seeing on, so what I'm seeing here
on this bit of paper is on the island,
the male's masturbate on average four times an hour.
So that's on average four times an hour.
They could have some better hours than that.
- In a good hour.
- And so what she realized this researcher is what she could do
is just kind of hang around,
'cause it happens so frequently.
And then when it happens, just quickly get in there
with the pipette and suck it up.
And she does that.
The main problem being that they often lick the ground
or their hands clean before she can get close
because semen happens to be highly nutritious
and they don't want to waste the nutrients.
- Devious, devious mechanics.
- Yeah, they all randy though, they're randy.
Um, you can have so many more times an hour.
- Yeah, they'd like to masturbate.
- Look, we all like to masturbate,
but they should get a job.
(laughing)
- You know when crocodiles die,
they bloat and float.
They're bloaters and floaters.
Because of all these gasses being released,
they keep them afloat.
And they float for over a month without thinking.
- Wow.
- So I don't understand why we don't see crocodiles
floating down.
- Well, we must do.
- We must do.
- Maybe we do in countries with crocodiles.
- Just think they're lugs.
- Yeah.
- Or crocodiles because they're very stealth, aren't they?
- That's true.
- They're very stealthy.
- They don't do much movement.
So if you saw one going like that,
you'd think, oh, he's on a cheeky mission.
- Cockroaches go on the back, don't they?
When they die, famously.
- Oh, yes.
- Yeah.
- The reason being that they have long legs for an insect
and they have a high sensor of gravity.
The sensor of gravity is quite near that bone kind of thing.
And as they get older,
they kind of start to get weighed down to their bump side.
And then when they kind of eventually die,
they flip over and they don't have enough energy
in their arms.
They don't have enough strength in their legs
to put them back over.
And the same thing happens if you give them kind of pesticides,
they spasm and they'll flip over
and then they won't have the energy left
in their legs to flip them back.
- So they're flipping over their head.
They're not rolling over sideways.
- They're flipping over vertically
because their bones weigh down.
- Exactly, they do that flip.
- Well, I don't know if it's exactly like that.
It could be a slightly sideways, slightly back flippy thing.
I don't know about that.
But basically, you're walking around with a heavy bump
and as you get older, you're less able to deal with it.
- We know it feels.
- Tortuses have that same problem.
- Do they?
- Obviously, they've got round shells.
But they have this really weird balancing act
that they need to strike
because bigger animals obviously do better
because they're stronger and they can fight other males
and they can compete more.
But also, if they get too big,
a bigger shell means that it's hard to write yourself again.
So you have all the advantages of being big,
but if you lose one fight
and you then get rolled over onto your back,
it's much likely that you won't be able to
write yourself again.
- Oh, yeah.
- It's a trade-off.
- It's basically putting all your eggs in one basket.
It'll be really big.
There's a really interesting thing about tortoises
which we covered on QI years and years ago.
And that is that it's possible to invent a shape
that you put it on a table
and it always flips over to a certain side.
- I just chewed to the shape of the thing.
It's felt like a gumbok,
but I think it's pronounced more like gumbots.
Anyway, so this shape has been invented by computer scientists
and it took us decades to do it
and they managed to do it through using computers.
But tortoises, some tortoises have this exact same shape.
And so if they flip over,
they naturally kind of roll back onto their feet.
- Oh wow.
- That's so cool.
- That's awesome.
Was the inventor of the gumbok inspired by totals
or with tortoises, or is that?
- I believe he was.
I've met him and I can't remember.
- Oh, was it vice versa?
You're going to watch the turtles?
We went to one of his shows and thought, guys,
we should try that.
- Yeah, I was so proud of myself
for not finishing the set so you can clearly do
where I was going with that.
I was like, no, 'cause James started talking.
I thought, ah, that looks like a clever question now.
- I wasn't gonna let him save you.
- Diamonds are the hardest substance in the world.
I read a, whoop, they're not James.
- James is in diesel.
- In diesel.
- They're not, what is that?
- They're the hardest naturally occurrence.
- Sorry, that's what I meant to say.
Yes, the hardest naturally occurrence substance.
You can't scratch a diamond,
except with another diamond you can.
- Yeah.
- So you can scratch a diamond with a diamond.
- That's what it means.
- That's what hardness means in this sense.
It means that you can scratch something with something.
- So hardness is whether something can be scratched
and toughness is whether it shatters into a thousand pieces
if you hit it with something.
So diamonds, because the layers of carbon are very tough,
you know, internally, but do you hit it with a hammer?
Bang, smash it.
- Right.
- So don't try that.
- Don't do that.
- Yeah.
- And that's, I think we may have said this before,
that's what traders used to do.
If someone had mined a diamond,
there was someone's group, there's people who'd say,
well, okay, let's have a look.
And we'll just give it a quick test to see
if it's a real diamond.
I'll just hit it with this hammer, bang, smash it.
And then he says, I'm so sorry,
it wasn't a real diamond after all.
It was something else.
- But I'll keep the shards.
- I'll keep the shards and I'll pay you a nominal sum
for them.
I'll pay you a tiny bit to keep yourself going, you know?
And then they'd just sell off a load of smaller diamonds.
- A very clever.
- Very clever, yeah.
- Or you could groom back together
and make a bigger diamond again.
- Oh god.
- I think that's where the imperfections come in.
- Come on down to Hannah's shitty diamond store.
(all laughing)
We got loads of rubbish diamonds full of glue.
- I've got some stuff on quarantine.
- Oh, right.
- Yeah.
Comes from the Italian for 40.
Quarantee, which...
- Because you used to have to stay 40 days in quarantine.
- Yeah, that makes sense.
- Incubation period of the Black Death
supposedly.
- Oh, okay.
- They put astronauts in quarantine.
- That's right.
- When they come back down.
Do you know why?
- Yeah, because of radiation and in case in space
they were given some sort of flu disease.
It was to do with diseases, wasn't it?
- Well, it is a little bit.
- Aliens with smallpox.
- Yeah, so you might think if you were a sci-fi fan
that it was to stop alien diseases coming to Earth.
But it's actually because their immune system
is lessened due to them being in space.
So when they come back down, they need to go in quarantine
so they don't pick up bugs on Earth.
- Is that so amazing?
- Technically that you're putting the entire rest
of the world in quarantine.
- Yeah.
- Yes.
- That's just true of all quarantine.
Just flip around the exit mentions.
- That's fine.
(laughing)
- Yeah, I suppose that is true.
- There was, you know, just picking up on that quickly.
When the Apollo 11 astronauts came down,
they had to do that.
They had to be in quarantine in this room
where they had a sort of kitchen in there
and living quarters and so on.
They had to stay in there for ages
before they could do any of their parades around the world.
- Wow.
- And what ended up happening was if a scientist accidentally
kind of was infected as it were with the room
that they were kept in because they were delivering stuff
and so on, I guess, in suits.
- And then it was for possible space cooties, wasn't it?
- Yes, yes.
Those scientists then had to move in with them.
So there was a whole batch of people
that subtly got, or might have been infected.
So therefore needed to be quarantined.
- It's people came along to give them some food
and they got infected.
- Exactly.
- It's like a horror film.
It's like, oh, where's Sarah?
I better go and find out.
Oh no, what's Bernard gone now?
- It's a bit like a game of sardines.
- It is, it is, exactly.
And there was a suggestion, and I'm not saying this is true,
but there was a suggestion that some of the people
who accidentally had to go into the quarantine
looked like ladies of the night,
who made their way into there and had to live out.
- I don't even know what the implication you're making is.
- Prostitutes.
- Was it postitutes?
- No, 'cause it's back on Earth now.
(laughing)
- And also, space prostitutes don't exist.
- Oh yeah, it's like, yeah.
- But it was another time, wasn't it, the '60s?
- Yeah.
- I mean, it literally was, yes, to you know.
(laughing)
- I looked at some skillful number people,
and I was looking at like the world record
for memorizing numbers and stuff like that.
- Okay.
- And the world record for most digits memorized
in one minute has two different sections,
one with the light on and one with the light off.
'Cause apparently, it's miles easier when the lights off.
- That makes sense, 'cause there's no distractions.
- I guess so, right?
But you can close your eyes.
- How do you see the number to memorize?
(laughing)
- Maybe that's another reason.
But yeah, maybe you're allowed a little torch
or something, I don't know.
- All right.
- But perhaps I'll give you an audio recording of it.
- Maybe, I don't know.
So this is for binary digits, so it's zeros and ones.
- Okay, the one, the specific one I'm looking at.
And the record for most zeros and ones memorized
in one minute with the light on is 107.
With the light off, it's 273.
- Oh, wow.
- Isn't that amazing?
That makes that much difference.
- That's incredible.
- So all mass exams should be held in the dark, shouldn't they?
- I guess so, if they were all in binary.
(laughing)
- Mine, mine are worse.
- Did you just quickly one thing on chocolate?
I think it's quite funny.
Bernie Madoff, remember him, is now running a chocolate racket
in prison.
So... - Who's he again, sorry?
- You know, he's the guy who...
- He ran a massive Ponzi screen, didn't he?
- Ponzi screen.
(laughing)
Yeah, so he was a business man who it turned out
was stealing lots of people's investments.
So he got millions and millions of pounds
and stole lots of money.
And he's running this chocolate racket.
And in prison in America now, he's really respected
'cause he stole a more money than anyone else in there.
So he wrote this letter to his daughter
saying he's quite the celebrity in there.
Other inmates treat him like a mafia don
and call him Uncle Bernie.
I can't walk anywhere without people shouting their greetings
and encouragement.
It's really quite sweet.
And he's brought up all the chocolate in the prison.
And now he runs this racket
where the only person you can get it from is him.
And so he makes a big profit.
- How's it work?
'Cause it sounds like that should be illegal, right?
- Hi.
- It's unusual to have people committing
a very similar crime in prison
to the one they were put in there.
- Yeah.
- And then to announce it, I mean,
do prison guards not read news or?
- But that's not illegal.
- It's not illegal.
- No, what, just to buy up to get in there first
and buy up all the stuff so you can sell it
on for a profit, that's okay.
- It's immoral.
- Right.
- It's a bit of a monopoly, but I don't think there's
like anti-monopoly rules in prisons.
- It's touting.
- It is touting, yeah.
- Okay.
- Well, good luck to him.
I think that's what you're saying.
- Couldn't have happened to a nice guy.
- God, I'd love to know where the boxes are
from, Dealer, no deal.
(laughing)
- Your notice, I said nothing in that whole bit
'cause I was busy thinking,
"Gaddy, yeah, did they wear no diamonds
"just got them in his house?"
- Yeah.
He probably, I reckon he uses them to wrap Christmas presents.
- That would be such a good idea if he doesn't
and he's listening.
- But that's a great Christmas present.
So you unwrap it.
There's a box, you open the boxes, nothing inside.
And you're like, oh, this is terrible.
And he says, actually, it's one of the boxes
from Dealer, no deal.
And you're like, that's the best present ever,
no-leadment and Christmas is saved.
- Hmm, yeah.
- I would be still unhappy with Dealer, no deal.
- Box is my Christmas present, just the two of you
who's thinking about it.
- If it was a real one that was used on the show.
- I really intentionally did not want that as a present.
- Great.
(laughing)
I'm sure someone else will have it.
- Yeah, I bought it now.
- Sorry, no, we thought she'd love it.
- Or he might use it for storage.
- Yeah.
- Or if he goes shopping, putting his shopping in the boxes.
- Yeah, he just goes everywhere.
If you look at every phone of him these days,
he's actually got a box with him.
- If he gets fired, once he got fired from a job,
do you think he'd clear this desk in those boxes?
- Yeah, when he got cats or, yeah.
- Yeah, how do you move in there?
Has he put handles on them or wheels?
- Yeah, 'cause they don't have handles today.
- No, very easy to carry.
- How many items of check-in luggage really have today?
So I've got 15.
(laughing)
- I read a thing.
There's a basketball player called Jimmy Butler.
He plays for the Chicago Bulls.
I think he's just been traded, but I'm not sure to wear.
But he, I read it article, this is the, in the headline,
it says that Jimmy Butler took out his car rear-view mirror
as a reminder to never look back.
(laughing)
- That was awesome.
- It was promptly arrested.
(laughing)
- Have you heard of the North American Walnut Sphinx caterpillar?
- No, that's a goody.
(laughing)
It pretends to be a bird to freak birds out.
- A bird's freak's out to other birds.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- That's one thing they most used to.
They used to hang it around with birds.
- Sorry, I should clarify.
- They make a noise like a freaked out bird.
- Oh, no.
- I'll just scare the other incoming birds away.
- Exactly, so what they do, it's amazing.
They, to make the noise, they have not quite lungs
in the sense that we understand they have these holes
along their sides called spiracles, exactly.
And to make the noise, they squeeze themselves shut
like an accordion.
(laughing)
It's amazing.
And that, when they do that, it makes a noise that goes,
"Eee!"
And it sounds exactly like a bird's alarm call saying,
"There is a bird of prey nearby,"
or, "Get out of here, we're under attack."
And so the other birds all fly off as soon as
this caterpillar makes a noise.
- No, they do it to scare the birds away.
- They do it to scare the birds away,
because the birds would prey on them.
- Is that, is that evolution or is that coincidence
at the note, the specific note?
- That's everything's evolution, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- That's what we all are, the product of.
- What was the other option,
of it that could even happen?
- Coincidence.
(laughing)
- Well, yeah.
It could be evolution by coincidence.
- Yeah, at least, it probably started as a bit of a coincidence.
- That's what I was looking at.
- But that's how evolution works.
Evolution always starts as a coincidence,
which then evolves into being a pattern.
- That's it.
- Yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- No, but if you were an animal
and you were living on the Galapagos
and the trees were too high,
and the leaves were too high on the tree,
it's not coincidence for you to grow your neck to try and...
- Yes, it is.
It's a coincidence that there was someone
who was born with a really long neck.
- No, but don't you grow your neck?
- No, oh my god.
- That's Lemarkism.
- That's Lemarkism, the original evolution.
And in some people's eyes are the best.
(laughing)
- One individual gets born with a slightly longer neck.
Slightly, not one individual is born with 50 per cent.
(laughing)
- That's a coincidence.
- That has a million children
'cause it's got all the leaves.
Slightly longer neck and then can get one or two more leaves
and then it's a bit more likely to pass on its genes.
- Yes, I knew that bit.
- Right, did you though?
(laughing)
It just sounded a lot like he didn't.
- Yeah, when I was reading about caterpillars,
I read this statement that said that basically
all they're doing is collecting food
for the moment where they go into their chrysalis stage.
So their whole life as a caterpillar
is just to feed themselves in order for that.
Like how I moved house the other day,
it'd be like as if my whole life was just collecting boxes
for the mood.
- For the food, I mean in order to live and breathe
and for their processes to work,
they have to be metabolizing some of the food.
They can't just all be, I mean they're just creating
as well. - No, yeah, they're effectively
just like I just need to just eat
and get myself ready.
- They are also using the food a little bit
for energy as a caterpillar.
- Yes, totally, yeah, no but it's.
- But what's the point of using all that energy
so that you can turn into a butterfly?
- Exactly, it's the same as Dan saving up for his new house.
Like he has spent some of the money on, you know,
co-comprostedutes and whatever.
But eventually he's been saving up for this house.
- Got it.
They're putting something aside is what you're saying.
They've got a little savings account on the side.
- Yeah, but it defines their whole existence.
- Right.
- Because then there a new thing.
There a new, it's a whole new account.
- Who would you just say what defines
the existence of a caterpillar?
- I didn't know I read it in an article.
- I don't know if a caterpillar would agree with that.
- They probably wouldn't be able to argue me to try to.
- Totally agree.
- Even though they're caterpillars.
(all laughing)
- Do you know Auctioneers watch videos
of other Auctioneers at their best?
Sort of like the greatest hits of auctioneering.
- Do you mean like auctioneers have to do that
as part of their training?
- No, no, they watch it to marvel at the complexity
of what certain Auctioneers have done.
So there's a guy called Chris Birch
who's acknowledged as Christie's greatest Auctioneer.
Some people acknowledge him as the greatest Auctioneer
of all time.
- What do I think?
(all laughing)
- I think I've slightly made that up.
- He basically, so he joined Christie's in 1970
and he averaged, now I'm just gonna read this sentence
as it's written, I didn't fully understand it
'cause I can't believe it's true.
Averaging more than $1 million a minute in sales
up to his retirement in 2012.
- No, can't be true.
- Can't be true, right?
- No, very fast.
- That's his, that's per minutes across his sales, isn't it?
So if an Auction takes 50 minutes,
then his average was 1 million a minute.
- Ah, in the 30 minutes.
- So you've got a 50 million auctioneer.
- So she sells one painting for $25 million in one minute.
He can then sit around for 24 minutes.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Really not try.
- He does, that makes it interesting.
- But so there's a video of him
that Auctioneers love to watch.
And he sold the 10 most expensive works
ever sold at Auction in the world.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
And the video is of him selling Monae's water lilies in New York.
And in it, he's taking bids from three people in the room
and two people on the phone.
And what they're watching is the magic of him
being able to juggle between it all be charming and witty
and it's a sort of master class in auctioneering videos.
- Well, I mean, I listen to other podcasts.
So it's the same kind of thing.
- Yeah, I mean, you want to, yeah,
if you do love auctioneering and you're an auctioneer,
of course, you're going to watch videos.
I just didn't know that they existed
that there's a greatest hits out there.
- Yeah.
- There are DVDs and things you can get.
The most greatest auctioneers.
Yeah, the most we are.
- I don't think that's the biggest auction
of all time though, even the walking is one.
I've got one that was bigger.
- Go on.
- Yeah.
- The entire Roman Empire was auctioned.
It was auctioned off in 193 AD.
Yeah, it was auctioned off by the Praetorian Guard
who took bids from a couple of people.
It was a closed auction, there wasn't anyone could bid.
And this is according to Cassie's deal
who wrote a history of Rome.
And two people were bidding saw Pikianas
and Marcus Didier's Salvia's Julianas
and he made the maximum bid.
Supposedly, it was the equivalent
of about five million quid in today's money,
which I think surely someone else could have stumped up more.
- It was past its best in 193 AD.
- Yeah, it was true.
- Yeah.
- Some, some damage.
(laughing)
But then several careless owners.
- So at the moment, British police are investigating
a caterpillar thief who has stolen
from a nature reserve in Norfolk
some milk parsley plants, right?
Now there is a kind of butterfly in Britain
called the Swallowtail.
It's the largest native British butterfly
and the caterpillars only eat milk parsley.
And these plants in Norfolk had Swallowtail caterpillars
on them.
So the police think that they've been stolen
and the plants will be kept alive
and then eventually the caterpillars will turn into butterflies
and then collectors will kill the butterflies.
And they're very rare these butterflies
'cause they only feed on these plants, right?
- So wait, so someone's thrown the plants
in order to get the caterpillars
that they can sell to collectors?
- Yes.
- Well, no, to turn the caterpillars into butterflies
to be killed for collectors, yeah.
- Yeah, but then you're breeding caterpillars, I suppose.
So you want to make more of the species?
- Then you're immediately killing the butterflies
as soon as it comes out of the thing.
- Right.
- Yeah, kind of swings around about this.
- No, it's all swigs.
(laughing)
- Craft playground.
- Do you know that they're used to play cricket
on the ice in the fins?
And this was in North, in what's it called,
in East Anglia, in England?
- Was that not quite confusing
if they were wearing their wipes?
(laughing)
- No, this would take place in the 18th,
in the 19th century.
And I read one account saying that the fielding
and batting of many of the players was considered
to be far superior and more graceful
than any cricketing on the green.
- Really?
- So apparently playing cricket on ice is better.
- Were they in skates or were they just running around with me?
- I think they were on skates, yeah.
- That must be amazing.
- Yeah, I mean, the ball will go so far.
If you hit it, it goes up, yeah, yeah.
- Standing on skates to bat.
- Hang on, why would the ball go far?
- 'Cause it was skid on the ice.
- Oh, once it hit the ground,
if we were going to give you superhuman power
of hitting on the ice.
(laughing)
- Just quickly on the dutch
and how good they are at skating.
- Oh, they're amazing at speed skating, aren't they?
- This is the thing, okay.
So they're now so good that other countries
are refusing to play against the moment.
(laughing)
There's no point.
In Sotchi, in 2014, the Norwegians dropped out
of the 10,000 meter speed skating race,
ostensibly because they said,
we want to focus on the team event, actually,
just 'cause they knew they get marmalized by the dutch.
And so, annoying, love skating as well.
So that's a big thing.
So the women's 1,500 meter team,
they came first, second, third, and fourth in that event.
And out of 36 medals, the dutch got 23.
No other team got more than three.
- Maybe it's on fur, 'cause they're the tallest nation, aren't they?
So perhaps it's on fur, 'cause they're legs are too long.
- But they will have a higher center of gravity, meaning.
- Sure.
- That is easier than to fall over.
- Are we sure that being tall is an advantage in ice skating, I think.
- We are certainly not sure of that.
- Really long legs might help, I guess, if you're
trying to, if you're pelling yourself forward,
'cause you can go further from each stroke, maybe,
and it's like a more efficient use of energy, perhaps.
- I don't know, I guess.
- I would suggest that if Jamaica were to take part in this event,
they might be as good as, if not better, than the dutch.
- I think we've just come with a sequel to cool runnings.
(laughing)
- But the fastest skater, the world record holder
for the fastest skater is a Russian,
called Pavel Kuliznikov, and he, whatever,
how would you say it then, James?
- Kolesnikov.
- Kolesnikov, yeah, they go.
(laughing)
Pavel Kolesnikov, and to be fair,
I didn't even read the name until just now.
I should have written the phonetic spelling down.
And he went at, he was registered going at,
53 kilometres an hour, registered going,
not well, like a police camera, but like,
he, I just think that's astonishingly fast for a skater,
and he was in a 500 metre rate, so he picked up speed fast.
- How many is that in Malzana, please?
I don't know, I can't be bothered with this.
- It's going to be 32.91, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Is that, that's fast, isn't it?
- Yeah. - Can you say in both run of 30 miles an hour?
He's not, it doesn't normally happen in Malzana,
does it?
They do it in seconds per 100 metres.
(laughing)
- I think it'll be nice if it was Malzana for the spectators.
- He can run at approximately 9.9 seconds per 100 metres.
- I'm not sure what that is in Malzana.
- Someone at home can work it out.
- I think it's less, I think it's about 20 that he runs, isn't it?
- Oh, that's not very, that's like a built-up area.
(laughing)
- I was looking up lonely insects,
and I was looking up cockroaches,
and they suffer from isolation syndrome,
if they're left on their own, and they die,
so, or they are not able to mature properly,
and this is really weird, so the way that cockroaches
are really affectionate physically,
so you know, if you see them, they're always crawling
all over each other and stuff, and touching each other,
and it turns out all this physical contact stimulates them
to grow, so if you isolate a cockroach,
even if you give it food and water, then it won't grow,
and it won't melt properly, and it won't mature,
but you can make it mature by poking it with a feather.
(laughing)
So, yeah, and that convinces them
that they're having this physical contact
with their fellow cockroaches, and they grow properly mature.
- That's amazing.
Does it have to be a feather, or?
- It can probably actually be any kind of slightly
ridiculous device.
- Is there a limit to how big a cockroach grows?
- Yes.
- 'Cause they can maintain it, right?
Like, if they were touching another cockroach,
they're like, "I just want to grow a bit today,"
and so they touch a cockroach.
- So, you're saying, if you get a cockroach,
and you tickle it for, like, let's say, seven weeks,
yeah, it might be the size of a dog.
- Exactly, that's my question.
- Maybe, try it.
- I think Andy's skeptical.
- I'm skeptical, and I'm surprised I know
that you're encouraging this life of a coward, isn't it?
- And we've cli-bottled a lot of the stupid things
he said today, I thought we'd just let this go.
(laughing)
- So, for many years, in many places, collecting flies
and giving them to the government has gotten you money.
So, in China, officials in Luai Yang
offered $125 per 2,000 dead flies during a campaign.
Each fly was worth about $0.7.
- Was that a massive amount for a fly?
- This recently, sorry.
- I know, it's quite recently, yeah.
- The scent is quite a lot bigger than a fly as well.
- Yeah, that's not really how money works.
(laughing)
- It's interesting that usually,
the money's less than the thing that you made.
- Don't touch it at all, actually.
- That's not true at all.
- That goes to the shop with loads of flies,
so they say, you can't pay with that,
and you're like, well, it's heavier than a pound note.
- Oh, it's weird, 'cause the sandwich
weighs a lot more than 20 pounds,
but the 20 pound note is heavier.
(laughing)
- It doesn't really make sense.
- It doesn't really.
- It doesn't really, I completely retry that.
- It's ridiculous thing to say.
- So, in...
- 'Cause then you wouldn't be able to buy anything.
(laughing)
- You're not gonna learn that diamonds, are you?
- I just bought my first house.
- Oh, man, that must be tough.
Yeah, I'd find a coin as big as a house.
(laughing)
- That's what happens on the island of Yap in Micronesia,
'cause they have massive stone coins with holes in them,
and the bigger the better, really.
- Yeah, that's what I was doing with that.
- It's embarrassing.
(laughing)
- Salvador Dali, he was obsessed with breasts,
wasn't he, as in a lot of his art depicts breasts,
but his ultimate obsession was with the other,
'cause he said it's a very weird sexual thing.
It's half penis and half other.
- Well, sorry.
- Sorry, sorry.
(laughing)
It's half penis, half breast, all other.
- It more sense is an utter half penis.
- It's incorrect, Salvador Dali is the correct.
He went out on a limb, he was wrong.
- A UFC fighter called Justine Kish,
she was in a fight,
and halfway through the match,
she was held in, I think, in a stranglehold,
and as a result, she put herself midfights in the octagon.
- Nice.
- Still won the match,
and she got offered a bum-wiping product
as her sponsor for future- - Do you mean Tyler Mesa?
- No, it's, it's wipes.
- She goes, I'll shop your wipes.
- Yes, can I have some bum-wiping products, please?
(laughing)
- Yeah, this is how the test goes.
It's quite equivalent when they're not allowed to call it
a jaffa cake, so they can call it filled biscuits
with chocolate on top.
(laughing)
- Without the chocolate on chocolate,
it's just one.
(laughing)
- But actually, this wasn't Tyler pay for you.
- No, no, it's wipes, it's bum-wipes.
- Yes, wipes.
- Wet wipes for adults as opposed to babies.
So yeah, so she thought she was gonna do it,
and she was really good,
'cause she won the match anyway,
and she came off and they asked her about it,
and she said, "Shit, it happens."
- Did she go, it's very nice.
- Did she use it as a weapon in the fight?
I mean, in no holds barred.
- There's no weapons in UFC.
- But there's no rules, right?
- Yeah.
- There's no rules, that's true.
- It's not eye-gouging if you rub your shit
in some space.
- That's true.
Oh, do you mean did she use the poo in the fight?
- Not her wipes.
(laughing)
- Right.
- I'll wipe the floor with you.
(laughing)
- Have you heard of the, in Holland,
there's a race in Holland called the Elf Staden Tocht.
The Leven Skirer told me about this, actually.
So it's this race that happens,
well, it happens whenever it's able to happen.
So sometimes it doesn't happen for 20 years,
sometimes it'll happen in consecutive years,
and it's apparently a massive event in Holland
when it does happen.
And it is a ice skating tour
that is about 200 kilometers long
and goes to 11 cities,
and that's what the name is,
it's the 11th city tour.
And apparently it's just a massive event.
And what happens is, every year,
everything gets cold and freezes in winter,
and they go around the race track
and these go along the network and come out.
Yeah, exactly.
And they have to make sure that the ice is sticking off,
'cause it's an amateur contest,
and the professionals and amateurs take part.
And so they're loads and loads of people take part in it,
and then pretty much the rest of the country,
all cool and sick, and watch it on television.
And no, apparently that's like a thing.
It's like, so they stay home, like watch it.
It's a bit like, I know, the Grand National here,
but everybody watches it or something.
- Yeah, all of them.
(laughing)
- Or any sports event.
- A massive sports event,
but everyone watches it, yeah, absolutely.
- Yeah, I have heard of that,
but I think global warming means it hasn't happened for a while.
- Yeah, it hasn't happened for a while.
There was one that was going to happen in 2012,
and they called it, and what happens is,
they decide they're gonna call it,
and then it has to happen in the next 48 hours,
so everyone has to rush to get prepared.
But then it didn't happen even though they called it,
because the ice just wasn't thick and--
- It's so exciting.
- And there was actually speaking of ice preparation,
they do this thing called ice transplanting,
which is taking thick ice from one place,
and moving it to say a bit under a bridge,
where the ice isn't very thick,
and to kind of fusing it to the ice.
It's like a skin transplant,
but yeah, isn't that really cool?
- 'Cause it has to be six inches thick
along the entire 200 kilometers of the course,
and obviously that's very seldom gonna happen.
- Yeah.
- Why aren't the climate change lobby using this more
in their PR?
I really think that might persuade the likes of Donald Trump
and another such people, surely.
If we know that this canal ice race is gonna end,
- It's on track and people would step up to the plate.
- Yeah, it's on track as a secret passion
for ice, it's getting race racing.
I don't think he does.
- Who would it for this?
- Yeah, it is incredible.
It's so cool.
- Do you mind if I ask why people are monitoring
the koala populations?
Do we know that?
- Yeah, I think more--
- Do you mind if I ask?
- It wasn't that person on the course, you know?
(laughing)
- Sorry, it's not me finding really invasive.
- Did you guys see that photo from March of this year?
There was a guy sitting at a train station.
He looked up, and he just couldn't believe what he saw.
He took a photo to prove it.
He was stopped at Seven Sisters Station,
sitting right there on the platform with seven nuns.
Seven nuns, seven sisters.
And he took a photo of it, yeah.
- Do you think an eighth nun wanted to come on that trip,
but they were like, "Guys, we can't."
- No, this is like the moon landing's being fake.
If you look in the photo, there is an eighth nun.
- Well, there's an eighth man--
- No, there's one man, but--
- No, he's an eighth in the party.
- Oh, I thought I saw an eighth nun when I looked at the photo.
- Oh, really?
- So was there an eighth nun behind the other nuns?
- You're right, there's an eighth nun!
- Oh my God, ruined.
- Oh, man, I'm sorry, I feel like I've killed Christmas.
- God, did you do it that easy with the moon landing's as well?
(laughing)
- Have you heard of open-source seeds?
No. - No.
- Okay, so--
- Is that seeds that don't charge you to read them?
- Kind of.
- Okay.
- I think these are the seeds that are in these libraries,
these open-source seeds.
- Well, so in the 1930s, the USA started applying patent law
to plants.
So there are various plants where the intellectual property
is owned.
- Like, you can own an avocado?
- Well, you can own an avocado,
but you can own the whole avocado.
- The whole concept of the avocado.
- The whole species of the, yeah.
They've got this new kind of rice that's called golden rice,
which is hardier and it grows faster and better
and therefore is prevented starvation.
That is owned by someone, the intellectual property for it.
- Does that mean you're not allowed to grow it
or you're not allowed to give it the name?
- I think you're not allowed to then, I'm not sure about this,
I think you're then not allowed to breed it, develop it,
and then make money selling your own ex for strain of it,
but I'm not certain.
So anyway-- - No commercial use, basically.
And I think that's because that specific breed of rice
was growing in space.
And it was like the means that it took to do that
and then means, well, therefore,
those people deserve a kind of a cut of any profits.
- Well, I don't think it's the specific of the space thing,
but I just think-- - Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's the specific
I see, yeah.
- The effort went into making that new breed of rice.
- Yeah, so if you, it's kind of like developing a medicine,
in some ways, that if you develop the medicine,
you then get the rights to it
because you've spent money developing it,
but they've now got this thing called open-source seeds.
German breeders are experimenting with it.
You're not allowed to patent anything
that you get out of it, any new great strains
that you get, but you don't have to pay anybody
to do the developing and--
- Okay. - Isn't that weird?
- Yeah, that's truly bizarre.
And it doesn't seem morally great, surely.
If you're not allowed to let anyone grow
this thing that could be a great food source,
that you can probably-- - Right.
It might not incentivise people to develop new strains
if you can't own it.
So there's a bit of a-- - That's it.
- That sort of capitalism.
- This is cognitiveism.
(laughing)
So I'm getting one simple sentence.
- Imagine you'd like everybody to have an off-to-eat anna.
- Well, well, I'm sorry.
(laughing)
- I suppose it's not a million miles away
from patenting a Mars bar.
- Or a strain of Apple,
that isn't like a granny's myth or something.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- A fan I was in charge.
Just be formless lumps of chocolate
and new garlic we'd be eating now.
- And everyone would get one, wouldn't they?
It's a better world.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]