Hi everyone welcome to this week's episode of No Such Thing as a Fish. One
little bit of time sensitive news to let you know this morning or afternoon or
evening depending on when you're listening is that we are doing a live
show coming up next Monday that's Monday the 12th of August and it is in
London at the Udder Belly. It's gonna be a full podcast and then in between we're
gonna do lots of little bits and pieces that we're trying out ahead of our
upcoming tour so you get to see lots of stuff that frankly no one will ever see
again but it's gonna be a whole load of fun. If you'd like to get tickets for that
then you'll have to be really quick because tickets went on sale earlier
this week and we've already announced it to our club fish members. It's also a
very small venue so there won't be many tickets left but if you go to
nosixthingasafish.com forward slash live then you'll be able to get those and
actually you'll be able to get tickets to any of our upcoming live shows.
Secondarily or actually probably much more excitingly for most of you we have
a very very very very very special guest on today's show. Who is it Anna? It is
none other than the hero of many of our youths anyone who watched Jackass as a
kid or a teen and current hero still Johnny Knoxville. We were so excited to
learn a few months ago that he is a fan of no such thing as a fish and in fact
just a big old nerd and so we persuaded him to come on the show and it was
truly brilliant so fun to do it with someone who knows exactly what it's
about and who is a genuine geek about so many cool things. He himself has
another brilliant podcast called pretty sure I can fly. It is an exploration of
things that limit human beings and then the people who smash down those
limitations they interview awesome people who've done incredible things it's
him and Elna Baker who you might know from this American life definitely worth
listening to but first of all hello Andy here we actually have a bonus
announcement which is that we are making a sneaky trip to the Edinburgh Fringe in
just a few days time on the 14th of August we're going to be at the Edinburgh
Playhouse at 8 p.m. this is our last pre-tour live show so it's just going to
be a brand new episode of the podcast itself it's going to be so much fun if
you're at the Fringe or if you know someone who is or if you simply live in
Edinburgh we would love to see you there and to lure as many of you in as
possible we have sneakily lowered ticket prices so there are now plenty of
tickets available for just 25 pounds if you would like to come and see us go to
no such thing as a fish.com/live that's it hope to see you there on with the show
hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish a weekly podcast
coming to you from four undisclosed locations around the world my name is
Dan Schreiber I'm sitting here with James Harkin Anna Tyshinski and Johnny
Knoxville and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our
four favorite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order here we
go starting with fact number one that is Johnny. Johnny Paycheck who scored a
number one hit with take this job and shove it once shot a man over a bowl of
turtle soup country music is so badass yeah guys don't prejudge because he had
had a day yeah he had had a day go and justify it wait what do you mean over a
bowl of turtle soup well I'm going to get to that later but he took umbrage to
the fact that he was offered a bowl of turtle soup and so he had to retaliate
he had no choice so you gotta be careful Anna because I don't want you to be shot
over a discussion of a shooting over some turtle soup thank God this is on zoom
yeah he's in a bar right and a fan cool mind in his own bit yeah he was what
happened was it was 1985 he just wound up his tour and he was hanging out at a
Hell's Angels clubhouse because he loved to hang out the Hell's Angels and at
that point a bomb threat got called in from another motorcycle gang so thinking
quickly he gathered up all the cocaine in the clubhouse got in his car and took
off and he's going to his mom's house in Ohio along the way he stops at this bar
right and he is pinned on cocaine and he walks in and these two guys walk up to
him and really crowed them and talking to him really chatty one guy's name is
Larry Wise and they start drinking together and they exchange hats which
incensed paycheck it made him angry one was holding a bottle and I believe
Paycheck's lawyer later said that that he was scared of broken bottles and that
further inflamed him I think that's some bullshit they made up afterwards then
the guys like hey Johnny we got some turtle soup out in the truck would you
like some turtle soup and that was the final straw right cool he thought well
they must think I'm some kind of hick and so he pulled his 22 out of his
waistband and shot Larry in the head but Johnny's so short it just skims up his
brow and shoots his hat off like a borrower he called me that's cool yeah
Larry didn't even know he'd been shot until he'd been over and his ears were
ringing and he saw blood all over the floor and at that point he said I know
I had been shot and he just runs out of the bar as fast as he can and Paycheck
follows him going oh come on back Larry I won't shoot you no more that's really
interesting I didn't know this story and I thought well for me turtle soup is
supposed to be really tasty no yeah I've never had it I think wasn't the thing
that in the 19th century all the posh people loved it and it was meant to be
delicious and then fell out of favor but is it a hick thing do we think it was
meant as an insult no I think they were just he was he was on like eight ball or
two so anything was going to come across weird to Johnny Paycheck yeah and he
fought it for ages didn't he it was it went back and forth as a case about
whether or not he was guilty and it was only years later that he eventually was
found guilty by a court and and got a jail sentence off the back of it yeah
for in 91 he went to Chilacothe prison for seven to nine years but he was only
in there for two before the governor big dick Celeste partied him
did he give himself that big name yeah that was yeah that was self-given
if you're a man called Celeste I think you've got to have big dick as the
preamble property who is this Johnny Paycheck then Johnny because I'm not
into country music I must admit is he a big name yes he was a wonderful bass
player and singer he played with George Jones for many years and then he went
out on his own in the 60s actually him and his friend founded Little Darling
Records in the 60s so he was way ahead of the curve on that and in the 70s he had
a lot of hits with the outlaw country movement which I was actually was not
familiar with the outlaw country movement but it sounds like a bunch of
people just thought country was way too soft or had gone a bit soft and so
outlaw country artists were basically the hardcore country guys right who lived
really rough and ready lives and he's the extreme example like it couldn't
help Johnny Paycheck when he was in court and they were citing previous songs
that he had published like pardon me I've got someone to kill I like a great
drink in in driving yeah yeah his big song was called take this job and shove
it and yeah that was written by a guy called David Allen Coe who also spent
time in Chili Kothi prison and he only got into songwriting when he was in
prison because one of the inmates that he was hanging out with was another guy
called Screamin' Jay Hawkins who is a huge singer he did that song I put a
spell on you but um I mean that prison was produced a lot of great country
artists can I just say this guy was in court right yeah and they're using his
songs as evidence against you know I realized they're just songs like this
guy who sang I put a spell on you did he get done for witchcraft yeah right no
they obviously didn't I'm just saying when you've got a catalogue with quite
aggressive murdery sounding things it can't help I think I think it does with
drill music here which I don't even know if Johnny would know about right but
at some that sometimes used against people I believe drill music lyrics but
yeah he became sort of a working-class hero a bit with take this job and shove
it right I think people yes we're a big fan of that because it was tough living
in America around about that time people didn't like their bosses the New York
Times obituary of him described him as someone who led a rowdy jail-prone life
yeah quite a few prison sentences yeah he got in trouble a lot he was on tour
with Patsy Klein and he and he stole her car they were playing this fairgrounds
and he stole her car and they're like up paycheck has stolen her car and they
just closed the front gates of the fairgrounds and he just drove round and
round the fairgrounds till the car ran out of gas and then he got out and went
back to the show what's interesting is it sounds a bit like the rowdy life was
slightly encouraged I was reading an interview with Willie Nelson so he was
on the publicity road plugging his new book which is called roll me up and
smoke me when I die and he was saying you know did you ever get into scrapes
just to have the material and his responses I don't want to mention any
names but I do know one country singer whose manager would intentionally get
him in trouble with his girlfriends and wives and then get him drunk just so
that he could write because that's when he penned his best stuff and it sounds
like Willie Nelson had a wildlife as well this is one of the questions from
the interviewer your first wife Martha once sewed you up in a bedsheet while
you were asleep and beat you with a broomstick was she a particularly
crafty woman or were you a really bad husband oh it was a combination of both
like in Willie didn't have to worry because he had this drummer Paul English
who started out as a pimp and Fort Worth and Willie was having trouble getting
paid for his shows so he hired Paul English to be his drummer and collect
for him after the shows he had his gun in Bill Graham's mouth Paul English oh my
god Bill Graham was like a famous promoter and Bill Graham was trying to
hoodwink them on the payment and he's like let me leave and I'll go get the
money and English had his gun in his mouth says no you're gonna stay right
here son send him to get the money and that guy went got the money and Willie
got paid how long did he wait just out of curiosity how long was that gun in the
mouth because that you know a bank run can take a while can't it oh there was
drooling he comes back 30 minutes later and he's like I forgot the pen I'm sorry
I'm gonna have to go do it again is this what it's still like is Keith Urban
rocking around with a with a revolver I don't think it's like it was in in the
day oh well you know Billy Joe Shaver legendary singer songwriter was in a
bar in Lorena Texas and this guy was being disrespectful to Billy Joe telling
him to shut up after a while Billy Joe goes let's go outside son and they went
outside and Billy Joe walked over to his car guy's pistol walk up to the man goes
where do you want it and then shot him in the mouth or as Billy Joe said right
between the mother and the fucker and the guy lived out of interest when he asked
the question where do you want it and then he shot him in the mouth had the guy
asked for the mouth no he didn't answer you didn't he didn't give him time to
answer which is where I have problem with the story but other than that you know I
love Billy Joe sure yeah yeah the mouth no sorry the tow the tow I'm afraid I
have to take your first answer just one thing about Johnny paycheck that kind of
endeared me to him because he is a rough guy and he led quite dark life but one
quite sweet story I liked was he was asked to sing the national anthem in a
stadium before one of the Atlanta Falcons football games so he's there a
Falcons game the crowds is massive and as he struck the first cord he forgot all
the worse the American national anthem
and he just it sounds awful and he said it was it was horrible and he just made up
the words he just made up kind of nonsense words poor guy that's amazing
really I didn't know that story I have to look that I want to see if there's any
footage of that I think there might be because they've recorded what the
lyrics were that he made up I think he was a songwriter
so yeah imagine if they were just way better than the original
yeah we changed it based on them and he did clean himself up later on I think
didn't he Johnny paycheck and he would give anti-drug talks to kids and stuff
but everyone was just still expecting him to be off his face on cocaine and
pissed and all that kind of stuff so I think he kind of even though he was
clean he did play up to it quite a lot yeah didn't he
and that song take your take this job and shove it
it got turned into a movie yeah I really love this it's the first
movie to ever have a monster truck in it
it's the best piece of information and apparently it like started the big monster
truck craze in America wow oh what a what a cool interlinking bit of history
yeah the the guy who wrote take this job and shove it as you mentioned
earlier David Allen Cole between the ages of nine and 35 he spent about half
that time in prison in and out of correctional institutions
and got out became a singer songwriter had a lot of success
but in the 80s he stopped singing to become a magician
and let me tell you he is the scariest looking
magician you have ever seen so funny and ventriloquist
and actually Penn from Penn and Teller
said that he saw David Allen Cole perform as a kid
and he had a big influence on him really so yeah I don't know if I trust someone
hanging around with that crew I'd expect if they said they were going to
saw someone in half they might just actually saw them in half
so yeah that would be serious um he's his son by the way is a podcaster
so Tyler Mahon Co and he makes a show called cocaine and rhinestones
which actually sounds brilliant it's all about the sort of mysteries of country
music and the history of its stars and so on
so yeah because Co called himself the rhinestone cowboy didn't he
and that was way before the mysterious rhinestone cowboy
he formed in a mask and here is here's a picture of him
when he was with his ventriloquist dummy is he the most frightening
I've talked to Tyler Co about that and he goes my dad told me that dummy was
real and alive and that really scared me when I was little
I could just imagine someone going tell me where you want me to shoot you and
the dummy goes in his mouth no not in his mouth yeah in his mouth
okay it is time for fact number two and that is my fact
my fact is that in the 1980s skateboarder Nardis Carpus
had his merchandise banned in many schools and shops because it was believed
he was evil after some people noticed that his first name
Nardis spelt backwards was satan
wow and was it like how he changed his name to satan backwards
no he's he's um I mean Johnny you actually you know this guy the skateboarder
but he's Lithuanian by descent and uh yeah it's a it's a name there it means
birth of Christ but it is satan backwards and when
people saw that there was a bit of a panic that what if this guy
is in cahoots with the devil we can't have his skateboard and backpack
sold in our shops and so he suffered a sort of ban
it wasn't a countrywide ban but certainly it affected him and made news
so funny yeah he overcame that ban because he was
one of the most legendary street skaters him and Mark Gonzalez
you know I think Nardis was the first guy to ollie up on a rail
and uh and an ollie as the three of us have probably been learning some
skating terminology and ollie is the one where you jump in the air with your
skateboard right yeah it's where you it's where you so
you need a skateboard that is got uh two bits that flip up at the end as
opposed to like the street skate board where it's flat on one end push down
slide your foot forward raise in the air and land and I you forget that Dan
really is into skateboard yeah I was skater yeah my whole my whole
teenage are we in a podcast where 50% of us can do an ollie yeah
oh I I can't I'm tear I would only skate when we needed footage
of someone smashing right so you're good at falling off
yeah yes but yeah I'm just uh on Nardis quickly he as Johnny's just pointed
out he was one of the originals he was one of the guys who took skating
into the modern era such of street skating he was
one of the first people um if not the first credited with doing a grind
down a rail he didn't land it that's still though is like yeah it was like wow
that doesn't count but the idea the idea yeah but anyone could have an I can
have an idea of what I'm gonna do then if I can't do it then
yeah but that's like saying any astronauts that died before they got to
space because the ship blew up aren't astronauts no you didn't make it funny
no it's not it's like me saying that my daughter's got a little rocket ship and
she's singing zoom zoom going to the moon and she's an astronaut
no no he's come on he didn't just look at the rail and say I want to do that and
then fall over it sounds like he actually got up onto it right okay yeah
he also he also innovated the idea of wall skating where you can go off the
side of the street and literally go on the wall and come back down and land and
so that was him as well so he's a big he's a big player in the in the history
of modern skating but it's interesting because skating has always been
associated with sort of debauchery and it's kind of like the country music of
the the sports world right yeah it's especially in the 90s
obviously skating has just become an olympic sport and the previous olympics
I think was the debut for it and so I went on their website and they've got
a really interesting history of skateboarding on there including the
fact that in 1978 for a decade skateboarding was banned in Norway
because kind of like like not us they just thought it's leading to all these
deaths it's a bad influence and so on they'd heard that a hundred thousand
people had been injured and that 28 children had died
and so importing skateboards and having any ramps of any kind were not allowed
in Norway and so there was a black market there was like a hidden
forest area that people would set up halfpipes and they would
they would sneakily make black market boards that they would pretend with
something else and then you would turn them into a full skateboard and
so it was through decade what do they pretend it was do you think they
pretended it was a weird flute or something
it's still banned in Manchester in England is it skateboarding yeah yeah
because dangerous um I think it was because it was associated with youths
yeah do you know what I mean like actually the place where everyone
skateboards in Manchester they still do it they're just not allowed to
yeah I mean because you can't stop kids from skateboarding
to be fair it's quite dangerous I think it is on safety grounds that it tends to
be banned and people get injured it reminds me
quite a lot of and I don't know if they have this in America as well but in
Britain at the moment there's a lot of panic about scooters
you know those electric scooters people ride um they're so dangerous and there's
lots of spurious stats thrown around about how dangerous they are
but it's it's quite risky but also that's what makes it cool and I was reading
that the reason actually skateboarding really struggled to get into the
Olympics for a while was because skateboarders didn't want to because
the Olympics is kind of lame and really mainstream and normal
people like me watch it every night whereas skateboarders
are really cool and so I think there was a you know a lot of
organizations did not campaign to get included in the Olympics because
it's really interesting I think we might have said this before we started
recording about how uh breakdancing is coming into the Olympics
yeah soon and we're all looking forward to it but I know a lot of people in the
breakdancing community were not happy about it being in the Olympics for that
exact same reason and what they thought was that a lot of
ballroom dancers think that ballroom dancing should be in the Olympics and
all these different kind of dancing and they thought that the ballroom dancers
were using breakdancing as like a gateway drug to the Olympics and then
once breakdancing is in all of the dancing will get in
and they thought the Olympics I don't have a problem with that actually because
there's some sports that like dressage where the horse pants is I'm like what
is happening right now yeah my girlfriend loves it
I'll get in trouble for saying that but I'm just I can't get behind it
I agree I think a lot of the equestrian stuff is the horses need the metals
some of the equestrian competitors are really quite old because I was thinking
Britain sent a team of three skateboarders and it's the biggest age
range in a skateboarding team and I thought maybe the guide that we sent
Andy McDonald might be the oldest competitor so he's 51
I think actually I think he turned 52 yesterday
and the two other girls that we've sent are 16 so that's quite nice the team is
two 16 year olds and then someone who's more than three times their age
but yeah in the equestrian you get 60 something year olds
yeah just goes to show it the horses aren't 60 something are they
yeah you try to think what event could I possibly
do well in in the Olympics and it would have to be something where you sit on a
horse or yeah definitely I'm too old to be a
skateboarder I reckon because I was reading about a 1080
trick which is uh six turns right on a skateboard
that sounds impossible a six that sounds like James if you want to try it I'll
film it yeah yeah I think is it not because it's
that if it's the number of degrees it would be three turns right if it's 1080
yeah unless unless the 11 year olds dad was standing at the side
and just went gave them extra spins as they were going by I guess it is it's
three 360s isn't it so yeah the first person to ever do it
on a standard ramp was 11 years old and it previously only been done on what's
called a mega ramp which is a bit like a ski jump
and the only people who'd done that last time I checked were
11 years old 12 years old 15 years old and 15 years old
and I'm wondering at the age of 45 whether I'll maybe a bit beyond it
well like I said the other guy's 51 so it obviously takes all sorts but it does
seem to be dominated by people under the age of 20
usually when you see those it's like Tony Hawk waiting at the bottom of the
ramp with like a nine-year-old at this like 200 foot ramp and he's like just
give it a go and that seems to be his gig at the moment forcing
nine-year-olds down ramps Tony Hawk seems to be the only
person who's gained mainstream fame and it's massive mainstream fame
I'm not totally sure how especially because he retired when he was 30 31 I
think from competing anyway and the the thing I
could find that he's done most recently is get into a big conversation with Apple
about what the skateboard emoji should look like
so when you try and say skateboard in your whatsapp messages which
we all do a lot obviously the skateboard there is based on his
skateboard because when we've talked about the consortium that designs
emojis but when they released what they thought was going to be their
skateboard emoji in 2017 he messaged them being like that
shit that looks like something from the 80s here's a photo of my skateboard do
you want to give it another go right so so why is he so big because he is the
only one I've heard of as well like he had video games and stuff right no one
has done more for the sport of skateboarding than Tony he's
like the ambassador of skateboard and he's one of the greatest skaters of
all time and he's very intelligent well spoken
and he also when he landed the 900 back in I can't remember when it was
he was already big but he exploded you know after that I think that's when the
Tony Hawk games came out and he's uh the 900
is that number of degrees turn yes yeah that is spinning around in the air
yes loads of times loads of times of a big rep
he as James points out this the the the big moment in terms of commercialness
was the video games Tony Hawk Pro Skater was a global
sensation he effectively became what Michael Jordan is to basketball he
became to skateboarding uh interestingly he's ruined the life of
one man in the UK who is a quite well known
comedian called Tony Hawks with a nest at the end
whose whole life has been absolutely ruined his online life with people
mistaking him as the skater so a few years ago he actually
published a book called Tony Hawks the A to Z of skateboarding
where he replies to the emails of everyone who's asked him for skateboarding
advice with just terrible uninformed responses
that's going to confuse people even more people like me who do always confuse
them now I'm like hang on he's the one who's written the skateboarding book
when jackass started we got sued by this man
named jack ass because we had ruined his good name
that's incredible did you ever beat him did you ever get to
I never got to meet mr ass no I would love to
mr ass suggests that the case is still going on the respectful way
and there was some legal trouble with the guy from my hometown
whose name was reverend general Johnny Knoxville
who sold plots of land on the moon and oh yes I think he came after me at one
point and oh wow yeah interesting for my
birthday one year I wanted to sue all my friends but my
attorney talked me out of it I was just gonna make up some
I don't know I just thought it'd be funny to like sue 10 of my friends and then
have to hire attorneys and just be a big pain in their ass
yeah yeah how many friends do you have left now
out of interest well that's true I would have had to
sue like three people multiple times yeah
while we're talking about skateboarding I you know most of the jackass guys
we came from big brother magazine which was a skateboarding magazine owned by
Larry flint he owned a bunch of mags not as art
directed one of the articles I wrote for a snowboarding mag but anyway a big
brother there was a mix up in the shipping department
one day and all the people that were supposed to get
big brother magazine got taboo magazine which was Larry flint's dirtiest
magazine and and all the people that were supposed
to get taboo got big brother so it was it was really bad
because a bunch of 14 year olds got taboo and a bunch of dribble
ejaculators got you know big brother and I don't know who was more upset I
would assume the people who got taboo I don't know I think some of those 14
year olds were pretty delighted oh best day yeah yeah yeah taken yeah
I found a skateboarding record I think we could break
oh goodness world record okay um let's do it I think
well maybe Johnny or Dan you can say I'm totally wrong but basically on
February 17th 2017 a guy called Brandon Gonzalez
performed a stationary manual that lasted two hours and 55 minutes and now I
obviously had to look up where that was but it's just standing it's just
standing on your skateboard right no with one foot in the air and one foot on
the ground no but the but the the tail can't touch the
ground oh can it not so it's a balance act you
would be balancing I didn't see that from the picture
on the two back wheels doing her 27th hour standing on a skateboard come on
guys I'm absolutely smashing this it's so
easy but Guinness adjudicated going behind her going oh
shit I didn't see okay no I got this wrong man okay I take that back I'm
sorry okay yeah no is the answer we cannot
break that one
okay it is time for fact number three that is Anna my fact this week is that
when Chuck Yeager broke the sound barrier he brought 220 gallons of alcohol on the
flight with him nice I've done a trick in us Anna I've
done a trick but I found this so surprising
so Chuck Yeager broke the sound barrier in 1947
in the bell x1 plane and the fuel it used was alcohol
like it was just a huge tank of alcohol so it was burning liquid oxygen and then
a mixture of five parts alcohol to one part
water which seems incredibly weird and is not something that
like occasionally you talk about alcohol fuel there are jokes that Prince
Charles runs his cars off wine there are certain places that
use ethanol in their vehicles but it doesn't seem that ordinary but it seems
like yeah he ran them off ethanol I imagine it's quite dangerous
I suppose you wouldn't want to drop a drop a lit match in there
but then you wouldn't want to win any of it and you wouldn't want to drink it
halfway through the flight either yeah multiple if you distill it through a
sock it's probably safe because I think that's what people in prison do with
rubbing alcohol they distill it through their sock and then
but hey kids don't do that you know because but you know if you're desperate
if you've run out of wine yeah yeah was that fuel for all the p-51 bombers at the
time um I'm not sure I know it was fuel for the
flights that he flew over that time period yeah I don't think he will have been
I think because this was a very experimental plane right yeah yeah it
was flying it was more modeled on a rocket I think
and he nicknamed it sweetly the glamorous glenus
after his fiance who was called glenus fade dickhouse I know thank god he didn't
go for the surname we mentioned our product is a production
company no really yeah that's our production
companies come off it no way they're not the glenus
well no no it just uh that was a coincidence
yeah and it was sweet but I remember I was reading
a book about Chuck Yeager and to woo his wife he said stick with me honey and
you'll be farting through silk
had a real way with words Chuck Yeager
nice the the night before he broke the sound barrier this is
widely known he he had broke his ribs in a horse riding accident
and the doctor who is rumored to have patched him up
was this man colonel John Paul Stapp now
he was a physician flight surgeon and led some of the most groundbreaking
experiments on deceleration uh it was like the late 40s to mid 50s
and they were trying to determine what it was like for pilots to
eject at high altitudes and also what they can withstand in a plane crash
so they thought a person could only withstand 18 g's
of force and a g is like the amount of force the earth's
gravitational field exerts on human body when you're standing
still anyway they thought they could only withstand 18 g's
and he knew that was wrong because being a flight surgeon he could look at the
crash records and see that these pilots had
was stood more than that but the plane had failed
so he did all these experiments and one was
they had this rocket sled and he would strap himself to it
and he would go up to speeds which eventually reached 630 miles an hour
and stop within 1.5 seconds oh yeah it's not safe
no and 630 miles an hour by the way was faster than
a speeding bullet at that time wow and come to a complete stop
and i think the last time he did it he experienced
46.2 g's wow and he went temporarily blind afterwards
and not only that not only did he go temporarily blind
but he ended up with two black eyes because when he stopped
his eyes shot forward into his socket so hard
like somebody sees Jessica Rabbit yeah exactly
they went blank and he ended up with black eyes and
prior to doing it he was so sure that this blindness would happen
that he spent a lot of time in his room blindfolded and trying to work out how
to exist without sight anymore because he thought
that's what's going to happen that's so cool that's like being punched in the
face from the inside isn't it yeah inside your head
exactly but i think am i right that he broke the
land speed record i think he was known as the fastest man on earth
yeah time magazine did a bit he was on all the tv shows he was a huge star then
and now no one knows him yeah that's weird i read that
when he stopped for that instant his body weighed about 7700 pounds
what yeah um which is about the same as a white rhino
wow because your weight is your mass times the gravitational
but he did he didn't balloon to it did he no no it's just like
it's more of a mathematical thing really but yeah what a shame
he was trying to prove what humans could withstand but it feels like it's a loose
definition of withstand because yeah he went blind had black eyes he cracked
his ribs he broke his wrists his respiratory and
circulatory systems were really badly damaged
i mean you know there's withstand again there's um
living through in good health isn't there yeah there's what's standing and
there's a showing off yeah exactly there's a thin line between
a great guitar fill and a smart ass guitar player
he's i don't quite get that but i think i agree with it
he's also the reason by the way for the term murphy's law yeah we have murphy's
law because of him yeah because on on an experiment
that was done five years earlier where they're testing out the speeds it was
captain murphy who was part of the test and
afterwards when snap was utterly injured like
really broken murphy just kind of explained that anything that can go
wrong will go wrong in different words that became murphy's law
it needs an addendum anything that can go wrong will go wrong if you are working
with kernel john snap who doesn't mental shit
snap did nothing wrong he was just the passenger it was murphy
have you johnny i i imagine within the uh the world of jackass that you've
done a few things testing the pull of gravity um
well gravity is the funniest comedian of all time
and in my opinion i never reached a speed of 630 miles an hour on anything
but yeah gravity did play a part that in newton's third law of motion
without those two things i'd have no career
thank god for physics yes thank god that's so good you know snap is also
the reason we have uh seatbelts in cars
now yeah he was also testing restraint systems
and finally got the air force to listen when he explained that we're losing
more pilots on the ground than we are in the air
and there's a snap car crash conference that he founded i think still goes on
today so wow what a good guy
yeah should we talk a bit more about chart keager oh yeah yeah
please um he was really hardcore another really
hardcore one along with those country artists in world war two
he um distinguished himself by being just amazing at dog fighting
basically didn't hear and he loved it um so great in a plane but he
had this episode i didn't know about where he was shot down over france
and so he has to bail out with his parachute and he said he could see
german soldiers all over the ground below but luckily he landed
in a forest uh but this meant that he had to climb over the mountains to cross
the border to get into safe territory and so he's like knee deep in snow he's
had to bail out of his plane he's with a comrade
and they almost get caught and have a really awful scrape when they find a
hut to sleep in and the guy he's with leaves his socks
outside the cabin to dry which i'd be so pissed off about
german soldiers came past how did they be distilling their alcohol
if he's a good point that's oh wow so yeah the
Germans came past and they started shooting at them so then they leap out
the window and his navigator who's the guy with him
is badly shot but then an incredibly cool thing i think this is what happened
they both jumped onto or chuck basically carried his badly injured
navigator onto a log slide which i think must have
just been one of those log flumes that they used to carry logs down mountains
and they cascaded down the mountain on this log side to escape
he then amputates his friend's leg with a pen knife
yeah just out of anger because he's so pissed off with him
that's one less sock you'll need
but yeah then he takes his leg off and then he leaves him by the side of the
road says bye and fortunately he's rescued and
saved but i mean jager didn't know that jager just
left a legless man on the side of the road and yeah he had one leg he didn't
he didn't take both his legs off you gotta make some hard decisions
yeah yeah he got picked up by the resistance and
at the time if you spent time with the resistance and got back to america you
were no longer allowed to fly again because if
you got shot down again you may give up the resistance
but he went to washington and lobbied to i don't know what was washington but he
lobbied with a general and said look i want to go back
if i get caught i won't say a word and i think he was the first person to be
allowed to fly again after being captured
wow this is jager right yeah when he was young this was way before he was
chuck jager this was just just a hard-ass kid
because then when he was doing that all of his flying
afterwards by all rights he should have been one of the first astronauts right
you would have expected him to be like he couldn't get in because he didn't have a
degree and i get the feeling that that really pissed
him off for pretty much his whole life after that
yeah impression it's interesting there's it's a big role
in the movie the right stuff which was a book by tom wolf where you see him
sort of getting overlooked because he was the man you know he
yes he could do anything in the movie he kind of makes
pizza with it but yeah you get the impression that he should have been
there with neil on the moon wow widely recognizes the greatest natural pilot to
ever live he had 2010 vision yeah uses built for it
what is that because i thought 2020 was the best but it's clearly not right if
2010 is better anything that you can see from
10 meters he could see the same from 20 meters
okay so it's twice as good as you twice as good actually a lot more than that for
you but for a normal person yeah yeah i'm not a good
person to use of that um how interesting and he yeah
i mean bringing up the apollo astronauts um the glennis fey his wife
uh such a such a shame that the sound barrier wasn't broken in a plane called
the dick house that's such a shame but he named he named three of his
initial planes after her the glamorous glenn and then glennis
became a name afterwards and they were married until
his dying day and i think her dying day in fact sorry her dying day
um he died 2020 didn't he um i used to i used to follow him facebook i used to
get updates all the time from from chucky agar he was very active on facebook
was he yeah um but yeah that was rare all the apollo and mercury
astronauts ended in divorce multiple times and him and his wife were a unit
all the way to the end and in fact i think he used that when he was when
there was a discussing who's going to try and break the sound barrier who's
going to be our test pilot i think they said there was an argument that it
should be someone who was single and childless because then if they died
it didn't matter it was just one person and i think he argued no it's much
better to choose someone like me who's got a wife and a little boy who i love
because i'll be much more careful and uh so i'll make sure that i do
survive it it's an argument that worked for him so we don't need to interrogate
now fill her up with booze i'm going on a horse ride
yeah he did uh an experiment with kernel john paul staff as well uh they
did a wind blast experiment where they went up in a plane
without a canopy on it and reached speeds of over 500 miles an hour
and people were saying no don't do that you're going to be decapitated this or
that but you know they were fine decapitated by just the the them that
much the wind yeah how were they fine i'm really
surprised because i'm a story that is always told about me is when my mom was
driving the car when i was a baby and they had you know you had like a you've
got roof window what do you call it sunroof sunroof thank you um and
my dad was holding me and my mom was a very fast driver and my dad thought it
would be really funny to lift me up he was just holding me on his lap
lifted me up and put my head out the window and my mom said she's never been
so furious with him i mean in a way it was her fault for driving 100 miles an
hour along main road but um i think i i think it wasn't that fun for me as a
baby i'll be honest anna i don't think anyone
comes out well with that story i was an innocent victim
i can just see in the background johnny slightly going tell me those footage
that i could use in the future
oh yeah they survived it
okay it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is james okay my fact this week is that according to tradition
of the banner people of ethopia before a man can become a man
he has to learn how to walk on stilts
okay you know like i see i don't drive but i'm told that if i fail
the driving test enough times they just give it to you
is there like that's not true that's not true no no no all right i'll learn then
okay damn you're thinking how many times can you fall off the stilts before they
just go okay have your penis anywhere yeah exactly
i think they always have a penis it's just like their culture
has got like quite a complex level of age groups like you go from this age group
to this age group to this age group uh and to go from and actually this is true
of a lot of people around the world but to go from adolescence to manhud
they have a ceremony and part of that ceremony involves them having to strike
a balance on stilts and it's supposed to show that
you're strong minded independently willed confident
and ready to take on a wife okay it's what all women want
yeah man you can walk on stilts yeah i've walked on stilts before
it's pretty yeah yeah i've had i you know not
ginormously high ones but i would say four feet in the air at least
and that's high they're fine they're they're really easy to get used to
yeah straight away what was the context in which you're walking on stilts
i think i was at a house that just had a lot of um party gear and stilts were
part of the the gear and i just gave it a badge maybe you just have a natural
affinity to stilts wow yeah it can't be that easy
because people make a living from doing it so it can't be that well no but they
do more complicated things with it right like i'm just
yeah and they do it funny clothes and to be fair when i was watching a video of
these banner kids some kids on stilts and they mostly look like they're having
so much fun and they find it extremely entertaining which it would be
and also the interviewer says to one of these little kids who's just running
around on stilts so how long have you been doing this how long does it take to
get ready is it months years and the guys like i just started yesterday mate
it's i mean so maybe i think dan might be right i think like this is a piece of
cake you may be right and the idea was that the tribe would
traditionally use stilts to avoid wild animals and also you can see over the
savannah yes absolutely because actually there's
a tradition in europe of shepherds using stilts for the same reason
because you can get much higher up and you can see where all your sheep's are
and stuff like that is this the landis region it's over quite a lot of Europe
yeah the landis especially the landis in southwestern france this is amazing
they basically everyone in this town existed on stilts but it largely was
the farmers and exactly it was for that you would you would be on your stilts so
that you could see where all your sheep where it was also very
mushy and muddy in the ground and so it was very useful to get around by
standing on the stilt you had a big stick
which was what you would use to what's the word for when you're
getting the sheep into shepherd yeah you'd shepherd them with your big old
hood and but you would then use the big stick as a
seat so you like a tripod so you'd place your bum on it and they would just do
their knitting all day long would they yeah
oh that's nice with their recently shorn sheep's wool presumably yeah
exactly do with it lovely yeah these the banner people it's
weird that they say it's to then escape predators
because they also paint their bodies in black and white stripes that do resemble
quite closely a zebra it came with them and i was offering tips
i feel like don't don't disguise yourself as a zebra
yeah that's true one of the other ceremonies that they do is when they're
just about to get married uh and that is a bull-weeping ceremony
so you line up a load of cows in a row and everyone has to run
and jump over the backs of four cows without falling
and if you can do that then you're allowed to get married whoa four cows
it's not for you know like it's not like evil keneval jumping over four at once
yeah jump over one like slight hurdles okay yeah yeah
well i think i'd like to see james jump over four at once
i'm really uh becoming focused on james doing his son i'm actually very
scared of cows so perfect yeah what else are you scared of james
oh commitment i'll make sure your wife doesn't listen to this episode then
when we were filming wild boys we came across a lot of
rite of passages for boys to become a man and they're a lot were quite
entertaining and one sent my friend chris ponies to the hospital
the satari moe tribe uh hope i'm pronouncing that right in brazil
they will go out in the jungle and gather up bullet ants which are one of the
worst stings in the uh insect kingdom it's like 30
times worse than a bee sting and they'll gather up all the bullet ants
and they'll weave them into a glove of leaves with their
stingers sticking out and to become a man you have to put
your hand in the glove of bullet ants for 10 minutes
and take it and steve olimpanius both did it and
there was most excruciating pain that that was it
they've endured yeah and that's a high bar for them in fact
wow yes more than that's good to know because i think we might have mentioned
bullet ants before and you know they're this extreme pain animal and sometimes
i think are they that painful or are they just kind of they've gained this
reputation but you can verify steve says hurts a lot
yeah dude yeah um yeah ponies had to go to the hospital
because he had an allergic reaction anytime he gets stung by anything he
has to go to the hospital um i was looking up just i was just
googling around with the word stilt and i discovered that one of the greatest
early day basketball players had the nickname the stilt which was
wilt the stilt chamberlain which i i had no idea about yeah so wilt chamberlain
very famously scored a hundred points in a single game
he did free throws in that match underarm which we know is a better way of doing
three throws but we also know that basketball players think they look too
wimpy when they're doing it so they do it in the
overarm way instead he also is responsible for the fact
that when you take a shot at the foul line so ana i know
it's going to be hard to describe but this is a thing when you're
fouled you go when you get two shots in the basket in the key
and then then ana has just written a book about sport
it's called a lot of old balls the qi book of sport
it's available now in all good bug shops and she knows everything about wilt
chamberlain so you know all about this you shot yourself in the foot there down
if you didn't want us to mention it better better than in the mouth ana
so um where do you want it so yeah so um he's responsible for a major rule change
within basketball as well which is the fact that when he used to shoot at the
foul line he's six for eleven he would jump and
dunk it and that's not allowed anymore so they said you have to remain behind
the foul line but the stilt thing is really
interesting in his name wilt the stilt chamberlain because
everyone called him it it was the nickname that was used in every paper
and magazine and he hated it it was given to him in the early days and when
people were on his team were playing on a opposing team their their coaches
would be like don't call him the stilt he'll go nuts he's he's really upset
why didn't he hate it what's wrong with the stilt it's not they called him wilt
the asshole he won't yeah i don't he will calm down
dickhouse chamberlain he well he could have been called that he
supposedly that's another story on yeah apparently 20 000 women were bedded by
wilt the stilt um he's sure they were but he loved the name the dipper or dippy
and he got it because as i said he was ginormous six foot 11 and it's got
nothing to do with basketball it was one day he kept walking into doorways
because he's so tall and one doorway cracked him in the eyes
he got a black eye and they started calling him dippy because
they needed to remind him to dip down anytime he was heading out of doorway
and that's the name he loved but he was wilt the stilt to the end well i had to
say wilt the stilt it's a little snappier yeah yeah yeah it is
and cool and you can't make your own nicknames guys so
get over that yeah well big dick james harkin
says different it's like a walking stick full of bagels
i think the tallest stilt walk in history it certainly claims to be
speaking of people who make their own nicknames a guy called roi maloy
which bit is the nickname in roi maloy yeah i think
it's not even a good one i just think he wasn't born roi maloy
i think that might be a you know to make his name rhyme maybe it doesn't even
qualify as a nickname all right he's like a nom de plume
a nom de plume exactly thank you so he's set a bunch of world records for world
records and in 2008 he set the unverified world
record for the tallest stilts walk ever but i was looking up i
again i i know i keep making wild claims but i think we can break this one too
um johnny you could definitely do this surely you've done something similar to
this because it was 17 meter high stilts which is high that's like
five stories yeah there you go for all the yanks
there you go for the yanks um and he had to mount them by going up to the fifth
story of a building and lean the stilts next to the building and then he mounts
them from there wow but then it's a little bit like
if you're teaching a baby to walk he's got his helpers you can just see their
hands in the video and he's clinging onto their hands and then he just let's go
for a second does a really quick bloop bloop bloop bloop bloop one two three
four five on the spot on the stilts and then falls back into their arms again
and says that's the tallest stilts walk in history
i don't think that counts i don't think it counts either i think you've got to get
from a to b and they need to be in different places
did they hand him his penis after you're now a man
17 meter penis have you not ever walked on stilts johnny it seems like the kind
of thing that jackass would have done some kind of still walking stunts i can
barely walk on my own two feet which really helped me in stunts
but steve o was a clown when we initially hired him he worked at a carnival
a circus inside of a swap meet in florida it was bleak
so he did a lot of stunt walking and we we did one or two things with stilts but
they're nice to look at but you need a little blunt force trauma
to to make something watchable sure well you can still walk into a into a wall if
you want yeah but yeah do you know i'm
something interesting i haven't actually got the research on this i just this is
something i remember is that with stilt walking
there was a person who had cerebral palsy and found that their walking was
better when they were on stilts it helped to improve them
in some respects with their gait and how they're walking and michael j fox
also talks about that when he goes ice skating it really
causes the tremors that he has to sort of mellow down and rest a bit
interesting interesting i wonder the medical benefits of i'm not suggesting
that everyone be just ice skating and on stilts if there no ice skating on
stilts i love it there you go that's how you get the blunt trauma
yeah yeah harkin stunt there we go yeah
hello my name is james harken and this is ice skating on stilts
i'm there i'm there
okay that's it that is all of our facts thank you so much for listening
if you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we've said
over the course of this show we can all be found on various bits of social
media i'm on instagram on at schreiberland james
my instagram is no such thing as james harken johnny
my instagram is johnny noxville and anna where can they get to us as a group
you can get us on instagram at no such thing as a fish or twitter
at no such thing or you can email podcast at qi.com
yeah well you can go to our website no such thing as a fish.com
check it out all previous episodes are up there all of the upcoming tour dates
for our thunder nerds tour can be found on there and a link to our secret club
clubfish is also there but the main thing for you to do right now
is to switch this episode off and head over to a new show
it's johnny's show pretty sure i can fly is the name
it is a show where they look into great historical characters from history
johnny do you want anything to that it ain't too good but it's long
that's my tinder profile all right that's it we'll be back again next
week with another episode we'll see you then goodbye
(upbeat music)