(upbeat music)
- Hey everyone, welcome to another episode of Fish.
Dan here, hope you're doing well.
Just wanna let you know before we get into the show
about our guest joining us today.
It's one of our favorites.
Someone who's joined us a number of times
over the last few years, it is New Zealand comedian,
Melanie Bracewell.
So Mel, if you haven't heard her on the show before,
is someone whose work you may have seen in other places.
Her stand-up clips are always popping up online
for any doom scrollers out there.
If you're an Aussie, you'll know her
from the TV show She Co hosts called The Cheap Seats.
If you're a fan of Taskmaster
and have consumed all the international formats,
you will have seen Mel on series four
of the New Zealand Taskmaster.
And if you're a general connoisseur of comedy,
it's good to know that she has had a hand
in the writing of such shows as the rebooted time bandits
and also the absolutely brilliant Wellington Paranormal
of which she starred in two episodes as well.
But this is all stuff that's on the screen
over on the other side of the planet.
What about us in the UK?
Well, good news.
Mel is in the country right now on a stand-up tour,
literally happening as I speak.
So the good news is you can see her in person
doing the thing she does best,
which is stand-up with her new show called A Little Treat.
And if you wanna find all the details for that,
go to her Instagram.
It's @MelanieBracewell or just Google her name
and A Little Treat UK tour.
It'll all come up,
but basically as of March 1st, she's gonna be in Dorwich,
then she's gonna be going to Brighton, Liverpool, Manchester,
Edinburgh, Newcastle, Glasgow, Leeds and Cardiff.
So it's a limited run, but the tickets are selling fast,
so quickly get in now before she heads back over to Oz,
where just a heads up for the Aussies and New Zealanders,
she's gonna be on tour with this show from May.
All the details are online, but for now, enjoy her here,
dorking out with me, Andy and James,
on no such thing as a fish, on with the show.
(upbeat music)
(bell ringing)
(speaking in foreign language)
(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and Mel Bracewell, and once again,
we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Mel.
- My fact this week is that the New Zealand government
is stopping invasive species by using
Selina Gomez Oreos.
- That's huge.
- It's specifically possum.
So there's a huge possum problem in New Zealand.
There's no natural predators for possums.
Basically, they were trying to lure out
the really persistent possums that weren't
able to be trapped by other means.
They say what happens often is that they will go
and have a little bit of bait, get a bit sick,
and then go, "I'm never gonna eat that bait ever again,"
or they get almost stuck in a trap,
and then they don't ever go towards traps again.
So they were trying to find something that would lure
these possums that are very afraid of the traps in,
and what works specifically was Oreos,
but not as any, they had to be the Selina Gomez Oreos
because they like them so much.
- So they have a combination of chocolate and cinnamon
that possums just love.
- What a review.
What a review for the Oreos.
- I reckon I would be straight in those traps.
- Yeah, really.
- They do sound very, this is not an effort
for Selina Gomez or for Oreos.
But she's put a lot of work into the flavour profile, I think.
- Oh yeah, it was like years.
She really wanted to be in it.
- She was in the lab, wasn't she?
- She wanted to be in Oreos.
- It hasn't been a new album from her in quite some time.
- If you're a singer, that's another...
- Sorry, who do you think Selina Gomez is?
- I don't know, I was faster.
- A scientist?
- This was an article on the Spinoff,
which is a New Zealand website,
and that was one of my favourite parts of the article
is that the scientist does not know who Selina Gomez is.
He said, "I don't know who she is,
I just know she makes a good Oreo."
What was she saying?
- She has made no comment.
They have asked repeatedly,
"What do you think that your Oreos are being used
to wipe out for us in New Zealand?"
- She's a busy woman.
- What's a tough gig as well?
Because it is being used for what is getting rid of a pest.
- It's kind of...
- It's being used to protect native New Zealand.
- Absolutely.
- But at a cost of killing an animal.
If you're against that, that's a big issue.
- Like, if you sent her an email this week,
I don't know if you did or not,
but if you sent her an email,
say, "Dear Miss Gomez,
have you been killing gunnables in New Zealand?"
She's not gonna respond to that.
- P.S., what do you do?
What's your line of work?
- The line she's used as the strap line
is great for movie night
and make wonderful birthday treats
and music award-watch party snacks.
She didn't include an exterminating
and invasive species.
- The initial experiment that they had toyed with,
what they would do is they'd leave these things outside of traps
so that the possums would get a taste for them.
And what they were toying up was actually using drugs,
like addictive drugs, right?
And then they read a study about chocolate and cinnamon
having similar properties in similar properties of addiction.
And so they would leave them out and not trap them
and then get them addicted to these Oreos
and then that's really interesting.
- Well, they're gonna stop making these things.
This is a limited edition Oreo.
- That's the issue, yeah.
- They're gonna run out
and they're gonna need something else to lure
in the possums into the traps.
- Yeah.
- No, since it's a fish kit cut.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- What do you think?
- I don't want to be part of them.
- It's nice for podcast listening parties.
- Fish, are we just saying fish flavored kit cut?
- No, cinnamon and chocolate.
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
The possums aren't gonna eat that.
- No, fish flavored kit cut.
- I think I would.
- Would you?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- Fish ringer.
- It's not legally protected term, is it?
- Right, very true.
- So these guys have come over to New Zealand
from Australia, is that right?
- That's right.
- Yeah, Australia.
And then there's some pieces that have been introduced
from England as well.
And sorry guys, sorry to bring it up.
But look, we were bought for that song.
(laughing)
We were asked to come.
So the reason that they're not a problem
as much in Australia is because they do have predators.
And one of them is the powerful owl.
- Oh.
- And the powerful owl is Australia's largest owl.
And it is able to disembowel a possum
in less than 20 seconds.
- Wow.
- That's impressive when you say it like that.
But I've no metric of how long it should take me
to disembowel a possum.
- You know what I mean, like, like we're--
- Bring it in.
(laughing)
- So I know what you mean, wow.
- The interesting thing, the reason they disembowel it
is because they're meat eaters
and they're not interested in eating vegetables,
but the possums eat vegetables.
And so they don't want to eat their insides
because they're just full of useless green stuff.
They want to eat their meat.
- The equivalent of a kid picking the peas out
of their food.
- Nice.
(laughing)
- Do you know why possums were brought over
to New Zealand in the first place?
- They were brought over for the fur trade.
- Oh yeah.
- And it didn't work for a fur,
but then the numbers exploded.
And I think there are now 47 million give or take,
which ironically would be plenty for a thriving fur.
- That's a lot of fur.
- That's one of the fur trades then said,
like maybe about 15, 20 years ago.
- Hey, why don't we turn these guys into lovely pelts?
And that's a really good idea.
Wait a minute.
Why don't you the guys who brought them over
to the first place?
- I'm not trying to say I'm on the side of big fur.
- Yeah.
- But then, as you say, you've got loads of invasions.
You've got weasels and stoats and rabbits.
The really annoying thing,
the stoats were brought in to control the rabbits,
which had been brought in.
- Yeah.
- I don't know.
- It's the old lady who's followed a fly.
- Yeah.
- Yes.
- It's mad.
- The other thing they're doing with them is
it's become a bit of a delicacy over in places
like Hong Kong and Taiwan and China and so on.
And so they're sold over there.
And they're sold under the name Kiwi Bear.
- That's the meal that you have.
- Kiwi Bear.
- Yeah, it does, doesn't it?
Yeah.
- One pest that really ravages New Zealand
and it's more difficult to get rid of are hedgehogs.
And what people think is because hedgehogs are quite cute.
Is that they're cuter and they're diabolical.
They'll eat, they'll eat birds, eggs, and things like that.
But because people think they're cute.
They're less likely to want to.
- Can I give you a 10?
- Yeah.
- They're a bit of them.
- Because when we were a kid, we were told
that if you build a bonfire, a hedgehog will always go inside it.
So you have to check it before you set it on fire.
That hedgehogs.
- That's true.
- So I think they're attracted to them or something?
- They're hibernating them, don't they?
- Today.
- They go and they think,
"Oh, lovely, nice pile of leaves."
- Yeah, yeah.
- I was wondering about this.
Is that working?
- That your responses make it look like an accident.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
It's called the Beatrix Potter effect.
It's why, apparently there are more in New Zealand
than in Britain.
Which is where they're obviously native to Britain
than not native to New Zealand.
And it's been proposed that we put all the hedgehogs
on a big chip and sail it over.
- Yeah.
- But I don't think it's a project.
- What did you do?
- I was not being proposed by anyone.
- What they had said was that the reason they introduced it
was to remind settlers of gardens in the UK,
is the reason that you put them on a big ship and send them back
because if you put them on a small dinghy,
they're just gonna pop like...
(laughing)
- Yep.
- So I'm just thinking if it did hit something
and they had to do an escape,
quick everyone into the emergence, oh shit.
(laughing)
- Women and children first, hedgehogs definitely last.
- Is it controversial with it?
'Cause I know that you've got this whole
and brilliant national scheme.
- Yeah.
- I love it. - Yeah.
- Predator-free New Zealand.
- Yes, yes.
- Like I'm a fan of all those individual elements, right?
- You guys are trying it here, very slowly though.
(laughing)
- We're starting at the top, you know?
- That's a print sandwich, aren't we?
- I was trying to get there, but I didn't want to say it.
(laughing)
- We've just all had a buzz on our phones
that he's been arrested to.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, he's trying to arresting the possum, you know?
Sorry, but it seemed like it's a very sort of big
community effort, you know?
People are setting up traps in their gardens.
- Yeah.
- There was this school in 2022
on a place called, is it Rackiera or Stewart Island?
- Oh, yeah.
- And they had a hundred day challenge for the children
to kill as many rodents as possible.
- Yeah.
- And the 40 students who were taking part,
they caught 600 rats between them.
One five-year-old did in 60 rats over three months.
- That's the thing that they say
if a kid is trying to harm animals,
that's like the sign of a psychopath,
but we're trying to sort of get them to get to that point.
- It's a controversial thing to an extent,
because about a decade before that in 2010,
a school got questioned because they did this,
they did this kind of hunt for possums and for rats,
but then they got the kids to play a game of possum tossing
where who could throw the possum, the furthest,
and a lot of surveys to see how people felt about that.
- I gotta say, in 20 years' time,
you guys are gonna have an enormous prison population
or some incredible sports teams
with just a killer instinct.
(laughing)
- Absolutely.
- The New Zealand Empire begins to spread across the world.
- I can go the other way, so New Zealand has bush ticks
as do Australia, but they've recently been introduced
to America with quite a lot of problems.
And so much so, the first one they found
was a couple of years ago in New Jersey,
and a woman had been sharing her sheep
and she came in with these ticks over her
and said, I think there's a problem here
and it turned out to be these invasive ones.
And she had so many on her,
she had over 1,000 on her pants alone.
- Wow, she was just head to toe in these ticks.
- In ticks.
- Wait, does the person know her sheep?
- It was a person.
- Got it.
- And she survived.
- She survived, yeah.
So if you don't pull them out and leave the head in,
particularly Aussie ones, you get Lyme disease.
- Yeah, I assume they just sprayed her
with something not very nice and the ticks fell off.
- Oh, what a pickle.
- That's a being.
(laughing)
- And what it is, isn't it?
What's the pickle?
Like, as in...
- It's covered in a thousand ticks.
- There's no good side.
- Oh, I thought a pickle means like,
what a pickle I've found myself in.
- Do you think that there's two sides to a pickle?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- I think being in a pickle is bad overall.
- Is it?
- That's saying, there's two sides to every pickle.
(laughing)
- That's the name of my older brother.
- Oh, I guess that in a pickle,
you think of someone who's trying to make a decision.
- Yeah.
- Right, I can't.
- What a pickle if I'm myself in.
- No, you're in trouble.
- It's like, but in a pickle,
it's kind of both sides are still bad, right?
- No, you're on the homes of a dilemma.
You're in a pickle.
- Yeah, a nightmare.
- What about a pickle?
(laughing)
Unbelievable.
You can't rely on guests just to hoof you out of problems.
(laughing)
Well, have you ever seen a peacock wild in New Zealand?
- I haven't seen them wild in New Zealand.
I think I may have seen them wild in Australia.
- Oh, okay.
Is there a big problem in New Zealand as well?
- Yeah, okay.
- Which I didn't know about.
And it's partly because the possums
have been successfully trapped and hunted
in various areas.
Well, no one's eating those delicious, delicious peacock eggs.
They're also invasive and they're feral
and they're very hard to catch
because they're very wary of humans.
They flee, they do lots of damage to crops
and things like that.
But obviously, they're also very beautiful.
- Oh, yeah.
- They're kind of the best animals to get over there
when you have them.
- Yeah, cute.
- But it is for the amazing birds of New Zealand,
which are beautiful.
And in the areas where they've managed to fence it off,
they've done various islands.
The birds have all come back.
- Yeah.
- And it's now a cacophony of incredible birds
nesting there and it is pretty amazing.
- It is beautiful.
- Yeah.
And if it takes a million possums skulls
to crush under our heels, we'll do it.
(laughing)
Fish kick cats are now available in your local stores.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that one of the reasons
married couples slept in twin beds in Victorian England
is because doctors claimed that the weak sleepers
stole their partner's vitality during the night.
- Mmm, I think that's true.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Oh, you're sick.
- Would you say like if I'm snoring all night
and my wife's just gonna wake up tired?
- Yes.
- Absolutely.
I think though it could be the weak sleepers
also the one who wakes easily.
So you would be, so it's a hell of a pickle.
- But this is a situation.
(laughing)
- And what's the good part of it?
- Yeah.
- But this isn't about snoring waking up.
This is just about someone being an energy draze.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it's sapping the vital.
- It went more to it, didn't it?
It was like electromagnetic energy
was being sucked from you.
- Okay, in that case, who the hell is saying this shit?
- Well, this is Victorian England.
So, all right, okay.
- Yeah, all of it, all of it to England.
We're currently looking into getting twin beds
in our house and as happens with you guys,
you start Googling stuff and you know,
what do I know about twin beds?
- Unfortunately.
- But the thing is with you,
this is getting more into it
because previously you're a bunk bed sweatshirt.
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, I'm currently sleeping in a bottom bunk bed
of my son's room while my wife's in bed
with our three kids.
- All right.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Looking into getting twin beds.
- Yeah, but not for me and my wife
for our two youngest kids.
- Okay, thank you.
- I'm just kidding.
(laughing)
- Now you know that your vitality is being drained.
That may change, you may.
- Fortunately, someone had the same question
about the history of twin beds
and that was Lancaster University Professor Hillary Hines
and she wrote a cultural history of twin beds.
As she was looking into it,
she discovered that it was believed in around 1860s
that it would literally be taking away your energy.
- But the quotes are so extreme,
but this was one of my favorites.
Each sleeper should have a single bed
in a large, clean, light room.
So it's to pass all the hours of sleep in a pure fresh air.
And those who fail in this,
well in the end fail in health and strength of lemon brain
and will die while their days are not all told.
- Oh, wow.
- It's like, they should, you should do this
and then it's going, no, you'll die.
- You will die.
- It's very powerful, you know.
It's quite persuasive.
- There's like quite a long standing history
of people sleeping in separate rooms,
even in the British aristocracy.
And that is because, well, for lots of different reasons,
one reason because you're just going to have a better night's sleep
quite often.
But secondly, because they thought that it was unhealthy
to sleep in the same bed,
because germ theory had just come out
and they didn't really know how the germs would work.
And the other thing is like,
if you wanted a bit of romance,
you could go to your partner's room
rather than sort of like nudging them with a cold foot
and saying, do you fancy a bit?
You actually have to knock on the door and say, you know,
let me in.
- You're an action-tik-nix.
(all laughing)
- Interesting that you should,
that was my technique and that was my wife's technique.
- We seem to be in a pickle.
- There's also the other thing of this
with, so the Edwardian, so early 20th century,
a big bit of the reason that they had separate rooms
was to allow adultery.
- Oh.
- But, bum, bum, bum, because upper class Edwardian society
was absolutely right with the adultery.
And it was kind of expected
that the husband and wife would get married,
they'd have some children,
and then, what's the children are out?
It's free play.
- Right.
- And so, out of the house or the womb?
- Out of the womb.
- Okay, so while the children are still living there.
- Ideally, they'll be at school
or off on a trip or whatever.
- No, no, no, it's not when they've grown up and moved out.
It's literally in the family home.
- It's literally, it's especially,
not just in the family home,
but in grandhouses where you might go visiting,
you might go for a weekend party or something,
so you'd have single rooms.
And some of these rooms have little brass brackets outside
with a little name label saying exactly who's in where.
And supposedly, it was to help the butler identify who was who.
But it had a very useful second purpose
of allowing a bit of hanky-panky,
so you're not knocking on the wrong door
in the middle of the night
and ending up in a real, you know, tangle.
- Even more than that, there was a house called
Wentworth Woodhouse in South Yorkshire, which was the biggest house
in England, basically, and today,
when they had all the tops coming to visit,
they gave everyone a map to all the bedrooms.
- Brilliant.
- So you could kind of look at the map and go,
"Oh, I want to go to Mrs. Jones's room."
So I need to go up here down there, around there.
This Wentworth Woodhouse was the biggest private house
in the whole of England.
- Right.
- Victorian era.
How many bedrooms do you think it had?
- Ooh.
- Riddle me this.
- I'll say, I mean, bedrooms, I'll say high,
jubble figures.
- Yeah.
- I mean, it can't have more than about 50 or 60 bedrooms
I would have seen. - Oh, I was going way more.
- Oh, wow.
- Oh, wow, wow. - Oh, wow.
- The dead crusher.
- The fat, I mean, it's heavy.
- Oh, silly.
(laughing)
- I feel like the other times I feel on this podcast,
Dad, you always ruin the kissing game.
(laughing)
You get so high.
The real fact feels kind of lame and comparison.
- You want me backing me up?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I listen to Andy.
- I'm sorry, sorry.
- Well, no, I think, 'cause I was thinking that,
I know George Harrison has a house,
which is absolutely monstrous, like it's huge,
and I thought that that had in the hundreds.
I thought that had close to like 400.
So I'm going to say, 400.
(laughing)
- Okay, I'm going to say, well, maybe I'll lowball it.
I'll say 42.
- Okay, okay.
- Well, I said 50 or 60.
- Yeah.
- 42, 400.
- George Harrison, well, on about 4.
- My sweet Lord, Dan is the closest.
- Oh, yes.
- Oh my gosh, I'm sorry for doubting you.
- There we go, 300 rooms.
- Wow.
- Really close to you.
- Basically, there would have big hunting parties,
wherever one would come and shoot guns and stuff.
- But interestingly,
- Interesting, it was only two bathrooms,
'cause of the punting arrangements of the time.
- Yeah.
- And that was fine.
Yeah.
- Yeah.
- And these were quite modern.
This is the interesting thing.
Because of the association with greater hygiene
and not having your energy sapped away from you,
they were seen from the late 19th century and early 20th
to be the mom thing.
Now we think of them as being quite old fashioned,
but they were really kind of modern and quite cool.
- They were, but again, it was for the richer people.
- Oh yeah, yeah.
- And normal people, like forever,
normal people would share beds.
And then what happened was around the 50s.
There were a few different reasons,
but one of the reasons is television started to be more realistic
and television shows would show married couple
and also the haze code had finished.
So people were allowed to show men and women in bed together.
So people started showing men and women in bed together
and everyone thought, well, now that's the modern thing.
That's the fashion thing.
- Oh, is that what changed?
- That's a few different things.
- The haze code was fascinating.
'Cause in Hollywood, you had a guideline saying,
don'ts and be careful within movies.
So the don'ts were explicitly do not do this.
The be careful were, this is the guideline,
if you're gonna do this kind of scene,
and if someone who is watching it finds that offensive,
they will not allow for that to be in the movie.
So one of the things, that's very useful in the bedroom too,
to have don'ts and be careful.
- Yes.
- You know?
- I've always got a side on the side of this bed.
No heavy petting, no bombing, no running.
- No cold foot nudging me.
(laughing)
- Yeah, this was a big problem for Hollywood.
So there's a specific example of a movie
where the Marital Bed was one mattress
and it was a Lucille Ball movie,
and they had to re-shoot the scenes.
So it cost $30,000 for them to go and re-shoot this.
And it was simply that they just had to have it
something like 12 inches apart.
That was like the expected length
of how far the beds needed to be far.
- Oh, it's sort of safe.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
- In real distance for me.
Am I right?
(laughing and laughing)
Oh my God.
Okay, so some opinions about whether you prefer
to sleep in bed with a partner or not.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- This is a recent poll by you, Gov.
Five percent say their dream arrangement
is different beds in the same room.
So that is twin beds, okay.
Ten percent say different beds in different rooms
in the dream.
Seventy-six percent say same bed in same room.
- Interesting.
- Nobody says same bed but different rooms.
(laughing)
- That's it.
- Wow, what a challenge.
- Just my preference.
- Well, there was some studies that determine
that often when people sleep with their partner,
their subjective view of how well they slept was higher.
But the truth is that they had a worse sleep.
- Oh, interesting.
- So I feel like is what sleep track is due to my brain.
Where I feel like I've had a great sleep
and I wake up and I'll say you've had a horrendous sleep.
And then I'll be in a bad mood.
I'll go well, it told me I've had a bad sleep.
So I'll spend the rest of my day feeling bad.
But in the opposite, I'll have a,
I feel like I've had a terrible sleep.
And then my phone will say it was a great one.
I'll go, you know what,
let's really put a people in my step.
- Yeah, I think for a lot of people,
if you have a partner, there's a sense of safety.
- Yes.
- So you sort of turn around there there,
everything's okay.
So it doesn't matter that you woke up,
you did it so you could check
and you feel a lot more safe.
- Did you read the Murray Stopes line?
- Yeah.
- So she, Murray Stopes, who was very, very famous
for writing a book called "Married Love."
And she was a campaigner for birth control?
- Yes.
- Yes, big campaigner for that, that kind of thing.
She wrote that the twin bed set
was an invention of the devil, jealous of married bliss.
- I see.
- And she proposed that you shouldn't have twin beds,
instead the wife should have a room with a double bed
and the husband should have a bedroom to himself
for general use, keeping the wife's bedroom
a romantic place.
I think, and then the husband can like have a bed
that's in the shape of a race car.
(laughing)
- The heat man.
- Exactly.
- Yes.
- I would kill for that person
about that right now.
(laughing)
- On an unusual bed sharing story,
this John Adams and Benjamin Franklin shared a bed once.
It's an excerpt from his diary in 1775.
- John Adams of America, and okay.
- In 1776, he described the time he had to share
a tiny bed with Benjamin Franklin,
and instead of sleeping, they had an argument
that whether to keep the windows open or closed,
Franklin eventually won the argument
when Adams got too tired and fell asleep.
- Nice.
- Who really wins?
Because Adams is falling asleep first.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah, sure.
- And also, Adams became president of Franklin,
never did.
- Yeah, double win.
- Double win for Adams, you two Franklin.
(laughing)
- Nice.
- I mentioned before that snoring's a problem.
There's been a new study that gives you a way out
of snoring, and that is, before you go to bed,
you have to blow on a cunt shell.
(laughing)
- Oh, no way.
- You might have seen the study before
that if you blow on did reduce, that's supposed to help
because it helps your breathing.
You have to do circular breathings.
Well, apparently cunt shells are even better,
because if you learn properly how to blow a cunt shell,
you have to do very deep breathing.
You have to do very strong exhalations,
and also the spiral shape of the shell
gives a unique type of blow.
That means you won't snore.
- No way.
- I've got it.
- I've got it, I've got it.
- Oh my gosh.
- Yeah, no, I've got a big blowable, it makes an incredible note when you blow it.
- It's really good you get it from. - Long way where it was.
Yeah, it was an island a holiday and I think someone like the Caribbean was many years ago.
But it makes a great noise. - Was it not when your school crashed on that desert island?
- I'd rather not talk about that weekend.
- If you were the only survivor, how weak were the race?
- I was king of that island, Joel.
Wow, wearing my possum skull armor.
Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is Andy.
My fact is, it's eight degrees warmer inside a daffodil than outside.
If you're feeling chilly and you're listening to this, there's a daffodil nearby.
Spring is coming. Get it in there.
- You could put most a little pink.
- Are you about to open up when I think you're about to open up?
- No, no, okay.
Because when I saw the list of facts, I saw a daffodil out while I was going for a walk.
And so I put my finger in the daffodil.
And I sent the photo to Dan and he did not reply to the photo.
- I'm sorry, but it was such a ominous thing to see.
- It was uncomfortable when I was sitting next to my wife and mal slipped into my DMs
with a picture of her fingering a daffodil.
- Is it doing some research from the shot?
- Yeah, that's a photo there. Amazing.
- Was it what?
- Yeah, I can't tell.
It was such a cold day that I don't know, like,
because it's up to eight degrees, right?
That requires probably a bit of sunshine.
- You probably also need to keep it in there for a certain amount of time.
And you can't just stand there with your finger in a daffodil.
- The part people will pop over.
But basically, the daffodils are really interesting.
They're not like a normal flower because they've got this trumpet thing,
which most flowers don't have.
And they want to get bees in and pollinating insects in general.
And often, daffos are some of the first flowers of spring.
So it's quite cold still when they're up.
And the cone acts as a wind break.
And the petals are directing sunlight inwards.
And third thing, the stem is turning the trumpet away from cold breezes.
So basically, they're making it a lovely,
as warm as possible environment to lure in any pollinating insects
that are up and about at this time of year.
- I love it. I love it.
- It's like a restaurant with a fireplace.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's very nice.
- So it's very charming.
- So I think there aren't any bees around at this time of year.
Are they really?
- No, probably not.
- I think they'll be pollinated by flies.
- Yes.
- And this is the thing, the flies that are around this time of year,
they tend to be colourblind.
And so that's why the flowers that you see this time of year,
like snow drops and daffodils are white and yellow,
because they stand out against the greens.
- Oh, contrast is the main thing, yeah, yeah.
- And then later in the year, you get more colourful ones.
- It's so good.
- Does the heat in the daffodil sort of warm up the pollen?
So it's like, like a hot meal.
- Is it like, is there any?
- Yeah, I like it.
Yes, I'm going to say yes, it absolutely does.
- Anyone have your daffs out already?
- Yes.
- We're recording this on the 19th of February.
- I've got a couple of my gardeners.
- I do, they started coming up a few days ago, yeah.
- How are they looking?
- They're looking at yellow.
- Yeah, is the head like bent a little bit?
- It is, it's bending down.
- Oh, dear.
Because according to English folklore,
that means you're going to die this year.
- Oh, damn.
- Oh, man.
- No, no, that is a pickle.
(laughing)
- Beautiful flowers or death.
- Oh, that's very funny.
- If you dream of them, any maiden who dreams of daffodils
is warned not to go into a wood with her lover.
- Right.
- And if you see the first daffodil of the year
out of all your friends and stuff,
it means you'll have more gold than silver
for the rest of the year.
Though silver's doing quite well, isn't it?
- Yeah, both are overpriced at the moment.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I'm just saying if you're about Bitcoin.
(laughing)
- But even more gold in silver doesn't necessarily mean
like more money.
If you had a million silver coins and two gold coins,
you still have more wealth or more.
- Well, also they're both good things.
It's like a reverse pickle.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- And the daffodil bending over though.
- Yeah.
- That's quite sort of daffodilish to do, I would say.
I would say it's a classic daffodil move.
In fact, the name daffodil, when it goes back to Narcissus,
which is what the family it's from, is it?
- Yeah.
- That was obviously because when Narcissus was looking down
into the water, he couldn't stop staring at his reflection
in the mythology and they say that daffodils do the same.
They look down at the water and looking at themselves.
- But do you know that Narcissus is actually Narcissus poeticus?
It seems, which is a different, it's not the daffodil that you know.
It's a related daffodil, which is white.
And so the, like, that's the one that Linnaeus called the Narcissus
because he based it on that bit of mythology.
- Oh.
- And one of them.
- And one of them is just a related flower.
- We just have a related flower.
- That's so interesting.
- This is the really weird thing.
There are 36 different species of daffodil, right?
But they became very popular for breeding and crossbreeding
and making your own variety.
The different to species is varieties, right?
So there are 36 species of daff,
but there are 27,000 varieties.
- Yes. - It's crazy.
- And there's that lovely.
- And loads of them are not attractive to insects.
- Right.
- Because they've been bred by plant breeders for their looks.
They've not been breeding them for their, you know,
their pollen qualities or anything,
or their attractiveness to insects.
So they've taken over the process.
So that selection process has meant that lots of daffodils
that you get these days are not actually especially.
- So humans have to go in and propagate them, do they?
- Yeah, yeah.
If you look carefully, if you have a garden
or some daffodil garden, just keep an eye out
'cause you'll often find a creepy old man.
- With a finger in a daffodil.
- That's what I have.
(laughing)
- I'll send the photo to all of you guys.
- But there's lots of, if you go online,
there's lots of missing daffodils in the UK now
of these crossbreeds that they're really hoping
are still out there.
So you can find a list of people saying,
if you live in this area.
So for example, Lewis in the UK, in Sussex,
there is a daffodil that's known as the Sussex bonfire.
So they have a big bonfire of night celebration there
and a local...
- It's so many did he in charge.
(laughing)
- Yeah, there's a local plant-reader
called Noel Burr, who created this thing.
And it hasn't been seen for the last 20 years,
but they think it must still be in someone's garden.
They just haven't identified it.
So they sort of say, please look around, see if you can find this.
- But they look so similar, it's like a Weasewolly.
'Cause it's like, do they look like a ordinary daffodil?
- I think they do have different horses.
- Yeah, yeah.
There's the Mrs. Auro Backhouse daffodil as well
that's missing, they're desperately hoping to find.
The Mrs. William Copeland daffodil.
There's all these amazing little crossbreeds
that become famous.
- There's hope that you show them daffodil hunters.
- Yes.
- I feel like going around looking
for interesting daffodils.
- Yes, that's good.
- Like, you know, what's his name?
Bob Martimer, like his show where he just fishes.
And, you know, people will love it
because it's like nice and relaxing.
You see lots of countryside,
and you also get a great comedian.
- Yeah.
- I think that's a really good thing.
- Just me crawling through people's gardens.
(laughing)
- Just looking for a rare daffodil.
- But I'm doing it with rummage, so I love it, yeah.
- Have you guys heard of Peter Bar, the daffodil king?
- No.
- So, daffodils originally came from Spain and Portugal,
and then they were brought here by the Romans.
And that means that in Spain and Portugal,
you have lots of different varieties of daffodils,
and in order to make the new ones,
you need to get some of the old ones and then cross them.
So he rode through Spain and Portugal,
sleeping under rocks with only a single blanket for comfort.
And was once mistaken for a famous bandit by police
as he went around looking for daffodils.
- Oh.
- And he made thousands and thousands of these.
- It sounds like something someone seems to say
that they're tough.
Like, I just sleep on a rock, see who they are.
- And let's see.
- And let's see who they are.
(all laughing)
- That looks like they're from the menosphere.
- My wife has her own bed, and of course I just sleep
on the rocks.
(all laughing)
- I read a newspaper clipping about this guy,
Peter Bar, the daffodil king.
And the clipping said that the only other man
close to claiming the title was Dorian Smith,
but that gentleman is too content with his ownership
of the Cili Isles to enter in a vain rivalry.
- He owned the Cili Isles.
- These are the little islands off the coast of Cornwall,
is it, they're really, yeah, yeah.
- Cornwall is king of daffodils.
- Is it?
- Yeah.
- That's the biggest producer of daffodils in the world.
- Well, Britain is the biggest country.
It's like, this is where world leaders in daff production.
- Yes.
- It's not nothing.
(all laughing)
- It's not anything, 30, 30 million tons of bulbs.
- Can I see a million tons of bulbs?
- Yeah, yeah.
- It doesn't sound plausible.
- That could be a number that's over 100 years.
I'm not sure if that's an annual produce,
but-- - Oh, right.
- No, of course it is.
(all laughing)
- Interesting.
- Yeah, you're the biggest--
- And as well, I just cut flowers,
people buy them 'cause they look nice.
- Yeah, exactly, but-- - It's awesome.
- We have mentioned this before,
but I have forgot it.
They're very poisonous.
- I should have known-- - They get like cats or dogs
and things can't eat it.
- Well, and humans.
- And humans, oh yes.
- Oh, okay.
(all laughing)
- Which it's my way.
- I'll call up brunch.
(all laughing)
- Well, no, but this is a problem,
'cause often when you go into a local supermarket,
the flowers will be positioned right next to the fruit
and veg, right?
And there's been people saying you've got to stop leaving
the daffodils near the Chinese vegetables,
near the onions, because they can be mistaken for them.
And people have been hospitalized quite a few times.
- If you have a daffodil,
like-- - Me and that wake the mistaken for that.
- So they're often sold, we're not open yet, right?
- Yeah, right.
- So they look a little bit like spring onions,
and there are also some other like spring greens
that you get in China that look quite a lot like them.
- Right.
- As written and article by John Robertson,
who works at the Poison Garden in Annock.
- Oh, yeah. - To know that.
- It's like a garden with all poisonous plants in it.
And he's found lots of examples of people
being poisoned by daffodils.
He said there was some parents who were not very well,
and they had a couple of children
who were just old enough to make a stew.
- No. - And they went and picked out
what they thought were onions and put them in
and they were daffodil bulbs.
- What is the right age to make a stew?
(all laughing)
- It's a really good question, is that?
- No one of you have to get your license in the UK.
- I don't know if that's a thing in your ear.
- On bees and heat, a study from North Carolina State University
found that bumblebees carrying pollen,
their bodies heat up depending on how much pollen they have.
It's a workout.
So the weight of the pollen that they're carrying around
makes their bodies warmer.
And so they're afraid that global warming,
the workout of carrying pollen will be too much for them.
- Oh no. - And they'll overheat.
- I know. - It's true.
- You know what happens if, sorry to interrupt,
but you know what happens if a bee overheats.
We've mentioned this on our show before,
it ejaculates itself to death.
- That's really, yeah.
- Really, it just can't stop, it's just.
- It can't stop, yeah.
I can't remember the exact details,
but I remember that sentence very clearly.
- Yeah, yeah. - It's a reason.
- Wow. - Stick to the mind.
Just on the thing that Mel said,
they are now flowering two or three weeks earlier
than in the past.
This is a climatey thing.
This is a while getting warmer things.
So, if Wordsworth went for his famous walk with his sister
today, there might be nothing there at all.
'Cause all they do have already flowered
a couple of weeks ago, he'd have had to
have a ride about something else.
- Right.
- It doesn't seem like the biggest problem
when it's going-- - The reclining door's open.
- Yeah, this is not the biggest effect
of climate change that you can think of,
but it is bad, you know.
- But that is the thing about it is he says,
I wandered lonely as a cloud,
but he wasn't lonely.
He was with his sister the whole time.
- But if he'd said I wandered out there
with my sister, what's the rhyme?
Blister, I suppose, I've got a blister.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I mean, I've spent a few days in here.
I don't think the clouds are there lonely.
There's quite a few hanging out together.
- That's yesterday.
(all laughing)
- That's a thick mask across the countryside.
Yeah, you're right.
(all laughing)
- So, maybe he went in an ironic way.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that you may be able
to cure chronically blocked noses
with a snot transplant.
(all laughing)
- Lovely.
- It's future guys.
- Yeah.
- Incredible.
- It does sound good.
- Yeah.
- We do that, I thought.
- Yeah, so I'm here, I'll be.
- Yeah, well, I mean, I don't know if you suffer
from this kind of thing I do.
Definitely, chronic rhinocytus.
In fact, I had surgery for it a few years ago,
and that was kind of the best way to deal with it.
And it kind of still is.
I read about a new study in new scientists this week,
and they've come up with this idea
of basically siphoning snot out of someone
and shoving it right up there.
It's as simple as that, really.
- But surely the people that don't have blocked noses
don't have a lot of snot to offer.
So they could probably only be a donor for one person.
(all laughing)
- There's a way to clear.
- Yeah, who you mean, well.
- Basically everyone has some kind of microbiome
in their sinuses, and what you're trying to do
is get those bacteria and viruses out of a healthy person's nose
and put them into an unhealthy person's nose.
- It's really cool.
- I think it just sounds like a great idea.
So it was one of the pioneers of it.
A scientist called Amy Molls.
- Yes, Amy Molls from Vancouver,
and another guy called Anders Mortensen from Helsingburg.
- Yes, and so she was inspired by fecal transplants.
Which we've talked about before as being very useful.
- You don't want to get those two mixed up.
- Absolutely not.
(all laughing)
- You've just put snot up this person's bum.
- Wait a minute, that means.
(all laughing)
- So yeah, it gets referred to as a sinus probiotic.
'Cause you've got, you know, this,
you're fighting snot with snot basically.
'Cause this thing, chronic sinus condition
or chronic rhino sinusitis, it sounds awful.
- It's a shocker.
- So you've had it.
- I still kind of have it,
but the surgery helped quite a lot.
- You've mentioned your sinuses in the past,
but I've always thought, yeah, I've got a cold too.
And I'm so sorry James.
- Like basically, I got often can't breathe.
- Yes, yes, yes.
- Just kind of vital for living.
- Absolutely, that's probably one.
But it gets dismissed by lots of doctors as a minor inconvenience,
but people living with it,
which might be up to 10% I read approaching this number.
Your face hurts, you're always bunged up,
you lose your sense of smell, headaches, bad breath.
- Try again on an aeroplane.
- Oh yeah, of course.
- Wow.
- Soon as you, you know, when your ears sort of,
when your ears pop, when that happens for you,
I just get this incredible pain and my sinuses.
- I've had that, if you've got enough light
and you've got a bit of a cold,
that can happen, god, it'll just suddenly.
- Oh, and that, well, allegedly,
people with it seem to be 77% likely to have depression
than those without.
'Cause it's just sort of chronically debilitating.
- Do you think there's a research team as a game?
You guys guess what?
The name of the research team trying to work out,
they're using like AI to work out the cause of,
this rhinocytus in people.
- Okay.
- What is the name of this research team?
- The sort of game.
- Like the acronym, you mean?
- It's not an acronym, it's just like a fun bit of wordplay.
And it's like, when you read it, you go, of course.
- Okay, blow, who knows how to fix this?
- I mean, you've got the right pun.
It turns out, well, in terms of it is, it's got nose in it,
but it's medical.
And it's about figuring out.
- Do you know Tom?
- No, it's so much simpler than that.
It's literally just a word in the medical field
that you would use a lot, a doctor.
What does a doctor do to you?
- Diet nose.
- Yes!
(audience cheering)
- Lovely.
- Yeah, yeah, too good, too good.
- That's pretty good.
- Because Dan, you talked about acronyms.
There is the way to measure,
whether you have chronic sinusitis,
is the cyanone nasal outcome test or snot.
- Beautiful, lovely.
- And they basically give you 22 things.
Do you need to blow your nose?
Do you sneeze a lot?
Do you have a running nose and you put how often?
Does it happen all the time or does it happen never?
- What's interesting is how much mucous
and snot we produce per day?
- A bucket.
- It's buckets, it's 1.5 liters per day
is what the body produces.
- Okay, that's like a large bottle of Coca-Cola, isn't it?
- Yeah, and it's used for various different things.
I didn't realize it was used for.
It lubricates poo, so then it makes it easier to exit our body.
- Yeah, you're saying it with a slightly disgusted look
on your face, but you try going without.
You'll be crying out for that mucous to come back.
- I know.
- I don't know how I try to do that.
- You try going down.
(laughing)
- I don't know what things were of the like,
"It's a mucous to you, how dare you."
I don't know how bad it got for you
on the Lord of the Flies island,
but we keep our poo's lubricated.
- But that's the thing is that people obviously
would find the idea of eating snot disgusting,
but we are swallowing our snot all the time.
Most of those liters, we're just swallowing it.
- Yeah, 'cause it traps, you know, like,
bacteria or tiny hairs or whatever
that are all landing in your body,
and it can be in the lining to your lungs and things like that.
Then you bring that up, you know,
that sort of trap gets full of the pollutants,
you bring it up, you swallow it out it goes.
- Easy.
- One interesting thing about picking your nose and eating it
is that according to some scientists,
they think that might be a good thing
because the pathogens that get stuck in your nose
are the weaker ones because they haven't managed
to get all the way up, so if you take those ones out
and eat them, then that's like a vaccine.
- Like a vaccine, exactly, I should say,
not all scientists.
- Right, okay, no that's good to know.
Before this podcast, we're calling actually Mel,
sent me a photo of her with her finger jammed up,
and I was like, "I didn't understand it from now."
- Yeah.
- It's so much warmer out of there.
(laughing)
- You can get terrible sinusitis if you're a tortoise.
There was a tortoise.
- It's already doing these tortoises, isn't it?
(laughing)
- There's a tortoise in Bristol Zoo in 2014,
called Helen, who had a terrible nasal infection,
and they gave them a cross van to biotics
and lots of sinus rinses and stuff.
And the reason is that tortoises can't cough,
and so if you get the infection,
they can't get it out of their body.
But the reason I mainly bring it up
is that this tortoise, called Helen,
has a underfloor heated sand pit.
- No way.
- And it's been a bizarre point on this show, Mel,
that Andy hasn't got underfloor heating in his house.
- Oh my gosh.
- That makes me sound like an insane diva.
(laughing)
I'm just saying that Romans had it 2,000 years ago.
Why don't we all have it?
- It's not just me.
- It's like, why does Helen have it?
- You don't want to know, right now.
(laughing)
- And again, that genuinely want the hell.
There are humans out there who could do with underfloor heating.
(laughing)
- Some of them around this table.
- Wow.
- Well, congratulations, Helen.
I'll be very happy.
- I hope your sign-in sign doesn't never get to be wrong.
(laughing)
- Cold medicine in the UK is substantially worse
than it used to be.
- It's not right.
- Yeah.
- Is this pseudo-effort drain or no?
This is not to do with the actual--
- Certainly is.
- Oh, it is, right.
Okay, is it because they outlawed pseudo-effort drain
in New Zealand for a bit and they've brought it back?
- Who did that?
- Because it's very easy to turn that cold medication
into drugs.
- Yes.
- It is.
- A key ingredient of crystal meth
- Yeah.
- Is pseudo-effort drain.
And pseudo-effort drain is where pseudo-fed
gets its name from.
- Okay.
- Do you hear it?
- Yeah, pseudo-effort drain.
- And it was used with it, right?
- It was used with it's in the name.
It was used for decades.
And in 2008, I'm replaced with something
much less effective, called phenelephrine.
And I mean, it's good news if you don't like crystal meth
being a big part of your community.
- Bad news, if you have chronic sinusitis.
- Yeah.
- Can't you get it?
- Like.
- Can I get it under the cancer somewhere?
- I think there are very specific--
- The problem is I can't get my head under the cancer
because it all goes into my eyes.
(laughing)
- There are very specific circumstances,
I think under which a doctor will give it to you,
but it's not just ladled out now
because it's too easy to use it to make crystal meth.
- I've written a new script called "Bloing Bed"
and I think it's going to be really exciting.
I'm really excited, very nice.
- Yes.
- A doctor, German doctor called Wilhelm Fleiss
was a friend of Freud.
And he thought that your nose got more swollen once a month
and it kind of had its own menstrual cycle.
- Oh.
- And he thought that the swelling of the nose
caused some kind of like sexual disorders.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- That's way far to thought.
- Pritch.
- Okay.
And now I sit back and allow Dan to explain
what the hell he was thinking with that insurrection.
- Well, I just know that--
- Take the tempo out, you know,
before you talk to his Dan.
(laughing)
- I've always thought that the nose was very similar
to a vagina.
- You've always thought that.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- As a young boy.
- As a young boy, I just always thought,
no, because we share a very similar week.
My nose and vagina share very similar tissues
on the inside, right?
- They have erectile tissues.
- Yeah.
- Exactly.
- And it is true that if you get excited down there,
it can give you a block nose.
Sometimes that's called honeymoon rhinitis.
And it's because the blood rushes
to the erectile tissue in both places.
- Whoa.
- But this guy, Wilhelm Fleiss,
he thought that the best way to deal with it
is to take a cane.
- Wow.
- And he thought that if you took a cane,
then it would stop your nose from going through
this menstrual cycle and that it would stop
your sexual disorders.
And surprise, surprise, Sigmund Freud, absolutely agreed.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- And was the one who would prescribe him this cocaine
so that his patients would feel better.
- Oh, give it a go.
(laughing)
- It was a big cold and flu remedy, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- Cocaine was just a standard thing.
Again, cocaine, crystal meth, all these drugs,
before we really understood.
- And heroin was good for cuffs, wasn't it?
- I was trying to think of a pun that whole time
and the only thing I could think of,
you've got a stiffie and a stuffy.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- It's all like a gear, it's all like a gear.
- Can I tell you one more weird transplant?
- Yes, please.
- That's not transplants.
So there is a belief among some doctors
that we might within the next 10 years
get the first ever head transplant.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- It's pretty interesting.
So this is a surgeon called Bruce Matthew,
who's a former NHS Neurosurgeon.
He's also qualified.
And basically, it's really a body transplant, actually.
- Yeah.
- Because it's the same.
- Yeah, it's the same.
- It's taking--
- Yeah, true.
The head is the person.
- The head is the person.
No, it's not the same person.
Because if they say we're giving you a head transplant,
that means they're going to take off your head
and put someone else's head on.
But what happens to your head?
- Your head, but the key thing apparently
is that your head and your spinal column
have to be kept together.
There's no way of just taking off a head
and putting it on another body.
It has to be head and spinal column, okay?
- Okay.
- And then I found myself looking into
what other transplants we can do.
So shoulder replacement surgery, absolutely handy.
That's fine.
Knee surgery, again, very calm by now, knee replacement.
But we don't seem, as far as I know, to do toe transplants.
- Toes onto your fingers, I've seen that.
- Toe becomes thumb.
That is the gold standard for letting you pinch things again.
- Okay.
- But I don't think they ever say we're going to take a toll.
- Is it because you can manage without one of your toes?
- I have a broken toe and the doctors go,
we don't really, we're not going to put your toe in a car.
So I just have a toe that just doesn't bend.
- Oh, okay.
- You can't live your life without working kidneys, right?
- Yeah.
- But if you lose one of your toes, it's not great
or you can live your life.
- But if you don't want to get many people to sign up
to donating their body, if they find out,
they're just donating their toes.
- I think your toe could save someone's awkward conversation
at the pool.
- Yeah, yeah.
It's not top of the list of things to solve, for sure.
- That's the absolute.
- Yeah, that's true.
- Wait, so okay, so we're doing heads, shoulders.
- Yeah.
- Is that what's going on here?
- Oh my god, I can't believe that.
- No, I knew the second you said it.
I could see in your face.
You didn't just mention toes for no reason.
There's no waste with Andy, he's not.
- Wow.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found online.
I'm on @tribaland on Instagram, James.
- Instagram is no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy, Andrew Hunter M and Mel.
- @melonybracewell.
- Nice, and you are in the UK right now.
- In the UK, touring.
- Touring around, so come and see my shirt, if you'd like.
- Yeah, all the dates are on your Instagram, right?
So you can, it's a pin of post.
- Yes, you can check it out.
And also, if you can't come, I'll be releasing it
as a special sometime during the year, so.
- Amazing.
- Yeah, you can check it on it.
- Great, okay, cool.
Well, also, if you want to get to us as a group,
podcast at qi.com is the place to send your emails.
If you've got any amazing facts that you want to let us know
about, we do our show, Little Fish, where we gather together
all the best of those facts, and we read them out.
That's every Monday, or if you want to give us some feedback
about things that we've talked about in main episodes
that you think we need to know about, we have another show,
which is part of our Secret Members Club Club Fish,
which you can get by going to patreon.com/nosuchthingasafish.
And Andy goes through all those emails.
He picks the best of them out, and we do that show,
drop us a line, where we discuss them all.
So check that out.
Otherwise, why not just come back next week,
'cause we're gonna have another episode,
thanks as ever, to Lee and Lee, and Ethan Ruperelia,
as well as the larger Fish Buster team here
at the Officers in Hobern, and we'll see you next week.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)