(whimsical music)
(speaking in foreign language)
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing as a Fish" a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI Offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Anna Tishinsky and I'm joined today
by Ann Miller, James Harkin and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we've gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order here, they are starting with Ann.
- My fact is that the alarm clock
on the mere space station made the same noise
as their emergency alarm.
- That'll wait you up, wouldn't it?
- It would wake you up with a start.
This is Helen Sherman, he was the first Britain space.
He spent eight days up there in 1991
and she was interviewed recently and said, quote,
you'd wake up unsure if it was time to get up
or if you were leaking oxygen.
It got us out of our sleeping bags pretty quick.
- And was that why they did it, do we know?
Or was it just like they didn't have any other sounds on file?
- I like to think we just thought we've got one alarm.
That'll work. - That'll do.
It does sound like a really effective way
of getting out of bed, I mean.
- Terrifying. - Smart.
- Yeah.
- Wake up.
Fearing for your life.
- That's pretty much how I feel waking up every morning.
Did you know that her mission, the Juno mission,
was actually a commercial mission
and while she was up there,
she had to do an advert for Interflora.
- No. - Did she?
- Was it because Interflora like Interstellar,
was that the reasoning?
- You should work an advertising Andy.
I'm not sure, actually.
- Wake the flower company, Interflora.
- Yeah, they actually weren't Interstellar though,
where they were probably closer to our stellar
than they were on Earth.
- For some other time. - They were interplanetary.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- For whoever you're Inter, get them.
(laughing)
- Nice footage. - You should not work
in advertising.
(laughing)
- Meer sounds incredibly shonky.
- So there was a thing about how the solar panels were damaged.
That was how, I find it really all the space stations
are solar powered, I suppose it's obvious.
But often the lights would go out
and they'd just have to wait in the dark
until they came back on, really.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Yeah, it was really dodgy, wasn't it?
They had a few very near, near disaster incidents.
It's caught fire in the '90s in 1997 of fire started
and they tried to extinguish it with a wet towel at first,
I think, which made it worse.
It just made everything very smoky.
So they all had to put their respiratory masks on
at which point they realized
that half the respiratory mask didn't work.
And so while they weren't working
and they were all suffocating,
they tried to pull the fire extinguishers off the wall.
And I think seven out of the 10 fire extinguishers
were actually stuck to the wall
so they couldn't be removed to put the fire out.
- How did they get it out?
- They got the other three fire extinguishers
and used those instead and they were fine.
But it sounds entertaining, so it's terrifying.
- Do you think they called that a mere miss?
- Probably not. - I hope they did.
So the mere space station, when it was decommissioned,
it just had to be sent back into the atmosphere
to shatter over the Pacific.
And it looks really beautiful.
So I really loved that idea.
And when the International Space Station
is decommissioned, it's deobased.
That'll do the same thing, I think.
So it just gets brought back into a sorbit
and then you make sure that it gets brought back
at a place where it's not gonna rain down
over a well populated area.
And it looks like a whole,
it looks like a meteor shower or something, doesn't it?
Is that where they all land in Point Nemo, Andy?
- Yes.
- So Point Nemo is the area of the ocean
that's furthest away from any land.
And is it full of, I remember you told me this,
is it full of space ships?
- It's a full of old spacecraft.
That's where they try and get them all to land
or they sort of, they work it out.
- There's those remote spots.
- Exactly, yeah, so there's the least transfer of the life,
unless you're on a fishing expedition to Point Nemo.
- To get away from it all.
- Fun finding Nemo themed expedition in the way.
- Oh, it's the idea for it.
- Yeah, here's a cool thing I found out.
Once you get back, so in space, basically,
you're a bit like a superhuman.
Chris Hadfield said, you know,
you can move a massive fridge or whatever
with the tips of his fingers.
I don't know why he was moving a fridge out on the ISS.
But he said that when you get back,
obviously you're much weaker 'cause your muscles
atrophy in space, but the other thing he said
is that you can feel the weight of your lips
and your tongue.
And you have to get used to speaking
with a tongue that weighs something.
- That's great.
Now I can feel the weight of my tongue.
- I was saying that in space, he had sort of automatically
learned how to speak with a weightless tongue
'cause you're all weightless,
so you don't really realize at the time.
And when you return, it's a little bit harder.
- That's amazing.
Is it also hard then to keep your eyes open?
And then when you come back to earth from outer space,
surely you feel the weight of gravity.
- When Helen Sharman came back,
she said that she kind of felt a bit weird
and that her brain felt heavy.
- Wow.
- Maybe she just got way cleverer in space.
- Way more stuff.
- Is that what happens that your brain gets heavier,
the cleverer you are?
- Yes.
- Everyone knows you get smarter in space,
and your brain gets heavier when you get cleverer.
- It's like how a full kindle with a tiny, tiny point
of a gram more than an empty kindle.
- Oh yeah.
- So our brains are like.
- Hang on, surely if you learn something
and new connections are made in your brain, yeah.
They weigh something though, don't they?
Those cells, I mean, doesn't that mean
that a really clever brain will weigh a tiny bit more,
the more with no information?
- That's why they used to try and like examine
like Einstein's brain and stuff, didn't they?
'Cause they thought they have like a secret
of big brains or small brains.
- I don't think anyone knows.
- I think this is a conversation for the neuroscientist
podcast, rather than a bunch of idiots
who don't know anything about neuroscience.
- I can tell you a historical thing about this.
I think it was golden, but it was certainly someone
like that from their Victorian age
who was kind of believed in eugenics or something.
And he thought the people with bigger heads
must have bigger brains and must be smarter,
but he needed to work out how to weigh people's brains
and how to find the size of their heads.
And so what he would do is he'd go into a pub
and find two people with kind of big heads
and then start an argument between them
and say, "This guy says your head's small."
And he can't tell you the angle.
This guy says, "Your head's small."
And he goes, "But don't worry, I'll measure your heads."
And that'll tell you who's the best.
And then he got his measurements that way.
- Was he, and he just had a lot of refusals
going up and politely asking people,
so we had to come up with a way around it.
- I didn't measure my head.
- I'd just say yes though, if someone asked me
if they wanted to measure my head.
- I'd be well offered.
- Yeah, if anyone wants my head measured.
- If you ever see other in the streets.
- Variant aim measure.
- Happy to help.
- Can we talk about alarm clocks?
- Yeah. - alarm clocks.
- So the first alarm clock only went off
at four in the morning that I had found.
- Yes, that's fantastic.
- After it was invented, it took another 60 years
before the first alarm clock was invented,
which you could not.
- Why not?
- People want to get up at four a year.
- It was just one guy, he called Levi Hutchins.
He was from New Hampshire and he started work
soon after four AM, so that was the time he got up.
So he just set it, it was totally adaptable.
And so the first alarm clock that you could adjust
was patented in France in 1847, but he was 1787.
- I have a type of alarm clock.
This is from a designer called Randolpho
and it's called The Good Morning Underwear.
And it's a pair of pants that vibrates
to wake you up in the morning.
- Wow. - Okay.
- This is a designer who kind of likes
to do electronic clothing or wearable tech,
especially underwear.
And he said, "I finally wanted to make a garment
that my girlfriend would actually want to wear."
While it might be hard to believe,
when I made the clap off bra, it was not really for her.
- The clap off bra.
- Yeah, so what you do is you clap
and then your girlfriend or wife's bra falls off.
- That's fantastic.
- Well, if you went to a comedy club.
- Yeah. - Just have to hope everyone is really bad.
- I read about two simple alarm clocks,
one of which I would say is higher risks than the other.
One is that you can build, if you build your house,
so when you have your bedroom,
so you're the window where the sun comes in,
then that actually you'll wake up in the morning,
which is a lovely idea waking up to the sunrise.
The other idea is that you just drink loads of water
before you go to sleep and your body will wake you up.
- I do that.
- And it works 80% of the time.
(laughing)
- But supposedly it's a Native American thing, isn't it?
And then it still got practiced even into the 20th century.
- What was the drinking thing?
- Yeah.
- Oh my gosh, I am so connected to my fellow Native Americans.
They used to drink that.
- They used to drink water, not Pinot Grigio.
(laughing)
- I read that alarm clocks is one of the most common things
displaced by smart phones.
- Yeah, that makes a lot of sense.
I've still got three alarm clocks actually,
so I'm keeping the industry going.
- But how do you?
Are they all set at different times?
- Two of them have broken.
- Oh, okay, why do you still keep them?
- 'Cause I have this fantasy that I'm going to go
into the back of one and fix it one day.
- That's an incredible fantasy.
(laughing)
- Your dreams must be amazing.
- Pretty wild inside of my head.
(laughing)
Clock fixing and stamp collecting.
All night long, my dreams.
- So just a couple more weird alarm clocks.
These are off Kickstarter.
These are current Kickstarter alarm clocks.
One of them is, as soon as you wake up,
it gives you your estimated life expectancy
and your financial information.
And it's supposed to be the most depressing alarm clock
of all time.
- Is that worse than the emergency alarm going off?
- I think it is 'cause it says you're gonna die in 20 years
and you've got no money.
- Mom, this is early.
If you're a billionaire child,
then that's what you do.
- You wake up like I'm winning.
- Yeah.
- Come on, bring on the tape.
What's the idea that it will force you together
because you need to make more money
and spend as much time awake as possible before death?
- I think it's a bit like a memento-mari
which is kind of it just reminds you
that you will die one day and it helps you grasp life.
- No, not remotely.
- Okay, fine.
- I try to cheat it by killing myself immediately
and do like, "Ah, you're wrong."
(laughing)
- Well, you'll hope you the winner there.
- Just immediately spend the load of money
on Amazon to kill yourself.
(laughing)
- In your face, Mr. Alarm.
- What was it, was there another one James?
- Here's another one, the money shredding alarm clock.
(laughing)
He, this is a guy who combined a clock kit
with a USB paper shredder
and basically put a load of money in there
and then the alarm goes off
and the slower it takes you to wake up
and turn the alarm off,
the more of your money gets shredded.
- That is fantastic.
- A tip, hot tip for people out there.
Put your partner's money in it.
(laughing)
- Steve, for as long as you like.
- There's somebody who doesn't have a joint bank account.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, time for our second fact
and that is from James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that
the Bosnian National Anthem
is almost identical in melody
to the theme for the movie
National Lampoon's Animal House.
(laughing)
- Sounds awesome.
- Right.
- Who came first?
- National Lampoon came first.
- Basically Bosnian is quite a new country
and when it became a country,
they needed a national anthem
and they found a guy to write it
and we think that perhaps he might have been somehow
- So unconsciously.
- So unconsciously perhaps influenced by this movie.
- Because if you were going to pick a movie
to nick the theme tune of it,
probably wouldn't be National Lampoon's Animal House.
- That's true, although if you Googled National Anthem
and spelt it slightly wrong
and it said, did you mean National Lampoon?
(laughing)
- National Lampoon, this will do.
- Well, the other thing is that
the National Anthem of Bosnia has no official lyrics.
So you really are just listening to the theme tune.
(laughing)
- And Google it, go on to YouTube and listen to them
because they are remarkably similar.
And this fact actually comes from a book
that I read a fantastic book called
"Republic or Death" by a guy called Alex Marshall
and it's full of kind of QI facts about National Anthem.
So I absolutely love it.
I've found so much stuff in there.
- So he, Alex Marshall is quite firmly sympathetic
towards the guy who wrote this isn't here,
do Sancestic.
- That's right.
- And says it implies that it really was a subconscious
thing and I think this guy might have been screwed out
of quite a bit of money from the Bosnian government now
who are refusing to pay him
because they didn't like the lyrics that he wrote eventually.
- Yeah, the lyrics have been written
and they've been approved by one body
but they still haven't been approved by a council of ministers.
So at the moment there are no lyrics.
- The Spanish one hasn't got any words either, hasn't.
- Oh, is it not?
- I don't know.
- They had a competition to give words for it
but no one really liked them so they took them out.
- Oh really?
- They're amazing.
Yes, South Sudan, obviously.
It's still the world's newest country, isn't it?
- Yeah, it must be.
- They had an X-factor style competition for theirs
with literally had a row of judges
and you had to present it.
And I did not know that South Sudan
was nearly called the Nile Republic.
- What's it?
- It was one of the names they considered, yeah.
- So there's a story attested to in the 19th century
which is that the Sultan of Malaysia visited Queen Victoria
was invited to visit Queen Victoria in 1888 I think
and they didn't have a national anthem at the time,
the Malaysians.
But when the Sultan got to meet Queen Victoria,
her aide said, oh by the way,
when we're formally welcoming you,
we want to be able to sing and play on national anthem.
So what is it?
And the aide was too embarrassed to say we don't have one.
And so he just thought of the first unique think of
which was some local tune from the say shells
that he'd once heard, which was a French origin I think
and hummed that.
And to this day, that is the Malaysian national anthem.
- Why?
- No way.
- Didn't they change the Malaysian anthem
when they came independent?
Because Benjamin Britain wrote one for them in 1957.
- Oh, did he?
- But he had, he'd only been in the country for a few hours.
He didn't particularly have the best time.
- The lyrics are all about the airport.
- He was supposed to be here.
- They have great Tobleros and lovely duty free.
- He was a bit pricey.
Now he's supposed to go and visit a rubber plantation,
but instead spent the whole trip terrified,
he's going to be attacked under attack.
And he said, quote, we had a taste of what it's like
to live always armed in a fear of one's life.
And at one point, they were stuck in a thunderstorm,
and spent the entire hour terrified
that someone was going to find them.
- And did all these quotes make it
into the lyrics he wrote for the national anthem?
- They didn't go with his national anthem.
(laughing)
'Cause they had a huge competition in the '50s,
and they didn't like their entries.
They thought we'll ask Benjamin Britain
to see if he can come up with something.
And instead, they went with a cabaret song, I think.
- Oh, I have a fact about cabaret songs
in national anthems.
- Great.
- So, the Germans, only sing the third verse
of their national anthem.
And that's partly because the first verse begins,
Deutsche Landu Bras, very heavily associated,
with Nazi times, obviously.
So, after the Second World War, West Germany
had no official national anthem,
'cause there was a big program of what was called
"D-Nazification",
where they were trying to restore civil society
as it had been before, 1933.
So, at football matches,
people started singing a carnival song
as their kind of unofficial national anthem,
which was taking the Mickey out of the allied powers,
who were still obviously occupying at the time.
So, that was another carnival song that got used as a...
- Oh, did they actually use it
as a national anthem for a while?
- No, it was always unofficial.
Sometimes they started playing it
and Belgian soldiers who were occupying, heard it,
and they stood up thinking,
"Oh, this is the national anthem, then, that's great."
- Isn't there a verse of "God Save the Queen"
that we don't sing,
because it's got a line about rebellious scots to crush?
- I always sing that one.
- I only sing that one.
- Can I feel very secure to be here?
- God Save the Queen, wasn't that the national anthem
for a lot of countries when it was first written?
- Like, Lichtenstein had the same tune,
but I think they have different words.
- Lichtenstein, it would be amazing
if they had the same words.
- It's already done, we could just change it.
- God Save the Queen, Lichtenstein.
(all laughing)
Apparently, when Lichtenstein played football
against Scotland, they always get the national anthem boot.
- Oh, so my favorite story ever
with Scottish people, if it were matches,
when they went to Italy,
and allegedly, we're singing,
"We're going to deep fry our pizzas."
- Oh, yeah.
- I just think it's...
- So, I think a lot of countries had the English national anthem
before anyone else had a national anthem.
So, I think God Save the King was the first
that came up in 1745 and became our national anthem.
And lots of other countries thought,
"Okay, that sounds like a good idea, national anthems."
But didn't think to write their own.
And so, you know, within a few decades,
the German states, Russia, Denmark,
the kingdom of Hawaii,
they all had the English national anthem
as their national anthem, as in that melody.
And Lichtenstein is the one that still kept it,
couldn't be bothered to ever drop it.
- I read a list of national anthem titles,
and there are some from around the world,
which are unbelievably good, let's hear some.
So, I think the best around the entire world
is Bhutan's The Thunder Dragon Kingdom.
- Yes. - Amazing.
Poland has, Poland is not yet lost
so long as we still live very lively.
Equatorial guineas is let us tread the path
of our immense happiness.
- That's quite nice. - Good luck.
- I like Vanuatu's, which is Yumi, Yumi, Yumi.
(laughing)
- Is it really?
- Yumi, Yumi, Yumi, it's so good in my tummy.
- It's the same verse, isn't it?
- It means we, we, we.
- As in us, us, us.
- Yeah. - Not as in you're in you're in you're in you're in you.
I mean, they have to be insane, wouldn't they?
- The cleanup operation is awful after everyone saw it.
(laughing)
- So, Bikina Faso, their national anthem
is one single night, and these are the opening lights.
This is in translation, obviously.
But, against the humiliating bondage of a thousand years,
repacity came from afar to subjugate them for a hundred years
against the cynical malice in the shape of neo-colonialism
and its petty local servants.
- Wow.
- I prefer Yumi, Yumi, Yumi.
(laughing)
- The English public don't want God save the Queen
to be their national anthem, mostly.
So, at the moment, I think a bill was proposed in Parliament
at the start of this year to have an English national anthem
'cause weird English people get upset
that we have to share our national anthem
with the Scottish and the Welsh.
- They're also not thrilled.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- I'm the Northern Irish.
- And the Northern Irish.
- And the Lichtenstonian.
- And the Lichtenstonians.
Okay, too many people are sharing God save the Queen
and there's not enough to go around.
So, there's a movement to change the English national anthem.
And I think one of the popular choices is obviously land
of Hope and Glory, which I think 55% of the English public
would like, which is a catchy tune,
but which, Elgar, who wrote the tune for it,
didn't like, and he really hated the way
that it was appropriated for kind of jingoistic causes,
and it was sung to get the English troops
riled up in the First World War,
and Elgar already disapproved of that,
and he didn't like the lyrics that were written to it,
which were written by someone else.
So, when you're seeing that feeling patriotic,
you should know that the man who wrote it
was not up for that.
- I think we should ask the internet
what should be our national anthem?
- Don't get us.
Queenie McQueen face will win by a country mile.
- There'd be something like it's raining there now,
something like that.
(laughing)
- Well, the Massey A's, strong candidate
for the best national anthem ever, really, really exciting,
was written by a royalist.
The composer was a massive royalist,
and considering it's so revolutionary,
that's a bit surprising.
- Oh, really? - Yeah.
- He was asked to write it by the mayor of Strasbourg.
- Oh, what's he?
- Can I just say a quick story about plagiarism?
- Yes, please.
- That really entertained me that I'd never read.
It's just about a nature writer,
this seems like a bit of a crowbar,
but I read something written by a nature writer
called Paul Tolme,
and he visited South Dakota in 2005
to write an academic article on Black-footed ferrets.
He noticed a few years later that a bodice ripper
kind of raunchy book by a writer called Cassie Edwards
contained verbatim, his description of Black-footed ferrets.
So he says, she writes raunchy stories about Native Americans
having forbidden relationships with frontiers women.
- Oh, I thought you were going to say with ferrets.
(laughing)
- No, bizarrely enough.
There's just a scene where they have raunchies,
I've said the word raunchy a lot.
There's a scene where they have sex,
and after they have sex,
they start having a chat about ferrets,
and in that chat about ferrets,
there's a really incongruous description,
academic description of ferrets,
and he said, yeah, it was a sudden dialogue
between a hunky American Indian
and a lustful pioneer woman,
which was the height of absurdity.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, on to fact number three, and that is Ande's Facts.
- My fact is that crows can bear a grudge for nine years
and two generations.
- That is fantastic.
- What have you done to these crows Ande's?
- There's a crow I know called Enigo Montoya,
and I killed his father.
(laughing)
Is that a reference to something I don't get?
The Princess Bride.
(laughing)
So, okay, so this is from a book that's just out,
it's called The Genius of Birds,
it's by Jennifer Ackerman,
and it is a fantastic book.
So, basically, crows can remember a face.
Okay, they can remember a load of faces,
and they can teach their offspring
and their friends to dislike you as well.
- Why do they do that, though?
- Basically, a load of scientists put on masks
and then bothered crows.
(laughing)
Basically, and they captured them,
or they used the word abducted in some write-ups of this,
but they just sort of captured them
and then released them, wearing a particular mask.
So, they had a caveman mask for one of these experiments.
And then when they were released,
the birds remembered which kind of face had treated them badly,
or which kind of face had treated them well, fed them.
And then they would dive bomb the threatening masks,
and then they left it for, in some cases, up to nine years,
and the mobbing still happened.
The birds had remembered from years and years previously,
and other birds, which had not hatched at the time
of the original attacks,
were taught to join in this mobbing,
and then when they saw you thereafter,
they would mob you, 'cause they knew.
- Can I ask, why were they wearing masks?
'Cause they didn't want the crows to hate their normal faces.
- I think it was, because they were on the university campus,
and you can't just teach all birds on the campus to hate--
- No, actually, I do want this one.
It's because they were worried that if they didn't have masks,
it'd be something in their facial expressions,
the birds were reacting to it, it was a mask.
It was sort of controlled for each time they did it.
- It's not like there was an old scientist
who once did this experiment,
and then all the birds in the whole world hated him.
- I'd rather have to wear a mask
when I was doing the bird experiment
than have to wear a mask at all other times.
- All other times.
But this is a study, one thing that they did
when they were wearing masks,
'cause I don't think they were real ones or a replica crew.
They carry a, what looked like a dead crow
to sort of taunt the crows,
and then they'd be like, that's a bad person,
they've killed a crow.
They also did it with pigeons.
A pigeons could not care less.
I think that's a dead pigeon.
They didn't look, they didn't do anything.
So, crows and pathetic pigeons, they'll let you go.
- That's fantastic.
- Well, they are very advanced crows, aren't they?
And so, corvids are my favorite type of bird, by a long way,
'cause they're, what?
- Sorry, it's just funny to have a favorite type of bird.
- That has a better than hummingbirds, they're pretty cool.
- You don't bring your hummingbird biases in here.
This is a podcast about crows.
If you wanted a podcast about hummingbirds,
you should have gone elsewhere.
- So, corvids are their family or a genus or?
- Corvids are family, I think.
- So they're like ravens.
- Ravens, crows, jays, magpies, all birds like that.
And they're much better than parrots are at talking,
for instance, they can vocalize them more impressively,
so parrots can copy your words,
but they always speak in that power voice.
And whereas, I can imitate power voices very well,
they can't imitate mine.
- But crows can do all the accents.
- Crows can do all the accents.
- Actually, you know the radio show, Death Riggas.
It's just all crows.
- There's a man who's trained his raven
to chant "Nevermore" from the Edgar Allan Poe poem.
So, he chants it in, 'cause he's so good
at mimicking his own voice in this terrifying man's voice.
- It's so good.
- Yeah. - That would give me nightmares.
- Yeah.
- Did Edgar Allan Poe in life take advantage of the fact
that his surname and the word poem are really similar?
And another Edgar Allan Poe.
(laughing)
He should have done.
I mean, maybe he wouldn't have died penniless
at the edge of about 40,
if he'd only had a bit of commercial mass.
(laughing)
He had a terrible life.
Everyone around him died incredibly young,
and yeah, he was completely blighted.
He made no money from his poems, and yeah.
But if he'd have had commercial expert,
Andrew Hunter Murray with it.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
So, one thing that says it's called mobbing behavior.
Basically, when birds all attack an individual
at the same time.
And the birds mostly do it with birds of prey.
So, small birds will attack big birds.
- Oh yeah.
- But basically, they will defecate or vomit
on birds of prey so much that the bird of prey has to leave,
because they can be quite corrosive.
Obviously, vomit is very acidic.
And the bird of prey will have to leave,
because its feathers might be damaged.
- I think that is very bold.
I wouldn't approach to tiger, for instance,
and vomit on it.
- Hoping that it's fur would be eroded fast enough
before eight.
- It would need me.
- But you might find yourself defecating.
(laughing)
- But if your family were all with you,
you might all go and vomit on the tiger.
(laughing)
- Worst trip to nosely safari path ever.
- But there is a video online of otters mobbing a crocodile.
I mean, it is unbelievably good.
- Wow, really?
- The otters are all advancing on the crocodile,
and it's backing away, scared from them.
I mean, they're not vomiting or--
- But they could be about.
- Maybe.
But occasionally, the crocodile snaps a bit,
but it is losing, basically.
- But the crocodile is aquatic,
if it did get vomit, it would just submerge itself,
and then come out of that.
- I don't think the otters are vomiting, are they?
They're just being aggressive.
They're just being aggressive and advance going on.
And now I'm thinking about it.
I don't think this has happened,
but it's possible someone just reversed
the tape of a crocodile advance.
About to reach a load of otters.
(laughing)
- Crows like to pull tails of cats and animals
to like to tease them, play with them.
- What?
- And I read, so you know how tricky to do,
and you have somebody, you see somebody,
and you tap them on a shoulder,
but you're actually on the other side,
because you've reached round.
Jack does do that to rooks.
So Jack does think up to a rook and pull its tail,
and then the other jack does on the other side,
and we're going to steal every rook was eating.
- No way.
- Yeah, it's like an distraction,
like a two-man con.
So one taps the, and then the other one's like,
"Yes, dinner."
- That's great.
- It's not all that's so clever.
- Yeah.
- You know, when crows hide their foods,
they hide it in the ground,
and they also remember where they hid it,
but also remember how long that food has
before it goes bad.
So they would bother going back to food that's gone bad.
- No. - Yeah.
- And also similar to the Ravens,
they, if crows have crows,
they're friends with her around their five.
If a crew who they don't like isn't the area,
they'll go back and then hide it somewhere else later.
- Wow. - Because they didn't even observe.
- Yeah, well, hummingbirds can fly backwards, so.
(laughing)
- James, will you drop this insane hummingbird
fixation of yours?
(laughing)
- I read an article on Atlas Obscura
talking about crow brains.
It was a bit weird.
They asked, "Can they fall in love?"
And the scientist said, "We don't and probably can't know
if they fall in love, but we like to consider it."
This is quite nice.
And then the article goes on, "Just for good measure,
we asked whether, given a machine design,
specifically for the purpose,
a crow could drive a car."
(laughing)
- To which the scientist said, "I have no idea."
I think probably I have an idea that they probably,
they can't even reach that, well.
- Did you see that stroke?
What was it called when dogs fly a plane
or something that was on recently?
- And could they?
- Well, they claimed it was flying the plane.
I think the dog was just sitting in a seat.
- I saw that.
- That was a cult pilot.
- It was a cult, yeah, I mean, you'd be mad
(laughing)
to send sensitive cameras and stuff.
Expensive filming equipment.
- With an unaccompanied tax.
(laughing)
- On a 7472 in the next, you'll imagine,
sitting in your seat, and over the tunnel.
(laughing)
- Where?
- You'll probably do it again in English in a minute.
(laughing)
- So actually, just going back to that,
what actually happened on this TV show?
- I can't remember if it's the guy, the pilot took them up
and then they handed over control to the dog.
(laughing)
And there was a train over behind the dog.
I think what it was was the dog had it had it.
- The poor's were kind of through the joystick.
- Is it a joystick?
- Yeah.
- Whatever steer is the plane.
The dog had that, and I think it made some turns,
but also some unnext to them, and they were.
So they took a train to what to do.
I think Kroza never had a better chance.
'Cause Kroza is actually my anyway.
- I mean, I think we're flying out.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- Because they can talk, they can make the tunnel announcements
and uncomprehensibly.
- What if it was a Kro and you didn't know?
- Would you be angry or thrilled if the big reveal
at the end of your 747 flight was a Kro
coming out of the cockpit and going surprise?
- I'd be a bit of both, I think.
- Yeah.
- I'd be surprised, sir.
(laughing)
- Yeah, James is a stagger that the hummingbird hadn't done it.
- Why would you fly backwards all the way?
(laughing)
- I just wanted to say one thing about grudges.
- Okay.
- It's just quite...
- Not now Anna, not now.
(laughing)
- Let's talk about it after the recording ends.
- Andy, it was my last biscuit.
(laughing)
- It was four years ago.
- Men are more vengeful than women.
- We'll see about that.
(laughing)
- That's just my fight.
- No, there was a study done saying men bear grudges more
and they aren't as good at forgiving people
when they've been wronged until you explain to them
how they might have also done that.
- In words of one syllable.
(laughing)
- Exactly.
So it seems bizarre.
It seems like when you show them and how to empathize
then they do forgive as easily as women.
So in this study, the women who remembered their wrongs
were no more likely to forgive those wrongs
when you reminded women that they had also wronged people.
But the men became much more likely
to forgive people who had wronged them
when you reminded them, oh but didn't you do this person wrong.
So it's just many that little extra reminder.
- They're like simple crows aren't they?
(laughing)
- Women are hummingbirds to the male raven.
(upbeat music)
- Let's move on to the final fact.
- And that is my fact.
- My fact is that in 1959, the man who set the record time
for swimming the Panama Canal was declared an honorary ship
by the Panama Canal Authority.
- That's crazy.
- Amazing.
Although on the way back he did have to carry a load
of 450 cotton bales.
(laughing)
- This was a guy called Captain Robert Legg.
- He got all Bob Legg.
(laughing)
- Well there's Bob Legg with his bobbing legs.
They called him as his swam by.
And he made the journey in 1958, in 21 hours and 54 minutes,
which is pretty fast to swim the 77 kilometers
of the Panama Canal.
And yeah, the next year, the governor of the Panama Canal
authority, Mr. William Potter,
presented him with a certificate,
which announced that he was an honorary ship,
an honorary vessel in recognition of his achievement.
- That's great.
- I like that if you work hard you could become anything.
(laughing)
- Yeah, when he was a kid they probably said
a little bobby leg.
What do you want to be when you grow up?
He's like, I want to be a ship.
- You dreamer.
- Yeah.
- Well, can you be a bit more realistic please, Bob?
(laughing)
You'll be in a council.
- That's fantastic.
- It is good.
Another thing I liked is that people who attempted
to swim in the Panama Canal were treated like ships
in another sense, which is that they had to pay tolls
as they went through the locks.
And they were weight-based tolls.
So they had to be weighed and sized up to work out
how much they had to pay.
And so, Bob leg had to pay 72 cents for each lock crossing
which was actually the weight of a one ton vessel.
- But the first man who swam it paid 35 cents I think
because he was only, he was declared a small proportion
of a one ton vessel.
- I have 36 cents on my file.
I don't know which one's right.
He was called Richard Halliburton.
- Yes.
- I love Richard Halliburton so much.
So, he was an amazing guy.
Well, he disappeared in 1939, we assume he died.
I mean, he's probably dead now.
But he crossed the out by elephant.
He descended into the Mayan Well of Death.
(laughing)
He wasn't a nice guy.
He flew a bike lane over the Taj Mahal upside down.
- That's fantastic.
Can I ask what the Mayan Well of Death is?
- You can ask James.
(laughing)
- If I had read that, that would be the first thing I googled.
- Oh, that wasn't curious.
(laughing)
- The Mayan Well of Death is a Mayer sort of sacred well
in I think it's in Colombia.
And lots of people have fallen into there
and died and things, but not Halliburton.
- Halliburton.
- He was an unbelievable,
and he wrote these newspaper columns and books
all about his adventures all over the world.
And there was quite a lot of embellishment in them.
So, you know, some things need a pinch of salt.
But he swam the Panama Canal.
I think it was the first one to do it.
- He was the first one to do it.
It's going through all the locks as well.
Because the first people to actually swim
from one end to the other were two people
who worked on the canal.
'Cause they thought the honor of swimming
it should go to people who worked on it.
And they, because they worked on the canal six days a week,
they could only swim it on Sundays.
And so it took them quite a long time in stages.
- Yeah.
I like this headline from when Halliburton swam the canal in,
so it was 1928 when he did it.
And I just read a headline from the time,
which is, "Alligators annoy authors
"froming Panama Canal."
(laughing)
- I just thought, "I think that's the wrong way round."
Like, he's the one who's in their canal.
- You should have bought some autos to go off.
(laughing)
- So about the prices that you have to pay,
the most that anyone's ever paid is a cruise ship
called the Norwegian Pearl.
And they paid $375,600 to go through.
You paid by birth, by the number of people you can carry.
And there's a thing called Priority Passage.
So if there's a queue,
quite often there's a queue of a load of ships waiting.
There was one time, there was a seven-day delay,
a 90-ship queue waiting.
And these people paid kind of extra money
so they could kind of jump the queue.
And they paid $220,300.
And it would normally have been 13,430.
- Well, they really wanted to get their wares over.
- Yeah, I know, but that's,
isn't it great though?
Can you imagine sort of getting there
and there's 90 ships ahead of you?
- I don't know how they would overtake each other though.
- Because they are huge, aren't they?
They're made to the ships that go down the Panagma Canal
are often made specifically in order to fit through the canal.
And the technical term for them is Panamax,
which is the maximum width you can be
in order to get through.
And they don't look ridiculous if you don't have that.
- So is it Panama with an X at the end, Panamax?
- You've got it, you've got it, one just.
- Smart, if only Edgar Allan Poe had that kind of forward thinking.
- Do you want to hear my favourite canal facts?
- Yeah.
- In 1978 there was British waterways,
the group were out, cleaning out the canal, dredging it,
and they pulled out a chain with a bit of wood on the end,
and it was a plug, and they drained the Chesterfield Canal.
- No.
- Oh, the fuck in it.
- Oh my god.
- And I thought that can't be true.
And I was googling it, and then there's a found a thing
with the guy who did it, it was called Bill Thorpe,
and his aunt told the story and said that Bill couldn't believe it.
And the canal crust said that every canal has
some sort of draining system, that's how they're maintained.
- So you can't drain it now.
- They get a better, because I thought this is amazing.
And I found in 2009 there's an aqueduct, an erectum,
and it needs to be drained for inspection
to see how it was all doing.
And so a ten-year-old boy won the chance
to pull the plug in the competition.
- Oh.
- They let him drain the entire aqueduct.
- Can he really, a canal can be drained
by a ten-year-old little weakling?
- This is the aqueduct.
So it released 1.5 million liters of water in the aqueduct,
and he said it wasn't actually that hard to do.
- Wow.
- It's really cool to drain the aqueduct.
- It is cool, I want to do that.
- Yeah, you know, there was a phase in canals
between when we decided that having mules pull our things
along the water wasn't going to work.
And between that phase, and when we came up with diesel,
there was a phase when canal boats were supposed
to be electrically powered.
And there were quite a few built, especially in Germany
and France and Belgium, I think, and a few in America,
which had cables running along the top of them.
So it was like electricity lines.
And the canal boats would be connected to the electricity lines
above them, and then be carried along like that.
That's us. - That's us.
- Very dangerous.
- Yeah, water and electricity.
- Yeah.
- And you were in the middle of it.
- It has on the tillet. - Incredible.
- There's still one left.
It's the Straussi ferry in Germany, if you want to visit.
They look really cool.
- That's amazing.
- So when they, obviously, they used to have horses
pulling them along the banks.
And then, obviously that's a problem when you get to the tunnel
'cause you can't just shove the horse in the canal
and make it go along inside the tunnel.
So they had men called Leggers.
And what you would do, you would lie on top of the boat
and you would stick your legs into the air
and you would use that to slowly push, again,
to sort of upside down, walk the canal boat
along through the tunnel.
- That's so cool, right?
- It's really interesting, right?
- I used to love it in a blatant book called
"Sawcy Jane Family."
That was the name of the canal.
- "Sawcy Jane."
- It was the family who got canal holiday.
And at some point, they sent the horse over the hill
'cause they were going through tunnel,
but they didn't explain how the boat carried on moving.
- Oh, yeah.
- So now I know that someone on the top
was peddling against the ceiling.
- Yeah, that's so cool.
- "Sawcy Jane" lay on her back with a legs of the air.
(laughing)
- Don't ruin my childhood.
- Why was that?
- Quietly that out.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's all of our facts.
Thanks so much for listening.
And if you want to get in touch with us,
you can contact these guys on Twitter.
So Anne is at...
- @miller_m.
- James.
- @egshapedndy.
- @andruhunterm.
- And you can email me on podcast@QI.com.
If you want to listen to any of our previous
episodes, you can go to know such things at fish.com.
And we'll be back with another episode next week.
See you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)