(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of Little Fish Before We Start.
Andrew Hunter Murray has something he'd like to say to you all,
just to keep his inbox from bulging quite so much.
- So this is a little, thanks James, hi everybody.
This is a little pre-apology and correction.
I run a small quiz in the middle of this show
about the oldest ever James Bond.
I can't wait for you to hear it, it's really fun.
And in it we say, the two oldest James bonds,
I won't give away which ones now,
but I just like to point out,
I do know that Sean Connery was 53
when he was in, never say never again.
But it's not a canon Bond film,
it's not one of the official ones,
which is why it's not included in the quiz.
I woke up sweating, realizing
that I had not made this clear in the show itself
all makes sense soon.
- Let it never be said that we don't take
these silly little quizzes, extremely serious thing.
Seriously, there's a quiz about carrots coming up
that is honestly the most serious quiz
I've ever run on this show.
I'm so excited.
Too many spoilers ending.
- Sorry, yes.
If you would like to get more apologies, corrections,
and bonus info, why not join Club Fish.
This is our special secret members club.
We do a four nightly show called Doppers Align
where you get this kind of sizzling
behind the scenes hot goss about the show itself.
So if you want to join that, just go to patreon.com/nosuchthingasafish.
Next announcement, before we start this week,
let me show if you heard our episode,
which went out a few days ago with none other than Michael Palin,
then we got a little bit of an extra treat for you.
We filmed the whole thing and we put it up on YouTube.
- What?
- Yeah, I'm sorry James, did you not know?
I was wearing my bikini the whole way through.
- Yes, I know.
It did, Michael did comment when you were out of the room.
He said, "What a friendly young lady that is."
(laughing)
Yeah, so we filmed the whole thing.
It's on YouTube.
You can see us, like, worshipping Michael Palin in real time.
It's great, it's great fun.
- Just go on to YouTube and search for our names
or search for.
- No such thing as a fish.
- No such thing as a fish and I'm sure you'll find it.
- But for now, enjoy this little fish.
On with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
(waves crashing)
- Hello and welcome to Little Fish.
This is our new weekly show where we read out your facts.
We've had enough of our facts.
Let's have some of yours.
You've been sending them in to podcast@QI.com
and they are terrific.
And so we're gonna share some of the absolute cremd
that I crem with you now.
Who's got a fact?
Who would like to kick off?
- I'm here, I'm here with Dan Shriver in James Harkin.
- Hey Andy.
- My name's Andrew Hunter Murray.
Do I say all that?
- I don't think I said that last week.
- Well.
- Last week I was here with Andrew Hunter Murray
and Dan Shriver.
(laughing)
- Great.
- And in case I forget to say it, next week,
I will be with Andrew Hunter Murray in James Harkin.
- A great stroller gives a fact.
- All right, Gabe Bollard said, big fan of the show,
I saw Dan post on Instagram that he found the book
claiming to feature posthumous interviews
with Elvis Presley's ghost.
How this is true is written by Hans Holzer,
who is the person who sort of defined what a ghost hunter was
and very much inspired Dan Acroid
for ghost busters and so on.
He's added a fact that has nothing to do with that.
Says in the early 90s, when the United States Postal Service
proposed issuing an Elvis Presley stamp,
there was an effort to block it
because someone must be dead in order to appear
on a US postage stamp.
And Elvis, they said, was still alive.
(laughing)
- That's wonderful.
- That's really good.
- That's nice.
- That is very funny.
That is a thing, isn't it?
You have to be dead in order to be on a stamp.
- Definitely used to be the case.
- Yeah.
- I'm not sure it still is.
- So Neil Armstrong landing on the moon was okay
because you couldn't see his face.
So it was a generic astronaut even though it was--
- Such nonsense.
- Yeah.
- Clearly, just we're proud we put someone on the moon
so we're gonna break the stamp rule.
- Yeah.
- So what that is?
Like, well, they were saying,
oh, it's an astronaut rather than Neil Armstrong.
- Yes.
- Well, what's the next astronaut's name?
- Do you remember as well that that led to Buzz Aldrin's dad
standing outside the White House with a placard
that read, "My son stood on there too."
- And it was him being furious there.
- Michael Collins' mum was there saying,
Michael didn't actually stand on the moon,
but he was just dead at a car driving around the ring
around the White House.
(laughing)
- Yeah, I think as well that one person in the UK
did sneak onto a stamp accidentally who was still alive
and that's Roger Taylor from Queen
'cause they did a Freddie Mercury stamp
but in the background, Taylor's drumming.
And so technically they have put someone--
- But you are allowed the Queen on stamps.
- Compulsory.
- So a member of Queen feels fair as well.
- Yeah, brilliant.
- There we go.
- Are you sure you're allowed?
Are you not?
There's the rule the same in the UK
that you can't be honest about unless you do.
- Again, I think it used to be.
I'm not sure if it still is now,
but definitely used to be.
- We've lost so many of our traditions.
- Here is a fact.
- So this is from Chris Bemis.
And Chris Bemis says,
"My fact is the largest shopping mall in the US,
"Mall of America is kept warm in winter by human body heat."
- Oh, so is that the humans who are shopping in the mall
or is it a separate candle of trained humans
who just go around being hot?
- Do you remember in the last episode
we said that you have very high body heat
and so your watch runs faster than most people?
- Yeah.
- They've people, a lot of people like you in the basement.
No, this is just people who are shopping.
And actually, like I saw a Reddit on this
and they say that really the amount of heat
that's given off by the human bodies
is really, really negligible.
And while it does say on the website
that the mall has no central heating
and that it uses the body heat,
they're quite cagey with what they actually say
and probably all the individual stores
have their own heating systems.
- We also have a huge coal fire burning in the centre.
So we don't have central heating, but we...
So I think it's like, it's definitely claimed by the mall
but whether it's 100% true, I'm not absolutely certain.
And also they have all these sky lights
that this sunlight belongs out as well.
But here's a question for you.
Do you know in a few recent podcasts,
I've been saying, I'll ask you a question
and if you get the answer right,
you'll get a million quid or 10 million quid.
- Yes.
- Well, I'm gonna do another one of those,
but I'm a bit wary that eventually
you will get one of these right.
But for now, I'll give you 100 million quid.
- If you can tell me which country
the world's largest mall is according to Wikipedia.
- Okay.
- Eritrea.
- No.
- Mexico.
- No, unlucky lads.
(laughing)
- That goes into the pot for the next episode.
It's the Iran Mall in Tehran.
- Oh, no, no.
- The largest mall in the world.
- That's pretty good, is it?
- Just very...
- It's just bass, got hotels, it's got lots of,
it's just got all sorts of stuff in there.
- Big mall.
- Big or mall.
- Nice.
- I've got another fact.
- Go for it.
- Yeah.
- From Susanna Pate of British Carrots.
- Okay.
- This came in a little while ago.
- Sorry, you say plate of carrots.
- Sorry.
- Pate.
- Oh.
- Of British Carrots.
- Okay.
- Her name is Susanna Pate, and she works for,
I don't need to tell you guys who British Carrots are,
but they're just, you know, for the international list.
- They're a trade body, whose main job is to get us all
eating more carrots.
- Right.
- It's a hugely powerful organization.
Shadowey, I would say.
- Yeah.
- And she wrote because British Carrot Day was coming up.
- Okay.
- I was on the 3rd of October.
So we have missed it by quite some way.
But I just, I didn't want to leave, leave her out.
- Because...
- Because of that.
- Yeah, because of us.
- You know, I love a carrot.
- Absolutely.
- Is it strange that, well, that national carrot day is
in October, when presumably all the carrots have been
well found by then?
- James, I'd like to refer you to Susanna's email.
- Okay.
- Carrots are harvested 12 months of the year in the UK.
- Give me a break.
- So they, so they're one of the freshest and most versatile
vegetables we can all enjoy.
That's according to Harry Strausson,
who I presume grows carrots.
Anyway, I thought a couple of just little quiz questions
based off her facts.
- Yeah.
- How many carrot seeds are sewn in Britain each year?
- Um, each carrot seeds.
- Oh, each carrot seeds each year.
If I get within 10 billion of this, I'll be astonished.
- Okay, okay.
- I'm gonna say 50 billion.
Okay.
- Oh, I'm glad you're that high, because I was going high.
I was gonna say 200 billion.
- Well, it's 22 billion.
So down is that by a factor of 10.
- James got reasonably close to you.
- I mean, that didn't get close in the grand scheme of things.
- No, if they did plant 50 billion,
we'd have an insane over capacity of carrots.
- That's not a world I want 11.
Walk along the street just waiting through carrots
as you go to the office every day.
- All right.
- What is the total tonnage of carrots
that those 22 billion seeds between them produce?
So how many tons of carrots we're talking?
22 billion seeds, how many tons of carrots?
- Oh, I hate this quiz.
- It's fat quiz.
- I watched Richard Alston's House of Games
for the first ever time this week.
No offense, I'd be because you were on it,
and I didn't watch it where you were on it.
- Oh, I don't want it, don't worry.
- But they do this stuff, don't they?
Where you have to just make a random guess on things.
- Yeah, this is worse than House of Games.
I'm not afraid to admit that.
- Okay.
- All right, I'll go first, you go on first, last time.
- Six.
- Come on, play the game, mate.
- I ain't gonna go 100 billion.
- 100 billion.
- You think that every carrot seed
produces five tons of carrots?
- This is why you got invited down House of Games,
and I did it.
Yeah, that's a good pipe.
- But this is good because now we're tied.
- Yeah, you're right.
I'm ready to bet you both that.
Well, I'll guess 700,000 tons,
which is the correct answer.
- Oh, well done.
- And just out of interest,
that would stretch 1.4 million miles
if you put the carrots end to end.
- Great.
- Okay, carry on.
Next fact.
- Thank you, Ms. Plate.
- Paid.
- Only two questions in this quiz.
- Okay, one last question, what?
- 1.9 million miles.
- Percentage.
- Of the carrots consumers by in the UK
are grown in Britain.
- 38.
- You think, okay, 38.
We're only 38% self-sufficient in carrots.
- Ah, interesting.
You said the word only there.
Right, 9.
- Oh, James wins.
It's 97.
- That's good.
- I know.
So there's almost no need to buy imported carrots.
Almost.
So that's thank you, Susanna.
- Very good.
- And if you work for like the wallboard
or whatever podcast at qi.com.
The cheese bar, they're always doing stuff, aren't they?
- Yeah, brilliant.
- And we'll forward this app to Richard Osmond.
You should have a new job.
- Very same.
Tony Shane writes about a bond.
So a financial bond.
- Yeah.
- You buy a bond and it pays out a certain rate of interest
for a certain number of years, right?
And then when the bond returns,
you get all the original money you put in back.
- Yeah.
- So I pay 100 quid.
I get three quid a year for 10 years
and then I get 100 quid back.
Pretty good deal.
And it's if companies or governments
need to raise a lot of money initially
and fund something.
- A war first time.
- A war.
- Well.
- There is a bond which was issued in 1648,
which is still paying out.
(laughing)
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It was issued in the Netherlands, 377 years ago.
Charles I was still alive in England.
And it was the water authority.
They issued a bond and it's still paying.
- But you said, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Like you knew this.
- I feel like we may have covered
this.
- Oh really?
- A long time ago on a show.
- I'm not familiar with it.
- It's just stunning.
So the actual original bond is in Yale now.
It's passed through many hands over the centuries.
It's written on ghost kin.
- Oh wow.
- And it's so old.
And the number of water boards in the Netherlands
just needed to raise money for something.
And this isn't even the oldest bond in the world
that's still active.
There is one that was issued in 1624.
It had its 400th birthday last year.
It is still paying out.
And it was again, Dutch water utility.
They had this disaster where some drifting ice broke
through a dike, huge problem in the Netherlands
because it's all underwater.
They needed to raise money.
And this one pays about 13 euros still every year
that you're the bond holder.
- It's just so cool.
- Yeah.
- I think I should set one up so people can send me money
and I can become a spy or something.
- Wait, are you issuing the bond?
- Yeah, yeah, you'll be called the James Bond.
- Oh my god.
- It was a funny God.
- I gave you a second to notice
that you're walking into.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- All right.
Well, I actually did prepare a separate little quiz.
Who was the oldest bond?
- Oh.
- As in James Bond.
- James Bond, James Bond.
The oldest actor to play James Bond.
- Not Jamal.
- Correct.
Second oldest.
- Daniel Craig.
- Daniel Craig, correct.
Carry on.
(laughing)
- Why is this quiz?
- I'd sometimes, they're not all in parties.
It's not all like how many carrot seeds are there
in the UK every year.
Sometimes it's just a little confidence builder.
So Roger Moore was 57 when he hung up his false teeth
and wagon all of that.
And, but Daniel Craig was 51 when he stopped doing it.
- Yeah.
- In that last bond first.
- Not massively surprised.
What about our lays and beef of number three?
- I haven't written down any other.
- Oh.
- Tonery?
- I haven't written down any other names and ages.
Should have done.
- You probably didn't think we were going to get the first two
so quickly, I guess.
- I could have said I didn't.
- But, lays and beef, George lays and beef.
I, someone painted my old flat years and years ago
who had come, he'd, did I talk to his poor?
- No.
- Andy, this would be the best anecdote you've ever told us.
Shall we remember it?
(laughing)
- Wait, wait, wait.
This could tail off really quickly.
(laughing)
- Layson B's dead now, isn't he?
He's dead.
- I don't think he is.
- I better not say it like that.
(laughing)
- Okay, let me see, let me see.
- Melissa, imagine this anecdote, begins,
a friend of mine was painting a flat,
and ends with something just libelous against George,
I didn't mean it.
- He's very much going strong.
- Let's move on.
- Yeah.
- I told you, I was going to tail off.
I told you, we trusted you.
He had such a front loaded it so well.
He supposedly got the gig of bond
when he was having his hair done.
This is one of the stories that gets told.
And one of the broccoli's was sitting next to him.
- Big broccoli.
- We're sitting next to him.
- It can be broccoli, the producer.
- Gaby broccoli, Barbara.
- Or Barbara, it could have been Barbara.
- Yeah.
- And Layson, he shot him six times through the head, didn't he?
- Yes.
- So you've got what it takes, kid.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- He's also, do you remember that there was going to be
a bond of a very different nature,
a different kind of character, not strictly an actor?
And he wasn't allowed to be bond in the end
because his face looked a bit too much like a farmer's.
(laughing)
- We've spoken about this on the podcast.
It might have been a part of an edit.
- Someone's a bright blessed?
- No.
- You look too much like a farmer.
Who looks like a farmer?
- Interestingly, a book of theirs is right behind me,
but you're sitting in front of 500 books.
- Wait a minute, I know, I'm Miller.
(laughing)
- It is Randall Finds.
- Oh yeah.
- Remember Randall Finds went to auditions
and was-- - He was in the running.
- Yeah.
- I think it was either his hands look like a farmer
or his face, one of the two.
(upbeat music)
- I've got one, Andrew Price.
I'm a long-term listener living in North Carolina, USA,
where I work as a nurse.
I'm sending you an article I found in the New York Times
about a type of seabird, the Streaked Shearwater,
and the article is headlined, "These majestic seabirds
never stop pooping."
And basically, scientists did an experiment
on the Streaked Shearwater where they put cameras
on the bottoms of the birds pointing backwards.
And I think they were trying to work out
something about their flight or their flight dynamics
or something.
But basically, what they found is,
are these birds are constantly powing?
It's extraordinary.
It's 5% of their mass every hour.
- Whoa.
- I know.
And Andrew writes, "To put this into perspective,
this would be like me pooping out an 11 pound poop."
I don't like that word, poop.
Every hour about the same weight as a normal house cat.
(laughing)
Or 132 pounds, the weight of two Dalmatians
in the course of a 12 hour work day.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- 50 and a half days, and you have 101 Dalmatians.
- That's amazing.
- That's very upsetting.
What a bird.
- What a bird.
(laughing)
- Like you, Andrew, great fact.
- Yeah, that's brilliant.
- Well, Ma'am.
- Yeah, I got actually another poo one to read out here.
This was sent in by Liz May.
And she says that this is an article she spotted.
A woman in Australia has now been
in a year's long remission from severe bipolar disorder
after receiving homemade fecal transplant
animals from her husband.
- Oh, boy.
- Her case is one of the first in the world.
It may lead to improved treatments
for bipolar disorder.
- I don't think it will.
(laughing)
- So sorry, homemade, I don't even know how you would,
how you would think of home making
a fecal transplant animal.
- Yeah.
- Do you know what I mean?
It just wouldn't occur to me to, to do.
- No, which bit.
- Home making, I suppose.
- Like if I went to the doctor and he said,
look, it sounds crazy, but actually we think your microbiome
might be maladjusted and we think maybe we can get it
back into an equilibrium by doing this procedure.
But I don't think they would then say,
can you just go home and ask your,
but would you rather have someone else's poo up there
or would you rather have someone you know?
- Or would you think someone else's?
- Oh, really?
- Yes, because I think.
- Yeah, but that's because I have to keep,
if it's someone close to you, like a partner,
you have to look at them, I think it would,
I think it takes a little of the spark out of a marriage.
(laughing)
- I'm wondering the circumstances in which you raise
your idea, you know.
- Oh, you've got to build up to it.
That's baby steps.
- You can't just go straight in and say,
I think we should do this.
- You've got to be like.
- I wonder, I heard the Jones is at number 14
and doing quite an interesting thing.
I don't say we should do it.
I just, I just, you know,
it's something that kind of interests me a little bit.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I guess we could try it.
- We could try it.
- For your birthday, maybe.
- Great fact.
- Well, great that it worked as well.
- Yeah. - Around the coats.
- Rites, according to the Rale Shakespeare Company,
50% of the world's children study Shakespeare.
- Wow.
- That's nice, isn't it?
- That's great.
- I got to say.
- It's good for Britain,
because it gives us soft power around the world.
- And all the plays are bloody good.
- They are, they're really good.
Shakespeare's one of those writers,
whoever wants to, he's good.
And then you read him and actually he's really good.
- I'll leave you a tell.
- Tell us more about the Shakespeare part.
(laughing)
- Give us more of that.
- Well.
(laughing)
The guy who decorated my hat had a really interesting story
about Bill Beckton.
- He is dead, I can say that much.
- Oh, well he said he was a wanker.
(laughing)
- So this was a study done in 2014.
Okay, and it also named Shakespeare
as the most popular person associated with UK art
and culture in the world.
Can you name any other people who are on that list?
And I have a list of 13 other people.
- Charles Dickens.
- No.
- These are just any kind, any feel.
- Anyone in the world associates them
with UK art and culture.
- George Orwell.
- No.
- John Lennon.
- The Beatles.
- The Beatles, I'll give you.
- Oh, Jane Austen?
- No.
- Oh my god.
- That's way more likely to get these.
- Okay.
- David Bowie.
- No, for good guess.
- Edmund Hillary.
- No.
- Brian Blessed.
- Edmund Hillary is from New Zealand.
- Oh yeah.
(laughing)
- Okay, Dan's way more likely to get this.
- So we're thinking of John Plees.
- John Plees now.
- Freddie Mercury.
- No.
God, I genuinely thought you'd get a few more of these.
- The Queen.
- The Queen, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Queen.
- You kicked culture.
- Well culture.
- You're all so racing.
- I'm sorry to be a snobby,
but she just didn't, do you mean the old queen?
- Queen Elizabeth II.
- Yeah, the true queen.
- Yeah, yeah, go on.
Okay, so we had the Queen.
We had Shakespeare.
- And we've had the Beatles.
- I'm telling you, I'll give you McCartney as well,
'cause you said the Beatles.
- Twiggy.
- No.
- Sting.
- 2014.
- No, such thing as a fish.
(laughing)
- They've got anaticity, so I'll give you that.
No, not that.
- 2014, that's a clue, 2014.
- It's true.
- Similar on the way out.
- No.
- Dapper laughs.
- More famous than Lily Allen for sure.
- Endobs.
- Vernon Manning.
(laughing)
- And Dale is what I was saying before there.
- Dale.
- And Dale.
- And author.
- Philip Pullman.
- Terry Pratchard.
- Come on guys, the most famous British author.
- JK Rowling.
- Yes.
- A soccer player?
- Beckham.
- Correct.
- Really?
- An actor.
- Alan Rickman.
- No.
- Ray phones.
- Simon Callow.
(laughing)
- Benedict Cumberbatch.
- Okay, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And a puppet dog that sells car insurance.
- Churchill?
- Churchill.
- Churchill, it just says Churchill.
I assume it's that.
(laughing)
Good quiz, guys.
- It's pretty good.
- Well done.
- Wow, really good quiz.
- I'm gonna call the Churchill, make it onto the dog.
- The dog over the politics.
- It will be Winston Churchill, I'm sure.
- I wish.
- It's just always, I was just doing a funny.
- Let's go compare mere cats, play on that.
- Anyway, John is next week, but.
(laughing)
John is next week for my quiz, Pollock Teap.
On the on channel five.
- Oh.
- Okay, well, I think we, oh, it's not,
I'm not even hosting this, am I?
- You are hosting this one.
- Andy.
- With me, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Don't you think we should maybe end
and maybe do some curatorship?
- No, I want to do 20 more minutes of these,
of the UK culture and art figures.
(laughing)
- Yes, you're right, James.
We should wrap this up.
- Thank you so much for sending your facts in.
Just a reminder, podcast@QI.com.
If you'd like to have your facts.
- Oh, I don't think I did that last week.
So just to say, but also last week,
if you want to send a fact last week,
then it's podcast@QI.com.
- I'll explain to the dearth of facts
we've had in the inbox since last week.
No, thank you so much for listening to this bit.
And now let's have some fact custodian award ceremonies.
(laughing)
This is the thing we're doing where,
if you join Club Fish on Patreon
at the friend of the podcast tier,
if you join those exalted heights,
you get a fact, a headline fact
that we've done on the show in the past,
to be yours, your fact, in perpetuity,
forever and ever are meant.
It is your fact.
So we're gonna be dishing out a few of those now
to a few friends of the podcast who've joined.
So let's start with one.
Anyone want to kick off?
- I'll do one. - Lovely.
- Because this was originally my fact from episode nine.
And it is that it was fashionable in New York
at the end of the 19th century for women
to wear a bird of paradise feathers.
- Hmm. - And that fact is now under the custodianship
of Drumroll, please.
David Addis.
- Congratulations, David.
- Well done, David.
I actually have no memory of that fact whatsoever.
(laughing)
- You need to go back and listen to episode nine.
- I'm gonna, I'm gonna do.
- This is exciting for all of us to revisit all the episodes.
- And that was the thing that kicked off bird protection,
wasn't it?
As in, people were just wearing these bird feathers
with it nearly.
- Is that right? - These birds.
As many birds of paradise as they used to be,
a lot of lovely hats being made.
- Yeah. - Interesting.
- Yeah. - I think that is what happened.
It was the odd upon society, wasn't it?
- I know. - I think hip memory serves.
- Yeah. - Don't write 10 if it wasn't.
There was a thing called the plumage league,
which is just a flat out good name for a society.
- That's your own name, yeah.
- Very nice. - But yeah, congratulations to you, David.
- Lovely stuff. Should I read one out?
- Yeah. - This was my fact from episode nine.
Alan Cheering lost his buried treasure
when he couldn't crack his own code.
I don't know the idea.
- Yeah. - What a story.
This is now under the custodianship
of Martin Hill, congratulations, Martin.
And this was Alan Cheering in the lead up to World War II,
worried that all of his valuables were gonna be stolen.
So I think he traded it in for a couple of silver bars
or gold bars. - Oh yeah.
- And he buried them and he made a code
of where he buried them and he made a code of a code.
And then possibly even a code of a code of a code.
And then after the war. - He loved his codes.
- His big on codes. - His one thing
that we will say about Alan Cheering is he loved the code.
We love to crack a code.
And unfortunately in this case,
when he went back after the war to crack it,
the landscape had changed.
He couldn't quite understand his actual code itself.
And so he never found it.
It might still be out there.
I think the bit of England where he was meant
to have buried it is now sort of council estate.
So I think they would have dug it up.
- Is it there, blackly?
- I can't remember to be honest, but yeah.
- I thought it was.
- If you live anywhere in the Midlands,
why not dig up your garbage?
- Absolutely.
- Yeah.
- It's good for you anyway.
- Oh yeah, gardening.
- There you go.
Well, congrats, Martin Hill.
- Yeah. - Of course.
- Here's one.
This is going out to Aaron Hung.
And it's the fact that in 2011,
the largest sperm bank in the world stopped accepting sperm
from redheads.
- Sorry, Aaron, you got a bit of a--
- It's a blue one.
- It's a blue fact.
There's no doubt about that.
And I think it was--
- It was just a canner really.
- It's an anifact.
- Yeah.
- And the fact of course it was--
- I think it was a lack of demand.
I think it was classic anti-redhead prejudice.
- That is prejudice.
- Yeah.
- There's an interesting thing in history.
I read a paper about this that people have typically thought
that people with red hair are very sort of sexually active.
And they've had that reputation throughout history.
But the research has found out that the reason
that they had that reputation is because people just
generally found them more attractive.
- Oh right.
(laughing)
- And so they were having more sex,
but it's just because everyone fancied them.
- Yeah, right.
- Oh, that's not my counter narrative
to all the anti-gender prejudice.
- Absolutely.
- Good.
- Wesley Vetter, you are now the proud custodian
of this fact.
The English language has more words borrowed from Hawaiian
than from Welsh.
- Really?
- Yes.
- Wesley, that one is now yours.
This was an Andrew Murray original.
- Yeah.
And it's, I can't remember any words
that are borrowed from Hawaiian now.
- I like it.
- Wiki.
- Hula.
- I think Hula hoop.
- Yeah, Hula dancing.
- Yes.
- But also I think the thing is that in Hawaii,
they had lots of new plants that needed names.
And so we took them from Hawaiian.
- Right.
- Whereas when we went into Wales,
they had the same plants as we had.
- Right.
- Which is slightly like maybe leak.
- No, we already had leaks.
- Daffs?
- Daffs, yeah.
They still existed.
You know, there was no need to give Welsh names to these things.
- You're right.
And also, let's not forget the Andy Welsh prejudice.
- Of course.
- Which, but one interesting thing is that everyone found
the Welsh extreme.
We attracted.
- Yes.
- Oh yeah.
- Let's do another one.
This we had a guest on in this episode, episode 10.
And that guest was Eric Lampair.
- Eric Lampair.
- I haven't seen him for years.
- Well, do you know what?
You can see him currently in a movie.
- Oh.
- So there's a new--
- That's why I haven't seen him
because that's what they--
- So there's a movie out at the moment called
Grief as the Thingwood Feathers,
based on a max-ported book.
And it's Benedict Cumberbatch.
And there's a big black bird that appears in it.
- Is he playing the bird?
- He's inside the bird.
- Wow.
- So you don't see Eric, but he's on Stilts
and he is the bird in that film.
- Very cool.
- So we grew up.
- Eric.
- Yep.
- What was his fact?
- His fact was, in 1923,
Jockey Frank Hayes won a race in Belmont Park in New York,
despite being dead.
- Wow.
- Yeah, amazing fact.
That's Emma Goven.
And congratulations.
This is now your fact.
This was, he died on the final leg, Denny.
I think he had a heart attack while on the horse,
but the horse just kept running and won the race.
- Right.
- Yeah. - Gosh, that's amazing.
- Have we got time for any more Andy or--
- I think we've got time for three more.
- Three more, okay.
Well, I'll do one.
This one was a Dan Shriver fight from episode 10.
I've noticed things are fish.
And Dan said some buddhist monks run marathons
to achieve enlightenment.
And that fact now belongs to Mr. Dan Turner.
So Dan, congratulations.
- Yeah, that was one of my favorite earliest facts
on the podcast, which is this extraordinary thing
that they run these insanely long marathons
and the idea is that after,
however many days of doing it,
they would achieve enlightenment.
So rather than meditating your way to it,
you can actually bolt.
- But the thing is about meditating
as you can just sit there.
- Right.
- Yeah.
- I think I would prefer to do that method
of enlightenment than having to get your gym gear on.
(laughing)
- Rub your nipples with Vaseline.
I mean, I'll be doing that even if I'm just sitting down.
So that's a wash for me.
- That's sort of yeah, accidentally achieving enlightenment.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- Runners do that, don't they?
- Yes, they do.
- Oh, they do, they?
- Yeah.
- I thought we'd just getting an insight into your life, Andy.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- That's the thing.
- Otherwise you get jogger's nipple.
- Yeah, which can be very painful actually.
- Ooh, it sounds bad.
I've never run far enough to get jogger's nipple.
- I've had it.
- Have you?
- Did you butter them or?
- No, I just suffered for the next couple of days.
- Sensitive.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- I should move on more facts.
- All right, let's have a couple more.
This one goes out to Ben Caligari.
Congratulations, Ben.
Because you're getting an absolute slammer.
It's that the Slovakian and Slovenian embassies
in Washington meet once a month
to exchange wrongly addressed mail.
- Brilliant.
- Yep.
- Again, an early classic.
I feel like that was one of the poster facts
in our early days.
- It was Slovakia Slovenia.
- Yeah.
- They're not very close.
They're close in a global sense, but they're not.
- Not in a European sense.
- No.
- Yeah, not in a European sense.
They're not very close.
They're probably close in an embassy sense.
- Oh yeah.
- Maybe, maybe.
- I don't even know if that's a clothe of those embassies.
(laughing)
- It's awful when the guy from Afghanistan
has to go and visit the guy from Zimbabwe.
(laughing)
- Yeah, but that's just a great fact.
- And do we have time for one more?
- Yeah.
- Let's do it.
This one is going out to Alan Clark.
In the 18th century,
there were genuine medicines called
Alan's Nippel Linament for those joggers out there.
Grymsden's ice enough,
Miller's worm plums,
and Italian buzzing friend.
- This was your effect, eh?
- I remember that.
I remember that.
That was a great fact to find.
I can't remember how I found it now, but yeah.
Miller's worm plums is such a dodgy sounding.
It's like they put, Miller is a very nice word,
like our colleague Ann Miller,
but worm and plums are two of the worst words
you could hear from a doctor.
(laughing)
- If you've got,
don't the same sentence, you've got plum worms.
That's really bad.
- Yeah, I think it just meant that's the unit of medicine,
like a lozenge.
It's just a little plum that you have to take
to deal with your worms.
It's almost as if they've surrounded the unpleasant word worm
with Miller and plums,
which are, you know, I don't mind a plum.
I love a plum, actually.
- Do you?
- Yes, I cook.
It doesn't matter.
We can move on, but I cook.
- And then I want to hear more.
- I cook rather than nice plum and oat slice,
which I'm sure I've brought into the office for you guys
in the past.
No?
- I don't think so.
- Next week, next week.
- Chocolate sausages, the last thing I have from you.
- Okay, we can't get back into that.
- Okay, so tied to finish, Andy.
- I think so.
Thank you so much, everyone, for listening to Little Fish.
We'll be back in another week with another one
with more of our facts, with more of your facts.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us,
just email podcast@QI.com
or track us all down on social media.
That's it for now, see you next week.
Bye.
(upbeat music)
[MUSIC]