(upbeat music)
- Hey, Club Fish members.
Welcome to your secret bonus bit of content.
We've got a compilation for you today.
This is the best of the outtakes
of things that didn't make it to the main show.
It features me, James, Andy, and Anna,
but you've got some bonus voices joining us this week.
We've got Reese Darby, the brilliant Reese,
and of course, the excellent Miles Jump.
You will have heard them on recent episodes,
and this is all the stuff that didn't quite fit
into the main episodes.
Oh, and quickly before we get into it,
just a quick thank you to everyone
who came to the CrossWires Festival.
We had such a fun gig.
There was an awesome ending to it,
where we did a quiz with members from the audience.
It was just so much fun.
So thank you everyone who came there.
Some people traveled all the way from America
to come see the show.
Hope you enjoyed it.
And if anyone else wants to come and see us
do another live show,
we're returning to the London Podcast Festival.
We're gonna be there on the 5th and 6th of September.
We've got a couple of great guests
lined up to join us on stage.
Go to knowsuchthingasafish.com.
You'll find the links there.
Come and see us live.
And I believe that there's gonna be
online streaming as well.
So if you are overseas and you wanna watch it,
do check it out and buy your tickets
to watch it online as it happens live.
Last thing to mention is if you missed last week's,
drop us a line just to let you know
that the price of club fish is going up by one pound.
So it is gonna be three pounds 99 going forward.
Hope that's okay with you all.
We promise that we're gonna continue
to put out really fun formats.
So don't go anywhere.
And don't go anywhere right now.
'Cause here we go.
It's the compilation.
The four fishers recent miles on with the outtakes.
(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
There's a World War I connection
as well as World War II connection in ugly,
which is really cool actually.
So in World War I, there was an understandable fear
that the Germans were gonna invade via Essex.
And a plan was drawn up to evacuate
the whole of Essex to Oxfordshire.
1.4 million people.
I don't think they told the people of Oxfordshire,
but this plan--
- Yeah, you wouldn't, would you?
- You wouldn't mention it.
- There's gotta be some stuff happening.
Just don't worry about it.
- Just keep your doors shut.
But they all got these things from the council
saying this is what to do.
- Councils have really diminished, haven't they?
Now they sometimes can't collect glass.
- Well, it's the underfunding, isn't it?
We don't get the war warnings anymore.
And the information said,
when ugly church bells ring incessantly,
that's your sign, get out, go to Oxfordshire.
And they also, and they were told,
destroy all alcohol because if the Germans arrive
and they're invading and they get drunk,
that's even worse than a sober invading Nazi,
which is quite weird.
- Really, that is weird.
'Cause it wasn't the Battle of Fishguard
when the French came over in the 18th century.
The last time Britain was invaded at all, they arrived,
they all got drunk and couldn't do anything.
- Well, I think it's really on the fence.
Yes, will alcohol make the invaders worse or better?
And maybe it depends on whether they're French or German.
- Oh, yeah, maybe.
- But anyway, it's really cool
'cause everyone was given these evacuation routes
and it meant you had to take all the back roads
'cause the army would be using the main roads.
So they had these maps and there were arrows all over Essex,
painted on walls and trees and lamp posts
and big white arrows showing people the way.
And the only remnant that remains now is in ugly.
There's a wall which just has now only the little plaque left
saying this is where the big white arrow was saying,
get out of dodge.
- Imagine arriving as a Nazi going, where is everyone?
And then seeing giant arrows pointing towards
where you needed to go.
- We haven't got this through Winston.
Protestants have some good gear.
Like I was looking at Stanstead protests.
So there was a protest in Stanstead a few years ago
over a bunch of migrants who were being sent away
and that one of those taken in the dead of night,
stuck on a charter plane,
sent back to the country from which they'd come
from a while ago.
Big protest about that.
But the way they did it was they formed a circle
around the plane.
So they got bolt cutters, they got into Stanstead airport.
They formed a circle around the plane
and they'd locked themselves in this circle
by putting their arms in pipes filled with expanding foam
and like attaching their arms to each other.
So I put my arm in one end of the type
and he puts his arm in the other.
Well, you get it.
What is expanding foam?
You know those Chinese finger traps
that you put your fingers in
but like a super big version of that.
Yeah, exactly.
It's a giant one of those.
What if I need a piss?
Well, you can't, you just have to go loose.
You can't hold your willy.
So sorry, you're in a big circle
with your arms in the pipes or our fingers touching.
If you want them to be happy.
Possibly not.
I don't think they, I think you don't want them touching
because you could have a wider circumference
if you're not touching.
I guess so.
Oh yeah, true.
But what if I feel lonely or scared?
And I do want to be holding hands with someone.
They're the sacrifices you make to save.
Someone else can't even help me have a piss
'cause they've got their arms in the tube as well.
That's got to be, I've got it.
There's got to be an external agent
who's free to go around helping people have a piss.
There was one piss helper, yes.
But all you need to do then is arrest the piss assistant
and then the whole protest falls apart.
(laughing)
Yeah, they all wet themselves and it's over.
That's how all protests tend.
I need the toilet, let's go.
I've wet myself, all right, we're done for the day.
How did it end then?
How did they actually untube them?
They're still there.
Eight years.
That plane's stuck in the middle.
They tried to prosecute them on some,
actually anti-terrorism charges
before I judge a couple of years later.
They said that's fucking ridiculous
these guys aren't terrorists.
But they were extracted from the pipes first.
I don't think anyone's still walking around
with the pipe attached to their arms.
(laughing)
If you are writing, or you can't, probably.
If your piss helper is free,
we ask if they can drop us a line.
(laughing)
Is it Stanstead or Gatwick
that's won the award for best toilet, like multiple years?
I can't be Stanstead.
No?
No, unless they're talking about the entire airport,
it's being the toilet.
Is it, can I ask that, is it an individual cubicle
or is it a design of toilets?
No, no, it's the whole toilets, the cleanliness,
it's in the window as you go down into the toilets.
You know, you walked in and you go,
wow, about to pee.
Wait, there's a window as you go down?
Yeah, it's a little cabinet where they keep it.
You can see it.
Does your toilet not have a viewing window?
It should.
(laughing)
Can I give you a music recommendation
related to this fact?
It's my favorite song I found recently.
So in 1978, I'm sure some listeners remember,
there was the big frequency change
where all of the radio stations in the UK,
all the big BBC ones,
hopped to a different frequency
because of EU regulations
and no one had the internet then.
So it was like, how are they gonna know
that their station is at a different frequency?
Especially given that, I believe Radio 3
hopped to the frequency that used to be Radio 1.
So you'd tune in hoping for Tony Blackburn
and you'd get, in certain name of famous Radio 3 presenter
in the 1970s.
I honestly thought that Tony Blackburn
was currently on Radio 3.
(laughing)
He might be.
And the only reason I know it's him is because
one of the things they did to tell people was
Tony Blackburn stayed at Radio 3
for the day to tell people.
A bit like if you move house,
you stay at the house that you've just moved out of.
So when your mates come around, you can go,
I don't live here anymore.
So if you tuned in, he'd be like,
hello, it's me, Tony.
I'm not here anymore, though.
- That's not confusing at all.
- Go to the other station.
- Why can't they get someone else to say,
Tony doesn't live here anymore?
If you want him, he's on Radio 1.
- He's just a dedicated guy.
- That's great.
That's so good.
- There was also this incredible song
by the King singers who were very famous
at the time, acapella group from King's College, Cambridge.
They released a single to help people remember
all the new frequencies and you've got to look it up.
It's beautiful.
It starts just, I'll just give you the first line.
A new international agreement comes into effect
and many of the frequencies used for the BBC
will be changed at a time.
And it goes on like that.
- Is that the tune or have you just riffed that?
- It's a bit like that, you know?
So it's like acapella church music.
- Wow.
- But it told everyone what frequencies to go to.
- I reckon 'cause it said at a time,
that was a really weird way of saying it,
but the frequency for Radio 1 was 97 to 99.
So it was a rhyme if that was it.
- They were actually different frequencies at the time.
And so it's, and there wasn't that much rhyming in this,
I must say, much like a lot of Psalms.
- Do you remember the whole point of putting things
in a song to help you remember?
Did you make them rhyme?
- There's no way it makes it easier whatsoever.
- It's just a string of numbers,
sung by a bunch of choir boys.
- There were two, in fact, the world's only two
female fighter pilot aces, which I think to be an ace,
you sort of had to shoot down five planes or more,
vaguely varied.
But one of them was this woman called Lilia Litviak,
who was in one of the other regiments
that were flying for the Soviets in the Second World War.
And there was just an account where she recounted,
and people who were in the same regiment as her recounted,
which sounds really fun, where she was in this dogfight
with a German called Erwin Meyer,
and he'd shot down 12 planes before.
So he was well up there in ace territory.
And she defeated him really resoundingly.
And then it sounds like there's one of those nice moments
where he came right down, but he was okay.
But he was like, who the hell defeats me?
Introduce me to the man who just bested me.
And so they trotted him up.
Yeah, did you read about this?
- No, I'm just excited.
- You just, yeah, go on.
- So he got shot down, but he landed okay.
- He landed okay, and that way people
seemed to sometimes survive.
And demanded to be taken to the man who'd shot him down,
and was furious. - So presumptuous.
- I know, I know.
- I just think you don't automatically get to meet
the person who shot you down.
That's not, that's not my voice for you.
- What have you got to do?
- So follow themselves.
- Yeah, he was pissed off.
He was introduced to a woman, he said,
bugger off guys, come on,
where's the real guy, stop taking the piss.
- Very funny, okay, yeah.
- That happened to Mary Ellis,
who was another of the 88 girls.
She landed a Wellington bomber,
which was like a huge plane at the time,
at an RAF base.
And the staff said, oh, great, so where's the pilot?
And she said, oh, I'm the pilot.
And they point blank, refused to believe it,
to the extent of searching the plane,
'cause they thought they were being pranked.
Like there's no way this small one--
- And he also does that on like just normal domestic flights.
If it's a woman who comes up to Tammai,
he's like, come on, let's get the real one on.
- Ha, ha, ha, ha.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And then to Laura's mortgage,
she became a pilot after the war,
and she wasn't allowed to say,
this is your captain speaking.
- What?
- Because people would freak out
and presumably, you know,
storm the cockpit or whatever.
- Yes.
- Can I just say, I'm never quite sure on aeroplanes though,
when they say this is your captain,
I'm never sure if it's the person who's piloting
the plane speaking,
or the head of these steward and stewardessing staff.
- I think it's the captain.
- Yeah.
- This is the person piloting.
- When they say, this is the captain speaking,
generally speaking, it's the captain.
It's not the steward--
- Unless they say, this is the captain of catering speaking.
(laughing)
- You will receive your cups of tea very shortly.
I'm just texting at the moment to the airport actually.
- There's gonna be a little bit of turbulence
on the trolley this afternoon,
but we're gonna get your drinks to you.
- Yeah.
- Know who invented "Lost and Found" offices?
- Is it someone famous?
- Someone you've heard of.
- Conan Doyle, it's always Conan Doyle.
- Neither of those two,
but it's someone more famous, in fact,
than either of those two, I would say.
- Famous to Winston Churchill, Genghis Khan.
- Jesus.
- John Wayne.
- It was Napoleon Bonaparte.
- Oh, that's a good one.
- Oh, wow.
- Sorry, Andy.
- Napoleon won?
- Yeah.
- Cool.
- I can't remember what you're saying he invented now.
What, "Lost and Found"?
- "Lost and Found", yeah.
- It's been so long.
- So part of his thing, like,
Napoleon was bringing everything to Paris kind of thing,
like centralizing the whole country.
And as part of that,
he set up an office on the Île de Cité
for lost objects, and it still exists.
- Cool.
- And they have a cabinet of curiosities
that includes several human skulls,
a wooden leg, and two chunks of masonry
from the World Trade Center.
- Wow.
- Gosh.
- And can you believe that?
- Well, that's somehow got lost there.
- Well, that's the thing with "Lost and Found",
you don't know how it got there, right?
- How do they know the masonry
is from the World Trade Center?
- There must be clues.
- They've properly analyzed that, wow.
- I guess so.
- That was amazing.
- Yeah.
- And the modern system there was organized
by a guy called Louis Lapine,
who was known as the little man with a big stick.
And he was a French policeman,
and he was well known for sort of handling the crowds
in Paris whenever there was riots and stuff.
But he was also famous for accusing
friend of the podcast, Apollinaire,
of stealing the Mona Lisa.
Do you remember that story?
- Yeah, I'm sure you're very familiar.
- Yes, this was episode 352.
That was a very good one.
- Mm-hmm, thank you.
- I enjoyed that.
I think I was driving from Patney.
(all laughing)
- And had an accident.
It was very entertaining.
- But yeah, he was like really famous
and really like well respected.
But when this Mona Lisa--
- And a big stick.
- But you had a big stick, they had to respect him, yeah.
But when this Mona Lisa thing happened,
he lost all of his credibility, really.
- Mm-hmm.
- The police officer, Lapine.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- They say when you've got with the Mona Lisa,
'cause it's been stolen quite a few times,
but every time,
doesn't matter where you're coming from to steal it,
the painting can see you.
(all laughing)
- And this is actually a good hint.
The only way to get it without her seeing you
is going from behind.
- Oh, mm-hmm, yeah.
- Through the wall.
(all laughing)
- Don't take that advice out of context, please.
- Just on like early trends in general,
have you heard about Railway Mad Men?
- This was a--
- Oh, was that spin-off?
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- What was that?
- It was the opening theme.
- I was scared.
(all laughing)
- This was the thing,
like when trains were introduced and growing,
there was Railway Mania,
which was when everyone was just building trains,
across the UK in particular,
with no thought of whether they needed
to be a train, basically.
- No, they got given huge subsidies
for building train tracks and stuff.
- For a while, it was the most profitable thing you could do.
So people were just building mad little railways
out everywhere, thousands of miles.
But Railway Mad Men was a different thing.
People were worried, you know,
it's time of social change, blah, blah, blah.
And you were locked in the compartments,
that was another thing.
So people really freaked out at the prospect of train travel,
making people lose their wits,
specifically men as well,
and just go bananas and berserk, basically.
- Yeah, 'cause of the speed you were going?
- 'Cause of the speed.
- Also, it enclosed in tunnels a lot.
I think that was a problem.
- There was a lot of, yeah,
there's a historian called Amy Milne Smith,
and she did a fantastic report on this,
like a thesis about it.
So it was normal men who were completely fine,
but it was partly all the stuff you said, James,
and partly stress and overwork and anxiety of,
like just modern life, the modern condition,
meant that, you know, in 1869,
a gentleman suddenly took off all his clothing
and leaned out of the windows
of his carriage talking nonsense, you know.
And it was just apparently as soon as the train stopped,
or they got off the train,
they completely recovered their wits and they were fine.
It was literally the act of being on a moving train.
- Now, hang on, can I butt in with,
is there anything to do with sitting backwards on a train?
- Oh, don't know.
- 'Cause they looked into that scientific issue
whereby it could drive you mad
if you're always facing the wrong way
and going in a certain direction.
- Yeah, I know hate going backwards on a train.
- Feel sick, yeah, yeah.
- Do you?
- Yeah, none of you guys?
- I love it.
- Well, yeah, I don't, I'm not a fan of it.
So I think it could be linked to
a bit of madness that might come.
- I prefer it, I prefer sitting backwards on my--
- Do you?
- I actually prefer as well,
'cause if you crash head on to something,
then you have something to stop you from--
- Oh, y'all crash theory.
- Yeah, yeah.
And don't--
- You're backwards crash theory.
- Yeah, yeah, that's interesting.
- So you think, James,
that they should put all the seats in a car
backwards presumably?
- Well, I think I'm not the only person who thinks that.
- Really?
- I mean, that is safer.
- Except the driver's seat presumably.
(laughing)
- Just then all the cars reverse everywhere.
- Yeah, that's, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
You just lean around,
your arm over the other seat,
you do that classic move.
- Yeah, it's fine. - It's fine.
- Nice, nice.
- Yeah, everyone would drive a lot more slowly.
- Yes. - I'm safer.
- Do you guys know a right-handed bazaar called
Lasarusa, Talibula, Mina,
Verleni, Vavaca, Bulaima,
Kula, Kala, Kebalau?
- Yes, of course.
- Yeah, I have his shirt,
but it cuffs me a fortune to get his name on the pack.
(laughing)
- I do know him.
- Is it a real name of someone we have heard of?
- No, no, it's not.
It's just the longest cricketer's name ever,
but he's just a Pacific cricketer from Fiji.
He sounds like a great guy, largely 'cause of his long name.
His surname means returned alive
from Nankula Hospital at Lakemba Island in the Laugroup,
which is easier to pronounce if you want to do it that way.
- Last members for the Laugroup, please.
Last members for the Laugroup.
(laughing)
The bus is departing shortly.
- But yeah, he was great.
He used to, they played one international game,
Fiji, against New Zealand in the 1940s and '50s,
when he played and they made him serenade them
with South Sea songs after the match,
which he did, a game, a man, I know.
- You know that it took 120 years
after the invention of the cricket box
to event the cricket helmet.
- Okay, well I suppose that shows
where people's priorities lie, doesn't it?
Would you agree with that?
- I'd have thought, yeah, in terms of what you're keen on.
I suppose it, you've got a skull.
You don't have a penis skull.
- You don't have a genital exoskeleton.
- Exactly.
- Yes.
- We're hoping B's awesome, the guys can do something.
- It was 1850s.
- And the ball is generally going to be
in the lower part of your body.
- Amidships, yes.
- Well, it's to do with how bouncy the surface is,
as well, isn't it?
These days, it's very bouncy
because they're protected and stuff,
but if it was open to the elements all the time,
the bounce could be variable.
It's more likely to be lower and slower,
so you'd be more likely to take one in the plums
than in the noggin.
(laughing)
- Yeah, about 1850s was the Palmer's patent groin protector,
as it was called,
before that you'd just stuff a hanky down there
to sort of improvise it.
But it was only in the 1970s.
- Was your hanky made out of Kevlar or what?
- Yeah, yeah.
- If it's a very well-used hanky,
I think that can actually...
(laughing)
- By some point.
- Well, it's hard to fold.
(laughing)
A heavy head cold actually does protect you
in unpredictable ways, yeah.
- I suppose then you could have a sort of use the same one
as a kind of gumby hanky as the first crooked helmet.
(laughing)
It's very sort of snappy hanky tied in each corner.
- Would you ever commentate on cricket?
Well, have you done?
- I think I have done online, just briefly.
Yeah, it's quite an awesome responsibility,
to be perfectly honest.
If you're thinking other people can't see it,
then I've really got to.
- Yeah.
- You know, a bit like when you said it,
the drive in the left side,
I can't see it over my left shoulder.
Can you tell me if there's anything coming down that hill?
(laughing)
It's that sort of pressure, but for hours.
- It's days.
- You know, there could be several countries where,
and I've got to describe what's going on.
I think it's more high pressure work
than people imagine.
- I did read a description of what it's like
commentating on something like Test Match Special.
I can't remember who it was who,
well, like one of the famous commentators said,
look, this is the apex of human civilization.
You are sitting observing a nice cricket match happening.
People are sending in homemade cakes to you,
which you can then review on there
during a lull in play, basically.
- That the whole play is a lull.
- Yeah, it's sort of breathing space.
It's not like commentating on tennis or something like that,
which must be, you know, if you're a radio commentator
for tennis, that's horse racing or whatever.
- Exactly, you know, your word per minute is just--
- Exactly, yeah, yeah.
But this is, he was saying, I think, I think it was a he,
you are either, having to describe the immediate play,
which like, if there's something going on,
you need to explain that really clearly to the listener,
like you was saying, Miles.
And then during the quieter bits,
you're talking more about the overall shape of the game.
And during the really quiet bits,
you start talking about the grounds
and the whole history of cricket.
And so you've got three different modes
that you can switch between depending on what's going on.
- Oh, you've got mode full,
which is something completely unrelated.
Have you guys ever seen the clip of,
it's the Australian commentator,
and he tells the joke that ends,
it's a knick-knack, paddy-whack, give the frog a loan?
Right, look at Google.
- It's O'Keefe.
- It's O'Keefe, it's Kerio Keefe.
And he's, and I can't remember who he's commentating with,
but there's always a straight man
who's actually commentating on the cricket,
and then, you know, someone more jokey.
And he's trying to tell this very long joke.
And the other commentator is trying to get in the way
and explain what's happening in the cricket.
- And then every two minutes, he says, "And there's no run."
(all laughing)
- That's where you use your elbow
to test the temperature of bath water, for instance,
rather than your fingers aren't actually very sensitive
to people with their hands and go, "That's okay."
But it's not actually...
- I feel like my hands are sensitive to temperature.
I thought it was that your elbow
is the bit of you that's most like a baby.
- 'Cause I always wear gloves when it's cold,
I don't wear elbow patches, for instance.
- Oh, well, you should, Joe.
You lose so much heat through your elbows.
Yeah, yeah, but you're only,
but also you're down the skate park a lot,
with full protective equipment.
So they're elbow guards,
you just don't think of them as gloves.
- Of course.
- What's the sport where it's two villages versus another
and it is, there doesn't seem to be a limit on number,
it is basically getting a ball from...
- Yeah.
- There are two posts or something,
and it's going from one to...
- It's the oppies versus the downies,
or it's the uppers versus the downers,
and it's just like village football, really.
It's like old style.
- But there's no limit on numbers, are there?
- No, no.
Well, I think these days, the police limit, who can go.
(all laughing)
- Boo.
- Yeah.
- That's with, I mean, the sort of sports
where there's a flexibility, like I didn't realise,
lacrosse, there's a sort of set length,
or parameters where they went to the length
of the lacrosse pitch must be,
but actually there is no side boundary
that's entirely based on where you happen to be playing.
- Yeah.
- So you can set off running in one direction,
and you can just keep going until there's an obstacle,
essentially, that doesn't get out.
- Yeah, you know, yeah.
- We used to do that at school,
when I played football in the playground,
you would have one goal,
and you'd have two teams shooting towards the same goal,
and you would just get someone who would get the ball
and just run in the complete opposite direction
with the ball, so everyone had to chase after them.
- It's quite long routes.
- 'Cause there's no boundaries.
- But that is true in official lacrosse rules.
I think it's just women's lacrosse.
Weirdly, I think men's lacrosse does have boundaries,
but women's lacrosse--
- Men need boundaries to explain to them.
- Wasn't it something about, like,
the earliest games of lacrosse had an insane number of people?
- The American Lacrosse Foundation claims
the earliest games could have over 100,000 players.
- Stop it.
(laughing)
- And try commentating on that.
- State of those changing rooms, as well.
(laughing)
- It's like the handshake before the game is gonna take--
- It's a sort of roughy-toughy sport in America,
I think, isn't it, lacrosse?
We might associate lacrosse with girls' boarding school.
- Yeah, oh yeah.
- In America, they'd be surprised if men played rugby.
- Yeah, 'cause women's lacrosse and men's lacrosse
are just different games, aren't they?
They have different rules.
- Yeah, very different.
- Yeah, totally different.
- But you wouldn't hear phrases
like roughy-toughy in the men's lacrosse
that they play in America, for instance,
whereas you might in the female boarding school
lacrosse that you play here.
I've never heard roughy-toughy before.
- It might not exist as a phrase.
- Not a phrase, yeah.
- It might be some sort of post-surgery.
(laughing)
Think you should have bubbled up to the surface.
- On animals, golden hamsters can navigate their way home,
even when blindfolded and led in a complicated route
away from their nests.
- Can they?
How do they do it, do we know?
- No, I don't think we do know.
And it's really mysterious, isn't it?
'Cause some of these senses are not,
we don't fully understand.
So there's a thing called, what's it called,
the reed warbler bird.
And scientists wanted to disrupt,
they thought they must be using the Earth's magnetic field.
Okay, so we'll disrupt it.
So they attached small magnets
to these birds' foreheads in an experiment,
and they also blocked their view of the stars.
And, obviously, they couldn't navigate.
(laughing)
I don't really know what that proves.
- I mean, you see, the homing pigeons,
they used to use in the war to work out
where sort of various ships were in things.
Because they'd have their homing instincts
and they would know that they would fly
at a very particular pace.
And they would know what time they were released.
And so therefore, in the angle
from which they basically arrived,
they could work out how far away from that distance.
- Really?
- You'd work out the mass backwards.
So, right, they've arrived from over there.
They set off at this time, so they must be there for that.
- I usually travel 20 miles an hour.
- But how do they know where they set off from?
'Cause they've got a note on them.
Or what time they set off?
- Well, that information must be,
yes, I was gonna say that must be radio,
but then presumably the people were radioing
and say where they were.
But maybe there's so many,
maybe everything, any radio signal you send
can be intercepted, but not.
- I'm not gonna tell you where we are,
but it's 7.58 and I'm releasing the pigeons.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, make of that what you will.
(laughing)
- Good luck with that, Hitler, yeah.
Oh dear, Keith has gone off on one.
(laughing)
They were genuinely useful.
And they were sort of called up.
People that were sort of looked after pigeons
would suddenly, they would hide him on for them.
- Yeah, suddenly went from being complete weirdo loners
to very sought after people.
I'm so sorry.
- Oh my God.
- That's not how I feel about pigeon fancies, really.
- Half our audience are in the pigeon loft at the moment.
- I know.
I've got on satire, you know, Tatler,
we're all subscribers.
- Of course, yeah.
- That was meant to be satirical.
(laughing)
It was meant to be taking the piss.
- Can you explain what it is, sorry,
for those of us who grew up in Bolton?
- Sorry.
It's really not your area.
- It's not the world of interiors, but about people.
(laughing)
- So yes, Tatler for International Listeners
and anyone who's more civilized
is basically a magazine for high society.
It's like photographs of people
who aren't quite the royal family
'cause they probably can't get access to them,
but who are mates with the royal family having weddings.
- Is it Tatler that's got on the,
it's sort of on the back page.
There's always like a, it's not a high street honey,
but it's kind of a, it's like an eligible young lady
who is engaged.
I think maybe that's it is like,
look at this beautiful young woman.
She's just gone engaged.
You can't get together with her.
- Oh, right.
- Is that it?
- Probably that's it.
- I mean, it doesn't sound like
any other magazine would have that.
- Yeah, like Country Life has a sort of,
- Yeah.
- Made in the month.
- Maybe it's Country Life, I'm thinking of that,
but yes, it's a sort of an arty black and white photo.
- Yes.
- And sometimes I think it's like single and looking.
- Really?
- And free, available in your area,
all that kind of thing.
- This is the page three of--
- Except it's page like 128
'cause of all the adverts for posh watches in between.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And it's a monthly publication.
So it doesn't work in the way that sort of Metro used to have
I saw yesterday on the 802 Convox Law or something.
But it'd be like, I think I saw you back,
it must have been about four months ago.
(all laughing)
I think you admired my plowing.
- That's disgusting.
- My else.
(all laughing)
- Rude of me.
Yeah.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, so what about--
- Anyway, well, oh yeah, sorry.
It was founded by a guy called Richard Steele,
who called himself Isaac Bickerstaff when he edited Tatler.
And Isaac Bickerstaff, actually,
you'll remember the name, James.
- I do know the name, but why?
- It was because Jonathan Swift once published in 1708,
so another great, the other great probably satirist
of the time, published the Almanac Predictions of the Year
writing as Isaac Bickerstaff.
And he predicted the death of this astrologer
and society person called John Partridge.
And he predicted it on April the 1st.
It was an April Fool's joke.
And this poor guy, John Partridge,
who was a bit of a butt of jokes,
spent the rest of his life trying to convince people
he wasn't dead.
And Norm was turned up.
And he wrote a letter saying, "I'm not dead."
And Jonathan Swift said, "Well, that's a hoax,
'cause he is, you know, I've seen the body made."
- Oh, it was an unkind time.
A lot of sick burns being dished out all over the place.
Like saying, "One of the Irish are so hungry,
"why don't they just eat their babies?"
Which was during the famine.
And it was incredibly harsh satire.
- Imagine that, 'cause it sounds bad now,
but in the middle of the famine, it's actually even worse.
- It was bad.
- It's pitch black satire.
- I kind of draw attention to the famine,
and you know, the awful cruelty that has caused it.
But he's, you know, he's doing so through grief.
- These days, there's not enough nuance on Twitter
for people to get that.
I don't think if he'd have done it today.
- It's been sort of foremost satirist of your time,
just to be considered an edgelord,
with the absolute sort of brute force.
It's nuanced for heavens sake.
- One of you try, we're doing down the people.
I want one of you to tweet something
about a group of people eating babies today
and see what happens to you.
- I'm not on Twitter.
- So one of you two.
- On Twitter, it'll go down a storm these days.
I can show you that.
(all laughing)
- I could put it in a WhatsApp group.
- Just see.
- Yes.
- The Christmas one's gone quiet.
(all laughing)
- Just out of the blue.
Oh, what's Mars up to?
Oh.
- What are we thinking this year?
- Another pseudonym, John Barron.
Do you know this one?
- No. - John Barron, no.
- How do you know the name Barron?
- Barron.
- Is it Barron, or Barron, like, childless?
B-A-D-R-O-N.
- The Barron Knights.
- Who's a famous Barron these days.
- Barron Trump.
- Yes.
So Donald Trump's pseudonym, John Barron.
So when Forbes were doing the richest people list,
John Barron wrote to them saying,
oh, you've got to put Trump in here.
He's a billionaire.
- No.
- Yeah, and he's got a few others.
There's a guy called John Miller,
who once wrote to People magazine
who'd said something about Trump saying,
"Actually, Trump is a very compassionate husband,
and lots of beautiful women
are always asking to go out with him.
In fact, Madonna called and wanted to go out with him.
That, I could tell you."
- But what makes you think that's one of his pseudonyms?
- We, it came out in court later.
(laughing)
- Oh, that's devastating, mate.
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our outtakes.
If you have anything to say about them,
if you want to share any extra juicy bits of detail
that you know about them,
you can message us on podcast@qi.com.
Those emails go through to Andy,
and a lot of those emails then get taken over
to Drop Us a Line where we discuss them.
So send us your favorite facts, send us an anecdote,
send us anything that you think is worth sharing,
and hopefully it can make it onto Drop Us a Line.
Just a reminder, no such thing as a fish.com.
You got the ticket link for all of our upcoming gigs,
and two in particular,
which is the London Podcast Festival
that's gonna be happening near King's Cross at King's Place,
and that is the 5th and 6th of September.
So get your tickets now, and that's it.
We're gonna be back again with another episode
in a fortnight's time.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)