[Music]
Hi everybody, it's Andy and James here from No Such Thing as a Fish.
Hi, your favourite too.
[Laughs]
Shhh.
But, yes.
Now we're here with a little topper show announcement
because we've got some secret juicy gossip for you.
We sure have.
And that gossip is that we are going to be doing some live shows.
You didn't hear it from us.
But if you go to King's Place in London
on the 5th and 6th of September,
you can see not one, but two No Such Thing as a Fish live shows.
Dan and Anna will also be there for clarity.
Anna will not be there for clarity.
Yeah, sorry, yeah.
Dan will be.
And some very, very special guests.
Now, we have already booked one of these special guests
and I promise you, if I mentioned the name of that person right now,
we would sell out in seconds.
That's right.
And if it does sell out, there are streaming tickets available too.
You can watch the show live.
See what it's like when we're not rigorously and scrupulously edited.
Here, all the stuff we say that really should be edited out
by getting a streaming ticket.
And where do you get those tickets from, Andy?
I think if they just go to our website, there'll be a link.
No such thing as a fish.com.
Excellent.
Well, do that right now.
But in the meantime, it's time to say,
on with the podcast, on with the show.
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that before he was buried,
the poet Dylan Thomas was used as a poker table.
That doesn't feel very practical.
No.
The chicks are going to go everywhere.
And I imagine as a poet, you're wearing
a lot of ruffles, maybe a cravat.
You know, you're not going to be a smooth table.
No. OK.
So it's not his body that was physically used as the poker
table. Dylan Thomas, as a bit of backstory, had been in America
and he died on the 9th of November, 1953.
Let's get right to the, let's cut to the chase.
Was he born before he died?
I need to know all the context, Dan.
So yeah, it was really unfortunate.
He was 39 years old.
He was a big drinker.
There's a bit of mystery about what actually caused his death.
But there we have it, the facts.
He dies November, 1953.
His wife, Caitlin, decides she doesn't want him to be buried
in America.
She wants to bring him back home to Wales, his home country.
Yeah.
And so she puts him on a ship and he's in the hold.
And one night she's a bit disruptive upstairs
and she gets sent downstairs.
And it just so happens that she's
bunking up very near to his coffin.
And she notices that all the sailors gather around the coffin
and use it as the poker table.
And she thought he would have loved this.
Yeah.
So was it not obviously a coffin?
I think it might have been.
They might not have cared.
That's quite a macabre.
I would have tried to find another table
or just a packing crate or something.
Would you?
I would have gone out my way to find the coffin.
Yeah.
If you had there's a coffin on board.
I genuinely think when I go, if I could organize it
that my mates had a poker game on my coffin
and they didn't mind, then I'd be down for that.
It would be more golf for you, though, wouldn't it?
That's hard to play in a coffin.
Right.
You could be the last hole.
The 19th hole.
I'm hoping that I'm laid down face up, actually.
Apparently, like you said, there was some ruckus with Caitlyn.
I read that she was in a cabin with, and I quote,
some sort of glamor queen that she really didn't like.
And so she deliberately caused a ruckus
so that she would get kicked out of that cabin.
Yeah.
Yeah, having now read up about Caitlyn,
I wonder if that's true or if she was just generally causing
ruckus, because that was the thing about them.
They were sort of described as the prototype
Sid and Nancy of the sex pistols.
They were a couple that were destructive.
They'd get huge fights.
They would get drunk everywhere they went.
But what's crazy is that when Caitlyn got back,
she went on a pub crawl with the person who picked her up.
And Dylan was just left in the car park in the coffin
while they were getting pissed along the way in all the pubs
towards where his home was going to be.
Yeah.
Did you find the claim that he was buried in a banana-shaped
grave?
No.
OK, so we should say, also, most famous Welsh poet,
arguably, I'd say, ever?
For me, he is.
I mean, he's barred territory.
If someone asked me the name of a Welsh poet,
he would be the one.
Exactly.
And he certainly was barred from most of his local pubs.
Well, there is a claim, I read, that the grave digger was
Defan Mute, and he only knew that he was burying a man whose
favorite fruit was the banana.
So in tribute, he originally dug a banana-shaped grave
before being told off and told the grave digger.
Now, I just think if you're a professional grave digger,
you know that you very rarely get a banana-shaped coffin.
Yeah.
Do we know that his favorite fruit was banana?
Do you know, the original thing is so untrue that I haven't
even saw that yet.
I thought Defan Mute sounds like a Welsh name.
I thought that was a name.
So his death, Dan, you said that there was some weird things
about that.
Yeah.
There was the idea that he drank so much that the night
before he went into a coma, which then led to him going
to hospital and eventually dying,
he claimed to have drunk 18 whiskeys.
Also the line, say the line.
Supposedly his last words were, I've just drunk 18
straight whiskeys.
I think that's a record or something like that.
That's a great line.
But that's not true, is it?
He definitely said things after that.
I think he did say that, actually, in fairness.
But it was the day before and then the next day,
he did talk to people and said different things.
He said, God, kill for a banana right now.
So it was the doctor's fault, right?
So yeah, so he was sedated with some morphine.
And he went into a coma.
And he had pneumonia, which hadn't been diagnosed.
And that was the problem with the morphine.
But this is the interesting thing.
I think it's actually Dylan Thomas' fault.
Because he did make that joke about having
had all these whiskeys, right?
And then I believe his friend who'd overheard that,
when he was really ill, said to the doctor,
oh, well, he told me yesterday he'd had 18 straight whiskeys.
So the doctor very naturally assumes alcohol poisoning
and then gives him the morphine,
which puts him into the coma, which kills him.
So actually Dylan Thomas died of his own joke,
as well as medical misdiagnosis and all of that.
But basically it's because his friend said,
oh yeah, well, this is what he was saying.
- Well, it's possible he wasn't joking though,
because they went and interviewed the bartender
who was serving drinks at night.
And he said he didn't drink 18, absolutely not.
But someone pointed out that a shot in America
versus a shot back home is three times the amount.
So they think in his incredibly drunken state,
Dylan Thomas was doing math and worked out
how many that would have been back home, which was 18.
- Yeah, in fairness, the math was only three times six.
- But once you've had 18 whiskeys.
- He actually wasn't good at taking his drink.
He's got this reputation for being such a heavy drinker.
But I think people who knew him said actually,
he was kind of a lightweight.
So maybe he just seemed pissed a lot.
He had a famous sort of relationship slash,
what's an enemy ship?
- Frenemy?
- He was sort of a frenemy,
but without the fruit of it with Kingsley Amos,
who only met him once,
but used to write really awful things about his poetry.
- Okay.
- And Amos met him in 1951.
And he said he was an outstandingly unpleasant man
who cheated and stole from his friends
and peed on their carpets.
And he boozed a lot because it fitted his image as a poet
rather than out of any thirst or need.
- I think people, quite a lot of people
didn't really like him very much, even his friends.
- No, it's a shame if you like his poetry to read up on him
because it makes him quite unlikable, doesn't it?
- I think he considered himself to be a poet,
which meant he didn't need to get a proper job.
He could just sort of dilettantishly turn up at people's houses
and sleep on their sofas and urinate on their carpets.
Perhaps, I don't know.
But yeah, like one of his really good friends,
Norman Cameron, he wrote, "Who invited him in?
What was he doing here?
That insolent little ruffian, that crappulous lout?
When he quitted a sofa, he left behind a smear."
- Oh dear.
- That's what his friends thought of him,
what of his enemies.
- Right, but his fans kind of loved it, right?
They loved this image of a drunken poet
who was living up to that romantic idea
that they're sitting in a shed with a glass of whiskey,
writing these incredible lines.
And in his final eight years, you know, he died 39,
as I said, in the final eight years, he wrote six poems.
He spent basically the last period of his life
going on tours and talking and reading out his poems.
He became an orator as opposed to a writer.
And people would go because it was quite rock and roll.
Is Dylan Thomas gonna swear at someone in the crowd?
Is he gonna drunkenly fall off the stage and pass out?
- Is he gonna leave a smear on the sofa?
(all laughing)
- The curtain comes up and says,
"That's a sofa on the stage, get it Dylan!"
But he was kind of, you know, people were into that.
- I think he was less hard living in lots of ways.
So he lived for a while in a place called Lawn
and the Thomas family GP, the doctor,
wrote he didn't do any womanizing.
He was pretty sober.
He was very respectful.
He started the day by helping his dad
with the times crossword every morning.
Apparently his capacity for drink, I'm quoting now,
was very limited compared with the average hearty.
He couldn't drink very much.
Three or four pints was his absolute limit.
But then of his wife, Caitlyn, the doctor wrote,
"Caitlyn is a nymphomaniac and the first class bitch."
(all laughing)
- Is that a medical diagnosis back then?
She does seem a tough character.
But I really didn't know the thing
I found most unbelievable about him is
you say that he only wrote six poems
or whatever in his last seven years.
Really, he wrote all of his best poetry pretty much.
Everyone agrees by the time he was 19.
Isn't that insane?
I was a child when I was 19.
I was like, "You're thinking such immature stuff."
And that's why it's kind of nonsense.
I used to love him when I was a teenager
because I thought, "Well, this must mean something amazing."
But it was really heartening to read
all of these reviewers write about him and say,
"The words are beautiful,
"which is what's so fun about reading him,
"but no one knows what he's on about."
- He also, 'cause we were calling him a poet,
but he also wrote some pretty seminal other pieces.
Like he wrote "Under Milkwood," which was a play
which is still sort of known today.
- I did it at school.
- Did you really?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think people do, don't they, ladies?
- Who did you play?
- Sorry, no, for my GCSE English, I had to learn it.
- Okay, right, yeah, nice.
- You played a tree, admit it, you were one of the trees.
- But there's a lot of milk under me.
- You guys know AJP Taylor?
- I only know the name as well.
He was a really famous 20th century historian,
like mega famous at a time when historians were rock stars.
Anyway, Dylan Thomas befriended his wife, Margaret,
and--
- Euphemism?
- Well, she definitely had the hots for him.
And Dylan Thomas went to stay on the sofa
and did a lot of, like he would stay for a month.
And AJP Taylor liked to keep a barrel of beer in the house.
That was just his nice thing.
But he hated having Dylan Thomas to stay
'cause he would drink supposedly 15 pints a day
and he'd constantly have to be replacing his barrel.
And Taylor's wife, Margaret,
fell absolutely besotted with Dylan Thomas.
She spent all her money on him.
She wrote him erotic letters.
She persuaded AJP Taylor to buy a house
for 2,000 pounds for Dylan Thomas.
And Taylor said, "Okay, fine, if you stop giving him money,"
which she did not.
And then she bought him another house.
- Jesus Christ.
- He does sound like a really annoying guy to have to stay.
- I read one anecdote about him.
He went out drinking with novelist Philip Lindsay
and got his penis stuck in a honeypot.
(all laughing)
- We need the poo take.
- Great thing about this is in Andrew Lycet's biography
and it's kind of mostly there and not really anywhere else.
But it was from people who were there who said it happened.
But no one knows why he did that.
- No.
- Was it a honey trap?
(all laughing)
- They said on the same occasion,
he pushed a shirt button up his nose and couldn't get it out.
(all laughing)
You go into the A and E and you're like,
"Yeah, is this button thing?
"Can you get the button thing out, please?"
"Sir, there appears to be something."
"No, no, just the button."
(all laughing)
- I actually haven't just said, "Winnie the Pooh,"
I only know Winnie the Pooh-sized honeypots.
Do they come smaller?
- Wait, does Winnie the Pooh have massive honeypots?
- Yeah, his head gets stuck in them.
- Oh, yeah.
Maybe Dylan Thomas was very well endowed
and that's what kept the women falling in.
- But the shape of a honeypot is,
it expands as it gets towards the base, as it were.
It's not like a honey jar.
I could understand him getting his penis stuck in a honey jar.
- I was imagining a honey jar.
- It's a set honey or runny honey.
- You know, when you go to a travel lodge
and you get those tiny little jars of honey.
(all laughing)
- We're gonna have to ask you
to leave the breakfast buffet.
(all laughing)
- Everyone's got their own sized honeypot.
Yeah, it's full of tantalising details about biography.
It's amazing, 'cause he's spoken to everyone
who ever knew him, but people just give memories
without elaboration.
So there's those two, there's, on one occasion,
he managed to stab himself in the eye
while eating a plate of meatballs.
No, no further details.
How do you do that?
- How do you do that?
- And then someone else said there was a particular period
where he had to deal with his rubber fetishism.
No more on it.
- That's it, that's it, that's all we get.
- What did he do with rubber?
- Now, he's a very important poet.
He is part of the poet's corner in Westminster Abbey,
which is reserved for some of the greats,
it's Shakespeare and so on.
He originally wasn't in there.
And it all comes down to Jimmy Carter,
President Jimmy Carter, who lobbied for him to be in there.
- Why?
- He loves him to the point where he went
to certain bits of Wales just to be around the area
that Dylan Thomas would have been in.
Even wrote a poem called A President Expresses Concern
on a visit to Westminster Abbey by Jimmy Carter.
- No way.
- Gosh.
- That makes me like Dylan Thomas again,
having just gone off him.
Jimmy Carter liked him.
- Yeah, 'cause you're a massive Carter fan, yeah.
- Yeah.
What a weird presidential, like,
is that what happens on state visits?
- He campaigned a bit harder to get himself re-elected.
- Exactly.
- Well, it happened in '82,
so maybe he worked on it post-presidency,
but it was on that trip that he said, "Well, it was old."
- I can imagine Donald Trump at the moment
is trying to get Barney the big purple dinosaur
in Westminster Abbey.
- We'll do it, we'll do it.
Lawn, this place where he lived,
his local pub was a place called Brown's Hotel.
It was bought recently by, guess who?
- The game.
- The board makers.
- Sorry.
- Okay, give us a clue.
- What, the TV show?
(laughing)
- Why in a two runny skirt?
- No, what was Dylan Thomas?
He was a man behaving badly.
- Yeah.
- Oh, is it Martin Clues?
- It was Neil Morrissey.
- Oh, really?
- The other man behaving badly bought his local.
- Really?
- And Dylan Thomas was a man behaving badly,
and Neil Morrissey for international business
was about 30 years ago
in a second club called Mem Haven Badly.
- Yeah.
- That's a great fact.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that six out of 10 lakes are in Canada.
- That's amazing.
- Out of all the lakes in the world.
- That's wild.
- 60% are in Canada.
- It's big, Canada.
- It is big, but it's not 60% of the world's.
- No.
- It's a lamb ass.
It's a disproportionate number of lakes.
- So if you wake up after a big old
Dylan Thomas-style bender,
and you look and there's a lake there,
you're more likely than not in Canada.
- That's right.
- Yeah.
- Do we know how many and why?
- We do.
900,000 and geology is the short.
- No further questions.
- No, I got this on a great substrate
by a guy called Thomas Pueyo.
And basically, at the bottom, you've got the Great Lakes,
sort of celebrity lakes.
- Yeah.
- And then there's this line stretching across the country,
above which it's just monstrously full of lakes,
just lakes everywhere, like Thoreau Brick.
And it's because there's a region near the coast,
further up near the coastal mountains, which is lower,
'cause the mountains kind of depressed land around them
with their lamb mass, didn't know mountains did that.
And everywhere else in the world,
or most other places, these depressions,
they turn into river valleys, water flows along, right?
But Canada is very far north,
so it rains less, so there's less water.
And it's also to do with the ice sheets
that dug these huge holes in the ground.
And that leads to lakes when the ice retreats.
Do you know what I mean?
You've got basically lake-shaped masses everywhere.
- Yeah, it was the Laurentide ice sheet, wasn't it?
And that also formed Niagara Falls and the Great Lakes.
So it was a biggie.
And it might also have given us Noah's Ark.
So apparently the collapse of that ice sheet
caused the flooding of the Gibraltar,
Straits of Gibraltar, loads of water going
into the Mediterranean Sea, huge floods everywhere
about 8,000 years ago, and maybe all the myths
that we have about floods in all different cultures
have flood myths, maybe due to that collapse.
Love it.
- That's amazing.
It's crazy.
So 900,000 lakes in Canada, you're saying Andy.
Manitoba is an area that has 100,000 of those lakes.
And only 10,000 of those lakes have been named.
As of 2017, the number will have gone up,
but they're trying to give names
to every single lake that's out there.
- Can we campaign?
- Well, here's the thing to what have a lake named after us.
Doesn't work like that.
- Fish Lake.
- Well, this is a problem that there's not a big group
that names the lakes.
There's one main guy and then he's got a few assistants.
- What?
- Yeah.
- Well, that's why they haven't gone around
to name them all yet.
- It's been very slow.
He'll name like seven a year, but that's gone up now
with the assistants.
- Maybe as slow as Dylan Thomas writing poetry.
Is this guy just going around doing rock star shows
and saying, "I named lakes"?
- Exactly.
The thing he says is he gets a lot of calls
on Valentine's Day with people saying,
"Can I in a romantic gesture name this lake
"after my partner or girlfriend or boyfriend or whatever?"
And he says, "No, it doesn't work like that."
- Is he stressed that all these lakes don't have names
or is he relaxed about it?
- He's relaxed, he's taken his time.
What they're doing is basically naming it
after fallen soldiers from World War II and World War I.
And it's important work
because if you happen to have an accident at a lake,
how do you find it if there's no name?
- Dan, if it's important work,
maybe he should be trying to name more than seven
every year.
- He has, there was one year where they named 2,000.
Like it's with it because he got assistants in,
assistants came in.
- Pegas can't be choosers.
I think if I say, "Can you name your lake Polina?"
He shouldn't be saying, "No, I have to do it
"after this other thing instead."
- I think he should be accepting these names
because he needs 20,000 of them.
- He needs a lot of, he needs a lot.
And in fact, there's only been one exception so far.
One living person, when an Olympic gold medalist
in hockey was given a lake name,
he sort of got put ahead of all the fallen soldiers.
- They'll do anything for hockey players,
the Canadians, right Ney?
I think he needs to be sacked.
Sorry.
- Do you know what the most common lake name
in the United States of America is?
- Oh, is it, is it guessable?
- Maybe.
- Is it Big Lake or Deep Lake?
- No, but you're getting there.
It's very descriptive.
- Round Lake.
- Wet Lake.
- That's the closest.
It's Mud Lake.
- Really?
- Yeah, there are 900 Mud Lakes in America,
but they're endangered really,
'cause they're all getting renamed.
So Michigan, for instance, had 300 Mud Lakes,
but 71 of them have been changed in the last few years.
- Why are they changing them?
Is it not politically correct?
- Well, one reason that you want to,
like Mud Lake isn't very nice,
but number two, like Dan said,
you need to be able to tell exactly where something is.
So if you've got 700 Mud Lakes,
and you say I've injured myself next to Mud Lake,
what are they going to do?
- Yeah, you're right.
There are reports, and again,
this is at the level of Dylan Thomas
was buried in a banana shape.
- Oh God.
- It's great.
Well, there's a lake in Canada called Lake Minnewenka,
but that is true.
Some reports say it's the smallest lake in Canada,
and it appears not to be.
I think there are some smaller,
but it is home to a drowned village,
which is called Minnewenka Landing.
- Cool.
(laughing)
'Cause that was named after someone who drove a mini.
- It was when Tom Cruise lands his plane.
That's why he radiates into the control tower as a joke.
(laughing)
- All this depends on how you define a lake, right?
- Yeah.
- Because there's a thing called Lagos, L-A-G-O-S,
which is like a research.
It's like the Wikipedia of lakes,
where you go to if you wanna know anything
about lakes in North America,
but they define a lake as something that is one hectare
in area, surface area.
So that's about two football fields.
But if you were to count lakes that are like one hectare,
so half that size,
then the number of lakes in Canada
goes up to 3.5 million.
- Oh my goodness.
- That's getting stupid.
I was supposed to get a puddle.
- That guy at the naming office is gonna be,
probably still relaxed.
We've got time.
- And the other scientific definition of a lake
is it needs to have an aphotic zone.
So that's an area deep enough where
plants can't grow, 'cause they don't get enough light.
- Oh really?
- Okay.
- That's supposed to be the level between a pond and a lake.
- There's, interestingly, on the definition of a lake,
there's also the bigness of lakes.
So Lake Superior, one of the great lakes,
and the great lakes are all shared
between the US and Canada, except one, Lake Michigan.
Lake Superior is the largest lake on earth,
but only if you don't count the Caspian Sea,
which is about five times bigger.
And it's really interesting, the Caspian Sea controversy,
because Caspian Sea is technically a lake, I believe,
as in it's not connected to the sea,
but it has higher salinity than almost any other lake.
So it's a huge political debate
between Azerbaijan, Iran, Kazakhstan, Russia,
Turkmenistan, which all border this lake/sea,
'cause if it's a lake, you split it equally.
So that's why all the great lakes are split equally
between the US and Canada.
And it's usually important,
'cause it's got massive natural resources.
It's got loads of loads of oil deposits in it,
mineral deposits.
And so Iran, which has a very short coast on the Caspian,
is saying, no, it's definitely a lake.
Definitely a lake,
'cause I want to split it equally with the rest of you.
- Whereas if it's the seashore,
you own a distance away from the seashore.
- Depending on your length of coastline.
Exactly.
So then, you know, Russia's saying, or Kazakhstan,
which has a huge coastline,
is saying, this is bullshit.
You can't take a fifth of the oil in it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Wow.
- So which side do you fall on?
- And when would we get a resolution to...
- No, honestly, turn.
I think they got a few other things to iron out
in that region.
- Yeah, there was a massive meeting in 2018
called the Convention on the Legal Status
of the Caspian Sea, where all the countries met,
and they were there for weeks,
and they concluded it's neither a lake nor a sea.
- Oh, great.
- It's a pond.
Here's a lake.
This is also in the United States of America.
It's called Crater Lake,
and the Kalmath people who live around it
haven't looked at it for more than 7,000 years.
- No.
How close do they live?
- They don't know.
(all laughing)
- Do they fall in?
- No, they don't fall in.
So it's basically, it's a taboo.
- Wow.
- And it's, we think down to an eruption
that happened 7,700 years ago,
and then they preserved these stories
of this myth that's happened,
and that would be 300 generations of word of mouth
have kept this story going.
- Don't look at the lake.
- And they still don't look at the lake, yeah.
- What if you accidentally look at the lake?
- Another eruption, probably.
- Someone must have.
- No one's done it.
We don't know.
(all laughing)
- Well, we'd know.
We would know.
- We would know, yeah?
- Wow.
- That's crazy.
- Some lakes swing from side to side.
- Really? - Like a banana.
- Well, they're called banana lakes.
No, they're not.
- Okay.
- This is amazing though.
They're these things called sashes,
and the most famous one is in Lake Erie,
which is one of the great lakes.
But basically, it happens if there's a really strong wind
that's going in one direction on a lake,
and it keeps pushing the water up to one end,
and then the wind suddenly stops,
then the water, you can imagine like in a bath,
swings backwards, and it does extraordinary things.
Like in 2008, there were 16 feet high waves in Lake Erie
that flooded, it's Buffalo, I think,
in New York that always gets flooded.
In 1844, there was a 22 foot high Seish wave,
which caused this flood in Buffalo,
which destroyed the town completely,
just from this swinging lake.
- Crazy.
- 78 people died, it stopped the Niagara Falls from flowing,
'cause it dammed it up, 'cause like the force of all the water
pushed the ice to the top of Niagara Falls,
and stopped it flowing.
- What?
- Just from this swinging lake, isn't that cool?
- That's very cool.
Not the deaths, but yeah, the other stuff.
- Yeah, it was a long time ago.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- Canada is so big that the southernmost point of Canada
is closer to Brazil than it is
to the northernmost point of Canada.
- I don't believe you.
- Well, you've got to.
- Okay.
- Maths.
- How do we resolve this then?
(all laughing)
- We need a conference.
- I mean, yeah, only because I've seen maps.
- I mean, that's, it's about, there's not much in it,
it's about 10 kilometers in it, but it's a lot.
- 10 kilometers in it?
- Yeah.
- That's so close.
- Southernmost point of Canada to northernmost point
of Canada is 4,620 kilometers.
- Right.
- To Brazil, from the southernmost point of Canada,
it's 4,630.
- Yeah.
- That's like how my house in Margate is closer to Belgium
than it is to London.
- Yeah.
- That's wild.
- And it takes you hours and hours and hours
to get here every day.
(all laughing)
- I should stop going via Belgium.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that
at one Spanish football stadium,
they will stop you from eating sunflower seeds,
but they won't stop you from smoking.
- That is so weird.
Is it?
Are you allowed to smoke sunflower seeds, life hack?
- Oh, good thinking.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, roll up.
(all laughing)
- Actually, you're not really supposed to smoke,
but they don't enforce that ban.
- Oh, okay.
- But they are enforcing that ban on sunflower seeds,
and that's because if you go to Spanish football games,
you will often bring sunflower seeds with you as a snack.
They're called pipas,
and this team called Elche has decided to ban them
because people keep,
you kind of, you crack them open and eat the seeds inside,
and then you throw the shells away,
and the shells, they clog the drains,
they clog the pipes,
they rot and deteriorate the seeds,
the pigeons come, rats come,
and they're having to basically redo the entire stadium,
and part of the reason is because these sunflower seeds
are just all over the place and they're rotting,
and they're making everything ming in.
- Yeah, there's too many for them to clean up,
so as you arrive,
you just crack in shells underneath your foot,
go into your seats.
It's pretty amazing,
such a tiny thing causing such chaos.
- And this was in the times that I read this,
and one of the fans said this is the best thing
they could have done,
and now they just have to enforce the ban on smoking.
(laughing)
- Yeah, yeah.
Is it Spain-wide that these things are enjoyed?
- It's common throughout Spain, yeah.
- Really interesting,
'cause it's quite a hippie-ish, quite healthy thing,
I imagine, like, oh, I'm just eating some sunflower seeds.
- This is a really salty.
- Oh, okay, they're very snacky.
- This is the thing that I discovered,
it's this whole global culture that we do not have
in Britain of sunflower seeds being such a popular snack,
and they're all these countries,
so Spain is one of them,
where they're really popular,
across Eastern Europe,
Eastern European listeners,
writing, "Confirm how many sunflower seeds you eat a day."
China, the Middle East, Russia,
they're like this big deal snack,
and so I think in China, you have them in the shells,
and it's this great meditative experience,
the one girl was saying that you put it in your mouth,
you have to get the sunflower seed out of the shell.
- Yeah, you kind of do it with your teeth on it, yeah.
- So the little gray thing that I get
when I buy a packet of sunflower seeds
is not a sunflower seed,
it's actually, that's the kernel.
- Yeah, it's a kernel.
- A de-hulled kernel,
whereas people here are eating the naked seeds,
which are the black and white striped, they're bigger.
- Better inside, yeah.
- That is a sunflower seed.
- Yeah, and it's pretty amazing.
I went to the National Gallery the other day
to look specifically at Van Gogh's sunflowers, right?
- I was research with this fact.
- No, it's completely separate.
I was just, I thought, "God, it's around the corner,
why have I not been there?"
And I went, stood, and just stared,
and each flower, there's 11 flowers,
they contain about 2000, between one and 2000 seeds.
That would have been edible, you know, what was in the pot.
I find that fascinating.
I've never thought about it in that way before.
- No, me neither.
If you're really hungry
and you've got a sunflower growing in your kitchen,
scrape off the top, if it's reached ripeness,
and get some seeds out.
- There's like a TikTok trend at the moment
where people are like roasting entire sunflower heads
and eating them.
- Ooh. - They're really.
- I mean, it's just classic TikTok.
- That doesn't seem so.
- Everyone's a food expert
until you actually try what you're eating,
and then it's disgusting.
- Well, people do seem to rave about them.
And I was reading in China,
the way they harvest them is really cool.
So people go through with digmachetes
or massive pairs of scissors,
and they chop the heads off all the...
Yeah, or nail scissors, whatever you've got to have.
- Like you're opening a department store.
- Yeah, exactly, a lot of ribbons to cut.
They chop the heads off each individual sunflower,
but then they pick up the heads,
they spin them upside down,
and they plonk them back on top of the stalk,
and they leave them there for another week to dry.
And that's 'cause it saves having to dry them
in a certain space.
So you'll sometimes go to a big sunflower field in China
and be like, "Oh, the flowers are upside down."
- Yeah. - They've all been decapitated.
- They've all been decapitated
and had their heads put on upside down.
- Who did this?
- That's amazing. - What a psycho.
- So I should just say L.J., by the way,
the football team, they're from Alicante.
They were promoted to La Liga last season.
And I read as much as I could about them.
There's not a great deal of interesting stuff,
apart from the Ketman, the head Ketman is called Pepito,
whose name is Spanish for pumpkin seed.
- Lovely, lovely.
- It's not quite right, is it?
- No. - You haven't quite
got that almost all the time. - Almost got it.
I saw his name and I was like,
"That really looks like it means sunflower seed."
- Yeah. - But unfortunately,
no, 'pipas' is the sunflower seed,
which also means blowjobs in Greek.
- Golly. - Oh, cool.
- Well, that wasn't,
surely that one would have led to any confusion.
A load of Spanish football fans turn up at Panofinaikos.
- You've got to crack it open with your teeth.
(laughing)
- They are known these seeds as Spain's football foreplay.
I don't know if you can cross that phrase here.
But what is Britain's football foreplay?
- Pies. - You guys go to football with pies.
- Pies of pies. - Nice pie.
- As in, that's just foreplay in general, isn't it?
A nice steak and kidney pie.
- Scotch pies, they're called.
- What is a Scotch pie?
- Scotch pie is,
probably if you go to football in the South of England,
you don't really get this stuff,
but certainly in the North of England,
they're kind of made of pastry, like water pastry,
and they usually have mutton in them, lots of potato,
not so much meat, absolutely delicious.
- Yeah. - Yum.
- And they were supposedly despised by the Scottish Church,
because they were considered a sumptuous meal
and very similar to English pies.
So the Scottish Church tried to ban Scotch pies for a while,
but they never managed.
- I would say keep your beaks out, guys.
I just think that's not the jurisdiction to...
- Like the Church tends to get involved
in lots of different things, doesn't it?
Historically, especially the Scottish Church.
- I just think that's a bit like Jimmy Carter
getting involved in Dylan Thomas' posthumous reputation.
I just think, come on, prioritise.
- Not your area. - You've got perks to run.
- Actually, it was because of the Church,
I think that sunflower seeds came to be.
- Well, unless you're saying that God made them.
- Exactly.
Sorry, yeah, that we started eating sunflower seeds,
because, so they were huge in Russia first.
Russia was like 100 years ahead of the rest of us,
mainly in terms of turning them into oil,
which is where it's so valuable.
And it was basically because during any kind of fast,
Christian fasting or Lent or anything like that in Russia,
then any kind of vegetable oils were banned,
and then Peter the Great or his minions have discovered
that you could get oil from sunflower seeds.
- It was Peter the Great when he, you know,
he did his European tour, he saw them in like the Netherlands
or something and brought them back.
- He did, yes.
And then some peasant in Russia in the 19th century,
just working in the fields peasant,
built a machine to get oil out of them.
And because they were new oil,
the Church hadn't managed to create in its list
the name sunflower oil. - It's so funny.
- And so everyone just drenched their food
with sunflower oil during Lent.
That's why it was so popular.
- And now Ukraine and Russia is by far the biggest producers
of sunflower oil in the world, like by a billion.
- I read that, it's like, more than half the global production
is there. - Yeah.
And that's why Ukraine like the sunflower
is a symbol of Ukraine.
- I see, I didn't know that.
- It was used as well for mopping up basically
a lot of the radioactive waste during the Chernobyl disaster.
- Was it?
- Yeah, so the stems,
they noticed that when they put them into bodies of water,
that it would take up a lot of the radioactive elements
and then they could bring it away
and then they could discard it in a better way.
But so, sunflowers are planted largely
around nuclear radioactive areas in Chernobyl and use.
- Gosh, sunflowers are useful.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Famous pop culture person who eats sunflower seeds.
- Okay.
- Cardi B.
- Good shout.
- Someone that you guys have,
a character that you guys will be familiar with.
- Can you give us a clue?
- Olex Snoopy, a fictional character.
- Yeah, 1990s.
- 1990s fictional character.
- The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air.
- Very good, no.
- Dennis the Manus.
- No.
- Oh yeah, cartoon or real?
- Real.
- Zach from "Saved by the Bell".
- Okay, Blobby, Blobby, Blobby.
- British or American?
- American.
- Okay.
- One of the Simpsons.
- No, but one of the biggest shows of the 1990s.
- Friends.
- People are yelling this at home, not friends.
Something that Dan would like due to his other podcast.
- A weird equippity thing.
- Come on guys, the truth is out there.
- Oh, the ex-Fox Mulder loved Sunflower Seeds.
- Fox Mulder, he eats Sunflower Seeds all the way through it.
And he had to stop in the later series
because according to him,
it's hard to act with Sunflower Seeds.
But it was the creator, Chris Carter,
who would eat Sunflower Seeds.
And he kind of passed it on to the character.
But David D'Covny, who played Mulder,
wants people to know that he doesn't like
Sunflower Seeds and he also does not wear ties.
So fans are discouraged from sending him either.
- Poor guy, so he's forced to eat the Sunflower Seeds
constantly.
- And wear lots of ties as well.
Poor guy.
- I mentioned Van Gogh earlier.
There's another very famous art piece
which is called Sunflower Seeds.
Do you remember that?
- Ai Wei Wei.
- Ai Wei Wei, 2011.
So this is extraordinary.
He handcrafted Porcelain Sunflower Seeds
with his team, there was 1,600 people,
and they made 100 million of them.
- It feels like he's the guy to solve
the Canadian Lake naming dilemma.
Like they can just bang through that.
- If these 1,600 people, I'm sure, you know,
it's making a very important political point
and stuff like that.
But it's a long time to be making tiny ceramic seeds.
- Oh, I see, I think it's a bit of a waste of time.
- I mean, being a podcaster is a waste of time.
I'm fully accept that, but I just think...
- We've made 100 million identical episodes of this show.
But it has been useful, I would say.
Yes, what's the point?
- They weren't identical, were they?
They were slightly, I remember this.
- Oh, 'cause they handcrafted.
- I was talking about the episodes of the show,
which is why I remember the slight differences.
- Well, they put, and so they were first displayed
at the Turbine Hall at the Tate.
And if you've ever been there, you know what that's like.
- Yeah, you get these huge exhibits
that are really famous every year.
I went to that one, actually.
- Did you?
Did you get to walk on the seeds?
- No, I didn't.
- 'Cause I got to walk around on them.
- So to begin with, and it raised up about 10 centimetres
off the ground, that's how many seeds are where the height
that it reached to.
- Only 10 centimetres?
- Well, it's a big, it's huge hole.
- Yeah, it's a massive hole.
- Not very much.
- Put it in a smaller room, have 'em up to your neck.
That's what I would have done.
- Good idea.
- Like, that's exciting.
- No, that's hard.
So was the point he's making is that we're all different?
- No, the point he was making, I believe.
Well, there's lots of different points like much art,
but I think a lot of it.
And this is why the trampling was so important.
And I remember being so disappointed
is about the oppression and repression of the Chinese state
and all these people, these, you know,
billions of people in China being treated
just like one random identical sunflower to another.
Don't have your own.
- And I think Chairman Mao used to say
that the people of China were sunflower seeds.
And his idea is like, if you get all
of these hundred million seeds together,
then they make something very big and important.
But by themselves, they're kind of...
- Oh yeah, that's a different interpretation.
There you go.
- I don't know.
Like you, I went and was slightly disappointed
that I wasn't allowed to walk on them.
- And you weren't allowed, to begin with,
you were allowed to walk on them and then health and safety
because they thought little micro dust
was coming through from all the crunching.
But it worked out that the equivalent sunflower seeds
that he made, that Van Gogh would have to paint,
would be 50,000 flowers.
- Okay.
- Because it's about 2,000 seeds per herd, right?
- About 2,000.
I think that math, right?
I was 18 whiskies deep by the time I did that, but yeah.
- That's doable.
- Baseball players also love sunflower seeds, apparently,
in the USA.
There is this question of why baseball players
are constantly chewing.
'Cause they are.
If you look at them in the dugout, they're always eating.
So there's one big theory is that the game is boring.
- My daughter, when she gets bored,
she always asks, can I have a snack?
- Right, the theory is that's what they're doing.
You know, they're sporting guys.
They will burn it off, but basically,
it's a dull game to watch and to participate in.
- I really like lots of sports,
but I do find it difficult to sit in a stadium
through an entire baseball game.
- Right, there we go.
- I think there really is a divide in the world,
which no other sport has,
between people who understand why baseball's appealing
and are obsessed with it, and friends obsessed,
and the rest of us who think,
"Well, but it sounds like all the players are on our side."
- Well, they...
They know from the inside.
But they used to chew tobacco.
That's another theory why people,
they might choose sunflower seeds now,
'cause you don't chew tobacco anymore.
- But chewing tobacco could give them some buzz.
- And they had another big advantage.
When baseball players chew tobacco,
they could slobber their juice onto the ball.
(laughing)
- Interesting.
- And Phil and Thomas used to slather his juice
onto the surface of the...
(laughing)
- If you slobbered on the ball, it would become darker,
and that would be harder for the batter to see.
So it's a tricky, sneaky way
of making a camouflage ball.
- I understand this against the rules to do that.
- The rule was changed in 1920 to disallow ball defacing.
That was what it was defined as.
So maybe that's another reason
for the rise of the sunflower seed,
apart from the unbearable tedium of watching this game.
(laughing)
- Okay, speaking of tedious American sports,
I mean, I absolutely love American football,
but what snacks do you associate with American football?
- Weeners, get your weeners.
- Hot dogs, oh, that's the same as a weener, isn't it?
- So hot dogs, for me,
I would more have hot dogs at a baseball game, probably.
- Candy gloss.
- Nutshells.
- Yeah, all these are good answers.
- Caviar.
- Caviar is correct.
From the Caspian Sea, the belugas.
No, it's, I think for me, it's chicken wings.
- Okay.
- If you're watching the Super Bowl,
everyone in America basically eats chicken wings.
And this all came due to an accidental
over-order by a company in Buffalo.
They accidentally ordered a load of chicken wings
and they didn't know what to do with them.
And so they came up with a new recipe,
which was Buffalo wings.
So you basically put chili sauce and butter together
and it makes this sauce and they're absolutely delicious.
And this bar called Anchor Bay, they started making them.
And then a little bit later,
the Buffalo Bill's NFL team made it to the Super Bowl
for three years in a row.
And everyone associated the Buffalo Bill's team
with Buffalo wings.
And suddenly chicken wings became like the food
for the Super Bowl.
- So it's all a big mistake.
- It's a whole different thing.
But 1.6 billion chicken wings are eaten
on Super Bowl Sunday every year.
- Jesus.
I think, 'cause Americans get some shit sometimes
from the rest of the world
about certain elements of their culture.
But one of the greatest cultural things
that exists in America,
which I didn't really know that it was a thing,
is tailgating.
- Tailgating.
- Or the tailgate.
- Driving very close to the person in front of you.
- Well, indeed. - That's the only thing I know.
- That's all we know it as.
But like basically at any NFL match in the parking lot,
then you'll have a tailgate party and there's hosts.
And I was asking when my husband's lived in America
and he was like, yeah, I mean, literally everyone does it.
Every NFL match.
- I've been to a couple of NFL matches in America
and I never got invited to this party.
- I'm so sorry. - Wow, interesting.
- So wait, sorry, you go to the car park.
- Yep.
And there are just people who are such big fans of the team
that they cook up a massive feast.
They've made like a hundred burgers and pizzas for everyone
and loads of beers and just everyone has it.
They have a big party, but kind of anyone's invited.
So you go and it's called tailgating.
- Well, almost anyone's, don't rub it in, am I not?
(all laughing)
- I was starving that day.
- Driving around a completely empty town,
weren't you James?
- I was over a body.
- All the restaurants were closed.
(all laughing)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that Singaporeans drink
more than a bottle of Scotch per person per month,
which is twice as much as their nearest rivals.
- Wow. - Wow.
- What?
- I say the children of Dylan Thomas.
- I like the way you say rivals,
like there's a big sort of international competition
for who can drink the most Scotch.
- Per-old Latvia coming second,
desperately trying to catch up.
- Are they second Latvia?
- Latvia a second. - Really?
- Yeah.
- A bottle of Scotch per person per month.
- Isn't that insane?
- That is a lot.
- Latvia has their own, what is it now?
I have some at home.
It's like schnapps-y stuff that Latvians drink.
So, and they have balsam as well.
- Balsam, yeah.
- So like, they're spreading themselves too thin,
the Latvians, I didn't say that.
- You're right.
- I could call.
- Give up the balsam and having tasted the balsam,
just give up the balsam.
- Yeah, and then you'll win.
- Stick with the whiskey.
- So a bottle per person per month.
- Or they buy a bottle of Scotch per person per month.
And I think that's an important distinction
'cause I struggled to really find the reason.
- 'Cause I, like, I've got a bottle of whiskey at home
and I've been working on it pretty solidly
for a couple of years now.
And I mean, like, I've got past the halfway mark.
But is all this whiskey being drunk
or is it that it's just being bought and stored?
- Well, it's not clear.
So the stats are from the Scotch Whiskey Association.
So, which says that they export 12.76 bottles a year.
They have all the export figures.
In case you're wondering, domestically,
in case you're wondering,
"Oh, the Scottish surely drink more."
73 million bottles are sold domestically in the UK each year.
So even if every single UK bottle of whiskey
was sold in Scotland,
they'd only just be drinking as much whiskey
as the Singaporeans.
- And we know that Andy's having, you know?
- Andy's getting through.
- Working away on my famous grass, yeah.
- I've still got a bottle of whiskey in my house
that I bought on my honeymoon, which was 12 years ago.
- Really?
- Thank you.
- Is that for aging purposes?
- No, we only,
I only use it for whiskey sauce on Burns Night once a year.
- Is it, it's not unbelievably delicious whiskey,
is it that you're wasting on it?
- It's telescope, it's pretty good.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
- Okay, well, we're not contributing
to the English stats, obviously.
But it's weird.
I was looking it up.
Singaporeans very light drinkers.
They consume two litres of alcohol per person per year,
which is about five times less than we do as Brits.
And it seems to be,
when I was looking at like people talking about it,
Singaporeans talking about it, it is about investment.
And a lot of them are buying up whiskey now.
It's become a trendy thing.
It's a pretty wealthy country.
- Well, there's a lot of expats as well, so.
- Lots of expats, yeah, that's true.
- Who will skew the number of people and what they drink.
- If I go as a tourist to Singapore,
'cause I know it's a whiskey hub,
'cause then they've got lots of amazing whiskey
from around the world and whiskey shops and things,
and I buy a bottle there.
Does that count, do you think?
- A Judy Free Sitch, yeah.
- I've never been except, I think,
briefly to the airport once.
But it sounds like an amazing--
- The airport is nice, in fairness.
- And again, I didn't go specifically to--
(all laughing)
- I just went into Changi,
couple of glasses of whiskey, straight back out.
I'm half a glass of whiskey today.
I think that's a record.
(all laughing)
- But it's an amazingly weird place.
- It's cool, I've been.
- Yeah, yeah, I went a lot as a kid.
- I suppose it's not far from there.
So it's right at the bottom of Malaysia,
and it's much like Portsmouth in that it's an island,
but it's separated by a very narrow strip of water
from the rest of the mainland, as it were.
- Portsmouth, the south.
- It's the Portsmouth of the south.
- When you learn in Singapore,
there's a big banner that says much like Portsmouth, welcome.
- Here's another thing they drink there, Yakult.
- Oh yeah?
- So you know Yakult, that kind of little sort of yogurty drink
with probiotics in it.
Singapore is the only country in the world
that sells different flavors of Yakult.
- Is it?
- Interesting, so just a childhood thing,
Yakult was massive in my childhood in Hong Kong,
but I can't picture another flavor other than the basic.
- Well, honestly, they only do it in Singapore.
They also have the biggest serving size
of anywhere in the world, which is 100 milliliters.
Now you can get that one in Hong Kong as well.
You can get that in a few countries,
but you can't get it in the UK,
but you can get it in Singapore.
- You mean of spirits?
- No, sorry, of Yakult.
- Yakult.
- Yakult was the only Yakult.
- It's like a novelty Toblerone, right?
Like it's a--
- Yeah, and also in Singapore,
this is the only place they have it.
They have a Yakult home delivery service,
which started in 1986,
and they will bring you your Yakult to your door
if you want it.
- Jesus Christ.
Their gut health must be out of this world.
(all laughing)
- That's amazing.
- Isn't that weird?
- 'Cause it's an island.
It's got this kind of island culture,
you know, where just things are popular there
that aren't popular anywhere else.
Like they've got the world's first ever salmon ATM there.
- Okay, yeah.
- It's a vending machine.
In fact, there are dozens of vending machines
specifically for Norwegian salmon.
- But the salmon always try and swim back
into the vending machine.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, it's bizarre.
Norwegian salmon, there were 61 as of 2019,
but it stays fresh in there for two years.
- Salmon?
- 'Cause it's frozen.
- Oh, okay.
- Oh, you know.
- Okay.
- Like Singapore, when you go there,
and this is again from the viewpoint of a kid,
it's not particularly weird.
It was a bit intimidating because of the rules.
You were always told, can't chew gum there.
That's illegal.
You will be lashed if you chew gum.
- I remember the teller of that.
- Yeah, I remember every time I would go there,
just being like, wow, it's so clean here.
And yeah, there's a reason for that.
- I've just realized,
'cause I remember thinking that as well,
but maybe I misunderstood,
'cause if they're all drinking so much Scotch,
and they're all getting lashed every day.
(all laughing)
Maybe that's what it meant all along.
- Yeah, no, it is pretty wild.
I was surprised actually,
that the number one imported drink isn't gin.
That's just because simply of the Singapore Sling,
the most famous drink to have the name Singapore
in front of it.
- What's the second most famous?
- There are no others, so yeah.
But that is a massive drink there.
It was invented in Raffles, the hotel,
which is an extraordinary hotel.
I don't know if you've ever seen pictures of it.
But you've been to Raffles.
- In fact, I've had a Singapore Sling there.
- Have you?
So yeah, they say they, at the bar,
which is called the Long Bar,
they say that about 2,000 Singapore Slings
are made per day.
- I gotta say, I ordered one, had a sip,
and then ordered a beer.
- Right, really?
- I did not like it at all.
- 'Cause you didn't like it?
- Yeah, it's too sweet and sour.
- Yeah, it was basically invented
by one of the bar staff there,
because women were not really allowed to drink publicly.
And so you make this with pineapple and lime,
and you put the gin in,
but it looks like they're just having a nice fresh juice.
And so that's kind of how it kicked off.
James, when you went to that bar,
did you notice as you walk
that your feet were crunching everywhere on shells?
- Some classy shells?
- No.
- I don't recall that.
I don't remember it very well, to be honest,
'cause it was quite a lot of years ago,
but no, I don't think so.
I remember it being very colonial.
- Right, so they have peanuts there
that they give to you in bags,
but they don't give you a plate to put the shells on,
because it is tradition to throw them on the floor
immediately after you've eaten them.
- Oh, really?
- At the end of the day, they just have to sweep up
all the discarded shells that are sitting there.
- Nice for the cleaning staff.
Do they appreciate that tradition?
All those migrant laborer cleaning staff?
- It's part of it, yeah.
And also, here's a really interesting fact.
It is located on number one beach road.
However, there is no beach near it.
Riddle me this.
- Did there used to be a beach near it?
- There used to be, and there's so much reclaimed land.
- Oh, it wasn't named after Dylan Thomas's wife,
he was a nymphomaniac and a beach.
(all laughing)
- First class beach on that.
- There's that wild.
There used to be a beach right at the edge of it.
It's on beach road and so much land has been added
that it's no longer in sight.
- And Singapore is 20% larger than it was in the '60s.
And it's basically taken the land from Malaysia and Indonesia,
which you would think sounds like a war,
but they've not gone to war and taken the land in that way.
They've gone over there, taken all the sand,
and then created new land in Singapore.
So the sand comes from different countries.
It's Malaysian land, it's Indonesian sand,
but it's made Singapore 20% larger.
- And it's very controversial 'cause it's drained,
like they've banned it in Indonesia,
they banned it a while ago.
They've officially, I think almost all of it comes
from Cambodia now because it got banned elsewhere.
Cambodia banned it, but you can still make a huge amount
of money as a Cambodian who's willing to get your sacks out
and collect loads of sand and export it.
- Sounds muggling, yeah.
- 'Cause it is, I think a lot of stuff
about Singapore is to do with the fact it's so small.
And they import so much of their food
that they have to have innovative solutions
for feeding themselves and supplying their own stuff.
- And they've smashed that.
It was always the chart when I went,
I mean, which it was 20 years ago, but I think it's the same.
The only two things people ever told you about Singapore
and no offense to Singaporeans, I know there's more,
but the airport's amazing and the food's incredible.
And actually, when you live for three days,
once you know the food is the only thing really to do there,
once you've had kind of four meals in a row,
it's like, "Well, I can't enjoy this anymore.
What am I gonna do now?"
- How can you stop enjoying food?
- I've had them within about two hours.
He's just gone round stuffing your face.
- Actually, I just thought of something
that they did in Singapore that's like the NFL stuff,
which is they turn the car parks into like food halls.
- Oh, really?
- I'm sure they do that.
Yeah, I remember going to, it was like an old car park.
Once the car park closed and all the cars had gone,
suddenly it just opens up and they sell durian and--
- Yeah, okay, that sounds likely.
- That's the big thing, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- There's like one huge food hall.
- Graves, 'cause there's so little space going.
- They have to be all shaped like bananas
and they kind of tessellate with each other, don't they?
- They're all spooning.
- Oh, sweet.
- No, you get, they're digging up,
there used to be a couple of hundred cemeteries
in Singapore, now there are only about 60 left,
because they just need space.
You get 15 years only in the ground
if you choose to be buried and then you have to go elsewhere.
- Obviously, as we've said,
they're kind of big on their rules
and trying to stop people from doing certain things.
There was an anti-gambling advert in 2014
and this featured a little boy called Andy
and he was complaining to his friends
that his dad had bet his life savings
on Germany winning the World Cup
and Germany then won the 2014 World Cup.
(all laughing)
And the National Council on Problem Gambling said
that they decided to choose Germany
because they thought they were very unlikely to win,
but at least it would be realistic.
- You can never bet against the Germans in a World Cup.
- Exactly, they should have known.
But obviously everyone thought
that this was encouraging people to gamble.
So the council revamped the advert
and Andy, the little boy says, his friend asks,
"Your dad's team won, did you get your money back?"
And he said, "No, dad never stops,
he wants to bet one more time,"
on which he bet on Leicester winning
the next year's Premier League.
(all laughing)
- No, he didn't.
- That's so funny.
Yeah, lots of things banned.
That's the only thing I know.
Chewing gum, I know, obviously.
But I mean, it's pretty draconian there, isn't it?
So you can still be caned if you're a man under the age of 50.
- Another euphemism for getting drunk.
- Oh no, yeah, you're right.
But you can really, like, they have a cane
and they will, and it's sort of minor levels of crime,
but it's really painful.
Like, it's really bad.
And there are all sorts of rumours
about the procedure, it just, it's just--
- I thought that J-Walking could get you caned,
like, is what I thought when I went there.
I don't know if it was true, but--
- Mine of vandalism does.
- Weeing in a lift, Dan, you were there as a child,
did you say?
- Not at that age, but yeah.
- 'Cause they had a huge problem
with people weeing in the lift.
- Sorry, sorry.
At what age did you stop weeing in the lift, Dan?
(all laughing)
- Like 23.
- You're Dylan Thomas' face.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, 'cause everyone lives in high-rise buildings,
and in the '60s and '70s,
every lift stank of piss, and it was horrible,
and they had suggestions of how do we combat this,
'cause it's a really nasty social problem.
One block of flats just bought its own lift attendant,
like everyone chipped in,
and you'd have someone to, you know, press the buttons,
but also stop anyone weeing.
And eventually, in the 1988 war on piss,
they installed urine detectors in lifts,
and had a crack down,
and if a drop of weed hits the floor,
that urine detector detects it,
the lift slams to a halt,
and you have to wait there until the authorities come
and drag you off to Chokey.
- Oh my God.
- And the first people calling for it,
were I think, you know, boys who were just sort of...
- I wanna know, 'cause they had this problem
in other countries that most people live in high-rise.
You're so close to home when you're in a lift.
- What if you're going out?
(all laughing)
- It feels like go before you leave, right?
It just feels like you're so close
to having either just left your toilet,
or just arriving at your toilet.
- But you know what it's like.
When you really need the loo,
you suddenly can't hold it anymore
when you're 10 yards from your front door, right?
- Yeah, you let your guard down a bit, and then...
- Exactly, you relax.
- I don't think it's people who are incapable.
I don't think it's people who are almost home
who just can't hold it anymore.
I think it was just a...
I don't know, if I was visiting your home though, James,
I might we in the lift on the way up
just to kind of mark the territory.
- Why don't I live in a ground floor flat?
(all laughing)
- Through the front window, or whatever it might be.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @Sribeland, on Instagram, James.
- My Instagram is @NosicsThingers, James Harkin.
- Andy.
- My Instagram's @AndrewHunterM.
- And if you wanna get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can email podcast.qi.com,
or you can tweet @NoSuchThing,
or Instagram @NoSuchThingersFish.
- That's right.
Head to our website as well, by the way.
We have all of our previous episodes up there.
We have a link to the Gateway to Club Fish,
which is the secret members club that we have.
We do a lot of bonus episodes there.
Add free episodes as well.
Do check it out.
Or just come back next week,
'cause we'll have another episode waiting for you here.
See you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)