Hi everyone welcome to the end of 2020 oh my days we made it it's the end of the year and the
start of what hopefully will be an amazing 2021 for all of you guys um what have we got for you
well we have our annual clip show it's massive it's one and a half hours of all the bits that
didn't quite fit in the edits of this year's no such thing as a fish I really hope you like it
these are always my favorite episode because they go from one thing to another to another
you never know what you're gonna get but you do know that they'll always be something interesting
or something a bit silly okay well what else is there to say I suppose our book Fun You Should
Ask is still available in all shops if you got book tokens do people still get book tokens
well anyway it's it's in the shops Fun You Should Ask by the QILs and also next year we hope will be
a big year of touring for us as soon as the venue's open we will be back out there to do our thing
meet all you guys so keep an eye on know such things at fish.com for any details about that
and I believe there is one show that is currently on sale that will be in London in the spring
so get tickets for that get our book enjoy the show and we'll see you on the other side
Happy New Year on with a podcast
hey guys you've got a quick quiz question if the date is Wednesday the 31st of December
are you in the last week of the year yes yes that is incorrect you're in the first week of the year
so I'm afraid you're all have to leave what could not be in both no of course you can't be in both
what do you mean it's Wednesday the 31st of December you're in the last no but the week's
different isn't it because it's it's more heavy set on the other side of the week in days if it
was on a scale it would weigh over to the the new year week wouldn't it dan's describing better what
the international organization for standardization describes in terms of how to refer to weeks so
you know across the world we have to have the same definition of week one week two week three of a
year and the week week I gotta say I'm without the other side look the week week's up to start on a
Monday and we've got to have the same week so that trading and business internationally globally
works so there's an international body that decides what week one is and the definition of
week one of the year is the week with the year's first Thursday in it so if the first of January
is a Thursday then week one actually starts on the 29th of December which is that Monday right so
week one is that so if the 31st of December is on a Wednesday then you're actually in week one
of the next year because that's insane you can't have week one beginning two days before the year
ends I'm sorry it's absolutely no one does things in weeks anyway you do things in quarters
when it happens like that Anna always has her New Year's party on Sunday the 28th of December don't
it's an absolutely banging event with me me and my cat in attendance I'm sorry you guys have never
been able to make it just very quickly what number Archbishop of Paris do you reckon André
Ventois is is is he the current 23rd 22nd as far as I can tell he's the 30th
so that's his actual name André Ventois and he yeah he was born with the surname 23 and the
the best guess is that it was because and a sort of ancestor of his was found and adopted and they
were found on the 23rd of a month and so they were given that surname yeah so but as far as I can
tell he's the 30th there's there's a lot of breaks in their archbishops over the years so there might
be a few that are not in there hey what's Archbishop Ventois favourite band I don't know Andy what is
Archbishop Ventois favourite band Eiffel 65 and it's because they have a French name and then a
number oh really what well Eiffel Eiffel no no I do understand that yeah and he's French and he
has a number in his name you know what their favourite punk band is I don't know it's Blink 182
and that's because French people blink like the rest of us and there's a there's a number following
that I really think we should move this on I've got to get out of here what is Archbishop Ventois
favourite album by Adele there's a few options there 21 because he's called 23 and it's just another
number yeah yes very interesting he prepares it to the original 19 yeah are all of Adele's albums
numbered yeah oh mate yes yeah 19 that is the age she was when actually it's actually not the ages
anymore they've become untethered from her age but yeah I thought I was thinking she can't have
released 23 albums okay there's an Indian loser called Shiva Keshavan and he has been a true victim
of the Indian government's low prioritising of various olympic sports he it's you can understand
why the Indian government isn't prioritising the loot look no think about the Himalayas think about
the pre low territory you've got for looting I was just thinking that Sean Connery would be a good
luge manager like coach because he'd be like you're a looser you're a looser and all the SH's Sean
Connery's both got Shiva Keshavan you're a looser but so he had to train on wheels not in a proper
looge thing because that's normally on ice isn't it the looge he had to make a sled basically with
wheels on and just train on busy roads just going downhill in the Himalayas and he had there's
there's footage of him dodging a herd of goats which is in the middle of the road and he has
sort of frantically looge around you know um old mcdonald had a farm very well did you got familiar
yeah yeah eio well the earliest version we have was actually old mcdoogle had a farm eio and there's
an even earlier version which is not about a farm but it's old Missouri had a mule he high he high
ho and every country around the world has its own version of old mcdonald and they're all on
wikipedia of course so in turkish it's Ali Baba has a farm eio in swedish it's Per Olson has a farm
eio and in Serbian it's svakoyutro jedno jaje organismus nagudaje which means
one egg a day gives the strength to human organism wow they've just gone completely random i don't
understand that at all every other country in the world it's about someone having a farm and they're
just like don't eat your eggs when planes are actually just coming into land as a normal procedure
the way it works is that they have to get ready miles before they even see where the airport is
they got to get to a certain height and then there's a couple of things that they have to either see
they've got to either have eyes on the runway or the lights that they can see coming from it to
know that they're at the right height and it's actually the computer on board the airline that
makes them make a snap decision about whether or not they were able to land or if they're at the
wrong bit so as they're getting ready to that moment the computer will just yell out in the cockpit
decide that's all they get she goes decide and then they go yes we're doing it or they have to pull
out it sounds like a tv quiz show and now it's time to decide oh you would have won a speedboat but
you've died in a blink that's amazing do they get warning is there a sort of i'm gonna have to
have to hurry you here your time to think i hope you've made up your mind because in a minute
you're going to have to decide and then if they go for it it goes oh interesting decision
we'll come back after the break to see if you've made the right call
there is a problem with being in the center of america someone found out there's this massive
problem that was generated for someone who lives quite near the center of the us in fact
and this is to do with a company called maxmind have you read about this story about ip addresses
okay so it's so weird basically uh maxmind is this company who about sort of just over 10 years ago
started calculating the location of loads of ip addresses so you know with your computer you've
got an ip address maxmind figured out whereabouts they all were geographically and then it could
sell that information to companies like google and facebook and lots of other people um but often
when you're trying to work out where an ip address is you can't get it exact and sometimes it'll just
say this is somewhere in america or somewhere in the us and so for all of those maxmind just
default assumed that they were in the middle so they got the coordinates of roughly the middle
of america and said okay all the ip addresses that we can't quite place they just are here
and it turns out here is a rural farmhouse belonging to someone called joce taylor who now
has 600 million ip addresses registered to her farmhouse and it's it's a complete disaster because
basically if there's a troll online or if there's someone who's hacked your company or if there's
someone doing criminal activity online and the police are tracking them down they chase up their
ip address and they constantly find it's at joce taylor's farmhouse and she's just inundated with
kind of abuse and people writing her threatening letters and had no idea why for about eight years
she was just like why am i being oh no what's happening to me are we definitely journalist
tracked her down are we definitely discounting the fact that joce is like a massive cyber
criminal is that she's she's a criminal mastermind an 82 year old criminal mastermind it's possible
that's funny oh poor joce choice and apparently the verne scholars refer to the novel as around
the world in 80 days and the play as around the world in 80 days but with 80 the digits so that's
how you can tell the difference be honest i didn't get that from when you were reading it out i saw
the fatal flaw in transferring this visual thing in front of me to the audio medium really we're
really hoping you're going to say around the world in 80 plays was what they called the play he wasn't
that smart a guy you know people claim he was you know you know mitten crabs is if you catch one
is there always a string attached to another mitten crab on the other hand uh the cia they
collected a load of jokes in the selviet union in the 80s that was one of the things they did and
that got declassified quite recently um we're not quite sure why they did it but it might have been
a way to kind of gauge what people were thinking in the selviet union or maybe a way of undermining
the government or stuff so they found stuff like um there are two men waiting in a line to buy vodka
the first man says i've had enough save my place i'm going to shoot gorbachev two hours later he
returns to claim his place in the line his friend said did you get him and the man replies no the
line there was even longer than the line here that's a good joke it's not bad is it a man goes into a
shop a man goes into a shop and says you don't have any meat do you um no replies to sales lady
we don't have any fish it's a star across the street that doesn't have any meat again that's
good it works doesn't it i think that's really good yeah yeah were they planning on distributing
the big book of cia jokes about your country feels like it doesn't it my favourite person to have
sort of an olympic korea career and then a follow-up is a guy called uh ross rebagliati he was the
first person ever to win gold at the winter olympics in snowboarding which was in 1998
and it was really sad for him because he won gold and then he was drugs tested and they found cannabis
in his system and so he was immediately had his gold rescinded he was put in jail for maybe importing
it into japan i think which is where the olympics were and then within about 72 hours they then gave
the gold medal back because they went actually cannabis is not on our list of banned substances
as it was not back then um but he insisted that it was from secondhand smoke uh you know he hadn't
smoked weed for almost a year and it was nothing to do with him he was furious but he has now gone
on to found a company called legacy brands a cbd and cannabis consumables company and has a series
of different strains of weed named after him so that's that's his job now and since he wasn't
stoned then but he's stoned all the time now i guess you can never guess what's going to happen
can you because the the 1984 olympics promotion by mcdonald's about uh you could get a free item
off the menu every time the us team got on the podium uh i don't know what you got big mac for
gold or something fries for something or something um they didn't expect the soviet union to drop out
of the olympics so many american national anthem was playing all the time and uh there was i think
there was even a shortage of hamburger buns because people got so many so you've got to be
careful what you uh what you offer up i think yeah at any olympics saying that about team usa
is not quite cool oh you're right you want to make it team togo just be super cautious yeah
the danish basketball team i think you're gonna make it quite nation specific jamaica winter
olympics they had one year where it looked a bit dodgy quite a few burgers but otherwise you say
one more thing um just that you can bite so i think you were talking at the start about how
audio stuff can also maybe trigger um with hallucinations or change your brain makeup and
actually they have now invented headphones which i think either on the market now they're coming
onto the market soon which send electrical impulses into your brain and they cause it to release more
like dopamine and serotonin and oxytocin like happiness hormones essentially and they're called
i think they're called nirvana headphones so they stimulate the vagus nerve in your brain
apparently which then releases all those neurotransmitters and they'll do it in time to the beat of
the music you're listening to so you could even be listening to the verb or something but you'd be
over the moon oh unnecessary burn on the verb i love the verb but they're not upbeat yeah but
i've heard that they've tried that but the drugs don't work so it's hey there was wasn't there a
big clash in east berlin about updating the traffic light men because really that yeah the the east
had particular traffic light men and they were called ample menschen i think which is that literally
means exactly that the traffic light man and one of the things that was proposed is replacing all
of them and people in east berlin particularly said no we really we really like these particular
traffic lights it's sort of a something very recognizable very iconic about the south of the
city and so those i think were rolled out and in fact this is not useful for anyone at home but we
have one in a jar just here oh that's what this is about for right okay let's see it can we see it
okay yeah yeah it's here so this is a little tin of tea this is the ample man yeah and you'll recognize
the stop and the go you know what his yeah the go man looks a bit like an old monopoly man kind of
thing because that doesn't be yeah we've all seen lots of these right these are these are in
berlin well it's a big souvenir thing in berlin now yeah yeah but also on the traffic lights is the
noticeable thing exactly where you see a traffic light go and you're like i mean they're all the
souvenirs but they were well they were kept that's the that's sort of the point yeah yeah they're
really cool they're much more jaunty mmm i'm just not sure that show and tell is ever going to work
as a podcast but it works when you had your own time so maybe the american dairy association has
a page on its website called famous cows of the world and it's a good read there are a whole
bunch of cows on there but my favorite was elm farm ollie do you guys know about elm farm ollie
well neither did i but it was the first cow to fly and also the uh when i say fly i should be clear
it's the first clown to ride in an aeroplane clown so it was a clown as well as a cow it's a
clown cow must have had massive shoes had a red nose and huge shoes i've lost it it was the first
cow to take a flight and it was the first cow to be milked mid-flight this was in Missouri in 1930
and it you know all these things have some kind of spurious scientific justification and so the
justification for this when they paid huge amounts of money to take it up was they wanted to observe
the mid-air and high altitude effect on animals in flight of their milking and of their milk and
it turns out it didn't make a difference to the milk but oh there was a farmer called bunts
else with bunts who milked her who then also became the first person to milk a cow mid-flight
so a huge sequence of first for elm farm ollie yeah it's good to be the one who's milking elm
farm ollie because if you if you ask you to smell her flower it's always going to be milk that squirts
out of it into your mouth okay that's it dad do you want to try it that a punch line to that
punch yeah i'd like to see you try it dad the master is smoking possibly told that
has wonky shut down now yeah has it what no it had new management a few years ago
i've definitely had it in the last year i can guarantee they don't do that kind of rude service
anymore they don't do the rude service uh all their trip advisor reviews went down hill slightly
after they stopped being rude to the customers because that was part of the experience they're
like three stars the guy was really nice to me he gave me my meal it was amazing i went there once
and we sat down on the table it was me and three other people and then halfway through the meal
literally halfway through the meal we went oh we need this table now you need to go upstairs
and they took all my stuff and made us sit on a much smaller table upstairs while they put other
people on our table wow i had a meal there with top davis who is uh people will know him on tv as
king gary and a few other tv shows and we went there and they put us on a big round table where
there was an entire family sitting and we had an old grandmother sitting in between us we weren't
even next to each other on the table oh it was wonderful great days wonkeys anyway our podcast
yeah back to the podcast
do you guys know about the debonish fibs family no you know well they're an uh extremely prominent
family in a sense in that their names are all over park benches across the uk and so this started
to be spotted about 10 years ago maybe a bit more and there are sort of park benches with you know
there's plaques on in memory of and they're always in memory of someone debonish fibs so for instance
in darmouth park near where i used to live there's one that was in memory of winter debonish fibs
and it said like to have everything just so and then the plaque was at a lopsided angle and there
was there was another one somewhere which was in memory of barbara debonish fibs whose wish was
to have a bench plaque inscribed with her last words unfortunately her last words were and then
it's a series of expectives the asterisk that's really funny currently scientists are trying to
find out uh who killed the dodo with a ct scanner whoa there was more than one dodo though that's
true but yes no that's true what do you mean though so do you mean like a specific one or is it i do
mean a specific one there's a dodo in oxford's museum of natural history and uh it's a celebrity
dodo actually although these days all dodo's are celebrities but um this is the one that
lewis carol may have seen when he was writing alice in wonderland and it might have inspired the
dodo in that but scientists thought that it had been killed uh some some way or that it had died
of natural causes actually because they thought it would be brought to uk threw it on a bonfire or
something i thought they destroyed it yeah well they've still got the skull all right that's the
main thing and so they they put the skull in a ct scanner and they found it didn't have natural
causes it was shot in the head with a shotgun so that is the opposite of natural causes um
and what they're trying to do now they've got a little bit of the lead that kind of impacted
with the back of the skull and they're trying to find out what country the lead from those shotgun
pellets was mined in and then they're going to try and find out where the shot was made from that
lead and they basically they're on the longest cold case ever where they're trying to find out 400
years later who pulled the trigger wow oh gosh what are they gonna do if prison is great great great
great grandchildren yeah exactly they're gonna get a knock on their door where are you on the fourth
of march 1596 it's just i was just looking into the quirks of iceland the country um i didn't know
this beer was banned there until 1989 really it was banned in 1915 they had a referendum and they
decided to ban beer and then in 1921 they had to change it a bit they legalized wine because
spain threatened to stop buying iceland's fish if iceland kept on refusing to import spanish wine
so they said okay i'm gonna have some wine and then they they allowed very very weak beer but they
didn't allow normal strength beer and this backfired badly because people just started putting vodka
into their incredibly weak beer and making a kind of horrible beer and vodka cocktail oh some of that
some of the spirits that you get in iceland are unbelievable i went to there's a restaurant that
specializes in slightly sort of quirky food and i ordered the fermented chuck and it comes in a jar
sealed kilner jar with a rubber thing and a very very strong glass of what are we called a schnapps
i don't know what you call it it's a very strong um pure alcohol thing uh and uh i said to the guy
i didn't order the schnapps he said you're going to need and you because for the sake of the other
diners you have to open the jar really really quickly and grab a little spoonful of this stuff
and stick it in your mouth and close it because it smells so terrible and the taste was the most
disgusting thing i've ever had it burned back at my throat and i and i did take a take the schnapps
as a shot i drank it so quickly anything to make the taste of the fermented shot go away
really thought you were going to turn around and say the amazing thing is it smells awful but the
taste is disgusting no it smells awful and also tastes awful correct um hey one bit of royal etiquette
which i think is um upheld in the royal family as opposed to being upheld by the tabloid press
is eating etiquette which is that and it doesn't it makes sense so the queen is served first you
would serve the queen first at a dinner and then when she stops eating really you're supposed to
stop eating as well and this has existed for a few hundred years and it was really difficult
with queen victoria because this was the practice then as well but queen victoria the thing about
her was she was incredibly greedy she used to eat extremely fast like her advisors used to say
stop eating so fast she got terrible indigestion she could eat seven courses in half an hour apparently
and she was always served first and so the people who were served last by the time they got their
plates they were sort of immediately whipped away from them again because queen victoria had
inhaled her first course i gotta say anna we've been for dinner quite a lot of times and you will
not let a plate go if there's any food left on it no matter whose plate it was yeah is this why
you've never met the queen because it's i did it once and i've been banned from dining with the queen
since desperately trying to lick everyone's plates is that it was taken away i had a quick look at
some things that you could get sent to prison for in finland oh yeah in 2015 the police asked
the members of the public that if they saw a pizza that was on sale for under six euros to inform the
police the way that they saw it is it's impossible to run a business where you sell pizzas for less
than six euros it's just the ingredients are too much it's completely impossible so if people are
doing that it means that they can't be paying the tax on the pizza which means that they must
be tax avoiders uh and so they asked literally asked people to say as soon if you see any pizza
on sale for underneath that price send us the menu and we'll arrest the guys that's so funny
that is a bargain price for a whole pizza yeah it is really unless you're in a shop in a shop
it's the kind of normal price for a shop pizza that's a very very posh shop pizza really isn't it
but i mean there are pizzas around the corner that you can take away delicious for a fiver
and i'm now wondering if it's my responsibility to be informing on them just tell the police in
finland because obviously the taxes in finland are a bit higher than they are in the uk so
probably it's more of a seven pound thing in the uk oh you feel bad if you got the whole
stuff and structure of the co-op sent to finish prison what are you in for i'm also in for selling
this pizza there's the pizza wing isn't there they're hard and criminals i went on ebay um to
look at what the most expensive items currently on ebay are that you can buy that are related to
lincoln did you find the horse hair yes so good so there's a look of hair there's a look of hair
from uh the horse you rode in the 1860 election called old bob and um old bob attended his funeral
and for just one thousand two hundred and fifty dollars you can buy a hair of this horse
one hair yeah actually yeah it's not a long strand one hair a single hair yeah you wouldn't
like if you open the envelope that could just fall onto the carpet and you've lost it if you're a
mafioso and you don't have the resources to put a whole horse's head on someone's pillow i'm just
thinking that you know as a middle-aged man who's losing his hair it shouldn't i shouldn't be letting
it go down the drain i should be saving this in case i become president or like the president's
also something in the future i don't know surely this is our next tour match park inside
i've got just one last thing about sort of ingenious ways of catching poachers people
who are trying to illegally catch all of these fish um during the early 80s to about 1998 there
was a guy who worked for the california u.s fish and wildlife service and his name was terry gross
and he was sort of sick of the fact that there were poachers that would go in the early morning
to catch all this salmon when that was highly illegal so you usually had to stop half an hour
after sunset and they would drive out at two or three in the morning and they would get away
with it because the tracks that were leading to all of these lakes were monitored by other poachers
so if they saw a truck come down that they knew was one of the wardens they would say quickly get
the boat in get out of there so they had plenty of warning so he had no idea what to do but then
he came up with this idea of putting on a wetsuit getting into the water before the day ended
and waiting patiently and what he would do is while they were fishing salmon he would loosen
the glove of his wetsuit and as they were fishing it would hook onto his glove and he would slowly
splash around and they would start going oh my god i've caught a massive salmon and he would go
harder and harder and they're like this is the biggest salmon we've ever got they've got this on
recording these words and they would slowly come in and they would get to him and as they got right
up to him he would say good morning gentlemen state fish and game warden you're under arrest
and he would pull out he would pull out of his wetsuit a citation book and he would give them
their fides and then he would go back in and try and catch more people and hire a glass mpr and this
american life um looked into it and they found that there were plenty of these people that used to do
this sit there for hours and get caught by a fisherman yeah wait but did they so did they
have their heads under water while they were waggling their glove above the water no because
it was so dark so they would they would sort of yes sit above and yeah but just in a nice little
spot it's brilliant this guy's an amazing guy that's real commitment to the job i don't know if
i'd sit in freezing cold water for a full day in a pond to catch a poacher i had a neighbour once
an elderly neighbour who would sleep in his car to try and catch car thieves really and he and he
called them right yeah waggling keys out of the window as soon as someone grabs them i was just
thinking them that this guy who's pretending to be a fish basically he's lucky that they're not
catching them with dynamite isn't he yeah because that does not work well actually
in the example in this interview they heard somebody go and get the net get the net and
then another voice goes get the net heck get the gun so one more thing about uh
olympians who have other jobs you know the brian brothers the the tennis the tennis guys the tennis
brands yeah we absolutely love the brian brothers uh so it's sort of best doubles partnership ever
of all time they've won a billion olympic medals and they have a second i don't know if i can call
it a job so i don't know how much profit they make from it but they also are a band they have the
brian brothers band and so bob plays the keyboard and mike is on uh the guitar or drums but he's
not on the drums when the drummer of the counting crows joins them which he does sometimes so like
the jit band and i mention it because everyone has to look up the 2009 song autograph which
i'd forgotten about but is it features cameos from andy murray and no fact jokovic and i'm
telling you i i wished to god it was this andy murray here because that would have been less
awkward than what they make andy murray the tennis player do it's it's about what a horrible
jurid is signing autographs after matches and andy murray's little rap section in the middle
includes the lyrics during wimbledon it gets really crazy my hand cramps up and my mind gets hazy
and um look i'm going to leave people to imagine the rest andy murray's rap section is never
the words that should never ever be put together another fun thing about ghost crabs is that they're
very house proud but only when they are sexually mature which maybe is the same for humans so when
males are not sexually mature and if you get female house crabs they burrow into the sand and
they leave these tiny little holes in the sand they're smaller than a tiny coin but they can go
four or five feet down which i think is kind of cool anyway they burrow holes into the sand and
they just throw the sand anywhere the sound that they've used to borrow they just chuck it all over
the beach but as soon as they hit sexual maturity they suddenly sculpt the sand into a perfect pyramid
and this is to sort of advertise themselves to ladies we think so a woman can look across a
beach and she'll spot the sexually mature men by the perfect pyramids that are next to their
entrances and you'll see you'll see the little entrance and then a little crabby footsteps
footprints going to the pyramid do you think that if a ghost crab goes to egypt they look over and
they go fucking hell there is a very attractive enormous ghost crab over there yeah very intimidating
trip very intimidating stag do for those males so you can find out a lot of things from city scans
of mummies they tried to they city scanned an egyptian priest called nas yamun and they scanned
his throat and his vocal cords and they could find out what his voice was like so they did the city
scan of his vocal cords they created a 3d printed vocal tract and then they kind of fired air down
it and they could work out exactly what he sounded like um and it's basically people on the internet
think he sounded a bit like britney spears cool oh i thought i thought i thought he just went
he goes like like that and you know how she goes yeah that's your cat you're thinking of
oh yeah sorry that's not pretty but yeah there was basically um they the sound did the rounds on
social media and a lot of britney spears fans were very excited about it wow i'm some released
material from 2000 years ago well the interesting thing is like nas yamun would have he was a priest
so he would have done a lot of singing and chanting in the temples so basically if you went back to
ancient egypt and you walked past the temple it would sound like someone's singing baby one more time
wow he wouldn't have been dressed as a schoolgirl though seems implausible might have been there's
probably a lot less chess players online than we actually think there are because they create fake
accounts and they build them up and up to be sort of well played chess players with high rankings
and then they play themselves and defeat that person so it's sort of creating bogus accounts in
order to defeat them and then raise your ranking imagine if it's just one guy have you heard of
sandbagging that's another cheating thing so yeah this is where you play deliberately badly to
qualify for a tournament that is actually a bit beneath you and then you win you take the brakes
off and you you thumb everybody that's that happens in golf as well people claim like you
you play badly for ages until your handicap gets way worse and then eventually you go right
today is the day that i'm going to try and win the tournament it's extremely locked down upon
yeah yeah well they've got measures in place don't they i think they have actual measures
in place now on the chess side to stop that so i think if you ever yeah i think it's if you ever
achieved certain high scores they look at it and go well there's no way that you can now suck that
much because you got to this level and if you if you won a certain amount of cash prize like a high
cash prize well how did you get to that you must be good you must be sandbagging us in order to
to do that so very embarrassing if you're not sandbagging and you are just having a really bad
exact night have you just got lucky one time yeah it happened i think they had to change the rules
or tighten them a few years ago because there was a middle school so sad when you're sort of forcing
12 year olds to do this but in texas it's called henderson middle school and they entered a competition
where you had to have a ranking under 900 and then they absolutely smashed it they were investigated
and it turned out they'd lost all of their previous 28 matches and they're really good and someone
worked out the chances of having lost them all being as good as they were and it was one in
sextillion that they could have lost all 28 which is like if they'd been then playing chess since
the start of the universe and everywhere in the universe it still wouldn't have happened probably
so they were disqualified but 12 year olds come on okay i think it's not impossible that some
people get to a really good position on chess.com because they're only playing people who are
deliberately losing in order to sandbag so they think they're incredible they win a big cash prize
and then the next time they play it their deficiencies are revealed and then they get banned
from playing because chess.com thinks they were the ones doing it it's absolutely mind field
it's a vicious cycle um other people who go down um sort of scavenging and and hunting around the
the lost rivers are the it's tiburn is that the pronunciation is it the tiburn angling society
yes the tiburn angling society it's just wonderful they they meet up once a year to report on the
fish they found it's always zero so it's not the greatest angling society but they are obsessed
with the idea of daylighting which is the idea of bringing these hidden rivers back to the surface
through destruction of the stuff on top of bringing the tiburn back to being what it once
gloriously was and it's an extraordinary thing that they put together in around 2000 where they
put a full report to show how they would do it where it would go it would demolish about one
billion pounds worth of real estate unfortunately telling it's only Buckingham Palace that needs
to go really it's Buckingham Palace that's part of their plan they want to get rid of it
i've one more thing about Houdini's habits at home when Houdini and his wife had an argument
he would leave he'd walk around the block and then he'd come back and he would open the door of
the room where his wife was and throw his hat into the room right if it was thrown out again
she was still angry and i guess he would do it again and if the hat remained in the room
she she calmed down and they were going and resolve it what if the argument was about him
leaving his clothes hanging around the house all the time like a lot of the arguments in my house
so i read a paper called Man and mongooses in indian culture by Derek Olodrick i'm not sure
that's how you pronounce his name but i'm looking up afterwards and i found the oldest known story
about mongooses and it's from 3 000 years ago there's a king who's having a feast and then a
mongoose walks in and half of his body is made out of gold and he comes in and he rolls in all
the food of the feast and the king's like what the hell are you doing and he said oh well i once
rolled in the food of a brahman uh like a really holy uh hindu guy uh and the brahman was so holy
that he turned when he rolled in his food he turned half into gold and this mongoose is going
around looking for another holy person so he can turn his whole body into gold right i don't know
if you want your whole body turned into gold i'm pretty sure king miters taught us that didn't he
yeah i really haven't come across each other king miters didn't turn into gold did he yeah
no no he turned everything he touched into gold he didn't like get a gold finger
and then no but what he but he regressed his leg and he had a gold leg i know he regressed it
because he couldn't eat but wait a minute what happened no no he regressed it because you couldn't
well partly because you if you touched another person who he loved they turned into gold and
that's based on the fact that people don't want to be turned into gold yeah what happened if
with king miters touched himself do we know in is it in the story or they didn't do that in those
days james it was a cleaner time i there was something about finland that was actually the
original article i read and it's about um and so an amazing fact that i didn't know and i can't
remember how the journalist lewis segwayed into it but i'm just going to segue into it by saying
she also mentioned that finland's only monarch the only monarch it's ever had is this german guy
who never visited finland that's all right and they this is in 1917 they got independence from
russia and they started off thinking we want a king everyone else has got or a queen um everyone
else has got one where should we find one we obviously don't have a royal family here in
finland because we're brand new and so they picked this guy uh frederick charles of hess
and he was a german prince they designed a crown for him which i think you can still
see it's on display somewhere in finland and then before he even had a chance to enter the country
they changed their mind uh after a few months and he abdicated
ah that's it that's did he abdicate from overseas as in he yeah he was out still outside god that's
been good in those days when there were all those new countries being formed and if you were if you
were a minor noble in anywhere in europe whenever there was a new country you must have been there
with your fingers crossed thinking oh maybe i'm going to be king at that you're sitting in the
waiting room with all the other potential monarchs going in for their interviews
i hope that bastard from schleswig holstein doesn't get it he's coming out looking all cocky
really ace the practical the waving section of the interview
here's one quick thing on forgeries um there is a forger or there was a forger called elmer
de horre he was a hungarian um in the united states and he did forgeries of loads of people
Picasso matisse and he did loads of forgeries of madigliani okay and he did so many madigliani
that these days it's impossible to compile a catalogue of madigliani's work because we don't
know what is real and what is a forgery by this guy de horre and the reason i bring it up is because
he has a collection of all of his forgeries and it's run by a guy called mark forgy no
who's got extremely fast internet as well hasn't
i like to have you guys come across freddy and truce overstegan no who were not today not
he's not at the hotel here um they were part of the dutch resistance in fact and they were
14 and 16 years old respectively and they were killers cold-blooded killers and they called
their kills liquidations which was kind of terrifying and apparently the 14 year old actually
looked about 12 so it was quite easy for them to get away with killing because no one expected
to be killed by a 12 year old girl and the way they did it was they had various methods but they
cycled around quite a lot i guess cycling was a thing for these resistance ladies and they would
ambush collaborators so they'd be on two bikes and they'd have pistols in their bike baskets
and they'd ambush them or sometimes they'd do a drive-by so freddy would be riding the bike and
truce would be on the back and you know cycle past them collaborators and just shoot them up as you
ride by off into the sunset and what was the liquidation bit or was that just a fancy they
would just shoot them as opposed there was no melting down no they didn't have like a vat of
acid in their cellar they dragged Nazi bodies cool get back what you didn't melt them down
no we just we just did a drive-by and shot them well you got to melt them down mate
maybe they did because i didn't look into it enough there are a few sort of modern
loopholes for companies in britain that don't have a liquor license and i was reading about one
place which was there was a new craft distillery in yorkshire that was being set up in a disused
train station so they'd done it up and it was for it was going to be for gin i believe and it's
called tapling and megan distilleries and by the time they were about to launch all the paperwork
hadn't been done yet for their license but they had this big party that they wanted to promote
their drinks so what they had to do was they looked and found a loophole which is if you're on a
moving train you don't need a liquor license so all trains that you buy alcohol on they don't
need a license a moving train is exempt from it and the fact that they were in a train station
and they had a parked train there they got all the guests onto the train and they took it on a
two and a half hour ride just to one they just went one way turned around well not even turned
around just drove back again and did a two and a half hour gin masterclass once it was in motion
and that that allowed them the loophole of of having the party still if you had a bar which had
a miniature train on the counter so it sort of came two chewing along with your drink does that
count and then you wouldn't need a liquor license maybe you have to be on the train so if you went
to like what's that um what's that sushi place which has got the conveyor belt if you got a young
sushi and you sit on the conveyor belt technically you don't need a license don't sit on one of the
coloured plates you will be selected um i was looking at other ways that museums need to preserve
their artefacts and one is from fires serious problem and it's a really difficult choice for
museums because the main way to get rid of fires is with sprinkler systems but obviously if you
sprinkle a whole art gallery then you sort of ruin the paintings that way but so a lot of museums
kind of don't do it and that was a serious problem in brazil you might remember a couple of years
ago when the main museum in brazil destroyed 90 percent of its collection because of a fire and
they just didn't have the adequate protection but there is one place the Getty Museum in LA
which has such cool fireproof systems so they have like they had the big wildfires last year
and they were pretty much licking at the sides of the museum and the curators were completely
chilled out about it because it's so well protected so it's full of like Rembrandt's and Manet's but
they first of all they have a system where the oxygen can get sucked out of the rooms
so that as soon as a fire got in there it wouldn't be able to breathe and so it would just immediately
go out so it's like an anti-ventilation system and then they also have around the museum a million
gallon water tank and so as soon as a fire starts coming close they just start releasing water into
the ground all around the museum like a moat it's great and so firefighters who are fighting the
wildfires use the museum as like a rest area and a vantage point to look around at the rest of LA
and go ah well I guess I guess the art's okay wow really clever that's really clever uh well just
speaking of water um there was a museum in Spain which is the Museum of Underwater Archaeology
which is called Aqua uh and they've had a real problem with leaks this year
now hang on honestly they get all of their stuff is stuff that's been found underwater like statues
which are sunk or with um shipwrecks or anything that's come from the bottom of the ocean and they
have hundreds of thousands of things in there but they also have leaks in the basement and a lot of
damp causing problems with the wall and they're really worried about it and they reckon that it's
going to wreck all of the things which have been under water for thousands hundreds of years
oh no um have you guys heard of at nuclear trains a twitter account no no this is a really cool one
so it's a twitter bot um and it's made by two scientists who are called Matt Allinson and
Keir Little and what it does is it tracks trains which are carrying nuclear waste across the UK
so these trains go I didn't know they existed actually is that sorry I didn't know there were
trains that had uh nuclear well right you it's not they're yet to tweet
no no um well yeah I mean it's not it's not common knowledge but they sort of they have you have to
transport radioactive containers and trains are not a bad way of doing it they're very tightly
sealed um and these guys they're not pro or anti nuclear they they genuinely are just in it for
the trains as they say um and they have clarified that the radiation you would get because sometimes
these pass along platforms you know they go through brickson or whatever quite near passengers
but they've said that the radiation you would get if you were on the platform one of these
trains went by will be like you just eat one banana isn't that amazing that everyone on the
platform has just eaten the equivalent of one banana but would you feel it would you feel full
everyone slips over on the platform yeah no they don't emit bananas um they just get that much
radiation yeah exactly yeah yeah yeah but that's quite dangerous because if you are such a banana
lover that you're constantly operating on the banana eating cusp of getting radiation poisoning
and you manage it right you know you're eating 350 bananas a day and you know 351 would tip you
over the edge yeah yeah you're right yeah what happens then Andy if a train full of bananas
passes by what is the radiation level in that at that speed that that kills you immediately
so you have to transport bananas one by one don't they that's why they're so expensive once they
get to the shops do you know that this is one of my favorite totally random facts but you know
Penny Mordant who was very briefly actually Defense Secretary last year yeah and before that was
International Development Secretary you know she's named after a Royal Navy frigate wow she's named
after HMS Penelope that's so funny isn't that weird that's a really good giant frigate it's
because she's from an army family and actually it was known as HMS Pepperpot because it was
shelled so many so many times in World War two so she could easily be Pepperpot Mordant
don't she do that dive which is is that Iron Man's wife Pepperpots is Iron Man's girlfriend yeah
oh really yeah maybe that's why they didn't go with Pepperpot they didn't want her to be confused
why is she called Pepperpots it's a weird name it's because she comes from a comic book like all
these characters that they often they often have quite funny names and illiterate names don't they
yeah good point I read about one plane crash or you know emergency landing in 2013 this guy called
John Pedersen and he realized that his plane had had a little bit of damage and he wasn't going to
make it all the way to the nearest airports this was in around Chicago and so he saw a long road
and he thought well you know that's probably the best way to go I'm going to try and stop on this
road but obviously there's traffic on this road so he doesn't want to hit any and what he managed to
do was exactly time it so that when the lights went red and everyone stops that's when he landed
in the middle of this intersection is that amazing wow that's his story and he's sticking to it
I was reading this article about it in the Chicago newspaper and they said that he landed and didn't
hit anyone and he was in the middle of this intersection and then the lights changed and
two cars just went and didn't notice him and crashed into him what and then just apparently
it says and then mysteriously sped off so they kind of drove hit this plane and then thought oh
shit I've just hit a plane and they just did a hit and run on this left the seat of the accident
so I can't be bothered to fill the form in on this one no one's going to believe that are they
I'm never going to get this sort of claim this plane just pulled out in front of me
people always think that pneumatic technology is going to be the next big thing I think there was
a lot of excitement in the US about 40 years ago that it was going to be how we all disposed of our
rubbish and so Disneyland I think was a pioneer of this right so their entire garbage disposal
system is fully pneumatic so if you're in Disneyland you put something in a bin and then it drops down
into a tunnel system and every 20 minutes it just gets sucked about 60 miles an hour to a collection
point there are a lot of theme park nerds who are about to get angry at you because it's the magic
kingdom of Walt Disney world in Florida not Disneyland I guarantee you're gonna thank you for
that correction I got to do a behind the scenes tour there once so I actually got to see some of the
tunnels that those go through and you're just kind of walking through the backstage tunnels and there's
just this tube next to you where every 20 minutes or so you just hear this hang on so do you do you
have to sort of dive out the way every 20 minutes no it's just it's just a tube on a wall it's not
like a transparent how big is the tube can you fit a human in it it's 20 inches diameter I think
can you fit a mouse in it 20 inches okay so that's pretty big yeah I reckon yeah I I've been to
Disneyland and Disney world as well and the rides I don't really like them as much I prefer the
Universal ones the rides but if there was a garbage chute I think then I would be definitely
going for you could sell t-shirts saying why don't you get sucked off at Disneyland
like the rubbish for our pneumatic tube system I will I will argue with you for like half an hour
that Universal's rides are terrible compared to Disney's but we do not have the time for that
have you heard of Jebediah Buxton uh no I don't think so my favorite plaque plucky
in the UK lived in Derbyshire the label is mental calculator so Jebediah Buxton lived in the early
18th century I we think he was an autistic savant you know people who could do unbelievable
calculations in their head so Jebediah Buxton was once asked after a church sermon what did
you think of the sermon and he said oh I just counted how many words there were in it he just
gave a word count that's so good I know he was self he was completely self-taught not formally
trained at all and didn't know much about anything except numbers but knew everything about numbers
so he walked around the local area which is called Elmton which is about a thousand acres
and he could give its size not only in acres but also in square inches wow he was amazing
sorry I have no idea what you just said because I was trying to count the number of words you were
saying
not as easy as it sounds is it it really isn't really is not uh if you get a seal and you blindfold
it and you give it a pair of earmuffs then it can't find fish um I'm not surprised yeah yeah
I'm not surprised at all actually sorry I've misread this they can find fish oh if you blindfold
them and give them earmuffs okay that's gone from being an incredibly underwhelming fact
it's being quite interesting and it's because they use their whiskers right and the whiskers
can tell the movements in the water and this is amazing so when fish swim we talked before that
they have like lots of eddies and vortices and stuff like that which they leave in the water
these seals whiskers can detect these tiny little vortices in a fish that swam past 30 seconds ago
so it swam past 30 seconds ago and it can still feel where it was and then it can still follow the
track of the fish to get that even if it's wearing earmuffs oh wow that is amazing can it tell sort
of the time that's passed rather than up to 30 like can they be like oh 15 seconds ahead because
they can tell the strength of the wait they can't tell the future not the future what I'm saying
is they could count up to 30 but when they feel it let's say it's a wake that comes past 15 seconds
after it's been there can they know it's 15 seconds I don't know if they can count up to 30
I don't know if they know it's exactly 30 but I think they will have a basic idea of time
and we'll know that and know that the vortices will be stronger if it has gone more recently
passed I mean it's like smelling something you know you feel like getting stronger as you get
closer don't you yeah you don't when you're trying to find something in your house where the smells
coming from you're not counting this you know your nose isn't saying that's exactly five meters away
but you can tell that it's closer or further guys don't do that I think if you want to sue anyone
you should sue the makers of Sherlock Holmes baffled have you guys seen that movie no it's from 1900
it's the first ever movie with Sherlock Holmes in it and it's an American silent film and basically
it's very much against the canon of Sherlock Holmes because what happens is people keep kind of
stealing things from under his nose and then using trick photography they just disappear
and then you just get a picture of Sherlock Holmes going oh what happened there why did they disappear
and then they reappear in another part of the room and then they steal something else
and then disappear again and it goes on like that for a couple of minutes and I just don't think
that that's really I mean first of all he doesn't solve anything he just stands there looking confused
yeah he's baffled yeah well that was made in 1900 I believe right is that right James so there's
another one which I'd love to see 1916 the mystery of the leaping fish and this was a movie where
Sherlock Holmes was sort of lampooed by Douglas Fairbanks Douglas Fairbanks junior who was one
of Hollywood's leading actors at the time he was a swashbuckling adventurer and he along with Charlie
Chaplin they set up they set up UA United Artists and he was a huge influence in Hollywood back in
the day and he played basically the druggy version of Sherlock Holmes really bringing up that side
of his character so the way that in the movie he was presented he wasn't called Sherlock Holmes
he was called Coke Anyday E-N-N-Y-D-A-Y as his surname and he had a bandolier of syringes that he
wore across his chest so he was constantly injecting himself as the movie went along with cocaine yeah
he had a clock with the clock face it says eats drinks sleeps and dope instead of the numbers
so he would know when to inject himself and the idea was that Coke Anyday was trying to find all
of these drug barons and once he caught them he would sample all the drugs that they had
as he was busting them and Fairbanks hated the movie after it came out it was only a two-realer
and he just said this is horrific but that's one of the earliest Sherlock Holmes movies as well
amazing do you say 1916? 1916 yeah houses but that Dan that was the first year as the first full length
Sherlock Holmes film but this was a bit more serious because he was because it wasn't a mad
cocaine rob it was um he was played by William Gillette who was a distant cousin of the Gillette
razor family yeah Gillette exactly yeah um and uh William Gillette was a really interesting guy so
he only played Sherlock Holmes in one movie but um that was after he played him on stage about
1,300 times he'd come up with a stage version of it and yeah and he and Arthur Conan Doyle were
actually friends they I mean Arthur Conan Doyle was probably pleased because he managed to work
out a way of doing the character well on stage and it was you know respectful and all of this
but also entertaining and when they met I really like this William Gillette um they were meeting
I think on the same train and Gillette got off the train dressed as Holmes and then he found Arthur
Conan Doyle and he examined him through a magnifying glass and that was from that point onwards they
were firm friends Conan Doyle loved it yeah that's it's a risky move isn't it because he really is
yeah yeah he might think you were taking the piss a little bit but we also we had um temperance bars
in Britain which were super popular around the end of the 19th century again with this big push to
stop people drinking and apparently for every little mill town there would be at least three
temperance bars which is essentially like a I mean the cafe like a milk bar like it's a cafe
yeah I think they might they used to be not not that long ago there was definitely one in Lancashire
I know that much well there's one left now and uh it's Fitzpatrick's in Lancashire you're absolutely
right and the owner of Fitzpatrick's in 2012 he'd just been on Harry Biker's actually and talking
about the great stuff about non-alcoholic drinks like dandelion burdock and how great abstinence is
and how popular the bar still was and then he was done for drink driving have you guys heard of the
nuclear bomb that was dropped on the gregs but I can understand that okay gregs well no I've tricked
you with my words this is the story of the only nuclear bomb that has ever been dropped on American
soil by an American plane okay and it fell on the family who were called the gregs um they lived in
South Carolina parents three kids uh their cousin everyone was playing the kids were playing in the
in the yard next door to the garden right perfectly normal afternoon high above them in the sky there's
a plane which is doing a training exercise with a real nuclear bomb where they have to transport
it across the country um so training exercise there had been some kind of mess up with getting it
sort of locked into its um its sort of um hangar thing you know it's hanging there above the
bomb bay doors um so the captain sends a crew member to adjust the the locking mechanism the
crew member uh can't quite get a handle these are huge bombs it looks like a you know it looks like
a whale weighs about three tons the crew member climbs slightly up the side of the bomb and reaches
up to grab something to get a handhold unfortunately what he grabs is the emergency bomb release
mechanism right oh and then does he fly down on it like in dr strange level so the exact well the
bomb falls onto the bomb bay doors right which crumple like paper yeah the crew member makes
an x shape with his body and just about stays inside the plane okay the bomb is now falling
towards the completely unaware greg family house it lands in their garden it makes a crater 15 meters
across and 10 meters deep the no one is killed the family are all injured but they they you know
they became superheroes no they become superheroes um the family's chickens unfortunately were
vaporized but the but thank god the bomb did not go fully nuclear it kind of had the
safety catch on but then amazingly they stayed the the crew was so apologetic they were so
mortified they'd done this and they wrote to the family apologizing and they stayed in touch for
years with the crew this family the great even to the extent that one of them visited the family
for a week's holiday many years later wow that's so nice that's incredible that must have been an
embarrassing moment because i used to get embarrassed enough you know when you had to knock on your
neighbor's door and say i'm really sorry i've kicked my football into your garden i am so sorry i have
dropped my nuclear bomb in your backyard um in the vietnam war i don't think we've ever mentioned
operation wandering soul have we which was one of the tactics that the us used against vietnamese
soldiers which was to play ghost noises incredibly loudly out of helicopters and from u.s soldiers
sort of hidden in vietnam they'd have these big boomboxes and play ghost noises that doesn't seem
like it would work because helicopters are extremely loud and it's not like you're gonna
they're not like they can sneak up on you and then play this noise you're going to be first thing
is you hear the helicopter and you're going to go why a ghost driving helicopters now doesn't make
any sense you're so right the idea was that in vietnam the belief is that if you don't get a
proper burial then your soul wanders the earth and so they actually recorded south vietnamese
people they recruited south vietnamese people to record themselves shrieking and screaming and
saying my friends i've come back to let you know that i am dead i'm dead don't end up like me go
home quickly wow really crazy and the vietnamese soldiers mainly didn't believe them and all it
did was give them a target to return fire to so oh no that would still scare me i have to say if
if the four of us were out you know in a in a jungle and we were scared in a boombox had a voice of
saying alex bell saying don't come over here i'm dead i get scared by that what situation why are we
in the jungle then i mean what how badly wrong is our tour gone that way we're on foot in vietnamese
jungle and why still alex bell yeah and why does it take a boombox and a helicopter and the jungle
for you to pay any attention to alex bell alex if you're listening here's how you get us to
actually upload the podcast correctly when you say there there are all these museums around
nice and some of them do sound i would say of limited interest so there's a museum there's an
island called hi me hi me um and there's collector on there who's collection museum whatever you like
it's a lifetime of paper napkins which are organized by theme into binders and for online
her sofa is covered in binders full of paper napkins i just does anybody else feel an overwhelming
sense of sadness well there's napkins there to wipe your tears away so yeah that's so true
place to have a cry um they have a museum of sea monsters but the way that they've done that is
they have the stories of sea monsters um like any museum might do but the founders they phoned
every single care home in iceland and they asked for all of the elderly residents do you know any
stories about sea monsters that have happened in your history or have you heard any stories
and they collected all of those and they're all the stories that are in the museum which i think
is a really good way of finding social history isn't it yeah so wonderful but that's the origin of
of grim's fairy tales in the first place isn't it the grim brothers didn't write them they went
around and collected them they really mostly from women yeah there's a woman i think she was called
daughter wilder who gave lots of the stories but they went around and particularly older women
asked them for the stories that they remember i mean really we ought to be doing more of that
i think that that kind of gathering of stories is a wonderful thing so good for them that's great
yeah it sounds wonderful it sounds like an incredible filing system but done as an entire
country where they're all dedicated to filing one aspect to social history yeah it's just yeah
it's incredible with the grim brothers i read a story which i really hope is true i always keep
meaning to look it up which is when they were gathering the stories one of the brothers was
trying to get a great story of a sailor or some guy who who knew a bunch and he said what can i
give you to give me your story and the sailor needed new trousers so the grim brother gave
his trousers on the spot to this guy to wear and then gave him his story and he took it down sort of
you know trouserless as he was as he was taking it just love i love that kind of i need your story
what do you need my trousers fine go for it did that wait did the guy did the guy who was talking
to not have any trousers on no he was probably just was he approaching a trouserless man and say
tell me your story i think a trouserless sailor there's another story there yeah wait was it the
story of when he the poo i'm actually in Berlin there was a traffic jam this year that was in the
news which was this is in february and this was created by one german artist who calls himself
an artist called simon weckert who created a traffic jam by just pulling a handcart so he was
on foot and pulling a handcart behind him carrying 99 phones so how google maps works is when it's
giving you traffic updates it assesses all the number of phones in a certain area and then assumes
that those are lots of people in cars and then assumes that that means there's a huge traffic jam
so google assumed massive traffic jam on this one bridge and it redirected traffic around it
and this guy was just him on his own walking through the centre of berlin he actually walked
past google's offices just to do a sort of middle finger up to them i guess that must be so freaky
for the guys at google they must say oh my god the traffic jam it's coming this way
it's an invisible one they're the worst that's hilarious they they claim to be supportive google
a google spokesperson said whether via car or cart or camel we love seeing creative uses of google
maps as it helps us make our work better oh yeah doesn't sound like they really liked it and now
that guy has been killed he's been disappeared won't find him on google maps anymore um one thing
that's quite similar which is uh about modern technology and slightly hacking it is the old
teslas um which would drive you could set them to drive just underneath the speed limit wherever
you were um they would read the traffic signs and so researchers at mackafee realised that if you
got a 35 mile per hour traffic sign and you got some black sticky tape and turned the three into an
eight then your tesla would drive at 85 miles an hour in nine wow these are the old teslas and
new ones don't do that anymore um i think possibly thanks to this little bit of um work by mackafee
but it just i mean especially as a 35 mile an hour traffic signs are usually in places that
need people to slow down it's yeah yeah and that's that's why we're still in the trialing stage really
of the driverless cars isn't it like one smear on a speed sign and everyone dies have we ever talked
about just that reminds me of the tree of tenoray which is in um always in i think Liberia but
somewhere up there and um it was the most isolated tree in the world and there was no tree anywhere
for like i don't know 100 miles in any direction and then it got knocked over by a libyan truck
driver literally there's nothing else to and he just decided i'm just going to drive straight into
that by accident that must have been like the scene in austin powers where the guy's being
about to be run over by the steamroller and he's shouting no from about 20 meters away very very
slowly do you think the guy the truck driver was similarly i don't see anything else i think that's
a really unfair analogy because in austin powers the idiot is the person who's about to be run over
so that implies you're blaming the tree and the tree's gone to extreme lengths to escape traffic
collisions it's so socially distanced that tree it is i think what it is is there's something about
people when they're driving if there's a massive area with nothing there at all but there's one
thing then some reason you just kind of get drawn towards it like your brain just can't
avoid it there there is a thing called target fixation isn't there where someone is so focused
on avoiding a thing that they keep looking at the thing and aiming towards it accidentally the
conversation equivalent is that thing which is in the meaning of lift where there's something
you're trying to avoid talking about and so you can never avoid talking about it and i think the
example that's given in that book is if you're talking to someone with one leg and you find
your conversation is liberally peppered with references to long john silver or the last leg
of the ua for competition it reminds me of um michael windsor who is now basal brushes pa
jenny you're always you're always name dropping i am friends with basal brush aren't you that's why
i'm friends with basal brush so the way he got the job was he rang up basal brushes creator's son
as basal brush and auditioned for him during that you just just was in character the whole time
did the voice perfectly got his mannerisms and he got the job
phone call which is an absolutely bold move because yeah you've got the potential to really
upset somebody who literally this guy sees basal brush as his brother that's how um that's how
peter cellars as well got his first job peter cellars of inspector clue so fame and the goonshow
and so on he was getting nowhere and he was an impressionist and he called up the bbc and he
did an impression of the the head of the bbc at the time saying to the person who's the producer
picking up going have you got this peter cellars not in american it's where's peter cellars where's
this peter cellars guy hey this kid's hard i hear you've got to get him you've got to get him now
so yeah say he imitated it and the guy went oh i'm so sorry well yeah we'll book him and peter
cellars later admitted that was actually me but the guy was so impressed that's hilarious that's
actually how rory bremnes still keeps getting jobs he can do a very good impression of the director
general of the bbc that's not fair rory bremnes great i don't know why i said that do you know
vanilla ice is real name oh i feel like i should um oh gosh i can't remember it's a piece called
rob rob van winkel oh yeah anyway apparently why on earth would you change that i mean that's
a fantastic name and also wait a minute it scans perfectly doesn't it rip van winkel
he wouldn't have to do ice ice baby he's got you're absolutely right yeah he was called vanilla
because he was the only one in his friendship group who was white and he got called that and
then he had a dance move called the ice right i didn't i didn't know it was white i didn't know
anything about it you're kidding he almost played london i think in 2019 or 2020 possibly yeah 2018
or 2019 on ice it's going to be his first vanilla ice on ice no funster yeah and he sings a song
where the lyrics are ice ice baby this guy has an obsession he's got a problem it's an issue
actually um like crowley has something in common with rex lambett uh founding editor of bbc's list
the magazine is it that they were both insane i suppose so actually you'll get sued for that and
this is about being sued as well so um allister crowley tried to sue a writer called nina hamnet
for libel because she called him a black magician um she said he was into black magic and he said
that this wasn't true and he tried to sue her and he lost and he was declared bankrupt and then
towards the end basically he became a big drug addict because he'd taken a lot of drugs before
and then he became a real drug addict and he died quite young um but i was reading about nina hamnet
and according to wikipedia she was a welsh artist and writer who was an expert on sailor shanties
and became known as the queen of bohemia she sounds incredible isn't she um she was basically um like
one of the main people in soho around the 1930s who kind of knew absolutely everyone um she had
an incredible bohemian life but actually when she sued crowley it became such big news that it really
kind of wrecked her life and she became a bit of a alcoholic just walking around taverns in fitrovia
trading anecdotes for drinks sad if you take on black magic you're always wins yeah um i was amazed
about other people's connections to the occult around this time and people who i thought were
just legit humans so the way crowley first got into this whole world was i think he joined
an order which is called the hermetic order of the golden dawn and another leading figure in that
was yate which as in wb yate and he was actually him and his partner more gone famously his sort of
muse and also iin nesbit who wrote the samyard if anyone's read that um anyway like five children
in it yeah exactly wow sort of makes sense when you think about it you can imagine someone who
was into weirdo magic writing that yeah but yates was a chapter leader for this order and crowley
didn't like him and there was this big rivalry going on about who should be ruling this chapel
crowley or yates and eventually crowley invaded his chapel mid sermon he launched what he called
an astral siege on the chapel which involved um kicking the doors down and he was wearing a kilt
for some reason and a cyrus mask because it's by by egyptian mythology and he started casting
spells and waving daggers around and the police had to come and break it up wow well yeah the big
story of that it's called the battle of blithe road and the story is that he came through and he
started propelling black magic at yates and the others as he was coming up the stairs yates was
using white magic and the white magic toppled him over down the stairs now that's what they say
but when you read into it what it actually was is he was coming up the stairs and yates
and his buddy who was a boxer was kicking him back down the stairs is that what white magic is
white magic is some big guy kicking you down the stairs yeah exactly he's one of the gladiators
this is white magic but this this order the idea was they wanted to discover a unified theory that
explained the magical world so that they could bring endless possibilities to magicians that
was why they were set up and that's why yates joined he wanted to use it for good um and so
he joined crowley and he had a mentor there and the name of his mentor alan bennett wow yeah how
good i mean it's not actual alan bennett obviously i was summoning a demon yesterday
um this year has had an exciting new naval battle which is great because you know not as many
classic naval counters as there yeah definitely well i don't want to get old Jeremy carbon on your
aster i promise this is a good one because this is the first naval battle in the caribbean for
75 years um and it's between uh venezuela uh venezuelan naval patrol vessel which was doing the
rounds um defending the motherland and so on and it had guns anti aircraft guns that machine guns
mounted on the deck lots of stuff on the other side was a portuguese cruise ship uh which included
an 80 seat theater a sauna and a jacuzzi okay the venezuelan patrol vessels as it said you're being
very territorially aggressive or something they basically they were chanting her arm a bit
they approached they ordered it to come into port uh in venezuela and you know surrender and all of
this they then opened fire and then they rammed the ship okay they rammed the cruise ship but
unfortunately they didn't realize that the cruise ship question the resolute was built for polar
cruising and i had a one meter thick hull the venezuelan naval patrol vessel crumpled basically
like a tin can 44 sailors had to be rescued unbelievably embarrassing wow yeah that must
have really that must have really livened up that cruise ship cruise for the on board and and if you
look out on your left you'll see the venezuelan navy and venezuela is now owned by thomas cuck is
that right that's right yeah amazing you know that there's a lot of art that just sits out at sea
on private yachts that often are worth sort of two to three times the value of the yacht itself
they're such valuable pieces of art so for example um joe louis has a 200 million pound super yacht he
is the majority stakeholder of totland hot spurs the football club he is he's a very he's a billionaire
in the uk and um he has a yacht and that moored and when it moored people could see through the
window and they saw hanging inside one of the rooms a francis bacon painting that sold anonymously
christies for 26 million pounds and so there's courses you can take now to train people for the
practical care of onboard art collection because everyone on board doesn't know how to look after
these you know so priceless pieces of art and they keep getting damaged when they're out at sea and
you know someone will pour um someone will pop a champagne bottle and a cork might hit a priceless
piece of art or in some cases there was one guy a john michelle basquiat who's an artist
who has little bits of corn flakes that are hanging off the paintings and they were very
worried that they were going to be ripped off thinking that maybe the kids on board had spilt
their corn flakes onto the painting itself um you can't you can't spill corn flakes onto a painting
that's hanging vertically on i don't know dad you've got kids how how far does the food fly
when it gets spilt exactly you very much can but that the ceiling fresco at the back of them is
just a ball of cocoa pops isn't it yeah i think if you're putting cereal on your paintings then
you shouldn't have an automatic right that it's taken seriously yeah well apparently in this
case it was a mistake he was eating corn flakes looking at his painting as he was laying on the
floor and it fell on it and it became part of the art is what they say in this article
but then one of the more famous ones is that um some millionaire or billionaire owners came back
onto their yacht and they've been told by that the captain had unwrapped a piece of art that had
arrived for them onto the yacht and had hung the painting on the wall and this was a horrific moment
to hear it because the piece of art that they'd unwrapped was a bit of art done by christo and
john claude and their way of doing art is they wrap things up so they just wrap stuff up and so
effectively the captain had taken the actual art off put it into a room with all the hot pipes and
then hung up this painting on the wall and you might know some of their work they did the the
rice stag in berlin they they wrapped the entire that's what they do they just go around wrapping
things so yeah so there's courses now for teaching you how to look after art on the high seas very
good so funny god i bet after that there was a famous dog he was called don the talking dog
and he was called the canine phenomenon phenomenon of the century he debuted in 1912
and he had a vocabulary that reached eight words what words were they well please don't say rough
and breathe back i think it was a bit like that they were all in german first of all
he could say he could say harbin he could say kuchen he could which means cake and the first one
means have uh he could say he could kind of say ja and nine and he could say ruha oh come on i need
a i need a recording of this or i will not believe well he was really saying he was absolutely
massive he was like he was when he came over to america so he was big in germany obviously like
you're gonna be big in germany if you speak german but when he came over to america there was a lot
of kind of german expats there and they were really excited and so they met him on the coming
off the ship a load of reporters and asked him for a quote which his owner said he was too seasick
to give a quote when he arrived but he was very impressed by new york but whenever he went on
stage he would kind of answer a series of questions presumably the answers were always harbin or kuchen
or something like that but the point was that he would make noises that sound a bit like it but
according to um the journal science someone did an actual paper on it they said that really he's
only just making noises and it's the people in the audience that are interpreting it as words
they sound a bit like words but obviously he doesn't really know what he's doing and it helps
that the german language sounds quite a lot more like a dog barking than sort of the spanish language
i mean you wouldn't get away with a big romantic language and a dog trying to impersonate that
you're absolutely right when i don't understand a question or i can't quite um determine what the
person said i give an answer that is uh in determined as well so it could be uh a sort of a mixture
of yes and no or or i'm not sure so you know and because i don't know what the person said but i
still want to respond because they're staring at me so i'll often say something like oh and
and they and they go are you sure and i'll go uh so that's just a little hint there for some people
you might want to it's a little little skill you can have that's sort of a halfway noise in russian
you can say yes no yes no which means no dan yet means no right as well and you see how we have a
term called oh yeah nah oh yeah probably heard of this one that's right yeah yeah so when people
say you go into the beach oh yeah nah and you what does that mean does that mean yes on well it means
you might but you just see how you go oh okay and they might say to you are you into it have
you seen this thing are you into it oh yeah you know you could be but you don't want to give it away
so it's a wonderful response because and then you can't you can't actually
respond again to that by law in new zealand so if you've received an oh yeah nah you can't go
look which is it because then you're just you're shunned i suppose you could just you could just
say maybe i guess it's a similar word no because then you're really giving it away that you're
not sure okay yeah all right it's not right yeah nah is is is the full spectrum okay very non-committal
country an entire country that's terrified of commitment that's actually that's actually an
option that's actually an option on the upcoming election ballot isn't it it is yeah yes no oh yeah
nah now even though it ends on nah this the the year part is going to be strong oh yeah no
oh really the way you say it well it is yeah there's different ways of saying it so i don't
assume it meant no in the end the one you end on seems to be the dominant one ask me ask me whether
it does oh does it just mean no right great should we get back to talking dogs
and the breath actually can be a problem in some places like the edvard monk museum in norway
they say that the scream is fading the screen which is his most famous work is fading because of
people's breath and that's because he used very cheap low quality paint he used cadmium sulfide
paints monk when he did his painting and it means that when you breathe on it it kind of gets worse
and worse and worse and they're trying to stop people from breathing and that means they should
they should replace it with the screen yeah the screen in front of the screen yeah very nice
sorry it was too good that i didn't like one of those ones i was afraid to breathe in front of
it in case in case the joke faded to the car should we um we can stop there actually
should we cast it yeah let's do that that was a great one no no it's fine i was only going to
talk about um taser tampons we could let's talk about taser tampons quickly yeah and then we
can move on after that i read the press store so some modern uh self-defense gadgets that obviously
it's still a bit of a growth area even though a lot of these things get released and they're not
legal to carry so there is a killer engagement ring with a particularly sharp cut diamond
an unbreakable umbrella which waks just as strong as a steel pipe but weighs only one pound and 11
ounces i think my favorite is the pink stinger which is a stun gun made to look like a tampon
it can deliver a 50 000 volt shock and can be used handheld or shot out to distances up to 14 feet
so that's that's a heck of a tampon i think i've seen that done in thailand actually um
so no but you don't wear it as a tampon before you fire it at your it's like a pink ball thing
no it's it's to be hidden within your handbag and nobody would know not presumably among your
other tampons yeah you don't want to accidentally get the wrong one do you yeah although if you've
got enemies and they ask for a tampon in the bathroom that's a hell of a prank
prank
50 000 volt prank prank goes wrong man doesn't understand what a prank is
lovely wow that's extraordinary those are all on the market we can yeah they're they're available
somewhere and i cannot guarantee that they are legal in in the territory in which you're currently
listening so please don't waste your money i got one last thing which is i was i like the idea of
the name center for north dakota so i just quickly looked into other names of north dakota to see if
there's any fun names and i found there's a place called flasher which is great in north dakota place
called zap and zap kind of the only major thing i could find that happened there was in 1969 there
was a movement called zip to zap where the mayor of zap suddenly found two to three thousand partiers
tearing up the streets and setting bonfires in the middle of them
to have this big party and they had to get the national garden to push them out
why was that called zip to zap i thought you were going to say the mayor zip wired into zap
no i think it was just a group of people that let's zip over to zap and have a massive party
is the uh i believe and then lastly a place called buttsville which is a cool name
but that is weird there's a lot of butts in um in that part of the world isn't there because um
butts like means uh it's like a raised bit of land or something so there's but yeah so in
montana and wyoming and dakota's there's loads of butts you're not going to believe this in south
dakota there is a place which was the original center of north america which was done by drawing
two lines and it is called snake butt really yeah and they put an obelisk on it uh and they
named it the approximate center of north america and um then in 1930 they changed their minds and
decided it was in rugby north dakota but it was snake butt a confusing name because it's actually
really hard to work out where a snake's butt is really is do you know what i said i was having a
look so i was going looking through some old books and uh maybe this is just me having sort of
locked down brain but i suddenly had a look at one of the poo and i hadn't realized quite how
philosophical it is so there's a wonderful bit where piglet and poo are sitting underneath the
big tree and piglet says what if this big tree falls down and poo says what if it doesn't and i
just thought it's a great attitude to life isn't it instead of catastrophizing and thinking what
if this terrible thing happens i like that attitude i mean or am i being ridiculous and
we don't know you're right i have to say it sounds like poo is praying for an end to the pain there
it sounds like he's taking piglet there on the assumption the tree will fall on them both
but i really like that why are we always worrying about the bad thing that's going to happen what
if yeah what if it doesn't we just sit here happily and not worry about bad things happening to it