we run it on QI a few years ago yeah um which was there's no such thing as a fish
isn't it nice or something as a fish? no seriously it's in a tea
Oxford dictionary of underwater life he says it right there first paragraph no
such thing as a fish
hey everyone welcome to another edition of no such thing as a fish a weekly
podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden my name is Dan
Shriver sitting here with the regular three QI elves Anichesensky Andy Murray
and James Harkin and we've got joining us today on fact checking Judy's
Freddie Somes and once again we have gathered around the microphones and
our offices to tell each other our favorite facts from the last seven days so in
no particular order here we go
first up it's James oh my fact this week is that the CEO of Levi's chip
Berg hasn't washed his jeans in more than a year
so when you first mentioned this to us yes I thought that wasn't that
surprising because I didn't really wash jeans and didn't realise that was a
thing I was shocked and I wanted to know where his mother was
and I wash my jeans every day but Aniches crisps up a plate come on that's true
can't trust his household habits but apparently I'm right right so a jeans
a fish or no I don't know yeah well there are lots of people who think that you
shouldn't wash jeans because it fades the colors and it spoils the fabric but
that's people who work for jeans companies not so much microbiologists who
tend to think that you probably should wash them because there's going to be
lots of bacteria on there and so how much bacteria are we talking okay so there
was a student at the University of Alberta called Josh Ley holy and he as an
experiment wore the same pair of jeans for 15 months without washing them
and after two weeks he found that he had around a thousand to two thousand
bacteria per square centimetre that was on the front of the jeans
1500 to 2500 on the back and between 8,000 and 10,000 in the crop
area lovely I wonder how many more that is than we
have on our skin yeah well you do have bacteria on your skin we have we have 10
times more bacterial cells than human cells in our bodies is that right yes most
of them are very small cells in the gut but 90% of you is not human
yeah and doesn't isn't that where all the smell comes from
so you should remember saying this to you guys a long time ago but that's where
that's why you smell it's not you it's a little animal that's
it's a very poor excuse on a date though it's not me it's the 90% of cells which
aren't me in my body so if someone ever says to you oh you smell of sweat today
you just say no I smell of bacterial feces actually
in your face where are you going don't get in that taxi
promise for us
and so I don't know do you just not do anything with your jeans and or do you put
them in the freezer like some people do I don't really understand this freezer thing
what's the freezer thing well that's what this this guy from Levi says that
instead of washing you can click you can kill the bacteria by putting your
jeans in the freezer and one it it means that it doesn't fade the jeans and
what have you but too it also will save water and apparently
people are using a lot of water all the time uselessly for washing their jeans
so that's a bit like that's like a cool way of cleaning in the same way that
remember the person who used to have an asbestos um tablecloth
oh yeah Charlemagne yeah yeah yeah do you know about that Andy
okay so like Dan says exactly that he had an asbestos tablecloth
after each meal he would take it out throw it in the fire
and then let the fire clean it and then he would bring it out and use it again
did he die young by any chance can I tell you my favorite thing about this Levi's bass
yeah go on is that I just like that the head of Levi's
wears Levi's yeah it's just I love anytime you hear a story where someone uses the thing
that they created or or that they're the head of like when I was wearing my
nose which thing is a fish t-shirt that cue I recordings this week exactly yeah
there's no shame in the buy online in New Zealand not from us not from us
I like it even more so when you see the the company getting in trouble for
something to do with their own company like for example Jimmy Wales who created
Wikipedia got in trouble for editing his own Wikipedia page
which is the top line of what you're not meant to do and he got busted for it
and I don't know what he was thinking because it comes up as edited by Jimmy Wales
I think we tweeted this the other day and Freddie you might have to check which
you news they were but there's an American uni that
or a guidelines on plagiarism and it was all plagiarized from another American
oh yeah that's a great fact that was yeah that's it's a cue I tweet if you can find that
do we know who invented jeans by the way well there's a difference between
jeans and blue jeans you know the blue jeans that everyone wears today
yeah we're invented in the late 19th century in America but this is cool
there have been paintings discovered from the 1650s where people are wearing
the blue cloth sort of fixed him with white which is the you know the proper
jean fabric and the artist is unknown but he's called the master of the blue jeans
and so in one there's a peasant wearing a blue skirt and others boy in a rip dark blue jacket
and it looks like they're wearing jeans in the 1600s yeah yeah and double denim it's very very cool
that's so mean because that's where it comes from denim doesn't it?
would possibly denim is from neem or it's either there or it's from
genoa in Italy which is where they think we might get the word jeans from
but that's not that's not blue jeans with the rivets in those those were the ones which
took over the whole world yeah but Levi's didn't call their product jeans did they for a long time
um i think for the first 107 years they called them waste overalls really we had a fact in one
of our books that half of the world's population are wearing jeans at any one time oh yeah um
can't remember where it came from i think i missed maybe i know where it came from oh go on
well it was a man called miller who visited lots and lots of countries and in every country he
visited he stopped and counted the first 100 people to walk by and in each one he found that almost
half of the population were wearing jeans on any given date which is unbelievable yeah it's fantastic
i'm wearing jeans now i'm wearing jeans yeah me too i'm not wearing jeans yeah i'm just
smelling it i thought yeah just going back to um not really washing etc um there was a very famous
dirty celebrity um in the um 19th century i think i think i think i thought we were going to say
in the 1970s and he was called dirty dick you know dirty dicks pub uh some Liverpool street
and the Liverpool street station uh on bishopsgate uh and what happened was on his uh wedding day his
fiancee died very sadly and then after that he refused to wash or clean for the rest of his life
and lived in this place in in London and he became really famous for being dirty and never washing and
if you sent any letters uh addressed to the dirty warehouse in London they would always get to him
because he was self-famous for being dirty well there wasn't much in Queen Victoria that washing
was really bad for you as well didn't she? Was it people did? Yeah in 19th century very unwashedable
okay um before we move on uh Freddie have you got anything to add? Yeah so um the tweet that was on
quick immediately other day was that um a university in Oregon has plagiarized the section on
plagiarism in its student handbook um from the section on plagiarism in stanford university's handbook
wow so good um we took that tweet from omg facts okay let's uh move on to fact number two and this
fact is my one uh it's a long one so I was just I found this pretty astonishing the first successful
transatlantic flight which happened in 1919 was made by two guys from Manchester but it's one of
those trips where uh it was just a complete disaster but they managed to do it but my favorite bit about
the fact is that at one point they got completely lost while they were in the air they were just
covered in cloud and fog and when they came out of the cloud and fog thinking that they were 13,000
feet in the air it turned out they were only 60 feet above the water and not only that that they
were flying sideways on a 90 degree angle to the surface of the ocean wow how will they try and
always know when I'm at 90 degrees because of gravity yeah were they so tense while they were
flying that they just didn't oh so stiff they were they were so tense now I got this from Bill
Bryson's book one summer america 1927 he was saying this is how tense it was for them to do it the
guy who was in front who was called allcock was holding onto the wheel they didn't have a cover
over them it was like a convertible plane and the other guy's job who was brown had to sit forward
and using his two index fingers as kind of windshield wipers on the goggles of allcock that was his
job to basically just be wiping them away he also had to jump out onto the wings of the plane six
times in order to knock icing off and get back on ice you mean ice they flew through the great cake
yeah so when was this what year was this 1919 um they did the first transatlantic yeah yeah
yeah but they went from Canada didn't they they went from Newfoundland yeah to Ireland yeah um but at
one point they even went the wrong way they did a loop and started heading back towards Canada
it is pretty easy to get disorientated I think when you're flying um shame on me I can't
remember who it was but there was an explorer who was in a balloon and he went up very very high
and sort of passed out or fell asleep or something like that and then when he woke up um he thought he'd
landed and so decided to get out of the plane to just walk on the snow which he saw below and only
when he was halfway out of the balloon did he realize that it wasn't snow it was actually the clouds
and he was still 20,000 feet up oh my god uh in 1914 when you look at the military use of airplanes
this is fact here that the French Air Corps had the largest air force in the world larger than
Germany, Britain, Italy, Russia, Japan and Austria all combined and they only had three dozen
planes and that was the largest in the world so how many to the rest of us have four each or
between us each each and America had two and in the space of four years they went up to
Britain having 55,000, Germany having 48,000, Italy having 20,000 and France still have 36
do you want to hear something cool about Lindbergh? Yes please you made the first solo flight from
New York to Paris he was the 19th person to cross the Atlantic in a plane oh really?
yeah see the first solo then he was the first solo New York to Paris that was the thing and New York
is a much further distance because obviously it's further down the coast so lots of people talk
about the amazing length you went to to cut down the weight of the plane and even cut the top and the
bottom off his map so that it would save a couple of ounces but he also had this thing he said I had
an arm burst cup which is a device for condensing the moisture from human breath into drinking water
how cool is that? Why don't we still have these? He didn't realize how famous he was going to be
did he? He knew he might be in the papers so he he subscribed to a cutting service that would send
all the newspaper cuttings to his mother's house thinking it would just be a few here or there
but of course it was in every single newspaper for days and days and days and by the end of his
first week his mother discovered to a horror that a fleet of trucks was preparing to deliver several
tons of newspaper articles to our house. Reports were at the time like if he left something on his
plate you know a meal like corn on the cob that waiters would fight over it because that would
become really precious I could drum as drumstick after a gig yeah exactly an actual drumstick for corn
so the right flyer was the right brothers plane that they first flew and what's the highest
altitude that any part of it reached? 20 feet 30 feet I'm thinking it's a QI question so I think
I know the answer yeah go on is it the moon? It's so the moon oh of course another one of
nails little trinkets you brought up Neil Armstrong brought it up to brought up a bit of the wing
we had a few series ago Buzz Aldrin on Museum of Curiosity sister show to QI and no such thing as a fish
cousin of no such thing as a fish and I found this fact that I hadn't read in any of his biographies
I can't even remember where I found it now but I I mentioned it to him in person because I thought
this is gonna be amazing to say that Buzz Aldrin I discovered that his dad was mates with one of
the right brothers so within the father's lifetime he knew the first person to fly a plane and his
son became the first well second person to stand on the moon and so I said to him you might have
actually met him because you were at the same air force base where your dad and he worked and he
went yeah I guess so and he just wasn't interested I thought I delivered I think it's the way
you tell him dad the right brothers dad told them that they were never allowed to fly together didn't
he because he was right that one of them was going to die so they only flew together once in their
whole life and you know on that so after their first flight in the right flyer in 1983 I think it was
then so they they took turns flying and they had goes on it and they flew further and further and
then they had a chat about it stood next to the plane had a chat about it and the right flyer never
flew again after that day because a gust of wind picked it up and afflicted over a bunch of times
and broke it oh really yeah just as they were talking they're like oh shit there goes that do you
guys know who was the first woman to fly solo in an aeroplane is it not a female lady human
is it a female animal is it a female ant is it a tortoise it's not even a qi thing it's just a
question and it's a question to which none of you know the answer tell us the answer god damn it it
was blanched you at Scott of course because the story was quite good because she was the first
woman to fly solo in an aeroplane she reached 40 feet and it was in 1910 and she was a friend of an
aviator called Glenn Curtis and he like was a time in in those days nobody thought a woman should
really be in an aeroplane and he allowed her to sort of taxi around the airfield in the aeroplane
but she wasn't allowed to take off and then something happened we don't know what happened
on september the second in 1910 and she managed to take off and ended up going up to 40 feet in the air
and no one really knows how she managed to do it because what he would do is he he would insert a
block of wood behind the throttle to stop her from reaching the necessary speed to take off and then
assume that a woman would not have the intelligence to remove a block of wood from behind the throttle
because my theory is that's probably what she did or it might have come loose itself and did she
land it yeah so she didn't die no she didn't die okay that's good news good blanche I have a
fun fact about the guy who invented the autopilot oh cool um who was Lawrence Ferry who I think you're
familiar with Andy yeah but so he also inadvertently invented something else which was the mile high
club sorry I was going to make that like attention thing so yeah in 1916 he was going flying lessons
to this socialite called Mrs Waldo Pierce whose husband to make this story a bit more poignant was
driving an ambulance in France at the time in the war her husband was friends with Anna's
Hemingway by coincidence um so Lawrence Ferry autopilot inventor Mrs Waldo Pierce go up in his
plane he uses his autopilot um to flight the plane for a while while he has a quick uh bit of uh
whatever you want to give it how's your father bumpy bumpy with Mrs Waldo um and the plane crashed
something went wrong with the autopilot people think that they kicked it during their
relations and kicked the autopilot of course and the plane crashed into a duck pond and they were found
unclothed by duck hunters fortunately her husband was driving an ambulance nearby
sperry claim they'd been divested by the force of the crash when they emerged
isn't there a fact that the first ever hot air balloon trip there was some hanky panky going on
in there it's not the first ever because i think that was the mongolian brothers
George Bigin and Latisha Sage went up in a balloon organised by an Italian man called Lunardi
but he got out just at the last minute and it went over Piccadilly and as it went over Piccadilly
people could see sage on all fours um although she maintained that she was not having sex i think
she said she was looking for something like i can't remember for sure and all of all of her
clothes had fallen off in the excitement of going up and so then later on in these big wager books
that they have in London clubs um one one wager reads "Lord Chambley has given two guineas to Lord
Derby to receive 500 guineas whenever his lordship plays hospitals with a woman in a balloon a
thousand yards from the earth" maybe people's clothes were just much more poorly designed in the
olden days maybe they just never washed their jeans they just fell off crumbling away
okay um time from fact number three and there is annas uh yeah my fact is that in 2007 a
woman called Evan Latimer inherited Napoleon's penis from her father so that happened yep um so
basically at Napoleon's autopsy in 1921 there were 17 doctors present um and it's thought that
the main his physician his main doctor cut off his penis we know that bits of his body were removed
so his heart was removed because he wanted it sent to his wife his strange wife although i never
got her and there's a theory that it was eaten by rats um and anyway then it was later admitted by one
of the doctors who was there that other bits of Napoleon's body were also removed so it resurfaced
at the beginning of the 20th century from the family of the priest who was also present at the
autopsy whom the physician had given it to um and yeah it was put up it was sold to a collector and
it's been sold at various auctions and it's been on display in New York in 1974 only three thousand
dollars he bought it for in 1977 that would have been more money a bit more but also it was questionable
whether it was his penis at all but was this woman upset that you know did her elder sister get
the Duke of Wellington's penis in the well or something was it was the whole bequest penises
of one side because his penis is certainly diminutive it measures 1.5 inches now and there is a
defense that it wasn't very well preserved so there's been some shriveling but it's it's been
likened to various things it's been likened over the years by people who've seen it to shriveled
eel beef jerky and a bit of leather um and it's 1.5 inches um yeah it was described as a mummified
tendon I believe when he removed it was a very delicate way of describing a severed penis yeah certainly
better than shriveled eel I first read this fact in a book called the antiques magpie which is
really good um and it's written by an antiques rocho expert he thinks that the reason the willy
was locked off was because the physician was annoyed at being left out of Napoleon's will
oh I know I read it it was the chaplain who wanted it done as an act of revenge um because
uh Napoleon kept calling him impotent well he did give it to the chaplain so maybe they both had
a chat in the pub one night and he was like I'm really pissed off in the polian I'm not in his will
and the chaplain was like I'm pissed off in the polian too he's called me impotent and they agreed
to it maybe they maybe they each got half which explains its size that's such a good point yeah um
it's actually three inches we've been unfair the thing is that often Napoleon was captured at
Waterloo all of his belongings were sent on tour around England very much like the x factor
rocho today for example so his carriage was sent around the country and it drew crowds it had
had little objects that he had owned like a gold tongue scraper a flesh brush and a chocolate
pot sorry what's a flesh brush I think I'm not certain it's a brush with hard bristles that you
use to stimulate your skin and stimulate blood flow but I am not certain did you guys know that
this this is a bit of research that I did in the b-series and no one liked it Napoleon um
had a little jeanie that he used to talk to called it a little one point five it
straight up jeanie honestly it's more but it works magic just rub it just rub it
um no he he had a um it's apparently someone who before big battles used to come from the stars
called the red man is what he called them the red man and he first appeared during the battle of
the pyramids and the supposedly Napoleon said he made a pact a ten-year pact with this jeanie
oh weird uh recipes since penis uh that was sold um and it turned out later to be a dried up piece of
sea cucumber and not a penis at all just can you imagine all the women who were disappointed in
the bedroom by that and Tutankhamoon another famous person was the only mummy uh who was buried
within the wrecked penis wow someone else is on his own yes one of the best sentences
set out loud in this office i'm convinced was one night when me and james were sitting here uh
and putting music to one of the no such thing as a fish podcast and in a moment of silence
where james saw oh i've got you know i should just start a conversation james said to me
hey did you know over 600 men in the world have two dicks
yeah no that is true like 600 men have two dicks there was a circus performer who had two penises
remember him no um no i missed i missed that i missed when i was seven that zippo circus
you were concentrating on the clouds and the elephants yeah there we go
don't see the man exposing himself by the door of the tent um that's true i'm not sure he was
part of the circus i'm thinking about it it might be two ben
so the guy was called um Juan Baptista dos Santos and he was known as the man with two penises
and he was born in pharaoh in Portugal in 1843 and in 1865 he turned down the sum of 200 000
francs to appear for two years with a French circus huh and press of guy that would be very
difficult for his tailor though which way to serve dressed to the left no actually both to the left and
the right okay moving on to our final fact to the show fact number four Andy yours my fact is
to say i don't care about something a german person has the option of saying it's sausage to me
or in german does this me a worst um yeah so there there's a rich heritage of sausage sayings in
germany um there's another one which suggests that it's very important is that sausage is very
important where you say uh is gate undiwurst which is it's all about the sausage um anyway this is
from a blog on uh Oxford dictionaries website from the oup they have other ones like um if you're
sulking you aren't playing the offended liver pate de belay dig de liver worst spielin
that's like i think that's like referring to the bottom lip sticking out isn't it it's like a bit of
liver is it i think so yeah they have a sausage academy i believe do they what yeah you can get a sausage
diploma and in germany you can get is it a diploma that's also a sausage i i also have a sausage
diploma i got it from banger university and is right there's uh 1,300 students have earned
certificates at the sausage academy they learn things like what's the right master to put with
what sausage and which is the best log to drink with it in america they have the national hotdog
academy and they do a similar thing they have rules about eating hotdogs uh and so for instance one
of them is don't take more than five bites to finish a hotdog for foot long weeners seven bites are
acceptable and also don't use ketchup on your hotdog after the age of eighteen mustard relish
onions cheese and chili are acceptable the first hotdog eating competition was held in 1916
which i think was in the states so the year before they entered the war when they were still
locking around and the winner ate 13 frankfurters i don't know in what time scale that was but recently
the the latest record i've found is from last year where at a man eight 69 hotdogs in 10 minutes with
buns i highly recommend anyone listening if they want to find out more about this kind of hotdog
eating competition stuff uh i just read an article by john ronson in his book lost at sea called
the hunger games and he interviews the top the person who set that record that Andy just read out
it's him into john ronson interviewing him and it's phenomenal the industry great breakthrough was um
a very small slight looking i think japanese yeah who came up with the incredible innovation that you
don't have to chew your way through the buns you dip them in water which makes them a lot smaller a
lot easier to swallow quickly and revolutionize the game but actually it was the fosbrew flot moment
in competitive hotdog eating but actually there is controversy whether you should be allowed to do
that it sounds like cheating i think i definitely think you shouldn't i'm afraid to say no um i found a
there's a japanese book uh which is it's published in edambrough and it's called the insider's guide
to scotland obviously though with a japanese title that's the translated title and in the book
they um advise anyone from japan visiting scotland to avoid eating the sausages
oh yeah um speaking of um parts of the uk and sausages um there is a Welsh product called dragon
sausages and it had to be taken off the shelves because it didn't contain any dragons
right yeah a power scounty council spokesman said the product was not sufficiently precise to
inform a purchaser of the true nature of the food there's a man called david harding in london
who's become the first official sausage addict and he's spent two more than two grand on therapy
to try and get over it um because he can't live he says i genuinely cannot bear the thought of living
without sausages he thinks he's had at least one sausage a day since he was three and he's having
therapy to why would you need therapy to get over that just buys it then i'm going anyway
to find another sausage oh yeah that's that's your attitude to old drugs isn't it
it's a very good sign okay in everywhere why don't you just carry on just like it's a shot
it just have some more cocaine and it's like man up um sausages are very elderly um
they are they've been long and noble history haven't they? yeah i've found a lot of things online
i don't need to properly stack it up but i think they're older than ancient Rome
yes which is cool i'm pretty sure they are um i think poma mentions one
there's an aristophany's play called the knights as in knights of the round table uh in which a
sausage seller uh beats a demagogue in conversation over politics because he knows how to do all the
stuff like minting up policies and stuff them and dress them up looking all nice and pretty
uh yeah well that's the thing they say laws are like sausages don't they?
yeah was it Bismarck? I think it was Bismarck who said it um laws are like sausages it's best not to
watch them being made yeah something like that and so we talk about how old sausages are um they were
banned um or blood sausages were banned by Leo the wise he ruled in the um attempt century and he
banned the blood sausage and the pronouncement was like this it said we hereby forbid all persons
either to use or sell it and we give notice that if anyone should in contempt of divine
law have been found to have prepared blood as food whether he sells or buys it he shall have all his
property confiscated wow and after being severely scourged and disgracefully shaved he shall be exiled
for life disgracefully shaved what is that that's wonderful that's very funny um the Catholic church
bound them in the fourth century as well because um they were thought to be a part of pagan rituals
which they were often hey this is really exciting there's uh there's a bunch of forgotten grim fairy
tales stories and one of them is called the mouse the bird and the sausage a mouse with a bird
of the sausage set up a house together for a while and things are going well birds job was to fly
into the forest every day bring back wood mouse carried water let the fire set the table sausage
did the cooking making sure their meals were probably flavoured by rolling around in them
I think we should then wrap up yeah okay uh Freddie do you want to add anything before we wrap up
yeah I I have one thing um it's kind of mundane but pretty impressive all the same so as
actually commissioned in 2000 the creation of the world's longest sausage and it was made in
Sheffield and it measured 59.14 kilometers kilometers yeah 36.75 miles wow did they just not
turn on the thing which divides the sausages up you know so they just have a continuous production line
one sausage that must be it oh that's great good fact that's good there's one of the world's most
frightening penis metaphor with that Napoleon looked on with envy okay that's it for this
episode a no such thing as a fish that is all of our facts if you want to talk to us about any of
the things that we've mentioned in this podcast you can get us all on our Twitter handles I'm at
Shriberland Anna is not on Twitter still but if you haven't seen the push there's a big push for
you to get on Twitter now from you three trending in this office only yeah but if you do want to ask
any questions about the podcast if you go to uh qi.com/podcast and there's the email address you
can write to me on there you go you can write to Anna on there James uh my Twitter is @xshaped
Andy @andrewhunterm and Freddie my Twitter is rf soams you can also head over to qi.com/podcast where
we're gonna have all sorts of extra information videos and links that you can click onto and explore
further into the stories that we've been talking about we'll be back again next week with another
episode until then goodbye
you
[BLANK_AUDIO]