- Hi, everybody.
Before we start the show, I just wanted to let you know
I'm joined by a very exciting guest right now.
It is a world acclaimed author, Andrew Hunter Murray.
Hello, Andrew.
- Hello.
- You've written a book right here.
- Yes, I've written a book.
It's called "A Beginner's Guide to Breaking and Entering."
It's out in paperback now.
- Yes, I've actually read it.
And not even just 'cause I'm friends with him
because it's such a fun read.
And it's actually not a guide to how to break into a house
and burgle it, which is obviously what I was hoping for.
- It's even better than that.
Tell us about it.
- Well, it's about a young guy called Al
who lives in lovely, empty second homes
when the real life owners are away.
He doesn't break things, he doesn't steal things.
He just makes his way in,
lives in these gorgeous places, and then gets out again.
And this book is the story of when he and his friends
break into the wrong home on the wrong day,
someone ends up dead, not his fault,
and things just get more complicated from there.
It's a caper.
- It is a plus, a little bit of satire
in the housing market, which every good book needs.
And obviously he joins up with a fun motley crew
of fellow breakers and enterers.
It really is such a fun book to read.
And I believe it's available in bookshops, is that right?
- It's available in all bookshops.
And even better, if you're an audio person,
it's in a two for one deal on Audible.
That and one of my other books the last day
are both included in the current Audible deal,
which is lasting a few more days
where you can get two books for one credit.
- Do it, go, listen to the book and then read the book.
- Do both, it really is worth it.
And speaking of guests, we had a fantastic guest on today.
We had so much fun with her in the episode
that you're about to hear.
It was the excellent comedian Rosie Holt,
who I'm sure many of you are familiar with.
And once you've listened to this, if you're in the market
for some very sharp skewering of what's going on
in politics today, you have to check out her podcast,
which is called Non-Censored.
On the other hand, if what you fancy
is a very witty satire on the last government,
then check out her book, which is called Why We Were Right.
So that is Non-Censored, the podcast,
or Why We Were Right, the book.
But for now, enjoy the show.
- On with the podcast.
(jazz music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray, and Rosie Holt.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Rosie.
- My fact this week is all the werewolves
in the film Howling 2 are actually monkeys
because the wrong costumes were delivered.
(laughing)
- So, so much to unpack here.
You said Howling 2, like every listener's gonna know.
- Everyone knows about the famous film Howling 2.
I think somewhere Howling 2 was called
the worst sequel of all time.
(laughing)
- Those people clearly never saw Howling 8.
- And you're a fan, right Rosie?
- Sort of, I'm fascinated by it.
So, I don't wanna spoil too much for people
who are really excited about watching Howling 2,
but it leaves off where Howling 1
(laughing)
finishes, where spoiler alert,
the female lead turns into a werewolf and she is killed.
And at the beginning of Howling 2, it's her funeral.
And the best line ever is where Christopher Liu
pops up, 'cause why not?
And he says, he says, I'm afraid your sister was a werewolf.
And the guy goes, God damn it,
that's my sister you're talking about.
(laughing)
- And he says it at the funeral.
- Yes.
- And he turns over to the funeral,
no one knows who he is.
He's just a weird guy.
- Just a weird old guy.
- He stands at the back and then says that.
And you can understand, we haven't led up to,
like, did you know there are more things on earth
than a dreamt of, you know, like the werewolves exist.
As far as I can tell, this is fresh news for this guy.
- No, it's a cold open.
- I must say, 'cause I think I might be the person on the planet
who's watched Howling 2 most recently.
- I finished one hour ago and then I came straight
directly here.
(laughing)
And it's really good.
- Watching it with the knowledge of what happened
with these costumes, it was a mix-up.
They were Planet of the Apes TV series.
- Oh yeah, that's the costume story.
- Yeah, so basically, they were sent the costumes.
The costumes were late.
When they opened the costumes,
it was actually from the Planet of the Apes TV show.
And then, good old Christopher Lee saved the day
because he said, this is what we're going to do, Philippe,
that's the director.
We're going to shoot a scene where we simply explain
that werewolves go through three phases,
a human phase, a monkey phase, and then a werewolf phase.
And that will solve everything.
- No.
- And it did. - And it did.
- Yes. - Yeah.
- And that's what they do. - Yeah.
- Pretty much.
- So do they look like monkeys?
- They look exactly like monkeys.
- They look exactly like monkeys from Planet of the Apes.
(laughing)
- It's really confusing.
And they shot it all in the dark.
And then later on, once they got a werewolf head,
they spliced in lots of shots of a random werewolf head
crossing a screen.
It's terrific.
It's so good.
I mean, there's so much in this film.
- Yes.
And there's lots of great little facts.
So the other thing about the costumes
was there's a threesome scene where they're all werewolves
and they're all having sexy fun.
But if you probably remember, Andrew.
- I remember the scene very well.
- Yes.
It's not a terribly, I mean, vigorous threesome.
They're sort of tentatively stroking each other
and growling, and it's because,
so they'd had to be covered in hair for the costumes.
And this took, I think this took like eight hours.
And then they found out that when you touched each other,
the hair came off.
- Yeah.
- So therefore they were having to not touch each other
because they realized if they actually did an orgy,
well, a film orgy, all their costumes would fall off.
- 'Cause it wasn't a costume.
It was them naked for eight hours with them putting
little bits of hair on them.
- Oh, was it them naked?
Like, yeah.
- Sorry, I didn't explain that very well.
It would have made more sense to put them
in the monkey costumes for this.
But I guess they thought because they're sort of naked,
it's still going to be sexy-ish.
- It's not quite as sexy as the monkey costume.
- Yeah.
- It's the hairiest and most chased three
some ever committed.
- It's a rare double award.
Rosie, is this one of your favorite films or something?
- It's not one of my favorite films,
but I do have a real soft spot for it.
- 'Cause it's genuinely so bad it's good.
- It is so bad it's good.
- After the first 10 minutes, I thought,
I hope, I can't believe we're going to cover this
in case someone watches it.
And now, I say watch it.
- Yeah.
Do you totally?
- I mean, it has, the weird thing about Christopher Lee
is that he's a good actor who's only done shit films
with a few exceptions, obviously.
- Lord of the Rings, Man with the Golden Gun,
The Wicker Man, one of the greatest horror films
I've ever made.
- So he's done some good films,
but he's done a lot of really bad films.
- I think the only reason he did this movie
was 'cause he realized he hadn't done a werewolf movie.
So he thought, okay.
- And thought, this is the one.
- This is the one, howling two.
- This is the one.
- The filming of this one sounds amazing.
'Cause Christopher Lee, we must have mentioned before,
is like an amazing character.
He had this great war past where he worked for the SOE,
the special operations executive in the war,
which was like the secret service under Churchill.
No one really knows what he did there
'cause he was never allowed to talk about it.
But it seems like the one person he confided in
was the director of this film,
who was called Philippe Mora.
- Yeah, 'cause he was a Nazi hunter.
- Yes.
- But apparently they landed in Czechoslovakia,
which it was at the time, where it was being filmed.
And they got to the airport
and there was this huge crowd of people
who were all like cheering and waving
and giving this heroes welcome.
- Wait, hang on.
- Yeah, go on.
- Quick query.
- Go.
- He was a super secret war hero and Nazi hunter.
And yet he's so globally famous as a Nazi hunter
that everyone in the Czech Republic
knows who he is at the airport.
- He must have been like James Bond,
where he just didn't hide.
- Is that totally plausible?
- No, no, there were elements of his war past
that were known at that point.
'Cause it was the 80s by then.
And basically it seemed to be widely accepted
that as part of his spying war history,
he'd been involved in the assassination of Reinhard Heidrich,
who was the highest ranking Nazi ever,
assassinated by the West.
So he landed in Prague and he got this heroes welcome.
And the director was like, one, do that's for one.
Christopher Lee was like, I'm gonna stop you there.
It'll be for me.
- For my Nazi killing.
- I have seen a couple of stories saying
did he exaggerate his war record at all?
And I haven't had the time to properly look into them.
And I just hope he didn't.
- I didn't want to be scared to do that.
- If he got such a heroes welcome,
surely he didn't exaggerate any of it.
- Yeah, but it could have been--
- He was also a globally favoured film star at the time.
They might be showing any old stuff.
- I don't think that's relevant.
I don't think that's what to do with it.
- The checks are above that.
- But because it was filmed in Czechsvakia,
Christopher Lee and Sibyl Daning, was it Sibyl Danning?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, they both were getting followed the whole time
while they were shooting by two creepy men
who would sit in the corner
when they ate in the restaurant in the evening.
- As in like Iron Curtain's bunnies or secret police?
- Yes, Iron Curtain's smiles.
- Oh, Iron Curtain's smiles.
'Cause they did, yeah, they did.
They were making phone calls back home
and they could hear them in the background,
just like men breathing and coughing
as they were listening in on the conversations.
- It's worth it, guys.
Were they that the Soviet Union had?
No wonder it fell apart.
If it didn't have its shit together to stay quiet
on a phone call, it was just listening.
- I think they're using the Christopher Lee,
tell you I'm a Nazi murderer process.
They don't care.
- The lead actress is Sibyl Danning, as you just said.
There is a bit of the film,
a slightly sexy bit where she rips her shirt off.
It's a very charged scene, you know?
But she apparently had been asked to do this
in lots of films because she was very attractive
and she was a bit bored of it.
And she said, "Do you know what?
I think I'd like to do just one topless scene
or even one topless shot entirely in this film.
Is that okay?"
And the actress said, "Yeah, great, great, great."
Anyway, she turns out--
- So she said, "I want to be limited to one."
- Yes, she just wants to do this once, which happened.
She then turns up to the premiere of the film
where the credits, the closing sequence of the credits
uses that shot a further 17 times
for absolutely no reason.
- Yeah, it just has, on repeat, like exposing her chest.
- No.
- Wow.
- Like a sort of sexy gift.
- If you give them an inch, they will take a month off.
- But it's so Mora, the director, back to him for a second,
he didn't know they were going to do that
to Danning, the actress.
So he actually--
- Because they were friends, weren't they?
- They were friends.
And he kind of, at the end of the movie,
they brought in some other people to do a final edit on it.
And part of that edit was throwing in 17 shots
of her topless during the credit sequence.
And he was really pissed off by that.
So he then goes on, he says,
"I want to make Howling 3 because I want to fix
"the reputation of what this did."
- Because of that credit sequence.
- Well, he was just pissed off.
- The whole film, I think.
A lot of rehab work on your career.
I don't think the credit sequence is the main problem.
It's problematic, but it's, woof.
- Yeah, so Howling 3 sounds amazing.
Howling 3, the marsupials.
This then is set in Australia, has no reoccurring characters,
has no plot that is connected to anything else.
In it, the humans that are transformed into the Howling
have pouches like marsupials.
- Amazing.
- Yeah, it sounds pretty amazing.
He generally just in praise of Mora,
'cause he's an Aussie film director,
and I'd never heard of him.
But his list of movies is extraordinary.
I'm really obsessed with a movie that he directed
called "Teridactile Women" from Beverly Hills.
- Wow. - I know, right?
So listen to the plot.
Paleontologist Dick Chandler discovers a dinosaur egg
prompting an eccentric witch doctor named Salvador Dali
to put a curse on Chandler's wife, Pixie,
causing her to slowly transform into a pterodactyl.
After Pixie lays an egg,
Dick tracks down Salvador Dali and apologizes,
and the curse is lifted.
(laughing)
Now, Barry Humphries is in this movie.
It's like a proper movie.
I can't wait to see that.
- Barry Humphries.
- Barry Humphries is in it.
There's a bit where Christopher Lee says in "Howling 2,"
right, there are some sort of King werewolves
and Queen werewolves, they cannot be killed with silver.
This is like, there's an oh no moment, oh no,
what are we gonna do?
They just says they can be killed with titanium,
which, although a slightly harder method to get hold of,
was very much easily available at the time.
(laughing)
It's stunning.
- Is that a copyright thing with Bran Stoker's people?
- I have no idea.
- I read an interview with the director,
and he was really so, 'cause it got so panned,
and he's so enthusiastic about it,
and everything he got asked, he'd go,
"Thank you for asking that."
And one of the things he said, which I liked,
was in the poster, there's Sibyl Danning,
she's wearing these sunglasses,
which will obviously appear in the movie,
and that came about 'cause he said that she came along
and she had conjunctivitis, and they were like,
"What, what were we doing?"
He was like, "Don't worry, you're a werewolf,
and a werewolf can wear sunglasses indoors
if they want to."
(laughing)
- And that's what your identity is like the concealed now.
- I read that somewhere that that became
very influential in the movie industry.
So if you think of the Lost Boys,
the vampire movies and so on,
they're all wearing glasses,
and according to numerous people,
that was a direct influence.
It suddenly was cool to do it.
- It's hard to imagine this film had any influence.
(laughing)
- I think it might have been the '80s.
Christopher Lee's in it, it was a proper release.
It's part of a massive franchise.
- Yeah.
- I was just looking at monkey costumes.
- Oh yeah.
- And the gorilla movies used to be a really big thing
in the '20s and '30s.
They were a cultural preoccupation.
I suppose they are now.
- Why? - Actually, Kong.
- Anything else?
- It's all leading up to King Kong.
Basically, they started with normal-sized gorillas,
and then they worked their way up to Kong.
But we still have loads of Kong stuff now,
and we're still having plenty of the games.
So this is a permanent societal thing.
But there was one guy called Charles Gamora,
who was known as the King of the Gorilla Men
in the '20s and '30s,
partly because he had his own suit.
(laughing)
So any film that needed a gorilla,
get Charles Gamora on set now.
And he'd done a bit of, he'd seen,
he was very convincing in his suit.
And he was the right sort of height,
and he looked into the San Diego Zoo
and sort of observed them.
And so he was trying to do it properly,
he was trying to go in method.
Anyway, in 30 years, he was in 43 films,
39 of which involved him being a gorilla.
- Right.
- The others, he played two aliens,
one bear and one cannibal.
- Same suit with bits sewn onto it.
- Same suit.
- Oh, I don't know.
(laughing)
- It just sounds great.
He's the one called the Monster and the Girl,
where a gorilla receives the brain of a man
who is seeking revenge
because he was wrongfully executed.
- Right.
- Yeah.
- The brain goes into the gorilla.
- That's really good.
- I mean, I really hope Modern Hollywood
is still using the, well, he's got a suit.
(laughing)
- Andy Serkis just has a great costume like that.
- Well, that's how Downey Jr. got Iron Man.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the author,
Elizabeth Gaskell, died in the middle of saying,
"When I am dead, but only got as far as when..."
(laughing)
- So, how do people know?
- This is really interesting.
She, we should just say very quickly
before we get into it, this is Elizabeth Gaskell,
Mrs. Gaskell, as she was often known.
She was an English novelist.
She wrote short stories.
She was a biographer, most famously having written a book
about Charlotte Bronte.
Maybe we'll get onto that.
- Although that's certainly not like, you know,
she's most famously wrote.
- Yes, it really works in fiction.
- Yes, Mary Barton.
- Yes, she was one of our great Victorian novelists.
- But at the time, she was most famous
for writing biography.
- Her obituary basically said,
"Charlotte Bronte's biographer dead."
- Yes.
- When?
- When, exactly.
- So, what happened was, this is 1865.
She is 55 years old.
She's at her home, which is a sort of secret home
that she's purchased.
- Yeah, I feel like we'll go into that as that story.
- I'm just leaving some little plot moments as we go along.
So, she's at her house.
She's sitting with her daughters
and suddenly she keels over and she dies,
but she dies mid-anichthote.
And we know what happened
because of a reverend called Reverend Hawkes,
who recounted the story, as was told to him
by one of the daughters.
So, she was with her daughters and her son-in-law.
She was telling a story and she says,
"The judge said when,"
and then that's when she passed away.
Now, she was telling an anecdote.
Fortunately, one of the four people there
had already heard this anecdote,
presumably so many times
that they knew exactly what was coming next.
And the line that was meant to come next
was, "The judge said, 'When I'm dead,
'Lady Crompton can visit Rome.'"
A classic line.
- Yes, classic line.
- Everybody laughed.
I think you can see where she was going in the conversation
because a little bit of backstory is
that Justice Crompton had just died.
He was her son-in-law's dad
and I think her son-in-law's present.
So, the guy she's talking about
is the person who said, "When I am dead."
So, I imagine she was going on to say,
"So now, lucky lady Crompton can book her flight to Rome."
Because, you know, it was relevant.
It's funny 'cause he is dead,
so it's got a bit of gallows humor to it.
- You've sort of solved the end of the anecdote.
- I think that's what's happened.
Yeah, it's like Edwin Drude has finally been revealed.
- Thank God.
How great, though, to sort of not be lost on that last word.
Like, we should all practice our final words
with someone in confidence beforehand
so that if we do go mid-sentence,
I mean, I will be saying something
I've already said loads of times already
'cause I'm down to a limited stock of anecdotes now.
Just people know my things.
- Do you think it was a bit of a let down, though,
when they said, "Well, she started by saying
"wet," and then someone went, "No, no, actually,
"she's told that several times before."
- A bit of a bore, actually, Lizzie.
- Always whining about the same stuff.
That's probably why old people
repeat anecdotes all the time, isn't it?
Just to make sure that once they're saying their anecdote,
that we know where they were going with it.
- Very wise, yeah. - Yeah, that's very wise.
- She's, has anyone read this?
- I've read Mary Barton.
Thank you.
- You've read North and South.
- Thank you.
- I think I've read North and South.
Or Mary Barton.
- Or have you just seen the TV series?
- No, I'm gonna be a little bit heretical.
I don't think she's all that.
I mean, she's good.
They're good novels, but they're very Victorian.
They're a bit, you know, they haven't aged brilliantly.
- I think they've got, I think they really have.
I think she's much more radical than people.
- Yes, that's what I don't like, yeah, yeah.
- Mary Barton, it's a sort of a working class character,
and it's very much in that life,
which was, you know, not so much the dumb thing back then.
- I completely agree.
I think, like, her and Dickens are two people
who really engage with people
who are having a shit old time in life,
more than almost any other Victorian novelist, you know,
'cause they're all about factory workers,
the strife between bosses and laborers.
Not into that though, are you, Andy?
- I like reading about aristocrats
with minor social problems.
(all laughing)
That's my thing.
- 'Cause she did write about that stuff.
It was really controversial, wasn't it?
And in her community as well, particularly,
where she was representing these characters,
'cause I believe I actually haven't read any of her stuff,
but it sounds as if the other writers of the time
who were in the same field,
so Bronte, a friend of hers, Austin,
they would write about a period slightly gone,
whereas she was writing in the present,
and then that, so that was a bit more controversial.
And there's a few books.
She had one book called "Ruth,"
which was very controversial,
and they actually burnt copies in her local church.
- Yes, members of her own church.
- Yeah, which is. - Which is.
- Why did they do that?
- 'Cause it was debauched.
- It's about a fallen woman.
- Oh, yes, they should be about.
- I know how it's a threesome scene actually.
Wolfs dressed as gorillas.
- That's what fallen women do, yes.
- Gascall wasn't allowed into her husband's library.
He had to get books out for her.
It's very weird.
- Really? - Yeah.
- Local library, not like his personal.
Like, no, not his, she was allowed,
she was allowed the run of the house at home,
but no, he was a member of the library.
- She wasn't allowed his library, like Bluebeard.
- What's that?
- You know the tell of Bluebeard,
where he marries this young woman,
and he says, "You can go in any room you like,
"except for this one."
- You're talking about Beauty and the Beast.
- No, I'm not talking about Bluebeard.
- Are you talking about the pirate?
- What's in the room?
- No, everybody.
- Kurt Vonnegut novel?
- No, it's a very famous tale that none of you have heard of.
- I think I know what's in the room,
but you say it, you say it, what's in the room?
- So she finally, 'cause he keeps going away,
so she's wandering around all these rooms,
and she gets impatient.
She goes, "I just want to know what's in the mystery room."
So she uses the skeleton key.
I think it's the skeleton key, maybe I've embellished that.
And she opens it,
and inside are all the dead bodies of his previous wife.
- Oh!
- Don't draw attention to it, you idiot man.
But then he comes back, and he goes,
"Oh dear, looks like I'm gonna have to kill you too,
"because you opened the door."
- Another notch in the skeleton key.
- Yes, and the other notch is going to escape.
- Yes, it's a funny old story, isn't it?
- Where's it from?
- Is it an author we know?
Is it almost like a photo?
- No, it's very old, it's a very old tale.
- Right, I can't.
- That wasn't the case in Gaskell's husband's library,
as far as I know.
- Well, you don't know, because no one went in there.
- That's true.
- But the thing about her,
I think which kind of annoys people or bores at them,
is that she actually was really normal.
And the thing that's quite nice about her
is that she just basically had a really happy life.
She was quite conventional in how she lived, you know?
She married this vicar.
- Wait, or was she?
- Or what, do you know the hidden history of her orgies?
(laughing)
The mass orgies.
- Well, wasn't there a rumour going round when she died
that she and her husband were separated?
And that's why she was in the separate house.
- Well, I do think that that's got weight.
So I'm glad other people who aren't gossips like me
have said it, because I'm not a gossip.
- I only bring the fat, you're an intellectual.
- So separate house, she bought her own house.
- The house she dies in, yes.
- Without telling her husband.
- And the story is that it was a surprise for her husband,
like a retirement home.
Oh, we're going to move to the country,
this lovely mansion, and she was in the house
with all her daughters saying,
isn't daddy going to be delighted?
But I agree it's a bit--
- So all the children are there as well?
- Yeah, I mean, which is why slightly the story suggests
that that is what was going on.
But is he at home at the breakfast table at the house?
Well, I think it's very quiet this morning, isn't it?
- God, they're sleeping in today.
I bet they were separated.
- Okay, do you reckon?
- Yeah, I think so.
- Or it was a secret death house.
Sorry.
She thought my time is up.
I like how animals like to go and die under a log
or something.
She thought I'm going to die in a house
that's a huge faff to buy a full house, isn't it?
- Yeah, but houses are cheaper then.
I think it was probably easier to do.
A few years ago, a university got a collection of letters
that were written by someone who was friends
with Elizabeth Gaskell and they were having correspondence
and in it, Gaskell predicted her death that year.
She said to her, I'm not going to make it
to the end of the year.
- So I'd better buy a house.
- Yeah, but perhaps she didn't know
that she was doing so well.
She could sense it.
- There is an argument in Gaskell's life.
So the house, the secret house that she bought
was in Alton, in Hampshire, which is where--
- Jane Austen lived, yeah.
- For the last years of her life.
- And Alton Towers, is that there?
- No, it's in a completely different place.
It's hundreds of miles away.
But Gaskell grew up in Stratford-upon-Avon,
home of--
- Shakespeare.
- So is this a lay line?
- You guys weren't quick enough.
(laughing)
- So is this an argument for lay lines
in terms of literary creativity, probably?
- There's certainly something going on, isn't there?
- Yeah, certainly, I think.
Do you know she gave us the word "squiffy" to mean drunk?
- Really?
- Oh, brilliant.
I know, I love that fact.
- I love the sound of her, I have to say.
As in, when you read about her social life,
there is this comparison, I think, with Dickens,
where Dickens was partying all the time.
He was everywhere.
He went around the world.
That's exactly what Gaskell did
in a time where it felt like
that would have been much harder.
She was a mother of how many children
did she have in total?
- Five.
- I think she was pregnant seven times.
A couple of the children didn't live.
- Okay, right.
Five daughters and one son, yeah, survived,
which is quite a lot.
- That is, yeah.
She was writing, she wrote quite a few novels,
a lot of short stories, a biography.
She traveled the world.
She was constantly said to be dancing
half the night at parties.
She was a real socialite.
I think she sounds really fun.
- I think you would have gotten along with her very well.
- Yeah, it feels like it. - It was a real butterfly.
- She even wrote one of her novels
while she was staying with Florence Nightingale.
Like, she just touches all these little elements
of the past, which I really love.
- She sounds like someone who deserves
to have been let in the library.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- I don't know though.
- I know.
- It's a slippery slope, isn't it?
- I think she should have been allowed in that library.
- You let them in libraries one day, you know, the next day.
- They just go in there willy-nilly.
- Yeah, exactly.
- It's like getting squiffy.
- I have another theory about her
that I think we should spread this gossip.
Her brother, John, and have you read about him?
He was seven years older than her.
So she had, her mom died when she was one
and she was sent to live with an aunt who she loved
and she lived in this very female dominated community.
It was all women.
But she did have this older brother
who still lived with her dad and they wrote
to each other a lot and he was really fond of her.
And then he joined the merchant navy
and they kept writing to each other.
And then he just vanishes.
And everyone says he was either abducted by pirates
in India or his ship sank.
But she, after writing the years, she's 17.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Bluebeard, yes, kidnapped.
- A bluebeard and a blackbeard, brothers or friends,
they must know each other.
- They're naughty cousins.
(laughing)
- So, yes, it's vicious.
And she never mentioned it.
She never mentioned him to her kids except to say,
"Oh, I don't really remember him."
- Really?
- Of course you'd remember him.
- Too painful or?
- Well, I don't know.
- What's your theory?
You seem to be driving at something here, Anna.
- I think-
- Is he in the library?
- I think his corpse was on the shelves.
I think maybe he ran away with like an Indian lady
and told only her and she can never tell anyone.
- That's a good theory.
- Yeah, I like that.
- Just on people who wrote anonymously.
'Cause Gaskell was always, by a lady,
would appear on her title pages.
I think she was Mrs. Gaskell later in her career.
But I didn't really realize how common this was.
So between 1750 and 1790, 80% of all novels
did not list an author on the title page.
Male and female writers, it just wasn't a thing.
For women, it was because it was a bit risqu
to be writing a novel.
It was too similar to prostitution,
which I mean, that's genuinely the theory I wrote.
But by a lady was a good phrase to use
because it showed that the author
was someone of a decent class.
So Jane Austen was by a lady
and then later on by the same lady
who brought you sense and sensibility.
I was genuinely at that.
And she never saw her own name on a title page, Jane Austen.
She's kind of tragic.
- Yeah, it's sad.
Do you think other books at the time
were written by a different lady?
(all laughing)
- Not that lady.
I can't believe it's not a lady.
Yeah.
But all of it, like Tristan Shandy, Byron stuff,
Jonathan Swift, it's all anonymous.
- Really? - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- 'Cause the novel was quite new then, wasn't it?
Maybe it was still a bit like,
oh, this might not go down very well in history.
- It was risqu, definitely.
And it was quite fun as well.
So Jonathan Swift, he sent his stuff
to a publisher via someone else.
So there was no way of tracing it back to him.
- Really? - Yeah, yeah.
- And then when the printer said,
"Look, who is the author of 'Gulliver's Travels'?"
Swift and his friend, Alexander Pope,
they pretended, "I don't know, I don't know who wrote this."
They would even write letters to each other privately,
saying, "Who wrote this 'Gulliver's Travels' book?"
Completely between themselves.
- Yeah. - "I don't know.
It's so funny."
They just, it was a bit of a game, you know?
- But was there a royalty thing
that they would still have in place?
- Yeah, I guess you could be paid anonymously
quite easily at the time.
- There's just one person who's called like Anna Lady,
who's just funneling all the money accidentally sent out.
(laughing)
- Gaskell obviously gave all her money to her husband
at first, and in fact, I think it went to him automatically
'cause married women weren't allowed to earn money.
- You really don't approve of this husband, I tell you.
He came from his library.
- Apparently it was very affectionate.
I was listening to a--
- And that's why she bought a secret house.
(laughing)
- I think it was a little joke.
He was the one who suggested she write
to get over the death of her one-year-old son
who very sadly died, and he said,
"As to help you with grieving, write a novel."
Probably not suspecting she was gonna become
a world famous novelist.
And yes, when she got paid, it went straight to him,
and he sort of jokely pocketed it saying,
"Well, you know, women shouldn't be earning
"or in control of the purse strings, should they?
"I'll give you some pocket money."
But I think it was all meant--
- Was he saying that?
- All meant to Jess, too.
It was all meant to Jess.
- It was a different time.
It's so hard to know when it's written, isn't it?
You didn't know the tone.
- Yeah, they needed more emojis, I think.
(laughing)
- How much of history would be different
if emojis existed?
(laughing)
- I have nothing to offer but blood,
toil, tears, and sweat.
Winky.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that one of Ovid's tips
for seducing a woman you fancied
was to pretend you'd seen dust on her cleavage
and then go to brush it off.
- It's a great line, isn't it?
Oh, you've got a very dusty cleavage.
(laughing)
It's what every woman wants to hear.
- Yeah.
- Anna, when you say go to brush it off,
follow through and actually brush it off?
- Follow through, yes.
So these were his exact words.
- Follow.
- Go to and then complete the brush.
- Complete.
- Do you think it's like an updated thing of the,
no, sorry, a down-dated thing?
(laughing)
Because now it's, if you've got an eyelash,
oh, you've got an eyelash on your cheek, isn't it?
And then the man like removes the eyelash.
- You know this man, come on.
- I have a pocket full of eyelashes
that I try and subtly sprinkle onto people's cheeks.
- Yeah, that's true.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Absolute classic, absolute classic.
- Have you had that tried on you?
Is that, does it work?
- Oh, you've got an eyelash on your...
(laughing)
And then they lift it off your face.
- What harm is that eyelash doing there?
- And then they go take a, make a wish.
So maybe it's the same.
It was like, take you, you've got some dust
on your cleavage.
And then they hold it out going, make a wish.
- Blow on it like a dandelion.
I think this book of ours might contain a lot of things
that you guys could try out.
And I'd love to hear the results.
So this is a book called "Ars Amatoria"
and Ovid was a Roman writer.
He wrote this in year two AD.
- And it got in early.
- Box fresh.
- It got in early, so couple of millennia ago.
His exact words were, as often happens,
if perchance, a little dust should fall
on the bosom of the fair,
it must be brushed off with your fingers.
And if there should be no dust,
still brush off that none.
- It would work for me.
(laughing)
I'd like it.
- He has so much good stuff in there.
Oh, he also said, "Let it be your object
to please the husband of the fair one that you fancy."
I suppose we're assuming.
- Oh, this is naughty.
- Because once made a friend,
he will be more serviceable for your designs.
So I think you'll get invitations to the house
a little bit more.
- Not like come in and have a hairy threesome.
- No.
- No, he did specify that.
(laughing)
- Specify no bad gorilla costumes and no threesome.
- I mean, he was a very risque writer at the time.
He was, what's the word?
He was not evicted, he was deported.
- Yeah.
- He was banned.
- Exiled.
- Exiled to the worst place in the world at the time.
He claimed seems to have been a completely normal city
in modern day Romania,
but compared with Rome, I guess it was rubbish.
- Okay.
- And for the last 10 years of his life,
he spent there writing the "Tristii",
which were basically sad letters saying,
"Please can I come back to Rome?"
To everyone he knew in Rome, including the emperor.
But I think he was evicted because he was,
he was quite a libidness,
quite a licentious writer,
lots of sexy stuff in the Ars Amatoria,
lots of love poetry,
but it's quite mysterious why he was actually kicked out.
- Yeah, we don't know.
- No one knows for sure.
- There might have been a scandal
involving the daughter of the emperor, Augustus.
- Yeah, Junior.
I think maybe it was the scandal.
- It might have been a general back-to-basics campaign
that Augustus was running,
'cause Rome was getting a little bit CD
and Augustus didn't really like that.
And he was trying to raise public morals a bit
and Ovid was stood out there saying,
"Get Dustin", you know, all of that.
So it's really unclear why he was.
- Get Dustin.
(all laughing)
- Bang!
- Man for some Dustin, these ladies.
- So there were three volumes of this book, right?
The Art of Love, first one, which teaches the reader
how to seduce a woman.
The second one then is, okay, okay, you've got her.
Now, how do you continue to seduce her?
Which is very interesting.
And then the third one is how for women,
so there must have been feedback going,
"Hey, this is all very man-based.
Can we get the opposite version?"
So he wrote, "How a woman can seduce a man."
But the fourth volume, which is a separate book,
is the most exciting one.
- The Marsupials.
- Yeah, lover.
(all laughing)
- Develop a pouch in your front.
- Remedia Amoris.
This is the book of how if it's unrequited love,
do you stop loving a person?
What a great idea for a book.
- It's a terrific sequel.
- It's fantastic.
- The publishers must have been absolutely chuffed.
It's got great advice in it as well, the Remedia.
There's, "Join the Army."
- Oh, boom.
- Become a lawyer.
Become a farmer.
Get a hobby.
- How is this supposed to get you out of unrequited love?
- I think it's when your heart broken,
it's how to get over it.
- It's distraction.
- It's not like my dad gave me some advice
once when I was a teenager
and I was very heartbroken over a boy
who did not love me back.
And my dad said, "Just picture him on the loo."
- Oh, wow.
- Really?
- I can see that going in there.
- Well, there is a similar-ish thing.
- Yeah, it is.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Did it work?
- No, and I said to Dad,
'cause he said, "I was in love with Sarah."
I can't remember her's name.
There's a girl he was in love with when he was a teenager.
And he said, "And I..."
- I'm gonna shout at her right now.
(all laughing)
- Cleveland, Sarah Cleveland.
- Oh, thank God, great.
Now we're legally secure, yeah.
- So I was in love with Sarah Cleveland
and I would picture her on the loo to get me over her.
And I said, "Did it work?"
And he went, "No."
- Right.
- If anything, I developed a weird fetish
that has dawned my life ever since.
(all laughing)
- Well, okay, well, Ovid wrote,
"Maybe this would have worked alternatively."
And this is about if you're a man
and you had your heart broken by a woman,
go and see her unannounced, right?
- Early in the morning.
- When she hasn't got her makeup on.
And you'll be reminded.
- She's got two.
(all laughing)
- She does, don't I claim it?
- They need a broom to get that out of love.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, he also, the classic kind of like teenage movie
techniques burn all the items that are associated with them.
So sit with a fire and throw the letters in,
the love letters and the bits of clothing
or whatever's been left over in your house.
Do that and, but what a great book.
What a forward thinking book.
- He had to, yes, there are some ropey bits of it.
Maybe it doesn't stand up to a lot of feminism,
but he was a very pro makeup, actually.
He wrote a whole separate book on why women
should wear makeup because there was a lot of pushback
in society at the time about how women were
overdressing their faces with makeup.
- Augustus, back to basics.
Let's take off that thick slap.
- Exactly.
- And just have natural beauty.
- And he was like, "No, natural beauty."
- Yeah, no, have you seen their natural faces underneath?
And that's also a good read.
- Lots of slap, dusty bosoms.
(all laughing)
- He gets quoted a lot as a kind of proto pickup artist.
- Yeah.
- And there was a brief trend when that sort of--
- Neil Strauss, the game.
- Sort of grim thing of pickup artistry was doing a thing.
A lot of like proto bros were saying,
"You can't read Ovid."
In much the same way that they were all saying,
"You've got to read Sun Tzu's, The Art of War."
- Are you reading that?
Are you really?
- Are you actually reading Marx or really,
it says meditations, are you?
- It did actually really remind me of that.
I didn't realise people are connected to those.
It reminded me of that game mentality.
But a lot of his advice is quite sort of modern,
like when he says how you should befriend the lady's maid.
- Yes.
- And that's how to get in there.
- Yes, very clever.
- So it is a bit like that, yeah.
I mean, he's--
- How would he do that with a friend who's a lady's maid?
What kind of life do you need for a gig?
(all laughing)
- So modern.
- That is what you do.
(all laughing)
- But one of the people who's written loads about this
is a woman called Donna Zuckerberg, who is a classicist.
And she's written a book called Classics Beyond the Manosphere,
all about this.
And she is an interesting person.
She's the only Zuckerberg sibling
not to have become a tech titan.
- Wow.
- Yeah, she's a sister of Mark
and there are four, I think four Zuckerbergs.
And yeah.
- Well, she, yeah, she wrote a book as well
as the one that you were talking about
called Not All Dead White Men.
And the idea was she was talking about
how the sort of alt-right of America
have really harnessed all the Roman ideas and so on.
And of it is very much connected to the Neil Strauss
the game pickup artist movement that's going on.
And she wants to keep showing the connection
between those two things.
And it's so interesting that she is Mark Zuckerberg's sister
because the very first thing that he did
was a site called FaceMash
where you got students who went to Harvard University,
both women, their pictures, which he hacked off a system
and you ranked who you thought was hotter.
That was the original Facebook, basically.
And so she must have been horrified by that
and decided to dedicate her life
to showing what a misogynistic move that was by her brother.
- Sounds like they have parted ways.
Well, so she's saying Ovid was a misogynist
and so these guys sort of see--
- She's not necessarily, she's sort of saying that
as Andy was saying before,
it's that thing of using an old historical idea
to give legitimacy to why you're--
- We can't all blame the fact
that men keep the threatening my maid.
(laughing)
- Oh, no, Ovid.
- 'Cause a lot of it does obviously read quite sleazy,
but a lot of it doesn't.
You know, he says, send very eloquent love notes.
Cry in front of your loved one.
I don't recall seeing Andrew Tate saying,
"You've gotta be able to cry in front of her."
You know, that's not, it is a bit different.
- But what's also different
in which Donna Zuckerberg writes about in her book
is that it was actually,
it was quite a lot more dangerous
in the times the advice that he was giving
because when he was saying things like,
befriend the husband of the person you're fancying,
there was death penalties back in the day
for things like if you were having a child out of wedlock,
if you were, well, it was dangerous.
It was, there would be certain things
that you weren't allowed to do that in this day and age.
You'd get away as sort of just, it's bad manners, but--
- Is that how you think the affair's gonna go down then?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- That's Charlie Berger's.
- No, but yeah, so she points out
that the risk level was much higher back then
if you were employing these tactics
and they worked on certain women in society.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- And he suffered the pay the price
'cause he suffered relegatio.
- He did.
- That was the official term for the exile
that he was put through.
- And he died out in--
- Died out there?
Relegatio was the mildest form of exile.
- What I want to know is when he died,
was he with somebody?
Was he, did he find love?
Did he die in exile alone?
- His last word was when, and sadly--
(laughing)
We don't know the answer.
No, he died very unhappy.
The last 10 years, he was writing these trusty-eye letters
and it was, his book had been banned from libraries
and he said, "Look, it's completely awful out here
"in modern day Romania."
He said, "You know, the wine freezes in the jars
"and the ice is so thick on the black sea,
"the dolphins can't even jump through the water."
You know, really horrible, poor guy.
But he was constantly writing poems to his friends
and to the emperor and to his wife,
probably in that order, to defend his cause,
say, "I'm really sorry about all the licentious stuff.
"I can change, and I will change,
"and create pity for himself," and it did not work.
- That's so sad, it reminds me a bit of,
you know how John Dunn used to write lots of sexy poems?
And then, in his later life, he did lots of like,
"Nuh," all his poems were like, "No, ah, God, God, ah."
They were all, that was the kind of vibe.
- Right.
- I didn't know he'd got more like that.
I feel like I've read more of the sexy stuff.
- Yeah, as only ones are all sexy,
and then the later ones are all more self-hating,
"God, forgive me," and I'm like, "Sexy past."
- God, we all turn into such balls, don't we?
It's like Tolstoy.
No one ever stays the fun playboy/playgirl.
Yeah, it's very sad.
- Bit of a good update on Ovid.
I do have a bit of good news about the...
- So right with that sentence.
- Is this breaking news?
Has this just come in?
- It's recent because Ovid's exile was eventually revoked
in 2017, when Rome's city council,
who were not what they once were, I suspect,
voted to repair the serious wrong that he had suffered,
and say his exile was now officially ended.
- Was he like the knight in Indiana Jones 3?
Is he loud?
- He came back, he came back.
- Oh, so bad.
- You decided, why is he here?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that the largest collection
of contemporary South African art in the world
is in Nando's.
- Which branch?
- Every branch.
No, no, I'm joking.
The Manchester, Salford Key's one.
- That's a good one.
- Yeah, and it's big.
So there was a terrific piece in The Guardian recently
about Nando's collection of modern South African art.
Nando's is a chicken restaurant.
For anyone who doesn't know,
I don't know, we have American listeners.
Do you have Nando's?
- I don't think they do have Nando's
in the United States.
- In America, should we have a Nando's everywhere?
- Nando's is global, yeah.
- Yeah.
- But it's the biggest here, I think it's worth explaining.
I've only been to one.
- Here is the highest ever peri peri penetration
on the planet, I think, in this country.
You've only ever been to one Nando's.
- Would you guys, in fact, yeah.
- Oh, on tour?
- On tour, was it?
Was it the one at Salford?
- It was the one at Salford, yeah.
And I only went for the art.
(laughing)
- Would you like anything, madam?
Just a tour of your 70s pieces, please, yeah.
Seriously, you've only been to Nando's once in your life.
- Yeah, I don't really like dry chicken.
- Well, it is quite dry chicken.
- It's dry.
- But he says that there are more than 20 countries, Nando's.
- Uh-huh.
- I think you've got to be more than that, you know.
- Yeah.
- Actually, it's not that much, isn't it, really,
in the grand scheme of countries.
- It depends on the countries.
- Yeah, if you're only in Tuvalu, Vanuatu.
- Yeah, then you're doing something wrong
in your marketing, I think.
- Yeah, so I don't know if they're in the USA,
but yeah, they've got about 1,200 restaurants,
and across those restaurants,
they own 32,000 odd pieces of art,
and they buy another couple of thousand every year.
And it's the main, seems to be the main thing,
keeping the South African contemporary art market going.
- Well, it's really nice.
- They re-support artists, yeah.
- They have a thing called the Creative Block Programme,
where they basically hand out wooden blocks
for it to be drawn on.
So it's original commissions as well,
and they have programs where they look after artists.
It's, I don't know, the rest of the business is like--
- Sorry, they like send wooden blocks to South Africans
and say, "Draw something on this and send it back to us."
- Well, two artists who are on the scheme,
like they run all these schemes for young artists,
and they run a thing where it's an apprenticeship program
where they take disadvantaged young people
who don't have skills, and they train them up over three years
to become mosaicists or ceramicists.
- Oh, wow!
- It's quite cool, yeah.
And then obviously you get skills.
So yeah, so Nando's doing something quite good.
I don't know many other restaurants that--
- No.
- Oh, any of the restaurants that do this.
Does Pizza Express have a--
- Well, we didn't know this about Nando's, you know.
Pizza Express might have the largest collection
of statues in the world, but we don't know.
They also do a mentorship scheme,
which is basically for furniture, lighting designers.
They have a lot of this stuff.
The only one that I can think of
that does a similar kind of scheme is Whole Foods.
Globally, in every Whole Foods,
they hire someone who is the artist in store.
So when you go into Whole Foods,
you might see a lot of different art.
You might see a lot of different,
like paper mache sculptures around the mushrooms.
They might have a big mushroom.
That's one person who's doing it bespoke
for the Whole Foods as part of the payroll.
- Really? - Yeah.
- And they're always sculptures of the food.
- No, no, like whatever it is,
whatever they decide to do
as the resident artist of Whole Foods,
they get to do. - Okay, sorry.
I thought you meant it was like, you know,
in Japan when they show sushi,
they have sushi models outside restaurants.
It's not like that.
You're like in the carrots
and you've got caramel. - No, no, no.
It'll be signs, it will be posters,
whatever they want to do, but that's their job.
They're the Whole Foods artist.
- That's really cool.
- Yeah, I was quite slow on the uptake on that.
I was thinking, what are they working behind the counter?
It's like, well, let's take an artist
and get them giving out fish.
- Give them a proper career.
- Something that'll earn them some money.
- I just want, we're buying this salmon, this broccoli,
and I'd like a sketch of me, please,
while you ring it up.
- Domino's Pizza.
- Do they have corporate art?
- Well, they have a really close link to Frank Lloyd Wright.
Like probably the most famous architects,
20th century American architects, one of them.
And like, you know, had all these utopian visions
of what he wanted to do with his architecture.
And the founder of Domino's Pizza,
this chap called Thomas Monaghan,
and he bloody loved Frank Lloyd Wright,
it was in the '60s when he founded him,
and he was responsible in the '80s
for Frank Lloyd Wright's works,
like his furnishings and his decorative art,
going up in price, single-handedly,
'cause he just spent millions.
- Did Frank design the little table
that goes inside the pizza box?
- I don't understand.
So what was Frank doing to the pizzas?
- Ah, so...
- He was a side job just to fund the architecture.
- I don't think Frank gave a shit about pizzas,
but I think he was dead by this point.
(all laughing)
- So this is getting more tenuous by the moment.
- No, because the whole of Domino's Pizza
is like based around Frank Lloyd Wright architecture.
So its center of operations is a place called Domino's Farms,
it's World HQ, and the whole building
is meant to imitate Frank Lloyd Wright's
prairie style buildings.
Because the founder of Domino's is so obsessed with him,
and there's a whole section in it,
which is a gallery and exhibition
of Frank Lloyd Wright artworks, which he's bought up.
He's spent more on Frank Lloyd Wright artwork
than anyone else in the world.
- Rosie, do you collect art?
Have you got any pieces in your house?
- No, not yet.
- Okay.
- Anyone else?
- I might from this Frank man.
(all laughing)
Again, I don't know if he's still available to buy from.
Are you an Ando's fan?
So like you, I find the chicken a bit dry.
Also, is it free range?
I don't know if the chicken's free range, is it?
- It's already good.
- And like, if I have battery chicken, I get chicken guilt.
- Okay, but it is an interesting place in general,
because, well, it started in 1987, as did I.
- That is interesting.
- Yeah, yeah.
So, you know, I feel an affinity with them,
but there is this big thing of the Nando's black card,
and I know I've got three people who've all got one,
which means you have free Nando's anytime, any place.
- Forever and ever.
- Yeah, my buddy Tom Davis had it.
Do you know Big Tom?
- Yes.
- Yeah, Tom and I used to go almost every day
with his black card in Kentish town.
- You've got to use one of the black cards.
- Many times.
- And why was he given one?
'Cause the person I know who had one was a radio host
who was cool at the time.
- It's just for being famous.
I think they're open for that.
- Tom wasn't famous at the time.
- How did he get one then?
- Tom called up Nando's,
and he said, "I'm interested in the black card."
And then he got called up to the chicken council,
and he had to present his case for why he wanted it.
- Who sits on the chicken council?
- That's a, we don't know, that's like the library.
We don't know what's going on.
(all laughing)
- Are they in chicken suits?
- Well, they wanted chicken suits,
but they only had gorilla suits at the time.
- Do you know anyone who has the dishume dice?
You heard about the dishume dice.
So Isha Anakbar has the dishume dice,
and what it is, is at the end, you throw the dice,
and if it lands, if you get two sixes,
then you get to get the whole meal for free.
- Really?
- No way.
And what do you have to do to get the dishume dice?
- I don't know.
- Yes, 'cause that feels like a relatively low-risk
financial investment for them.
Send a couple of plastic dice out to some influencers,
and they have a one-in-thirty-six chance
of getting their meal for free.
- I went, and he rolled, and we'd ordered so much food,
and he got it, we got it all for free,
and they were so...
- He got two sixes.
- I think they were really upset
because they looked like they didn't even know...
- Oh my god.
I mean, yeah.
- 'Cause you can get them weighted.
You can get those, but that's what I would do.
I would go off and have them weighted
so that no matter what, they land on six.
- Maybe you can't do that
'cause their special dishume dice.
- They must be designed to look like this.
But if you pay just a few thousand pounds
to a dice craster, he'll be able to make you two double six
every time, but then that'll go on the spreadsheet
at Dishume's queue.
- Well, you know that spot, don't tell your mate.
I know the world-leading dice.
He makes the weighted dices.
He does them for people like, "Get out!"
- Dan, I thought you were just bullshitting then
when you were saying with such authority,
you know you can get any dice you like weighted.
- I had drinks with him with the world-leading...
- You're giving away background secrets.
Are you supposed to tell us?
- We can redact that in the, yeah.
- He's very good friends with my friend
who's the Loch Ness Monster Hunter
and we had drinks on Loch Ness
and he told us all about the dice he showed us.
Anyway, that's an incredible fact about Dishume.
- Yeah, that's terrific.
- That's an incredible fact of yours about Tom
because Nando's insist that the only rule is
they never give their black card to anyone who asked for it.
They say it's just if you're famous.
- But how wonderful.
Before this, I didn't even know there was a chicken committee.
(laughing)
So you think, what are the chicken committee
doing the rest of the chicken?
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's wall-to-wall.
They're pecking, they're walking.
(laughing)
- I was looking at some logo stuff.
Corporate art logos.
Do you guys know/remember?
I don't know if any of you are old enough.
Rosie, don't know how old you are, you could be 60.
- I am 60.
- And if so, you might remember the time
when the Starbucks logo was naked.
- Oh.
- So you know she has hair over her breast now,
she used to have tits out.
- Oh, naked.
- Stop it, did she?
Are you gonna have to Google this right now?
- Yeah, 'cause she's a mermaid, right?
- Is she?
- Yeah, yeah, she's a mermaid.
Although she has two tails,
so it's quite an unconventional mermaid.
- Oh, look, there she is.
- She's actually quite unattractive and frumpy.
- She's very unattractive.
I don't wanna judge her.
- I'll judge her.
- This is a 15th century drawing of a siren though,
and that was the Starbucks logo.
- She looks like you're drunk uncle at a wedding.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
She does look drunk,
'cause she looks like she's saying,
"I've caught these two fish,"
and doesn't realize she's holding her own lower body.
- Oh, that's classic, yeah, yeah.
- Wow, so for two women who are very positive
about Mrs. Gaskell, it's not universal sisterhood.
- No, no.
- This is not what a feminist looks like.
- I don't know, they're both in agreement though.
At least it's consistency.
- You just gotta go with us.
- That's what true femininity looks like.
- So that was the Starbucks logo,
a weird 15th century--
- Why did they change it?
That's not it.
- Well, it's just an upgrade, isn't it?
Yeah, it's a Nordic woodcut.
She is, yeah, boobs out and bits of tail in each hand.
She looks more like she's holding fish now,
'cause you can't see the bottom of her tail.
So if you look at the Starbucks logo,
it looks like she's just holding two dead fish.
- Right.
- I don't think they sell anything with fish.
- They don't sell anything fish-related.
- No, they do, they do the tuna macchiato.
That is lovely.
(laughing)
That's really nice.
So it was a controversial
because she agreed to the one woodcut,
but then they put her on all of the cups and all of the--
- Yes.
- Yeah, right.
- Just to tie together this with the howling,
I didn't spot any artworks on display in howling too.
- Right.
- But it's really hard to use original art in films.
There are, like the world of image rights
has tightened up a lot lately.
You can't just, if you want to show the Mona Lisa
or Girl with a Palm Earring or whatever,
you can't just stick a print in a frame
and pretend in the film.
'Cause artistic estates get a bit funny about that
and rightful owners and all of this.
So lots of times when they make a film
which features art, or they want it to include
really famous art, they take weeks and weeks
making replicas and then the estate of the artist
insists that the artwork is destroyed,
that the filmmakers record and film
the destruction of the artwork
and then send them the evidence
of the fake artwork being destroyed.
- That's so interesting 'cause you would figure--
- That's insane.
- You'd figure that would go on a memorabilia market
as opposed to being passed off as a--
- I don't know what they're worried about.
It might be passing off, yeah.
There was a film about Basquiat in 1996
and the estate asked for so much money
to use Basquiat images that they said,
well, we can't make the film.
So instead, they just knocked up a load
of Basquiat style artwork.
But then they had to have a lawyer look at all of the artworks
and say, that's fine, that's fine,
that's too close to actual Basquiat, can't use that.
- Wow, wow.
- So all of that is sort of artist approved, yeah.
- Is any film producer ever experimented
when they get that initial rejection
with saying, okay, well instead,
we'll draw a load of badly sketched cock and balls
to claim that's Basquiat
and see what the estate has to say about that?
- I don't know.
- I think the house is strong position.
- You'd be a great film producer.
You'd be like really ballsy.
- That doesn't work for the movie.
(all laughing)
- If it's a da Vinci code, it's a bluff.
- Yeah, in the da Vinci code,
if the Mona Lisa looked like--
- It's like a cock and balls.
(all laughing)
You've got to hope that they bring first.
Otherwise, you're stuck with the wind film.
- Who's gonna look more stupid?
I don't know, I don't know.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @triberland on Instagram, Andy.
- I'm @andrewhunterm on please go.
- Are you on social media?
- Oh yes, I am @rosyisaholt on Instagram
and various others.
It sounds rude, but it's not.
- It's not rude. - It's not rude.
- It could be. - It's just the way
I delivered it.
- And Anna, if they want to get to us as a group.
- You can get us on Instagram @knowssuchthingasafish
or Twitter @knowssuchthing or podcast@qi.com
is the email address.
- Yeah, and Rosie, if they want to find anything else
about what you're up to,
is there anywhere else they should be checking out?
- Check out my podcast, Noncensored, which is very funny.
- Well, do check that out.
You can also go to our website,
Knowssuchthingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
There's also links to a live show that we're doing
later this year in Sheffield
as part of the Crossed Wires Festival.
That's gonna be really exciting.
There's also bits of merchandise
and there is a link to our secret club, Club Fish,
where we have bonus episodes that go up all the time.
Do check that out.
Otherwise, just come back next week.
We will be back with another episode.
We will see you then.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]