(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Anna Tyshinski, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and James Harkin, and once again,
we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
- My fact is that one traditional Irish recipe
for Blemange involves moss.
- Here we go.
- So, this is a cool fact about an old Irish pudding,
and it's--
- That's what they say if you have to say it's cool.
- Yeah, they have to tell the listener.
- It's interesting, and it's cool.
And it's actually from a hack-eye magazine,
which I know you read--
- That's Anna, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, sort of.
- You stole my 19.
- I know, I'm on your turf already.
But basically, there is this pudding,
and it's made from a thing called dried carrageen.
Okay, now, it's called moss, it's called Irish moss,
it's not actually moss, it's a kind of algae,
and it's brown and crusty stuff
when you take it out of the water, you dry out.
- Sounds delicious.
(laughing)
- You have to boil it in milk for 20 minutes.
- Okay.
- And the thing is, when you boil it in milk,
it vomits out this huge--
- Sounds absolutely delicious.
- You thought we were having your own cookery show.
You were next in my jello.
- It sort of vomits out this jelly stuff.
- Yeah.
- And you add the sugar and vanilla
to make it slightly sweet, and you whisk it all up,
and then you let it chill a bit.
- I just love just going off the jello analogy,
the way that you really, when you said vomiting up,
you said it a few times, and you really stressed it.
And then when you got to the nice bit
of adding some vanilla and sugar,
you were like, "Oh yeah, we'll just gloss over that."
That's fine.
- Yeah, and then you've got your moss blommage.
- And it apparently, it's quite crap, isn't it?
- Well, what's bad about it?
- I just think it's extremely bland,
but I think it's good if you add a little bit.
- It doesn't really taste of any,
some people say it tastes of the sea.
- Yes.
- But actually, I think it just tastes really bland.
And they used to give it to sick people, didn't they?
If you were ill and infirm,
you might get some of this pudding.
It's in a 19th century handbook of invalid cooking
by Murray Boland, that's one of the early recipes.
- Okay, right.
- And other recipes in that book,
oatmeal mush, delicious, scraped beef.
- Scraped beef.
- Milk lemonade, which just sounds disgusting to me.
Apart from it contains sherry, milk lemonade.
And restorative jelly.
And the restorative part of that is it has port in it.
- Oh, okay, nice.
- Like alko jelly kind of thing.
- I wish we were doing hello fresh ads in this period,
where these were the recipes that we were advertising.
- This algae, this seaweed,
how do you pronounce it again, Andy?
- I said carrageen.
- Carrageen, yeah.
This is one of those stealth things that's in our life
in so many different ways that we don't quite recognize.
So if you look at the back of the ingredients list
on many of the things in your house,
you're gonna find this as one of the elements.
So it's in things like toothpaste.
It's in shampoo and cosmetics.
Firefighters use it to get a better foam
when they're fighting fires.
It's part of that.
Yeah, it's used in that.
It's used in personal lubricants.
Check your ingredients at home.
But it's everywhere.
Shoe polish everywhere.
- Laxatives.
- Laxatives, yeah.
- Helps those slide out.
It seems to be a couch.
- It's good for helping things slide out.
- Yeah, yeah.
But it's very controversial.
Did you guys read about the rabid controversy
surrounding carrageen?
Well--
- Is this athletes?
- Oh, it's not, maybe there are two.
- Oh no, okay, okay.
- Oh my God, okay, let's compare controversies.
This is just that it could be very bad for you
and cause deadly diseases.
It doesn't.
But--
- What?
- Yeah, there was a roller coaster.
- 'Cause it was a very much a one dip roller coaster.
- This is a rumour that goes around in health circles
about carrageenan, which is like the extract
from the seaweed and carrageenan.
- Ultra concentrated.
- Essence.
- Yes, and that is used, as we've said,
in lots of thicknesses.
It's also in ice cream, cottage cheese, soy milk,
things like that.
And there was a academic called Joanne Tabakman,
who I think is still going campaigning against it,
who said a few years ago that it caused all sorts of
cancers, Parkinson's, heart disease, things like that.
She was actually looking at a different thing.
So it turned out someone looked into the study
and she was looking at something that was called like--
- Gamma radiation.
- Yeah, a slightly different kind of seaweed.
But it's great, and if you go on any health website,
it's like avoid carrageen, it will give you cancer,
it'll give you heart attacks, it'll give you--
So don't believe it.
- It's almost carcinogen.
Like the word is very similar, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Maybe that's what she studied.
She looked at carcinogens and said,
"Well, these all cause cancer."
- Next to each other in the dictionary.
- Its latter name is really fun.
It's called Chondus Crispus.
- Ah!
- It's just a nice-- - Chondus Crispus.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I'd like to hear about the sport in controversy,
and I'd like to have a guess of what it might be,
'cause it's like a slippery thing, right?
So maybe they attach it to toboggan's
when you do bobsled, and it makes you fly down the bobsled.
- That's correct, that's absolutely right.
(laughing)
- Or, here's another version.
They put a load of it in the swimming pool,
and it thickens up the water,
and it means that you can just run across the water
in a swimming race.
- That would help everyone though.
You have to put it in one lane.
(laughing)
One lane, someone doing the 50 meters.
- Yeah, okay.
- Or you could do it in your opponent's lane,
and so it slows them down.
- I'd also like a quarter swimming through the big pool.
- I think you have to have a lot of caragine
to turn water into a solid.
- Imagine the Olympic swimming pool.
You've got one beautiful clear lane of water,
and all the others are plamange, basically.
(laughing)
- So it's neither of those things.
- It's neither of those.
No, the Australian cricket team
have been using it for years to--
- No, they haven't. - Classic, all right.
(laughing)
It's bad that I believe that.
- What it is, is actually, I don't think it's a control,
I jumped the gun a bit.
I think it's also been used by athletes
and bodybuilders, although I'm not completely sure
if what capacity.
- Maybe make them smoother.
To make them look smoother.
- That might be it, yeah.
- There's the control.
- I said I jumped the gun on it, I really.
But there is, okay, there is a thing.
It's an aphrodisiac, which is good news, but for rats.
- So, okay. - Good news for rats.
- It's fancy rats. - It's fancy rats.
- Really, I mean, it really,
and I think it's a fertility aid, actually.
It ramps up your testicles, is the phrase I've written down.
- Ramps up your testicles.
- You don't want to put ramps up your testicles,
that's gonna be.
- Odd, not too much and tiny little effusions now.
Climbing up, wheelchair-friendly testicles.
Fun.
- What does it do, sorry, to your testicles?
- It ramps them up.
- What's that mean, like the outer coating,
or like the inner ball?
- It gives the sperm a lot more motility,
and I think it makes the balls bigger, maybe, as well.
- The caragine is responsible for my fair lady,
the musical. - Really?
- Well, we'll see.
- Wow.
- So, it's used in medical circuits.
- These are terrible headlines,
these are like those websites, they're like,
did you know that?
- I mean, it's just not there.
- The controversy, you're seaweed.
- Well, it's used medicinally, Irish masks.
It's good for like your throat,
it's supposed to be good for your throat.
In fact, there's some evidence
that it might stunt the replication of COVID, as well,
although that's not certain yet.
But anyway, the person who introduced it
into medical use was a guy called Mr. Todd Hunter.
And Mr. Todd Hunter is more famous as a playwright.
Okay, and he did a play called
The Land of Hearts Desire in Dublin,
and it was so bad, so, so bad,
that everyone just booed him off.
They kept booing him, every time he put it on,
they booed him off, they booed him off,
was taken off the rotor of the playhouse,
and it was replaced by Arms of the Man,
which was the first success of George Bernard Shaw,
who went on to write Pygmalion,
which my fair lady was based on.
- Yes. - I was gonna guess that.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- That's flawless. - That's amazing.
- Actually, I think that does check out, that's great.
I've got in my notes here, I don't know who wrote these.
The Irish Moss saved America,
because there was a lot of it grown in the USA,
and there, in fact, there's a town near Boston,
it's called Skituate.
Skituated, very near Boston, brilliant,
which is, supposedly, it calls itself
the most Irish town in the whole of the USA,
about 50% of the population there are Irish,
and from the 1840s onwards,
it was a big site for Irish moss farming,
as in they farmed it, they grew it.
- Yeah, you get it, it kind of comes onto the shore
in North America and in Europe, doesn't it?
- Exactly, yeah, yeah, and he saw some in the water,
and he thought, wait, I know that,
I recognize that from when I was in Ireland,
and so he set up the industry, basically,
this guy who's called Daniel Ward.
Anyway, so it became big, big, big industry for this town.
During the Second World War,
suddenly, there was a thing called agar,
it's an agar jelly, you know?
That was no longer available,
'cause that was grown in the Far East.
- Okay, and you need agar to grow bacteria and stuff?
- Well, it's a thickening agent,
it's in all sorts of foods,
and basically, it was no longer available,
'cause it was largely grown in Japan and places like that,
which were obviously no longer trading with the USA.
Irish moss carrion, and basically,
rocketed in production.
In Canada, they made 261,000 pounds in 1941.
The next year, they made over 2 million pounds
of this stuff for use in foods.
Yeah, it was a huge deal.
- And why did it save America?
- Well--
- Otherwise, they would have starved to death
if they didn't have ice cream or whatever.
- Well, they wouldn't have had pleasant sauces,
drinks of war, in fact, on morale.
- Yeah, yeah, is it called the man in the high castle,
where they imagined that the Germans
had won the Second World War?
- I think we should make a prequel of it,
where we actually look at what the reason
they lost the war, and it was because of this lack of aga.
- Probably, that's huge, yeah.
- That's right.
- So, are you buying that?
- Nope.
(laughing)
- You know how we were saying
that carrageen was in health food?
Always has been, many thousands of years has been round,
and I came across an article in the New York Times
in, I think it was, like, 1904 or something,
and it was, I just found it really amusing
how little the police obviously had to do at this time.
So, it was a story about how a Romanian gypsy woman
had been arrested in Jamaica for charging over $7,000,
which was a lot then, for basically Irish moss.
- It's a lot now for Irish moss.
- It's good.
- It is, don't pay that for Irish moss.
- But how much Irish moss are we talking about?
- It was a very small tincture
dropped in a glass of water, in secret.
- $7,000?
- Yeah, it's too much, isn't it?
- Who's the buyer?
- Well, it was this lady who had a hunchback
that she wanted cured, so she employed a healer,
this woman who said she was Romanian.
Anyway, the healer said she boiled some water,
she covered it with cloth and she said,
"Look at that water, don't touch it, don't move,
"don't tell anyone for 24 hours what I've done,
"and then you'll be cured."
And the woman, idiot, ruined the cure by telling her mates,
she was like, "Look, I've employed this doctor,
"but I'm a bit suspicious about the cure,"
'cause she just told me to, like,
not touch this glass of water for 24 hours.
- For 24 hours, while she goes to the coast
and gets the nearest ship with her new $7,000.
- Well, no, 'cause she'd only charged,
like, a hundred at that point.
So, the woman reported it to the police.
Two detectives came to her house,
hid behind the curtains,
and the Romanian lady came back to say,
"You know, okay, that was the first step,
"now the next step comes,"
and the detectives saw her slip some Irish moss
into the water and then say,
"Okay, now I'm gonna charge you $7,000,"
and then, as she was gonna hand over the money
in the details, the detectives jumped up.
- Do you get police doing that much these days?
Sort of, "We'll come into your house,
"hide behind your curtains."
- I think that's fine. - That's whether you don't.
I think it's a disgrace.
I want, for my taxes,
I want policemen hiding behind my curtains
every day of the week.
- Did she have an exact time she was coming back?
How long were the police hiding behind the curtains?
- She said Wednesday.
- Passing another cup of tea behind the curtains.
(laughing)
- She had to knock,
so they could just hang out in the kitchen,
I suppose, until--
- Like a surprise party.
Everyone, everyone, quick, quick, quick, quick.
- Exactly, exactly.
- False alarm, it's an Amazon delivery.
- Did you guys hear about Mim Flynn?
- Mim Flynn. - Mim Flynn.
- The Irish mossing queen?
- No. - No.
(laughing)
- She was, she wasn't a beauty queen or anything.
She was the queen of the Irish moss industry
because she was a great mosser,
and she started at the age of nine.
- Is a mosser someone who eats it or who collects it?
- Harvested it.
- I think she was in Skituate, Skituate.
- I thought you said she was Irish.
- No, Irish moss.
- Oh, I see.
- Oh, where was she? - She was the--
- America. - In Skituate.
- She was the American Irish mossing--
- Did we not pay attention?
Remember his hilarious pun earlier?
- It's just outside Boston.
- I blank them out too, but--
- Skituated, just outside Boston.
- I must not have been here at the time.
- I didn't hear.
- I don't think I was.
- I don't think there was any evidence.
- Audio, imagine if I had to out your original paper.
(laughing)
- So, but yeah, give us more about her.
Is she-- - How's she doing?
- I think she's passed away now.
- Right.
- But Skituate these days,
it does have a mossing museum.
- Cool.
- Yeah. - Is it?
- Yeah, yeah.
There's no longer much of an industry as Moot Evices.
- Well, if you're in Skituate,
and you're wondering what to do.
- Yeah, also, I've probably said Skituate wrong.
That all the way through.
- So, look on the map, don't ask a local.
- Yeah, yeah.
Get a pair of compasses, put the middle point in Boston,
and the other arm to 30 miles,
and it'll be on that line.
- Which way? - Which way?
- Which way?
- Well, it'll be coastal.
So, I only know it's 30 miles outside Boston.
- Okay, cool.
(laughing)
- Just go 30 miles south of Boston,
along the coast, and if it's not there,
go 60 miles north.
(laughing)
- So, just on Belmont,
we should talk about the fact that
it was only quite recently
that it stopped containing meat.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Really? - Yeah.
Weird.
So, Belmont's been around since,
I think the earliest recipe
maybe comes from Baghdad in the 10th century,
a long time,
and it was only in the 18th century
they thought, "Let's stop putting chicken in this."
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It just sounds so rough.
- They just used chicken as,
basically, in the same way
that they used this seaweed
as kind of to make it more gelatinous,
to make it stringy.
It had a pleasant stringiness, I think.
- Oh, lovely.
- And you shredded and really pounded up the chicken,
so it lost all of its flavor, I believe,
and mixed it up with some almond milk
and some sugar and some rice.
And yum, and they still eat it in turkey,
almost the same thing, it seems like.
- Oh, really?
What actually would the chicken in still?
- Yeah, yeah, it's called tavuk gogsu,
and it literally means,
and I really want English people to have gone
and ordered it, having done the Google translate,
'cause it literally means chicken breast.
But you order it, and what you get is a blamange.
(laughing)
You look at everything on the menu,
and you're like, "Oh, I can't, I don't want that, I don't."
Oh, chicken breast!
(laughing)
That's safe.
- What a weird-ass chicken, so they have it in turkey.
- Have you guys heard of Bompas and Pa?
- No.
- They're a jelly innovation firm,
and they basically do absolutely mad things
with jelly all the time.
They're constantly coming up with incredible innovations,
and weird flavors, and anyway,
I just look through a list of all the things
they've done over the years.
One year, for Valentine's Day, they created a jelly
which was called throbber.
- Oh, boy.
- THROBR, which I can--
- Sounds like an app, doesn't it?
- It does sound like an app.
It's amazing what this jelly does.
It locks onto your heart rate,
and it pulses in time with your heart rate
as you're eating it.
I don't know.
So if you get very excited as you're eating
the jelly, the jelly itself will start reflecting that.
- It does feel like, 'cause it's called throbber,
that perhaps, if you got an erection,
the stiffer your erection, the stiffer the jelly
would get.
(all laughing)
- Make a steak knife for this one.
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that when communism fell
in Czechoslovakia, the US ambassador in the country
was Shirley Temple.
(all laughing)
- Really weird.
- I think this is amazing.
Some people might know this already.
I've spoken to one or two people who have,
but to me, Shirley Temple is a child movie star
who basically retired when she was 10 years old.
- Exactly.
- But actually, when she got a bit older,
when she was 44, she became a diplomat,
and she did loads of stuff for the US.
She was the first woman to serve as US ambassador to Ghana,
but she was also the ambassador in Czechoslovakia in 1989
when the Velvet Revolution happened,
and the communist regime fell in what is now Czechia,
and Slovakia.
- Yeah. - Amazing.
- It is amazing.
- Weirdly, she was sort of there
towards the start as well, wasn't she?
She thinks maybe one of the things that helped her
get that gig was the fact that in the '60s,
she'd been in Czechoslovakia,
and I think she was working for a multiple sclerosis foundation,
which is where she got her taste
for international diplomacy and stuff,
so her brother had MS,
and so she founded this organization.
She was doing some international work in Czechoslovakia,
and she happened to be there at the time
that the Russians basically invaded
to crush the uprising, to crush the Prague Spring,
and yeah, she remembers watching from her balcony
as a woman got gunned down,
and that made her think, yeah,
I'll take a career in diplomacy.
(laughing)
- Yeah, the other thing was that she married
her second husband in, I think, in her 30s,
and he was an aquaculture engineer and oceanographer,
so that also got her to go into the environmental side
of diplomacy, so that was part of it.
- She's really, I mean, so she did have political ambitions
outside of being an ambassador.
She was a Republican candidate.
She wanted to run for the House of Representatives in 1967,
and she lost out to a guy called Congressman Pete McCloskey,
but she obviously had close relationships
with the leading Republicans at the time,
because it was under Gerald Ford
that she was the ambassador to Ghana.
She was under Ronald Reagan when she did another
of her posts, and then the Czechoslovakia one
was George H.W. Bush, Bush Sr.
She must have been really good mates with them,
and you can see that this child stock,
'cause Shirley Temple really is even to my generation.
I used to watch her movies in black and white as a kid.
Like, I know-- - When were you born?
(laughing)
- Danny, you're 100 years old.
- Right, okay.
- Yeah, no, but no, like, she's still a name
that most of us know.
I mean, largely it might because of the drink,
the non-alcoholic mocktail that you can get.
- But before this, I thought Shirley Temple,
old child, sort of, like, curly hair, child actor,
like, hugely famous child star,
and also non-alcoholic drink.
- I only thought Good Ship Lollipop,
which was that song that she sang.
That's basically all I know about.
- But in a lot of her early films,
she preaches fiscal responsibility,
and the importance of a low-tax, small state.
So it's kind of unsurprising that her--
- That's who we should have seen it, actually.
- She was an independent Republican candidate,
I think, for the 1967 election
to be a part of the U.S. House of Representatives.
- What does that mean in the end?
- I believe that it means she was Republican,
but she wasn't officially on the ticket, I think.
I'm not sure about that.
But she said during the election,
"I think men are fine and here to stay,
"but I have a hunch that it wouldn't hurt
"to have a woman's viewpoint expressed
"in that delegation of 38 men."
- Mmm, yeah. - Too much too soon, Shirley.
(laughing)
- She started, okay, so she's a child actor, as we know,
in sort of like age six.
She was already winning like special Oscars
that were being given to her.
Like, she was a big deal.
What's, I did not know this.
There's something quite seedy about her intro
into the world of acting.
Nothing against her.
It's her parents who obviously signed her up.
She was three at the time, you know.
And it was part of this thing called baby burlesques.
- Yes, it's incredibly weird.
- Yeah, did you watch it?
'Cause I didn't.
(laughing)
- The bad news is we've all had our laptops taken away.
Is it online, I assume, or is it not?
- It must be somewhere, right?
- It must be historical.
- 'Cause it's quite obscure.
It's like early 30s.
I think it's hard.
I couldn't find an online version.
There's one film which I reckon you can get
on YouTube if you tried.
- Oh, it's on the dark web.
(laughing)
- So what, yeah, sorry, Dad, you should tell what it was.
- Yeah, okay, so it's described by The New York Times
as a series of sexually suggestive one real shorts
in which children played all the roles.
- Yeah, so what it was is basically
they were parodies of films for grown-ups.
So at the time, all the grown-up stars
were people like Marlena Dietrich and Mae West,
and they were obviously very sexy women
with very flirtatious dialogue.
And these baby burlesques,
they kind of did parody versions of these films
where there are children playing the roles.
- Like Bugsie Malone, I guess, right?
Is like a close version of it.
- Yeah, but not with like saucy dialogue.
- It's so weird. - I'm a three-year-old.
- So weird.
- In defense of the olden days.
- Oh, come on. - I think it was probably okay.
It was a comedy, and they wore,
so they'd wear sexy outfits on the top half,
and then they'd have their nappies on,
on the bottom half,
like they're doing kind of a Zoom meeting from home.
(laughing)
- I don't think it would get made today.
- No. - And the stories
that Shirley Temple would tell about it
in later in her autobiography,
where she'd say that if they got in trouble,
the kids that were part of this production
would be sent off to a sound booth
where they'd have to sit on a block of ice.
- Apparently, every night,
Shirley Temple's mother would curl her hair
into 56 perfect curls,
so she would have to sit there
and do her hair every single night.
And then she would be read a bedtime story,
but the bedtime story was the next day's script
that she had to learn.
And so the mother would read the lines from the script,
and she'd have to parrot them back,
and she'd keep doing that until she fell asleep.
- So Shirley Temple's mom got her,
she does sound like a proper, classic,
good old fashioned Hollywood insane pushy mum, as in.
She ensured that other child actors
who might threaten her daughter's roles
had their parts cut.
- Which parts?
(laughing)
Body parts. - Fingers, yeah, yeah.
And so she was very protective,
very, very forceful in getting Shirley too fame.
Also, one thing she stole from Shirley Temple herself
was the year of her life.
She knocked a year off Shirley Temple's age.
So Shirley was at her--
- That's actually giving someone an extra year.
- Oh my God, she's the perfect mum.
(laughing)
- I mean, if my mum could suddenly turn around
and say that I'm 35, that'd be great.
- Well, no, but she wouldn't be.
She'd be telling you a year, as in,
so Shirley Temple was at her 12th birthday party,
and her mum said, "Oh, by the way, you're 13."
- Ah, well, but when she was nine,
they said that she was eight.
- But that's why, so that's because
it's all part of the same story.
- It's all the same process.
See, when she was three or four, her mum thought,
"Oh no, she's getting a bit too old
"for this whole baby game."
Like, she's about to be,
no, I think she was about to turn five and a half
or something, so her mum was like,
"Right, we're gonna make her four and a half again."
And then Shirley, from the age of four and a half,
thought that she was four and a half,
five and a half, six and a half,
and then it was when she was 12
that her mum went, "Actually, surprise."
Welcome to a teenagerhood.
- She's like turning the clock back in the autumn
and turning it forward again in the spring.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. - Exactly.
- So your mum could do this for you, James,
but you'd be on borrowed time.
- I'm perhaps borrowing time at this stage of my life.
I am up for borrowing any time I can borrow.
And on her eighth birthday, so she was actually nine,
but she was, I thought she was eight,
she got 135,000 gifts.
- Yeah, that's amazing, isn't it?
- Pretty amazing.
And it was sent to her by fans around the world, right?
- No, all from her mum. - It wasn't just her parents,
yeah, her mum was, yeah.
- She got a kangaroo from Australia.
- That's a burden, anything. - What?
- Is it?
Well, you can keep other presents in the pouch.
- Good point, guys, it's a suitcase.
- Yeah, it sounds, her life just sounds insane.
She was the biggest box office star of the year
in 1936, '37, and '38,
which I think were the years where she was eight, nine,
and 10, I mean.
- She's the biggest child star that's ever been.
There's been no contest ever since, really.
- Carly Culkin is the only other one I could think of.
- I think in terms of the amount she earned at the time,
the fact that she was the only person
anyone wanted in any films,
between the ages of three and 10,
she was in 29 films.
1935, her salary was $2,500 a week.
This is when she was seven, six or seven.
- That was a lot of money in those days.
It wasn't just like a third of a tincture of Iron Moss.
- God, her house was stuffed with Iron Moss though, wow.
She was also responsible
for quite a random bit of cultural input, possibly,
and that is the Novel, The Power and the Glory.
- Okay.
- By Graham Greene, and this is because
she had sort of a feud with Graham Greene
at the age of sort of nine, eight or nine.
- It's so funny, I didn't celebrate with you.
- Do you remember in the 90s or the early 2000s,
they used to have celebrity boxing
and like Ricky Gervais fought with,
I don't know, some random person.
- Did they?
- Yeah, yeah.
- I don't remember that.
- Like Patrick Kilty or something like that, yeah.
- I just want to see Graham Greene in Shirley Temple.
- Clocking Shirley Temple.
- That is a pay-per-view I would pay for.
- I think I'd back Shirley.
She was pretty tough under those ringlets.
He was quite mean about her.
He wrote a review of her films saying,
sort of suggesting that she was trained
to deliberately be a bit cocket-ish.
Saying she symbolized dimpled depravity.
She had a well-developed rump.
And suggesting that her films were targeting
sleazy middle-aged men.
And it's unclear how humorous he was being.
Having read it, I don't think he was being that humorous.
I think it was just a pretty nasty review.
And then her mum and Fox decided to sue him for slander,
for saying that, for suggesting that.
And he, according to a friend who wrote a biography of him,
years later, he realized that he was about to be sued.
And so he might go to prison.
So he fled from England, where he was, to Mexico,
which didn't have any extradition rules.
And in Mexico, that was where he was inspired to write,
maybe his greatest magnum opus,
Para and the Glory, set in Mexico.
- Done a case.
- About oppression of Catholics.
- As an adult, she broke the ice, whatever,
she sent him a copy.
- She was been sitting on all that time.
- She sent him a copy of her autobiography,
and she invited him to tea.
So clearly there weren't very many hard feelings
on her part.
- Well, she was a diplomat, wasn't she?
- Oh, yeah, there you go.
- Well, she had got 3,500 pounds
from Graham Greene in the settlement.
- I wonder how much she saw of that, though.
I haven't got this written down,
but I do, in the course of reading,
remember that a lot of the money was taken
by the parents and wasn't seen by Shirley.
So I've got the figures.
- Yeah, what are they?
- Right, she earned $3,200,000 in her acting career,
quite a lot of money at the time.
By the time she was 22 years old,
there was $44,000 left.
- And was that because it was depleted by her parents?
- It was her dad, right?
So her dad was a banker,
and so he was in charge of all of her money,
obviously her parents, they would be,
but she'd never blamed him.
She reckons that he got duped.
So basically he made a load of bad investments
because people could see he was making a load of money,
and he didn't really, you know, he wasn't the greatest.
He left school when he was in seventh grade.
He wasn't the greatest banker of all time.
- I wonder if she was a banker?
He was kind of like a monopoly banker, basically.
"I'll be the banker, yeah, great."
- They should have looked underneath the bar.
That's where the money would have been.
But yeah, she said that she didn't blame him one little bit,
and it was the people that counseled him
who were the bad guys. - Who were the baddies, okay.
- Just a quite a nice link between her past
and her sort of future,
if you're placing yourself in 1940.
It goes back to this fact,
James' fact at the start of the show,
so when communism fell.
So basically, she never liked references
to her history as a child star, you know.
She would say it's not for everyone.
Everyone was a child.
How come I'm the only one who,
as a very high achieving diplomat and politician,
you know, gets labeled as former child star?
- Well, not everyone.
Like, that kind of havel wasn't in movies.
- We don't know.
There might have been some obscured Czech films
undiscovered with him spouting philosophy age nine.
But she did give them a treat just once.
So it was when communism did fall in Czechoslovakia,
big day, very exciting.
She called all of her senior staff together,
shut the doors, very private room,
and apparently looked them very sternly in the eye
and said, "I'm only going to do this once."
And then she started prancing around the room
and singing on the good chip lot.
(all laughing)
- That's amazing. - It's awesome.
- I've just got one thing on child stars
and how to become a child star, because--
- A bit late for us.
- A bit late for us, but you know,
I've got a kid on the way,
so I could actually get going on this,
which is there's a company called Jam 2000,
and they're the agency that basically,
when you see a baby in the UK on TV
and call the midwife, even the crown or Sherlock,
if there's a baby in it,
it's a good chance that Jam 2000 gave them.
So when the baby is born,
the baby can get an acting license
within a few hours of being born.
In America, it takes about 15 days.
You've got to be 15 days old to get a worker's permit
or acting. - How do you,
do you need to audition?
Like, when you're coming out of the birth canal,
you're like, "Mary, come lie down."
- Exactly.
So that's the issue.
They say that often people complain,
like, "This baby's crying all the time."
They say, "Well, you just happened to have
been given a crying baby."
Unfortunately, that's the case.
But they do have specifications that they like,
so triplets or twins are particularly liked,
because twins, most likely,
you're gonna be born three weeks early.
Triplets, in some cases, seven weeks early, right?
- Is that good?
- It's good. - I guess they'll be extra small
'cause they can get older and they can look newborn.
- Exactly.
- I actually thought it would be that
they would only have to work for 20 minutes at a time
'cause you can keep swapping them in and out.
- That's the other reason.
So when they're looking for tiny babies,
twins are fantastic.
They're tiny, but you can do double time
because you've got two babies to swap in there.
- Oh, babies look almost identical anyway.
- So you would think so, right?
But sometimes it's to do with hair and sometimes to do,
but yeah, so the youngest that this company said
that they've ever handed over as a four-day-old baby
in order to be used.
- Amazing.
- And so it's a great article
where it just tells you about different types
babies have been using and just a little nugget
for any Star Wars fans out there.
In Star Wars Revenge of the Sith,
we get to see Luke and Leia, who are twins that are born.
- Wait, that's episode three.
- Three, yeah.
- So you get to see them as babies
and that's where you learn that their brother and sister
in the series and the babies that were used for that
were actually one, which was a guy called Aidan Barton.
He plays both Luke and Leia.
- Really?
- So when you look at them--
- He's like, "Alex Guinness in kind hearts and coronets."
(laughing)
- Yeah, he's Eddie Murphy and then meet--
- What a reference to you to make James.
From somebody who hasn't seen any films made before
about 1987, for you to make a kind hearts and coronets
reference, what have you done with James?
- That's just somebody who does a lot of quizzes.
(laughing)
Sorry, yeah, I've not seen Star Wars.
What are you talking about?
- So-- - Twins.
- Also, can I, can I, quick, quick, sorry.
- No, no, no, no, I know what you're gonna say
and don't say it because we're going--
- The point of which you find out in the series
that Luke and Leia are siblings.
- Yeah, if you start at episode one like a psychopath.
- James, where would you start?
- One.
- There we go.
When's he gonna find out?
- Come on, you've asked James the only person
who doesn't know when to start watching Star Wars
and I think that's an unfair sample.
- It's the first episode, there's a second episode
that you find out.
- Presumably, they wouldn't have called
them episode one, two, and three
if they didn't want you to watch them first, would they?
- Absolutely, no, no, no.
- It's absolutely correct.
Jabba the Hutt was actually played
by a six-week-old baby on that episode.
Very overfed.
(upbeat music)
Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that there used to be a cinema
in Melbourne, Australia that had a cloakroom
to keep your babies in.
(laughing)
What?
So this was called the Sun Theater
and this was a place where when you were arriving
at the cinema, you would have a cloakroom
but rather than leaving your coat in there,
you would push your baby in its pram into the cloakroom,
be given a ticket, and then go watch the movie.
Now, obviously you don't want to completely abandon
your baby, so while you're watching the movie,
if your baby in the cloakroom kicks off
and starts crying inconsolably,
the ticket number that you hold will flash up
on the screen of the movie to let you know
that you're desperately needed in the cloakroom
so you can get out and look after your baby.
- It's very clever.
- Brilliant.
- Hang on, would it flash up for all the other members
of the audience?
Is it gonna replace the image that was on the screen
or is it a little thing in the corner that's subtle?
- Like, I think just a quick superimpose
at the number 29, whatever.
- Really, on the screen, mid-film?
- I think that would be all right.
- But be mid-film, I don't know if it would be
directly over the whole thing, it might be in the corner.
I couldn't actually find that out.
- It's a must-be corner.
- I don't know.
- I'll be so annoying 'cause babies cry constantly
and if you've got 50 babies at a big blockbuster film
in the cloakroom, you're just gonna be watching a series
of numbers flashing up in the national lottery.
- Exactly.
(laughing)
- So this--
- It's ingenious.
- It was a very clever idea and this was--
- Why do we not have it today?
- Exactly, why don't we?
It seems like a very--
- 'Cause people don't think they should just leave their babies.
- Yeah, I don't think I'd leave my baby now
that I say that out loud.
- Well, your baby's probably in the movie.
- That's right, it's in the movie, yeah.
Well, you do have baby cinema now,
which we take my son to go and see.
- Yeah, I got to that.
- Yeah, we took--
- You really should take your child along sometimes.
- I know, I know.
- The first movie that we took, "Wilf" to see,
Fenella, my wife took "Wilf" to see was the movie
that was on the biopic of Churchill
that came out about four years back.
- So all the babies look like Churchill.
- Like "Wilf" was really into it
'cause he was like, "Wow, it's me in a suit when I'm older."
This is amazing.
So the Sun Theater had opened up in Melbourne in 1938
and it was a single screen theater.
It had 1,050 seats and it was really massive.
It was a big deal and then over time,
people stopped going as much and they had to sell
and new owners turned it into smaller screens.
So they stopped doing it.
It's no longer a, you don't bring your Pram in there anymore,
which is a shame.
- And I can't find any other cinema that did this.
- No, no, yeah. - I think it was just this one.
- There are people who've left their children
in cloak rooms before.
I won't go so far as to say, "This is a thing,"
because it's not.
But in 1999, Tony Blair's chief of staff
was a guy called Jonathan Powell and--
- Oh, I remember Powell.
Oh, those are the good old days, weren't they?
- Friend of Anna.
Anyway, he went to the Groucho Club
and left his eight-week-old daughter
with a cloakroom attendant and that was--
And there was a brief comment about it
and then the family complained saying,
"The child has a right to a private life,"
and I think the newspaper said,
"Well, don't leave the child in the cloakroom then."
Anyway, but the Observer sent a reporter
called Saskia Sessons, who took a colleague of hers,
five-month-old baby, to various cloakrooms all over London.
It's a great feature.
So King's Cross left luggage office?
Absolutely not.
The Ivy Restaurant?
Yes, please leave the baby with us.
We'll stash him on a ledge.
National Gallery were incredibly rude to Saskia
and her young friend.
One of the cloakroom attendants said,
"Out of the question."
The second said, "You need your head examined,"
and the third said, "That's very, very irresponsible."
- Get on, yeah. - I know.
- So, wait a minute, that was all in the same--
- That was all so close.
- She keeps saying, "I want a second opinion."
"I want a third opinion."
- But restaurants seemed to be much more willing.
The Oxo Tower Brasserie, which is a restaurant in London,
said, "Yes, of course, please leave the baby with us."
- I guess restaurants are smaller,
so you can go to the parent if there's an issue,
whereas National Gallery feel like
you can lose the parent, right?
- That's true, yeah.
- One famous person left in the cloakroom
is a character from Importance of Being Earnest,
left in a handbag in the station.
So I thought I'd look into that play by Oscar Wilde.
Yeah, so Oscar Wilde famously,
could you tell I can't find anything else about cloakrooms?
So he was famously brought up with charges of immorality,
wasn't he, because he was homosexual.
And in 1952, there was a movie,
the first movie made of the Importance of Being Earnest,
and it was directed by a guy called Anthony Asquith.
And Anthony Asquith was the son of Herbert Henry Asquith,
who was home secretary,
and he was the one who brought the charges of immorality
against Oscar Wilde,
which got him imprisoned in Reading jail.
- That's interesting.
- Yeah, and so he was the one who got him imprisoned,
and then his son was the director of the movie.
- That's really good.
- You look great full circle.
- I found some famous people who worked in cloakrooms.
- Oh yeah, cool.
- Mark Ormond.
- Oh, from Soft Cell.
- Soft Cell.
- Of Tainted Love fame.
- Can I just ask, is that the most famous,
and you're going to less and less?
'Cause I haven't heard of him,
I'm gonna scratch off the dress.
- Don't worry, I actually,
I started with my weakest one.
- Okay, great.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Where did he work in the cloakroom?
Sorry, did you solve?
- Probably at the front bit, where you take his clothes.
- So he was high up in the role.
- I didn't write it down, I'm sorry.
- Silla Black.
- Yeah.
- The cloakroom attendant at the cavern club.
- Who else is on your list?
- Boy George.
- Boy George, yeah.
- He, um.
- At the culture club, wasn't it?
(laughing)
- Good, sorry.
That's the band that Boy George was in.
- Thank you, didn't get it yet.
- Yeah, and Boy George is a singer in the band.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Cool, I don't want to ruin every joke by asking,
so sometimes I'll just stay quiet and let it happen.
- Karma Chameleon was the big hit.
- That didn't help the joke.
- No, just I'm just helping Anna understand who this is.
- Good to learn.
- He was interviewed about it later,
and he said, "I was always rippling through pockets
"and handbags, most people were too pissed to notice."
- Oh, yeah.
- Any babies in the handbags?
- He didn't find the people.
- Riffling, hey?
- In my notes, I've got riffing,
but that can't possibly be true.
- No, I just would always say rifling.
- That's better, then that is correct, yep.
Sorry, yeah.
- On cloakrooms.
- Oh, yeah.
- I read, so I think we've talked before about
how popcorn wasn't really loud in cinemas until the third,
and it was sort of post-depression, I think,
when everyone was so depressed.
They were like, "Let us have the popcorn."
And also, yeah, the cinemas filled that.
- They thought people would tread it
into the nice carpets, didn't they?
- Well, before that, exactly.
They thought people would tread it into the carpets.
It was too noisy,
and so you used to have to leave your popcorn in the cloakroom
'cause people set up popcorn stands all outside cinemas,
and they sell it to you, leaving the cloakroom.
- That's amazing, just hand it in like a gun or something,
and then you get it back afterwards.
- You take a gun to the cinema?
- No, sorry, I'm thinking of the thing in Old West.
- Every time someone looks at their phone
in the middle of a movie.
(laughing)
- You got in a lot of trouble in your tour
of some national gallery clothes, didn't you?
Keep my AK-47.
- Wasn't there a thing where you had to hand in your gun
when you went to a Wild West bar?
- Towns, like most of the Wild West towns
wouldn't allow guns inside,
so they would have a way to sort of stop, you know?
- I think that's where--
- Often you had them taken at the periphery
of what we've talked about.
- In fact, I think we said that in the OK Corral,
problem was the reason it happened
is 'cause they hadn't put their guns
in the cloakroom before they arrived.
- Exactly, that's what I'm thinking of.
That's my incredibly convoluted part of that, you know?
- Actually, speaking of weapons in cloakrooms,
tell me something famous about the Houses of Parliament.
- Oh yeah, the swords in the cloakroom.
You've got a place for your swords.
- There are hooks in the cloakroom
so you can hang up your sword.
- Yep, absolutely.
If you go into the Houses of Parliament cloakrooms,
all the coat hangers have a loop of pink ribbon around them,
and that is for holding your sword.
So you're not allowed to sword in the chamber.
And I read a good expose of the fact that this,
there's no evidence, this is true.
So various reasons.
So in the massive fire in the 1830s,
when everything was destroyed,
that was way after anyone would ever bring swords in.
And so it's weird that they would have the sword hooks.
But even if they were for swords,
the first mention that they were was 1928,
and it was like an MP saying,
"Hey, they've got ribbons there."
And that's from the olden days 'cause of the sword thing.
And actually, all the mentions before that
say they were for a much more sensible item.
- Umbrella's.
There you go.
- I've got a bit of Australian cinema news
just while we were talking about Aussie cinemas.
Australia's longest running pornographic cinema
is finally going to shut down.
And according to the article,
it's called the Crazy Horse Cinema.
dozens of 90 year old pensioners
are gonna be absolutely distraught
'cause it's their meeting place.
- There's a big group of 90.
- What did she say?
What's she doing?
She's gonna get a cold.
He's not a real plumber.
Sorry, what?
- Yeah, this place has been open for many years.
And supposedly it's a really good meeting ground
for a lot of these 90 year old pensioners.
So they all meet up there at 10 a.m.
- Very early to start.
- Very early.
This comes from a quote from the lady.
They come and they do their thing in the morning.
- Disgusting.
(laughing)
They come and then they have their meeting.
- Yeah, they could come and do their thing in the morning,
whatever that is they do.
And then they go and maybe do some shopping for the wife
and maybe have some lunch
and then come back if they like.
What they get is--
- Oh, they sell mail pensioners.
- It's mail pensioners
and they get a $10 pensioner all day ticket
to the porno cinema.
- What?
So sorry, when they're having this meeting,
is it in the cinema?
Why won't you film? - It's not really a meeting, is it?
It's sort of like a gathering.
- I even think as a teenager,
I would be able to get my money's worth
from an old day ticket on a graphic cinema.
(laughing)
It's a pensioner.
- For angry sales in Australia.
(laughing)
- That's so funny.
- Yeah, so these guys, these nine-year-olds
have been going for 20 years.
So, you know, they were a fruity, fresh 70-year-olds
at the time.
And yeah, and then obviously--
- These lads are gonna be thrilled
when they find out about the internet.
(laughing)
- Yeah, that's, you know, so they're distraught
at the moment.
And it's closing this year.
This is from this year, this article.
- Good, but crazy, the crazy boys.
- Knock it down, so the ground with salt.
- I don't know.
It keeps them out for the full day,
which is judging by the sounds of these men.
Sounds like some of the boys.
- That's the poor idea, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Is popcorn allowed?
- Um, as a matter of the cup,
it's got bigger concerns, actually.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the original vapes
were Pez dispensers.
(laughing)
So, you know, for people in the UK who maybe don't,
Pez dispensers are like those sweet holders.
They're a huge deal in America, right?
They're kind of tubes that hold sweets,
and they have a funny head on top.
- Well, yeah, so you got a little funny head,
and you tip the head back,
and it's like an elevator system where the latest sweet
that's sitting on top arrives at the top,
bing, and you get to pull it out,
and it's a little rectangular sweetie.
- Like a brick, but much smaller.
- Exactly, like a tiny brick built.
- Yeah, if you were building a house for an else.
- Imagine if you were building a house,
but you had an elevator,
and every time you needed to put a brick on,
the brick had to come up in an elevator.
- Yeah.
- And then it would come out.
- Well, this is a classically helpful,
no such thing as a fishing explainer.
- The lucky thing is,
everyone knows one of Pez,
(all laughing)
- That was a waste of your time in ours.
- Yeah, it's, yeah, and you,
- Are you gonna, so you're gonna try as well now?
- I think of them as kind of confectionary staplers,
'cause you have to load it in cartilage with sweets,
don't you, and you like some staples.
- That's actually the best simile that we've had so far.
- That was actually really good, yeah.
- We'll allow it.
Anyway, Pez sweets were created in 1927 in Vienna.
- And people smoke them.
- And people load them into their cigarettes.
No, but they were created
by a guy called Edward Haas III,
and he was an anti-smoking campaigner,
thought it was bad for your health,
well done, very forward-thinking of him,
and he wanted to create a tablet
that helped people to cut down on smoking or overeating.
And so they were these mint tablets,
and that was what they were explicitly for.
Early advert said, "No smoking, pezzing allowed."
Like vaping.
And then when the dispensers came about in the '50s,
they are sort of, well, the first ones were shaped
so like really like cigarette lighters,
and they were for adults, marketed very much for adults.
- And they used to send women in sort of like
quite cleavage-heavy dresses around in vans.
- Cleavage-heavy.
- Low putts, we call them.
- Yeah, cleavage-heavy, not all right.
I guess we're wearing a very cleavage-heavy top tonight.
It's a cut.
Your saucy fashion show, the descriptions are not good.
- They said they do look a bit like lighters,
but according to Sean Peterson,
who's the historian at Pez Candy, incorporated,
they were only designed that way to fit into pockets.
It's just a coincidence that they look like lighters
'cause lighters are also designed to go into pockets.
- Yeah, I did hear that Pez Candy,
incorporated does have an official historian, I thought.
- Sean Peterson.
- It's a very light historian gig,
as in it's a very, very small area of history.
- I reckon he does other stuff.
- You'd have to.
- I think usually the historians in these kind of companies
are actually someone who does another job,
but in their spare time, they kind of--
- I'm sure you're right,
because otherwise you'd feel like a fool
turning up at a historian's conference.
They'd be like, "What do you study?"
"Oh, the 19th century mostly, what about you?"
(laughing)
- You sat next to Mary Beard on one side
and Dan Snow on the other side.
(laughing)
- But yeah, it was until they came to America
that they still, even when the dispensers were added,
this was a way to give up smoking.
And apparently it was only when they went to America
in the '50s and tried to market them there
and they were targeting adults,
kids how to quit smoking.
America didn't have the same appetite to quit smoking.
I think maybe there wasn't such a campaign back then
as there was in Austria, saying this is bad.
And so they thought, let's start putting fun,
turning them into fun kid shapes
and marketing them to children.
- Yeah, and changing the taste, obviously,
of the thing from a sort of anti-smoking nicotine--
- Well, they wasn't just peppermint.
- No, no, but as in they changed it to sweeties.
They made this.
- But they were always minty.
- They were always minty on the start.
- 'Cause that's where the name comes from.
It comes from the German for peppermint.
- Oh, yeah.
- Weirdly, one of the first flavors they had was chlorophyll.
- Yeah.
- What?
- So what is that?
- It's the green stuff you get in leaves.
- It's hard to know what it tastes like.
- Exactly.
- I've never thought of it as anything.
- It tastes like grass, I reckon.
- I would imagine so too, but it's such a weird flavor.
Can we talk about Edouard Haas, the third?
- Haas, yes.
- So it's a really interesting family,
because his father, Edward Haas the second,
was a baked goods merchant.
Okay, so it's all baking powder.
And his father, Edward Haas--
- It's not actually a baked good, is it?
- It's a good for baking.
- What a good point, it's a baking goods.
Yeah, yeah, sorry, I stand corrected.
Okay, but basically, Edward the third
seems to have invented the first ready-made cake mixture.
It's a huge deal.
- So wait a minute, was this the one who did Paz,
or is this--
- The one who did Paz, the third, yeah.
Edward the third is the guy who did Hassan
for the baking of health sponge cakes.
Edward's grandfather, Edward Haas the first, okay.
I've read one reference to this.
"I cannot find any more detail anywhere,
"but there's a source online which claims that he died
"as a result of medical experiments he did on himself."
There's no further evidence that I found.
So if you know, please write in and enlighten us,
because it's not clear what he was doing to himself.
- They're in the baking industry, what could he have done?
He added too much bicarbonate soda to himself.
- He wanted to know how hot to bake things,
so he tested the temperature himself.
- Sat in the oven.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, he cut a hole in his neck
so he could dispense loads of bread
when he took his head back.
(laughing)
- It's so unclear what he did.
There's no further detail, so mystery.
- So the evolution of the Paz dispenser itself
is very exciting, you know.
Poor Haas the third didn't get to see the feet
that were added to the bottom of a Paz dispenser
to allow it to stand.
That was a big innovation.
It's the Paz we know and love.
- That was 1987, I believe, wasn't it?
- That was in '87.
- And they had weird designs before it.
So before they added the feet, there was one in 1956,
they invented a sort of space gun.
And also, from what I've seen, regular looking guns.
So the idea is that the gun would shoot out.
It's like a pistol would shoot out the Paz at the end
into your mouth.
- Of course, you have to put the gun in your mouth.
- It doesn't seem like.
- The guy who set up the Paz dispenser,
as we know it, is a guy, well,
the guy who was in charge of the decision, basically,
was a man called Curtis Alina,
who was a European.
He was born in Prague in 1922.
He was Jewish and that was not a good time
to be born Jewish in Central Europe in Prague.
His family were all sent to concentration camps.
He was the only surviving member of his family
in Europe after the war.
He went to the USA and he started working for Paz.
But the US and the European Paz
were kind of two different camps.
They were quite remote from each other.
They weren't really tied together
and he had to persuade the Viennese outfit.
They wanted serious sober grown-up mints,
you know, adult mints,
that this dispenser thing was a good idea.
But I just, I mention all of this
because there's a weird link to Sigmund Freud,
who was from Vienna.
- Okay, I'm gonna copy the old James Harkinville circle here.
- But the link is not just that they're both in Vienna.
- Well, he lived across the street from Sigmund Freud
when he was a boy, supposedly.
And there was this brilliant website I found
which is called Freud's Butcher.com,
which is about the history of Sigmund Freud
by an author called E.D. Jarrellim.
She's great.
It's a blog about genealogy, psychology and meat, okay?
And there's a theory that she posits
that Edward Haas III might have been considering
Freud's theory of oral fixation
when he came up with the idea
of substituting peppermint sweets for cigarettes.
- Oh, I see.
Not that the Paz dispenser looks a bit like a penis.
- No, that's not.
Although that's an excellent evolution of the theory.
Maybe he was only thinking about it subconsciously,
but wouldn't that be appropriate given that it's Freud?
- Yeah?
- What a load of absolute balls.
Oh, he happened to live in opposite Freud.
What weird convoluted thing can we attribute to that?
- Are you right?
She says it's a huge stretch.
- She says that as well.
- She also says that.
- Okay, I disagree.
- So have you guys come across Steve Gloo?
- Oh, no.
- The Paz Outlaw.
- The Paz Outlaw, self-styled.
- I can't believe I genuinely got like a tingle of goosebumps.
You both got excited by that.
Who's Steve Gloo?
- He is basically the king of collecting pezzas.
So he would go to Europe
and he would get all of these really, really rare pezzas,
sometimes digging through garbage
to try and get ones which had been thrown out.
And then he would take them back to America
and he would sell them to Paz enthusiasts.
And he said at one stage he was making $4.5 million.
He made that much in total selling pez candy dispensers
that he'd taken from Eastern Europe and sold in America.
- And it seemed to be there was some kind of loophole
in terms of importing them or...
- Well, he just sort of snuck through customs
quite a lot with them.
And it was, honestly, so this is where I first...
- Where was he hiding them?
- I think often they didn't check.
- It's just the right shape.
That's why they're shaped like that.
- It wasn't one per trip.
- I don't think that would have been profitable.
- Just a little Mickey Mouse head sticking out his rectum.
- Help yourself to one more year down there.
- Yeah, this is how I came across this fact initially.
I was reading a review of "The Pez Outlaw"
which is coming out this year, I think.
And it's the film based on his adventures.
And it sounds proper exciting stuff.
It was him and his son who's an equally avid collector.
And he was real down and out.
Like wasn't making any money until he came across
this big scam where he'd fly to Eastern Europe,
go into factories and basically bribe factory workers
to give him a bunch of pez he knew
would be incredibly valuable.
But they drive around in this truck.
Apparently his son said he'd drive 24 hours straight.
He'd be so tired that he often crashed the truck
but just kept plugging away.
And he had this amazing rival called Patek
who was another Pez guy who also got first dibs
in the factories and flogged pez.
And apparently at one point glue pursued Patek
across Austria in a car chase.
And I said that they like drove on pavements.
They were on the wrong side of the road.
They had to bribe police with Pez dispensers
full of cash he played.
(laughing)
- It could only be tiny little son teams.
- They went with notes apparently.
I don't know how many notes you can fit in.
A couple of hundred dollar bills maybe.
- But then of course big Pez got involved, right?
- Big Pez?
- And so this guy decided he sort of
did a little bit of a deal with a guy in Hungary
and said that this guy would make extras for him.
And they would discontinued ones as well sometimes.
So they'd be really, really good expensive,
you know, rare Pezes.
This guy in Hungary would make them for him
and he would buy loads of them
and then take them back to America and sell them.
But one day he logged into the Pez website
and he found a new section called misfit dispensers.
And it was all the ones that he'd bought
from this guy in Hungary,
but Pez was selling them for like a dollar each.
And they basically just flooded the market
with other ones.
And he reckons that it left him $250,000 in debt.
This one trick.
And when he rang up this broker in Hungary and said,
"What's happened? Why are they doing this?"
The broker said, "The right hand knows
what the left is doing."
So basically it was all a scam.
They just basically fitted him up.
- That's extraordinary.
- So the dispenser was made by someone called Oscar.
(speaks in foreign language)
And his patent actually said that it would be helpful
for people who have only one hand.
So it was a way of dispensing sweets from a box,
but you only need one hand to do it.
And that's what it says in the patent.
It's useful for people with one hand.
- That's why it's so useful, actually,
for the pensioners at Dan's Blue Movie Cinema
who want to have a hand-free and enjoy a cinema snack.
- Dan's Blue Movie Cinema, as it is otherwise known.
- As it will be, 'cause they're selling it, aren't they?
- I have a balloon in my beard.
- Because in the patent it says it's important
not only for persons who have only one hand,
but also persons who often have only one hand free.
- Right. - There we go.
- His occupation causes their hands
to become smeared with dirt.
- Well, this is all brilliant news, Dan.
- Get in touch with your drums.
- Freud's penis dispenser in one hand
and your actual penis in the other.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
- That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland, Andy.
- @AndrewHunterM. - James.
- @JamesHarkin. - And Anna.
- You can email a podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, where you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website,
NoSuchThingIsOfFish.com.
Check out all of our previous episodes up there.
Make sure to check out Club Fish.
We have exciting things hidden in a secret club,
like extra compilation episodes,
and drop us a line where we go through the mailbag
and share our favorite stories and facts that you've sent in.
Otherwise, just come back here next week,
where we will be here waiting for you with another episode.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]