(upbeat music)
Okay everybody, secret message alert.
This is Andy speaking.
This is a secret message only for clubfish members.
If you're listening to this
and you're not a clubfish member, turn off your ears.
Stop listening right now.
This is extremely hush hush knowledge
that we're about to tell you.
The fact is, when you signed up to clubfish,
we told you we'd give you a bit of advance warning
of live shows.
Guess what?
That's what I'm doing now.
We are doing some live, no such thing as a fish shows
in London, in Swing in London at the Soho Theatre.
We're gonna be there from the 17th of July
to the 21st of August.
If you can't make either of those two dates,
there are all sorts of dates in the middle.
We're doing 11 shows at the Soho Theatre this summer.
Sometimes we're doing two in a night.
It's gonna be insane.
There are gonna be special guests every single show.
It's gonna be off the hook.
And if you, with your clubfish membership gold card,
want to turn up at these shows,
all you need to do to get tickets
in advance of everyone else is go to
nosuchthingasafish.com/soho.
That'll take you to the theatre website.
You just need to register with the theatre.
And if you're asked for a password to get onto the page,
the password is yeti, all capitals, Y-E-T-I.
The password is yeti.
Good luck.
See you there.
We're counting on you.
This message will end in a few seconds.
Thank you.
Let's get started on with the drop as a line.
Hi.
No, I did it wrong.
(laughing)
(phone ringing)
(upbeat music)
Hi.
- Oh, that was much better.
- Yeah, that was it.
- That's the Andy Wing.
- Hi, everybody.
Welcome to drop as a line.
This is the bit of clubfish where we talk about your emails
and the things you've sent in,
which agree with what we've said
or maybe disagree with it
or maybe just offer your own perspectives.
It's a two way street podcasting.
- No, very much a one way street normally.
- It's, what it's like, it's like a highway,
but we have recently opened a small service channel
running back the other way.
- We're driving the wrong way down a highway.
- Yeah, and so let's read the messages
that are in your cars.
- It's getting good.
- I quite like this torture.
I think starting every show with a tortured metaphor.
- How have I done that before?
- No, but I like it.
- Oh, okay, yeah, yeah, all right.
Well, let's strap in, do opposite belts and set off.
- Strap in and do opposite belts.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Cool.
- Here's a good one.
Okay, here's a nice procedural question.
- Okay.
- This is from Pete from Bolton, right?
- Oh, great.
- Pete says, just a quick one that's all,
oh, he says hello specifically to you, James,
'cause you're from Bolton as well.
- Hi, Pete.
- And then he asks also which bit of Bolton you're from.
- I was brought up in Black Rod,
which is just outside Bolton.
And then I grew up in Ladybridge.
And then I moved to Morris Green.
And then I moved out of Bolton.
- Is Black Rod anything to do with the Queens?
- Yeah, you know what, it is to do with it
in the fact that it has the same name.
- Yeah.
- Other than that, nothing to do with it.
- Do you know what?
That's why I asked.
(laughing)
- Anyway, let's get on to the meat of Pete's message.
- Pete's?
(laughing)
- To Pete's meat.
Here we go.
Just a quick one that's always confused me a little bit.
And I was reminded of it on the latest podcast
with Hannah Fry.
"You know how you all inform each other
"of your facts before the show has to be able to prepare.
"When you act surprised or impressed by someone's fact,
"is it A, you already know the fact,
"but still act like it's novel
"to make it sound like a good fact,
"or B, you kind of know what the fact is about,
"but you don't know the whole fact.
"James is the biggest proprietor of the,
"ah, is that right?
"Interesting, or that's amazing."
And I'm always left feeling like,
wait, didn't you already know that?
(laughing)
If you only know kind of what the fact is gonna be,
I'd love to see on what premise
some of Dan's facts have been rejected.
(laughing)
- So okay, yeah, over to you.
- Well, I don't think missing words
would help us choose a fact
because we do need to know what the subject is.
So if you're missing the subject from it,
that wouldn't work.
The truth is it's a mixture, isn't it,
of acting and delivery.
When someone delivers their fact in a funny way,
of course it makes you laugh, or--
- I think it would be a problem with this podcast
if every time someone said a fact
that one of us already knew,
we replied with, "Yes, I already knew that."
So I think it's just normal conversation
with your friends, right?
If your friends sometimes tell you something
and you already know some of it,
you still act slightly surprised
'cause you want a conversation with them.
- Definitely.
- It's just normal.
- And it's worth saying that
that's the only thing we do know.
When you're listening to the show,
we don't share any of the other facts.
There's no plan jokes or anything.
It's all new.
Just the headline is the only thing we go off.
- That's true.
All right, thanks to Pete.
- And your meat.
- Okay.
(laughing)
I quite like the procedural stuff.
There's another procedural question.
This is a spicy one.
- Spicy meat.
(laughing)
- It's from Federico.
- Has this got a name?
'Cause you've named some of the other sections.
- That's a good point.
- Like get to the meat.
Do you think we can call it that?
- Meat cute.
- I think meat cute, but wow.
I think spicy meat.
Spicy meat is the bit of the pod
where we open up a pepper army
and we see what's inside.
Federico writes, "Hey guys,
"over the many, many years I've been listening to fish,
"never, not once has James hosted the show."
- No, true.
- I know this is the best kept secret,
not only of the podcast,
but the whole QI HQ Corporation,
Inc. and Co. Global Entertainment giant.
I'm genuinely curious about this.
These are possible reasons I thought about.
Here's where we get to the spicy meat.
One, is it because he already has a senior position at QI?
Thus he's paid more.
Thus hosting the podcast would be overkill.
(laughing)
Number two, or is it because he hijacked the episode
and turned it into a bottomless golf of golf quotes?
(laughing)
Three, or is it rather because he really can't be bothered
and when Dan's not there,
either Anna or Andy always rushed to volunteer.
I'm sure I'm touching on something so sensitive
that you might refuse to answer
and that's why I'll be waiting for your response
with trepidation.
Best Federico.
- Lovely question.
- I don't really know why.
Well, I always thought of it as, I just wasn't a host
and Dan was a host
and then I always think that Anna's the next best host.
But,
(laughing)
- What, sorry?
- And so whenever Dan's not here,
I'm always like, Anna, why don't you host?
And Anna's usually like, no, I'm the host, yeah.
So yeah, I think I'm just far down.
The pecking order really in hosts.
I don't feel like I'm a host.
I don't feel like I have that authority that Dan has.
- You feel like I'm a third best host?
- It's only 'cause you keep injecting
those tortured metaphors right at the time.
The editing time is intense.
- It's the third best in a very, very high field.
- It's on the podium, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Yep.
(laughing)
- Yeah, no, I just don't really see myself
as the host of this show, so.
- I think as well it was sort of, to begin with,
you were seen as the, I was gonna, I was gonna,
this is the origins of it.
- I was gonna host it.
You were gonna be, as it were, the Alan Davis,
but you were the clever one.
So I was the idiot hosting, but you were the clever one.
And so when, then when it became a four,
that still was in our head that you were like,
never the host, you were the guy who was always,
you were the oracle, you were the--
- I feel like more like the Richard Osman
than the Alan Davis maybe.
- That's a good point, yeah.
- Kind of the person who just has the facts
and brings them in.
Then actually, of course, the actual show is
we all end up having facts and stuff.
But yeah, that was kind of the thought in my head
when we first started out the show.
- 'Cause I was never meant to have a fact.
What a mistake to change it.
What were we thinking?
- Here's a bit of cross on something you said recently, Dan.
- Oh yeah.
- Seth Sibesma, I hope I'm pronouncing it right.
I'm sorry if I'm not, Seth, says,
I don't mean to alarm you, but in episode 127,
Dan says that by the time the episode is launched
into space, do you remember we were gonna do that?
There's a sort of digital upload to the moon.
And land on the moon in 2024,
all of the podcast crew will be dead
due to a horrible explosion in the QI office
in 2023.
- Oh.
That's really interesting.
- And you said this in about 2016.
Please all be extra cautious this year
and perhaps hire an inspector to ensure the integrity
of gas lines and other potentially explosive elements
of your new offices.
- We have just moved into a new building
and we weren't allowed to have a poo in the building
because there were issues.
I wonder if some sort of drainage explosion
is on the carbon. - I think we're safe.
Like because Anna's not coming into the office
at the moment.
- Yes.
- So we're safe until Anna comes back.
- Okay.
- Oh, that's a point.
So Margaret Daniel wrote on the same subject.
She said, Dan quips in this episode
that all the elves will disappear in 2023.
Ironically, Anna has disappeared.
- Oh yeah.
- Then the rest of you disappeared
from the original office.
- Oh yeah, maybe that's what you meant.
This is a bit of a Nostradamus thing, isn't it?
- It is.
- Nostradamus said something slightly vague
and we're trying to shoehorn the facts into it.
- Nostradamus, these are my shit predictions.
- Nostradamus.
Here's a great fact that we got sent.
- We didn't go to the moon, by the way,
just to add that.
- Oh yeah, didn't that fall apart?
- We did, yeah.
So we did a, in one of our tour shows,
that was my first half, I sort of mentioned the fact
that we were meant to go to the moon
and then our mission got canceled
because the team that were funding it fell short.
Just short by a hundred million dollars.
(laughing)
- It's like us giving them a tanner.
It's so weird.
- Yeah.
- It's really weird.
- So yeah, so we never made it to the moon.
- No.
Oh well.
Here's a fact from Christian Ryder.
This is a great one.
Christian was looking at the surname Sizzers,
which apparently comes from the Latin word for a tailor,
and there was a small family of Russian Jews
with that surname that fled the pogrom of Alexander II
to America in the 1870s or '80s.
And I got to thinking even more.
And after a lot of searching and many hours wasted
on findagrave.com, I found the ultimate.
At the Jewish cemetery of Mount Sinai Memorial Park
in the Hollywood Hills, there are three Jewish men
who all lived at the same time in the area
and may well have known each other.
They were--
- Oh no, I've got it.
- Really?
- Milton H. Rock.
- Beautiful.
- Harry W. Paper and Samuel Sizzers.
- No, that's brilliant.
That's so funny.
What bit of the show are we in right now, by the way?
Are we still in Spicy Meat?
- No, no, we've moved on from the Spicy Meat course
to an amusing sorbet in between.
(laughing)
- Amusing sorbet.
- And it was boot, yeah, yeah.
- And we've moved on to another tortured metaphor.
- Yeah, so yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Wow, that's a brilliant fact.
- Isn't that incredible?
- That's incredible.
- Yeah, amazing.
- So good, and apparently he's tried to find out
a bit more about them.
On Rock's grave, Milton Rock--
- Rock killed the Sizzers, Sizzers killed Paper.
It's a triple homicide.
- Rock might have been a spy.
On Rock's grave, it says broke the Japanese code.
So he might have been part of the team
working on the Japanese equivalent of the enigma code.
- Cool.
- Which is amazing.
But there's not much information.
Anyway, Christian, thank you so much.
What a stunning--
- Yeah, incredible.
- What a fact.
- Incredible.
- That's good.
Ben writes about Hannah Fry's cabbie.
- Oh yeah?
- Oh yeah.
- So this was, Hannah came on the show
and she has a personal cabbie who she uses
and he can find any place in London
from just a photograph.
He knows exactly where you are.
- Yeah.
- Well, Ben writes, Hannah Fry's cabbie.
You do know that location data is included
in the background of the most photos taken on a phone.
He might be clever or he might be devious.
(laughing)
- Best wishes, Ben.
- That would be devious if that was true.
(laughing)
- Is that true?
You can just, any photo I sent to you,
you can get the location data from my photo.
- I'm not sure I would have the skills to do it,
but I think there would be metadata in there.
- Yeah.
- But not if I post on Twitter or something, right?
- I don't, I think normally if you post it on Twitter,
you're just posting the image.
But I'm just looking at an image I took on my phone now
and trying to get to the metadata.
- Oh no, I haven't added a location,
but it's got all the other data about how the photo was taken.
It's a photo of my car ownership certificate.
(laughing)
- Oh, you own a car, doing all right for yourself?
- I said I own a certificate, James.
Not a car.
(laughing)
I'm saving up for the car.
- Yeah?
(laughing)
- I nearly gave away a personal fact about myself.
Okay, here's another one.
This is a really great one.
It's kind of based on the music,
'cause we were talking a lot about Dan's thing of music
and people--
- The suit players.
- The suit is, this is moving the conversation on a lot,
so it's a new field.
It's from Phil Boyd, who says,
"Leland Sklar, who is probably the most recorded
"bass player ever due to his work with Phil Collins,
"Toto, James Taylor, and many, many more.
"He's played on thousands of albums, apparently.
"He had a special switch placed on one of his bass guitars
"that he regularly uses in the studio.
"The switch isn't connected to anything,
"and switching it does nothing at all,
"except trick record producers who ask him
"if he could change his tone to make it more muddy
"or bright or whatever."
- Brilliant, brilliant.
- So when a producer asks him,
he's flicks the producer switch
and plays exactly the same as before.
(laughing)
And then they say how much better it is than before.
- That's incredible.
- Yeah.
I'm really fascinated by--
- When you get tricked by something,
but you're at a high end of your profession, right?
Like you--
- Like a wine expert who gets fooled by a--
- Exactly.
- A really cheap bottle of wine,
and thinks it's great.
- Yeah, if you're, we were in the pub the other day
with my friend, who's, I would say, a very clever person,
and he had a beer downstairs, went upstairs,
and he said the beer was flat.
So they came over with two glasses of the same beer,
and what he didn't know was one was for me,
and one was for him.
He thought they were two different samples
from upstairs and downstairs,
and he said, "Yes, you can clearly taste that
"the one on the right is different to the one on the left,
"even though it was the exact same."
And I just, I find that fascinating
that our brains can, weirdly, he's a brain surgeon,
so you should know what his brain's doing.
But they play those tricks on us.
It's fascinating. - Yeah, that's really clever.
- Okay, here's another one.
It's from William Lay.
Hi, everyone.
- Hi, William.
- Hello, William.
- Do you like bricks?
- Love 'em.
(laughing)
- I don't really have an opinion on them.
- Do you like bricks so much you start a website
dedicated to cataloging them,
but only if they have a word or name stamped into them?
- No. - Well, Dave Salary does.
It's a genuinely really interesting website
to have a poke around, stumbled across it
in the comments of Reddit thread,
and immediately thought,
"This has Andrew Hunter Murray written all over it."
(laughing)
- What, one of the bricks has Andrew Hunter Murray
written all over it?
- And, you know, I went to the website, Old Bricks,
and it's bloody good.
- Okay, so the one you've just shown us says 007 on it.
- I know.
It's nothing to do with James Bond.
It's possibly a refractory brick batch number.
Anyway, it's brocross.com/bricks.
- Okay, are we doing a new thing
where people can send us interesting websites
about really dull subjects now?
- And then you just look at it while we stare at you?
(laughing)
- I'm sorry for trying to advance the form
of Drop As A Light.
I'm sorry for daring to innovate, you know?
- Which part of the tortured food metaphor is this?
'Cause it feels like--
- It's a lull.
It's a lull. (laughing)
The mains have taken quite a long time to come now, actually.
- Can I, sorry, can we get some more bread
stuck to there while we're waiting?
(laughing)
- Okay, okay.
- Oh, just on food, actually.
I got sent a thing.
I annoyingly haven't written down the name of the person,
so I'm really sorry, but you'll know who you are.
She said, "I was telling my mum about tender stem broccoli
"and how it was created by a Japanese company.
"I told her the next time she sees some
"to look for a little copyright icon,
"she went to a fridge, pulled out a pack of tender stem
"broccoli instead, looking for the symbol on the broccoli."
(laughing)
- Oh, that's so funny.
- Yeah, that's so good.
Here is a very cool thing.
So you know, this is the thing that's been going
in droppers of line since February.
So it's quite an advanced conversation now,
but it's about the longest day?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Okay.
- Okay, so yeah, we've said, someone sent in saying
that when the clocks go back or forward,
that's the longest day,
and various pedants are giving different answers.
Is that right?
- That's exactly right.
So Mark Jacobs writes,
he's got a new variant of the theory, I love this.
- Great.
- I meant to send you this fact a few years ago,
found it during, he was gonna be on a Radio 4 program
about leap years.
The fact didn't make it onto that show,
and I fully expect it to meet the same fate here.
(laughing)
- I'm excited.
- Can I just say, if you've ever meant to be
on a radio show, and you had some amazing facts
for that show, and they weren't good enough
for that show, do send them on, please.
- Please do.
Okay, this is the fact.
The fact is that the claim for being historically
the longest day of the year,
could be said to be held by the 24th of February,
which every four years used to be 48 hours long.
- Okay.
- Because it was the original leap day
in the Roman calendar.
It was the bisect style day.
So instead of there being a 29th of February,
you would do, February was still 28 days long,
but you'd have a really long 24th of February.
You'd have two 24s.
- Two 24s, yeah.
- That's ironic, isn't it?
Because if the TV show 24 was based on that day,
they would have to have 48 episodes.
- That's true.
- Jack Bauer is, sorry, a Roman senator in this?
- Yeah, okay.
- A very exhausted one by the end.
(laughing)
- Yeah, and apparently this was used in Britain
well into the 18th century.
- That's truly interesting.
- Probably the second 24th of February,
and it was officially replaced
by an act of parliament in 1750.
- That's great, okay.
- Yeah.
- That's the longest day.
- Thank you, Mark.
- Until next week's episode.
- Longest day, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Definitely.
- Who can beat it?
- Well, Charlie Thompson just points
a little bit of clarification.
Based on the trivia question about the longest day,
I had a light bulb moment that I think was caused
by listening to the show for too long, not possible.
Someone born at 1.59 AM on October the 29th of 2023
would be younger than someone born at 1.01 AM on that day.
- Okay.
- That's cool.
- Yeah, that's interesting.
- Oh, I see.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Quirk there?
- Yeah.
- Quirk of time?
- Yeah, that's really that interesting in most cases.
But let's say it was Royal Twins.
- Oh!
- That could be really interesting, couldn't it?
- Yes, that's really good.
- You think you've won, and then, yeah.
- Yeah, well, like when you both turn 18 and then someone
dies and you become the new king or queen,
you look at your birth certificate.
One of them looks younger, but it's not actually,
it's basically a new game of thrones, I think.
- That's brilliant.
- Just from that one fact we could extrapolate
an entire universe.
- That is the best possible plot implication of that fact,
I think.
- Yeah.
- Nice, genuinely, I really strongly mean that.
Just to briefly circle back to, like, spicy meat.
- Yeah, let's get back to the spicy meat.
- Connor Wagstaff writes, "Despite listening for so long,
"I had never seen the faces behind the voices
"until browsing your website the other day."
Those such things as fish.com.
I was really surprised.
I hope this doesn't sound rude.
- I'm sure it will.
- It will.
Let's see how Andrew and James look, because, can you guess?
- He thought we were both women.
(laughing)
- No, this is something we've had before.
- Yeah, people often mistake my voice for your voice
or my face for your face.
- Your face and voice, should we swap?
- That's it.
Apparently your face suits my voice better and vice versa.
- Yeah, Andrew looks as my mental image of James was
and vice versa.
I wonder if this is something you've heard before
or whether I'm just being exceedingly strange
by thinking about it and then also emailing.
Not at all.
That's the main bit of feedback we get
when people see us after listening.
- The thing is, I am from the north of England.
Andy, I don't think that you look like a northerner.
You don't look like someone who's come
from the backwaters of Bolton.
So I don't know why people think that.
I think it might be that you have a deeper voice
and I'm older.
- Maybe that's it.
Maybe that's it.
- Could be.
- Yeah.
You're saying that my pocket square,
my triple breasted suit.
- All I'm saying is, do you remember when we talked
about there was a group of people who did a survey
of pubs in the north and they couldn't find
any northerners to do it.
So they got a load of posh southerners
to pretend to be northerners.
I'm saying you couldn't pull that off.
- I think you're right.
I think I wouldn't get down my first half
of Shandy.
- I often see, there's a thing of, a lot of people say,
oh, it's really nice having the four different
distinctive voices we can tell who's talking.
But I do often see that you and I,
some people go, I can't tell between Dan and Andy.
- Really?
- Yeah, which feels really unfair on you.
Because that means--
- It's not unfair, you've got a nice voice.
- Well no, it's the shit coming out of it.
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You can be labeled with some of these inaccurate facts.
- Yeah, that's a good point.
The posh people coming to the north,
I don't think I've told this story before.
So Anna came, we did a show in Manchester.
And Anna stayed with my sister.
And so we had to drive from Bolton to Manchester.
And I drove, I can't remember why I was driving,
but I was driving down.
And she was in the passenger seat.
And I was giving her the tour of Bolton.
So I was like, and on your right, you can see B&Q.
And on the left, you can see the old
Bolton Wanderers Stadium and whatever.
And I drove down, I said, and on the left here,
it's the tip.
And Anna's like, oh, the tip.
That's interesting.
I didn't know Bolton was famous for that.
I'm like, what?
I like the tip, you know, like where you throw away
your old dishwashers and stuff.
And she went, oh, I thought it was like another name
for a castle or something.
- Is that a name for it?
- I don't think so, but she thought that the Bolton tip
might have been some kind of old, you know--
- Yeah, the tip that's all this point.
- But it presumably looks like a tip.
- It was, you couldn't really see the tip itself.
You could see the gates.
- That's someone recently thrown away a castle.
(laughing)
That would be confusing.
- Wow, yeah.
Here's a bit of interesting, really interesting
bonus info from Louise who writes to say,
"Howdy, that's not the interesting bit.
"I thought you'd like to know where the Natural History
"museum storage warehouse is."
- Oh, so this is the warehouse that has all the whale bones,
which is a secret, and Philip Piperi was particularly
put out by the fact that we wouldn't know where it was.
- Yeah, so Louise writes, "Unless they have others
"that aren't listed," which I guess is possible,
"is this one in Wandsworth."
(laughing)
And she attaches a link, and it's on governmentbuildings.co.uk.
I used to live just by it, but there's nothing to give away
the secrets inside.
- How big are the doors?
'Cause they had noted big doors, didn't they?
- It's just a map, sadly.
It doesn't have the--
- Could we get on Google Street View
and see how big the doors are?
- Oh yeah, we probably could.
Yeah, let me do that now.
- More from staring at Andy as he looks at websites.
- And I've just clicked on the bit
that's marked on the field, and it's an empty field.
(laughing)
It's an invisible warehouse.
- You know, if you ever go on Google Maps
and you search for certain areas of America,
it's all pixelated, and they don't let you see.
And Google are kind of in on it,
and they will pixelate things
that governments don't want you to see.
Do you think that Google Street View
has put an image of an empty field here
because it doesn't want people to know
where the whale bones are?
- Almost certainly.
And actually, looking at the outline of this field now,
it's in the shape of a whale.
(laughing)
- Well, it could be an underground warehouse.
- It could be.
- We could have been looking at the ceiling there, basically,
the rooftop.
- What a good point.
- Yeah.
- Okay, thank you, Louise,
for that potentially criminally compromising
bit of information.
She says, she adds, "If the whale bones get stolen,
don't blame me."
Don't see who else will be responsible.
(laughing)
That's almost all.
That's almost all for this time.
We've got one last message from Toby Bird.
So I guess this is the after dinner mint.
- Okay.
- We skipped a few courses.
(laughing)
- Which was--
- I was still waiting for the make up.
(laughing)
- Sorry.
Sorry.
Not at the drop of the line restaurant.
(laughing)
That's all starters, soulmates, after dinner mints.
- Wow, yeah.
Okay, well, this is from Toby Bird.
Hello, nice to think of the fish.
On the most recent podcast,
Andy mentioned bimetallic strips.
- Oh, yeah.
Really cool.
Kettles, right?
- And kettles, which work because the two metals
expand at different rates
when the water temperature increases.
- Yeah.
- And that's how kettles turn themselves off.
- Really, I can't believe anyone listening
didn't already know that, I have to say.
- Really?
- I do think that bimetallic strips
are quite a well-known thing.
- You're a man of science, though.
- I guess so.
- And you did physics, didn't you, at uni.
So you know, I mean, you're--
- Okay, maybe.
- You worked on that kettle shop for years as well.
(laughing)
- Just putting two bits of metal together.
That was my whole job.
- Yeah.
- It's an incredibly unsexy dance, isn't it?
The bimetallic strip.
(laughing)
Well, Toby writes, "I thought you would find it interesting,"
and I don't think he's writing to James here, clearly,
"that there are some materials that shrink
when you heat them up."
- Okay.
- Oh, that is interesting.
- Yeah.
- Thanks to physics.
(laughing)
- Well, now he's explained that.
Let's move on.
I think that's the end of the show, is it?
- No, it's a slightly complicated explanation,
which I would not do justice to,
but just take it from Toby Bird and from us,
that you get some materials that shrink
when you heat them up and enjoy that.
- That's physics.
(laughing)
And there's the slogan of this week's episode
of "Drop Us a Line."
Bye.
(upbeat music)
Okay, and that's it.
On that bombshell about bimetallic strips,
we're gonna end it.
Thank you so much for all of your correspondence.
It genuinely, it makes us laugh.
It makes us think.
It sometimes makes us cry.
So please do send us more of it.
Podcast at qi.com.
If you want to send us anything, please do.
And we'll be back in a month with another one of these.
And in a couple of weeks with...
- Something new.
- Alternate format.
(laughing)
Bye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]