(upbeat music)
- Hi there, Dan and Andy here.
Just a little announcement before we start this week's show.
Uh, we have reached the point where next week,
Anna Tajinsky will return.
This is very exciting.
She's back.
Yeah, she's back, baby.
And we've had an amazing run of guests.
It's been so fun, but there's no one we love more than Anna.
So it's very exciting that she's gonna be back.
So put it in your calendars.
However, we've got a very exciting final guest episode
to go out with before the return of Anna
and that is with a fellow QIL.
Yes, you may remember Manu Onreo.
She has been on Ask the Elf, our little bonus show
and Manu as well as being one of the writers of QIL
is on the podcast Lunchbox MV,
which of course is also made by QIL Productions.
Lunchbox MV is a show all about food,
food from around the world, food related paraphernalia.
It is the food show, it's Manu, it's Jack Chambers,
another Elf who you will have heard on Fish
and Fish Product to the Past and Rosie McKean,
the Pastor Queen.
Oh, yes, yeah.
And so, as Andy says, Lunchbox MV,
they each come to the table each episode
with their Lunchbox and each episode takes on a theme
and they kind of blow your mind
with all sorts of interesting takes
on the history of that food and so on.
So there's about 65 episodes out there now,
everything from the episode called Asparagus
through to mangoes, through to food art.
What are these all about?
You have to listen to find out.
That's right.
So if you enjoy Manu's appearance on Fish Today,
we're short, you will enjoy Lunchbox MV, check it out.
Check it out now and one last thing
before we leap into this week's episode is to say,
hey, do you like listening to us four dorks talk every week
and you want more?
Yeah.
Why not become a member of the secret private members club?
The one where we put up bonus episodes
where we have video, where we have online quizzes.
It's a magical place and it's called Club Fish.
That's right, just go to patreon.com/clubfish today
and check it out and join us.
- Join us. - Okay.
But for now, enjoy Fish, enjoy Manu
and enjoy some seaweed.
Okay, on with the show.
As a little teaser there.
Really good.
I feel teased.
(soft music)
(speaking in foreign language)
Hello and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin, and Manu Onrio.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, it's Manu.
- Okay, today my factors, seaweed bubbles
could stop you getting pregnant.
- That is a relief.
- Oh no. - I have been trying to avoid it.
There you come.
Is that where Andy talks to a woman about seaweed bubbles
and they don't want to have sex with a banymar.
- I mean, that would also work.
- Yep.
- No, so actually, this is a semi-edible seaweed bubble
and I brought an example for you to sample
if you would like to.
- Yes, please.
- I brought with me something called agar agar jelly
which is what my Indonesian aunties to make.
So it's a sweet coconutty dessert thing.
This one has been put in the fridge
and it's made using a seaweed gelatin.
So it's vegan, it's very squishy.
No pressure to eat it, but I mean,
I think it's delicious.
- Okay, Dan, can you explain what it looks like
before Andy is desperate to go.
- Yeah, yeah.
It looks like a giant bit of tofu on top
of a jelly-like substance underneath.
Like a whiteboard marker, you know?
It's got that kind of vibe about.
- Like a whiteboard rubber.
- Yeah, a rubber, rather.
- It looks like food we were told food would be
in the future in the '60s.
Like in the future they'll only eat
just this wobbling jet colorless wee gelatin.
But it tastes like a rose dinner, incredibly.
- Yeah. - It tastes like a full rose dinner.
- Have someone tell us what it tastes like.
- Yeah, so they brought my tongs.
- It's enormously gelatinous.
- It kind of just disappears in your mouth
as soon as you bite.
It sort of just slides down.
- Is it like he's in a jellyfish?
- Sorry?
- Yeah, it's like a jellyfish that's been in a mold,
which jelly I suppose has because it's a jellyfish.
- Yeah, yeah.
- James, you're not tempted.
- I'm not a big fan of seaweed, I have to say.
- Oh, okay.
- I will eat stuff if that was disgusting
and it was like a dare, I would eat it
because it's quite nice.
- Yeah, 'cause you've done the museum
of disgusting foods.
- Yeah, I would do that just for the show,
but to enjoy it, I just, I'm very bad at texture.
- It is very wobbly.
- I think it tastes fantastic.
- I love it.
- Are you saying if I go home now,
maybe my wife won't get pregnant 'cause I've eaten that?
- No, basically, agarose, the sugar derived from agar agar,
which is what we've just eaten,
is used to make these special beads
that can trick sperm into binding with them
to kind of protect the eggs,
and this was all done in mice.
And what they did is they covered these beads
in a protein called Zona Policida glycoprotein II
or ZP2 for short.
And what this does is it tricks sperm into thinking
that whatever it is is the egg
'cause it's basically sending out signals being like,
"I'm an egg, I'm an egg."
And the sperm are attracted to it.
- It's like having a weather spoons,
and then next door to the weather spoons,
you've got another weather spoons
that's made entirely out of jelly.
- Yes.
- But they kind of cover it
in the smell of stale beer and desperation,
so that people are tricked into thinking is that,
and then all the men sort of water was
as weather spoons, but they get stuck to the outside.
- That is exactly right.
- Yeah.
- The in-house weather spoon ambassador
is looking absolutely curious for this.
- Actually, it tracks a very good clientele.
- Oh, it's a spoon?
- I have no idea, it's a spoon, Sven.
- 1.49 for a pint of ruddles.
- Oh!
- He's not a fool.
He's not a fool.
He's a drug, but he's no, he's full.
- I love that.
- He's a drug and a loser, but he's no fool.
- Yeah, that's very cool.
- That's extraordinary.
- It's a decoy.
- It's a decoy item.
- Exactly.
- And we use this agar jelly,
because basically it has the same consistency as an egg,
so it tricks them into eggs, is that?
- Yeah, I think they use this kind of arugost jelly,
a lot in microbiology to kind of sift through substances
and build structures, 'cause it's basically
like a nice squishy building block.
And you can make.
- Yeah, and things love living on it.
- Yeah.
- In the same way that agar, which agarose is derived from,
is really good for petri dishes.
- Exactly.
- Right.
- I'm using this, so it's in test mode at the moment.
- So this is a group of cellular biologists from Maryland in 2016.
I tried to find out whether it's actually in development,
because I think it's a fantastic non-hormone or contraceptive
if it works, but like any kind of medicine,
these drugs take a long time to develop,
and I couldn't find out if they're actually in production,
which I think means they're probably not.
- I'm gonna stick with the good old fashioned methods.
- Oh yeah.
- Which.
- Conversation.
(laughing)
- Talk about wallpaper long enough.
- Oh no.
- And eggs.
(laughing)
- But what is really cool is it works both ways.
So not only would it create decoy eggs,
because the strongest sperm stick to it the fastest,
it can also be used to select really strong sperm for OVF.
So it's like a great way to prevent
and a great way to encourage pregnancy when it's wanted.
- That would be outside of intercourse, right?
That would be a petri dish situation.
- Yes, exactly.
- Exactly.
- And then you bring the claw in.
- So the use of agar to, and agarose to be used in science,
it comes from the meeting of a cock and a funny.
- Really, I can't believe you found that.
That's what I'm thinking about the same.
- So in 1881, the funny Hess was a German technician,
and she was working with Robert Cock,
and she had seen people using agar agar to make jam,
and they've been using it for a long time.
They basically make in this stuff that you've made, man.
They've been used it for a long time,
and they needed something to grow bacteria around,
and she said, "Well, why don't we try this?"
And Robert Cock did try that,
and then he managed to isolate the tuberculum bacterium,
which caused tuberculosis,
and he won the Nobel Prize for that.
But he didn't mention funny in his speech or anything like that.
- Boo, boo, boo.
How many times a day do you guys eat seaweed?
- On an average day.
- Well, I had some this morning.
Did you?
- Yeah, I had sushi this morning.
- I don't care, I don't worry.
- It's actually nice.
- The weather's been the breakfast,
it's been changing a lot, isn't it?
- You see?
- Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
- I don't know English at all.
My daughter loves it, but I don't like it at all.
- But probably, James, you eat seaweed several times a day.
- No, yes.
- Never.
- This is the crazy thing.
Most commercially-produced foods rely on phycololoids.
Phycololoids.
These are commercial extracts that are derived from seaweed,
and basically what they're terrific at is thickening
and stabilizing and jelling,
and all the things that you need food to do commercially
are you get liquids and paste, various liquids and paste.
And what is modern commercial food, except a mix
of liquids and pastes solidified?
- Yeah, yeah.
- So jelly beans, frozen cheesecake,
ready-made lasagna.
- James, I'm talking about your breakfast every day.
- Ice, what about cold burnt toast
with low cholesterol spread?
- Cold burnt toast is on here.
- Surely spread.
- There's lots of spreads, I'm sure.
- Can lunch and meat, James?
I know you love a can lunch and meat.
Chocolate milk.
- I'm actually, when I got to a restaurant,
I asked them if they have a non-phycololoid.
- And you?
- I love you.
- They say any allergy, sir?
Yes, I don't really.
Phycololoids.
- It's stunning what it's an eggnog.
- Right, yeah.
- I know there's been a few niche ones in there,
but a lot of them.
- This is great concertoceptive chat.
Right now, and it's fruit yogurt.
I've got it.
Some poor girl with a corner of a party.
Fish fingers.
Post law forever.
(all laughing)
Have you guys heard of the kelp highway hypothesis?
- Excellent.
- No, I haven't.
- Okay, so kelp is a type of seaweed.
- A type of seaweed.
- A highway is, so the kelp is moving somewhere?
- It's actually not kelp moving, it's people moving,
thanks to kelp and it's a hypothesis.
Okay, it's the theory.
We all know the boring old theory
about how people got into the new world
over the arctic, or Lamborghini, whatever.
- Yeah, the very bridge, maybe.
- Maybe the very bridge, whatever.
Actually, what this theory posits is that there are these
massive kelp forests stretching all the way
from Alaska down to Southern California.
I mean, down the coast of Canada and the USA basically,
and across from Japan.
The theory is, early humans settled the Americas
basically by following the kelp.
- Cool.
- And that's how they had the nutrients
to get along that route, didn't they?
- So they're not like walking on the kelp.
- They're not walking on the kelp.
- They're going, they're eating the kelp.
And Northern California used to have these huge pyramids
of mollusk shells from where the early settlers
had eaten them, feasted, and they were all flattened sadly.
But they used to be there, these massive great pyramids
of what they'd left behind.
- Very cool, that's very cool.
- And this agarega that we have on the table.
There are a few interesting things about that.
So you know the bubbles in bubble tea
that usually made of tapioca,
but you can make them out of this as well.
- Okay.
- And so you can get special ones that have this in.
And also, the way that you make it
is you get the seaweed, and then you put it on the beach,
and then you dry it off, and then you freeze it,
and then you thaw it again, and then you freeze it,
then you thaw it again.
But this was discovered accidentally
by a Japanese innkeeper in 1658,
when he accidentally left it outside
on a frosty morning, came back, it was frozen.
Thought, oh no, I'm going to have to bring that in,
and then make the same mistake for day after day after day,
and kept freezing it, and then found that it had got rid
of a lot of the impurities,
and that they could make proper agar jelly out of it.
- Because family is saying, can you please bring in
that seaweed?
I'm busy, I'm busy, I'll do it, I'll do it, I'll do it.
That's a wonderful accidental discovery,
a story.
- A lot of discoveries happen.
- By co-cups.
- Yep, and Fanny.
- And Fanny up there.
- Colleges.
Right, her out of history.
I was looking into futuristic seaweed.
There's a group called the Safe Seaweed Coalition.
- Nice.
- This is my kind of people.
- Yeah.
- I don't know if there's a dangerous seaweed coalition.
Possibly there is, but basically they advocate
farming more of it.
And what they think is that if we just add a bit more seaweed,
this will help secure a good chunk of the world's food supply.
If we found on 0.03% of the ocean surface,
you could add 10% of the world's food supply,
and free up a load of land that's currently used
for farming crops.
You can actually provide a lot of this stuff with seaweed.
And there are various ideas, like there are seaweed slash wind farms,
which is lovely where you've basically strung out lines,
grown seaweed on them next to a wind farm.
It just grows, it doesn't need land,
it doesn't need fresh water, it doesn't need fertilizers.
It just grows.
- Yeah.
- And then you have a step by attaching it to the wind turbine
and pulling it up like a spaghetti fart.
- Yeah.
- It's exactly like that.
But basically, I think it was the food of tomorrow.
I think you're just going to sometimes you just have to add
some whimsy to these ideas.
Otherwise, people are not going to go for them.
I hate you.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that in Disney's three little pigs,
the pig who built his house out of bricks was voiced
by a man who were up in a house made of sticks.
- Such a good fact.
- How did you find this?
- I was, I got lost down the rabbit hole highway
and I randomly discovered it.
So this was a very famous actor in his day, voice actor,
as well as a screen actor.
He was called Pinto Colvig.
We'll get into him in a bit,
but he was the voice not only behind one of the little pigs,
but he was the original voice of goofy.
He was two of the seven dwarves in Snow White.
He did a lot of big voices for Disney.
And yeah, I read that he was the pig
who made his house of bricks
and I thought, I wonder if he lived in a house made of sticks.
And I spent three hours googling.
And I eventually found...
- Was it remote control fish?
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- That's the term we use when you hope a fact is true
and you desperately search to try and prove it.
- So a house made of sticks.
We're not just talking about wooden house here.
- We are talking about wooden house wooden house here.
- I don't know, but it's a technical term, isn't it?
- Yeah, stick build is a term that you would use
for wooden houses.
- When you say he grew up there,
he didn't live there his whole life, did he?
- No.
- Like he had to leave when the big bad wolf flew in hell.
- Yeah, they fled town.
So the house is a very specific house.
You can still see it on Google Maps.
I did that this morning.
The address is 410 South Oregon street,
Jacksonville in Oregon.
And I found an original description of it
which was it's a one and one half story wood frame house
with gable roof that stands on the hillside
overlooking much of Jacksonville.
- Question.
You said it's a one and a half story building?
- Yeah.
- What's going on there?
- Mezzanine.
- Mezzanine?
- Yeah.
- It must be.
- Come on, did that.
- Exactly.
- When you said this fact round,
my first thought was great fact.
Second thought was, I don't really know this Disney
three little pigs, like I know all the movies of Disney.
I thought I did.
But then I watched it on YouTube.
And it's a short, but I definitely knew it.
Like I had it growing up.
I think we must have had it on cassette or something
growing up because it's the one which has the song
who's afraid of a big bad wolf.
- It's 1933 that it was made.
It is a short, but it won the Oscar
for best short animation that year.
But yeah, he was an amazing character
and other notable things that he did in his career.
He voiced one of the munchkins in the Wizard of Oz.
He's one of those guys where his footprints
is just kind of on all these major classics.
But most importantly, for a decade,
he played Bozo the Clown.
He was the first Bozo the Clown.
He was the original, was he?
'Cause Bozo the Clown was a big franchise.
- Right.
- There were Bozo's all over the place.
And that's why we did a thing about Clowns
and I researched Bozo's and I never mentioned it.
Basically, there's a spell.
In fact, recently, there were a rush
of obitories of Bozo's.
- Yeah.
- And you see a headlight, like Bozo the Clown has died.
- Oh, some other Bozo's died.
- So basically, it's very much who's this clown, you know?
It's just loads of loads of Bozo's.
- Including his son, who was Bozo as well.
- Oh my god. - Yeah, Nipo Clown though.
- But I think that in 2026,
I reckon we'd be more familiar with Goofy
than Bozo the Clown in the UK.
- Absolutely, very true.
- I would just say that his son also played Bozo
the Clown and therefore will have had big shoes to fill.
- Ah.
- He will say that. - Very nice.
- James, can you just edit the hymn back when we were?
- It's not really gonna work.
I'm gonna have to keep the big gaps.
- That's okay.
(laughing)
He voiced Sleepy and Grumpy, yeah, as well.
And he was the original voice of Pluto and Bluto.
- His Bluto.
- Bluto is Bluto. - Bluto is Bluto.
- The Minion.
- Popeye.
- Yeah, he took over that role.
So he wasn't the original Bluto,
but he was the original Goofy
and he fell out with Walt Disney.
And after he fell out with Disney and left,
there was a couple of years where there was no Goofy
because they just didn't replace him.
- Was he on Goofy?
- Basically, he owned the voice
and he owned the mannerisms.
- Interesting.
- Because he invented a character called the Apple Knocker.
And the Apple Knocker was based on someone he knew growing up.
He called him a gritty half baked village knit wet.
- Oh.
- And this Apple Knocker, but he based his voice
and his mannerisms and the way that he walked on this person.
And then Goofy came along and he used his existing character.
So it meant that like there were lots of things
that you couldn't copy from Disney,
but you could copy Goofy because it wasn't really on by Disney.
- I do really nice story from Pinter's autobiography
about making Snow White.
- Oh yeah.
- He was also a fantastic musician.
I think he played the clarinet.
And they have a deleted scene about soup.
And it's just a really long stint of them singing about soup.
But the way they created the noises
were actually having soup every day,
making all of these slurping, gurgling sounds,
but in harmony with each other,
like a seven-part harmony for each of the dwarves.
And they had a really big argument about what liquid it should be
'cause no one wanted to eat soup.
First thing in the morning for like days on end
creating the song.
So they were gonna use water,
but that wasn't like slurpy, gurgly enough.
Then they all decided beer.
We'll just do beer.
We all love beer.
But it was too frothy.
And it wasn't gonna make the slurping noises that they wanted.
So they landed on buttermilk.
So they spent nearly a week just slurping buttermilk
and created this incredible song.
- Just one more thing on this three little pigs movie.
It came out in 1933 which was the worst year of the Depression.
Basically, who's afraid of the big bad wolf
became a song that everyone would sing
as if to say, you know, we'll get through this, you know.
Like things can only get better by D-ream.
It was like the bat song of its day.
- I do like, there are a few behind the scenes things about it.
There's the song in it where they have to rhyme
the word wolf at the end of one of the lines
and they don't manage it.
They spent three hours with everyone,
every creative member of the team
sitting around with the Persian Gulf.
That's why I'm saying now.
- Yeah, they couldn't find it in the end.
And so they decided, let's just fix it
by making the two pigs play a flute and a violin
in place of a word.
- There was also a bit later a children's book
which was based on the three little pigs
that encouraged children to invest their pocket money
in war bonds.
- Wait, I know about this.
There was a second world war three little pigs
made in Canada, a special version
which where practical pig is one of the parts.
- Yeah, that was a one of the big.
- He builds his house from Canadian war bonds.
- Yeah, yeah.
So that was the Canadian one
and then the Americans did their own version
a little bit later.
- People would be so cross today,
if you suggested children,
but their pocket money into war bonds.
I think that's quite a good idea.
- What is a bond like?
It's not a physical thing, is it?
- It's where you give a load of money to the government
and they promise to give you some back with interest
but they use the money for war.
- Yeah, you need to raise a lot of money now
for tanks, planes, whatever.
So for the investors, it's kind of a good idea
because it's the government who's giving you
the money so in theory they shouldn't default on them.
- You're not giving anything physical back.
You could build a...
- No.
- That's true.
- I'm premium bonds, you at least get a certificate.
(laughing)
- It's from the premium bonds.
I'm saying it's a little...
Why is it known with this?
Sorry, okay, okay.
I'm at the party again.
(laughing)
I really know it as the source of the play
and who's afraid of Virginia Woolf?
By Albert Albey.
- Which I have read, so.
- Okay, yeah, I mean the titles based on it
but I think largely speaking, the plot is quite different.
- I think it's about sort of unhappy married couples.
I don't think it's anything really.
I don't think it's any big bad wolf at all, yeah.
- Doesn't even feature Virginia Woolf
as a character as far as I remember.
- Doesn't it?
- They sing the song.
- They don't sing anything.
I mean, they take all the fun out of it, basically.
- That's so funny, 'cause I don't know that one.
I just know me, I'm afraid of Virginia Woolf
by Alan Bennett.
Which is a play about that play.
But I don't know your play.
Interesting, wow, we piece it together.
- I've got a bit on pigs actually building.
- Yes, please.
So pigs build nests.
I had no idea.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, there was a study published in 2002
that followed a group of wild pigs.
On the coastal plains of South Carolina
and they found that ones who are farrowing
so that some females are about to give birth
started building nests out of all of this,
like natural material.
But yeah, loads of animals build nests.
Like loads of mammals build nests, cats, dogs, humans.
- Guerrillas. - Guerrillas.
- Guerrillas, exactly.
But in 2013, a group of researchers were studying
human nesting and they found women were more likely
to get really into cleaning and organizing
in their third trimester of pregnancy.
- Yeah.
- You do hear that, they do.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Like people primping the nest.
- Mm-hmm.
- Yeah.
- What about houses made of sticks, Andy?
- Okay, I have a wooden house link
to the first ever friend of the podcast.
- James Garfield.
- Oh, yeah.
- Oh, did he, a lot of those earlier presidents
came from log cabins, didn't they?
- Everyone was obsessed with saying
they had been born in a log cabin.
- Yeah. - If he was standing for president,
it was almost a requirement of the job
that he had to say, well, I was born in a log cabin, of course.
- It was the equivalent of a British prime minister
saying that they supported a football team.
- Yes, exactly.
- I have her in saying, Iseapar, Ashton Villa,
yeah, of course she do that.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Exactly.
So Lincoln, there is a Lincoln Memorial log cabin replica
inside a national park, which is inside a massive stone temple
that was built to Lincoln.
They just said they'd have a replica of the log cabin.
It's incredibly weird.
But basically, just, you had to do it.
Like, Rutherford B. Hayes grew up in a great big house,
but it had a log extension.
So he was able to claim log cabin status.
James Garfield, I think, was the final president born
in a log cabin in 1831.
- That's cool.
- And I just found a little side factor about him.
You know, so he was shot.
- Yes, yeah.
- Eight everything through his own house.
After he was shot, he was taken to the White House.
And it was decided that he would do much better
if he had a seaside holiday.
- Right.
- But he needed to be taken to a seaside location.
- Yeah.
- 300 men worked insanely hard,
laying a railway track to a little cottage
on the coast for him.
- Was that nuts?
- It's really cool.
- Is this research you did in episode one
of "Nose of Things" official?
You're finally getting to use.
- I've been, man, you're a little sick.
I've been trying to get this in every episode,
since episode one.
- No, it's making a fantastic.
- We still get houses made out of wood.
Buildings made out of wood.
Wood and skyscrapers are known as plice scrapers.
And you get those all around the world.
There's a 20 story one in Sweden.
There's a 25 story one in Milwaukee.
And in London, they're talking about building
one called the Oakwood Tower,
which will be 300 meters high.
We'll be in Barbican, not Oakwood,
which is quite confusing,
but they're gonna build this big wooden tower, apparently.
- That's insane.
- How wooden are we talking?
All the lifts made of wood.
- So it's the structure,
so where you would have steel beams
that are holding everything together,
you would have wooden beams.
And then like the panels,
you would have like plywood panels, I guess.
And the reason is that actually wood
is very good for the environment,
weirdly enough, better than concrete.
Would you believe that?
- Is it?
- It's amazing.
The energy required to produce
a laminated wooden beam
is one sixth of what would be used for a steel beam.
- Right, that's good.
- It's basically a building of a big tree, aren't you?
You are. - It's a big tree house.
- It is in a way, yeah.
- Do you know about horse mergers' big tree house?
- Oh, do I?
- Yeah.
- It was said to be the biggest tree house of all time.
Who's that?
- Horace Burgess, he was a minister.
He lived in Crossville, Tennessee.
- A minister as in the church minister.
- Yeah, church minister.
- You're really making us drag this out of me.
(laughing)
So it was an American church minister, Horace Burgess.
Sorry, just the way he said, "Horace Burgess."
It's not like, you know, "Horace Burgess."
- Horace Burgess, we don't know.
- Horace?
- He got a message from God,
saying you should build a tree house.
And I'll make sure you've got all the material.
We did it, we had great time with Noah.
So just, he was dug a boat.
But now I want a tree house to go with it.
- Yeah, he said, "I'll see that you never run out of material."
And so he decided to build it.
And he did.
He built a 30 meter tall tree house.
He built it largely on his own.
He had 500 pounds of penny nails.
He had a nail gun that he did it by himself.
You'd seen pictures of it.
It's remarkable.
People got married in it.
And when they weren't getting married in it,
he used the space for the marriage as a basketball court.
- But it burned down.
- Oh, well.
- And it took 15 minutes to burn down.
I can't tell if he's saying that's a long time or not long.
- That's very quick to burn down.
- Yeah.
- This would be the best episode of Grand Designs
I ever seen.
- Yeah.
- Well, it took him decades.
So there'd be a lot of revisits to see how he was getting on.
But yeah, it was a new owner.
The new owner had just bought it and it burnt down.
But he didn't have insurance.
So he kind of just said no more about it.
- He said no more about it.
- Yeah, he just, I think he was so depressed about
the fact that he'd bought this thing
and then he let it burn down.
- Do you think God was upset that he'd sold it
and that's why God burned it down?
- So he'd likely to.
- Could be.
Horace said it was always a pain, the tree house.
You know, he was only doing it because God said to do it.
And every marriage that happened
and then ended in divorce.
So he was sort of happy to be rid of it.
- What is the story of the play?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, there's time for fact number three.
And that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is, Spain is spinning.
(laughing)
- How?
- How indeed.
Well, it is all down to plate tectonics,
continental drift and a lot of other boring stuff
you learned at school.
But this is something that's been found out
by a researcher at the University of the Bass Country
called Asia Mandarieta.
And basically, they just put a load of GPS stations
all over the country and looked at all the data
that came out of it.
And when Asia looked at all the data,
he found that the European and Asian plates,
so the continents are on these plates,
they're moving closer to each other all the time.
But while they're doing it,
the Spanish part of it is very slightly rotating.
- Is there going to be a time
where Spain is upside down?
Is what we all want to do?
- Good question.
No, it's not spinning in that way.
It's not spinning so that the bottom of Spain
will be on the top soon.
It's more spinning so that Malaga will be in the north.
- Oh, that's what I mean.
So the bottom will be spinning like a vinyl roundabout.
- Like a roundabout, yeah, yeah.
So what I'm saying is it will go round.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- So it's spinning around the Western Pyrenees, isn't it?
So from the northern part, that's the pivot.
And then Malaga's slowly going clockwise.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- Sorry, I thought you meant that the...
- I will want to go round the Pyrenees.
- There's not much sun today, isn't it?
- How fast is it spinning?
- Very slowly down.
- Okay, so my holidays are still in the same place.
- We're talking geological-type scales here
and even with your planning of holidays,
I think it's not going to affect it too much.
- This is the thing I don't understand
about continental drift, black tectonics.
- Yeah.
- Because I know that India,
the reason we have Himalayas, the Himalayas,
is that India walloped into Tibet, basically, right?
Like it just slowly, slowly, slowly moved
and then it crunched and then it crunched
the land upwards.
- If I was in South Tibet, would I look at India approaching
and even at the two ends of my life?
Well, I think it's a bit closer.
- Not really.
- I better haul my feet out of the sea.
You know, that kind of thing.
- The difference is so small
that you would never really know.
It's said, but unless there's an earthquake,
and that's why this work that this guy's doing
and why other geologists is so important.
'Cause when you're working out how all these plates are moving,
it means you can better predict things like earthquakes
and volcanoes and other events like that.
- Exactly.
- Yes, wild.
I remember Richard Turner, who has been a guest
on "No Such Thing" as a fish years ago.
Remember him telling me that he half remembers
when he was a very young kid at schools,
it not being an accepted idea,
the idea of continental drifts,
the idea of tectonic plates,
and that's how the planet works.
- So Rich, we should say, is as old as Methuselac.
(laughing)
No, he isn't that old.
In actual fact, it's true.
Like, I would say until the '60s,
it wasn't completely agreed.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it was this guy who initially came up
with the idea in the early 1900s called Alfred Vegner,
and he basically was just looking initially at a map
and going, "Oh, it's like a jigsaw.
"This bit looks like that fits in there."
- Yeah.
- This bit looks like that fits in there.
And he was very lucky.
He was able to go to both the coasts of two bits
where he believed this might be the case
and he found similar geology there, similar rocks,
and he thought, "Hang on a second, this is making more sense."
So he and others pushed forward this idea,
but he died in 1930, and it wasn't accepted really
until the '60s as James says.
- There are a couple of seminal papers in the '60s
that led to it being properly accepted.
So one was Dan McKenzie's co-authorship
of the North Pacific, an example of tectonic sonosphere.
Okay, so that was in I think '66 or '67.
I had a little look, 'cause I found a comparison point,
widespread acceptance of the theory of plate tectonics
is younger than Barack Obama.
- Okay.
- So I thought I'd look for other people
who are older than widespread existence
of the theory of plate tectonics.
- So does that, are you saying that it started in 1966?
- Give or take.
I think it was properly formalized and finalized, though.
- I think Alan Davis was born in 1966.
- Why, great point.
He's not on my list.
Robert Downey, Jr., older than plate tectonics
being widely accepted.
- Oh yeah.
- Chris Rock.
- Very good.
- Thank you.
- He's the only, he's the only appropriate one.
- Right.
(laughing)
- Slash.
- Kind of like the breaking up of the ground
after an earthquake.
- You're doing really well, Brad Pitt.
- Yeah.
- It's a bit.
- Nicholas Cage.
Sandra Bullock.
- Some of these are less good.
- Keanu Reeves.
Now we're going completely on that.
- Liz Hurley.
- And again, I was not looking for appropriate people.
I was just surprised that Liz Hurley
is older than plate tectonics.
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- So what we're doing here is we're listing people
who are at 60, but don't look at it.
- Yeah.
- That's why he went through a lot of Hollywood names,
I suppose.
- Yeah, like Keanu Reeves and Liz Hurley
both look terrific, you know,
but they're older than plate tectonics.
- They're not older than plate tectonics, of course.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Which has been going since the earth again.
- Yeah.
- You're right.
- There are dozens moving as well.
- Yeah.
- And spending a little bit.
We are like over hundreds of million years,
we are going to move north east,
but we are going to ride along with Europe.
We're kind of forever tethered to Europe,
which feels like there's some metaphor there.
(laughing)
- Not really sure what it is.
But yeah, we're basically,
and then the Mediterranean Sea is going to close,
and there'll be a huge mountain belt,
like the Himalayas, which is where the Mediterranean
now is, so like Ibiza is just going to become
like a huge mountain.
- Oh.
- But we're going to move further north east,
so it's going to get colder.
- Oh.
- And then eventually it all comes back,
and we're all one big gondwana land again.
- Really, that's what I'm sorry to see, I do.
- They name the next big sea gondwana.
- They have, but I can't remember what it is.
You know gondwana land, which is one of these.
Do you know who named that?
- Is it a friend of the podcast?
- No, it's someone you've never heard of.
- Oh, let me guess.
(laughing)
- Is it a Tennessee minister?
Cool.
- But it's someone who shares a name
with someone you absolutely have heard of.
- These are great clues.
(laughing)
- By the way, if you haven't joined our online quiz,
let's talk about this.
James is around as a thriller.
- Is this someone like Chris Rock?
- No, it's someone very unlike Chris Rock.
It's Dr. Seuss.
- Oh, okay.
- Dr. Edward Seuss, who was an Austrian geologist.
And he kind of is known as the father of continental drift.
And he was the one who kind of noticed
that the fossils in Africa and South America
were kind of the same, especially if you look at ferns
or really, really old plants.
And so he came up with the idea
that we were once a big continent
and he called it gondwana land.
- That's so cool.
- But he thought that it wasn't that they came apart
and came together.
He thought that the water just filled in the gaps
and then disappeared again
and then filled in the gaps and disappeared again, right?
So he got it a little bit wrong, but.
- Well, there was so many theories that were going around.
There was one that was created by a man called Charles Habgood
who wrote a book in 1958.
So just before continental drift was accepted
called the Earth's Shifting Crust.
And that got a lot of exposure
because Albert Einstein wrote the forward to that book.
And this was the idea that the cataclysmic shift
that the polar ice caps that we get told about all the time
were the poles shift from north to south.
- Oh yeah.
- That's the reason that the earth is the way that it is now
because that spread all the countries out to where they are.
- And it was a shift of magnetism spreads out
the actual concepts.
- Yeah, exactly.
But it was a pseudoscience idea.
At the time though, it was being accepted as a real thing
to the point where Einstein thought it was a great idea.
And this guy, by the way, the reason he came up with this idea
is because he was trying to work out
how Atlantis could have disappeared in a day
in the night and there we go.
And he thought, okay, it would have needed a big moment
like the pole shifting.
- Well, I will say, in defense of this nutter that you found out
and Albert Einstein won.
- Albert Einstein won.
- It is important for things like the earth's magnetic field
and in fact, earth is the only planet
which has plate tectonics, and that's bizarre.
And it might be that it helped life survive
because what happens is the earth was a snowball
two and a half billion years ago.
I mean, really, really very long ago.
It wasn't before life, but it was, you know,
it was very inhospitable.
But plate tectonics create a lot of volcanoes.
That throws up a lot of carbon dioxide,
which then rainfall scrubs out of the atmosphere.
- I see.
- And it helps make the earth temperature stable enough
for life.
So there's a theory that plate tectonics are actually one
of the things that makes earth this fantastic environment.
- I think on Venus, like, it's so hot
when the crust sort of moves, the inside just comes up
and then just fills in the gaps.
- Yeah.
- So there's no drift.
It just kind of just fills in the gaps immediately.
- It's a constant solid mass.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, there's one of the moons of Jupiter is I/O,
which is just volcanoes, volcanoes, volcanoes,
all the time.
And the whole plate is just covered in lava so constantly
that it's very hard to get anything, you know, built.
- But I think in that, is it not that Disney cartoon
where they go to try and mine that moon?
And they say, I/O, I/O.
(laughing)
Didn't see it coming.
- Oh, you must have seen that one coming.
- No, no, I walked right into it.
I saw something coming.
- I didn't, I didn't know where you were.
(laughing)
- I'll be honest, I didn't know where I was going
for a lot of that.
(laughing)
- I read the name of every continental plate
and every minor plate and only one of them is amusing.
- Going in.
- How many are there?
- Ah, if she doesn't.
Okay, I put a lot of time into reading that list.
- Is it the China plate?
That would be quite funny.
- Oh, that is good.
- Oh, yes.
- Oh, damn, I didn't check for the China plate.
- There was only half, it does not work.
(laughing)
- This one is a microplate of South America.
It's called the South Sandwich Plate.
- Ah, that looks good.
- And the Wikipedia says not to be confused
with a culinary sandwich plate.
Someone having a little joke there.
- Who's got a dedicated sandwich plate?
There's my question.
- I think, oh, all right, let's move on.
(laughing)
- Plate tectonics have been proposed as one way
of getting rid of nuclear waste.
- I read about this.
- Yeah, really weird.
- I just like shove it under the carpet.
- Basically, but sort of iconic trenches, like the Mariana.
They wanna put, they wanna put it down there
right to the bottom.
- That's one of my tuts had trenches.
(laughing)
And the idea is that over time,
the plate tectonics would sort of push it down.
They would cover it and push it down
into the mantle of the other.
- With a gun to your head, James.
Could you name another three trenches?
'Cause it's, I'm thinking it's the only one I've got.
- Yeah.
- I know there's a really deep one up in the,
in the Arctic, my camera was called.
- 'Cause the Mariana isn't the deepest.
- Yeah.
- No, it is the deepest, but it's not the closest
to the center of the earth.
- I see.
- Because the earth is like a blade spheroid.
So it's fatter in its middle, like a lot of us.
If you go down to the bottom of the Arctic Ocean,
the trench is there.
I close it to the center of the earth.
- I'm very impressed that you've named it.
You wanna know.
(laughing)
- Dan, you're saying this presumably doesn't work or?
- I don't think they've tried it.
- I don't like it.
- It got right.
- I think they didn't like it either in the end.
- Yeah. - It feels messy.
It was proposed by a scientist called James/Jim Bard.
And he patented the method of waste disposal.
So it's like using subduction zones.
Those are the kind of areas where it gets sucked
and pushed down.
And he wrote a really angry letter
to the nuclear waste management organization in Canada
after they'd rejected his proposal.
And in it, he lists why it's a bad idea.
So the fact that it might return to the surface
by a volcanic eruption.
- I feel like that's my main worry about it.
It's like you shove it under the carpet
and then one there, it just comes up.
- Also, it's really illegal to dump
nuclear waste in the sea in a lot of places.
- It takes the law, you know, we're bright.
(laughing)
- We're bright, we're corrupt, we could do what we love.
- And also, it would take so long
that the risk of leakage would be super high.
- Yeah, okay, okay, okay.
Let's keep on fire, I get it.
It just makes it like we normally do.
It's a good idea.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show
and that is Andy.
- My fact is, in the 1970s,
the American car industry complained about new rules
which said you could no longer include
sperm whale brain oil.
(laughing)
- Woop.
- God, look at the amount.
- This is crazy.
- I can imagine Clarkson having a guy like that
on one of those columns since you can no longer use.
Yeah, whale oil was a massive business
for a couple of centuries.
There is a separate thing,
I'm sure we'll talk about both kinds of oil.
There's a separate thing in sperm whale's heads,
the sperm whale brain oil.
Also known as spermacetti.
And until 1972, which is really quite recent,
lots of American car brands included
in their transmission sperm whale brain oil.
A bit of your car was once in the head of a sperm whale.
It's insane.
- Do you have a list of celebrities
who are older than non-sperm whale car?
- Everyone I've named before, everyone I've named before
and more besides, that's written down.
(laughing)
- I was literally, got my phone out to Google
those as you were speaking.
- Alan Carr.
- Find some people born in 1974.
- Okay, let's have a look.
- Okay, I'll just tell these guys why you haven't done.
- Okay, movie stars.
Born in the nicest one.
First thing that came up, as if I've searched this before.
- Oh, spooky.
- Mark Walberg, you and McGregor.
- You and McGregor.
- John Ham, Regina King, Tyler Gugito.
I don't know any of these people.
- Yeah.
- Try to do 17.
- Okay, we clan.
- Oh, okay.
- Okay, Indiana Jones.
- Right.
- Jada Pinkett Smith.
- Yep.
- Keep that well oil out of your mouth.
(laughing)
- Christina Applegate.
- You see what I'm saying?
- Johnny Knoxville.
- Oh.
- When Johnny Knoxville was a little baby,
they were still putting whale brain oil in cars.
- Yeah.
- I think that's insane, I think it's insane.
And I think this is a very good news story.
The human species, we decimated whales.
We have now changed the laws in all sorts of ways
and all sorts of brave campaigners
and clever lawyers and all this,
that the laws have been changed.
And now, with a very few minor disonorable exceptions,
Japan, Norway, anyway, whatever.
No one kills whales anymore.
And it's not for guy, Iceland.
- And Iceland.
No, but basically this, and it is a good oil.
As in, if you were looking at it purely
from an effective transmission point of view,
it was the best oil to use.
- Really.
- Well, the car industry complained a lot.
They wind massively saying, well,
you know what, your transmissions are gonna break down more.
And the terrible thing is, for the first couple of years,
they did.
I said, "Cart transmissions became a little bit worse
for a couple of years."
- I heard they were eight times more likely to break down.
- Yeah, they were.
- I'm not saying that I didn't know what a car transmission was.
- I know.
- Until this week.
It's the kind of thing that, if I take my car to the garage,
they all look, you're transmissions gone.
- Yeah.
When did you last shove a whale in this?
(laughing)
We're gonna have to, there's a shortage of whales as well.
We're trying to get, we're looking at our paperwork.
- But it's the system that transfers mechanical power
from the engine to the wheels.
- Yeah.
It's important under the car.
- It's pretty much all of the car.
- Yeah, that's it.
- I can't believe that car.
(laughing)
- I think potentially an electric car
wouldn't need sperm whale brain oil.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause it doesn't, I don't think it operates a car.
- It needs lubrication though.
- Everything needs lubrication.
- Well that's what I was gonna ask you Andy,
'cause you said there's a two types of oil
that we'd be getting from whales.
So there'd be a general oil
and then there's the specific spermaceti,
which is in there.
- So the front of their head, top half of their head.
So 18th and 19th century candles would often use whale oil.
Was that the spermaceti?
Or was that just the, that's normally just the stuff.
If you catch a lot of different whale species,
you can, you can render down their blubber.
I mean, you literally burn the blubber
and turn it into the oil.
The sperm whale stuff was very specifically good
because of all these properties
that it helps fight rust.
It operates at high temperatures.
So there's a reason why they use that in machinery.
- I read it also for lamps.
It was really good because it didn't smoke.
- What sperm whale?
- spermaceti.
- Okay, yeah, yeah.
- As a lubricant, it is, it maintains its viscosity
across really big range of temperatures.
- Right.
- And much like agar agar.
That's why it was so good as a jelly
because you can heat it up and it won't melt.
- Perfect.
- Sleep.
- Cool.
- Good, nice is, guys.
- Very nice.
- But no, it was, it was a really big,
I mean, whale oil was just used for so much stuff.
In 1935, 84% of all whale oil was used to make margarine.
Like a lot of your margarine would be whale.
- What is?
- That was in the '30s, right?
- Even in the '60s, you know?
- In a way, way, way, way.
- Oh yeah.
(laughing)
- I, people, Bond.
- I think Donald Trump is just in--
- Younger.
- 1934, am I looking for?
- Yeah.
- 1934.
- God, that's, and that's, I'm gonna say,
Alan Bennett was 1934, the author of "Me."
I'm afraid of Virginia Woolf.
- Bridget Bardot, Shirley McClain, Maggie Smith.
- Oh.
- I'll put the second of Belgium
could have had badgering with whale oil, I bet.
- No, they didn't stop using it.
They were just that. - I didn't know.
- That's how much was being used.
That proportion of it has been used.
- I'll say again.
- You see, you see.
It was a huge thing.
- I read it was used in planes as well.
I could go all the way up in the sky.
- Which bit of planes?
Like the transition?
- The end of the transmission, yeah.
- Yeah, the bits that needed to glide over each other
that really could-- - Okay.
- You know what?
It got even further than the sky.
- What?
- Space, the final frontier.
- Oh yeah.
- Yes, indeed.
NASA apparently lubed its moon landers.
(laughing)
- It's about whale oil.
- That feels like a euphemism as it does.
- It does.
- It's blue my moon lander.
- It's around in some kind of game show, isn't it?
- Yeah, but this is according to a book called
"Unfamiliar Fishes" by Sarah Val.
And she says that they used it until the ban on whaling
in 1986.
- Right, I read a lot of furious NASA geeks
who basically said that it's been said
that it's been used on the Hubble telescope,
which it hasn't.
They said that it was part of the looming process
for the lens and so on.
There's quite a few claims of it being used in space
that have been just spread incorrectly.
First World War, a big user of whale oil.
So British soldiers would rub their feet with whale oil
because it helped, it probably helped with things
like trench fur to something like that.
Yeah, yeah, it's a single battalion,
which is about a thousand men,
would get through 10 gallons a day of whale oil.
And it was used to make nitroglycerin.
It was used for soap.
You would smear your face with whale grease.
Basically, if we didn't have whale oil,
the first World War might not have happened.
So it's the whale fault ready.
- Why do they need to be so oily whales?
Do we know?
- Well, I think they use their oil for buoyancy, right?
But the spermaceti ones have oils in the melon,
which is in the front of their head,
and we don't know exactly what that's for,
but I think this idea that it might be used
to kind of get signals and co-location.
- Yeah, co-location.
I think that's the idea.
- They're incredible, they're incredible animals
and sperm whales, they're really fantastic.
- It would be a really nice thing
about hunting avoidance in sperm whales.
In 2001, there was some newly digitized logbooks
from whale hunters in the North Pacific.
And they found that over not that long a span of time,
the whales had all learnt to swim upwind of the boats
that were harpooning them, which were wind powered.
So the boats would go one way and the whales would go the other way.
And the strike rate for harpoonists
fell by 58%, which is so cruel.
- Oh, yes.
- In your face, harpoonists.
Eat it, Ishmael.
- That's hell.
(all laughing)
- Is that the first line of Moby Dick?
- No, no, no, no.
- Eat it, Ishmael.
- As it is, it might be Dick from the Welfare Collective, yeah.
(all laughing)
- So, Andy, we have established that you like crockery.
- Sure.
- Summer's quite.
- Yeah.
- You also like cutlery.
- Ooh.
- So, what do you think
you would do with a mincing knife?
(all laughing)
- Is it a knife which has a mincing tool on the end?
So, for mincing meat.
So, it's like got a grid of sharp metal on the end
and I just shove it into the meat and that minces it.
- Not quite.
And remember we're talking about whales.
- Okay.
I'm still thinking about a mince pie though.
But my mince pies contain whale meat.
- Do they?
- Yeah.
- Oh, is it for mincing up a whale?
- I'm gonna get pretty much as,
not minces in like mince just means chopping up smaller, right?
- Yeah.
- So, if you were to get the blubber
and you were to put it into the pot,
if the smaller it is, the more surface area,
it has the easier it is to melt down to turn into oil.
So, they would use a mincing knife for that.
And they had all sorts of specialised cutlery
on these whaling ships.
So, as well as a mincing knife,
they had a cutting spade.
They had a head spade.
They had a chopper.
They had a boarding knife.
Which you would grab onto your bit of whale
because you're doing all this stuff in the water, right?
You can't get the whale and put it onto your boat.
It's way too big.
- Oh, I thought your whale is on the side of the boat.
- Back in the day, you're cutting up your whale in the sea.
- Yeah, of course.
Like, whales are so enormous.
Like, you can't get a ship.
That's that big until very, very recently.
- Yeah.
- So yeah, you would have your body knife
where you would kind of skewer a bit of meat
and throw it onto the deck so that they can put it
onto the pot skimmer, which you would...
- Just an endless cutlery draw on these ships.
(laughing)
- You know what?
This is the first time I've been there.
I've listened to a load of cutlery on this show
and you've not been excited.
- I know.
I know.
Do you ever have a dinner party
where you've provided too many guests
that you run out of your main cutlery?
You have to improvise.
Give them a minute.
You won't notice, that's fine.
- Excuse me.
Is this grapefruit fork or is it a cutting spade?
(laughing)
- That's what I mean about it being a good news story.
Like a century ago this was just completely powerful
the course and loads and loads of people
just worked with this kind of killing whales
and chopping them up.
Have you heard of Wacan?
- No, I haven't.
- Have you ever had a punt?
- Is it a Wake bacon?
- Is it a Woke bacon?
- It's a Woke bacon.
(laughing)
- Yeah, that sounds woken.
Thank you.
(laughing)
Wacan was a corned beef substitute in the 1940s,
which was made of whales.
- Oh.
- That's during the war they tried to get
the British to eat whales, didn't they?
And everyone thinks it's utterly disgusting whales.
- Well, I think it was after the war, weirdly.
'Cause most of the, or at not most,
but a lot of the food shortage was the second half of the 40s.
- Sorry.
- When the war was even over
and they sent whalers off to the Antarctic
'cause there were genuine, like, real food shortage
to Britain. - Yeah, yeah.
- And so they said, do you want to try Wacan?
The 1951 report, a new, unwashed meat.
Unrashed is great.
You can buy as much of this as you like.
Wacan reached British shops last week.
It is corned whale meat with its fishy flavor removed.
And apparently it had not been removed sufficiently
to make it not taste like whale, and it was not popular.
- Well meat is just not tasty.
If you live in the far north and you don't have any other option,
then maybe you might eat it.
But otherwise, like, the whalers, they wouldn't eat it.
They wouldn't catch a whale.
And they'd have shit tons of this meat.
Like, whales are big.
You could feed your sailors for months and months and months.
But they'd rather not eat it
and they'd just rather eat their biscuits and stuff.
- I'll have the green salad.
Is that all right?
That's the thing about you.
- Would you guys try it?
- Are you going to be brought some in?
- If I had, would you?
- When I was in Iceland, I did consider having it,
but I decided against it at the last minute
and ordered the puffin instead.
- Oh wow.
- Was it a puffingance?
- Oh that's it.
- Puffin was not good.
- No, it didn't.
- He was so noble and talented, that's a joke.
It's not a joke.
- It's not a joke, no?
- Ah, yeah.
- It was quite a long time ago this.
- Yeah, it was a nice one.
- But yeah, like puffin is not nice.
It's still fishy.
And it's quite oily.
- Right.
- But there's a brewery in Iceland
that still brews with whale meat.
I think it's like a Fadi product, but in 2025,
they released a beer that was brewed
with whale testicles.
- Okay.
- I would try that for sure.
- Yeah, nice.
Well, they smoked them beforehand with sheep dung.
- Dung, yeah.
- So that was used in the brewing cycle
and it was, I mean, it was pasteurised out,
but apparently it's got yellow.
This funky, smoky flavour released
for a festive season.
- I'm sorry.
I think there's a horseshoe theory of foods,
which is where extreme deprivation would mean
you had to eat whale knackers with sheep's shit.
And then extreme fancy food in us means
you're eating exactly the same thing.
- I think the people in Iceland
are the only people who have seen the advert
for Karlsberg, probably the best beer in the world
have gone, "Yeah, maybe it is."
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this show,
we can all be found online.
I'm on @Streiberland on Instagram, James.
- My Instagram is no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy.
- And you're on to him.
- And Manu, you're online.
- Yeah, can I plug our lunchbox envy podcast socials?
- Yeah, good.
- Because I am non-existent.
- Oh.
- So yeah, you can find lunchbox envy pod at
@lunchboxenvpod.
We are on YouTube, Facebook, Instagram and TikTok.
- Very nice.
And that is your pod that you co-host.
- Yes.
- It is.
- It's not a pod of whales.
- No, it's not a pod of whales.
It is a fully fledged pod cast.
Also yeah, we look at weird,
weird and wonderful foods.
And we have a fantastic chef and food writer
called Rosie McKean, who's on as well.
And then myself and Jack Chambers,
who's another QI off.
- Yeah, very cool.
And it's wherever you get your podcasts.
Also, if you would like to write to any of us
about the things that have been said
and you want to have them come on our show,
drop us a line, which is the sort of feedback show
that we do.
Just send them to podcast@QI.com.
Andy goes through all the emails.
He cherry picks the best and we discuss them.
We love finding out about all the experiences
that you've had as a result of listening
to something we've spoken about.
Anything you wanna tell us send us there
or perhaps you have a great fact.
If you've got a fact that you want us to read out
on one of our shows,
we do an audience fact-based show called Little Fish
goes out every Monday, send us your fact there
again, podcast@QI.com.
And hopefully we'll read one of them out on the shows.
Otherwise, just come back here next week.
We're gonna have another episode.
Thank you as ever to our Fish Busters team.
That's Lee and Lee, Ethan Ruperalia,
as well as the other Fish Busters out there.
And we'll be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]