Hey, clubfish members, welcome to your bonus bit of content.
We've got a compilation for you today.
You're going to hear not only the four regular fishers,
but you're also going to get the brilliant comedian Olga Koch.
And you're also going to hear the voice and facts of Lee-ing Lee,
one of the QI elves who works on no such thing as a fish and the TV show QI.
So here we go.
Here's all the stuff that we couldn't cram into the main episodes on with the show.
Well, it's Biggest Meatball.
OK. I have a name.
Can I just jump in there, Andy?
Because I saw this as well.
Can I just ask the two people who haven't seen this?
Do you think it's bigger or smaller than a Blue Whales testicle?
What? The world's biggest meatball?
Yeah. Bigger?
Smaller.
Andy, how big is the biggest meatball?
It's £1,700, which in new money is...
I don't know, actually.
What about in whale testicle?
Well, over to my colleague.
Only £150 maximum, so you're right, Olga.
So it is bigger?
Much bigger, yeah.
Bigger than a whale's testicle.
Gosh.
So the criteria for the Guinness World Record meatball, not testicle,
meatball is it was on a South Carolina, it was an Italian-American club,
and they said, we know meatballs, we can do this.
And they had a special cast iron cooking pod for it.
I think they might have had to custom make the pod.
Yeah, how do you cook that through?
It's so thick.
Well, that's exactly the criteria.
It had to be the biggest, obviously, by weight.
It had to not fall apart when removed from the pod.
Oh, my God, that is tough, actually.
And it had to be edible.
But it, disappointingly, I did look into it a bit more.
It did not all have to be eaten,
as in the judge just peeled off a strip and he ate that.
Like I said, it's edible.
I would think you would have to, like, Bruce Bogtrotter style,
sit it down in front of somebody who has then got to finish it.
Yeah.
How big is it if you were like...
I think it's about the size of a very large pig.
Oh, that's not that big.
Are we talking this table?
Not quite this table, but it's very big.
And they put up the recipe on the website,
which is ingredients that serves 4,500 people.
[LAUGHTER]
Do you guys know what the international language of space is?
Ooh, I should think English.
Is there an answer to this?
Esperanto?
It's kind of an answer.
Martian.
It's definitely not the right answer.
It's a sign language.
No, it's the language of love.
Yes, how can we feel?
It must be English.
It must be English or Russian,
because that's what all the astronauts are.
Yeah, you're so close to it.
Oh, both.
Runglish.
Runglish is a mixture of both Russian and English.
So the majority of the astronauts that go into space
are either Russian-speaking or English-speaking.
There are multiple nationalities,
but you are not allowed to go up as an American astronaut
unless you learn Russian fluently.
That's true.
Why? Is that true?
Helen Sharman spoke Russian.
Yeah, Tim Peake had to learn Russian.
What if you're-- well, that's because if you're going
to the International Space Station, right,
surely there must have been some US-only mission.
Buzz Aldrin doesn't know Russian, does he?
No, so this is--
Sorry, this is current.
Just terrifying.
Yeah, because I don't think Leica spoke Russian.
Yeah.
But the flip side is that the Russian cosmonauts
need to speak English fluently as well.
So what ends up happening is that in space,
you have a new language, Runglish,
whereby shortcuts are used between both the languages.
So you'll start a sentence in Russian,
but maybe end it in English, because you're just
using key words to--
so that's how they speak in space, largely to each other
if they're talking to someone who's--
But that's like how I try and get by in a shop
if I'm in a foreign country.
And I know--
I know, can I have, or I know, what is the cost of?
And then I'll tail off, and I'll say that sausage or whatever.
Yeah, yeah.
You just say it with the accent, right?
Yeah.
So in German, how might you buy a sausage?
Done.
If you feel this, that's--
Sausage.
--a cherry-versed bit there.
Yeah, yeah, but--
That's German.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I was--
I was too good at German, I'm afraid.
I don't know, I can't even pronounce.
How would you say if there's a sausage on the table?
I would be stuffed.
I was like, yeah.
That's the first is alf, whatever, tish, as we know.
Yeah, yeah.
Done.
Just while we're on space, I've got a Russian linguistic
moment that was interesting that happened.
In the early days when they were sending up
the first cosmonauts into space,
and they were orbiting for like two days or whatever,
and then they'd come back down.
So there was a series of missions called Vostok.
And Vostok 4 had a cosmonaut called Popovich.
And Popovich was meant to be up there for four days,
but he ended up coming down early.
And the reason-- there's a lot of--
because there's always hidden stuff about this,
but one of the acknowledged possible reasons
that he came back down is while he was up there,
he was talking to comms, and he was looking down at the Earth,
and he saw a thunderstorm.
And he went, oh, there's a thunderstorm.
He completely forgot that there was a code word
that they had created, which is that if he was getting
space sickness, and this was a new thing
that they didn't understand, you would say thunderstorm.
Give him a word of something he'll never say.
Exactly.
So he says thunderstorm.
The mission ends a couple of days early.
There was a lot of stuff in there,
like the amount of oxygen and stuff like that.
Something went slightly wrong, and they were a bit worried
that maybe they should bring him back in case
it broke all together.
But largely they think it's because they put him on edge
when he said, I can see a thunderstorm.
They went, he's done the code.
So they brought him down.
Yeah.
Oh my god.
Yeah, cool guy.
What a wally.
That is funny.
Yeah.
That is a fun fact.
And he was meant to be, he was as contender to be Gagarian.
He was meant to be the first person in space.
So he really wanted to get to space.
He had four days.
He was going to be the longest anyone had done it.
And then, yeah.
Wow.
Came back early.
Gosh.
This is the worst competitive eating
I've ever seen on half of a sandwich
is taking you 45 minutes.
Surely there's a slow eating competition as well.
That would be lovely.
Because you need to continuously be eating though, right?
That's true.
You can anecdote at the same time.
I always finish my meals last, because I'm chatting away.
You're an only child, Andy.
Yeah.
I think there's a thing about--
How long have we known each other?
Yeah, no, I didn't know that you were an only child.
But I think there's a thing with only children
is they tend to eat slower.
Because if you're in a big family,
you just have to get at the food before going to the house.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Only children have a certain--
and I mean this is a compliment--
young Sheldon quality to say.
Sort of precociousness.
You're not the first and you won't be the last.
I'm so sorry.
I don't know you at all.
Was it received as a compliment?
This is going to be the first walk out on such a busy fish,
but it's not me who's walking.
Interestingly, the Eagles were knocked off
from the biggest selling album in America
by Michael Jackson's Thriller when he passed away,
that kind of surge.
And then they took it back over in 2018.
So it's gone back to the top.
Because people just keep buying it.
That is blowing my mind.
It's nuts, isn't it?
I didn't think they were that big.
Because not one of them is the Beatles?
That's crazy.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, I read a really fun thing about Queen the other day,
which is when they got massive internationally.
You know that thing that people often do
where they just write Santa, North Pole,
and it gets sent and it might find its way there.
A lot of people just put Queen, England, to send it to them,
but all their mail went to Buckingham Palace.
That was so funny.
The Queen was just constantly getting messages
to Freddie Mercury from someone in Germany.
That's very funny.
I read that they found the first scribbles
of Bohemian Rhapsody, and it was called Mongolian Rhapsody.
Really?
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, they're both regions?
Yeah, and they both scan.
They both scan.
But Bohemian just feels like a better nationality or--
It's because Bohemian has a different meaning, doesn't it?
Yeah, I mean nothing against Mongolians.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, no, no, no.
But Bohemian, if you're sort of Lucian,
living the urban nightlife lifestyle, yeah.
What year are you from?
I don't know.
[LAUGHTER]
They are home to weirdos like that giant bacterium
and other freaks of nature, literally.
As something else, I think we've mentioned once
is the mangrove rifulus, which is the only fish that
lives completely on mangrove.
So you get fish that live sometimes in mangroves.
They're very useful places for little fish to hide.
It's like base.
They hide from big fish, because big fish can't survive there.
You swim among the roots, and they're
small little niches to--
Exactly, it's a really good hide-and-seek game.
But the mangrove rifulus is the only one
that can live there all the time.
And it can survive for 66 days out of water,
because the water often recedes in mangrove forests, low tide.
And so they can live--
I think we've mentioned before, they live in trees sometimes.
[LAUGHTER]
Film, bitch.
Sorry?
[LAUGHTER]
Film, bitch.
Oh, bitch.
Sorry, sorry.
It came out as bitch, didn't it?
I heard film, bitch.
Film, bitch.
This is why my pitch presentations are Hollywood.
Of course, I've got to be wrong.
Pitch for a film, fish out of water, right?
And it's about a little mangrove rifulus,
which is on day 63 out of 66.
OK.
He's got to get back into the--
The thing is, though, the term fish out of water
refers to someone who's in a position they're not usually
in, but this guy is actually adapted to that situation
of living out of the water.
Yeah, it's a positive film, a positive message,
is that it's fine to be a fish out of water.
Well, that's a spoiler alert, isn't it?
Is it fine, or does it make it in time?
God, you guys are really intense as a panel for--
it's good to stress test the idea, though.
Thank you, before we take it to Tinseltown.
I think that's a good--
I think it's ready now.
I don't think I heard the plot, as well.
Bitch.
OK.
Everyone's a critic at this point, right?
Oh, it doesn't have a plot.
Oh, that's a spoiler.
Oh, there's nothing happening in this film.
I'm trying here to secure our next phase of this podcast
where we move mostly into scripts.
Can I quickly tell you about Phil Swern?
Yes.
Phil Swern, he devised Popmaster on Radio 2,
but he was also the only person to own every single top 40
record in the UK Singles Chart from its origins in 1952
until the mid '90s.
He bought every single one.
He reckoned he had between 6 and 1/2 to 7 million records.
Oh, my goodness.
Wow.
They're all vinyl, yeah.
Obviously, we don't do so many vinyls anymore, so he stopped.
He got to a stage where he knew how much
he had in his collection and which ones he needed.
And so he would go to a record fair,
and as soon as anyone saw him, they just double the price
of anything that they had, because they knew that he
would pay the money for it.
Yeah.
There was a place called Beano's in Croydon,
which unfortunately is closed now,
but it was the largest record store in Europe.
And they said, here's the key to the stock room.
Just go in.
Anything that you want, just anything you can find,
you can have it.
And the last record he needed for his collection
was Diana Decker's Poppa Peccalino, which is the only one
he didn't have.
And he found it in a car book fair,
and he said to the guy, how much do you want for this?
And the guy said, 90p.
And he said, I'll give you 50p for it.
What he didn't know is that he would have paid anything.
Can I just really--
I know we have to move on, but can I quickly
say something that Evian has given us?
The writing style of Ernest Hemingway.
It's thanks to Evian.
So Hemingway was living in Europe,
and he wanted to show his works to an editor.
He might be able to write, publish a new book.
And so he asked his wife, Hadley, who
was living in Paris at the time, where his base was,
to bring his notes up so that he could show them to an editor.
Hadley decided to pick up not just one or two bits,
but literally everything.
So she picked up all of his notes,
all of his copies of his notes, basically all of his writings,
everything that Hemingway ever produced.
She picked it all up and put it in one bag.
She went to the Garde Leon to go and see Hemingway.
She realized it was a long trip, so went
to get a bottle of Evian from a shop.
When she came back, the bag was gone,
including all of Hemingway's stuff.
She went to see Hemingway, was crying the whole way
because she couldn't believe what has happened.
She gets to Hemingway.
He says, oh, don't worry, I've got copies.
She's like, I got bad news about the copies.
They're also in the bag.
So what happened was Hemingway now doesn't have any
of the work that he's been working on for years,
but still thinks it's time for him to become a writer.
So he decides to change his writing style
and start writing really short sentences.
- So was he really for it?
- He was just trying to rewrite everything but far.
- Yeah.
- There's no time for these adjectives.
- It's not amazing.
- That's incredible.
- No way.
- Apparently that's true.
- Have you heard of a pot wallopper borough?
- This is a--
- No.
- Pot wallopper.
Can we guess?
- No.
- Pot walloping is like, you would hit a pot,
make a lot of noise, and sometimes it would be like,
if someone wanted to be punished,
but you didn't want to sell them to the prison,
you might make this noise to kind of, like--
- Was that called rough music?
- Sort of social punishment.
- Make the noise to what?
- Kind of embarrass them.
- Yeah, turn it upside someone's house
if they've not paid their tax or if they've mistreated
a dog or whatever, I don't know.
- And if it's due to that?
- Nope.
(laughing)
- So in the 18th century, right,
they didn't have the secret ballot yet.
There were no curtains in the polling booths.
You had to call out your vote.
- It was seen as anti-English, wasn't it?
- Yeah, and it was written down
and lists were actually published
of how everyone had voted, so it was a big,
it was a sort of public thing.
- It's like you weren't supposed
to be embarrassed by your vote, right?
- No, exactly, whereas as we know,
often you should.
(laughing)
I don't mean that.
So there was a place in,
so for example, there were these pot wallopper boroughs,
right, where the only people who could vote
were people who could boil or wallop a pot
on a hearth in their house.
- So they owned the house.
- You owned a house which features a hearth
which you could boil a pot on.
'Cause some houses were completely tumbled down
and they were rubbish.
People lived in a hay barn or something.
That's not, you can't wallop a pot on the hearth in there.
- Right.
- You would have had to have had some convoluted logic
to guess that.
(laughing)
- Pretty obvious, frankly.
So you have to qualify for these quite,
the franchise was limited,
not just to people who owned property,
but you had to be a housekeeper.
You had to be not in receipt of arms.
You had to live in which is like local charity.
So alms, sorry, alms.
- Alms, alms.
- Also, obviously you had to be an adult man.
And you could be challenged when you went to vote, right?
So when you went to vote.
- Wallop this pan.
(laughing)
- People can put up their hand and say,
"I haven't seen him walloping a pot for years or whatever."
Or you know, "I saw him taking some alms."
And so, and this is the amazing thing.
When people went door to door canvassing for votes,
they were not only trying to persuade you
to vote in their direction,
they were also gathering data like,
"Doesn't look like he's got a pot or whatever."
So they would then use that data against you
on voting day.
- But if you were campaigning
and you were wanting more people to vote for you,
would there be kind of slightly unscrupulous politicians
who would give people hearths?
- Yeah, hot pots.
- Hot pots.
- Yeah, teach you how to wallop.
- Yeah, teach your man to wallop.
And you'll vote for you in parliament.
- "Age of Sale" stuff is so cool.
Like, I just, I really, really like all of it.
So here's a nice one about the color scheme
of "Age of Sale" ships.
This is great, right?
- Okay.
- So the Navy tried repeatedly to get captains
to paint their ships the Navy colors.
And captains had quite a little latitude
and they kept on just ignoring it
and painting them whatever they wanted.
- What?
Are the Navy colors Navy?
- Navy blue?
- No, sorry.
There was a Royal Navy color scheme
which was adopted more after Nelson adopted it
'cause obviously it was very popular.
And it's called the Nelson Checker.
And it's bands of, the ship looks like a wasp basically.
It's bands of yellow and black.
- What, like no such thing as a fish?
- It's exactly like that.
- Okay.
- This whole podcast is a nod to that.
I thought we all knew that, right, okay.
So basically, like horizontal stripes
of black and yellow, right?
But the ships have gun decks, don't they?
So the gun holes, the gun ports are black
and they are all along the yellow band, right?
- Nice.
- So if you're sailing along
and you are ready for battle
or you're about to attack someone,
the ship, it looks like a chessboard
because you've got a black band
and then yellow but studded with black.
- Okay.
- Whereas if the gun ports are closed
and you're not ready for action,
you've got uniform bands of black and yellow.
So that's really handy.
If you're sailing into a harbor
and you want to show that you're friendly
or you're not a threat.
- I see.
- The color scheme is useful to signal your intention.
- Can I ask, also, would different countries
have different colors like football kits
so you would know who was on your team?
- Yes.
- Would they?
- Yeah, definitely.
And I think, I don't know what,
I don't know whether you had,
you know, you kind of had home and away.
(laughing)
Always away.
- It's away for everyone.
(laughing)
- Wait, so you were saying that they have,
then Royal Navy had the color scheme
but the captains ignored them.
- Yeah.
- So what did they do instead?
- Throughout the 18th century,
they just disguised themselves as the French
to make it a bit harder and add a little bit of free song.
- Yeah, that was bad form, wasn't it?
That's pirate stuff.
I don't know.
- I think it was.
And friendly fire was a problem with ships in this period.
Well, yeah, 'cause you'd fire a cannon
and you would quite often have it land
on the ship in front of you,
which was one of your allies,
rather than the ship a bit further away,
which was one of your enemies.
And this is where this revolutionary technique came about,
which I didn't know about.
- So can I just ask,
previously would you have your entire fleet like a conga
where you would have one and everyone would be behind you?
- Well, that's so interesting you say that.
That was what you did.
This was the huge turning point that came in the age of sail,
which is kind of what made,
partly made Britannia rule the waves,
which is that ships used to all go in a line,
like all facing each other.
And you'd be sort of behind your mate
and you'd be all in a cluster
and the friendly fire would be a problem.
So then it's a week.
- No, no, no, no.
You would be strung out in a big long line,
all sideways facing on towards each other.
I mean, friendly fire was a massive problem
when ships got close to each other
'cause you couldn't see anything.
- Yes, I think it was just, it could end up more messy.
Whereas what then they decided to do
is the line ahead formation,
which is literally like you're in a queue
and the ships go past the enemy one by one
and fire cannons at them.
So if you're in...
- Like when you have a football match
and each of the teams walks past each other and shakes hands.
- Exactly like that.
You know, I was thinking it was like the queen shaking hands,
but yes, like footballers or the queen, same kind of deal.
- But it only works if one of the sides does it.
This is the thing.
- Yeah, once everyone gets cracked.
- This side stops and then like divides
into two attacking formations
and goes through the enemy line.
- For the listener, Andy is drawing up a...
- Sorry.
- Very detailed diagrams.
- I've got an over-enthusiastic.
- Oh, no, no, we don't need the salt.
Oh, no, he's pushing them around with a long stick.
Oh my God.
No, the black boat, no, put the black boat away, Andy.
- I'm sorry.
I just love this stuff so much.
- Stop twirling your moustache.
(all laughing)
- That's great.
- Can I give you some names of British ships?
- Yeah, stand me to move on.
- HMS Abercrombie, HMS Affleck, HMS Amazon, HMS Broke,
HMS Desperate, HMS Flirt, HMS Kale, HMS Keith,
HMS Kwan, HMS Spanker, HMS Terrible, and HMS Trump.
- Lot's of one pick there.
- Brilliant.
- So of those, one of them I deliberately mispronounced
for comic effect.
Can you guess which one it is?
Abercrombie, Affleck, HMS Broke, HMS Desperate, HMS Flirt,
HMS Kale, HMS Keith, HMS Kwan, HMS Spanker, HMS Terrible,
and HMS Trump.
- It's not Spanker.
I've got a shi-
I've got a nautical hat with Spanker
on written on the hat, which was a prop from that series.
- I've got a photo of you in said hat,
which I think actually comes up whenever you ring me,
a picture of you with Spanker written on your head.
- That's brilliant.
- I've got Spanker, Flirt,
and then there was another ship called Titan Uranus.
'Cause that was a real ship,
but it was commercial, not naval.
- That's right.
- It was not Royal Navy, so there was no...
- Keith?
- No, it's HMS Broke.
- Baroque?
- It's actually Baroque,
because it was named after a guy called Sir Philip Baroque,
but it's spelled Baroque.
- Oh, okay.
- Yeah, anyway, that's something we'll cut.
- Must have been funny when the ship came in for repairs.
- If it ain't Baroque, it affects it anyway, hey.
I've got favorite mugs.
- Do you?
- Yeah, oh God, yeah.
- Oh yeah.
- There are certain mugs,
which if I see them in the cupboard,
I think, oh yeah, I'll have that one.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And then the bad ones I'll give to my wife.
(all laughing)
- What constitutes a bad mug in your eyes?
- I just have certain ones where I like the way the handle
sits on the fingers, that kind of thing.
- Do you like a thin rim or a thick rim?
- Oh, come on, let's not go into Andy's personal life.
♪ Sun in the day ♪
- I mean, after 10 years, I'm not,
I'm actually not gonna answer that question.
No, I don't mind.
- Do you know what I mean?
Like you get those tall cups or even like a bone china cup
which's got a very thin rim,
or you get your standard mug which's got a thicker rim.
I actually prefer a thicker rim.
- I don't mind a fine bone, but I will have a,
oh, no, I prefer a slightly thicker mug, you know?
- Yeah.
- You were saying, James, that this guy couldn't be removed
from parliament for being of not sound mind,
and they did introduce a law called the lunacy brackets
vacating of seats acts in 1886 to allow MPs to be removed,
and you got inspected,
and then six months later, you got inspected again,
and if you'd managed to stay of unsound mind
for six months, then you got removed.
So that could happen, but I didn't realize that.
Who can you name who's resigned from parliament?
- Boris Johnson.
- Incorrect.
- Anna, is this the thing about
you can't resign from parliament?
- Yeah.
- Oh, I see.
Is that the trick?
- Is that you?
- This is the trick.
- Are you tricking us all?
- 'Cause I didn't--
- So Nadine has just left the Chilton Hundreds, was it, or?
- The Chilton Hundreds, yes.
- This has international lists of the Klaxon all over it.
- I think exactly.
I think the international listeners,
I just think it's the kind of thing
that Americans love about England, or hate.
- Settle in, international listeners.
The international listeners switched off a long time ago,
actually, I don't know where or when.
- Go on.
- I think this might be the kind of
tragically British thing that international listeners love,
so listen up.
You cannot resign from parliament.
No one's ever done it, because in 1624,
it was made illegal for an MP to quit.
But you also are not allowed to be an MP
while you're also holding an office
for profit under the crown.
So there's basically a fake job,
which is being crown steward and bailiff
of the Chilton Hundreds, and you have to take that job.
It must be one of the most taken, like,
the single posts that's had the most occupants in history.
- There's another one, isn't there?
- If you have to have two MPs resigning
close to each other.
- There's a backup.
- So there's the Chilton Hundreds, and then there's--
- Chilton Two-Hundreds?
(laughing)
- I can't remember what the other one's called.
- I can't remember what the other one is.
- It's bailiff of the Manor of North Stead,
or something like that.
- Wait, so this job doesn't actually exist.
- No, but you have to accept it.
- Right.
- But Tony Blair has been it
after he stepped down as an MP.
- Right, the Dean Doris has been it.
- And you are it until the next person resigns,
and then they're in.
- And then they become the best.
- Yeah.
- It's very, I like that.
- It's great.
It's strong stuff.
- Do they still get paid when you're,
is this job, well, it's a job.
You must get something.
Peppercorn maybe.
- It's interesting.
I wonder if they do send you a fiver or something.
Okay, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
We will be back again next week.
If you wanna get in, we'll back, yep.
Hello.
- Hello.
(laughing)
It is harder than it looks.
- Hello.
- Well, that was a great rehearsal, guys.
(laughing)
- Are you ready to kick off?
Can we start with all this?
(laughing)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our outtakes.
All some hosting from Anna at the end there.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that were said
during the course of this compilation,
you could email us on podcast@ky.com.
And Andy could bring some of those comments
to the Drop Us a Line,
which we should have in a couple of weeks
back here as part of Club Fish.
Or you can find us on our various social media accounts.
And do remember, by the way,
to go and see Olga Cock live if you can.
She's on tour at the moment throughout the UK
with her show Prawn Cocktail.
And then she's going to Australia
and she's gonna be doing some of the major cities there.
So go to Rock'n'Rolga, which is her website.
It's got all the details of the upcoming gigs.
And yeah, go and see it.
She's brilliant live.
Anyway, that's it for us.
We're gonna be back again with more Club Fish stuff
in a couple of weeks.
So we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)