No one is coming to you from 2020 Audio.
My name is Dan Schreiber and I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray, James Harkin
and Annotch is Innski and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our
4th favorite facts from the last 7 days and in no particular order here we go.
Sorry Dan, can I ask you who 2020 Audio is?
Yes.
I came out of nowhere a little bit.
Yeah sorry about that.
2020 Audio is where we are recording the audiobook for our Book of the Year which will
be entitled "Audio Book of the Year" and we are in the very booth that it has been recorded.
Yes.
The honour of being in the same booth as the no such thing as a fish team when they recorded
the audio but not 1 hour ago.
That author is, we are mere podcasters, such an honour.
Okay, starting with fact number 1 and that is Andy.
My fact is that there are whales alive today who were alive before Moby Dick was written.
Wow.
Does that mean so that book was written about a real whale?
Yes.
So might that whale still be alive?
No.
So because there are different kinds of whales there are particular whales which do live
for at least 200 years.
We know that but they are bow head whales and I think the whale and Moby Dick was a sperm
whale.
Yeah.
So I don't know how long live sperm whales are actually.
It is possible.
Wow.
There is a bow head.
Sorry you said bow head whales.
So bow head whales are they have got a life expectancy that can actually go up to 250 years
I remember.
So that would mean that not only were they alive longer then let's say the book itself
Moby Dick was written but potentially there is one that is alive that was born the year
that Herman Melville the author of Moby Dick was born.
Oh wow.
Yeah he wrote the book at 32 years old.
Wow.
And it was in 1851.
Yes.
And here is another thing the first New England Whalers so the first people from North America
who were whaling around there they started in 1791 and that was 227 years ago.
So there might be some whales alive who remember a time before whaling in that area of the
world.
Wow.
Oh my god the time when they were free roaming the waters with no fear.
Well this is the thing.
So there was this massive bout of whaling in the Arctic especially between 1848 and 1915.
So the bowhead whales in the Arctic all but about I think 1200 of them were killed 30 years
ago they're only about 1200 left.
So it's not like we have an individual we can definitely point to that whale and say that
one was alive before Moby Dick.
But they did find one recently which had a harpoon in it and they tested the age of the
harpoon and they found it had only been manufactured between 1879 and 1885 that specific harpoon.
So the whale was probably harpooned sometime from 1885 to 95 or it could be someone who
just likes old harpoons like a modern day guy who's you know he's just using really old
material.
It could have been harpooned three years ago with an ancient harpoon supported off the day.
But they reckon that that one that they found the harpoon and was 211 years old.
So that's yeah.
So basically these bowhead whales in particular are very very old.
And it's one of the best ways to date them sometimes is when the harpoons came from because
they're often found with harpoons in them embedded in their blubber, aren't they?
But we should say with bowhead whales you were saying there were only about 1200 left.
That was about 30, 30 years ago.
And today there are 14,000 some good whale news.
Oh, that was good.
So that actually conservation is really worth.
Wow.
But yeah people used to harpoon a lot but whales can survive a huge amount of harpooning.
So in fact the whale that Moby Dick was based on was a real life whale called Mocha Dick.
You can see how a Melville really uses imagination when he switched names there.
And Mocha Dick was a super famous whale in the 1830s, sort of terrorised boaters.
And it was swim really calmly next to a wailing boat.
But then at the first sign of aggression from the boat it would like attack the boat and
tip people out.
And when it finally died in 1839 it had 19 harpoons lodged in its side.
Wow.
There he is bits of harpoon.
19.
Wow.
Because they get stuck in the blubber don't they?
Yeah.
And Mocha Dick was a sperm whale I think.
Of the bowhead whales they have more blubber than anyone they have up to half a meter thick
of blubber.
Wow.
That is a lot I think.
You sort of body shaming the old bowhead a little bit aren't you?
Well they're really weird animals aren't they?
Because they've got a skull which is up to 40% of their body length.
So the skull alone could be over five meters long.
And the really weird thing about them is that they have the largest mouth of any living
animal.
But they have no teeth.
Like large in terms of depth breath.
I think volume.
Volume.
Yeah.
So it's larger than a blue whale's mouth even though the bowhead is slightly smaller it's
got such a massive head that I've read this fact about blue whales which I guess must
be true about bowhead whales if it's true about blue whales which you might not be.
But it is that the amount of water that a blue whale can fit in its mouth is heavier than
a blue whale itself.
What?
Oh really?
Yeah.
That's plausible actually isn't it?
Are you going to say why don't they sink?
No, I wasn't.
I was going to say do they expand to a double blue whale size like a pufferfish?
No it's about different densities so I guess water's more dense.
Yeah.
Then blubber especially because blubber's quite buoyant isn't it?
That's why women I think are often better at floating.
This is actually only my subjective experience but I find it quite easy to swim and I'm
often swimming with men who sink more easily and I think it's because women naturally
have a bit more water fat.
But you are going regularly harpoon to a little downside aren't you?
I've got 14 harpoons in pale in my sight at this moment.
I should just sorry just one more thing I learned about harpoons that I didn't know which
I found out from that one that was discovered that was 130 years old.
They had explosives in them which I didn't realise they did so they harpoon them and they
were timed explosive.
This is in the mid 19th century, timed explosive so they went inside and then they were
timed to explode once in there.
They didn't use harpoons to kill whales did they?
That's you kill a whale with a lance or with a club or something like that.
You use your harpoon to kind of catch it and then it kind of drags you along until it
gets tired and then once it's tired you can kind of kill it with something else.
I see.
The bowhead whales, have we said before that they have giant penises in their heads?
What?
Well, sort of very penis equivalent thing.
They have this massive ridge of tissue and it's called the corpus cavernosum axilaris.
Now any latin or penis fans might remember that there is a thing in the human penis called
the corpus cavernosum and that's the thing which fills with blood, those are the chambers
which fill up and they do the same thing in the whale but they're to cool the whale down.
So when the whale is swimming around and is getting really active there's a real risk
that they'll overheat because they've got so much blood there they can get really hot
really easily so they engorge this corpus cavernosum axilaris which means in the head with blood
and then it opens its mouth, cold sea water flows in, cools the blood flows back out.
So it's their way of cooling themselves down using this giant head penis.
That's weird that they need to cool themselves down because they are found in cool water which
is one of the reasons for their longevity, isn't it?
Yeah, but they're constantly wearing a really thick coat basically and if you're trying
to do anything in a thick coat or warm up, it is a bit like having a big coat all
the time on a cold day but then whenever you want to cool down, get in an erection and pouring
cold water into your butts and that's effectively what we're saying, isn't it?
Yeah, it doesn't sound like a crazy way of cooling down.
It does.
I think people would call you crazy if you started doing that.
Not on the bus.
Oh, I actually have a coat fact related to whales.
Yeah, I love this. Some of the earliest waterproof jackets were made from whale intestines and
it was the innuets who used to wear them because they are really waterproof.
I was thinking intestines are full of water, bodily water, but very permeable because the
nutrients have to permeate through them and so yeah, they would turn them into waterproof
jackets.
That is amazing.
I don't really know what an intestine looks like but I imagine it's a bit like a puffer
jacket because it's going to have lots of folds in it.
You're right.
All the folds.
So, what would they do to preserve it so it doesn't rot?
Oh, I guess they're keeping it on ice most of the time anyway.
Yeah, that's a good point.
That's a good point.
If you dry it out, I guess.
Don't know that.
Oh, that's true.
We wear leather clothes sometimes.
Yeah.
Just cure it.
Yeah, cure it with urine, for instance, if you get cow hide and then you put a load of urine
on it for ages and ages and ages, it'll get cured and it won't go rotten.
This is very weird.
I have another whale based clothing fact, which I didn't even realise and it's about
Moby Dick too.
So, there's a whole chapter in Moby Dick on the whale's penis and it's called the casak.
It's pretty gruesome reading but the men, the whalers, they cut off a whale's penis, they
skin it and then they turn the skin into a sleeveless robe, kind of like a onesie.
Oh, cool.
Yeah.
And it's specifically for a man called the mincer and his job is to chop blubber and keep
cooking it in the pot.
Isn't it true that someone had a yacht?
I want to say Jackie Onassis.
It was Onassis, the husband, yeah.
Aristotle Onassis.
And well, I think you're going to know this fact, Dan, if you say that.
But did they have a chair, which was, had whale penis as the, yeah, it was the skin of
the chair was whale penis, I believe.
Who's upholsted in it, yeah.
Oh.
Hmm.
Who thought, first, of pissing on a cow hide to cure it?
What?
Unknown genius.
They, they used piss for a lot of things, didn't they?
Yeah.
They tried everything.
Don't they?
We on everything.
See what sticks.
Mostly it's not useful.
It's always just one person in the village going, have you pissed on it?
Just for everything.
Every new thing being tested.
Well, my, my iPhone stuff worked.
I wonder though, if the penis bit in Moby Dick stayed in the British version, because the
one that was printed in Britain was massively changed, wasn't it?
Which caused serious problems.
So when it was published, I think it was actually published in the UK, maybe just before America,
because there were weird copyright in quirk, that, um, they wanted to avoid piracy.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Um, but it was printed in the UK first, but the UK publishers were kind of a combination
of really careless and really prudish.
They cut huge tracks of it out and also they cut out the epilogue.
And I should say if you haven't read Moby Dick and you don't want a spoiler, then fast
forward, like the next 15 seconds of this, but, oh, I put my hands on my ears, but I've
got cancer.
It's just going to make the sound more intense.
Yeah.
And also, when James says cans, he doesn't mean actual cans on his head, so I'm wearing headphones.
I'm wearing the southern French city of Canada.
Anyone who tuned out will be tuning back in right around now.
Go away for five minutes and then come back.
Disappear, go make a cup of tea. Um, basically, the epilogue is a crucial part of Moby Dick,
because it's narrated by famously by Ishmael, hence call me Ishmael, being that famous line.
But, uh, at the sort of apparent end of Moby Dick, then the ship goes down, everyone dies.
It's only in the epilogue that it's explained that Ishmael has survived.
So that was cut out and it got terrible reviews in Britain, because all the reviewers said,
"Well, it doesn't make any sense how the hell is this story being narrated by someone
who clearly died at the end of the book?"
Yeah, the ghost of Ishmael.
Yeah.
The reviews were so bad, so I read about a few of them, um, one review in the Boston Post said,
"We have read nearly one half of this book and are satisfied that the London Athenaeum
is right in calling it an ill-compounded mixture of romance and matter effect."
And the spectator said, "Nothing should be introduced into a novel which it is physically
impossible for the writer to have known, thus he must not describe the conversation of
miners in a pit if they all perish."
So that was exactly that problem that you mentioned about it, yeah.
And it killed his career.
Yeah, he had a terrible career as an author for someone who's a household name.
It's all 315 copies, and he then just gave up.
But actually it didn't become popular, I think, until relatively recently, is that right?
I think it was the 1950s, because the British flawed edition remained the most commonly
read one for so long, and it was only when, like, the seminal text was published, and
I think the 50s that people suddenly went, "Ah, this is quite good now that it makes sense."
Yeah.
And his other stuff sounds really interesting.
He wrote a book called The Confidence Man, and it's a book which is all about a con man
who fools people.
It's set on one single day, and I think it's known to be the first book ever to just be
set in a single day.
And that day happens to be April Fool's Day, because he's conning someone, and the book
itself was released on April Fool's Day to tie in with that.
Just one other thing as well, that Herman Melville, in what he's written, is he wrote what
is said to be the longest poem in American literature.
It's almost 18,000 lines.
Are you going to read it for us now?
If you want to fast forward it, hold it for a little bit, three hours.
What's it about?
It's a poem and pilgrimage in the Holy Land.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Sounds great.
On very old things.
Oh, yeah.
This was in the news this year.
I'm not sure if it's true, but it has been claimed that some Russian scientists have
found an extinct lion cub underneath the snow in Siberia.
And inside that lion cub, they found two nematode worms, which must be at least 40,000 years
old, and they brought them back to life.
So there are two 40,000 year old worms currently living in Russia.
They came over to Salisbury for two days.
Not for that.
I mean, isn't that amazing?
That is amazing.
Wait, so they were...
Sorry.
What?
So how did they bring them back to life?
40,000 years ago.
Yeah.
These worms were just happily living inside a rectum of a lion.
And then the lion died.
And then it got frozen.
And then they just kind of went into almost like a hibernation kind of thing.
And when they defrosted them 40,000 years later, they just kind of, you on and off.
And they're alive again.
The Austin Powers of the world.
They've been against none of the cultural references.
It's going to be so difficult bringing them up to speed.
It would be interesting.
We'll never know, but to put a modern day of a species worm next to it and just...
See if they chat.
Just to know if that...
See if they get up.
Like, I would love to know how much has happened in the worm world.
There would be enough of a difference in their conversation.
I'd love to know what you think you would see.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Because I'm telling you, it would be nothing.
They're just going to sit next to each other for a bit.
I wonder if they'd have sex with each other.
Oh, yeah.
Because there's an age difference, isn't there, and then there's like 40,000 year-age difference.
Well, do you know that a very big age difference I found in nature, actually,
is that between the world's oldest tortoise.
So tortoises and other animals that lives a long time.
And the oldest living one is Jonathan.
He's 186 years old.
And the girl that he's been trying to get off with is only 26.
He's been trying to get off with her since 1991.
The problem he might have been having is that they discovered last year.
Frederica is actually most probably a male.
Oh.
Oh, sorry.
You said, girl, I think you made a human woman that he was sort of infatuated with as a tortoise.
No, sorry.
You were a female tortoise.
A girl tortoise, yes.
Yeah.
Turns out he's just been trying to mount another man, make babies.
Which is fine.
Of course.
It's totally fine.
It just won't make babies.
No.
And also, if you're a hundred and seventy odd years old, you're probably quite right-wing
in your opinions.
Do you think he's most certainly homophobic?
I just say, at that age, I think people do get a bit like that, but they...
I don't know.
I think tortoises are more open-minded.
I can't believe I was getting shit for talking about what worms would say to each other.
You would just say tortoises are more open-minded.
Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the European Space Agency has a sound system so loud that if you
heard it, it would kill you.
Your head would explode is probably not what would happen.
This is claimed by the ESA.
They've said that they have this big sound system.
Well, they definitely do have the sound system.
Definitely.
Yes, they have the sound system.
It's in the Netherlands.
And it's the ESA's large European acoustic facility, otherwise known as LEAF.
It's 16.4 meters tall.
It's 11 meters wide, 9 meters deep, and it uses nitrogen gas in order to make the sounds.
And what they use it for is to test rockets.
They smash sound into rockets to simulate what it might be like for when a rocket is
exiting or re-entering Earth.
So what they've said is that if you were in this room and they closed their door and this
was put on, that it could kill you, that's a bit disputed by I think every site I've read
that talks about it.
We're not sure that it could do that.
It only gets up to, I believe, 154 decibels.
Most scientists believe that 154 decibels probably will boast your ear drums, it will cause
pain, but it won't explode your head in the way that perhaps they're suggesting.
But it won't be pleasant.
It won't be pleasant.
Especially depends what kind of music it is as well, don't forget.
Yeah, do we know what kind of music they play to the rockets?
Well, I read it.
I read it.
No, it's just sound, unfortunately, as in...
Well, sorry, grab that.
The music they say, "No, it's just sound."
You and Jonathan, the talk just ain't funny.
Well, one guy who was interviewed about it who works there says that they do, you know,
you plug an iPod in and he would love to play rock music, whatever, but actually it's
just a bunch of noise.
And so basically with what sound waves are, it's molecules in the air and they're kind
of getting closer together and further apart, closer together and further apart, so it's
a change in pressure.
So if you make a sound loud enough, there'll be a big enough change in pressure that it
would definitely kill you, in my opinion.
Wow.
I'm pretty sure it would.
It would probably explode your lungs, but I don't see any reason why it couldn't explode
your head as well.
Wow.
I think sound waves become a shock wave, basically, at a certain point, effectively,
and they're about 190, where it's then like the, you know, the shock wave that makes a big
sonic boom.
But yeah, they apparently also, it doesn't have to be sounds that you can hear.
So there's infrasound, which is sounds that are out of the range of human hearing frequencies.
And people have found that if you expose humans to infrasounds that are over 100 decibels,
they have blood pressure and respiratory rate changes that they can't control.
They just feel their breathing changing.
And if you take the decibel level high enough, even though they can't even hear the sound,
their lungs will deflate and inflate.
So it can be used as a means of like artificial respiration if you play this inaudible sound.
It's amazing.
That's so weird.
So any of these things, loudness is basically how big the amplitude and whatever it is.
So it could be really, really, really, really loud, but you still can't hear it because
it's below, say, 60 Hz.
Yeah, right.
And that, to me, that just blows my mind a little bit because how something can be really
loud, but you can't hear it.
That just doesn't make any sense.
It's astonishing.
Well, I don't like it because it can affect you.
Who knows what sounds are being played right now that are screwing with our brains?
No.
Well, that's what they thought, didn't they?
In the American Embassy in Cuba or something?
Yeah.
So everyone's feeling sick.
And they thought maybe there's some infrasound kind of weapon they were using.
I think probably we think that isn't true, right?
I don't think they could work in fear it.
They've not decided one way or the other.
Or they certainly haven't said if they have.
So loud noise also causes heart disease.
Really?
Yeah.
So it's really strange.
It induces a stress response.
It disrupts your body at a cellular level and it induces a kind of fight or flight response.
So when the stress hormones increase, that can lead to vascular damage.
And this happens even if you're asleep, a loud noise will increase your blood pressure.
Wow.
So it's kind of the same.
Even if you're not hearing it consciously, it just affects the body.
Yeah.
And every time I've ever walked into a club, I immediately want to run away as fast.
That will be it.
That will be possible.
Did you know the scientists have only just discovered why cocks don't deffin themselves?
Cockrels.
Roles.
Cockrels?
Let's call them roosters.
So roosters crow at over 100 decibels, which is extremely loud.
It's the same as running a chainsaw right next to your ear.
Wow.
And we didn't know why they don't just go deaf, why the eardrums don't explode.
And they've looked into them and there are a couple of reasons.
So they've got an eardrum that's surrounded by a nice soft squishy tissue.
But also, when they tilt their head back to start crowing, then they've got this little
flap of material which drops down and covers their ear canal completely.
So they've got their own built-in ear plug.
Oh my god.
Do you remember those dolls that you would get as a kid and as you sat it up, the eyes open
and then the way you lay them, the same fingers.
Yeah, it's exactly the same thing.
The same technology.
Yeah.
Wow.
That is amazing.
It's cool.
It's like being able to stick your fingers in your ears if you don't have fingers.
It's like having a finger inside your ear that you could just kind of maneuver it inside
the ear and stick it in the little canal.
It's exactly like that.
Hey, you know that song "Rock and Roll Ain't Noise Pollution" by AC/DC?
No.
It's track 10 on Back and Black.
It's one of the more famous songs.
It's a very good one.
Sing it for us.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
We're not allowed.
For legal reasons.
The lyrics are "Rock and Roll Ain't Noise Pollution".
Okay.
The Mississippi State University, who recently tested whether or not "Rock and Roll" is
or "Ain't Noise Pollution" to aphids.
Piss!
No, sorry.
To beetles.
They played rock two beetles.
There's a beetle called Lady Beetles.
They're living fields and they play on aphids.
And the scientists played AC/DC at them quite loud, along with some other music.
And they found that when it was country and folk music, the beetles didn't mind.
But when it was AC/DC, specifically back in black, the number of aphids they caught was
cut in half.
And the aphid population rocketed and then the plants in the field were 25% smaller.
So it has a big impact on farming, basically.
So they have concluded, they said, as fans of AC/DC, we sadly must disagree with the band
and conclude that "Rock and Roll" is "Noise Pollution" for beetles.
That's so weird.
I find that so weird.
Do you?
Because I think AC/DC is melodic, as much as we're about to get into the argument about
whether it's metal or rock.
No, I just find that a bit odd.
Yeah, but we don't know what's making them stop eating the aphids.
It might be that they're enjoying the music so much.
They're just kind of bopping around and they don't have time to do that.
Yeah, or they've gone off to buy the CD or something.
That's possible.
Just speaking of music, metal, Metallica this year has released a whiskey.
So they're like growing a number of bands that are releasing their own alcohols.
They've gone for whiskey, but the way that they are distilling the whiskey, the distilling
process, is they are playing heavy metal to the whiskey.
Right.
It's very cool.
So it's a process that then they're calling black noise and the idea is it's shaping
the whiskey's flavor.
So they play Metallica's music through a subwoofer and they disrupt the whiskey inside the barrel.
So it's sort of just getting mixed up and mixed up and it's a molecular level of infusion
going on.
Yeah, what is absolute bullshit.
No, no, no, no.
I think they do this all the time to whiskey, don't they?
There's always they are.
This one's been at the bottom of the sea.
Yeah.
This one's been in space.
This one's like, can they not just make nice whiskey that people want to buy?
It's good.
Listen, I'm getting this from a very, very good source.
This is the press release released by the band.
And yeah, it it's increased wood interaction that kicks up the wood flavor characteristics
in the whiskey.
I don't know what that means.
I don't know where the wood bit came in.
The wood comes from the barrel.
For the barrels.
The whole point is that the wood you use in the barrels sort of reacts with the spirit.
That's where the taste comes from whiskey, the barrels.
As in they put tasteless alcohol in there and then it's in the barrels for 25 years and
it seeps in all the flavor from the wood and that's where the whiskey plays the sweet.
Is it 25 years for you?
It's over.
That's just a six week whiskey.
And it just gives it a quick dip.
It just gives it a quick dip.
Is that right?
That is...
I mean, it's not a million miles from what I get.
Well, there you go.
You're the healthiest.
It followed 500,000 people over a 10-year period and then looked at who had died at the end of it.
And it found that you reduced your chance of death by 14% of your drinking eight plus cups
of coffee and by 16% if you drink seven cups of coffee a day.
Is it the caffeine that's the good ingredient or is it coffee in general?
Is it the good ingredient or is it coffee in general?
Is it the normal coffee?
Would they still be healthy?
And there's no hope here.
Sorry.
No, they don't know because it's just a statistical study.
It's not a biological study as it was.
They've just looked at who's dead.
Right.
But they've adjusted for other factors as in it could be...
Yes.
I'm sure they've done all the stuff that scientists are meant to do, like a chance for other mitigating
factors.
One would hope.
South Korean schools aren't the only place to abandon coffee.
Go on.
Bit of a history.
All of Sweden did in 1746.
Wow.
Yeah.
This was very interesting.
They banned coffee and it was banned by King Gustav III.
And it was banned because they just thought that it was very bad for your health.
So what he wanted to do was ban it and then experiment on it to see whether or not he was
right in his belief or whether or not his advisors who told him that were right in their
belief.
So what they did was they started giving it to convicted criminals to test to see whether
if they drunk coffee all day, every day or at least, you know, they all ended up being
beheaded.
So it was included.
Very bad for you.
Well, here's the thing.
The King ordered an experiment to be done on two identical twins.
They were both on death row, but they were both put just for life imprisonment if they
went and did this because they wanted to see how long it could last.
So one was given coffee every day and the other one was given tea.
And unfortunately, Gustav III died before the experiment finished.
He was having energy drinks every day, wasn't he?
Yes.
Exactly.
Yeah.
No, he was assassinated in 1792.
Sorry.
Sorry, guys.
Too soon.
But yeah, we don't fully know what happened.
Well, no, the really great thing was that so the two doctors were assigned to study the patients,
one doctor each, but both the doctors and King Gustav all died before either the tea drinker
or the coffee drinker.
Yeah.
Great.
I've read an account saying that the tea drinker died first and that the solitary coffee
drinker, who was meant to be living this unhealthy, life-start drinking coffee, lived longest
of all of them.
I think there is a question that it's a pocketful tale though.
I mean, it sounds so neat.
Yeah.
I found somewhere else where it was banned.
Gone.
This is in the Ottoman Empire.
So there were lots, so it's basically originated for the first time in Yemen in the 15th century,
as in grinding the beans, mixing with liquid.
There have been various other attempts to use caffeine beans before that.
Yemen is, or modern day Yemen, I guess, is where it first appeared.
Same as India's ad.
Really?
Is he from Yemen?
Yeah, he is.
He was born there, wasn't he?
Yeah.
Well, I thought that might go somewhere different, so.
He then moved to Bexhillon Sea, which is where comedians like Milligan and those stations
are ensuring the early bit of the Second World War.
Where is that, Bexhillon Sea?
Bexhillon Sea is just near.
It's on the coast.
It's sort of, you can see France in the distance.
Oh, on the South Coast.
Wow, there's some really nice towns here.
Unbelievable.
I've got some stuff here.
Thank you about Yemen, where he is, I'm trying to say.
So basically, it became really popular because it was very delicious, but also it was seen
as quite dangerous, quite political, because you'd have a coffee house, which is where people
meet and they can discuss, and they can discuss politics.
So it's not like meeting at a mosque where things are a bit more police than you're only
there for religious purposes.
So it's a secular space, and also the coffee was brewed for 20 minutes and it was served
very, very hot, so you could only drink it in tiny sips, so you kind of have to chat.
So the Ottoman Sultan in 1633 cracked down on it, and this is supposedly true, that he
walked around Istanbul in disguise with a big sword ready to behead anybody he found drinking
coffee.
Is that right?
Well, this is the story, and again, it may well be apocryphal.
I love the detail of a big sword.
He wasn't turning no fruit knife around.
It was banned by Frederick the Great, 1781, because he thought that people should be taking
beer instead of beer gruel instead of coffee.
He thought it was a bit of a luxury.
Beer gruel.
Beer gruel would be like the porridgey stuff that you get at the bottom when you've been
brewing beer.
And he was brought up on that and he thought other people should be having that.
They shouldn't be having this luxurious stuff from Yemen.
But he actually did himself have coffee, although the difference was he bowled his with instead
of water champagne.
Yeah.
Wow.
Oh.
That's way to have it.
Would that be nice?
Would it?
Yeah.
I think after the fourth or fifth cup, you start to enjoy it a bit more.
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is Chazinski.
My fact this week is that facial recognition technology for chickens allows you to pre-order
a specific chicken and watch it grow on the farm before it ends up on your plate.
It's actually quite nice.
This is a technology that's just being patented and developed in China.
And it's to make sure that your chicken is totally free range.
And they've developed really advanced facial recognition technology for chickens, which
is about, you know, late '90s percent accuracy.
And so you pre-order your chicken.
And then I guess four to six months later, once it's waddled about on its nice free range
farm for a while, and you've been able to check it every once in a while, then you get
to eat it.
You check in on it.
Check, check.
You check.
You check in on it.
Well, yeah, facial recognition is going to be everywhere, isn't it?
Well, the technology seems, yeah, really advanced in some areas and really crap in others.
For instance, there was the trial at the 2017 Champions League final in Cardiff, where
it was revealed that it'd wrongly identified more than 2,000 people.
So the technology flagged up 2,470 people as potential criminals by comparing them to a
database of potential criminals.
It turned out 2,297 of those flags were false positives.
Well, it's still sub-positive, though.
Some positives.
I think the police at the moment have a 98% false positive rate for their facial recognition
technology.
No, but those, the South Wales police, they've been improving that technology since the
Champions League final.
I think they switched to a new algorithm and at a recent event, they only got 10 false
positives, which was 0.02% of the total number of matches.
I'm skeptical.
So I went to an exhibition last night at Somerset House.
It's really good.
It's basically a massive design exhibition that's taken over the whole thing.
It's on for a few weeks.
Each country has its own room and design piece.
And the American one was testing facial recognition.
So I had a go and it asks you to sit in a chair and it scans your face and it does lots of,
you know, investigating your face, everything about it, and then tells you how old it thinks
you are, whether you're male or female, all that kind of thing.
And you're skeptical about this because I think you're a hundred and seventy-five-year-old
tartarist.
Oh, yeah.
It wasn't quite that wrong, but it asked me to try and look really angry.
And so I did.
I tried really hard.
You know, I put loads of angry faces.
I see those faces.
You've all seen those faces a lot.
Give us a fake, angry face that you were giving it.
Oh, that.
To me, it's screaming constipation.
But basically, then, I guess what expression I was trying to do, and it said calm, and then
it gets my age.
And I was there with my friend.
She did it and I did it.
It said it.
It thought I was a female age 15 to 20, which is extremely flashing, but I'm not the kind
of person.
I mean, no one has wrinkles between 15 and 20.
Why can't it spot that?
And it said my poor friend was a female age 55 to 65.
Who's my age?
So I think the average they got it right.
Pretty much.
Right.
Is that what they're going for?
In Finland, they're testing a new technology.
So the idea is that when you walk into a shop, they're developing scanners that when you
walk in up to the till, you give a meaningful nod, as it says in the quotes, that's how they've
said in this video, you give a meaningful nod to the scanner, and that's how you pay.
And it's memorized through, in the same way, with your bank card details, your face is
going on.
Creepy, creepy, creepy, creepy.
Yeah.
I am going to trick all this facial recognition stuff, and I found out a method I can do.
I deliberately disfiguring your own face.
That's right.
So it turns out that you can't trick good facial recognition systems by wearing makeup.
Even if you're wearing weird goth style makeup, it doesn't work.
But there is a guy online, and his name is Taki on, that's his Twitter account, he has
found that the kind of makeup worn by fans of the insane clown posse, aka Juggalos, right?
They wear very heavy clown makeup, and it completely redefines what the computer sees
as your jawline.
So we may still see people wearing clown masks for bank robberies, but they'll just be
wearing clown makeup instead.
That's very clever.
Oh.
But they tried to train them up, didn't they?
Recently, I think you mentioned fleetingly in a podcast a few months ago, Andy, that the
South Wales Police sent facial recognition AI to a massive Elvis impersonator festival,
the biggest one in the world, in order to hone its techniques to see if it could distinguish
between different Elvis impersonators.
Oh, speaking of Elvis, I've been reading up on him recently.
I was reading this one article that was published on the enemy, and it's one of those things
that we don't usually naturally go to when we're doing our research, you know, something
that's like 101 amazing things that you'll, but this article called 75 geeky facts you
might not know about Elvis Presley.
And it was genuinely incredible every time I give this one.
Okay, here's one.
The inspiration for Elvis Presley's trademark jumpsuit and quiff look was a comic book hero
Captain Marvel Jr. is what inspired Elvis Presley's look.
This is the geekiest foundations for what it seemed to be the coolest singer of the 1950s
and so did he say that was, did he used to read them?
He must have, as a kid, yeah, he was obsessed with them, I believe, when he was younger.
And so that's what he based his look on.
Here's another one just before he died, Elvis commissioned his stage electrician to design
a version of his big white jumpsuit that he wore, which would fire laser beams into
the audience from the suit.
I mean, that's incredible.
I've not heard that before.
Do you know Elvis?
He, Elvis impersonators.
Do you know the first Elvis impersonator was in 1954, which is two years before Elvis's
first hit single?
What?
This guy was called Carl Cheesy Nelson.
That is.
Cheesy.
It was his nickname.
That was his middle name.
Okay.
And basically, what had happened was Elvis had been delayed for a show and this guy was
a really good friend of Elvis.
And so he did the whole show just copying his entire style.
That's so cool.
So, yeah, that's amazing.
That's amazing.
That's so funny.
Just while we're on impersonators, and again, from this NME article, really fascinating.
In Somalia, going to strict Islamic law, Elvis impersonators are required to have beards.
Right.
So you can do everything.
And I'm reading these facts word for word, I should say.
It's such a brilliant article.
Just one more thing I found really interesting about facial recognition.
Oh, yeah.
Do you know that shops in London have it specifically for celebrities?
So a bunch of stores in London, more than a dozen stores in 2013, installed this technology,
which is VIP facial recognition technology, to stop that moment when someone super famous
walks in.
And as a shop assistant, you're supposed to be really kind of nice and sequest to them,
but you don't know who they are.
So it has a database of all celebrities' faces, and as soon as a celebrity walks in, then
a thing pops up on these guys' tills that says, "Oh, Julia Roberts has just entered the
building."
And also with a bit of info about her, like, she is this size, and she likes this style of
thing, and go and force her to buy some shit.
If only Hugh Grant had had that in Notting Hill when Julia Roberts walked into his bookshop.
Oh, if only.
They could have done the whole film in half an hour.
You're so right.
And he would have sold her a book she actually wanted to buy, because it would have had a preferences.
I have a thing about facial recognition and celebrities.
This is weirdly similar to that.
So still on the tricking facial recognition thing, there are specially designed glasses
which can make facial recognition computers think that you are Miller Yovervitch.
Who?
Miller Yovervitch?
Yeah, Miller Yovervitch.
She's in the fifth element.
She's a model slash actor, resident, she's in all six of the resident evil movies, and
she does a brilliant job at them.
So they only tell you when it's her?
No, no, no.
They make the computer think that you are Miller Yovervitch.
Got it.
So it's really bizarre.
They've got, they can be made up to look like normal tortoise glasses, but on the front
of the rims, they've got these specially printed images, okay?
And the frames kind of overlay the face with pixels.
And when the computer looks at you, it's calculations are disturbed and it thinks that you are
someone else in its database.
And I think there are limits.
As in I think you, you might have to be a woman, for example, with that, with a slightly
different bone structure, or you might need to be white as Miller Yovervitch.
Do you think wholesale people might start robbing banks, looking like Miller Yovervitch?
What an idea.
Yeah.
And then she's just going to get arrested, obviously.
Just be her in the insane clown posse in prison.
Okay.
That is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said over
the course of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland.
James.
@JamesHarkin.
Andy.
Andrew Hunter M.
And Shazinski.
You can email podcast@QI.com.
Or you can go to our group account, which is @nosuchthing.
You can also go to our Facebook page.
No such thing as a fish or our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
We have everything up there.
All of our previous episodes linked to our upcoming tour in 2019.
We have links to our new book, which is coming out very soon.
And we just want to also say very quickly a thank you to 2020 audio for allowing us to record
here today.
Also a massive thank you to Ruben, who's next door right now, recording this for us.
He did our audio book, he's awesome, and he's a DJ.
So go find him on what's your @Ruben, do you have a Twitter app?
@Rubiconuk.
Okay, that's it, we'll be back again next week.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[Music]
[BLANK_AUDIO]