(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray
and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered
around the microphones with our four favorite facts
from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the komaru
is the only species that gets better at reproducing
when it has been struck by lightning.
(laughing)
- It's quite cartoonish the way you've made it sound.
- Yeah.
- Like the lightning goes in, it goes (sneezes)
and then it's better at reproducing, right?
Get your minds out of the gutter of people at home
because the komaru is a type of tree.
It is a, well, specifically the tonka bean tree.
And a load of scientists have been looking
at lightning strikes in Panama
and they've looked at all the different trees
that have been struck.
And actually it's over a 40 year period
that they've done this.
And they found that if you're a tree,
you're substantially more likely to die
if you live next to a tonka bean tree.
- Yeah.
- And it's because they get struck by lightning a lot.
And when they get struck by lightning,
the lightning sort of bounces off them
and goes to these other trees and kills these trees.
- It's crazy.
- They also have parasites, sort of vines and stuff on them.
And the lightning kills those vines as well.
And as a result, when they've been struck by lightning
a number of times,
they have a 14 fold increase in lifetime seed production.
So they create more seeds when they've been struck by lightning
because they get rid of all the competition and stuff.
And that makes it better for them to reproduce.
- It's amazing as well
'cause there must be a lot of these trees.
It's not like it's just a single tree out there, right?
There's tons, but within its own lifetime,
after maturity will be struck
by at least five different bolts of lightning.
I mean, that's insane.
Yeah, five times.
- Also imagine having one child
and then you're struck by lightning
and then you have 14 children.
- Yeah.
- That's very stressful.
- You mean that's what's going on?
- Well, James was just saying they're 14 times
more romantically successful.
- It's bad enough being struck by lightning,
but then if you have to look after a lot of kids afterwards.
- I see.
Even worse.
- Salt in the wound.
- Exactly.
Fortunately trees are very, very, very bad parents
in general.
- They just had their hands off on me.
(all laughing)
- They're big old trees as well.
130 feet, they can get up to, I mean, these are gigantic.
- Which makes them more likely to be struck by lightning
of course, 'cause they're often the tallest tree
in the canopy.
- Yeah.
It's strange, isn't it?
'Cause lots of trees, when they're hit by lightning,
I think we might've said this in the past,
they will explode.
- Oh yeah.
- And that's 'cause the temperature just gets so hot
inside and they explode.
- 'Cause they have water in there and the water expands
because it's heated up so much.
- Exactly.
And there's this theory that the...
Is it Kumaru?
Is it Kumaru, Kumaru?
- Well, I'm gonna call it a Kumaru
because I find that a funny word.
- And that's your right.
It's your right.
(all laughing)
- It's Kumaru.
- Kumaru, okay.
There's this theory that these trees have
really high internal conductivity,
so they're like a wire already almost.
So that means that the lightning can flow through them
without building up that massive blasting heat inside,
which will kill it.
Which is very, I mean, presumably that's evolved.
- Yeah.
- Hasn't everything.
- That's a solid point, yeah.
- Do you know who's most likely to get struck
by lightning?
What outdoor activity?
- Oh, so I would say golfers.
- Andy, you always talk about golf, honestly.
- The ladder carrying championships of Estonia.
(all laughing)
- Very risky at all.
- The Tonka Bean climbing championships in Panama.
There is a common misconception that golfers
are the most likely to be struck by lightning
because they are outside.
- Metal rods.
- Metal rods, big metal golf clubs,
and they're holding with them.
But there has been a study and they found
the most common is football, actually.
- Oh, really?
- And the reason being that people will carry on playing
football, that soccer I'm talking about,
and they'll carry on playing in bad weather.
- Whereas golfers are just looking for an excuse
to go inside and drink a beer, aren't they?
- Yeah, but honestly, if you play golf
and you hear any thunder, you have to come in,
that's the rule.
- Oh, really?
- I thought you weren't meant to come in?
I thought you were meant to lie down on the ground
with your bottom in the air.
- That's not a specific golf rule.
- What is that?
- Are you thinking of an off-stretch?
- As we're doing this, the US Open Golf
has just started in Oatbunt.
And I think if there's any lightning there,
you won't see Rory McElroy and Scotty Sheffler
taking down their trousers.
- I've been saying trousers.
- You definitely added that.
- But it's easier if the trousers are off,
so you can pop the flag in the top.
(laughing)
- No, that is, there is a theory,
and this is more generally if you're stuck outside
in the lightning, that if you're lower down, obviously,
they're slightly to be struck,
so you should kind of go on your haunches.
And if you put your bum in the air,
then the electricity will hit your bum
and travel down to the earth without going into your brain.
- Thank you. - Really?
- That's a sensible save.
- Hold it once.
- Saved your...
(laughing)
But we've said in the past
that it's really dangerous for humans.
- Lighting.
(laughing)
- One of those controversial podcasts.
- But we've also pointed out that between 85 and 90%
of people who are struck by lightning survive.
They do have long-term life damages,
but they do manage to survive.
- And do you guys read about Ray Caldwell?
- No.
- Okay, he was a baseball player.
He was playing for the Cleveland Indians
versus the Philadelphia Athletics.
This was in 1919.
He's just joined this team, and it is his first match.
He needs it to go well.
And he pitches the whole match.
There's nine innings, he's pitched eight.
On the ninth inning, that suddenly a thunderstorm hits,
lightning cracks down, strikes him,
everyone sees him get struck by it, they run to him,
he gets back up and says,
"I've got to make a good impression."
And he pitches the final few pitches
and gets a guy out.
- And when he threw it, like,
was the ball, like, super electric?
(laughing)
- Gosh.
- There's one thing that you can do
that will help you survive in a lightning strike.
- Yeah.
- And that is having a wet head.
And this is due to the fact
that the lightning will hit your head,
but then the water will conduct it down away
from your brain, and it might go over your whole body
rather than just going straight into your brain.
And also, because you have got water on your head,
it's not as hot.
- Yeah.
- So your brain doesn't get boiled.
- So it will turn the water to steam.
- Yeah, yeah, I mean, it's still very likely
to do you a lot of damage, but it can help slightly.
- If it's between standing outside in the rain,
saying, "I need to get my head wet,
"so I'm okay," and going inside.
- Go inside.
- Right, that's first thing going inside,
but failing that head wet. - So I think in all circumstances,
if there's a lightning storm, you're safer indoors.
- Well, well.
- Uh-oh.
- That was a terrific piece.
This was two years ago.
I think it was in the Guardian.
There's a guy called Aidan Rowan.
And the headline was,
"I was struck by lightning while sitting on my sofa."
Okay, and this was a guy, he was at home,
lived in Abingdon, which is small towns.
- Oldest town in the UK?
- Lovely.
Well, he was at home, he was playing on his PlayStation.
The window was open, the weather was a bit bad,
but you know, it's nice to have a bit of fresh air sometimes
on the weather's bed.
- Sometimes when it's thundering and lightning,
it's quite, you know, electrical air is really nice.
- Wonderful.
- Yeah, it's absolutely fine.
- There was a huge crack.
Get your mind out of it, stop.
Get off the girl's floor, stop.
He heard a huge noise of thunder.
Then it felt like someone had dropped
something very heavy on him.
He smelt singed flesh.
And like, basically, his arm was burning
sort of like scaling and boiled and all of this.
And like, he and his husband went to hospital
and it turned out lightning had bounced off water droplets
on his window sill and into the room.
- Oh, clever.
- Final destination stuff, isn't it?
- It is.
- Well, remember, I got mocked on this very show
for having mentioned that I shouldn't be taking baths
during lightning storms, 'cause remember,
it could travel through the pipes.
Remember the lady who was blown out the bath?
(all laughing)
- There was a huge crack there as well.
- But he said, it's lucky, so this is a tip
if you're playing on your PlayStation
and the weather's bad.
He said, one doctor said it was lucky
that I had my foot on the floor
while I was playing the game,
otherwise I wouldn't have been grounded.
And he could have been completely killed by that.
But he's a blacksmith, which is interesting.
- Yeah, no nice detail, thanks.
- It was like Thor, Thor and Hammer and-
- Yeah, yeah, and also that he's a God of Thunder.
How do we know that it bounced off that water droplet?
I just, it feels like something
that no one could possibly have documented.
- You're right.
- Oh, I saw it.
- Maybe there was an initial contact burn
on the windowsill, perhaps, I don't know.
- I see, I see.
- But he then, I find this interesting,
he bought a lottery ticket just to check
if he'd become psychic.
And he won six quid.
(all laughing)
- Did he deliberately think, well, I am psychic now,
but I don't want to go for the main numbers
because then everyone's gonna, you know.
- You don't want to have pressure touch,
like man, hit by lightning then wins lottery.
You got the pressure-
- You just go for six quid.
'Cause if you won six quid 100 times every week.
- The dream amount to win on the lottery
is enough to buy you another ticket plus a bit.
- Yes.
- That's the way to fly low under the radar
and steadily build up a million pounds.
- Very true.
- I, why psychic?
I would have thought he bought it
because he thought maybe I'm really lucky.
I survive being hit by lightning.
- 'Cause his brain might have, you know,
I mean, I don't need to go into the details.
- Yeah.
- A lot of people think, and there are stories
all over history of things being cured by lightning.
It's one of the tribe, nothing else has worked.
Like there was quite a lot of people say
that they have blindness and deafness cured.
- I just another case where it just seems so improbable
that you could survive.
I found a guy called Casey Wagner,
who was out attending a fun day of an event
called Rednecks with Paychecks.
And he was sitting under a tree
when he got hit by lightning, okay?
It shot his body upwards.
- I bet he did hit a redneck after that.
(all laughing)
- People could see this happening.
He got hit by a second bolt of lightning.
He got hit twice.
And what it hit, this is so unfortunate
'cause you wonder if he was wearing normal shoes.
- It might not have happened,
but he happened to be a rodeo clown
and he was wearing his clown shoes,
which are obviously longer than your regular shoes.
- Is a rodeo clown a real clown?
- I guess so, yeah.
- I'm sorry for the ignorance.
I just thought it was an insult.
- It's like somebody's badly prepared for a rodeo.
- Oh!
- But you're saying it's an actual clown at the rodeo.
- It's the reverse of someone saying
this isn't my first rodeo.
- Yeah.
- Yes.
- Hang on, is rodeo clown even a phrase?
Don't you know it is a phrase?
- I know that phrase.
- I read it as I took it.
It says his job as a rodeo clown.
You don't have a job as someone who's an idiot
or rocking up.
- So a rodeo clown?
(laughing)
- Don't throw stones.
- I think after these 12 years you can call that a job.
(laughing)
- You're saying that...
- Can I just say around this table
only one of us has heard the phrase rodeo clown.
- Yeah.
- No two, right?
Andy and Dan.
- No, Dan thought it was a job.
- So you know what?
The fishing box, I know.
'Cause I do the emails.
It's gonna be absolutely stuffed with
how dare you disrespect the ancient profession
of rodeo clown.
I've been a rodeo clown nine years, man and boy.
So what happened with his shoes?
Sorry?
- Well, it struck his shoe.
I've extrapolated the idea to think that maybe his shoe
was longer 'cause it was a clown shoe.
(laughing)
And all that water in a squirty buttonhole
will have boiled immediately.
(laughing)
- Can I quickly mention something about Tonka trees?
- Yeah, go for it.
- So Tonka beans are delicious, but lethal.
So if you eat too many of them,
like in sheep, five grams, about two teaspoons is fatal.
In humans, we don't really know what's fatal
because we can't really do that experiment,
but it is illegal to use Tonka beans
in your food in America.
And for a long time, they used it
'cause it tastes really delicious,
like a vanilla, licorice, caramel, loaves.
They used it in ice cream and stuff for a long time.
In America now, still, if you go to a really,
really, really, really posh restaurant,
then they will still serve you Tonka stuff
even though it's illegal.
- I love this, it's like the secret illegal bean.
And it's--
- But it's just on menus, openly.
- Yeah, it's 'cause of this chemical inside the bean
called Kumarin.
And also, the amount of Kumarin you'd have to consume
equates to so many beans,
which equates to so many puddings at the restaurant.
I read that as a human, you'd have to eat one gram
of Kumarin, not of Tonka beans,
of the chemical that's extracted
to experience any ill effects whatsoever.
That equates to about 30 beans worth of Kumarin.
And that would be about 250 puddings at this--
- That's true, although the actual limit,
as in, if the FDA did have a limit,
or if the EU had a limit,
it would be a quarter of a Tonka bean.
And the reason is because we can't test it on humans
about what's good for you or bad for you.
So what they do is they test it on an animal,
and then they say, okay, well, that's what that is
for a baboon or for a dog or whatever.
We're gonna multiply it by 100
for the human safety factor.
And that's how they work out the human safety factors.
They have like a massive window.
- That is so cautious.
- I know, but that's how they do it.
- That's too much, isn't it?
- The delicious puddings we're missing out on,
there are secret puddings all over the world
that we're not allowed to have.
- We're allowed to have it, we're not American.
- It's just the Americans.
- We're gonna have Tonka beans, upper asses?
(all laughing)
- While you're on the golf course,
I'll just pop this in here, madam,
and I hope you enjoy those rich flavors.
(all laughing)
- I don't even know what I was trying to say.
Do you know what it's also in?
I really didn't know this.
So the kumaran, this thing that's poisonous,
very slightly poisonous,
or in very small amounts in these things,
it's also in cinnamon,
but that's only because cinnamon isn't really cinnamon.
I did not know this.
Check the cinnamon in your cupboard.
It doesn't, most of it is not true cinnamon,
which comes from the bark of the cinnamonum virum,
and that's native to Sri Lanka.
It's actually from a plant called the cassia, cassia cinnamon,
which is, which is not true cinnamon at all,
even though it's claiming to be.
And one teaspoon of it, in fact,
sends you over kumaran safety limits set by the EU.
Again, very cautious.
I do overload with cinnamon sometimes.
On the old porridge,
you're probably breaking EU law
every time you have a nice cinnamon porridge.
- 20 cinnamon buns.
If they're those really delicious cinnamon-y ones,
you know where the middle is really cinnamon-y.
If you have 20 of those, then that's really...
- And sometimes after a night out,
when you go to one of those late night pastry places
in London, it's not impossible that's happened.
- Yeah. Oh, yes.
- Everyone else going to the kebab shop and is like, "No."
(laughing)
- The lottery do me.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in the 1400s,
the king of Korea put a big drum outside his palace,
and anyone in the kingdom who wanted to complain
about something was encouraged to come and bang it.
I bet they were not encouraged.
I bet they were strongly deterred,
except under the direst extremity.
- No way.
- He said, "Come one, come all."
Anything pissing you off?
Your wife nagging you too much?
Your shoes too tight? - He might say,
"Come one, come all," because it was the concept of one
in Korea, which is if someone causes you a slight,
or let's say someone steals something off you
and they're not properly punished,
then your level of one,
your kind of negative emotions are out of balance.
And this person who was sort of starting these new laws
and trying to keep everyone happy,
this was one of the things he was like,
if your one is out of level due to someone else,
then that person will get punished.
- That was a beautiful segue from the word one
to the concept of one.
- Can I tell you one other thing about one?
- Oh, God. - Very nice.
- Who was this king, what was he called?
- King Dae Jong.
- Do you know what his birth name was?
- It was something different, I can tell you that.
- His birth name, considering he put a big drum
outside his palace, was Lee Bangwon.
- Lovely stuff.
But he really did, he was king from 1400 to 1418,
it was in the Chosun dynasty,
which is sort of the massive deal,
Korean dynasty went on for a thousand years.
And it was called the Sin Mungo Drum.
And it really was part of a system,
and there were three layers of appeal,
before you got to the drum,
you could go to your county level courts,
regional level, national level,
if they all reject your,
my kettle's broken complaint or whatever it is,
then you go to the drum.
- It's like, I wanna talk to your manager,
and if you don't get the manager,
I'm going straight to the drum.
- Exactly, exactly.
You bang on the drum, the king deals with it.
- Yeah, I do imagine that,
'cause the idea was that anyone could bang the drum.
But I feel like they would have made it quite clear
that this is a, are you really sure
you want to bang the drum?
'Cause if you hadn't gone through
these three layers of lower courts,
I'm sure you'd probably have been immediately executed
for even touching the drum, you know?
- Yeah, exactly.
- The king is a busy guy.
- He's a busy guy.
You're clearly an annoying customer,
if you've made it this far.
- He's a vexatious litigation in action.
- He was a killer, Taijong.
Friend of the podcast, by the way.
We have mentioned him before.
- We've got some questionable friends,
and we've never denied it.
- Yeah, we've mentioned him before.
He was the guy who, so this Joe's son,
period dynasty that we're talking about,
they used to have people writing every single thing down
about the royalty, and he once fell off a horse,
and he didn't want that recorded,
but what has then been recorded is him falling off the horse
and saying to the historians,
"Don't record this happening."
- Yeah, it's the Barbara Streisand effect.
- Yes.
- It's the earliest known example
of Barbara Streisand in the world.
- Exactly, but no, he did like to kill.
So you would be pretty brave to bang that drum.
- Who did he kill?
- So he executed the four brothers of his wife.
He executed his father-in-law,
his younger brother.
- That's a tough Christmas.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, he was-
- But to be fair, he executed people
who were quite high up the social strata.
- He was a progressive.
Is that what we're saying?
- I think he was progressive.
Well, in a weird way, he did,
like he really wanted to kind of democratize stuff in a way.
That's the whole idea of this drum is like,
he believes the common people are the ones to be trusted.
He's like, women and men are exactly the same.
Enslaved people are exactly the same as the nobles,
but basically what he wanted to do was crush noble power.
So yeah, he, I mean, any brother or brother-in-law
or step-brother who seemed like might overthrow him,
he really upset his dad,
who sounds like he was quite nice.
- What?
- Excuse me, I'm gonna throw in one brother-in-law.
- This was the guy who started the chosen dynasty, right?
- Yeah.
- By overthrowing the other dynasty.
- You don't start a dynasty without breaking a few eggs.
- Who hasn't overthrown a dynasty?
- Taijong was the king we're talking about with the big drum.
His father was known as Taijo.
And I think he sort of ousted his father from power.
There was a lot of strife,
a lot of people were killed off along the way,
a lot of rival claimants all bumped off.
So after Taijong became king,
his father, Taijo, was still alive and no longer king.
And Taijong started sending him messengers
to try and heal that breach.
Who his father then had beheaded as an indirect message
that he would never forgive Taijong.
- I think executing the messengers is a really shabby move.
- Yeah.
- It's not good, but-
- You can just send the messenger back
to the thing saying, "No, I do not forgive you."
- Also, I think when you do that,
you're supposed to like cut the hand off the messengers
so that he can go back and say, "Look what happened to me."
If you cut the head off,
you just stuck with the body of a messenger.
- Exactly.
- You just think my messengers must have got lost.
- Yeah, right, I'll send someone.
Hence he kept sending messengers.
What a horrible system.
- Yeah.
- I guess what I saw as this touching angle
is why he was angry though.
- Why was he angry then?
- He was angry because,
so Taijong had been king and then he'd abdicated.
People constantly abdicating, not dying.
And then he made another one of his sons king,
who Taijong overthrew,
and then Taijong killed a bunch of his brothers,
as we've said,
and his dad was just really upset with him
for killing his other kids.
So his dad was like,
"I'm so pissed off that you killed my kids."
- Yeah, yeah.
- And I think that's a few messengers' heads
that were gonna roll to punish your son.
- We've ascertained we're in terms of aristocracy
versus messenger court, Anna's loyalties lie with, okay?
- I like the way that all these things
where people's heads are rolling left, right, and center
are known as the first and second strife of princes.
- Yeah.
- It feels like they're underplaying it a bit.
- Yeah, we've got a euphemism, such things.
- I don't like any of the people involved, I should say.
- Yeah, they're all quite bad, aren't they?
- He was smart, Taijong.
He was the only king in the history of Korea
who passed the civil service exam.
- Really?
- Remember, we've said in the past,
they have these really, really tough civil service exams
to see who gets the jobs?
Well, he passed it and none of his brothers passed it,
but they also got into the civil service
due to the system that if your parents are really rich,
you get it anyway, which they had at the time.
But yeah, he got through this
and he decided he wanted to be a tattooist.
- Really?
- Yeah, 'cause it was a big deal job in the time.
If there was a criminal and they did something wrong,
you would tattoo the criminal with whatever they'd done wrong
so that people would know.
And it was a really important job
and that's what he wanted to be,
but then in the end he became king.
- Was there, 'cause some tattoos are quite subtle
and you can hide them.
I presume if you're the criminal,
you can't say, can you do it really small
and on my inner thigh?
Presumably it has to be like back of the hand or something.
Like I'm a purse snatcher or whatever.
- I think it was in specific, they had rules.
- Could you get extra tattoos after that one to kind of,
you know how people these days,
if they've got like an embarrassing tattoo,
they'll try and add to it too.
- Yeah, like what was it?
Oh, it's slightly the other way,
but Johnny Depp had Winona forever
and then got rid of it and it said, why no forever?
- Oh, yes. - Exactly.
Could you add extra things?
I can't think of how you'd adapt the phrase purse snatcher
to be benign, but mm.
- I am not a.
- Yeah, exactly.
- No, there were very strict rules about tattooing in general.
- But so this is the king who wanted to be the tattooist.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, he wasn't the king of the time.
He was just like a prince.
- Okay.
I got a little detail about his death
the day he died, Taijong, which is that,
so he abdicated, right?
Four years later, he dies.
And there's a thing which is drought
is often connected to your relationship with the gods.
And in the 1400s, it was believed
that royalty were connected to it.
So sometimes the king would go to an area
and if it rained, that would be seen
as a miracle brought on by the king.
So when he was in his dying day, the king himself,
he said, I'm gonna make it rain.
And on the day he died, it torrential rained
and for so long, it was like 10 days
to the point where it actually destroyed crops
because it was so much.
But this has been a legend, but people have gone back
and they found through all the records
that it did rain on the day that he died.
So it's seen as a miracle day.
- Is it a miracle if it rains?
I mean, I know Korea's not as bad as Britain.
And yeah, yeah, I can see that they really wanted it.
- I think that's often what happens in those circumstances
is it's been a drought for so long
and so the ground gets really hard.
And then you get a big rain storm
like you would naturally get after a lot of hot weather,
but there's nowhere for the water to go.
So it all kind of--
- Yeah, bloody floods.
And then God goes, well, what the hell did you want?
Everyone gets really upset about that.
What do you want from me?
Yeah, he abdicated because I think he wanted
to train up his son basically, who was Sejong.
And he basically is known as Korea's greatest ever leader
for lots and lots of reasons.
But partly 'cause I don't think he's the only king ever
to have invented a completely new alphabet from scratch.
And it's still the alphabet that they use today.
- I think what a pain in the ass
to invent an entirely new alphabet.
Because if you're the king,
everyone has to go along with your alphabet as well.
There's no way you can soft launch an alphabet
and say, well, we'll see if it takes off
and see if anyone starts using this new alphabet.
Do we know why he invented a new alphabet?
- Well, I think they were using the Chinese alphabet
which didn't match Korean noises at the time.
And so they were like, we need one that fits.
And he was very smart.
He was an academic.
So actually his alphabet was so good
that they've kept on using it.
- Well, that's very impressive.
I didn't know that.
I love the idea of workshopping an alphabet though.
Like just get some guys in, have some beers,
just see where it takes us.
- Make some of the noises you make every day.
- Yeah, that one, I'm gonna draw a symbol for that one.
- To reckon with the Beers thing,
that's why the end of the alphabet is so fucked up
with X, Y's and Z's.
Yes, everyone's just pissed by that place.
- It's a late night.
- Let's go for an X, what?
- Is that why he's sleeping in Z's?
- That's right.
- Have you never gone to the end of the alphabet?
It goes, W, X, Y, Z, vomit.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, time for fact number three.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the artist George Brack
once spent 10 days trying to get rid of a squirrel
that kept reappearing in his painting.
- This guy sounds like an idiot.
Once you just keep drawing the squirrel,
rubbing it out, drawing the squirrel.
- Yes, and it's a job, James.
You can be an idiot and make money.
So this obviously very famous artist.
I read this in a book.
We recently did a show with John Lloyd
and we talked about Picasso in it.
And off the back of it, I went on holiday
and I took Francois Gileau's autobiography,
which is her life in Picasso.
She talks about the fact that Brack and Picasso
had this moment where in their cubism period,
they were both staring at a painting
that Brack was painting.
And he just said, Picasso just said to him,
"What's that squirrel doing there?"
And he said, "Oh my God, what is that squirrel doing there?"
Now obviously there was no squirrel there,
but they could see the squirrel.
- 'Cause was it like, what would you call it?
Like-- - Impressionistic?
- Yeah, like an impressionistic painting
where it wasn't a picture of a bowl of fruit
and there's a squirrel in there, right?
- Well, no, exactly, but he was painting
a package of tobacco and a pipe.
- Oh, so it was still life.
- Yeah, it was still life.
- But it was just like in the corner,
it was like the shadows made it look like that, right?
- Yeah, exactly, and they could see the squirrel.
So he paints it away,
but as he's constantly transforming the painting
over the next eight to 10 days,
the squirrel keeps popping up in a new different place.
The squirrel returns.
And so he spends close to 10 days
until he invites Picasso back and Picasso and him both agree,
yes, the squirrel is now gone
and now they know that the painting is as it should be.
- Do you think there's a chance
Picasso never saw the squirrel
and just thought, I'm gonna psych out my mate here.
This is gonna really pit him off.
- Slow him down.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Let's get ahead.
- Let's deal with the competition.
I had never heard of Brack before this.
- Okay.
- Is he really, is he made for this?
- Well, they've found us
of Cubism where it's Picasso and Brack.
- Oh, okay.
- He's biggy, yeah, okay.
- In that world, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- He's bigger in the art world than in the cricket world.
(laughing)
- Is it, and this is Cubism that was,
sorry, not impressionism, Cubism.
So lots of different shapes.
- Yeah, Cubes.
- It's mostly, yeah.
- And what are we all except a selection of Cubes
arranged in a pile?
- Think of a Picasso painting, like a really wonky one.
- Yeah.
- You're kind of on the Cubism vibe there.
- Is this a perennial hazard for Cubist painters?
Like, what people constantly saying,
"I love that castle you've done."
You can say, "Yes, thank you very much."
- No.
- "Spent ages on the castle."
They're sweated over that.
- No, and this was, this is actually a really good point.
This is the main point about it,
is that Picasso was saying
you were painting something to be seen.
You were not painting an illusion.
So if we're seeing a squirrel in your painting,
you've painted an illusion.
You've allowed for it to be interpreted in this way.
- And this is all a form of something called "Paradolia,"
which is where you see faces or images
in something that don't really exist.
When you look in the sky and you see a cloud
and you think, "Oh, that looks like Mother Teresa or something,"
then that is because you're seeing things
that aren't really there.
- Well, why does she bless me then?
Why does she reach down and the cloud touches my nose
and I feel electricity?
What's going on there?
- Well, it is, "Paradolia" can be associated
with schizophrenia.
It can be associated with extreme creativity.
- Well, that's, can't be why I've got it.
(all laughing)
But is it, I read that it was also neurosis
and even conspiracy theorists are more likely
because they're forming patterns everywhere.
They're thinking, "That's an interesting coincidence.
That's interesting. That's interesting."
Maybe think of you, Dan.
You know, you're a very good at coincidence generation.
- Yeah, well, okay.
- So the usually faces more than the rest of us, maybe.
- I don't think so because I'm not a conspiracy theorist,
but the face on Mars is the most famous one,
I would say in the conspiracy world.
There was a photo that was taken by the Viking space probe
and you can see what looks like a giant face
on the surface of Mars.
That was found decades ago
and that has built a whole industry of ideas
that ancient aliens landed there
and built stuff and so on.
- And what proof is it of life?
Is it like someone died and they were a giant
and then they turned into a rock?
Just their face.
- Because actually, if you look at civilization today,
there aren't loads of faces.
It's loads of buildings.
- And tools and some bones.
It's so rare you just see a human face left over
from 4,000 years ago.
- As a representative of the conspiracy theorists,
I'd like to say there are people that believe it.
Next time you're at my house,
I've got about six books I can lend you,
which very much put forward that idea.
No, it's who knows.
They just thought it looked man-made
is rather what it is, is the main thing.
- Nazca lines, the shapes were viewed from above
and they say an abyss giant.
He's a big face on the ground and a whole lot else besides.
- Good point.
So people with faces also make faces.
- Yeah.
Do you know what?
Just on that word, pareidolia,
this idea of seeing faces and things,
Picasso had a theory that that is how art began to begin with.
He thinks that early man was looking around
and seeing faces in rocks and seeing,
and thinking, oh, why don't I
trace over that or why don't I try and mimic that?
- Well, there's evidence of that.
This is really cool.
So it's believed that maybe Neanderthals
also experienced pareidolia and early man.
There was a stone found, a pebble,
and it has a human fingerprint on it
and one red dot of ochre.
And that helps it look a little bit like a face.
It helps to make a little bit of a nose
in between a bit of pebble that looks like eyes
and a little bit that could look like a mouth.
And I read a study about it,
which was titled "More than a Fingerprint on a Pebble",
which is defensive to so- - Just a real question mark
on that.
- It was, no, it was "More than a Fingerprint on a Pebble".
Surely.
- That's better 'cause you made it sound quite desperate.
- Well, it dates back 43,000 years.
And they think it is evidence that early humans were saying,
oh, that looks a bit like a face.
I'll add a bit of art and a little one dot
and that'll make it look even more like a face.
So this is a long historical tendency we all have.
- Would make sense.
Seeing Jesus' face, that's a very common one to appear.
We all know what that looks like.
First time it appeared is in a 1977 flower tortilla.
So it was a woman called Maria Rubio
and she was making burritos for her husband in New Mexico
and she saw Jesus' face.
And it really is the famous face of Jesus in a tortilla.
She snipped out his face.
She took it to a priest at the local church.
She said, "What the hell's going on here?"
And the priest was like, "Well, you've been visited by Jesus."
And it actually sort of ruined their lives.
So thousands and thousands of people visited
from all across like Central and South America
and North America came to the house.
They displayed it in this glass case.
But people expected her to do amazing things.
They thought she could heal
and they thought she had these incredible powers.
So they'd come and they'd bring their sick children
and say, "Heal me."
And she, you know, she agonized over it.
She didn't want a profit out of the tortilla
and she wanted to help people,
but she couldn't heal them.
And she just said in the end it was a complete nightmare,
but she was too religious to destroy it
'cause you can't destroy the face of Jesus
once it's entered your home.
- Right, but once you smear guacamole on it,
you're not going to be able to see it anyway.
- It's what he would have wanted.
- What did she do with it?
- She kept it for years and years
and it broke of its own accord in 2005.
- With its own accord.
That's a miracle, like a tortilla that magically fractures.
- It'd be like a Jesus jigsaw.
Oh yeah, nice.
Maybe that's how the grandkids use it today.
- There might be a reason why Jesus is seen so much.
Although I know you get,
there's a famous Virgin Mary tortilla.
A lot of Mexican foods that the trinity are appearing on,
which is interesting.
- Yes, maybe it lends itself to faces
'cause it's got those little bubbles in it
that look like eyes and a nose, doesn't it?
- We once saw the devil in a chicken pacora.
- Okay.
- Lucky you.
- Back up a second.
- It's like it's not always Mexican food.
- No, you're right.
- Well, that's really food for thought.
- Yeah.
- What are you still doing on this podcast?
Shouldn't you be touring the world with your millions?
- Anywhere we called our pacora, Derek pacora.
- Oh, very nice.
- What did you do with him?
Is he in a glass cabinet somewhere?
- I eventually went in the bin.
We didn't eat him.
- Wow.
- Didn't you?
- No.
- Too scared.
- The devil's pacora, no way.
Was it a spicy pacora?
- I don't know, I didn't eat it.
- No.
(laughing)
- So the reason that Jesus might appear more
is a thing to do with pareidolia in general.
And that is that people think when they see a face
in anything that is male,
80% of the faces that people perceive,
whether, you know, it's just a collection of lines
or whatever, 80% are male.
- Is that patriarchy stuff?
- I think it probably is.
Unless they clearly have, you know, long hair,
lustrous eyelashes, a big science saying I am female
or whatever it is, people just think that's a bloke.
- Is it that, 'cause the two biggies really
are the Virgin Mary and Jesus, right?
But do you mean that there'll be a lot of men's names
in the mix and just the Virgin Mary?
- No, I guess we just see random faces most of the time, right?
We don't see usually Mary or Jesus,
we just go, "Ah, looks like a face."
- Yeah, I see.
- I think it's like if you were to draw a circle
with two dots where eyes might be
and a dot where the nose is in a line where the mouth is,
a lot of people just say, "Oh, look at that man."
- Yes.
- That kind of thing.
- Yeah, that's it.
I'm afraid I think it probably,
there isn't a better explanation than patriarchy.
- There never is, Andy. - Wow.
- Or a worse explanation.
- Even in shapes. - Wow, a lot of ways.
- Auditory Paradolia.
If you're walking through the woods,
there might be some wind rustling through the leaves.
There might be a water going by
and people often hear the names.
Ah, it does happen quite a lot, it seems, it turns out.
And it can happen with electric fans,
with airplane engines, with washing machines.
Anywhere where there's kind of white noise,
sort of uncertain what the noise is.
The reason is that your brain kind of just fills
in the gaps and so if this white noise,
this washing machine is making lots of weird noises
and a couple of those noises sound a bit like an a and a n,
then you would think, oh, someone said Anna.
But even though it's just like a few frequencies
that sound a little bit like those letters.
- It's not just people who are called things like,
"Pshh." (all laughing)
- The name takes an hour to pronounce,
but only half an hour if you put them on a quick cycle.
(all laughing)
I really like the thing of why this happens in general,
like the evolutionary theory as to why it happens,
which is that it is useful to us evolutionarily
to perceive a pattern where there may or may not be one.
So that particularly applies to, let's say,
if you're in an environment with predators,
it is more useful to see a bear
that is not there than not to see a bear that is there.
And there's a terrific book, actually,
called "The Tiger That Isn't,"
which is mostly a book about stats,
but it's really good about finding signals
and patterns and all that.
It's a great book about maths.
But yeah, that seems to be the reason why it happens
and maybe that it's useful to see faces
because you might be--
- Yeah, just keep us prepared.
- And just you're lonely
and you want to hang out with someone.
- We're social creatures.
The only reason we've been successful as a species
is that we're team players and like anyone else.
What does that require?
It requires us to spot faces.
- Does it matter that nine out of 10 faces we spot
are actually dots on a PCOR or?
(laughing)
- You've got so many friends
until it's pointed out to you that actually--
(laughing)
- Eating alone in the Indian restaurant
at a 10-person table again.
(laughing)
- And then like to go right to the modern day,
if you are sitting there
and you think your phone is vibrating in your pocket
and it isn't vibrating in your pocket,
that's another kind of paradox.
- I've got that.
- And that's because you've got it right now.
- Not right now, but I have it almost daily.
- Oh, it's extremely common.
- I've been calling you for weeks, Dan.
(laughing)
- I thought I'd been chatting to you.
Was that the wall with a dot on it?
(laughing)
- And again, it's just the brain sort of like
feels some kind of vibration
and remembers all the other times it have vibrated there
and then just fills in the gaps.
- I get that a fair bit.
But Dan, do you think it's anyone in particular ringing?
As we know now it is Anna,
but do you think, do you think, oh my agent?
You know, like, if there's someone you hope is.
- No, no, I don't.
- Hello, don't try the speaking.
I'm free, I'm ready.
(laughing)
Half my usual rate, I'll do it.
- Idiot fire.
(laughing)
- Rodeo clowns are us.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Andy.
- My fact is, across the world,
there are over a hundred serious collectors
of airline sick bags.
Serious.
- How serious?
- I'm not talking amateur hour.
Oh, I have a draw, but I don't do it much.
You know, these are players.
- Yeah? - Yeah.
- These are traders, they are curators.
- Absolutely. - Yeah.
- There is a community and it's thriving.
It's hopping.
- How many qualifies as serious then for you?
- Well, I wouldn't talk to anyone
who had less than a hundred and fifty, five.
- I think that's fair.
How many do you have?
- I don't have any, I'm just a reporter in this world.
But so, I mean, the figures vary.
One article I read said a hundred collectors,
another said 250.
They could fit into a medium-sized theater, definitely.
And there are some record holders.
There's a guy called Nick Vermeerlund,
who I believe has most,
certainly in the mid 6,290 as per a CNN article.
Yeah, as of 2012, he may have collected more since,
his wife may have persuaded him to throw them out since.
We don't know, but he had that many then.
Yeah, so he's got maybe most that have ever been had.
- That's pretty cool. - It's not.
- Why do they do it?
- Oh, you know, you've got to pass the time, haven't you?
- I read one person called Steve Sildberg,
who told CNN that he'd collected them
because nobody else collects them.
He'll be gutted to hear this episode of Fish Money.
- He's great.
- So he has 3,000 more than,
and he runs airsicknessbags.com,
which is a really good website for those
wanting to get into it.
- It's amazing what it throws up.
- Oh, God.
- He writes, while this website and hobby
is an enormous waste of time,
I like to think it's a high-quality waste of time
than many other places on the web.
And he's just really good.
- Look at some of his examples on his website.
- Go on.
- The Duke makes us puke from 1988,
which was given out at the Republican National Convention,
referring to Mike Dukakis.
- That's good.
- There was the Hen Knight Party Bag from 2005,
which is a British sick bag.
And each bag displays a vomit stain
and exhorts you to place gob here and heave.
And it comes with the caveats.
Please dispose of properly, do not reheat,
not suitable for home freezing.
- Jesus.
(laughing)
- So good.
His site is great.
So yeah, Steve or upheave Steve, as he's known.
He is one of the major baggists, as they're known.
And it is, as James is saying,
it's sort of like, it's not just airline bags.
You've got horror movies used to do novelty bags
that you would give out as well
for people that might barf in the cinema.
He collects those.
NASA, he's managed to track down a few
of the air sickness bags that went up with astronauts
and so on.
- Are they mostly used?
- No, no, no, no, these are pristine.
- Never used.
- No, of course they wouldn't fit flat in the archfiles,
if you--
- I did look for some though on eBay.
I did think there must be an air sick bag
that was vomited into by Taylor Swift
or something going for thousands,
but couldn't find anything.
- Thank God, that's your wife.
(laughing)
You said about the horror movies,
they still do that today.
Terrify 3 that came out earlier this year.
If you went to the first screening of that,
they gave you some sick bags,
Saw 10, which came out last year.
They gave it you as well.
- Saw 10?
- Yeah.
It was a pretty good one, Saw 10.
- What was it?
- The Human Centipede, The Passion of the Christ,
The Mark of the Devil,
all different movies where they gave sick bags
out to the audience, especially in the screenings.
- The Passion of the Christ.
- Yeah, in Belfast, when it was shown in Belfast.
- Wow.
- It was a blasphemy, presumably.
- Actually no, because there are some violent bits in it.
- Oh yeah, I think it gets pretty,
I don't know if you'd know how the story ends, Anna,
but it's not a PG.
- But it's just that the sick bags are a gimmick
for what I assumed were B horror movies,
saying, "Ha ha, look how scary we are."
I thought The Passion of the Christ
took itself a bit more seriously.
- Yeah, I think it was like the theaters did it,
and I think they were trying to make a point a little bit
by ironically, 'cause I went to watch that in Belfast
and got a sick bag and vomited in it.
- You're kidding.
- But when I looked in it,
it looked just like Jesus Christ himself.
(both laughing)
- He got hit by lightning.
- Who, Mel Gibson?
- No, the actor who played Jesus
in The Passion of the Christ.
That's one of the famous on set stories.
- He got struck by lightning.
- It's very hard to get down from that cross
quickly when the storm starts.
(both laughing)
- Fortunately, the cross was made out of tonka bean tree.
- The two thieves who are on either side of it,
they got it much more.
- That's how, I'm sorry, he got hit by lightning.
- That's a story that's online,
and I'm only just saying it out loud
'cause it's the connection between lightning and that,
so it might be wrong, but it's, yeah.
- Weirdly, one thing that always gets hit by lightning,
sorry, this is a telescope back to earlier in the show,
is the statues of Jesus that it's always happening.
Christ the Redeemer gets hit several times a year
'cause it's very busy.
- Yeah, on the top of a mountain
in a very humid part of the world.
- I know, but it seems like a sort of event for God
is zapping statues of Christ.
It seems like he's saying all the time,
"Look, I want you to try something else."
Anyway, Steve Silverberg, he has a loving partner,
we should say, of whom he says, "She's amused by it,
"but has no interest in getting involved."
And he's had some bad experiences in the past
before he met his lovely partner
of women who just didn't like it.
- Is there not something to raise on the first date,
I would say, would be my advice to a sick bank collector.
- That's more of a third date kind of revelation.
- That's exactly it.
So he, at one point, at his work,
he was introduced to a new colleague
and the person introducing them said,
"This is Steve, he works in IT and he collects sick bags
"and we've never got on from then onwards."
I think that's a tough introduction to recover from.
- It's all right, well, all right.
- He's great though, I think he's really cool.
- The sick bag was invented by Gilmore Tillman Schendhal
in 1949, who later made the world's first
communication satellite.
It was a way that you could have live television
that was going from one side of America
to the other by bouncing it off this satellite
that he invented.
- That's cool.
- And it was the same technology really,
'cause he made plastics.
And he invented the idea of being able to put plastic
on the inside of a bag so that when you throw up in it,
it doesn't all leak out.
- It's pretty obvious, isn't it?
You've got plastic bags, you've got paper bags,
he just put them together.
- Someone needed to do it.
- I could have done that.
- Someone needed to, and he did it.
I couldn't have made the first satellite,
but I could have done the bag thing.
- But the satellite thing was, again, it was plastics.
And what he invented was the thing that allowed everything
to be stuck to the satellite without all falling off.
- Okay.
- Basically, all the reflective stuff.
- And he's kind of more known for the bag, isn't he,
than the satellite, and that really annoyed him in his day.
- No, it did.
In his life title, all the quotes from his wife and so on
just said this is what dogged him his whole life.
Everyone always brought up the sick bags
rather than him.
- It's 'cause most people can't collect
communication satellites.
I still think a little bit of a sense of humor failure, mate.
I think you've got to own it, right?
- Yeah, I agree, I totally agree.
Interestingly, there's a big complaint going on around
the world right now amongst the baggists,
because it's a dying art.
Sick bags aren't as prominent as they used to be.
And if they are there now,
they kind of plain largely in a lot of cases.
There used to be great designs,
like there's a deer vomiting on one,
which is apparently really loved, beautiful design.
There's funny jokes on a bunch of them.
Now, because plane flights are getting less turbulent
because we're flying so much higher,
it's getting a bit more safer.
People aren't using them as much.
So air sickness is going down,
hence they're investing.
- Well, do you know, actually, I looked into this
and people have never been sick on planes.
Even the 1930s, they did a study of 0.2%
of people with sick on planes they found.
I don't know why we've been using them for so long.
They, and I have always thought...
- Well, I mean, if you're on an aeroplane
and there's 600 people, someone's gonna get sick, right?
If it's 0.2%.
- When it's that rare,
and I don't want to put the responsibility
always on the individual,
but just bring your own sick bag.
- Are you sure that I think--
- I don't think that if I'm working on that aeroplane
and someone's getting sick,
I don't want to be, well,
I don't mind if you vomit everywhere
because you should have brought your own bag.
- Fair enough, fair enough.
- It's your seat, you know, you pay for it,
you do your own it.
And also, I think if someone gets off the plane
that they haven't used their sick bag,
you don't have to replace it.
- That's a good point. - So it's a relatively low cost.
Once every seat has one sick bag,
you only need to replace one sick bag every 500 flights.
- That's a really good point.
- The Hermes Birkin bag.
Anna, I know you're deep in the world of high fashion.
- I am, yes, yes.
- Jane Birkin. - It's one of my favorite bags.
- Yeah, Jane Birkin.
- I've been reading nonstop about that bag.
Well, it started as a drawing on an airline sick bag.
Cool. - Sorry, what is it?
- It's a bag.
It's a very famous fashionable bag.
- Oh.
- It's got a picture of a vomiting tear on it.
(laughing)
- And it's not a sick bag.
- No, it's not. - It's not a fashionable sick bag.
- It's just a fashionable bag.
You can be sick in it, help yourself.
- If you bought it, no one's stopping you.
It'll be the most expensive truck up of your life.
- She was a very famous actor and singer,
both in England and France during the '70s.
And yeah, she was sort of an it girl
as well as being a super talented singer.
- Well, she was also good at drawing bags.
She ended up on a flight next to the head of Hermes.
And she told him I always need a big bag
to carry all my stuff around.
I think she might have been a recent mom at the time
and you know you need a lot of paraphernalia.
- I feel like he saw her bag fall down
and all the bits fell out.
And they wanted to design something
that meant everything to her.
- Something just workshopped.
I mean, I think this story has given a lot more creators
that they designed a slightly bigger bag basically.
Like the story of how she drew this bag
on the L1 sick bag, she drew a bag.
- This is as impressive as putting a plastic bag
inside a paper bag, you know.
You made a bit of a bigger bag.
Well done. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Some other stuff on collectors.
- Oh, yeah. - Yeah.
- The largest collection of silver coins in the world
exists thanks to cost 11 crisis.
That was a crisis that was had
by Jose Manuel Costa-Lavin, a Mexican man.
- Oh my God.
- Yeah, Costa-Lavin.
- Costa-Lavin crisis.
- Oh, wow.
- Jose Manuel Costa-Lavin got cancer
and decided to distract himself from the cancer
by traveling the world looking for silver coins.
Now he's clear of cancer
and has the world's largest collection.
- Okay, I've just got a few questions.
(laughing)
- About the process of how you got to this fact.
Did you start with the pun and find the fact
that the fact appeared in you?
- I went through the Guinness World Records website
and looked for all the collectors,
which I think is about 120 pages.
- Okay. - And looked for any funny names.
So the largest collection of irons is 30,071
by a guy called Ion Chirescu from Romania.
And the largest collection of Pikachu memorabilia
is by someone called Lisa Courtney.
- Oh, Courtney. - Courtney Pokemon.
- Courtney Pokemon. - Oh, nice.
- And the largest collection of Superman memorabilia
is by a guy called Perfecto P. Ball Hag.
- Okay, so that's just an outright funny about name.
- Just a funny name.
- Perfecto P. Ball Hag.
Mr. and Mrs. Ball Hag.
He's gonna have a tough time in the playground.
We gotta give him a name.
- No, no, it's worse.
Actually, sorry, I misread it.
It's Perfecto P. Ball Hag, Jr.
(all laughing)
- It's toughen me up.
It'll toughen him up.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland on Instagram, James.
- I've got a few TikToks on my TikTok account now,
which is no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy.
- I'm on Instagram @PerfectoPBallHag for third.
(all laughing)
Andrew Hunter M.
And Anna, if they wanna get to us as a group.
- You can go to Instagram @NoSuchThingAsAFish
or @NoSuchThingOnTwitter
or you can email our podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
Check everything out that is up there.
There's all our previous episodes.
There was a link to Club Fish,
our secret place where we put up bonus episodes,
ad-free content and so on.
It's really good.
Or you can just come back here next week
'cause we will be back with another episode.
We will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)