(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, Merry Christmas and a happy new year
from all of us at No Such Thing as a Fish.
Hope you had a nice Christmas.
If not, I hope it was manageable at least
and I hope we're all looking forward to
what is in store for 2025.
We've taken a little bit of a break this week
after a very, very busy year
where we've written all sorts of books
and been on tour around the world
and what we have for you instead of a normal episode
is a compilation of the best bits
that didn't quite make it into the show
from our UK, Ireland and Sweden leg of our tour.
So what you'll get here is lots of silly things
that didn't quite fit in the show.
You get loads and loads of extra facts.
Really hope you enjoy it.
But I don't really wanna keep up any more of your time
so all I'll say is happy new year and on with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- We ran out of QI by himself.
- Yeah.
- Which was No Such Thing as a Fish.
- No Such Thing as a Fish.
- No, seriously, it's in the OX office.
- From the QI offices in Covent Garden.
- And then at the end,
it turns out you get to run over by a train.
- Let me just do one more thing about Mars.
- Oh my God, I'm surrounded by idiots.
(upbeat music)
- Good evening and welcome to No Such Thing as a Fish.
Are you ready for the show?
(audience cheering)
Then please welcome to the stage,
No Such Thing as a Fish.
(audience cheering)
- Hi everyone.
Wow.
- Holy moly.
- Hey guys.
Thanks so much for coming.
- Hello.
- How are you guys doing?
(audience cheering)
Let's do this.
Welcome to our 10 year anniversary show.
Tonight is gonna be a party.
It's gonna be an awesome night.
We're gonna be celebrating your facts as well.
You've sent a bunch in.
Thank you very much.
James, you've been collecting them, right?
- Yes, I've got a few here.
For instance, Napoleon fell in love with Josephine
because she could do a naughty act called the zigzags.
And nobody knows what the zigzags were.
- Wow.
Really?
- Well, according to random person who texted me.
- Wow.
- And there's no better sauce than that.
Can we get the lights up on the audience, please?
Oh, hello.
- Oh.
- Oh, wow.
Oh, you guys are much more attractive
than I thought you were gonna be.
(audience laughing)
Okay, here is a fact sent by someone in this room.
This is brilliant, actually.
Between Heathrow and Rome, from takeoff to touchdown,
the flight time is the exact run length time
of the 2000 film "Gladiator."
If you've got a window seat on the right side of the plane,
you'll be flying over the Colosseum as Maximus and Commodus
enter the arena for the final battle.
- Fuck off.
- That's great.
- That's amazing.
- Wow.
Isn't that great?
- Very good thing.
- The blue whale produces the largest fart bubble.
(audience laughing)
It's so large, a zebra who makes the loudest fart
can fit in it.
(audience laughing)
- Oh, gold.
- In Tudor, England, there was a type of criminal
called a bear top trickster.
A woman would flash her breasts to lure men into a house.
Once he'd come inside, brackets, the house,
he would be robbed.
(audience laughing)
- He would be what?
- Robbed.
- Oh, he would be robbed.
- Oh, okay.
- That's very cool.
- Yeah, the funny bit was the brackets bit, really.
- Yeah, yeah.
That's good, thanks.
When dragonflies get tired, they suck water up their bum
and jet it out to propel themselves forward.
(audience laughing)
- That's so cool.
- It's funny 'cause I would have thought
that's quite tiring in itself.
- It does feel tiring, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- I'm just clenching now, and yeah, yeah.
- Have you guys read about a story I love last year
is about probably the two most influential writers,
academics, who write about honesty,
who have released a bunch of papers.
We definitely have come across them in our work.
They released a very famous paper
sort of showing that basically,
if you nudge people a certain way,
they'll be more honest.
So, for instance, in a dinner.
- Which part of their body do you have to touch?
(audience laughing)
- No one did that.
It's against sort of like study principles,
but if you have to sign a bit at the top
of your tax return that says,
"I promise I've told the truth,"
rather than at the bottom,
the study showed that people are more honest
'cause they've just signed this.
The thing is, these two famous people,
one of whom, Dan Ariely, wrote a book called
The Honest Truth About Dishonesty,
were cheating in the paper, allegedly, I have to say,
but were cheated in the paper,
and the data was falsified.
And not only falsified, but falsified in a way
that even I could tell because it's in two different fonts.
(audience laughing)
They just, the data that was true was in Calibri font,
and then there was a bunch of Cambria thrown in.
(audience laughing)
- Hey, I found the equivalent
to the American movie, 127 Hours.
You know where Ann Rolston gets stuck
while he's out on his own,
and his arm gets trapped underneath a boulder.
He eventually has to chop off his arm
in order to survive,
and he does that 127 hours into it.
So I found the British edition of it.
It should be called 60 Hours.
This is a man called Joe Galliat from Yoval in Somerset,
who spent two days underneath his sofa after it fell on him,
and he couldn't get out of it
because he had a few back problems,
and he only survived because when the sofa fell over,
a bottle of whiskey rolled towards him,
(audience laughing)
and he survived sipping whiskey for two days.
- What kind of substance?
- Until a neighbor noticed
that his curtains hadn't moved in two days
and thought something's wrong with Joe,
and they went and they found him,
and then he survived.
He spent five days in hospital,
but he said he was there for two whole days.
And at first he said, I took a sip of the whiskey,
and I thought, oh, well, this isn't too bad.
(audience laughing)
- What are they called?
The door sausages.
- Yeah, door sausages.
- What are they called?
- Trapped excluders.
- Yes.
- Door sausages, is that what you mean?
(audience laughing)
- Another insight into the Murray home life.
Another veil ripped away
from my carefully crafted persona.
(audience laughing)
Oh, well.
- I have to go as a translator
whenever you go to DFS, don't I, Andy?
(audience laughing)
He wants one of those brown marshmallow sitting things.
Sofa, yeah, he wants a sofa.
- Wow, what's James Harkin?
- Oh, there are no anagrams of that.
(audience laughing)
- Hey, speaking of storytellers from overseas.
Surely Shane Jerkin.
No, does that work?
- Wow, you just did that?
- Well, I don't know if it's right.
(audience laughing)
Come back in a few minutes.
- Yeah, yeah.
(audience laughing)
So there's another thing which happens around the world,
which, okay, no, let's just pause and watch Andy write.
(audience laughing)
- No, oh. - Use the E twice.
(imitates sound)
It worked.
No, it's Shane Jerkin.
(audience laughing)
- I worked at some more.
- You know who was one of the most rich people in America
off the back of Beavers?
Was John Jacob Astor.
And he became a billionaire,
and he's a name that a few of you might be going,
"John Jacob Astor, how do I know that name?"
He was at the time of the sinking of the Titanic,
possibly the richest man in America,
maybe even the world,
and he's one of the men who died on the Titanic.
And so his fortune was largely about Beavers.
And when I read that, I just thought,
I do wonder if in the final seconds of his life,
if he thought, "Friendly, we had a bunch of Beavers here,
"and we could have plugged this whole up in instinct."
- Yeah.
- What do you think?
- Maybe, maybe that was his final thought.
Or maybe, oh, I wish I'd worn my entire full body
Beaver onesie tonight, and then I could just swim away.
- Yes.
- I think that's weighing you down.
I do.
I think even lying on that door is not gonna keep you up
if you're wearing the full Beaver onesie.
- This is how I'd use my time travel moment.
If I got one time in a machine, that's where I'd go.
Not to save him, just to go,
"Andy and I have a bit of a bet going."
(audience laughing)
- Actually, did you know that,
sorry, speaking of ambassadors and names,
that the U.S. ambassador to Denmark
used to be called Dick Sweat?
(audience laughing)
And there was, this is 1998, 2001.
- When this goes out, someone who knows it's going,
"Dick, you made, you were on, no such thing as a fish,
"you gotta have a listen."
- No, I don't know why they're laughing at your name.
(audience laughing)
- They must have cut out the interesting bit
they said about you afterwards.
(audience laughing)
- Yes, he was.
His opponent actually campaigned to have his name removed
from the ballot paper 'cause he said,
"In the phone book, he's listed as Lantos Sweat,
"so it's not legally correct."
But obviously, his opponents just worried
that everyone's gonna vote for Dick Sweat
if they see it, right?
- Yeah, yeah.
I like, there was a guy called Soren Sorensen Adams
who invented a type of itching powder
which basically transformed the world of jokes, right?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Like this guy, I can't believe he's not a name
that I have known before this.
He did itching powder, he did the--
- The joy buzzer.
- The joy buzzer in your hand.
- He did, what did he do?
He did sneezing powder.
- The squirting flower.
- Squirting flower, the guy was a genius.
- He refused to do the whoopie cushion.
- Did he?
- He said that was vulgar.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- And this was the man behind the dirty Fido
plastic toy thing.
- What's that?
- That's the sort of fake dog poo.
- Oh yeah, and then fake vomit, he did as well.
- Did fake vomit?
And he said, no, whoopie cushion is too far.
So they went elsewhere.
- One of your earliest facts down was that whoopie cushion
was invented by a great ancient Roman.
So for him to say that was lowbrow.
- Oh, come on, you know, it's credited to an emperor
called Elagabalus, but his birth name was Bacianus.
(audience laughing)
The whoopie cushion was invented by Bacianus.
Like, it's the greatest fact that I've ever,
I feel like I was the first person to notice it.
Like--
- Unbelievable, the classical scholars
haven't pointed that out before.
(audience laughing)
- Fools.
- How many people do you think you could fit in a phone box?
- Oh, that's good.
- 'Cause this was a thing, wasn't it?
In the 1950s and '60s.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- Sort of classic red wall.
- You would get one of these classic phone boxes.
You would stuff as many students in as you can.
Well, they would stuff themselves in.
You wouldn't be able to do that.
- It was 'cause it was before the age of group Zoom calls,
wasn't it?
(all laughing)
- What ages are we talking here?
Like, are we allowed--
- They tended to be students,
so there would have been, I guess, teenagers.
- But you look down on if there's a tiny corner left
and you shove a one-year-old in there.
Like, is that--
(audience laughing)
- Well, this is the interesting thing.
Like, there were loads of different rules,
but the official rules, basically,
you had to be more or less adult-sized.
You had to get at least part of the greater portion
of your body into a standard upright phone booth.
- I'm going to say low ball and say three.
(all laughing)
- Ooh, yeah, two.
- Nine.
- I'm going to say 15.
- Okay, well, the answer,
the official record from March 20th, 1959, was 25.
- Whoa! - Whoa!
- But there was a Canadian school
that claimed to have got 40 students in a phone box,
but it was later found that they'd turned it on its side
and they used a much larger phone box than normal.
(all laughing)
So then they put the official rules in,
and the really amazing thing is that only in England,
they had an additional rule
that as well as all getting in there,
the group had to be able to either place
or answer a phone call while they were in there.
- Amazing. - So good.
(all laughing)
- In 2011, Chinese magician called Fu Yandong
his pièce de résistance was six goldfish
doing synchronized swimming.
(all laughing)
- Really?
- Yeah, 53 different animal rights groups complained
(all laughing)
saying it is quite clearly magnets in their stomachs
and they are being interviewed.
- Oh, God!
- Yeah.
- Oh, my God. - Oh, God, Andy.
- Do they check Olympians for that, for magnets?
(all laughing)
- Do you know that Simon Cowell and Ricky Gervais
look like Stonehenge?
- This is according to the clothing company, Jackamo,
who made the thing called the architecture of man.
And this doesn't really make any sense,
but apparently to train their staff,
they would choose famous people
and say what monuments they look like.
And that supposedly would help their staff
work out people's sizes.
I know, it doesn't make any sense at all.
- Why do you just say you look a bit like Ricky Gervais?
- Why goes through the needless answer to the step of,
you look like Stone7 from Stonehenge?
- I reckon probably less people would be insulted
by saying they look like Stonehenge
than they look like Ricky Gervais.
- Very true.
- Perhaps.
But yeah, so Ricky Gervais and Simon Cowell
look like Stonehenge.
Russell Crowe and Jay-Z look like the Tine Bridge.
And James Corden looks like the Gherkin.
(all laughing)
- That's amazing.
- Sorry, personal addings though.
But my friend, we were at a party once,
you guys know him, and he was a packed party
and he really needed the toilet.
And the window that was at the room led to an alleyway.
So he thought there's no one going to be walking there.
So he opened up the window and he peed out the window, right?
And about five minutes later the door gets kicked
into the room and this soaked man comes walking in,
going, who fucking pissed on me?
And we all had to go, that didn't happen here, I don't know.
But it's really hard to keep a straight face
when a man soaked in urine is angry at you.
- Sorry, that man must have stood still.
- I don't know.
- Underneath.
What sounds like quite a thick shower of urine.
- I never questioned why he was so soaked, yeah.
- Speak up your reaction.
- Who did that?
That's not in my life, you.
Give me your number.
- Oh God.
Wow, wow.
- If you're itching, you know why it's scratching works.
It's kind of interesting this.
- Oh yeah?
- I'm not sure it's funny, but it is interesting, okay.
Basically you scratch it and your body thinks
that something bad is happening to you
and that is more important than the itch itself.
And so the scratch sort of blocks off
the pathways to your brain.
So you've got a little itch, you scratch
and your body thinks, oh my God, someone's scratching me.
And then it concentrates way more on that
than it does on the itch itself.
What that means is if you have an itch,
it also works if you tickle yourself.
And it also works if you press down on it
or if you put something cold on it, it all does the same thing.
- So we could have been tickling ourselves all these years
rather than scratching.
- Exactly.
- Well there's even been studies that if you have an itch
on one side, it likes you on your left side of your body,
if you look in a mirror and you scratch
the other side of your body because it has the idea
that then you will get rid of the itch, yeah.
- Does that work for everyone or just idiots?
(audience laughing)
- Well, it works for idiots and me because I tested it
and it does work.
We sort of have Beethoven to thank for CDs.
Not the entire technology, but one very important bit,
which is the reason that CDs are the diameter that they are
and the length of time that they can take on as a recording
is because the man who invented them
wanted to be able to play all of Beethoven's ninth symphony
in one go without having to change the CD.
So he needed 75 minutes worth of music on there
in order to do it and that's what defined it.
That was his condition.
- That's really cool.
- And if you don't know what CD is, you can Google it.
- When Osama bin Laden was killed,
it was by SEAL Team Six, right?
Two days after SEAL Team Six took him out,
guess who tried to trademark SEAL Team Six?
- SEAL?
- That would be incredible.
- The singer SEAL.
- Yeah, the singer SEAL, no, Walt Disney.
The Walt Disney company tried, they--
- How would we have guessed that?
(audience laughs)
- Good point, yeah.
- It just would have been a long, first off.
- It was a long game.
- Is it because, well, is it because they were gonna make
like a cartoon with loads of SEALs
who went around killing terrorists?
- They were gonna, 'cause Disney's gone, obviously,
into more dramas, like, yeah.
And so they thought, wow, this would be an amazing series.
We'll do SEAL Team Six.
And so that was their first thought though,
immediately after Osama bin Laden died.
They have someone in their company who does that and goes,
let's trademark that.
And so, yeah.
But Disney are famously a benevolent
and charming corporation, I don't understand.
- What do you want them to do?
Have a month of mourning for Osama bin Laden?
I think fair enough, Disney.
- Bit of respect for the great man, he'd been good.
(audience laughs)
- And let's end on that, Dan.
- We actually do need to move on.
So that's annoying that we are ending on that, but.
(audience laughs)
Not great for my career.
(upbeat music)
(audience cheers)
- Yeah.
- How are we doing?
- Has anyone spotted what's missing from the stage?
And there's wine, that's correct.
- Yeah, I'm gonna have to do something so unprofessional.
I thought I'd save it for this.
Someone backstage, I forgot to bring my wine on
and I won't be able to make it through without.
Could you possibly fill right to the brim?
(audience laughs)
Thanks.
As you were.
(Dan laughs)
- It's like working with Gilgud himself.
(audience laughs)
- Quickly, 'cause you did say Gilgud,
laughingly compared me to Gilgud, but.
- Here's James, everybody.
Here's our tour manager, James.
- James Hingley, everyone.
(audience cheers)
- Save the show for this.
- As if Gilgud was the epitome of professionalism.
Was it not him who was once in the audience of a play
really pissed, he'd been at the pub all day,
he was with his mate and he leaned over to his mate
and whispered, oh, this is really good,
this is where I come on.
(audience laughs)
Pretty sure, so.
- Yeah.
- There's kind of caricatures that you get
on the street these days, where they're just rude about you
and you have to pay them with a tenner,
or whatever it is.
- Yeah, exactly.
- I've never had that done.
- Haven't you? - Because I'm too afraid to,
basically.
- But the thing is about you, Andy,
is you have no discernible features.
- Wow.
(audience laughs)
- Do you remember when people would draw fan art of us
and they'd have silly hair, glasses, woman's hair,
and just a stick figure?
- A guy, just a guy.
- Generic stick man for Andy.
- That did happen.
- Weirdly, it looks exactly like you
whenever we saw them.
(audience laughs)
- He actually, did you read,
there's just one other thing about George Cookshack.
So he was famous for being Dickens Illustrator as well,
he illustrated a lot of Dickens books,
and he claimed that he actually came up
with the whole plot for Oliver Twist
and said he wanted to call it Frank Foundling.
And so I think him and Dickens ended on slightly bad terms.
- Frank Foundling.
- Bad man.
- It could have been.
- It works, yeah.
- It's a bit decadent, yeah.
- But he was an obsessive bore of a T-totaler,
and he was once burgled, and he caught the burglar,
and while grasping him with one hand,
he felt his pulse with the other hand,
and noticed that it was the usual 75 beats a minute.
Therefore, had not been increased
by the exertion and the excitement at all,
and so he started expounding on the benefits of temperance
to the burglar that he'd caught, explaining,
"You see, it's because I don't drink, my pulse, feel it."
So the police came along,
he's still lecturing this poor burglar
who bit off more than he could chew about not drinking.
- That's so funny.
- What is a lunette?
Not the lunette, you might say.
- A lawn yet was the perspectacle, wasn't it?
A lunette is a light, a whole full of light.
- Torture thing?
- Yes, it's a torture thing.
- French torture thing?
- Yes.
- French accent?
- Not the lunette.
(laughing)
- It is the hole where you put your head through in a guillotine.
- Oh, very good.
- It's a lunette.
Probably they mostly just said not the guillotine, surely?
- Not the lunette.
- I don't think the specific detail of the hole
is what's worrying.
It's more what's above the lunette.
- I just like the idea of the guy who's gonna do the,
with the axe of the mask on going,
"Ugh, a connoisseur."
(laughing)
- Pleasure to meet you.
- Am I right that actually,
if you're having your head chopped off,
you never have to see the lunette,
because you can't fit your head through that hole, can't you?
Don't you put your neck on the, on the dip?
- Would you put it on the block?
- And then they put the thing down over your neck.
- Yeah, right.
- Oh, yeah.
- Maybe in some design.
So perhaps the one sweet relief
is that you don't have to see the lunette.
- You never see the lunette.
- Another cool protester,
I just like really, Wavy Gravy.
- Oh yeah, Wavy Gravy.
- I thought you'd be a Wavy Gravy fan.
He was the emcee for Woodstock,
hung out with all those beat generation people,
and he nominated nobody to be president in 1976.
I think it was.
And he was just really cool.
He had a son called
Howdy Doogood Gravy Tomahawk Truck Stock Romney.
- Is he in relation to Mitt Romney?
And do they socialize?
- Yeah, brothers, yeah.
He goes by the name Jordan.
- Here's a weird thing about the Queen's car.
She had multiple cars,
but they all had the same license plate number.
It was the same, she, yeah, had the red license.
- D1 GL1Z, was it, or something like that?
- No, it was a.
- Took a little while for some of you to work that out.
- It was, no, it was Jiggy 280.
- Jiggy?
- Yeah, Jgy 280.
And at any time that she got a new car,
she had that as the personalized license plate.
And I can't see if there's something
that was a reason behind it.
- What could it stand for?
- Yeah.
- It was just gallivanting.
You help me out here.
- Yeah, come here on the map.
- I thought it was very interesting,
researching this, that in China, they hate new car smell.
It's so weird.
So we famously love new car smell.
And they're always trying to replicate
that smell of a new car.
- So what, this is when you buy a new car.
- Yeah.
And it's got all the surfaces in it,
still have the new chemicals on them
that are gradually being released.
And, yeah, it's like.
- Delicious carcinogens, isn't it?
- Yes, exactly.
- Is it bad for you, new car smell?
- I believe it's bad for you.
- It's slightly bad for you.
They've done studies and it's like,
it's a little bit above what we'd recommend
you're inhaling.
So don't just sniff the seat,
let the seats in your car day after day.
But new car smell, the Brits really like it.
But in China, they've actually,
Ford have had to come up with an odour remover
for car smells because in China,
they hate it so much.
And in 2018, it was affecting car sales.
So they hired, in 2017, Ford hired 18 golden noses,
which were human beings whose job it was
to go inside a car and rate the smell
from not perceptible to extremely disturbing.
And then they'd work out ways to get rid of it.
And they patented a device in the end,
which basically drives your car to a clean area,
winds down the windows and airs it out.
And then senses when the car smells gone.
- Right.
- And then drives it back.
- That's cool.
- And Chinese people to buy it, isn't that weird?
- Yeah, do you know also,
you said that the new car smell being leather.
But actually, so Rolls Royce had a lot of complaints
that their cars had lost the leathery smell.
So they sent in this team,
they were called SG Gordon Limited,
to try and distill new car smell
so that they could put it into their new cars
that don't have new car smell,
so that it smells like a new car.
- Okay.
- And what ended up happening is that they discovered
that it wasn't the leather predominantly
that gave the smell.
It wasn't the wood that you would get in certain cars.
So a lot of cars now have replaced wood with plastic.
And so the mixture is-
- Who has a wooden car these days?
- Well, Rolls Royce, particularly,
yeah, would still have the idea.
I mean, it doesn't even matter who has that anymore.
That's where the smell of the old car came from.
- Oh, interesting.
But there are still some wooden cars.
And I think it is a combination of wooden surfaces.
I don't know.
- Yeah.
- I'm driving a car with wood in it.
Not a wooden car.
Like the Hogany on the inside and stuff.
- Ooh.
- Yeah.
It's when I was dating the queen.
(audience laughing)
- Bruce Lee against Superman.
That doesn't even work because he, in the movie,
he plays Kato from the Green Hornet,
which was the big TV show that Bruce Lee starred in in America.
So he had a big kung fu career in Hong Kong
and Chinese movies,
but he also had an amazing American career.
And Kato, as the Green Hornet was one.
So he's against Superman,
but Kato's part of the Batman universe.
So, oh wait, that's the same universe.
Scratch that, everyone.
(audience laughing)
I'll hand my nerd credentials back in.
There you go.
- I'll be honest, you lost me about two minutes ago.
- Yeah, take those credentials back, please.
- Do you know that water flows?
Do you know that water flows?
- Yeah, water flows.
- I would have to, otherwise it would all sink
to the bottom of the sea, wouldn't it?
- Hang on, some of it floats on the top, though.
- Water flows.
If you drop a meter of water in the middle
of some other water, it'll just stay there.
- So like different kind of water to--
- Oh no, they're different, yeah, yeah.
Like salt water and fresh water
are different densities, I believe, so yeah.
- But if you've got a whole body of normal tap water
and then you drop some more tap water in,
then it'll just stay there, bobbing around,
like it's the same place.
- It doesn't sort of like integrate,
it just sits on top.
- It doesn't sit on top like a Lego brick
on top of more Lego, it goes--
- Isn't that what floating is?
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, I mean, the other water's gotta move out of the way.
If you move your, I guess what I'm trying to say--
- Kyle and Andy, why is it that if I'm in a bath
and I want to make it hotter, and I turn on the hot tap,
I don't just get a small cube of really hot water
after the tap, and I don't have to put different--
- Well, that's 'cause you're swishing around
with your rubber duck and all that.
That's like, that's you being the wave sister.
But milk doesn't float despite the name, Milk Float.
- Right.
(audience laughing)
Jesus Christ.
So don't leave your cube of milk on top of the ocean.
(audience laughing)
You'll never see it again.
- There is a thing called, what is it, dendrophilia,
which is basically the sexualization of trees.
I mean, that is a real thing that happens.
I found a Wikipedia page on it.
It's the most interesting write-up I've ever read
on a Wikipedia page, says many people use vegetables
and fruits such as cucumbers or carrots
to insert into their anus.
- Whoa, whoa.
(audience laughing)
As an object to receive sexual pleasure or orgasms
when they masturbate, in men, holes can be used
inside trees or trunks, assimilating the shape
of a vagina through which the penis is inserted.
- Why are you reading this, Dad?
(audience laughing)
- Well, this is the relevant bit.
- Why did you have to read all that film?
- Many people experience feelings toward plants
after having sex in a garden, forest, greenhouse,
or bedroom with many plants.
(audience laughing)
The use of flowers to caress the body
is also included in tendrophilia.
And that's, so it's a big thing.
- Can I tell you a cool thing about smell
that is amazing in insane?
Okay, get this.
Right, what do you smell with?
- Your nose.
(burps)
- You don't smell with your, so this is amazing.
The nose is merely the pipe that takes the smells
to where you really smell.
(audience laughing)
The place you smell, I'm gonna do a big boop
with my finger pointing to where you actually smell.
- Oh, this'll be great on audio.
(audience laughing)
(burps)
- Wow.
- Your eyebrows?
- In the level of your eyebrows--
- In between your eyebrows.
- Right in between your eyebrows.
Okay, the air goes up into your nose.
Sure, we all know that.
And then it curls around these little structures
which carry the scent molecules
of what you're trying to smell, right?
That's the most important thing.
They stop on the mucous membrane,
and this is where it is.
It's level with your eyebrows,
and that's where the smell molecules actually get detected
and received by this mucous membrane.
- So could you cut out the middle man
and just drill a hole in between,
in like the Frida Carlos spot?
- Yep, yep, yep, you could, yeah, yeah.
- We should do that.
- We recommend it.
(audience laughing)
- Wow.
- Isn't that amazing?
- Yeah.
- That's where you smell.
- Very cool.
- You think you smell with your nose, sure,
but you don't.
- Yeah, it's just a vehicle.
- Why isn't anyone more shocked about this?
- They're stunned into silence.
- It's not your nose is a place pretty close to your nose.
(audience laughing)
Inside what probably you could probably say is your nose.
- Wait, let me do the eyes now, let me do the eyes.
(audience laughing)
- I got one thing as well,
which is this is just for anyone
who's listened to this fact and gone,
ah, if only I could read something
about someone having sex with a tree.
I just realized I read an entire novel in my 20s
about this exact thing.
It's called a melon for ecstasy,
and it's all about a guy who goes around shagging trees, right?
- So, Dan, I am not remotely surprised
that you read this novel.
I feel like I'd be stagnant if you hadn't read it.
- Also, when does Dan's butt club podcast come out?
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, so basically the increased holes
bored into the trunks of local trees,
all of them 33 inches from the ground
at an angle at between 15 and 20 degrees
to the horizontal attracts the suspicion of the police.
(audience laughing)
It infuriates the council who see it as vandalism
and excites ornithological society members
who believe it indicates the return
of the fabulously requested woodpecker.
And the whole story is about the guy.
- There's some kind of pecker that is chasing.
(audience laughing)
It's an amazing book, a melon for ecstasy.
Everyone needs to get it.
Yeah, his main worry is not being caught.
It's all the splinters he gets as he's doing it.
- Oh my God.
- Anyway, we should move on, right?
(audience laughing)
- That was your choice to do that.
- I know.
(audience laughing)
- Oh, I did it.
(upbeat music)
- You ready for more facts?
(audience cheering)
Thank you everyone who sent in a fact to us already.
So James, what do you got, mate?
- Oh yes, and this is the bit where I read one out, isn't it?
That's fine.
- Slick.
- We spend a lot of time rehearsing this show.
- Here's the fact.
At Prince Now King Charles and Diana's wedding,
the head waiter got a black eye from the queen.
I know this because said head waiter of Claridge's
is my grandfather.
- Wow.
- Is this from Dan?
(audience laughing)
- Extra details.
She, the queen, danced into a giant apple decoration
which swung into his face.
(audience laughing)
She then followed him into the kitchen
to make sure he was okay.
- That's nice.
- Nice, isn't it?
Okay, here's another eyebrow one.
- Yeah.
- The common adjectives used before breasts in books
are in order, left, full, big, right, and ample.
- I thought in...
(audience laughing)
I thought in order was one of them when you said that.
- And that was said by someone who had
a large machine learning data set at work
and worked it out for themselves.
- Wow.
That actually, that was another death by the way,
like a torture thing that they used to do according to legend
which is they would take two trees
and they would tie them together.
So they would bend them right in
and they would hold a rope that was holding them tight
and then they would take the offending criminal
and they would attach a rope to either side of the tree.
Some say with just one leg to each tree
and they would cut the rope
and the trees would fling away
and you would be ripped in half.
- Yeah, yeah.
- But is it like a wishbone where
whichever tree got the big at heart?
(audience laughing)
- You're right, it should be like a cracker.
There should be a joke on one side of that, yeah.
- That was a thing that did happen,
not just in the personal part, I think,
'cause Saint Corona died in that way.
- Really?
- Yeah, patron saint of viruses.
- No.
- No, but like Saint Corona, I don't know what--
- Saint Corona had a giant mime shoved into his throat.
I'm pretty sure.
- Do you know how a tosser died actually?
- No.
- This is according to a Spasius
who was writing in the first century.
So quite a long time after,
but a Spasius said she was killed
and eaten by her son Xerxes in a fit of distraction.
- A fit of distraction?
- Oh, further information.
And I don't even know who was distracted.
Who was he?
He was eating a steak
and accidentally got his mum on the way.
- Oh my God.
Hey, you know, just super quickly back
to Dennis Popp and Ace of Base.
There was a thing that he used to do,
which eventually a lot of other pop musicians would do as well,
which was called the LA Car Test.
And the idea was you were gonna be able to make it in America
if your song was good enough to be played in a car in LA.
So what he would do is he would take finished songs
and he would send them over to LA
and he would people over there, drive on the highways,
listening to the songs in cars, going, "Yeah, man, groovy."
- That's cool.
- Yeah, and that's the LA Car Test.
So songs were deliberately like fixed or given a boost
simply by what the response was.
- That's so interesting.
'Cause like we always, like with podcasts as well,
you're supposed to play it in a car as well
because the audio is slightly different.
So if your audio is not quite right,
it's different if you hear it in headphones
than if you hear it in a car.
So I wonder if it's something like that.
- Do you do that when you're editing our show?
Do you go out for a drive?
- No, 'cause it's so funny.
I would just veer off the road.
No, if there's a slight audio problem,
I will do that, yeah.
- Do you?
- Yes.
(laughing)
- Get in the car.
- That's amazing.
(laughing)
I think that's really cool.
I think that's really cool, guys.
- Don't you agree?
Yeah, there you go.
- I don't think they,
that didn't sound like you really meant that.
- No.
(laughing)
- Can I just, on older people lying about things,
there was a big thing in the 1950s.
There was suddenly this hunt
for the last remaining US Civil War veterans.
And there was a guy called Walter Williams
who was declared in 1959 to have been
the last surviving veteran who then died.
And there was this massive week of official mourning
in Houston, there was a funeral procession,
more than 100,000 people came to line the streets
to say farewell to this guy,
the last person who'd been there.
In the 90s, a researcher looked into it,
found out that he'd been eight when the war ended
and definitely had not fought in the American Civil War.
But not only that, looked into all the other veterans
in the 1950s who were saying they were the oldest surviving
and they were all fake.
So, the person who acclaimed the oldest living veteran,
the oldest surviving veteran title from, was another phony.
The researcher found that every one of the 12
last remaining people to have survived the Civil War
had not fought in the Civil War.
There'd been a--
- Did they meet up and just occasionally look at each other
and go, "I know, I know, me either."
- They did, there was a reunion.
He said there'd been a veteran's reunion
and all the veterans who'd gone must have just been going,
"Yeah, you remember Alamo, was that Alamo?"
Yeah, and Dave, yeah.
- How weird is that?
- This is from 2011.
This is a statement that was put on a paintballing website,
okay, these are the words.
"Due to an incident at our Croydon Paintballing Center,
"you will be given special information
"on the dangers of paintballing with enhanced boobs
"and asked to sign a disclaimer.
"You will also be issued with extra padding
"to protect your implants while paintballing."
This was put up there because during a paintball session,
someone was shot in the boob and it exploded.
And apparently it was ruptured after it was hit
and this has been a huge problem, apparently.
It's very dangerous to have enhanced boobs while paintballing.
- A huge problem. - Yeah.
- That's it.
I was looking up some well-known clowns
and a well-known one in Britain working today
is Matty Faint, who's co-curator of the Clown Museum,
or who was that a couple of years ago, at least,
and he does kids parties and a lot of clowns now lament
the decline of the clown and they blame Disney.
Like a lot of entertainers now come to kids parties
dressed as Disney characters instead of clowns,
things like that.
But he said recently he did a kids party,
so he went to the kids' house and he performed as a clown
and it went down dreadfully well.
20 children laughing their asses off.
And then the mum said, "Thanks very much."
Paid him by and then he went upstairs to get changed
into his normal clothes and he came downstairs,
at which point the mother turned around,
saw him, grabbed him by the throat, shouting,
"Who are you? What are you doing in my house?"
LAUGHTER
'Cause to her, it's just a weird man
and normal clothes coming down her staircase.
That's so good. It's a dangerous job.
Here's a great Croydon Flight anecdote
from the Golden Age of Travel, right?
Uh-huh. And this is at a time when pilot nicknames included
Dizzy, Count Vodka, and Scruffy the Undertaker Robinson.
So there's a, like, you're in safe hands.
This is in 1924. There was a flight from Croydon to Paris
and someone looked out of the window and saw,
on the wing of the plane, as the plane was in the air,
a mechanic on the wing trying to fix the throttle mid-air.
Wow. Because he was trying to repair it.
He realised he couldn't, so he just stayed on the wing of the plane
for the entire flight to Paris.
Hang on. He had got on after it took off, right?
It wasn't like he was doing it on the ground
and then they forgot to tell him they were taking off.
I am not sure.
I think he climbed out in mid-air.
How do you do that, Andy? How do you do that, Andy?
He just held it open until the plane landed.
Well, they didn't use to fly very high, did they?
They flew really, really low. Yeah, they were going at 30,000 feet.
But they still fly fast.
Again, at the time, not very fast.
It's still scary.
There's no height of plane flight where I'm like,
"It's not actually that high. Don't really mind."
Yeah, I'll get on the wing.
It is scary. That's why this was a news story at the time
and why I think it's a relevant anecdote now.
Yeah. Yeah. It was scary and hard for the guy.
That's the point. Yeah.
So there was a study in 2019 about learning from your failures.
And basically, the conclusion was that failure
is an essential ingredient to success.
You have to fail to be successful.
But that doesn't alone make you successful.
You have to learn from your mistakes.
But I just found it so interesting in terms of, like,
the cold, hard-eye of academia, the way they worked this out.
It was a huge study and it looked at three different things.
So it looked at 777,000 grant applications
submitted to the Institute of Health
to see if they were successful or failures.
It looked at 46 years' worth of startup investments
to see if businesses were successful
or whether they were failures and what was the cause of that.
And it looked at 170,000 terrorist attacks
to see if they were failures.
And I think that's a bold thing.
And I don't know what involved, but it concluded,
and it looked, you know, a successful terrorist attack
is obviously a failure for most of us,
but a success for certain people.
So reassuringly, the test found that for,
if you're looking for a grant,
if you're trying to get a grant from the Institute of Health,
the average failure rate is 2.03 failures before you succeed.
For a startup, 1.5, and terrorists fail almost four times
before they succeed.
So, and we've got to cheer one person
cheering for the anti-terrorist brigade.
Well, as we all know,
Dan thinks her son of the laden is a great guy, so...
It's Maria Therese, the Queen of France.
So she was Spanish, but she was the wife of Louis XIV.
Oh, yeah.
She was in labor in 1661.
And in the old days, if you were royal,
it was basically open season for your birth.
Oh, everyone would come and watch?
Everyone just came and watched.
So when Maria and Therese gave birth,
there were nearly 200 people in her chambers,
mostly in an outer room,
but quite a few in the inner room as well.
And when Maria Therese, sort of a century earlier,
was giving birth,
lots of princesses and various dukes
started coming in to witness her giving birth.
And she hated it. She kept shouting,
"I don't want to give birth. I want to die."
And she had to shout that
because there were Spanish actors and musicians
dancing a ballet beneath the windows.
And they had guitars and casinettes
to remind her that she was Spanish.
(LAUGHTER)
There is another study.
This is an amazing one, where they looked at surgeons
who were doing coronary bypasses.
Right.
And they looked at ones that were successful
and the ones that were failures.
And they saw, if you did a failure,
were you going to be more successful in the future?
So have you learned from your mistakes?
Yeah.
And what they found was that actually that is true.
So surgeons who made mistakes,
they did tend to get much more successful as they went on,
but only to a certain level.
And after a certain amount of failing again and again and again,
you just get really, really shitted it.
Really?
Because you're just like, "Oh, I can't do this."
You just lose all confidence.
Yeah, right.
You're stuck in a rut.
I have that with getting facts right.
(LAUGHTER)
I've just given up at this point.
Yeah.
So I named my son Ted.
His middle name is Harpo after the Marx brother Harpo.
But Harpo is Oprah Winfrey's company as well.
I would assume that that would have been trademarked,
but I had no problems.
Oh, my God.
Oprah is Harpo backwards.
(LAUGHTER)
Yes.
And that's why she named the company that.
Oh, she knows that.
Okay, fine.
(LAUGHTER)
Well, um...
What a wild ride for you for five seconds.
That was huge.
I've got to move this on.
Oh, really?
Yeah, we need to get out of here.
Can I tell you about Mandels?
What?
Oh, I don't know.
Mandels.
These are male candles.
Okay.
'Cause there's a big problem for the candle industry,
which is that they're only hitting half the population.
Women tend to buy, like, more than 90% of candles.
Men tend not to buy them.
Okay.
And there have been consistent attempts to get blokes to buy candles.
So scents published have included aftershave, fine.
Chrome.
(LAUGHTER)
Fine.
The browser.
Smoked leather.
Okay.
Rome.
(LAUGHTER)
Not a Roman candle like a firework.
Just the smells of Rome.
(LAUGHTER)
And there's one exhaust.
And I just wanted to read you the...
(LAUGHTER)
Like, here's the blurb.
Do you find yourself taking a minute in the morning to enjoy the unique scent of exhaust
when you turn your car on?
(LAUGHTER)
We pray that you do not get down on your knees and enjoy the musky smell straight from the
sauce, but we do pray you buy our candles so you can enjoy the smell with light.
We do pray you buy our candles so you can enjoy the smell with less danger.
Avoid the headache.
Good God.
Yeah.
Wow.
They've really got men, haven't they?
Yeah.
(LAUGHTER)
So my parents opened up a salon in Hong Kong.
First customer my mum ever did was Robert Kwok.
And he immediately...
(LAUGHTER)
He's too rich to keep that in the show, please.
Okay.
Here's the thing.
Do you think you learn from your failures?
Yeah, I think so.
No question.
I reckon.
That's the whole point, isn't it?
Well, there's this common idea that, you know, oh, well, actually I just failed my way until
I succeeded.
But you learn from your mistakes, right?
But I think people don't tend to.
Like failing repeatedly is not a good way to succeed.
You do actually have to think about why you fail, don't you, and then act on it.
Yes.
And people...
So it's quite hard to do experiments on whether you learn from your failures, but here is one
experiment.
Scientists got people to do a practice test, right?
They gave them feedback, fake feedback on how they performed, and then they would do a real
test.
And they were asked how happy it would make them if they did well.
So the people who got negative feedback immediately said, "Oh, well, I wouldn't care at all if
I did well on the real test."
They were lying.
They were protecting themselves, you know.
And then when they did the second test, they got given fake feedback again.
And so you got full marks.
And they were thrilled.
They were so happy that they'd done well.
So people try and protect their self-image as competent people.
And when they get proof that they're wrong, it does away with that image.
I've just realized I read out the wrong fact in relation to the leading, which makes this
bit of the show something I will not learn from.
But it was all part of the plan.
It's a bit about failure.
You're living it right now.
That's insane.
You failed literally in the moment, as you were telling us.
Beautiful.
The thing that seems relevant to me about what you were saying.
Yeah.
And I wonder if this is what you meant to say.
Let me know.
Hang on, Andy's going through something right now.
I feel like we should all pause and just watch it.
You know, like in an Edinburgh documentary where you don't interfere?
I feel like...
Is that what you do when someone really fucks up?
You get everyone to pause and watch it?
Yeah.
And then something in the background goes, "Here we see the podcaster struggling with his words."
[music]