[ you can hear the music ]
- [ you can hear the music ]
- Hello, and welcome to another episode of "No Such Thing as a Fish"
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Covern Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber, and I am sitting here with James Harkin,
I am Richard Zinsky, and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the White House's Oval Office
is a giant weighing scale.
- What do they use it for normally?
- Wailing the President.
- No, to see how heavy he is.
- No, it's not.
- So are you waving? - Yeah, that's what I thought.
- Yeah, it's to see that he's there full stop.
So the secret service need a monitor
where the President is at all times.
However, they're not allowed into the Oval Office.
He doesn't want them in there, so they have to stand outside.
Now, when the doors open, they can see where he is,
but when the door is shut, they can't see where the President is.
So if you look at pictures of the Oval Office,
there is a giant oval carpet that literally spans the entire office room
except for a few inches to the wall.
And underneath it are weighing pads that are connected to a line
that goes outside.
So the secret service can see where he is in the Oval Office
purely by where he's standing.
- I think I would get a load of objects
that weighed exactly the same as me
and just keep moving them around the office
just to blind up the secret service.
- Like Indiana Jones at the beginning of the first film.
- Yeah.
- But it's kind of like, if you've seen Harry Potter,
the Marauder's Map, where they just follow the footsteps on the map.
That's what the secret service have to have.
- Except it's not a Marauder's Map,
because the things are labeled as the President.
It's just someone who weighs roughly the same amount as the President, right?
So it's definitely Obama's in the Oval Office,
or someone who is also human sized as in the Oval Office.
- Yeah, or two people in the Oval Office.
It's just way of making sure that no one kidnaps him through a window, maybe.
- Well, they allowed him to the Oval Office.
- I don't know, actually.
This is a fact, which I haven't seen in many places.
It's from Brad Meltzer, who is a best-selling novelist,
but also works at the White House and gives tours.
And he did a Huffington Post piece where he said,
"Here is secret service secrets."
And that was the top one.
- 'Cause he got lots of randomers into the Oval Office.
I'd be a bit insulted as his secret service if I wasn't allowed in.
- Well, I think it's more, they're probably allowed in at some point.
I don't think it's like a total ban on secret service people.
I think when he's working on a day-to-day basis,
he doesn't want secret service people.
- Let's say they're doing something really important,
which is quite classified,
and only the people who need to know are in there,
so the other guys just stood outside, like playing cards or something.
- Do you think if he puts on a bit of weight,
they start giving him a slide look?
- Right.
- So, are you sure about that biscuit, Mr. President?
(laughing)
- This article by Brad Meltzer also mentions
that anytime we hear about the White House going under renovations
of an old room, it's actually that the secret service
are conducting an investigation,
and it's the only way of giving an excuse
to allow for the first family to be out of the White House
while renovations are going on,
but it actually means they're conducting an investigation.
- Is that right?
- This will always be that.
- No, no, but I think there's been a few cases.
It's a sort of, like, inside knowledge thing
that if there's an investigation by the secret service,
they will say currently unobenerate.
- What are they investigating?
- That needs the President to be away.
- It's hard to research them,
because they're quite open about some things,
but then other things are surprisingly secretive.
- It is surprising, isn't it?
It's not that they would want to keep anything from us.
- It's controversial.
Are they telling the truth?
Is the author telling the truth?
We know a bit too much about the secret service, it seems, recently.
- I thought it would just be called the service.
- Exactly, yeah, the open service.
- You know that we have a lot of presidents and leaders
who like exercise and like jogging.
Obviously, when they go out on a jog,
they have to be accompanied by their little secret service cabal
who have to jog with them.
For instance, there was an article, I think this is in the Atlantic,
by someone who'd been in the secret service under Clinton,
and he said it was a complete nightmare,
because Clinton loved running,
and they even built him his own little running track
inside the White House grounds,
but he didn't like it, he liked to be out there with the people.
Whenever Clinton went for a run,
a bunch of them all had to go for a run as well,
but not just for a run.
They had to go for a run carrying like all their guns and weapons,
and it'd be super alert,
and always be ready to attack someone
if they attacked the president.
And so it sounds like absolutely hell.
- Imagine if Moll Farrah became president.
(laughing)
- Oh my gosh, who would you, that's true.
There are five people to qualify from being president,
and they're the five fastest people in the world,
because surely you need five people faster than the president.
- But Moll's not in the five fastest people in the world, is he?
- For running distances,
which is what Moll's was doing.
I mean, it's hardly, you say ball becomes president,
and you can only run 100 metres, 200 metres.
What trouble could he get in?
- But he won't be able to get away,
because at least the secret time is busing more people
to start running after the first 5,000 metres,
but no president Farrah has been running.
- So when president Farrah is running,
what they'll do is they'll all be running in like a relay,
and they pass the gun.
(laughing)
- Yeah, they do have to, it's quite funny,
when you look into sort of odd little things
that they have to prepare for in the safety of a president,
like Clinton going for his runs.
So do you remember that famous incident
where George Bush swallowed a pretzel
and started choking on it?
Apparently, that was a thing that they had to try and work out
how to avoid from ever happening again,
because-- - So did they all suck the pretzel?
So called the pretzel first.
- Exactly, what do you do in that situation?
So the only thing-- - The only thing--
- The only thing-- (laughing)
- The only thing that they could come up with
was a sort of emergency push button,
which I assumed he should have had anyway.
- Or the pretzel button.
- No, it's not exclusively for pretzel, if he's--
- It's a pretzel shake, I hope they made a pretzel shake.
(laughing)
- Some of the presidential secret service things,
I read in one book called Personality Character
and Leadership in the White House.
I don't know if it's true.
That Gerald Ford, whenever he farted,
would blame the secret service who were around him.
(laughing)
Oh, God, Jesus, guys, can you not keep a bit of the car room?
- That's amazing.
- Apparently, that's true.
- I guess that's true.
We spoke about this before on the podcast.
There was one president.
I think it was Johnson, who would just,
if he was taking a piss, would just urinate
on the secret service member and say,
"I can do this, I'm the president."
- I think the story went, something like,
it was LBJ, wasn't it?
And I think what happened was he went for a piss
on the side of the road when they were driving somewhere
and they kind of did like a human wall around him
and then there's like a gust of wind
and it blew the pee on to one of the guys,
and he said, "Excuse me, Mr. President, you're peeing on me."
And he said, "Well, it's my prerogative to do that."
I think that's what the story is anyway.
- Okay.
- Makes him slightly less unpleasant
than deliberately weeing on his...
- Yes, yes.
- Every time he needed to do a cool one of them into the office.
(laughing)
There was a assassination attempt that was made on Ronald Reagan
and it was made by John Hinckley, Jr.
and one of the secret service guys, a guy called Jerry Parr,
is the guy who got Ronald Reagan into the limousine
and got him off to...
And notice that he blood was coming out of his mouth
and said, "We need to get to the hospital right now."
So he said to have saved Ronald Reagan's life.
Interestingly, he became a secret service officer
because he had watched a movie called Code of the Secret Service.
Years before, which starred Ronald Reagan
as a secret service guy.
- No way!
- Yeah, so he ended up saving the life of the guy
who got him into it through...
- So Ronald Reagan saved his own life in a way.
- Exactly.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- That's incredible.
- Yes, really cool.
- That made a good movie in itself, wasn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Just one thing about the British secret services,
which I thought was interesting.
So during the Second World War,
they obviously requisitioned a load of, you know,
country houses and castles and things like that
and stately homes.
And one place they had was in Scotland.
It was called Invaler Lodge.
And it was used for spies who weren't good enough to spy,
but had already learned too much secret information
to be allowed to leave.
(laughing)
- That way.
- Yeah, wow.
- And they had to stay there for the rest of the war.
- One of them, one unfortunate man who had signed up to spy,
he was refused to actually go and spy in the field
because apparently he was outstandingly ugly.
So there was a report which said he'd be recognized anywhere.
Once he'd never forgotten.
He has no teeth at all, except two gold tusks and two incisors.
(laughing)
Poor man.
- But they must have been as well.
Like by the time they all left,
everyone would have known the secrets
that they were meant to be keeping as well.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Have come here.
Wow, I got told this thing about.
(laughing)
The one guy goes, "No!"
"Come on, Mike!"
(upbeat rock music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that because male bumblebees
rely on sight to find females,
they sometimes find themselves chasing after aeroplanes.
(laughing)
- So presumably their eyesight is not very good?
- Well, it's good for an insect.
(laughing)
But it's not good for like an eagle.
- Oh, okay.
- Okay.
- Bumblebees do have kind of good eyesight
as in they can see lots of colors.
- Yeah.
- People didn't realize they could see colors
and then Carl Frisch is a cold.
That guy who works out that they did the waggle dance,
he's quite famous scientist.
- Yeah, he got a Nobel Prize for that.
- Yeah, and he did an experiments where he proved
that they could see colors by getting loads of gray,
like gray card and then one colored card
and always put the food on the colored one
that could always tell where it was.
So they do have color sight.
- So are you saying we need to stop painting
our aeroplane Stripe Black and Yellow?
(laughing)
- Well, there is a Stripe Black and Yellow aeroplane
and it is the smallest airplane that has flown.
- Is it the size of a bee?
- It's called the Bumblebees a bit bigger.
It's eight foot ten inches in length
and the wingspan is five foot six
and it's tiny.
- It's so small.
- Yeah.
It's a bike lane as well.
- I mean, it does not look like it should get off the ground.
The wings are so small that you shouldn't think it has enough left.
- It looks like your car has just had some wings.
And not even as big as your car
because it fits five people in a car.
- Here's my armspan.
It's six inches shorter than my armspan across the whole plane.
- And yes.
- The wingtip.
- Looking at that, despite the fact that that's Black and Yellow
and is the smallest plane, I still think B's are idiots.
They look at something that size.
I think it's genuinely a bee.
- Do they chase after the plane once it's in flight
or is there a lot of B's at Heathrow?
- It's in flight.
So I got this from a newsletter of the Bee Conservation Society.
It's all about how male bees find the queens.
And there are different ways of doing it.
One way that they do it is by all load of males
kind of leave their smells around in a certain area.
Their pheromones.
And they kind of do it as a gang.
And they put loads and loads of stuff around them.
Then the queen just smells tons and tons of males
and then goes down and then they make that way.
And another way is by kind of chasing after a female.
So they'll see one in flight and they'll chase after the female.
And even though their eyesight is kind of good for insects,
it's not quite that good.
And so if they see something which is small looking
but actually is far away and is flying,
then they can sometimes, according to this newsletter,
mistake it for an aeroplane.
- Do we know how far they get towards the plane
before they realise the mistake?
- They realise the mistake and then they have to casually turn around
as though they weren't chasing.
- Do you mean like what you tried to get onto a tube train
and it goes away and you pretend you weren't buffing gas?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Or do they think that there's just certain female bees
out there or male bees that are extremely fast?
- Like Matt, he was like, "President, you saying bolter of the bees?"
- No, it didn't go that far into the psychology of the bee.
- That makes more sense that it's at a distance though.
- I sort of can forgive the bee slightly.
I think it planets like a bee from far away.
- Sorry, just one more thing on the colours that bees can see.
They can't really see red,
but they can see things that are further in the spectrum,
so they can see like ultraviolet.
They can see a little bit of yellow and orange.
They can see blue. They can see violet.
And they can see another colour which I saw in a website
was called bee purple. And bee purple is a colour that we can't see,
which is like a combination of yellow and ultraviolet.
- Really?
- That's so cool.
- How do we know they can see it?
Have they done paintings and there's just these big blind spots?
- I don't know, I think you can,
if you know the wavelength that something gives off,
you can know that there is a colour there even if you can't see it.
- So they can tell that it's a sort of purple-ish
in the spectrum area. - That's so cool.
I don't think you can mix normal colours with ultraviolet as well.
- I don't think so. But it makes sense that you can, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- I don't know.
- As you mixed it with the colour would gradually disappear
because we can't see stuff in the ultraviolet spectrum.
So we'll be putting an invisibility cloak on.
Manufacturers of invisibility cloak should take notes.
- I imagine that it doesn't quite work like that.
- I think she's absolutely right.
- See? I'm not the only one that gets slammed from my Harry Potter references.
- Stop being right.
- Do we know if there's anything in our day-to-day life
that is actually that be purple,
but we obviously just see it as purple?
- Well, there are plants which have colours
that if you shine a UV light on them,
you can see that they glow in a certain way,
that you can't see as humans,
but bees presumably can't see
because they point towards the centre of the plant.
So they're pointing the bee to the centre of the plant,
but if you or I were to look at it, we would never see those arrows.
- Okay.
- But we would see it as a different colour.
We wouldn't see it as nothing.
- Yes, exactly.
- It would be invisible.
- You look bees aren't the only things that make honey.
I did not know this.
- Really?
- Wops.
- Wops make honey.
- Do they?
- Yeah.
- There's a particular species of it called
the brachigastra mellificator.
And apparently you can even eat that wasps honey,
but I don't think it's found because it's quite hard to breed wasps.
- I don't know why it's not found.
- A single pound of clover honey
requires 8.7 million flowers to be manufactured.
8.7 million flowers for one pound of clover honey.
- Oh my god, I go through so much honey.
- That's terrible.
- I mean, the flowers can do multiple pollinations.
It's all right?
- Okay.
- Have you guys heard about
and I only realised as we were about start recording
that actually this article's from 2015.
So potentially this already now exists.
But the highway for bees in Norway?
- No.
- In Oslo and Norway, they want to make life better for bees basically
and they have a lot of green spaces.
And the idea is that they want to create networks
so that the bees can go between the green spaces
through sort of like alleyways that are created in buildings
and between buildings and so on.
- In buildings?
- Yeah, so like literally tunnels inside.
- Yeah, like trying to get in the left.
- Well, no, imagine in this room.
- Yeah.
- You have their own-- - Get the next lift.
- Yeah, they just, it's like tunnels and so on
and the bees can travel and find their way
to the next green place that they're going to.
- I think it might be that.
But I thought it would be like rooftop gardens and stuff
rather than actually inside the buildings.
- Yeah, I probably made that up.
- They put signposts on rooftops saying
bees you're allowed to fly over.
- What they do is that bees are in one place.
They might want to go to another place
and they just make sure there's a corridor
of green spaces where they can go.
- So they put green on the rooftops?
- Yeah.
- And flowers that they like and things like this.
- Yeah, lovely.
- Because you can make your garden really be friendly.
They're all these specific flowers that you can grow
and you guarantee bees.
- And London is basically covered in bees.
- Yeah, it's true.
- Basically.
- Yeah.
- When you say basically you mean knots.
- So many rooftops.
- Do you mean the hips to be hives in shortage?
- No, I mean the Royal Festival Hall has a bee hive on top of it.
Harrods has a bee hive on top of it.
And there's one specific London beekeeper
who goes to all of these different places.
- And is he, does he do parkour?
- Do you just jump from one to the other?
- But it is a problem because it's really fashionable
to have a bee hive and it's really cool.
But what they haven't done is planted 8.7 million flowers.
So you get exhausted bee hives
and they haven't got enough flowers and plants to pollinate.
So what you should actually do is plant a wild flower meadow
because that's not as sexy as getting a load of bees
off the internet.
- That's true.
- If you do have a garden,
but not many people do have gardens in London,
but if you do have them,
you should plant lots of flowers, shouldn't you?
- Yeah.
- Did you know there's such a thing as a bee beautician?
- No.
- A bee beautician.
Yeah.
So her job is to brush bees hair,
to wash them with shampoo.
So bees are, when specimens are collected,
then they're preserved in ethanol
and that makes them kind of soggy and slimy.
And she has to prepare them to be fit for display.
So she's got, she's concocted special bee shampoo
and then she dunks it in the bee shampoo
and then she hangs it out.
So she inserts a tiny, tiny pin,
I think, at the hinge of one of its legs.
And then she's created a blow dryer for bees.
- Of course.
- No.
- Yeah, so she at first tried actual blow dryers,
but she found that they were too violent.
So it used to be...
- She's gone.
- She's just got the little legs left in the clamp
and the rest of the bee.
- She does say so it used to blow their limbs off
and then she'd have to glue the limbs back on,
which is the whole other thing.
- Glue the limbs back on.
- Yeah, but she did say something interesting about bees,
which is that they have lots of split ends.
And so that's why she has to use a special shampoo,
it's because they get very clumpy and frizzy when they get wet.
- What is this shampoo?
- It's a mixture of water and sodium bicarbonate or something.
- Okay.
- But wasps don't have split ends,
so if you don't want frizzy hair, be a wasp.
- It's a bit late for me, really.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is Andrew Hunter Murray.
- My fact is that running a leaf blower for 30 minutes
creates more emissions than driving a pickup truck
3,800 miles.
- No way.
- That is incredible.
- It does sound unbelievably untrue, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- I'm following the words of James Fallow,
who's a correspondent at the Atlantic,
which is a very reputable magazine.
And he has a campaign against these things.
Well, I guess if you were pro,
then you wouldn't work out the emissions.
What he says is that about a third of the petrol they use,
because they use petrol gas in America,
is vomited out in aerosol form.
And that gets mixed in with tiny particles of oil
in the exhaust, in the droplets.
So he has calculated that.
Which if true means that you could drive from Coven Garden
to Jerusalem.
- Wow.
- I think they compared it to a particular type of pickup, didn't they?
- Sorry, yeah, F-150.
Maybe it's an unbelievably clean.
- I think it is.
- I think it is an extremely efficient one.
But it's still good.
I mean, it's still amazing.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I thought the F-150 was a model of Cassiot watch.
Is it not?
- That's the F-91W.
- Great.
- Anyway.
- So is he suggesting we all try and clear our leaves
with pickup trucks?
Because I think it's gonna be harder.
- If you use the F-150 and you can blow it in the right way,
I guess you could save technically on emissions?
- You could.
- The exhaust pipe pointed the right direction.
- Imagine trying to drive a B with the leaf plug.
(laughing)
It will legs everywhere.
- Yeah, so I mean, people really hate these things.
- Yeah, the horrible.
I think they make the most disgusting noise
and they should all be banned.
I genuinely do think that.
- They're very, very, very loud.
- And I think they're unnecessary.
Just rake your bloody garden, guys.
- That must be easier to blow it than rake it, though.
- Also, you're blowing it into someone else's spot, aren't you?
Or do you blow it into a pile?
- I think you blow it into a pile.
- Blowing it into a pile, okay.
- I've got leaves all over my bloody garden at the moment.
I would kill for a blower.
- Your garden's small.
- I don't need to be rude.
(laughing)
- Well, that is quite rude.
- All I'm saying is, it's evidently rakeable.
You couldn't pick up truck in your garden.
- I think, kill for a blower.
It was the most rude thing in that sentence by a long mile.
(laughing)
- Oh dear.
- Yeah, but I can see that they are.
I think my neighbours have got one.
They are pretty loud.
- If your neighbours have got one,
you will definitely know about it.
- Well, there is a big loud noise coming from my neighbours
every now and then in the autumn.
(laughing)
- That's what it is.
You don't want to pry.
- Well, it could be that.
It sounds a bit like an aeroplane taking off.
Is that what they sound like?
- Yeah, they do.
- Unless do they have an airstrip in their garden?
- Well, they're going to be.
(laughing)
- Oh dear.
In California, there are 20 cities that have banned us.
- Wow.
- Yeah, I was reading an article by the Kendall family,
who are from California, are in a state where they want to get it banned.
And they're pointing out that the reason it's so annoying,
and this definitely does ring true,
is that compared to a lawnmower,
which can be as loud,
but operates at the same kind of frequency
and volume the whole time,
leaf blow is really go up and down, don't they?
So you can't predict it.
So you're constantly being shocked by its volume increases
and decreases.
- That's very interesting.
- That's what stresses you out.
- How long have we had leaf blowers, by the way?
Does anyone know?
Since about the 50s or 60s?
- Yeah, 50s.
Except in Japan, in 19th century,
they used like bellows that used for a fire as leaf blowers.
- Oh, they.
- Yeah, I haven't seen a photo of the bellows.
I tried to find one,
and I couldn't find a picture of Japanese ancient leaf blowing bellows.
- No, but there is an early book.
But the 1950s reference is weird.
If anyone can tell us if this is true,
Wikipedia claims, and this is from a book called,
"Everything you ever needed to know about leaf blowers."
So you would have thought this would be the authority on it.
But this claims it was invented by a guy called Dom Quinto,
who originally designed it in the 1950s as an agricultural sprayer.
But people were taking out the spraying device
and just using it to blow their leaves on it.
But there's no evidence aside from this book
that this Dom Quinto chap ever existed.
So if you are him, always offspring, get in touch.
- Do you know who invented the rake?
- No.
- Is it Mike Rake?
No, it's not Mike Rake.
I mean, these are always a bit dubious, aren't they?
But apparently the steel rake,
which is kind of a bit springy,
and the modern day one that's good for raking stuff with,
was invented by a guy called Chester Greenwood,
who also supposedly invented earmuffs.
- Really?
- Apparently.
- Wow.
- And he's quite famous in North America in Maine
that there's a certain town where every year
they have a celebration of his inventing.
- What are they doing?
They've put a load of earmuffs to go on raking stuff out.
- Yeah.
- To drown out the noise of the leaf blowers.
- They're trying to protest against.
- They kind of do that, I think.
They kind of wear earmuffs.
They have an earmuff parade and stuff.
- They have a parade!
- I think they don't really bother about the rake part
of it that much.
They're more bothered about the earmuffs
because he was quite young when he invented them.
He was like 16 or 17 or so.
- I thought it was 13.
- 13, yeah, it could be.
- Maine sounds like a very exciting place to live, doesn't it?
That's their highlight of the year.
- Well, the thing is, it's cold and they have a lot of trees.
So earmuffs and rakes are the kind of things you might invent
if you live there.
- And they have every major horror story
that we know of in popular culture,
set there through Stephen King,
because he lives in Bangor, Maine.
So it, the clown, is from Maine and...
- Okay, you can't credit an entire state for one person
that it's produced.
(laughter)
- I know, but well done, Maine.
- There is a cool thing you can do with leaf blowers,
which is turn them into a hovercraft.
- Can you?
- Yeah.
There's a very cool video online of a Texan man
called Ryan Craven.
So shout out to Texas who created Ryan Craven.
(laughter)
Who sort of four of them together into a kind of platform
and he puts the skateboard across the platform.
And it hovers very, very low off the ground,
but it does hover.
- You know, on Fallen Leaves,
I was actually looking at this for cause in the TV show
we did this week, no such things in news.
We were talking about Chernobyl.
- Is that still available on iPlayer?
- I think it might be, yeah.
And actually, if you're international, it's on YouTube.
- That's it.
- But that's besides the point, Jay.
- Jay, how would you find that?
- You go to Know Such Things The News.com.
- Thanks for asking.
- Yeah.
Anyway, we recorded a TV show this week.
And we mentioned Chernobyl.
(laughter)
And Leaves in Chernobyl don't decompose
because the radioactivity means that the bacteria
are no longer there, can no longer survive.
So they can't decompose the leaves.
And so there are, you know, that it's missing this fungus
and the worms and the microbes and stuff like that.
And so it's just building up this huge floor of dead leaves.
And at the moment, if a forest fire started,
which can't happen, it's that in temperatures,
it would be a complete disaster with spread radiation,
much, much further and wider than it is already,
because it would just catch fire to all these dry dead leaves
out on the ground.
- That's like in Australia, a sort of Aussie non-nuclear version
of that is the eucalyptus tree,
because their leaves, when they drop off the tree,
they have a kind of sort of what's called like a toxic name palm
thing about them in that they're too hard to break down
for all the insects and animals.
They sit there, dry as hell.
And if a forest fire starts and it hits a eucalyptus patch,
that will just go massively up in flame,
just sitting there waiting to be caught on fire.
- And this must be because a eucalyptus tree
is one of the trees that love being set on fire,
because how they spread their seeds.
- Yes, they love to be set on fire.
They sort of have an inner tree waiting
to break out of the bigger tree.
And forest fires is what brings that to happen.
- I think they're pretty much ambivalent about the whole thing.
- Do you think they don't even know their trees?
- In 2011, someone patented a glove rake,
which is really cool.
It's a normal glove, except it's got these five long,
you look a bit like him with scissors hands,
except we were able to break hands.
And you could just go around breaking stuff up
with your bare hands.
- You have to be on your hands and knees.
- You would have to be on your hands and knees.
- That's not going to be nice.
I mean, because it's the middle of autumn.
It's going to be damp.
- Edward rake hands, by the way,
would have been really useful in that scene
where Edward Scissor-Hands cuts all the hedges.
(laughing)
He could have been on the side cleaning up.
- Yeah, there's a lot.
Edward, been back hands comes along.
(laughing)
Guys, why are we all called Edward?
- We're not related.
We've got different surnames.
(laughing)
- They've all got the surnames.
- Hands.
- Wait, is it a double barrel surname?
- Yeah, so what are the married Mrs. Scissor?
One of the married Mrs. Rake.
- I've never noticed before the moment
where we come up with a title of an episode.
I think no such thing as Edward, been back hands.
(laughing)
Okay, it is time to move on to our final fact of the show
and that is Chuzinsky.
- Yes, my fact is that early humans had spiky penises.
(laughing)
- That is insane.
How early?
- I actually couldn't believe it.
Just a couple of weeks ago.
- 6.30 this month.
(laughing)
- No, this was a study on human genes that was done in 2011
and it found that about 700,000 years ago,
so before our common ancestors split into modern humans
and the Andethals, then we have the gene
that carries penis spines.
And then that gene seems to have been deleted
when we evolved into modern humans today.
But lots of other, like almost all other primates
still have penis spines.
- Too bad.
- Yeah, they do except for spider monkeys, I think,
all primates have penis spines.
And what do the spines feel like as in...
(laughing)
If I gripped a chimped penis, would I be arrested?
- Be arrested, yeah.
(laughing)
- Would I cut my hands?
Would the palms of my hands be sliced?
- The ones on primates I think are more bumpy.
Some are not really spiky spines, like cats, I think, too.
But I think they're more like lumps.
I've slightly blunt spiked.
- You've never seen the film with Tisopee in this, have you?
(laughing)
- So just to go into quickly, the reason that we might well,
that men might have had spiky penises in the past.
We're not totally sure about it.
But we think it might be because what it can do is
it can help clear out rival sperm from a female vagina.
So if you get the spikes in, then as it's sort of retracting,
they scrape the edge of a vagina
and they'll bring out any sperm that's been left in there
by someone else.
And they can break through a little sperm sack
and break it open to make the sperm.
- No animals, isn't it?
I think dragonflies have like spayed shaped penises
that they do with that.
- It must be really hard to study the evolution
of human penises because the lack of bone means that
how can you, how can you, you just, there's nothing.
- So erotic, all bones, no bone.
- All bone and bone.
(laughing)
- That's what you said that a few times.
- I've gotta change my strapline on a lot of dating sites.
(laughing)
- We might have had a bone.
I must stop saying we, in reference to our penises,
then might have had a bone.
We don't know, but other primates do have a penile bone,
I think, don't they?
And it has a lot of advantages having a bone there
because it means you can push it out much quicker
than having to wait for the blood to engorge it.
(laughing)
Just flip right out and it can stay out for longer.
And I think Richard Dawkins is one.
(laughing)
- Richard Dawkins, in the selfish gene,
wrote that the advantage of humans not having this
is that having to get blood flowing in there
shows that you've got like a healthy blood flow,
shows is kind of a sign of good health,
so women are more attracted to it.
So that might be why we've a men of evolved.
- Okay.
- Penises without the bone,
because it's harder to get it blown up.
- I've heard so, in place of the bone,
there is a new thing that they're testing out,
which is a metal rod.
So some men could now have a metal rod inside their penis.
And the idea is for,
it's done, do you remember where it's done, Andy?
- In hospitals mostly.
(laughing)
- If it's big off with you and about,
you should be very careful.
(laughing)
- So the idea is that this is for people
suffering from erectile dysfunction
and if they've gone through various courses,
they're gonna then say on health services
or whatever they will say you can have this.
And the idea is that it's a little metal rod inside,
but when you want an erection,
you can press a button like a remote control
and it pre-heats this metal bar
to a heat point where it expands within you.
- Yo, I'm never gonna get on a flight, are you?
(laughing)
- I mean, that's just not,
it's just not gonna happen, you know?
Every single time you're gonna set it off,
they're gonna get that paddle thing.
You're gonna go up and down your body,
you can get to the rod.
- Yeah.
- What, and you think you just go,
never mind, I'm going home, doesn't matter.
- I think that would happen, yeah.
- Yeah.
- The other thing is you can get a bit of cartilage
but if you have erectile problems,
and then you have to just kind of maneuver
the penis into position.
So it's kind of permanently erect from that point.
That's in Mary Roach's book, "Bonk,"
which is about science and sex,
and it's an amazing book.
- Oh, it's incredible book, yeah.
- So this is partly about how males
of various species manage to get rid of competition,
'cause the spines are often used to scrape,
to scrape out the sperm out of the vagina.
- Yeah.
- And so I was looking at other ways
that you get rid of the competition.
And one is that, in mice, sperm club together
as a group to beat rival sperm.
- It's exactly like--
- Like where I saw it.
- What?
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- The jets of the sperm?
(laughing)
- It's exactly like in a cycling race,
which James will know more about,
where they move faster if they move as a group,
so they can tell if they're the sperm
that belong to the same person,
and all the sperm that belong to that person get together,
and all the sperm that belong to another person get together.
This is in these mice inside this female mouse.
- Yeah.
- And so they, as a group, they move much faster
than they do individually.
What's that called?
It's like the--
- Peloton, peloton effect.
- It's a peloton.
It's the peloton of sperm.
And then when they get near the finish line,
suddenly they all start to beat them away.
- Someone breaks away.
- Yeah.
- And then the muck haven't dish sperm wins.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- So they're just programmed.
It'll be smell or--
- No, what is it?
What is it?
How do they know this?
- How can they grow together?
- Well, cells can be programmed to do things.
So I imagine it must be that.
It's inside the DNA of the cell.
That has instructions of what it should do.
It makes the tails wag.
- Yeah.
- And also, if they have their specific rendition
of "Keep Cool" from my site's story,
then they can tell.
- Which is the best song to sing for a sperm.
Because you do need to keep lower than the ambient temperature of the body.
- Yeah, it's weird that they want the lyrics in the original website.
(laughter)
- Okay, that is it.
And as all of our facts,
thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Triberland.
- James.
- @EdShakes.
- Andy.
- @AndriHunterM.
- Chazinski.
- You can email podcast@QI.com.
- Yeah, or you can go to our group, Twitter account,
which is @QIPodcast.
Or go to nosuchthingasaffish.com.
That has all of our previous episodes.
Also, you can go to nosuchthingas.com,
which has all of the episodes from our recent TV series
in which we dissect most interesting news for the last seven days.
Alright, that's it guys.
We will be back again next week with another episode.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]