- Hey everyone, welcome to this week's episode of Fish.
We've got a very exciting one for you today.
It is our Valentine's Day special.
So yeah, we've collected together some of the sexiest,
most romantic facts that we could possibly find
for your listening pleasure.
And we'll be getting to that
over the course of this episode.
However, before we get into that,
I've just got a quick announcement,
which is that we have a live show coming up
in July at the Crossed Wires Festival podcast in Sheffield.
So the Crossed Wires podcast festival is fantastic.
It debuted last year.
It was co-created by our good buddy, Alice Levine,
from My Dad Wrote a Porno,
and they are back this year for round two.
And really excitingly, she has invited us to be part of it.
So we will be there to record a live episode
at the City Hall on the 6th of July at 2PM.
And if you wanna come along,
you just need to head to knowsuchthingasafish.com/live
to get your tickets right now.
It's gonna be great fun.
As I say, a live podcast recording
with a bunch of silly extra bits thrown in as well.
And if you get a chance,
why not head over to the crossedwires.live website as well.
That's the address.
So many great shows are gonna be there this year.
It's so awesome that these podcast festivals
are erupting around the UK.
Do support them and do come see us.
We'd love to see you there.
All right, well, let's get into this week's episode.
It is our Valentine's Day special.
Enjoy our sexy, sexy facts on with the show.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with James Harkin, Anna Tyshinski
and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite Valentine's Day facts.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
- My fact is, before flirting with females,
young male dolphins practice on their male friends.
- Happy Valentine's Day, everyone.
- Yeah, this is an erotic special.
- Roses are red, this fact is very blue.
- It is quite blue, actually.
- Well, what do they practice?
How blue is it?
- Well, that's--
- 'Cause dolphins are blue?
- Yeah, they're rude.
- Are they?
- Well, they're sort of blueish, aren't they, in cartoons?
- Yeah, they're gray, gray blue.
- They're gray.
- Bluey gray.
This is a place that actually is a friend of the podcast.
It's Shark Bay in Australia,
where some research was done.
We said it was renamed Safety Beach.
- Yeah, we did.
- Yeah, I think that was fake.
I think that's a retraction we need to make.
- Oh, great, okay.
- Are we all making that as a group?
- No, just me, leave it to me.
You guys, you guys stay unblemished.
So there's a group of dolphins who've been living there
and they've been studying for about 40 years.
They're really, really well,
the best-studied group of dolphins in the world.
They have very complicated social relationships
with each other.
Scientists find it very useful to kind of keep tabs on them.
And these young males, they pall up in groups of two or three
and they coordinate their behavior
to consort particular females.
And that, this is where it gets a bit,
flirting is a very nice way of describing it
'cause male dolphins sort of coerce
and harass individual females
and try and separate them from whichever males
they're hanging out with.
But then they do some displays of acrobatics
and somersaults.
It sounds like a sort of sea world thing.
- Uh-huh.
- You know, they do tricks.
They do also bite her sometimes.
Anyway, they are really getting some mixed signals here.
I don't want to get all rubbing thickie on your ass.
- Look at the somersaults, look at the somersaults.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so, but they do practice with each other.
And the ones who practice with each other
have better success later in life.
Romantically, you know, they farther more offspring
than the ones that don't.
- Do they ever fall in love with each other accidentally?
- Oh my God.
- Good question.
- Flipper three.
- Reminds me a bit of a Friends episode
where Joey helps trigger the janitor to dance.
He's his dance partner and he sort of starts
to wish that he was his real dance partner.
I wonder if there are dolphins out there
who just are like, let's have one more practice.
- I think so.
I mean, there's lots of, there are occasionally,
I find a lot of headlines in the mail,
the Daily Mail saying things like,
more gay dolphins spotted off Canada
like it's very bright and concerned for them.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, they can't, they can't be quite aggro,
can't they?
- Oh yeah.
- The dolphins.
And like, but it is sort of their male bonds
are sort of nice.
It does seem like this study, I think,
was the first to reveal that they have a buddy system
and they'll pick a best friend.
Some of the males, not all of the males,
they'll pick a best friend.
And that'll be someone that they hang out with
for their whole life.
And sometimes you'll have the two male buddies
who hang out together.
And if they're separated for up to decades,
I think it is when they come back together,
they're their best friends still.
- Once there's quite a few ways that dolphins can mate,
there's a sort of T-section shape that they do.
So the male dolphin goes sort of horizontal
against the vertical of the female dolphin
in order to have sex.
There's a few other methods.
One method that gets described for one of the dolphins
is having this buddy, the wingman come,
and at surface level sort of hold for buoyancy reasons.
So they're sort of there just to prop him up
to make sure the sex can happen.
Which a lot of NASA scientists are saying
that might be the best way that humans will have sex.
- We're not taking dolphins up to Mars.
- We're not taking dolphins, we're just screwing like them.
If sex is happening, there needs to be a third astronaut
to come in and just hold everything together.
- Dave, Dave, sex is happening.
Come on in.
(all laughing)
- Surely not.
- But there was a recent report by someone
who's trying to work on the problem
of population and space. - By a space pervert.
(all laughing)
- I think dolphins are perverts really.
I think by any means.
- Well, they have sex often with their mothers, male dolphins.
- No.
- Yeah, bottom-nosed dolphins like to gather
around gray whales when they're mating.
No one really knows why,
but they just enjoy watching.
- Right.
- You can't get porn underwater.
- So their mom's nipples are up their butt,
so when they breastfeed-- - It is, it is.
So when they breastfeed, they literally burrow their--
- That can't be true.
- Dolphin noses into the anus of their mom.
- No, that can't be true.
- It's true.
- Is it really?
- I didn't just come up with that.
(all laughing)
I mean, it's possible I did just come up with that, but.
- Okay, can we bust one myth?
- Yeah, sure.
- This is exciting stuff not to blow wide open,
but to close down.
And it's a thing we have propagated actually in the past.
So, you know, it's like the rest for us.
It's the blowhole, the blowhole sex myth.
- What's the myth that they have sex with their blowholes?
- Yeah.
- And we've claimed that.
- I think so.
- Have we?
- We're perverts. - A long time ago.
Like nine years ago, I think, you know,
we're different people now.
- What's the truth then?
- I think, well, there's one mention of it
in a paper in 1994.
- Oh, you shagged one blowhole.
(all laughing)
And the researcher, a researcher called Justin Gregg
spoke to the person who had authored that 1994 article
who said, and I'm quoting here,
"With regard to the blowhole,
they never inserted the penis entirely."
I don't know whether that stands up in court
and the I'm gonna say.
- What percentage of the penis?
Oh, only 25, that's fine.
- But they breathe through it.
Turns out they can breathe through their mouth as well,
which we didn't know until 2016.
It's assumed that they can't breathe
because we've never seen them breathing through their mouth.
But they found one dolphin with a damaged blowhole.
Blowhole.
(all laughing)
One of a...
Are you being serious?
You have a damaged blowhole.
(all laughing)
- No word.
Or what?
The damage.
But they found that it was breathing through its mouth
as a result.
So possibly even dolphins don't know
they can breathe through their mouth.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- We call them clever.
(all laughing)
- I feel like everything I've said is a lie so far.
- Where did you get all this stuff from, Dan?
- It's just stuff I know.
(all laughing)
We've talked a lot in the past
about dolphins having military connections.
They've worked with the military a lot.
I didn't know this.
There's like the biggest horde of nuclear weapons
is in a submarine base in America
and it's protected by military dolphins.
So anyone trying to get access to it
has to face a dolphin.
Isn't that amazing?
And what happens is...
- Sometimes I think you have your own
different Google and their experts.
(all laughing)
- Well, the interesting thing is if they...
So they can't...
It's very hard to monitor an underwater base
with nuclear weapons.
So they need an animal that can just be there
all the time to do it.
- Where is this?
Sorry, where...
- It's near Boston.
- U.S.
- Yeah, you can't give away the exact location,
I'm sure, Dan.
- Yeah, sorry, Seattle.
It's 20 miles.
- Oh, it's Seattle.
(all laughing)
- 5,000 miles from Boston.
- It's the world's largest single location
of our smell of nuclear weapons.
- Wow, it's underwater.
- Certainly at the time of writing.
It's underwater, right?
And so they have these military dolphins
and they have this amazing thing
where if someone's swimming
to try and get access to this submarine base
to steal a nuke of one man just swimming to get to it,
the dolphins have a metal plate in their mouth
that when they go up and rub up against the swimmer,
they can attach like a handcuff,
like a subtle handcuff going to your leg.
- What are you talking about?
- Honestly, this is what happens.
It goes around the leg or the arm of the person
and then it deploys a boy and floats them,
like just goes whoop,
and they just disappear up to the surface.
- Were they arrested by a police dolphin at the top?
(all laughing)
- The dolphins are purely underwater based,
so that becomes a human problem
when they arrive at the top.
- Right, that's either extraordinary
or what are you talking about?
- No, that's incredible, unbelievable.
- This was in 2010, so it's possible the dolphins were fine.
- Oh yeah, yeah, they're moving on to par places now.
- Well, they get seals as well,
Navy seals, but like actual seals.
- Oh yeah, I feel like we have actually mentioned that before.
We can't just laugh at everything Dan said.
- No, from now on though. - Some of it is true.
- You gotta start with something more believable, Dan,
and then build up to this.
- Well, we know that they do this kind of stuff.
- It's only Cold War superpowers, isn't it?
It's only America and Russia that--
- That we know of. - That we know of,
that have trained dolphins.
- I thought Israel did.
- Oh yeah, they did, they did.
I'm sure other military powers
have experimented with all that stuff.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- You know, paw poises that you mentioned.
You know, they're the reason that we call tortoises,
tortoises. - No.
- Which I don't think we've mentioned before,
but because paw poise,
which is basically a dolphin-- - I'm highly pregnant here.
It's a whole show.
- It does feel a bit like it, doesn't it?
- No, this is absolutely correct.
Paw poise, etymologically, it means pigfish,
so the paw is like, has the same root as pork
and poise is like, poise on poise, fish.
Tortoises were always tortoise.
They ended just in US,
probably coming from a word meaning twisted.
But once we started having paw poises,
people went, well, since we spell that like that,
should we make it tortoises as well?
'Cause it sounds similar.
And we think that's the only theory we have
for why suddenly, about 500 years ago,
we started spelling tortoise like tortoise.
- Someone was writing a poem and they're just like--
(laughing)
- I got nothing after tortoise.
- That was the main economic activity 500 years ago,
was the sonnet, unfortunately.
And so, it was really important.
- Can we talk about dolphin vaginas?
- Of course. - Quickly.
They have clitorises,
and the clitorises are so accessible
when they're having sex
that we think they're probably used for pleasure.
- Okay.
- But the vagina is really,
it's like, unlike most mammals
where it's really just like a straight tube,
with them it goes in all sorts of different directions
and stuff like that.
And you can tell what species a dolphin is
by looking at its vagina.
- It's like a labyrinth,
so they can decide whether or not
they want to be impregnated.
- Sorry, do you mean it's like a maze?
'Cause of course, a labyrinth only has one root, doesn't it?
So that wouldn't fool anyone.
- Labyrinth is like a spiral.
- There's no dead ends in a labyrinth.
- Yes, no, it's a maze, not a labyrinth, sorry.
- 'Cause we'd get a lot of emails
if we left it like that. - You're right, you're right.
- Can I just very quickly mention
the basketball player who had a great altercation
with the dolphin, Clifford Ray.
- Oh, okay, yeah. - Can I still about him?
He became super famous for this in 1978 for a short while.
There was a dolphin called Mr. Spock.
They realized that there was a bolt
and a really sharp screw stuck in its stomach
and second stomach down, so quite far in.
The vet says, "I can't operate to remove it.
"My arm won't reach down its throat enough."
And then they were like, "Who's got really long arms?
"This basketball player, Clifford Ray,
"famously has arms of three foot nine inches long,
"which is long."
So they got in touch with Clifford
and he was at a premier in, for some reason,
and he was taking a premier in,
waiting to go to a, you know, to a game.
And he rocked up and he was guided by speakerphone,
by an expert in retrieving stuff
from the insides of dolphins,
while he inserted his three foot nine inch long arm
into the dolphin. - And he's like,
it's like a labyrinth in here.
- The other end, the other end.
(all laughing)
- Why am I holding a nipple?
- Wait, sorry, why was he on speakerphone?
'Cause he wasn't there.
- No, no, sorry, the basketball player was there.
The vet was-- - The vet?
- Who needed to guide them?
The expert vet, who knew all that.
- You're not gonna turn up to the most interesting
dolphin-based event of your life.
He was staying in the Holiday Inn up in the next town.
It was too good to make. - My gosh.
- They didn't have much time.
- And they said, once his arm was in,
it was three minutes, and after that,
the dolphin would suffocate.
And he had to get all the way down, wave his arm.
- Wait, he's got a bow hole?
- What?
- He's got a bow hole?
- It'd have been dumb.
(all laughing)
- There's four dolphins.
- It turns out there's just one dolphin in the world.
There's this guy.
- Can I ask a question, if they're short on time,
the dolphin is obviously in one place.
They immediately go, who's got long arms
in the immediate vicinity, and he happens to be in town?
- Well, he's from California, so it was the same state.
- Okay, right.
- And they needed really long arms.
- Right.
- Like, not just like you're a bit tall.
- Mr. Tickle was embossed.
(all laughing)
- Wait, he did it, he did it.
He did it with only, when there were 15 seconds to spare,
he says he just remembers the vet on the other end of the line.
- Did they have a big basketball club ticking down?
- Come on, time out.
(all laughing)
- What if he didn't, he would die.
- Would have suffocated him.
- And did Mr. Spock live long and prosper?
- Hey, there we go.
- And there we go.
- A gentle end to a very upsetting story.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the adult
who's come closest to freezing to death
and being brought back to life,
got together with the person who resuscitated her.
- Mmm.
- Was it Anna from Frozen?
- It should have been.
- Maybe that's who Anna from Frozen was named after.
- It is not, it is Anna.
- 'Cause she is called Anna, isn't it?
- Yes, yes.
- Anna Bagenholm.
- Anna Bagenholm, who's Swedish,
but she was in Norway at the time.
This is, I don't know why I'm speaking like that.
This was 1999, and she was skiing with two colleagues.
And it's just the most amazing story,
so I'll do a short version,
and then we'll probably do a long version.
Basically, she's skiing, she plunges head first
through a massive layer of ice,
and she's stuck there for ages and ages,
and she gets very bad hypothermia,
her heart stops beating, her breathing stops, she's dead.
She's completely dead.
And then eventually she gets extracted from the ice.
And the crucial thing that happens as soon as she's extracted,
and very important to remember this
for any hypothermia sufferers,
is that she received CPR straight away
from her two colleagues who've been skiing with her.
One of whom was a chap called Torvind Nysheim,
who gave her CPR,
and it seemed to have absolutely no effect at the time.
- The other one's going, "Let it go!"
- Oh, my God.
- Oh, Jesus Christ.
James is poised to use that in the body as possible,
but have you got that out of your system?
Yeah? No more famous lyrics than that?
- I don't know any of this.
- Okay, I think that's a relief for everyone.
Anyway, it's thought the CPR probably saved her life,
along with a bunch of other incredible doctors.
When she got to hospital,
there were over a hundred doctors in the room,
or medical staff in the room with her.
And she did live, and then a few years later,
she got together with this chap.
And I believe, as of 2022, they were still together.
- Oh, lovely.
- But really, this was a way of crowbaring
this amazing story into a Valentine's special.
- Yeah, it is an amazing story.
And at that time, they thought,
"No way she's coming back."
For all the doctors, she was literally,
this was medicine into the unknown, right?
It was, that's a Frozen 2 song, just for you all there.
- It wasn't.
- Medicine into the unknown.
Oh, into the unknown, sorry.
Medicine into the unknown.
(laughing)
- Frozen 2, she becomes a GP, she, yeah.
- There's a polar bear who's swallowed a plastic bag,
and we need the world's best curling team
to go and get it out.
- This was a phenomenal thing.
They thought, "No way is she gonna survive,"
except they seem to have a phrase there, the doctors,
which is something like,
"You're not dead until we warm you up first."
So no one who's cold can be declared dead.
You've got to bring them back to war.
- I think that's true around the world,
and it's a really crucial thing about being that cold,
because, again, this is what a lot of hypothermia sites say.
They're like, "Don't assume they're dead, no heart rate,
"no breathing, pallid skin, why is she,
"but it could be that once you warm them up again,
"you come back to life."
- It's like a goldfish, isn't it?
If your goldfish is floating upside down,
it might not be dead.
It might just have a swim bladder problem.
- Is that so?
- Yeah.
- So don't flush it down the toilet.
- That's really good advice.
- And in the same way with these people.
- Yeah, don't flush them down, as they do.
Ignore it when they're done.
- So this accident she had, she was skiing,
she had a fall, she went through a hole in the ice,
eight inches of ice, thick ice,
and she was trapped under the water.
Her clothes are immediately soaked,
therefore they're very heavy.
The shock paralyzes your muscles, so you can't move, right?
So her friends catch up with her, they--
- And they can only see her feet in skiing, can they?
- They can only see her feet, they cannot pull her out,
because just the position she's in.
- And also just this is, 'cause she's in the water,
she's submerged, it's a random air pocket
that her face happens to be next to
that allows for her to keep breathing in there.
- It's stunning, so she's breathing for seven minutes,
but she's in the water for 40 minutes.
A team of rescuers arrive, they can't get her out
with a rope or a snow shovel,
it's not thick enough to get through the ice.
So she's there, I think another 30 or 40 minutes.
- Another 40 minutes, yeah.
- And then a team arrives with a pointy shovel,
which they use to dig through the ice and get her out.
So she's been in the water for 80 minutes freezing.
She's white, she's cold, nothing, nothing is happening.
It's just extraordinary.
- It's amazing. - Well, she's dead.
- She's dead. - She's dead.
- She's dead, well, except she's not.
- Well, I mean, what's the definition of death?
- Exactly, is she warm?
I don't think so, guys.
- Good point, good point.
She had no heartbeat for four hours
between when her head went through the ice
and when her heart rate came back.
- Extraordinary, and it was like nine hours,
and they say like hundreds of doctors and nurses
who were just working on her the entire time,
just trying to bring her back, and they did it.
And when they did, she was paralyzed to begin with
and pissed off, so why did you bring me back?
Why did you make me become alive again?
I now have to live a life
where I'm not gonna be the person that I wanted to be.
And she eventually calmed down.
- Well, after she realized she wasn't paralyzed.
- It took a long time, though,
for her to get her body completely back to normal.
- I think it was within not too long, actually.
And then she did apologize.
So, yeah, not the romantic reunion initially
with poor old Naishim, who's like,
"Oh, she's gonna fall in love with me now," in her eyes.
- And then her heart melted.
- Ah, it's Valentine's Day.
- I love it.
- The thing, I find it nuts is she's skewed again.
- Absolute loon.
She's really into downhill skiing.
- Six years later, she's skewed again.
Just extraordinary.
- Did she stay on peace from that one?
- I don't know.
- No, I think she's into--
- She just went to the cafe a bit.
(all laughing)
- I believe she's really into extreme skiing still.
- Really?
- Because people are insane.
- Can we say what she got down to?
So, normally, your core temperature is 37 degrees, right?
If your core goes down below 35,
you're officially in hypothermia.
Her core temperature went down to 13.7 degrees Celsius.
- And then a bit later, there was a kid who went to 13,
who's the coldest anyone has ever been.
- Yeah.
- And apparently, this is more common to work in children.
This idea of sort of freezing yourself
and then coming back to life.
And it's because you have a greater surface area
compared to your volume,
which means that you cool down a lot quicker.
- Oh, of course, and that's why--
- And you wanna do that quick freezing at the start.
That's kind of how it works.
- So, that's why you need to keep babies warm at night
'cause they cool down faster.
So, the thing is when you get really, really cold,
the oxygen demand of your brain lowers drastically.
And if you're cold enough before your heart stops,
that's the key.
That's why doing the CPR is so important.
Then the cell death, which normally happens
when you don't have any circulation, it doesn't happen.
So, her brain needed no oxygen, basically.
- I think it was like, it had 10%
of the oxygen requirements of your brain normally.
- Oh, sorry, go on.
- Well, just to say that because this happened,
they're now using the idea of freezing people down.
If people have had a stroke or if they've had liver failure
or something like that,
the idea now is get people really, really, really cold
and they might survive.
- Yes, and in fact, even though it's quite standard now
or it's done a lot,
but we actually don't know why it works.
And they think that actually,
it's not about the effects of your heart stopping,
which deprives your brain of oxygen.
It's actually about when your heart starts again.
And I didn't know this, but if you have a heart attack
or if your heart stops,
one of the really common ways that you die
is when your heart starts again.
And it's this thing called reperfusion.
And it means that if your heart's been stopped for long enough,
then all the chemistry in your brain has changed so much
in ways that they don't quite understand.
If blood suddenly floods back in there,
it completely messes it up and you die.
- Oh, wow.
- And so in this way,
I think it allows that to happen much more gradually
or it slows the brain down
and allows it to be a bit more controlled.
- Is the word reaper a deliberate use there
of the danger, reperfusion?
- No, it's not reperfusion.
- I see, it's not that-- - I think it's probably
just reperfusion again. - Perfusion with the ray
on the front.
- Yeah, the standard prefix, re.
- Interesting.
- It should put the A in though.
Did you guys read about the two things that happen
when you have hypothermia that are most bizarre?
- Oh, yeah, yes.
If someone has died of hypothermia,
you shouldn't just look on the floor,
look in all the crevices and look in all the shelving units
because they might be curled up in there
because it's a reaction. - Terminal burrowing.
- Terminal burrowing, yeah.
That was interesting.
The other one is taking your clothes off, isn't it?
- Yes, and it seems to happen a lot.
There was one study that was done that looked,
I think, about 70 people who died of hypothermia
and it found almost all of them
did this thing called terminal burrowing,
which, as you say, is where you crawl under a bed
or behind a cupboard or onto a shelf.
And it just feels like, you know,
when you have a cat who's dying,
it crawls to the very corner under a bed.
It's like the last protective hibernation thing.
- Like a really deep instinct, basically.
- Yes, deep.
And the other thing that a quarter of the people did
was this thing called paradoxical undressing,
which, again, people who've had hypothermia
often found completely naked.
And that's because, at first, you know,
you have vasodilation where all your veins
in your extremities constricts
to try and flood blood to your internal organs
to keep you warm when you've got hypothermia.
But then that takes loads and loads of effort
for your muscles and your body just gives up.
All the blood floods back to your extremities
and so suddenly you're like,
"God, bizarrely, I'm really hot."
And you take off all your clothes.
So hot.
- So maybe the song that's getting hot in here
is actually the last throes of someone
who's suffering severe hypothermia.
- That's what it's about, yeah.
- Yeah, the lyric is from Scott's diary, isn't it?
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that if ancient
Mesopotamia had Valentine's cards,
they would probably contain pictures of knees.
- So we've had the flirting,
we've now got together with Torvind,
and now we're sending each other Valentine's cards.
- Now we're on our knees.
- We should've done it the other way around, shouldn't we?
You don't send a Valentine's card
once you've got together with someone.
- Anna, this is exactly what I said to these guys
before we came on air.
- And I disagree, Anna.
I think it's much more common.
I think most Valentine's cards are bought by people
joylessly on the 13th of February in a train station.
(laughing)
- I thought you always put, like,
from anonymous on your Valentine's cards,
that's the whole point of them.
- I put anonymous on all the ones I send,
apart from the one to my wife.
(laughing)
- Should I explain the fact?
- Yeah, yeah.
- So this is a new study about,
they looked at a load of cuneiform texts.
This is some scientists at the University of Finland,
and they looked at loads of phrases
that are about emotions,
and they looked at what parts of the body
were used in those phrases.
And they found that happiness is mostly felt
in the liver, for instance.
Shard and Freud are mostly in the lip.
- Amazing that Shard and Freud was on the list
of what was a really basic,
it was like happy, sad, anger, Shard and Freud are.
- On the lip?
- On the lip, yeah.
- You kind of curl your lip.
- And they found that love was in order,
in the knee, liver, heart, back, and male genitalia.
- Sounds about right.
- That's like that song, my neck, my back.
- It's like, head, shoulder, knee, my liver.
- Like, head, shoulders, knees and toes.
Knee, liver, heart and back, genitalia.
- I would struggle to pinpoint where my liver was,
as in if I wouldn't know where to say
if I was feeling something in my liver.
- The reason that that is a thing is that
when you open up a body after someone's died,
the liver is so big compared to everything else,
you would naturally think that was a really important
part of the body.
- I'm just really impressed that they had that knowledge of,
as in like, that knowledge was widespread,
that that was a phrase.
- Well, they didn't know where it was, I suppose,
necessarily if you were an ordinary guy.
You'd just say, like, in the same way,
I'd say my heart bleeds for you,
and that would, I guess, show sympathy
and you'd say it's associated with the heart.
You might say, oh, my liver erupts with rage.
But it is true, the liver seems to have been the heart
for hundreds and hundreds of years and loads of civilizations.
And they had, it was so important that they thought
that gods imprinted their desires on livers.
So, and this is in ancient Mesopotamia,
but when you sacrifice a sheep, let's say,
its liver would then be taken out
and they used to make clay liver models
of the exact shape of the liver
that that sheep had had inside it.
And then they would analyze the models
like you'd read a poem and that would tell them the future.
'Cause they thought the god will have put their desire
and the future onto the liver shape of this sheep.
- But how do you know you've got the right sheep?
It just feels like a very inefficient system.
- I think God knows, I think maybe God changes the shape
as it's being sacrificed.
So God sees that you're sacrificing that sheep
and then quickly molds the liver into that shape.
I'm not sure exactly that logic.
- No, we shouldn't, we shouldn't try.
Where is Mesopotamia again, is it Turkey?
- Iraq.
- Iraq, yeah.
And we're talking 2,500 BC-ish.
- Long time ago.
- Oh, it's a very long time ago.
But this is--
- That is civilization.
- It sort of is.
We're all this writing these cuneiform tablets.
And so we keep finding out more and more about it
'cause more are found.
They've survived the test of time.
These amazing clay tablets that are found
in their hundreds and thousands in hordes
whenever they--
- It's 'cause they're made of clay, right?
- Exactly, yeah, it was--
- Not like Balencian's cards.
- Exactly, for all we know, there were millions of them.
So it was a huge trade back then.
'Cause it was thought up until recently
that 1,500 BC was when we started kissing.
- You mean the oldest depiction we found
or we actually found a couple locked in--
- No, the oldest depiction of it.
But actually we now have records via cuneiform
that show us that back then they were very romantic
and they were kissing and not just within marriage,
they were also kissing as dates and socially and so on.
And there's only one other major contestant
to say that it's older, which is a kiss
that may have happened between a Neanderthal
and a human over 100,000 years ago.
And they know this because they found a microbe inside
on the skull of a human, but you would only get it
from a Neanderthal.
So they know that a bit of tonsil hockey was going on.
- Well, they were playing that game where you--
- Pass a balloon. - Pass a egg, pass a balloon.
- Oh, an egg. - An egg?
- You pass on, is it not an egg from one mouth to the next?
What did you think it was?
- It was of a big mouth.
- Those are quite big.
- Yeah, you could do it with a quail's egg.
But again, that's quite socially restrictive.
- Was it like scrambled or poached
or the kind of egg which is--
- I'm thinking in shell.
I'm sure we did it with eggs.
- I mean, you can fit an egg in your mouth,
but it is a choking hazard,
I would say. - Oh, yeah.
It's not sexy, I think.
Ugh, it's locked behind my teeth.
(laughing)
- I've misunderstood the rules.
- That's very funny.
That's, yeah.
I mean, we say I go weak at the knees.
- Yes, exactly, I was thinking that, yeah.
Yeah, I think knees would be in our list of things.
The weird thing I found was under sexual attraction,
which was one of the simple emotions they had.
The six body parts, was it five?
Five body parts associated with that.
Well, what would you guess was in there?
Eyes, you would think, right?
- I would have thought, firstly, genitals.
I mean, genitals feature so much
in so many other emotions,
like kind of distress or contempt.
Sexual attraction, genitals and penis aren't in there.
It's head, knee, neck, hand and ankle.
- Head, knee, knee, neck, neck and ankle.
- Ankle's a bit of an odd one, isn't it?
- Well, like Victorians.
Like Chilbert and Ankle.
- Yeah, if you've got restrictive social practices.
- What period are we talking about?
- This is the same study.
- This is ancient Mesopotamia.
- Oh, right.
'Cause there's a whole subcategory now
of celebrity spotting on celebrities' knees.
- Not that period.
We're not looking at that period.
- Is it like wiki knees or something?
- No, it's like how if we look at a sort of photo
of Meghan Markle, you'll see Casper,
the friendly ghost's face on her knee.
- Oh, there was a thing where,
oh no, I'm getting it wrong.
I thought Sandy Tuxwick might have been on someone's knees.
- She was, exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
There's a lot of faces that are appearing on knees recently.
- I would presume it's normally,
I mean, no disrespect to the glorious Sandy.
It's normally people with quite wrinkly faces
who are being spotted in other people's knees.
- No.
- It surely is very rarely,
'cause knees are knobbly, you know, wrinkly.
- Wrinkly?
My knees are perfectly smooth.
- Oh. - Yeah.
- Casper the friendly ghost,
doesn't ever notice that.
- Anna, you've been having routine knee Botox knees.
(laughing)
- Knees, they have a lot of nerve endings.
So they are known as an erogenous zone.
And that's because you have nerves that go through your knee
that do everything that in your feet
and up at the top of your thighs as well.
Basically, all the nerves that are in your leg
have to go through your knees.
So they have a lot of nerve endings.
- That's good.
- And the attraction to knees,
the paraphilia of that is called genufilia.
- Oh, like genuflecting?
- Exactly, yeah.
Do you want some more of those, by the way?
- Yes, please.
- Alvin O'Lagnea is the attraction to--
- Alvin, a chipmunk, I can eat.
(laughing)
- It's the midriff.
- Okay.
- The belly button and tummy and stuff.
- Nice.
- Bro midophilia.
- Bro.
- Yeah, it's like--
- Podcasters.
(laughing)
- It's the attraction to body odor.
- Oh, wow.
- And matiaphilia is tough.
It's the attraction to non-normal looking eyes.
And it comes from the Greek term for the evil eye.
- Hard.
- Like those dogs that have one eye of different colors.
- Like David Bowie, I guess.
- And like David Bowie.
- Quite a few of those.
I would think of not sort of unnatural attractions,
like midriffs, you know, a traditionally,
a slightly sexy thing.
So I've got the midriff out.
- It's interesting 'cause a paraffilia by definition
should be attraction to something atypical.
But then when you look at the list,
there was one which is normalphilia,
which is the attraction to normal things.
(laughing)
- Right.
- So is that normal things to be attracted to
or normal things like a table?
(laughing)
That is unusual.
- Oh, that is unusual.
Then yeah, I read one earlier today, weirdly,
nothing to do with this about being sexually attracted
to people falling downstairs.
(laughing)
- What?
- And that's why you always sit down to watch an episode
you'd be afraid of.
(laughing)
- His pants around his ankles.
- Setting my family out of the room.
- Right, everyone out.
- If you've got any videos of yourself falling downstairs
and send it to dad and he'll give you 250 pounds.
(laughing)
- All right, here's a little micro quiz.
Which of these phrases is the oldest?
I'm gonna give you three.
To have someone over your knee.
- Like to spank them kind of thing.
- That's the implication.
- Right.
- A knee slapper.
- That's a joke.
And upon the knees of the gods.
- Oh, I don't know what that one means.
So that's why I would say that would be the oldest
'cause I've never heard of it.
- Okay.
- Do you mean thigh slapper?
I've never heard of a knee slapper.
- A knee slapper is the phrase.
- Is it?
- Yeah.
I think thigh slapper too.
Depends on how funny the joke is.
- Of course.
- Well, how long your legs were?
- And what you wearing?
(laughing)
- For that basketball player,
it was an ankle slapper.
(laughing)
- Okay.
James is saying upon the knees of the gods is oldest.
- Probably knee slapper, I reckon.
- Yeah, I'm gonna say knee slapper as well
because I'll do the third one
just for the sake of having a full house.
- To have someone over your knee.
- Yeah.
- Upon the knees of the gods is ancient Greek.
- What does it mean?
- Well, that's what one would have get.
- Yeah, that was the obvious one, Andy.
- Yeah, well, James got there first.
So maybe you two should fuck up your ideas a bit next time.
- You'd be great in a quiz, Dan.
It's like, what is the capital of France?
Paris.
Oh, that was the obvious answer, guys.
- We knew that as well, actually.
- It did feel like Andy would be pulling
some sort of rock up run for our feet
rather than just going.
- No, I'm a nice guy.
I leave the rock under your feet.
- Right, okay.
- It's the one you're thinking of
is the title of my quiz format.
(laughing)
It's an ancient Greek phrase, theon engounasi,
which means it's beyond human control.
It's like it's in the lap of the gods, actually,
but it's on the knees of the gods.
Okay, a knee slapper is from 1955
and to have someone over your knee takes to 1866,
which is quite something
that someone used that phrase on me recently.
- Say the phrase again?
- To have someone over your knee.
- And someone used that on you?
- Yeah, it was a removals guy
the last time I was moving in the house.
- Yeah.
- I'd left something at the bottom of the staircase, right?
'Cause I was moving down the--
- That's how they fall down the stairs.
(laughing)
- You haven't sent me that video yet, by the way.
I'd paid good money for that.
- I'd put like a glass picture frame
at the bottom of the stairs
and I hadn't moved it out to the van or whatever.
And he said, "I'd have you over my knee
if you were one of my boys."
- It was a whole unusual thing.
- It was much nicer than the way he made it sound.
- I also think that this whole quiz
is leading up to that anecdote.
- Yeah.
- How could you think that?
(laughing)
- When the anecdote was so bad.
- Unless there's one extra bit you're not telling us.
- Nope.
- Okay.
- That's the subtitle of the quiz.
- That's all there is to it.
- Um, here's a song from Chicago,
which I won't sing, but I'll read you the lyrics.
- The band Chicago.
- Or the musical Chicago.
- The musical.
- No, the city.
(laughing)
- That's a buster, isn't it?
- The pizza company.
Um, okay, so it's from the musical.
Why don't we paint the town and all that jazz?
I'm gonna rouge my knees and roll my stockings down.
- Yep.
- That's weird, isn't it?
- Yes, why do they, I've never questioned that before.
I'm gonna rouge my knees.
Hmm.
- Carpet burn.
- It's not carpet burn, Dan.
Like, why would you,
why you'd be deliberately faking a carpet burn
on your knees with rouge?
- Well, that's pretty sexy, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- You wanna know how I got these knees?
I'll never tell.
- So yeah, rouge as in makeup, red makeup.
And this was a popular thing in the flapper period,
which was to put makeup on your knees.
- Like a little face.
- In actual fact, sometimes they put,
there were some images of young women
with quite short skirts and with little faces on their knees.
- Is that one because it's soundly toxic on both knees?
- That's good flirting.
I think that's really good flirting.
If you're opposite someone on a train, for example,
you just, whoop, you hook up your skirt a little bit.
There's your winking face on your knee.
And then you, you know, you see if they notice.
- Yeah, it's good.
- Isn't that good?
I'm sorry, that's creative flirting.
- If you're pulling up your kill
to say that it's winking at you.
(all laughing)
- That's no sparring.
- But yeah, this was the thing.
It was women had started to be able to show their knees
and they decided, well, we're going to make the most of it.
And so they started putting makeup on.
- So it's poor men were suddenly going around saying,
did you know women's knees have smiley face on them?
(all laughing)
That's amazing.
- That's great.
- Only animal with four knees.
- Dogs, cats, elephants.
- Quadrupeds.
- Any quadruped.
- No, no, they don't have countless knees on the back.
No animals have four knees.
Zero, one animal has four kneecaps.
- Yeah.
- And it only has two legs.
(all laughing)
- I know the answer.
Are we still playing Andy's quiz?
'Cause I can get it if yes.
- This is a horrible riddle in a cave in ancient Greece.
It's ridiculous.
Sorry.
What you're saying is that all animals,
all quadrupeds, they have arms and legs rather.
They may walk around on all fours.
- Exactly.
- But their skeleton structure is.
- They have elbows and knees.
They don't have four knees.
- Exactly.
Sorry, that's.
- And there's one bipedal one that has four knees.
- We should just let Dan answer.
- Well, two knees are hidden under a coat of feathers.
- Oh, they're all hidden.
- Are we talking about the same animal here?
- Yeah, we are.
I think you just haven't looked
at the diagrams closely enough.
(all laughing)
- Right, so it's feathered.
- Okay, if it's two-legged and feathered, an ostrich.
- Yes!
James, that's very good, actually.
- Well, it was either that or an emu or a cassowary.
- Whose quiz is better?
Like mine, where it's to get me into a dull anecdote,
or Anna's, where it's a mental shit show.
(all laughing)
I haven't worked out the format,
but I think the kernel of an idea is there.
This is really interesting.
We only found out recently that ostriches
have four kneecaps.
Everything else has two, and sort of four knees.
So if you look at birds like ostriches,
the thing that you might think is a knee,
if you're an idiot, is actually the ankle, right?
Because if you look at those birds--
- The knees are up inside.
- The knees are up inside the feathers, yeah.
- They've got really long feet bones.
- Exactly.
- It's like how horses, like the lower half of their leg,
is actually their middle toe.
Precisely, all animals like that.
But up, though, under their feathers,
they seem to have two sets of knees.
We really don't know why.
Two sets of knees, two sets of kneecaps.
And who knows why, but cassowaries and emus
don't have any at the end.
Dan, back me up on this.
- It's true.
- Yeah.
- It's a great quiz, but the host says back me up, Dan.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that once married,
some Australian Aboriginals spend the rest of their lives
actively avoiding their mother-in-law.
- Hey, didn't know I was an Australian Aboriginal, hey.
- I actually think my mother-in-law's brilliant.
(all laughing)
- So this is a thing that's called avoidance speech.
And a lot of native Australians have this
as part of their culture, where once they're married,
the idea of talking to their in-laws
is suddenly something that's seen as taboo,
and you never do.
And there's quite a few examples of modern-day marriages
where this is still adhered to.
So I was reading a blog by a guy who was saying that
with his parents-in-laws, he can't hand food directly
to them either, as well as not talking to them.
- It must make the egg game very difficult.
(all laughing)
- You can't look at them directly
if he has something that he needs to ask them.
He needs to ask them through the wife.
So she goes and gets their permission
or finds out something for them.
And it's seen as something that's a marker of respect
in these families.
And the same person who was writing this blog,
who did that with his wife, now has that
with his relationship with his daughter's husband.
And then your language gets changed as well.
So they won't say the name.
They'll say my mother-in-law and father-in-law.
They won't use their actual name.
And if they're in a room with them and they're watching TV,
let's say the son-in-laws in the room,
he'll face the wall away.
So he's not acknowledging them.
Why are they watching TV?
That's a very anti-social thing to do.
So annoying.
What's happening now?
And what's happening now?
- No, no, no, please.
My wife just told me what's happening now, not you.
Why do these taboos exist?
That's what I'm really baffled by.
- Well, they are around the world, aren't they?
- It's extraordinary.
Native America, across Africa, Australian originals,
what, and I haven't read an explanation.
- I did read them.
- Which satisfies me.
- It's potentially a respect thing.
It might be a way of preventing any hanky-panky.
- I think it's not.
I think it's gotta be shagging.
- There was a big article I read
called "The Mother-in-Law Taboo" by A.E.M.J. Pans,
which is one of the main papers on this subject.
And he reckons that basically it's to indicate publicly
that the son-in-law and the mother-in-law
are not having sex with each other.
- But it makes me think they are.
That's the weird thing.
It's always in the office.
It's always the two people who are completely pretending
they don't know each other exist
who turn out to have been having a torrid affair.
- Is it?
- It's exactly what I thought.
And also it will make you fancy them.
The more you're told you're not allowed to speak
with someone or stick your tongue down their throat,
the more you want it, don't you?
- A bit of fruit.
- Yes.
Also, why was that bad?
- Why is it bad to have it with your father-in-law?
Why is it bad?
- So the reason is that it happens more
in matrilineal cultures.
So, and it's like this taboo, it does happen.
And that's true.
And it tends to be that the women
have very particular roles that they have.
And the idea is that your mother-in-law
is not taking over the job
of what your wife is supposed to do.
- I see.
- So there might be lots of different things
that a wife is supposed to do in this culture,
one of which is sleeping with the husband,
but they're trying to show
that this definitely isn't happening
and that the generation has moved on
to the next generation.
That's the idea.
- And I suppose that's the woman,
other woman that you would see most often.
So if you were going to shag anyone else,
it would probably be your wife's mum.
And I think sometimes mother-in-law taboos
also apply to like your mother-in-law's mate.
Sometimes mother-in-law can be a bit of a broader term.
So it can be a few women who are also really close to you.
- Yeah, we should say these taboos,
they vary a lot between different groups.
So in some cases, it's completely avoiding them physically.
In some, it's using a particular,
like a different language to address them.
And in some, it's using a subset of language.
So there's a group called Deer Bell is a language.
And the main language is called Gouel.
And the language for your mother-in-law is Dianghi.
I'm trying to pronounce it wrong.
But it's like, it's missing particular words
that might be erotic flash points.
- Sorry, like what?
- Oh loads, erotic flash points.
- Like ankle.
- I mean, there are loads, are there?
Pubic hair, sweaty smell, you know.
You don't want to mention that
in case things just pop off suddenly.
So yeah, yeah.
- So you're saying you don't say that those words
in front of your mother-in-law either?
- I'd have to have a really good reason
to talk about pubic hair in front of my mother-in-law.
- Exactly, I think anyone would.
- But that's the thing, it's not mad taboo
against sleeping with your mother-in-law.
- I read one thing.
This is by a US historian called Hampton Sides.
And that the reason I'm saying it's by him
is 'cause I don't believe it.
But he wrote that in the Navajo people,
husbands are not allowed to look at their mother-in-laws
and it's so important
that the mother-in-laws would wear little bells
on their clothes so that he could hear them coming.
- I think that's true.
- I just can't believe it's true.
But it was, he's a proper historian.
- I think that's true.
- Like he's a bird and they're the cat.
- Yeah, exactly.
- I think there was a first-hand account.
And it's similar to the Kaurawai people in West Papua
who shout when they're going round corners
for exactly the same reason.
The mother-in-law, son-in-law taboo,
they'll shout to make clear if a son-in-law's there,
go away, and also if the son-in-law's friends
see the mum coming, they'll run and find the son
and say, "She's coming, she's coming."
- That's interesting.
That's like working in a restaurant.
Whenever you go round the corner, you go corner.
- Oh, nice.
- So that people coming in the other direction
don't hit you and you drop all the food.
- Is that when you're going in and out of the kitchen
is where you shout something like that?
- Yeah, at any time, when you're going in a blind corner.
- Well, and like, did your grandparents
always used to honk the horn
going around any corner driving?
(laughing)
- No.
- Didn't they?
It's so embarrassing.
- Oh my God, that time we went to that labyrinth,
it was a nightmare.
(laughing)
- I used to hate it so much.
Every corner, gamma honked her horn.
It was just awful.
Yeah, it was so motivating.
- That's so funny.
- Sometimes I think you have to concentrate really hard
to keep these taboos going.
So there's one in a similar mother-in-law, son-in-law taboo
in southwestern Ethiopia.
And it's a practice called Balisha.
And it's basically that married women
can't speak the name of their husband's mother or father,
but they also can't speak any word
beginning with the same syllable
of their husband or father's name.
So--
- So if my mother-in-law was called Pat,
I couldn't say, what's the word we can use, Pat?
- Pat the dog?
- Yeah, right, I'd have to say, can you stroke the dog?
- What was the name of that World War II general from America?
(laughing)
- Eisenhower.
- What's the name of that postman?
(laughing)
- That's interesting.
- You'd have to concentrate so much.
- But apparently in those cultures where that's the case,
you're taught another language
so that if you were in that situation,
not only will you be able to know what to do,
but you will say words everyone else will know as well.
- And some of them, you do have another language, yeah.
And then some, they're just like,
come up with another word, say stroke,
which isn't the same as passing.
So, you know.
- Horseman stroke.
(laughing)
- Incest taboos.
- Oh, yeah.
- From around the world, including Anglo-Saxon,
I wanted to see if it existed in this country.
And according to the penitential of Theodore,
which is from the seventh century,
if a brother commits fornication with his brother,
he has to do penance for 15 years.
So that's 15 years without eating meat or drinking wine
if you have sex with your brother.
- Okay.
- Climby.
- That's a lot, I don't know.
- That's a lot, that's a lot.
- It's not worth it, it's not worth it, would you say?
(laughing)
- Well, there was a thing in Old England,
the swesterosunu, which is where that's your sister's son.
Right?
- So it's a nephew.
- Yeah, exactly.
But it's specifically with your sister's son
because your sister's son, your nephew,
is definitely related to you by blood.
Because you and your sister have both come
from the same mother,
so you are definitely related by blood
and she has given birth to her son.
- Yeah, so even if there was hanky-panky going on
in any of these situations, it's still related.
- Right.
- Like, if my wife has cheated on me,
my son might not be my own,
but my sister's son is definitely related to me by blood.
So that is a sort of rock solid relationship to form.
- Yeah, that should be where inheritance goes.
I'm surprised that's not where inheritance works more often.
- To the sisters.
- Yeah, 'cause it's the one you can trust, as you say.
- Yeah, yeah, you can't trust anyone.
- We should change the rules.
(laughing)
- Mothers in law?
- Yeah.
- I just found some famous mothers in law.
- Okay.
- Would you remember last time we talked about
L. Frank Baum's mother-in-law?
- We did.
- Until the Gage.
So I thought I'd try and find any more notable
mothers-in-law.
- Yeah.
- The mother-in-law of the Marquis de Sade
was really annoyed with him.
- Oh, is she?
- Yeah.
- Well, a lot of people were.
- Yeah, he ran off to Italy with his wife's younger sister.
- Yeah.
- So she was furious about that.
Also, she's still her mother-in-law.
She's the same mother-in-law even with him.
- You don't need to explain that.
I think that's--
- I think you do.
Why don't you be flattered?
It's like, don't fancy one of my daughters.
You fancy both of them.
- Yeah.
Well, she got him arrested.
She helped the authorities hunt him down.
And he spent most of the rest of his life
in prison or in asylum.
But he had also been committing horrible crimes.
- Yeah.
Jumping back to the L. Frant Baum very quickly,
the Tin Man in the movie, he had a son.
Do you know who his mother-in-law was?
- The Tin Man's wife.
- So the actor who plays the Tin Man has a son.
Who's his mother-in-law in real life?
- Well, will it be his wife?
- His wife's mom.
- So he got married to someone who had a notable mother.
Who became his mother-in-law.
- Dan's quiz feels like the least good of all.
This is not guessable.
- It's got the best reveal.
It was Judy Garland.
Because Dorothy had a daughter, Liza Minnelli.
Liza Minnelli married the Tin Man's son.
- Did not know that that's cool.
- Yeah.
- That is cool.
- There you go.
- That is quite a good quiz where the questions
are completely stupid all over the place.
But the answers are absolutely amazing.
Isn't that what QI is?
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That's all of our sexy romantic facts.
(laughing)
If you'd like to get in contact with any one of us
or send us a Valentine.
- Hope you weren't listening with your mother-in-law.
We can all be found on our very social media accounts.
I'm on @Sribeland on Instagram, James.
- My Instagram is @NosageThink as James Harkin.
- Andy.
- I'm on Blue Sky at @AndrewHondurem.
- And Anna, if they want to get to us as a group.
You can email podcast.QI.com or tweet @NosageThink
or Instagram @NosageThinkasafish.
- That's right, yep.
Or you can go to our website, nosagethinkasafish.com.
All of the previous episodes are up there.
There's bits of merchandise that you can check out as well.
And there is Club Fish, which is our secret club
where we put up a lot of bonus episodes and so on.
It's really fun.
Join today if you haven't.
Otherwise, just come back next week.
We'll be back with another episode
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[MUSIC PLAYING]