Hi everybody Andy here just before we start this week's show wanted to let you know we have a very special guest on
This week Anna is away very sadly. She's on her holidays. But the great news is that in her place
We have the absolutely magnificent Rachel Paris now
I'm sure you may have heard of Rachel if you haven't frankly wherever you're being guys. She's a
Comedian she's a musician. She's an actor an improviser. She does it all
She has been on so many brilliant shows and she is a musical comedian as well
She tours the country with a grand piano performing
Magnificently funny solo shows. She's basically the heir to Tom Lear and Tim Minchin put together and on top of it all
She has just published her first book. It's called Advice from Strangers
And it's a kind of comedy book slash memoir slash feminist manifesto
All centered around the time that she traveled around the country asking her audiences to give her pieces of advice
It's funny. It's serious. It's hilarious. It's uplifting and we're so glad that she could come on the show because as you're about to hear
She was absolutely great. So that's it without further ado on with the show
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Covert Garden
My name is Dan Schreiber. I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray James Harkin
And it's our very special guest Rachel Paris and once again
We have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order here
We go starting with fact number one and that is Rachel
My fact is that list the composer played the piano so hard in his concerts that he regularly broke piano strings and
Superfans would nick those strings and make bracelets out of them
I've so I don't play the piano
But it feels like that's quite a hard thing to do to break a string
It's a break of a guitar string, right? Yeah, but piano string. It's rare
He's not the only person to ever do that, but I think that I think that it happened to him all the time
That was like his thing is I'm gonna break this. Why was he so angry? I don't know. Maybe he just had like really heavy hands or something
There were there were comments that he had massive hands
Which allowed for him to stretch a lot of piano players say that that's not actually a thing
There was certain there were certain patterns that he would play that a big hand doesn't necessarily
We actually have plaster casts of his hands, so we know exactly how big they are. Yeah, do you mean in your home?
They're here tonight
We find that his fingers were slender and long, but they weren't like massively long light
I think right man enough had really big hands man enough had 12 inches and his hands I
Measured mine mines nine inch span because I've got pretty good small hands
But a big stretch on but yeah, when you measure 12 inches out on a rule, that's insane
So right man enough was known for having like absurdly big hands and you can only play right man enough pieces
If you've got those you can fake it a bit
But you have to do some very clever maneuvering if Rachmaninoff was alive today
Yeah, and if he if he did that mine, you know when you mime a phone
Your thumb in your little finger. Yeah, he would it's the top of his head with his thumb knock his hat off
He could only mime a car phone from the 80s
So this whole thing of him banging on the piano
He was a passionate amazing player and that was kind of a thing. He was like a rock and roll list
Like rock and roll wasn't a list but fortunately if he did smash up a piano
He always had two pianos on stage with them
That's such a cool idea and I'm not sure if it was necessarily because he knew he was gonna smash up a piano
It's because he was such a showman that he wanted to give both sides of his face basically to the audience
So he didn't have a roadie bringing on the piano when he broke his like dragging it along. I think he would drag it out
Really? Yeah, it's like I read an account of a gig where he
He he dragged the second piano out and I think if you were an audience member there was a second piano
You would be slightly disappointed if it didn't come into play. Yeah, you think he hadn't given it his all
It's like a Checos piano, isn't it?
And he had these like beautiful flowing locks of hair which made him very popular as he really had the whole like Elvis
You know someone coined the term listomania
Yeah, that people were absolutely obsessed with him the way they are sort of today about pop stars
But he actually had the talent to earn it. But yeah, people would ask for locks of his hair
Yes, and they would collect his cigarette butts
They would wear them in the chains on their necklaces with his initials
There is it like it's a it did happen and apparently everyone hated it because she was carrying another stinky old cigar end basically
They were like Susan
I was reading listomania does sounds like it was a bit of a just like beatlemania
You know where it was just screaming girls and stuff like that
But apparently the original term the mania was used in terms medically
It was it wasn't just that people were just getting too excited
They genuinely thought that this might be leading to medical conditions
So if list came into town, they'd be like, you know, we got to get doctors ready. We got I'm making that up
To effect. So that's what the mania meant. It was right people actually got ill. Yeah, exactly
I was thinking that his performance is a bit like you too, Andy and Rachel you do ostentatious, right?
Which is an improvised Jane Austen play and his concerts were quite a bit like that
I was reading it's a while since I've seen you two live by
Paulie received
Well, he would like get what a member of his audience to give him a little sort of motif a little theme
And they might just go do-do-do-do-do or something maybe not like the Nokia theme
And then he would spend the rest of the concert just like doing the amazing bits
He had a very interesting life, so he was he was a prodigy as a child and he was your hot house by his
No
These was like doodling around to they were but it was kind of interesting just on that
We'll go back to that but like because mass market pianos are just coming and also the French Revolution had just happened
So you had pianos were only played by posh people and they were really really expensive and you could only get them if you
Super posh but then
Suddenly just around the time of Mozart and then list after him
Suddenly you could get cheap pianos and that meant that children could play it children could practice it
And so you had these children coming up who were as good as the you know posh
You know and also all the previous pianos were cheap if slightly spattered with the blood of aristocrats
Some somewhere
But so you get so his dad took him around his dad worked him like a dog for years
You know years his father died when Franz was 15 and he he took pupils as a 15 year old prodigy
And then had this incredible performing career until I think his late 30s maybe and then step back
Yeah, because he had a lover a countess love hello who who encouraged him to compose
She said look this before me is all well and good
he's making a lot of money, but and he just kind of stepped back he moved to Weimar and
Just started composing who was the lover do you know? Yes? She was called countess
No, sorry. She was a princess. He was married to a countess and traded up to Princess Caroline von sein Wittgenstein
Anyway, she left her own marriage for him
And there was this whole thing about whether they could annul the marriage so they could be her marriage
So they could be married and the Pope agreed to it and then he changed his mind
It was a big old thing
But yes, so he took a really crap job as a couple meister at the court of Weimar and he had to wear
Archaic clothes to perform. Oh, well cuz he was a rock star and then he went
Suddenly it's like a music beef eater or something
I did think of ostentatious a bit and that you're basically dressing and stuff that was the hide-of-fashion 200 years ago
And the pay was so bad. It only paid for his cigars
But we don't know how quality his cigars were to be fair. Yeah. Yeah, that's true. Yeah, he could have sold the one eBay afterwards
Yeah, and Caroline de sein Wittgenstein
She was a Catholic princess wasn't she and she got him into Catholicism and then he went on to try and become the Pope's
personal
He wanted to be the official composer to the Pope
But he was turned down and the alleged story of why he was turned down is that apparently he was playing in the
Cloisters one day and all the nuns in the nunnery ran to him and started kissing him and
And the Pope decided well if he's like that if he's gonna have that effect on women
We're not gonna have him as the official how hot was this guy
Was I think he was he was six foot two. We've established. He had big old hands
Yeah, and he had a lot of mistresses in his life
He did he did in later life take holy orders, but minor holy orders. He didn't become a full priest
I think maybe because it would have involved of our celibacy and he was just he wasn't quite ready
He just did it as a hobby
Well, here's a weird thing in 2018 in Spain's got talent
He didn't
Showed up
He did not show up itself
However, he kind of did in a way because one of the competitors of that year was a guy called Michael Andreas
Who's supposedly the great-great-grandson of lists really?
Supposedly and he said to be the son of not only list but of one of his prodigies lists prodigies
Who was called Sophie mentor and Sophie mentor was supposedly the best his favorite and she did have a kid
But by all the accounts she had it with someone else, but this guy's claiming that he is the great descended from both lines
Yeah descended from both lines
So he's even picked like a mother that you can't trace it back to so supposedly we have a descendant who's incredible by the way
I've seen him play. He was a prodigy as well. He was a child prodigy
He was winning competitions since he was five years old
Rachel because you're a classical pianist. I am I think I was a prodigy
Piano competitions when I was small and I was teaching when I was 15. Really. Yeah. Wow. We teaching what I'm saying
Is you don't have to be a prodigy to teach at 15?
Were you teaching smaller children or were you teaching? Yeah smaller children. So I was like grade eight and I was teaching grade one
That's really impressive. That's a guy that you're smoking at the moment. I like that
I do think if you've got the willingness to practice and basic like strong musical aptitude and if you start young then you're gonna be a child prodigy
Moving down like fuck wasn't that shit hot, but like, you know, that's so interesting. Do you hear how words get there?
Do you guys know Lang Lang? Yeah, one of the big concerto players piano players of recent years and he's a global name
He only got into playing piano. He was a child prodigy by the way. Oh, yeah
I want to see Rachel and Britain's got talent. A little kid comes up. Like this again. Go on. Child prodigy, it just means has a piano and the time
He was inspired hearing Liszt's Hungarian Rhapsody in number two by Tom from Tom and Jerry
And that's how he got into playing the piano. Oh, I totally grew up watching that. I can really understand that. Yeah
I was called the cat concerto and it was Tom was playing piano Jerry's on the inside gets woken up and they start having a fight
It's an amazing piece. Supposedly a lot of piano players began their love watching this one cartoon of Tom and Jerry
And then when you get older the the piece. Yeah, it's the Hungarian Rhapsody, which is already a phenomenal piece incredibly difficult to play
I can play the first few pages and then it gets to the really hard bit and I'm like no, but in the cartoon which I had on VHS
So I've watched it over and over and over again. They mess with it
They pull it around and they go into like the can can and they go into little jazz bit in the middle of it
And then return to the piece. So when I got older and I started playing it, I had I had be like, oh, oh the can can doesn't happen here
This bit doesn't turn into jazz. So confusing. I've got one other connection that Liszt made in his life
So we said before Liszt had big old hands, right? Yeah. Yeah. There's someone else he met who also had big hands
George Elliot. George Elliot. George Elliot. We have a running fact on this podcast that George Elliot had great big hands
She had one big head. She could play right now, but only the right hand
Did she have different size hands? Yeah, but we don't. Supposedly, she was a dairy maid in younger life and she turned the butter
I milked the cows. I milked the cows and this gave one absolutely honking hulk fist
Wow. And if you look at pictures of her, they never show her right hand. They didn't have enough paint. Didn't have enough paint
But basically old big hands herself. George Elliot. Big hand herself. Sorry. In 1854 she visited Liszt with her lover George Lewis
They were fleeing scandal because he'd left his wife to be with female George Elliot and they made friends
They had coffee together. Imagine the conversations they would have had. Wow. High five
[Laughter]
Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is James
Okay, my fact this week is that the downhill skiing at the Nagano Olympics in 1998 was postponed due to snow
[Laughter]
Too much. Too much. Too much snow
If you go on Encyclopedia Britannica about the Nagano Olympics, it says the most memorable aspect of the Nagano Games was arguably the weather
Oh, wow. It said it brought heavy snow and periods of freezing rain. There was even an earthquake
An earthquake? Yes, that's incredible. Where is Nagano? It's in Japan
Oh, well that's prone to earthquakes, isn't it? You want to pick somewhere right in the middle of a tectonic plate if you don't want to
Yeah, it wasn't like a massive one, but everyone felt it who was there at the time
If you were halfway through a ski jump, you'd be the only person who didn't feel it
And you'd land and everyone else would have fallen over a door
Maybe the earth moves to your advantage by about 50 meters until you've broken the world record
[Laughter]
But yeah, the LA Times said at the time, they said, "We are seeing firsthand the fundamental problem of the Winter Olympics they are held during the winter"
It's like the ski resorts often have not enough snow, don't they? Or they say, "Oh, the snow hasn't happened" or "It's fallen"
Do you ever get the wrong kind of snow? I feel like that's a...
Yeah, I've been dragged into the world of snow by my husband
Oh, you walked through that wardrobe, didn't you?
That's it, yeah, what a nightmare
My husband's a huge skier in snowboarder
I am not never skied before meeting him and I get dragged to ski resorts now
and I keep trying to learn to ski really painfully
But also, yeah, the cancellations for snow happen at ski resorts all the time
They're like, "Yeah, the slope's closed because of snow"
Yeah, I think that skiing is something that you should be a child prodigy at, right?
Because it's easier to learn when you're a child and you don't have the fear
I learn when I was in my 30s and I say, "Learned"
It sounds like we're at a similar standard
It's the worst thing
I feel like for me at the moment, skiing is simply trying to stop
It's all it is, I'm going to deep plow all the way down
Why aren't I stopping?
Deep plow, what's that?
When you put your skis in a V-shape
I see
Whenever I've gone skiing, I've mastered the going fast and the spinning
and the, you know, not the spinning, sort of the sharp turns
Spinning, spinning as well
I've mastered the roly-poly down the hill as well
But I've never mastered the sideways stop
So no matter how cool I've looked, I've always had to go into the big V-plow
Hangerly
Like Spider-Man trying to hold the train from falling off the track
That's a pretty cool way of describing what you're doing
I'm sure it looks that good when you're doing it
That's going down, doing his pizza
He's got Spider-Man, Spider-Man
With great power!
Oh, do you think Spider-Man's ever been skiing?
Sorry, never mind
But would he enjoy it?
Spiders don't like the cold, do they?
He's not a real spider
He's not a real man
He's neither, he's a freak
He's just a boy
I'm the only one who's never been skiing
I'm surprised you've never been skiing
Why?
Not because you seem like someone who would have been skiing
Because you're posh
I think that's why we're all dancing around
I think if people were to meet me and you
They'd think I haven't been skiing and you have been skiing
I see
But it just goes to show that you shouldn't judge a book by its cover
People would look at me and say he must be just eating pies and drinking blue wicked
Too much to be skiing
People look at me and see like polo and croquet
I'm afraid so
Oh dear
You guys all know this and it's all really common
So ski jumpers, they have to get a little friction on the bottom of the skis as possible
Because I guess you get loads of ski
But they got fast
Yeah, and the plasticky on the bottom
And they drip hot wax onto it
And then they iron their skis sometimes
To get the wax distributed
Yeah, and all the ski makers are really secretive
Like competitive ski teams are really secretive about the ingredients of their wax
Oh really?
Yeah, because they give the bottles boring looking labels or code names and all this
But the wax wears off as you're going down
So that's a problem
And in 2007 a pair of chemists who were called Peter Styring and Alex Ruth
They developed, I love this, skis which wax themselves
Self waxing ski
So you pour the liquid wax into a little reservoir
Which is between your boot and the ski
Self waxing, you're doing a lot of the work, the skis aren't doing it
Exactly, yeah, but then it's there
So you've got it like an air, so you've got a bubble beneath it
And then you're not allowed to have any means of power down there
But the wax feeds into this little tube
Which runs all the way along the ski surface
And as you go into a turn, you put pressure down, don't you?
And it sort of pops a bit of the wax along the bottom of the ski
That's clever
I don't know if it was allowed or banned or anything like that
It feels super off the books
It does, doesn't it?
The coldness of the Winter Olympics, it is a problem
It's like a big problem for a lot of the events
One of the early day things that happened in 1924 games
Is that the guys who were having to use the stopwatches
In order to monitor how fast you were crossing the line
Their hands just got too cold and so they were just getting it wrong
All the time
So there was actually a gold medalist who won
Who was called Charles Dutrell, who was an American
Who won his event despite being utterly perplexed
By the fact that he'd managed it
Because he'd never ever trained for this event before
He came in thinking, "I'm going to come last of everyone"
And he ended up winning it
He didn't even train for the event, he sort of just showed up and did it
Are you telling us that the stopwatch didn't work?
Exactly, the stopwatch ran a bit too long
Oh sorry, a bit too quick
The guys' hands were freezing and it was a big problem
So, yeah
Did you hear about Remy Lindholm in the Beijing Olympics quite recently?
No
He did the 50K cross country ski
Well, it was 50K, but it got short into 30K because the weather was so bad
And at the very end, he needed a heat pack to treat his frostbitten penis
Apparently, he should have kept it in his trousers
He forgot one of his poles
And the thing is, this is the second time that that happened to him in less than a year
Does he have an unusually frostbite prone penis, I wonder
It feels like he must do it, there must be something there
Maybe he's not wearing a crucial thermal pant layer or something
None of his mates have told him
Yeah, the thermal pants are available
He's still going on one thin pair of M&S briefs
The article I read didn't presuppose what was going on
Yeah, I think that now it's happened a second time
I think we are allowed to ask the question
Maybe you're prone to it once it's happened once
Oh yeah
The tip never really recovers
Bloody hell
It's just a guess, you know, I'm not an expert
Yeah
Anyway, that was the thing that happened
Poor guy
I found another quite funny cancellation of a sports event
In 2016, the Premier League match between Manu and Bournemouth
Sorry, I said Manu, that's Manchester United
For people who don't know
And that's football
American football
No, I knew you wouldn't know
You don't look like a football fan
Too busy teeing up for another trucker
What?
That's polo 10
Well, half of it was
So they had to cancel the match at the very last minute
When a suspicious item was found in the gents' loo at Old Trafford
But the suspicious item had been put there
By the security firm that was monitoring for suspicious items
So they'd done it as a trial test thing
This is what a suspicious item looks like
Yeah, like, can you see, if you can find it, what's the drill, what will you do
But they accidentally left it there
And the match got cancelled
Wow, so funny, I wonder what it looked like
Probably had wires coming out
Exactly, they had a big sort of black cartoon ball
With a fuse coming out
And bomb written in white on the side
Have you guys heard of the, this is an amazing thing, it was proposed
In 2002, it was a British firm called Snowdonia Gateway Limited
They wanted to build a revolving ski slope
Okay?
Okay
So what it would be, it would be 13 stories high
And it would be kind of like a record player, but on an angle
Okay, if you can imagine that
And you would start down the slope
As the slope revolved and moved upwards
Okay, now the incline was going to be 300 meters long
But the plan was, if you skied slowly enough
And if it got up to its full revolving speed
Permanent skiing
Wow
But the speed that I skied
Which is really, really slope like
I'm going to be going backwards around that
You'd fall off the top
Yeah, and they would generate permanent fresh snow with snow guns
It's really clever
That's extraordinary
So it never happened, sadly, as far as I can tell
Is it because it's completely impossible to build?
Weirdly, no
I think it was just too ambitious an example of the thing
So these days, I think there is at least one rotating disc slope ski simulator
In Europe
I think it's someone like the Netherlands
But it's quite small, it's not 13 stories high
And allowing you to like a sort of ski giant mountain thing
That's so cool
It just sounds so much fun
Wow, it sounds incredible
I can see the problem that if you were at a certain speed
You would just be stuck
Like you would have to be rescued, right?
Well, they can turn it, they can slow it
Yeah, at the end of the day
Like they're not going to stop it for every middle speed skier, right?
No, they have to get down eventually
It might be like the waltzes that you just have a one go
And then you have to come off and other people go on
Imagine the poor guy, poor guy, right?
It's my frostbitten penis twice
He's going to have one more ski in a very nice time
Oh, no!
I'm never coming off!
Okay, it is time for fact number three
That is Andy
My effect is that the 18th century health writer
William Buchan told his readers
That anyone suffering from persistent deafness
Might benefit from pouring their own urine
Into their ears each night
That's really good
I'm just looking at my notes
Because I paraphrased what you said to us
And I've written
In 1772, William Buchan told people to piss in their own ears
Wow
He pretty much did
Pretty much, right?
Can I just say, it does seem possible
That the first person who heard this advice
Simply misheard
Oh, yeah?
No, they are deaf
Did they say, you know, "I know a guy in touring"
Or "Do you want some tea? I'm pouring"
Are they reliable sources, right?
Well, William Buchan was this writer
He wrote this book called "Domestic Medicine"
Which was basically the Beal and Endle
Of health advice in the 18th century
He was a proper doctor
And I think it was actually pretty good
As in he wasn't a quack
He was really trying
And it had chapters on absolutely everything under the sun
One of the chapters is on deafness
And he writes, "A gentleman on whose veracity I can depend
Told me that after using many things to no purpose
For an obstinate deafness, he was at last advised
To put a few drops of his own urine warm into his ears
Every night and morning
From which he received great benefit"
Okay
He does say you could also use a salt solution
Would it work?
Like, let's say you've got wax in your ears
Would it moisten them, perhaps?
I might do
You'd need phenomenal aim
That's the problem
That's the...
It's a few drops
That's a good detail that I didn't know
When I tried it earlier this morning
That would have been very helpful
But he also had advice in the book for putting onions
Onion juice in your ear
In order to help with deafness
So is it just a sort of like any liquid that has some kind of
I don't know, acidic property or something?
This is the thought slightly is that
Earache will eventually go
And the thought is that maybe what it was
Was a sort of pseudo thing
Where it was just making it feel a bit bearable
And then you mistake in the fact that it
That it happens because people still parents
There's blogs all over on those mum blogs
We'll be missing a little bit
No, using onions
Using onions
No, it's a community, Andy
That book, by the way, "Domestic Medicine"
There is an argument that it might not have been
Written by William Buchan
And might have been written by friend of the show
Willie Smelly
Who's Willie Smelly?
The original gynecologist
The original midwife
Midwife
Not that Willie Smelly
The other Willie Smelly
The encyclopedia
The first editor
Yeah, so there are two famous Willie Smellys
From the 19th century
And 19th century, one of them
And this one, according to Smelly's son
Who's called Ker Smelly
He said that Willie Smelly
Might have entirely rewritten his original draft
So Buchan handed in his draft
And then Smelly sort of put all of his own bits in
So it could be that his was normal
And then Smelly added the urea stuff
I wouldn't want Willie Smelly's urine in my ears
Also, the interesting thing about this book
Is that it was sort of a sort of equivalent
To what I'm trying to say would be a magician
Releasing all of the trade secrets
Of how to do tricks
Because doctors at the time
Didn't want patients to know this kind of thing
They actually looked down on this book
Saying you shouldn't be giving this information
Out to the patients
Of what we do
And so he kind of put it all in
Might you put like just one bit of advice in there
That was wrong
To try and trick people into
Or a bit like those
Like internet spoiler things
It's like, step one is this
But for more, contact your doctor
He wrote a lot of medical advice
William Buchan
He wrote this book called Advice to Mothers
Which again, quite democratising
Of becoming a parent
Oh god, I'm strapping in for this
He wrote, well
He wrote to mothers that, and I'm quoting here
In all cases of dwarfishness or deformity
99 out of 100 are owing to the folly, misconduct
Or neglect of mothers
Wow
Which was, I'm sure, science at the time
But...
It's just nice
For mothers to feel more guilt
There isn't enough going around
Yeah, I think mothers didn't feel bad
Until he really advanced the form
So, yeah, yeah, yeah
He was an amazing guy
Like, he started young
He was a child prodigy, actually
He was going around pissing at other children's ears
Like, we're joking about this
But I do feel like, as it goes on
This is proving my point
It's just like, anyone who excels at anything
Probably excels as a child
Yeah, it's true, yeah
No, he supposedly was the amateur doctor
To the village when he was still at school
So he was so...
So annoying
Oh, it's not like...
You'd be so annoyed by him
Wouldn't you be the baby doctor?
Not if he was helping you
No, you would be annoyed
Really?
Especially if he's helping you
What doctors have to put up with
Particularly baby doctors
It sounds horrific
Imagine a 12-year-old boy coming to you
When you're pregnant going, "Oh, it's your fault!"
You haven't been behaving right
You know, one of the things that Buckin suggested
That when you...
If you'd burnt yourself
The cure was to hold it back near a fire
What?
Yeah
I did read that
Hold it quite near the fire
There was a few other things
Like you should put salt on it
Salt?
Yeah
It's like the old saying goes
Rub salt in the wound
And everyone's a winner
It does sound like he was like a child doctor
But he didn't go on to learn any more
Just left the knowledge he had at 12
One of the earliest records
For treating hearing loss
Is from the Ebers Papyrus
Which is an old ancient Egyptian papyrus
And that's specifically for wax buildup
And they suggest that you put olive oil
Red lead, ant eggs, bat wings
Or goat urine into your ears
So they do go for the urine quite early
And also, olive oil, use that now
Olive oil for blood tears
Yeah
Do you hang the bat wings out like a...
They're literally flapping out your ears
Rachel, you've just written a book of advice
Effectively, based on old advice from strangers
Correct
Is there any honkingly bad advice that you received?
Because I saw some of the gigs where you collected advice
Yeah, correct
Well, some of it I just really didn't agree with
Some of it was very individual
Like acquire as many guinea pigs as possible
And that openness is bound to follow
Which I really profound as a previous owner of a guinea pig
I don't think that's true
I don't think they improve in large numbers
Yes
Well, you didn't try
No, that's true
You only have one
You didn't pass through the threshold, which is nine
In Peru, they eat guinea pigs, don't they?
So if it was a Peruvian person
It might be just a way of, you know, stocking up before lockdown
Yeah
Give a man a guinea pig and a leap for a day
Give a man two guinea pigs
As long as what is male and once female
And they're both of the right age
They're sort of, yeah
And they fancy each other
And this consent
Yeah
And he'll eat for the rest of his life
I also, I enjoyed and really disagree with the advice
Given smile whenever possible
Which I think is a very old school idea of like
Just whack a smile on no matter what you're feeling
And it made me think of all those songs of like
Smile when your heart is breaking
Put on a happy smile, you know
Like all the wartime songs about smiling through the war
Smiling through loss
Smiling through tragedy
Smiling through heartbreak
Which was very of the 20th century
It was very keep calm and carry on
Bottle it in
Yeah, exactly
Don't let your smile ruin my day
Bottle it up
Pour a few drops into your ears
Each night and morning
So yes, I did not agree with that advice
But it's quite common advice it's still given
Do you know the first agony art was?
No
So far as we know?
No, I don't know
Clarina
Plenty of the elder
No, okay, so I would say this is, James is closer in time
Possibly the 1600s
It's probably really in the break
In 1691 there was a guy called John Dunton
And he had an experience where he was having an affair
He needed some advice anonymously
But there was nowhere to ask
And so rather than thinking I'll just leave that
He thought, "Wow, what if there was a place I could ask?"
And so he invented an entire magazine
The Athenian Gazette, which its job was basically
To just answer questions
So members of the public would just send in their questions
And everyone on staff would write answers to
And that is sort of like the modern version of the agony art
There's probably examples of things like the Oracle of Delphi
And all that sort of like the original agony art
So this Athenian Gazette
Or Athenian Mercury, it was also called
It was supposedly this group of a dozen of the best astrologers
And mathematicians and philosophers in the whole of London
And scholars and all this
Actually, it was just him and his brother-in-law
And two other blokes
And they were complete amateurs
And they didn't know anything
But people loved writing in the questions
So the questions included
What is the cause of suction?
This is about love and relationships
Why do Scotchman hate swine's flesh?
Good questions
I really like this one
If I'm thinking of committing any great and enormous crime and sin as adultery
But do not personally and actually commit it
Am I guilty of the crime and sin?
That's a great question
Wow, I mean, that's given to agony aunts today
Yeah, that's true
Here's a couple more
Why does love generally turn to coldness and neglect after marriage?
I don't write it, Polly, if you're listening, I'm just reading it
It was a bit QI-ish actually
So one of them was
Why should the putting of a man's hand in cold water
Occasion a sudden emission of urine?
Yeah, we have done that
Yeah, and they said
And I have done that again in life
And they said it's not true
They pointed out it's a vulgar error
What?
Sorry
It was a coincidence then
That you pissed yourself
We did that to our baby last week
Wait, wait
So he had a fever
We were in hospital doing some checks
And they said to check for a urine infection
We really need a urine sample
And obviously it's a baby
You can't just make him wait
And he was a bit dehydrated from the fever
So he was weaning not very often
So they gave us a test tube with a funnel
And they said you've just got to sit here
And wait for him to wait
And be ready to leap into action
So bless him
I was just for like a good hour and a half
He was just sitting there
With like my husband holding him up
Me like staring at his winky
Waiting, waiting to leap for the way
And we were, it got to like an hour
And we were like, oh my god
I don't think we should blame parents
But she does have a complex
Me just staring at it
Shaking a little tube
And at the end we were like
What about that thing of like
If you put your hand or your foot in water
Then it will make you wee
So we tried it
So we got one of those cardboard
Bucket things that they had in the hospital
And we filled it with warm water
And we put his feet in it
And it didn't work initially
But about two minutes after he'd stopped
Having his feet in water
And what he did then wee
But again, it's probably a coincidence
We don't know
That's science
Maybe it's taking your feet out of warm water
That makes you do that
But people don't normally go to sleep
In a swimming pool
So we don't know
We don't know
One other interesting notable name
From this period
Who was into agony arting
Slash uncleing
Was Daniel Defoe
Oh
Author of Robinson Crusoe
And yeah
He would reply to members of the public
And interestingly
You know
A lot of these replies were sometimes really crude
So in one reply to someone
He actually called someone
Even though he sort of blanked out the full spelling of it
But he called someone a whore
You know, he basically disagreed with what she was trying to ask
In terms of illicit sexual stuff
And he said you were a whore
I mean, it was really quite crude back then
Terrible
Just going back to deafness
I got very into this woman
Called Jaipreet Verdi
Has written a book about
Historical cures for deafness
And it's also about
The concept of deafness needing a cure
It's very interesting
But she talks about ear trumpets
You know, like, remember in "Allo Allo"
It's like the ear trumpet
The sort of comedy item that is the ear trumpet
But in Victorian times
They would be customized
So a lady say in morning
That the example they've got in a museum
It's been painted black
And trimmed with lace
That's cool
That's her outfit
And at first historians thought
You know, this was a sign of like
She had to hide it, you know, to be discreet
Because it was an embarrassing thing to have
But actually this author is making the point that
How cool, it's really sort of owning
Your deafness
And it's customizing
What you need
It's sort of the equivalent of like, you know
Pimping out your walking stick
Or signing a cast, in a way
Surely it's pimping up, isn't it?
Not pimping out
Pimping out your walking stick
You sort of put it in the street with a little sign
And Daniel Defoe calls it a whore
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
And that is my fact
My fact this week is that a tourist guide in Whitby
Got so tired of being asked where Dracula was buried
That he commissioned a headstone
Just so that he could point at it
Instead of explaining that Dracula wasn't real
So this is apparently, it's a big problem in Whitby
Whitby is one of the great scenes of Dracula
When Dracula makes his way over to England
And it is where Bram Stoker spent a few months
Where he went looking around
And he incorporated a lot of the landscapes
A lot of the churches
Even some of the names from the gravestones
Into the story
And the issue is that when visitors come
A lot of them don't actually realize that Dracula doesn't exist
So one particular guy, Harry Collett
Who's a tour guide
And he does tours around Whitby about Dracula
So sick of being asked this question
He did get one commissioned a headstone
Which he can just point to as they're on the track
And say, look, that's where he's buried
Do you think maybe he should give up his job as a tour guide
If he's sick of people asking him questions about Dracula?
Yeah, well I guess that is a very good point
Hang on, what does the headstone say?
Does it say Dracula's here?
Or does it say Dracula's not real?
No, it says Dracula
And then I guess the dates of Dracula on it
That's a great idea for your headstone, isn't it?
When eventually you die, it's like
Here lies James Harkin
Of course he wasn't real
I thought he was just trying to...
Because the church has put a sign on its door
Saying Dracula's a fictional character
So I thought he might be doing that
Because actually, if someone tries to dig up Dracula
They'll find, ooh, there's nobody there
It's only gonna add fuel to the fire
That's true
Yeah, this church, the St. Mary's Church
This is the church that appears in the book
They constantly have people coming to the church
Who are Dracula fans, asking about Dracula
Apparently the pews are just quite often filled with Goths
Who are sitting there just enjoying the scene
Well it's Gothsville
Yeah, it is Gothsville
Whitby is, they have a twice annual
In fact, they have four Goth festivals a year, right?
So they've got the Whitby Goth weekend
Which has been going since the 90s
And then, in 2019, a rival event was set up
Called Tomorrow's Ghosts
There was a spooky schism in the Whitby Goth weekend event
The founder had set it up
And there was a parting of ways with a venue
And so now there's a rival festival this year
Called Tomorrow's Ghosts
And I read their website about this year's autumn festival
It says this
Our headline is for 2022
Our Fields of the Nephilim
Who take the Friday night headline slot
And really need little introduction
Topping the bill on Saturday night are the loveless
Who need some introduction
They actually put that
That's really good
It's got a cool, quite gothic-y heritage
This whole area anyway
Yeah, not just Dracula
I mean, St. Hilda was Whitby, wasn't she?
St. Hilda was Abbess of Whitby
Did she, like, drive the snakes out of Whitby or something?
That's a story
That's the story
Well, she turned them to stone
Is that not...
That's driving them out in a way
It's hard to drive them out
They're less likely to bite you if they're made of stone
Is that what the Ammonite stones are all about?
That's what they call them
The Snake Stones of Whitby
And they're Ammonites
But some people would carve little heads on
So, Ammonite is like a little fossil
That looks a bit like a snake, right?
Yeah
Especially if you draw her face on it
Yeah, exactly
Yeah
Yeah, and she was...
She started a monastery
Which is on the spot where this place
She would talk about St. Mary's
St. Mary's, right?
Yeah
And, yeah, she resolved the date of Easter
Yeah, she was part of the team
Who did that?
Okay
There was the Synod of Whitby in 664 AD
Where they all got together in Whitby
And decided when we should have Easter
Because some people were doing it in the Celtic time
And some people were doing it in the Roman time
Yeah
And we thought, let's move down to the Roman time
So, she...
That was 664
She was probably still alive in 666 AD
She was, actually
Yeah, yeah, yeah
She was like a teacher as well
She taught Kathmon
Who was the first English poet that we know the name of
She was his teacher
The question, though, that we're all asking
Was she a child prodigy, James?
I know not
I went to St. Hilda's College
Did you?
Yes
And then they have a little Ammonite on their shield
Did they?
Wow
That's cool
I think that's called...
That species is called Hildoceras
Really?
It was named in honour of her
It was found in that area
Yeah, nice
There's a really cool set of stairs in Whitby
Oh, yeah
Ooh
Yeah
They sound pretty spooky
As you head up to St. Mary's Church
It's 199 steps to get to the top
That's intracular, isn't it?
Yes
That's bench and intracular
Yeah, yeah
As you're going up them, there's little rest points
Little...
Ooh, benches
Benches
So, you sit on this bench
And you think you're sitting on a regular bench
But, actually, it's not a regular bench
It's not...
No, it's not a possessed bench either
It wasn't built by yetis
It was because the graveyard with St. Mary's Church
Was at the top
Yeah
You had all the pool-bearers who were coming to carry up
All of the dead bodies to get to the church
And it's a very tiring business
So, what's now used as seats, these planks of wood
Were actually pit stops to put the dead bodies on
So that they could get rest
Yeah, it is spooky
It is spooky
The dead men's...
Benches
Another thing about Whitby
Is if you go to Saltwick Nab, which is just south of Whitby
You'll see where the cliffs are
There's huge chunks taken out of the cliffs
And that's because they tried to get alum
Which is a thing you get in shale, it's a type of rock
And it's really useful because you could bind colours to cloth
By using it
But it didn't work on its own
You needed ammonia as well
And the way they got their ammonia was from stale urine
Ah, urine again
Urine again, we come back to urine
And so, in Whitby, they used to have barrels
Where you would go and wean to the barrel
And then they would take the wee to the alum mines
And then they would colour their cloths
And did they have a little trough of warm water
That you could stand in
If you were struggling to get yourself going
Yeah
What point does urine go stale?
I've never thought about that
Well, I would say if you don't drink it straight from the sauce
You could put it in a cup first
If you drink it straight from the sauce
The point is, and I think we've mentioned this in a quite recent podcast
Is ammonia isn't naturally in urine
And ammonia is made by bacteria
Urine is generally more or less sterile
So you get your urine, the bacteria comes from the air
Goes into the urine, makes ammonia
And that's when it becomes stale
So it takes a couple of hours
Have you ever forgotten to flush a toilet and then gone on holiday?
Wow
And then come back
That's when it stale
Oh my god
But Dan, if you're bottling it correctly with sterilised bottles
It lasts years
She's got to visit Andy's urine distillery
Keep it out of the sunlight
Wacker label on it
It's bringing them on the plane
It's from my ears actually
You have to bring so many under 100ml bottles though
That's the really annoying thing
Anyway, this urine, they couldn't get enough in Whitby
So they ended up putting barrels in Newcastle and London
To get enough urine
That's a long way away
A lot of piss, isn't it? Yeah, from a long distance
Well, there's a lot of people in London
So that was one reason why they went there
And they always tried to get the urine from poor people
So they put barrels in the poor areas
And they would want poor people's piss
Why?
Because it was illiterative
No, why do you think it was?
Something about poor people's diet or consumption of alcohol
Because he's got it
He's only got it, got it
Did they wanted it to be more?
No, they thought that the poor people wouldn't be able to afford alcohol
And so they didn't want alcohol in the urine
Because they thought it wouldn't set the colours properly
Do you know where Dracula was from?
He was from Transylvania
Well, exactly
But there is a minority theory that he was from Devon
Is this theory put forward by Devon?
There's a writer called Andy Struthers
Who claims that Bram Stoker was inspired by a load of different things
But he claims there was especially an Exeter writer called Sabine Beringould
Who'd written a book about werewolves, which Bram Stoker read
And a vampire story called Marjorie of Queather
And was therefore claiming that Dracula was effectively from Devon
Which I think would make him less spooky
I'm gonna drink your blood
Do you mind?
All right, my lover
Yeah, but his descendant, Bram Stoker's descendant said there's a mix of sources
Actually, you can't just say
Well, one of the sources was about Drackel, wasn't it?
Vlad the Impaler, who was from Transylvania
Was he a Wallachian or something like that?
And he supposedly read about this guy while he was in Whitby
So he went down to what was the coffee house end
And the public library there
He found the book there and that's what gave the inspirations
As you say, there's a lot of different accounts
He was already working on a novel, but it was about a character he called Count Wampire
Sounds like a Count Wampire
I thought that was the original... Wampire was the original Germanic
Still sounds stupid though
Okay, cool, sorry
I am a Wampire
Or rather, I am a Wampire
I've been to Dracula's Castle
How do you?
Actually, yeah, in fact, I've been to both of them
There's one which is real and one of them which is fake
The one which is fake is called Bran Castle
And that looks really gothic
It looks amazing
It looks like it could be his castle, but it really isn't
And there's another one which was his actual castle
It's about a hundred miles away
And that is just a... you know, it's a semi-detached house
I thought it was like Vlad the Impaler's
Yeah, but it's just like ruins really
And they have a few stakes with dolls on them
They do
But in the Bran Castle, it's way better
Because they've got a proper, you know, gift shop
Bran Castle, they've really made big on the publicity, haven't they?
So last year, Bran Castle got a bit of publicity
Because they offered free doses of the COVID-19 jabs
What?!
Yeah, with doctors wearing fang stickers
And they put it in your neck
No, they didn't put it in your neck
Interesting fact, I was in Bran on the day of the Brexit referendum
Oh!
You're gonna have a spooky loss of trade
Okay, that's it
That's all of our facts
Thank you so much for listening
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
About the things that we've said over the course of this podcast
We can be found on our Twitter accounts
I'm on @Sriberland
Andy
@AndrewHunterM
James
@JamesHarken
And Rachel
And you can go to our group account which is @NoSearchThing
Or our website, NoSearchThingAsAfish.com
All the previous episodes are up there, do check it out
We will be back again next week with another episode
We will see you then
Goodbye
(upbeat music)