(phone rings)
- We don't want that or who don't want that.
(upbeat music)
- Hi, Andy.
- How's it going?
- Oh, super good.
- Oh, so good.
- Yeah, really excited, big fan of the show.
Oh, welcome, bonus bone, real life, love it all.
- It's all changed.
- I said, yeah.
- Welcome to Drop us a Line, our audience feedback show.
- My name's Andrew Hunter Murray, do you want me?
- I'm Dan Schreiber, and this is Jane Tarkin.
- Yeah, yeah.
- When you say audience feedback show,
is the ratio of audience feedback
to a amount of time we spend naming sections
gonna be a little bit better this week?
- It depends on how you define better.
(laughing)
- I think so, yes, but I think you won't.
- Are they asking for more,
more non-actual meaty facts
than just us trying to think of puns silently?
- When we write stuff down?
- When is this show?
Okay, ouch.
- When is this show ever been about meaty facts?
This is the whimsy zone.
This is about you, the listener slash viewer,
and what you think of what we've been putting out
on our little show.
- Okay, some of the jokes we've made,
it's just the big show for you now.
(laughing)
- I would say the amount of time I spend on Drop us a Line
is now outweighing the amount of time I spend on Fish.
- Cool.
- For me, this is where my career is going.
- It's feedback.
(laughing)
- Let's start with, let's start with some emails we've had.
- That's my way, it's literally why we're here
before you move on to the song, no.
Okay, I'm not gonna cry with laughter
before the first name's been read out.
That's not happening, okay?
So, number one, the section naming section,
which I asked for suggestions for last time.
(laughing)
And the inbox has been bulging
with people suggesting section names
for the section naming section.
- Okay.
- And Louisa Primo suggests C Mantix.
- Yeah, which is a good ocean pun.
I think that's really good.
Great Fruit Street says, "A place for everything."
- Yeah.
- "Because a place in like the fish a place."
But I think that's a harder one to get away with
because place is just such a common word
that you can't hear the fish pun.
- Yeah, because when it's on a fish and chip shop,
you can read it.
- Exactly, exactly.
- When it's in Jim's place.
- Yeah.
So, and because of our medium,
I'm sorry, "Great Fruit Street."
I think it's not quite right for us.
John Gallagher writes, "Dear Anna, please come back."
(laughing)
- I think they speak for all of us.
I'll just read this out and then we'll get into it.
"Dear Anna, please come back and tell the boys
"that they are morons."
And it should be called bonus "buy a bass."
That's soup, that fishy soup.
And for God's sake, please stop calling them sections
when they are clearly fillets.
- Okay.
- Okay, John, Anna hasn't been seen in this inbox
for three years, right?
I'm the captain now.
- Also, I can say, exactly,
well, I would say to that, she does not care.
(laughing)
- She doesn't care about whether it's bonus,
Brem or bonus, bonus.
- She does not.
- No, she's got a hell of a shock
when she gets back and finds out she has to do this.
Again, yeah.
But John, interestingly, for a guy writing about fish puns,
writes from a place in New South Wales
called "Scholl Haven."
- Cool.
- When you said a place from in New South Wales,
how are you spelling that?
- Yeah.
- And New South Wales as well.
- Oh, Wales.
- Oh my God.
That's really great.
Okay.
And you see, we've discovered something fresh and true already.
It's all downhill from here.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- So what are we naming the section?
- It doesn't matter.
(laughing)
- Let's have a bit of a bonus, bonus, Brem.
- Okay. - Right.
- Yeah.
- Raphael Alvarez, right.
Just listen to the latest little fish
where you talk about removing the avocado pits.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, shove it out with your finger on the backside.
(laughing)
- Well.
- Yeah.
Preferences may vary, but yeah.
(laughing)
And James, you were talking about this online trend.
- Yeah, there was an online trend
where people would hit the stone with a knife
and then twist it and pull the stone out
as opposed to Dan's sticking your finger in the backside
or whatever it was.
(laughing)
- Yeah, yeah.
- You're just pushing it with your thumbs.
- But James, you were saying that was a,
like you slapper knife.
- Yeah, and people were like cutting their hands
and it was called avocado hand-express.
- Exactly.
- From a few weeks.
Well, Raphael writes, having grown up in Mexico,
removing it by catching it with a knife
and twisting it out is literally the only way
I have ever done it.
- Okay.
- So we're teaching Mexico to suck eggs here.
Basically, they know this already.
Fun fact, which I find very interesting.
If you do want to eat the skin,
there are a few varieties with edible skin.
- Oh, that's cool.
It's just a Mexican, which is like a plum skin.
You could just wash it and bite right in.
- That's nice.
- That's a nice thing.
- Because you said the skin was the best part.
- I did.
- But I was joking, but I was right.
- There's the best kind of being right.
- Absolutely.
- Thank you, Raphael, for that.
We're gonna switch gear now
and go into some, get yourself off the hooks.
- Okay.
- 'Cause we've had a fair few of these
and they're really good.
- When you say switching gear, are we going faster?
Or into reverse?
(laughing)
- We're going into reverse.
We're gonna go back and just have a look
at where we've been driving.
- Yeah.
- And see if we made any errors minor or major
along the way.
- Right.
- Yeah?
- Okay.
- Harry Not says, "Read your recent episode
"where you were pitching a movie based on some kind
"of crossover between Air Force One and Mickey Mouse One."
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- Which was a good idea.
- Yeah, so Mickey Mouse One was Walt Disney's plane.
- Right.
- Oh yes, this was a little fish.
- Yes, yeah.
- So firstly, Harry says, "Sign me up by the way.
"Sounds like a hit.
Agreed."
- Great.
- But Harry adds, actually,
if the president got onto Mickey Mouse One,
then its call sign would change to Air Force One
because the call sign applies to any plane
carrying the president not a specific plane.
- Yeah.
- That's true.
And that's true of Mickey Mouse as well.
If he gets on Air Force one,
automatically because Mickey Mouse one.
(laughing)
- So yeah, well done, Harry.
You got us.
- Yeah.
- Very nice.
- Oh, like it, checkmate.
- Checkmate.
It's a technical checkmate.
Harry says, "I assume you've had thousands
"of messages about this."
(laughing)
But in your last drop of the line,
you said that when people say that,
they're the only ones who write in,
so let's test that theory out.
Harry, you're the only person who wrote in,
nice line about the Air.
Yeah.
Francisco Ross.
- Yeah, okay.
- This is for you, Dan.
- Oh yeah.
- Right, so Dan was talking recently
about Merv Griffin's wife coming up
with a concept of jeopardy.
- Oh yeah, I know it's coming.
- I quoted her using an example.
- Yeah.
- Answer 79 Whistful Vista question.
Is that where Fibba and Molly McGee live?
Dan indicates that those were friends of the Griffins,
which would have made the question impossible
for a wider audience.
- Yeah, so I remember at the time,
I did a quick click on the name and it said that,
a radio show starring a very famous couple
who were, their show was a radio thing.
So I thought, oh, okay, so they knew the couple.
What I didn't realize was that those names,
Molly and Fibba McGee, was that the names?
Were the characters that the real life couple were playing?
So I saw the real life couple and assumed
that it must have been them.
So yeah, a silly mistake.
So it was a famous address
because it was the address of this fictional.
- Yeah.
- It's like you saying the Basil Faulty
and Civil Faulty were friends of Merv Griffin.
You know.
- Okay.
- No, okay.
It's fun.
It was a minor technical error,
but it was also pointed out by Christopher Stohill,
Holly Stratton, Jane Boggess and various others.
- Yeah, it's very good.
'Cause it's, you know, we're talking about
a long time ago.
- Sure, yeah.
- So yeah.
- Yeah.
- Nice to know.
It's still got its footprints in the culture of America.
- Big time.
- Yeah, big time.
That was our rodeo micro-clown of the week.
- Okay.
- Nice.
- Yeah.
- Guy Walker of Kraken writes Kraken's company.
- Oh, okay.
- Well, the ones that made up.
- Yeah, the run.
- I know.
- And it was, it makes sea monsters?
- That's right.
- Probably shouldn't say his company.
Should we?
- Don't know.
- Well, it's in his email signature.
He's not writing anything offensive.
I think it's, I think it's fine.
- You're getting quite defensive about this, Andy.
- Well, I just, I hope I haven't.
- Well, we don't know which Kraken it is.
If it's not the run, we're at a loss.
- No, no, no.
It's related to the company Octopus, the electricity firm.
- Okay.
- They have a sister firm called Kraken.
- Do they?
- Yes.
- Okay.
- Who works?
- There must be loads of guy walkers at this place.
- Oh yeah.
- Anyway, he says some very offensive stuff,
which I'm not going to read out, but then he says,
"My bosses are shit."
(all laughing)
Let's get past all that.
I listened to the latest little fish this morning
on a run, and wanted to give you
the power to correct James.
- What was his name again?
- Guy Walker.
Reverse stamina tip to terminus him.
He runs everywhere.
- But he is a guy.
- Is he?
- I think so.
Anyway, guy writes, "Wanted to give you
the power to correct James."
- Uh-oh.
- So I'm just going to see if I could think
of something else to distract you.
(all laughing)
- You can, you can.
The history here, I was the software engineer
who wrote the chips.exe for McDonald's.
- Oh yeah, interesting.
Okay, so the exe is a program,
and it was a payroll program that I read
might have been on the computers,
which you order at McDonald's,
and when there's an error,
it just comes up on the screen,
and people assumed it was due to the fries
when it wasn't, but what's Mr. Walker saying?
- Well, guy writes, "I was the software engineer
who wrote the chips.exe from McDonald's
when I was in their software team for about 10 years."
Chips.exe was me being a smartass
with how I named files for my own amusement.
We as a team used to do this all the time.
The handheld order software was called Shesberg,
as in cheeseburger.exe, and so on.
The chips.exe error would occur
when the software showed that an order was
a particular thing happened at the order.
- That's fantastic, yeah.
- And you know what?
I think that this, I might be wrong,
but I think that this might be information
that is not available elsewhere,
'cause I see lots of people online sort of discussing
this and wondering where it came from,
and the version I came up with was the one
which was most commonly asserted.
But like I said at the time, I wasn't really sure.
And I don't think that this, I haven't seen it online,
so that's pretty, that's an exclusive.
- We've added to the, it's an exclusive.
- Let's get our PR onto it.
This is, we've been needing this for a long time.
- This is good.
- That's very cool.
I know, thank you, go.
Dave Henley of South Carolina.
- Uh-huh.
- Wow, ads, I love how much you get blown away
by big places in America.
- It was so weird, like, two episodes ago,
there was people from South Africa and from Europe
and all this and you went, such, such person,
from Florida.
(laughing)
- Yeah, I suppose I'm just impressed
that these places are out there, you know?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Anyway, Dave from South Carolina,
- I know.
- Right, in February 22nd's Little Fish,
you discussed Crash McDonald's computers
displaying the message chips.exe
failed.
It reminded me of something from my time as a student
at the University of Birmingham in the early naughties.
At the time, the Travel West Midlands website
would frequently make Netscape Crash
with the message bus error.
- Ah.
- And that's a computer thing, I think, a bus error.
It wasn't a bag for buses.
- Yes.
- That's good.
- That they run buses bus company.
Very cool.
Thank you, Dave.
- I'm impressed that knowledge is in South Carolina.
- Yeah, I know.
When you said he's from Birmingham, I thought it would be Alabama.
- Oh yes.
- He doesn't.
- No, he said West Midlands.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's unclear why he'd be at the University in Alabama
and he could be going on the Travel West Midlands website
for some reason we don't know.
- That's true.
- Yeah.
- Anyway, well, very cool.
Well, let's go now to Wine Corner.
- Wine Corner?
- Yeah.
- As in having a wine or the alcohol.
- It's both.
(laughing)
- Do you go hand in hand?
- Yeah.
- This class of wine isn't very nice.
(laughing)
- Well, there's the sting for the next week's episode.
- Oli here, a sommelier from Sydney.
- What?
- Long time listener.
I'm currently halfway through app 622
listening to Andy's beautiful description
of the Tuscan countryside.
And we were talking about geothermal, weren't we?
- Yeah.
- When I was jolted out of my listening experience
by James's mention of enjoying a glass of Montepulciano
in the region, which you say have a nice glass
of Montepulciano.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Unfortunately for James, Montepulciano the grape
isn't usually found in Tuscany.
You're more likely to find it on the Adriatic coast
in regions such as Abruzzo and March.
What you do find in Tuscany is the village of Montepulciano.
- Okay.
- Which has some beautiful vineyards
planted primarily with San Giovanni.
Frankly, I'd expect better from someone
who's cat exclusively drinks Evian.
(laughing)
I say the reason that I said that is because I have sat
in a cafe overlooking the lean-in tariff pizza
drinking Montepulciano wine.
- Not a lot of wine.
- It wasn't according to what he heard.
(laughing)
- It wasn't a piece of wimsy.
It was a prustian memory.
- Yeah.
So, pour that in your glass and smoke it, Ollie.
(laughing)
- What I would just say is that restaurants
don't exclusively sell wine from the area that they're in.
- No, but it was good that Ollie says
I would apologize for the pedantry,
but this is about as useful as my many years of study
are likely to be as good knowledge.
- It is, it's really good knowledge, yeah.
- And he finally says, contrary to recent correspondence,
I'm going to back myself and say this is the only email
you're going to receive on the topic.
We've had hundreds, Ollie, about hundreds.
(laughing)
- That's really good.
- There we go.
- Yeah, very good.
- An apology to Cameron Roberts now,
who says in the latest episode,
you talk about Ralph Feins, what's it, Ray Feins?
At one point you guys mentioned some of the movies he was in
and someone I think Dan said Shakespeare in love.
It was not Ray Feins in that movie.
- Who is it?
- This is Brother Joseph Feins.
- Oh, I forgot about the brother.
- Yeah.
- You know what, I often will, when I'm editing,
I'll check these things, but with movies of that era,
I just assumed Dan's going to know that stuff.
- That's such a silly era.
- Of course, one's in James Bond, one's in Shakespeare in love.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- There's another rule.
- One is Voldemort, what is in Shakespeare in love?
- One is one of the most famous actors on the planet,
and one is primarily in Shakespeare in love.
- I know for instance, Joseph Feins.
- Has he had a big career outside that?
I don't know.
- He must have.
- He was in Shakespeare in love.
And Cameron adds, this is part of the reason I read this out.
An extra side note, Rayfe's full name is actually
Rayfe Twistleton Wickham Feins.
That's his surname.
- Yeah, Twistleton Wickham Feins, triple barrel.
- Triple barrel.
- Triple barrel, which is a very distinctive surname.
So distinctive that I noticed that one of the scientists
from the 1950s, I was reviewing in my dissertation,
had the same surname.
- What?
- So I guess Rayfe Feins is also related to a scientist
who did a lot on sleeping sickness in cattle in the 1950s.
(laughing)
- That's amazing, that's lovely.
- So one last get yourself off the hook.
This is an era I made.
We've had a lot today, haven't we?
- Areas.
- Yeah.
- I think probably you've just been saving them up
for the last few weeks,
'cause we'd be mostly doing section naming.
- Maybe.
- I mean, it's been, yeah.
- Don't want to.
- Rayfe Feins, that awful Monty Pulciano
- Disaster thing, you said James.
(laughing)
- The McGee's or whatever they were called.
- Oh, they were a Monty McGee.
- Yeah.
- So that was half a morning clearing that out of the...
Anyway, one last one for me, and then we'll press on.
We'll have some fun.
Not that your email, James Dales, wasn't fun.
James writes, "Restoration House"
is in Rochester,
and is recognized as the inspiration
for "Satis House" in great expectations.
I said this.
Rod Hull lived in, who was a British French reliquist
with a big bird called EMU.
- Yeah.
- He had a, it wasn't a French reliquist.
It was a kind of puppet act, wasn't it?
- Yeah, exactly, he didn't speak.
- Yeah, he lived in basically Miss Havishim's house
from great expectations.
- And he died from that roof.
- Right.
So, that house was owned and restored by Rod Hull,
restoration house, okay?
He saved it from being turned into a car park, apparently.
Unfortunately, the restoration almost bankrupted him,
forcing him to move to Winchell Sea,
to the bungalow with poor TV reception,
from whose roof he took a fatal fall.
- Okay.
- So he did not...
- Is this now freaking record like that?
- You know what, I really...
I quite annoyed by that,
because I've been telling other people that fact.
- I know.
- I bet right now, there were so many people
rocking up to that house,
saying, is that the aerial that Rod Hull fell off from?
And the local guide's going, what is going on?
Where has this come from?
- It's actually a urban myth that Rod Hull fell
from the roof of Miss Havishim's house.
He did own the house for a while,
but he then moved to a bungalow.
It makes more sense.
You would climb onto the roof of a bungalow
and have a go at fixing an aerial,
but presumably Miss Havishim's enormous gothic mansion.
- Also, the higher an aerial is,
the better reception it'll get anyway.
- Absolutely, look, it's all...
The signs were there that Winchell was a cock up.
I don't think it's an exaggeration to say
that of all the facts that you've told me
in the last 12 years, this is the one
that I've told other people because I've enjoyed it so much.
- Oh, I'm sorry, and it's not even true.
- This feels like a top of show in main episode apology,
I think.
- Open up, no, I don't think that.
- That's a card we played, I think, twice.
- Yeah.
- So have you been telling people
that he fell off Miss Havishim's roof?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You can still, you just make it,
he lived in, it's interesting that Rotten
lived in Miss Havishim's house.
- Yeah, but I gotta ring up all those people again.
- I'm saying again.
- No, I still don't want any insurance,
but that thing that I told you.
- This is gonna have some kind of effect
that we're not aware of.
There's gonna be a final question in millionaire
where someone smuggly is gonna be sitting there
going, "Ruchester, final answer."
- The question would be which town in Kent
was the home of Rotten, which we took a fatal call.
- It has to be a difficult question.
It's for a million questions.
- For a million, for a million questions.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, sorry to the loser.
- Well, I'm gonna ask the audience.
- Oh, 100% of them said "Ruchester."
- It's still gonna have to phone a friend.
Andy, are you there?
(laughing)
- I'm absolutely certain about it, mate.
Good luck.
Cut me in on that million.
- All right, take care.
- Okay.
Oliver Walker says,
"Don't listen to anything my brother guy says."
(laughing)
- I just listened to an episode on a drive from Santander.
Not the bank, the place in Spain.
- Yeah, nice.
- Spain?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Down to the Costa Blanca.
- Okay, that's decent drive.
- And as soon as I heard James talk about Konga caterpillars,
I thought, hold on, he must be talking
about processionary caterpillars from Spain,
confirm minutes later by his car park comment.
And apparently they're a big thing there.
And they're lethal.
- Really?
- They can kill a dog.
- Oh my God.
- If his plane's dead dogs in the car park at the same time.
(laughing)
- I had to park in a disabled spot.
- Yeah.
So Oliver says, "We have a few pine trees in our garden.
"One day I found the guy who cleans our pool,
"setting light to some caterpillars."
- Oh my gosh.
- He explained the only way to deal with him
is to set him on fire.
And a few other people have confirmed this,
John and Madrid, Ian Meridan and Stephen Wicks,
have all written in about these caterpillars.
- Cool.
- And they're bastards.
They're really, really bad for you.
Stingy.
- Oh wow.
- Yeah, I mean, they look really cute.
- Yeah.
- Well, they're not bastards.
They're just them, they're just being themselves.
- Yeah.
- They're just bastard apologist.
(laughing)
- Right.
Time for a sperm sandwich.
(laughing)
If he found three, yummy.
If he found three emails,
he'd wish mentioned sperm in a different context.
So I thought I'd try a new sandwich.
- So it's a bread sandwich, but with sperm.
'Cause there's no meat.
All right.
- Right.
- Hope there's no meat.
(laughing)
- Well, Joseph Faber writes an email with the headline,
"Injaculate isn't compressible."
- Which one of us said it was?
- Uh, Joseph is a long time listener
and long time emailer, and says, "I'm sure."
I'm sure you got inundated by letters about this.
- Okay.
- Never.
It's the carrot discovery callus ever making that claim.
- Well, see what you think.
In the February eight little fish episode,
you talked about the amount of data in a single,
"Injaculate."
- Oh, I see.
- And James suggested it would be easily compressible
because it's all essentially the same data.
- Sorry.
I thought you meant compressible, as if you could squit.
I thought he was saying you could use it in hydraulics
or something.
(laughing)
Like if hydraulics in your car are broken,
you just, there's all the robots come out.
You just fill it.
- That's quite the roadside site.
Sometimes you do go past people
who are broken down and you think, "I'll offer."
(laughing)
- Come on, come on.
- Comes out to James in the car park.
What is he doing?
What are these dead dogs?
(laughing)
- Just drive on, honey.
Drive on.
- Oh, but Joseph claims that in reality,
each sperm is genetically unique because of meiosis,
shuffling chromosomes before gametes are formed.
So the data isn't a bunch of identical files
and as such, resists neat compression.
- Yeah.
- All right.
- I think resists neat compression.
I think neat is doing a bit of work there.
- Yeah, well, there we go.
- Thank you, Joseph, it's a great point.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it's good to have it in.
That's layer one of the sandwich.
- Okay.
- Melissa Hull just sends an amusing picture
from the compendium of cookery and reliable recipes.
It's a very old cut book from...
(laughing)
They just stuck together, are they?
It's from 1890, it says to keep,
this is just a household tip, this book.
To keep starch from sticking to ions,
rub with a little piece of wax or sperm.
- Hmm, okay.
- Oh, what does it mean?
- This is 1890.
- What sperm?
- People aren't acknowledging, they have legs in public.
No one is gonna say, "Rub sperm on your iron."
(laughing)
- Also don't rub sperm on your iron.
- Maybe they didn't, you know that button
that sort of squirts water out in the night.
- That's it, they didn't have that in those days.
- That's right, I'm sure they didn't.
- The sperm.
- Sperm, well oil?
- Oh, it could be that.
I was gonna say sperm is Latin,
I think, or Greek four seed.
- Yeah.
- Yeah?
- Could be one of those things.
- But sperm is set, he feels right,
which is that oil you get from a whale.
- Yeah.
- Facts as well, spermologists collect.
- Yeah, so spermologist is someone who collects facts,
but it's analogous to someone collecting little seeds
or something, or whatever.
- Very nice, that's great at a mology.
And we're now through to the final bread, the bread bit.
Colin Crookshank writes in regarding using,
- Yes, we said, a salmon sperm is used in a heart treatment.
- Oh, yes.
- Or a drug derived initially from salmon sperm.
I think they synthesized it these days
and they don't rely on salmon these days.
But Colin says, "Heparin is derived from pig intestine mucus."
Not sure if that came up in your research.
I guess the patient is having a surf and turf meal
without realizing it.
- So it's this, it was heparin poisoning, I think,
that you use the salmon sperm derived thing to cure.
- Yes, that's it, that's it.
- Yeah, yeah.
So if you've had too much of your pig intestine oil,
then you can treat it with some salmon sperm.
- Right. - Yum, yum.
- Plum, plum.
- Ooh, extreme fish.
- Yay!
- We've had an extreme fish or two.
- Is this your favorite bit then?
- I do, I like when people are out and about
in their experiencing something.
- This is really good.
We've got two extreme fish, Anna Scanborg writes,
"I will soon be taking you to Everest Base Camp."
- Yes, cool.
- "The Chola Pass" and "Goccio Lake" in the pool
as I'm going on a long track in April,
and I find fish is the greatest distraction
when the going gets tough.
- Yeah.
- This is incredible, she adds.
You have previously walked 950 kilometers with me
when I walked the Camino in Spain.
- Oh, cool. - Oh, how cool is that?
- I've always wanted to do the Camino in Spain.
I've never done it.
- Yeah.
- But apparently I have now, so.
- Yes, yeah.
(laughing)
- They're gonna change the rules, aren't they,
for Everest, I think?
- Right.
- I think they're gonna change it
that you can't climb it until you've climbed
at least one other of the big mountains.
- I thought you were gonna say no podcasts.
No listening.
- No, the rest is politics, for comparison.
You can hear it from multiple speakers.
- Oh.
- I really like that idea of a bucket list of places
where we'd love to have been played.
I suppose to, you know, climbing Everest-based camp.
- Yeah.
- Play the Everest-based camp.
- I'm gonna think where my number one place would be.
The ISS would be cool.
We found out that an astronaut was listening
to us up there.
- That's the dream, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Marianna's trench.
- Could be great.
- Yeah, that would be great.
- James Cameron's off and down there.
- He is.
- Yeah.
- researching at the Avatar Films.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- It's very blue.
- Yeah. - It's very blue.
- Yeah.
- It's actually pitch black.
- I don't write him.
- Podcast and gyro.
(laughing)
- It's blue for a bit.
- You can't see it.
The Marianna's trench is not blue.
On the way down it is.
- You count us for the first 100 meters.
There's a tinge of blue.
- That is crushing darkness.
(laughing)
- I actually think Avatar could be improved
by making it all crushingly dark.
(laughing)
- That's a really funny idea.
Martin Williams says,
"I live in Waterloo, Canada,
where we get both extremely hot
and extremely cold weather.
I often listen to fish when doing chores outside
around the house,
and I realized recently I've done so during
both some of the coldest and hottest days
my city has ever recorded,
while shoveling my driveway in early 2015,
and also when retarring it last June
in ambient temperatures of minus 34
and plus 33 C respectively."
Wow.
So Martin is claiming that he has listened to fish
and weather ranging by 67 Celsius in exactly the same spot.
- Okay.
- And if you adjust for wind chill and humidity effects,
it's actually 92 degrees Celsius.
- Yeah, yeah.
And he reconciles must be a record.
- He thinks so, yeah.
He says, "I may not hold this record for long,
but I claim it first."
And I challenge others to exceed it.
- Very good.
- Yeah.
- Maybe if you're in the Column Fusion reactor
in Oxfordshire,
where it also is next to the coldest place.
- Yeah, yes.
- Yes, that's gonna be the only.
(laughing)
- That's really challenging.
- Yeah.
- It's a good theory.
- Really cool.
- Let's have a few little quick names to finish off.
Should we have some names, names, names
that you think are named one thing
because of the name,
but actually they're named after the person who.
- I thought of one the other day
that was not in your list, which is Larry Page.
I invented PageRank.
- That's really good.
- Ah.
- It's a program that ranks pages on.
- Yes, that's almost perfect.
That's one of the first examples
you'd use, isn't it, before you get into the deep cuts.
Like the one sent in by Caroline Uens,
who writes there is a DNA detection technique
called the Southern Blot.
There's also a Northern Blot for RNA detection
and the Western Blot for protein detection.
The Southern Blot is named after a man called Edwin Southern.
- Wow.
- Yeah. - Very nice.
Very good. - That's cool.
- Joe Sir, C-Y-R,
my name is Joe Sir and I'm an avid listener for Massachusetts.
My fact, I wanted to share is that there is
an edible berry found in not have literally
been to Massachusetts.
I don't know, I'm so excited.
But it's not really all went together.
- Yeah.
- Did we?
- Did we play Boston?
- We did. - Oh, yes.
- Yes, good for you.
- Okay.
- So let's just calm down.
My fact is that there is an edible berry
found in Northern regions around the world,
which is known in Newfoundland.
- Newfoundland.
- Newfoundland, Newfoundland.
Newfoundland.
As, and Labrador.
Labrador.
- Labrador. - Labrador.
- Labrador.
The berry is known as the bake apple.
This name is believed to have come from the French becapele,
meaning what is the name of this berry?
(laughing)
- Okay. - Isn't that good?
- That's very nice. - That's very good.
- Yeah.
And lastly, a nominative determinism
from Joseph Hewitt,
who says, "Just saw that the director of off-com led
"just leading online porn access, et cetera,
"is George Lusty."
(laughing)
- Lovely.
- Lovely stuff.
- Well, my friends, that's it for this episode of Doppers Align.
We've come to the end of the road and good.
- It's been a journey.
- Yeah.
- It's been great.
Have you guys had a good time?
- I'm still having a good time.
- Yeah.
- This is my favorite part of the show.
(laughing)
- Watching me seamlessly and smoothly end it.
- Yeah, yeah. - Yeah.
- What?
- Nothing, nothing.
- You look at me with this grin like,
oh, let's just see Andy Cope with, you know.
- That's a smile of admiration.
- It's not, I've never seen you do,
I would recognize him as a sneaker of admiration.
(laughing)
- It's weird, 'cause I've got a lot of material.
I should be able to fall back on the reams of paper
I bring along every time.
- Yeah, yeah.
- You've got nothing.
You guys are going in nude every time.
- Well, just that living.
- It's crazy, how good you guys are on this show
and how bad I am, given that I hold all the cards.
(laughing)
- It's nuts.
Anyway, thank you for watching all listening
and we'll be back in the fall with more.
And if you have anything to send us,
it's podcast@qr.com.
It's the email address of the inbox,
which receives emails, which I have,
and then, yeah.
- Which I then open and read.
And then I save them in a word document, the best ones.
And I bring that word document
and that's what I've been really sure of today.
Okay, bye.
- Doctor.
(upbeat music)
- Anyway, thank you for watching all listening
and we'll be back in the fall with more.
And if you have anything to send us,
it's podcast@qr.com.
It's the email address of the inbox,
which receives emails, which I then, yeah.
Which I then open and read.
And then I save them in a word document, the best ones.
And I bring that word document
and that's what I've been really sure of today.
Okay, bye.
- Doctor.
(upbeat music)