Hey there club fish members, Dan here. Welcome to your exclusive extra secret bit of bonus
content and this time we have for you a very exciting compilation. Exciting because as
with last time it is rampact with the bonanza of comedy dorks so as well as me, Andy and
James you are going to get the soothing nerdy tones of John Lloyd, Hank Green, Hannah Fry,
Harriet Lloyd and Sally Phillips. Sally Phillips's episode it's worth noting is from the British
Library gig that we did a few months back and so you're going to hear at the end of
this episode a very quick Q&A that we managed to sneak in at the end of that show and unfortunately
we couldn't do longer because we ran over from the main show but they are super fun,
these live shows and it is worth saying that if you do want to come to one of those we
do have three left this year so far so we're going to be doing two more at the Soho Theatre
on the 21st of August now unfortunately it's sold out but if you happen to be in central
London on the day do just check their website because there are returns and also sometimes
they just release tickets that they've held back but if you do want to come to another
live show in September we have one on the 14th of September at Kings Place for the London
podcast festival and that show is also sold out however unlike the Soho shows we are live
streaming it so if you had to know such thing as a fish.com/live and click on the link for
the Kings Place gig you will be able to buy live stream tickets so that you can watch it
from the comfort of your own home on top of that you can also discuss what we're saying
live as it happens in the Discord as there is a dedicated thread in there for people
who are watching it live to just chat as we go along so do check that out but otherwise
for the meantime enjoy the compilation.
[Music]
Does the table feel bigger to you guys?
No.
Doesn't it?
Oh that's interesting.
It just feels bigger.
No it is bigger.
No.
Is it?
It feels bigger.
It definitely feels bigger.
Do we normally have something in the middle?
No.
Do we have a feeling as well?
Well I'm now but only because you put it in my head.
Let's before we lose all this magic.
Let's go.
Oh my god.
Okay.
All right.
I'll tell you a fact that is true though.
Perfect.
You've been taking lessons from Dan in the segue.
Well actually I don't know that this is true.
I'm going to tell you a muck fact which you can check later.
That's a great time.
A muck fact.
There used to be a thing about McDonald's.
McDonald's nutrition muck facts.
Which I used to love.
Yeah.
It's like a fact but a muck fact.
Jane Goodall's son.
She did chimpanzees.
That's right isn't it?
Yeah that's right.
She had a son and she used to keep him in a cage
to protect him from the chimpanzees which were aggressive.
Guess what he does now for a job?
A prison warden.
Shock photographer.
Oh.
He just wants to be back in the cage.
Well I don't know.
He feels safe.
It's a safe place.
I would love to interview him.
Yeah.
That is incredible.
Isn't it?
Let's check it's true by the way.
I've definitely been told that in a product by someone who might know.
I've got a doll of Jane Goodall.
It's like a Barbie doll of Jane Goodall right?
Really?
Yeah.
For my daughter.
That's so weird.
For your daughter.
What's, what are the, does it have accessories?
Yeah it has a little David Grey beard which is the name of the chimpanzee
who she loads after.
A little boy in a cage.
But the thing is like, I know Dan collects a lot of celebrity,
you know, memorabilia and almost all the people end up, you know,
celebrities, they end up getting in trouble for something.
I thought I was safe with Jane Goodall.
Yeah.
I thought there's no way that she could get cancelled.
Well, let's start it tonight.
No she's not.
I do it.
What has she done?
She kept herself in a cage.
No but we all keep our kids in.
So he didn't get killed by aggressive chimpanzees.
So what is a cot but a weak cage?
Exactly.
A cage there to talk.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, that's amazing.
You know that, I mean animals and show business is a marriage made in hell.
Yeah.
We were talking earlier about how this unarmed stick insect
made it from New Zealand in the lots over to the UK.
So stick insects are on every continent except Antarctica.
We've got them globally and you find a lot of these ones
that shouldn't be appearing in other countries somehow there.
Do you know how they do it?
How do stick insects get to other countries?
Yeah.
But not through logs.
Toothpicks.
They pretend to be toothpicks.
That's good.
Very nice.
So you'll be in a Chinese restaurant going to clean your teeth and then, yeah.
Is it ballooning like spiders that kind of thing?
No, it's not.
Poosticks, they float down the slow moving rivers.
I don't know.
It's hitchhiking.
It is hitchhiking.
It's hitchhiking through birds.
So birds will eat a stick insect.
But then you'll have inside a stick insect an egg.
And the egg doesn't need to be fertilized in order to be viable and give birth.
And they can travel through the whole digestive system.
Birds will eat a stick insect, fly, you know, migrate somewhere,
poo out these eggs, which will still be usable.
And they get born in these countries.
It's so clever.
Yeah, it's extraordinary.
The amazing thing about that is if you ever see pictures of stick insect eggs,
and we might mention this before, they look like seeds.
Yeah.
Which is amazing if you think that you're made to look like a stick,
and your babies or your eggs are made to look like seeds.
It's just so, you know, I just think the evolution of that is so super.
And the mimicry that the fact that they like, they, they wave in the wind.
Yeah.
If they need to.
But the idea being, of course, that birds like to eat seeds.
And so if the birds like to eat the seeds,
then they also like to eat things that look like seeds.
So sometimes they just get the eggs directly into them and then poo them out.
Exactly.
That's right. Yeah.
Can I tell you one more thing about animals in children's literature?
Yeah, go on.
So the story of Peter Pan.
Yeah.
Features a crocodile.
Swallowed a clock.
In 2011, there was a crocodile which was in a zoo in Ukraine
and it swallowed a mobile phone.
And the owner was a lady called Rimmer Golovko
and the zookeeper's didn't believe her.
They said the crocodile can't possibly have swallowed him up by phone.
And the crocodile started ringing.
And they realized, no, he absolutely has swallowed that phone.
She was trying to take a really cool shot of the,
of the crocodile from, from, you know, just inside the enclosure.
And unfortunately, yeah.
And they, they really, there isn't an ending to the story
because they were trying to pep him up
because he was feeling a bit peaky.
Oh, no.
They were, the way to pep up a crocodile that's feeling a bit peaky,
it turns out, is to feed it live quail rather than pork.
Okay. Yeah.
I suppose crocodiles, they eat like stones, don't they,
to help them digest things, I think, do they?
Oh, maybe.
So they don't always have just food in the stomach.
No.
So I'm just trying to not have a good spin on this.
Even an early Anokia will trouble it.
Scientists, those weirdos, mad,
they, they found out that crocodiles like classical music.
Really?
And they prefer classical music,
and they therefore think that dinosaurs would have enjoyed classical music as well.
And the way they did that was they got a crocodile to do an MRI scan.
And the report says, you know, with some technical difficulty,
it was quite hard to get the crocodile into the scanner.
Because you need it to be awake to listen to the music, don't you?
You need it to be awake to listen to the music, exactly.
I think it's very loud in an MRI scanner.
Yeah.
I imagine it was horrifying for the crocodile.
Poor thing.
Yeah, exactly.
At least it had a bit of Mozart to listen to.
Yeah, I guess.
It's quite interesting the effect of music on animals.
Shall I hit you with some more of those facts?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, I investigated that a tiny bit,
and went down the deepest of rabbit holes.
Well, one was a bit dumb.
It's just sharks appear scarier if accompanied by ominous music.
No.
You say it's a bit dumb, but I think it's a bit dumb-dumb.
Yeah, dumb-dumb-dumb.
Yes, exactly.
But they were then encouraging documentary makers
to be very, very careful of the soundtracks that they used.
Oh, really?
Yeah, because how animals are seen in documentaries
has a direct impact on how much money you can raise
for that particular breed in conservation.
That's true.
I was watching a TV show yesterday which featured some sharks,
and earlier in the show there was some ominous music,
and at the end, actually, there was some rather majestic music.
And it does change the way you feel.
How much money did you give?
None.
Right.
I was trying to find famous pig walkers.
The other some.
I got one.
Found one.
Not the Middle Ages, unfortunately.
Abraham Lincoln.
No.
Yeah, Abraham Lincoln.
So in America, we touched on this 200 episodes or so very briefly.
Drovers would take pigs across America.
In 1847, there was one toll gate in North Carolina
that showed the number of animals that came through.
You had 692 sheep, 898 cattle, 1,317 horses, and 51,753 hogs.
Wow.
So it was a big business doing this.
And one of the people who used to bring them onto a riverboat
was Abraham Lincoln.
So he'd meet them at a point, and he would walk them all onto riverboats.
Now, the thing with moving pigs around is pigs get really distracted,
as you're saying.
Like, you know, it doesn't need a leash.
What do we do?
If pigs see a body of water, like a little puddle,
all of them will run for the puddle and want to go in and roll around.
So it's really hard to move them.
So what they used to do, and Lincoln used to do this as well,
is you used to sew the eyelids shut of the pigs.
Oh, no.
And you would herd them, and then when they got to where you were going,
you would undo the sew-ins.
And they voted this guy in as president.
Yeah.
Just blindfold the pigs.
It must be easier to blindfold a pig.
Well, I don't know.
But Lincoln had a needle, he had a thread.
He would sew the eyelids shut.
I reckon they could probably shake the blindfold off, right?
They are clever, and they are willful.
That's awful.
That's where he got the ham in his name from.
Previously, it was called Abraham Lincoln.
[LAUGHTER]
Hey, have you guys heard of the wrinkle-faced bat?
No.
I have.
They're so ugly.
Oh, God, this is incredible.
I didn't know about this until researching for this.
It's a pretty-- yeah, it's a pretty ugly bat.
It's got a lot of excessive skin on its face.
But one thing it has, which is really special and quite unique,
is it's got this extra flap of skin that sits underneath on its chin,
and it can put it up over its face.
So it's like COVID times.
Like a mask.
Yeah, it's a mask.
But what?
Because it's a bat.
The bat has a mask against COVID.
Yeah, but also--
That's how this all happened.
[LAUGHTER]
How did they get it to begin with?
You're right.
But when you look at it, it's like a reverse Batman head,
because Batman doesn't cover the mouth, but has the bat head.
But in this case--
Does he?
Yeah.
Hold my bat, man.
He's got a--
Yeah.
One of my chief problems with Batman is that he really does not
consider the anatomy of bats at all in his costumes.
He's really-- bats are very small and not threatening and have
the highest voices.
There's nothing bat-like about Batman.
Yeah, that's true.
Yeah.
The nipples thing is always a thing.
Those could be very pronounced goosebumps.
We don't know.
Bats do have-- I think they do have nipples.
Do they have nipples?
Oh, I thought there was always an issue.
I mean, they're mammals.
You're right.
Sorry.
It's that they often take off the nipples on his suit.
That's an issue.
Oh, that's the-- God, what are they thinking?
Yeah.
I thought the nipples on bats were in the armpits.
Often.
That's-- sorry.
No, that's it.
They've put the nipples in the wrong spot on the suit.
That's it.
That's what's wrong with it.
They didn't film Groundhog Day in "Punks of Tony."
Really?
Yeah, it's not filmed there.
It doesn't look right or something.
They have-- where it was filmed, they have things like--
there's a scene in the movie where Bill Murray always
stands in a puddle.
Yeah.
And they have a little plaque there now.
This is where he stood in the puddle every single day.
That's great.
Yeah.
And a few other spots around the tent.
The people go-- if you went to wherever it is--
Yeah.
Would you deliberately step in a puddle there for a photo
up like they do at--
Like Abbey Road kind of thing?
Yes, yeah, yeah.
I think people liked it.
I think you would, James.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Because you love going to places that are unique and--
No, you're right.
I would.
Yeah, that's-- yeah.
But the dino is still there.
He has a scene in the dino where he, like,
chucks everything around.
Sorry, can I just say it?
Maybe you sound, James, like I'm saying you do incredibly
hacked or something.
No, no.
But so--
Your photo of you holding up the Leading Tarapisa,
I think it's brilliant.
Well, I took a photo of people taking photos of the Leading
Tarapisa and then just try to lean behind her.
So they were holding me up.
One of my favorite videos I've seen, a friend of ours,
mutual friend, don't know if you know her.
Carrie Ed Katia, giving-- she's a--
Yeah, yeah.
--comedian.
She went to Paris and as every-- sorry, not Paris.
I'll stick you in the eye.
So-- and then she left there to do a tarpisa.
She walked around.
There's about 50 people that are doing that Leaning pose
with their hands in the air.
And she ran around giving high-five to my turns
to every single person.
Maybe we should all install a second knocker.
Yeah.
You have to label it.
Well, my lady hands would appreciate that.
Absolutely.
Heavy knocker that I have to keep lifting.
I think, really, you have doorbells, so don't you?
I was going to say I do.
That implies you have one knocker on.
I think if you're saying we're going to have a second knocker.
He does have a doorbell.
I don't mean to give away too much about that.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, it's quite a rare thing to have on your door-to-door knocker
these days.
So I think you've given away a bit much about where you live.
And if you put a second one, then definitely everyone's--
[LAUGHTER]
Everyone's like, that's his house.
I have to install a secret second knocker.
A cupboard that you open the door.
There's a knocker inside.
Yeah, yeah.
I'll do that.
No, I've got it.
Do you guys not have a knocker on your door?
I don't.
I don't think so.
I can't remember.
I do know other people in knockers, though.
[LAUGHTER]
That's just another tangent.
What a sentence.
It was so good.
Andy talking earlier about waste disposal.
Of course, pig toilets used to be a thing in China, especially.
And the idea was that you would have your toilet.
It would be on the first floor.
And the pigs would be living on the ground floor.
And they would just eat your excrement.
Oh, no.
And they took-- they existed from at least 200 BC.
And they were still existent at least in 2005.
You could see them in northern China.
Wow.
And some of the really, really far north provinces.
2005?
Yeah, yeah.
Holy moly.
As far as I know, they might still exist.
But we don't know about any.
But it's really clever because, obviously, your poo can be used as fertilizer.
But it's not great to be put in human poo everywhere because, you know,
it might have parasites or it smells really bad or whatever.
But if you feed it to a pig, then the pig's internal, you know,
stomach will get rid of a lot of the problems that human poo might have.
And when it comes out, it's cleaner.
And pig poo doesn't smell nearly as bad as human poo.
So you end up-- you're basically, you know,
manufacturing this excellent poo from human poo by putting it through a pig.
That's extraordinary.
Yeah.
Isn't it cool?
That's amazing.
Yeah.
It would put me off the-- it would put me off eating the pig.
You know, a lot of religions don't eat pork, right?
And one of the reasons, I think, is because in these kind of pig toilets
or pigs eating excrement was in the areas where these religions started.
Right.
And it was only when the Romans got the pigs and sort of the pigs
that had eaten acorns outside of the cities
and stopped eating human excrement that the Romans thought,
"Well, we should eat these things because they're not eating human poo anymore."
Yeah.
And so, yeah, that's why some parts of the world still will eat bacon
and ham and whatever, but a lot of religions won't.
Can I tell you a pig competition that used to happen in--
Yeah, go on.
--rural cotswolds?
Yeah.
It was at the turn of the 20th century in the cotswolds,
and it was a pub Saturday night competition,
which was effectively pig karaoke.
Okay.
So you have to sing a song,
but you have to sing a song while holding a pig under your arm,
a small pig.
Mm-hmm.
And it's a popular song of the day.
Does it have to be a duet with the pig?
No, it's just you, but--
So what is the pig doing in this case?
Well, if you smile or laugh at all during the song,
you're disqualified, and the pig wriggles, obviously,
and your friends are allowed to shout abuse at you as you're doing it.
But if you win, you get to keep the pig.
Okay.
So that's just a fun competition for the pub.
What happens?
Talking about American pig handling, did you know that--
I just had nothing to say to that, Andy.
I'm really sorry.
No, no.
There's nothing to say to it.
I was trying to think what singers they could be singing,
and it just couldn't come.
Oh, I see.
Yeah.
Did you know that the Texas Senate recently passed a bill
making it legal to shoot wild pigs from hot air balloons?
Okay.
I mean, that's a niche sport, isn't it?
But apparently it's now legal.
Is that still legal?
I think we mentioned that in the book of the year years ago.
It was just happening.
I don't even know if it was passed.
Yeah, it's 2017, I think it was.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's a real problem with feral hugs, don't they?
In America.
Yeah.
And that's why they do that.
Is that in kites, I think, that you're allowed to shoot
from hot air balloons?
It is because it's smoother to shoot it from a hot air balloon.
As in, hot air balloons are quite sedate.
So you can probably aim quite well.
Yeah.
And they don't make a lot of noise like a helicopter,
so they wouldn't scare the pigs.
It's a good idea.
It's a great idea.
If you dress it right, it might look like a giant disco ball
in the sky.
Yeah.
And also, we mentioned a few weeks ago--
next week.
Next week, we're going to mention how well you make hot air balloons
out of intestines of animals, didn't they?
Yeah, that's right.
How do you see the future, James?
That's amazing.
One more thing about insects and their footprints,
which I found cool.
Oh.
So insects leave little damp footprints wherever they go.
That's cute.
And you normally don't notice them, obviously.
Spandle.
Leave wet footprints on the floor.
So insects spandle wherever they go.
Brilliant.
Each footprint is a quadrillionth of a liter.
It's not helpful.
It's very small amount, obviously.
And it was believed, until quite recently,
that the liquid is helping them to stick to the leaf.
Like, you know, when you have a glass with a wet bottom,
it sticks to the table or whatever on the coast.
And so that was what it was believed to be.
But there was an experiment conducted by a Cambridge scientist
called David Labonte, and it was done on stick insects.
This is how I came across this.
And this study was published in the scientific journal
Soft Matter, which sounds great.
And he put wires on stick insects feet,
because they're quite slow and they're quite docile.
And then he measured with a tiny sensor,
the force that was required to lift their feet off glass plates
at various different amounts of wetness.
This is really a hard experiment to do.
And it turns out, this is the really exciting thing,
that the liquid may actually let them unstick their feet,
rather than being the other way around.
It's like a release, release a quadrillionth of a liter.
Because that is one of the interesting things, isn't it?
Because everyone thinks they're called stick insects
because they look like sticks,
but it's because they stick to things.
Oh, no. Is that? No.
Oh, no. There you go. I believed it.
I did. I was totally...
Have you heard of the Euro Club?
No, I haven't.
This is a new invention.
Oh, no.
It is a golf club.
Oh, this sounds great.
Let's say you're out playing golf.
And the base where you go is...
Clubhouse?
Jesus Christ.
It's far away.
But hang on, I need the toilet.
Euro Club is a hollow club where you can take off the lid.
The invention comes with a kind of curtain
that you can put over.
That's lovely.
And you are able to relieve yourself into your golf clubs.
Brilliant.
And then continue on with your game.
Okay, well, sorry, James.
You'll have a few thoughts, but I've got a few too.
Yeah, well, why don't you go first?
I mean me too, frankly.
So, firstly, it presupposes that there are no trees
anywhere near this golf course.
Are you allowed to go on trees?
Well, it's...
Can you have a tree wee?
It is regularly done,
but I think it's kind of frowned upon,
like just urinating in the open.
And also, women can't do that.
Well, it doesn't sound like women can piss into a golf club,
either, mate.
You can have a she-wee.
You can have a she-wee onto the Euro Club.
That'll affect the swing
and that'll affect the hold of the golf club, you know.
Well, I want to know that if you urinate in sweat,
there's going to be...
It's going to change the way that it feels to swing, right?
Yeah.
As you hold it up,
it's all going to be down the end
where you're the top end of the club.
Also, you need to make sure that seal is...
Absolutely.
I don't know if these people
have had any centrifugal forces.
I was going to say watertight.
Piss tight.
That seal needs to be.
Actually, I am thinking,
like, Hannah, you'd know better than me,
but if you hold a golf club like this,
the urine is going to be in your hand
when you're holding it at the top of the swing.
Exactly.
And then when you come down,
the momentum of the urine going down the club
should give you more angular momentum
and should make you hit the ball further.
Hmm.
I mean, sure.
Maybe that's the secret of a lot of great golfers.
That's why.
They've been using the Euro...
Tiger Woods.
Yeah, Tiger Woods, yeah.
Piss filled club for his entire career.
What's your secret?
It just smiles enigmatically when you get away.
That's brilliant.
So, famous fake tan brand is Saint-Tropez.
Mm-hmm.
And I thought I'd look into Saint-Tropez
because it's a famous place
where people might go to get suntans and stuff,
and that's why it's got the name.
It became famous thanks to Brigitte Bardot,
who, she came from a really wealthy family
and her parents had a house there,
but also due to a big argument about topless bathing.
And this was in 1964,
and everyone wanted to do topless bathing in Saint-Tropez,
but the mayor really did not want them to do it.
And there was a massive argument.
It's really famous in France.
And the mayor went so far as to order a helicopter
which he flew over all of the beaches
looking for women who had the tops off.
Dropping towels on them from the height.
Isn't that amazing?
I mean, if he was so bothered by it,
I mean, maybe just consider not looking.
I think if you're the mayor, you have to.
You have to go around looking at everyone on the beach.
Wow.
Do you remember there used to be an airplane
that rock stars used?
So, Zeppelin used it.
It had an open fire chimney.
What inside?
It had a fireplace.
It did.
You can see photos.
They're sitting around like an open fire by a chimney.
Have we not discussed that before?
No.
Have we not?
I can't remember.
Look, I think it's all about benefit and reward, right?
Risk-reward ratio.
And on that, it seems way off.
It's rock and roll, Hannah.
The chimney sweep has got to go up
when you're at 30,000 feet.
I remember through Time magazine's Best Inventions of 2022,
which was pretty good.
Oh, I think I know one of these.
Oh, go for it.
Is one of them a prosthetic hand
that you can try with your mind?
There was one like that.
Yeah.
It was incredible.
I kind of went for the less good ones.
Tasty tape, I thought was pretty cool.
That's nice.
It's like cellotape for burritos.
So, you know, you make a burrito
and it kind of can fall apart and stuff.
This is edible cellotape, and it means you can like...
That's brilliant.
It is a genius idea, isn't it?
Sorry, it's edible.
Is it tasty?
It's called tasty tape, so...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It could be cool as advertising.
Put some Hannah's MSG on it.
Yeah?
Everything's tasty.
That's just quite a nice idea, isn't it?
I think that's a great idea.
Yeah.
Yeah, like that.
Say goodbye to burrito-collapsed misery.
Do you bring your own tape to the burrito...
Party.
Yeah.
It's not a big dispenser at the counter.
Okay.
I would say it's more if you're making them yourself.
I would say you advise...
They can fold effectively.
I mean, they're folding wizards.
Yeah.
They are very good.
They're crows, and really, they don't...
Actually, I've never had it fall apart.
I genuinely thought you were about to admit
that you'd never had a burrito.
If you make your own fajitas, for instance.
Yes.
Like, you're at home making fajitas.
Sure.
They do fall apart, like, don't they?
Oh, do they not?
You are an expert origami.
They're pretty good.
They keep the shape.
You're not putting enough stuff in.
No, maybe that's it.
Maybe that's it.
Yeah.
Yeah, your bread to filling ratio needs to be addressed.
They are a bit.
They are a bit at the tiny tip of the fajita world.
It's a slightly sad affair.
'Cause if you go to Formula One, you kind of sat in your place
and they fly past it about a million miles an hour.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Like, just see them for one second.
I have always thought that about watching it light.
Like, doesn't it just go past you and then...
It does, yeah.
Yeah.
I did that with the Olympic cycling.
Yeah, yeah.
And same with the Tour de France self-replace.
Weighted, boom, and then we waited four hours.
And then, boom, the other way.
Got on the bus with the dogs.
They were pissed off as well.
Did I ever tell you that thing about my friend who was in France
and was on the tour?
I've done that on the show.
I don't think so.
I love it anyway.
A friend of mine went to the Tour de France.
He knew this at the time, got a house, rented a house,
and the Tour de France came right past the house.
Wow.
So he had his whole family with him
and he had people from his work and they all watched it.
And he found out that the house was for sale.
So he bought the house and he went,
"We're going to come back every year
and we're going to watch the Tour de France from this spot."
Not knowing that the Tour de France changes its route
every single year.
Oh, my God.
It's brilliant.
It still has the house.
(APPLAUSE)
So if you can play the music a bit,
this is the shows over now.
Can I ask, who's the person who sent me a message
saying the newest species in Lizard in New Zealand
was discovered by me?
Are you lying?
Wow.
That's not evidence.
It's circumstantial out there.
But also, that wasn't the person who was asking,
"What are you lying about?"
Are you Ben Barr?
Can we get a mic over, actually?
Let's quickly get a mic.
Tell us your name, first of all.
I'm Lockie.
He's definitely from New Zealand.
Hi, Lockie.
We've established.
I named a hoplodactylus tohu after working with
some of the indigenous Mori communities in New Zealand,
because it was important to their tribes or whatever
that lived in the area that the species was in.
You named it what? A hoplodactylus?
It's called hoplodactylus tohu.
What is it? It's a gecko.
Oh, wow.
It's a New Zealand gecko, which is the odds of that happening.
Oh, my God, you must have been seeing it at the whole show.
You didn't fucking see it?
Yeah, I was going to wait till the end.
I wasn't going to be...
That's amazing. That's incredible.
Wait, so you found a new species of gecko
or a very old species of gecko?
Yeah, it's always been there, but no one knew it.
No one knew it existed.
That's amazing. Yeah, using DNA stuff, we found it.
So, I got a message just today from someone
saying, because we did a fact about
stick insects on a previous fish episode,
it's just gone out with John Lloyd.
John Lloyd, the creator of QI
and, you know, Blackadder
and Spitting Image.
I think he's here. John, are you here?
Is he here? Yeah, he is.
Yeah, that's our founder.
Blackadder, Spitting Image,
not the minor-clock news, but the legend.
So, we did this fact,
and someone messaged me saying,
"Just in case you're not completely sick of stick insects,
check out the Lord Howe Island
Phasmid."
Phasmid? Phasmid, yeah.
Phasmid, yeah.
And then she wrote, "Full disclosure,
it was my dad who found it
when he went climbing Balls Pyramid
with Dick Smith."
Balls and Dick?
That's the... Yeah, love it.
That's wonderful.
Oh, thank you very much, Loki, that's brilliant.
Are we going to do some more? Yeah, one or two more.
Okay, so, we'll have to be really quick, I guess.
Yeah, yeah, quick.
Someone messaged saying,
"What is the one disgusting fact
that you wish you'd never learned?"
Oh, there's a frog called the horror frog.
Oh, no, there's a frog...
There's a frog fertility thing. It's really horrible.
Uh...
We were in Wales when we did it on the show.
It was in Cardiff in the Glee Club,
and the audience physically...
We're all repulsed, but I can't remember
the details of the fact now.
So, if you go back 300 episodes
and listen to that, you're welcome.
Have you got one?
I've got one. There are orangutan brothels.
No.
There are where...
Do you want me not just to say it?
No, say it. I'll tell you how I found this out,
because the story is quite funny.
I was filming Death in Paradise,
and I really didn't want to go.
I was like, "I don't like this show."
Imagine if you don't do this show.
I'd turn it down three times.
Because if you don't do it, I'm going to drop you
because you just don't want to be on telly.
You wouldn't be hosting dog award ceremonies.
That's your thing.
It was only when I got on the plane
that I went, "Actually, I'm going to the Caribbean
for 10 days. It's not that bad."
And I got out there, and I had a really great time.
Had the most amazing cast,
a brilliant gang of renegades.
And one of the people,
Francis,
who was telling us about house he had
in Borneo, and he said,
"Oh, you know,
it was a very small house,
and there were a reed roof,
and snakes used to fall in when it rained."
And I said, "Oh, that's awful. I couldn't handle that."
I couldn't handle that. He said, "It wasn't the worst thing, though.
The worst thing was the
sex tourists going through the jungle
to have sex with the orangutans."
And I was like, "No way."
And we said, "The orangutans are threatened."
And I said,
"Oh, because of the logging?"
And he went, "No, because of the sex tourists going in
and having sex with them." I said, "Oh, that's awful."
And Nick Moran from
what's he called, you know,
the lock stock,
he said,
"Oh, that's disgusting." He said,
"They have sex with the orangutans." He said,
"I wouldn't fuck a ginger human," he said.
[laughter]
Like the problem,
like the problem was that the orangutan
was orange.
[laughter]
Sorry, Andy. I know your parents are in.
I'm sorry.
Sorry, Andy's mum and dad.
[laughter]
Oh, look.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
Well, once again, Sally has brought us to the end
of a show.
Thank you so much, everyone.
Thank you. Have a good night.
[applause]
[music]
All right, that's it.
That is all of our outtakes.
Hope you enjoyed that.
As ever, if you want to get in touch with me or Andy or James,
you can go to our Twitter accounts
or you can email us on podcast@qi.com.
Send us any
thoughts, any discoveries, any ideas,
any jokes,
whatever it is you want. Send us facts,
and hopefully they can make their way to a
drop us a line in the future.
All right, everyone, we'll be back again
with more bonus content in the
coming weeks, and we will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)