We run it on QI a few years ago.
Yeah.
Which was, there's no such thing as a fish.
You did a nice, such thing as a fish.
No, seriously, it's in the Oxford Dictionary of Underwater Life.
He says it, ride that first paragraph, no such thing as a fish.
Hello, welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming
to you from the QI offices in Covern Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Andy Murray, James Parkin, and Anna Chazinsky.
And once again, we've gathered around the microphone with our four favorite facts on the
last seven days.
So here we go, in no particular order, let's do it.
James, back number one.
My fact this week is that in the 17th century, there was a prophet called Dorothy Harling,
who would kill you of your sins by urinating on the afflicted part of your body.
Wow.
When you've got a sin, what was the afflicted part of your body?
Well, if you'd been swearing, it could be your mouth.
Right.
Yeah.
If you'd stolen something, it could be your hands, I guess.
Okay.
If you'd thought a dirty thought, your brain would piss in your ear.
Into your ear.
She would whip people first.
She would whip you first to try and get rid of the sins and then she'd urinate on you.
And she was known as the permanent spring.
This sounds more like a chapter from 50 Shades of Grey.
Does it?
Oh, yeah.
Whipping.
I mean, that's all very bondage-based activity.
It wasn't uncommon to use urine in a weird medical way though, was it, in around that time
in the 17th century.
No.
So they had people who would smell or look at the colour, or even sometimes the flavour of
people's urine in order to diagnose disease.
And they had, you know, those colour wheels you get.
They had a urine wheel like pantone.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And they had 20 different colours of urine around the edge of it.
20 Shades of Pea.
And so the end it was all to do with the humourism, whether you're four humour's were in order.
But I think that would work.
I think if your urine tasted sweet, then you might be diabetics.
That's how they used to do that, right?
Yeah.
Doctors used to diagnose you that way.
It was called Thomas Willis, the man who discovered it, and in 1674, he said that diabetic
people's urine was wonderfully sweet as if it were imbued with honey or sugar.
And it was called Willis's disease for a long time, diabetes, because of him discovering
it.
Plylly said that you could use urine for a whole bunch of ailments, but stale urine mixed
with ash could be rubbed on your baby for nappy rash.
Which sounds just like a really unpleasant way to be entering the world.
I think there's like Mayan tablet or something like that that says this is about the patient.
If all else fails, have him remove one sandal, urinate in it, and drink the urine.
And this was if everything else in that the doctor prescribed didn't work, then that was
the last thing you should try.
Oh, sandals are they full of holes?
Good point.
I don't know how I would retain lipid in my sandals.
So actually drinking urine has been thought by quacks for centuries as being a way of solving
any problems that you have.
I think we mentioned it on QI, that, and we have a website address that we bought called
drinkmyurin.co.uk, and if you go on to that, then it takes you to the QI website.
And what that means is because we still own it, all of the QI.com URLs can also be written
as drinkmyurin.co.uk.
So if you go on to drinkmyurin.co.uk/podcast, you'll find our podcast page.
Speaking of drinking urine, there's so many people of Scandinavia and Northern Scandinavia.
People thought for ages that they would feed magic mushrooms to their reindeer, and then
they would drink their reindeer here.
Oh, I agree with that.
Yeah.
So, and then they get high off magic mushrooms, but without getting the poisonous effect
and vomiting, which is what happens if you eat them directly, if you eat too much.
And then this anthropologist came along and debunked this whole thing and said the Sami
people did not drink reindeer urine.
And then he went and interviewed a Sami person, so he wrote a whole book about how they don't,
and then he met some Sami people and they were like, "Yeah, we do this all the time."
Oh, no.
So we had to write another book saying, "Actually."
They do it.
I read a thing about the coriac people in Siberia.
They would take us sort of hallucinogenic psychedelic mushroom, and the mushroom would send them insane
into like a beautiful psychedelic thing.
The problem was it's quite expensive, and so it has a thing in it where when you urinate
it doesn't dilute the hallucinogenic in it, and so basically it comes out just as strong,
just slightly diluted from the initial thing that you're taking.
So the people who couldn't afford to take the mushroom would buy the urine off the people
who just had a trip so that they could then have that.
So in Siberia, Russia, they used to, if you had chewing gum, you would chew it, and so you
didn't have the taste anymore, and then you'd pass that onto someone else to have the remnants
of the taste?
Why?
Because it was so rare.
But if there was no taste left?
Yeah, but I think I'm right in saying your mouth kind of gets used to the taste, so there's
still some left.
It does, and that's why there's always room for pudding.
It's called sensory-specific satiety, SSS, and if you are really full of your main course,
you think, "Oh, I can't eat any more of this," whatever it is, you're having risotto.
And then someone says, "Hey, how about a proffittoral?"
Your taste buds perk up, and you think, "Oh, wait, maybe I can squeeze in a bit more food,
because it's a different flavor."
It's a different flavor, right?
Okay.
I got a good urine fact.
Well, it turns out that we urinate 50% more than we drink per day.
How could that be?
That's what I thought.
Because you're breathing in water vapor.
No, it's because all the foods that get broken down, there's lots of water in foods.
Oh, that's awesome.
Yeah.
That's amazing.
Yeah, that is good.
Hold on.
Thanks.
I thought it was going to be because we are half yetis, and yetis are the little dita.
The first obscenity law in England was in 1663, when poet Sir Charles Sedley got too drunk,
shouted, "Blasphemous things from a balcony in Covent Garden, and urinated on the crowd
below."
Oh.
And that was also the last law written in Norman French in the UK.
Wow.
That's it.
Yeah.
That's a nice coincidence.
We should get a balcony.
And Sigmund Freud viewed urinating in public as a sign of strong subconscious ambition.
Oh, did he?
Yeah.
And if that's true, Central London on a Friday night is one of the most ambitious places in
the world.
I've got one more thing about you.
Yeah.
So, oh, which do you want?
Do you want the one about rabbits or the one about the future?
Oh, the future.
The future.
So, as well as these doctors who were genuinely trying to work out how you could use urine to
diagnose disease, there were people who practiced the art of Euromency, which is the art
of telling the future using urine, and they were also known as piss profits, a bit more
vulgarly.
But, they took omens from different signs in it, so some people took omens from the colour
of the client's urine or from its taste, or they read the bubbles immediately after it
hit the bowl.
So, you would have to weigh in in the divination bowl.
And if there were large bubbles spread out, you were about to come into money.
There were small bubbles packed together.
But it would be illness or someone who loved to die, and I know.
Oh, no.
So, it would die just because I'd peed bubbles.
Small, packed together bubbles.
Yes.
Right.
So, be careful.
Can you imagine?
Wow.
Yeah.
And it was very common in the 17th century.
A lot of people slag them off, Ben Johnson, so that they were 30-facy, nasty-patey, lousy-farticle
rogues.
Famously mature, man.
So, this young lady Dorothy Harling, she was thought to have been someone who was predicted
in the book of revelations, or a lot of these people called French prophets who came over.
They were hoganos, and they were them.
They claimed that they were, you know, prophets from the Bible.
But I just really like prophets.
I like, you know, people who think that they're gods, or...
Yeah.
But I love this guy.
There was a guy called Cooper.
I remember his first name, and he was living in London.
He was unemployed.
And some of his friends, some of his Indian friends told him that he looked and moved just
like an ancient Indian goddess.
And he thought, "Oh, well, that sounds quite good."
Anyway, so he then went to Gujarat, and he claimed to be this ancient goddess in human form.
And now he lives in a holy saffron robe, living among 80 eunuchs.
Why didn't he say to his friends, "Okay, great, whatever, let's have another drink."
Who takes their friends' comments on how they look that seriously?
Yeah, but...
Every time I saw my mum, I believe I was beautiful, if that was the way he used to be.
Oh, you are beautiful, and I don't know.
Well, thanks guys.
Okay, time for fact number two, and that is Yulcha Zinski.
So my fact is that, despite the fact that homosexuality is completely illegal in the south
to Dan, a woman can have a female husband and a child can have a female father.
Oh, how does that work?
So it makes sense because it's true actually across parts of East Africa in various tribes,
one of the tribes is the new air tribe, and if a woman is infertile, it's a way of herbing
able to continue her family line.
So this infertile woman has a father who wants to pass on property to a son or a grandson.
Right.
So the infertile woman marries another woman, and then this other woman has a secret lover
whom she has some sex with, gets pregnant, and then she has a child by that man, but that
child is officially the child of the infertile woman and the other woman.
And then everything like legal, societal, cultural rights, everything like that, it's all the
same as if they were a normal husband and wife marriage.
It's openly accepted that that's what's done, and it's enshrined in law, and there's this
other weird thing as well, which is, I think this is another tribe in Kenya, it's the courier
tribe, which is called daughter-in-law marriage.
Wait, the courier tribe?
The courier tribe, yeah, where they make the font, right?
Yes indeed, and they just carry stuff back and forth.
That's what I thought, yeah, they were delivering stuff.
Yeah.
They deliver babies.
Oh no, the courier, K-U-R-I-A tribe, and they have this thing called daughter-in-law marriage
where an infertile woman marries another woman, and then she gives as a wife the other woman
to her fictitious son.
So this woman doesn't have any sons, but she marries a woman and then donates that woman
to her made-up son, and so that woman now counts as her daughter-in-law, and then that woman
gets pregnant, and then that counts as her grandchild.
It's a very confusing system.
So it's like having your friend marry your imaginary friend?
Yes, yes, exactly, because having a daughter-in-law is a sign of status in certain African tribes
and again, confers certain cultural systems.
It's pretty great.
Oh my God, it's pretty great.
There is problems if you can't have children yourself, but you want to keep their family
line going.
Yeah.
It's ingenious.
There are lots of women in Albania who live as men, aren't there?
Yeah, is it a canoeing law or something like that?
I think so, yeah.
But actually, I say there are lots.
There are very few now, because it's a very old custom, and most of the remaining ones
are in their 70s, 80s or even 90s, so.
But they simply live as men, so they dress as men, they live as men.
And do they pretend that they are men?
Or does everyone know that they're women, but they just say-
I don't know, but they're a woman, but they have the status of a man.
Yeah, all you have to do is dress as the man, and then people accept that you are.
Yeah.
And that's just a way society works.
You don't marry.
You're not allowed to marry, and you're known as a swan virgin, I think.
That's right.
Yeah, yeah.
But you are officially a man, even though you're a celibate man, and you won't marry a woman.
Okay.
But you're unannounced.
There is a canoeing law in Albania, and he says it's a very old fashion one, but I think
there's one other thing, if I'm right, it's the same thing where, if your wife is having
sex with another guy, you're allowed to kill them, but you have to kill them both at the
same time with one bullet, and they have to be in the act at the time.
Wow.
Could you guys just line up there please?
Yeah.
It's still-
I think that's a needlessly complicated work around.
You could just say you're not allowed to murder anyone.
Yes.
It's a loophole, isn't it?
It is a loophole.
It almost sounds as if it happened once, and they went, "Oh no, no, it's legal.
Do you not read those comments?"
In France, you can marry dead people.
Okay.
It's called posthumous marriage, and the idea is that, say, I have a fiance, and she's
going to inherit half of what I own, but then I die, legally, she'd have no right to it,
so that, do the marriage after I've died, and then she legally is part of that family, and
owns half of the oroms, all of their stuff.
That makes sense.
These are all ingenious solutions to the natural problems of life, and how it gets in the
way of stability.
The societal problems of life, mainly in the case of gender discrimination, and it's
quite funny, the idea is that they really miss the point that women go to the lawmakers
and say, "Oh, the gay people in Africa," and say, "We're really sick of this discrimination,
and the lawmakers go, "Okay, we'll let you pretend to be a man."
Does that solve the problem?
It's like...
No, not really.
If the suffragettes had gone down that road, then we'd be living in a hundred percent
male Britain today.
All of you have the legal right to be men.
We were talking about France, a French wedding custom in the Overn region in certain villages.
It's called La Routie.
They have the wedding, and then the married couple then go after their bed chamber, and then
it's traditional for the wedding guests to interrupt their bed chamber in the middle of
the night, overturn their bed chamber, and then they fill up a chamber pot with all the
leftover wine, champagne, food, sometimes toilet paper, apparently tampon soaked in tomato
sauce, and they force the bride and groom to drink the contents of this chamber pot as
a wedding ritual.
It's boost to signify their intimacy of their future life together or something.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
Romantic, right?
What a great way to ruin someone's wedding night.
I'm definitely going to start doing that to my friends.
Or they also fill up with champagne and chocolate, sometimes, which symbolises urine and
feces.
Yeah.
I have a bit of a worry about champagne representing urine, because it has lots of bubbles
in it, and presumably everyone's just going to die in a small pack together bubbles as
well.
Yeah.
There's another wedding which I really want the verification of it, so if anyone belongs
to the Tidong tribe in Borneo who's listening to this podcast, or who knows of them, apparently,
if you get married in this tribe, you're not allowed to urinate or defecate or wash for
three days after you get married.
And it's just on this one person's blog who went and hung out with the Tidong tribe, but
I couldn't find reference to it anywhere else.
So three days you have to hold it in.
That's amazing.
I admire that.
There's been a problem with this, because if the Tidong tribe in Borneo, in the middle
of the jungle are listening, how are they going to tell you because you're not on Twitter?
That's a good point.
I forgot that's the only way they communicate.
Also, holding it in for three days just after a wedding is tough, because you drink a lot
of the wedding.
That's so true.
And it's going to be the most unsavory after those three days.
It's the least romantic way again to end them, as you both fighting your way to the toilet
for an explosive session.
Anyway.
Have you heard of Bride Pie?
This is an English wedding tradition, so you have wedding cake, everyone knows about that.
But traditionally in the 17th, 18th centuries around that time, you would also have Bride
Pie.
And this is a savoury dish, and it had lots of little things in it, like cox combs, you
know those, from a cockerel, or lamb's testicles, or goose giblets.
This sounds like a very unsavory pie to me.
There was one recipe for a Bride Pie in Robert Mays book, The Accomplished Cook, which
included Veal Sweepbreds, Ox Tung's, A Pine of Oysters, Bacon, Chasnuts, Lemon Juice, Pickle
Berry's Wine, A Life Snake for Entertainment purposes, More Oysters and an Onion.
I always find my pies aren't entertaining, dear milk and mobré, I was most disappointed
on getting to the end of my pie to find you had left out the Life Snake.
Please, can you rectify this situation?
Marriages in Sudan, do you remember that famous guy who married a goat?
Oh, yeah.
He had to, didn't he?
He was helped by law.
He was caught in the Clagrante Delector, and they said, "Well, in order to preserve the
honour of the goat who was called Rose, he had to marry her."
And Rose, unfortunately, died about a year later after she swallowed a plastic bag.
How convenient for a man.
In India, people sometimes marry trees, don't they?
Why would you marry a tree?
It's an astrological thing, so in certain parts of India, you are manglic, if you're born
on a certain day of the month, which means that astrologically you have bad luck and in
marriage, it means that you'll likely be married to a lot of different husbands, either
they'll die or you'll get divorced, and the way to counterbalance that is in a ceremony
which is called arc-viva or cum-viva, where you marry a tree or an urn, and that's your
first marriage, and so that means, and you do the full ceremony, and that means you've
done marriage number one, now you can do marriage number two.
And I think the former Miss World of 1990 was a tree, 1996, and she did this in, I think,
2003 or 2004, because she was very superstitious, and she was born under this sign.
And the idea is that after you get married, you then chop down the tree or smash the urn.
Not to be recommended with genuine husbands.
It's not bad for the tree though, yeah.
And the tree's delight, you're going to marry a beautiful woman.
It's the wedding night, I'm so excited.
Excuse the guy with the eggs approach.
Okay, time for fact number three, and that is my fact, my fact this week, it's a discovery
that Tommy Flowers, the man who was responsible for the first ever, I guess the first ever
computer you could call it, Colossus, which was designed during World War II, is that when
they were pushing forward the idea that the Colossus should be made, it kept blowing up,
because it was made of 100, 100, 500 different valves, kept blowing up every time they turned
it on, and they said this can't work, and he was convinced it could work.
He worked out that by turning it on and off, that that's what was blowing it up.
So the first ever bit of IT advice was to not turn it off, then turn it back on again.
That's brilliant.
That's really funny.
So this is Tommy Flowers.
Tommy Flowers, yeah, Tommy Flowers used to work for the post office.
So he designed this thing, he put it forward, they said no to it, after they said no to it,
he solved the problem, and then they said no to it again, because it just took up too much
space and it was going to take a year to make, so he just went ahead with it anyway, as a
kind of half-secret project, which is an amazing half-secret project to have, because it was
the size of a room in Bletchley.
I don't know how you hide that, I don't know.
Yeah, in Bletchley among people whose job it is to find out any secrets you might have.
Literally the worst place in the world are trying to keep the secret.
That's such a good boy.
That's so funny.
Well, we found that all this computer ever, well what's always cited as the oldest computer
ever, was only discovered in, I think it was 1902, I want to say, anyway, early 20th Century,
was that ancient Greek computer from the 2nd century BC, which is called the Antikythera.
The Antikythera, yeah.
Is that definitely a computer, do we think?
Everyone always refers to it as a computer, so it's an unbelievably complex system of
cogs, which if you spin a handle on it, which correctly show you the rotation of all the
planets that have been discovered at the time, which has five planets, I think, and could
predict a lunar eclipse and a solar eclipse, and they didn't make anything nearly as complicated
as that for another 1,500 years or so.
If anyone listening to this is thinking, oh, look into that later, Google it right now
while you remember.
Maybe after the show.
Or maybe after the show.
Just press pause and check it out, because it's the most extraordinary looking item, and
it's so out of place and time, that's the thing.
You look at it, and it's like all those books that used to come out back in the 70s by Eric
Von Daniken and stuff saying, oh, there were ancient batteries and stuff, and you look at
it and you go, no, of course not, this is completely falsified.
This is the real deal.
This is a thing that just, it's so complicated.
It is.
It's insane.
I'm calling it, I think that's a computer.
They were computers used to refer to someone who just worked out when Easter was.
Really?
They would have a monk whose job it was to work out all the dates and all their feasts
and stuff like that.
They used to be in the main one and they were called computers.
If you tried turning him off and then turning him back on again.
I read that the Colossus was actually dismantled, a bunch of them were dismantled, I think eight
of the ten, and all of the parts that made it up went into the spares of post office systems
again.
Really?
So a large part, and apparently those are still being used today.
So a large part of the postal service is still being used using parts from Colossus,
the very first computer.
It explains a lot.
A couple of years ago at AQI Recording, we had some charity guests and one of the people
I met there was he ran the computers which control a lot of trains all over the UK and
he said they run on every system that you can imagine.
There are still trains that are running on MS DOS in Britain today and there are ones
which run on apples and when they first built the computing systems, a lot of the levers
for the points changing and things like that, they used parts from old RAF planes and
levers and things like that, amazingly cool, hodgepodge way of doing it.
The problem with that is of course that when you have things going wrong, you don't have
the parts to replace them because there's such antiquated systems and also if you had someone
who had to fix a computer system and it's written in some old code that no one does any
more than your completely screwed.
MS DOS is going to come back, James.
Is it?
C, colon slash slash.
Yes.
Do you know who wrote the, do you remember the opening music for Microsoft when your
computer would turn on that music that it would make like that one?
It was exactly that.
Yeah.
Do you know who wrote that?
Is it Brian Eno?
Yeah.
No, there wasn't that one actually.
Oh right.
I couldn't tell which one that one was that James was doing.
He wrote Brian Eno wrote the one that went, sounds like him.
He got given a list of about 100 words, descriptive words saying it needs to be sexy, informative,
exciting, ambitious, all these words and it needs to be in 0.75 seconds or 3.4 seconds.
And so the great secret of it was that he wrote it on a Mac.
Oh really?
Yeah.
Really?
The first laptop was sold in 1982.
They were selling them door to door.
They were priced around $20,000 in today's money so pretty expensive things.
They were pretty big, about 11 pounds.
But the main problem, the reason people don't want to buy them is because they had a keyboard
on them and like big executives who worked in offices thought that typing stuff was something
that would be done by secretaries not by themselves.
Wow.
And so they really resisted having anything that had a keyboard on it.
That's really a status indicator.
Yeah.
That's incredible.
Computers have changed quite a lot.
I was reading in the news just this week.
They have a supercomputer that read 100,000 scientific papers in two hours and cross-referenced
all of them against each other and found completely new types of biology.
What?
I know.
Really?
It's quite complicated to explain what it was but it was something like they were looking
for a specific compound and they looked for mentions of it in all these 100,000 papers
and cross-referenced them against each other and they found new types of these compounds
that they didn't know existed before or something like that anyway.
That's absolutely unbelievable.
I know.
I can't really work out what it means.
I haven't seen it.
I'll post it on my Twitter feed if people want to read that but it's absolutely amazing.
So I was looking into code breaking during World War II.
The guy who invented, who came up with the Nigma Arthur Sherbius didn't know where he'd
come up with.
He died in 1929 in a carriage accident, I think, before he knew that it was being put
to that kind of use.
But he also invented the electric pillow.
Sorry, what's an electric pillow?
I assume it's so he patented a way of transmitting heat through various objects and so I think
it's like an electric blanket.
Oh.
Just to keep your head really hot.
I don't know why you want that.
Because that's one problem, isn't it?
The pillows get too hot.
Yeah.
You turn the pillow over and the other side's even hotter.
Okay, time for our final fact of the show and that is Andy Murray.
Hello.
My fact is that a couple of botanists from Q Gardens recently checked a £1.29 bag of
Porcini mushrooms from the supermarket and they found three species which were previously
unknown to science.
That's pretty cool.
Yeah.
They thought they'd run it through a DNA sequencer.
As you do.
Do they do that before they eat all of their meals?
Try it.
It's a bit like horse meat in Lasagna kind of thing, is it?
Like they thought they were Porcini, but I don't know, it's like unicorn Lasagna.
Yeah.
Give me a go.
So does that mean we're just missing them all because they just happen to be botanists?
We've all probably eaten mushrooms that are completely unknown to science.
So they got to name them, which is cool.
You don't often get to name three new species.
What did they call them?
They call them Latin names which translate as white beef liver, delicious cattle liver
fungus and the third one just means edible.
Ran out of ideas.
One of the people who has a lot of animals named after them whose lives is an explorer
in Venezuela called Charles Bruech Carayas and he has a lot of animals attributed to him
partially because in Venezuela there's so many undiscovered species that any time he
goes to a new one of the tabletop mountains, he just discovers tons of new species.
It's so diverse up there as well.
They say that if you're on the top of these tabletop mountains, if you have two bodies
of water literally meters apart from each other, the fish inside this one will be a complete
different species of the fish inside of the one sitting beside it.
That's how varied and...
So are you talking about the Andes, did you say?
Because the orchids that are in the Andes, the Ecuadorian Andes, they have more orchids
than anywhere else on the planet that are endemic, only found there.
One botanist called Lou Jost found four new species of orchid in a single day all hidden
in the same patch of moss.
Wow.
Isn't that amazing?
There was a new species of chameleon found in Tanzania and it was found after a snake
spat out a still undigested specimen in the feet of a British scientist.
Wow.
There's a snake there.
He's like, "Oh no, there's a snake!"
And then it sort of vomits up a chameleon and goes, "Oh, that's a new one.
I haven't seen that before."
Incredible.
That's like, that happens all the time, it seems, to these sort of zoologist and stuff.
The guy who discovered a new species of monkey that fell into his notebook.
I know it wasn't monkey, it was a new species of frog, a dark frog that fell into his
notebook as he was catapult.
Did he press it?
Like a flower?
I'm sure, leave it for three days, and then show it to my teacher.
My favorite species discovery is a really exciting discovery in 2010 of a species called
the Australopithecus sediba, which is a type of hominid, a new type of hominid they found.
And basically this guy, Lee Burgers, a paleoanthropologist, and he was in South Africa on a paleoanarchological
dick looking for fossils and new species.
So while he was doing this, his nine-year-old son, nearby, Matthew, was playing with the dog
and tripped over a clavicle and jawbone which turned out belong to a new species of hominid
and brought it back to his dad.
He was obviously like, "Shut up, son, I'm busy now.
Go away, come back later."
Turn out, he discovered a new human, basically.
Wow.
Incredible.
Okay, so this is, I really like this.
We don't know for sure how many species of gerbil there are.
Oh, that's great.
We know of 95, but I think no one's properly looked into it, like with so many species animals,
we have no idea how many there are.
Among the 95 known species of gerbil are Wagner's gerbil, as well as Cheezmans, the South African
hairy footed, Swaldies, Pleasant, Burton's, Julian's, Vivaceus, and Rigenbach's.
Swaldies, I like Pleasant gerbil.
Pleasant gerbil.
Yeah.
I don't believe such thing exists.
Gerbil.
I think I feel about gerbil.
It's like you feel about mushrooms.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Not too many of them know.
They have an indefinable aura of death around them.
Is that a fact?
No.
I mean, that's what Jane thinks about mushrooms.
Oh, right.
Okay, got it on the subject of gerbils, finding stuff in food.
There was a guy in Killington, which is quite near where I'm from, in Oxfordshire recently,
who bought online from Tesco's a pack of hovis sliced bread, and there's just the best
picture of it.
So he found a whole mouse inside the bread, and it was sort of, it looks like something
fossilized, but it's this complete mouse, and it took about four slices of bread.
But without a tail, and he'd already eaten some.
So was the genuine I found half a maggot in my food.
Premiere foods, who made the bread, admitted it had failed to ensure all stages of food production
were protected against contamination.
Wow.
The food standards authority allows up to 20 maggots per 100 grams of mushrooms, before
it's a problem, and 75 mites before 20 maggots per 100 grams of mushrooms.
That's quite a lot.
It is quite a lot, isn't it?
100 grams, which is very much.
I suppose mushrooms, dried mushrooms are very light, so 100 grams is quite a lot.
It's not dried, it's drained.
Oh, okay.
So just normal mushrooms.
There is a species of mushroom, named recently called Fallas Druziai, and that was named
after a guy called Bob Druze, and obviously Fallas, because it's shaped like a penis.
And so this, basically, is named Bob Druze's penis.
Oh, it's a name of...
Wow.
It's a name of the thing.
And does someone really not like Bob Druze?
No, it was in his honor, they were friends of his, and he said, in an interview with a newspaper,
he said, "I am utterly delighted."
The funny thing is that it is...
I'm sorry.
What?
This is going to go wrong.
No.
He said...
I am utterly delighted.
The funny thing is that it is the second smile I stole from my shoe.
I can't do this.
Do you need someone else to read it out to you?
I don't know.
Sorry, I don't know.
What else to read this, because I keep laughing.
Bob Druze said, "I am utterly delighted.
The funny thing is that it's the second smallest known mushroom in his genus, and it grows sideways
almost live."
Okay?
There you go.
That's amazing.
Yeah, but he was delighted that it was named after him.
It also emits a foul-older and attracts plagues.
But I understand why he's so pleased.
It's a mushroom on the other hand.
It's going to be a rose named after June Whitfield.
Oh, yeah.
The catalogue description.
It says it's good in the bed, but best up against the wall.
Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thanks so much, everyone, for listening.
If you want to get in contact with any of us, you can do so via the Twitter account @QIPodcast,
which we are all logged into, et cetera, for Anna, so you can send us whatever you think,
and we'll answer it.
Otherwise, you can get us on our individual Twitter handles.
I'm on @Sriberland.
James.
@X-shaped.
Andy.
@Andruhunter-M.
The tree.
It's five E's at the end there.
Anna.
You can email podcast@QIPodcast.com.
Yes.
Okay.
And so, yeah, that's it.
We'll be back again next week.
If you go to drinkmyurin.co.uk/podcast.
You can see all the previous episodes for no such thing as a fish, and we'll be back again
next week with another collection of our four favorite things that we found out from
the past seven days.
Okay.
See you then.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]