[upbeat music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast coming
to you from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Triber, and I'm sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray, and
Aniches Inski, and once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite
facts from the last seven days and in no particular order, here we go, starting with you, James
Harkin.
Okay, my fact this week is that the word "wow" was popular in Scotland for 400 years before
it caught on in the rest of the English-speaking world.
You were so waiting for one of those together, weren't you?
Oh, hang on.
Wow.
You're in the right place, and yeah, isn't that crazy?
It's first use, 1513, this is according to the Oxford English Dictionary, in a translation
of the "Need" by G Douglas, whoever that was.
Was it in the original author, Virgil?
Yeah.
You're right.
But G Douglas was a Scottish person, and he said out on their 100-spirits, "Wow,
thou crayous."
And then the first time it gets used really in the English-speaking world is about the 1890s,
and Burns uses it, and a few other Scottish writers use it as well.
And it was in that context, it's meant as an exclamation.
It looks like it doesn't it?
"Wow, thou crayous."
Yeah.
You're crying.
Wow.
Yeah.
So why was Scottish people keeping it to themselves?
Like a secret for 400 years?
Maybe the only exciting things that happened in the world were all in Scotland.
That's true.
They were ahead with inventions and the enlightenment.
There was much more to say "wow" to.
That's true.
And there was necessarily elsewhere.
Yeah.
So, yeah, Andy brings up a good point.
How is it that we must have been, people were communicating, obviously, from Scotland and
England and Ireland and further places, would they have been saying it to their face?
Do we know?
Or?
So you think that when the English went back down South, they go, "Wow, what a bunch of
minutes."
"Wow, thank God he's gone."
Well, we don't know.
Basically, this is, as with all of these citations, this is the evidence that we have.
So the only evidence that we have that it was spoken by anyone or written by anyone was
in Scotland.
And then when the evidence for it being spoken in England and the rest of the world comes
in, that's all later on.
Okay.
But it seems like they were deliberately keeping it secret for everyone, I guess.
As soon as an English person comes along, they will have an agreement to shut up.
Do you know another very old Scottish word, first used in Scotland, is "boot."
Really?
"Boo."
Same meaning?
Yeah, it's a word that's used in the north of Scotland to frighten crying children.
Oh, no.
So they were already frightened and crying?
But does that frighten them out of their tears?
It does sometimes with children, doesn't it?
I've tried it.
Does it?
Yeah, just on rounds.
You do not sometimes make it worse.
I think it's 50/50.
It's definitely worth a try though.
It's quite fun.
But then you might try it like eight times, and by then it's like, you know, you do it once
and it gets worse, and then you do it again, thinking, "Oh, I'll bring it back to the
last time."
It just gets worse again.
It's a slippery slope.
It feels like ink.
But so another early reference this might give more of a guide to what context it was
using was used by Sir Walter Scott in 1830, and he used to write papers on the esoteric,
on the paranormal.
I had no idea about that.
So he wrote a paper on, it was called "Letters on Demonology and Witchcraft," and that
was from 1830, and the sentence he had in it was, "We start and are afraid when we hear
one cry, boo," but he's spelled it B-O-H.
So sorry, is he claiming that ghost shout boo?
Is that where we've got the original idea that ridiculous ghost shout boo?
Yeah, I guess so.
I guess so.
Ghost go boo.
In comics, they say boo.
They say boo.
Do they?
Yeah.
It depends on the kind of days.
It's a lot like Scottish dialects.
I think different ghosts from different places have the different ways of speaking, don't
they?
Yeah.
Different pronunciations.
So the Scottish also have, Scott has 421 words for snow, which is, so I think a lot of people
used to say that Scandinavian had thousands of words for snow.
They were like this, yeah.
So they've got these amazing words for snow, and this is taken from all the Scottish dialects.
So there are a lot of Scottish dialects from all around the country, and that's different
to Gallic.
And there was a study done a couple of years ago by a Scottish, the Soros compiler that
found they have words, "a specific to snow," like, "sneazle," which is to begin to rain
or snow.
"Skelf" is a large snowflake.
"Fuctor" is to fall lightly and come down in odd flakes, "Fuctor," it's really "Fuctoring"
out there.
That sounds very Germanic.
Germanic.
Fuctor.
No.
It does a bit, but it also sounds a bit Scottish, and it obviously is a Germanic language.
The thing with the Eskimos, I think, is that you could technically say that they do have
100 words for snow, but the way it is is they have one or two or maybe four or five roots,
which kind of means snow, and then the rest of them, you can just put like a prefix or a suffix
after it to make another word, which means this type of snow, or this type of snow.
So it's snowing a bit, or it's snowing a lot, or 98 other variations.
We would, it counts heavy snow and light snow, and you know, "Fuctor" snow, all this
word for thing.
Just in this study that they did, the Soros, they also looked at words that Scottish people
have for sport.
They figured there'd be a lot of sporting words as well.
And they assumed that football would have the most words they used to refer to it, because
football's popular sport.
And actually, it turns out that the sport of marbles has many more words in its way.
That is more of a football.
Yeah, so marbles has things like, it had 369 different items of vocabulary linked to it
in Scotland.
Have you got me?
Yeah.
There's "Runtit", which is having lost all of one's marbles to one's opponent.
There's a "neave", which is a method of cheating and delivering the shot by advancing
the hand too far.
I remember having that done to me when I was a kid.
Wow.
So marbles actually are more popular in Scotland than football in some ways.
And are these words from Scottish dialects or are they "gaylequads"?
They're words from Scottish dialects, and I think you mean "galic".
I think I mean "gayle".
Oh my god.
Guys, we've just spent the last 15 minutes before this podcast arguing about this.
Yeah.
That was an act of war that Andy just pulled out there.
All I'm saying is what my glass we didn't father has said, and now I think of it, I'm
not certain whether he said "galic" or "gaylec", but I'm pretty sure it was "gaylec".
I know.
Please write in.
In your hundreds.
Sorry.
Is Marbles competitive on, like, is it, is it, is it competitive?
No, but as in like, you know how we have darts on TV here?
Is there marbles on TV in Scotland?
Yeah, the Marbles channel.
You're kidding.
Are you working?
I am.
I'm kidding, yeah.
No, I think it's just like an old-fashioned game, isn't it like, for instance, Skittles or
something like that?
Yeah.
It's not one.
It's a bit more old-fashioned than parks.
All of them parks, parks go back to the Romans.
The Romans had 500 different words to describe parks, didn't they?
So there is another word, which Millens Open Dictionary took in August.
So some dictionaries have an open section where anyone can submit a word, and it's like
a holding pen for words, and then they take the words that they can find actual evidence
for.
Very few.
And what a few of them, I imagine.
Yeah, very few.
Well, actually, they say about three-quarters fall into the disallowed sections, and they
said that those are words that your friends have invented, obscenities, the names of people
you dislike, and what you would like to do to them.
But with me, all three of those are just one word.
Can you share that, or is we'd have to edit that out?
We'd have to edit that out.
We'd have to edit the out of the room.
But the word that they took in August was "Ballbag."
Oh, yeah.
After Hurricane Ballbag.
After Hurricane Ballbag, which was a storm in 2011, and all the papers, it was so annoying
that all the papers call it Hurricane Ballbag for Ballbag, yeah, but with a W, Ballbag.
And when Nigel Farage visited Scotland in 2013, he was greeted with cries of "Night you're
you're a Ballbag."
Was that a reference to the hurricane of political activity that he engendered to you?
I can only assume that it is.
I can't think of any other reason why people would compare him to a Ballbag, yeah.
Is there a picture of him next to that word in the dictionary?
I don't know.
They don't really go for pictures in the dictionary, but maybe in the children's edition
they'll have a picture of him.
It's weird that that's a saying, actually, isn't it, if you look up stupid, there'd be a picture
of you.
Because, as you say, the dictionary is a book that does not go in for pictures at all.
They should say, if you looked up stupid in the dictionary, there'd be a lengthy verbal
description of you.
However, if you were to look it up in the children's dictionary or the picture dictionary, there
would be a picture of you.
Can I just...
Or in "pictionary."
Sorry, it's still going.
What is "pictionary"?
That's a game, right?
It's a game.
Yeah.
It's an ancient Roman game then.
It's earlier than Pogs.
Just on Scots dialects.
So there was a sentence in 2011 which asked Scottish people if they spoke Scots.
And there was a website that was set up to help people out with this in case they didn't
know if they did, because it's dialects.
A lot of Scottish people might speak a dialect, but think they're actually speaking just
kind of bad English.
And so there's now a website called "I Can" - A-Y-E-C-A-N, which is really fun.
And it plays the dialects of all the different regions of Scotland, and if you can understand
them, it shows that you speak that dialect.
Does it also play bad English just in case that's what you speak?
Yeah, that's actually become a Scottish dialect now in its own right.
What they should do is put bad English at the top, and so you click on that, and it's bad
English and you're like, "Okay, I definitely don't have any of the rest," rather than going
through all of the dialects.
All of the dialects get into the end and go, "No, it was bad English after all."
I don't know if you go through all, because if you're from Glasgow for instance, it's
very unlikely that you'll speak the 'Shetland' dialects unless you're in England.
They spoke something very similar to Old Norse for a long time, didn't they?
Yeah, Noun.
Until only like two or three hundred years ago.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's clung on.
Because it came because Norway owned Shetland, didn't it?
What's clung on, sorry, is that the name of it?
It clung on.
Oh, it clung on.
Sorry, that's just my bad diction.
You've got bad English.
I've got bad English.
So I found another Scottish word, which is "glamour" is Scottish, which I didn't know.
And...
Because I've heard of that in English as well.
Yeah.
Well, we use it now.
It's past onto us.
That's right.
Yeah.
But I used to just assume 'glamour' meant, you know, someone who looks very glamorous is
someone who's dressed very well in high fashion.
But the definition of 'glamour', at least the original definition is 'magic' enchantment
spell.
So whenever a magician says 'my glamorous assistant', he's actually saying 'my magical assistant'.
Is that really true?
Yeah.
As in, that's why he says, "I don't know.
I'm assuming that must be the origin of why not why not.
That can't be the main origin of why all the traditions say 'my glamorous assistant'.
No.
'Plamour' meant something astonishing, like magical, and then it meant something beautiful,
and then it was used by magicians, and then done made this connection.
Yeah.
So that's what it works.
Okay, well, what a beautiful connection.
That's what it's called.
They might be saying 'my magical assistant'.
So the Collins English dictionary, they have a Scottish wing, and they recently added,
so they have words of the year, which we've discussed on the TV show as well.
So they added things like...
What TV shows that?
There's no such thing as the news.
It's the BBC 2 TV show.
When's that?
It's on Wednesday night.
It's on BBC 2, after news night.
Okay.
They added words like 'neverendum'.
I've heard of this.
Which is just, you know, this debate about the referendum.
I think that Bob Bagg was talking about the whole time.
Yeah, exactly.
That just keeps going on, and they've also added 'Nicolabilia'.
Any guesses?
Is it a lot of things that you collect that are made out of nickel?
No.
Not bad.
I call the rage this year.
James is desk, he's biding up.
Is it like loose change?
Because that's like nickels.
No, think of the 'Nicola' bit of Nickelestogen.
Nickelestogen.
It's merchandise.
She collects nickels.
No.
It's merchandise-feeding the face of Nickelestogen.
Oh, really?
And I'm unsure about how much this is used.
I haven't found out my relatives.
Right.
And ask them.
I've just got a couple more things on exclamations.
So one that I use all the time is Holy Moly.
And I assume that I got that from the early Batman series.
Holy Moly Batman.
So there's actually a Wikipedia article
where they've listed every single Holy something that Robin has said.
And there's hundreds of them.
And I've just picked out a few.
Holy bank balance.
That's one.
Holy contributing to the delinquency of miners.
Batman.
And holy priceless collection of Etruscan snoods.
In context, they might make sense.
I think it was plot point explaining.
I think it was, I think, he was just trying to remind you
that we're looking at Etruscan snoods here.
Holy crobat, Batman.
But weirdly, the one missing from the list, Holy Moly.
Not on the list.
Because it's a catchphrase that's owned by Captain Marvel.
You were saying holy.
That's what kind of a lot of ults are, aren't they?
They're kind of things against the church.
Gosh means it's another way of saying God.
Gagzooks.
But when I was looking up gosh, I found out that people used to say
Losh, which was like shot for Lord.
Yeah.
In the 18th century.
Losh.
Oh, that's pretty good.
That is no.
I'm not really like that.
Just on Fuddleduddle, another explanation.
That's got a more recent history.
Do you know where that came from?
Fuddleduddle.
No.
Yeah.
Fuddleduddle, that thing we say all the time to exclaim.
That comes from Pierre Trudeau.
So you know Justin Trudeau's dad, who was Prime Minister of Canada in the 70s.
Yeah.
He was in a parliamentary debate when he was Prime Minister.
And the opposition says something he didn't like.
And he moused what the opposition then went out to journalists and complained,
looked a lot like a word beginning with F, then a word beginning with O.
So they said, what were you thinking when you mouled those two words?
And he said, well, what's the nature of your thoughts, gentlemen?
When you say Fuddleduddle.
So he sort of claimed it was Fuddleduddle.
And then that's caught on, in a way.
They always fuck off.
And then actually recently last year, Justin made a speech where he did admit
that his dad hadn't, in fact, said Fuddleduddle.
Right.
Yeah, scandal.
There was an Israeli guy.
He was 90 years old.
And he said, he was in the news about five, ten years ago saying that he invented
"Have a nice day."
And he was like, I don't know what I was thinking.
It just came into my head.
And I just said, have a nice day.
And then before I knew, everyone was saying it.
Okay.
It is time for fact number two.
And that is Anna.
My fact this week is that at least 61 species live in elephant footprints.
That's so cool.
It's so cool.
Wow.
So exclusively live in...
No.
So this is a paper that was published a couple of months ago.
I read about it in Scientific American.
And they've just studied the mini ecosystems that are elephant footprints.
And they found 61 species in them.
And that's where only studying a few.
So all these creatures are living in elephant footprints.
But they make it their permanent habitat because they look to older footprints.
And they found that they'd have much, many more animals in them.
And that's because dead leaves have fallen into them and things like that.
So it's become a bit like richer environment for them.
But yeah, you get tadpoles in them.
So moving around, you get mites, mayflies, leeches...
So none of the big hitters.
You don't get any...
They don't get dolphins in there.
Oh yeah, no. Cheaterly, they can hold 200 litres of water.
Isn't that amazing?
But...
Yeah, maybe a liter is less than we think it is.
Yeah, how much...
Oh, well, it's an African liter, which is five million.
No, I don't know.
I think it's...
Yeah.
If you had to express that in something that I don't understand...
It would be nearly 400 points.
Wow.
In one footprint.
Yeah, I think that's...
I was so skeptical.
But I guess in mud, then they'll sink very deep, weren't they?
Yes.
Does that count as a footprint, then?
If, like, your leg is in...
You think it's a leg print.
That's a leg print.
It's a full elephant print, if he just gets completely stuck in.
And the other thing I do is they hop from footprint to footprint.
Well, elephant...
No!
I read they can't even jump.
They call them stepping stone habitats.
And apparently...
Because during the dry season, it's really important, for animals.
Yeah, yeah.
And if the elephants weren't walking through this area,
they would disappear during the dry season.
And other species would not be able to live in these areas.
Wow.
But I mean, this raises more cause for concern at elephant poaching, obviously,
because it looks like these elephant footprints are preserving a lot of these creatures.
Massive housing crisis.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
I mean, I was already quite concerned about elephant poaching.
But now I hear that tadpoles are involved.
I'm breaking it.
Well, the thing is, like, with all this kind of thing,
the elephants, you can be concerned about the elephants.
But actually, it's the fact that they're top, you know, species in an ecosystem.
And actually, it is.
There's hundreds and hundreds of different species that rely on them.
So, like, if you want to save an elephant,
it's mostly the other animals you should be worried about, really.
Yeah, yeah.
They don't look as cool as an elephant, do they?
It's true.
But also, is it not that they loads of plants that they disperse the seeds?
Yeah.
They really do.
Who do you sorry?
Elephants.
So people got, they're called ecological engineers,
because they properly create habitats for other animals to live in,
don't they?
By knocking down all the trees and seed dispersal.
They're good for lions.
Right.
Because they knock down trees as they move along and they convert forest to scrubland,
which means you get smaller animals living in the scrubland,
which means that lions prey on the smaller animals.
So not so good for the smaller animals, then?
No, but good for the lions.
Yeah.
And apparently, they have 96 species of seed a day on average in their poo,
which they disperse across the areas they're moving through.
They're like large insects, really, aren't they, spreading?
They're like big bees.
No.
Spreading seeds.
They are.
They're almost like pollinators.
They're so unlike insects.
They spread the seed of plants.
I mean, that one incredibly specific respect, they're quite like us.
And they've got six legs, is that right?
So just to get my head around it, these animals, they're most found there.
Where else would they live if not in the footprints?
In puns and stuff.
So there are fewer puns around, especially in the dry season.
Yeah.
So they'll find this kind of footprint, which has turned into a pond,
and they'll live there.
If it wasn't there, they'd have to try and find another pond.
But the more puns there are, the more places they can live,
and the better their species will do.
Yeah.
Okay.
I got it now.
Do you know one amazing use for elephant poo?
If you're dying of thirst.
Oh, no.
Yes.
You can squeeze it together and wring a few drops of water out of it.
Yeah.
Baragrills does that, doesn't he?
I think he did it with camel poo, as opposed to elephant poo.
Maybe it was elephant poo, but you can see footage of that.
There's not much bacteria in there.
Botswana gets 650,000 kilos of elephant droppings.
That's Botswana alone every day.
Wow.
So much.
Yeah.
They pop it up.
It is a lot.
No one's denying it.
All right, but I'm waiting for one of you to try to deny it.
It's not that much.
It is that much.
So I was looking into other odd places that you find species living in.
Okay.
That aren't necessarily natural to their habitat.
There's researchers have been looking in this specific African cave because they found out about this group of crocodiles who live in this cave.
And it's really rare because they're out of sunlight for most of the time.
They feed off bats that live in the cave and so on.
Yeah, they have just a totally different eating habit.
The thing is they do go out though.
So they're not going to go blind.
They're not going to adapt to nighttime.
Because they're going to need the heat because they don't make their own heat.
Yeah, exactly.
But they do spend a lot of time there.
And one thing they notice, they did think for a while, at least to begin with, like, wow, I wonder if this is a completely different species or subspecies of crocodile because it was orange.
And they were like, what's going on here?
And it turns out that because of the water that they're in in the caves, there's so much bat poo that goes into the water that it's colored the crocodiles into a different color.
So they come out and they're like, whoa, what's this weird color?
And it's just batshit.
Do you think that's where the phrase batshit crazy comes from?
Because they look so crazy. They've turned orange and the other crocodiles are going, you look batshit crazy.
It could be, yeah.
I don't think so.
There's actually this other amazing cave that has its own ecosystem, which I found out about.
So this is called the Sondoun Cave in Vietnam, apologies if I've mispronounced that.
This is the world's largest cave and it was discovered in 2009 by a British guy.
So that's what when it's reported it was discovered, even though I think the people in Vietnam knew about it.
But it's this huge cave, so it has a jungle in it if you go into it.
So it's got a jungle with, you should honestly look up, look up pictures of this place.
It's extraordinary.
The trees are fun.
And inside the jungle there's a desert.
Inside that there's an ocean.
Why won't you believe me?
The bottom is another massive cave.
The Russian doll of caves.
There's a jungle with trees that are 30 metres tall.
It has its own river.
It's got a centre parts.
And all these new species have been found in it anyway.
So yeah, honestly look up pictures of it.
So they found a new type of gecko, a tree frog, a new type of striped hair.
Living inside this cave completely underground.
The main cabin of it is so big it has its own climate, so it has rain clouds.
Which I imagine means it actually rains inside this huge cave.
Where is this again?
It's in Vietnam.
Can I just say one last thing?
Yes, sure.
As I read this the other day, I haven't got the full details here.
But there's a species of crab and they're polygamous.
So the males have sex with loads of different females and vice versa.
If these crabs find a turtle shell with just the right gap between the shell and the bottom of the turtle
that will fit two crabs in, then a male and a female crab will go and live inside the turtle shell
and they'll have a monogamous relationship.
And they won't have sex with anyone else, they'll just live there.
But anywhere else they live, they'll have loads of partners.
But if they find that little niche, then they'll kind of stay together.
It's like a suburb.
It's right if you move into the perfect house, then your relationship can be repaired.
Absolutely, yeah.
It's a lesson here.
Okay, it is time to move on to fact number three.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the original edition of Wisden's Cricketer's Almanac
was 112 pages long and because the author wasn't sure what to put in it,
was padded out with accounts of the trial of King Charles I.
So if you don't know what this book is, this is published annually
and it is the ultimate Cricketer's book.
And the current edition, the 2016 edition, is over 1,500 pages long.
So it's a huge book, it has nothing but cricket.
But the very first edition, Wisden was like, I don't have enough cricket to put in this.
But I need to make it worth buying.
So he added the accounts of the trial from King Charles of Earth.
He also put in battles of the English Civil War and also Britain's canals,
the size of them and length.
And also the rules of quiting.
Yeah, what is that?
Quiting is where you, I think you have a quite is like kind of a circular thing,
a bit like a horseshoe and you throw it to a stick and it goes around the stick.
And if you get it around the stick, you get points.
It's based on pub garden games, quits.
We should actually not only explain what quiting is but probably for our American explain what cricket is.
I think so.
It's like baseball on the a lot slower.
That'll do it.
And there are tea breaks.
Yeah.
And I still find that insane.
So I didn't know that because I didn't really follow cricket.
But halfway through a day of playing cricket, they all stop to have cups of tea.
No, you have tea as in food.
You would have like sandwiches and stuff.
Yeah, to see to English people who know about cricket,
that seems like the most normal thing in the world.
Yeah.
I mean, you go for fun.
I mean, I should know that in theory.
Yeah.
Well, actually, do Australia play cricket anymore?
You can.
Out.
Interesting fact about the Cricketers Almanac.
Yeah.
Really interesting fact.
Get ready.
Hold on to your seats.
So it's been published every year since 1864.
And for the first six years, it was published.
It was Wiston's Cricketers Almanac.
But for the subsequent however many years,
it's been Wiston's Cricketers Almanac.
With the apostrophe on the other side of the S.
Which S, Wiston's or Cricketers.
Cricketers.
Yeah, but there's only ever been one Wiston.
So it's always been from one Wiston, but originally it was for only one Cricketer.
It was for one Cricketer for the first six years.
It was just aimed at one Cricketer.
No one knows if that Cricketer is.
But John Wiston, the founder, was quite an interesting guy.
He was a Cricketer.
And his nickname was The Little Wonder.
Because he was five foot nothing.
And he weighed seven stone when he started his career.
And he was tiny.
And yet in one match in 1850 he bowled out all ten of the opposite team in a single innings.
Which I think it's written online that this is the only time that's ever happened in a first class match.
So they were all bowled out as in he hit the stunts rather than then being caught out or, you know, got out in another way.
There are about ten ways you can be caught up.
That's great.
Yeah.
Well done here.
On page 657 of the year 2000 edition.
The Leicester Spinball and Matthew Brimson exposed himself.
And nobody noticed at the time.
And it went into the edition.
And then about six days after it had been published, someone wrote in and said, this guy's middle stump is in this picture.
Matthew Engel, who was editor at the time, wrote about this.
And he said, in the 2000 Leicestershire photo, one of their most obscure players was laughing.
Oh, having chosen to expose himself to the camera, his only contribution to Cricketer history.
Oh, the Leicestershire squad was large.
The page was small, so was our editorial team, and so was the appendage.
Okay, this guy got slammed by the said.
Yeah, absolutely.
It is kind of embarrassing that nobody noticed for a week.
Yeah.
And then he was asked to apologise and he didn't.
And apparently he said, well, he said it was the editor's fault because they should have spotted it.
And Engel said, oh, do you think we need to employ a full-time penis spotter then?
So, did you know the first Cricket Balls were rolled along the ground?
That was the first way you bowled and Cricket.
Really?
And this is very early, yeah.
So it was more like croquet.
Kind of, yeah.
Right.
Except you were allowed to roll the ball along the ground.
And the idea being that it was still trying to hit stumps behind.
Yeah, yeah.
So, is it French Cricket where you throw very, very low?
You aim for someone's legs.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Cricket on their own, basically.
So instead of having wickets that you aim for, you aim for their legs.
Yeah.
So, and this is very exciting.
So one of the first bowlers to pitch was a guy called Edward Lumpy Stevens.
Lumpy was his nickname.
And there's a book.
He got that nickname after he exposed himself.
There's a book called the author's 11.
And it says, the name Lumpy may have come either from his ability to pitch the ball on any protrusion on the pitch.
Or his fondness for eating a whole apple pie at a time.
Yeah.
You know, in all the kind of, if you read, you know, amazing things about Wisden's Cricket as Almanac.
One of the claims they make is that both PG Woodhouse got the name Jeaves from Wisden Cricket as Almanac.
And Sherlock Holmes was named after a Cricket as well.
Conan Doyle used to read Wisden's Cricket as Almanac.
I can't see any evidence that that's true though.
So I think that's one of those myths that's been going around.
That's where they got them.
Because you do have quotes from PG Woodhouse saying that he knew Jeaves the Cricketer and he was a big fan of his.
And that's where the name came from.
So presumably he didn't need to discover that in a book.
He already knew that.
That reminds me that Blowfelt, the bad guy in James Bond is named after Henry Blowfelt's father.
Oh, yes.
The family.
Who is a Cricket commentator?
Yeah, Henry Blowfelt's a Cricket commentator.
We met him last year. He came on our radio show Museum of Curiosity.
And he told this story about how In Fleming was in a gentleman's club in London and was looking through the members list and saw Blowfelt's father in there and decided to name him after that.
Wow.
Was there beef between them?
No, I don't think so.
Because he named Goldfinger after the architect Goldfinger who he didn't like at all.
And he tried to sue him, didn't he?
Like he was very Goldfinger tried to sue him.
Yeah, Goldfinger was very angry about that.
Yeah.
And the most famous copy of Wisden is a 1939 edition belonging to EW Swanton.
He was a Cricket writer and then he was taken prisoner by the Japanese in the war.
And it was so popular with all the other prisoners of war that everyone used to borrow it.
And he had to turn it into like a library book so people could take it at different times.
And then it became really, really thumbed through.
It was stamped not subversive by the Japanese.
And then it was printed in the book, and it was printed in the book, and it was printed in the book.
And it was printed in the book, and it was printed in the book.
And it was printed in the book, and it was printed in the book, and it was printed in the book, and it was printed in the book.
And it was printed in the book.
And it was printed in the book, and it was printed in the book.
And the auction said, the passer of this remarkable object
is unknown and all this, you know, stuff.
But it came from a place called the Wilkes Formation,
which is where there was a swamp.
And there is a theory that actually it's plant material
and lumps of mineral, because sometimes things get--
lumps of ash get turned into clay.
And they get squeezed through not holes in trees.
I mean, how is-- it's not that much different than a poo, is it?
Exactly.
It's basically--
Yeah, it's basically being pushed through like a tube
or toothpaste.
So there is a theory that that's that.
But you'd have to cut it in two to take a slice,
because there'll be organic material in there
if it isn't covered in.
I found a really good website called The Poozyum.
Did you guys see that?
No.
Did no one see it?
I've seen The Poozyum.
Isn't it great?
I didn't look at the website I saw it referred to.
And I think that was a funny name.
Exactly.
So it puts you off to look at it, because you think this is a silly name.
It's not going to be good.
This is a guy who much like the person you've just said
with the largest collection has dedicated his life
to understanding and cataloging and reporting on copper lights.
And it's fantastic.
It's an incredible website.
It's got pictures.
It's got all the latest news stories.
I just honestly highly recommend Poozyum.
Give us an example of a brilliant Poozyum news story.
What?
He was telling you how you can make your own.
I know how to take things.
I've been dedicating my life to making my own.
How you can make your own poo fossil in time.
So he says you, and this was done in an interview
that he reposted on his own site by Jason Rosenfeld
on Silicon Exit, which is a website.
Did this great interview with him?
So he said that the way that you can make your own copper light
is that you start off by eating a bunch of corn and peanuts
every few days.
And that will give the copper light interesting inclusions
and make it worth more money when someone finds it
a special treasure.
Because that's easier to tell if something is genuinely poo
because it has little bits sticking out of it of insects
or whatever.
That helps them identify it.
And then you dig it into a very deep hole
and then put the soil over immediately.
So nothing gets to it.
That in theory is how you make your own fossil poo
if someone wants to start going on that.
It's an incredibly weird thing to do.
Or you put in a lake.
How come?
It sinks through the water, right?
And it gets to the bottom.
And there's much less oxygen down there for it
for bacteria to eat it.
So the hope is that over time,
anaerobic bacteria gradually replace the matter with minerals.
But for best results, you have to poo in the lake.
You have to get in the lake.
Do the poo.
Get out of the lake.
OK.
I mean, there are other ways to make your mark on this Earth.
It's very unreliable because, you know,
the world would be covered in poo if they all survived.
So in fact, it's a really valuable substance, right?
Because it used to be important as fertilizer, copper light.
And so when they discovered this,
then it became something that people mined.
And there are various places in the UK
where copper light mining was an important industry.
So one of the main centers of this
was a place called Shillington in Bedfordshire.
And this was in the mid-19th century.
It's population doubled because loads of people flocked.
It was a bit like the gold rush.
It was the UK equivalent of the gold rush.
People flocked.
As ever, America's always better, isn't it?
We've had a third rush, America.
If you go to Bedfordshire,
all the streets are paved with chairs.
So the brilliant thing about this place
is that there's big boost to the local economy.
And it was actually a bit of a problem
because these pubs multiplied
because copper light miners were paid--
They desperately to drink away the memories
of what they spend their day doing.
[LAUGHTER]
Well, they had quite a lot of fights.
So there was tension and everything.
I mean, exactly at the gold rush.
Can I just say, in the gold rush,
people used to go to the pubs and pay for their drinks
with little bits of gold that they found.
Yeah.
People used to just go with a--
They're like, this isn't an ancient one.
Yeah.
Forgeries from half an hour ago.
[LAUGHTER]
The great thing about this place is it's called Shillington.
Its name has actually changed in the 1880s,
because it was worried it was going to offend Queen Victoria,
because it was called Shillington.
Yeah, really?
Yeah.
Shillington was the heart of ship mining.
Wow.
That's amazing.
Hello to anyone living in Shillington.
Yeah.
He's learning that for the first time.
Is that coincidence?
It's coincidence.
Like glamorous assistant.
Like it's a total coincidence?
It's coincidence.
Wow.
They only discovered the third seam in the mid-19th century.
And it had been around for hundreds of years before that.
They called it the "treacle mines."
To that.
Likely.
Yeah, they used to, yeah.
That's the worst euphemism I've ever had ever had ever had ever had.
Horrible.
It's weird that there's a seam, isn't it?
You would think that they'd be scattered fairly evenly.
But actually, it all comes from a time when the south of England was covered
in hundreds of meters of water flooded, and all the land animals died.
So there's a lot remaining from that period.
Yeah.
So Andy, the whole idea of copper light selling more
if it looks actually like a poo.
I was reading, again, in this interview from Pusium,
that the reason that that's so precious is actually most fossilized poo.
The reason it doesn't retain the shape of a poo is that most animals will do it from a height, obviously.
And then it experiences what he calls the splatter effect.
So it's very hard to get a poo-shaped fossil because most of it has splattered once it hits the ground.
Get in the lake.
Get in the lake as the answer, yeah.
What?
Slow it down on the descent.
Absolutely, yeah.
Very good.
You say they're so precious.
This guy, George Transon, his most valuable copper light is called precious.
Just to make him a tiny bit more creepy, I did a business inquiry.
No.
I wonder because the splatter effect thing I just said was he's talking literally about precious in this sentence.
Is this the same guy?
Does he run Pusium?
I don't know.
I think that your guy runs the Pusium.
I've just checked it.
That's a great sight.
The guy knows what he's talking about.
Sure does.
Something related to copper lights are regurgitolites, which is, well, what do you think?
Fossilized vomit?
Correct.
Yeah.
Really good because often this will be something.
If you've got fossilized poo and you can see what someone's eaten, but it's obviously been through the digestive system.
If it's fossilized vomit, then obviously not been quite as far through the digestive system.
So you can see a lot better what these things have eaten.
So there was a bit of vomit cuffed up by an X-Fiasaur, 160 million years ago.
And it's still got little bits of the, like, ammonites and stuff that were in there.
That's amazing.
It's really cool.
It's so shame for the X-Fiasaur who vomited and thought, "God, I hope no one remembers this moment."
160 million years later.
There's still reminiscing.
There's an even more embarrassing thing.
We think we have a 300 year old piece of Bishop's excrement.
Wow.
This is in the news this week.
So there's a Danish Bishop.
It's in the news.
I didn't see him possessing.
I don't think it's credible.
There's a Danish Bishop called Jens Bircherod.
And he lived in a city called Alborg until 1708.
And 80 years ago, archaeologists found in his private mid and a lump of stuff.
And now it's been analysed.
And they think it's Bishop's poo.
It could be the Bishop's wife.
But it's God.
I'm very dumb.
18th century Denmark was a very liberal place.
No, one professor said this is a way of making history through the back door.
The way the tree called mine.
And they're going to put it probably in the local museum.
But it's so embarrassing.
No, I think it's good to be proud of it.
So there's a village called Bassingborn, hello to those in Bassingborn as well,
which was another home of coprolite mining.
And they wanted to erect a statue as a monument to their village's great history in 2005.
And there were some contenders.
So they could have had a heron.
There were lots of beautiful herons there.
They thought about having a Second World War bomber because they had a strong Second World War history.
And then one of the suggestions was a large poo.
And the village voted and they voted for the poo.
So they've got, don't let the public vote on things.
Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter account.
So I'm on our Striberland, James.
That's X-shaped, Andy.
That's Andrew Hunter, and Anna.
You can email podcast@QI.com.
Yep, or you can go to our group Twitter account, which is @QIPodcast, or our website, nosuchthingasaffish.com,
where we have all of our previous episodes.
You can also go to nosuchthingasthenews.com, which has all of our TV show episodes.
Topical look at the world.
Week by week.
We will be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[Music]
(upbeat music)