Hey everyone, just like to let you know that we are joined today by the wonderful Amy
Glad Hill.
Now even if you're a fairly new listener to know such things afish, you will know Amy
because it's not that long ago since she came on.
But we don't have many more weeks before Anna comes back and we thought who do we want
back?
Who do we want back on the show?
Who do we enjoy the show so much with that we just can't wait to get them back on and
with all the people who fit that bill, Amy was the one who we wanted most.
So we messaged her, she's very busy at the moment but she said yes.
Why is she so busy?
Well, she has just been on last one laughing UK, the second series of that.
It is so funny, it's one of the best TV moments of the year so far and Amy is in that.
She is also in the new series of Taskmaster, I know loads of you who listen to this show
Love Taskmaster so you will see Amy on that show but she also has her own podcast.
She does a podcast called Northern News with former fish alumnus Ian Smith and she also
does another podcast called Single Ladies in Your Area.
Both of these podcasts are absolutely amazing.
I have been on the Northern News one, it's such fun, those two are so funny, oh my goodness
they are so funny.
Definitely go and check those out wherever you get your podcasts.
And they're also on Patreon, just like another podcast you might have heard of, called No
Six Things, a fish.
Yes, we are on Patreon, now it's just trying to find a new different way of announcing
that.
If you go to patreon.com/clubfish, then you can sign up there.
When you sign up you'll get loads of free stuff, there's plenty of stuff there for anyone
who doesn't want to pay but if you would like to give us a few pounds each month then there
are various different tiers where you can get various different things.
The first one is plenty more fish where you get droppers aligned which is our audience
feedback show and so much fun and also you get ad free episodes which I know for a lot
of you is a big old poll so please do that but mostly if you do that you are supporting
the podcast.
But actually you're supporting the podcast by being here and listening to this show with
the incredible, amazing, infectiously funny Amy Clevd Hill, up with the podcast.
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming
to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Huntson Murray and
Amy Clevd Hill and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four favourite
facts from the last seven days and in a particular order here we go.
Starting with fact number one and that is Amy.
Okay so my fact this week is according to science one of the best ways to avoid laughing
is to think about wallpaper.
This fact comes to me slightly too late, I wish I'd have discovered this fact, what a year
ago really.
Okay so for context you recently started on last one laughing, the TV show where you have
to try and survive the entire process of the show by not laughing and you were on with
people like David Mitchell and Sam Campbell, so questions to you, if this is a scientific
method, would you have your own method?
I did actually, less scientific, there was lots of snacks in the room and I thought if my
mouth was always full of flumps, marshmallows, you can't laugh, but that isn't science it turns
out, but I think it did help, if you've got a mouth full of something you're less inclined
to.
I don't think I showed you having flumps, flumps are a funny food as well, they're quite
a risky food, that's quite a kind editor I think, who doesn't know, they weren't imaginary
flumps, they were real flumps, no you give y'all kids an Easter, imaginary Easter eggs are
in garden, oh look at that, I said one, no I thought because part of the wallpaper idea
is a distraction tool, so whatever you imagine, you're imagining wallpaper, exactly, no you're
really looking at wallpaper but it's a distraction tool, therefore if you were imagining flumps
in your mouth and fitting, ooh I could fit more, more in, you might distract yourself,
feels very fun, yeah, well, it feels like, not to criticize your technique Amy but I don't
know how helpful it would be, are you stopping laughs getting in, no you're stopping them
getting out, oh yeah, so laughter comes from within, oh that's true, so maybe once you swallowed
the flump then the laughter is going to come out, well just, it doesn't cork it is what
you're saying, yeah I guess I just can't quite, yeah, so I read this study and it is distractions
one of the things, right, another one is kind of controlling, trying to control your facial
muscles, which we did see on the show, yeah, male, poor old male, she liked to do that, did
she, she was gurning, like it was the 90s, yeah, so she had this like, like lower jaw protrusion
I get, like an under bite, she'd give herself an under bite but it was so effective, so she
was really like pulling their muscles in her jaw but then it turns out and she, she has
said this in the brush, she's had to go and see a specialist for a jaw injury, that's funny,
is gurning, is that a drug thing?
Yes, so I'm told, that's another question, and then one other thing that they said is good
for it is to re-appraise the jokes in a non-funny manner, which I think is a kind of David
Mitchley thing, isn't it?
Yeah, but I think that's quite difficult because I think to re-appraise a joke, you have to
understand why it's funny, so then you think, "Oh, that's funny for these reasons, how
do we make it less funny?"
And I think that's a risky strategy.
And there are, like, surprise jokes of the most dangerous of all, if you're trying not
to laugh.
Yes.
As in, there is a moment in, for international listeners, last but not least, you can't
go and see it, it's terrific, there's a moment where Alan Carr gets out a sausage
machine and it starts firing out a high-speed sausage, and there's almost no way to immediately
re-appraise that as a serious malfunction of a sausage machine, oh dear, I hope they haven't
greased that properly.
That's really hard.
On the other hand, you can think, "Oh no, he's going to lose all that sausage."
Yeah.
Like, that's how you re-appraise it, right?
I think very fast.
You've got to re-appraise it on the opening before it gets to the punch, right?
Okay.
Englishman Irishman and Scottishman walk into a bar, you think, "Oh, what's the likelihood
that those three work?"
You don't even listen to them, right?
You just interact yourself with it.
You think this guy doesn't make sausages?
Hell, hell, there's Alan Carr, you know what it's about to do.
Is it safe?
It's not safe, Michael.
There we go.
I'm not laughing.
Most laughter, in conversation, happens, after banal comments, not funny ones.
Is this your experience?
Really?
That's my experience, yeah.
Well, last time I came on, I did laugh a lot.
Right.
So, what is it out of...
It's not to do with whether it's funny or not.
It's just kind of social grease.
Yeah.
And also, the person talking laughs more than the people they're talking to, you're almost
every conversation.
Oh, yeah.
It's by more than about half, half as much more, yeah, yeah.
And obviously, it's different in a professional comedy scenario, I guess.
But what's difficult is when the trickiest thing in that program is the conversations, you
know, when someone's on the stage doing their joke, you're, you know, you've got flumps in
your mouth, you're ready.
Oh, yeah.
But it's the little conversations that are really difficult because it's surprising.
And Bob Mortimer is lovely, and I told him that I was nervous about doing it.
And he said, the first half an hour is the hardest, because when that buzzer goes off, you
get all this giddy energy, and you're almost ready to laugh, because you just told
you shouldn't, you're almost ready to laugh anywhere.
So when the buzzer goes off, he came over to me to have like a neutral conversation to help
me.
But because you're in this prime situation, and Bob Mortimer is that, you know, a meet
you're away from your face, and he was going, he was just trying to be nice, but it was so
hard.
And he said, yeah, me.
Are you happy with your Hoover?
And I was like, oh, my God, why is that the funniest thing I've ever heard?
You know, you might have had a competitive advantage in there, according to the University
of Buffalo, because according to the history of comedy professor there, Andrew Scots, red
heads are seen as funny, generally, and most of the people, don't look at the sheet red
as well.
Yeah.
So you two would have had competitive advantage.
This is all culturally brought on to us by circus clowns, basically, clowns always had
big red wigs, largely it's what they could be seen from any bit of the circus attend if
you're sitting at the back.
You know, it's the clowns.
Is it also true that people with red noses and big feet are also seen as funny, yeah?
Probably.
I don't know.
If that's what we're saying, that the clown is, yes, it's just culture.
Is this regionally, has this been stress tested in Scotland and Ireland, which have many more
people with red hair?
Nothing I got from them.
That's true.
This is Buffalo.
Okay.
So, yeah.
Last one laughing US, you might have the advantage, that's a really good point, that's my strategy
would have buckled immediately as I walked it with my dyed red hair.
Wow.
They've looked at laughter and then fed it into a computer to see what kind of laughter
there is.
This is how you analyse comedy, you work out what's funny.
This is at the University of Amsterdam and they found that there's two different types
of laughter.
So, a computer can tell the difference between tickle laughter and every other kind of
laughter and all the other laughter if you're watching a sitcom or you're watching stand-up
or you're with your mates or whatever, they're all the same, but tickle laughter is completely
different and the algorithm can tell the difference.
Is it more panic?
I guess it's more panty, baby, like panty is a funny word.
That's interesting, because there is fear, when you're being tickled, there is fear.
There's fear, pure fear.
Oh, yeah, we had a tickle truce in my house between me and my other son, Wilf, tickle
truce.
A literal tickle truce, he can't tickle me because the pain is so great for me and I'm
not laughing.
He's doing it wrong.
I just have to do it with.
I find it so unbelievably painful.
I actually try.
That didn't tickle me that time.
James is tickling me by the way, everyone.
I think I got a splint.
Yeah.
But then I can't tickle Wilf because he happened to ages ago, but I tickled him and he went,
"Oh, daddy!"
No, he went, "You've tickled the way out of me."
And he purses himself every time I tickle him, so there is a tickle truce.
You once told a joke so funny that one of the children chatted themselves.
Didn't you?
Wasn't it, was it in the bath?
It was in the bath, which is not a good place for it to happen.
At least it's contained.
It's contained in the big bath, but you see, it's not until you try and grab it and then
it breaks until it's like a, it's like a, a cloning machine when you try and grab it.
What was the joke?
Can you remember?
Oh, don't tell it like that.
I don't know.
I want to see you on last one laughing at just all the other kind of shit in themselves.
No!
Amy, your laugh is quite infectious.
Oh, thanks.
It's not.
It is in the positive way.
If you're laughing, you could probably want to laugh, you know, because I once caught a
bad laugh from someone.
And I had a few years.
It wasn't.
No.
It's someone new to you, no, very well.
Was it Dan's son?
No.
If shit's coming out every time it's a bad laugh, yeah.
You were sitting.
And you looked at those jacuzzi sessions.
I mean, that was a really tricky laugh.
That's sail.
Yeah, of course he was John Lloyd.
Okay.
Founder of QI.
Yeah.
So he has a very distinctive laugh, which.
Ha, ha, ha.
Yes.
And it's, he has a bigger laugh as well for really, really funny stuff.
He's got a big laugh.
But even when he's like, and that's him genuinely, he's genuinely laughing.
Really?
And for about five years ones, I could only laugh like that.
And I don't know how I got it.
Hey.
Because it is like a contagious thing and it is a social thing.
Yeah.
And it's like, a copy of people's laughs that shows respect, personally.
I respect John.
Is it exactly that?
That's probably exactly that.
So do you think people in different cultures have different laughs?
Like would you be able to tell just from a laugh if someone was like, oh, that person's
Italian or, oh, that person.
That's interesting.
Well, French.
Ha, ha, ha.
Yeah.
And we get a close to the end of the, so hopefully it's everyone wants to do, but that's
crack on.
Wow.
But you know what I mean?
Do you think you would be able to tell?
Yeah.
You would.
I think you would.
Yeah, maybe.
You definitely tell a difference between modern humans and old humans.
Because can you guess how old humans would laugh?
It was not.
Ha, ha, ha.
Because they couldn't make those sounds.
They couldn't make those sounds.
The humans managed to say, huh, sound quite late in our development.
Wow.
So before that, he, he, he, that still has an accident.
Oh, okay.
Was it like the count from Sesame Street?
Ah.
Oh, yeah.
Here's a primitive human.
Yeah.
Well, obviously we don't know, but it appears to have been more panty.
And that's because like if you look at eggs today, for instance, they have more of a panting
laugh when they.
Oh, wow.
Totally.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That was very good.
You've done that before.
We have enough.
Oh, wait, wait, wait.
Wallpaper.
Do you want to do a wallpaper?
I've got that.
No, it's fine.
It's just.
I've read so much about wallpaper.
I've got pages here of wallpaper stuff.
I've got a little bit of wallpaper stuff.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
Another wallpaper thing.
I tried to find out what's the least funny wallpaper to add to the thing, in case I ever
need to not laugh again.
And the least funny thing I could find about wallpaper was the Victorian wallpaper was
often bright green, but it had arsenic in it.
Oh.
So a lot of it actually was quite fatal.
Oh, nice.
So that's.
Yeah, that's got to be the least funny.
That's not funny.
It's not funny.
Unless you're driven to hysteria as part of the poisoning, which sometimes happens, right?
That would happen with like mercury poisoning.
Yes.
Not sure about arsenic.
It's more death.
Just pure death.
Just pure death that one.
That's not fun at all.
No, no, no, no.
I joined the.
I've joined the wallpaper history society as part of research for this fact.
Sure.
You weren't already a member.
It's a good price.
I've pegged it to my previous membership, and it's exactly the same price as the Association
of Lighthouse Keepers, which I will show a member of when you meet another member of the
wallpaper association.
Do you say, "How's it hanging?"
Yeah.
Strip poker is a much more tame affair than the wallpaper society.
No, it's good.
You get a copy of the wallpaper history review, packed with over 100 pages of wallpaper
and wall covering related information.
That's good.
You get priority booking on some wallpaper history society events, and priority booking.
How many times have we got to the front, sorry, sir?
25 quid.
For the year?
That's not bad, is it?
It's not bad.
You could spend it on worse.
Yeah.
I can't think of anything.
Oh.
Okay.
It is time for fact number two, and that is
my fact.
My fact this week is that until 1960, American cinemagoras watched movies in no particular order.
So this is...
Light momenta.
That's not particular.
Well, that's actually in a particular order.
It's just backwards, isn't it?
It's just backwards.
Any Christopher Nolan film.
Yeah.
This is...
Oh, it's not going on there with time.
Yeah.
Tenets is in both particular order.
Exactly.
The most radical thing Christopher Nolan could do now would just be to release a film
that starts at the beginning, gets through the middle, gets to the end.
We've got a grudge going, but me and him and me, we don't need to get into it.
No, I get it.
I thought Tenet was one of the only films I nearly walked out of the cinemagoras.
Really?
Yeah.
I think I got really obsessed because they just kept saying the word 'algorithm' for no reason
and being really smoke about it.
They just had 'algorithm' so much, but it started becoming funny and I was like, 'I don't know.
I've got a leave.
I can't be laughing at the word 'algorithm'.
I've got to go.
Note to anyone.
The series three of Amy returns.
I've got a bunch of pub marks on my marks and say, 'Hey, they watch your favourite algorithm.'
[laughter]
What's wrong with you?
Well, paper.
Now, this is an amazing little detail about American cinema, which is prior to 1960.
I mean, watch the beginning of the movie.
Yeah.
And they used to know if a movie was going to be hit.
If people got to the bit they'd already seen and wanted to watch it again.
Yeah.
Because they enjoyed it so much.
Like if you go to a, like an art gallery in the show movies.
They like that.
Yes.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And they would have double bells, too.
They would have double bells.
They would have another whole film.
A whole lot of film.
And it was really frustrating for a lot of filmmakers.
They desperately tried to say, get there at the start.
Because it has a plot that works really nicely when you see it in the order where it made it.
Yeah.
Exactly.
So what changed this all was in 1960 Alfred Hitchcock released Psycho.
He made it his big campaign.
You have to see Psycho at this starting time and watch it till the end.
You have to see Psycho at this end.
There should be a nationwide go to the show on time campaign.
And he would have skeletons that would fly out of certain moments is all very creative stuff.
He always wanted to be a proper filmmaker.
Mel Brooks was the producer of the elephant man.
But they took his name off the credits.
He asked to because he was like,
Everyone will be laughing when they see that.
But it was fantastic.