(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, James here.
I am here with some amazing upcoming news.
In fact, this is like a teaser to the actual news.
And that is that we have some big changes
coming to No Such Things A Fish.
We are going big time.
There will be more facts.
There will be more silliness.
There will be more of everything you love
about No Such Things A Fish,
but I'm not gonna tell you everything quite yet
because it will all be revealed
when we launch this Friday.
So this is just to warn you that you might see
a few changes on our page over the next couple of days.
But the key message really is that everything you get
right now is staying exactly the same on Patreon
and on Apple, same price, same content.
We will be adding some extra things.
And of course, what I always say
when we make these announcements is true
that the main show will always be free
to listen for everyone.
Okay, that's all I have to say.
I know it's a bit of a tease.
We're really excited about what's coming up.
We can't wait to see what other things about it
when she gets back.
But yeah, listen out on Friday
for all of the information about our new tears,
our new perks and all our new stuff coming
to the brand new No Such Things A Fish.
Did I say new enough times?