(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered
around the microphones with our four favorite facts
from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
- The beep was invented in 1957.
- Was it?
- No, well.
(laughing)
So I got this from an article which I won't name
because it turns out now to be incorrect.
But basically, it's about the beep that happened
on the Sputnik satellite, it was launched in 1957.
And really annoyingly, Anna has found about 58 examples
of beeps dating back to the mid-40th century.
And it's just like, welcome back, Anna.
- Thank you so much. - Thank you so much.
- She's awesome.
- Yeah, we didn't get this from Maisie Adler,
but I tell you that much.
Listened politely to the fact, I didn't question it.
But it certainly, the beep became popular
and a big thing about Sputnik was the fact that it beeped.
And in fact, I think, I think,
that's all Sputnik could do.
- Pretty much what it did, yeah.
- Yeah, it was the size of a big pumpkin
and it was a ball of aluminium or metal
and it just flew around.
- I would say the main thing it could do
was go around the earth in orbit.
Like the beep was secondary almost.
- Yeah.
- You're right, you're right.
The main thing was it could fly around the world.
That's true.
But no one would have known if it wasn't beeping.
- Yes.
- Because it was broadcasting radio pulses.
It was orbited the earth every hour and a half, roughly.
It beeped for 21 days only.
But the beep was seen as quite spooky
'cause you could hear it.
How radio people could tune in and listen to Sputnik.
- Amazing.
- Life magazine said it was an eerie, intermittent croak.
And for a fair number of people--
- Doesn't sound like a beep, actually, does it?
- No, if you--
- I guess if you don't know what a beep is,
'cause it's only been mentioned five million times
in history.
- I guess for a few people it would have been
the first electronic beep that heard.
- Pretty amazing, really.
And it was the beep that changed the world, right?
Because suddenly the Americans were like,
oh shit, Russia's in space.
This is evidence 'cause we can hear it beeping.
We're gonna have to do something about that.
And then they decided to create NASA and go to the moon.
- Yeah.
- There's a theory that if the Soviets hadn't launched
Sputnik, or America had launched the first satellite,
then you wouldn't have had the moon program in the same way.
- I'm sure that's true.
- You might not have had Apollo.
'Cause it really frightened America.
- Oh, definitely.
- Just literally a ball that went beep.
- But the other thing is the reason it was so shiny
is 'cause they also, the idea was the guy Karlov
who created it or who designed it,
he decided that he wanted it shiny
so that people will be able to see it in space.
But actually it was way too small
and no one could see it.
- Was it?
- Yeah.
I mean, if you had a really good telescope, you could, but.
- I think you could at dawn and dusk.
Although you'd have to know where to be pointing.
It would probably be very hard to spot.
- Not really.
He wanted it to be quite a lot bigger as well
so that people will be able to see it.
- But it really did freak people out at the time.
Even Kruschev said, "Now we not only have a rocket
"that can fly to other countries,
"but we have a satellite that flies around the world.
"I don't have to point to this with my finger.
"Any idiot can see it.
"They might as well put bombers and fighters
"in the museum."
He was just alluding to, "We're now the superpower."
- It's nukes, isn't it, is what he's referring to.
If we can put that on there.
- Of course, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Our technology is sophisticated.
- And the Americans not long after
tried to send up their satellite.
That didn't work.
It was called Kaputnik, I think they called it.
Not the Americans, the Russians, making fun of it.
- Yes, it was called the Vanguard.
- Yeah.
- The Vanguard one, yeah.
And they sort of panicked after Sputnik.
And it was, what, two months later?
- Yeah.
- And it was so embarrassing.
It exploded on the launch pad.
Then it fired into a nearby swamp.
But unfortunately, the firing into a swamp
had made the sensors on board think,
"Oh, great, we're in orbit."
So then it just started beeping from the swamp.
So embarrassing.
It's just mortifying.
- As well as Kaputnik, it was also known as
Flopnik, Pufnik, or Staputnik.
- Staputnik, I love that.
- That's great.
- It's not often you think that Soviet Russia
was a really fun place to be.
But I think for that week,
it would have been a really fun place
to be hanging out in Russia.
- Just hilarious.
- Just comedy gold.
Well, do you know why they didn't choose
the other project called Project Orbiter,
which had more advanced technology within it?
And it was run by someone, and here's your clue.
It was run by Werner von Braun, who was,
would you, in German, you'd say brown, not brawn.
- Oh, I thought it was brawn.
- You'd say brawn.
- In English, he knows what brown is.
- Well, I know him as von Braun.
- That's how I know him.
- Yeah.
- So it was managed by Werner von Braun,
who was a Nazi.
And the Americans thought it might be a bit awkward
if our first satellite that we get into space
was built by a Nazi.
So he was a Nazi who was, at the end of the war,
as were quite a few Nazi scientists.
He was taken on by America
so they could get Nick Nazi technology.
And so they started using his brain and then--
- And his brawn.
(laughing)
- Okay, that's it.
- We can all go home now.
- I like one of the cultural things that happened with this
is that in the way that everything after Watergate
became gate, Nick became popularized in Western cultures.
So there was Peace Nick, there was Beat Nick,
Neat Nick, we're all different words,
but Beat Nick is one that's really stuck out for us.
- I thought it came from Ludnick,
which is a Yiddish word meaning a bit of a--
- It did, Nick was already used as--
- Nick was already being used, yes.
But it popularized it.
- It was popularized.
(laughing)
- In Russian, Nick is just, it means a person.
Like, as in, you know, someone called Nick.
Podcast Nick would be someone who makes podcasts.
- Oh, that's cool, yeah.
- You know how we're saying it was a massive deal
and you know, Khrushchev made this huge speech saying
we've conquered the world now, et cetera?
- Yeah.
- Well, they launched Sputnik
and then no one really got that it was a big deal.
Khrushchev announced it to the cocktail party he was at
and everyone sort of politely clapped
and didn't understand it.
Prafter, the next day, it was like a little thing
way down on their front page.
- It was almost not on the front page.
- It got less prominent than Marshal Zukov
visiting Yugoslavia, which arguably, in historical terms,
turns out to have been a smaller story.
(laughing)
- How interesting, so why did they do that?
- But it was because of how the world reacted.
- It was 'cause the West reacted in the future.
It was the West assumed technological superiority.
- The next day in Prafter, it was all over the headlines
because the U.S. had suddenly, you know,
the New York Times said,
"Oh my God, they've beaten us, we're flattened, we're ruined."
And Rush went, "Oh, maybe this is a huge deal
"that we've done this, well done us."
And then they got really excited about it.
- I did read a report saying Khrushchev announced it.
Like, he got the news from the launchpad,
whatever, that it was in orbit,
and smiled and was happy and announced it to the room
and then went to sleep that night.
But the alternative to that is him
remaining permanently awake for the rest of his life.
(laughing)
- In America, there were lots of restaurants
that released merch.
There was Sputnik Lollipops.
There was a toy manufacturer, did a scooter,
which was just the same scooter,
but they called it Pednik.
There were spherical containers that held ice creams.
They would put antennas on top
so that you would have the straw as the Sputnik kind of,
look, 'cause they had antennae that were coming out.
- Yeah, so the Lollipops have multiple stalks.
- I reckon the pole is-- - Stalks, poles.
- Yeah, yeah, exactly.
- It had multiple antennae, right?
Did it have two or four?
- Four, I think.
- Four. - Yeah, that's true.
- That's really hard to eat a lollipop,
which has got four sticks sticking in it.
- Yeah. - Or four people
can eat it at the same time or hold one stick
and then lick it. (laughing)
No?
How many kids have you got done?
Three kids. - Three, yeah.
- If you could have one lollipop that you'd buy them
and all three of them could eat it.
- You contain them, they'd be in one location.
(laughing)
- I don't know, I think, sorry,
but if they're all licking one lollipop at the same time,
people are gonna think they're snogging.
(laughing)
And so do services, we'll get 'em for home.
I mean, that's true.
And then the next thing that happened,
so obviously America's smashed back on its heels,
it's reeling, the next thing happens, Sputnik II.
And this one's big and it's got a dog on it.
- Yeah. - And that's, you know,
it's like that.
- And that was when they invented the bark, wasn't it?
(laughing)
- And that was Paul Bloody Leica,
who had a pretty rotten time in space
and then sort of conked out.
- Which means barker, in fact, Leica, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think she was causing me else.
- What all this was leading up to
was the 40th anniversary of the Soviet Union
being founded, right, 'cause it's 1957,
October, October Revolution, all of that stuff,
November, depending on the calendar.
Anyway, there was a theory in the West
that the Soviet Union was launching a third Sputnik,
which was going to go to the moon
with a hydrogen bomb on it.
- And an elephant.
(laughing)
- And there was a lunar eclipse coming up,
so the moon was going to be completely blotted out,
you know, in the shadow of the sun,
or shadow of the earth, sorry.
So the theory was that they were gonna detonate
the bomb against the moon
and create a kind of super full moon,
'cause it would be even brighter than a normal full moon
with this, you know.
And anyway, they weren't doing that.
- Well, they did do lots of Sputnik,
well, Sputnik just means satellite,
so anything that they send up is a Sputnik, basically.
But yeah, they've done 20 odd, I think, now.
- But none of them have been the moon blowing up.
No, which was a stupid idea.
I don't even think I'd know if I saw something
that was a bit brighter and a bit bigger than the moon,
'cause you haven't got the actual moon to compare it to.
- Yeah, maybe.
- Well, it would be a full moon for a second
as the detonation happened.
You would think something was up.
- Every now and then, like once every month or so,
do you not go outside and go up?
The moon's quite big tonight.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
It's a certain time of day, isn't it?
Yeah, do you think that's always a Sputnik?
- I think that's it.
Every morning, when the moon is near the horizon,
that's the Russians blowing it up.
- Oh, I think they're wasting a lot of resources on this.
- Yuri Gagarin, first man to orbit the Earth?
- Yep.
- Cosmonauts? - First man in space.
- First man in space.
- Was he?
I thought someone had gone up a bit before that, but not.
- Gone past the carman line.
- He was the first.
- That space.
- Yuri's, yeah, acknowledged as first.
- I'm a carman waiting in the sky.
Was originally written about that.
- He was five foot two,
which means that he would only just qualify it
to be an air stewardess on Ryanair.
- Right.
- But.
- Which was his dream, wasn't it?
- It's what he was trying to do all that time.
He was just trying to get the attention of Michael O'Leary.
- I mean, it was really bad.
Because the first time he went in space,
it was one thing, but he had to pay for his seat.
- And you know the space dogs?
- The Soviet ones.
- Lika?
- Lika.
Well, there's an argument that they preserved peace
and stopped the world from imploding,
exploding due to nuclear attack.
And here is the argument.
So in 1960, the Soviets sent up some more dogs.
They were called Belka and Strelka.
And they went into orbit with some rats
and a rabbit and some flies.
And they orbited the world 17 times
and they came back down and they were big celebrities.
They had chat shows and stuff.
- Who had chat shows?
- I don't think they actually hosted their own chat shows.
Sorry.
I think they might have just guessed it.
They wrote in a small segment.
- But hosting is a good idea.
Every week the guest has to feed Belka and Strelka.
I think that's a really nice idea.
- Lovely.
Let's pitch it.
It's our next commission.
Anyway, so they were the first dogs who survived
'cause some people were a bit sad that Lika didn't.
Anyway, soon after that, JFK and Kristoff
and their wives had a meeting, a summit,
in Vienna and it was awkward as things often were
at the time between America and the USSR.
And then Jackie Kennedy broke the tension
by saying to Kristoff,
"Oh, what happened to those two lovely dogs
"that you sent into space, by the way?"
And Kristoff said, "Oh, they actually had puppies.
"Do you want one?"
And he posted to her.
So a few weeks later--
(laughing)
- It arrived, unfortunately.
Not quite as alive as it was in the Cuban Missile Crisis.
(laughing)
Oh no, he put the bubble wrap in the envelope and it was fine.
Yeah, so a puppy arrived at the White House.
- Were they called pupnics?
- I actually think they might have called them pupnics.
- That would make sense.
- That rings a bell.
It would make sense.
I think they had the same sense of humor as you did
in the White House at the time.
- Okay, I'm just gonna collect Spot the Dog.
- Oh yeah, Spotnick.
- Suggestions.
- Mudnick.
Mudnick.
There we go.
- Yeah, very good.
- Mudnick.
- Just edit out my one,
you got three really good ones.
(laughing)
- So keep that comment in so everyone will always want that.
Write in with your speculations
as to Annie's shit suggestion.
(laughing)
Anyway, he was a White House puppy pet
and it really calmed things down.
I mean, obviously things didn't remain calm
for the subsequent 30 years.
- That's sad.
Yelka and Stelka are the only ones
that you learn about in Russian schools really.
They don't really mention Leica very much.
- Yeah, yeah.
So sad.
After Leica went up,
dog lovers worldwide protested.
There was a march at the UN
with featuring dogs wearing protest signs.
- Wow.
There was also a producer of a chat,
so I was like, what am I gonna do now?
(laughing)
- Can we say a thing or two about Beeps?
- Oh sure, yeah.
We don't have time to list all the previous Beeps
prior to this one.
- Let's see how far we get.
So this is a really fun thing about Beeps.
Skodas, right, the cars.
- Oh yeah.
- The horns get tested, don't they?
Car horns get tested.
And these days they're tested way more
in the development process
than they ever have been before.
- Okay.
- So Skodas in the '70s were tested 50,000 times
to make sure they wouldn't run out of Beeps
after that.
- Sorry, you beeped a horn 50,000 times
before selling the car.
- I don't think.
(laughing)
- You beeped it 50,000 first and it ran out.
- No, no, no.
- You do that in the car dealership.
(laughing)
I'm just gonna go quick.
That doesn't happen.
- 50,000.
- Every car that Skoda sells.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- It happens.
- It happens in the development process.
- 'Cause I have a Skoda and I've got this big handprint
in the middle of my steering wheel.
- Everyone's dry.
- Do they not crash test every car
before they sell that there's one?
(laughing)
Just gonna drive this into a wall
before we send it to you, sir?
(laughing)
- So no.
- Sorry, yeah.
- They test it.
- But these days, electric Skodas,
they get 150,000.
But that's regionally specific.
And when they sell cars in India,
they're tested 500,000 times.
- What?
- 'Cause in India, use of the car horn is way bigger.
Like, everyone is beeping all the time.
So they have to test half a million honks before.
- Wow.
- I was saying in India,
like they do honk in the way you're supposed to honk.
As the only time you're ever supposed to honk
is if someone, to let someone know
you're there to stop an accident.
- Right.
- If you drive in India,
they're doing that because they're about to drive into you
and they're honking and stuff.
They don't do it in the UK like honk, honk,
the traffic light's gone, you need to move.
- Oh, yeah, that's true.
- They do proper honking in India.
- I think you're also encouraged to honk
as a way of saying goodbye to somebody
not gonna see you for a few weeks, aren't you?
- That's actually, yeah, that's the only other time.
- Is that the highway cut?
- It's in the highway cut, is it?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And also honk if you love blah,
whatever's on the sign at the side of the line.
That's important too.
(laughing)
- So when buying a car, as well as asking for mileage,
you should ask for a honkage, is that what we're saying?
- How many honks you've got,
how many honks you've packed into this bad boy?
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that William Gladstone
once canceled an evening engagement
so he could binge on the latest popular drama series.
(laughing)
So this is William Gladstone,
who was a British prime minister,
and quite famously quite door and serious and whatever.
So I quite like the idea of him,
you know, watching Breaking Bad or whatever.
But obviously this wasn't that.
This was The Woman in White,
which was a story by Wilkie Collins,
which was originally done in...
- Cereals.
- It was originally sold in breakfast cereals.
(laughing)
So it was a free gift at the bottom of our flex boxes.
And it was originally done in cereals, in magazines,
and then the entire book came out in 1860, I think,
1859, 1860, and he got it and he wanted to read it.
So he just canceled his...
- I love it.
- It's so great. - I love it.
Imagine...
- What if he was taking a date, though?
Do you still love it?
- Oh!
- What if the date went to the theater,
and I was like, "Where's Willie?"
(laughing)
- He's with Wilkie.
- He's with William Wilkie.
- You don't get...
What's he called Wilkie?
What's that his name?
- He knows his middle name,
so he was William Wilkie Collins.
- Okay, but I'm just saying you don't get Wilkie's anymore.
- Well, actually, he wanted to be called Wilkie,
so he insisted that you never call him Mr. Collins,
or you never call him William Collins or whatever.
He insisted that everyone just called him Cher or Madonna.
He was just Wilkie.
- Really?
- Well, 'cause his dad and his grandfather,
I think, were both Williams as well.
So I think it was one of those cases
where the middle name suddenly became the first name,
and it was an honorary first name.
- But I think he wanted us to drop the surname as well.
We should just be saying Wilkie.
- Well, that's what he wanted, but you know.
- I think we should do what shows him respect for the guy.
- Yeah.
- The Oxford Dictionary of National Biography says
it was typical of his dislike of formality,
'cause he was quite an odd cookie.
- He was a rum-cove, and he was rum.
Can we talk about the book quickly?
- Yeah, let's do that.
- 'Cause the book is, it's really good.
- Have you read it?
- I have read it, I mean, years and years ago.
- Yeah, I have, and I'm really excited to.
- I've read "The Woman in White" and "The Moonstone,"
and he wrote, I think, about 20 novels,
and those are the two sort of big hits.
- I've read the first 50 pages
'cause I bought it on Tuesday, and--
- It's pretty good.
- Really big, isn't it really big?
- Yeah, it's huge.
- But they got paid by writing a chapter at a time,
so you would, you just, and so it came out in this magazine.
It was a Dickens-owned magazine called "All the Year Round,"
and when it was first published in chapter four,
chapter by chapter sales, went from 40,000 to 300,000.
It was mega, it was so exciting.
- But it's weird that he caused Dickens's publication
to become so popular, because he actually,
kind of, hero worshiped Dickens, didn't he?
Whereas really, Dickens should have been thanking him
for making his magazine, "All Year Round,"
or whatever, go through the route.
- Well, he was younger, he was a protege of Dickens,
and then Dickens quickly fell in love with him
and sort of the roles slightly reversed,
where he sort of was inspired by Wilkie's writing.
- But he did do this weird, like, Dickens tribute tour,
'cause we've talked about Dickens traveling around the world
and giving lectures, and then he immediately traveled
around the world giving public readings
and going to the same locations that Dickens had.
- Wow. - I think he took holidays
at Dickens' favorite holiday resorts.
- Did he?
And then they fell out, didn't they?
- Did they?
- They fell out because Charles Dickens' daughter, Kate,
married Wilkie Collins' brother, Charles.
- Oh!
- And they really properly fell out,
and then Collins started really slagging off all of his books.
He called Barnaby Road the weakest book
that Dickens ever wrote.
- To be fair, that's true,
and I don't think that's necessarily
slagging off his books, is it?
- He was ranking them, he was ranking them.
- He was ranking them, yeah.
- Imagine if I'd ranked all the episodes
of this podcast in order, which I definitely haven't,
so we should--
- He then went on to say that Dombie and son's
no intelligent person can have read it
without astonishment of the badness of it.
- Yeah, I guess. - That's not good, yeah.
- Critique.
- He called in Edwin Drude the melancholy work
of a worn-out brain.
- Oh, God, well, that was fun finish, that's unfair.
- Yeah, and he must have said it
after Dickens died as well, right?
- Yeah, there's stories that he was asked to finish, Drude,
'cause they thought that he knew Dickens so well
in the writing style.
- Well, that's weird, 'cause Collins,
when he was writing a book called No Name,
he got really ill, and Dickens offered to take over.
He said, "I know you don't need the help,
but if just in case you do want that finished,
I can do it for you."
So they both were involved in that kind of project.
That thing of them, so Dickens' daughter
marrying Wilkie Collins' brother,
I guess they would have been the same age
'cause Collins was a much younger man.
But part of the reason that Dickens really didn't like
the situation was that Wilkie Collins' brother, Charles,
was apparently a complete, just like milk toast, wet blanket.
- Well, he wasn't very wet because he refused to have baths
because he almost drowned when he was five years old,
and he was petrified by water for the rest of his life
and wouldn't even get into a bath.
- Right.
- Okay, that might have been part of it.
But it's so weird, 'cause they looked, apparently,
both sibling and child Dickens' daughter, Katie,
they both looked the most like.
Like, Wilkie Collins' brother looked just like him,
and Katie Dickens looked just like Charles Dickens.
- Oh, really, okay.
- She had their little goatee beard, didn't she?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- That's very funny.
- They met through a bloke called Augustus Egg.
That was their mutual friend, I know.
- Who did Wilkie and Dickens with her?
- Dickens and Collins, yeah, yeah, yeah.
And they went on holiday with Egg,
and Collins lectured Egg on art,
and hummed opera airs incorrectly and interminably
was the report.
- The meeting of those two,
they actually met because they were acting
in the same play at the time, right?
So Dickens brought him onto a production.
- The play that they met in was by Edward Bill Williton,
who wrote, "It was a dark and stormy night."
He's the guy who wrote that sentence.
- Yes.
- And this is the great thing.
Okay, so this looks back to the woman in white
because Bill Williton hated the woman in white.
He said it was great trash.
I think he meant big trash rather than like,
"Oh, it's great trash," you know?
And the point is that Bill Williton had had his wife,
Rosina, committed to an asylum a couple of years before,
and that plotline is in the woman in white.
- That's how interesting.
- And all of Collins' works in some way.
Loads of them are about women being mistreated by men,
or being, you know, like--
- There's very much to spoil if you haven't read
the woman in white, by the way.
- Oh, yeah, that's right.
- Then let's start from the end at this stage.
- Can I just say, I don't think we should be giving
a spy list of classic words in this picture.
- Yeah, but Collins dedicated the book to the man
who, the commissioner for lunacy was his title,
who had helped release Rosina from the asylum.
- Really?
- So obviously, Bill Williton hated the book
because it was such a slam on him in a way.
- It turns out, and yeah, that makes sense
'cause I was reading an obituary of Wilkie Collins
just after he died, and this friend of his who was writing it
said that when he wrote the woman in white,
Collins had told him he received a letter
from Rosina, Lytton's wife, who said,
"I really enjoyed your book,
"but I thought the villain," she said, "Camp Fosco.
"I thought the villain was a really poor villain,
"not realistic at all, you know.
"Next time if you want a villain, come to me.
"I have my eyes upon a villain every minute of the day.
"It is my husband."
- Oh, nice.
- So one of those things that happened
when the book came out is it was one of those things
we've spoken about where when things take off,
the merch just starts rolling in.
You know, there was a waltz that was named after it.
There were cloaks, there were hats.
Perfumes were made that were sort of like meant to be
the woman in white's perfume.
It was just full of merch around London.
- Walter became a fashionable name for babies
'cause there's a character named Walter.
- Right, did it, that was the thing.
- Yeah, Walter's the hero, isn't he?
The kind of slightly boring hero,
and the heroine is slightly boring as well.
- Wow, so I'm not allowed to spoiler the ending,
but you're allowed to spoiler the fact
that people in it are slightly boring.
- Terrible.
- It's not a spoiler, I think that's more of an opinion.
Do you know what really annoys me
about basically all adaptations?
- And this applies to lots of stuff,
but I'm gonna use the woman in white to vent.
There have been loads of films and TV series of it
over the years, and the most recent was 2018 I saw
with Jesse Buckley in it, who's an attractive actress.
And the thing that I remember from the woman in white
is that there are these two quite extreme characters
who are the real good characters.
There's Count Fosco, who's this hugely fat Italian villain,
and then there's Marion, who is very sharp,
very bright, very bold, and very ugly.
She's got a moustache, she's got a huge masculine jaw.
She's ugly enough that Walt was almost repulsed by her when,
'cause she looks really attractive from behind.
It's one of those weird sort of '90s rom-com reveals.
She turns around, and he's like, "Oh, that face!"
- Is this "Shallow Hell?"
Is "Shallow Hell" based on one of the words?
(all laughing)
- I think it must have been said, "Shallow Hell."
- Have you thought she looked attractive from behind?
And yeah, every single adaptation, she's not ugly.
- How interesting.
Do you think that the actors
are taking away jobs from ugly actors?
- I genuinely do.
I really think that they are quite incredibly annoying.
No, they sort of make themselves look a bit tomboyish.
And I think it's bullshit in entertainment today.
You don't do it with men.
- No, they do fit people up a lot.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Well, they just pick a fit actress to play an ugly role,
'cause they think that people can't handle
watching an unattractive woman.
- Okay, yeah.
- Do they mention it in the dialogue?
Like, as if people go up to her in the movie
and go, "You're an ugly person."
(all laughing)
And she's just then looking stunning.
And I'm like, "Oh, yes, I know this face."
Stop, I'm completely dark.
- It does happen, the Jack Reacher books,
those were adapted, and they put Tom Cruise in the role.
And that was the biggest uproar about the whole thing,
is that he's meant to be six foot 10.
He's meant to be hulkingly massive.
- And then you've got this. - That's just drastic miscasting.
As in, obviously, Tom Cruise is brilliant,
but he doesn't look like Jack Reacher,
who I think at one point stops a bullet with his chest.
(all laughing)
I think at one point in the books, anyway.
Can we talk a bit about "Working Colourns?"
- Yeah.
- So his health situation was quite interesting,
because it was bad, he had bad health.
If he had good health, it wouldn't be nearly as interesting.
- Unless it was really good.
- One of it was so good, he was still alive.
- Then he'd be alive.
- Yeah.
- As it was, he had neuralgia, rheumatism,
spasm suffocation, I don't think we know what that was,
gout in the eyes, a boil on his groin.
At one point, his partner Caroline had to mesmerize his feet
to try and cure them.
- Oh, wow.
- Yeah.
- How do you mesmerize?
We've talked about mesmerism before,
but how do you do it to feet?
- You know, when you sit down on your leg for too long,
and it goes to sleep.
- Yeah.
- Is that it?
- It's gotta be that.
Yeah, it's gotta be something like that.
- You just sat on them.
- I don't know.
- 'Cause he had gout eyes,
so he couldn't do it through mesmerizing his eyes.
Like, they were really bunged up.
- Well, you don't get gout in your eyes.
- That's what I thought.
- No, I know, but when you read the descriptions
of what happened to his eyes,
they were bleeding, they were pussy, they were--
- But I believe, again,
this is based on this obit written by his friend.
He said that he went round to his house when he was older,
and he couldn't stop looking at his eyes,
'cause they looked so weird,
and he couldn't really meet your eye properly.
And eventually, Colin said,
"I see you're looking at my eyes.
"I know it's distracting.
"I've got gout eye," and the friend implies,
and we know this is a fact,
that it's probably all the Lordenham he was taking.
- Yeah, yeah, it's so neat.
- His eyes to come up quite blurry, rather than--
- Oh, of course.
- It wasn't a disease of the eye.
He was just off his face all the time.
- It's gonna be great in his biopic
when Tom Cruise is playing him,
and they're saying, "Your eyes, they're horrible."
(all laughing)
- Apparently, he was taking enough
to kill six people every day.
- Yeah.
- And he was also taking poppers
in about the same amount for his heart.
- Didn't see a student in the early 2000s.
- Wait, did poppers, I didn't think poppers existed.
- Well, I'm ill nitrate.
- Oh, right.
- So, yeah, that's--
- They didn't come in this fun,
colorful packets that they do now.
- I wouldn't know, actually.
(all laughing)
- And he was taking arsenic as well at the same time.
- Oh, my God.
- All that meant that he saw ghosts all the time.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, he thought he had a doppelganger,
a ghost willky, that was with him.
- And it was just a mirror, wasn't it?
- How did he come up with that amazing name for the ghost?
- He's one of the best.
- Yeah, he would, like Dan says,
the doppelganger would be around,
there would be ghosts pushing down the stairs
when he was trying to go up to bed,
so he couldn't climb it.
A bit, you know, that dream that people have
where you just can't get up a hill
and kind of be quicksand, that kind of thing,
but it was ghosts pushing him down.
And then when he got to the top of the stairs,
he would be met by a green woman with tusks.
- Oh.
- I mean, do you think maybe you're only taking enough
to kill five people a day, might be a good idea, will you?
- No, no.
- And his love life as well was absolutely,
it was just really interesting.
It was kind of--
- For the time, I guess it was--
- Interesting because he was someone of the best.
(laughing)
- He's very healthy.
- No, interesting even for today, I would say, Dan.
If someone these days had this love life,
I would be interested, I want to know more.
He didn't want to marry, fine,
and he was in a relationship
with a woman called Caroline Graves.
She was a widow, she had a child from earlier relationship.
And then he started an affair
with a woman called Martha Rudd, right?
And she was, I think, about 20 when they met.
And they had three children together.
Caroline Graves didn't love this.
She went off to marry someone else.
- Fair enough.
- Completely fair enough.
And he actually went to the wedding,
so it might have been all--
- I think it was quite friendly.
- Yeah.
- I got the impression there wasn't too much resentment.
- So that's good.
So then Wilkie Collins is in a relationship
with his new woman, Martha Rudd.
They have three children together.
He sort of keeps them in a flat away from his house.
And he only wants to be known as Dawson
when he goes over, I think.
- Cool.
- He just sort of has an assumed name for the landlady.
He doesn't want any publicity, all of that.
But then Caroline, his previous partner,
her marriage doesn't work out.
So she comes back, she lives with him,
and he's just rattling between two families back and forth.
And then sometimes he takes them all on holiday together
to Ramsgate and puts them in boarding houses
next to each other and all the kids play together.
And they have a great time.
- I think the kids play together,
but the women never meet.
- Yeah.
- It's weird.
- It's so weird.
- And he's at one, I presume at one house or the other
all the time.
- Wow.
- And they just have to kind of, that's the situation.
- It sounds like a sort of amateur play
where the women are both played by the same person.
'Cause it's so important they never meet.
They live basically on the same street.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Exactly.
- They walk out of the door and they're like,
"Oh, you just missed it."
- Exactly.
And she's going to drive it out of breath.
"Oh, you missed it."
- That's married Mrs. Doubtfully.
(laughing)
- Do you know when Martha was born?
- No.
- She was born in Martham.
(laughing)
- That sounds like you just conjugated her name.
- It's the accusative, actually.
Yeah, very unimaginative parents, Martham in Norfolk.
- I was going to say, where the heck is Martham?
- I think it's a village in Norfolk.
- That's so good.
- So did they name her after the village?
- Not clear.
Did try to find out.
Funnily enough, it wasn't one of those facts
that's been recorded to history,
as far as I could tell.
I wasn't born in Peniston.
(laughing)
- If you are in Martham listening to this now,
please write in.
- Yeah.
- Just tell us what it's like.
- Send us a photo.
(laughing)
- I know I'm a bit unsure about that,
but you don't do the emails anymore,
rather.
- Oh, yeah, sorry.
Of course, inundate us with emails.
(laughing)
Everyone from Martham.
- If you've ever been to Martham,
or been any place beginning with that,
then write it.
(laughing)
'Cause the last time I said that,
I said something like,
if you are eating particular foods
in America right now,
and it was thanks to that bloke,
David Fairchild, who imported them all.
And we got a lot of emails of people eating avocados,
people eating rice.
I can't remember what it was,
but it was a lot.
- Martha tended,
so Martha said she could have married Wilkie Collins
whenever she wanted.
That was a bit of a lady that had to protest too much thing.
But she didn't go to his funeral,
nor did their kids, weirdly.
But then, she did.
- She was there, but she was called Caroline Gray.
(laughing)
- Where's Martha?
- She did go to the balloon.
(laughing)
After Caroline died,
she took over tending Wilkie Collins grave.
So it just seems like there's so much happening
below the surface we don't know about.
- Caroline was also buried in that grave.
- Yes, Caroline was buried in the same plot.
- I suppose she tended Caroline's grave as well,
but she quickly dug herself into the coffin for a while.
(laughing)
Oh, thanks for looking up to my grave.
Clives out of the coffin, no problem.
(laughing)
Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that 15th century Korean royals
had their lives so thoroughly documented
that the records include kings complaining
about their recorders recording them.
So, this was sent to me by my friend, Mark Vent.
I've never heard of it.
It's called The Annals of the Joseon Dynasty,
where basically they recorded literally everything,
included in these accounts.
In 1404, for example,
there was a king who fell off a horse by accident.
He was really embarrassed,
and he went up to the guy recording it saying,
"Can you not put in the whole horse-falling thing?"
And the guy put it in.
So we've got an account of the king
then bitching about the guy going,
"I bet he's put in the horse thing, hasn't he?"
- He said, "Stop writing.
"No, no, stop writing that.
"Don't write that either, you bastard."
- You know the never-ending story?
There's a character sitting on the top of a mountain,
transcribing everything.
This is basically how they treated their entire dynasty.
And as a result, we've got 500 years' worth
of complete records of the king
and all of the king's administrators.
- It's brilliant.
- Yeah, it's incredible.
- It's such a good idea.
Unlike now, where literally this week,
we're hearing that people are deleting WhatsApps every,
you know, they're doing government business,
and they're deleting the WhatsApps every seven days,
so we never know what they said.
- You're right.
If we doubt this system, they couldn't have done it,
'cause the king wasn't even allowed to see it.
- It wasn't allowed to see it.
- After he died, you weren't allowed to look
at the recordings of what you've done and said.
- Yeah, exactly.
The rules were very strict about who couldn't look
in the annals, but they were broken sometimes.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- So there was, I've read an account of a tyrant king
who looked in the annals and then six people were executed
because of what he found written in there.
So I think after that, they probably had to tighten
up the rules.
Maybe he was the reason the kings then weren't allowed
to look in the annals.
- So what it was, I mean, I don't know if this is
the specific account you're talking about,
but the people who were writing the histories often went
back in to change what they've written because the king
wasn't allowed to look at what happened.
You know, he'd have to die and then people could look
at what was said about him, but politicians would get word
that maybe something was written down.
So the historiographers would go back into it
and kind of change it.
And the king found out about that and he got really pissed
off that they were more petrified of the politicians
than the king himself of what the king would do.
And then that got banned.
- So you weren't allowed to then go in and change
your own story?
- They were known as the literati purges, weren't they?
(laughing)
And the one Andy's talking about who was Yon Sangun,
who was the tyrant king, he closed down the university
and turned it into his personal pleasure grounds
where he would import young girls from around the provinces.
He also demolished a huge area where people were living
in the capital and turned it into his own hunting grounds.
And then when everyone complained, he told his ministers
they weren't allowed to speak and they had to wear a sign
saying, "A mouth is a door that brings in disaster.
A tongue is a sword that cuts off a head."
- I really thought it was gonna rhyme.
(laughing)
- It probably was in Korea.
- It's Korean, yeah.
(laughing)
- Wait, a tongue is a sword?
- It feels like you could say plaster at some point.
A tongue is a sword that--
- Calls for a plaster, yeah?
- It's a plaster.
- Wait, what's the mouth?
- A mouth is a door that brings in disaster.
A tongue is a sword that calls for a plaster.
- Looks good.
- It's not amazing, but it's hard to work with.
- I think it's good.
- What are the teeth?
- Something knocked out by your master.
- Oh, very good.
- Lovely.
- Anyway, he sounds like a rotter.
(laughing)
Yeah, it was really strange.
There were eventually about 2,000 volumes of this stuff.
2,000 volumes.
And it was all sorts of clobber as well.
It was the weather, it was diplomatic affairs,
it was the economy.
It was, you know.
- Probably quite a boring job to actually do it.
Day in, day out, dribbling away.
And you must have had this constantly saying,
"So can you slow down, please?"
- Sorry, can you say that again?
- Yeah.
- And then you have to write that down.
- Yes.
- And then I wrote down, "Can you slow down, please?"
- Sorry, can you fall off the horse again, but slower?
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's 1,967 books in total is what they have.
They say if you stacked it,
it would be taller than a 10-story building.
Is the height we're talking of these books,
which just means nothing,
but that's quite fun as a visual.
- Thank you for explaining why you've mentioned it.
- But the point that they make in this thing is,
until it's been digitized,
it was an intensely hard history to get your head around
because--
- 'Cause you gotta climb nine stars
to get to the level you want.
- Yeah, exactly.
Well, there's no, it's not a history book.
It's not written like, "Here's the story of the king."
You've got a bit of the king,
and then you've suddenly got the weather report,
and you have to hunt through 1,900 volumes
to find the thing you're looking for.
Obviously there's, you know, when the periods--
- There's days of the stuff, but yeah.
- Yeah, exactly.
- But now it has been digitized, right?
- It has, yeah.
- And it's the plan is to translate them
into English by the year 2033.
- Okay.
This dynasty was an interesting one.
It was a very long-lasting dynasty.
- Yeah, 500 years.
- Yeah, 500.
- 1392 until, well, accounts vary,
but I'm going with 1910.
- Hmm, controversial.
- Well, Japan invaded Korea at that point.
Certainly not despite it.
That was, yeah, in the 14th century, when it started,
it was, you know, the big deal was that they were moving
from an old aristocracy to state-trained bureaucrats
who were running the show,
and that was, you know.
- It was very much in the Eastern tradition
of meritocracy, having preceded us.
Well, they were just much more organized than we were.
- It was a meritocracy as long as you weren't a woman.
- Oh, God, yeah, women had an absolute whale of a time,
of course.
There was a ruling from behind the bamboo screen
was a thing in the Choson dynasty,
which was when, if you were a regent,
so obviously if a male royal hadn't come of age yet,
and you were the mother, then you could rule,
but you had to sit behind the bamboo screen at the time
when he sat on the throne, acting like he was saying stuff.
- Oh, do you have your hand up his bum at the time?
(all laughing)
I mean, if we thought that those three kids
looking the same lot, he was going to get social services in.
- The ruling from behind the screen, that was quite cool.
- Yeah, it was really cool.
- We've spoken about that before, haven't we?
- What we've spoken about it in Russia.
- Yeah, when someone was behind, literally, the throne.
- The chair.
- Yeah, yeah, just go, "Why don't you say?"
But here, you weren't hit, like they knew you were there,
'cause there's a big screen, maybe with nice pictures on it.
But have a fight a lot,
if your grandmother or your mother ruled.
There was one queen, I think,
who ruled for about 25 years from behind the screen.
- What?
Oh, really? - With the same regent?
- Yeah. - It's kind of that,
you're not ready yet, so I'm sorry.
(all laughing)
- Oh, I thought they had a rule that when you turned 20,
so it was if you were under 20.
- They did, but lots of weird stuff always happens,
and she liked power, and so it was a bit like,
oh, actually, you're not qualified, it turns out,
and she was machinating behind the scenes
to make sure she stayed in control.
But it was, one of the good things about them
recording all these details,
was that you got just a lot of blood and gore,
'cause everyone, like Royals were in the past,
almost everywhere, everyone was quite bloodthirsty.
So one of the stories that I liked that was recorded
was the story of Prince Sado.
(all laughing)
You know what, Sado?
- Is that the English translation, or?
- It basically should be, 'cause he was a sad character.
This was in the 1700s, and his dad was King Yong Zhou,
who really wanted Sado to be studious and clever.
- Sounds like he was.
(all laughing)
- Well, sadly, he wasn't.
He was actually a free spirit.
He wanted to be a musician and an artist kind of type.
- Oh, yeah, classic.
- His dad was a super lame, bullied him,
used to mock him in front of the eunuchs, and the ladies.
- Not in front of the eunuchs.
(all laughing)
No, that's so unkind.
- It's the worst, and it drove Sado a bit mad.
Sado went mad-o, and he sort of,
he went from being a really gentle, sweet boy
to murdering everyone, and he used to walk into chambers
holding severed heads of eunuchs, in fact.
- Guess what else I've cut off?
Yeah, yeah, that kind of thing, yeah.
- Yeah, and so his father was then like,
"Well, we can't have this, we can't have you inheriting,
"so you're gonna have to die,
"but you're not allowed to defile the royal body
"by actually killing someone."
So he asked his son to commit suicide,
and Sado, Sado, though he was,
was not Sado enough to commit suicide,
so his dad said, "Okay, well then,
"can you climb into this rice chest?"
And then he locked him in a rice chest and starved him to death.
- Wait, did he know that that was gonna be locked?
- I guess maybe he thought really,
look, I guess this has to happen.
- Was he put in the chest?
- It might have been,
there might have been someone gently encouraging him
with a hand. - Although, although,
is there any animals, you know?
- Yeah, if it's in the animals, then it must have happened,
otherwise it'd be like, you know,
"Don't say that I'm shoving my son
"into this rice chest right now."
- Yeah, you're right, he got involuntarily.
- Yeah. - There was a place,
I can't remember where it was.
The tradition was that you couldn't kill the king,
but you could put them in a bag
and hit the bag very hard with a club.
And I think that was the...
- I think that was the Ottoman Empire, wasn't it?
- It was the Ottomans, I'm sorry, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think you beat them in some kind of rugs sometimes,
didn't you, so that you couldn't spill blood?
- You say, "I'm just beating this rug,"
and actually it contains the king or whatever.
And that was the means of executing very, very posh people.
- Right, wasn't there a tradition,
there was a pirate tradition as well,
wasn't there, of chest, putting people in chests and--
- That's treasure.
(laughing)
- That goes back to the people,
when they picked up my treasure.
(laughing)
- It's some poor, desiccated skeleton in there.
- No, it's hook, I'm thinking of the movie hook.
- Oh, you're not, you're not really.
- Yeah, right at the beginning, yeah,
but they put them in the boo box, the boo box,
and he goes inside. - The boo box.
- Yeah, and you would have a slide,
and you'd put scorpions in and close it.
- We don't need to go into the details,
I don't think it is historical facts.
- Interesting fact, it was Glenn Close,
who played the male pirate,
and no one really knew that, uncredited, yeah.
- Hook, who played hook?
- No, played the pirate put in the treasure chest, yeah.
- Okay, so. - Anybody's done it.
- One interesting thing about these annals is,
like Andy said, they kind of would tell you the weather,
and stuff like that.
But it also would tell you whenever there was an aurora,
and there was a time between 1645 and 1715,
which we now sometimes call the mini ice age,
and we've managed to use, or not we,
a guy called Jan and his team,
managed to use the records, looking into the history books,
and have worked out the solar cycles
that were happening around that time.
- Beautiful. - By the number of auroras
that were recorded in the annals.
- That's so cool. - Isn't that cool?
- That's amazing. - And so we now know
that around that time, the solar cycle
was only about eight years,
whereas it's normally a bit longer than that.
- That's incredible. - I just love that stuff.
- There's also UFO encounters
in the Chosen dynasty, which is very exciting.
So, September 1609, there was a reported case
of things shaped like a bowl in the sky.
And there's a few paranormal things
that make it in there as well, but what's really amazing,
I'm so excited by this, I haven't seen it yet,
but it's obviously immediately become
one of my favorite TV shows.
The Chosen X Files, it's a real TV show,
and it's a historical, and it uses accounts
from the Chosen annals as the basis for each episode,
and there's an ancient investigator of the time
who is assigned to go and investigate
all of the weird paranormalities
that we find in the annals.
- What kind of things are we talking about?
- Oh, I just told you, the UFO.
- A bowl in the fall of the sky.
- A bowl shape across the moon, sounds like.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, who knows?
I mean, it's obviously not a UFO,
but they recorded it as unidentified stuff,
there's cursed items, all that sort of stuff,
and yeah, it's been turned into a-
- Well, that's the good thing about the annals
is that it's really easy to re-enact
so much of what happened.
So you can make an incredibly accurate historical
representation, and I think historical re-enactments
are much more popular and common
in Korea now of this period,
because you know exactly what people were wearing,
exactly how they ate their meals,
like meals were described in such detail,
and the order in which meals,
like the order in which different foods
had to be placed on the table.
It was all extremely ordered life.
Everything was very ceremonial,
and so you'd have to bring in the sausages first,
and then the cabbage five minutes later,
and we know all of this.
So re-enactments, piece of cake.
- That's cool.
- Welcome to the piece of cake company.
(laughing)
- Can you guess the seven sins for which you were allowed
to divorce your wife under the Joseon dynasty?
- So her sins, not mine.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Adultery.
- Wives weren't allowed to divorce their husbands.
- Adultery's in there, yes.
- Seft.
- Very good stealing is in there, yes.
- Inability to have children is usually one of them.
- Yes, very good.
Fairly to produce a male heir.
You can have daughters if you want, but you'll get divorced.
- Touching my stuff.
What about?
(laughing)
- It's not actually on there, it's been an oversight.
I've been moving the remote control from where I like it,
where I like it, next to where I sit on the sofa,
to apparently a better place next to the television.
- Why would you put it next to the television?
It's a remote control.
It should be remotes from the place that it's beeping to.
- I don't know if I meant to unleash this.
- No, no, this is brilliant.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, I love my wife and it's all going right.
(laughing)
- We've only got three so far, haven't we?
- You've done Fairly to produce a male heir,
adultery, stealing.
- Well, not maintaining the household properly.
- No, that's not, there's excessive jealousy
towards other women in the household
who I guess would often be concubines.
So you can't, yeah, you can divorce your wife.
- Bad mouthing with the friends, they were overheard,
spotted in the annals.
- I'm gonna give you that, talking excessively.
- Ooh.
(laughing)
- Too much chat, you're gone.
The last one is serious disease.
- Oh, right.
- So you've got to, I mean, I think that is irresponsible
to get a bad disease when you're trying
to produce a male heir.
- Yeah, if you've got, if your wife's got gout eyes,
I'm not gonna, I'm not gonna get that.
- Exactly, get rid of them love.
- So the remote control thing you're stuck with?
- I think I might have just missed it out, yeah,
and I think my body was eight since, yeah.
- Eight, yeah.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in real life,
it was difficult to free Willy
because he couldn't hold his breath under water
for long enough, but this is about the film Free Willy.
- Which, if you haven't seen it,
is a classic '90s kids movie, it's brilliant.
- Is it?
- 1993, it's so good, it really is great.
- I know it's about a whale.
- Yep.
- Who is freed.
- Yes.
- I feel like there is a scene where he jumps over a wall.
- Yes, very good.
- And that is his friend with a child who's working to free
and that is not a spoiler because the climactic moment
of the film is on not only the title,
it's also in the trailer and on the poster.
- It's the poster.
- It's the whole thing, it's the weirdest thing.
- I like Anna Karenina having a train on the front cover.
- No, Andy, it's called Free Willy,
it's not called Free Willy question, Mark.
We know that the Free Willy is gonna happen, shall we?
- No, because Free Willy is like an imperative,
like Free Willy, you don't know they obey it, do you?
- Oh, it's not an adjective.
- No, no, no.
- No, it's not.
(laughing)
- Well, actually he starts the film as a Free Will
before being captured by some rascally fisherman,
you know, some scoundrels.
So he starts off as Free Willy.
- But yeah, most of the film, he's not free,
so really, to be accurate, it should have been called
Captive Willy 'cause that's the majority of the film.
(laughing)
Captive Willy is in another genre entirely in films.
- So he was a real whale, he was called Keiko.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, and he was, so yeah, there was this whale
called Keiko and after the film came out, basically,
it was incredibly popular.
Anyone who was a child online, he's probably,
remember seeing it, except James.
And after it came out, there was this massive campaign
and in fact, the film at the end of it had a number to call
if you wanted to save the whales,
but it was an environmental agency that you got through to.
But actually, most people who called the number
or many thousands just wanted that specific whale to be free.
They were like, but what about the actor in the film?
The actor who plays the whale?
- The kid, oh right.
- No one gives shit about the kid, he's still in captivity.
So yeah, there was this campaign to free Keiko.
So they had to train this whale that had been in captivity
for 15 years to learn to live in the wild.
Then it was an incredibly arduous, resource-intensive process.
And one of the things about Keiko was that
couldn't hold his breath underwater.
And whales need to obviously,
'cause they can't breathe underwater.
So Killer Whales, which he was,
hold their breath usually for about 15 minutes underwater.
He couldn't even make sort of three,
but they did manage to train him.
And by the time they released him,
he could hold his breath for 13 minutes.
So very good.
- Oh right, so he had a pretty unhappy life in the wild.
He was used to living with humans.
He'd been living with humans almost all his life,
and he was taken to Iceland,
and then he made his way over to Norway,
but he really was pretty dependent on humans
for the rest of his life, pretty sad.
- It's very interesting because there's a side
of environmentalists and people look after animals
who say this was the worst thing in the world,
to let him back out into the wild
because of all these reasons.
How could he attach himself to a pod?
He's been fed frozen herring, his last 13 years.
But the people who did it still maintained
it was the best thing to do,
and that he was the second oldest orca
to live in captivity ever.
In the time that he was in there,
something like 13 other orcas died
to just show how quickly the mortality rate was.
- Yeah, and he did, yeah, exactly.
He might have died anyway.
He just died of a disease
shortly after managing to be released.
But yeah, and he hung around on the edge of a pod,
but it was mostly tragic, or silly at least,
because there should have been a fund
for broad environmentally good reasons
rather than probably a fund to just release this one whale,
which was fine in captivity.
- The release I think is that in free willies,
certainly two and three,
the willie is played completely by an animatronic whale.
- Yeah.
- It's an early example of AI taking away jobs.
- Well, largely in one, it was played
by an animatronic whale as well.
- And CGI.
- For the bits where the child is putting his hand
in the whale's mouth,
I think they did have to have that in the middle.
- Sorry to interrupt, because I don't know this movie.
In free willie two, three, and four,
you're saying it's the same willie,
as in the character is the same willie.
- He's freed.
- But then what?
- Oh, so, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
- In free willie two, he's gone home.
He's found his pod, and he's found his mum,
which is exciting.
I think there's an oil spill or something bad.
That might be the film three.
And then it turns out, look at me jumping
in front of Dan when Dan's got the entire plot in his head.
And film three, he started a family
and he's got a pregnant one.
- Oh, so he is free throughout those extra films.
- They keep trying to capture him again,
and the kid from the first movie appears in the second.
So it's the same cast trying to make sure
he remains free is the idea.
- So by that point, the title is an adjective.
He is free willie, rather than an imperative.
- And it was sad because the character, you know,
meets up with his pod again and gets together
with the lady whale and, you know,
she's expecting a baby in the third film.
And yet K-Code never experienced any of this.
It's sad.
- Yes, it is sad.
- Absolutely sad.
- And two and three has the same cast,
but four, they sort of thought the story is now told.
So they had to entirely recast it.
And Bindi Irwin, the daughter of Steve Irwin,
Crocodile Hunter, is the lead role.
- Get out.
- You know, I will stay in.
- It's free Bindi.
And is it a different whale?
- I've seen it.
I can't remember.
- 'Cause we've seen Jaws 4.
- Yes.
- Which is, I think the kid of--
- It's the descendant.
It might be that, possibly.
- It's the kid of the original shark,
which is attacking the family.
But not family by blood.
Family by marriage of the original people.
- Oh my God.
- And it follows them across the world.
It's like--
- Through telepathy.
- This shark knows about sort of
social relationships as well as smell and blood.
- No, I stopped describing it, please.
- Have you heard of Auker the movie
while we're talking about movies?
- Auker, no.
- So I wondered if there was like a killer whale movie,
which was a bit like Jaws.
- Oh, right.
- And it turns out there is.
It's called Auker the movie from 1970, whenever it was.
And basically someone had watched Jaws,
seen how popular it was.
And thought, what's scarier than a shark?
A killer whale.
- Yeah.
- And it--
- Incorrect, but okay.
- Oh, killer whales literally eat sharks for breakfast.
- Yeah, killer whales don't harm humans.
- They do in captivity.
- The area against us, sorry.
Two instances, 'cause we're really horrible to them.
Killer whales do not eat humans.
- I think sharks generally speaking don't eat humans.
- The number of shark incidents.
Look, we all like our ocean friends, okay?
- A few people a year do get,
people do get attacked by sharks.
- Killer whales do not attack humans in the wild.
- What about the boats they've been attacking
in the last year?
- They attack boats.
They're not killing humans.
- Who goes on boats?
- They're not humans.
(laughing)
- And you're giving them either too much
or too little credit, right?
You're right.
- Anyway, you've got an approval rating of 9%.
(laughing)
- Oh, really?
- I don't have that, we have seen the sequel
and the sequel and the sequel, sequel, sequel, sequel.
- Yeah.
- Bob Irwin, Steve Sarn is in Auker 4.
- So when they were auditioning for the movie.
- Yeah.
- Free Willy.
- They auditioned lots of different whales.
I don't know what the process was.
- Singing.
- I think maybe.
(laughing)
But 21 of the 23 whales they auditioned belong to SeaWorld.
- Right.
- And SeaWorld apparently uncomfortable
with the movie's message,
which is basically, you're caging whales, you monsters.
This is an incredibly medieval barbaric thing to do.
- Yeah.
- And they asked at one point for a new ending.
- But presumably it went with Willy's days captive.
(laughing)
- He does it.
- Yeah.
- He jumps back over the wall.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- Yeah, and so I think they got Keiko
from a Mexican sea life park because of SeaWorld.
- They did, which is quite odd
because the Mexican park was in very poor condition
and the whale, Keiko, was in very poor condition in it.
But the Mexican owners, the Mexican park,
were absolutely fine with the message.
- Right.
- I think they were a bit like, yeah, no,
it's shit here for the whales.
You should spread the word.
- That was weird for Keiko in that Mexican park
because the water, rather than pouring sea water
for it to live in, they just had water,
which they added salt to.
(laughing)
Like it was really bad.
- I mean, in theory, that sounds like the same,
but I bet it's not.
- It's just kind of not gonna be, is it?
- No, no.
- It probably tastes weird.
- Yeah.
- Seasoned water.
- Seasoned your water.
- And the altitude's quite high up
for what Keiko would have been used to.
- Seats.
(laughing)
- And so it can level up.
- So what altitude do you normally live at, Keiko?
(laughing)
- Jesus.
- He didn't live in one of those really high seas.
(laughing)
- Those are the high seas that the pirates go in.
- That's it?
- Yeah.
- Why do you think the whales are alpine sea experience?
I'm not happy.
(laughing)
- Here's the thing, I watched a clip of it last night,
and actually it's amazing to,
James, not included in this, but when you watch it back,
my memory of Willie going over as a phenomenal scene,
and watch it again, they use CGI,
and it's really obvious when it lands in on the other side.
You can see the splash would kind of
computer graphics, early computer graphics.
- Couldn't do water in those days, could you?
In fact, it's still hard to do water.
- Right.
- I think that's sensible though,
'cause you have got an eight-year-old child actor
firing the 1,300 kilo rubber whale over that.
- Take 12, we're gonna need another kid.
(laughing)
- And there was a stunt, as you said then,
there was a stunt double, which was coated in 1,300 kilos.
Oh, sorry, that's 1,300 kilos of rubber
just on the outside. - On the outside, yeah.
- That's just the skin, and the special effects supervisor
said that the dummy looked so realistic to Keiko
that he became aroused when he saw it.
(laughing)
Did not happen to Keiko in the end.
Obviously he died. - Except Brian died.
- Well, yes.
- He got pneumonia.
- After he died.
- Oh, okay.
Reincarnated as a rabbit.
- Before that, well, possibly, but he was buried.
- Oh, okay, let's see. - Really?
- That poor grave digger, imagine being told
that's your gig this morning.
- Poor, what they call the people who carry them.
- Polbearers. - Polbearers.
- 2,000 Polbearers.
- Yeah, they were so weird.
That was, 'cause he died in Norway,
or off the, in the fjords of Norway.
- Right.
- Normally, you would just tow the whale out to sea
and then attach a deep weight to it, and it would sink.
- Okay, and that would be good for the environment
'cause animals in the bottom of the sea can feed on it.
- Yeah, they didn't do that.
They dug an enormous grave, and then just slid him in.
- And is it marked as in, has it become a destination?
- There's a little can of stones, which marks the grave.
It's right next to the sea, obviously, in land.
- It's not in a churchyard.
- It was not in Birmingham, or anywhere,
really, really far in town, I don't know.
- On top of a mountain, oh, we always love the altitude.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, but they grabbed a special permission.
There are only seven people at the funeral,
which I find very sad.
- How many whales?
(all laughing)
- None.
- You know, we were saying earlier
about how killer whales might slam into a boat?
- Yeah.
- And scientists aren't quite fully sure
why that happens.
And there's a theory that the reason it happens
is because if a boat is out at sea
and it's turned its engine off,
they think it's possible that the killer whales
love going up to the back of the boat
and feeling the water get propelled
through the jet, through its propeller.
And it's a bit like a fun kind of like,
like if you're in a jacuzzi and you've got--
- Like a wave machine, yeah.
- Yeah, exactly like that.
So if they see one and it's not on,
the thought is that they're slamming into the boat
in frustration to make it start,
make that thing happen that they're going to.
No one knows that for sure.
- Well, the thing is, is if you look
in the newspaper archives, you do see
that every now and then there's a spike.
Like in 1953, there was a spike of if you search
for orca ramming boat or killer whale ramming boat,
you'll see one.
There was another one in 2001.
And it's just, I think it happens quite regularly.
And once one of them gets in the news,
a few more people are like,
"Oh, that happened to me today,
so let's get in the use of it."
I don't know if that's true, but that's--
- I'm sure that's part of it, definitely, yeah.
- They have periods, killer whales.
So one of the only other mammals to have periods.
But, sorry, they have menopause.
- Oh, okay.
- And they're one of the only other mammals
to have menopause. - I'm the opposite, in fact.
(laughing)
- They have menopause and you get postmenopausal females.
And we're not really sure why this is,
why they have menopause.
But it has been found that postmenopausal female orcas
like to have sex with adolescent males.
- Oh, wow. - Young males.
- And there's one particular--
- The Coopers of the Sea.
- Exactly, yes.
And there's a woman called Deborah Giles,
who's Director of Research.
(laughing)
- Very hands-on research.
- So in case you're listening, I'm sure you don't do that.
You might do that.
It's fine if you do.
- Right in, right in the middle of the snow.
- Deborah has had nothing to do with any--
She's just Director of Research
at the Center for Whale Research.
And she explains, the reason the old ladies
are doing this to the young boys could be,
so it could be to provide them with sex ed,
show them the ropes, show them some good moves.
And also it's because females
who are looking for a sexually active male to copulate with,
they reject ones that they don't think are quite up to scratch.
And young males, when they get rejected by the female orcas,
get really upset and pissed off
much like a young 15-year-old boy
who has been embarrassed in front of his friends
when he asks out a girl.
And it causes tensions in the group
'cause these young males act out and they get disruptive.
So the older females who are post-menopausal,
so they can't, they go and have sex with them and--
- It's like a pity, a pity.
- It's pity sex, yeah.
- Wow.
- Yeah, it's Stifler's mum.
- Stifler's mum.
- It's not so much--
- Another 90s film reference for him.
(laughing)
- Killer Whales, they like changes in altitude.
So if you get big ships that are kind of trying
to catch fish at the bottom of the sea,
then it's an easy place to get some fish
if you're a killer whale.
Basically you go down to where they're catching it,
if they're dredging and you might get some good--
- Oh yeah.
- Some good Patagonian tooth fish.
And they found that quite recently
there was an adult female killer whale
who got to the depth of 1,087 meters
in order to get these fish.
Which is about as deep as Mount Snowden is high.
- Wow.
- So that's quite a big altitude difference.
- You say wow, it's way easier to go down than to go up.
- No, just as I said, I like fish.
- Okay, let's see you either walk to the top of Snowden,
well by the way, there's a train,
or go all the way 1,000 meters to the bottom of the ocean.
- Oh look, I may not have the whale anatomy
that makes it as easy as it is, but it's fast.
- Hannah, it's easier to come up,
it's easier to float to the surface than just to sink down.
You have to actively push against the force
of all that water.
- Think of the pressure down there.
- I'm finding it a bit hard though
to visualize the Snowden reference.
How many volumes of the Anaheim of the Judson Dynasty
are we talking?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Schreiberland, Andy.
- @AndrewHunterM.
- James. - @JamesHarken.
- And Anna.
- You can email podcast.qi.com and Andy will reply.
- Yeah, where you can go to our group account
which is @NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThingIsTheFish.com,
check out all of our previous episodes
'cause they're up there,
also check out the little bits of merch that we have there,
and also get to Club Fish,
which is our secret members club
where we have lots of bonus episodes, fun content,
and a general amazing land called Discord
where all the listeners of the club hang out
and chat to each other, so do that.
But otherwise, if not, come back here next week
'cause we'll have another episode waiting for you
and we'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]