(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin, and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in the 1940s,
a mystery man traveled America measuring the holes
in donuts and passing a ruling on what size they should be.
- Pervert.
(laughing)
It's got pervert written all over it.
- That didn't even cross my mind.
Now I'm looking down all my research on this guy
and questioning his motives.
- Yeah, I didn't as well.
Why is he a pervert?
What's going on?
- Just it's weird having an obsession with measuring holes
and putting your mucky little fingers in there,
and like, what are you doing?
- 'Cause he got mucky fingers.
(laughing)
- 'Cause they got sugar on them, 'cause they're all the donuts.
- We don't know he wasn't a good hand washer.
In fact, we know almost nothing about him.
- What was he measuring the holes with?
That's what I wanna know.
- Come on, people.
- Okay, now I get it.
(laughing)
- Edward Velasca was a perfectly innocent donut aficionado.
And this, I started looking into this
'cause there's a picture that occasionally pops up online
of a man who's holding up a big sign
with three pictures on it.
And the sign says size of donut hole down through the years.
And then there's three pictures of donuts
in 1927, '37, and '48.
And there are just all these reports in the late 1940s
of this guy, Edward Velasca, going around America
and announcing that donut holes will be shrinking.
And that, he says, is because people
are getting dunked dimples from handling the existing size,
which I think meant if the hole's too big,
you leave a dent in your donut when you dip it.
- Pervert, pervert, pervert, pervert.
I'm sorry.
This is just a screen spread.
Also, this was the 1940s.
The world had big things on its plate.
- No longer.
- Nah, they've forgotten all that.
It was '47.
- First half of the '40s was a very stressful time.
- It was.
- But second half was donut city.
- No, you're right, people.
- Maybe he was in the war, and when peace comes,
I'm gonna get back to doing what I love.
- I'm thinking PTSD.
- This, actually, that was the most plausible explanation.
- It's all it holds, isn't it?
- It's a, kkkk.
- Oh, yes, of course.
- It's the D in PTSD for donut.
I didn't know that, I did not know that.
- So there's a great photo, isn't there,
of him holding up a board,
and he's pointing to three different donuts over the years.
- That's the one.
- That's the one in that, exactly.
And that photo, we have that thanks
to a Smithsonian collection of donut ephemera,
which is collected by Sally L. Steinberg.
She is the donut princess of America,
and she wrote a book.
- Self-appointed.
She wrote a book called The Donut Book,
The Origins, History, Literature, Law, Taste,
Etiquette, Traditions, Techniques, Varieties,
Mathematics, Mythology, Commerce, Philosophy,
Cuisine, and Glory of the Donut,
which I found a copy of, and it is insane.
It's an insane book, but it's so brilliantly researched.
And she's the person who has this photo
that we now know of as a result of her collection.
- Yeah, if you thought the Smithsonian
had very serious things in its collection, it doesn't.
It has donut ephemera from this girl,
who was the granddaughter of that.
I think the reason she calls herself a princess,
'cause she was the granddaughter of Adolf Levitt,
a refugee from Russia in the 1920s,
who made America's first donut machine.
So it got called The Donut King, and she's his offspring.
- 'Cause obviously Russia did away with the monarchy,
didn't they, in the start of the 20th century,
but they didn't figure for the donut monarchy, did they?
- Yeah, indeed.
They were chasing him down for decades, actually.
A lot of Stalin's resources went in, tracking him down.
- He was supposedly inspired,
so it goes back to the war, actually,
where people were cooking biscuits and dough,
and they were putting them on bayonets
and giving them out to soldiers,
so you would have the whole, so that you could kebab it.
That's, there's lots of stories
about how he had the inspiration.
That's one that's mentioned.
- I think it's definitely true
that they did have donuts in the war, though, isn't it?
In the First World War,
they had the Salvation Army volunteers
who went there on the front line,
and they just went there to make various sweet meats
and cakes and stuff,
but they realized that donuts, actually,
you don't really need many ingredients for them.
You don't need to bake them.
You can just cook them in oil,
so they're really easy to do right on the front line.
And I think the popularity of donuts,
people put it down to that
because the servicemen came home
and they kind of got a taste for the donut.
- Quite brave, these, they were called the dough lassies?
The Salvation Army, and there's some men in the tents as well,
the Salvation Army tents, and plenty of women, too,
and they were sort of looking after the American soldiers,
and sometimes they got shrapnel in the tents,
they were that close to the front lines, and yeah.
- That's how sprinkles were born.
(laughing)
- And didn't they, they used Stolder's helmets
as frying pan?
- As cooking pan.
- Really?
- They used bayonets to store the donuts on them.
- This is amazing.
The whole of war was just a donut production unit.
- It was, that was what it was for.
- Wait, is it a bayonet charge they're doing,
or are they just bringing us some lovely new donut?
- Is that a jam, or is it, yeah.
- Open your mouth, and cross your fingers.
No, they did, they said they used Stolder's helmets,
they'd asked for a Stolder's helmet to double up
as a frying pan, 'cause they didn't have
any of the equipment at first.
Well, this is what they claimed,
but I don't believe these women, because they also claim--
- Your cash price.
(laughing)
- There were two women who started it, really,
it was their idea, and Helen Pervience,
who was one of those, another Perv.
- Another Perv, yeah.
- She wrote that in one day,
her and her one colleague, Margaret,
who were making these in their frying pans,
using their shell casings as rolling pins,
she wrote they'd make in one day 2,500 donuts,
100 cupcakes, 50 pies, 800 pancakes,
and 255 gallons of cocoa,
which James, you've worked in catering.
- That's a lot.
- That's not possible.
- War catering, isn't it?
Can we talk about the mad donut myth,
I think this is not true of donuts in general.
- Okay, go on, 'cause I'm gonna counter it,
I think it might be true.
- Oh, okay, while we're in New England,
they had been brought over as oily cooks,
which is the Dutch word meaning oily cakes,
cakes were cooked in oil,
and then in New England,
there was a woman called Elizabeth Gregory,
and her son was a ship's captain,
and she wanted to feed him,
you know, keep him well fed at sea and all of that,
and she put nuts in the center of the little cake she made,
there was dough in the middle, dough, nuts, donuts,
and supposedly her son, Hanson Gregory,
put the hole in donuts,
because he was a ship's captain,
he was at the wheel having one of his snacks,
a terrible storm blew up,
he was trying to control this big ship's wheel,
he jams his donut on the wheel.
- Are you deliberately making up extra stuff now?
- This is the story.
- He skews it on the ship's wheel to control the donut,
while he's, you know, helming with it.
- It makes total sense.
- He's trying to control the ship and keep his lovely donut.
- I actually think, Andy,
that you were not going to go down any of this rope,
but as soon as I said that, I believe it,
you thought, right, what is the most ridiculous thing
that I could possibly say?
- What's the back end of that story?
They make it through the storm,
he removes the donuts,
and everyone goes, what's that?
- I think that's it.
- Is that it?
- He did claim that he had made the hole himself,
but he claimed he'd done it on purpose,
rather than jamming it on the wheel later.
- Yeah, with good reason,
because it wasn't cooking properly on the inside.
- So I'm skeptical about Elizabeth Gregory
put the nuts in the middle,
but I think he just said it wasn't cooking right
on the inside, so I thought, take the inside out,
and then it cooks right.
- I'm with Anna, I think the nut thing doesn't make sense,
because the word nut just means a cake,
like ginger nuts or biscuits or whatever,
but the fact that it was invented by him
and he put the hole in, the dates do work.
- Okay, okay.
- So it definitely was invented somewhere around New England,
and it was definitely around that time
when we first see donuts with holes in.
And he was really proud of it, like if he didn't do it,
he really embraced the idea that he did.
- He definitely thought he did.
- He did, or he wanted to convince the world.
And he would say, when an interviewer asked him in 1916,
when he was 85 years old, how he felt about it,
was he pleased when he got the results
of this first donut ever that he made?
He said, "Was Columbus pleased when he landed in America?"
- What year was that?
- That was 19-- - 1492.
- It was 1916, and I know what you're gonna say.
We have bigger fish to fry.
- Another period of total war,
which for America at the time--
- For America at a healthy and time of peace.
- Do you know the idea of dunking donuts,
very big in America, not sure if it's massive here,
is it massive here?
- Do you mean the shop or the--
- I mean the act itself of doing it.
- It's not, I don't think it's a big thing here.
- But in America, it was, and there's a lot of theories
about who was the first person to do it,
where it came from.
- It was a ship's captain who's donut fell overboard
during the Boston Tea Party.
This is delicious.
- Well, the donut princess has put forward a few theories
in the donut book.
One is that she said that it began in the Civil War,
it was inspired by soldiers dunking hardtack into coffee,
hardtack being a type of biscuit
that they would put in or a cracker.
But then there's this other theory
that Hollywood actress who was really big called May Murray,
so namesake of you, Andy.
She was sitting in a cafe, she was holding her donut
and it slipped out of her fingers and fell into her coffee
and she picked it out.
And the person with her did the same thing
to make it look like it was intentional.
And because so many people were watching,
they went, "Wow, what's that?"
And it became a fad off the back of this famous actress.
- Wouldn't you love to be a person
who was famous or respected or feared enough
that you could do something really stupid
and it became copied and trendy?
- The other day I was playing golf
and someone said to me halfway around,
"Oh, your flies are undone."
Imagine if the next day you come into central London
and everyone's got their flies in.
- Yeah, exactly. - That's the dream, isn't it?
- That doesn't happen, there'll be many examples of that.
- You know, in our, a bit of behind the scenes
inside baseball here, you know our Google document
where we put what subjects we've researched each week
so that we don't go in different directions.
We all spelt the word "donut" differently, right?
And I spelt it the American way, D-O-N-U-T,
because I just think everyone knows what you mean
and it just saves a few characters.
- Same time, yeah.
- But the interesting thing about that, I think,
is the original spelling was D-O-N-O-T-E-S, for donuts.
- Donut days. - Donuties.
- Donut days, yes. - And that's from 1782.
And then we have donuts with D-O-U-G-H, nuts,
which is the British way of spelling it.
And that's kind of takes over and becomes the main thing.
And then the spelling D-O-N-U-T,
which is how Americans spell it.
There's a journalist called Kate Taylor
for Business Insider who looked at this
and found that basically,
if you look at where Dunkin' Donuts opens throughout America,
you can see where the spelling changes.
And spelling basically changes wherever Dunkin' Donuts goes.
People start spelling it that way.
- They used to spell it with the "U-G-H" in the middle.
- And obviously now Dunkin' Donuts is ubiquitous in America,
so everyone spells it any time.
- That makes sense because you're in all the old newspaper archives,
the Americans are spelling it with a "G-H".
But I must admit, I put it in our public doc,
public to the four of us with a "G-H",
but in my private notes, it's too much effort
to put those extra three letters in and I just got it out.
- Get out. - Sorry.
- It's amazing. - We keep saying Dunkin' Donuts.
Do you know in America it's no longer called that?
It's now just called Dunkin'.
They've lost the donuts.
And I think it's largely because as the donut ambassador,
not weighed in, the donut archduke, not made a statement.
- Well, it sounds like they don't sell as many donuts
as they used to back in the day.
They're largely a coffee and restaurant place.
Dunkin' is what they're called colloquially,
you know, that people just say, "Let's go to Dunkin'".
So it's gone, but except globally,
we've still got it as Dunkin' Donuts.
- I think we should not leave out
the world's leading donut consuming country in this.
- San Marino. - San Marino.
- And that's by Shea Volly, but it's not per person.
It's just, that's amazing.
- No, I've seen the claim in various places
that it's actually Canada.
- Yeah, I saw that.
It's amazing that, isn't it?
- Really?
- Tim Hortons is the chain.
- He's a hockey player.
- Yes, now, sadly, no longer with us.
I don't know. - Related to the--
- No, I don't believe so.
I don't believe so.
But yeah, it's a big-- - He used to skate over
and he would put donuts on the end of his ice skates.
- Well, they can be dangerous.
In the Donut Princesses book, she cites a few times
where donuts can lead to major issues
under a title called What Can Donuts Do?
On the highway, I saw a man stuff a chocolate
donut in his mouth.
Then his car skidded into two cars
for a three car crackup.
So just a word of warning.
- That's a donut fault, that, isn't it?
- What are the chances of the Donut Princesses
watching you in a car eating a donut,
leading to a crash, right?
What's her outfit like?
- That's probably what put him up when he was driving.
He's like, "My God, that woman's dressed
in just two donuts over her nipples."
- That would be such a bad nipple cover
'cause it would be the only bit that it didn't turn.
Didn't cover, wouldn't it?
- That's what makes it sexy.
And you get the nipple access.
- I was reading that.
Have you guys come across this thing that in France,
anything that is a sweet fried cake
has the nickname of nuns fart?
- Really?
- I think nun fart is a specific thing.
- That's a specific cake, I think.
It's so light and airy that it's like a nun's fart.
- It's like a profiterole, isn't it?
- Oh, that's not the story that I read.
- Oh, God.
- Okay, according to the Donut Princesses, the--
- Okay, now, because we know what nuns fart is,
now I'm thinking that maybe not everything
the Donut Princesses saying it might be true.
- So, no, she definitely saw someone crash a car
after eating a chocolate donut.
She says that a long time ago,
there was a nun called Agnes,
and Agnes and her fellow nuns were in the kitchen
making some stuff,
and one of them had some sweet dough on a spoon,
and Agnes farted really loud,
and it made the other nun laugh so much
that she dropped the dough into the water
with the oil in it, frying it, and what?
This is the Smithsonian's leading doughnut ephemera expert
who is putting this in her brilliant book,
and yeah, and so that became the byword for you,
it's a nun's fart because it inspired the dish.
- In which religious tract did the nuns
record this for posterity?
One of us has got to write this moment down.
- That's very funny, yeah.
I thought it was just 'cause it was a lovely light cake,
but now I realize it's because of Agnes,
specific incident, my goodness.
- Agnes the nun.
- Why do cops like doughnuts?
- That's the myth, isn't it?
- Yeah. - In America?
- I don't think it's a myth.
- They do buy doughnuts.
- Yeah, they do.
- Why?
- 'Cause they've got, they have like a deal,
do they get like 20% off every purchase?
- No.
- If you're on a, like a stakeout,
might be the last day on the force.
- Yeah.
- But you're having to sit out there for 24 hours
while the hoodlums are doing whatever they do inside.
- That's it, can you hang it round your gun?
- Is it, is it so messy?
- I was in the middle of a bit of whimsy here at the house.
- Oh, sorry, sorry, sorry, I got too excited.
- They're tired, so they need to drink coffee
and what goes with coffee doughnuts?
- Well, not far off actually, yeah.
Sort of irritating, considering it was whimsy.
No, basically it was, the sort of,
the idea of it comes from the '50s.
It was when cops were often on the late night beat
and they were the only snacks available.
They were the only shops open a lot of the time
'cause they have a morning rush
and they would have to stay up late baking away
for the morning.
So it was one of the only options available to them.
- I want James's 'Women's Call the Wire' version.
I want that to continue rather than that.
A quite mundane to be honest explanation for, yeah.
- Sorry, yeah.
- Can you make something better up,
like the doughnut princess?
- Sorry, my guys, my guys are tired now.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that scientists
are using poetry from the past to protect porpoises.
- Beautifully illiterated.
Is that the most illiterative fact we've ever had?
Do you think?
- I think so, yeah.
- If it had been to protect slugs,
would you have still put it forward as a fact?
- I would have still said the word scientist at the start
but the rest of it might have been different.
(laughing)
- Sonnet, from the 17th century to save slugs.
- Anyway, sorry, porpoises, porpoises.
- Yeah, so this is a team
from the Chinese Academy of Sciences
and they looked at 700 ancient Chinese poems
dating back nearly 2000 years
and then they've managed to work out the habitat
that has been lost in the time, which is extensive.
- So is it like someone in the fifth century
writes a poem saying,
oh, I saw a great porpoise over here
and it reminded me of--
- Yeah, so we know where on the Yangtze River,
so this is all on the Yangtze River in China,
that we know where they will have lived,
where they will have written, where they will have visited
and they write about porpoises
because porpoises are really big, they're really obvious,
they're quite active on the surface of the water.
Especially when there's thunderstorms,
they kind of jump around and try and catch fish
and so that's obviously quite a moment
for someone to write poetry about.
So, yeah, there's lots of examples of it in history
and they've kind of mapped it out
and then they looked at actual science
and they said, yeah, it's the same
as what actual science says.
- That's really cool.
- So it kind of fills in the gaps a little bit.
- Yeah, it's brilliant.
- That's nice.
- One of the poets was an emperor.
It was one of the, yeah, he was--
- Was it a stoner emperor?
(laughing)
- Qianlong, he was sailing across the Yangtze River
and yeah, he wrote,
"Porpuses chased moonlight on silvered tides
"as dragons summoned storm clouds loom in sight."
And that was used as part of the--
- Very cool.
And of course, dragons have died out now as well, haven't they?
So, that is one of the problems
because a lot of the things that people wrote
were metaphorical, so you're not always,
you have to kind of read the poem, understand the poem
and then work out, are they talking about a porpoise
that they've seen or are they talking about a long lost love?
- Yeah, particularly in China, you're right.
All of this stuff is like Qianlong himself,
he had a concubine who was called the Fragrant Concubine
and she's--
- Doesn't say much for the rest of the concubines.
(laughing)
- So, he may, I'll go for the Fragrant one again.
He was overseas and he smelt her and he was like,
"Oh my God, I've never smelt anything like you before."
He was like, "Oh, he didn't smell her from overseas."
He was overseas, yeah.
- Was she also overseas though?
- Yeah, obviously, he was next to her guys.
He was next to her.
- I'm imagining, he saw a picture of her smelling
like a cartoon character floats towards her.
(laughing)
- Well, he fell in love with her
and he was like, "I must make her one of my concubines."
And the deal was struck and she came back
and she was bathed in camel's milk all the way
as she was coming back to make sure
that her fragrance remained there.
- Preserved the fragrance.
- Yeah, but then we don't know if she was real or not.
- That suggests that she smelled like camel's milk,
doesn't it?
- Hang on, wait, what's the porpoise
and she was called known as the Fragrant Porpoise Woman?
- No, no, no, I was saying that all these metaphors,
dragons and so on were used, like even in his life,
we have a concubine who's written about
and we don't know if she was real or not.
- I see.
- It's sort of a mythic road.
- Yeah, maybe I've been misunderstanding poetry
all my life so far, but sometimes when I read poems,
I don't assume that it's all based
in scientific historical facts.
- Well, it depends on the poet, doesn't it?
Philip Larkin, if he says I found a hedgehog,
you sort of trust that.
These ones are finless porpoises, aren't they?
- Yes.
- Which are very cool.
I believe the only freshwater porpoise in the world,
every other kind lives out at sea.
And porpoises are just a family of toothed whales,
small whales, basically.
But finless really gave me pause
and I was really surprised to read that.
And it turns out they do, I was thinking they would,
how do they move?
- They're just like a sausage.
- They're just like a sort of gray sausage in the water.
It turns out they just don't have a dorsal fin on their back.
Yeah, they do have flippers on the front.
- Interesting.
- Yes.
- Oh, yes, yes.
- I find it really interesting and very surprising
having read this, that dolphins and porpoises
are not the two most closely related animals to each other.
- Oh, what?
- Isn't that weird?
Well, you would think that who is most closely related
to a porpoise, a dolphin, absolutely.
But actually it's not that at all, is it?
- Who is it?
- No, a hedgehog.
- It's the other toothed whales, basically.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Looks-wise, I feel quite bad for them
'cause they're basically confated with dolphins.
And essentially, whenever they're described,
they're like fat, snub-nosed, spayed-toothed dolphins.
That's why when you're like,
what's the difference between a porpoise and a dolphin?
It's like a dolphin has a beautiful, elegant long nose.
Porpoise has this squashed thing.
- I think they're charming.
- And they're stocky.
They're stocky, though.
Come on, they're broad, aren't they?
- They're all stocky, they're the long nose.
- When will you see a thin dolphin, yuck?
- Have you guys seen, there's a Wikipedia page
which is sort of known for its joke.
So it's the list of cetaceans
and it's got all the whales, dolphins
and porpoises listed down.
- Like a cetacean-needed kind of thing.
- Exactly.
So what they have is that they have the name
of the animal and then they'll say,
how many are in the wild?
And then they have a photo
and if they're missing a photo, they say, cetacean-needed.
- Oh, that's very good.
- It's very good.
And the list, I think, used to have more,
but it's down to one now.
It's just got one cetacean-needed,
which is the Durrani-Yagala's Beaked Whale.
And there are photos out there,
but just no one's put one on Wikipedia.
So if anyone out there wants to fill the final cetacean-needed.
- And spoil the joke.
- Wow.
- Is that the reason they haven't put it up?
'Cause they want to keep the joke?
- That's what I was thinking.
But it's pretty depressing reading as well, by the way,
despite the really great gag,
because it does show how many are left in the wild
with certain porpoises and dolphins and whales,
and it's really scary.
- These ones are down to about 1,200.
They've had a very, very slight bounce back,
but the numbers are still so much lower
than they were even 30 years ago.
It's 'cause the Yanksie has a lot of sand mining,
much of it illegal, and it obviously just completely
messes up their habitat, you know?
- Yeah.
- The Vaquita is probably the worst, right?
- In a good way.
- Yeah.
There was how many do we reckon about a dozen?
In 2021, the estimate was 10 porpoises
remaining in the wild.
The problem is that there's a fish called the totoaba,
and their swim bladders are very popular in Chinese medicine.
They're known as aquatic cocaine.
- They go for like $50,000 per bladder.
- It's mental.
- It's insane.
- Is that the Vaquita?
- No, that's the totoaba.
So people fish for that fish,
and then they end up damaging the Vaquita.
- The fishing nets just happened.
They're the same size.
- But the Vaquitas live off Mexico.
- Yeah.
- But it's crazy that a demand for something in China
is messing up species.
- The Chinese ones, they used to have similar fish in China,
but they died out, and so they go to the Mexican ones instead.
- Chinese medicine does have quite a lot to answer,
doesn't it?
When you read about extinctions,
there's a lot of animals.
- I gotta say though, the prices, they are eye-watering.
And you can kind of see where the poachers
are coming from, kind of curious.
- Oh, I'd do it.
I'd kill the last day in a heartbeat.
That's gonna get me a million dollars.
- It's mental how expensive they are for a swim bladder.
- Yeah.
- That's crazy.
- And also, maybe they're all experts,
but I wouldn't be able to tell totoaba swim bladder
from a cod swim bladder.
- No, you're right.
There's in fact, do you know what, guys?
There's money to be made here in faking swim bladders,
and we'll protect the Vaquita at the same time.
- Oh, great.
All right, we'll head to shop
at nosuchthingasfish.com.
(all laughing)
Oh my God.
Can we talk about the harbour porpoise, please?
'Cause that one's not doing so badly
in endangerment terms, relatively.
And they are amazing.
So, this is a thing specifically about their mating.
And if you wanna see a harbour porpoise mate,
there's one place in the world to go.
And it's the Golden Gate Bridge.
Ah, 'cause they hang out in the sort of narrow
channels of water under that very romantic, and you just--
- When you say one place,
is this like the Sargato Sea for eels?
All harbour porpoises from all around the world,
congregate under the Golden Gate Bridge.
- No, no, no, it's just a good place
'cause you have a great vantage point
through the slats like a pervert, basically.
And it's called the funnel of love
is where these channels are that they mate.
- Cool.
- Did you guys read about the mating process?
- No.
- It's crazy.
It takes one second, okay?
So, basically, the female will surface for air.
That's her big mistake.
She very briefly swims along the surface,
at which point a nearby male
will just prang himself at her like a torpedo,
approaching 100% of the time from the left-hand side,
that's important.
The female has about half a second to assess
whether she wants to raise this male's offspring,
and either twist towards him or away from him, basically.
So, if it goes wrong, he just goes,
"Beyoing," bounces off,
corkscrews out of the water, it goes off.
And if it goes right,
then there's a very, very, very quick coupling,
and then--
- For a second.
- For a one second,
and then she might well be pregnant.
But it's really interesting,
is this evolutionary race going on,
the male's penis is very asymmetrical,
and it might be because males have worked out
the optimal angle to approach from,
to give themselves a chance,
and the female's reproductive tract is very complicated,
potentially because the female's trying to,
in evolutionary terms,
have a bit more control over this procedure,
and scientists have worked all this out.
The males have approached from that side
to get around the vaginal folding.
- So, you could tell, if you were a female,
and you turned around,
you'd know that this person's interested in you,
because of the angle they're coming at.
- Well, he's swimming towards you with a penis,
a third of the length of his body, very, very fast.
So, like, the signals are not mixed.
This is not a--
- This is not a rubbing, thicky moment.
- And their testes go massive.
They've got big testicles in breeding season.
The total body mass can go in the testes,
can be represented as four to six percent of their body weight.
- It'll be three kilos for you, Deb.
- Yes.
- Nice.
- Like, 'cause four to six percent doesn't sound much,
but then three kilos would be a...
How much is that?
Like, at least twice as much.
- Well, I'd have to contact my tailor.
(both laughing)
- Yeah, bad news, though, for harvopopsis in Britain,
we have some pollutants called PCBs,
polychlorinated biphenyls,
and they were used in, like, old light bulbs
and hydraulic fluids and stuff like that,
but they're used for many, many years.
They're banned now, but they're still in the environment.
And if a harper has too much of that,
then the testes will shrink.
- Oh, no.
- Another thing about harvopopsis
that I think this might explain why
they can only make for one second
is 'cause they have to be eating all the time.
- Oh, really?
- So they live in cold water,
which requires lots and lots of energy,
and they're quite small.
And so they can only eat really small fish.
And so they need just hundreds of them.
And there's a study that found that they can hunt
up to 550 fish per hour.
- Oh, gosh.
- And they have a 90% hunting success rate as well,
which I think is up there with dragonflies,
which I think we've said are the most successful hunters.
But yeah, if you're eating 500 fish an hour,
you just don't really have time
to do anything else at all.
- And you're saying they have to be eating
just to maintain their body weight?
- Yes, I think they lose,
they would lose 10% of their body weight a day
if they didn't eat.
So they die very quickly, they disappear.
- Gosh.
- I know, what an easy diet, though.
Imagine if you were told you were going to lose
10% of your body weight a day if you didn't eat.
And please, please.
- 'Cause then pick up the sea that they've got in them.
- I can still imagine it getting to about 5 p.m.
and me seeing that key line,
pie-end operation thinking I'll start tomorrow.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is in Canada,
tractor tires are filled up with vegetable juice.
This is so interesting.
It's a ballast thing.
So you've got tractors with the center of gravity's way off
and you could tip over, that's very, very dangerous.
So you need to counter that weight now.
So instead of putting air into these giant back tires,
beet juice is something that is used a lot.
And for various reasons,
one is that in Canada gets very cold.
If you put water in there, that could freeze.
So that's really bad for the whole tractor in its own right.
So they use this because it can get really cold
and not freeze.
- And you've got a, yet you put a straw in,
nice little drink on a cold day.
- I just want to say as well,
like ballast is not just used to stop you tipping,
it's to give you grip.
So let's say it's a really muddy day or even an icy day
and you want to get your tractor to go down a muddy field,
then you need the weight in your tires to help you get grip.
- Yeah. - Lovely.
- Ethylene glycol is used as well,
but the problem is that is toxic.
So if it leaks out of the tire,
animals around who are eating it can die.
So they don't like to use that.
And then windshield washer fluid is used.
That's very good as well.
Yeah, that's very good as well.
- I didn't think you got windshield water fluid
in that quantity.
- Well, you don't really get juice in that quantity either.
So you've got to go to specialist places to get it.
- That's a very good point.
- I think windscreen fluid is also flammable.
- Oh, cool, I mean, not cool, but you know.
- So that's another reason why you might want to go
for the beach juice. - Oh, dangerous.
There we go, I've retaken that.
We should say just a little shout out
to the commercial name for this beach juice,
which is Rim Guard.
- Yes. - The heaviest.
- The heaviest non-corrosive tire ballast on the market.
And I went to their website and the two options are
find a dealer of Rim Guard or become a dealer.
I thought I was incredibly tempted to click onto a book.
Anyway, would anyone like to buy,
if any listeners would like to buy
300,000 gallons of Rim Guard, please contact me.
- I wonder why you came in such a big overcoat today.
- I've got a bit of Rim Guard, mate.
- God, your rims got mad.
- Anyway, tractors, tractors.
- Invented, I think, in Britain.
- Ooh, couldn't agree more.
- Britain, Britain, Britain, all right.
Probably the first version of them was,
you would get two traction engines,
two big steam engines on either side of your field,
and you put a big rope between the two of them,
and then you would attach something to the rope,
like a plowing machine, and you would pull it
from one side of the field to the other.
And that was before we had any kind of tractors,
like we know them today.
- I think that's a good shout, yeah, traction engines.
- Yeah, yeah.
There's a real mystery about the tractor,
which is why it took so long to catch on,
and it comes up a lot in conversations
about what we can expect from them.
- With Andy.
(laughing)
- So it's often used in chats about how long
we should expect driverless cars to catch on,
why isn't AI moving as fast as we think it is?
You know, a new technology comes along.
Everyone says, as they did in the 1910s,
when tractors came along basically,
like to mechanize farming, everyone said,
well, this is gonna revolutionize farming immediately
and completely replace horses.
And incredibly, by 1942, in Britain,
horses still outnumbered tractors by 30 to one
on British farms.
It took until the late 1950s for tractors
to overtake horses, so that's like half a century.
And yeah, it's an example of slow diffusion,
where everyone said, this is it, end of horses.
- And actually horses are just really good,
'cause they're flexible and they don't use up fuel.
- They don't use fuel, there was a depression,
so people didn't really have the money
to make the big tractor investments at the time,
but they did have the money to employ some bloke
to look after the horses, 'cause labor was cheap.
They weren't that good at first,
like they didn't have pneumatic tires,
so they just sank in the mud quite a lot.
- Right, yes, the tires were solid rubber
or solid metal, in some cases.
They were not very useful.
This is a really interesting thing
about the change it made.
So in 1910, the USA had 25 million horses
and mules on its farms.
By 1960, there were three million left,
so that is a huge decline,
and they'd been replaced by five million tractors,
'cause one tractor can do the work of lots of horses,
basically.
- But in 1963 million, I find it still really surprising.
- Yeah. - That's happening.
- America's big, isn't it?
But in 1910, this is the other thing
that tractors changed.
One in three Americans worked on a farm.
- Wow. - One in three.
By 2010, a century later,
it was 2% of the workforce worked on a farm.
- 1910, that's wild.
- It is.
It's a massive shift over the last hundred years,
and the same will be true in lots of other countries,
obviously, you know.
- I'm surprised it's one in 50 now.
- Yeah.
- When you think how big cities are
and how much population lives in cities.
- Yeah, get more tractors, lads.
Why is it all hand pulling these plows?
- Well, that might be including people
who work on farm shops and things, I don't know.
- Yeah, people who work in the Whole Foods
probably can't serve them.
- No doubt, that's technically agriculture, yeah.
- You've got the Amish, of course,
who don't love using tractors,
so they're doing a lot of it.
You know, that probably takes quite a lot of labour.
But I was looking into the Amish's use of tractors,
'cause you picture an Amish horse and cart, right?
And you picture a horse drawn plow.
- So these are the people
who don't like to use any technology?
- Yes. - Are they in Pennsylvania?
- Yep. - Okay.
- So I--
- Big shout out to our Amish listeners, we should say.
- Yeah, I'm pro this.
So they don't use tractors.
- Do they use podcasts?
- I think there's quite a lot of variety
within the Amish community.
And I think if you're at the quite technological end,
you might be listening to a podcast right now.
- Well, write in if you're Amish
and you listen and tell us how.
- Please do, write in with your quill.
(all laughing)
- Just get us on TikTok, guys.
- But they don't use tractors
just because they think it's a slippery slope to cars,
basically.
- Well, the ballast means it's not a slippery slope.
Maybe they haven't discovered the vegetable oil in which case.
So there's lots of Amish websites that say
you'll have a tractor on your farm
and it'll run little errands,
it'll carry hay bales around,
it will fill up silo,
but don't use it in the fields
'cause then you'll get a taste
for how good they are at driving.
And the next thing is you'll be on the roads.
And actually a lot of Amish people use the old tractors
with just the metal tires
because they really damage roads.
So that's to remove the temptation.
So if you've just got metal,
what are they called those spikes
that you have for proper traction on old metal tires?
- Winter tires.
- Lugs, lugs.
Then you can't get onto a road 'cause you're ruining it.
So you're stuck in your field.
- Right.
- Anyway, I thought, you know, that's interesting.
- That's certainly how I got into driving.
I started in a tractor
and now I'm knee deep in Maserati's, that's a nightmare.
- Well, that's the original Lamborghini was a tractor.
- Right.
- So Ferruccio Lamborghini founded his tractor company
way before he founded it as a car company.
- So he's slippery slope.
- They still make them though 'cause on Clarkson's farm,
he has a Lamborghini tractor.
- Yeah.
And he got really rich after selling a lot of them.
And so he started buying nice expensive cars
and he bought a Ferrari.
And he was really annoyed with how the clutch worked
in one of his Ferraris.
And he was also really annoyed that when he pointed it out,
the sales team were just really bad with him.
So he got into an argument with Enzo Ferrari
and said, you need to make this better.
And he said, go away.
And so he went, I will, and I will invent my own car,
which is better version of your car.
So the Lamborghini was built to spite the Ferrari.
It's a proper rivalry, but it started with tractors.
- I read a guy, there's a book called Lamborghini Supercar
Supreme, which was written by like a big historian
of this time.
And they think, even though Lamborghini said
that this is what happened, and even Ferrari said
this is what happened, they reckon it probably
didn't happen.
And it was all marketing stuff that that's.
- Well, I killed the joy of the story.
- I know, sorry.
- We can accept that these two people might have
raced down the story, but they've said it.
- And then they attached donuts to the exhaust pipe.
Lamborghini, a lot of these people actually started
because they were into car racing.
And Lamborghini was into car racing
for a very short amount of time.
He entered one of his early cars into the 1947
Mila Miglia road event.
And two thirds of the way through the race,
he crashed into a cafe and never raced again.
And apparently he crashed his car into the cafe.
And the cafe owner was like discombobulated.
And he said, I'll have a glass of wine, please.
- Brilliant.
- To toast the end of my racing career.
- And they didn't give him a glass of wine, did they?
- Well, it's a cafe, it depends on what time of day it was.
And what their license is.
- Oh, if it's in Italy.
- You think even if someone's crashed their sort of
tractor race car through the wall of your cafe,
you're serving them wine?
- I think I would do that because then I'd be to the police.
Look, he's been drinking.
(all laughing)
But I think all of these are kind of slightly
exaggerated stories.
- They're all worthy of the doughnut princess herself.
Can I talk about my tractor hero?
We've all got one.
Robert William Thompson, he was a Scottish engineer.
He made the first mechanical road haulage vehicle.
It was a steam traction engine.
So he invented the pneumatic tire in the 1840s.
Really before there were decent roads for a pneumatic tire.
Also before there were cars.
And in fact, really before there were bikes.
So he invented something that the world wasn't yet ready for.
- Right.
- So, and he--
- Running around with a steering wheel going.
I don't think I can do with this.
- It's gonna change the world.
And he invented it, but there was a lack of demand,
as I've said, and the rubber was really expensive.
So he couldn't make it commercial.
And so he went off and invented the self-filling fountain pen
instead.
- Oh, wow.
- It was such a great inventor and engineer.
And he had invented these tires and he tried them
in Regent's Park.
There was a big trial of two carriages next to each other.
One with pneumatic tires, one without.
And the pneumatic tire one was much nicer to ride in
and much more smooth and comfortable.
But yeah, there just wasn't the demand.
- If you, like, let's say you know how to make cars,
which I certainly don't know how to do that,
but a lot of people do.
And you think, okay, well, I've also made a time travel machine.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go back to the time
before cars, and I'm gonna make the first car.
And I'm gonna be, you know, my kids will be billionaires.
You can't go back too far, can you?
You have to go back to the time
just before the first one was made.
Because if you do go back too far, they don't have roads.
- You're right.
The conditions need to be in place.
Otherwise, you'd then have to invent the road.
And you don't know how to invent the road.
- Look would have it.
You brought a fountain pen with you.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
That is Andy.
My fact is that if civilization comes to an end,
one of the best places to be is a cafe
in Fort Mason, San Francisco.
- Mm-hmm.
- Is that so?
You got a good view of the poppers shagging.
You're gonna have to occupy yourself in the aftertimes.
That's gonna be one of the few things that is entertaining.
(laughing)
No, this is quite a cool thing.
It's a library that's called the Manual for Civilization.
And it's a collection of three and a half thousand books,
basically, which contain the operating instructions
for Earth, how you would start civilization again
from scratch if you had to.
And it's run by this organization called the Long Now,
who are, they're quite sort of eccentric,
but they say we need to be focusing
on the next 10,000 years, you know,
we've got problems with intermediate,
but actually we've got to preserve civilization.
- Yeah, yeah, I'm not gonna do my recycling
because what's gonna happen in 10,000 years?
- Yeah, exactly, exactly.
So it was a phrase that was coined,
I think unknowingly by Brian Eno, the musician.
He was talking with Stuart Brand
and a few other guys who are the founders of the Long Now.
And they were saying all the stuff about,
remember how back in the day,
people used to talk about the year 2000
and all the like, what's going on in the year two?
And we don't do that.
We don't talk about the year 3000
in the way that they would talk about.
- I think not much has changed,
but we live under water.
(laughing)
I think philosophers have talked about this for years.
- That's a huge change as well.
The infrastructural changes.
How do you mean not much change?
(laughing)
How do trades work under water?
What are you saying?
Okay, Buzz has been talking about it,
but not many other people.
But yeah, so like in the Long Now Foundation,
for example, we're not living in the year 2025,
we're living in the year 2020-25.
- I really like, it's quite teenage to do.
They were founded in '09, 1996.
- I mean, everything that I read about these guys,
it does sound like teenagers
who have just read a book for the first time go,
ah, but dude, what about this?
- Well, Stuart Brand, the founder,
he's part of that old counterculture America.
He was part of LSD and all that.
He had these big hippie ideas of changing the world.
And so he's, yeah, those little things,
I think they were a bit sort of hippie-ish in their ideas.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I mean, there's a very good thing to be focusing on.
Obviously, I mean, it's largely what responsible people
who look to the future do focus on,
but what I quite like is that this cafe,
which has the big library in it, doesn't it?
So the cafe is called The Interval,
and it was founded with such great ideals,
and it reminded me a little bit,
and I say this with complete fondness,
of QI actually set up its own bar many years ago.
And I'm sure many other people have done this,
thought I'm gonna set up a cafe,
but the idea is that everyone's gonna have
amazing conversations.
So the idea of this cafe is everyone will be discussing
topics relating to long-term thinking,
how to save the world in 10,000 years,
and you go to the TripAdvisor reviews,
and the only thing they say is,
"God, the cocktails are good."
- Oh, really?
(laughing)
- And that was true of the QI club as well.
- Yeah.
- The cocktails were amazing.
I wanna just say on the record that I disagree.
I think we should be looking at the problems
that are immediate and deal with those,
and I don't think we should be saying,
"Yeah, we don't need to save the purposes
"because we need to worry about what we're doing
"in 10,000 years."
- I think that's a fair point.
- It's just a lot easier to kick it down the road, I think.
- Oh, I think to be fair, that is what they're about.
I don't think that, I don't think they're saying,
let's forget about it,
they're looking to extend ourselves to 10,000 years.
- Yeah.
- You don't think so?
- Well, it's hard to allocate your resources,
like the stuff that the world is losing now,
like biodiversity and things like that,
I think is a really, really immediate,
impressive concern.
And then you have to preserve it for a long time,
but sometimes like,
you have to put out the fire that's burning now,
rather than say, "Hey, maybe this fire will spread, man."
- Yeah. - No, sorry,
that's not how it's done. - No, I'm just saying
that Stuart Brown, he created the Whole Earth Catalog.
- What is the Whole Earth Catalog?
- It was an idea of going, where are we now?
What do we need to look at?
How do we save things?
It's a big collaboration project.
- Well, explain this, Dan.
Why are they building a clock in a Texas mountain,
which will function for the next 10,000 years,
and which you won't be able to visit?
- Well, you mean the one that was conceived
by a millionaire funded by the world's richest man,
and built in his private space pot inside his mountain?
- That's right.
- Well, that does sound like it'll help us in the long term.
- Okay, guys, when you put it like that,
now I sound like a horrible man.
- No, no, no, Jeff Bezos has funded it.
It's simply called The Clock, and--
- That's not what I call him.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, and Brian Nino's involved in that, too.
- Yeah, yeah, he's a founding member of--
- I think it like, ticks once a year or something, does it?
I remember reading about it.
Like, as in, instead of ticking once a second,
it ticks once a year,
and the cuckoo comes out once every millennium or something.
I think that was the original thing,
but for some reason they changed it,
and it plays a tone every 1,000 years instead of the cuckoo.
But originally they were gonna go for the cuckoo,
probably because they thought,
well, the cuckoo have died out by then,
and we don't give a fuck about that.
- They're not about saving stuff now.
They are about whatever's in charge in 10,000 years, save that.
- It's more about the idea,
is to change your manner of thinking,
not think about the modern day,
just about what's happening today and tomorrow,
but to think in the long term, that's their idea.
- Yeah. - Okay.
Like, you know, go on a diet today,
and next week you'll feel better,
rather than eat chocolate today.
- Well, they would be more like,
well, maybe I should buy some really, really big clothes,
because I'm not gonna have a diet for a while,
but I know that in 20 years' time,
I'm gonna be morbidly obese.
- That's actually a really good,
you should start marketing big clothes.
- This library has 3,500 books, as mentioned.
I found a list of some of the books that are in there,
'cause they are interesting.
What are the books that are rebuilding?
- So please tell me that the princess's book is in there.
(laughing)
- There's Dirt, The Erosion of Civilizations.
There's six Ian M. Bank novels.
- They have quite a lot of sci-fi,
as you might expect from some sci-fi thinkers.
- But I was talking to a scientist the other day,
who said that a lot of scientific ideas are inspired
by reading nothing but science fiction.
So they are valuable things, I think.
- Completely, but I think they haven't chosen
all the books yet.
As of the year '0, 2014,
they only had about 1,400 nominations for their library,
and of those 200 were sci-fi.
And I just think, if you need a book
on how to build a water wheel,
and you've accidentally got all five Dune novels
in your way, or Dune is in there.
- I know all sorts of courses in there.
- They will be useful for kindling.
- Yeah, that's true.
- I wonder if they have The Buck.
- Ooh, The Buck. - Have you guys heard of The Buck?
- What's that?
- This was the third most successful
Kickstarter campaign of all time.
It's a book that I own as well, I have one.
It's 2.3 kilograms, so almost as heavy as Dan's testicles
if he was a corpus.
And it was written by a group of escape room designers.
And the idea is this one book will help you
restart civilization if you have it.
So on the first page, it tells you how to make string,
and how to start fire, and how to make wheels.
And then it goes all the way to the last pages,
which tells you how to play football,
and how to make sex toys, and stuff like that.
- Well, ironically, my testicles are the other thing
you need to restart civilization.
So that's true.
- That book and my balls are the--
- The sex toy that they came up with
was a five foot tall fountain, and you pour water into it.
And as the water goes down, it creates a vacuum
that makes a sucking action on a handy attachment
that you can attach to yourself.
- Do you need the fountain?
I mean, is that the best way of creating that suction?
With the technology you've got after reading the book?
- Well, to be honest, they do tell you
how to make electricity and stuff in the book.
So I'm not sure why, 'cause this is right at the end,
they do this, but yeah.
- They probably had a few pages left, and they thought,
well, we've got to fill up the book somehow.
So we may as well, you know.
- It's a great book though.
- It does sound really interesting.
I know that it's not dealing with the immediate problems
facing the world.
I do find it quite interesting.
- It is interesting, the idea of--
- It's fun to think about in 10,000 years.
I mean, I don't know if you guys listened
to the 80,000 hours podcast, but--
- I've listened to the first hour, but yeah.
(laughing)
- They're always talking about the deep future
and what we do about it.
And there was one I listened to recently
where they interviewed Paul Cristiano,
who's a AI researcher who thinks about,
how should we leave a message to, let's say, lizard people
if they're the only ones who have survived in 20,000 years?
Sweetly, the first thing that happened in the interview
was he said, let's say lizards are what have survived.
How can we leave a message for them
once they've evolved to say, don't do this, do that?
And Rob Wiblin, who's the host, said,
I must interrupt now, 'cause apparently
there's some insane conspiracy theory
that I've never really heard about,
about lizard people running the world.
And I just want to be clear, and I was like--
- Yeah, they're already here, mate.
What's he talking about?
- Yeah, we're there.
- Is that King Charles?
- I did feel like you guys are so well-informed,
but you don't know the right stuff.
You don't know about the crazy lizard conspiracy theory.
- Many of the doughnut royal family
are actually lizards themselves.
(laughing)
But anyway, his solution, which I quite liked was,
you need to draw attention to a spot in Earth
where we can leave a message saying,
don't create nuclear weapons,
or whatever it is we want to say.
And Paul Cristiano's suggestion was,
there's this massive magnetic anomaly in Russia.
So if we're talking tens of thousands of years
in the future, anything that you carve on a rock
or a big structure you make will have descended
into the Earth, or tectonic plates will have moved.
But magnetism doesn't really change.
And there's this amazing thing called the Kursk anomaly,
I think it's called, and it's in Russia.
And if you go there, your compass goes totally mad.
The magnetism is insane.
And it's riddled with iron deposits.
And he was like, it's really easy to find
quite early on in civilization
once you've worked out magnetism.
Go there and then we can encode loads of,
just draw loads of maps there.
- Right.
- Leave them that message.
- Have we checked that magnetic anomaly
for messages from previous civilizations?
- What a good point.
- Yes, we actually have,
I've got a book called "Ancient Aliens."
(laughing)
I think it's kind of interesting.
Like, let's say humans die out,
as is probably likely over a long period, right?
But then some other animals don't die out.
Then what will the next big species be?
Like the lizards, obviously,
they've had their go with dinosaurs really, arguably, right?
- Is it a turn-based system?
- It's turn-based, so we've had lizards,
so we've had a mammal.
- Yeah, yeah.
So one idea is octopuses.
- Okay, I would happily give it to them.
- Yeah, so like, let's say there's a big problem on earth,
on land-based earth that we've probably caused,
then maybe at the bottom of the sea, they'll be okay.
And the idea is that they would probably
go straight to renewable energy,
'cause they can't really burn coal down there,
'cause they're underwater.
But what they do have is tidal power and hydrothermal,
so heat coming from the bottom of the ocean.
- Great.
- So they will be able to go straight in
at the, you know, the Tesla stage.
- That's really, that's quite a comforting thought, actually.
- Work octopuses.
- Oh, God.
Oh, you'll be one of the right-wing octopus journalists.
Oh, what's wrong with getting off out of Calvary?
- That's the missing lyric from the Bust-It-Sog, isn't it?
Not much has changed, except we are now ruled
by our octopus overlords.
You've got to cut a verse, lads.
This is really an important verse.
No, cut it.
It doesn't play well with the 18 to 24 market.
Cut the octopus verse.
Okay, let's say we're going to the stars, then.
You need a crew mission which takes dozens of generations, right?
How many people do you need on your spaceship?
- See, like, I kind of want to go on my own.
- Okay.
- I'm not sure I could last the journey.
- That's the octopus mindset.
You're going to love the anti-social octopus age.
- Talking to other people?
- Well, yeah, for like tens of thousands of years.
- Well, you'll die at some point, which is the consolation.
- Probably quite early, given what my crewmates will think.
James, can you, you just pop in the airlock and again,
I've dropped a contact lens, I just want to know if we find it.
No, so basically, the mission lasts many generations.
Sorry, that's the thing I missed out.
- I see.
- It's going to take centuries and centuries and centuries
to get to the planet that we've picked, as I knew her.
- So, it's the question, Andy, sorry to interrupt.
It's the question, how many people do we need
so that we don't die out from imbreding?
- Bingo.
- Right.
- Okay.
- Bingo, yeah.
- Like four?
I mean, if you have a child with your cousin,
it's basically fine.
- Yes, they will have children at some point, though,
won't they Anna?
You've not thought this through.
- It's exactly, that's like, that's okay for one generation.
- Yeah.
- And then it gets progressively worse.
- Yes.
- You've got the ancient Egyptians will tell you.
- You've got to go for 6,000 years.
- See, I'm a short-term thinker.
- Absolutely.
- I've got you up all along now.
- You're not one.
- I'm going to go around a hundred.
- Mm-hmm.
- Um, two, just me and my sister.
- And bud.
(laughing)
- It's going to be incest at some point.
You might as well get it over with, don't we?
- Let's nip it in the bud.
- Let's.
(laughing)
- One of you is right, and it's obviously James.
- Who's it?
(laughing)
- This is the easiest game show ever
when you're up against two idiots.
(laughing)
- Send me and Dan somewhere else, honestly.
Make sure we're not on a ship.
- I don't think we're sending you
to one of the good planets.
(laughing)
Anna and Dan's weird incest mission.
You're not going to get a plum posting.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found online.
I'm on @shribeland on Instagram, James.
- I'm on TikTok, no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy, I'm on Instagram @andrewhunterm.
- And if you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can go to Instagram @no such thing as a fish,
Twitter @nosuchthing or email podcast at qi.com.
- Yeah, or you can go to our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
There's a link to some live shows that we're doing
later this year.
Otherwise, just come back next week
'cause we will be back here with another episode.
We'll see you all then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)