(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of No Six Things of Fish, where we were joined
by the incredibly funny, amazing, Maisie Adam.
Now anyone who is familiar with our parent TV show, QI,
will know all about Maisie.
She's burst onto the scene in the last few years
and it is no exaggeration to say
that I think she is the funniest newcomer
that we've had on QI over the last few years.
She's absolutely brilliant.
It was a great fun doing this show with her.
If you'd like to learn anything more about Maisie,
then the best way to find out what she's doing
is to go to her website, which is MaisieAdam.com.
M-A-I-S-I-E-A-D-A-M.
One thing I should quickly mention
is that Maisie mentions Ethan in this show.
That was a reference to something that happened
before the microphones came on, but I had to keep it in.
So just to let you know,
Ethan is one of the QILs who does a lot of our tech stuff.
If you are a Clubfish member,
you might remember his episode of "Meet the Elves"
where he gave us a fiendish question that we had to solve.
We do those "Meet the Elves" shows every now and then
on Clubfish.
It's one very good reason, one of many in fact,
that you should subscribe.
And if you'd like to do that, then you can go to, of course,
no such thing as a fish.com/apple
and no such thing as a fish.com/patreon.
Anyway, one final thing before we do the show,
today's episode marks the end of our nine months
of Anna Replacement shows.
Yes, you got it.
Next week, she will be back.
Anna will be back on the podcast.
So whatever you do, don't miss that episode.
Listen to it 10 times.
You want her to see the figures boosting up
when she comes back on the show.
But in the meantime,
really hope you enjoy this show with Maisie.
And all that's left to say is on with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with James Harkin,
Andrew Hunter Murray, and Maisie Adam.
And once again,
we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Maisie.
- Okay, here we go.
The first fizzy drink tasted of urine.
Do with that what you will.
- Not drink it, that's first of all.
- So it was Fanta.
No, sorry, that's what mankind.
- Oh, to slam.
- To slam.
- Expect a cease and desist from Fanta offices.
- What a slam on a soft drink
that was invented for the Nazis.
- Was it really Fanta?
- I believe it was.
- It was.
- But what a good target for me to pick, really, I suppose.
- Yeah, yeah.
- If you were going to kick one, yeah, Fanta's the one.
- I think they couldn't get American soft drinks,
and so they had to make their own.
And it wasn't the Nazis, Hitler wasn't on the floor,
sorting it out himself,
but it was made during the Nazi regime.
- Oh, okay, by Nazis.
- No, by Nazis, for Nazis.
- That was the slogan, oh God.
But the first fizzy drink was invented
in my hometown of Leeds by a man called Joseph Priestley.
But crucially, it tasted of urine.
- Because people in Leeds--
- We know what we like and we like what we know.
- Here's the crucial question, though.
It tasted of urine, but did it have urine in it?
- Yes, it did.
So how did he invent this?
How did he invent this work?
- Accidentally, as all best things come about.
Accidentally, it was at this brewery,
he basically accidentally discovered
the act of carbonating water, right?
He was like a human soda stream, but by accident.
- Right, brilliant.
So he's worked out how to carbonate water.
And then what he does is he makes a machine
where you can get the CO2 and you can squeeze it
into some water and it'll make it fizzy.
But as part of that machine, he had a pig's bladder.
- Okay.
- Just on hand.
In those days, it was quite common to have pigs' bladders.
You know, you used to play football with pigs' bladders.
It was part of day-to-day life.
- Everyone had a pig's bladder on them.
Like a pen nowadays.
(laughing)
- Can I borrow your pigs' bladder?
- Yeah.
- Dan, can I borrow a pig's bladder?
- This one's been chewed.
(laughing)
So he had a pig's bladder as part of the system.
And he gave one of his glasses of water, fizzy water,
to a friend called John Nooth.
And John Nooth said, "This tastes like piss."
Like, you can't sell this to people
because it tastes disgusting, it tastes like piss.
And he thought that it tasted like piss
because it had been squeezed through this bladder.
Now, Priestly couldn't taste the piss in his own water.
He thought that it tasted absolutely fine.
- Okay.
- And he claimed that Nooth's servants
were maybe urinating in his drinks
because he was such a bad boss.
- Why?
- Really, it was a rift between.
- It really was.
You know, this is sharing your scientific discovery
with a colleague, like Nooth, that's a big deal.
- Yeah.
- But Nooth said, he wrote a paper,
he didn't even quietly say to Priestly,
"I think this tastes a bit pissy."
He wrote a paper for the Royal Society saying,
"In some trials, which I have made
"with Dr. Priestly's apparatus,
"it always happened that the water acquired
"and urinous flavor."
(laughing)
- That's bad, isn't it?
- And it was so predominant that it could not be swallowed
without some degree of reluctance.
- And he didn't run that by Priestly first.
- No.
- Just going, "Can I just double check?
"I'm not the only one tasting weed here."
- I'm glad you didn't, like, you know, you've got B.O.,
and instead of your friends telling you you've got B.O.,
they go to the Royal Society, and that's pretty bad.
- Yeah, that's amazing.
- Priestly claimed that many ladies had tried the water,
and nobody had complained about the urinous flavor.
- He's not looking good for Nooth here.
- So does history tell us whether or not
his servants were pissing?
- Well, we don't know.
- We don't know.
- That seems unlikely.
- But no, and then no one else reported
the urin flavor outside of him?
- Well, then Nooth invented a new system
that didn't have pigs' bladders in it.
- Right, okay.
- And it effectively was the sodas.
- But also, were his servants involved in making it?
- No, they must have been to a certain extent.
He will have had lab technicians.
- What was the missing factor
when it didn't taste of urine?
Was it the servants or the pigs' bladder?
- It was definitely the pigs' bladder.
- Okay.
- We're unsure about the servants.
- Yeah.
- Is this the secret?
You know how every one of these companies
has a secret ingredient that we haven't been told about?
They've just been hiding piss from us this whole time.
- Yeah, but like 11 herbs and spices and piss.
(all laughing)
- Just before we go on on this,
can I tell you about one thing about Nooth?
- Okay.
- John Mervyn Nooth.
- One name.
- It was such a good name.
He once had a coughing fit and coughed out a bullet.
(all laughing)
- I know.
- Okay.
- Did he kill the person sat up his head?
(all laughing)
So he had this terrible coughing fit.
He was like, "Oh, really coughing awfully."
He'd been out in the evening.
And he thought he was gonna die.
His coughing was so bad, this was at about 17.99.
And he threw himself down on the bed,
coughing with great violence.
And then when he got up,
he'd coughed out something incredibly hard.
- Yeah.
- And it turned out just before he got ill,
he'd been having a glass of wine
and then he'd been called away.
So he'd quickly drained the wine
and it had lead shot in it.
- Oh, okay.
- So, okay, right.
- Not a bullet.
- Not an actual bullet.
- But a bit.
(all laughing)
- A lead shot.
- Still a bit of lead shot.
- So if you were to buy, in the older days,
if you were to buy like a partridge for dinner,
they would often have bits of lead in it
from where it had been shot.
- Oh, I see.
- 'Cause it's like scatter shot.
- Oh, okay. - Bullet.
- Okay, but still. - Shotgun pellets.
- Okay. - Shotgun pellets.
- Shrapnel of a bullet that he still swallowed.
Okay, so the animal was killed with a bullet.
That was in there.
- Yeah, shotgun. - I think that counts.
Yeah, yeah. - Yeah, yeah.
- He'd coughed it out. - It's a bullet.
- Well, it's part of a bullet, right?
- Do we know if coughing up a bullet makes you taste piss?
(all laughing)
- Did the part, whoever the bullet went into
had that animal wet itself when it died.
- Yeah, yeah. - Drenched the bullet in whee.
He swallowed them.
- He doesn't notice 'cause of the whine.
- He doesn't notice.
- And everyone's like,
"Pal, have you ever noticed that
"everything you taste off tastes a piss?
"Maybe you've got a piss-soaked bullet."
- Stuck in your throat. - Yeah.
- Taste puts on it. - It's wide open.
- Wow, that's food for thought.
- So New Thend went on to make these soda streams,
which he called gasogines, or gasogines,
and they were really famous.
And basically, if you were anyone who was anyone
in the, when was it, in the 19th century,
then you would have a gasogine machine,
which was like a soda stream.
- Not much has changed really now,
isn't it?
It's still quite a power move to have a soda stream.
- It really is. - It really is.
Yeah, I feel like they've, no,
I feel like they've recently been overtaken by,
if you've got an air fryer, that's the thing.
- Yeah, yeah. - It's an air fryer.
But soda streams were a bit of a power move.
You look like you've got a soda stream.
- A soda stream. - You could tell, by the way,
you were brewing up to that.
- I've got one as well. - Oh my God.
- Here's what's embarrassing. - This sounds as gold plated.
- Mine's gold plated, and we haven't used it
in, I think, two years now.
It just sits there as a display.
- Why do you have a gold plated soda stream?
- My wife likes gold things.
- Is she?
It's your house like Donald Trump's house.
- Oh my God.
- No, actually, it's probably the only gold thing
in our house. - Oh, is it the only thing?
- The only thing. - Yeah.
- Oh, that's not true. - What about the dining table?
- Yeah, the toilet and the chairs.
- Do you remember Trump's house?
- That's real gold, the wallpaper,
and the front of the house.
- And my children.
- Is your wife painted like that woman in gold?
- I think what it was with soda streams
is when I was a kid, they were really,
if one of my friends had a soda stream,
it was like they were the coolest kid in town.
But now it's because you don't want to buy bottles
of fizzy water 'cause it's bad for the environment
or something, isn't it?
- Well, and you can make super sparkling water as well.
And you can get the syrups
that you can make your own tonic water.
- Coca-Cola. - Yeah, but it's not
Coca-Cola, is it?
No, it is, it is.
- Is it real Coca-Cola? - Well, it's not real.
- Well, it's not real.
- No, no, no, it is.
- What it is. - Fans are
for all those Nazi parties in the house.
(laughing)
- It tastes like, this is a good thing,
and I would, you know,
if soda stream ought to advertise on Fish,
that'd be fine by me, just throwing it out there.
But it tastes like the Coke you'd get on a ferry.
You know that kind of Coke?
- No. - Or sort of like a ferry.
- Like Roller-Cola.
- It's not completely, it's a bit like that.
Yeah, what's Roller-Cola?
- Like bad Coke, like knock-off Coke.
- It was like 5P when Coca-Cola was 20P,
Roller-Cola was 5P.
- I just want to reiterate, this stuff is great.
I love it.
I'm so happy with my soda stream.
I have used mine in the last two years.
- I actually don't think that soda stream
are going to have on their advertising
like the Coke you get on a ferry.
- Yeah, that's nearly as bad a slogan
as buy Nazis for Nazis.
(laughing)
- But it's really good.
It's really good I use it all the time.
- It tastes like piss.
- Yeah.
- Good, as it should do.
- But I am.
- Just like Mumbo used to make.
(laughing)
- I think that might be something to do
with my servants though.
I just have a hunch.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Presley, just a quick word about Presley.
- What a guy.
- What a guy, so fluent in six languages.
He wrote over 500 books in pamphlets.
What an amazing scientist.
- That sounds like someone who's written 490 pamphlets.
(laughing)
- Yeah, 499 pamphlets.
One book listing all of the pamphlets that you can read.
He's credited with inventing or discovering
how oxygen is made up.
He was a lunatic, very excitingly.
So the Lunar Society, which was this thing
with Erasmus Darwin and all these amazing scientists
at the time.
They used to meet when it was a full moon
so they could see their way home
using the light of the moon in the very dark night.
It's really cool, eh?
Yeah, what an extraordinary character.
- The thing about him being a lunatic,
that meant he was kind of pro-science.
- Yeah.
- He was also not of the Protestant faith
and he was also kind of sympathetic
with the French Revolution.
And this meant that he had lots of enemies
and lots of people didn't like him.
And there's a thing called the Presley riots.
So he moved to Birmingham after he left Leeds
and they had a dinner to sort of say
how great the French Revolution was.
And a load of people in Birmingham decided
to wreck their place where they had the dinner
and then go to Presley's house and Wreck his house.
- Was he in?
- He was, he was in when they started to come
with the pitchforks and the-
- Oh, like proper Wreck his house.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, they did.
- Oh.
- And his lamp, oh, they didn't just,
not the lamp off the mantelpiece, they went full.
- He and his wife managed to get to the hills
so they could see what was happening.
But they were away from the mob.
But his son was still there.
And his son was trying to kind of save everything.
And in the end, he had to flee as well.
And the interesting thing about it
is because it was anti-establishment
and it was the establishment who were attacking him,
we think that possibly some people involved
in the Birmingham government
might have been involved with this.
- Right.
- And Pitt, who was the prime minister then,
they asked for help against these rioters
and they were very, very slow to react.
The government were like, oh yeah, we'll help, we'll help.
But it was like days and days and days
before they sent anyone to Birmingham to help.
So really they were kind of in on it as well, the government.
- Yeah, just crazy.
- Or at least kind of passive on it.
- Yeah, complicit, yeah.
- Samuel Johnson called him an evil man.
Like he was really in it.
- Yeah.
- It was a bit harsh.
- He really did not like carbonated drinks.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
It's sort of weird to imagine now
how controversial it was at the time.
- Yeah, it's mad, isn't it?
- But he supported, yeah.
- Just to be pro-science.
- He also supported the American Revolution.
- And he was a bit equivocal on the monarchy
and on the idea of virgin birth.
- Yeah.
- So it was all, you know.
- He was quite loved by the American government,
wasn't he?
- When he got there, yeah.
- He was very popular.
- Hung out with George Washington.
- They love a carbonated drink, though.
(laughing)
You've ever seen the Super Bowl?
You can't move for Pepsi, Grant, sponsorship.
- Have you ever heard of this school
around the area of leads?
Oh, I think it's around the area of leads.
Batley Grammar School?
- I know Batley.
- You know Batley?
I would very much believe that they have a grammar school.
- Yeah, well, this is where he went to school.
- Oh, yeah.
- So very, very old school, obviously,
because he went to it, yeah.
And I looked into it to see if they'd produced
any other sort of interesting drinks
through their students, and it turns out that they did.
- No.
- Yeah, Richard John Reid, the co-founder
of Innocent Smoothies and Innocent Drinks
went to the very same school.
- He went to Batley?
- Yeah, he went to Batley Grammar School.
- Batley Grammar, that's great.
- And more so than the smoothies,
he is sort of the person who is credited
with pioneering wackaging.
Wackaging, yeah.
- Like putting the little hats on top, is that what that is?
- No, it's now when the drink sort of says
on the side and says put in the fridge.
- Hi, I'm a smoothie.
- Yeah, put me in the fridge.
- Oh, it gives the personalities to the package.
- It was them, wasn't it, who invented that?
- Yeah, more specifically, this guy from Batley School
was credited, yeah, Richard Reid.
- I was so pro Batley School until you said that.
I think they need to burn it down.
- But also though, as soon as you said it,
and you said he was the inventor of Innocence Mealy,
I immediately just pictured him to be wearing
one of these knitted hats,
going around Batley Grammar School corridors
in a little knitted woolly hat,
going brrr, I'm cold, put me in the fridge.
Oh, there's Richard again, there's bullying.
- Has anyone heard of the soft drink Golaka Pei?
- Golaka Pei.
- Oh, one word.
- No, it's two words, Golaka,
G-O-L-O-K-A-N-M-P-A-Y.
- Golaka Pei, no?
- No, what is it from?
- It's from India.
- Oh no.
- Oh what?
- Is it uriny?
- It's very uriny.
- Oh no, whose wee is in it?
- It's cow urine, 5% by volume, cow urine.
- Five percent, that's a bit piss heavy for a drink.
- We should say we did a fact ages ago
about the fact that cow urine is drunk more,
over there is kind of, it's more normalized
as a drink, isn't it?
- Certainly more normalized than it is here, I would say.
- But you wouldn't drink it as just cow urine,
it's an ingredient in something.
- I'm afraid some people do.
- Yeah, you just drink it.
- Straight?
- Yeah.
- So it's,
- No.
- We haven't tried it.
- No, would you?
- Yeah.
- You would try it.
- For just to be able to say.
- Ethan, bring in the cow urine.
(all laughing)
- Ethan is Dan's gold-covered servant, by the way.
- He's coming in like Julie Walters with two suits.
(all laughing)
- I love that it's milkmates busy milking the cow one morning,
Dan is fractionally behind the milk boy.
- Calling on the penis, yeah.
(all laughing)
- So yeah, we have said before,
there's the Cow Commission of India,
and this is, they're linked to like Hindu nationalist groups,
and they think that according to their traditional medicine,
cow urine is supposed to be an antidote for all sorts of,
I mean, anything you can think of,
inflammation, eczema, arthritis, leprosy.
- A bit of cow piss sorts it out.
- A bit of cow piss is supposed to sort it out.
Currently no concrete scientific evidence that it works,
but you can buy a soft drink called Golaka Pei,
which contains 5% urine,
but at least it does contain other herbs.
- That's nice for them to put those in, isn't it?
- Yeah, such as Tulsi Brahmi and Shank Pushpi,
and orange and lemon as well.
- So herbs, orange, lemon, and cow whey.
- Yeah, that's a drink.
- I'm afraid so.
- And a drink not exclusively used for getting better,
like some people will just have that on the go.
- Like Luca's own, I suppose.
- Yeah, yes, yes.
- 'Cause that is a good illness drink.
- It's an illness drink,
but some people are having it day to day life.
- Absolutely.
- Do you think, sorry to bring the tone down
on this quite high brow podcast,
do you think they taste wildly different, can we, in pig whey?
- No, but I reckon probably an expert would be able to.
I reckon you'll be able to learn.
- You reckon there's somebody that could have a sip of both.
- Absolutely.
- Be able to point out like how people can point out
Coke and Pepsi.
Someone's out there doing it with pig and cow whey.
- Yeah, 'cause I could do Coke and Diet Coke, I reckon.
- Oh yeah, oh, Diet Coke.
Well, Diet Coke tastes like this.
(all laughing)
- I can do tea and coffee, I don't even know what you're down to.
- Oh, Andy, you really thought that was a big thing, did you?
I don't want to brag, guys, but I know the difference.
- Like on your first go.
- Diet Coke and Diet Coke are more similar to each other
than I think you're in a pig urine whey.
- Please go.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that Brazilian footballer,
Formiga, is the only athlete to ever compete
in a team sport in seven Olympics.
But when she was born, it was illegal for women
to play football in Brazil.
- This is such a good fact.
This is such a good fact about such a good player.
- Oh yeah, do you know about Formiga?
- Yeah, so, and also, as you say,
it was illegal when she was born,
and so women's football wasn't in the Olympics.
So that means that she has played in every Olympics
where women's football has existed.
- Right.
- So the next Olympics will be the first one
in women's football history not to feature Formiga.
- Do you like her for a hundred meters run
that have been in every race since 1896?
- Yeah.
- It's like that, isn't it?
- It's unreal.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So, '96 was her first one.
- Yes, so she was born in '78, I think, yeah.
And Brazil had a law from 1941 until 1979,
and they didn't really make it proper until 1981,
that girls and women were not allowed to play football,
but wasn't just professional,
they weren't allowed to play in schools
or even play for fun.
So my daughter, on Friday,
will go to her first football lesson.
She's 18, 19 months old,
and if she was Formiga, it would have been illegal,
she could have been arrested for going and playing football.
- It's absolutely insane,
'cause there's a very famous player called Marta, right?
And she wasn't allowed to play football,
actively discouraged, she really wanted to.
So she used to just on the street,
just have a balled up bits of shopping bags,
basically to use as a ball, playing on her own.
Then she would sort of sneak in to play with other teams,
which were boys entirely,
and it was a horrible experience for her.
If she ever scored a goal, it was seen as a terrible thing.
Like, you've embarrassed that boy.
- It's an attack on the men's score.
And so, never ever was she given this moment
of sort of, you know, you've done good.
- It was an incredible press conference, Marta gave,
'cause she retired after the World Cup just gone,
and it was really quite emotional watching
because she's touching on, I mean,
women's football across the globe, as we all know,
has been hugely under-platformed,
under-represented, hugely disrespected as a sport,
bad enough in this country with the FA banning it
for 15 years, but in Brazil, as you say,
with that very sort of paternalistic, moralism,
sort of society existing, it was an actual attack on,
and it's all down to that it wasn't appropriate
for a woman with her build to be playing football.
But yeah, Famigo was 19 at her first one,
43 at the last of the World Cup.
43 represent in your country.
- And she only ever missed one World Cup,
which was the 1991.
She's done seven of those as well.
- Unbelievable.
- The thing is as well that Marta was
Brazil's leading scorer in history.
She scored 115 goals,
Neymar's the second with 79, Pelé 77.
And Famigo had the highest number of appearances,
which was 234, which is insane.
- It's unreal.
- It's more than 100 games, more than Cafu,
who's got the highest in the men's game.
- Yeah, and Marta, just with the stats,
she's the current record holder for the most goals
ever scored in a World Cup, in one World Cup,
which is 17 goals, and that's for both men
and women's football.
- That's a lot. - For one World Cup,
that's a lot.
- It's mad, isn't it?
- Do you?
- You find it like Neymar recently surpassed Pelé's record,
and like the huge notice that that gets,
that it's always like screaming from the rooftops,
who's the goat in football?
We always end up talking about men.
The goats are often in the women's game,
because they've had to be.
It's truly incredible.
- I watched it.
- Sorry, sorry.
- What?
- Please.
- Go on, you watch some football.
(all laughing)
- Just as I watched last night,
just as a nice bit of timing,
the series Welcome to Wrexham
is currently airing its second series,
and one of the episodes that comes up mid-series,
which I watched last night,
it's the latest episode as of recording,
it was all about the Wrexham women's team.
- Yeah, so good at it.
- No, far better than any,
they make it to the,
as far as we are in the series right now,
they've just made it to the top of their league,
but they take on the closest ranking team,
and they beat them 11 to one, I think it was.
And yeah, it's just astonishing.
And it's so good, I guess that it's now changing,
isn't it?
- It's ever growing, but it's thanks to players,
like for me, you go for like Marta,
like in our own coaching, like Kelly Smith,
or, well, even if you go right far back
to sort of dick curl ladies,
who were all sort of...
- Early 20th century team,
the dick curl ladies, yeah.
- Basically the ones pre-war,
that were getting all of the big crowds,
and then the war happened,
and everyone was like,
"No, we need to make the men feel good."
- Yeah.
- So it was banned in the UK women playing football.
Basically, they weren't allowed to play
on FA affiliated grounds, which was all the grounds.
And that ban was from 1921 until the '70s,
so like you say, about 50 years.
But there was also bans in France, in Norway, in Germany,
and usually the case was that this,
they thought that sport was unsuitable
for the female body, like you say,
but in West Germany's case,
they specifically said that it was a women's soul
that would be in Germany.
- Oh, and I think that's quite nice
as a sort of novel way of like,
oh, we've had loads of complaints about the body,
and they're like, "Oh, damaging women all this time."
- What are we gonna say there?
What are we gonna say?
- They might have meant the soul of their feet,
but it's not how it's spelled.
But you don't get footballers who are like,
"Oh, they're not playing this week
because they injured their soul."
- And I think that would be nice.
I think, and also,
I think spiritual stuff should be taken,
like the referee should be able to say,
immoral.
- Immoral play.
- Yeah, I didn't see the play,
but your aura has turned a nasty shade of red,
and I think--
- I'm just a ref going, I'm going,
"I'm getting bad vibes."
- Yeah, exactly.
- Red card.
- That'd be really fun.
- Of all the countries as well,
to say bad for the soul of a woman,
you wouldn't expect Germany.
That's not very,
it's not particularly Germanic to say, is it?
- Yeah, it's not very quantifiable.
- Of the soul.
You'd expect that from one
of the more romantic language countries.
- Nietzsche wouldn't agree.
- Well.
(laughing)
- And he, honestly.
- Here's the thing.
So, there was a recent study,
and I quite like this,
it's assessed that women's football
is better to watch than men's.
So it's a Swedish sports company who conducted this,
they're called Speedeo,
and they compare the women's Euros in the men's World Cup,
and they tried to do it as mathematically as possible.
So what they found is that women are less risk averse
than men in the style of play.
And again, they're just comparing women's Euros
and men's World Cup.
But those are two, obviously, big international tournaments.
- Okay, so for instance,
the men's teams might deliberately hold back
and try and not concede goals,
whereas the women's team aren't bothered.
- That's it.
So when the women's Euros passes,
moved teams forward 3.7 meters,
and in the men's World Cup, it was 2.5 meters.
- Really?
- That doesn't sound like a lot,
but yeah, that's a big difference.
- I do love you to be the commentator of the World Cup.
- And I believe that was a 2.6 meter pass.
- Oh, yes.
- You're running along the sidelines with that wheel,
that pizza cutter wheel.
- Massive great spreadsheet.
I'm trying to keep track of everyone.
So is that a massive difference?
- Well, I mean, down 2.5, 3.7.
Sorry, I forgot.
I'm talking to the man who can tell the difference
between Coke and Diet Coke, of course,
you would know the meters' differential.
- That's 50% more per pass, you know, almost 50% more.
Yeah, it's not like 10 centimeters shy of being 50% more,
but still, but one stats expert said, I just love this.
It's almost like the men are playing a game of chess
and the women are playing something
a bit more interesting than chess.
(laughing)
Can I say piss off because actually,
some of us like watching chess.
- Like 3D chess like they have in Star Wars.
- Star Wars.
- Wars.
- Shit.
- No, oh yeah.
- Probably both.
- Well, it's, now we're on my home turf, I'm afraid.
- You're all wrong.
It's Harry Potter 1, remember?
- We're on the big statues, moving forward.
- We will get emails just to say in Star Wars,
they have the hologram chest, don't they?
With the monsters.
And I think in Star Trek, I don't know what they have.
- You've lost me here, lads, I'll be honest with you.
You've lost me here.
- Go back to football.
- I think so.
It is definitely like quite a different game in terms,
like it feels at the ground,
it's a very different experience watching the game.
It's a far more inclusive, positive atmosphere,
but actually on the pitch, that's interesting.
- So you play, don't you?
- Yeah.
- How far do you normally pass?
- Oh, I reckon I'm working at the moment with a good 2.7,
I would say, yeah, 2.7.
Now, I think we've heard a lot in the World Cup,
a lot of people observing that there was a bit less diving
and a bit less sort of,
gonna get emails here from blokes, as we always do,
but going, "Oh, really, we don't dive."
Actually, no, on this podcast, you won't,
you probably get quite nice people.
- No, no, it's the first time I've,
I reckon as a learning about football.
- I think metoxic masculinity is probably quite low
on the listenership on here.
- Oh, excuse me, I'm currently doing the inbox,
can I tell you, the number of laddie emails.
- It's full of not all men.
- Yeah, really?
(laughing)
- One thing I found about watching women's games
as opposed to men's games is that everyone
who's at the ground is watching the game.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- So like, if you go and watch a men's football match,
quite often you're watching the opposing fans.
- Yeah.
- Or, you know, they, well, you're there to--
- They're watching you?
- Yeah, you're kind of singing and chanting.
- Rehearsing the chant.
- Yeah.
- Rehearsing.
- Let's not remember, it's not singing and chanting,
it's doing a lot of hand gestures at each other.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- Regardless of what's happening on the pitch.
- Unsupported ones.
- Yeah, yeah, it's not, it's not thumbs up.
It's not thumbs up, I think.
(laughing)
It's not a heart shake from across the stands.
- Yeah, 'cause you could, I mean,
your whole end of the stands could do a great big heart.
- If you ever go and watch, if you ever go and watch Leeds,
that's what they do.
- I'd love it, Addy's just there shouting across the game,
"I love your shirt."
- Yeah, yeah.
- I'm like, "Shirt, where's that from?"
- But yeah, and I went to watch,
I think it was a World Cup in France,
but everyone there was watching the game.
- Right.
- And really no one is doing anything else.
- Yeah, but it is interesting to hear the actual
clinical differences of the on-pitch play.
- Maybe if the men's players kick the ball
a bit less far or further, actually,
then it might improve the mood in the stands.
- Yeah, maybe they would need to make
all those hand gestures.
(laughing)
- Maybe, cool.
- Formiga is Portuguese for aunt.
- Oh, yeah?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause she's got six legs.
(laughing)
- She's got six legs.
- And she can carry 19 times her own body weight,
can't she?
- And actually, I just realized that an old word for aunt
was pismaya because they smell of urine.
- Oh, yeah.
- Oh, look at this.
- There we go.
- So she's called aunt.
That was a nickname that was given to her
when she was at school.
And it was when she was playing football,
they said that she used to play tenaciously
and unselfishly.
She was much like how an aunt would operate
within its own colony.
Yeah, so she was very much busy all the time
and always helping out.
She hated it.
Hated it as a kid.
She learned to just accept it,
but she said, "In the beginning, I didn't like it very much."
You know, I thought it was weird.
- It's quite as if she's small, doesn't it, I guess?
- Yeah, the actual reasoning for it is nice,
but to be called aunt.
- Yeah, well, she said, "I don't have an antennae."
Like, why would I?
- That's true.
- She's getting a bit hung up on where are my mandibles?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Can I see if, Macy, I wonder if you've seen this movie.
- Okay.
- It's called, it's called--
- Titanic.
(laughing)
- Fend it right back.
- Yeah.
- It's called, "Escape to Victory."
- No, I've not seen this film.
- Has no one seen this film?
- What class?
- It's very famous.
- Is it?
- I've never heard of this film before.
It's stars, Sylvester Stallone.
- I'm Pele.
- Michael Cain, Pele and Bobby Moore.
- What?
- I mean, that is the real expendable.
- So is it a football, or it sounds like a prison?
- It is.
- It is, it's a prison movie whereby--
- There's "Gate Through Football."
- They set up a match during the match
as part of the match prep.
But I just love there's a Stallone, Michael Cain,
Bobby Moore, and--
- That's mad.
- Yeah, I know.
- Oh my God, I didn't see this film.
- I know, I really need to see it.
- Is it any good?
- It's a classic.
- Yeah, I can read between those lights.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It's one of the things they used to show it on like,
Sunday evening.
- Can I just say, if anybody ever went,
"Macy Adam, I haven't seen a comedy, what's it like?"
And somebody went, "It's classic."
(laughing)
- I think that would be absolutely harrowing.
- He'd rather be made by Nazis for this one.
(laughing)
- One for the tour poster.
- One last thing on Pelle,
just while we're on him very quickly.
Pelle's last ever match, 1977, he played,
and it was an exhibition match,
and it was the New York Cosmos against Santos,
and two teams that he used to play for.
So, in order to make sure that he wasn't siding
with any particular team,
in the first half, he played with one team,
and in the second half, he played with the other team.
- Lovely.
- It's final match ever.
- Absolutely love that.
Only Pelle could get away with doing that, though.
- Yeah.
- I think so.
- So, he didn't change ends.
- Oh, yes.
- Which must give you a slight advantage, right?
Possibly.
- Also, probably being Pelle gives you a slight advantage.
- Yeah, that's why he was so good.
(laughing)
- When I was at school,
we used to obviously play football for the schools,
and a lot of the schools would have pictures
that were on massive slants.
- Oh, my God.
- And so, like, you'd be in the first half,
you'd be winning five, nearly.
You'd end up losing, like, 21-five.
- I played a league in Brighton,
and we played on one the other day.
If you've ever been to Whitehawk's ground,
it's a fantastic club, it's Whitehawk,
but their ground is on a slope, sort of, left to right,
and up to that, like, you could ski down it.
You could ski down it.
- There was one that I played at school in Bolton.
This was, I think it was in primary school,
and it was, like, slanted, like you say,
from one wing to the other.
- Yeah.
- You can imagine that.
And we were all primary school kids,
so we didn't really know how to play football,
and so the ball would just always end up rolling
to the bottom at all 22 kids.
(laughing)
- It's part of the pitch.
- A lot of corner balls from one specific corner.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
That is Andy.
- My fact is that American schools have a sport
of competitive meat judging.
- No.
No.
- Wait.
(laughing)
- Meat judging.
It's less dodgy than it sounds.
- Absolutely believe.
- It's made, I should say,
this was sent in by an audience member called Kevin Fegan.
So thank you, Kevin.
- Kevin Fegan.
(laughing)
- Fegan.
- Yeah.
- Kevin Fegan.
- Yeah, like Kevin Keegan, but with an F.
- Yeah.
- Oh, all right.
But he's not a vegan.
- Yeah.
- He didn't say it as evil.
- He's a vegetarian.
(laughing)
- God, come on.
- Kevin, if you're American--
- If you think I'm better than that, mate,
you've not had any episodes.
- I loved it.
I loved it.
- What's Kevin saying?
- Kevin's saying, well, that's what it is.
That's the fact.
- That there's meat judging.
- It's competitive meat judging.
And I think this might be the most American sport possible.
- How can you judge meat?
What's the criteria?
- Oh, well, is this a pig or is it a cow?
(laughing)
- Step one, that's the absolute baseline.
No, no, no.
This is, okay, it's a college sport.
It's an intercollegiate sport, right?
So it's sort of students who are playing it.
And they, like all over the country,
teams of students practice all year,
and then they get to the competition.
And what you have to do is,
you're presented with a range of meat carcasses,
and you have to judge the yield,
how much meat you'll get out of it,
how much fat there is in it,
the consumer experience, the age of the carcass,
and you have to do all this by sight only.
- Sight only.
- Oh, so they don't just put a slab of meat in front of you
and you go, pork?
- No, no, no, no.
- Not just guess if it's beef or pork or lamb.
I'll just say, I reckon I'd be all right at this.
- Andy, do you think as someone who can tell the difference
between diet cooking and no cooking,
that you won't be good at the spot?
- I think I might.
- Yeah, I think.
- It sounds amazing.
- It's like meat chess, basically.
It's really like, you get 10 minutes to inspect each carcass.
You know, they're hanging up in front of you.
You're not really touching them much.
- You're in like a big cold fridge.
- Like a couple of butchers.
You're in that, and then you're asked to guess yield.
- Yeah, I mean, all sorts.
- How many portions you get?
- My favorite one is, and this is purely by sight,
you have to go and evaluate whether a table of 10 cuts
that are laid down fit a checklist
of the United States Department of Agricultural Standards.
- Who's revising this?
- Oh, people put so much work in it.
They train sometimes for 12 hours a day
leading up to the competition.
- Whilst they're in college.
Have you seen how expensive college is in America?
How fuming would these parents be if they knew?
Are you revising?
Well, I've been looking at my chickens.
(laughing)
They must get a scholarship, I guess, right?
You know, like if you're--
- You can't get a meat scholarship.
Sure, like, surely not.
- You only play also, they're kind of competitors.
They're kind of like the Mayflies of the sporting world.
They get, you get one season.
That's it.
You can't play twice.
You can't play in two consecutive years.
Not like Farmiga, who can play.
- You can't be the Farmiga without each other.
(laughing)
- Which is a nightmare for the coaches
that pick their star meat examiners.
- Trying them up for one season and then they're out.
- Then you're back, yeah, you're just back to the start.
Finding fresh blood, you have to.
- Why would you bother, genuinely,
why would you bother pursuing this
if you can't become one of the great meat judges
who can't do it year in, year out?
- There are talent scouts who come to the competitions.
- You're lying.
- No, I'm not.
I swear, I swear.
They, I mean, a lot of the students
are already studying agriculture, that kind of thing.
So a lot of the competitors will end up going into meat
professionally, you know, the U.S.
- Oh, so they might be scouted to go into these top jobs
because of how well they did at the meat judges.
- If you're the head of a meat company
and you really want the best meat judges
to be part of your company, you'll pay lots of money.
- So you'll go to some intercollegiate competition
and be like, wow, Steven's very good at clocking.
- Yeah, wow.
- And 80% of them go into food and livestock industry jobs
after college.
- I mean, 20% don't know.
(laughing)
- There might be some savants who have studied it.
- 20% just doing it for food.
They're going into equipment.
- They're studying poetry.
The meat is pure passion for them.
And then, yeah, exactly.
- It's just a side hobby.
- I just love it.
I love it so much.
- But you do, you do get like the formiga of this,
even though the span is just one season.
So there is, there is one person called Maddie Ainsley.
And Maddie Ainsley did seven competitions like for me.
- 'Cause around the country.
- You go around the country.
- There are seven different competitions.
- Within the year.
So this is taking up a lot of your year.
This is not like one meat competition.
And she won five of the sevens.
- That's great.
- She's the all star.
- It's going to go all bad day.
- Yeah.
- Wow, that's great.
There was one guy called Rody Hawkins,
who was a former meat judge from Tennessee.
And this is the only--
- That can't be a sentence.
(laughing)
Rody Hawkins, meat judge from Tennessee.
This is like if Chuck GPT wrote a novel.
(laughing)
- He was a former meat judge from Tennessee.
- Right, an American novel.
Rody Hawkins from Tennessee.
- He's the only famous one I could find
who went from meat judging to greater things.
He co-invented Lunchables, which is a famous--
- Sorry.
- They're good.
- No, no, no, come on.
He's judging the quality of meat.
And he came out with Lunchables.
(laughing)
- It's like a little plastic toast.
- Processed.
- With some squares of processed ham
and some squares of processed cheese
and some crackers.
- Right.
- Yeah, must've been up all night thinking about it.
(laughing)
- I read a Sports Illustrated article on meat judging.
- That was great.
- It's an amazing article.
And there's a bit that explains exactly what it takes
to enter these competitions and be a meat.
So to be a meat judge, quick decision making,
critical reasoning, self assurance,
and above all the ability to quiet one's mind
for up to six hours standing in frigid temperatures
in total silence.
And according to a judge from 2015--
- Feels like the fourth point is quite a big step up.
I was like self assurance, yeah.
And then you read the fourth one and I was like,
ah, down, stop me.
- Fifth ability to judge meat.
(laughing)
- Exactly.
But what the quote from the judge from 2015 said,
and this is to do with the total silence,
you have to fight your own demons
in the meat judging cooler.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
- I don't want to fight demons in a meat judging cooler.
- Who are the demons in the meat judging cooler?
- All yours.
It's just the internal voices.
- The internal voices in the six hours
of silence as you stare and trying to work out
if it's agriculturally sound.
- There are moments where,
so this might have been in the same piece.
There was a student from Texas Tech.
She was called Taylor Schertz.
She was a second year student.
What's that?
(laughing)
Again, I think a rom-com set in the meat judging world
would be, genuinely would be good.
- Meat cute.
There we go.
- Oh, God.
- The heads bump over a frozen beef cart.
(laughing)
- No, so she, at one point,
was the foremost meat judge in the country.
And I think, I don't know what year this was.
She was competing, but there was a competition in Houston.
This just shows you how brutal meat judging is, right?
She was in the top 10 nationally.
She was doing brilliantly.
And then she misjudged the age of one beef carcass
and plummeted down to 36.
- Wow. - To 36 position.
So, you know, just, it can be--
- How wrong did she get it really wrong?
(laughing)
- This meat is from 1743.
- I think this meat's alive.
(laughing)
- I don't know, it doesn't relate,
but it just goes to show it's, it's tough.
I think they have some in Australia too.
I think there is meat judging there too.
- Wow.
- It sounds like you have to judge the hot carcass weight.
- Yeah.
- The amount of kidney fat, amount of heart fat,
area of rib eye muscle.
- All from just looking at it.
- Yeah.
- If you got stuck in a freezer,
like one of these big butcher freezers,
let's say you're kind of, the door closes itself,
but you put your foot there to stop it from closing,
but then you slip on a sausage or something.
And your foot goes out of the way and the door closes.
It doesn't open from the inside.
What's the best thing inside the freezer
to help you get through that door, I would say?
- Do you know the answer?
- Yeah, this is a real thing that happened last.
- Oh, wasn't, yeah, wasn't there a guy
who beat his way out with something?
(laughing)
- Is there a bone?
- Oh, a bone.
- Interesting.
- A skeleton key bone that you can,
yeah, he calves, he's a whittler.
- Well, you get the wishbone
and you wish that you can get one.
(laughing)
- It's not having a poo and using the frozen poo too.
- No, I don't.
- Dan, you're in a freezer, everything's frozen.
There's no need to have the poo.
- If only I had something to freeze.
(laughing)
Guess I gotta take a shit.
- That's the only logical thing to do here.
Shit my way out.
- Dan, this lift has been stopped for just 30 seconds.
Wait to see it.
- No, no, no, I insist, I'll get us out of this.
- I must freeze the poo to fashion it into a presser
to press the button for help.
(laughing)
- A room full of frozen meats.
I'll find my own tools, thank you.
(laughing)
- So you say no to that though.
- Why did I never broadcast your Desert Island Dicks
episode, Dan?
(laughing)
- No music for me, thank you, Laura.
- My next track.
(laughing)
- So your luxury item is...
- No, it wasn't that.
- What happened?
- What?
- This really happened.
- Now this really happened to a guy called Mr. McCabe
who's a butcher and apparently the beef is too slippery.
If you grab a frozen beef,
it's kind of too slippy to bash your way out.
- Okay.
- If you get a big sort of chunk of lamb,
you can't really, you can't get any purchase on it
and it's often too big.
But the perfect thing is a black pudding.
If you get a full black pudding,
especially one made by the Royal Butcher,
H.M. Sheridan of Ballata, Aberdeenshire.
These are exactly the right size.
- That's specific.
Did he tell you this last?
- What a weird secret sponsorship.
(laughing)
- Are you getting money on the side?
- Apparently it's almost exactly the same size
because you know one of those police battering rams
that you knock down on the dance floor.
It's like that.
And this guy managed to knock his way out of the freezer
and he said, I'm really lucky.
We sell about two or three each week
and this was the last one we had.
- Oh wow.
- So if he'd have sold one more,
he would have been stuck there forever.
- That's brilliant.
- Are they buying them as battering rams?
Is that Aberdeen police?
(laughing)
- As he leaves the freezer, he looks back
and he's down in the corner.
- Daddy, you're coming.
No, thank you.
- I'll get myself now.
- 20 more shits.
I should have a battered ram out of this.
- I've got a sister.
- Type we went to an escape room with you, daddy.
(laughing)
- Yeah, no lab back there.
- How about this?
How about putting a door handle
on the other side of the door?
- Yeah, I mean, why do we not?
- Honestly, most of them do have.
- Okay, most do.
- Any that I've been in have got a big red button
that you can press and get out.
- That's cool, yeah.
- Sorry, how many freezers have you been in
that the door's shut and you have to let yourself out of?
- A couple.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- I used to work in kitchens and stuff.
- Oh, okay, okay.
Have you guys heard of wretchtubklat?
- Wretchtubklat.
- The rapper.
- I don't even know.
(laughing)
I don't even know what you're saying.
- Wretchtubklat.
How do you spell klat?
- K-L-A-T.
- This sounds like it's something from the Netherlands.
- It's actually Australia.
- Oh, okay, this is wrong.
- Wretchtubklat, is it a kind of meat, a rare meat?
- No.
- Is it a town like one of those weird sort of outback towns?
- A society?
- No.
- It's part of a kangaroo?
- What, is it anything to do with what anything
we're talking about?
- Is it a way of cheating at cricket?
- It's, oh, there we are.
James single-handedly lowering our Australian audience
to zero as the weeks go by.
No, what is it?
It is a secret butcher language.
- No wonder we haven't heard it, it's a secret.
- It's a butcher language, that's great.
- It's a secret butcher language.
Okay, so what do you think the secret language is?
- Oh, it's in meat displays in the window.
- Oh, I see.
- So you arrange the sofas.
- And it means I'm available.
- Yeah, it's like a traffic light party,
but for butchers only.
- Yeah, yeah, but for butchers.
- Well, the clue is in the name, Wretchtubklat.
- Oh, if you read it backwards,
or is it an anagram?
- Wretchtub, butcher, but talk butcher.
Butcher talk.
Butcher talk is the secret language that is shared.
And this has been going since the 1960s.
Butchers all over Australia use this,
and it's been in Australian movies as well.
Whereby they talk backwards to each other
so that they can say stuff that the customer can't hear
in order to, yeah, absolutely.
- In order to talk.
- Quick, get the age sauce.
(all laughing)
- In order to what?
- So you might say, on steltuck, knee, et, poos,
(all laughing)
and that means no cutlets in the shop.
And you would say that out loud
so that everyone, sometimes a massive butchers in Australia
might have 20 butchers, the serving people,
and they would know to just immediately eliminate that
as part of the process.
- Ah, I see, but you don't upset the customer.
- Exactly, and you don't want to upset the customer.
On dug kuf e kaff.
Oh, good food.
- Fake.
- It's no good, fuck face.
(all laughing)
- Really good that they've worked that out.
- It's pretty, like the rest of it,
like as the examples, it's pretty misogynistic, I have to say.
- Why is it needed though?
- Well, largely because if there's a difficult customer,
they want to be able to say difficult customer.
- To be rude about it.
- It feels like, but the most of customer facing roles
that haven't had to do this, has there?
- Yeah, no, but I guess you're all in one line
and if you need to get a message down the line to,
everyone hears it in the shop.
- So you're already sticking up for these sexist butchers.
- I'm not, I'm telling you that it exists.
That's what I'm trying to say.
- It's actually in my rom-com now,
the meat judging rom-com.
I think there should be a nice, like maybe the lovers
speak to each other using a butcher talk,
whatever it was called.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Something clatch.
- Yeah, retch tub clatch.
- Retch tub clatch.
- Yeah, subtitled the entire movie
so that you can see what makes it more classy, I guess.
- Yeah, but it just says no good, fuck face.
But along the bottom of the,
that's nice and romantic, isn't it?
- That's the closing line, that's it.
- And the kiss, and...
- Frankly, my dear.
(all laughing)
- I don't do cook-a-club.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the first wireless headset microphone
was made for Kate Bush.
And it was made out of an old coat hanger.
- Oh, wow.
First of all, how?
- Well, you're just making it sort of go around the ears,
aren't you?
You need the perfect bit that actually,
that you use the hanger.
- Yeah.
- You would attach the microphone, which would be--
- Oh, so you're just wearing a coat hanger around your ear?
- Exactly. - Oh, okay.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's basically those Madonna mics, right?
- Yeah.
- Those steps mics, I would call them, but yes.
- Yeah, Brittany Mike.
- Brittany Mike.
It should be called a Bush Mike, basically,
because she is the founder.
- Does it quite roll up too well, does it?
(all laughing)
At best, you're thinking of a problematic president,
at worst, if you're thinking of something much,
much more than what you are.
- But yeah, so this is, so it's interesting to know
that we know the very first time anyone wore
one of these Madonna Brittany mics,
and it was Kate Bush.
It was on her tour, The Tour of Life, in 1979.
It was a song called Moving, which was the opening number,
and the reason that she needed it
was because there was so much choreography.
There was so much costume change and everything,
movement that she needed her hands
for everything that she did.
She couldn't hold a microphone.
So it was one of the sound engineers.
Two names come up when you look into it.
It's a bit hard to nail it down,
but one person was called Martin Fisher.
A lot of people said it was him.
Some people say it was Gordon Patterson.
It was definitely one of the two,
and it was on this tour that it was done,
and it was done on Kate Bush's only ever tour that she did.
- She only did one tour.
- She's never done another tour.
She's done a residency.
- She's not allowed to travel to Zarkite.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, she's not into it.
And it's a shame because it sounds like
she might've been one of the greatest touring acts
that you could ever see.
I mean, this--
- What would she have invented on her future tours?
- Exactly, yeah.
But listen, so this, the Tour of Life,
as I say it was called,
this is like a few highlights
that you would've seen in that show, right?
So we opened with Whalesong that was playing
with Kate Bush's shadow projected dancing
while the curtains were starting to part
and revealing the stage.
And then after a song or two,
the whole theater was filled with the sound of heartbeats
and red lights.
There was large oval upholstered red satin egg womb-like ball
that would be rolled onto stage with Kate inside
where she would sing the song Room for the Life
as she was rolled around the stage,
hence not being able to use her hands.
There was a moment where she was singing a song
called Violin where she was chased around the stage
by two dancers dressed as giant violins.
There was poetry readings from her brother.
A magician came out and did an act with a floating wand.
She came out as a World War II pilot.
She came out as a Wild Western cowboy-esque looking thing
with a rifle and she would shoot ribbons at the dancers.
I mean, the whole thing with every song
had a theme and a production to it
and it was a spectacle, basically.
- She's probably still writing the second song.
(laughing)
- Yeah, exactly.
- I did go and sit, do you know about,
what would it have been about 2016, maybe 2015,
something like that, nearly 10 years ago,
she did a night of about 20 nights at Hammersmith Apollo
and me and my mum managed to get tickets.
It was like, you know, when you get set up all the laptops,
it's like NASA space station trying to get tickets.
- F5, F5, F5.
- We got them, literally, we got them
and that was pretty, pretty good.
It was the first time she performed live
in somewhere like 25 years, unreal.
And she flew, she flew at the, no, she did, she flew.
So she did this song at the end
where suddenly like a big crash of thunder happened
and I don't, I mean, obviously she'll have been attached
to it, but like, you know the room I'm talking about,
the Apollo, right?
I don't know, 'cause she wasn't attached
to the ceiling directly above the audience,
but she flew right out to like,
what looked like touching distance to touch in the circle.
And she's, I think, you know, she wouldn't mind
of saying this, she's getting on his arcade.
Like, it was-- - She's 50 something now.
- I gasped purely out of admiration,
purely out of concern for her welfare
as she flew directly towards us.
We were in the circle.
It was like, absolutely terrifying
and incredible and mesmerising.
- Yeah, I think she's in her 60s now.
- Blimey. - Yeah, yeah.
- Was that by any chance, Wuthering Heights,
when she was doing that song?
- No, it wasn't that song, no, no.
It was like a, it was a really aggressive song.
It was that big crash of thunder and then she just sort of,
I think it was called the dawn of something
and she just flew out to us
and she looked like a big crow.
- And at the time, did you think she's flying?
- Yeah. - You did?
- Yeah, I did.
- I would as well with Kate Bush.
She has mystical qualities.
- Yeah, yeah, it was so good.
- Maybe she did, maybe she invented something.
- There we go.
- We don't have yet, like the bush rocket,
which kind of flies her up in the air.
Something hidden.
- Maybe that's why she doesn't talk
'cause she's like, I don't want everybody to know about it.
- Yeah.
I've invented flying, but I don't want to, I don't want to brag.
- So she, Kate Bush, shares a birthday with Emily Bronte,
who wrote "Wuthering Heights".
- No. - Which is her...
- It's interesting.
- I'm not gonna say it's her big song,
but it's one of the biggest, isn't it?
- That is big.
- That was the breakthrough song.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- That is big.
- And 30th of July, 1818 and 1958, respectively.
- That's amazing.
- And can I just tell you a quick thing
about the word "wuthering"?
- Oh yeah. - Yes, please.
- What does it mean?
- Yeah, no idea.
- Is it like any "wuthering"?
- "Wuthering Heights".
- "Wuthering Heights"?
- To fly to the circle of a venue.
- That's it, that's it.
- Yeah. - The "wuthering height".
- It feels, on a matter of peocly,
it feels like "wuthering" almost.
- Yeah.
- Like the wind, especially 'cause of the book,
it feels like the moors are blowing stuff and...
- That's pretty much it, is it?
- But it's pretty much, she, I think,
was just about the first to say "wuthering", 'cause it was...
- Is it "wuthering" but with a Yorkshire accent?
- It's not. - It's not.
(laughing)
- It's not from there.
- It's a book dictated by Nora.
- It was previously used much more as "wuthering",
with an H, an extra H, "wuthering",
which meant rushing along,
and it was usually a reference to wind,
like just like you were saying, James,
and a "witherer" was a lusty, a strong, or a stout person.
- Really, 'cause like "withered" now
is the opposite of lusty and strong.
- And it's again with an extra H,
so it's a "witherer", you know,
that was in the Francis Groves Dictionary
of the Volga Tongue, his one was.
And there was also a word to make a whizzing
or a rushing noise, which was "to wuther".
- To wuther.
- So it could have been "wuthering heights".
- That's "wuthering heights".
- It sounds like something Elmer Fudd would write.
(laughing)
- "Wuthering heights".
- It does sound like, "Watch out, I'm watering here!"
(laughing)
- She hadn't read the book
when she wrote "Wuthering Heights", Kate Bush.
- Really?
- She gets a lot of the plot points in.
- Oh, she does?
- She must have read the spark notes or something.
- She'd watched "The Adaptation" on the BBC,
which was really big the year before.
It was absolutely massive.
And she wrote the song based on the book
and then later on read the book.
- Oh, but that's dangerous,
'cause sometimes they really change the plot, don't they?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I did, in me, a-level drama.
We had to do, what's that Noel Coward play with Elvira?
"Blide Spirit".
- "Blide Spirit".
- In the film, there's a car crash at the end,
and I hadn't read the rest of the play,
and I just wrote about the car crash at the end.
(laughing)
I got called into Mrs. Bray's office,
and she was like, "So can you just tell me again?"
Which bit inspired you to talk about the car crash scene?
And I was literally just chatting pure,
I was woodering on, and she was like, "Yep, yep."
And so it's not in the play, maybe,
it's only in the film. - That's incredible.
- And she made me write it all again.
- I had the exact same experience
with Winnie the Pooh and "The Blustery Day" as--
- Oh, come on. - In your A-levels.
(laughing)
- Fortunately, the--
- Did you think Winnie was a Pooh?
(laughing)
- Piglet uses him to beat his way out of a freezer,
doesn't he? (laughing)
- No, fortunately, in my case,
the screen adaption was very close to the source material,
so I got away with it, but it was, I know that fear, yeah.
- I searched on the newspaper archives,
newspapers.com and the British newspaper archives
for the first mention of Kate Bush.
And the first mention I could find
was from the Burton Observer and Chronicle,
and it was from the week that "Wuthering Heights" came out,
because she was pretty unknown at that stage.
And in the first week, it went to, I think,
like number 29 in the charts.
It wasn't like huge, but it was there.
And the review said,
how do we stop Emily Bronte spinning in her grave?
The easiest way would be to call back
in all the copies of Kate Bush's "Wuthering Heights".
Singing the role of ghostly Kathy,
she appeals for Heathcliff to let her in.
If Heathcliff has any sense,
he'll plug his ears with cotton wool and go to bed.
- Wow. - What a tit.
- I believe that's the first review of that.
- Who wrote that?
- It was in the Burton Observer,
and it was just initials.
I think it was said A-H or something,
so I didn't say who the person was.
- Oh, God, I bet A-H is just constantly hoping
they never get revealed.
(laughing)
- No, it must be a different A-H.
There was loads of people with A-H at the Burton.
- I really tried to look in the Burton Observer
and Chronicle history to see if anyone
who'd worked there had these initials,
and they couldn't find them.
- Wow, you were trying to get a witch hunt going.
- Oh, God. - I was gonna email them
and say, "What do you think about it?"
- Yeah. - But this is so weird
because there's another connection there.
The novel got shocking reviews when it came out.
- Really? - Yeah.
So one said, "The only consolation
which we have in reflecting on it
is that it will never be generally read."
- Oh, wow. - And another wrote,
"How a human being could have attempted
such a book as the present without committing suicide
before he had finished a dozen chapters is a mystery."
- Wow. - Wow.
- I mean, admittedly, I do own a copy
and haven't read it, so.
- Did you not read it at school?
- No, we didn't. - Really?
- No, we didn't either.
- Really? - I've read it.
It is, look, I'm an Ambronte fan.
I'm gonna put my cards on the table.
I prefer Anne.
I think Emily's a bit overrated.
- Wow. - See, this is
what we get like this far. - A-H.
(laughing)
- I'm A-H-M, yeah, yeah. - He is, yeah.
- That is his initials. - Yeah.
- I mean, is it possible that A-H was paying tribute
to he actually, or she actually loved the song
and just wanted to reflect the original review
of the rap for the book itself? - I see.
- No way, no way.
- Nah. - Seems implausible.
- A-H is listening at home going, "Yes, yes, buy it,
"buy that, yes, please." (laughing)
- But a wireless mic born from a coat hanger.
- Yeah.
- That's exciting, 'cause now they're everywhere.
- Yeah, yeah.
Just on microphones.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- In the 1930s, the BBC had a special microphone
which was only for the use of the royal family.
- Oh. - And it's in the BBC
to this day, it's an artifact of,
so it was when they started doing royal broadcasts
at Christmas, I think that was in the '30s.
- Yeah, yeah. - I think it was George V.
He started doing that. - Yeah, yeah.
- And I think a BBC sound engineer
saw the standard microphone that they were going to do it with
and thought, "This is not good enough for the king."
- Wow. - And just,
and quickly put some regal blue velvet cloth over it,
which you would think would slightly dampen the--
- It might help, it stops at some point.
- It actually helps, yeah.
- Maybe a good point.
And anyway, as the years went by,
they got more and more elaborate.
And so they ended up with this beautiful, weird-looking thing
which was in a kind of gilded cage.
- Wow. - Yeah.
- It's from Dan's home.
(all laughing)
- That's really cool.
Is it because they worried that, like,
non-regal spets might get into it or something?
- No, I think it was just that we have to make it fancy
for the king or queen to use.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Kate Bush met the queen.
Went to Buckingham Palace in 2005.
She asked for her autograph.
- Who asked for whose autograph?
- Bush asked for a queen. - Oh, okay.
- Yeah. - She's the queen.
Huge fan.
- I mean, it's plausible, isn't it?
- It is plausible.
- And what did the queen do?
- Fuck off. - Yeah, exactly.
- The queen's not allowed to give out autographs.
I think. - She's not.
- Okay, someone tries to do credit card for all of that.
- You're not allowed to, yeah.
- That's just scamming the queen.
(all laughing)
- No, what is it?
- She said, (speaking foreign language)
- Oh, right.
(all laughing)
- If you were gonna try and scam the queen,
you did the mum's maiden name.
- Yeah, post-lion, yeah. - And often, she did haven't--
- And then you could, the name of the first--
- Streety grew up on? - Yeah.
- The actual heirs that just have like a first name.
- Charles Windsor and stuff like that, I guess.
- Oh, yeah.
- I think if you had the queen's autograph,
you might be able to start wars against other countries.
- Yes, that's true.
- Oh, yeah, that's probably--
- That's a big thing.
And Kate Bush, as we know--
- It's arguably more--
- She does want to do that.
She has tried several times.
- I would say that poses a bigger threat as well
than just logging into the queen's Amazon prime.
(all laughing)
- I can't imagine anyone called Bush
starting a legal war.
(all laughing)
- That sounds very unlikely.
- No, no.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland, James--
- @JamesHarken.
- Andie--
- @AndrewHunterM.
- And Maisie.
- @MaisieAtom.
I was a poll knight thinking of that one.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, or you can go to our group account,
which is @KnowSuchThing.
You can write into us at podcast@QI.com
or you can go to our website,
KnowSuchThingAsAfish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
Do check them out.
Otherwise, we're gonna be back again next week
with another episode and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)