(electronic music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin,
Anichezinski and Drew Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones.
- Can't do it, can't do it.
- I think it's Drew Hunter Murray.
- It's Drew Hunter Murray.
- It's not that, it's not that.
I've acetate, we acetate last week.
It's lightning.
I wanna stick with that.
Please never Drew.
- Oh.
- I love Drew's photograph.
- And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with my facts, my fact this week is that
in the final years of its construction,
Mount Rushmore was built by baseball players.
- Nice.
- Did they run out of dynamite?
And they said, "Well, we better just get a bunch of guys
with bad stuff."
(laughing)
No, so Mount Rushmore was constructed
between 1927 and 1941 in the first early stages
and actually right up until about 1938.
It was being led by a guy called Gutson Borglum
and Gutson Borglum had a sun working on it called Lincoln
and Lincoln was obsessed with baseball
and he really wanted to put a baseball team together.
So from 1938, when he started hiring all the people
to work on it, one of the things that he required you
to be able to do was play baseball
so that you could be part of the team.
It almost didn't matter if you were able to be
(laughing)
- Is it true?
Well, one of the guys, his name's Nick Clifford,
he's the last construction worker on Mount Rushmore
who's still alive and you can meet him in the summers.
So if you're this year, 2017 in the summer,
he's 95 years old at the moment.
Go to Mount Rushmore and he sits there
and he gives tours, he explains what's going on,
how they built it, he signs books
and he hands out baseball cards from the team
and they actually competed in amateur baseball
and they made it to the semi-finals, they came in third.
So they were really good and...
- The semi-finals of...
- Of the amateur baseball, no one's heard of League.
(laughing)
- Just in the Mount Rushmore area.
- Yeah, no, I'm not fully sure on that actually.
- Actually, it did sound when you read people's memoirs
about it, it sounds like they had a really good team work
kind of bond, doesn't it, the workers.
So they all had these weird nicknames
so they were all called stuff like
lively and polluca and red and hoot and whiskey.
- And howdy.
- And howdy, yeah.
- And one guy's called Howdy.
- Did you read the story about what Howdy did
to one of his teammates at one point?
- No.
- So they played quite a lot of pranks on each other, I think.
So one of their favourite pranks was
if a new builder came on site,
then when he was going up on an out-sale,
then you'd like loosen it so he'd drop down a few feet
and think he was plummeting to his death.
- That's bullying, isn't it?
- Yeah, but bullying is always funny for the bullies,
and so I think most of them enjoyed it.
- Okay.
- It was very good nature.
- Who will speak for bullies?
- Hannah will speak for bullies.
(laughing)
- Hey, I mean, good company these days.
But no, he did this thing where I think one of his
co-workers slapped him on the ass or something.
So to get him back,
they have an air hose that they used to remove all this
rock dust that was all over them at the end of the day.
They got covered in rock dust.
So it had really powerful blowing force.
And he got this air hose and he shoved it up.
His teammates us and it inflated his teammates in sides.
And everyone thought he was going to die.
So this guy said he blew up tighter than a drum.
And one of the witnesses said that when the hose connected,
you could see his belly swell right up.
He yelled, "My God, how do you've killed me?"
And then he had to start passing air
and he passed quite a lot of blood with it.
- If you're listening and you have access to high pressure
air hoses, do not try this at home.
- No fatalities of any of the workers on Mount Rushmore,
despite all the weird pranks that they would play on each other.
- Yeah.
- So when did you say it was finished, don't?
- 1941 is when they ran out of funding.
- Exactly, it's not finished.
- Yeah.
- Someone could still take up the metal.
They're meant to be down to the waist.
But once they've done the faces and the shoulders
and things, they sort of thought,
well, you know who they are.
It's good that they didn't start at the other end.
- You'd start on the waist.
(all laughing)
- Did you read that thing where it's not going to be
properly finished for 300,000 years?
That's because the granite erodes.
And it erodes by a very, very tiny bit.
And the person who was making it knew this.
And so he deliberately made all the faces slightly fatter.
So they'll just keep eroding and keep eroding.
And then apparently in 300,000 years,
all the proportions will be correct.
- That's amazing.
- That's incredible.
- But why did he plan it to be right in 300,000 years
rather than just, nah.
- To go with the 300,000th anniversary
of the Declaration of Independence.
(all laughing)
- Well, the thing is that the faces will still be,
you'll still have the outline of a face
for seven million years before they erode.
- Wow.
- And I read, this is in futility closet,
a website I read this.
The noses are about 240 inches long.
It will be 2.4 million years
before it's down to just a flat face.
If they erode all the way, they'll look like four Voldemort's.
That'd be quite cool.
- Yes.
So in 2.4 million years,
they'll think that four of the first presidents of America
were all Voldemort before, rather than just
the most recent ones.
(all laughing)
- They finished the heads at different times, right?
'Cause they would,
they worked on Washington and then they finished Washington,
then they started on the next one.
So they had different dedication ceremonies
for each one before they did the whole dedication at the end.
And before each dedication,
they would put a massive American flag
over the president's head,
and then they'd drop it to reveal.
- Wow.
- Here it is.
- So does that mean people didn't really know
who it was gonna be before they?
- I think I had a hunch.
- Maybe.
- You know, 90% of it was done with dynamite, Mount Rushmore.
- Yeah, I think that's amazing.
- Yeah, and they got to within four inches
of the final thing, just using dynamite,
and then they had to do the check.
- But the rest was done by hand, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- Like as in, they would make little holes
and then they just grab it out with their hands.
- It's like, called honeycoming.
- We do loads and loads and loads of little holes,
and then just pull it out.
- I think it's incredible that you would do
almost all of it with massive dynamite,
and the last bit, you would just kind of grab it out
with your hands.
- Yeah, that's really cool.
- On the actual baseball card that you can buy
of Nick,
- Contracted to the baseball last well.
He's actually holding one of the honeycomb devices
on the front.
As an old man, he's holding it.
So they've still got the original ones there.
- That's really cool.
- Yeah.
- I do get the feeling you're more interested
in the baseball side of this than the monuments side of them.
- Well, I just thought, yeah, I think it's pretty,
I mean, they clearly are as well.
If you go to the local cafe
on all of their trays is the story of the baseball team.
- They don't even point out the mountain to you.
- There is some barris that that's the focus point.
- Do they have, have they recovered it with those flags?
- Originally, it was not gonna be any president
on Mount Rushmore.
It was just gonna be a mountain.
- No.
- That's how God intended it.
- So the original plan,
before they got a burglum on board
was to have sort of figures from the American West.
So maybe Chief Red Cloud Buffalo Bill
and Lewis and Clark, the two explorers,
who explored a load around there,
and then cuts on to cover.
And he said, "There's absolutely no way
I'm spending my life's work on these non-entities.
It's gonna be presidents or nothing."
And he insisted and they did change the plan.
- Yeah, I have a baseball facts for you, Dan.
- Oh, great.
So during the war, during the Cold War,
America wanted to make a surveillance tunnel in Berlin.
They needed to get something on the floor
on the other side that they could use as a marker,
which is where the tunnel would go to.
And so what they would do is they'd play baseball
right near the wall and deliberately hit the ball over.
So the ball landed there and then they'd be able to survey it
and be able to see where the ball is and use that as a marker.
- Wow.
- So it's like, can we not have a ball back, please?
- Yeah, exactly that.
And what happened was the Germans were just too kind
and they just kept going and collecting the ball back.
- I couldn't do that sort of, so they could never do it.
- Oh, that's awesome, that's so good.
- Like a dog, like an annoying dog in World War II.
And also on baseball, the Americans designed a grenade
that was exactly the same shape and size
and weight as a baseball.
So the Americans could throw it easily.
Think, didn't they?
It was called the bino, really?
- Yeah, and that was to make it because it was,
and it was supposed to be thrown like a baseball
and then it exploded on impact.
- Was it painted as well to look like a baseball
and had stitching on it like a baseball?
- Yeah.
- Was there an amusing mix up at any point with these things?
- Yeah, maybe it's like Christmas and they get in the trenches
and they're like, okay, let's play football.
No, no, let's play baseball.
I brought my own ball.
- According to a medical report published in 1977
and the diseases of colon and rectum,
a 49-year-old man was admitted to San Francisco hospital
complaining of severe pain.
A firm, fixed round object was found to be lodged
high in his rectum.
The man then admitted that he and his sexual partner
had celebrated the Oakland Day's World Series win
by having a baseball inserted into his anus.
(laughing)
- Oh my God.
- Could have been worse.
- Could have been a bat.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, this time for fact number two
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that on some train journeys
in China passengers are forced to take it in turns
to use the seats so that everyone gets a chance
to sit down for some of the journey.
(groaning)
That's good, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- It has the southern rail of countries China.
(laughing)
- So this is the Spring Festival, Chinese New Year,
which is happening at the moment
and it's the biggest migration of humans in the world.
There's like three billion people making journeys
around China and while China infrastructure is pretty good
and it's getting better, it's still that's way too many people
to be moving around and there's only so many trains
you can have and they sell these tickets
and a lot of the journeys are quite long
and so they make a rule where everyone gets to sit down
for a little bit.
But I think that's quite a good rule actually.
- Yeah, that's great.
- Yeah, yeah.
- How many journeys did you second made?
- I've said three billion.
- Yeah, there's three billion journeys, isn't it?
Not three billion people.
- That's amazing.
- You have to go there and you have to come back
and then you might have to change a bit.
- Yeah, exactly.
I wonder if a change counts still as one journey though
'cause it does when you play a ticket, isn't it?
- Did you see that thing in the news?
I think it was today or yesterday where
say you're buying a ticket from London to Bolton.
Then you would have to pay a certain amount of money
but you go on this website and you say where you want to go
and it splits it all up so you might go
London to Watford, Watford to Milton Keynes,
Milton Keyes to Birmingham, Birmingham to Stoke Stoke to Bolton
and it works out the cost of all those
and you can save a load of money.
A lot of football fans from the FA Cup were using it
and they all saved a ton of money.
- Oh yeah, I saw that.
- You went on the news this morning.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- A guy had 52 tickets from one return journey
to a football match.
- 'Cause you need a ticket for each one
of these tiny little things
and so he just has a massive envelope full of tons
of tickets and whether ticker inspector comes,
you're like, okay, it's definitely one of these.
- That's amazing.
- Apparently that is true.
Although I think they're gonna try and make
all their tickets a bit easier
than that news article I read.
They're gonna change a lot of the tickets, aren't they?
There's something like three million different possible
tickets you can buy in the UK
and the majority of them have never been bought by anyone.
- No way.
- There's something like that, yeah.
Anyway, this isn't about trains.
This is about the Chinese movements of people.
- Oh yeah.
- So one thing about Chinese New Year
is that it's very confusing that it's called Spring.
It's called the Spring Festival
because it's obviously in winter.
- It's supposed to be like the start of spring, isn't it?
- Yeah, but it doesn't feel right.
- It's so optimistic.
So I think China divides the year into,
is it 20 sections which have different names
and then there's one section which is the first section
of the year which is start of spring
and that runs for a couple of weeks in mid February.
And so this is called Spring Festival
'cause I think it's the festival that comes
just on the cusp of start of spring period.
- Right.
- Which is just, I mean, it's not spring.
It's sweet that they're convincing themselves that it is.
- And it's called Chinese New Year.
It doesn't even have a new year.
It doesn't even have in first January.
- It's going on.
- Don't you grow up there.
What's this all about?
- What's the deal with Chinese New Year?
- Did you do the thing where you give each other
envelopes with money?
- Yeah, Lycee, it's called.
Or I'd probably pronounce that slightly wrong
but you used to say Gongsi Fatalai, Sitala,
and they would give you a red packet with money inside
and it was living in Hong Kong
which was a very affluent place.
It was amazing 'cause everyone gave you these packets
and it was the time to make money if you were a kid.
You would just walk around and walk up to adults
and say Gongsi Fatalai and they'd just give you a red packet.
And it was, yeah, yeah.
So if you went to a party, it was incredible.
It was like the tooth fairy went nuts
and everyone revealed themselves to be that person
and they're just handing you money.
- Is it just a kid?
'Cause I thought it was everyone
and then I thought at the end of the day
you'd end up equal.
- I left and I was a kid.
So yeah.
- You left a new, you stayed.
Got all the money.
While still a child fled the scene of the crime.
- Very crafty.
Just on the, everyone traveling everywhere
for Chinese New Year, there has been a story
in the news last week about one guy
who started cycling home
'cause he was very poor, couldn't afford a train ticket,
couldn't afford a plane.
So he started cycling really early
and he cycled for 30 days, he went 300 miles.
So 10 miles a day, it was not great.
But, okay, maybe it's a bad bike.
Anyway, he then found out.
- Rocky Turin.
- Yeah, it was gonna be a Rocky Turin.
Exactly, anyway, he then found out
he'd be going the wrong direction for 300 miles.
(laughing)
- No.
- Yeah, well, I don't know
because he was trying to travel 1000 miles supposedly
and it meant that he would have had to take three months
to get home.
So, I can't quite believe it.
But apparently he'd been living in internet cafes
'cause he was really broke.
- Yeah, but maybe he thought
that it was gonna get more than 10 miles a day, probably.
- Probably, yeah.
- Didn't bank on that Rocky Turin and the bad bike.
(laughing)
- Anyway, this was reported in the China People's Daily,
an organization I have no reason to mistrust.
- I remember reading that as well.
And the idea was that he kept asking people
which way to go and they all started telling
in the wrong direction.
(laughing)
- If you kept asking them, presumably,
he'd just have gone back and forth over the same 10 miles
to get it again and again.
(laughing)
- Just, can I just say something about crowded trains?
This is kind of about 'cause I didn't know this was a thing,
but in Japan, in Tokyo, they have pushers at stations
which are people to, I think they're called Oshia
and they're people to push people onto crowded trains.
And someone described it as perfectly happily.
Someone who's been pushed by a person said,
"It's like if you had a big laundry basket
"and it's overflowing, you just full stuff in there."
- You can see footage of this on YouTube,
if you look it up and it's extraordinary.
It's a, there's no more space like literally to even breathe
and you've got people shoving like crazy
to get those doors closed.
It's astonishing.
- And they pull people off as well, don't they?
- That's a bit much.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- How much do you have to give them in a red envelope to do that?
(laughing)
- No, they're called polar offers sometimes.
- No, they're not.
- I've seen them called polar offers.
- Mm, I'm sure.
- Wow.
- We used to have, in Hong Kong,
you used to be able to, in some cases, get your own carriage
if you were Western because of the number four.
So the superstition and number four is so great
that a lot of people wouldn't get anything
that had the number four on it.
- 'Cause it sounds like the word for death is that it?
- Which is death and yeah, it's the number four.
So if, say, a cable car that had number four on it
would be empty and so if you were,
if they could see a Western family,
they would go, come on out, and skip the two.
- Please, please, get into the death carriage.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- In 2005, this is the period when everyone's going
is known as Chunyun, I think.
- Yeah.
- So in the 2005 Chunyun period, the train offices
had certainly less than 100 phone lines,
more than 10, but less than 100.
So somewhere in the tens of phone lines
and they were getting 19.91 million calls per hour.
(laughing)
- You are number 10 million and 12 in the queue.
- Just one last thing, it's the Chinese year of the Cockrole
that's just started.
That's 2017.
Obviously it's every, what is it, every 12?
- 12 years until you return to your animal.
- So one of them was 1945 and 1945 was the first time
that the cartoon character Foghorn Leghorn was ever voiced.
So here's a year of the Cockrole character.
- Oh, that's good.
- And also, have you heard of Mike the headless chicken?
- Yeah.
- Must have done.
He was the guy who there was a family in America
and they were chopping the heads off chickens
and one of them stayed alive and ran around
for a couple of years and he was born also in 1945.
So he was also a year of the Cockrole guy.
- Oh, very nice.
- You know that all very arrogant though,
the year of the Cockrole types, the roosters
and this year of the roosters, the year of the vein,
the arrogant and the emotionally volatile.
- What are you?
- I am a tiger.
- What's your Chinese New Year side?
(laughing)
- It's interesting.
So what the description you just made
is taken very seriously back in China
and there were certain years where pregnancy rates
are extremely low because it's a very bad year
and I wish I could remember of the top of my head.
- And the year of the loser.
- But you have.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for fact number three
and that is Drew.
(laughing)
- Oh, this is the worst new name I've ever had.
I went to an old boy school for 11 years.
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is Lightning.
(laughing)
- My fact is that the moon has been collecting
tiny bits of earth for the last three billion years.
(laughing)
- Collecting.
- Like a baseball card.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Exactly what we're gonna do with them.
- It's going to, it's got an album
and it does swapsies with Venus.
(laughing)
- Yeah, this is really, really cool.
So there's a new discovery which has been published
in nature which is that the moon is dusted
in this fine layer of oxygen
and it was a bit of a puzzle as to how it had got there.
And it turns out that earth basically has a tail
of ions and atoms and electrons and things like this
which lashes out into space behind it.
- Wow.
- And normally the moon doesn't get any of it
but sometimes when the sun, the earth and the moon
are all lined up together, the moon is shielded
from the solar wind, right?
And then it gets a bit of a lashing of oxygen atoms.
So the really cool thing is that we don't have much evidence
of very, very early life on earth
like the first bacteria.
There is a chance that on the moon
there are fossil bacteria which got blasted out into space,
ended up on the moon, then got plowed under the moon's surface
or maybe buried by lava or this kind of thing.
So there's a chance there are fossils up there
of bacteria from the very early days of life on earth.
- Yeah, I mean, pretty unlikely.
- Pretty unlikely.
(laughing)
- That's quite a cool image
'cause obviously the earth is hurdling through space
and it's quite cool to know that we're leaving
like what an asteroid has that sort of tail out of the back.
So it stretches all the way around the sun
in the path that we go in.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, scientists call it a large dusty ring.
- Hmm.
(laughing)
- Good day.
- Yes, they do.
- I don't know why James is cracking up in the morning.
- I'm not laughing at all.
They could do with getting a bigger pump around.
(laughing)
- Yeah, the other thing about this tail that we're shedding
is our magnetic field and it's called a magneto tail,
is that when it does sweep through the moon,
it's full of these really, really hot, charged,
highly charged particles, which it sheds all over the moon.
And that means that on the surface of the moon,
suddenly voltages can climb up to hundreds and hundreds of volts.
So the surface of the moon, it's incredibly electric
'cause we've just shed all these eyes out.
- Wow.
- It's cool, isn't it?
- So Turecan, and if I stood on the moon,
then my hair would all go kind of wild
like had been static electricity fired.
- God, maybe.
- That'd be pretty cool, isn't it?
- You'd have to take your helmet off though,
so you would die, but I think it would be worth it
to find out.
(laughing)
- Could you take your helmet off on the moon
and then put it back on really quickly?
- Yeah. - If you held your breath.
- Well, and repressurise your suit and all of that.
- Yeah, kidding, really?
- As in, you can survive in outer space
for like 20 to 30 seconds without dying.
- But it's not worth the risk
'cause imagine if you took it off,
your hair went so static that you couldn't fit
the helmet off. (laughing)
- Do you know when the astronauts,
the fellows landed on the moon?
What are they called?
- Armstrong and Aldrin, when they landed on the moon,
do you know what the official schedule said?
They should do next.
- What?
- When they landed on the moon,
the official schedule was for them to have a nap.
- Yeah, well that's the whole reason
that a lot of problems were caused
with the actual footage of the moon landing
because they were asleep.
- No, 'cause they were not asleep.
They had scheduled a nap and Armstrong was so awake,
he said I'm not having a nap, we're gonna go out now.
The problem was is that the wrong side
of the earth was facing the moon when he wanted to go out.
So they had to re-root where they were gonna take
the signal from to bring back the signal of the moon.
So Park's observatory in Australia,
suddenly were the key people
because they had access to the moon.
America was on the other side of the...
- Wow.
- All because Neil Armstrong didn't wanna have a nap.
- He refused to have a nap.
So he messed up everything that was meant to happen
in terms of the televised footage.
Do you know what the words of the third man on the moon were?
- You'll do this.
- I do, but say it, yeah.
- That's how I should answer everything.
(all laughing)
So this is Pete Conrad, who went up in the Apollo 12 mission
a few years later.
So he was the third person to walk on the moon
and he had a bet with a journalist
who'd bet that NASA dictated what the first words
of anyone who stepped on the moon had to be
and he was saying no they don't and I'll prove it.
So the journalist told him he had to say a particular thing
and what he said was when he stepped,
when he took his first step, whoopie.
So the thing about this guy was he was a really short guy
and he stepped out and he said whoopie, man,
that may have been a small one for Neil,
but that's a long one for me.
And that was his first words as he stepped out of the spacecraft
and then actually as he stepped onto the moon itself,
he said, ooh, is that soft and queasy?
- Wow.
- Does anyone know the shortest trip ever to the moon?
- Well, let's engrom it, it didn't take very long at all.
Is it that one?
There's a 45 minute special, including the preamble.
(laughing)
- It must be that the moon landed on,
a bit of the moon landed on Earth and so on.
- No, no, just as in, I'm genuinely asking the question,
of all the times that humans have gone
from the Earth to around the moon,
what's the shortest amount of time it's taken?
- Do you mean the full trip?
- All the time. - From here to there.
- Oh. - From here to there.
- I would think it would take a couple of days
to get there.
- So. - That's a long way actually.
It's 250,000 miles can we take.
- I would say nine hours.
- Oh, that's so close.
- Is it?
- Yeah, eight and a half hours.
- That's amazing. - Well, 2006,
it was a new horizons probe.
So it didn't land on the moon,
but it went from the Earth to where the moon is.
- Eight hours. - In eight and a half hours.
- That's crazy.
- And that was in 2006, and the longest ever was in 2003,
and that was one year, one month, and two weeks.
It took them to get from here to the moon.
- Well, they kept asking for directions on the way.
People kept on messing around with them.
(laughing)
It's very rocky terrain, it's nice.
- No, that was a deliberate attempt to do it
with as little kind of fuel as possible.
- It's little publicity or interest.
- How are knowing to pull the short straw
and bid on the year long one?
Although it's been a people one on these, what are they?
- On neither one or any people.
- Yeah, yeah.
- When you think that a few hundred years ago,
it would take six months to get to Australia,
and now we can go to the moon in eight hours.
- Yeah.
- It's a substantial change, it's all the same.
(laughing)
- Up until researching this particular fact,
I would have said, if I was asked the question,
does the earth get heavier or lighter every year?
I would have said heavier.
- You would have said, yeah, I know that,
but what are you saying?
(laughing)
- Yeah, I would have said heavier
because I would have thought
with the amount of space dust and asteroids passing by,
we always hear about stuff coming into our atmosphere
that we would get heavier, but in fact, we do get lighter,
and it's because of all the escaping gas.
- So we expel in terms of stuff out of the atmosphere
and out of earth into space every year,
the equivalent weight of 890,000 humans.
- Wow.
- That's how much goes out.
So that's 50,000 tons that it gets lighter per year,
and we only take on 40,000 from things
entering the atmosphere from space.
- Wow.
- And helium just goes out into space.
I had no idea.
- Yeah, it is.
- When you get a helium balloon and you let go of it,
that's where it goes.
- No, well thank God for balloons.
- The moon is listed with helium balloons.
- I never appreciated what a great invention balloons were.
- Right, here's the thing.
If you do let a balloon go.
- Yeah.
- Words it go.
- It goes up all the leaks out of it
to make its way into space,
and then the balloon falls down again.
- Just pops and a bit of plastic goes somewhere.
- Yeah.
- And that plastic often ends up in the sea,
especially in coastal results or anything like that.
So a lot of places in America,
especially on the east coast, have banned helium balloons.
People letting helium balloons go
because it just causes so much crap in the sea.
- Oh really?
- It's very sensible.
- Yeah, it's good.
- Yeah, it makes sense.
Or you should make all balloons out of fish food.
- Yeah.
- Are you in a gradeable balloon?
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah.
- That must be invented.
- You can make a puff of fish into a balloon.
- You could.
- They do that.
- And then you slow it up with an air hose
like anotelerious Mount Rushmore prank.
You let the balloon go and then it's bleeding
and passing all the gases, stuff, which is so funny.
And then it falls into sea and another fish can eat it.
- They do that in check.
Not the whole story.
They don't chew the club, but they don't love a fish
into a balloon.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Chuzinski.
- My fact this week is that the most deadly user
of Portuguese Man of War Venom is not the Portuguese Man of War.
So the most deadly user of the Portuguese Man of War's Venom
is something that's called a blue dragon sea slug,
which is the most beautiful creature.
If you look it up, it's a kind of nudibranque
which are these little slug-like sea creatures.
It's really lovely looking.
And what it does is it goes and eats the Venom
on the Portuguese Man of War
and then it has these special limbs,
these special organs that are especially for storing Venom
and it pushes it out into these little organs.
These finger-like branches
and it is more concentrated at the end of those branches
than it is in the Portuguese Man of War.
And so when it administers the Venom to someone,
it's actually more effective than when the Portuguese Man of War
does it in Nixit and it makes it better.
- But it doesn't kill the Portuguese Man of War.
It just uses it like a gas station.
Like it goes up and it just fills up on its Venom.
So it sucks it out.
- And it hurts it as well.
- Yeah.
- It's like being hurt at a gas station.
(laughing)
And that happens to me quite a lot of petrol stations
'cause I always try to haggle.
So is it the, so it's the nudibranque who gets hurt?
- The nudibranque gets hurt.
It does have special adaptations
to stop it being too badly injured by the poison
'cause it's really poisonous.
So it has sort of special mucus,
which helps to shield it a bit.
And then, yeah, and then it adapts the stuff.
- Can I ask about nudibranque, really?
- So you would think if you saw a drawing, in the first time,
I think most people did see it,
was a drawing and it was from Captain Cook's Voyages.
It was the artist who did an illustration of it.
You would think it's fake.
You would think that this was a made up secreture.
And it's phenomenal 'cause it swims upside down.
- Yeah.
- And that's a kind of camouflage tactic.
- And it floats upside down at the surface.
Who's to say what's upside down then?
If that's how it lives, it's whole life.
- Yes.
- That's a good point.
So you're saying maybe all other animals are wrong?
- No, what I'm saying is if all humans walked around
with their head near the floor and their feet in the air,
then we would think that was the right way up.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- It's like saying to a bat, you sleep upside down.
- But they do.
- 'Cause I always sleep, I sleep.
- Yeah, this is the right way up.
- This is the right way up.
- Well, why are we launching this war
on correct placement of things?
- You started it.
- Why did it not say it?
- I just don't see that you can say
that he's swimming upside down.
If he spends his whole life upside down,
maybe that's the correct way for him to live.
- Does he spend his whole life upside down?
- I don't think so.
- Okay, so the way he floats is he inflates his stomach.
So I think maybe it's all about what's the back
and what's the stomach.
And the way that this guy floats
is by filling his stomach with gas.
And then he bobbles up to the top of the surface of the ocean.
And then he has his stomach keeping him afloat.
- Prime candidate for this new animal balloon
we've been talking about.
(laughing)
- Well, here's another thing about Needy Banks.
So they all have their anus above their head.
- Yeah.
- Which James is gonna say is perfectly normal
and why don't we all do it?
- No, what I'm saying is, maybe if you look at him
the other way up, which is how he wants to be looked,
that his head is in a perfectly normal position.
- No, because they twist around as they grow.
- So they start off with their anus
not near their head and then as they grow,
I think we talked about this with...
- Snails.
- Snails recently.
So same thing, you see slugs.
Their body twists 180 degrees as they grow.
So they're gills on their anus
that are right by the...
- Who's to say that when they're a baby nudie brink
that they're not upside down then
and they flip to be the right way around?
- You would be like us being born in a hand stamp
as you shouldn't, and us realizing
this didn't feel so right.
- I'm just like, I can't wait for my anus
to be nearer of my head.
Is that what they're all saying?
(laughing)
Can't wait for all the girls to fancy people
when they see how close to my head, my anus is.
(laughing)
- That would...
Their parents must say to them,
"These really are the best days of your life."
(laughing)
- You know, enjoy these days of distance
between your head and your anus when you get.
(laughing)
- There are nudier ranks which have disposable penises.
- Okay.
- So they're an afterlife.
So they both have a penis on their right-hand side.
So they stand next to each other.
- How do you know it's a right-hand side?
- They're not like that.
(laughing)
- So they stand next to each other
facing in opposite directions.
- Yeah.
- And then they sort of lock their penises
into each other.
- Yeah.
- And they transfer sperm both ways.
But then their penises break off
and fall to the ocean surface.
- Do you think that's a really terrifying moment
the first time it happens?
(laughing)
- I imagine it only happens once.
- No, does it?
- So they drop off, fall to the bottom of the sea.
And then within 24 hours sometimes,
they've regenerated a new one.
'Cause most of that penis is a big coil inside them
and it just grows out again.
- Oh cool.
- They would have noticed that
when they were a younger nudie branch alone in their shell,
having a little touch of themselves.
- I think a vigorous session might result in it.
- But again, the first time it happens,
it would be terrifying.
- That's true.
- You couldn't come back home after a night out
if you'd been sleeping around.
You couldn't come back home to your wife
and say, "Oh, nothing happened."
She's like, "Well, why'd you cut, followed up then?"
(laughing)
- So another nudie branch is solar-powered one.
If you guys spread about this one, it's so cool.
So it harvests.
It basically farms algae.
It eats algae and then it uses the photosynthesis
of the algae.
So the algae inside it photosynthesizes using the sun.
And then this is what this nudie branch gets its energy from.
And it has these little solar panels.
So if you look at it, you can see these little brown spots
on it, which are the specific zones
where it's put its algae
so that it can get the light from the sun
so that it can photosynthesize.
- Aren't we all solar powered?
- But we're not using photosynthesis.
And so they get the chloroplasts from the seaweed,
like the little green bits.
And that turns the sunlight into energy.
- Okay, well, that's pretty much it.
- So they can live for a year on sunlight alone, on solar.
- Wow.
- And you're right that all of our energy
eventually comes from the sun.
- Yeah, so like as humans, we're solar powered.
- Yeah, yeah.
- That was pretty much.
- Never thought of being solar powered before,
but I am.
- Well done.
(laughing)
- You are.
- It's worth knowing that about yourself.
- Yeah.
- So I grew up in Australia in my, after I took the money
and run from Hong Kong, and along the beaches,
you get blue bottles and blue bottles
in reading up about Portuguese Manor War
are the same kind of thing.
It's the same kind of animal.
And I thought that was an animal.
I thought it was a jellyfish.
So I've just discovered today that Portuguese Manor War
is basically a team effort of a bunch of different creatures
working as one.
- Yeah.
- Like when the power range is combined
to be that giant robot thing,
it's like that's what a Portuguese Manor War is.
- Yeah, that's a really good analogy actually.
- So I'm really confused about this.
I read somewhere that they were different species,
but they're not different species.
They're different kinds of animal
in the same species, all working together,
all having different things that they specialize in.
- So someone will be responsible for the sex, fun job,
someone's responsible for the digestion,
also quite a fun job.
And then there's probably someone responsible
for sort of pooing and stuff, which is probably less fun.
But yeah, it's like, they're called Siphonophores.
Siphonophores.
And yeah, it's a bunch of tiny organisms
which all perform-
- Dinosaur, yeah.
- They do, I'd never thought about their name before
and why they're called that.
And they're called that because they look like a Portuguese Manor
like a sailing boat.
And they really do.
And they've got this kind of sail
that sticks up out of the water.
And it performs the purpose of a sail,
which I didn't know.
So the way they get around is by, you know,
actively, you have to mate in sailing around
by sticking their sail up in the water.
- Underwater.
- No, no, above the water.
- Above the water.
- They have a surface sail that takes them to places.
- The sail sticks up above the water, it catches the wind.
And then another good candidate for the balloon,
they can deflate their sail
if they see a threat coming along like a turtle.
It's gonna make them.
And then they re-inflate it when it's gone.
- That's amazing.
- So you know how some animals are unbelievably poisonous
to humans.
Like there are frogs that can kill a thousand people
with a single thing.
Yeah, I was reading an article about why this is the case.
Why is it useful for a frog to be able to kill a thousand people
with a single thing?
And the really interesting thing is,
it's not useful at all, right?
It just happens that we're measuring
how many humans something could kill.
Or a snake can kill a quarter of a million mice.
It would be pointless for the snake.
But the thing is, animals always adapt their poison
to what they're hunting, right?
So there are loads of, for example,
hedgehogs that could survive a bite from a snake
which would kill a person much, much bigger.
But hedgehogs and snakes are in an arms race
of who's going to develop more poison
or better poison resistance, right?
So if you find a snake which is unbelievably poisonous,
you can bet there's probably a little rodent out there
which is unbelievably tough
and could take a huge amount of poison before dying.
- So I wonder with those little kind of tiny,
little colourful frogs that live in the Amazon.
- Yeah.
- What you're saying is there's some animal there
that is super hardcore that you just can't poison.
- Yeah, we don't know what it feels on them
that is nearly resistant to their poison maybe
and so they're having to constantly become more poisonous.
- You know that the Brazilian wandering spider
can give you when it bites you an erection.
So intense that you become impotent.
- That is tough, isn't it?
- Well, James found what I think is the best headlight
of the year so far.
I know we're just into early February,
but it was that, what was it?
- James, it was--
- Something like Mafia Boss with Permanent erection arrested.
- Yeah, finally arrested.
Mafia Boss with Permanent erection, finally arrested.
And he has a disease that means that he has a Permanent erection
and so throughout the whole article,
they're talking about his court case
and he's sitting in court.
It says with bag of ice on his genitals.
- He just--
- Permanent erection.
- He didn't want it to stand up and cut.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @shriberland, James, @shaped.
- Andy, @andruhontoemph.
- And Anna, you can email podcast@ky.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group podcast account,
which is @kypodcast.
You can also go to our website.
Know such thing as a fish.com.
That's got all of our previous episodes.
We will be back again next week with another rep.
We'll see you then, guys.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)