[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from four undisclosed locations in the UK.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski, Andrew Hunter Murray and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts
from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
Okay, my fact this week is that the world's best Tetris player is a 13 year old from Texas.
The world's second best player is his 15 year old brother.
Are they also the only remaining Tetris players left on the planet?
No!
Anna, I'll tell you.
It is hugely popular Anna.
Yeah, the third best is done by the sounds of it.
The only other player.
I just think imagine being in that family like your two year younger brother beats you
in the world championships.
But at least you are, you know, at least you're the second best.
So the best player is called Dog Playing Tetris.
I don't think that's his real name.
He beat his brother whose name is Pixel Andy.
The surname of these two people is Arteaga.
And if you go online, you can watch the final.
It's only one hour and 15 minutes with all the interviews as well,
which is 13 minutes shorter than the stop on my mum will shoot.
So it's a good use of your time if you want to.
But this is an interesting thing, I think,
which is that all the best Tetris players in the world were people of my age
who kind of grew up with it.
And then very recently, suddenly all these kids have come in
and started kicking everyone's ass at Tetris.
And the reason is that if you think about how I would play Tetris
as a kid, I would be like on my Game Boy or whatever playing on my own
and wouldn't really talk to anyone else about it and would just have to learn it.
Whereas these days they learn it all on YouTube
and they're all swapping tips and all that kind of stuff.
And so the standard of Tetris has just gone through the roof in the last few years.
I mean, just leave it to us.
Why are they stealing Tetris from us?
They've got a billion new fangled, colourful, high pixel games.
Just let us have Tetris.
No, it's new Tetrises. They're different games.
It's not like the same Game Boy.
That's like saying we shouldn't watch football anymore
because the Great Manchester United team of 1990 is no longer together.
But wait a minute.
I mean, it's still blocks coming down from the roof.
And in the World Championships, they are playing pretty much classic Tetris.
So the basic formula is pretty unchanged.
This is the same game.
Yeah. The classic Tetris World Championships only dates from 2010,
which I think is a massive swish anyway,
because it sounds like it's been going for centuries.
It started as a documentary, the World Tetris Championships.
There was a few people online arguing about who was the greatest ever player
and someone decided, well, let's get all these people together
and have them play against each other.
In that World Championships, the winner was a guy called Jonas Neubauer,
who unfortunately died earlier this year.
But one interesting thing about it, what I was saying,
about how you would kind of learn on your own and now you learn on YouTube,
there was the fourth place person was a woman called Dana Wilcox.
There was only two women in this Championships and she came fourth.
And when she turned up to the Championships,
that was the first time she learned that you can flip the
blocks in two different directions either clockwise or anti-clockwise.
Oh, no way.
And she'd become like one of the top 10 players in the whole world
without even knowing that.
How is that possible?
That's amazing.
Yeah.
I'm trying to remember if I knew that.
No, I don't think I did.
I don't think I did.
I lost to history.
Yes.
You know that champion you mentioned, James, Jonas Neubauer?
Yeah.
He won eight of the first 10 classic Tetris World Championships
and he came second in the other two.
So he's really very good at Tetris.
And he wrote an article in 2019 about his life in Tetris, basically,
which was lovely.
And he said, "Tetris has helped me to make quick and plentiful decisions
in everyday life.
Have you ever been to a restaurant with a 12-page menu?
I can scan the choices and make a decision almost immediately
without a shred of regret.
Even if they bring me the wrong order, I'll make it work."
I love that.
I just think.
Wow.
Yeah.
How does he relate this exactly?
Sorry, what's the logic leap between his Tetris champion status
and the fact he's fast ordering in restaurants?
Because you see the options.
You see the options in front of you.
You get presented with a range of choices and you think,
"Bang, I know how to make that work."
I see.
I thought he was just, he was so desperate to get back to his Game Boy
that he can't find a funny around choosing meals.
Do you think he only orders things like fish fingers and sausages
that are coming in that kind of blocky shape?
Absolutely, absolutely.
Square potato waffle.
Yeah.
That's too funny.
I actually watched an incredible moment in Tetris history.
It was Kevin Birrell who became the first ever Western Grandmaster.
So there's never been a Western Grandmaster outside of Japan.
And he recorded the video that allowed him to become a Grandmaster.
And what you need to do in order to get to Grandmaster level
is you complete Tetris and you then have to play
with invisible blocks over the credits.
And Kevin Birrell recorded him doing this.
It's a minute 40 seconds, which is 48 seconds shorter than,
"Stop on my mum will shoot the trailer on YouTube."
So you can save some time there.
And you watch him going, "Tetris," when he says that,
and the moment that he wins it and becomes Grandmaster,
you are just with him.
It's heaven.
And he's jumping around the room.
Yeah.
Do you think that any Grandmaster,
I'm going to use inverted commas for that, in Tetris,
has ever been introduced to a chess Grandmaster
and really claimed, looked them in the eye and said,
"I'm a Grandmaster too."
To have a Grandmaster Club
where all the Grandmasters of all the different games meet up.
The chess people aren't letting the Tetris guys in that club.
Why?
They are turning those guys away at the door.
You're a Grandmaster and Tetris.
Yeah.
Yeah, no.
Your instinctive finger movements are at a level of no other human.
Chess people take hours to play the game.
They take single move.
That's a fair point.
They're winning on speed.
True.
We haven't talked about the origins of it,
how it was officially owned by the Soviet Union.
It was this guy, Alexei Pajitnov,
who worked at the USSR's Academy of Science
in their computer lab.
And he liked making games.
And he liked geometric games.
And there was one which involved pentominos.
Whereas Tetris users, what are they called?
They're called tetrominoes, because it's four.
And he had made this game.
He didn't really know how to publish it.
And it was already being pirated overseas
because of how popular it was.
So he gave the rights to the government for 10 years.
And then the KGB got involved at one point
in terms of the rights selling.
They always did, didn't they?
They liked to have a finger in most pies back in the day.
Yeah.
He named it after quite odd stuff.
So Tetris, the Tetris and Tetris, that's just the four.
But then the isp bit is because his favorite sport was tennis.
It was mostly more for a man who devotes his life
to sitting in front of a computer screen designing games.
But I suppose you've got to have another hobby.
So yeah, Tetris and tennis.
And I quite like the whole ominos thing.
This grew out of the domino,
which was the original domino,
which is just a piece with two bits.
And then someone decided in sort of,
I think the 60s or 70s to make polyominoes a thing.
So that's one of those shapes
with various numbers of squares in them.
So yeah, you've got dominoes, you've got triominoes,
you've got pentominoes.
Did you say there was an original omino?
Or is that just the...
This is a botched etymology.
No, that's the stem.
Uh-huh.
I don't think it is, though,
because the dot in domino doesn't mean two.
No, no, it's not a proper set.
The dot was domino was a thing.
And then a person said,
"Oh, DOS sounds a bit like it could mean two.
So let's create this whole class of things."
It's fraudulent.
It's a fraudulent etymology, is what I'm saying.
Domino derives from a word.
It was originally, we think, a hood that priests...
Yes, Dominican monks, isn't it?
Yeah, exactly.
And so the domino was the hood worn by the Dominican monks.
You know, it doesn't mean anything.
So what should we call it then?
I haven't got an alternative etymology just lined up,
because I'm not a faker.
I wouldn't do that to you guys.
Okay.
I mean, you seem quite angry about it.
You had a few hours.
I would happily call it a dot domino,
because it's four sections,
and that could be two dominoes together.
Yeah.
Just sounds like you've got stutter.
Do you know why Tetris is so addictive?
This is due to something called the zygarnic effect.
And what it is, is that your brain is hardwired
to whenever there's an incomplete task,
you really, really want to fix it.
And so when the Tetris things come down,
every time you do complete a task
and you get rid of one or four of the lines,
then it always kind of gives you more things to do,
because there are more holes that you need to fill
and stuff like that.
And this was invented by a woman called Bluma Zygarnic,
who was Lithuanian,
and she worked this out quite early in her career.
And then she went on to get a job working for the Soviet Union,
but she carried on as a part-time research scientist,
which I quite like because she was all about
kind of incomplete tasks,
and she decided to carry on working part-time on it.
And then she won the Lewin Memorial Award,
but unfortunately the Soviet Union wouldn't let her collect it,
and she died before she could collect it.
So again, that's another incomplete task in her life.
So she died happy, probably.
Yeah.
She died doing what she loved, not completing a task.
Yeah, exactly.
And then there's the Tetris effect,
which we will have all suffered from.
I imagine.
Yes.
The Tetris effects.
I think this is coined by a wire writer in the '90s,
but basically where you start seeing Tetris blocks wherever you look.
You start, you know,
when everyone played Tetris in the '90s,
you close your eyes and you just see Tetris blocks falling in front of the greens.
And you can expand the Tetris effects to lots of other things.
So it basically means that you're doing something so much
to such a stupid extent
that everything in it is overlaid on the reality around you.
So sea legs is another example of the Tetris effects.
So you get off a boat.
Oh, yeah.
So you're not at sea anymore,
and yet you still feel like you're at sea.
Yeah, right.
Your body's too used to it.
Very nice.
Did you guys hear about the other study that was done on Tetris
about how it can help with traumatic memories?
This is amazing.
It's if you, you've suffered some kind of trauma.
Okay, so in this incident,
it was people who'd been in a traumatic car accident.
If you play Tetris for 20 minutes within six hours of the car crash,
you'll get 62% fewer intrusive memories in the following week.
It seems to prevent negative memories and flashbacks from even forming.
Because you think of Tetris instead or no?
I don't know.
It's kind of that within those first hours
is when the memories get consolidated for long-term storage, basically.
So if you just disrupt during that time,
Tetris seems to be especially good at it,
although I'm sure there are other things which could do it as well.
It kind of prevents the memories from forming in the first place,
and then you don't get flashbacks later down the line.
What if the terrible memory that you have is of being a 15-year-old
and your younger brother beats you in the well Tetris final?
You should play Super Mario.
Just briefly back to Alexei, the inventor of Tetris.
I love that the very first version of it,
he built on a computer that had no graphics capabilities.
So he had to make a text version of the game.
So the blocks were basically brackets put next to each other.
That was the first version.
And then Alexei didn't just invent Tetris.
He sort of quite quickly invented newer versions of the game.
So did any one of you guys play Hattris?
Hats come down with different, like a top hat and the, yeah.
It's literally that, it's literally that.
It's Tetris with hats and hats come down and you have to line them up.
So he invented Hattris and then...
I thought it was just playing Tetris three times.
It sounds a bit like it's called a Hattris.
That would be a fake etymology, Anna.
So sorry.
Yeah. So five hats of identical style had to be stacked.
And that's how you would remove them.
And entertainment weekly at the time said,
there is after all a cure for Tetris addiction.
It's Hattris habit that's even harder to kick.
There's word Tris as well, which was another Alexei game.
So word Tris, I actually think would be really fun.
The idea is that you had to create blocks of three letters.
So letters would drop and you'd have to create a word.
So you could make it, it's basically like a big crossword
and you just have to decide where to land a letter,
hoping, yeah, the next one, yeah, pretty cool game.
Do you know, I think that James would have point blank,
refused to play Tetris when it first came to the world.
So it was Andy sort of referenced it earlier,
but it was a big deal that it was a Soviet export.
And it was really, and no one had ever really
exported something for financial gains in the Soviet Union before
because it was so difficult to do
because that just wasn't what they were about, obviously.
So came out and the West was kind of very excited
and it seems like the Soviet Union aspect was a bit of a gimmick.
So they included the right visuals
on the Tetris packaging for the West.
And so, of course, when you got the Tetris box.
Oh my God, I know.
Backwards are, backwards are.
Oh my days.
I'm afraid it was backwards are.
Oh my.
I'm afraid it was spelled with the backwards are.
Brilliant practice.
Absolutely furious.
It's really, I think it's like the Tetris effect
that when you learn in Russian
and you just see these backwards letters everywhere,
you can only read them because you're used to doing it.
You can only read them in the correct way.
And it just, none of the words make any sense.
Maybe we're supposed to be pronouncing Tetris that way.
So how should we be pronouncing it, James?
It would be like.
But then also there's no I in the Russian language that looks like an I.
So.
I'm now picturing how pissed off James
must have been going to buy this backward are Tetris
as he's walking into Toys R Us to get it.
[LAUGHTER]
Hey, can I give you one last fact?
Which is that the link between Tetris and cats.
Was there a catress them?
There wasn't a catress.
I mean cats, the musical specifically.
Oh.
Which is that the text theme reached number six
in the UK charts in 1992.
And Andrew Lloyd Webber was the man behind it.
I bought it.
I remember.
Did he really?
Yeah, yeah.
He had a pseudonym.
He said he had the pseudonym Dr. Spin.
So you, James, walking to the shots would have just thought,
"Oh, I'm going to get the cool new track by Dr. Spin."
It was actually Andrew Lloyd Webber.
I think we knew at the time that it was Lloyd Webber.
I think.
I can't really remember it very well.
But it was like at the time,
a lot of video games kind of came out as dance tracks.
OK.
Oh, cool.
Andrew Lloyd Webber composed the tune.
No, he remixed it, didn't he?
Because it's an old, it's a very old, well, it's in Tetris.
So it sort of existed.
It's a Russian folksong.
Yeah.
It's by Nikolai Nekrasov.
And it's the story of a young peddler
who seduces a peasant girl in a field of rye.
And he keeps saying that he'll offer her
like some of his goods in return for a kiss slash a shag.
And then she accepts a ring from him
and he goes to sell his wares.
And he says, "When I get all my money,
then we'll kind of get married and stuff."
And that's where the song ends.
But the original poem, he actually gets robbed
and killed by a forest ranger when he asks for directions
on his way to the market.
But that's not in the song.
Game over.
OK, it is time for fact number two, and that is Anna.
My fact this week is that the Indian state of Madhya Pradesh
has ruled that all government offices must be cleaned
with cow urine on pain of death.
No, it's not death.
But it is a new ruling.
So Madhya Pradesh is the second biggest Indian state in size
and it's got 72 million people living in it.
And the government has released an order
saying that usually they'll use chemically made fennel,
P-H-E-N-Y-L, sort of chemical.
Oh, right, not there.
Oh, yeah.
Not the aniseed tasting vegetable.
Sorry, they're not just rubbing licorice flavour
all over the offices, although that would be awesome.
And they have to use cow urine instead
or use sort of an acid extracted from cow urine.
And the decision was made in a cow cabinet
that was held for the last year.
I think it's kind of quite a similar fennel or fennel
that they make from the cow urine, isn't it?
It's kind of a very similar thing.
And is it the insides of the offices
or is it like the walls on the outside or what do you know?
Oh, I think it's the insides.
I thought it was sort of like floors and surfaces.
Yeah, so in place of detergent, right?
Yeah, that's what you scrub with.
And the idea is they want to create demand for cow urine
in order that the state sets up loads of cow urine
bottling factories and cow urine extraction factories.
So they think that if they make this ruling
that they'll have to set up factories
that manufacture cow urine for them.
Okay, and the idea is that at the moment people keep cows,
especially for milking,
but then the male cows are often kind of abandoned often.
And so by creating this demand,
it means that if you have a male cow,
then you might not abandon it
because you can milk it for its urine.
Ah, that's a purpose.
I would have thought looking into the amount
that cow urine is used in India for various different things,
you wouldn't have a need for sort of creating more demand.
Yeah, well, there's a thing there,
which is that there are literally millions and millions
and millions of cows on the loose in India,
too sacred to be killed to the Hindu religion.
And so it is a supply and demand situation,
but unfortunately the supply is so massive compared
with a number of people willing to use cow urine for whatever.
So what else do they use it for, Dan?
So, you know, some people drink it there.
It's seen as a health drink.
I read particularly about one of Bollywood's biggest actors,
Akshay Kumar, who drinks it every single day
because it's part of his fitness regime.
So that's one of the things.
It's used for religious services as well.
So if a new baby is born
and you want to sort of bless your house for good luck,
you might, you know, put some cow urine around the house
in order to do that.
In fact, they sell it in London.
You can buy cow urine in London specifically for that,
that I believe is imported sometimes from India,
but also they manufacture it in Watford.
And it's called Gal-Mutra.
And there was a BBC report where they found it being sold
in certain shops sort of on the shelf above the naan bread.
And there was questions about whether or not
you should be doing that because it's...
Yeah, we should say this doesn't, it doesn't work.
It's not good for your health.
No, it doesn't help anything.
It doesn't have health properties.
We know that.
Do we know that for sure?
No, we don't know.
But I imagine it works no better than placebo
and in lots of cases, quite a lot worse than placebo.
It can contain harmful bacteria and cause diseases
such as leptospirosis, whatever that is.
Oh, right.
But are they in India where technology, science
is such a big thing?
Is there a big split between the people
who believe that this is useful than the people?
Is it kind of like homeopathy over there?
It's not seen as part of science.
It is, but obviously it's incredibly widespread.
So it's part of the Ayurveda medicine, isn't it?
Which 80% of people in India would subscribe to that
to some extent, I think.
But there definitely is a divide.
So for instance, here with this ruling,
there is a rival body that's been set up,
which has launched a competition
to challenge people to apply the scientific method
to all these claims that the government's releasing
about the good that cow urine can do
and basically prove that it can't do any good.
Because it's a big push by the government.
It's huge at the moment.
So there are cow ministries popping up
all over the country and cow ministers in states.
And it's kind of related a little bit
to obviously a bit of Hindu nationalism
at the top of government
and it promotes that side of things.
So yeah, there is a divide, but it's really widespread.
Okay.
Hey, by the way, if you spill your cup of cow urine
while you're drinking it in the office,
do you just sort of leave it?
Because it's what cleans up the office now?
Well, okay.
If you are in the office and you have a glass of water
and you spill it, do you just leave that?
Well, you've asked the wrong person here.
But would a normal person clean up?
Yes, I imagine they won't.
Well, yeah, I think you can analogize from that.
Yeah, it is really good analogy.
It is really bad.
Lots of scientists in India have basically
been under governmental pressure
to make research proposals
on the subject of Gomutra, which is cow urine.
Or the related substance, Pantrigevia,
which is a mix of milk, yogurt, butter.
Lovely so far.
Then cow urine and cow dung on top of that.
And basically they're saying
they won't get research funding
unless they research this stuff.
So, yeah, it's a problem.
Pantrigevia means five cow derivatives.
Just a bit of etymology.
Oh, that's clever.
It's just every bit of the cow,
apart from the meat, of course, goes into it.
Arguably, I would say the nicest bit,
although that wouldn't get me very far in India
because eating cows is so verboten
in almost all the country.
Cow politics in India dates back to the '60s.
And this was when Indira Gandhi was in charge.
Indira Gandhi, who was the daughter
of the famous politician...
I'd say...
Nehru!
I've completely ruined it.
I'm so sorry.
I was so excited that I learned that
from my Asia and Africa course at university in second year.
My foot was hovering over the landmine
and Anna just stepped in and put a safe mat in.
I can't believe I did that.
I apologise to the listeners.
I apologise to my parents.
I've been looking forward to that all week.
I knew he was going to fall for it.
Yeah, Nehru's daughter, wasn't she?
Look, we'll cut that.
Do it again.
Right, go.
I'll say quiet.
So, in 1966, there was a storm of the Indian parliament.
They were trying to pressurise Gandhi
to criminalise cow slaughter.
And she refused to kind of count out
to what they wanted.
And she had, like...
Well, very funny.
Oh, yeah, I didn't think that.
Yeah.
That's one thing that I hadn't been looking forward to all week.
I know you think that I was.
And you think that I've been leading up to that.
And that's the whole point of this fight, but no.
So then Gandhi negotiated with these protesters.
And actually, people really started respecting her
a lot more after that.
And her party, Congress, they chose the cow and calf symbol
as a result of this.
And then cow politics kind of became
quite a big thing in India.
But what I like about Indira Gandhi is
she started at quite a young age.
When she was 12 years old, she led a bunch of children
in a group called the Monkey Brigade,
which included 60,000 young revolutionaries.
And they would like send letters to people.
They would make flags.
They would put up notices before the demonstration
and stuff like this.
And even before that, when she was five years old,
she burned her own doll because she found out
it was made in England.
Wow.
Yeah.
The Monkey Brigade sounds like a deceptively innocuous name
for a bunch of revolutionaries.
It sounds like you're getting you little monkeys
as they're burning your house down.
Yes, correct.
It's the Lord Rama in the epic Ramayana
had an army of monkeys.
And so they were named after that.
And so what's the connection of why she has the name Gandhi?
Is that through a marriage or is that something to you?
She, I think, if memory serves, she was educated in England maybe,
but she met someone who was not related to Muhammad Gandhi
at university, I think.
Right.
It happened to be called Gandhi.
Yeah.
Wow.
It's a good name.
It's a good name to sort of take to the world of politics.
Like, if I was a politician and I had the chance
of changing my surname, I would so look for someone
with the surname Obama.
I just would.
What's your name, Cathy Obama?
Absolutely, we're marrying.
OK, here is another use of cow excrement.
It can be used as a mobile phone case.
There's one quite hard line Indian politician called
Shankar Lal who says that he has coated his mobile phone
with cow dung and he said, if cow dung can treat cancer,
why can't it save us from a phone's microwaves?
OK, there is a flaw in that logic, isn't there?
It's an if and it's a big if cow dung can treat cancer
because it can't.
It absolutely can't do that.
And this is a man who's speaking with poo down half
of the side of his face.
So, I wouldn't take him seriously, would you?
OK, it is time for fact number three and that is Andy.
My fact is that in 2020, a woman in the UK
received medical treatment in two different hospitals
at the same time.
What?
How is that?
I don't get it.
It's great.
Hey, what?
So exciting.
So this was a story that was in the news.
It was about a lady called Jan Ritzen
and she had a cancerous tumor in her leg.
Now, she needed to have the operation where the shin bone
was removed and then treated for the radiation.
But unfortunately, due to COVID, all sorts of cancer
operations have been moved to a specific hospital
which has been kept clear of COVID patients.
So procedures have kind of been separated out.
So the surgeons who were planning the operation
realized that they had to take out her shin bone,
take it to a different hospital, irradiate it
to completely kill any cancerous cells
while she was still under anaesthetic,
then bring it back and reinstall it in her leg.
Oh my God.
Unbelievable.
I know.
I phoned the surgeon who did the operation to ask him about it.
Oh, cool.
Yeah, he's an orthopedic on a call.
A psychologist called Ashish Mahendra.
And we had a whale of a time talking about it
because it's just such an interesting kind of miraculous procedure.
Was he the surgeon who dealt with it at the hospital
where she was or where the shin was?
Or was he just like the taxi driver?
No, no, no.
OK, so he was where the majority of Ms Ritzen was.
He was with her, most of her.
He wasn't with the shin bone.
I read him one article.
I don't know if Dr Mahendra said this to you,
but that she could watch the footage
of her shin bone being dealt with from her hospital bed.
So they filmed it and she could watch it.
But you said that she was anaesthetized,
so I don't know if that's possible.
Well, why would you want to watch that?
Oh, why not?
Oh, yeah.
I mean, what else is on Snooker at the moment?
I don't know.
Netflix?
You got Netflix.
Watch Stopping Your Mum or She?
I don't know.
Come on.
You'll watch an hour and 15 minutes of nerds playing Tetris
and you won't watch your own shin bone being operated on.
Well, is it a whole channel?
Can I flick over to someone's nose being operated on
in a separate hospital?
Like, is it just one?
I did say, when I spoke to Mr Mahendra,
he did say that she was under.
I'm pretty sure that he said that.
So I don't know whether she was on.
It's possible.
I think maybe she might have watched it afterwards, maybe.
She might have watched it on plus one or something.
Yeah.
But it's such a tricky operation to do this,
because when you remove...
Most of these tumors happen higher up,
maybe the knee or the hip, that's more common.
And reconstruction is much easier,
because you can give someone a hip replacement, can't you?
Or you can put some metal in which does the job.
When it's a shin bone,
it's much harder to reconstruct after the operation.
There's not much muscle cover.
The bone is really near the surface.
And there are many fewer options for reconstruction afterwards.
So the bone, the shin bone they had removed,
was the best thing to go back in.
And that's why they needed to do that.
They irradiated the bone, killed off all the cells.
But unfortunately, then you've killed off all the cells.
There's no live matter left in that bone,
and there normally is in our bones.
So they had to use her fibula, which is the next door bone,
and kind of use that as a spare
to put that right against the now dead shin bone
that was being reinstalled.
And that then helped to bring that bone back to life.
So amazing what we can do.
And then did you have to have like an arm bone taken out
to replace the fibula and then the side bone to replace the arm bone?
It's not like rearranging a spice rack where you think,
"Oh, well, if I just put that there."
The only other thing I asked about was the container they used,
because it's put in a special sterile container
to be driven across the city.
And he said there's no specific optimum size of the container.
It depends on the tumor, it depends on the bone.
So frequently they will have to tailor make
a suitable container for the bone that is being moved around.
I spoke to my sister-in-law, Beth, who used to be a nurse,
and she said that she thought probably the reason they don't do it much
is because of contamination, right?
You don't really want to be taking stuff
across the other side of the city
in case you get some dust on it or a bit of grease or something.
But then she did tell me that what they used to do
to stop that sometimes with...
You know, when you had to remove some skull,
some of your skull to release some pressure,
they would take that bone and then they would put it
inside your belly almost, like inside your body,
because that's where the perfect sterile place is for human bone.
Isn't that amazing?
Like they would cut you open, cut a little flap,
they would put it in there while they let it all the pressure release
and then they'd put it back.
That's incredible.
Isn't that amazing?
That's amazing.
I was talking also to a surgeon.
So my buddy Harry, Harris Akram, is a brain surgeon in London
and he was saying that when he was in India,
the hospital that he was staying at,
you would be fitted with this frame around your head.
Imagine like in all those sort of mad scientist movies
where they put this giant frame on your head.
So it's metallic and it's big and it really sits on and clamps on.
So they would put that on there.
But at the surgery in India, they didn't have an MRI scanner.
So they used to send their patients on the bus over to another hospital
wearing the frame on their head.
They would go have the scans done and be prepped
and then get the bus back and then have their surgery
once the scans have been sent over.
Yeah. So in India, you would see people with these giant frames on their head
who were just transporting themselves to a different hospital.
Very good for social distancing.
Because from what you're gesturing here,
it looks like you couldn't get that close to them.
Yeah, it's quite a big item.
It sounds like that thing on SOAR that rips people's heads open.
Like you put them in this contraption
and if you don't get the key in time,
I'm the only one who's seen that movie, okay never mind.
It's not a reassuring thing to say to the person who's diagnosed on the bus chains
on the way to their brain surgery.
I was reading actually a study about a particular brain surgery
where the surgeons use stickers to label little bits of the brain.
So this is kind of just a throwaway comment in this study,
but they referred to it as intraoperative electrical stimulation mapping
and they were basically trying to work out
which bits of their brain are responsible for which things.
And so what they did was they would have a,
you know, when patients are awake but you're operating on their brain,
the surgeons stimulated different parts of their brain
and then looked at what the patient did to see which things it affected.
So if they prodded one bit, the patient might lose language.
If they prodded another bit, the patient might start dribbling or something.
And then they added a little label to each little bit
saying language bit, dribbling bit, walking bit, playing the violin.
So I didn't see a picture but I'm imagining a brain covered in post-its.
That was incredible.
There was another world world first of surgery which happened last year.
This was the world's first double penis removal.
Just from one person.
From the same person.
It was a baby boy who was born with three penises.
One, not two, but three.
Yeah.
It's the first recorded ever case of human trifalia which is correct.
I was going to say tree-ness but that's
That's Alexi's latest game he's working on.
Anyone for tree-ness?
That's incredible.
Do they keep the middle one or the left one or the right one?
Ooh, good call.
They kept the functional one.
Which, yeah.
The other two were more stubs than full-on.
They would have been able to get erections in but they were built.
Could they urinate?
Could you urinate out of them?
You don't know if the chords.
Yeah, no, fair enough.
Fair enough.
Like a sprinkler system though, Dan.
You think you could stand him in a garden when he's older?
You could stand at all three urinals at the same time.
You could piss on three people's shoes at the same time.
Do you think you would keep them if that happened to you?
Would you ask to keep them because people do that for surgery, don't they?
It's a vex question.
Yeah, I don't know.
You wouldn't wear the mizirings or anything but you might keep them in a drawer.
Put them on a mantelpiece or something?
I wouldn't know someone who kept her hip bone after it was replaced, yeah.
Yeah, I was talking to someone we all know, Kase Molaker,
who's the curator of the Natural History Museum in Rotterdam.
Anytime he has surgery that is removed, a bit of his body is removed.
So like gallstones or anything like that,
he keeps it in a jar in his home and he's shown me them.
And all the things to do with his kids when they were born, placentas and so on,
they're all in formaldehyde sitting in his house.
I know what you're saying, Dan.
I love Kase, but he is a bit weird, so it's not...
Oh, he should turn it into a museum and call it Kases Cases.
Oh, that's good.
That's wrong.
Lovely.
Yeah, tall.
Yeah, it's weird the whole "do you keep your limbs" stuff.
I was reading a thing online from someone who used to work in a funeral home
and said that they'd been asked to keep a leg in a freezer
and it ended up being for over a decade
because the person who'd had it amputated
wanted to be buried with it in the end.
Wow, that's nice.
I think that's a bit cheeky.
Why?
Well, it's using someone's freezer space, isn't it?
If I said to Andy, "I've made some lasagna and I want to keep it,
but I don't have enough room in my freezer,
can I keep it in your freezer?"
I think, I'd say yes.
I know, but you would feel like you had to say yes.
As the years went by, I would slowly grow more lasagna in the freezer.
I think, "I've got some leftovers, but I can't freeze them
because James had bloody lasagna."
And you'd probably keep occasionally bringing up lasagna
just in case I remembered that, wouldn't you?
James, every conversation we had, I would bring up lasagna in some way
or freezing or leftovers.
Yeah, but this lady can't go.
Any plan on dying soon?
That's the only question she can ask.
Hey, no.
How's your health?
You can come to a rental agreement in the end.
I imagine that the rental agreement would be the best way for you.
Really? Okay.
Where James has to be for 50p a year, you could keep.
You're going to charge me to pop my lasagnas in your freezer.
After two years, James, which is my cuss off,
but I think that's reasonable, I would insist on some kind of arrangement.
That carefully, I thought we were friends.
I don't know if you've got a freezer.
I'm not getting involved in this.
49p a year.
[Laughter]
You get briefed on how to care for your limbs if you choose to keep them.
Do you get told?
Because you can be given them in formaldehyde and water.
For instance, there's one way they get stored.
And apparently you get a little briefing booklet,
which says you need to change the formaldehyde and water every 10 years.
So just setting alarm every 10 years is like changing the fish tank,
which I think is about the same from memory.
That is a great alarm to go off mid-meeting, isn't it, Eric?
[Laughter]
Oh, damn, sorry.
I just got to change the water and formaldehyde of my leg.
Just lean over behind you and release one spigot.
Start draining.
Do you know that people didn't really like wearing surgical gloves
when they first came in?
Like any technology, I suppose.
There's always some resistance.
But there's quite a lot of hesitation with surgical gloves,
because people would kind of root around with their hands,
and they felt like if they wore gloves,
then they wouldn't get the feeling,
and they wouldn't be able to do the job quite as well.
But one of the reasons is because some of the gloves that they used
were not exactly good for purpose.
So the first ones were like elbow length cotton or silk gloves,
and they would just get covered with blood within about two seconds,
and you'd have to keep changing them.
And then there was one surgeon who put wax directly onto his hands,
and so kind of dunked his hand in some molten wax,
and then let it dry, and then would use that.
And the idea, of course, was to try and make the operation sterile,
but a lot of people thought that maybe that's a bit pointless.
They thought it's impossible to make everything completely sterile,
so we should just accept there'll be some contamination,
but then try and kill the bacteria afterwards.
Do you know what I mean?
So there's like these two kind of sites of what they should do.
But now they use gloves.
Now they use gloves.
Which did they go with?
Yeah, although I'm not sure.
I think sterilization for operations, largely speaking, is orthodoxy now.
It's the preferred way.
Although sometimes you don't have a choice.
There was a case in 1995 when a woman just was getting onto a plane and slipped,
and she thought she was okay,
but then it turned out that she'd fractured her rib,
which had punctured her lung.
And the plane was already in the air,
and so they weren't going to be able to do an emergency landing
because the change in pressure might kill her.
And so they had to do something about it.
And there's these two doctors called Angus Wallace and Tom Wong.
And the case was written up in the British Medical Journal,
which honestly is such a good read.
It's an incredible story.
And they used a, they kind of got a urinary catheter,
which was in the first aid kit,
but it wasn't good to be used for a chest.
So they had to use a clothes hanger to stiffen it up.
They didn't have any sterilization stuff.
So they used Covoisier cognac to make it sterile.
They didn't have any surgical clamps.
So they held the incision open with a knife and fork.
Sorry, it's the first aid kit that's supposed to be on board.
Well, since then, since this happened,
the medical kits on certainly British airlines,
and I think American as well,
and probably throughout most of the world have improved a lot,
and they've got a lot more stuff now.
So I read the story too.
And I love that she had complained about it before the plane took off.
And she said that she'd had a slip and it was this rib problem.
So the doctors actually saw her before the plane took off
and they went, "Okay, no, you should be fine."
And then when it got up to high altitude,
it started really hurting.
And then she came clean that she hadn't just slipped.
She'd actually been knocked off her motorbike and hit by a car.
Just before getting on the plane.
So it was a proper accident.
Actually, it was 10 minutes, this bit of surgery,
and then they put this catheter in
and she spent the rest of the flight just watching the movie.
Yeah, unfortunately, it was top of my mumbled.
She died of boredom.
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that in 1990,
five children in America were given the first name
spelt A-B-C-D-E, or "absody".
All were born in Hawaii,
where the local alphabet doesn't actually contain the letters B, C, or D.
Wow, there's a lot of things to unpick here.
So it's pronounced absody.
There's actually a couple of pronunciations,
but that is one of them, yeah.
And sometimes pronounced absity,
which is what I'm going to call my gym.
Yeah, so this was in an article that sort of erupted in 2018
when a girl who was trying to book herself,
her mom was trying to get her and her daughter
onto Southwest airplanes,
they took a picture and put it online going,
"Look at the name of this girl.
She's her first name is A-B-C-D-E."
And kind of shamed her and that turned into a national story.
But then people were digging into it and finding out
that this isn't as rare a name as one girl in America.
It turned out that as of 2017, 373 girls
were named A-B-C-D-E, or "absody".
And further people have done sort of their little checks
into how far back the name goes.
And in 1990, five were registered as being given that name.
And all five of them were located in Hawaii.
And yeah, and it's been growing ever since as a name.
And it doesn't really have an origin as far as I can tell.
Well, I mean, it does probably, but no one knows it.
It must have started somewhere,
it must have met some alphabet teacher
in primary school going,
"Oh, I think that sounds like a nice name."
And spread from there, but we'll never know,
unless someone out there does.
Yeah, and it's, yeah.
So, so the Hawaii,
this is the modern Hawaiian alphabet that doesn't have it.
And I looked up our names.
James, there's no J in the Hawaiian modern alphabet as well.
So your name is different.
So Anna, your name,
if you were being translated into Hawaiian name,
is still Anna with one N, A-N-A.
James, you are Kimo, K-I-M-O.
Strong.
I am Caniella.
So K-A-N instead of a D.
And Andy, you are Analu.
A-N-A-L-U, that's what you are.
Analu, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, Analu.
I like, I like that pronunciation
and I'm sure it's correct.
I don't know what the pronunciation is.
It's A-N-A-L-U, yeah.
It sounds like a product.
Are you bored of Anasol?
Then try Analu.
I thought it sounded like a bathroom cleaner.
It's more like something to sit next to the cow urine, I think.
A sequel to Despicable Me.
Analu.
So baby names.
Baby names, we only know about baby names
due to a guy called Michael Shackleford, who in the...
Before him, people just didn't give Baby's names.
They were like, "What's this called?"
No idea.
Just don't know.
1997, so late.
We need Michael Shackleford here.
He was a guy who...
What are you talking about?
He worked at...
So it's the sort of...
We only know that there are 373 absities,
for example, because of Michael Shackleford.
He worked at the Social Security Administration in Baltimore
and he and his wife were expecting a baby
and he just wanted to know if they were going to have
a baby with a very common name,
because he was called Michael,
which was a massively common name in America.
And, you know, wherever you go,
three people born in his generation,
you know, someone shouts, "Michael,
three people turned around."
And they didn't want that.
So he thought he'd just program
in a little computer program
and work out the names.
And he thinks he was the first person
to see an accurate nationwide sampling of first names.
Wow.
And that was 1997.
Good old Mike.
A lot of people listening now think that I'm saying...
I read an amazing book called
Fru Fru Frisbee and Brick,
The Book of Unfortunate Baby Names by Russel Ash.
And it's got people such as Mabel Abel, Ruth Booth,
Danny Fanny, Hugh Glue, and Nelly Smelly.
These are all people who were around.
There was someone in the 1830s in New York
called Preserved Fish.
His father was called Preserved Fish
and his grandfather was also called Preserved Fish.
But his father and grandfather were both blacksmiths,
but he was actually a shipping merchant.
He started off as a whaler
and then started selling fish.
And he was called Preserved Fish.
Amazing.
That's brilliant.
That's pretty much the most...
It's not a subtle, nominative determinism, is it?
Yeah.
It's a bit too on the nose.
I like it.
Does it help the name when you add the third to the end of it?
I don't know.
Preserved Fish the Third.
Yeah, just sort of like, why are you called the...
Okay, the third.
I get it.
You've got weird-ass grandparents and parents.
Eurythroscoggins, Philae leg and posthumous mints.
Just three others.
Philae leg?
Philae, P-H-E-L-I-A, leg.
Posthumous mints.
I want all my mints to be posthumous.
Well, I've got some lasagna in my freezer, Anna.
I think you've been very welcome to.
Do you know when Baby sort of naming books took off?
1997.
No one had books before then.
Well, there were...
I mean, they sort of really did take off in the 80s.
But actually, they do date back way before that,
sort of names of interesting babies.
But they used to be in the back of cookbooks,
because cookbooks used to have all kinds of extra gubbins
in the later pages just to kind of pad out the recipes, I guess.
So Mrs. Clark's cookery book in 1883 was subtitled,
including what to name the baby.
It was kind of general all-purpose household guide.
So you've got that kind of thing in the 19th century.
It's weird, because you don't want to confuse a recipe
with a baby name.
I don't know what.
No, that's how actually preserved fish got his name.
Posthumous mints, yeah.
Couple of people who do have Hawaiian names that we all know.
So Keanu Reeves.
Keanu is a Hawaiian name.
And yeah, and it's a lovely unique name in Hollywood,
and it means cool mountain breeze.
But when he first started in Hollywood,
his agent said, this name's not going to work.
You need to go away and come back with another name,
because no one's going to hire you.
It's too weird.
So he agreed, and he went away, and he came back,
and he said, I've got my new name to his agents.
And they said, OK, what is it?
And he said, I want to now be known as Chuck Spadina.
Chuck Spadina.
So yeah, his agent said, I'm not sure that Chuck Spadina's
going to work.
Go away, come back with another one.
So then Keanu Reeves went away, brainstormed, came back,
and said, OK, I've got my new one.
I'll now be known as Templeton Page Taylor.
And they said, what?
Mate, you're not getting this.
And so they said, just keep Keanu.
And that's the only reason he kept it.
He was so ready to change it to either of those names.
So do you think that he came up with these stupid names
to stop the idea of him having to change it?
It was like a clever thing.
God, do you think he just is an idiot who doesn't know?
One all name at a time.
I think, yeah, I hadn't actually thought that.
So maybe that's exactly what he was doing.
Yeah, not sure.
It's sort of, that story reads like you're reading
Rumpelstiltskin backwards, doesn't it?
When you go and try and guess at the name every day.
Yeah.
In 1900, 91% of all children were given a name
from the top 1,000 most popular names.
This is in America.
But by 2000, only 75% of girls were given a name
from the top 1,000.
And for boys, it was 86%.
So a lot more children have been given unique names
or very unusual names.
And they've looked into this.
So it was a 1995 study and they find it's very common
in African American families.
And they looked at the whole country
over the whole of that century.
And they found that in Illinois in 1920,
31% of African American girls and 25% of African American boys
had unique names in the whole country.
And the reason they think this,
there's someone called Sandra L. West,
who is a co-author of the Encyclopedia of the Harlem Renaissance.
And a couple of scholars called Ayanna F. Brown
and Janice Tuck Lively.
And what they think is basically the surnames
that African American families have are often things
that were given during slavery times.
And they were forced upon them by white people.
Whereas the first name is something that's given to you
by a loved one, by a family member.
And so people will give names that kind of show
that they're loved by their family.
They can show that by giving them unique sort of special first names
because they're stuck with these old fashioned surnames.
That's interesting.
That we are definitely getting more into our unusual names.
There have been various studies about why we have,
but I mean, it's largely obviously
because we're a bunch of individualistic millennials,
I suppose, and everyone wants a special name for their kid.
But there's also a really interesting study
which I thought sounded like rubbish.
And then I saw it being written up in a serious and reliable way
about how there's an exact correlation between how recently
a U.S. state joined the union
and how many newborn babies get unusual names.
And so there's the idea that if you're a frontier settler,
so you're going and you're settling a new land,
you are more sort of bold.
It's more bold society.
It's more individualistic.
It's more gung-ho, get out and make your own way.
And it's much more likely that you'll be willing to break the mold
and give your kid a weird name.
So there's literally an exact inverse correlation
between common names and how recently a state was settled.
Same with Canada.
On the east of Canada, which was settled first,
kids have much more common names.
But the west of Canada, which was settled more recently,
still has that hangover of,
"Yeah, when you hear, we'll do what the fuck we want."
And that correlates.
Wow, that's a very interesting idea.
Not many Ivankas, it turns out,
that people thought that perhaps there might be more Ivankas
because she was a prominent political figure.
Do you know why that might be?
Not many Ivankas.
Because it sounds Russian-y,
which might be a bit off-putting to all Americans.
There's something about that.
Basically, there is not much fashion at the moment
for any name which contains the letters N and K
next to each other.
This is according to Laura Wattenberg,
who wrote the baby name wizard book
and runs babynamewizard.com.
She said that basically NK is very much out of fashion.
So Frank, for instance, very much out of fashion.
Frank Ivank, anything like that.
Yet my son, Wanker, is fucking the trend.
You can get consultants, can't you?
You can get professional advice on this, if you like.
There are various services which do it.
There's one which I found in America, which is called,
I love this, it's called Appalachian Mountain.
So it's Appalachian as in naming,
but obviously there are the Appalachian Mountain.
Thank you, Andy.
Just in case not everyone knows the Appalachian Mountains,
they're not in the top three mountain ranges, I would say.
I reckon I'm more familiar with the mountain range
than the word to mean to give someone a name, actually.
Great point, really good point.
Well, anyway, I've covered the ground,
I think pretty exhaustively now.
You can pay for the very basics is a 45-minute call
as a kind of urgent assistance thing.
If you're, I don't know, maybe if you're hanging around
outside the baptism office, whatever.
Or you can pay a lot more and get an eight-page report.
You know, if you need a baby name to work
in three different languages, let's say,
because the parents are from different places,
then you can get that and it'll really drill down
into the detail.
You want to avoid particular syllables,
that's what you go for.
Interesting, so they basically kind of go through,
you know, like in The Simpsons, when they name Bart,
they try and work out if there's anything
that rhymes with it and they go, "Cart, dart, eart."
No, we're fine.
Does this, for these people, basically do eight pages
of possible ways that your child could be bullied
in every different country?
Bullying nicknames, basically, yeah.
I think it's if you want to avoid
particular abbreviations of the name,
they can do that too.
Interesting.
I think if you need professional consultation
over what to name your child,
you've got to take a really long and hard look
at your capacity to make an independent decision.
Okay, well, my parents wanted to call me anal you,
so I'm glad for one that they took that advice.
Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland, James.
@JamesHarkin.
@Andy.
@AndrewContoM.
And @Chazinski.
You can email podcasts at qi.com.
Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThing is of fish.com,
where we have all of our previous episodes,
as well as links to any upcoming live shows
we might be doing and video links
to anything that we've done that's on YouTube.
Do check it out and come back again next week,
because we will be here with another episode,
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
Bye.
[Music]