- Hi everyone, just before we start this show,
I wanted to perform a tiny, tiny interview
about a very exciting new book that's been released.
It's a book called Impossible Things,
unbelievable answers to the world's weirdest questions.
And it's by renowned author and podcaster,
Dan Treiber, here with me today.
- Hello, thank you for having me.
- It's a real pleasure.
How would you describe what this book is about?
- This is a book where I look into all the mysteries
that kids are fascinated by.
Are we being visited by aliens?
Are there ghosts out there in haunted houses?
Are there monsters in the lock?
Do time travelers visit us?
All that sort of stuff.
I've actually gone on 10 adventures
to investigate it on behalf of kids.
Getting to the bottom of the history
of why we believe in this stuff,
how it's changed the course of the world.
And it's also just a funny little adventure
that kids will hopefully enjoy.
- Yes, if you are fans of this podcast at all,
this book is basically bang in line with that.
And when Dan's personality, it's full of amazing facts.
It doesn't say wrong stuff,
even though it's about all these weird, mysterious phenomena.
- Yeah, and it's as much written for adults as it is kids.
Fish listeners, it would really be a huge, huge deal for me
if you could go out and get a copy today.
It's really, really incredibly hard to sell books,
particularly kids' books.
And I would love to turn this into a series.
And I can only do that if it's a success.
And you are my best chance at that.
So please do pick up a copy online or in bookshots today.
- Okay, on with the show.
- On with the show.
(alarm blaring)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast this week coming to you live from Dublin.
(audience cheering)
My name is Dan Shriver.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray, and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that mathematician Blaise Pascal
once cured his toothache by thinking about maths.
(audience laughing)
- We went from like crazy rock and roll beginning to--
- Excuse me, but there is nothing more rock and roll
than maths.
- That's true.
- And especially 17th century French maths.
- And Blaise Pascal, what a hot name.
That's a rock star, I've never heard one.
- You don't get enough Blaise these days, do you?
- No.
- You need to come back.
So was this like one of those cures where if you've got
a pain, subject yourself to something even worse?
Like you've got a toothache, shoot yourself in the foot,
and you'll forget about the toothache, apparently.
- I see where you're going, but no, it's the exact opposite.
- He was thinking about problems concerning the cycloid,
which is a curve traced by a point on the edge of a circle.
- Rock and roll, wow.
- His toothache disappeared and he decided that it was
God that did it, and God was saying to him,
you need to carry on with the maths,
and carry on with the maths he did.
- Wow, that's good.
So Pascal, the only thing I'd ever heard of Pascal
before researching this fact is Pascal's wager,
and the idea is that if you, what is the idea?
Is that if you, even if you think it's unlikely
that a vengeful God does exist,
you may as well go through the motions
as if a vengeful God does exist,
because on the off chance that you're wrong
and he does exist, it's much better to have.
- You're absolutely fucked.
- Yeah, exactly.
But I think actually God is going to know
that you're doing that, right?
Because God knows everything.
So as soon as you say, oh yeah, I really believed you
all that time, he's going to go bullshit.
- Imagine if God turned out to be such a chump
that he didn't know when you truly believed in art.
He said, yeah, you believed, I saw it at the end.
You said, yes, come on in buddy, nice to see you.
By the way, that's always presented
as if he was a non-believer,
but he was very much into his religion.
So the idea of the wager did involve
you actually believing as well.
It wasn't just like, oh yeah, on the side kind of thing.
- Just quickly, in 2008, Paddy Power
offered Odds of Four to One that God existed.
- Hey.
- That was a good bet you could have made at the time.
- Yeah.
- Have they had to pay out?
- Not yet.
- Not yet, okay.
- They did say they would need
an independent authority to verify it.
I don't know who, I don't know who that is.
- Who's going to be independent in that situation?
Richard Dawkins, no he hasn't.
- No, he's, yeah, yeah.
- So this Blaise Pascal, he's such an interesting character.
So he very sadly, he lost his mother
when he was three years old.
And his father, Etienne, basically decided
that he was going to homeschool him.
And Etienne was himself an amateur mathematician.
However, he thought math isn't for the young,
like your brains are not ready when you're young.
You need to do this when you're like 14, 15.
So he took all the math books in the house
and he locked them up in a cupboard.
And he said, don't let me catch you,
read in any math around here.
And so he became very curious about it
because he'd seen his father talk about it
with his friends and so on.
So basically Pascal had to discover math
by thinking about it and landed on all the actual equations,
which is extraordinary.
- According to actually Pascal's sister,
the reason that his dad banned him from doing math,
and he really did, and no one was allowed to mention math
in front of Blaise, she said that he did it because he knew,
Etienne knew that math fills and greatly satisfies the mind
in such a huge way that he knew as soon as Blaise
heard about math, he wouldn't be interested in classics
or the humanities or anything like that.
So he was like, I know you're going to get addicted
as soon as you're exposed.
So I'm going to keep you away from it.
But of course it piqued his interest so much, Blaise's interest.
He was like, what is this mysterious thing?
I'm not allowed to access.
And then it does sound like this incredible moment.
A tear kind of came to my eye when I imagined Etienne,
maths lover, as he was,
going up to his 12-year-old son's bedroom, opening the door.
- Don't come in.
I'm doing some math.
- I'm doing some math.
- No, no, I'm masturbating, I'm masturbating.
You're not masturbating, you're math debating.
(audience laughing)
But he was right, that's what he was doing.
He was sitting there secretly drawing circles and triangles
and thinking about the relationship between angles.
- I mean, he discovered amazing stuff.
Well, it doesn't sound amazing to us.
He basically discovered that all the angles in a triangle
add up to 180, duh.
But we all studied maths, you see.
That's the difference.
Whereas this 12-year-old hadn't.
- He invented a calculator.
Again, mid 17th century, not a lot of calculators.
And it was called the pascaline,
named after him, obviously.
And he dedicated it to the French Chancellor.
And he got a patent of it.
And then, most French move ever,
he said, "No one else is allowed to make one,
"but me, I have to have total control over it
"so they didn't make any."
(audience laughing)
- It was for his dad, wasn't it?
'Cause I think his dad worked in the sob
and kind of accounting thing.
And his dad was always tired and stuff.
And he thought, "If I make this calculator,
"it'll make his life easier."
- He used an abacus, his dad.
And he invented it to do away with the need.
- So sweet.
And yet sort of so worrying in your child as well,
if they've done that.
But mostly really sweet.
- I know.
- And it was essentially a calculator
that allowed you to carry over,
which we all remember fondly,
which abacus didn't allow you to do.
So his calculator automatically carried over.
You know, carrying over.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
No one in the audience shouted, "No, what?"
- What is that?
- Is anyone here from the 1600s?
(audience laughing)
- So yeah, it was amazing.
But he'd got this gig being an accountant.
It was a really good gig.
And it was in Normandy.
And he was actually managing the taxes of the whole area.
But he had fallen from grace massively
and come back into the grace of the French authorities.
Not because of Blaise Pascal,
but because of Blaise's sister.
So basically Etienne's there.
He's pissed off Richelieu,
who's the French prime minister.
And he's basically been exiled.
So he's had to leave his three kids in Paris, Blaise,
and then Jacqueline and Gilbert.
And Jacqueline turns out to be such a talented playwright
and actress at the age of 10 or something
that she performs for Cardinal Richelieu.
And he's so charmed by her
that she goes up to him afterwards and says,
"Oh, I hope you like that.
"By the way, would you mind forgiving my dad,
"not putting him in prison in the Bastille,
"not cutting his head off
"and giving him a good position instead?"
And Richelieu said, "Yeah, right, you're cute.
"I'll do that."
(audience laughing)
- Precretious.
- So then a bit later, Blaise Pascal,
he was in a carriage and the horse is bolted
and they threw him into the Seine and he nearly died.
- 'Cause it's very polluted, isn't it?
As we know from the Olympics, so was it?
- But then he wrote an account of that accident
and he had sort of like, God came to him
while he was in the water
and that made him even more religious.
- It was called his Night of Fire
and he had a mystical moment and a realization
and he wrote this kind of poem
which apparently reads like a journal entry
and they only found it after he died.
- And the religion was Janssenism, wasn't it?
It was both him and his sister were Janssenists.
And the idea of Janssenism is we're all evil
and there's nothing you can do about it
and it's decided at the start
who's going to be saved by God
and who isn't going to be saved by God
and it really doesn't matter what you do while you're alive.
You're either fucked or not fucked.
- Right, what's in it for me?
Sorry.
(audience laughing)
- I've got some bad news for you, Andy.
- Oh no.
- Which didn't make any sense and I'm sure it would
if we spent longer than a day reading up on this
but to me, as James says, predestination,
nothing you can do.
But also, it's not like he went out
and had a great time because of it.
He had a shit time.
To be honest, I think he was a bore, Blaise Pascal.
He did the old classic mortifying himself.
It's called mortifying where he wore metal clothes
with spikes on the inside to hurt himself at all times.
So he could constantly be punished
and constantly banish vain and profane thoughts.
You know, he was so devout.
He completely abandoned maths really
for the last 10 years of his life.
The fun thing.
- Is that your definition of boring?
- Someone who wears metal spikes.
(laughing)
- If you have metal spikes facing outwards,
that's cool, that's SNN.
If the metal spikes are facing inwards.
(laughing)
- He always wore stockings soaked in brandy.
- Really?
- Yeah, I heard that.
- What's that for?
- I heard it.
I heard it.
Got some hot gauze, like I've read it in a document.
- Yeah, he thought, well, he did have very bad circulation.
He was very sickly in his 30s
and he thought that his circulation would improve
if he wore.
'Cause in those days, it was like, this is a hot thing.
Brandy is a hot thing.
It will improve the heat in your body.
It will help the circulation.
- It feels like it would do it.
- I mean, and then...
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- It might do it if it attracted people
to suckle at your tights.
(laughing)
As you well might.
- So he met Descartes.
This is hugely exciting in Paris in 1647.
He'd been away, he'd been really ill.
He'd just got back.
And then he and Descartes were in the same room.
I think it's the only time--
- Are they both famous at this point?
- I think they're both pretty famous.
- Wow.
- It's a huge, huge meeting of mind.
It's like--
- It's like Comic-Con, but for the--
- Oh my God, yeah.
It's like Comic-Con, but for the greatest thinkers
of all time.
And all the doctors have been suggesting to Pascal,
oh, you need to have more enemas and bloodlettings
and purging.
And Descartes said, have you just considered resting
and having some soup?
And it was a very, it went really badly.
- Right.
- So he didn't want the resting in the soup.
He wanted the enemas and purging.
- He wanted those.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Right.
- Weird guy.
- You know, James, the headline fact.
So he thought about mathematics in order
to cure his toothache.
Did the toothache, was it psychosomatic?
Did it actually--
- Yeah.
- Did he then have a cure?
- I think what happened was it just went away.
(audience laughs)
- Yeah.
- Right.
- And perhaps the maths might not have had everything
to do with it.
Call me a skeptic.
(audience laughs)
- But if you, you can take your mind off pain
if you fill your mouth with saliva.
Does anyone else do that?
- Really?
- Yeah, a few yeses and a few, more than a few.
- What?
- Okay, but if you, it's just something else
to focus on.
You just focus on filling your mouth with saliva.
Right, I've got to get these saliva ducks flowing.
- What's hurting on you?
Is it your teeth or anything on your teeth?
- Yeah, but not, I don't think this works
if you've broken your leg, for instance.
It only works in like a headache or something like that.
- It works for a limited amount of time on minor pains.
- But on all pain, that's really interesting.
- I would say all pain.
- So you've done it to yourself.
- I'm constantly doing it.
- So when's the last time you did it?
(audience laughs)
- I don't know.
- Do you think this could be used
in childbirth, for instance, Sandy?
(audience laughs)
- I don't see why not.
- I've tried a lot of other stuff
and it doesn't seem to have worked, so.
(audience laughs)
- Some of it does work.
- It's just leading over to your wife, okay.
- Have you thought about thinking of math equations?
(audience laughs)
- Look, just in your own time, what's six times 17?
- Hey, so do you know, toothache,
one of the earliest ideas of what it might be
is that you were infected with a tooth worm.
- Oh yeah.
- Amazing idea.
They thought there was a living creature inside there
that was wiggling around, trying to get out,
and that's what was causing all the pain inside,
and so this is ancient.
- I think it might be the oldest misconception
in humankind, the oldest that I've ever found anyway,
'cause the Babylonians believed it.
- And it lasted forever, I mean,
it lasted until the 18th century, basically,
when it was roundly debunked by Pierre Fochard, a dentist,
but it was believed everywhere, wasn't it?
Like, from ancient Egypt to Mesoamerica,
how are they getting hold of this idea?
- I briefly believed it while I was researching this,
'cause I was in the 17th century,
and I just didn't do the researching
of what a toothache is until later on,
so for a few hours in 2024, someone believed in tooth worms.
- That tooth worms existed.
- Irish remedies for toothache.
So is the National Folklore Collection much discussed still?
A little bit, okay, so it was school children,
they were sent out, sort of 10 to 14 year olds
were sent in their local area,
they wrote up all the folklore they could gather
from people who'd been alive,
so this was done, yeah, 1937, '38,
so the years it covered,
because of the age of the people they were talking to,
went back to the 1860s,
and a lot of the folklore was to do with how to cure,
it was warts, whooping cough, and toothache,
and the cures, I have to say, largely potato-based,
they were, I'm afraid.
- What do you do with said potato?
- You go into the garden, get a potato pecked by a crow,
put it in your pocket, and never let it fall out.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- That'll do it.
- That's it.
- And get a slice of raw potato, put it in your cheek,
it sounds fractionally more believable, you know?
- Yeah, that could work.
- Yeah, but by far the most common,
actually it was not potato, but it was frog-based,
was to keep a live frog in your mouth for a few minutes,
the frog gets the, oh, come on, it's all right.
(laughing)
Keep it in your mouth for a few minutes,
and then let it out, and it gets the toothache,
very sad for it, but it takes yours away.
And do you know this sign?
It's like you put an L on your forehead.
- James is calling me a loser, yeah.
- No, I'm not calling you a loser, so this sign,
this according to Canadian Medical Hall of Fame member
Ronald Meltzak, if you take the L sign
for calling someone a loser,
and then you rub an ice cube up and down the L,
then that will get rid of your toothache,
and it works in more than 50% of patients.
- Really?
- Yeah, and his theory, and he's tried this,
and his theory is your body sort of feels the cold,
and it blocks some pathways, some pain pathways
to your brain, and so it stops the.
- Wow.
- According to him.
- Yeah.
- Give it a go.
- And he's in the Canadian Medical Hall of Fame.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- That's pretty funny.
- Not 17th Century Hall of Fame,
the Modern Hall of Fame.
- Modern Canada, but modern.
(laughing)
- It is time for fact number two,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that it turns out,
Stonehenge isn't a henge.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- Isn't that nuts?
The only henge we know about isn't an actual henge.
- So what's going on?
What is it?
- Okay, this is according to English Heritage.
If you go on their site,
they have a fantastic page all about henges,
and obviously Stonehenge leads the category there,
but then you get to a little bit where it says
it isn't officially a proper henge,
as the main ditch is external to the main bank.
So what it is, in fact, is a protohenge.
Now here's the weird thing,
henges are only called henges
because they're named after Stonehenge.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- This cat has eaten its own tail.
- Yeah.
- It is amazing.
- It's where the ditches and where the raised bank is.
- But it's also the size as well.
It has to be over 65 feet across
when you would do the ditches.
- Okay.
- If they found loads of henges,
and they're all the same, apart from Stonehenge,
it feels like Stonehenge was assembled incorrectly,
but basically the packet instructions
clearly showed the ditch inside the bank or whatever,
or else I don't care.
But do you know what I mean?
Like, they just did it wrong.
'Cause I think there is a theory
that it was basically a reassembly from another site.
- Oh, it's a second-hand henge, basically.
- Yeah.
- It's basically--
- It's a henge me down, basically.
- Oh, lovely, lovely, very strong.
- Don't boom it, that wasn't prepped, you know what I mean?
- You've been sat all day writing that joke, haven't you done?
Yeah, there's another site in Wales, isn't there,
where they've looked at what's missing from there,
and what's in Stonehenge.
And it almost comes together as a whole thing, yeah.
Because they also worked out
that people were living there for ages,
and then they stopped living there,
and then they came back later,
and they stopped living there
about the same time as the stones left.
So it could be that they just decided to move to Salisbury
and took their big old stones with them.
- The baggage allowance must have been massive
in the olden days.
- There's also another theory by Geoffrey of Monmouth,
the 12th century author.
He says that Stonehenge was originally built in Ireland
by a group of giants from Africa.
- By a group of who?
- A group of giants from Africa.
- Oh, right, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Classic.
- And then Merlin took them over from Ireland to Britain.
- We're booing Merlin.
- Wow.
- Don't you mention his name in this town.
(audience laughing)
He knows what he did.
- That's actually just very good etymological knowledge
from this audience.
'Cause Merlin, of course, literally means shit,
Merlin.
It does, yeah.
One of our earliest facts in Welsh, it meant shit.
And that's why we changed it to Merlin
'cause we thought the name shit was too embarrassing.
- It was embarrassing.
- But he did indeed.
I think these giants brought it all the way to Ireland
from Africa, and then back to England.
And this was the prevailing theory,
or the most common popular theory, wasn't it,
until the 19th century.
I don't think many people believed it.
- It qualifies as a theory.
I don't know, there were lots of theories,
and they all sort of reflect the times
in which they were espoused.
So there's, you know, is it a calculator
to work out the seasons?
Is it a healing place?
Is it a spacecraft landing pad?
Is it a dating, literally a site for romance?
- Oh, not dating as in the data.
- No, sorry, not carbon dating, just dating.
- Right.
- How would the dating work?
- It's just a symbolic, sort of, meat meeting.
- But you would meet them, like,
let's go to Stonehenge and catch a...
- Catch something.
Well, that was really nice,
'cause it would be a dating site called Henge.
That would be very pleasing.
- Oh, yeah.
- Dan and I sitting right in that chair.
- Dan and I sitting next to each other on the plane.
What are you doing?
- Nothing.
- But one of the latest theories
is that it was basically a meeting place,
and it was actually a sort of community centre, effectively.
Like, it was an attempt to get people to come here,
get involved in a big project, work together,
'cause it was a time of big population decline and dispersal.
So it was just an attempt to kind of get people together,
you know?
- There's a lot of shit, isn't there, about Stonehenge?
But the nice thing is, there always has been.
When you look back at early 1800s sources,
people bitch about the fact that the number of theories
about where Stonehenge comes from
and why it's there are ridiculous.
So there was a whole spate of research
in the 1920s and 1930s.
There was an extremely authoritative account written
called The Stones of Stonehenge,
and his name was Edward Herbert Stone, which is nice.
- Very nice.
- There's Henry Brown as well, 1823.
He wrote what was officially the guidebook,
that's the first guidebook to Stonehenge,
and the theory that he puts in there,
which he kind of presents as fact,
is that it survived Noah's flood.
- There was a very interesting debate between two excavators.
Again, in the 20s and 30s,
when people were starting to do serious archaeology
about Stonehenge, rather than coming up with mad theories,
the two main explorers of it, and excavators of it,
were a woman called Maude Cunnington
and a man called Alexander Kaler.
And I got really obsessed with them
because they sort of hated each other.
Eventually, their rivalry came to center on this one stone,
and it was a stone that Maude visited in 1911.
So she'd gone to lift up another stone,
which is called Adam.
They give a couple of the stone's names, Adam and Eve, notably,
and she'd lifted up this other stone, which had fallen over.
- Was she a giant? Sorry.
- Yeah, sorry. I should have made it clear
that she brought quite a lot of heavy machinery with her.
A large number of other people lifted up the hen stone.
Cunnington came to the site in the 30s,
when that idiot woman, she's put it the wrong way up,
was determined she put it the wrong way up, flipped it over,
put it on its head.
Now, as they've looked at the stones
and realized that he got it wrong,
so there's this upside down stone there.
- Brilliant. - That's messing it all up,
solely the result of this rivalry between these two people.
- Wow. - Did they fall in love?
(audience laughing)
'Cause it sounds like everything you're saying is a rom-com.
- It does. I know.
Yes, this is the beginning of "You've got mail."
Yes, I didn't.
- Other places that are modeled on Stonehenge,
have you heard of a bonehenge?
Bonehenge is a--
- It's like an elephant graveyard kind of thing.
- Yeah, it's a mammoth bone circle in Russia.
- Oh, wow. - Made about 20,000 years ago.
Very cool. - Wow.
- Skonhenge.
(audience laughing)
- Is that as in scones?
- It's pronounced Skonhenge, that's correct.
That's a restaurant in California.
(audience laughing)
There was the time when Queen Elizabeth
was beamed onto the stones for her jubilee.
- What, is there a word for it?
- Thronehenge.
- Ah, damn it.
- And Ireland is home to a historic site
that was found by someone flying up an unmanned aerial vehicle.
(audience laughing)
- Would it by any chance be Dronehenge?
- Dronehenge!
- Amazing.
- So it is, it's still a mystery, isn't it?
Stonehenge, where the stones come from.
There's always new reports.
They suddenly think that some of the stones are from Wales.
- I think they've always thought from Wales.
- Sorry, from Scotland.
- Yeah, that's the huge news, isn't it?
- That's the big news, but recently they thought,
why don't we try and see if the method
of laying them down on sleds over logs
is something that is achievable?
And the result was they discovered
it's just incredibly easy to do that.
(audience laughing)
10 people can pull the stones in a very,
it's a slow manner,
but it's not as taxing as we thought it was.
- We've just given these guys so much credit
for hundreds of years, it's piece of piss.
- Do you know we found the original tape measures
that were probably used for Stonehenge?
- No, we don't.
- We have, this is so cool, okay?
- What?
- They're called the Folkton Drums,
and they're big stone cylinders carved from solid chalk,
right, and they are massive.
They're about 5,000 years old,
and each of them is a particular size,
so that if it goes around once, for example,
it's a number of multiples of 3.2 meters,
and that measurement crops up everywhere,
so we think those are the sort of tape measures
of the gods, and they could send off to Wales,
saying, can you bring me a stone that's this big,
according to the drums,
and they'll send back something
that's the right size for you.
- How cool is that?
- What if it was just like an earthquake,
and they landed like that?
- Yeah.
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, I mean, that's a good,
in many ways, an easier theory for us all, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Older than Stonehenge is New Grange.
In fact, I feel like your fact could have been
New Grange is not new, yeah.
- Oh, right, yeah, it's very old.
- But they've recently, yeah, very old,
older than Stonehenge,
they've recently done some DNA tests.
- What is it for international?
- Oh, sorry, for international listeners.
- And for those who maybe didn't do that better than reading?
(audience laughing)
- It's a huge, like a huge barrow,
it's a huge earth mat under the middle of Ireland,
which was probably a burial site, we think,
'cause they found some bodies in there,
and they've done some DNA tests,
and they found that there was a lot of incest going on.
And what they reckon is,
it was a bit like, you know, in ancient Egypt,
how all the kings and queens married each other,
and then, you know,
their children married each other and stuff like that.
They reckon there was a lot of that in Ireland at the time.
(audience laughing)
- Just one person cheering,
and a very worried-looking sister next to him.
(audience laughing)
- His mum and his sister and his cousin have all come along,
but thankfully they're all in the same seat.
(audience laughing)
- Sorry.
- Childish.
- But yeah, it's really interesting now,
because it implies a really elite system
of almost like pharaohs in Ireland.
- Wow, cool.
- And that's also where they found Dronehenge, isn't it?
- Yes, they found Dronehenge near thereabouts
where that bloke found Dronehenge,
and he's now published a book,
The Story Behind the Remarkable Neolithic Discovery,
about the events following the day he found it,
and how the world's media descended on him.
And I encourage you to look up the accounts,
because I don't know how much it was
headline news all around the world,
(audience laughing)
as is claimed in the book.
- I got one last thing,
which is that I've always wanted to go to Stonehenge.
I've never been, and as part of this research,
I thought, oh, I wonder if it's on TripAdvisor.
And it turns out it is,
and it has a lot of one-star reviews.
- No. - Yeah.
So this is one,
this is one going as back as 2014.
I was disgusted to find that this was just
a few rocks to look at.
(audience laughing)
Nothing to do, they should knock it down
and build an arcade or a fun fair.
Don't waste your time, what a silly place.
And then, August of 2023, someone wrote,
"I expected so much more than just stones placed
"in a circle.
"As a World Heritage site, at the very least,
"I would have expected an ice cream van."
(audience laughing)
I didn't fight the war for this.
- Next review. - Next review.
- Not even a henge.
(audience laughing)
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number three,
and that is Anne.
- My fact this week is that
the sport with the highest rate of concussion
is synchronized swimming.
- Is that 'cause one of the swimmers bangs their head
and everyone has to copy them?
(audience laughing)
- It's a funny line, James,
but it's a fundamental misunderstanding
of synchronized swimming.
We'll come on to that.
But I should caveat this by saying,
this is based on my reading
and not actual academic comparative studies.
But I have surmised this
from a lot that I've read about synchronized swimming.
It's extremely dangerous.
So I was reading an account of Bill Moreau,
who was the Vice President of Sports Medicine
for the US Olympic Committee between 2009 and 2019.
And he supervised lots of sports
for safety and health concerns.
And he supervised synchronized swimming.
And in a two week training camp,
he said 50% of the team sustained a concussion.
And that surpassed NFL and Aussie rules football.
- Are they, is that team just really shit?
(audience laughing)
Like, what are they, they must be,
'cause they can't be hitting the bottom of the pool.
- Okay, it's not allowed.
- You're not allowed, it's just knocking heads, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- It's crazy.
Well, they keep on trying to make it better
and better and better and better and better,
which means getting in tighter and tighter
and tighter to each other.
And you're flailing around
and you're upside down and you're kicking
and you just bang heads or kick each other
in the face all the time.
- Absolutely, it's colliding with each other.
- Sometimes I read an account from one of them
who, I think one of them broke another's nose accidentally
with a stray, you know, hand or foot or whatever
and they didn't notice.
- Well, 'cause you're so, they're so focused on the routine.
- Yeah, you're doing your job.
Here's the thing.
(audience laughing)
- Sorry, but if I punched you the nose right now,
you wouldn't continue with this fact.
- I'm a pro, I would continue on.
There's a photo for the audience at home
that's sitting behind us.
And what you can see on the photo here
is that the team is about to lob
one of their members up into the air right.
And the thing is in synchronized swimming,
you aren't allowed to touch the bottom right.
So the amount of kicking that you need to do
in order to get them up into the air
purely from swimming.
- It's insane.
- It's nuts, yeah.
- I would think that they would breed
synchronized swimmers who are just very tall
so they can touch the bottom.
But that is apparently not how the sport works.
- It's not, yeah.
- No, it's against the rules.
They're completely pointless and you wouldn't work.
But this photo and the idea that they are kicking
madly underwater to sustain this beautiful performance
above the water is epitomized by Sarah Oek
who was a great synchronized swimmer
who actually got kicked in the head and concussed
and spent three years recuperating from that.
And so retired.
But she said, "We make it look pretty above the water
but below it's a battlefield."
And it is like underwater, it's mad.
And there are lots of studies into concussion
in other sports.
The rugby is often cited as the worst.
That's three concussions per 1,000
kind of athletic exposures, which is one person in one game.
But reading about synchronized swimming,
there was Miriam Glez, who is the chief executive
of USA Syncro, which is their national organizing body,
said, "100% of my athletes will get a concussion
at some point."
And it is just crashing into and falling on each other.
- They have helmets.
- Well, they do in practice.
- But do they?
- They wear practice helmets.
- Yeah, they're made of silicon
and they've got like a honeycomb style make-up to them.
Yeah, very tasty, right?
Have a lick while you're down there.
(audience laughing)
- Don't ever, don't ever, ever, ever say that again.
- Obviously you can't see what's going on
under the water, but I don't think.
- I think that's, the judges would come down
very hard on that.
- Thanks.
(audience laughing)
- As long as they have some jump-up, it's all right.
- That is the thing, we're looking at the photo right now.
Doesn't look very synchronized, does it, right?
And that's the thing, we're saying synchronized swimming.
It's artistic swimming.
So it's not, synchronized has gone out as a term.
- But also, you were never synchronized with each other.
You were synchronized with the music.
- Yeah, that's right.
- Which is why you can have solo synchronized swimming.
I have an opinion, which is that,
I think this is a better sport under the water
than it is on top.
- Ah, yes.
- Whoa.
- Yeah, yeah, great.
- So you see the effort that goes in
and there are sometimes cameras under the water
and you can just see the furious effort that's going in.
And I think it's probably the only sport
where if you film it in a different medium,
it's, I don't, I'm not sure what I'm trying to say.
- I think it looks, it looks like shit.
- It's the only sport that takes place
between two forms of matter, right?
- Well, half of you are all swimming.
- All swimming.
- All diving for sure.
- All diving.
- Okay.
- Now, gradually diving.
- What's the one, water polo,
where they've got the ball?
- Yeah.
- That is crazy underneath
because they're literally like kicking and punching
and yeah, everything.
- I think to give Andy credit,
I think diving isn't the same
'cause diving ends once you enter the water, right?
And synchronized swimming is constantly taking part
in both media.
- Thank you.
- And there you go.
- So like, there's no sport
where half of your body is encased in solid
and half of you is in plasma.
It just doesn't happen.
So I think that's what makes it interesting.
- That is true.
- And people pass out quite regularly
'cause again, 'cause so much of it is under water,
you have to be holding your breath
a huge amount of the time
and holding your breath
while exerting yourself enormously.
And this is another reason why the concussion issue
in synchronized swimming is such a thing
is that it's probably extremely under-reported
because the symptoms of concussion
are very similar to the symptoms of swimming upside down
whilst holding your breath
whilst having to fling people out of the air quite a lot.
So imagine doing that.
You're there going, am I concussed or is this just
how you feel when you're doing this mad thing?
- That's so funny.
- Yeah.
- And then the training,
I mean, the training is incredibly stressful
and there's a lot of it.
But one of the things they do
is they do crossfit workouts with their mouths taped
because they have to hold their breath under water
for like up to two minutes.
And 'cause there's so much exertion,
they have to not just get fit
but be able to do these things while holding their breath.
So they'll take the mouths and do some crossfit.
- I can breathe with my nose.
So, in your face.
- I believe they probably take the nose as well.
- I think they probably do.
- So, and this is another sort of like cruel intensity
about it.
They're not allowed to wear swimming goggles.
- Yeah.
- No, it's not in the final thing.
- Yeah, 'cause the judges want to see their expression.
So the goggles aren't allowed to be there.
And as a result, they get really irritated eyes.
And so a lot of synchronized or artistic swimmers
bathe their eyes in milk.
'Cause apparently milk is very good for, yeah.
- And is that, that's not recommended
from the 17th century handbooks.
That's a genuine.
- That's Blaise Pascal says.
(laughing)
Like you say, they want to see their eyes.
They want to see their expressions.
They want to see them smiling.
And if you speak to any synchronized swimmer,
they all say that the smile is fake.
And the reason they're smiling is to kind of height the pain.
It's kind of a grimace.
'Cause the pain is so bad.
And they're like, "Yeah, sure."
(laughing)
- I mean, all of these reports about how tough it is
to come from synchronized swimmers.
- True.
- Yeah, but I mean--
- I'm just saying--
(laughing)
- How would the power left us?
No.
(laughing)
- It does obviously incredibly hard.
And obviously, if you come out of the water,
your natural instinct is to rub your face
and get the water out of your eyes.
And you're not allowed to do that
because you have to be looking at the judges.
And I think you meant to maintain eye contact
with the judges, with water in your eyes,
'cause you're mostly blind,
because you're not wearing your--
- It's crazy.
- It's really, it is very hard.
I take back my comment.
Please don't email him.
(laughing)
- And it, well, it is this very interesting thing,
which has a long history,
sort of kicked off officially in the 1890s.
And was about looking good.
It was only men who were allowed to do it at first.
And almost immediately,
people realized that women were much better candidates for it,
because A, we have much more fat on our body,
so we're more buoyant.
And B, people wanna look at women in swimsuits,
doing really pretty things.
And so, it's meant to be this display
of aesthetic brilliance.
But you do have these weird standards,
like the hair gel is amazing,
that they have to wear on their hair
to keep it looking completely,
staying completely still in the water and looking great.
So, the way they do their hair is called noxing,
with a K, K-N-O-X, and like, Fort Knox.
And it's because it's using nox gelatin,
which is a thing that's used to make jelly in cooking.
- Especially in America, I think,
it's like the main brand of gelatin.
- Is it?
Okay, okay, so there you go.
So it's like industrial strength,
and you spread this paste onto your head,
and it basically solidifies your hair,
so it can't move, and it's rock solid.
And then you go in.
- Nox, by the way, was run by a woman called Rose Nox,
who made this gelatin.
She was married to another guy who died,
and then she took over the business.
The first day she took over,
she closed the back door of the factory,
which previously all the women
had to go into a different door than all the men,
which was kind of a thing that did happen occasionally
in factories in America. - Really?
- Yeah, 'cause they didn't want them mixing
'cause they thought they wouldn't do any work
if they were flirting the whole time.
She made a five-day week for her workers
and gave them two weeks of paid vacation,
which really no one else was doing at the time.
And she wrote a book.
Her book was called "Seventy Easy Delicious Desserts"
made from sparkling carb's foot gelatin.
- No way! - Really?
- Sounds like a great book, though.
- So nice.
Did you guys hear of Esther Williams
in the course of the film?
- The movie star? - She was very cool.
She was a movie star who swam at the very elaborate routines.
In the sort of '40s and '50s,
there was a huge trend of aqua ballets
and the time it must be Barclay
and all of these amazing ballatic dance scenes.
She was great.
Her films included Neptune's Daughter,
Million Dollar Mermaid, Dangerous When Wet.
Just cool, cool films.
And she then had an unsuccessful move
into land-based acting.
And she was just flopping around.
- Well, there's a comedian called Fanny Bryce
who said of her, "Wet, she's a star.
"Dry, she ain't."
And she was very self-deprecating, though.
She said, "If they ever teach a duck to act,
"I'm in big trouble."
She's great.
She's so cool.
She once did a 35-metre dive in a film
playing another swimmer.
That was Million Dollar Mermaid.
She broke her neck.
She spent seven months in a body cast.
- Was that one of the land-based ones, actually?
(upbeat music)
- It is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that early phone boxes
came with a little man inside
who would arrange the call for you,
then wait outside until it was over.
- Aww.
- Very nice.
- That's lovely.
- Why did we get rid of it?
We could have had a really civilised time.
- Well, I guess it was because
everyone learned how to use phones.
- Yeah.
That's true, and they didn't in the first place.
So this is really interesting.
This is from a book called--
- Before you explain it,
when you say "little man" inside--
- Oh, yeah.
- Like a borrower, right?
- Yeah, like a borrower.
- A little abution?
- No.
- He has to be small enough to fit in the phone box.
- Yeah.
I mean, phone boxes, they're quite big.
- How little was the man?
- It's just a figure of speed.
Some of the men were probably normal
or even above average size, all right?
- I also, for the show we're doing in Ireland,
we have chosen the most quintessentially
English thing to talk about.
This will be 25 minutes on red phone boxes.
- I don't think it's any more English than Stonehenge.
- Very good.
- Stonehenge, built by a giant.
These phone boxes contained a little man.
- This is from a book
which, admittedly, is called Enigmatic England.
- And it's about...
- No, your audience!
- It's about these very early phone boxes.
So before you have the one person
sort of booth, you know, TARDIS style phone boxes,
you had call stations, which are more like a garden shed.
And they first appeared in 1886.
They're incredibly old.
And there would be an attendant inside
who would take your money, place the call,
wait outside in whatever the weather until you've finished.
I read some reports as well that they would also lock you in
so that you couldn't escape without paying.
- Oh, right, yeah.
- I think that was the thing, wasn't it?
'Cause you had to pay for it,
and they had no system of you just putting coins in
and it knowing that you put the right amount in
and then connecting you.
So you had to give them the money,
and then they would sort out all the connection part.
- Yeah, exactly.
So they had to go to a phone exchange to an operator.
It was really complicated.
And they would, I think, maybe time the call as well.
I don't know.
- Well, the first ones, actually.
So a lot of them were in post offices and shops,
the ones that didn't have little men.
So you might have it in a place
where there was already someone there.
But the first ones were in Manchester and Liverpool in 1885.
And in this one, you would give them the money,
they would set it off,
and then it said, this was from a newspaper article,
"A clockwork arrangement slowly moves an index finger
"visible to the user over a graduated arc."
So there's like a picture of someone's finger going,
"Like the countdown clock going do-do-do-do-do-do-do."
(laughter)
- Really?
- It's creepy, that, isn't it?
- That's amazing.
- Well, I noticed with your finger there is,
you did it anticlockwise to us,
so it was clockwise for the audience.
Was that deliberate?
- Oh, I've been working in Fierce for many years.
(laughter)
- Oh, God, you've just reminded me of a toothache cure.
Sorry.
(laughter)
It was to put a dead person's finger in your mouth.
- Wow!
- And rub it on the tooth.
Sorry, that's just...
- You reminded me, yeah.
- Was the finger connected to the dead person?
- I don't think it mattered.
- Or was it just--
(laughter)
- But I think, for ease of use,
you would probably disconnect it.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- When was this?
- This was the 1880s.
- It was such an exciting time,
the 1880s, in phone land, wasn't it?
Because it was--
- Show us.
- What was happening?
- Well, so--
- The invention of the phone, pretty much.
(laughter)
- That's a fairly seminal moment, yeah?
- It was mostly that.
I like the fact that phone operators
had to sort of know everyone in their area,
because there were so few people
who were subscribed to the telephone exchange.
As a phone operator, you'd call the operator,
and you'd say something like,
"Could you put me through to the doctor
"who specifically does knee stuff?
"I've got really sore knee."
And as an operator, you'd need to know that doctor
and which exchange point they were,
and plug them into the right thing.
- Have you tried attaching a frog to the knee?
(laughter)
- Do you have a dead man with you?
- Yeah, the first Irish telephone exchange
was set up in 1880,
but it had just five customers at the time.
- Right.
- But you think there would be an even number
so they could ring each other,
but I guess that's not how it worked.
- Do you know, I did check the phone book in Ireland
from that year, which is very short.
As you say, it got to about 19 or 20 customers
by the end of the year.
One of the customers was Messier's Guinness and Sons.
- Oh, wow!
- Yeah, they got in there,
'cause if you need your Guinness, you need it now.
- Right.
- That's so funny.
They had in 1885 an invention which was,
it was like an out of office email for phones.
- Okay.
- So if someone phoned you,
you could let them know that you were out
and you'd be back later.
Can you guess how that would work?
- Sorry, so you phoned them and--
- So you phoned me, I'm not in,
but I know that I'm gonna be back at four p.m.
So I'm gonna let you know.
- So I'm in the booth.
The finger beckons.
(laughter)
Is that it?
- No fingers involved.
- Okay.
- Oh, I know, I know,
'cause there weren't that many phones back then,
we're saying.
So what you would do is you would call up the operator
and say, "Anyone who tries to call my phone,
"can you let them know I'm out till 4.30?"
- Very good.
This is an invention.
It's a finger--
- So your phone is ringing on the desk
and I'm away from my desk.
So I need a mechanical claw to lift the phone
to a mechanical mouth.
- No fingers, no claws.
Employee boy, employee boy or girl?
- I don't think that's an invention, the boy.
- The boy.
This is when the boy was invented.
- Wow, the 1880s really were amazing.
- Basically what you would do
is if you're gonna be back at 4.00 p.m.,
as someone called, no one would answer it.
It would just go click, click, click, click,
and then would hang up.
And then they knew that you had to phone back at 4.00 p.m.
- Clever.
- Isn't that clever?
- That is.
- Yeah, that's amazing.
- That's very cool.
- The Bristol Mercury, I read about this invention,
they said this will be the most useful invention
of the time.
- Right.
- They were sure.
- This was a useful invention,
jumping a bit forward to 1905,
and there was a guy who was called Almond Stroger,
and he ran a funeral home in Kansas City,
and he invented the Stroger Pop Belly candlestick phone,
and he invented it.
- It's still a catchy name.
- 'Cause the candlestick is where you have that bit,
you pull by your ear, and then you hang it up,
and it sticks up by like a candlestick.
- Yeah, if you look at it, it does look like a candlestick,
yeah, or a candlestick holder rather.
But the reason he invented it
is because he worked in the funeral business,
and any time someone was calling up,
there was an operator whose husband
ran a rival funeral home,
and she kept putting it through to their home.
Yeah, and he was like, I'm losing all my business,
'cause she works on the inside,
she's feeding it to the wrong place,
so he's like, I'm gonna innovate the telephone,
and he did with numbers.
- Someone's stolen the finger from my husband, wasn't he?
- Hang on, 'cause I was about to say,
that's the best fact you've ever told me,
and were you about to say, so the story goes?
- Yes.
(audience laughing)
- Why do you do this to us?
- Well, no, because it's just covering my tracks, you know?
It's a, that is the story that that was the--
- It's a fantastic story.
- It's a great story. - Oh, dear.
In 1915, a three-minute call
between New York and San Francisco
cost the equivalent today of $500.
- Wow. - Three, wow.
- Yeah.
- These first ones, the ones that you were talking about
were three pence for three minutes.
- That's very good. - Yeah, yeah.
- Well, a lot of, it was for business only,
that was the thing, phones were for business,
they were for Guinness and Sons to place orders
or talk to their merchants or whatever,
and there were warnings in the early phone
that I'm quoting now, a document that said,
"It should not be used for the exchange of twaddle
"between foolish women."
(audience laughing)
- Wow. - Yeah.
No, and again, in 1909, one phone company manager
found that 30% of all calls were idle gossip,
and this was very frowned on because phones were,
you know, rare and precious,
and so they should only be for business and all that,
and then gradually phone company bosses started realizing,
oh, well, probably quite useful if people are speaking
on their phone for a long time.
- I think also, 'cause it clogged up the lines, didn't it?
Basically, if you were talking your twaddle to someone,
it meant that other people might not be able
to use the lines 'cause there weren't that many of them.
Eventually, we got the automatic payphone
where people could put coins in.
- Oh, yeah.
- So we had bad news for the little men.
(audience laughing)
- A lot of little guys.
- Unimplied all around the country.
- Putting out little signs.
(audience laughing)
- But this was invented by William Gray,
and his original invention is very clever.
So you have the thing that you talk into,
and there was a little bit of metal near the microphone,
and whenever you put the money in,
the little bit of metal slid out of the way
so you'd be able to talk,
and then as soon as your money ran out,
it would slide back into place,
so you wouldn't be able to hear the many of them.
- Ooh, nice little chat guillotine.
- Isn't that cool?
- That is cool.
- It's really cool.
- He also invented the chest protector
for baseball catchers.
- Oh, that big, like, buff looking thing that they wear.
- Yeah, the thing that protects the chest.
- Yeah.
(audience laughing)
- It's just two weird things to invent, isn't it?
- It is.
- Here's a little quiz from a California phone manual
in the early days.
I think this is the early 1900s.
Keep your what out of the opening of the phone?
(audience laughing)
- Keep your twaddle.
- Let's keep these.
- What's the opening of the phone?
- Whether your mouth is.
- Keep your tongue out?
- Oh.
Well, yes, but no.
- I'm just thinking, like, what is close by.
- Who's using phones at this time?
- Yeah, keep your nose out.
- saliva, saliva.
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, no, this is a manly thing.
- Oh, it's a manly thing?
- Yeah.
- Okay, penis.
(audience laughing)
- James, moustache.
Why on earth would you put your penis
into the mouthpiece?
(audience laughing)
- I can't help but think of a penis.
- I can't believe you would think of a penis.
That's disgraceful.
Oh, James, I'm really disappointed.
(audience laughing)
- So that was a phone manual.
How to use a phone.
I just had a thing on a phone book,
which is, you know, another phone-related book.
(audience laughing)
That's the link.
I just really like this.
This is someone found this randomly a few years ago.
They lived in Idaho,
and they wondered what would happen
if you looked up Adam West.
You remember Adam West?
- Batman.
- He died recently.
He was Batman.
- He died?
- I'm just, God, this is a big moment.
- Did he?
(audience laughing)
- Quite recently, the last couple of years, I think.
- Gosh.
- He was tied to a huge vat of acid.
(audience laughing)
- Anyway, this random guy on the internet
found out that he just idly looked up Adam West
in the phone book.
And the message in the phone book read in Idaho,
'cause Adam West lived in Idaho when he died,
the message read, "See Wayne, Bruce, Brackett's millionaire."
- No, literally.
- And so, you went to that listing in the phone book,
and then it said, "Please consult crime fighters
"in the yellow pages."
And then,
(audience laughing)
you went to that listing in the yellow pages,
and it said, "See Batman, white pages."
And then you went to that listing,
and it sent you back to Adam West in the phone book.
- Oh, okay, I need to end us here.
And that is it for our show tonight.
Thank you, Dublin, so much for being here.
(audience cheering)
That is all our facts.
We'll be back again next week with another episode.
We will see you then.
Good bye!
(audience cheering)
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]