(upbeat music)
- Hi, guys.
- Hi there, Andy.
- Welcome to Club Fish.
Anna, we have to address the listener as well as each other.
- Oh my God, are there listeners?
- I'm afraid so.
- Wow, somebody just told me that a while ago.
All right, listeners, welcome to Club Fish.
What is Club Fish?
Well, it's the secret exclusive VIP lounge
that we've just given you access to.
What does it offer? Snacks?
- So many snacks.
- Right.
- We still have to provide you your own actual snacks, but.
(laughing)
- No, what it is, is we get so many amazing emails
from all of you guys, and we have done over the years,
whether that's emails saying here's a bizarre, obscure fact
on mollusks, 'cause I'm the world expert,
or whether it's emails saying that thing
that Dan said last week, that was stupid.
We love them all equally.
- A full range from, I know more about you on this,
to I know more about Dan on this.
And we thought we genuinely get so much brilliant correspondence
that it was time to hand over to you, the listeners,
and record a little bonus section
with all of your correspondence.
- Although, if someone made a mistake of allowing Andy
to host it, so the next voice you will be hearing,
I'm afraid, it's still going to be Andrew Hunter Murray's.
- It's provisionally called Drop as a Line.
- Drop as a Line.
(speaking in foreign language)
(upbeat music)
- Hello, this is Drop as a Line,
which is the bit where we hear from fish listeners
who often send in facts, which are more interesting
than the ones we talked about, or corrections,
which are more accurate than the things
we talked about on the show.
So we might as well just kick off
with a few emails from listeners.
- Yeah, go after it, what we got?
- Well, which do you want first?
Do you want a correction, or do you want bonus info?
- Oh, I don't want to be hit so quickly in the show.
Obviously a correction for me, let's do a--
- Okay, we can do a bit of bonus info.
Cast your minds back to episode 311.
- Oh yeah, I remember it well.
- It's about two and a half years ago now,
but look, Laura Dunlop from Calgary in Alberta, Canada
has written in, just listening to episode 311
about dog shows and poop and such.
- Oh yeah, awesome. - We did talk about this.
All right, here we go.
To stop a dog from pooping in the ring,
the handlers can tell when a dog has to go--
- Wait a minute, why are they at this boxing fight?
(laughing)
What do you mean pooping in the ring?
- Oh, sorry, dog show, dog show ring.
- Oh, right, okay. - You're doing it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Sorry, to stop a dog from pooping in the ring,
off the dog show, the handlers can tell
when a dog has to go because of the size of their sphincter.
It looks larger when they have to go,
so to stop an accident from happening,
they put the sulfur end of a match in the anus--
- No, they don't. - Which immediately
makes the dog defecate before entering the ring.
I worked with a woman who had her dogs in shows,
and she told me that is how they do it.
The more you know, and then a rainbow emoji from Laura.
- How many dogs are set on fire before crafts
that we've never seen?
- That is incredible.
I have a related fact on that,
and that is that doctors can tell if you have a fistula
in that area of your body by testing
if you have an anal wink.
- Oh, sexy. - And that is exactly
what it sounds like. (laughing)
Uranus winks at them when they do a little kind of--
- That's so funny, it's floating.
- Hang on, you do a tickle and it closes.
- It closes slightly, yeah.
- Is it not supposed to do that?
- No, it does, and if it doesn't do that,
that means that you--
- Oh, so you meant to have a--
- You're supposed to have an anal wink, yeah.
- I'm actually testing now if I think I have an anal wink.
(laughing)
- I saw a great tweet the other day
from someone called Octopus Caveman,
@OctopusCaveman, who wrote,
"My son told me he learned that octopuses
"can climb through small cracks,
"so he's scared to swim in the ocean
"because an octopus might climb inside his butt,
"and now I'm scared to swim in the ocean."
- So here's the thing, octopuses can go through small cracks.
- Yeah.
- But they can't go through anything
that's smaller than their eye.
- Or their beak eye? - 'Cause there's an eye
that doesn't change.
- Presumably the size of an octopus's eye or beak changes
with the size of the octopus.
- Yeah, so if you see a tiny octopus with a small eye
or a small beak, then you might be scared,
but if it's a nice big sort of crackin' like one,
you're okay, it's not gonna get any--
- You're okay, you got other issues
if you see a crackin'.
(laughing)
- And all that means is that
you've got much more to be scared of,
because if you can't see an octopus that's so big
it can't climb inside your bottom,
then you might not be seeing the octopus,
which is small enough that it could.
- But then, if an octopus is that small,
do you even mind it going in your bottom?
- I think I would, that might be a problem.
- 'Cause they're so intelligent,
I would fear some sort of power-sharing arrangement
that we might not want to.
- You think they start a revolution then?
- We look like a ventriloquist.
- Like a takeover bit, basically.
We don't know how many people around the world
are just octopuses.
- So you know that bad guy in "Teenage Recent Ninja Turtles"?
- Shredder.
- There's one who kind of is a little octopus
that lives in his chest.
He went in through the anus.
(laughing)
- Interesting.
- That's part of the official "Teenage Recent" canon.
That's canon stuff, 'cause I love that episode.
(laughing)
- Sorry, what was the fact again?
Oh, it's about dog shows, isn't it?
- They put a match in a dog's bottom.
- Wasn't there, I think there was one recently
that went viral, where a dog pooed
in the middle of a dog show, wasn't there?
- There was, well, that's because clearly they hadn't-
- They hadn't checked the ring to save the ring.
Check the ring to save the ring.
(laughing)
Every dog owner's mantra.
- There are big posters up at Crofts, aren't there?
So check the ring to save the ring.
- If the conservative party was in charge of Crofts,
'cause they're always loving their slogans, aren't they?
(laughing)
- Yeah, for that.
- I'd love if there was a close-up shot
just before the dog took the shit
and its anus winked at the camera.
(laughing)
- Like Ann Robinson, the weakest link.
- God.
- Well, thank you, Laura.
(laughing)
That was incredibly helpful.
And you slightly regret starting on such an anus, you won,
but I think that's good.
- Well, that's what we did on the actual podcast.
- Remember, the first facts were,
well, the first facts was about Garfield's anus.
- Yeah, that's right.
- Starts, do you mean to go on?
- All right, well, I've now got a choice for you
of a bonus info or the correction.
It's still the same correction as before.
- Let's go with corrections.
- Corrections, yeah, we can take it.
- I don't know who the perp is actually on this one.
All right.
This is from Randolph Peters.
- Canada. - I don't like him already.
- Also.
- Wow.
- Also Canada.
- What have you taken against?
- Randolph or Peters?
- Well, it's that he's going to correct his answer.
(laughing)
- Also from Canada, I've just realized.
- Oh, Calgary Alberta?
- Doesn't specify.
- Probably.
- Brett the Hitman Hortz from there as well.
(laughing)
- You'll find out what his beef is.
The fact how I know he's Canadian
from the substance of this.
- Got it.
- Oh yeah.
- Dear, no such thing.
I'm trying to get my fellow Canadian friends
to listen to the podcast,
but when you relocate the CN Tower from Toronto to Seattle,
you make my job almost impossible.
Seattle Space Needle is 1/3 the size
of our manhood metaphor,
which is still the tallest free-standing tower
in the Western Hemisphere.
So there, if we can't trust you on towers,
what else are you making up?
- Well, Randolph, I would say to you
that if you go back and listen to the very start
of that podcast,
'cause this was one of our compilations,
it says here are things that didn't make it in the show
because we got the facts wrong.
- Ah.
- Does it say that?
- It does, yeah.
- So it's sort of a catch-all.
- It's because his compilation didn't go into an episode.
'Cause I obviously knew that I made that mistake.
- 'Cause I will say, Randolph,
that you're in good company.
This is probably one of the things
we've received more emails about
than a lot of other things lately.
So I didn't realize you were just pumping out wrong facts
in our compilations.
- God, I must feature heavily in that.
- The thing is that the entire fact was correct
'cause it was about sign language and stuff,
but it was a very slight error in the middle of it,
just why I was referring to you put the wrong,
I was just going off memory about where these places were,
got it mistaken with a space needle, very easily done.
But yeah, we kept it in the compilation.
But then the compilation is not canon, I suppose,
like that Teenage Mutant Ninja set.
- It's not canon.
It's not canon.
Like the anal octopus inside the rat.
- So Krang is actually a brain, I should say,
inside a robot.
- Okay, we can't open ourselves up
to corrections of corrections.
(all laughing)
- We will disappear up our own sphincters.
- But yeah, that was genuinely just a screw up.
- I completely didn't remember who said that.
I was hoping one of you would smoke yourselves out
or that I would be found to have said the thing.
(all laughing)
- What else have we got?
- Well, there's one more thing, it's slightly longer.
So it's from Laura Markowitz.
And I'll just, you know, I'll do sort of a slight praisey,
but it's about the episode,
No Such Thing as a Magnetic Skateboard,
which is quite recent.
And we were saying, when did the queen last jump?
Or was there any footage?
Okay.
- So this was you who said it, yeah.
- Well, Laura says,
while I don't have a photo of the queen jumping,
so ready, we're off to a tangent railway line.
- A queen, is that what she's gonna go with?
- No, there are photos of the Duke and Duchess
of Windsor jumping.
- Which ones are they?
- The abdicates.
- Oh, right, not the current ones.
- No, no, no, not the current ones.
'Cause this is from 1955, give or take.
- Jumping on the ship to Hotfooted America.
(all laughing)
- Let's bring this out of our mouth.
- You should get Philippe Halsman's jump book.
I think it is out of print, but you can get it used.
- Philippe Halsman was a celebrity portrait photographer
who, in the 1950s, started asking his subjects to jump
and then photograph them in midair.
- Oh, great.
- The book contains a collection of 191 celebrity jumps,
such as Marilyn Monroe, Richard Nixon,
Robert Oppenheimer, and many others,
including the Duke and Duchess of Windsor.
- Robert Oppenheimer more like, am I right?
(all clapping)
- That's why we thought we'd better do this bonus bit.
(all laughing)
- Stop with that, you gotta get it out of the system.
- That's the most.
- One thing that happened immediately after that episode
went out, I don't know if you saw it on Twitter,
but we got lots of tweets coming into us
because a trailer had just been released
for a documentary about the queen
in which the trailer footage of the queen is jumping.
- No, no. - That's true, that's amazing.
- I think she's doing a skip rope
or maybe she's just jumping, yeah.
- Oh, as a child?
- No, no, she's--
- She's doing a skipping rope, about a 99-year-old.
- Yeah, it was for the Diamond Jubilee.
They released some footage of her, yeah.
- I think that was the holograph, surely.
- No, no, it was as a child, I think.
- I thought she was-- - But as a young as well.
But someone sent in a later bit of evidence
from, I think, about 1970 of her jumping
and she's jumping off a boat onto a key or something.
- Oh, yeah.
- I'll just tell you the last bit of Laura's email
'cause it's quite interesting, it's about this book.
- Amazing book. - Testament eventually developed
a playful hypothesis that during the act of a jump,
a person's social mask would fall away
and you could see their true character underneath.
And the book includes this interpretation
of various styles of jumping
and what they reveal about the person
on at least two occasions,
Houseman was able to predict which politician
would win his party's nomination
based on how they responded to the request to jump.
- That's amazing.
'Cause I would have thought that,
let's say the next election's Biden versus Trump again.
I don't think Biden, Biden's a bit like
the 90-year-old queen, right?
He's gonna struggle to jump.
- Yeah. - But then Trump might not jump.
- White man can't jump.
(laughing)
- Do you know that Joe Biden
is older than Dialysis Machines?
- See. - He would still be allowed to,
he would still be allowed to use one.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- It's not a rule. - It's not a rule.
- It's not as soon as they were invented,
they were like, "Only babies!"
(laughing)
But yeah, that's just the thing.
- Trump's not much younger, is he?
- No, four years. - If we're doing
the Trump and Biden versus Dialysis Machines.
- I think Trump will be 78 by the time of the next day.
- Yeah.
Also, there's nothing wrong with it.
I get a bit antsy about the old ageism against presidents.
- Do you think that President Biden
has ever used a Dialysis machine?
- I believe not.
- This is my attempt to try and start another.
- There's a picture of him
when he's getting on the boat,
and he just needs that extra boost.
- Oh, so thanks very much, Laura.
- It sounds like a great book.
- It sounds incredible.
- I've just got one very last thing,
and it's a bit more sort of related
to the first fact we mentioned today.
It's from Kevin D'Aliere, Chicago, hi Kevin.
- So quite close to Canada.
- Pretty close.
(laughing)
- I hope you're enjoying the lovely CN Tower
that way you are in Chicago, Kevin.
(laughing)
Hello, so this is about the,
we mentioned a few weeks ago, the Dave Matthews Band.
- Oh yeah.
- Going over the King Street Bridge.
- Oh, of course, yeah, yeah.
- And dumping all of their liquid fecal matter
through the bridge, which is a grill, a grate,
and it landed on an open top tourist boat
that was passing underneath the bridge.
Okay, just a very brief one from Kevin.
Hello, just wanted to share
that the Dave Matthews incident
is still so prominent here in Chicago
that it's used to slam shitty movies.
He attaches an excerpt from the Chicago Sun Times,
review of the new Jurassic World film.
(laughing)
Which features the phrase,
"This is 2 hours and 27 minutes of pure dinosaur droppings,
"and the viewer is as helpless as a boat
"passing under a bridge on the Chicago River
"as the Dave Matthews Band unloads a torrent
"of foul waste from above."
- What?
That's amazing.
I'm just watching, reading that as a non-Chicago.
(laughing)
There's similes they use in Chicago, pretty, yeah?
- Four stars.
(laughing)
That's amazing.
Are you gonna wrap us up?
- All right, thanks, bye.
(laughing)
All right, everyone, thanks for listening
to this first iteration of Drop As A Line.
If you want to let us know any extra information
or clarifications or complaints or whatever,
then why not Drop As A Line?
And also, if you think of a better title,
you Drop As A Line.
(laughing)
Bye.
(upbeat music)