How are you doing?
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast coming
to you from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber and I'm sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray,
I'm Anna Chazinski and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four
favourite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, Anna Chazinski.
My fact this week is that a frog's tongue is 10 times softer than a human's tongue.
I've thought we had soft tongues already.
And yet?
You've been very lucky in your love life.
Does this mean that French kissing a frog will be unbelievably good?
Or unbelievably bad?
Yeah, because you don't want too much give, do you?
I don't know.
It really depends on your personal taste but it doesn't use it for kissing.
When the princess kisses the frog in the story, does she French kiss it and if so does
she notice that it's tongue is unbelievably soft?
That was probably in the original draft after that she kissed.
She went, "What the fuck is that?"
Actually, I do remember that in one of the really early versions of that, like in the old
French versions of that thing, I think she has sex with the frog to turn him into a
prince, I think so.
But unfortunately, who finds the frog's penis is 10 times softer than a human's finger.
So 10 times softer, that's pretty chilly, right?
It's soft.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it's soft.
It's because it's so that they can catch their prey effectively.
So if we start our tongue out and bash it into a fly, then we'd bash the fly away from
us.
But a frog's tongue is soft enough that if it bashes its tongue into a fly, it sort of moulds
into the various crevices of the cricket or whatever it is.
And then it can retract and pull it back in.
And it does this by having an extremely soft tongue.
And it also does it by having this incredible saliva.
So frog saliva is 50,000 times more viscous, so 50,000 times stickier than ours.
So that means if you do French kiss a frog, it's going to be hard to get away.
Wow.
Yeah, that's true.
So if a frog was looking stamps to put on, that would be really soddly stuck on, right?
Yeah.
And so in the early days of the post office, then every letter came with a frog attached.
They employed them at first.
It's incredible.
But the thing is that it changes, doesn't it?
Yes.
So it starts off like, so it incredibly thick, honey, and then when it's on the tongue,
and then when it hits the insect, for a moment, it liquefies, covers the insect completely,
like it gets around every angle of it, every knock, every cranny, so the insect is completely
covered in it, and then it hardens again, and then the frog pulls it back in.
How is that?
It evolves over time, I know, but I mean, it's incredible to think of that evolving.
And I can't believe that we've never bothered to look into it before.
It's such a common trope.
The idea of a frog darting out, it's tongue and grabbing an insect, and we've only just bothered
to work out how they do it.
But there's so many things that do that, right?
Like, chameleons.
Yeah.
So there's a lot of animals.
So I wonder if they do the same thing.
They do it in a slightly different way.
Yeah.
They evolve separately.
I think like Salamanders, they have like a kind of a skeletal bit attached to
the tongue, which fires it out, and the frog just kind of drops its jaw really,
really quickly, and that flicks it out like a flicky thing.
Because when I was reading the paper, so that's quite a different description to what
I read about how the tongue is used when it darts out in order to catch prey.
And they said that effectively what it was doing was it's acting almost like a bungee cord.
So it's gripping on to the prey and just sucking it back in a very kind of mild manner,
as opposed to like a whip.
Like as if you were coming back up on the bungee.
One of weird bungee jumps, if you don't, where you stand on the ground, and you wait
for a bungee rope to pull down and grab you on the way back.
Even more exciting, you jump off the cliff without a bungee rope, and then it comes down
and grabs you.
I mean, it pulls you up.
That'd be pretty exciting.
That'd be amazing.
Do you know how they found this out?
The scientist who did this, as a PhD student, called Alexis Noel, and she said, "I actually
got 15 frogs and scraped their tongues for a couple of hours one night.
It was pretty disgusting."
And she said, "It takes about half an hour to get a milliliter of frog saliva off their
tongue."
She says, "It's like the world's most precious material because it's so hard to get and you
get so little of it once you've done that."
But I don't think that necessarily makes it precious.
Well, it depends on her time, doesn't it?
If she charges like $2 million an hour, and it takes her that long, then it is really
precious.
But if she's, you know, on minimum wage, it's probably not that precious.
She's probably somewhere in between, isn't she?
Well she works under Dr David Ho.
He was the guy who came up with the idea that all animals or all mammals urinate for the
same amount of time, around 21 seconds.
And David Ho.
We met David Ho.
How are we?
Yeah.
He's won the Nignal Bell Prize.
We met him at the ignoble show in London.
Oh, yes, we did.
Yes, we did.
Well, we spoke to Martin.
He gave us his card.
You're right.
Is he a doctor?
He's a doctor, yeah.
Nice.
Yeah.
That's very cool.
He said of the frog's tongue that it's like a trampoline and a baseball mitt in that
stretch that catches you and then pulls back.
And the bungee cord.
Yeah, there's a lot of metaphors going on here.
Well, the other metaphor is on the softness of the tongue.
They said it's like freshly chewed chewing gum about that same stickiness and kind of softness.
Okay.
And also marshmallow fluff.
You know, if you get like a t-cake and you get marshmallow on your hands, you just can't
get it off like that.
Oh my god, a wonderful marshmallow fluff works like this.
And actually, if you bashed it really hard, it would suddenly turn to liquid and you
could get it off your finger.
You'd finally be able to catch all those flies you've been looking for.
Do you know, when the frog gets its tongue back in its mouth as well, it's then it has a problem,
which is that my saliva is like honey and it's incredibly sticky and I've got the fly
on my tongue and I can't get it off.
So do you know what they have to do?
They have to push their eyeballs down into their head onto their tongue to scrape the
fly off their tongue.
Well, it's not to scrape it because what I think we might have mentioned the eyeballs
thing before, but I think they just realise why that works because that's the same thing.
I think the eyeballs bash into it and it's the impacts that turns it into this very, very
liquid thing.
So what is it?
It's a non-utonian fluid which I've talked about before.
So it's like quick sand whereby whenever you agitate it, it changes its disgust.
But it's like the opposite of custard.
So it's a non-utonian fluid but it has the opposite effect.
Catch up is the same as frog saliva.
What?
What do you mean?
The same.
It's a non-utonian fluid as well, but this way round.
So that's why if you bash a glass, catch up bottle, then it will suddenly come flowing
out because if you hit it hard enough, then the viscosity of the liquid suddenly changes.
I was looking into tongues generally and we don't know how bats drink.
We're still looking into how bats drink and one of the things that they notice is that
they use their tongue as a sort of conveyor belt to bring the liquid up.
What does that mean?
It means that the tongue sort of...
Is it on rollers?
Yeah, and then I see it, yeah.
How does that work?
I don't know, Dan.
I think you don't know how bat tongues work.
I think you've slightly misunderstood the story.
No, it says scientists use their tongues as a kind of conveyor belt to slurp up nectar.
I think the key bit there is kind of...
Okay.
Because the amazing thing about it being conveyor belt would be if it woundled the way around
on its rotor and came back out, which is hard to believe they do.
Have you heard the myth about dog mouths?
Is it that they're cleaner than human mouths?
Yes.
Because I had not heard this myth until I was researching this fact.
But there is a myth that dog mouths are cleaner than human mouths and that it's fine as a result
to friend kiss them.
It's okay.
I think what happens is, now, you've read into this, you might know, but I think there
might be fewer bacteria, but the point is that they're all bacteria that you don't already
have in your mouth.
Yes.
And probably you don't really want in your mouth.
Yeah.
So there was an article on ABC News where they spoke to a vet and said it may be safer
because lots of the bacteria are species specific.
So you can't catch the same strep from a dog that you could from a person.
However, I did read also articles like I almost died after a dog saliva infection.
So I think it's not recommended.
Well, especially a rabid dog that can...
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
If you get rabid dog saliva and you've got any kind of cuts in your mouth, then you'll catch
rabies from that.
And they used to try to weaponize this.
So I think Lian, as he called, he's a Roman writer.
He wrote that if a rabid dog saliva could get into contact with someone, then they would
get rabies.
Leonardo da Vinci thought that this might be a good idea to use in war.
And there was a Polish general called Kazemir Semenovic who thought that he would get the
slubber from rabid dogs, put them in clay balls and fire them into, like, towns that besieged.
Is there hope that people will find the clay bottles on the ground and think, what is this?
I must put it in my mouth.
Or is it that they can fire into people's mouths?
Like, it just seems like such an inefficient distribution message.
They were firing into towns of toddlers who just picked them all up and tried to eat them.
You're right.
They should put it in, like, an Easter egg or something.
Yeah, exactly.
Something really crafted like that.
And then leave a load of Easter eggs outside, saying, sorry about the seeds going on a bit,
isn't it?
Have some Easter eggs.
But our official advice is, don't snog your dog, right?
I think, yeah, that's mine, even if it might be safe, even if you've got a very clean
dog.
Even if it's safe.
It's weird.
Yeah.
I have one more thing, which is that grey whales, this is so cool, they use their tongues
really cleverly to control their heat loss.
So they've always got mouths full of extremely cold ocean water, right?
So they might lose a massive amount of heat that way.
And that would, they might die as a result of, if they had a really warm tongue.
So what happens is, the arteries that take blood to their tongue, right, are really close
to the veins carrying blood away from the tongue.
And as the arteries get closer to the tongue, they transfer all the heat over from the artery
going to the tongue to the vein, heading back from the tongue, right?
Right.
So the blood on its way to the tongue cools down, and the blood on its way back to the heart
warms up.
And it sounds kind of like a, like a conveyor belt.
It is a lot like a conveyor belt, actually.
So when it gets to the end of the tongue, or when it gets to the tongue, it's incredibly
cold already.
This blood.
So the whale doesn't lose massive amounts of heat because its tongue is constantly in contact
with very cold water.
And that crafty.
Yeah.
I don't know if it's this whale, but there is some kind of whale that can thermoregulate
in that way, but by, it has erectile tissue in its tongue.
And so it can kind of engorge it with blood in the way that an erection would.
And so they would kind of, if they need to cool down, they get a massive kind of erection
in the mouth in the tongue.
And that will cool them down.
What you laugh about, Andy.
I'm just remembering a joke, so what's happening?
Do you want to just know how you can tell if you're an extrovert or an introvert by your
saliva?
Yeah, sure.
And if you are constantly leaving it in other people's mouths, you're an extrovert.
So there's a study that was done, I think, in the '60s, but I think it's been replicated
that showed that introverts salivate more.
So when you put drops of lemon on the tongue of people who are introverted by character,
they produce more saliva.
And it kind of makes sense because people who are introverts tend to react more strongly
to certain kind of stimulation.
But can make sense if you're constantly slubbering, you don't want to spend a lot of time with
me.
Every time you open your mouth, you spit in someone's face, you start to stop speaking.
Well, so apparently this works.
If you're not sure if you're an introvert or an extrovert, there's not the easiest way
to tell, but you get a cotton bud.
You tie a little bit of thread to the exact middle so that when you hold it by the thread,
it hangs horizontally.
And then you put one end of the tip in your mouth for 20 seconds and take it out.
And then you put lemon juice on your tongue, and then you put the other end of the tip on
your mouth for another 20 seconds.
So you're seeing how much you're salivating in response to the lemon juice.
And then you hold it by the thread.
And if it's hanging horizontally still, it means you haven't salivated much, which means
you're an extrovert.
And if it tilts, it means you've salivated quite a lot.
So the end one end is heavier now.
But it's a lot to do to tell you something that presumably you kind of already know.
If you've got the time to do this, you're an introvert.
OK, there's time for fact number two, and that is Andy.
My fact is that during the Second World War, Britain invented chocolate bars infused with
garlic to give to pilots who were shot down and needed to make their breath authentically
French.
So it's the idea that you land in France and you meet someone.
Yeah.
And they say, are you French?
And you just breathe on them and they go, oh, you must be French then, you're not actually
to speak French.
But I don't ask you why you're wearing an R.A.F uniform or none of this.
So this gets written about quite a lot.
I've tried to find concrete evidence of pilots actually being given these bars and using
them.
And I haven't found much.
I do know that it was invented as a thing, because it's written about a load of times
there was a guy called Charles Fraser Smith, who was kind of one of the original inspirations
of Q in the James Bond films.
So that's this guy.
And he did invent these things, as well as loads of other incredible stuff.
Yeah.
But I can't find out whether it was put into operation in the field.
Why didn't he just give them garlic?
It's not as though-- well, hey, it's not as though garlic goes especially well with chocolate
anyway.
And R.A.F pilots in World War II would be undergoing a lot of physical trauma and challenges
every day.
I didn't think they're going to have a problem with just easier a couple of cloves of garlic.
That's not going to be the final straw.
No, but this guy was James Bond's Q, right?
Yeah.
So Q never just-- there was always a double thing to the invention.
It's a pen that doubles as a-- so you would be like, it's just garlic.
You'd be like, "And?"
And it doubles as a chocolate bar.
That's Q.
It's not garlic, but doubles as a chocolate bar.
Well, it's a chocolate bar.
Yeah.
Garlic flavoured.
Well, I'm just saying.
A lot of people that go on missions isn't chocolate a thing, a sustenance.
So maybe he was trying to double up the sustenance with the-- so again, Q's mind is working
there.
He's doubling up.
Yeah, I'm very good.
Back to say about my criticism.
It was a great idea.
Yeah.
This was in the news because there was a very recent story, MI6 announced that their current
Q is a woman, which surprised a lot of people because they thought it was still--
That's my new talent from the James Bond fans, but no, it is, but he doubles up as a woman.
Did they tell us who these people are?
What's going on?
I think it's bizarre that you know who the head of MI5 and MI6 is.
Yeah, I do as well.
Really hard.
Probably aren't the real ones.
They can't be, right?
Like Stella Remington couldn't have been the headhead.
I think she was.
I mentioned she was, but on what James is saying, I think that you can't-- there must be someone
who is actually a secret head.
There's going to be someone who, if you ask them, they'll just not be able to say anything.
I don't know.
What if Stella Remington listens to this podcast, and she's sitting at home feeling bad now?
She's fine.
She's the fake head of MI6.
Okay, so I don't think we can say fake on a fake, that's all.
All I'm saying is, if I was in charge, I would make Stella Remington the fake one and then
have a real one.
Yes.
But she'd know at some point that she was the fake one after--
She's in on it.
Oh, she's in on it.
But she doesn't think she's running the show with secretly this.
She's an actor called Maureen.
Maureen Lippman.
Yeah.
I'm not going to recognise her though, they'll say I saw that Stella Remington in a--
Oh, the BT ad.
Yes.
She should be looking after the country's safety, not clocking on and doing BT adverts, and then
there'd be a scandal.
I love the BT adverts.
That's a reference from the early '80s.
That's the last thing I can remember that piece.
Well, she's going to be feeling sad at home because you haven't been keeping up with
her career.
So I don't think that you need to be secret unless you're in the field.
Next thing, another thing, I would assume.
Well, Stella Remington was the first person that they openly acknowledged as the head.
So that was a transparency thing that came in with one of the governments who decided
transparency was, I think.
So they did keep them secret.
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
That's not always been, though.
That was the thing that I think we've mentioned on a previous podcast.
And I don't know.
I think we almost mentioned it as an urban myth, the idea of the spy who was pregnant and
they discovered that she was a spy when she was delivering the baby because the pain
was so great, she started swearing in her own language.
Is that a myth?
I don't know.
I thought you meant that the baby came out and started speaking Russian.
Ah, that's fity of my life.
It's a great myth.
Or, I mean, if it's true, if it's in bad terms, it might be true.
Only that I've heard it and I've never personally questioned it, but it might, yeah, it
does have the width of the myth, doesn't it?
Do you guys know about Operation Lena?
No.
This was a German operation.
This was in 1940 and it was when 12 Germans spies were sent to Britain as to, like, do a bit
of a wrecky to plan Hitler's follow-up operation, which is going to be Operation Sealine, which
is going to be the invasion of Britain.
And so they were trained up as to how to appear British, apparently trained up to blend
right in.
And they were caught straight away because of their own stupidity, was what the British
officials said.
One of them went into a pub and ordered a pint of cider at 10 in the morning and, which is
a weird thing to do in any situation.
I can't think of anything more British.
No, you go to Gawick and Heathrow Airport.
Well, you'll see a lot of German spies there.
You'll see a lot of German spies there.
I'll see a lot of German spies there.
Do you know why they climb up trees?
I didn't know until I read this.
So the producer of King Kong had read the story of W. Douglas Bowden.
And W. Douglas Bowden had gone over and he was the first person to probably film Komodo Dragons,
bring back a few live Komodo dragons as well as samples of dead ones
that they'd shot while they were out there.
And he went out with his wife and he had basically the scenes that you see in King Kong
where they go to Skull Island to begin with is the kind of same setup of what they had.
Wait, did he tie his wife to a tree to draw Komodo Dragon?
No, but she almost got killed by Komodo Dragon while she was out there.
Yeah, she went out without her gun one day and she was walking past a carcass
that was laid out for Komodo Dragon that they were hoping to attract.
And one was coming.
So suddenly she was between the carcass and the Komodo Dragon.
And she laid down in the tall grass and really hoped that it hadn't seen her.
But she also suspected that it had and smelt her.
And so she accepted her death and just laid that because she knew it was that close.
And five feet away, the Komodo Dragon as it was coming towards her was shot by one of the assistance of burden.
So she survived.
She didn't deserve to survive.
Who just lies down and takes it.
At least try and make a run for it.
Well, she just knew there was no way.
Well, there is a way.
There are only slightly faster than climb a tree.
Well, they've just discovered them.
They don't know what their abilities are.
This is like a dinosaur.
And what kind of survival instinct is that?
So she just said, I'm dead.
She'd rather go to have me.
I've got a complete idiot.
That would work against some animals, though, wouldn't it?
They're playing dead.
Yeah. It's a big risk.
It's a big risk.
Brown bears and black bears, there's a different one of them.
I think brown bears, nothing works.
Because they're faster.
They can climb trees and they can just.
And then with black bears, I think you're supposed to kind of take your clothes off and slowly walk away from them
so that they get confused about what your clothes are.
You're just trying to make me have an embarrassing bear.
[LAUGHTER]
Noted pervert, hunter hunter Murray,
was found naked and mortal.
[LAUGHTER]
Back on the way, they taste things.
So they have this fork tongue and they stick it out and it gets like all the chemicals and the information from the air.
And then they retract it into their mouth and they rub it into pads on the bottom of their mouth.
And then they have to close their mouth and the pads on the bottom of their mouth touch the top of their mouth.
And that contains an organ that gives it to their brain.
So every time they want to taste something, you get it on your tongue, put it on the bottom of your mouth,
close your mouth, put it on the top of your mouth.
It just seems like a real dilemma.
That does.
But that does seem like a connoisseur as well.
It does, doesn't it?
Like what a professional.
It feels like someone's really tasting their food.
So in your mythical commuter dragon restaurant, there'll be a lot of consideration going on.
And getting notes of carcass, but also excrement.
[LAUGHTER]
Maybe that's why she laid still as well.
She thought, I mean, how often do you change your mind about the restaurant you're going to as soon as you get up to it
and see a better one next door?
Yes.
She knew she was bad tasting.
Yeah, exactly.
Two and a half miles away.
This commuter dragon made a booking.
Yeah.
He was on his way.
Are we sure she wasn't lying still covering herself in feces?
She probably was.
[LAUGHTER]
So there is a thing.
Their metabolism is a really slow reptiles, as we know, because they're, as we say, cold-blooded.
But their muscles can stay working for hours after death.
So there was an Atlantic article all about the process of dissecting a commuter dragon,
which is very hard.
Very low to the nose of knives, because their skin is so tough.
Really?
Yeah. And one of the students who was doing it, called Viv Allen,
said that she'd been studying an alligator, which would be shot, had a massive hole in his head.
And she stuck a knife into the alligator, and it walked off the table.
[LAUGHTER]
And they freaked out, obviously, because it was dead.
But their metabolism is so slow that their muscles can stay working for hours.
And if you hit the right nerve center, you can trigger lots of muscular contractions.
And she said, we freaked out. It just wouldn't stop moving.
We cut its head off just to make sure.
And then one of the undergrads was sick in it.
Oh, cut.
Wow.
I know.
Just quickly on reptiles surviving after they've been killed, a snake remains completely alive after you decapitate it.
Not just muscle, not just muscles, like spasming or anything.
A snake's head is totally alive for about an hour.
And after a full hour, it can see you and decide it's pissed off with you,
because you've cut its head from its body, and head it, so I don't know how it heads over to you.
But crawl its way over to you on its head and bite you.
That's amazing.
It's because they've got these ridiculously slow metabolism.
That's hilarious.
That's amazing.
So creepy.
It must be weird if they actually say, like, chase a mouse and they catch it and they eat it,
but it just walks through.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, it is time to move on to our final fact of the show, and that is James.
OK, my fact this week is that you can improve your darts game by training yourself to dream about darts.
But it's not worth it, because you have to dream about darts all the time.
Well, you know, there are worse dreams.
It's not a nightmare at least.
What depends on the game?
The dartboard is chasing you. It's a nightmare.
[LAUGHTER]
And it's trying to throw darts into your body and say, see how you like it.
I don't think that would improve your game if that's the way you dream about it.
[LAUGHTER]
Now, the way that this works, it was a study which they did on lucid dreamers.
And these are people who can kind of decide what they're going to dream about.
And it's the thing you can train yourself to do.
You go to sleep, and then you realize you're asleep, and you can say, OK, now I'm going to chase dragons,
because I know I'm asleep, whereas most people just dream passively.
Anyway, they got these people who could lucid dream to practice darts,
and they tested them afterwards, and the ones who did it were better at darts,
and the ones who didn't do it were worse at darts.
That's how you go.
Although they did specify that if people, the third group that practice darts in their waking life
were even better than the ones who practiced it in their sleep.
Sure.
But I imagine if you practice in your waking life and practice while you're asleep,
you're going to be even better.
So it sounds like this is quite early research, like the controversial as well.
A lot of people aren't sure whether or not it does actually improve.
It's just a small pool of stuff.
Oh, it's a small study, yeah.
Yeah.
But the thing is, it definitely does work.
I don't want to say definitely just in case, but it does appear to work,
is kind of in sport, just imagining that you're going to do something,
and that really helps your body to prepare for muscle memory and things like that.
I can absolutely believe it.
Haven't there been studies on people with their arms and casts
who've been asked to visualise themselves doing exercises with that arm?
Yes.
And it's been, their arm has become stronger than if they were,
than if they were not doing those visualisations.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, it absolutely.
So that is, I mean, dreaming doesn't sound very far from that at all.
I believe it.
There was one thing about this study as well with the lucid dreamers about darts,
dreams being what they are.
Sometimes they weren't exactly the same as a darts game.
So one of the people was throwing a dartboard that was actually looked exactly like a tree stump,
but that still helped them to get better.
Oh, sure.
So is it wood in the real world, I guess?
Yeah.
It's like, you find out the dartboard is your mum, that's different.
No, but I think the idea is, even if a dartboard turns into your mum
and you turn out to be naked and you're flying over Australia,
then you're still going to be better because you practice the darts bit.
Imagine if you got to the competition, you needed those exact conditions.
I'm Phil Taylor, the darts player.
Yeah.
He dreams about darts.
So sometimes I'm playing darts in my sleep and I wake myself up.
I hate it.
Drives me crackers because if I have a catnet, I'm dreaming about bloody darts.
Yeah.
So he is the best darts player of all time.
Right.
And he probably plays darts all the time in his normal life
because otherwise how would he get so good?
Yeah.
And he's probably just dreaming because you often dream about what you're doing.
You love them.
Actually, he's deliberately doing its practice.
Like if you play a computer game and when you close your eyes at night,
you can see images from the computer game.
Yeah, the Tetris effect.
Yeah, I used to get that all the time, but I used to play a lot of computer games.
Supposedly when Queen Elizabeth II and Prince Philip went on a tour of Australia
and they did something like 56 towns in 57 days.
So it was a megator. Philip at that point was dreaming of just waving in his dreams.
Yeah, I don't know if that's a proper fact.
It's in the crown, but I assume they pulled that from a book somewhere.
Wow.
You love the crown so much.
I can't believe it's taken you so long to crowbar it into this.
I know.
What is the crown?
Is it a film?
It's a Netflix.
It's written by Peter Morgan who wrote the Queen.
Right.
So he's very factual in his writing.
And yeah, neither of those stories mentions that they're all lizards.
Weirdly.
Have you ever seen the Queen try and catch a fly with her marshmallow-like tongue?
Like Ozzie LB8.
I know.
And I've sent all those emails about the honours committee to my management.
Incredible.
I'm filled the power.
So the nickname the power.
I went on to Wikipedia and saw a big list of all because they've all got sort of WWF nicknames
that they bring to the sport.
But what's really exciting is there's a lot of puns.
So Antonio Alcinas.
He's Spanish.
So what do you reckon his is?
Antonio Alcinas.
I don't know.
El d'Artador.
So that's it.
Jamie Harvey.
He's from Scotland.
What's his pun?
Tossing the dart.
No, Scotland.
Like Scotland the brave.
Some pun on this.
Brave dart.
Oh.
Mark Frost.
Where's he from?
Is he from Dartford?
Because otherwise I reckon we're going to struggle with someone from Dartford.
Could anybody be beaten by someone from Dartmore?
So the earliest form of darts, do you know why it was banned?
Why?
Do you know that it was banned?
It was because people kept on dying.
It's the earliest form of darts wall.
Yes.
No, it was called Puff and Dart and it involved a blowpipe.
And you go, you know, you would blow the dart towards the board.
And eventually, I mean, people kept on swallowing them by mistake.
And they could be--
Shucking instead of blowing.
Yeah.
They could be quite small.
And so eventually they thought, why don't we just get rid of the blowpipe element of the darts game?
Did you see read about that man last year or the year before last, who inhaled a dart?
But he inhaled a rubber dart 44 years ago.
And his parents took him to Annie and said, we think our sons inhaled a dart.
And they said, there's not really a dart in there, go away.
And then he didn't know about this.
And he's always had sinus problems.
And he sneezed.
This is in 2015.
He sneezed.
Please tell me you was standing right next to the dart bottle.
[LAUGHTER]
And he took him 5,000 pounds for prize money and the rubber dart.
So he sneezed and the rubber dart came out.
And it had been sitting in his nose for the last 44 years.
That is unbelievable.
James, you know darts terminology because you're a fan of the sport.
Sure.
Have you heard of the phrase, wankers 50?
[LAUGHTER]
I haven't.
No, what is a wankers 50?
It's-- I don't know if this is common or rare.
It doesn't seem common.
It's where you're aiming for a bullseye, which is 50.
Oh, yeah.
But you hit single 20, single 18, and single 12 instead.
OK.
So you do score 50, but you use three darts.
OK, have you heard of bagadix, which is B-A-G-A-D-I-X?
Oh, it's not an acronym.
No.
Oh.
What would begin with X in that acronym?
[LAUGHTER]
It's rhyming slang.
It's not an acronym.
OK.
It's rhyming slang for 26.
Oh, because if you're aiming for the treble 20,
you miss it on one side and get one, and on the other side you get five.
Exactly.
And I call that B and B, but I don't know why we call it that.
B and B is 2 and 6, and 2 and 6 is how much a bed and breakfast used to cost in the UK,
in two shillings and six months, in pre-decentralisation characters.
So what's bagadix?
26.
You know that as in, I don't know.
Should in that, like most rhyming slang has a meaning to a thing it's wrong to.
You know a bag.
Yeah.
So if you put some dicks in a bag.
OK.
See?
I don't know that it is that.
It sounds more like a bingo call, doesn't it?
Yeah.
Bagadix.
26.
[LAUGHTER]
This children do listen to this show.
Oh, it's not that bad.
A lot of people know what bingo is.
[LAUGHTER]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
OK, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shriverland.
James.
@XHAPES.
Andy.
@AndreyHunterM.
And Shazinski.
You can email podcast@QI.com.
Yep, or you can go to our group podcast account at QI Podcast.
Or go to our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
We've got all of our previous episodes up there.
We will be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)