(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another edition of No Such Thing
as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name's Andy and I'm sitting here
with three of the regular elves,
James Harkin, Alex Bell, and Anna Tajinsky.
And we've gathered our favorite facts from the last seven days
and we're now going to talk about them
in no particular order.
(upbeat music)
First fact is Alex.
- Okay, my fact is cows have friends and they get sad
when you separate them.
- Oh.
- How are they cow friends?
- Yeah, so basically Northampton University did a study.
So cows are her animals obviously.
- Pascine.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so they live in a herd but they get separated a lot
because they need to be milk, they need to be taken
into the vets, et cetera.
And Northampton University did a study where they looked
at cows when they're in a field and monitored all their behavior
to see which cows hung out with which other cows.
And then they separated them out into different combinations.
So sometimes they'd be removed from the herd in pairs
and sometimes they'd be with a cow they'd never hung out
with before or sometimes they'd be with their best friend.
(laughing)
- I don't know how we could work to that.
- Bracelets, but they wear bracelets.
- Yeah.
And sometimes they were on their own
and each time their heart rates
and cortisol levels were monitored
and from that apparently we can work out
whether cows get stressed or not.
- And cortisol we should say is the stress hormone,
is that right? - Right, yeah.
- Apparently there's quite a high level of stress
with integrating into a new herd.
So if you take a cow and you put it into--
- I was gonna say how stressful can it be being a cow?
- Well, very.
- If you don't know what your demise is going to be,
I would say very, but they don't.
- Given how little is going on in their lives,
I think any change is pretty stressful.
I mean, if you're moving how from one field to the other,
that's probably groundbreaking to them.
(laughing)
You think about it then?
- Yeah, so it's hard to tell if that counts as a friend.
- Yeah, we're kind of anthropomorphizing them, aren't we?
- Yeah, I think elephants always feel like they're the ones
that we're most justified anthropomorphizing
'cause they only have a weirdly human attitude
towards their dead, don't they?
- They mourn, don't they?
- Yeah, they mourn their dead
and they bury them sometimes with leaves and earth
and they'll come back to visit where the elephant died,
the family member died.
- The thing about elephant graveyards is that a myth
or is that real? - That is a myth, yeah.
- Yeah, so that's the idea that the elephants will go
to a certain place to die and then you'll find lots of bones
there because it's a special place for elephants.
- But you'd feel terrible if you were an elephant
and everyone else said, "Hey, come on,
we're going to the elephant graveyard."
And you said, "Why?"
And they said, "No reason."
(laughing)
- That's like the cartoon, "The Daily Mash of the Turkey,"
which is saying just before Christmas,
it's a bubble speech bubble coming out of the turkeys
mouth saying, "Hey guys, so are you doing any of the new year?"
I agree.
(laughing)
- Feel sad.
- But elephants, something really weird about elephants
or on it is if you show them on piece of ivory
and then a piece of wood, they get much more agitated
by the ivory and if you show them an elephant skull
and then the skull of another large animal,
like a hippo skull, they're much more agitated
by the elephant skull.
- Really?
- Elephant skulls are quite scary though, aren't they?
'Cause they have like a big hole, yes.
- That is true.
- The idea is that's where Cyclops myth might have come from.
'Cause it looks like there's a massive eye hole
in the middle, but actually it's where the trunk comes out from.
- Cows skulls only have, they only have bottom teeth.
So we have two sets of teeth, obviously,
is in the top teeth and bottom teeth.
They only have bottom teeth.
Where the top teeth should be,
there's just a sort of long area of bone.
So they grind up what they eat with teeth, yeah.
- Cows don't have upper teeth.
- So I was basically, I was looking into
how the digestive system of a cow,
so they're ruminants, which means that they basically
ferment the grass first.
So they pick up the grass by,
they actually curl their tongues round the grass
instead of ripping it up with their teeth,
which I thought it was really interesting.
Then they chew it, then it goes down into their stomach
and sits there for a while and ferments for a bit.
So they get nutrients out and then they regurgitate it
back into their mouths and chew it some more,
which is the ruminating, but, and that's cods now.
So that's where chewing the cod comes from
and then they sort of get again.
- Winding your tongue around the rate of grass
is quite sexy, isn't it?
(laughing)
- I've never seen a woman before yourself.
- You know, I've never seen a woman doing that.
- I need to go on more picnics.
(laughing)
- I bet cows tie cherries and knots as a final.
- Oh yeah.
- And that's what I was thinking of.
- What's that?
- You know, when you tie a cherry and a knot
with your tongue and then that kind of shows that you're--
- Yeah, cherry stock.
- That sounds incredibly difficult.
I don't think it was that good.
- It's not that hard.
- My brother can do it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It's not that hard as well.
- Once you learn how to do it, it's pretty easy.
And you're a babe back then, then.
(laughing)
- I can also pick up blades of grass with my tongue.
- And another animal which has friends is sharks.
If you can believe sharks have friends.
- I don't believe that.
- Oh, okay, some scientists analyzed a group
of a particular species of sharks,
which swim around together.
And they couldn't work out if they were swimming together
because there were just food sources,
which were close to each other,
or the home ranges were in the same place.
But they discovered that actually some shark
preferred the company of certain other sharks
and actively avoided other ones,
even though they were all in the same area
of their territories overlap.
So they concluded these sharks basically have friends.
- So that's what it should be.
- It could be that they have friends,
or it could be that they just have enemies
and they're hanging around these other guys
'cause they're not enemies.
- What's the definition of an enemy or a friend?
- True. - Yeah.
- This is quite interesting.
They're like, why would animals have friends?
And there must be an evolutionary reason for it.
And I read two possible explanations I'd never heard before.
So one of them was the enemy's enemy thing.
And evidence for that is in dolphins,
who there were two dolphins who had avoided each other.
So they didn't particularly like each other.
And then as soon as another dolphin came along,
that wasn't part of their group
and that was effectively an enemy to both of them,
those first two dolphins started hanging out
with each other became bestist buddies.
'Cause suddenly they unite against their common enemy.
- So what I feel is happening with this podcast actually
and then you got and you were all ganging up
on me and being horrible.
- Shut up Alex.
- Okay, I'm sorry.
- The other good explanation I thought about
why animals are friends to be attracted to the opposite sex.
So they studied McCax and there was a McCax
who was super attractive for like really good physical build,
et cetera, but he wasn't very good at making friends
with other males and women stopped shacking him.
So same as with humans I guess, if someone's unpopular.
- Again, we need to say female McCax.
(all laughing)
- I think just going back to the dolphins for a second,
they hang out in pods, I think, to feed though, don't they?
Because they swim around in a circle
making bubbles and trapping fish in those bubbles
so that they can eat them.
So that's kind of a useful reason for having friends.
- Yes, yes.
- I think the smallest unit of dolphins is two or three males
and they club up to guard the females basically
that they perceive as being theirs.
And then several of those little units
will group together to steal females from other males.
But sometimes two of those, even larger units,
will club up a format kind of coalition,
even though normally they're rivals.
- Wow.
- Then there must come an awkward moment
where the dolphins decide which one of them actually gets
to copulate with the female.
- Well, dolphins have a very varied sex life.
- So they can all do it, you're saying?
- Yeah, they have, they have blowhole sex.
And they have, they have all kinds of sex.
Blowhole jobs.
(all laughing)
Okay, there is one other sign that could be an indicator
that animals are friends with each other,
which is they measure the levels of oxytocin
inside them, which is known in humans as the love hormone.
And if you have it, you are more inclined
to trust other people and love them.
And they tested, this is interspecies friendships.
So that's very exciting.
- Oh, like test Disney film friendships.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
And they tested a terrier and a goat,
which were both young males.
And they were used to playing and having play fights
and sort of playfully nipping each other
and rolling around and this stuff.
And so they played for 15 minutes.
And then after that, they measured the levels
of oxytocin, the amount of oxytocin of the dog
had increased by 48%, which they said suggested
the dog was quite attached to the goat.
(all laughing)
However, the goats increase in oxytocin was 210%.
And the authors of this said,
we essentially found that the goat
might have been in love with the dog.
(all laughing)
Which is a tragic, unrequited thing.
It's so great.
- Now that's sad.
- Yeah.
So animal friendship is most people thought
that animals with big brains are more like to make friends.
And they found that fruit bats can make friends as well.
And they have tiny brains.
So that's quite confusing.
But they found this because things like
there was a pregnant fruit bat.
And they found that she was being groomed and hugged
repeatedly by another bat who was unrelated to her,
another female bat.
And then when she gave birth,
then the other female bat who'd been grooming her
and a third female fan-t her with their wings
to keep her cool.
- Wow.
- Just being nice to each other for no reason.
- I do have bats can fan each other with their wings.
That's amazing in itself, I think.
- Yeah, that is quite cool.
- Now I wish I had wings.
- Yeah, because that's a primary useful wings, isn't it?
That's the best thing you can use if you keep yourself cool.
(all laughing)
- Wow.
- You give it a try as well.
- I love it.
- I love it if James is a bird just sitting there
and I'm just going up to him James.
Why don't you have a, oh, you can do that with them too.
- D.H. Lawrence had a cow called Susan.
- Degrees.
- Yeah, which he loved and wrote so a lot about.
And there's one other celebrity cow that I found.
Elmpharm Olly, also known as the Sky Queen,
was the first cow to fly an aeroplane to fly in an aeroplane.
(all laughing)
The Sky Queen was the first.
- She struggled with landing for a while.
She was at the controls.
- That's how I got over the moon, right?
(all laughing)
- Yeah, so she was the first cow to fly in an aeroplane.
It was in 1930 at the International Air Exposition in Missouri.
A man called El's Worth Bunts became the first man
to milk a cow mid-flight.
Which he did in that flight.
He parachuted calm some milk down to the spectators below.
- That is the stupid one, brilliant thing.
That's fantastic.
- Right.
- Another thing that, sorry, another thing that...
- Oh my God.
- If that was intentional, then you're fired from the podcast.
- Another thing that affects cow lactation is slow songs.
Apparently if you play slow ballads to a cow,
then their lactation increases.
But if you play fast, clubby songs to a cow,
I think it was described as Euro Club Classics.
There's no effect on lactation at all.
- What the Euro Club Classics are.
- Yeah.
- I fall 65, probably that one.
- I'm a new, DVD, DVD, DVD.
(all laughing)
Thank you very much.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, time for fact number two,
which this week is James Harkin.
- Okay, my fact is that it's illegal to take a selfie
with a tiger in New York City.
- What?
- A big question.
(all laughing)
- Well, it kind of speaks for itself, really.
This is a new law that's come in.
And it prohibits direct contact
between members of the public and big cats.
So it's like with traveling circuses or that kind of thing.
And really, it's that you're not allowed any photos,
but obviously the press have put it forward
as no tiger selfies.
Because apparently tiger selfies are a thing
on our dating websites.
- Yes, to make...
I've just realized someone's told me about this.
And to make men look extra manly, apparently,
they photograph themselves next to big...
- It's completely animal.
- It's simultaneously manly and cuddly.
Because you're cuddling a tiger, but it's a tiger.
- Oh, no, Alex, we've done it, haven't you?
- I have a, I haven't seen it.
I have visited the blog, which I found this morning
called Tinder Guys with Tigers.
- But actually, thinking about it now,
if you're next to a tiger,
the tiger is big and manly and well, not manly,
but big and powerful, and next to him,
you're just going to look less powerful.
So you want to be next to a really weak,
like a hamster or something.
- There's lots of baby tiger photos.
- Ah, there.
- Or maybe women will be very disappointed
on the eventual dates,
'cause they assumed that it was the tiger in the photo.
(laughing)
Well, this is the technique that was surely first
patented by Vladimir Putin.
- Oh, yeah.
- Who has photos taken with every wild animal.
- But they're many dead, aren't they?
- No, there's a lot of the wild animals.
- He does some hunting ones,
but it's genuinely Putin swimming with dolphins on the internet.
- Dolphins who are previously enemies ganged off him again.
(laughing)
- He's trying to ban blow-hole sex.
- That's that I have, right there.
- I was looking into history of selfies,
'cause it seems quite like a modern thing.
So I had a look.
The earliest photograph of a person in American history
is actually a selfie.
It was taken by a guy called Robert Cornelius,
and he took it in 1839.
He was a lampmaker,
and he was responsible for developing a process
called Daggeropty, which was a short-lived photographic process
of some sort, which is probably during the 1840s.
The process was so slow that he was actually able
to set up the camera and then run into shot
for about a minute or so,
and then close the lens cap, which is quite, quite more--
- And the photos were called Daggeroptyps,
whether that was it.
- Wikipedia describes the photo,
which you can go and see as an off-center portrait
of a man with crossed arms and tautled hair.
So I reckon it would be pretty well on Instagram,
'cause that's pretty close to the mark.
For the first selfie, that's pretty well done.
- Yeah.
- Do we think that was the first self-portrait?
No, 'cause people have been drawing themselves for years,
but I had a look into what the first ever,
there's a collection of lines in a cave,
which may be a drawing of a face, 27,000 years old.
- We're kind of assuming this is the same person who drew it,
though, if we're saying it's a selfie.
- Exactly, yeah, it's open to debate.
- There are a few lines next to it
that look a bit like a tiger.
(laughing)
- 19th century portraits are fun.
We talked about the headless photos.
- Headless photos, so.
- So, yeah, Victorions like to photograph themselves
headless, I think, and carrying their heads
or with their heads and their laps.
They managed to doctor photos from a really early time.
So you get portraits from the 1850s and '60s
with their head and their--
- They were necessarily doctors.
They were like illusions.
- They actually didn't cut heads.
- The photo was so prestigious back then
that you would have your own head cut off
to have a photo made of you
so that it would look better.
- No, it only worked.
- A lot of them would be, like, it's hard to describe,
but there would be illusions.
So you'd have two people in the photo,
and one person would be sort of on the end of a table
with their head resting on it
and the rest of their body sort of out of shot.
And then another person would be organized in a way
that you didn't look like their head was there
and when you line up, it looked like their head was not
where it's supposed to be.
- Oh, that's very good.
And have you heard of, have you heard of snap shooting,
which was a game that people played?
- No.
- This is in the very early days of handheld cameras.
It's so much fun.
You had to escape while someone else tried
to take a photo of you.
- Oh, it's not cool.
- That's quite good.
- It's a bit like laser quest.
- Yeah, but it's laser quest.
Well, you don't know the results for three days
until you've had the photos developed.
- It sounds like a fun game.
- This is really interesting, I thought.
So, after National Geographic published its first wildlife
photographs in 1906 in the magazine,
and two of the National Geographic Society board members
resigned in disgust, 'cause wildlife photos.
- They said it was becoming a mere picture book
and that wasn't what the National Geographic was all about.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- A few more selfie things.
You know these selfie stick, yes, of course.
There's a thing called a selfie stick, do you know what that is?
- A selfie stick.
- Well, a selfie, I know, to my shame,
is a selfie of your own bottom.
- Yes.
- So is a stick to take a photo of your own bottom?
- That's right.
- A self-colonist could be cute.
(all laughing)
- No, it's not that.
- The article I read said,
it's curiously out of stock at the moment,
but is ostensibly a real product.
So I'm not sure if it's even real.
- Okay.
- But the idea is that you hold it,
and then it takes a picture of your bum,
and then you can send it to people, presumably.
You want to see that kind of thing?
- Oh, Brave New World.
(all laughing)
- The Statue of Liberty is taking one continuous long selfie.
I found this on Reddit today.
There's her hand, which is holding up the torch.
There's a camera video camera,
which you can stream a live feed from online,
and it's pointing down to her face,
so she's taking one.
- Wow.
- That is great.
- That is really good.
- That's such a good fact.
- Yeah.
- Vain as women in the world.
(all laughing)
- Does anyone have more?
- Some stuff about things illegal in New York.
- Oh, yeah.
- Okay, so it's strangely,
it's illegal to honk your horn in New York City,
unless it's an emergency.
- So that's another still accuracy then,
because anytime there's an establishing shot of New York,
there's a soundtrack,
there's lots of lots of hallways.
- No, no, no, no, that's not true.
- It's just that everyone's breaking the law.
- All right, there's a constant state of emergency.
(all laughing)
It's also illegal for three or more people
to dance in New York City.
- What?
- This is the rave laws that they have there.
So what constitutes a rave?
- Also in the same place.
- Yeah, you can have a book in the appointment with the city.
- Can I dance now?
- But what do you mean in the same place?
- It's okay if you're in your own home, actually.
But it's gonna be the people in your home have to be yourself.
People who live there are bona fide guests.
It's legal in churches.
And weirdly, it's also legal in premises licensed
as retail cigarette dealers.
- The cigarette buying dance, yeah.
(all laughing)
- So if you're in a bar and three of you are dancing?
- You need a dancing license.
- All so the bar might have a dancing license.
- Yeah, all the white constitutes an illegal rave.
And also, pinball machines are illegal in a lot of America,
but in New York until the 70s.
- Wow.
- It was because it was kind of gambling.
And in the 1940s, Mayor Lagadia smashed up
a load of pinball machines in front of the press
and threw them in the sea.
- He threw the press into the sea.
(all laughing)
- Recently, the Mayor of Riga drove a tank
over an illegally parked car to make a point.
Although he had illegally parked the car himself.
So it wasn't just a random illegal parked car.
- Well, it was the point he was making
that look at my big tank.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, clearly.
- That's true.
- Literally, it was parked properly.
- Big issues in Latvia.
- What were we talking about?
Hey, we're talking about it now.
So it's worked.
- Yeah, actually, guys, I'm double parked out there.
So I'm just gonna have to go
before the bear of Riga get laid.
(upbeat music)
- All right, time for fact number three, which is Anna.
- Yep, my fact this week is that
Morgh refrigerators in Turkey
are equipped with motion sensors, alarms,
and handles that open them from the inside
in case anyone in there wakes up.
- Perfectly, perfectly sensible precaution.
- I think so.
- Does it happen?
Ever?
- I don't think there's been any instances,
certainly not in that place of it happening.
But I think there's a widespread paranoia
in that area of Turkey.
It's in Malatia in Turkey.
And they have, yeah, so they've got like door handles
on the inside.
There are sensors all around the inside compartment,
so that if anything touches the walls,
then automatically the drawer comes open.
So the corpse is free to leave.
- But corpses move around a little bit, don't they?
- Because of escaping gases,
and I think eventually Riga wants to leave.
- Absolutely, but not very much.
- And also when they become zombies.
- Yes.
- That is a concern.
- In which case, why have we built easy access?
- Yes, it's easy access.
- More compartments.
- That's true.
If the zombie apocalypse happens,
these are gonna be the first guys out, aren't they?
- Yeah, and they'll let all the others out.
- In the 19th century,
there was no reliable indicator for death.
People did not know that it was your heartbeat.
- But that's still kind of true
because it could be brain activity.
- That's true.
- So I think actually there is a slight kind of argument
about how you can actually say that someone's dead,
whether it's the heartbeat,
whether it's the brain activity or whether it's...
- Yeah.
- It's almost like we know so much now
that we've blurred the boundary that we originally set.
- Yeah.
- Well, they just didn't have a boundary at all.
- They knew nothing at all of it,
and they had competitions to enter
where you would be given 1,500 francs
if you worked out an easy and reliable sign of death.
The winner was the heartbeat,
and it was the man Eugene Bouchou,
who invented the stethoscope,
and Eugene Bouchou sounds like
what you might hear down a stethoscope as well.
(all laughing)
- But it was fantastic,
and he got a lot of criticism for being so impetuous
as to say that you could bury someone
only two minutes after ascertaining that they were dead.
Everyone else said, "No, no, no, no, you should wait,"
and it took years.
- Did you say that he invented the stethoscope, sorry?
- Sorry, he didn't.
- Ah, yeah.
Because the stethoscope was invented by a guy
who was embarrassed when he had to take the heartbeat
of a particularly booksome lady, wasn't it?
And the way that he used to do it
was you would put your head right down next to someone's chest,
and he was embarrassed to kind of go into the breast area.
- So he left her alone.
"Excuse me while I go and invent something."
(all laughing)
- I might be wrong about this,
but I think he did it with a rolled-up newspaper
or something, and thought,
"Well, this works quite well,
and now I'm gonna make something even better."
I might be wrong about the last bit.
- I'm not sure.
- The other ideas suggested for the prize included,
sticking a thermometer into the stomach
to see if you were cold enough to be buried.
- To the rectum, would be good.
- I don't think anyone suggested that for this.
- Because you've got two different ways.
One, the shock of having something up your bum,
and two, the temperature.
- Yes, yeah.
- Okay, well, they're not actually still taking
submissions, but I will pass it on.
- Well, that?
- They also had attaching pinces to the nipples
of the brisium corpse.
Scott, just burning the patient's arm
with boiling water and seeing what happened.
Putting a multitude of leeches near the bottom,
or sticking it to my wife.
- Or sticking a very long needle with a flag at one end,
into the heart.
And if the patient was alive,
and there was any movement, the flag would wave a bit.
- What?
- And not for long.
- And then when he died, it would come down to half mass,
doesn't it?
- One doctor said that the patient's tongue
should be rhythmically pulled for three hours.
- We should say, a lot of this is from a fantastic book
by John Bonderson called "Berry Delive,"
and it has a huge amount of unbelievably interesting
information about this cultural fear over the centuries.
- Since you mentioned putting stuff up the anus.
In the late 18th century,
doctors William Hawes and Thomas Cogan decided
the best treatment for someone who seemed dead
after drowning was a tobacco enema.
And so they used to shove things up your anus, didn't they?
And that had like a dual purpose
of testing if someone was dead.
- By giving you a nice hit of tobacco.
- Exactly.
And it was thought that, first of all,
they would warm up the drowned person
by pumping tobacco up their bum.
And second, it was stimulate their respiration again.
And it got a lot more popular when they started doing it
with bellows, so they were a kid.
So before this, they were just doing it
with their mouth to the barn.
- No, mouth to arse resuscitation.
- Yeah, it was mouth to bone resuscitation,
which is problematic.
'Cause a lot of people had died of illnesses,
which involve quite a lot of fecal matter being infected.
So quite a few people who tried this,
doctors who tried this ended up dying themselves.
- To be fair, they were supposed to blow, not suck.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah, they did it wrong.
- But then once that doctor's died, presumably,
another doctor will come along and say,
"My god, this patient has died.
I must resuscitate it."
This is an awful chamber reaction.
If you've just stuck tobacco up someone's ass,
then you're going to suck instead of blow
because you've basically made a human cigarette.
- A human cigarette?
- It's going to be the sequel to the human's entity.
- They used to hang those tobacco enema bellows
up by the River Thames, where you would have life
built today or life rings, they would just have as standard.
- Have you guys heard of the Totenhaus?
- No.
- So these were literally that means house of the dead.
Obviously that's their 19th century Germany,
they're very popular.
These were basically large halls,
which are sometimes very lavish and are nearly decorated,
in which bodies were kept for several days
to ensure that they were really dead.
I think this is a pretty grim job.
If you were an attendant at this hall,
you had possibly had 12 hour shifts,
waiting for any signs of life,
terrifying, horrible job.
- But quite easy actually.
- So what's a call?
- Not a lot of times at which anyone actually wakes up,
I guess.
- Yeah, but if you missed that one time then, yeah.
- If you fell asleep at like one, five minute window.
- When that zombie apocalypse happened,
they all came and I'm like,
Jeff, what were you doing?
You were supposed to be watching them.
- It just woke up as an empty hall and you're like,
oh, shit.
- Yeah, the Paris Marg actually,
was around the turn of the 20th century,
it was arguably the most popular tourist destination
in Paris and that's at a time when
the Eiffel Tower was built as well.
They were getting up to 40,000 visitors in a single day.
- Did you start with mentalist items as well?
They were in some weird tourist attractions.
- Last week I was in Portugal and anyone who follows me
on Twitter will know this already,
but I went to a bone chapel.
It was in Evora, which is the town in the middle of Portugal.
And it was made by the monks and they took all of the bodies
out of the town and then sort of put them on the walls
in like some kind of weird...
- Tiling.
- Yeah, it's like tiling, yeah.
- Wow.
- So it decorates the whole chapel.
- The best thing about it was I took a photo of it
and put it on Facebook and Facebook recognized the skulls
and tried to make me tag with them as my friends,
because they were people.
- That's crazy.
- So they've just got real skeletons?
- Yeah, real skeletons, yeah.
- Hanging up.
- And they have actual dead bodies as well,
but when we were there, the dead bodies
would be taken down for restoration.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- But it was supposed to be a place where you would go
when you would think about your mortality and whatever.
- So you know a memento moris?
- No.
- Well, there are kind of things that remind us
that you're going to die, basically,
and that all this is temporary and all flesh is dust
and all of this stuff.
So it's just something to remind you.
So in lots of many of the Renaissance pictures,
there's a skull there, just to point out you're gonna die.
(laughing)
- Just like watching countdown.
- Oh, can you hear that?
- The memento mori and countdown could be the big clock.
- Oh, that's crazy.
- Dude, dude, dude, dude, dude, dude, dude.
- Dom.
(laughing)
- Oh, basically, as well as a memento mori,
there's also a memento vivare, which is a really nice thing.
It's a reminder that you are alive
and to take pleasure in life.
And you don't really hear much about it.
- So there was a thread of people who worked in morturies
comparing their experiences.
And there was someone who'd had a job in a mortuary
and they got in someone who'd died,
who'd been a hand model.
And he said it was really weird,
'cause he went into the service,
the funeral service that they were having
and they have lots of photographs up all over the place.
And almost all of the photographs
were just of this person's hand.
(laughing)
- So it was a funeral of that character
from the Adam's family.
(laughing)
- That's a thing.
- There was another one where a clown had died
and the person was buried in full clown costume.
The whole family were clowns.
All the friends were clowns
and at the family's request,
the funeral directors had to dress up as clowns as well.
- Didn't the shoes not fit in the coffin?
- They put him in the coffin
and all the sides fell out of it.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, and the final fact is my fact this week
and it is that Henry VIII had two official cradle rockers
who were paid three pounds a year each to rock his cradle.
I should stress, this is when he was a baby.
- I had a great image in my head before you told me that.
- Three pounds a year would have been a lot
in those days, presumably.
- It would have been more, but not a huge amount.
- And also my question is, did they go in shifts
or did they need two people to rock one cradle?
- Well, his cradle was massive.
It was five feet long and two feet wide
and this is the rocking one as well.
This isn't just a crib for a baby.
This is an actual rocking cradle.
Suspended from a wooden canvas
covered with crimson cloth of gold
and trimmed with ermine and it was ridiculous.
- Nice, it was Henry VIII, he went in.
- Well, not at the time, it was just a small baby at the time.
- His daughter, was it married the first time,
even she had four cradle rockers?
- Four.
- Yeah, and she had two cribs as well.
She had an everyday cradle, which was silver and gold,
I think, and then a cradle of estate
for special occasions for receiving visitors.
- The current queen has 733 cradle rockers.
(laughing)
Just goes up every time because they want to outdo
to take this one.
- Ever the sixth was given a baby replicate of a court
when he was not yet one year old, he had a chamberlain,
a vice chamberlain, a steward, a cofferer,
lots of other stuff.
- They were, they weren't other babies.
(laughing)
- That's a fantastic idea.
- Brilliant.
- Yeah, that's the most adorable thing I can think of.
(laughing)
They're all dressed as what is a little Thomas Kramma baby
and there's a Walsby baby.
- That's how I imagine.
- Little CBB's is wrong.
(laughing)
- No, so when Henry VIII's first son was born,
he Henry appointed him 40 staff immediately,
including a baker and a keeper of the cellar for some reason.
- It would be brilliant if they were babies as well,
wasn't it?
- I just love this idea of just community of babies
looking up to you like a tiny bit.
- Yeah, maybe a miniature bocky and palace.
- This is the Muppet Babies of the Tudor Court, I don't like it.
- They didn't call themselves Tudor, did they?
Didn't like that.
- No, what is that?
- It reminded them of their Welsh background Tudor
and they didn't like that.
Henry VIII referred to himself as the embodiment
of the union of the families of Lancaster in York,
rather than Tudor.
- Tudor snappier, isn't it?
- It is snappier.
It was like 100, 200, 200 years afterwards
when it became more common.
- Moving down the line, Queen Victoria.
Well, she sounds like she had a phobia of babies.
She described them as rather disgusting.
She described her own babies as frog-like
and frightful, went undressed.
And she had nine.
- I know, I know, I know, I know.
- Yes, you know.
- She's got a punishment.
- Yeah.
- She, when she was a baby,
her father described her as plump as a partridge
and more a pocket hercules and a pocket venus.
I think she was quite a fat baby.
- Hercules supposedly killed two snakes in his crib.
- Oh yeah.
- What did he do?
- I heard some vengeful goddess release them
towards them, didn't he?
And he smashed them together.
- Is that where the rattle was invented?
- Yes.
- He killed the snake.
- So they were rattle snakes.
- And then he turned around and used them as rattle.
- And someone was like,
if I take out the snake aspect of this,
it would make a great toy.
- But Queen Victoria, named Victoria,
very controversial.
Victoria wasn't really a name in Britain at the time.
Was it?
Not a girl's name.
And she was named after a mother who was German.
Got a lot of politicians and men at court
tried to make her change her name
when she was going to exceed to the throne.
- What too?
- Some more conventional.
So I think Elizabeth was suggested originally.
- When the queen gave birth to Prince Charles,
Prince Philip was playing squash at the time.
- That was easy.
- Yep.
- Did he leave the game?
- No, the queen was a name of the 30 hours.
But he played squash.
- That's a lot of game of squash.
- He must have been tired at the end of that.
- He is.
- Someone was taking care of it.
- Well he just comes together.
I'm exhausted.
What a day it's been.
How was your day?
- Do you know swaddling?
- Yeah.
- Which is where you just restrict babies very tightly
in their movements for the first few months of their life.
It's incredible that this happened
and that we still happens around the world, I think.
- Yeah.
- Does it simulate woman environment, is that right?
- I don't know.
And this used to happen.
Babies who were in their swaddling clothes
would sometimes be hung up from a nail on the wall
which was to give their carrots,
so you'd just sort of loop a bit of the swaddling
over a nail on the wall.
And the baby would just be entertained by its surroundings.
This is according to the Victoria and Albert Museum.
To give their carrots a rest
and to entertain them with the surrounding environment.
- Like a boy.
- It's a really funny idea, like a wall mounted baby.
- It'd be good if you had like sex tubulets
and they were just hanging up around the hole.
- Yeah, or you could put them like plaster ducks,
you could put them going up in a diagonal line.
(laughing)
- It was phased out.
I think it was widely perceived as being bad
for the baby's health.
- Obviously.
- Cradles and cots.
The first, in fact, actually I was looking into cradles
and cots on my side accidentally looking into prams,
but the first pram was invented in 1733
and it was made to be pulled along.
So it was like a small pram and it had a harness.
So it could be pulled along by a goat or a dog.
(laughing)
- That's adorable.
I imagine the mini Henry VIII baby
being pulled along by a dog.
- A dog and the goats who are best friends.
- Oh, god.
- It just needs film lines to tell.
(laughing)
- Pram is short for prambulator.
- Yeah.
- But there was no one walking, I guess.
- That's true.
- It was being pulled by an animal.
- Well, the dog and the goat would have been walking to it.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Walking into our hearts.
(laughing)
- Jesus.
- They called the first prams,
that when prams started becoming popular
in the mid 19th century,
I think they were called male carts
'cause they were based on design for male carts
when you just push like big packages along.
- And 'cause female babies weren't loud in them.
(laughing)
- I read that.
There's one book I've read this in and I can't find it verified,
but children's cots were initially used to be bassinets,
which would just sit on the floor.
And then they were raised off the floor due to a perception
that there were noxious fumes that existed below knee level
and explosive vapors that existed near the ceiling
and that the middle air of a room was the healthy air you had to breathe.
- Technically, isn't that true?
Because oxygen is flowerable,
so we need a top and calm dioxide is.
- It's the gas in the room just moves around too much
to use infection.
- Yeah, I know.
- If it was a very still room.
- We're onto the right idea
and we're killing our babies by leaving them on the floor.
It's very unusual putting babies in cradles,
having them sleeping cradles and cots and stuff
in most parts of the world.
It's really weird that we do that.
- So.
- Yeah, like vast majority of countries,
I think it's pretty much unheard of and babies just sleep
with their parents.
- Parents used to not really worry about washing their babies too much either.
- Oh yeah.
- Mothers in medieval times would dry nappies rather than wash them
and in the book I was reading about this,
a history of childhood.
This was because of the healing powers of urine.
- Right.
- And in bits of France,
people thought that if you washed a child's head,
you would make it simple-minded.
And if you cut its nails and hair before it was a year and a day old,
it would be respectively mute and a thief.
- Being mute is good if you're a thief because you make less noise.
- It's a really good point.
- Okay, here's a thing.
That's what we might as well make sure it's safe as well.
- Please make sure it's safe.
- Okay, cut its nails then.
(laughing)
- Yeah, extraordinary.
- Can I just do one thing about an unusual job that I read today?
Okay, so I was reading a book early on.
It's called Sex on Earth.
- Sex and Earth.
- What is that?
- I think it's a big phrase.
- Sorry.
- They were talking about the way that horses have sex
specifically in stud.
So they have, a stallion will come in and have sex with a female horse.
And they were explaining how this happens.
And there is a guy who's one and only job is to hold the base
of the stallion's penis while it is in the mare's vagina.
And his job is to feel for the tell-tale throbbing of ejaculation
so that he knows when it's finished.
- Oh my goodness.
- Why does he need to know that?
- It's so they can stop the act.
- But surely it stops anyway in nature.
- That much of a hurry that we need to write the usual bits over.
- I was going to say it's a brilliant book.
It's by Jules Howard.
It's absolutely real.
- But that's presumably why in nature,
you see a lot of skeletons of horses which have just died
because they didn't know when to stop having sex.
- Imagine how the stallion feels during all that.
In Paris, I presume.
- I don't know.
- I would if a horse turned up.
- That's it.
- Hold it in the face, you can hear this in his face.
- Did you just say I'm a stallion in bed?
- No, I said there's a stallion in bed.
- Okay, that's all of our facts.
Thank you very much indeed for listening.
We hope you have enjoyed it and we will, of course,
be back next week with another podcast.
Until then, you can follow us on Twitter.
We are @QiPodcast and you can also follow us
all individually on Twitter.
James is on @Xshaped.
Alex is on @AlexBellUnderschool.
I'm on @AndrewHunterM and for Anna.
- You can email podcast@Qi.com.
- But also #GetAnnerOnTwitter.
Thank you very much indeed for listening.
We hope you've enjoyed it and we have had a lot of fun.
So see you next week.
Bye.
(upbeat music)
We'll get together to show what we can do
And you hold on to me
And I'll hold on to you
(upbeat music)
We'll get together to show what we can do
And we'll get together to show what we can do