(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of "No such thing as a fish,"
which we recorded at the Underbelly Theatre
in London's Soho.
It was the first try at our brand new touring show,
but we did a full podcast in the middle of that show.
If you would like to see all of the other bits and bobs
that we will do on tour,
then you'll have to go and get tickets,
and you can get those at nosagethingsafish.com/live.
At this place, you can also learn
about our upcoming trip to Gothenburg.
We will be playing the Gothenburg Book Festival
on the 27th of September.
That will be a simple podcast recording,
but if you want to see all the other bells and whistles,
including quizzes and special guests,
and Andy probably talking nonsense
about a very obscure subject,
then you will have to come to one of our other shows
in Bristol, Dublin, Glasgow, Newcastle, Cardiff, London,
or Manchester.
Again, details for all of these shows
are at nosagethingsafish.com/live.
We'll also do some shows in Australia and New Zealand,
but they are, frankly, almost all sold out.
If you beg, borrow, and steal,
you might be able to find one or two tickets
in Perth and Christchurch.
I think there might be one or two
in our second additional show in Sydney,
but if you are living down under,
then really you should try and get those tickets
as soon as possible,
because they are virtually sold out.
While I'm here, it would be remiss of me not to remind you
that we've all written lots of books.
Anna and I have written a book called A Load of Old Balls.
Dan has got a book called The Theory of Everything Else,
as well as a kids book called Impossible Things,
and he has written novels, The Last Day, The Century,
A Beginner's Guide to Breaking and Entering
is his latest one.
If you're looking for something to read
over the remaining part of summer,
or indeed as the nights begin to draw in,
then please do consider getting our books,
because it makes us, and indeed our publishers,
very happy when you do so.
Anyway, enough of trying to sell you stuff.
The podcast is free, and of course, we'll always be free.
And so please do enjoy this free podcast,
recorded live at the Underbelly Theatre in Soho.
Okay, on with the podcast.
- There we go.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast,
this week coming to you live
from the Underbelly Boulevard in Soho.
(audience cheering)
- My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray, and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go,
starting with fact number one, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that Chinese students
in the 1700s could rent underwear with test answers on it
to smuggle into exam halls.
- Wow.
Do you say rent?
(audience laughing)
- If there are rental shops that are doing this,
surely the schools would be aware
that that was a thing, right?
- I think people were aware,
but the cheaters kept on getting smarter and smarter.
That's the thing about cheaters.
They can always outwit the boring law abiders.
This is in the civil service exams,
very famous Chinese civil service exams,
by far the oldest meritocratic system in the world,
going since the seventh century.
This exam is extremely hard to pass,
but if you did pass it,
you could be in the Chinese civil service.
It was very prestigious.
The exam's basically unchanged for 1500 years,
and throughout the period that existed
from the seventh century to the start of the 20th century,
there are these amazing stories of how people cheated.
- I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
If it's unchanged for 1500 years, I think I could pass.
(audience laughing)
- Oh yeah, Randy.
We're looking at a picture of a shirt.
(audience laughing)
I would like to see you memorize that,
even if it was in English.
It's unbelievably tiny characters on this vest, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- It is, and this is one of the cheating garments.
So these things were called cribbing garments.
And yeah, so there's evidence in the 1700s
of underwear made of paper with essays written on it.
Or, it's--
- Well, that says to me that what you can do
is just sort of remove one sheet at a time and hand it in.
(audience laughing)
- Surely you'd have to be rummaging around
in your undergarments to get the answers that you need,
'cause what you'd need is to learn a lot of Confucius.
That's basically what the exam is, isn't it?
You have to memorize 400,000 characters.
- Lots of learning by rote.
Michael Gove would have loved it.
- Yeah.
(audience laughing)
- It's just bizarre for all in the system.
They were so rigorous about catching cheaters.
They stripped, actually, they did everything,
but they then put you in an enclosed cubicle
for a few days to do the exam.
And in that enclosed cubicle,
you suddenly were about your underwear,
or the things you could actually rent
were little scripts that you were meant to sew
into your underwear or into your underclothes
with the test answers on them,
but it was absolutely tiny, the writing.
I think there was one which contained
722 finished compositions,
which was 520,000 characters,
and it was just in the underlining of the shirt.
- It's because basically it was a question.
You knew what the question was gonna be,
and you knew what the answer was,
but the test was, can you remember the answer?
- Right.
- And it's really long.
- Oh, it's a pure repetition.
- Pretty much, yeah.
- It's not right.
- And those, and that tiny, tiny writing
is what they use today to make the labels
with the washing instructions that go into your--
- It's not so.
- That's true.
- Is it?
- So they locked you away for three days?
- They did, yeah, yeah.
- Did you do the exam?
- Yeah, and you were very much locked.
- Could you take food and drink it?
- Yes, you bought your own little packed lunch, is?
- Well, I would write on a sausage my answers.
You know?
- Yeah, if the evidence after, right?
They can find it.
- Why are you bringing such an enormously long sausage
into the exam, Andy?
Well, thanks for asking.
And the room where you were, at least one of them,
this is the examination hall in Jiangnan,
you had your little room,
and there was lots of different rooms,
and then there was sort of an outer corridor,
and then it was surrounded by walls full of thorns
so that no one could come in and give you the answers.
- Wow.
- That is clever.
- And yeah, people kept outwitting it.
- Yeah?
- No one's ever gone to such great lengths to stop cheats,
and it just made the cheats better and better.
They used the dig tunnels underneath,
and then deliver notes to the students.
- Really?
- You must have had to be so precise
to get the exact cubicle that the student was in.
There's tens of thousands of people.
You just pop up in a stranger's cubicle.
- He's taking a shit while you're throwing up.
- I've actually written the answers on this shit.
(laughter)
- Well, it sounds like it hasn't changed, though, right?
Because modern China, I think it's still the case
that every year around 9.1 million high school students
are doing exams to go into university,
and it's a nightmare getting them to the exams.
Like, that's one of the biggest things
because everyone's really on edge.
You've got to get them from home there.
So, like, on days where the exams are happening,
there'll be very specific traffic lanes
that are purely for students taking exams.
Yeah, the families can drive them in.
So, it's like, yeah, exam day, this is the lane.
Express lane, purely for students.
- That's cool.
- Yeah.
- So, Dan, you grew up in Hong Kong, partly.
I know you weren't probably there with the edge
that you would have been taking these exams,
and you weren't trying to get into the Chinese civil service.
- You didn't know that?
- I mean, you're here now,
so things weren't pretty badly wrong.
(laughing)
- At last.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- That is deep cover.
- Did you ever get the advice from your parents
of if you do badly, your mother will die
in a pauper's grave?
Did they ever say that to you?
- Well, my mum and dad are here.
Did you ever say that to me?
- No, apparently not, yeah.
- And where has that come from, that advice?
- Apparently, as they're saying,
sometimes that Chinese high schoolers
with especially straight parents get told.
- Wow.
Do you wanna hear some of the questions
from modern day Chinese civil service exams?
- Yeah. - Wow.
- Actually, these are to get into
the next level of schooling.
- Okay.
- I like university kind of thing.
The containers for milk are always square boxes.
Containers for mineral water are always round bottles.
Round wine bottles are usually placed in square boxes.
Write a composition on the subtle philosophy
of round and square.
(laughing)
- Um, no, I do know this one.
Is that a modern, that's the one one?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Oh, I did that one.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Here's one.
It flies upward and a voice asks if it is tired.
It says no.
That's it.
- I'd say it.
Oh, I'd say it's, I'd say it's, I'd say it's.
- A toddler in a helicopter.
(laughing)
- You must be tired.
We've been out all day.
I'm not tired, I'm not tired.
- Do you know the answer?
- No.
- Why not?
- It's not a question.
- No, it's a prompt rather than a question, let's say.
- Oh, okay.
- Another one, comment on the civilized behavior in Beijing.
(laughing)
- Don't, Andy, don't.
- No, okay.
- For what object you have a passion deep in the soul?
You could choose a plant, an animal, or a utensil.
- Oh, it's a great question.
- I see, I think I see what's happened here.
- And it's problematic.
Basically, the one big criticism
of the civil service exams historically
was that they were too pro-former
and they were all about learning by rote,
didn't encourage creative thinking.
And I think what they've done is they've swung
way too far the other way.
(laughing)
- Ah, there was a good cheating scandal.
Well, there were a few great ones recently actually.
This was a niche one that I didn't know about.
This was in Montana in 2014.
And it was about 90 young officers in the military.
They were caught in a cheating scandal
where they'd been texting each other all the answers
for their questions.
They had to do a monthly test.
Unfortunately, they were the officers
in charge of nuclear missile launch
at the Malmström Air Force Base
and they had just been cheating all the way through.
And 'cause they'd been really worried,
they thought they had to get 100%
when actually it's only a 90% pass mark.
So, yeah.
- Wait, and they ended up in charge of--
- Nuclear launch.
- Right.
At that point, did they think
we may have prioritized the wrong thing here?
- They were all taken off their work.
And that's why no nukes were launched in 2014.
- Well, thank God.
- Thank God, yeah.
- Did you guys ever cheat?
Were you cheaters?
- No. - No.
- Goodness no.
- Come on, you're just more dishonest cheaters than I am.
- No, I would have shopped a cheater if I'd seen one,
but I was too busy focusing on my own work.
(audience laughs)
- I actually cheated for this episode.
- Did you?
- I sure did, yeah.
I asked ChatGPT for an interesting fact about cheating.
- Did you?
- Yeah, sure did.
I said, "Please make it surprising, unusual and quirky."
They said the headline, "Pigeons as Messengers."
In the early 2000s, some students in China
trained pigeons to carry crib sheets.
The pigeons were released from home
with the arms as tight as their legs
and flew to the students during exams.
It was hard to detect until the authorities
caught onto the flocks of pigeons
loitering around the exam halls.
(audience laughs)
Now, I have to say, I have tried to fact check this
and I can't find the evidence.
(audience laughs)
But I trust the robots as I think we all should.
- So why, when you can't find a source for my facts,
do you not trust it?
(audience laughs)
- The future is not in your hands, Dan.
Thank God, so.
- Have you guys seen the cheating hats that you can get?
So it's not, you can't actually buy them in retail shops,
but they happen in school classes
where teachers are a bit concerned
and they make peripheral blockers.
So you wear big elephant ears on the side of this hat.
So that if you try and look that way,
they're sort of sitting there, blocking you in.
- I would write the answers on the wings.
- Oh, yes.
Very nice, yeah.
- But I read an article about that
and it said that actually students quite like it.
They kind of feel like they're less stressed
because like normally they're thinking,
"Oh, people are thinking I'm going to be cheating,"
but it kind of takes it completely out of the equation.
- How the horse loves his blinkers, in a way.
- Oh, to see?
- I don't know, actually.
I mean, I don't know if horses like blinkers.
- There's another really good way of stopping people.
This is five and six year olds,
but it stops them from cheating, right?
You get them all in a room doing their exam.
They're in lines and you walk in with a magic wand
and you say, "I'm magicing a barrier between you
"so you can't read each other's answers,"
and that is enough to stop them from even trying.
- Really?
- They're faking it.
- You're right, that's great.
Now there's been a recent study in they found
that cheating went down by 20%
by people who did the magic wand tactic.
- Oh my.
- The Slytherin.
You could sort them right there in there.
(laughing)
- So in the 15th century, there was an exam
with one question that was so hard,
only two men in the entire country got it right.
- Oh wow.
- It was Tang Yin and his friend, Zhu Jing.
- They were both friends and they got it right.
And so obviously everyone thought,
just as Andy thought, "How interesting."
And so they were arrested,
accused of bribing officials,
and they all the way said that they didn't do it,
but Zhu spent his entire rest of his life
waiting for a pardon which never came.
He didn't get his job.
And it was so bad that all of his descendants
also refused to take the exam.
- Wait, they refused to take it?
Or they were refused?
- They refused to take it.
They were like, "No, we don't believe in this anymore."
And his great-great-grandson who's called Zhu Ziaky.
So that's, think about how long that is later.
He decided he wasn't gonna take this exam
because his great-great-grandfather
had been accused of cheating.
And he became China's most influential travel writer
of whatever century was the 18th century.
Because he would have gone, he was a genius.
He would have gone into the civil service
because he didn't wanna take the exam.
He did this instead.
- That's exactly why I didn't take it
when I was given the chance.
I had more to give.
(all laughing)
- When are you gonna start giving it down?
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number two, and that is Andy.
My fact is that in 2004, musician Jack White
released a single through the medium of a couch.
- Ooh.
- So Jack White, he was an upholsterer as a young man.
And one of his first bands actually was with another guy
who was an upholsterer.
They were a two piece band.
- Oh, that's cool.
- And they were upholstering by day and playing by night
and they had a great, then the band name was, any guesses?
- I was like, "Swayed is much better."
- They were called the upholsterers.
(all laughing)
- Okay.
- It's so clever, it's so simple, it's clever.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But he is better known as being in the White Stripes.
- Sorry, yes, White Stripes, and numerous other--
- Not to Andy.
(all laughing)
- The Who?
- No, I lost it.
- No, no, no, no, fuck.
(all laughing)
- So, they were in Detroit in 2004.
I think he just set up the White Stripes with Meg White,
but they had this little band and they were working
in an upholstery shop and they smuggled 100 singles
on vinyl into sofas in the shop that they were working in
and armchairs and only two have ever been found so far.
- Yeah.
- So, how's that?
- So, is it worth us ripping up our sofas?
- Yes, it is.
Go home tonight.
- 'Cause you don't know, yeah.
- And get busy.
And you won't be, even if you've got an x-ray machine,
you won't be able to x-ray it 'cause they did it
on transparent clear vinyl with transparency covers.
So, you cannot see it.
You can only know by destroying the sofa.
- They did this as a secret,
but we released a vinyl didn't we?
Years ago with Altenpop, this amazing record label.
And we also sold two copies.
(all laughing)
But they had this amazing idea for one of their bands
where they released the album,
but the only way you could buy the album
was to get it on the USB stick that they provided.
But the USB stick only came connected
to a very expensive bicycle.
So, you had to buy the bicycle in order to do it.
So, to buy the bicycle, that equates it
to something like 1,000 record sales
because it was a really good bike.
And so, the band technically sold,
in terms of building back their royalties, 1,000 copies.
So, that is ways that bands do that now.
- Wait, so did they just sell one?
- Just one.
- One sucker bought the bike.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- Things in sofas?
- Sure.
- Things in sofas.
- If anyone is a phobic of snakes,
might want to pop out for a bit.
(audience laughing)
This was something that happened quite recently.
North Ayrshire, in Scotland,
staff were cleaning a sofa at a second-hand shop
and a python fell out of it.
- Oh.
- Dead?
- Dead.
- Okay.
- So, that's fine.
So, it was a second-hand shop and they were cleaning it.
- Not fine for the python.
But, get this, the people who donated the sofa
confirmed that they had never had a pet snake
and that they had got it second-hand themselves.
So, it had been the whole time they had owned it.
It had probably been in there.
- Right.
- Did they not decompose pythons?
- No.
- Is there something special about that?
(audience laughing)
And that's why when you walk the streets of London,
you'd ankle deep in dead pythons.
- Yeah.
- They'd just stick around, yeah.
- Amazing.
- I know.
And the spokesman for the second-hand place said,
"Don't let this discourage you from buying re-use
from others.
This is a very, very rare downside."
(audience laughing)
- There was a study in, well, there were two studies in 2016
and one of them found that the typical Brit
finds £3.27 a year in their sofa,
which is exciting.
That was in March.
And then, in October, there was another study
showing that the average Brit finds £5.77 in their sofa.
What's happened between--
- Well, obviously, the first study
has brought it to everyone's attention
and everyone's gone, "Oh, I'm going to look at myself
in that one." - Oh, yeah.
- The average has gone way up.
- What year was this?
Was this recently?
- 2016.
- I feel like it's going down.
- It must have changed since then.
- Yeah, yeah.
- These days, you'll find half a Bitcoin down there.
(audience laughing)
- I read the study from 2017 that said 52% of people
had lost money down the side of their sofa
and only 46% said they found any money down their sofa.
- So there's money to be found?
- No, unfortunately, 6% of people said
they found money down someone else's sofa.
(audience laughing)
- Hey, I read a crazy thing about sofas.
This blew my mind today.
If you go and you off to buy a sofa
and you want to get a leather sofa
and you see in the shop, it says genuine leather,
you go, "Ah, that's going to be a great sofa," right?
- Right.
- It's a cheat.
It's a cheat.
- What?
- It's okay.
There are five kinds of leather sofas
that you can get in terms of quality
and the fourth worst is genuine leather
because they just call it genuine leather.
That's its name.
- Is it not leather?
- No, it can be up to the discretion of the maker.
It could be anything between one and 100% leather.
They could put 2% leather in there
and they market it as genuine leather
'cause that's what you call that style.
- Oh my God.
- Who do we write to?
- We are about to get sued by DFS.
- Really?
What are the other things called?
What's the genuine leather?
Okay, full grain leather is number one.
Top grain leather is number two,
which again, a bit confusing.
Split grain leather, number three.
Genuine leather comes in at number four
and then bonded leather,
which is basically just whatever the fuck
they want to put together.
- What's the 1% leather?
That's not good, yeah.
- Yeah, so just next time you're in a shop
and you see genuine leather, it's not.
- Good Lord.
- That's really good.
You should do consumer programs.
- Oh yeah.
- I see that in your stars.
Last year, police found something
down the back of a sofa in Florida
and it was a suspected drug dealer named Stacy.
And she was caught between the folds of a sofa.
- Oh my God.
- She was in there, the arrest photo is phenomenally good.
It's so good.
She's just emerging.
- But that is the most,
it's one of the most insanely awesome disguises
you'll ever see.
I know we've mentioned this a bunch of times before,
but like people who were trying to get across
from one side of Germany to the other
during the Berlin Wall, they would go in cars
and they would be the passenger seat.
So they would be inside, sitting within the leather.
Back in the day when they were taking Victorian photos
and kids because of the exposure time,
you'd have to take a photo, take one and a half minutes.
Parents would dress up as the sofa
and hold the kids on their legs
so that the kid would stay there for the minute and a half.
It took to do it.
Like we've got a whole history of dressing up
as sofas to do it, advance our species.
- Do you say advance?
- Yeah.
- Advance our species.
- Oh, advance, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I actually wanna, I've got to be in my bonnet about that
since you've raised it, which you have.
- J.D. Vance.
I was told, 'cause I'm not on social media
and so I don't pick up on sort of the news.
When I pick up on the real news, it's not on social media
but not the crap news that the rest of you read.
And you guys told me he had sex with a sofa.
- J.D. Vance, for future lists of the podcast is...
- What's the president?
(audience laughing)
- But who'd have thought that first lady,
the enormous sofa that came to the White House with a...
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, Travis surrounding me.
Someone just made it up on Twitter,
the idea that he'd had sex with a sofa.
- I see it's fake.
- It's completely fake.
- It's pure fake, it's pure fake.
It could have been one of your facts then.
There's not a grain of truth in it.
No, it is, it's not fake.
It's really not, yeah, it's genuinely nonsense.
- And now people feel they need to be referencing it.
What's happened to American debate?
Walt said, running mate of...
- Oh, he used to be the leader of the resistance, yes.
(audience laughing)
- I can't wait to debate this guy.
That is, if he's willing to get off the couch and show up.
I mean...
- Yeah, it was a bit weird.
- It's all gone a bit weird, hasn't it?
- Here's the thing, to get a bit political,
which is the most English way of saying
that item of furniture, sofa, couch, or seti?
- What's the most English way of saying it?
- Yeah.
- Okay, so couch is, I think, from French Couché.
So that's not a... - Good, very good.
- Okay, so what's left, couch and seti?
- Sofa, seti. - Sorry, sofa and seti.
- Sofa, did I read that one from Arabic?
- Very good.
- I shouldn't ask these questions to people
who've just spent a day researching sofas,
should I really?
- I think, yes, I think it's on the sofa in Arabic.
- Yeah, but I actually don't know what seti is from, so...
- It's from the old English setam,
meaning to sit down, like, to set something down.
- So that's properly old English?
- So if you want to speak proper old English,
I think there are different, like,
sofas have different arms and stuff like that these days.
Do you know what, in France,
they call one of those sofas
that has just one arm at the back of it,
and you kind of lie on it.
- I think that is a chaise longue.
- No, they call it a meridienne in France, a chaise longue.
If they're talking about a chaise longue,
they're referring to a deque chair.
- Isn't that interesting? - Isn't it really?
- Yeah.
- French for deque chair is chaise longue.
- A genuine murmur of shock and dismay went through the roof of that.
That's really interesting.
- What is a deque chair, if not a chaise longue
with all the cushions ripped off and put outside, I suppose?
- Exactly.
- Yeah, you just see where they're coming from.
- I'm very one of those Chinese civil service exams,
with musings like that.
Do you want to hear some sofa slang?
- Yeah.
- What is a sofa pounder?
- We're not back on chaisee pants, you know.
- No, come on.
Grow up.
- Is it a burger, but the buns look like sofas?
- That's really good.
- Oh, is it when you do, is it that cushion process
where you do the judo chop to make the sofa plump up?
Do you know what I mean?
- Yeah.
- That's a sofa pounder.
No, it's just an observer or a non-participant.
You're just sitting on the sofa.
What is to couch a porker?
- Again, guys.
- Did you have all this before, Anna told you
that JD Vance didn't do this.
- It's wasted research, so I'm just reading it out.
- So couch a porker, something to do with pig farming?
- No.
- Is there something to do with lyes?
- It's to just lie down and have a nap.
- Well, a different kind of lie, actually, but okay.
- And what is couch hockey for one?
(audience laughing)
- That one is rude.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, that one is rude.
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number three, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the mathematician
who developed GPS didn't make it to the job interview
where she'd later developed GPS
because she couldn't work out the directions to get there.
- Ah, 'cause you haven't invented GPS yet.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
This is an amazing woman, so Gladys West.
- Gladys?
- I think it's just, it's spelled with a Y,
but I think it's just Gladys.
So Gladys West, yeah.
- Are you saying the woman who invented GPS
has West in her name?
- Isn't that amazing?
- That's crackers.
- Yeah, yeah, so she's a co-developer
and she is an incredible woman.
She's still alive, she's in her 90s
and she believed for numbers of reasons
that she shouldn't go to this job interview,
which was offered to her, which was with the Navy
in America and she was an African-American.
She thought they're not gonna give me a job.
No women like me are given any kind of job.
There's only four people of color within the company as is.
Why would they give it to me?
I can't actually find it on a map,
so I don't know where I'm going even to get there.
And I just don't do job interviews 'cause I'm that good.
So she didn't go for the job interview,
but then they did end up chasing after her
and giving her the job.
And then many years later, through lots of developments,
she created what was the framework
of what then became GPS.
And so even then, after she invented this
or helped to invent this life-changing thing,
she still never used it
'cause she just preferred road maps.
(laughing)
And I think, is this right?
'Cause this is just from what I read.
But if GPS is like satellites,
it tells you where you are by things about snow satellites,
but they need to know the shape of the Earth.
And the Earth is not just--
- Round.
- There you go, Gladys.
- Oh, well, well, well, well.
- It is a rocky era.
It's not round, that's the whole point.
I mean, we know that it's a spheroid,
it's thicker at the equator,
but also there's lumps and bumps and tidal poles
and all that kind of stuff.
And she worked out the algorithms that account
for all of these little bumps on the Earth.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- And she did amazing things.
Like she was one of the people to determine
the movement of Pluto in relation to Neptune.
Amazing person.
By the way, Neptune was discovered by a couch.
- Well, yeah. - Go on.
- I said, John Couch Adams.
He was a British mathematician and astronomer.
Yeah, and he--
- I only referred him as John Sofa Adams.
- That's from the Arabic, he's John Sati Adams, actually.
- I sort of vaguely knew that GPS was a military thing.
Or like an American Department of Defense
sort of something thing.
But I had no idea.
It was really like, it's properly, it's still run by,
do you know who runs it these days?
- Space Force.
- Oh. - Space Force.
It's been handed over to them.
They're very new and they've got control of GPS now.
- Are they under the auspices of the US still
or has it been globalized?
- Space Force has not been spun out.
It's still, yeah, yeah.
- It's still America. - It's America.
- America. - Oh, the US government.
- Yeah, it's US government.
- The master control station is in Colorado.
And they're really young as well.
The average age of the, I don't know if they're called conductors.
They can't be called conductors.
Like, ding, ding, ding.
Everyone aboard the Space Force.
All aboard.
That's good.
No, but their average age is 23.
It's very heavy response.
- Wow. - That's, I know.
- Oh my God. - No, I can't trust that.
- I know.
- But it's-- - But it was--
- Hang on, like NASA, the Apollo missions,
everyone in mission control were youngins.
They were all late teens. - Were they 23?
- That's true. - Yeah, yeah, they were all,
they were all late teens.
- Give us a cheer if you're older than 23 in the audience.
(audience cheering)
- Nice.
Do we dare ask the following question?
Give us a cheer if you're under 23?
- Yeah. - Well, don't be ashamed.
- We've got an audience of people
who are too old to be in NASA.
I think that's what we've discovered.
- But the aim of it, according to Brad Parkinson,
it was also one of the guys named
the father of GPS.
I mean, all sorts of people are given titles about it,
but he was very important.
The mission was to drop five bombs in the same hole.
- Wow. - Wow, that is--
- Why do you want to drop five bombs in the same hole?
- In case, I think he was in a high-falutin' way
trying to say we need accuracy
in terms of where we're dropping our lethal bombs.
- Oh, I see.
- I don't think there was a particularly dangerous hole
that they needed to subdue.
- We've got to destroy that hole every time we hit it.
It just gets bigger.
(laughing)
- There was a worry, wasn't there,
that UK Trident Missiles used GPS
because GPS is an American military thing.
And if we were to go to war with America,
all they'd have to do is turn off the GPS
and our missiles wouldn't be able to hit anywhere.
- Right.
- But I believe that isn't true
because I was reading about how Trident Missiles
find their way to places.
And this is amazing.
They use stellar sighting.
- What's that mean?
- They look at the stars.
- What?
- Isn't that amazing? - That's incredible.
- Even at daytime, they can lock onto 11 stars.
- I guess it is. - Isn't that insane?
- I've got an app. - That's amazing.
- I've got an app where you can see
where the stars are even in daytime and that.
So, yeah, it's actually less impressive
when you know that they actually know
where they are and it's not through vision.
- Yeah, but you're a person.
This is a piece of rock.
It's a bit of rock, though.
(laughing)
Look, it's Trident, all right?
It's probably gonna be a bit old.
But that's unbelievable.
'Cause you don't want, if you've got your missiles,
you don't want them to rely on this technology,
which could be knocked out by someone else's Space Force.
- Yeah. - Wow.
- Mind you, using 11, why do you need to use so many?
'Cause GPS, we use four.
- Four what? - Four satellites, sorry.
So when we're navigating by GPS,
it means that the receiver in your car,
that's receiving signals from four satellites.
But I spent, I must have wasted four hours
working out why the fourth one exists.
So three of them are to, basically,
you work out how far you are from one satellite.
Then there's like a radius drawn around that
and you could be anywhere on that line.
And then you work out how far you are from a second
and that gives you two possible positions you could be in.
And then you work out how far you are from a third
and that tells you where you are.
- 'Cause that pinpoints you.
- Exactly, that pinpoints you.
And then there's a fourth one.
- Time. - And it's time.
Exactly, it's time.
- The fourth dimension.
We know where the suspect is.
(laughing)
- What about if we got there before it was a hole?
- And that's why GPS so often makes you late.
- So what is it, Anna?
What is it?
- It is time.
Basically, it's the fact that the clock in your Garmin
is shit, whereas the clock in all satellites
is an atomic clock.
They've in fact got four in case the first three cock up.
And so the fourth satellite is sort of acting
like a substitute clock.
- So I'm sure you're right.
I thought I had found out something different,
which is that it's your elevation.
It also is that, that's a complicated thing.
- Okay.
- Because the Earth, it's all spheres.
So actually, I think the other thing is that...
- It's all spheres.
Discuss.
Welcome to the Chinese civil service exams.
(laughing)
- Let me just check my pants.
- I know this, it's on my gusset, I'm sure of it.
- No, no, guys, please.
- That's so confused.
- Yeah.
- Why does GPS get it wrong sometimes then?
There's a whole Wikipedia article,
I saw called "Death by GPS."
- Okay, that is human error.
That is people following GPS when they shouldn't be,
when they can see there's a road in front of them
and the GPS has made an error about the terrain.
But that's more like a mapping error,
as far as I understand it.
- Okay.
- But there is a thing where in the early days of GPS,
you could either have good GPS,
which the American government had,
or you could have crap GPS,
which the rest of the world had,
apart from a few select allies.
And there was, it was called either,
what was it called?
Standard positioning service, crap GPS,
or GPS premium.
(laughing)
- Where you have to be an ally of a map.
- Club GPS, but just $3.99 a month,
(laughing)
will give you loads of extra content,
will give you more suspects to target.
(laughing)
Yeah, but it was because they didn't want hostile nations,
having access to the kind of pinpoint accuracy
that the US government had.
- I'm suddenly picturing me and my wife in a car
taking the wrong turn,
pummeling straight off the edge of a cliff,
and our last words being, should've gone premium.
(laughing)
Can I tell you about a GPS service from 1916?
- Oh yeah, wow.
- It was a Manhattan chauffeur called George Boyden,
and he painted this new technique.
And what it was, there would be a phonograph in your car,
and it would play recordings, say turn left now,
or turn right, or go straight on.
And it would be attached to your wheels.
And after you've got a certain distance,
it would know to play turn left now.
Isn't that clever?
- That's incredible.
- Well, obviously the problem is, if you miss one turning.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- We need to move on to our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week,
is that playing ice hockey can make you talk
in a Canadian accent.
(laughing)
- So, okay, so this is,
you don't even need to be around Canadians,
you just are, you've picked up your--
- You don't need to be a boot them.
(laughing)
- God, that was a crowbar again.
- That's literally the only word,
like we've said this before, we came on stage early,
I can't say any Canadian sounding words.
- I think a boot is the only one anyone can,
and you've hogged it now, so.
- All right, so this is a linguist
at the University of Rochester called Andrew Bray,
and he started out by studying the evolution
of hockey jargon, and then whenever he told anyone
about the project, they kept saying to him,
"Well, why don't you actually look at why American
"hockey players start sounding like fake Canadians?"
And he decided, "Yeah, why not, let's do that.
"Everyone's asking it, I might as well."
And so he's interviewed a lot of people,
interviewed a lot of Americans, a lot of Canadians,
and he found that up until about the age of 14,
if you're American, you don't really sound that Canadian,
but from then on, you really do start sounding
more and more Canadian, and what he reckons is,
you pick up hockey terms, like ice hockey slang,
and you say that in a Canadian way,
because that's what all your peers are saying,
and it kind of seeps into the rest of your vocabulary.
- What a Canadian, I'm thinking, Zamboni.
- Oh, that's interesting, I think that was American,
actually, but there was, let's say, for instance,
a hockey arena is known as a barn,
and a puck is known as a biscuit in Canadian terms.
- Okay, and then the accent sort of follows along
after the words.
- Yeah, you pick up the odd word,
and you say the odd word in that accent,
and then slowly you just start saying
more and more in that accent.
- God, we're so impressionable,
it's embarrassing, isn't it?
- That's not about roles.
You know, Gary Oldman, one of the most famous actors
from Britain, he went over to America,
and he does a lot of movies where he speaks
in an English, sorry, in an American accent.
When he moved back here, he had to have a language coach,
and an accent coach, basically--
- Language coach?
What actor is that?
- That's Canadian.
Authentic.
Wobbeck.
So, yeah, he had to have someone to re-teach him.
- Re-teach him his accent.
- In Canadian English, there are interesting vowel shifts
that they do, and I had never heard of any of this,
but there's a boot, which they don't actually say a boot.
If you listen to them closely, they say the,
okay, I'm gonna try and explain this.
When you say the about, ow, is too sound, right?
It's ah, and then ooh.
- Ow.
- About.
That's it, slow down.
- Right.
- What's that all about, and then ooh, right?
- Yeah.
- All right, Professor Higgins, move us on.
- But in Canada, the diphthong, which is that bit of it,
it starts with an exclusively Canadian sound
that not only can most people not say,
you can't even write it down in the--
- Can you say it?
- Well--
- Can you try?
- Starts with something like air,
and it moves to something like ooh,
but it's not a boat or a boot.
- It's ow.
- Well, exactly.
- Do you know that King Charles
is gonna start talking like Mr. T?
- Mr. T?
- What?
- When?
- Sometime in the future, this was a paper I was reading
about something called the intrusive L,
and it's the fact that people often drop their Ls,
so Mr. T might say, I pity the fool.
- Yeah.
- They kind of hear the L, but he doesn't actually say it.
- I pity the fool.
- There's a few of things like people might say,
cool, cool, cool, cool.
But they don't actually say the L,
they're just saying, ooh, really.
- Oh, right.
- If you say--
- Like, fool fighters, right?
That's, we call them, we call them.
(laughing)
- Yeah, or I'm just, I'm going to the zoo today.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- You know what, it's really interesting about that.
So apparently, according to the paper that I said,
it's basically an unstoppable trend,
and even the British royal family
is eventually going to speak like that.
But the really interesting thing is in Bristol,
they add an L, and they kind of overcompensate,
they over-correct.
They know that people often drop their Ls,
and so they'll add Ls where they shouldn't really be one.
And so there are some people in Bristol,
mostly older people, who might, instead of saying idea,
they'll say ideal, or they might say, instead of piano,
they say piano.
- Piano.
- It's not exactly a full L,
but it's kind of a slight L on it.
- And your logic is that they're trying to,
like there are lots of homeless Ls now,
that have been dropped of other people's speech,
and the good people of Bristol are trying to re-home them.
- Are they going to be the last people
to stand against the disappearing L?
- Well, presumably there'll be some other people
who kind of overcompensate as well.
But this is true, and it's so true in Bristol,
that the city of Bristol was originally called Brixto,
and the people of Bristol started saying Brixto,
and they added the L to Brixto,
and that's how they got the name.
So the name of the entire city comes from this overcompensator
and adding Ls at the end of words.
- Oh my God.
- Isn't that cool?
- Overcompensating for what, though?
- Yeah, all right, it's lovely, Bristol.
- You literally just explained it,
but it's still worth saying.
- It's the thing that I do of adding Rs,
where they don't belong.
- Oh, no, no.
- Americans do.
- But no American says Chicago, which is what I say.
- No, no, no one does.
- But you have an international accent that's sort of--
- I would say some Bristolians might say that.
- Chicago?
- But again, not like that.
Never like that.
- It's a very different musical.
- Yeah, she was right to shoot him, yeah.
- Name me a vowel.
Just name a vowel.
- Oh, I can't think of any now.
- Hi.
- Hi, brilliant, one.
- Yur.
- You, you, I, you, okay.
- E.
- I mean, we know the five.
- O.
- And A.
- A, brilliant.
- Where's the sixth?
- There's a sixth one.
- Y?
- Nope, it's not Y.
- Oh.
- Is it R?
- R.
- Get this, R, technically, is a vowel.
It's the secret sixth vowel.
What's a consonant, right?
You are closing something off in your mouth.
You're using your lips or your teeth or your tongue,
and you are closing something off.
F, or, someone just said, I agree, out of nowhere.
Right, that's what a consonant is,
but a vowel, you're an open tube.
Your mouth is an open tube.
- Okay.
- And you are, you're changing the shape of the tube,
but it's like, A, E, I, O, U.
They're all, the tube is open,
and R is the same.
- Right.
What's the really cool Spanish one where they say,
(speaking foreign language)
- That thing.
- We are wandering dangerously close.
- Well, no, I can't do it,
and it's so exciting every time I hit it.
- What is, what is it?
- You mean where they kind of lisp the lips?
- Yeah, like, mythically.
- There was a theory that that was,
that people were trying to copy a king, wasn't it?
- Really?
- One of the kings supposedly had a lisp.
- Every time I hear it, I just think that's such talent.
- I think, I feel like that was a while ago,
but speaking of people talking in an offensive manner,
(audience laughing)
and speaking of fake accents,
in the 1800s, late 1800s, early 1900s,
wealthier people used to throw poverty parties
and call them poverty parties.
And the invitations would say,
you are only allowed to wear rags and sacks
and your worst cloth and will only be served,
I think it was just an excuse not to serve
expensive canapes, it was like,
we will only serve stale bread and water.
And people would come and put on working class accents.
So this was a fashionable thing,
and there were lots of invitations.
And Irish especially, it was in America.
And so an Irish accent was seen to be quite working class,
full of Irish immigrants at the time,
and posh people turned up to parties
and had to speak the whole night in an Irish accent.
- Wow.
- That's a full party of canceled people.
- Yeah, that's amazing.
- Right there.
- That is weird.
- Yeah.
- Garcia, Garcia.
- You've been letting him.
(audience laughing)
- Your invoice in the post, Dan, you're already in.
- Do you know somewhere where you can be killed
for doing the wrong accent?
- The dance chair.
(audience laughing)
- This is the ant nest beetle.
And it is a beetle that goes into ants nests
and is able to mimic the ants chemical signatures.
But it's able to do lots of different ones.
And so if you're an ant that lives over here
or one that lives over here,
or maybe another species of ant,
it can change it very, very slightly.
So it gets all the different dialects of ant.
And if it gets it even slightly wrong,
the ants will kill them and eat them.
- Really?
- Oh, that's incredible.
- Even it's just like saying tomato
instead of tomato.
- Tomato.
- So they can't get drunk at all.
- No.
- Accidentally drop a tea and that's it.
Well, that's pretty interesting
because there's a lot of talk
about whether animals have accents or not.
- It's always claimed, right?
- What the definition of an accent is.
And there was a big story that went around about cows
having regional accents a few years ago.
- Ducks as well having regional accents.
- Well, I think that had more truth to it in 2006.
And I think we might have said this
'cause it was reported everywhere.
It was reported that cows moo in regional accents.
And it turns out that was just a big PR thing
from West Country Farmhouse Cheese Makers
- Really?
- To try and sell more cheese.
So, and they quoted this professor, John Wells,
who was a professor of phonetics at UCL,
who kept on saying, "I never said this."
These cheese guys called me and they said,
"Do you think cows moo in regional accents?"
And he said, "I think it's incredibly unlikely."
And they kept on saying, "But is it possible?"
And he said, "Well, birds do exhibit regional variants."
Yep, we'll take that as a yes.
- Oh my God, his career has presumably been ruined.
No one's talking to him.
None of the cows are talking to him
at any of the conferences.
Do you know what the most attractive accent is?
And this is a physiological thing.
- Oh, okay.
- What makes your heart go pitter-patter?
- Well, we've all got opinions.
- Wow.
- A Barcelona.
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, that's, oh.
- I'm feeling warm, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Used to be an attractive accent.
- I think this was a study of European accents,
in particular, done by--
- Most people would say French, right?
- Most people would say French.
And this was an online language tutor called Preply.
They attached heart rate monitors to 1,000 adults
and they played them pre-recorded chat-up lines.
I presume the same in every language.
- Yeah, right.
- And it found that being chatted up
in an Italian accent makes men and women's heart rates
rise by 23%.
- Really?
- 15 beats a minute higher
if you're getting that sweet, sweet Italian telling up.
- That's a lot of beats, actually.
- Come and stay with my mother.
- No.
(audience laughing)
- That's nice.
- So you actually ruined an entire nation for me.
(audience laughing)
- I am.
- I'm gonna need to move a song.
- What?
- Yeah, I'm afraid.
- You're done.
- English is the least sexy, sorry.
- Okay.
(audience laughing)
- Well, come and see my mother.
(audience clapping)
(upbeat music)
- All right, listen, we need to wrap up our show.
Okay, that is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @Shrieberland.
Andy?
- On Twitter, @AndrewHondre.
- James.
- My Twitter is JamesHarkin.
- And Anna, how can they get to us as a group?
- You can go to @NoSuchThing on Twitter
or @NoSuchThingsafish on Instagram
or email podcast at qi.com.
- Yeah, or go to our website,
nosuchthingsafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
There's also links to the secret club, Clubfish.
No one has checked that out yet, do check that out.
And of course, we're gonna be on tour.
We're going around a lot of bits of the earth
and we are gonna have fun dorking out
for our 10th year with Thunder Nerds.
Thank you so much, everyone, for coming here tonight.
We really appreciate it.
That was fun as hell.
We'll see you again.
Goodbye!
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]