(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber
and I am sitting at a very comfortable distance
from Anna Tyshensky, Andrew Hunter Murray
and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in 1877,
all able-bodied men in Nebraska were required by law
to spend up to 12 days killing grasshoppers.
- Wow, wow.
Wait a minute, I'm always looking for the loophole
up to 12 days.
(laughing)
It was, well, they had to spend two days, definitely.
So you can't get out of a weekend.
And then if there was further work needed,
then the government state government could call on you
to spend an extra 10 days.
- So it was up to 12 days
because some people enjoyed it so much,
it started to look psychopathic.
And it's like, all right, we need to cut you off here.
- Oh yeah.
(laughing)
- Or develop something else.
- You can't devote 365 to it.
- How many grasshoppers can there be that everyone,
I mean, I know Nebraska even though
is quite sparsely populated,
but that's a lot of grasshoppers to kill, isn't it?
- Definitely more than one grasshopper per person.
So it was a lot.
This was the Rocky Mountain Locust,
which is a grasshopper.
And it was this massive scourge in the 1870s and the 1860s.
It basically ruined the kind of Great Plains area,
so Kansas, Nebraska, the Dakotas, those kind of areas.
And it destroyed crops, it ruined people's livelihoods.
It drove the population out and they had to do something.
So the states passed various laws saying,
get out and do your duty, murder grasshoppers.
- Wow.
- It's insane, there's a sighting in 1875,
so two years before this law was put into place,
where it was estimated that there was 198,000 square miles
of locusts swarming.
So that's larger than the size of California.
- In that area of 198,000 square miles,
which I reckon is just a little bit smaller
than England and Scotland combined,
there were 12.5 trillion insects.
Okay, and to put that into perspective,
if you imagine taking a normal keyboard
on your computer and covering all of England
and Scotland in keyboards, so there's no gaps,
each grasshopper would have one keyboard to sit on
over the whole of England and Scotland.
- Well, why?
Why are you putting grasshoppers on keyboards?
- Grasshoppers give an infinite keyboard to eventually.
- They actually write out the works of Milton, don't they?
- They account for extraordinary, aren't they?
I mean, even every able-bodied man in Nebraska
wouldn't have been able to do a huge amount about this.
Because they ate the wool off sheep
when they were passing by, they're just so discreet.
They ate clothing off people's backs.
- I don't believe that.
I mean, it's probably true, but like, calm on.
- An unsexy striptease.
- There was a woman who claimed it, wasn't there?
Who said that she was wearing a white
and green stripey dress and she was descended on
by these grasshoppers and they ate all the green stripes,
at which point I guess all the white stripes fall off.
But, you know.
- That's where the white stripes
got the name from, actually.
The band, they were walking past this woman
and were like, what's the rest of her dress?
There were stories about how trains came to a halt
'cause they were skidding on locusts.
- Oh yeah.
- There were just so many on the ground
that they were just, yeah, wiping out.
- Laura Ingalls Wilder, who wrote
"The Little House" on the prairie,
she was there when this happened.
And one of her stories on the banks of Plum Creek,
they talk about this happening to her family.
And she said that her father had to walk 300 miles
to find work on a farm that didn't
have the grasshoppers on it.
- Jesus.
- If you can imagine that.
And that she would walk around
and they would squish under her birth feet
and she would hear the sound of millions of jaws
biting and chewing.
- Oh. - Nice.
- Wow. - Amazing.
- I mean, if you're faced with that,
actually what good can it do to spend 12 days?
12 days feels a bit undirect.
- Yeah, you gotta devote the whole year to it.
- Wait, how many did you say the word, James?
12 trillion. - 12.5 trillion.
- Okay, so then again, if every,
hang on, 12 trillion.
- No, if the whole of Nebraska gets a trillion a day.
- Yes.
Then it just needs one guy.
(laughing)
- If you have a million people in Nebraska say,
they have to get a million each per day.
- They are small though.
- It's a shame that we didn't just,
Nebraska didn't just allow this to just continue.
And there's just one spot on earth where humans are living
just completely covered, naked, covered in locusts.
- What?
- With no food to eat.
- That is a shame.
- We send care packages just as an experiment.
You know how sometimes big experiments happen?
- What are we experimenting on?
- Is there a symbiotic life with locusts
that we're missing out on
that they were trying to introduce us to?
- They actually only eat your clothes off you
so they can become your clothes.
(laughing)
- Well, some people did suggest that at the time
a symbiotic relationship with them kind of.
So Missouri state entomologist who's called Charles Riley,
he just said that why don't we just eat them?
They could be turned into soup
or prepared John the Baptist style.
And John the Baptist style is where you fry
grasshoppers with honey.
Because in Matthew first three chapter four in the Bible,
it says his meat was locusts and wild honey.
John the Baptist when he goes into the desert.
- Not sure it's gonna take off
as the next hit restaurant concept, is it?
- No.
- Wild honey, please.
- Yeah.
- Oh no.
The portions are gonna be massive.
- Have you guys eaten locusts?
- I haven't, but I do know that in Australia,
they rebranded them as sky prawns,
you know, to make them a bit more appealing.
- Very high in protein.
Like the North American communities
who lived in that area around the time.
So for instance, the Shoshone people, they would eat them.
So they would turn them into flour
and they would make bread out of grasshoppers and stuff.
So that's how they dealt with it
before it happened to the Westerners who went over.
Although I don't think they ever had it quite as bad
that we know.
- No, I mean, eating is not a solution to the 12 trillion,
is it?
You can't just wander down your field with your mouth open.
Well, problem solved.
My crop's absolutely fine.
- So the Rocky Mountain locust,
which we're talking about, which led to this plague,
was crazy at the time and we did fight battle with them.
And the battle was won by the humans to the point
that they're now an extinct species.
- Hang on, hang on, hang on.
You're giving us credit for that.
- No, I'm saying long-term, they are no longer on earth.
- How did we win the battle?
- Well, in-
- Why not because of us?
- No, no, no, I'm just saying history.
They're no longer here on our planet.
- Who writes the history books, Anna?
- Okay.
- I'll say it's because of us.
I think you're right, Dan.
- It was largely because of us, but also as animals.
And it was changing agricultural conditions.
- It was, yeah.
- Who changes the agricultural conditions.
- Thank you, James.
- Who brings the animals.
- Mr. Man.
- There we go.
- But we didn't do it on purpose.
- It was an accident.
- Yeah, we absolutely didn't want to do it.
And that's horrible to decimate a species to extinction.
But they can still be found,
despite being extinct in glaciers around there.
There's this one place,
which is called the Grasshopper Glacier.
And it's in Wyoming where all of them
have sort of just been frozen in time inside there.
And you can see them when you look into it
and people ship them out.
- Can they come back like cut in America or?
- There is a theory.
Some scientists think there might be
a few lurking around somewhere.
- Not ready to come back.
Like the glacier melts and suddenly the grasshopper's taken over.
- Not ready to mount the full counter attack,
but there are scientists who think
they might still be out there somewhere.
- Well, I thought, as in not in the glaciers,
but actually out there.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Yeah, because so we don't,
even though we've said like this agriculture
or environment or climate change,
but really we don't know, right?
It's a massive mystery.
And they just vanished.
So it was 1877, it was still pretty bad.
Pretty much by the 1880s, they'd gone.
I think the last spotting was in the like the eight 1901
or something or right at the start
of the 20th century anyway.
And they vanished, but it could just be
that they stopped swarming
because locusts just turned back into grasshoppers
when they go out of a swarm.
And they could just be hiding, as you say in plain sight,
waiting to regroup.
- When you say they turn into grasshoppers,
they don't change, do they?
We just change our name for them.
It's like literally one animal is called a grasshopper.
When it's with all its mates, we call them locusts.
- You're kidding.
- Yeah.
- It's not like Batman and suddenly
it's a whole change of outfit.
- They kind of, they do change outfit.
They definitely do.
- Yeah, they change color in it.
- Because they get stronger, they get darker,
they get more mobile, their color changes.
And in fact, until the 1920s,
they were assumed to be different species.
It's really weird.
There were two versions of this desert locust.
One is in Hulk mode and one is not.
And then we thought they were completely different.
- How quickly do they change though?
- That feels like that should take a while.
It's not as soon as they start swarming,
they just all turn blue.
- Kind of is, it's really weird.
So basically they have wild populations
which swell up after rains because there's lots of food.
So plants are growing so they can eat lots.
But then if the land gets parched,
they get pushed into a smaller and smaller area.
And then this chemical serotonin kicks in
in their brain, which we have to,
which is associated with happiness for us, I think.
But anyway, not for them because the serotonin
basically turns them into Hulk mode.
- We don't know that they're not happy.
- That's true, they can be thrilled.
And they just set off and they go for it.
And it's very rare for them to switch out of swarm mode
once they're in it because any offspring born
during a swarm are also swarmers.
- Yes, okay.
- I actually do know how you can turn them into locusts.
So the way you do that is you tickle them
on the back of the legs.
- Is that right?
- Yeah, and scientists tried this.
They had this theory that what happens is
they are incredibly antisocial.
Like grasshoppers hate each other, usually.
But when they get hungry,
they go to the same bit of food
and they start rubbing up against each other.
And eventually that rubbing stimulates them
to suddenly want to swarm.
- Do they become thigmo-tactic?
- I think they become thigmo-tactic, yeah.
- Favorite word, fish word.
- It's really the fish word.
- Friend of the podcast.
- Thigmo-tactic.
- We should have her on.
- That's really cool.
So that explains the serotonin thing, right?
Because they become like more loving
to their fellow grasshopper.
- Yes.
- Is that right?
- Yeah, or at least want to hang out with them.
Although there's also a theory
that the reason they're swarming is
they all want to eat each other.
So I don't know how much love that is.
- Yeah, I wish they do.
That's when I read that.
If they fall behind in the swarm,
whoever's behind will chew them up.
I mean, that is a terrible.
- That happens in the Tour de France as well, actually.
So one really important thing of this locust swarm
in the 1870s and 1880s is what did the farmers do?
Because basically all of their crops were taken.
They had no way of making any money,
but also they had no food
'cause all the crops had been eaten by locusts.
And so they asked the state for money,
but the state couldn't give them enough
because basically everyone was affected.
And so they went to the federal government
and there was a real discussion about that
because basically they thought
that their farmers might be turned soft
if they gave them any help, any charity, right?
And so they came up with these tests
to make sure that you were worthy enough to get aid.
As a farmer, you had to pledge an oath
that you possessed nothing of value
that could be sold for food or clothing
in order to get any charity at all.
- Sounds like, is this where Jacob Rees-Mogg
started his career?
(laughing)
- But yeah, I mean, in the end though,
eventually the federal government did step in
and kind of gave aid packages
and food packages to everyone.
And that was the start of what is now the typical response
to disasters in America.
It was also a fire in Chicago a bit earlier
that did a similar thing.
But yeah, this was a big step for America
as far as state aid was concerned.
- So they sort of did them a favor?
- Yeah. - A long run.
- Exactly, good old locusts.
- Good old locusts.
Another coping mechanism they had actually
before that came in was in Minnesota,
they had huge vats of boiling water
that they kept in the center
of some of the big cities there.
And there was a bounty of 50 cents a bushel on the locusts
and apparently 130,000 grasshoppers equals one bushel.
So you've got to get quite a lot to get you 50 cents.
And then you bring them to the city
and you chuck them in this vat of boiling water.
- Right. - Isn't that cool?
Like a cauldron?
- Yeah, or just to kill them off?
- Yeah, yeah. - Not to make a soup.
- No. - No.
Otherwise you just got a big locust lolly.
When they've tried that in various places around the world,
what often happens is people just start
breeding the animal, don't they?
- Yes, exactly.
- Poor guys at Jimmy's cricket shop,
which breed crickets, see this cloud on the horizon.
Well, bang goes business.
- Why is he not calling it Jiminy Crickets?
- Absolutely right.
- Yeah, well, it did almost bankrupt the state actually.
They had to cancel it almost straight away.
'Cause everyone's bringing in so many locusts.
- The bushel. - The bushel offer.
- Well, it's the 12 day thing, yeah.
'Cause too many businesses. - Wow.
- Yeah, can't afford it.
- If you guys heard of a megacolon.
- Oh, I thought that was you impersonating one.
- Yeah, exactly. - Yeah.
- It's not a punctuation that I accomplished earlier.
- I think I invulnerably made,
it's like I've been hypnotized to make that noise when I hear.
That's being said.
- Very obscure.
Darren Brown never thought that would come up
in your life again.
- A megacolon is you would--
- Okay, so this thing which I was talking about,
it's what happens if you get an infection in your colon.
And there was a mummy from 1,000 years ago
which had this infection.
And it was scanned with an electron microscope
and what they found is that for the last few months
of his life, he'd been fed solely on grasshoppers.
So that's all he'd eaten.
And what they'd done is we could tell from the microscope
that they'd taken all the legs off the grasshoppers
and just, and the heads and just got the bodies
which is really high in protein
and just kind of squished them together
and given them to this guy.
And this, as far as we can tell,
is the earliest example of any kind of nursing
or hospice care in the human race
that we have direct evidence for.
- Wow.
- But he had to prove that he'd sold off
anything he had of value before.
That's awesome.
- A megacolon.
- Mm.
- Oh, gosh.
- Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that when Henriette Dongeville
held a reception to celebrate being the first woman
to climb Mont Blanc, one guest was Maria Paradis
who had been to the top of the mountain 30 years earlier.
Riddle me that.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- She didn't climb it.
She swam up 'cause it was underwater.
- Oh, yeah, really?
- Oh, yeah, she was dropped on.
- She, from a plane had a top.
- First of all, Anna gets half a point
'cause she didn't climb up allegedly.
- Okay.
- But she wasn't dropped by a plane,
so you get minus 10.
- She was pretty hefty.
- She was born there.
She was top of the mountain 30 years earlier.
That's where her mom gave birth to her.
But then her mother would also have had to be there
and so would have then been the first woman at the top.
- Yeah, except she was dropped from a plane.
(laughing)
What year was this, James?
- So this was 1838 when Dongeville went up,
but Maria Parody went up in 1808.
And what happened was she was dragged up, we think.
- Kicking and screaming.
- Well, not really doing anything
'cause she kind of passed out halfway up the mountain.
- Wow.
- Is that a really fun drunk and night out prank kind of thing?
- Yeah.
- We'll have her wake up at the top of Mont Blanc.
- You'd usually carry someone rather than drag.
That's very caveman, isn't it?
- Yeah, it was.
So basically what happened was in 1808,
a few people had already gone at Mont Blanc
and they kind of talked this 18 year old servant
from Chamonix called Maria Parody to go up Mont Blanc.
And they said, if you do this, you'll become kind of famous
and you'll be able to make a load of money
and maybe it will help the hotel that you're working in.
It'll give them some publicity.
And so she's like, yeah, fine.
I mean, what's the worst that can happen?
We know about what happened
because she spoke to Alexander Dumas in 1811
and she told him that as she was almost to the top,
she felt her legs go to hell, she said.
And then the people who were going up with her
decided to take her each under one arm
and drag her to the top.
She was pulled, dragged and carried
to the top of the mountain, okay?
And then 30 years later,
this high society woman called Henriette Dongeville
decided that she wanted to be the first person
to really walk up Mont Blanc and she did that.
And then she invited this Maria Parody
to come to her party afterwards.
And there's a little bit of kind of classism
because first of all, Marie Parody was like,
I can't believe that a real lady
managed to get all the way up to a mountain.
I'm a peasant woman, I know the country,
I should be able to do it.
I can't believe you would.
But then Henriette was kind of dismissive of her
and she's like, well, at least I went up
by my own accord and stuff.
- She almost didn't get up on her own accord, did she?
She had exactly the same moment.
Yeah, Henriette, she had the same
where she suddenly buckled and she was on her back
and there were questions from the rest of the camp,
do we carry her up?
And she managed fortunately to sort of get her wits about her
and she said, no, I can do this, I can do this.
But yeah, almost carried up as well.
- The person who went up with her
was called Joseph Coutet or Coutet.
And when she kind of got near the top
and she felt like falling asleep, she felt really woozy,
Coutet said, look at her, asleep again.
This is the last lady I take up Mont Blanc.
(laughing)
Although that does sound like a euphemism
when I read it, doesn't it?
- Oh, I took her up Mont Blanc.
- Oh, what if this whole fact is a euphemism?
It's a really raunchy night.
- Oh my God.
It wasn't quite raunchy because Henriette Dongeville,
when she climbed up, she was wearing a boa.
She was wearing a--
- Constrictor or feather?
- Feather or fur, possibly.
But because obviously climbing gear for women
did not exist at the time
because only mad aristocratic ladies who were starting it,
she was wearing a petticoat over men's trousers
and then a bonnet with a veil and then a boa.
The whole thing weighed about six kilos.
So it was really heavy to be climbing out.
- She basically had to wear the men's clothes
because obviously that's the convenient way to get to the top
but she still felt like she had to wear
the women's stuff over the top.
- Yeah, and there is this amazing picture of her
going over a crevasse with a ladder,
which I actually didn't realize was the thing
that you did in climbing and it looks absolutely terrifying
when she's doing it because it's this massive drop
in the middle of it.
The ladder's just going between these two cliff edges
and she's there with these extremely heavy skirts
which she would have sort of scrambling over
which she would have thought
is gonna tip you over any minute.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And one of the reasons that she went up supposedly
is that she was quite jealous of other well-known women
that were kind of talking about going up Mont Blanc.
So the writer, Georges Sond, who you all know, I'm sure,
who's kind of mostly famous for wearing men's clothes
but she was kind of a really famous writer
who at the time was bigger than Victor Hugo
and Bolzac and people like that.
But she was kind of doing a lot of walking
in the foothills of Mont Blanc
and she was talking about how she might soon go up
and Henriette Doncheville decided no,
she was gonna do it first.
- That's great.
- It was not a prank.
That's what I would do if I was trying to trick someone
into going up Mont Blanc.
- Oh, I might go tomorrow morning.
I know the weather looks a bit dodgy, but yeah.
- The clothing, I mean, it is mad
that women were made to wear dresses
and there were sort of, you know, there were a few women
who were supposedly threatened with legal cases
for the fact that they were wearing men's trousers.
It was so controversial at the time
and there were systems where they did try to cheat it.
So I read about Aubrey Leblond who climbed Rotorne,
which is a mountain about 2,000 meters high.
And so there was a sort of compromise
which is that you would leave where you were staying.
Let's say you're staying in a hotel wearing the dress
or the skirt that you had with the trousers on
and then you would take it off
while you were doing the actual mountain climbing
and maybe no one would tell each other.
But so she made it to the top
and then on the way down,
realized she'd left her skirt up there.
So had to backtrack, go back up,
re-ascend this giant mountain together.
- So she had to carry her skirt to the top after drop.
She didn't just leave it in a bush or something
where she took it off.
She carried it that way up with her.
- You would leave it somewhere safe,
like if you're going swimming or whatever.
- Yeah, you don't swim holding your clothes
up above the water if you do.
- My sister once was climbing up a hill
in the lake district and then went to the top.
And when she got to the bottom,
she realized she'd left her phone at the top.
And that's how all the way back up,
then it looked good to get her phone down.
- Hey, have you all heard of Annie Smith Peck?
Annie Smith Peck is a mountaineer.
She climbed the Matterhorn in 1850.
And it's just so interesting
'cause she had to do it with total hatred
from all the male companions who were taking on again
'cause they just didn't want women doing it.
She wore trousers, they hated that scandalous.
So when she went up,
one thing that happened was they would constantly,
like the guys were just always having temper tantrums,
there would be strikes.
But at one point,
'cause they kind of just wanted to get rid of her
as part of the party,
they said that, well, it said that
when she was going across a crevasse field,
when she went out of view, they cut the rope,
the support rope.
- No, I was looking after her.
- Went back to camp and then she had to make her way back
and found them all sitting there.
And they were like, "Oh, you're still here."
- No, did that actually happen?
- That's according to the accounts, yeah.
And I think her accounts, that's what happened.
I mean, she was really impressive.
She once hung a votes for women sign
off the peak of a mountain in Peru, just to make a point.
- Who's gonna see that?
- I mean, good point.
- No one after her companions cut the ropes from the sign.
- You wanna do it in the middle of Trafalgar Square
or somewhere where people walk past all the day?
- That's a really good point.
Yep, can't fault you on that.
And then another time,
she climbed another mountain in Peru,
the North Peak of Huascaran, okay?
With some Swiss guides.
And it was renamed in her honor.
It was renamed Cumbre Ana Peck.
But at that point, the record,
I think the highest altitude,
maybe for a woman or maybe for that peak,
but it was held by another lady mountaineer
called Fanny Workman.
- Oh yeah, legend.
- Well, another legend,
but there was beef between them
because Workman was so annoyed
that Peck was claiming this record
that she paid for engineers
to go and recalculate the altitude of the mountain
and establish that she had actually climbed 600 meters
less than she had claimed to, than Peck had claimed.
- 600 meters, that's a big recalculation.
- It is a pretty big recalculation.
So the Workman would still have the record.
- That's pretty, yeah.
- So just while you're saying Annie Smith Peck
having something named after her,
the Matterhorn, not long after she went up that,
there was another explorer
who had a bit of it named after her.
So this was a mountaineer called Felicite Carol.
And she unfortunately didn't make it to the summit
when she was going.
She was with her father
and it's because she was wearing a skirt
and the skirt ballooned in the wind
and they thought this is too dangerous.
You can't go any higher.
Your skirt's gonna get in the way.
So the spot where that happened
is named the Matterhorn's Coal of Felicite.
And yeah, after her,
but she never got to make it to the top as a result.
- 'Cause it could have blown her up there
like Mary Brown in Office, that's true.
- Did you bring an umbrella as well?
- Have you heard of the book Mountaineering in Scotland?
- No.
- This is by an author called W.H. Murray,
William Hutchison Murray.
- Any relation?
- No, not as far as I know.
I wish because this is an amazing sounding book.
It was written on sheets of toilet paper
in prisoner of war camps in Germany during the war.
So Murray had been sent by his mother,
the complete works of Shakespeare in the post.
And that was an earlier time of the war
when the Red Cross parcels were still getting through
and you could receive post and things like that.
- It's a lot of postage that, isn't it?
- It's a lot of postage, yeah.
But he noticed that the paper was lovely and soft
and it was actually a lot better than the stuff
that they were being given as toilet paper.
- So it sounds like he used the complete works
of Shakespeare as loo roll and he saved his loo roll
and wrote his own book about Mountaineering
on the loo paper.
- Oh my God.
- I know, but the worst thing was then he was moved,
he wrote for a year, presumably getting along quite well
with his first draft.
- What kind of, what was he writing with?
Do we know?
- No, I don't know actually.
I don't know how he got a pencil.
Or a pencil, yeah.
- Was it 2B or not 2B?
- Oh my God.
Oh my God.
- He walked straight into that one.
- But then he was moved.
He was moved to another camp called Offlag 8F
and it was a much stricter prison camp.
I mean, I don't know how lenient the previous one was,
but basically the Gestapo searched everyone
very carefully on the way in
and his stash of toilet paper with a book on it
was found and taken off him.
And he had to write an entire second draft
on more toilet paper.
- No.
- Yeah.
- Oh my God.
- I know.
He claimed that the Gestapo had done him a favor
because his first draft was a bit flabby,
he needs a bit of time.
- Yeah.
- The most generous prisoner of war you've ever,
I actually kind of liked the Gestapo.
- Do you think that when he only had the toilet paper left
that he kind of would hold it in so that he didn't use it?
By the end, he would have had a mega-coal on it, I reckon.
- Oh my God.
(laughs)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is Andy.
- The fact is that the queen in her garden
has a collection of fake rocks.
- She has a lot of gardens.
- Do we have a specific one?
She has gardens at Buckingham Palace, though, specifically.
- How's this in the main garden?
- Her main garden, I would say.
There is a fake rock called Pullermite
and she's got a lot of it.
- Is it, sorry, is that specific rock called,
did she name it Pullermite?
Like, cause she's got Dave sitting next to it,
it's a real rock.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Yeah, this is a kind of rock invented by,
it's so weird that you can invent a rock.
There was a gardener called James Pullum
and he invented this rock and it became a craze.
Can you explain to us how you invent a rock?
- Yeah, so he was a gardener
and he noticed that there was a bit of a trend going on
for when people have been traveling
and they might bring plants back with them
and this relates to the Victorian fern craze as well.
This was a big craze for having ferns and collecting ferns.
So the problem is that ferns don't like growing on lawns.
You know, most gardens at the time
were, you know, nice flat lawns of grass.
And he was a gardener and also he knew a bit about engineering
and he started offering people their own personal ravines
to put their alpine plants and ferns in
and he made this material from his own recipe
and he took the recipe to his grave.
And so he started offering people their own personal rocks
that you could shape and build and mold
into the exactly shapes that you wanted.
And this became a craze, people,
lots and lots of gardens had these fake rocks in.
- It's environmentally friendly
'cause you don't have to go and dig it out of a mountain
or something.
- Yeah, I guess so.
It takes a lot less transportation, yeah.
- And it was 'cause it does sound like a thing
that would be shunted by the rich as something, you know,
we just want natural stuff.
But as you say, you know, the queen has it
in Buckingham Palace, many famous family, the Rothschilds
and so on, we're all really keen on it.
So this was, yeah, it was a big deal.
- It was a big deal.
- It's everywhere.
I no longer trust any rocks I see.
What if this is puller made?
- There's a big list online, isn't there?
Of all the places you can find it, including Las Vegas.
- Really?
- Yeah, the Bellagio, there's like,
I think there's a fountain that's made out of it.
- Wow.
- Well, the first time that we properly,
I think outside of a show, saw each other
during the sort of first lockdown having ended
was we were at St. James's Park,
weren't we, we were sitting there
and the rocks by the Duck Island Cottage
are also those kind of rocks.
- Are they?
- Right next to it.
- Exactly, no rock is safe from puller.
It's really insane.
Even seaside towns like Folkestone, Ramsgate,
they went nuts for it.
They actually, I think quite badly damaged
the council finances by spending all their money
on pullermite because they wanted extra rocks
for the sea to make it more rocky.
- Oh, why?
- This isn't rocky enough.
- That just makes swimming in the sea
more and more unpleasant.
- I think it's not inside the sea.
So for example, Folkestone got paths and tunnels
to get people down from the cliffs.
They wanted a gorgeous natural way to show people down.
And so next time you see a rock, check.
- Yeah, check.
- So how can you check?
Can you give it a knock in its hollow?
It's not right, it's a rock.
- Most of the rocks you see day to day will be rocks.
- Oh, sure, absolutely.
Yeah, but that's just law of averages.
But do take a photo and send them to Andy.
Anytime you see a rock, I'll go through that.
I'll tell you, if your rock is--
- They're a bit lighter, aren't they?
They're lighter than normal rocks.
And they'll just look faker.
- They'll look a little bit like
when you're queuing at a theme park, you know,
the rockeries that you have.
Not quite as plastic as that.
- Not as plastic.
- No, it's more realistic version of that.
You're right.
- They were incredibly successful, weren't they?
James Pullham.
He set up this company, which is James Pullham and Son.
And it was a company that just went on and on.
So when he retired, he handed it over to his son, James Pullham.
And then when he retired,
he handed it over to his son, James Pullham.
- I think it was the second James Pullham
who invented Pullhamite, wasn't it?
As opposed to the first one.
- I think you're right.
- I think.
- So, okay, minus one of the James Pullhams
from that list there.
- He was helped by two of the other
James Pullhams later in life,
but also helped by another brother
called Michelangelo Pullham.
What a name.
- He's not living up to that name, it's a fake rock.
- Everyone else in the family's called James
and he's called Michelangelo.
- But it's two names, isn't it?
He's Michelangelo Pullham.
They've divided Michelangelo in two.
He's, you know, to the untrained eye,
he's Michel Pullham, real name Angelo.
- But he did all of the designing, didn't he, as well?
Yeah, so if you ever needed a rock,
but it needs to be in a certain shape,
you gave it to Michelangelo Pullham
and he did the shaping for it.
- That's brilliant.
- If you ever want a cherub to be emerging from your rock.
- We should give a shout out to the book about this
by Claude Hitching.
- Ah, Claude Hitching.
What a man.
- He is the man on Pullamite.
So he's written a book called The Pullam Legacy
and I mean, he has spent, I think, decades
tracking down bits of Pullamite
because we still don't know where it all is.
That's why I'm saying you've got to check.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's all over the country, but there weren't, you know,
accurate records kept everywhere this company worked.
- I mean, it's not as urgent as like landmines and stuff, is it?
Nothing's gonna happen if we don't find it.
- When he started looking into it,
he discovered that five of his direct ancestors
all had worked for the Pullam company at some point.
- Oh, wow, really?
- And so he had a personal connection, yeah.
And so basically he has, as Andy says,
spent so long trying to track down
where bits of missing Pullamite have gone.
Sort of historically important bits in the Pullamite world.
Where have they gone?
Where Pullamite fans are like, "Oh, I can't believe we lost this."
And some of them have turned up in places like,
he found there was the Q Fountain,
which was made for the International Exhibition in 1862.
- Really?
- It had disappeared.
And where is it now?
That's where James said earlier, Las Vegas.
It found its way there.
- Oh, that's the one at the Bellagio?
- Exactly.
- Wow.
- That was a famous one in the UK.
Pullamite fans distressed that they couldn't find it anymore.
It disappeared.
- That's incredible.
- One amazing Pullam legacy.
One of the biggest projects of James Pullam number three
is the Landscape Garden at Friar Park.
Which is, yeah, and you don't know about this.
It's near Henley, and you'll see why Dunn knows about this.
It's maintained by a woman called Olivia Harrison,
who is George Harrison's widow.
And they bought it, but it sounds incredible.
So originally it was sort of designed by its owner,
who's called Frank Crisp,
this really eccentric guy who basically,
why are you looking at me so?
- It's a funny name.
- It's just a nice name.
- He's a Frank Crisp.
- Crisp by name.
- Crisp by nature.
- He was a crispy eccentric man who designed his garden
to look like an Alpine landscape, basically.
So full of these fake rocks that he got done by Pullam.
- And sorry, just with the Alpine thing,
he actually had a model of the Matterhorn made.
- Yes. - Out of rocks.
- Not actual size.
- Not actual size, different scale, yeah.
But yeah, the Matterhorn is there.
- That's incredible.
- Yeah, amazing.
So it takes up like lots of acres,
that Matterhorn is pretty big,
and that's not Pullam, that was someone else.
But basically it got really overgrown.
I think some nuns moved into it for a while,
and it got dilapidated.
And then George Harrison bought it
and said, "I'm gonna take this over."
And they cleared it, and they found all this stuff.
Like the Matterhorn was just sort of sticking out
of a bunch of rubble.
They barely even knew it was there.
And it sounds like he had this incredible moment, George.
There's some sort of fake lakes built there.
And at one point, he lowered himself on a rope
into this cavern that was below this lake.
So I guess this lake's on a, yeah,
there's like a cave below this lake.
- Sorry, the Cavern Club?
Or yeah, what?
- What?
- The Cavern Club where the Beatles played in Liverpool.
- I should know that.
- Even I know that.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Actual Beatles hater.
- Maybe that's what drew him to it.
That's how he knew.
'Cause he lowered himself into this cavern
and underneath was this whole grotto.
So like pulomite grotto with these sparkling kind of courts
and stuff on the walls.
This like crazy magical landscape.
- Wow.
- And yeah, and now you can kind of row through it
and look at all these diamonds glistening
on the walls and stuff.
And yeah, it sounds incredible.
- They do keep discovering these places.
So even recently in 2000,
there was a couple who moved into a house,
Dewstow house it was called.
And they started to notice all these weird rocks
sticking out of the ground.
- Okay.
- And they then started digging.
And they discovered this huge labyrinthine underground
environment, this massive rock garden,
magical caverns, water flowing from one to another,
tunnel systems, fountains, fake stalactites.
The whole thing was this enormous mad pulomite project
which a man called Henry Oakley had commissioned.
He was a railway director and he spent years
having this incredible environment built for himself
which just got buried.
It got buried under the M4 as it were
because there were all these mounds of earth
that were excavated to build the M4
and they just got dumped on top of it.
- Okay.
- And the owners started to notice
and they started excavating it.
And then a few years after that it won the award.
Alan Titchmarsh did a series on Britain's best back gardens
and it came in at number eight.
- Oh, what a renaissance.
- Yeah.
- That little bit of land.
- Number eight.
- Yeah, number eight, yeah, not the top seven.
- Not top five, yeah.
- Imagine how exciting it is.
I honestly think that all our listeners
should go home now and dig up their entire gardens
in case there's a pulomite grotto under them.
- Yes, that's a good idea.
- You know, pulomite obviously wasn't the first fake rock
and the sort of the only successful fake rock
in the first of the 1700s was code stone.
So this was the 1770s, it was basically invented
and it was the fake rock to have.
And there were lots of startups,
lots of fake rock startups that tried to make their own.
Nothing came anywhere close to code stone.
And it was this business that was run for 50 years
by this amazing woman, Eleanor Code,
who just decided, I think it was 1771,
she met this guy who made some fake stone
and she bought up this massive factory
and said, okay, start making it.
And she fired him almost immediately
'cause decided he wasn't good enough
and brought on someone better at making fake rock.
And she was amazing business woman.
So 50 years, she made this stone,
which if you've seen the lion on the South Bank,
that big lion, that's made of code stone.
And that is hollow, so you can tell by knocking on it.
And if you look inside code stone,
which usually you can't 'cause it's like a statue,
if you drill inside, you can see the fingerprints
of the people who pushed it
into the plaster molds on the inside.
- Oh, that is cool.
- Code sounds awesome, Eleanor Code,
'cause she worked with her mom for decades,
also called Eleanor Code,
and there's a lot of confusion about which code was which.
- Yeah, and have you heard about her grandma?
- No, Eleanor Code.
- Her grandma, I actually don't know
first name of her grandma.
- Is there a thing about having,
being a person who makes rocks
and having no imagination for names?
(all laughing)
- And it's very much kept in the family, the rock thing.
Yeah, Eleanor Code's grandmother
obviously had the business mindset as well.
She ran a textile business in Tiviton,
and she sent spies to Norwich,
which was very good on textiles,
who would then steal all of their tricks,
then come back and be successful.
And she did things like she got carried around Tiviton
in a sedan chair all the time.
(all laughing)
She was a good character.
- Wow. - She sounds awesome.
- Yeah. - Have you guys heard
of gunite? - No, gunite.
- It's another fake rock.
Can you guess how you make gunite?
- Fire it from a gun?
- Correct.
- Oh, no. - Yes.
- You get a gun, it's not like a small gun,
it's like a big sort of hosepipe gun,
and you fire out this dry sort of concretey material,
and then you have a little bit of water
at the nozzle of the gun,
which kind of goes into the concrete as it comes out,
and then you can fire it wherever you want to put a rock.
- So cool. - It's almost like
a 3D printer for rocks.
- And it's used on bridges, isn't it?
If you ever see a bridge, really, or a tunnel,
then it's probably gunite or shotcrete.
It also gets called the dry and wet versions.
- Shotcrete gets used in taxidermy, I think.
- Yeah, does it? - Yeah.
- It's because it's quite easy to shape.
- Yeah, exactly, and so is it, God, I've forgotten,
is it you're shaping and then you're putting the scale
on top of it?
- Well, what you can do with concrete
is you can make the shape of something out of iron,
and you can fire the concrete onto it,
and it'll, yeah, like a mold, and it'll go on that.
- Yeah. - That kind of thing.
- You don't have to make a mold for it,
you can't fire it, 'cause what's it landing on?
You can't just fire it into mid-air,
and it's like a spark plug. - Of course, of course, of course.
- That makes sense, that's awesome.
- Ugly rocks are sort of venerated in China.
I didn't really know about this thing, scholars rocks,
but you'd recognize them, and since the eighth century,
Confucians have, Confucian academics have basically said,
ugly, jagged rocks are great for contemplation,
and the idea is that they represent Confucianism,
they're uncompromising.
So from the eighth century, there's been a trend
for getting the ugliest rock you can find,
or the most jagged, or pitted, or misshapen,
putting it in your garden, and watching it.
(both laughing)
- That's really awesome. - To see what happens.
- Wow, I know Anna, I think I know this about you,
'cause I know it about me,
you used to collect rocks when you were a kid, right?
- Yeah, of that I found in my gravel, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, did you like look for the ugly ones,
or for the attractive ones?
- I was very shallow, I wasn't a philosopher,
I just went for the fit ones, yeah.
Something pink and sparkly.
- Wow, are there competitions?
- There actually should be, what they are.
- Ugly rock of the year.
- There must be, 'cause they're judged
on certain qualities, so it must be,
for the sake of something, there are four categories,
and these were determined by a guy called Mifu
in the 12th century, who used to,
- He was in charge of the Mifu movement.
(both laughing)
- Yeah, he was a great campaigner for his day,
and he used to bow to rocks, so when he met royalty,
he'd walk in and bow to the rock instead of the emperor,
and people got annoyed.
- Instead of the emperor?
- Yeah.
- Probably absolutely had to his own life.
- Maybe he was just short-sighted, we don't know.
- I met the queen a couple of years ago,
but I only really talked to the Pelomite rocks
in the fucking palace.
(both laughing)
- Anyway, they're judged, just to finish that,
they are judged on their thinness, their openness,
their holes, and their wrinkles.
You want to max out on all of that?
- Can't we all?
- Yes.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that following a theory
that they wouldn't burn up on re-entry,
Japanese scientists once planned to fly paper airplanes
from the International Space Station back onto Earth.
- Okay. - Very cool.
- Now, why does that mean therefore you'd do it?
'Cause I understand that maybe you wouldn't burn up
because you're not going that fast, but even so,
is it instead of something?
- Well, I guess we are always trying to work out
different ways of doing space travel,
constantly seeing who knows how important space paper.
- Lightweight vehicles for re-entry
would be immensely useful to have.
So if you can start--
- You're not gonna sit on that paper aeroplane, are you?
- Well, no, but you might sit inside a big paper aeroplane,
which are all treated card or something,
or there are chemical compounds--
- Oh, so is that what I was testing?
- They were, I mean, that's what they said
the justification was, was lighter vehicles for re-entry.
- You don't need a reason for science, Hannah.
You can do science for science's sake.
- Good point. - All right.
- It discovers its own discoveries.
Is that what that's what scientists say, isn't it?
- Yeah, that's the line, that's the official line in Latin.
- So how come they never did these happen?
- Well, it's a really hard thing to do.
It was a really nice idea.
So this was in 2008 and there were researchers
at the University of Tokyo who teamed up
with Japan's Origami Airplane Association.
So this was gonna be origami paper planes
that were put together and put through.
And so they did all these tests in wind tunnels
at the University and they managed to show
that this plane could actually hold its own
at huge speeds of wind passing through it.
So it all looked like it could possibly work.
The problem is, is that if they did try it
and it came back into the earth,
it's so tiny without any GPS device on it,
we would just know nothing.
It would be impossible to tell in 2008.
- I think another problem is,
I would say at least two thirds of the paper aeroplanes
that I ever make either kind of go straight up
and stall and land where I threw them
or go straight down and crash into the ground.
So you need to train your astronauts
to be proper paper aeroplane makers, don't you?
- That's true.
- And they've already got a lot on their plates.
- They've got a lot of training today.
- Well, origami is useful in space in other ways, isn't it?
So I guess I can see where they're coming from.
I think it's been used by Japan on solar panels.
And in fact, by NASA more recently,
they certainly had a plan to, and they use mirror folds.
And I think, is that how you pronounce it?
We've done it on QI.
- Mirror folds are basically how you fold maps, for instance,
you know, when they fold up really small and flat
and then you can spring them out with
so that they're really big.
- It's almost like an accordion.
Like you, they're in a really small little square
and then you pull them out and then you push them back in
and pull them out and push them back in.
And then like a normal map,
you're always trying to find the folds and stuff.
But these just kind of go back where they should do.
- That's really cool.
- 'Cause it'd be so annoying if an accordion
was like a normal map where every time you pushed it in,
you had to fold it and it's up the right way.
- What do you think is the world record
for folding 1,000 origami cranes?
- 1,000.
(laughing)
- Damn it.
What time, how long do you think it took the person?
So do you remember I did this a few years ago?
- Yes.
- It took me about two months.
- Okay.
- Yeah, you did it in the office as well
'cause you're hiding it from your,
it was a present for your wife.
And yeah, so.
- I wasn't hiding it from my wife.
- Yeah, it was a present for her.
So you were building it.
- I was really embarrassed and I didn't want to tell her.
No, it was a gift.
But yeah, how long do you reckon it takes to do 1,000?
- Eight hours.
- Eight hours, that's a bit less than one a minute.
- But this is gonna be the record, right?
So this is someone who's, I'm gonna say,
I'm gonna go as low as like two hours.
- What?
- Just for this?
- 1,000.
- Yeah, just because like.
- But how many seconds are there in an hour?
- It's not gonna take a second to do a crane.
Surely a minute to do a crane, a bit less maybe.
- I think it'll take a couple of minutes.
I don't know, I think a couple of days.
- Couple of days, thank you, Andy, because these two.
(laughing)
- Sorry, Jay.
- Poor Evelyn Chia of Colchester, England.
(laughing)
- Henceforth known as the slacker.
What did she do then?
- She is a teenager from Colchester
and she did it in nine hours and 31 minutes.
- Well, that's much more impressive
than I would have thought, Dan and Anna.
(laughing)
- I think.
- Two hours.
- How good do they have to be?
I mean, can I just scrunch up lots of bits of paper
and claim their cranes?
- I'll be honest, when I did it towards the end of the 1,000,
they got less and less looking like cranes.
- Did you hide those cranes at the back of the crowd?
- I really do, yeah.
But she did it as a fundraiser for NHS charities.
- Nice.
- And in fact, I gave her some money for it
'cause I was so impressed
'cause it did take me literally two months to do it.
- That's very cool.
- But yeah.
- Oh, that's lovely.
- I was reading the Encyclopedia Britannica article
on origami and the origins of it.
And it's the first unequivocal document
that talks about origami is a poem by Ihara Saikaku,
which was written in 1680, which talks about these butterflies
made from paper.
But this guy, Ihara Saikaku,
he once composed 23,500 verses in a single day.
- Jesus.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- Does it have a chorus?
Is it a cheek?
Half of them are the same.
- I think they're on different subjects.
- Are there even that many subjects?
- I already saw.
And apparently in the 20th century,
origami was helped by the fact that it was used a lot
in Rudolf Steiner's schools,
which Dan, you went to one of those.
- I was a Steiner, yeah, I'm a Steiner kid.
- Did you learn how to make origami?
- Yeah, we did, but we did do Japanese classes.
So I don't know if it was integrated.
We didn't have separate origami.
- Okay, 'cause apparently, according to the article,
they emphasize kind of hands-on learning for kids
as opposed to rote learning.
And so, yeah, origami was very popular,
especially in the German Steiner schools.
- Okay, yeah, I mean, we definitely did origami at school.
- That's very interesting, 'cause I think Germany
kind of brought advanced origami to Japan
via kindergarten. - Really?
- The kindergarten movement obviously started in Germany.
It's a German word.
And this is the 1830s, and this guy, Friedrich Frohbill,
decided that origami would be a great way
of educating children in both maths and art,
'cause it's very mathematical and logical,
and like very difficult spatial reasoning,
but also quite artistic.
And he exported this around the world
with this kindergarten movement,
and it was really taken up in Japan,
where they were already doing quite a lot
of slightly simpler origami,
but then they started making pigs and houses
and sofas and stuff like that.
- Cool, so Germany exported origami to Japan,
is what you're saying?
- I'm saying Japan had a kind of origami,
and then Germany exported a more advanced kind.
- We think probably invented in China origami
because paper was invented in China.
So, yeah, probably the first people to fold paper
were the first people to invent it.
But then went to Japan and became big bear,
then came over, picked up by Germany,
improved, sent back over to Japan again.
- And if there are, for German, Japanese, Chinese listeners,
we are not denigrating any origami
or treatments of any countries, okay?
Please don't write in.
- And if you do, please don't fold it
in such a way that we can't read the letters.
(laughing)
- The person who popularized origami in the West
is a guy called Gershon Legman, and he--
(laughing)
- Was he a breast man or a Legman?
- Well, it's funny you should ask.
He did a bunch of other things.
So, the way he popularized it was,
he found this origami prodigy called Akira Yoshizawa,
and he put on exhibitions of his work and stuff,
and it all spread.
But the other things he tried,
he tried lots of stuff, Gershon Legman.
He collected vulgar limericks,
so he had a massive collection of scene limericks.
- He wrote the book, "The Rationale of a Dirty Joe."
- Yes.
- It's a seminal set of books.
- And it's by someone called Legman.
- Well, it's also called by, what's his first name?
- Gershon.
But he uses G.
So, G spot Legman.
- Wow.
- Sorry, G dot.
- Yeah, so G spot Legman was the name for his--
- That's a stretch, so don't, you don't call it a spot.
You don't say, can you put a spot
at the end of that sentence, please?
- Yeah, that was his little gag.
- Wow.
- Cool.
- This is so weird seeing the interests
of Dan intersect with what we're talking about.
(laughing)
Not dirty jokes, that doesn't mean jokes in general.
- I just know, yeah, these books are like cult classics.
- Yeah.
- He said, "No ideas."
- Well, Andy wrote, yeah, 'cause he wrote stuff
about how to give good oral sex, I think,
like the best oral sex in gratification,
maybe that's where you know from.
- I'm not saying I have that copy,
but yeah, I've definitely got the joke books.
- He invented the vibrating dildo.
- Got that, got that.
(laughing)
- Okay, well, you can have a spin off Gershon Legman podcast,
but yeah, cool guy.
- Wow.
The prodigy you just mentioned, Akira Yoshioaza,
he does sound very interesting.
He pioneered wet folding.
Before that, I'm not sure wet folding was a technique.
- And can you explain what wet folding is?
- Absolutely, wet folding is the main, I'd say,
division in the origami world.
Wet folders dampen the paper
so they can get the curves just right.
Dry folders, I don't need to explain.
Don't do the wetting.
And yeah, so Yoshioaza was the guy who--
- Really?
- He worked as an origami man from 1937 onwards,
I think when he was very young.
- Right.
- Yeah, and he eliminated cutting from the procedure.
So you used to cut the paper, I think,
before you were folding it.
- Okay.
- And that's another, again,
you know, Fosbury Flop moment in the development of origami
where, you know, you're not cutting things
'cause that's like making a snowflake
when you're a kid, you know, you fold it up
and you can't-- - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- That feels like the anti-Fosbury Flop moment.
That's like you've banned the Fosbury Flop
and you're back stuck with a scissor kick again.
(laughing)
I run it because you're not allowed to scissor it.
- It's a reverse Fosbury.
(laughing)
- Another very cool origami figure
was this guy called Robert Lang.
Did you guys read by him?
- How do you say he's an origami figure?
Is that a human in the origami world
or was he made of paper?
- He's not made of paper, he is just into paper.
- Got it.
- And a bit like this guy, Andy, he was a physicist.
He worked at NASA's Jet Propulsion Lab
and then he decided he preferred folding paper
and he was this mass prodigy
who was doing very well in physics
and it was 2001, he finally decided to give it all up
'cause it was taking up so much of his time
folding paper things.
And he's been very useful with his origami.
So for instance, airbags made based
on origami principles now.
And that's because they went to Robert Lang
and they said, look, we really like the way
that you can fold something really small
and then it can expand really big.
Like he was able to do that.
- On that note, in 2013, there was a company
which announced it was inventing an origami condom
for Bill Gates.
- For Bill Gates?
(laughing)
- As he got such an unusually shaped penis,
he has to have a special condom made.
- Bill and Bill Gates Foundation is what I mean.
I was using it on his shorthand and I'm sorry.
I'm sorry, please don't sue.
(laughing)
There was a designer called Danny Resnick
and he had worked out an origami condom
which apparently was much more comfortable to put on,
fit on more easily and it opened up like an accordion.
- I can play the accordion a little bit.
And when you first open it up, it makes quite a weird noise.
- I don't know if it wheezed as it was opened up.
Anyway, it never happened because Resnick himself
was accused of fraud the next year
and had to pay back the public fancy being granted.
So the world is still waiting for the origami condom.
- It would be great if it did play a tune as he wanted it.
- You can't get that little keyboard
onto something that size, I don't think.
- It's good it's gonna sound,
every time you have sex, it's gonna sound like a sea shanty.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Soon will the weather bag come.
(laughing)
- Well, I hope it is soon.
(upbeat music)
Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland, James.
- @JamesHarken.
- Andie.
- @AndrewHunterM.
- And Anna.
- You can email our podcast at qi.com.
- Or you can go to @NoSuchThing or go to our website.
NoSuchThingAsAfish.com.
All of our previous episodes are there.
Do check them out and do look at our upcoming tour dates.
We are back on the road later this year.
Hopefully we can see some of you there.
If not, keep listening,
'cause we will be back next week with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)