(upbeat music)
- Hey everyone, welcome to this week's episode of Fish.
Before we begin, we've just got a bit of announcement,
really exciting announcement.
We are releasing a behind-the-scenes documentary
that was filmed during our 2017 tour of the UK.
And it's us on buses, it's us ironing sharks.
It's us.
- Can I just say, Dad, it's buses.
It's not just like buses that the public go on, is it?
It's not like we're on the 19 bus to Angel.
- Yeah, and actually it's not even plural buses.
It's one bus, which is actually a van.
So it's, I'm just trying to big it up here.
What it is, is if you ever wanted to see what it's like
when we actually go out on the road
and we visit all these places in the UK
and put on these shows, it's a sort of just
little background insight.
It's like a very less, less funny version of spinal tap.
- Yeah, if you wanna know some kind of like
weird twisted secrets from Andy's past
or some weird twisted secrets from James's past
or some perfectly normal innocent secrets from my past,
that they're all in there, there's some interviews,
we were interviewed and there's some of us
just pissing around, really.
- Yeah, this is gonna be available on Monday,
the 29th and January, it's gonna be online exclusively.
That's right, we said no to H&B.
- What about people who aren't online?
- They will live in ignorance.
- This will bring the last of the world onto the internet.
(laughing)
- Yeah, you can get it on iTunes this Monday
and you'll be able to get it from Google Play
on Amazon in the very near future.
It's 1.49 per episode and it's 4.99
for the bundle of four.
- And what's it called?
- This is the highlight, Andy.
(laughing)
This is why we deliberately saved this to a last.
- Yeah.
- Should we all say it together?
- Sure.
- It's called the highlight.
- The highlight. - No such thing as a fit.
Present behind the gills.
- It's called behind the gills, get it, get it now.
- Yeah. - Okay, on with the show.
- Do we have a saying behind the gills clearly enough?
It's called behind the gills.
(upbeat music)
- Hold on, hold on.
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast,
this week coming to you from Dunstable.
(audience cheering)
- My name is Dan Schreiber and I am sitting here
with Anna Chazinski, Andrew Hunter Murray
and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order.
Here we go, starting with you, James Harkin.
- Okay, my fact this week is the King Ferdinand of Bulgaria
was so scared of being murdered on the Oriental Express
that he locked himself in the toilet.
(audience laughing)
- Had he read the book, is that why?
- So amazingly enough, this happened at the turn
of the 20th century, so it happened before the book.
So the book came out, before the book,
which came out in 1934 and before the film,
which came out two weeks ago.
(audience laughing)
- Wow. - Did he lock himself
in the toilet for the whole journey?
- Do we know?
- No, well we know that he definitely didn't do it
for the whole journey because one thing we do know
is that as soon as they got into Bulgaria,
he decided he wanted to drive the train.
(audience laughing)
- And isn't it the case that when he got given the controls,
I know that it's very hard to mess up driving a train
'cause you're on a track, but he would put the speed up
'cause he was a speed freak and it would go exceptionally fast
and they were worried that it was gonna derail
because he was just loving the...
- Yeah, that's true.
- Do we know why he was so...
I mean, were people after his head
or were trains just known for murdering the olden days?
- It's a bit of the first bit actually
because it was just after he'd become king
and he was known as Foxy Ferdinand.
- Oh.
- And he was known as that 'cause he was a bit of a dandy.
Okay, and to start with, he wasn't very popular.
For instance, Queen Victoria said he is totally unfit,
delicate, eccentric and effeminate
and he should be stopped at once.
(audience laughing)
- Wow.
- And in his country, by the end, they loved him,
but to start off with, he was quite unpopular.
- He was, wasn't he?
He was sort of a wimp, I think.
- That's right.
- So his mum seemed to control a lot of his life.
Like, for instance, his mum got him the job as king
and it...
(audience laughing)
- I mean, that is how monarchy works, I think.
- Well, that's not how he worked here, is it?
Because...
- It's not.
She bought him the job.
- So Bulgaria, it was very unpopular
the job as king of Bulgaria at that point.
'Cause I think there was a lot of controversy,
there was a lot of intrigue and corruption in royal circles.
So the job, actually, the throne, as they called it,
was offered to a bunch of other people
before it was offered to him.
So it was offered to the princes of Denmark
to princes from the Caucasus, to the king of Romania.
And they all said, no, I think I'm all right, thanks.
And so eventually, Foxyford announced mum said,
all right, if I give you this amount of money,
will you let my son be king?
- Of this place, and that's how he got there.
It was just so embarrassing.
- King Edward of Britain died in 1910.
And Foxyford was on the way to the funeral.
And he got a massive argument
over where his private railway carriage should go
in the train, because things of precedence,
he thought, well, my carriage should obviously
be right at the front behind the driver.
And he lost to Archduke Franz Ferdinand.
So Archduke Franz Ferdinand got his carriage
to go right behind the driver.
But that meant that Archduke would have to pass
through King Ferdinand's carriage to get to the dining car.
And Ferdinand just locked the door.
(audience laughing)
He just said, no, you're not coming through.
- But things still worked out, okay,
but Franz Ferdinand, didn't they?
So. - I did.
- On the bright side.
It's actually a really nice thing.
- It's too soon, weirdly.
(audience laughing)
- Is it?
- I think when it's over 100 years, you're in the clear.
- Yeah.
- It's weird.
We have talked about him before.
If you've listened to the podcast for a while,
it's quite nice because one of our main podcast facts
about two years ago was that Kaiser Wilhelm
once slapped him on the bottom.
And he was so offended by this that he was gonna give him
an arms contract, but then he gave it away to someone else.
And in that show, we talked about Kaiser Wilhelm a lot.
So now we're kind of coming back.
Like, if you did a series, you'd cover one.
- Yeah, we've seen it from the other angle, aren't we?
- Oh, yeah.
He was very upset about the bottom slapping.
(audience laughing)
- It's like that new episode of 50 Shades of Grey,
isn't it from Grey's side?
- I didn't know that was what it was.
- And with a slapping part?
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- A lot of body slapping in 50 Shades of Grey, I gather.
- I think it's written a bit different
to how you just, he walked in, saw the body.
(audience laughing)
That's getting a slap, he said.
- Heal James, I really regret getting Andrew
on tomorrow to ghost right in the second one.
(audience laughing)
- I read another method of how a Bulgarian,
or in this case, all of Bulgaria, avoided being killed.
And it is, and I've been assured that this is not true,
but I think it's worth saying.
(audience laughing)
And the nice thing is, we've now got that on tape,
so you can stitch that before any fact
downstairs in the future ever.
(audience laughing)
No, but so this is true in Bulgaria,
when a Bulgarian is signaling yes,
when you ask them a question,
they do it with a horizontal,
they shake their head.
They shake their head, as what we would know is no,
they shake as a yes.
And when you ask a question that is a yes answer,
they don't do a full nod, but they do an up,
which is what we would take to be yes, right?
- Is that, sorry, someone just said yes,
and do we have a Bulgarian?
- That is true.
- Yeah, so that, I know that, if we have a Bulgarian,
we won't know whether they are in the audience,
'cause are you a Bulgarian?
(audience laughing)
Well, well, confusingly, apparently,
if you're talking to a Bulgarian,
and they know that you're from some other country,
they then reappropriate it, so they do that, the opposite way.
So it's very confusing, 'cause you don't know
which one is the right answer to it.
This whole thing was about how they stopped being killed.
- Yes, yes.
(audience laughing)
So apparently, this goes back to the Ottoman times,
and this is when Turks used to hold a sword
to the neck of them and to the Bulgarians and ask them,
and it was on an angle to ask them, are you a Christian?
And to say that they were, they had to change it,
because that was the most efficient way
to not slice their neck through movement
of a sword being held tightly, 'cause they said it.
- They could have just said it.
(audience laughing)
- Ah, they could have just said it.
- Yeah, I didn't, that's why I was told it's not true.
Okay.
- But we're saying, right?
- Oh, yeah, absolutely, yeah.
- He was absolutely worth saying.
- Oh, yeah.
- The Orient Express was amazing, though,
even more amazing than that.
It was amazing because so many great people traveled on it.
It was, if you were famous or if you were a world leader,
then you traveled on it.
So King Leopold used it to transport himself
to Constantinople, where he'd arranged,
made some complicated arrangements
with a harem to infiltrate a harem.
So he get involved in that.
The president of France traveled on it at one point.
This is actually in 1920, and in 1920,
what happened was there was a guy working the signal box
and a man-brain per jammer stumbled up to him
in the middle of the night and said,
"Hey, please help me.
I've just fallen off the train.
I've fallen out of the window and off the train.
I'm the president of France."
And the guy in the signal box said,
and I'm Napoleon Bonaparte, according to those accounts,
but it was actually the president of France.
It was Paul Deschanel of France.
He'd fallen out of the window of the Orient Express,
and he had to resign very shortly afterwards,
'cause it was so humiliating.
- No.
- I mean, it was slightly to do that.
It was also slightly to do the fact
that he'd recently received the British ambassador
to France naked, except for the ceremonial decorations
of his office, and that he'd walked out of a state meeting
straight into a lake fully clothed.
(laughing)
- So it was a few of the circumstances going on there
as well as the Orient Express thing.
- It was the straw that broke the camel's back,
and it was-- - It was what he told his wife.
- It was the camel.
- It's when I fell off the train.
That's what I did, it.
- I have some stuff about the luxury trains.
- So did you know that in the early days of rail,
lots of very wealthy people had their own
private train carriages, and you could just pay
and have your train carriage kind of put onto a train.
- Oh, like the Queen has one of those, doesn't she?
- Well, she's got a whole train, in fact.
But for example, there were private carriages,
and there were family carriages,
which you could just get a carriage
for just for you and your family,
and you would attach it to a train and then change it,
and at the start of the 20th century,
Manchester had several gentleman's club carriages,
not in the spearment rhino sense guys.
They would have clubs, you would pay a subscription,
and then you would get to use that railway carriage,
and there were lockers, and you had to be elected,
and you had to obey the rules, specifically the rules
about whether you could open the window or not,
and when it was appropriate.
- Wow.
- And you had to turn up to the station on time, presumably.
- You just had access to the train carriage
if you joined the club, and there was a gentleman's club
on wheels.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Yeah, okay. - Fun.
Something.
- Well, you know, it's nice to give James something to edit,
isn't it?
(laughing)
- I think we're giving him too much to edit at this point.
- You know, the orange express, the first murder
that happened on the orange express
was the year after Agatha Christie published her novel.
- What's it? - Yeah.
- Yeah, and also, do you know how the person was caught?
- No, no, what happened?
- It's a really cool story, so basically,
there was a woman who was pushed out of a window,
so who was killed and then pushed out of a window.
- There's no cool so far, Ernest.
(laughing)
- It's extremely harrowing.
- Sorry.
- I'm so record, too soon.
(laughing)
- Sorry, it was 1935, so it is a bit too soon.
She was pushed out of the window,
and her body was found on the tracks,
and all of her possessions, except for a silver fox scarf,
so a foxkin scarf that she'd been wearing,
and then by total chance, so this got around
that the scarf was missing,
and a policeman in Switzerland,
a few weeks later, spotted a silver fox scarf
being worn by a woman, and then went up to her
and said, "Where's she getting that?"
And she said, "From this guy,"
and it turned out that guy had done the murder.
- Wow.
- Sorry, the murderer gave it to me.
- The murderer.
- Yeah.
- I got it from a guy who called himself Mr. Murderer.
- It's crazy to give away the one bit of evidence
that links you to a crime, to a random person.
- It was pretty stupid, wasn't it?
- It was very stupid.
- Yeah.
- So the surrender at the end of World War I
was signed on the Orritic Express,
but it was signed in a particular carriage,
which in 1940 Hitler ordered to be hauled
to the precise spot where it happened,
and that's where he organized the terms of the French surrender.
- He wasn't absolutely dead.
- He was such a prick.
- And I was saying, hey, you've just beat him front, okay?
A great military power.
You don't need to go on about it.
Even by Hitler's standards, that's pretty petty, isn't it?
- It's so petty.
And do you know what he did next?
When he started losing the war,
he had that drain carriage blown up,
so they couldn't make him surrender in it again.
- Oh, what?
- Hitler, forget the drain carriage.
- Oh man.
- God, the more I hear about this guy.
(audience laughing)
- We need to move on to our second fact, guys.
- I just have one tiny thing.
- Yeah, yeah, go for it.
- This is about the Queen's private train.
She's got the royal train.
And it's actually pretty doubly inside.
It's not really blingy and Louis XIV-ish.
It's pretty cool and calm.
Anyway, there's just one thing that happened in it,
which I really like.
So it travels around the country to pick up the royals
and drop them off and so on.
And once, it was on its way to pick up Prince Charles
for a royal function.
And it stopped very briefly at a station.
But nobody noticed a middle-aged woman
on the platform to see it and get on.
And she just sat at one of the tables in the dining car.
And it is quite well-decorated, not good.
It's not a standard train.
And she just sat there and a member of staff
was walking through and said,
"You do know this is the Queen's train, don't you?"
And she said, "No, I did not know that."
(audience laughing)
"I'm sorry, when do we get to slow?"
And she was given some light refreshments
and then escorted off at the next stop.
Ah, I shouldn't let her stay.
And she's out there somewhere,
but she knows the other side of this story.
Let's move on to our next fact.
Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the new goalie
of the ice hockey team, the Belfast Giants,
is allergic to ice.
(audience laughing)
- It's allergic to ice.
- Ice, amazing.
- Yeah, and how do we know he's allergic to ice?
- He's told us, they noticed when after a match,
he went into a really cold bath.
And as he was sitting in the ice cold bath that they have,
he was breaking out on top.
And then the breakout, which was sort of raised red lumps,
got really dark below and they quickly got him out.
And they said, "You have this disease,
which is a condition of, you're just allergic
to cold temperatures, you're highly sensitive to it."
And so as a result, when he is playing on the ice,
he can't stay still.
He has to keep his blood circulating
and moving around and so on.
Yeah, so when the game is going on
on the other side of the ice, what's it?
Rink, the rink, the rink.
He's there, sort of just.
- 'Cause the other side of the ice implies
a underside of the ice, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, that's okay.
- So this guy's called Chris Truel
and he started playing with the Belfast Giant.
So I believe he's a junior goalie.
He's, so there's three of them.
And yeah, so he just constantly has to move around.
Otherwise-- - He's goalie, that's the thing.
So does he sometimes have to move around
out of the goal mouth?
- This is the problem.
- Yeah.
- I mean, I, yeah, I don't know if it is a problem,
but I assume that that is a problem.
Sounds like a problem.
- Yeah, it does, doesn't it?
- He's not, he's really cool about it though.
If you watch an interview,
he's very much like he's not--
- But he's not too cool.
- He's not too cool at all. - He's not too cool at all.
- Yeah, it's an allergy to the cold, right?
It's not, 'cause there's a different allergy,
which is an allergy to water,
which is like you can be allergic to your own tears
and stuff, can't you?
So every time you cry, you then cry even more.
But it's not that, it's the coldness of it.
- Yeah, it's cool.
So I've been avoid saying the word 'cause I can't,
I can't pronounce it, but it's erotic carrier.
That's the, is that a dire pronoun?
- Yeah, erotic carrier, that's the condition
that he has.
- The test for it is very simple.
The doctor will just hold a piece of ice against you
and then see if you come out in a red lump.
- Yeah, I mean, that makes sense, right?
I'm not saying there's a better test.
No, I mean, that literally is the test.
It's like finding out if you're allergic to bees
by doctor holding a bee to you and letting it--
- Is that the test for bee allergies?
- It seems like it couldn't be.
The doctor doesn't say, "Hey, eat a load of these walnuts
and we'll see what happens." - Well, yeah.
- All right, you're fine on those.
Let's see if you're allergic to wasps.
Sorry, let's bring that up.
(laughing)
- Do you know what one way of selling
if you've gotten allergic reaction is,
which I'd never heard of?
Is something called baboon syndrome?
- Oh, what's that?
- And that's, well, what would you guess?
What's the defining filter?
- You get a big, you get a big bum bum of red.
- Yeah.
- Big, got 50 shades of grey again.
(laughing)
And he came in with a big bum bum of red.
- Yeah, it's having a big red bum
and it's one of the ways you can exhibit allergic reaction
is bright red buttocks,
a particularly penicillin reaction
or like a nickel reaction.
- Specifically to the bum.
- And you can just have eaten some penicillin
and then your bum goes red.
- Yeah.
- It's amazing.
- The boon syndrome, yeah.
- Over another ironic sports allergy.
- Oh, yeah.
- There's a jocky.
A very young jocky called Sean Bowen.
He raced in the Grand National a couple of years ago.
As a child, he was allergic to horses.
And he grew up, he would get eczema.
Any time he went near a horse,
but then he grew out of it
and then he would practice by sitting on a sofa
and whipping it.
(laughing)
- He would sit on the arm of the sofa and thrash it.
- Ah, that's so funny.
- Do you know who else was allergic to horses?
Clint Eastwood.
- No.
- No way.
- All his movies, he had stunt doubles
and he would do it but he would break out
if he was on a horse for too long.
But yeah, Clint Eastwood allergic to horses.
- That's why he looks so pissed off all the time.
(laughing)
- Hannah, before you were saying about the person
who was allergic to the wrong tears,
there was a woman who was allergic to the allergy medicine
she took to deal with her allergies.
(laughing)
- Oh man.
- So basically, she got ill with some other allergy
and then she took an anti-histamine called Benadryl
and then that caused her shortness of breath, wheezing
and she went to hospital
and then when she was in hospital,
they gave her more Benadryl.
(laughing)
- Oh God.
- God.
- Oh my God.
- That Harrison Schmidt, Apollo astronaut Harrison Schmidt,
one of the only people to land on the moon,
was allergic to the moon.
- Oh yeah.
- Can you believe that though?
He was allergic to the moon.
So you might think that's really weird
because you're in a suit when you get onto the moon.
It was when he got back off the moon into the capsule
and they took the suit off
and supposedly the smellers of like gunpowder sort of smell.
That is what gave him the allergies
and he broke out as well in sort of, in hype.
So one of the only, and there's only 12 people
who have landed on the moon
and one of them was allergic to the moon.
- That's amazing.
- That's pretty huge, right?
And there's no way of testing before you go.
- How do you test?
- Tennis player, Layton Hewitt, allergic to grass
as in the floor of the windowed in courts.
Yeah, not weed.
- You know horses can be allergic to grass.
- Horses can be allergic to grass.
- Yeah, yeah, horses get allergic to grass
and they have to, it's really sad.
So there's a woman who's got a horse
and you have to cover them
and this big anti-allergy sock from head to toe.
And they get allergic to, you get allergies to grass
and hay and seeds, all the nuts and seeds that they get fed.
- It's amazing that you can describe a murder
as pretty cool, but a horse wearing a giant sock
is somehow really sad.
- I know.
- It's because they get weepy.
They genuinely get weepy.
They cry tears and they get itchy and they get sneezy.
- Which of the other dwarfs do they get?
(laughing)
- The cure for it is to rub on some doc.
- There we go.
- That's good. - That's good.
- So if you're hypersensitive of the whole of just everything,
like electricity and stuff,
you can go to a town in America.
It's in Arizona, it's called Snowflake.
- No. - Okay.
And it doesn't get its name because it's full of snowflakes,
like moaning millennial, so whatever.
It gets its name because it was founded by two people
called Araster Snow and William Jordan Flake.
- No way.
(laughing)
- What?
- That's incredible.
- Isn't that amazing?
- But do you think they thought we'd better found something now
because we've met?
- What do you think Flake Snow?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Wait, so they founded a town for people to escape their allergies?
- No, they founded a town they were Mormon pioneers,
but they founded it well away from cities and stuff like that.
So if you're allergic to wifi and all you think you are
and electricity and stuff like that,
then this is a place where you can go and be away from that.
- Where did you say it was?
- It's in Arizona.
- Arizona.
- Oh, yeah, really remote.
- Some of it is.
- Yeah.
- Phoenix.
- When was that, was that 19th century originally?
- Well, it was founded in 1878 where people are going there now.
- But this was a real thing when allergies came into the world.
Hey, we don't know how they appeared in the world.
It was in the 19th century.
And then beat it became a really fashionable thing
because it was the wealthier classes
that were allergic to stuff, wasn't it?
And so they began to be hay fever holidays
that were recommended.
And that would be if you lived in New York,
the idea was that you were getting allergic reactions
to the city like you say.
So Lake Superior and the White Mountain, New Hampshire,
they would all advertise like hay fever holidays
or allergy escapes, which is a way to get away from your allergies.
It was a very fashionable thing to have.
- Yeah, it's very cool.
- Anything about hockey, that ice hockey?
- Yeah, sure, yeah.
- So this sounds quite cool.
Underwater ice hockey.
- Wow.
- Okay, it's played upside down underneath frozen pools.
- No.
- So that is the other side of the ice
that I was talking about.
- Wow.
- And they use a wooden puck, so it floats.
And basically you can only stay under,
they don't use breathing apparatus.
So you can only stay underwater for 30 seconds
and then you go back up and then you go back down again.
And it's next goal wins.
So it's only one goal, two of the scars first wins.
- Wow.
- They're not wearing all the hockey stuff, are they?
- Well, they have a stick.
- They have a stick, but are they in trunks and with a stick?
- Trunks and stick.
- That is amazing.
- Yep.
Don't confuse it with underwater hockey.
Underwater hockey is on the floor of a swimming pool
with a sinking puck.
So you have a really heavy sinking puck.
It's on the bottom and you're playing it
along the bottom of a swimming pool.
- But how can you hit something underwater
and have momentum?
- Yes, momentum still works on the water.
(laughing)
I mean, the laws of physics still work on the water.
But you are right that it's more viscous
so it would be more difficult.
- It would be really hard, right?
- Yeah, you would hit it, and it would.
- It's harder.
- The whole thing sounds harder.
(laughing)
- Almost everything is harder underwater.
- Swimming's not swimming is one of the very few exceptions
to this rule then.
(laughing)
But mostly you have a fri and egg underwater.
It's a nightmare.
(laughing)
- That's true.
- It's not coaching an egg and the egg.
- Just a break.
(laughing)
- More to it.
(clapping)
- No, ice hockey.
- Yeah, I go on.
- Yeah, I became obsessed with the fights in ice hockey.
- Oh yes.
- Oh my goodness, there are so many fights.
- Oh yeah.
- And I didn't know anything about ice hockey
and I think you watched it a lot.
- I watched it a lot.
- You watched it a lot, yeah.
But I didn't know that they were regulated
as fisticuffs in the rule book of ice hockey.
And you know, there are lots of unwritten rules as well.
So you have to agree to a fight
and you can't hit someone with your stick.
- Yeah, I mean they still do, but you're not supposed to.
But you would have one player on your team
who's kind of the guy who does the fighting.
- And how does, is he only allowed to fight
the other team's fighter guy?
Or could he fight the other guy?
- They're the guys who kind of start it
and then everyone gets in on the act.
- Okay.
- But they're called the enforcer basically
and you would have, say the other team is doing really well
and you kind of wanna stop them in their tracks a little bit
then you might start a fight to try and put them off
and then you might carry on.
- But it's Andy, have you seen it?
- I've seen it, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
It's actively, not officially, but it's actively encouraged
by the crowd and it's part of the game.
Yeah, so they throw their gloves off,
they take their helmet off, they go around each other
with their fists like that
and then they absolutely wallop each other
and it's part of the tradition.
It happened in fact in the first game ever,
first ever ice hockey game.
- It was, it was not between the hockey players.
It was between the ice hockey players
and the ice skaters who were pissed off
that they'd taken their ring to,
and it was after the match so it didn't get reported
but there was a fight in the very first ever ice hockey match.
- Sometimes it goes a little bit too far.
I read about one Russian game between Avangard and Vityaz.
The fighting in that game started after three minutes.
Actually, it was three minutes 27
when a Brawl take place between basically
all the players on both teams.
- Wow.
- Okay, a few of the players were sent to the synbin
and then they started the game again
of three seconds later, another fight started.
And then eight more players were sent off.
And then the game started again
and then two seconds later, there was a third fight.
And then at that stage so many people had been sent off
that they couldn't carry on the game
so they just abandoned it.
- Oh my God.
- And both teams were given a five-nil defeat.
Teams lost five-nil.
- How'd you do, darling?
Well, we lost but some of the other guys.
- Hey, we need to move on to our next fact very shortly.
Should I move us on now?
- Yes, we should.
- Ready to go, yeah.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is Andrew Hunter Murray.
- My fact is that after every festival,
the founder of Glastonbury has to drive around his farm
with a giant magnet.
And the reason he has to do that
is that there are tent pegs left
across his entire farm in the ground
and he can't see them.
So there's a specially customized tractor
with a giant magnet strapped onto the front of it.
- Wow.
- So cool.
- Which he drives around, it weighs over a ton.
I think he has someone to do it for him
because he's quite old now, Michael Davis.
- But what do you reckon it weighs
after he's done doing it?
- I guess 100 or 150 tons.
- Wow, I don't, I don't, I don't.
(audience laughing)
- That's crazy.
- I know, it's nuts, isn't it?
- Why do you have the actual answer down?
- No, I just curious, I hear.
- No, okay.
- Because you're adding metal to metal
and then that adds up.
- Yeah, no, it does, is you?
- You're not wrong.
- Yeah.
- It's true, but I reckon if these guys hadn't laughed,
you'd have taken 150 tons because I'm not sure
you know what a ton is.
- I was telling all the answers.
- That's not the answer, I was teasing.
- That's not the answer, I don't know.
- Okay.
(audience laughing)
- But something in that region?
- Yeah.
- No, no, no, no, no, no.
- Now we're in that region, okay.
- I don't know, I'm afraid.
- But there are thousands of thousands of tents,
which get abandoned, you know.
- And they need to pick them up
because in the past cows have been grazing
on these tent pegs and it can injure them quite badly.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, well they, yeah, they choke for cows.
'Cause he's got a very successful dairy.
I didn't quite realize that Michael Evers
is one of the most successful dairy farmers in the area.
So the guy who founded it, yeah.
And that's why it's so quite famously,
I think at the first Glastonbury ever,
you got free pint of milk, I think.
- It was one pound to get in, wasn't it?
One pound to get in, you got a free bottle of milk.
- Yeah, really?
- And then at the most recent Glastonbury,
you could see pole dancing robots,
make a cucumber trumpet,
and jump off a trolley ship shaped like a fish.
(audience laughing)
- It's lost its way, hasn't it?
Lost its way, no free milk.
Do you get free milk still?
- No mate.
- Bloody hell.
- He does, he's a judge of cheese competitions though.
- At the festival.
Not at the festival, no, no.
- I've completely misunderstood what the festival is like,
I think, I've never been.
The very first one, it was in 1970
and it was called Worthy Farm Pop Festival.
And the bee had a great article about the first Glastonbury
and they put up one of the flyers for it
and the flyers, it was so sweet, they said,
the acts will include the kinks, Wayne Fontana,
and at least six other groups.
(audience laughing)
And in the event, neither the kinks nor Wayne Fontana turned up.
- Wow, wow.
- The six others turned up.
- Well T-Rex turned up to replace their blinders.
So, yeah, pretty good.
- Oh yeah, and that's famously where T-Rex exploded
into the popular consciousness of the British public.
- Yeah.
- I'd memorize that sentence from the article that I read.
(audience laughing)
So, what year was that?
- 1970.
- 1970, right, God.
So, he's been going for it.
He's quite old now, Michael.
Yeah, he's eighties.
- Yeah, he's very cool though.
So, everyone probably watched Glastonbury this year
and he, Jeremy Corbyn was there and got up on stage.
So, Jeremy Corbyn is a parliamentary beard of the year winner
and actually, Michael Evers, if you can picture him,
has a very impressive beard himself.
And he went up on stage with Jeremy Corbyn.
Jeremy Corbyn gave him the Labour Manifesto.
And as that was being handed over,
there were just two beard legends on stage
because Michael Evers won beard of the decade in 2009.
- Wow.
- In the world.
So, he beat Fidel Castro to the top spot.
- You're kidding.
- Yeah.
- You know, there's a secret underground piano bar
at Glastonbury, what?
- Yeah, and a reporter from the beab
went looking for it as a recent festival
and he reported back that there is no piano that I can see.
The bar does not turn out to sell alcohol
and most of it is not underground.
(audience laughing)
- And also not a secret now, it's been a moment.
- That was not a secret either, though.
- He's against alcohol.
Well, he's not a drinker, is he?
The Glastonbury founder, Michael Evers.
No, and he's never taken any drugs.
He's anti-smoking.
He's a real methodist.
It's, I can't tell if it's a disappointment or really nice.
But, yeah, and he always wears shorts.
This is the thing he's famous for.
He always wears shorts, whatever time of year it is.
And do you know why he does that?
- He likes to keep his legs cool.
- That makes a lot of sense, actually.
- He's got lovely calf muscles.
- Yes, it's that.
It is that he...
- What?
- He was like, he's a very famous kind of, you know,
liberal hippie campaigner.
And he was an anti-thatcher march in the early,
a touchy years, and he said, his GP's wife was walking behind me.
And she said, do you know, Michael,
you've got the most amazing legs.
And no one had ever said that to me before.
And so I've worn shorts ever since.
(laughing)
- I love the idea that maybe it affects everyone.
So when he meets all the bands,
Coldplay will come up to him, like, hi, but...
Oh my goodness.
(laughing)
What are the flowers?
Just everyone's...
- Yeah, Stanley, yeah, nice.
- Some other cool festivals from the world.
The untold festival took place in Transylvania,
and you could pay with your blood.
- Whoa!
- Yeah.
If you signed up to become a blood donor,
you got a discount.
And if you showed up in person at a centre nearby,
then you would get a free one day ticket on the spot.
- Wow.
- But wouldn't you be a bit tired to enjoy the festival?
Yeah, it doesn't, it tires you out, doesn't it?
- No, I mean, I mean, you can still hear music.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's not too bad, a problem.
I got one, James, I really like.
This is from last year, it was the Newfoundland Lobster Festival.
Yeah, and what I like about it is that,
due to a mess up of transporting the Lobsters to the festival,
they didn't have any Lobsters at the festival.
And so instead, everyone had to eat hot dogs.
(laughing)
It was on an airplane, and the airplane went to the wrong destination,
or they put it onto the wrong carrier.
Yeah, so you've got delivered to a whole different place,
and they're like, we're waiting for the Lobsters.
- Why, if they have to get the Lobsters over by-played,
why are they having a Lobster Festival?
- It's a very good party.
- No, I'm not sure, because maybe they got it
from a great Lobster place like Florida or something like that.
- Then have the festival in Florida.
- No, but they live in Newfoundland, they can't just read.
- They don't have the festival, like?
- No, but they want to, I don't have a Caribbean festival
in South London to buy.
- Yeah, but you could, because that's what people do.
- But why would I fly in three tons of sand?
It doesn't make any sense to them.
(laughing)
- I'd just have a South London festival.
- Okay, that's true, but where did the Lobsters end up?
Do we know?
- No, I just a different place, and then the problem is,
is by the time they got there, this was the complaint,
they said some of the Lobsters had died,
which is what I thought you'd want when you were about to eat one,
so that shouldn't be a problem.
Do you want, oh, you want them alive right after the...
- Well, you keep them alive in your bath, don't you?
If you buy a Lobster to eat, then it...
- Yeah, that's one of the other things
it's easier to do underwater is keep a Lobster alive.
(laughing)
So it's three now.
- You were just saying about transporting these Lobsters.
- Yeah.
- And there was a mud festival in New Zealand called Mudtopia,
and they transported five tons of mud from South Korea.
- Wow.
- Those mud salesmen must have thought all their Christmases
have come up once.
I've had another year of no orders,
I guess it's time to shut down the mud export business.
- Dreaming, dreaming, hello.
- It's New Zealand.
We'd like five tons of mud, five tons.
We've only got four tons.
We're back to going out of business.
(laughing)
- Don't, that's true.
And basically, I mean, just to finish it,
they needed this mud for the mud festival,
and they said the local councillor said,
"I know there's a perception that we have enough mud ourselves,
but you can't just pull any old mud out of the ground
and throw it at people."
There could be anything in there
that might end up making people sick.
So basically, the South Korean stuff
had had some kind of stuff done to it stop it,
making people sick.
- It's clean mud.
- Clean mud?
- Wow.
- Which is amazing to yourself, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Do you know that at the Redding and Leeds festivals
this year, I don't know if anyone went,
but there was pineapples were banned.
So there's a list of banned stuff on,
you know, that you're not allowed to take in submachine guns
or bombs or anything.
And then pineapples was added to the list.
And that's because of this ban that I've never heard of,
probably everyone else has called glass animals.
But yeah, they've just got a lyric in their song,
which says pineapples are in my head.
And so whenever they have a gig,
everyone who comes to the gig apparently brings pineapples
and they can cause a lot of damage.
And so they have to put on the ban list.
- What damage?
- What damage can you get?
- They're spiky, they're really super spiky.
- They're really, yeah, they're really spiky.
- Yeah. - Yeah, no, I didn't think about it that way
when you said it, Jane.
So when Dan back you up, fair play.
- They're spiky.
Okay, maybe in future shows we can get everyone
on the front row to throw pineapples at you.
How would you like that?
- Yeah, it's fair.
- You've only ever seen them in those chopped up cubes
in marks and spenters, haven't you?
- I'm normally being presented them at an ambassador's dinner
in the '70s.
- Did you guys do anything on magnets at all?
- No. - Yeah.
- Yeah, come on, let's do some foreign bed.
- Just quickly, have you guys heard of a thing
called the Iron Harvest?
Because I've never heard of this.
This is a thing that happens every year in Belgium and France
and it's a harvest, literally, of iron from the First World War.
And it's still turning up in farmer's fields
across Belgium and France.
- Wow.
- So during the First World War,
for every square meter of territory on the Western front,
a ton of explosives was fired.
Every square meter.
So it normally turns out--
- That's a lot done, by the way.
- Yeah.
(audience laughing)
- That doesn't sound a lot.
And so in spring and autumn is when the farmer's plow
their fields and that's when the ground slowly turns it up.
And the French mine clearing department
gets sent about 900 tons of unexploded bombs every year.
- Wow.
- A few years ago, just around EEPRA itself,
just around EEPRA, they got 160 tons of metal,
which is not to fill five large lorries.
All First World War stuff.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- That's crazy.
- Do you know something they use magnets for?
In the 1930s and early 20th century,
that's quite cool.
- Okay, a health thing?
- It is a health thing.
It's for eye problems.
So I read this on Boeing Boeing, I think,
which sounds not like a legit website.
- It's real loud.
- Boeing Boeing is brilliant.
- Boeing Boeing is great.
It's just the way you said it.
It sounded like a weird toy.
I read it on Boeing Boeing.
(audience laughing)
- So what kind of eye problems might you have?
- So you'd have stuff caught in your eyes.
So people used to get eye and filings caught in their eyes
when they worked in industrial, you know, in factories and stuff.
And there was invented in Minneapolis,
this piece of equipment that weighed 800 pounds.
So that is the way of, I think, about five full grown women.
And it was a magnet.
It had the pull of 10 horsepower.
It involved 7,000 feet of wire.
And it came towards your eye.
And you had a tiny bit of metal stuck in the back of it.
And then it sucked the metal out.
- Whoa.
- But surely it would suck it out.
- Through your eye.
- I would have thought as well.
I've only seen the advertisements in the British newspaper archive.
- I think if you got something in your eye,
it's not gonna be directly behind your eyeball, probably.
- Oh yeah.
- It's just not.
- I wouldn't risk.
It could come out through the lid.
I don't know.
10 horsepower is more than you need
to suck a tiny bit of metal out of your eye.
- 10 horsepower.
- You would think one horse could do that.
(audience laughing)
Hey, we need to move on to our final fact of the show.
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is Chuzinski.
- My fact this week is that during World War II,
the owners of Foils bookshop protected the store
from Nazi bombs by covering the roof in copies of Mein Kampf.
(audience laughing)
- It's so good.
- It's so nice.
- Yeah.
- This one's got that nice, is it?
- Nice is the wrong word.
- Yeah.
- But it was fitting.
So this is William Foil who set up foils.
And so at World War II, he filled sandbags
with all these old books.
And in order to kind of bolster the shop
against the bombs during the blitz in London.
And he said that he was covering the roof
with copies of Mein Kampf.
And newsreels at the time said,
"Foils of London is stacked with copies of Mein Kampf
in the place of sandbags."
- Yeah, that's what it is.
- That's what it is.
- Just for context, for overseas listeners,
we make this podcast, usually in Covenant Garden,
which is in Soho-ish area.
On Charing Cross Road is Foils Bookshop,
which is a 15 minute walk from where we work.
And it's one of the most iconic bookshops in London.
It's an independent bookshop.
And it was known for its eccentricities.
And it's been going for a very long time.
And it's still one of the iconic bookshops of London.
- Yeah.
- A Mein Kampf was a book by Hitler.
(audience laughing)
- It's one of the iconic bookshops.
Oh, what's he done now?
Is there more?
- It's not even the only time that the foils
had a run in with the Nazis.
So in fact, earlier than that, Christina Foil,
who was the daughter of William the founder,
when the Nazis held their book "Burnings",
she wrote to Adolf Hitler saying,
"We'll give you a good price, we'll buy them, don't burn them."
Which is good.
And then the reply was negative but respectful, apparently.
- Yeah.
- And then in 1939, Christina also invited Hitler,
Mussolini, and Stalin, to speak at one of her literary lunches.
- Wow.
- So they used to have these lunches with incredible figures
from the world of literature.
And she invited all three.
- Wow.
- Hitler replied that he had urgent business in Germany.
Mussolini and Poland.
(audience laughing)
- Mussolini said that he might visit
when things quiet him down a bit.
(audience laughing)
- Stalin didn't reply, didn't he?
- Rude.
- Okay.
- She was a character, actually.
And not in a massively positive sense, maybe.
So Foil has been through some tough times,
partly because of her.
So she wasn't really a fan of her,
the people who worked in her bookshop.
So she used to summarily sack them
before they'd worked for six months
because after six months,
you're entitled to better employment rights.
So if you work for foils,
then you get sacked up to six months.
And this meant that you got quite not very good staff,
and you got not very dedicated staff,
and there was a story of someone
who came in in the '60s or '70s and asked for Ulysses,
and the person at the till replied
that Ulysses had gone out to lunch,
but would serve them as soon as possible.
- All right, nice.
They have changed that policy now, by the way.
I just want to say that,
'cause hopefully they'll keep stocking our book
and they'll attack their HR policies.
- The other thing I've changed is,
they've changed their payment system,
and Christina was quite concerned about staff
possibly stealing from the shop,
maybe because they weren't paid very much,
but the old payment system,
designed to stop staff stealing when does follows.
You had to queue up for the book,
and then you had to get a docket for it
from a staff member,
then you had to queue up to pay for the book,
then you would get the docket stamped
to prove that you had paid for the book,
then you would have to queue up a third time
at the counter you'd been to first to collect the book.
- Wow. - Yeah.
And also, she didn't even organize her books
by, in any sensible way.
She organized them by publisher, didn't she?
- Yes. (laughing)
- Do you know who all your books are published by?
- Because we're random house, by the way,
an excellent company, but no, you don't,
and you can do alphabetically or by genre, no, she didn't.
- Do you know when that lasted until?
- That lasted till 1999.
- No. - Yeah.
- We should say because it sounds like we're slamming them,
but falls obviously amazing,
and also all this information
is on the most brilliant page on their website.
So they're one of these sites
that obviously has some amazing research
are working for them,
and they've got a really good site
falls bookshop of their history and stories and foils.
- Yeah, she's got that.
- She died in 1999, Christina,
and she really was the end of an era,
but after she died, they had a refit
in which they discovered a lift that nobody knew about.
(laughing)
- Wow. - Yeah.
- Where did it go?
- Up and down, mostly.
(laughing)
- And it's just moved like a year ago,
so it was in this iconic spot on Charing Cross Road,
still on Charing Cross Road,
but it's moved down the road.
But apparently, and I went to it many times,
I'm sure you guys did as well.
It was a labyrinth of these different weird,
tiny crevices you could get,
you find yourself hours going a new spot in the bookshop,
you didn't know existed, and they had,
it was a sort of in joke amongst the shop,
because they had an in-house staff magazine,
and they always had a lost property section
in the, you know, lost and found,
and one of the things that they wrote was found,
Paul Potter of Made-A-Vale,
after wandering for an hour, trying to find his way out.
And that happened, that happened a lot,
where people, customers would just get lost,
and you know, the partners would be like,
have you seen my husband and are like,
do you have an hour, 'cause we will,
we will find his, your husband, 'cause we may have him.
(audience laughing)
So Christina ran the bookshop after her father, William,
retired in 1945, and she ran it into the '90s,
and she claimed that she read an entire book every day,
had never done her own housework, all cooking,
and she only ever drank champagne.
She was asked what would happen if she lost her chef,
and she said there was always milk, champagne,
and smoked salmon in the fridge.
(audience laughing)
Mine can't.
- Yeah. - No, really?
(audience laughing)
- Current bestseller rank on Amazon.
- Yeah.
- 1,471,284.
- Okay.
- So they're beating us, aren't they?
(audience laughing)
They, the mine can't team.
- But it's not even in the top 700 in the fascism category.
- Oh!
- It's not for the 700 in the world.
- That's fascism. - That's gotta hurt.
- But fascism and Nazi books do sell.
There's a famous story about Alan Koran,
the famous woodcissed and father of Victoria Koran,
and he'd noticed that the most popular titles in Britain
in those days were about cats, gulf, and Nazis,
and so he called his book "Gulfing for Cats"
and put a massive swastika on the cover.
(audience laughing)
The one thing I didn't know about mine camp
is that it hadn't a company in picture book.
(audience laughing)
Not even kidding.
- Really?
- It was called "The Hitler Nobody Knows,"
and it was designed to improve Hitler's public image,
'cause his image was very, very bad at the start,
'cause obviously he was a thug
and he'd organized putches and things like that.
- He didn't get much better, did he?
- He didn't get much better, but this in Germany
turned around the public image of him a lot,
'cause it was like a family album.
It began with photos of him as a baby,
and photos of him as a--
- He still had a tiny little mustache.
(audience laughing)
- Ironically, he looked like Churchill.
But it was massively popular.
It sold over 400,000 copies by 1942.
- And this was, came along with mine camp--
- No, it was another of the works designed
to improve his public image.
So it wasn't a buy one, get one, free thing,
or anything like that, but yeah.
- 'Cause they've released a manga version
of mine camp now, and someone here is a huge fan.
(audience laughing)
- So is Hitler portrayed as Japanese in it?
- I think he is, yes, I assume he is.
So this is weirdly in Japan and Turkey.
There are manga versions of mine camp,
and it was introduced a few years ago in Japan,
and it sold 45,000 copies to bizarre.
And then in India, there's a version
which is used for business and management students
who advised to read it.
- It seemed very different over there, I think,
'cause they were quite geographically detached
from the things that happened in World War II in Europe.
And they don't really get taught about the Holocaust
as much as we do and stuff like that.
So they just sit completely differently.
So in India, they have a Hitler Cafe,
a Hitler fashion store, and Hitler ice cream.
- Really?
- Yeah.
(audience laughing)
- We need to wrap up very shortly.
Do you guys have anything before we do?
- I've one more story, it's about foils though.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's Christopher Foil, who took over
from his aunt, Christina.
It's just an anecdote he told about a time
when he was working in the shop and he wrestled a shop lifter.
And I just wanted to tell you it 'cause I love it.
He said, he chased him out of the shop, he saw him leaving,
and they got into Soho Square right nearby.
And he said, I was very calm, very friendly.
I said, excuse me, I think you might have some books there.
You didn't pay for, would you like to come back to foils
and we'll just discuss it?
Anyway, at that point, they usually come back quietly,
all they lash out or run away or whatever.
This chap lashed out.
I remember, he kept on trying to kick me in the groin.
So what I did was, with one hand, I held him away from me
by the knot of his tie.
By the other, I held him by the end of his tie.
Anyway, we ended up grappling and I remember
we were rolling around in the gutter in the next moment.
I found myself being hauled to my feet
by a burly policeman and he by another.
The curious thing about this man was,
they were books on breaking codes and ciphers.
It turned out, he was an officer in MI5.
(audience laughing)
Okay, should we wrap up guys?
We're gonna wrap up.
Okay, that is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Streiberland, Andy.
@AndreyHunterM, James.
- @JamesHarkin and Chazinski.
- You can email podcast@QI.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @nosuchthing, or you can go to our website.
Nosuchthing is a fish.com.
We have all of our previous episodes up there.
We also have a link to our book, The Book of the Year,
which is out now and we're about to give a copy of it
away to a member of the audience here tonight in Dunstable.
We've picked out our favorite fact from the ones
that you guys sent in and have we got it here who was,
who was, I got it.
And I'm just going to take my phone off airplane.
Oh, Jesus.
I'm really, I am, can I do it?
Shall I do another Hitler fact?
- Yes.
- Great.
- Yep.
Thank you.
- So during the Iran hostage crisis,
the CIA managed to sneak some agents into Tehran
and they had false German passports.
Okay, and one of the agents was stopped
by the customs officials and they said,
"Something's wrong with your passport."
They said, "This is the first time I've seen a German passport
"which has a middle initial instead of a full name."
And they said, "Your name is given as Joseph H. Schmidt."
And the guy was, "Oh my God, I'm going to get caught."
And then he suddenly came up with a brainwave
and he said, "Well, oh yeah, when I was born,
"they gave me my middle name as Hitler
"and I have a special permission not to use it."
(audience laughs)
That's clever, isn't it?
- Yeah, that's good.
- Did they buy it?
- Yeah, they bought it.
- Oh, nice.
- And Joseph H was H Henry, by any chance, you know?
- It was a made-up name, done.
(audience laughs)
- How's the fact finally going, Andy?
- It's fun.
- Great, let's get it out.
- This is from, it's one of the ones that came in on Twitter
and it's from @gtomorrow, you in?
- Hey. - Oh, hey.
- And, well, we all loved it so much.
Is that the French language has 17 different words
for surrender?
(audience laughs)
- Nice, coming, collect your book from us at the end.
(audience applauds)
- Thanks so much, guys, we'll see you later.
Good night!
(audience cheers and applauds)
(upbeat music)
(audience applauds)