(upbeat music)
- Hey everyone, welcome to the very first episode
of Fish in the Year 2024.
This is gonna be a really big year for us.
We're incredibly excited.
It's our 10 year anniversary.
10 years of fish this March.
That's over 500 episodes, 29,000 facts.
Actually, so far 29,597 facts, to be exact.
We know that because Andy keeps a spreadsheet.
So thanks to everyone who's been tuning in all this time.
I hope you had a great holiday break.
Hope you had a great New Year's.
We got a great episode for you today.
James is away on holiday at the moment.
So in his place, we have another James, a Reese James.
I'm sure you're all aware of Reese James.
He's an amazing stand-up comedian.
He's appeared on multiple TV shows and radio shows.
Most predominantly I would say as a regular or mock the week,
where for years he was a panelist.
And actually, if you go to Reese's Instagram account,
which is @ReeceJamesy, so that's Reese James,
but with a Y at the end,
you'll find the funniest Instagram account out there
in my personal opinion.
It's the reason I basically stayed on Instagram
for a long time.
He's uploaded all of his single one-liners
that he's delivered on the show mock the week
from over the years.
And honestly, you will be in tears laughing.
So get that into your life, follow him there.
And if you want more long-form stuff by him,
you can go to his YouTube account
where you'll find an entire radio show
that's been uploaded there.
And that's called Reese Search.
As in Reese's name, but mixed with research, Reese Search.
And to describe that show the best way would be to say
it's answering all of life's big questions,
but done in a sort of brass-eye mold.
It's incredibly funny and you must check it out.
But in the meantime, don't go anywhere
'cause you can enjoy him here on No Such Thing as a Fish.
So here we go, on with the show.
Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here
with Anna Tyshinski, Andrew Hunter Murray, and Reese James.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Reese.
- Soap is the best way to move a building.
How do you feel about that?
- That was so dramatically presented.
I really enjoyed it.
- And I actually had other options,
I had other options of ways to introduce that headline.
I went with that basic, really simple one.
But I was gonna say something like,
washing, removing stains, moving buildings.
Just three of the hats soap wears.
That's what I was gonna go with,
but it's the first fact, keep it simple.
But just so you know, I had that in the locker.
- No, no, no, absolutely.
I think you played it right though.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, so what's the story here then?
- So in Nova Scotia, at last,
I felt very local news this story.
So, and there was like a local news video about it.
But basically, an old Victorian building
that was mostly used as a hotel for about a hundred years.
It was gonna get knocked down.
Then a company bought it because they wanted to attach it
to a planned apartment block, sort of 30 feet away.
And instead of moving it the traditional way with rollers,
they used 700 bars of ivory soap,
because that's the softest soap.
And therefore, the slippiest.
- All right.
- And they did that successfully
to then get it onto new foundations.
And then once that is complete,
they are going to move the whole thing back.
- What?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Why?
- That's the end, I don't know.
They're gonna move, 'cause basically it's now,
it's like a protected landmark of this old building, I think.
And so, they were gonna restore the whole thing
and put it back to where it was,
which to me just suggests you wanted to move it with soap.
You didn't need to move this.
- Yeah, if it's protected,
but we've also proved beyond doubt that it's mobile,
it doesn't matter where it is as long as we're protecting it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Taking it on the road.
(all laughing)
- I found it amazing how little soap you need to move.
I mean, I looked at the photo, this is a big building.
700 bars of soap, it's obviously lots of bars of soap,
but it's not that many windows.
- Surface area wise, it doesn't feel like a lot.
- Right.
- Well, they didn't even use 700 bars.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, they took some home, didn't they?
I think some of the builders took,
there was 20 to 40 bars left.
So they used most of it, they estimated quite well.
- Yeah, no, but I mean--
- At last.
- Oh my gosh, I'm gonna hear that a lot.
- The crazy thing is, this is not the first time
that soap's been used to move buildings,
but it's clearly an essential ingredient
as part of the process of what they're doing,
and it was as they were getting ready to move it,
that's they went, we don't have any soap.
So it's not even like they bought it
in industrial bulk amounts.
What ended up happening was the guy who was in charge of it,
his wife, Leanne, had to run to 15 shops
around the area, and by using 970 something bucks,
the equivalent of 700 parts of soap.
- When you put it like that,
it suddenly sounds quite taskmaster, doesn't it?
It's like there's a panning there of like, oh my God.
- And he wasn't, this guy, Sheldon Rushden,
the lead builder guy, said, I think he said at first,
he thought, I'll just ask my wife
if we can use some of our soap from home,
and it was only when she said,
we're absolutely not doing that,
I'm not giving up our personal supply
that she offered to drive around,
which made me think, how many bars of soap
are you stoppiling in your house?
- Yeah, exactly.
- But also, how precious are you
about where the soap is your personal supply or not?
- Exactly.
- Sorry, surely, if it was like,
yeah, you can use some of our old soap,
but use some of the budget to get us some new soap.
Surely the same thing.
- You're right, as you've written diary entries
on the wrapping. - Yeah, it's got sentimental value,
her own personal or soap.
- I think once you're mixing work with pleasure,
it's sort of...
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And it's, we are not meant,
we're not actually sponsored by Ivory Soap this week,
but it is very, very soft apparently, and that's great.
- So, and if you do use the offer code fish,
you are gonna get 20% off all of it.
- You'll get nothing, you'll get absolutely nothing.
You'll get a weird look.
But, so what the basic method you use
to move the building is,
so you dig under the building, don't you,
and then you put steel beams under the building,
then you lift the whole thing up by one inch
on hydraulic jacks, just jack it up one inch,
and you slide the soap underneath it on trays,
and then I think you lower, then you lower an inch,
and it just kind of squishes the soap,
but it's incredibly soapy now.
- Yeah, so you leave it overnight to squish the soap, right?
You sit it on the soap overnight,
which I feel like the building's heavy enough
that you only need to sit it on the soap for 10 minutes.
- These guys are experts, haven't they?
- They know what they're doing.
- And then what, you're trying to create
a sort of slip and slide aspect to it.
I bet they can just push it,
and it's just about the weight you push it,
where it's like curling.
And then it just doesn't land in the bit
you want the building to be, and eventually it's like,
nah, I squished it too hard, it's gone in the sea!
- It's a thousand of them with brooms created.
- Have any of you curled?
- Never.
- I've curled, I've curled, I've curled.
Sorry, but I curl.
I was trained by the British Olympic curling duo
for the Winter Olympics just gone.
- Yeah, clung?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, old big time.
Whose names are, and then just insert them,
if you want to.
(laughing)
They were lovely.
- Why were you hoping to be the third member of the team?
- Yeah, I did, I think, four team GBs, like YouTube thing,
I went and had to do four Winter Olympic sports,
because in the Summer Olympic podcast,
I had said, as a joke,
I reckon I could master any Olympic sport in a day.
- Right.
- And I was just, you know, I was being hyperbolic,
and then suddenly their next series I said, go on then,
and I mastered none of them in several days.
One of them's curling though, which was the easiest,
but it's like insane at first,
because also they're not very technical with their language,
so they literally just call it grippy shoe and slippy shoe,
and you have one of these.
- Oh, that's like bowling.
- Yeah, right, right, right.
- You're basically in the slippy, yeah, yeah.
- So you have, they gave me like this thing
that goes under your shin as you slide along at first.
It's basically like a little ice skate, but it just rests.
I think you just have that at first,
and then you're supposed to just slide on your actual shin.
But they give you that at first,
that's like barriers in bowling, I reckon.
Or like the thing you push the ball down to make in.
- I see, I see.
How did you do?
- Pretty badly, I think.
But it was better than when I had to do speed skating
and smashed open my chin on the last shot of the whole thing.
- Oh, wow.
- Yeah, that was much worse.
- They should have given you a little ski
for the bottom of your chin.
Like you'll need a curling for that situation.
- We just come in today dressed fully in skis, by the way.
Head to toe, skis for every limb.
- Well, the only issue with the idea with this building
being the curling system is you could probably get it
into place with one big push,
but then you might have a rival building behind you
knock you out using the same system.
- You know, the Titanic was put on soap.
I think we've said before that the Titanic was put on soap
to go down the slipway, to get in like the whale blubber
and all that sort of stuff.
- Yeah, it was tallow and oil and soap,
and it was 20 tons of it that was used.
It was kind of amazing, but obviously.
- That's more than 700 bars, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- But I did, so I was just reading a bit more about that.
I'd never read this before,
that workers, they would go to the slipway afterwards
and try and gather up any spare soap that was left over.
- Oh, to use themselves.
- Interesting.
- But it was also covered in sort of oil and--
- You could probably wash it, right?
You could probably rush away that,
and then you've got the soap sitting underneath.
- I guess so.
- Yeah, I don't think soap gets,
'cause you can just wash off the upper layer.
- There is a big debate online
about whether you can get soap dirty.
(laughing)
- Welcome to the show.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- This is the kind of controversy we try on the way.
- Of course you can, of course you can.
I'm willing to weigh in on this debate.
Of course you can get soap, are you mad?
Of course you can get soap dirty.
- I believe, of course you can get soap dirty,
but it doesn't stop it cleaning you.
So it doesn't matter.
- Interesting.
- If you're soap's dirty,
it doesn't make a difference.
- Yeah, the level of dirty,
it would have to be for the dirt on it to make you dirtier.
- Yeah.
- That way the cleanliness of the soap being applied to you
is so dirty.
- Yeah.
- But you're at that point right off that bar of soap.
- Sometimes in horrible pubs,
there will be a bar of soap at the sinks.
And you look at it and you think,
oh, I'm actually, I'm not sure.
- Well, this is a thing.
There was a report that was done,
a sort of a research project to look into
how clean actually are in bathrooms like pubs and stuff.
How clean is the soap that you're getting?
And they've worked out that some of the dispensers
are left for so long,
where they're not maintained and they get cracks in it,
that you can go to the toilet, wash your hands with the soap
and leave with dirtier hands,
then you arrived with,
yeah, because they found 15 types of bacteria
that were sitting on these dispensers
that would make it onto your hand as part of the soap.
- Right.
- And, yeah.
- Yeah, same pull handles in the toilet,
when you think, I know what people are doing in here.
- I'm gonna make a call on this toilet thing
and say it doesn't make your hands dirtier
than after you wash them.
'Cause it doesn't matter if there's bacteria
on the soap dispenser,
on the soap dispenser, it does matter.
- Well, yeah.
- Don't even see it.
But on the soap dispenser,
isn't the point of soap that it gets onto your hands
and then it makes the water and the dirt on your hands
more slippery and so it gets them off
and it doesn't matter if there's bacteria on the dispenser.
- Yes, it does.
- The soap immediately gets all of that off.
So, which is why it doesn't matter
if a bar of soap is dirty.
- No, but that's the amazing thing about soap
and it's why it's so incredible that we,
you know, as a species discovered it millennia ago,
it not only makes the dirt and stuff on your hands slippery
to slide off, but it also has this structure
which tears open bacteria and viruses.
It's amazing.
- Yeah.
- Like it's, okay, I just, so I want to read this
'cause I don't want to get it wrong.
Each molecule of soap has a head which bonds with water
and then a tail which hates water, right?
So, and sort of it's hydrophobic, you know,
and tries to avoid it at all costs.
- That's horrible identity crisis.
- I know, I know, I know.
- It must.
- It's poor molecule.
- And so the tail seeks oils and fats and things.
And basically, bacteria and viruses,
they're surrounded by a lipid membrane, a fatty membrane.
And when they touch soap, the soap kind of envelops it
and also the soap molecule tails,
which are trying to avoid water,
realize there is a fatty layer on that bacterium
and burrow into it, they sort of wedge themselves in
and that reps the bacterium apart.
So that's the other thing that's going on
as well as making things slippier.
- Yeah.
- It's just amazing.
- It's incredible.
- And it smells nice.
- It smells nice.
- Lest we forget.
- Naturally.
- That was the main comment of the builders
after they moved that building.
- And it smelled nice.
- Honestly, they said they went away smelling great.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Do you know though, what is better out of,
I feel like I've presented this in a really obvious way now,
out of antibacterial soap and just a bar of soap.
- Anti-bacterial.
- Dan, you idiot.
I mean, I even said it, so the answer was clear.
No, there's a serious worry that people are converting
to antibacterial soap a lot and hand soap.
And there's a guy called Professor Lithko,
who works at Monash University in Australia.
And he says that he thinks they should all be banned
antimicrobial soaps because they're not better
than just a bar of soap, even though we,
I mean, we've got them all over our house now.
There's a COVID hangover.
Not better than a bar of soap.
Hand soap is why you don't use water,
are significantly less good because, you know,
when you get a hand sanitizer, that's a lot less good.
- Yeah, is it?
- Yeah, 'cause the water doesn't,
you need the water to scrub away and wash off that layer.
And he says that they're causing a huge amount
of antibiotic resistance because we're shoving
this antibacterial soap at our hands
and all the bacteria is becoming kind of superbugs
on our hands.
- Yes.
- And he explains. - They're attracting.
- Exactly, we're all gonna have
just these superbugs living on us.
So really, and this really surprised me,
it's not about the antimicrobial chemical properties,
really, as much as it is about the scrub.
But actually, the key is, as long as you scrub
your hands really hard with the water, it scrapes them off.
- And with the soap?
- And with the soap.
- It does, all right, but soap is the thing, really.
- But yes, there's definitely something psychological
about the smell and presentation, though, right,
of how clean you feel, 'cause natural soaps don't feel,
they obviously are better, and you could make soap
out of just oil and lard, basically, can't you?
- Yeah, yeah.
- You know, I find rubbing oil on my body,
I don't feel, and lard,
- It's lime, isn't it?
- It's being massively clean.
And they're saying it's like that,
and the scrub of that is what actually makes you clean.
- Why am I getting so turned on?
- I need it.
(laughing)
- Well, I shouldn't be rubbing myself, but you need,
I need, it has to have a scent, or I won't feel.
- It does it.
- Well, also, I've not used a bar of soap for years,
and I find a bar of soap disgusting.
- Haven't you, I always only use bars.
- Never a bar, never a bar.
Come on.
- I don't mind a bar of soap.
- Are you a cartoon?
Are you all cartoon?
(laughing)
- What do you do?
- I don't use, in our house, we have the, yeah,
we have liquid soap as opposed to a bar of soap.
- Yeah, we pump a little pump,
and I like a shower or gel type situation.
- I've never heard of pump soap.
I'm familiar with the concept,
but you should just feel very guilty,
because of course, you are single-handedly destroying
the world with all of your plastics.
- No palm oil, always say no palm oil, please.
What, it's the issue of plastic?
- Yeah, plastic, is it around?
- Right, who are you saying it to?
Are you saying your personal soap?
- No palm oil, please.
- To my bottom, sorry, I don't make that clear.
(laughing)
Most soaps, again, I actually haven't bought bar in ages.
Aren't they covered in quite a plastic-y kind of wrapping?
- Yes, Dan, but--
- Paper, but--
- Is it paper these days?
(laughing)
- Okay, there's a, right, there is a spectrum,
what we see is a spectrum is here,
from Anna, who is this only old-fashioned bar of soap
that have to be cut from the mother block,
and then wrapped in cruise-proof paper.
(laughing)
Up to Dan, who has like those auto dispensers
at every doorway in his house.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So, the other board, this is such a good thing to say,
but actually, if you use bar soap,
it's got a slightly lower carbon footprint
than the travel emissions,
'cause you're not, you know, with liquid soap,
you're mostly transporting the water.
- Yeah, but what about, okay,
but what about the satisfaction of a foam burst?
You ever used a foam burst?
I've, okay, briefly obsessed with foam bursts.
- What is a foam burst?
- It's just a soap that is literally designed
to become extra foamy when you're lathering,
and so, you know, you feel, it's exciting.
- It's very exciting, where to start or end your day.
- Just, feels like you're not engaging
with the ethical issues here,
where you get very much set and foam based.
- Listen, and I'm happy with this girl record,
I couldn't give a fuck about the ethical issues at all.
(laughing)
I flew here.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that the 19th century author,
Thomas Hardy, had two funerals at the same time.
- Did you say 19th century author,
so we didn't confuse him with the 21st century actor?
'Cause he's still alive.
- This is Tom Hardy, Thomas Hardy,
who wrote, I'm confusing it already,
Jude the Obscure, Tess of the Durbovilles,
Mayor of Castor Bridge.
- We don't need the full bibliography.
- About 900 poems, he was a big deal.
- He was.
- He was mega famous, actually.
And that was sort of what led to this problem, basically.
He was meant to be buried in Dorset
in his native Stinsford with his first wife, right?
And it was all ready to go.
There was a space on the tombstone for him,
his name to be added, you know?
And then he died, and then his friends,
including James Barry of Peter Pan fame,
and Sidney Cockrell,
who slightly less well-treated by history,
but you know, I'm sure a big deal at the time.
They went to his home basically on his death,
and they said, we think he should be buried
in Poets Corner in Westminster Abbey.
He's a huge, huge deal.
And they kind of bullied Thomas Hardy's second wife,
Florence, into going along with it, you know?
- Right.
- She sort of said, well, okay, fine.
So they struck a deal whereby he went to Poets Corner,
and his heart went to Stinsford.
And they both had a funeral at 2 p.m.
on the 16th of January, 1928, and that was the...
- I mean, real Sophie's choice for his second wife.
Sorry, you're either gonna be buried in Poets Corner,
which is not where he's supposed to be,
or with your other wife, your previous wife.
And, oh no, we'll just take your heart to your previous wife.
- I know, it's really...
- Where's your mother?
Where the fuck are you coming in all of this?
You can take a look.
- Where am I ending up?
- What?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It's true.
And also, like, well, I think reading into it more,
I think his family was there as well,
so that was kind of...
- Stinsford.
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, no, not Poets Corner.
(all laughing)
And so, because his wife, his first wife,
they didn't particularly get on too well,
like, deep into the marriage.
To begin with, they did, but there was a lot of...
- No, it was a...
- There's a painful marriage
according to a lot of the friends
and close relatives and so on.
- And her, herself, and him, himself.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So why did he want to be there?
- Well, the family, I guess.
She just happened to be there.
- Right.
- I didn't know he felt huge regret
about what a dick he was to her, it was said.
He treated her quite bad.
She kept a book.
- Yes.
- That's the weirdest title I've ever heard.
- Yeah, so he found after she died,
and they did have this difficult relationship, didn't they?
And she's a very interesting, weird character.
But he found in the attic, after she died,
a diary that she'd written, basically called something like,
"What I Think of My Husband."
- Yeah, that's it.
- And just loads of bitching about him.
And he did, and he feels so awful.
And he felt really guilty reading that.
And I think he burned it, so we don't know.
- Immediately, yeah.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- I feel so bad about it.
Okay, let's just pop that in the fire.
- He burned it on the gaslight.
(laughing)
- I think that's Every Husband's Nightmare.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's fine to go for it, yeah.
- It's titled that, oh my God.
- It's not a dream for every wife, I'm gonna tell you.
- You're not picking up a book called,
"What I Think of My Husband"
and expecting a positive review, are you?
- He's great!
- End of book.
- Oh dear.
- Always helps, he was listened.
- She lived in the attic.
She just moved into the attic after a while.
A while after their relationship started to go really wrong.
She was kind of the, she was the sane woman in the attic.
- Well, I mean, sources differ on the sanity level, right?
- And then he remarried, he married Florence,
who was 39 years his junior.
There's a big difference, though.
- The list of, not even guests at the funeral of Thomas Hardy,
but the Paul Bearers.
You had, just before mentioned, James Barry,
J.M. Barry was one of the Paul Bearers.
You had George Bernard Shaw.
You had the Prime Minister, Stanley Baldwin,
as one of the Paul Bearers.
And then, you know, various other names
that were obviously massive.
- Two Prime Ministers being Paul Bearers,
but one of them wasn't Prime Minister yet.
- That's right, leader of the opposition at the time.
- Ramsay McDonald, who was then the first Labour Prime Minister.
Rudyard Kipling.
- And Kipling, yeah.
- Paul's the Paul Bearer.
- I mean, I guess, is this that surprising?
Like, if Richard Ellsman dies,
I wouldn't be massively surprised
if like Sebastian Folks, Ian McEwan.
- Yeah, but this is the equivalent
of Richard Sunak and Keir Starmer also turning up.
- I don't think you get a lot of volunteers
to carry that coffin.
He's a big lad.
- Oh yeah, your Paul Bearer list would be very long,
wouldn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Paul McEwan's idea was 'cause he had 10.
- Did he?
- Which feels like a lot.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Normally you can fit six.
- Yeah, good point.
- You know.
- Very squeezed in.
- I know, I know.
- I think he was definitely quite puny as a baby.
And his mother gave birth and they went,
well, we'll set that aside 'cause it's not alive
and we'll retrieve the mother.
And they put him to one side thinking that he wasn't alive.
And then the midwife,
who probably wasn't doing a job particularly well,
said after a few minutes,
oh, hang on a second, this baby's alive.
We should keep it going.
- Good grief.
- And he was very,
and for the first few weeks,
everyone assumed that he would die.
And he was quite a weakling, I think, when he was younger.
- Are you guys any fans of his stuff?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, I read 'Test of the Doverbills' at school
and it was the first, as it were, literature book
that I'd write up until then,
I was reading 'Spin Off Indiana Jones Novelizations'
and it blew my mind.
I thought it was fantastic.
- Yeah.
- And he wrote my favorite poem.
- Which one?
- 'The Darkling Thrush', amazing poem.
If you wanna read it.
- Well, he considered himself a poet
more than an author, didn't he?
Despite these, like, similar--
- He was much more successful as an author, right?
That's just like, yeah.
- He was extremely successful as a poet as well.
And the last 30 years of his life,
he only wrote poetry, didn't he?
- Yeah.
- Well, he had success, but this, to me,
is like, Ant and Deck considering themselves musicians.
But they've been successful in the charts,
but you wouldn't say the famous, he had a repertoire.
- Musicians, Ant and Deck, have died.
It's not what's gonna be--
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But this, to me, is just like, you know,
his Twitter bio would just be one of those ones
that's just like a list.
Poet, author, son, father, husband, twice.
- For anyone who's listening who's not a fan,
they're basically, the books are,
they're amazing, but they're also incredibly gloomy.
As in, they feature all sorts of, you know,
terribly unhappy people, you know,
making poor decisions and getting on badly with each other.
That's--
- Although, I think that he has a reputation.
Far from the running crowd is not a gloomy book.
Everyone always says such sad books,
but yeah, don't read "Judy Obscure," if you like.
- So "Judy Obscure," the Guardian, a few years ago,
they produced this fantastic infographic
on what each book contains in terms of various traumas.
Right, so "Judy Obscure" was by a long shot, the winner,
but it features, they just listed,
like, in little bullet points, what it features.
An unhappy relationship, a death,
another unhappy relationship, another unhappy relationship,
grinding poverty, suicide, murder, murder.
That's one child who kills two others and then himself.
Miscarriage, alcoholism, another death,
and animal genitalia-related injury,
which I had forgotten about,
but which does feature in "Judy Obscure."
- Does it, what happens? - Which bit is that?
- Jude, he meets his wife, Arabella,
when she throws a pig's-pizzle, a pig's penis at him,
and it wallops him on the bones.
- It's like, when you said animal-related
genital injury, I would never have guessed that.
I was going to something biting something.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But I never would have thought
it was the animal's genital that was in--
- It was doing the injury.
It caused it to be a different part of his body.
- No, yeah, dismembered pig dick was not.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Which is what I saw coming.
- On my bingo card for 1894.
(all laughing)
- I, so, got the training today to King's Cross,
and I had a bit of time on my hands,
and I went to see something pretty incredible.
- The tree? - Yeah.
I went to see the hardy tree.
- What's that?
- The hardy tree is Old St. Pancras Church,
which is just up the road from St. Pancras Station,
international, and it's a church
where you have a graveyard there,
and when hardy, prior to becoming a full-time writer,
I think maybe he was dabbling in writing at that point,
but he was an architect beforehand,
and he used to work in London,
and he worked for a company which was called Blumfield,
and one of the things that Blumfield needed to do
was they needed to move a lot of the graves
that were in the area to make room for a new rail track.
It was the mainland, midland Grand Railway,
and so they had to exhume bodies,
and it was something like thousands of bodies
that they had to exhume,
and they had all these leftover tombstones,
and hardy did this thing where there's
about a hundred of them of these tombstones,
they are all sort of layered in towards the tree,
and it's so hard to describe.
- They like circle the tree.
- Is the tree, 'cause the tree fell down, isn't it?
- The tree fell down in 2022.
- Oh, has it fallen?
I saw it years ago, but it was like the roots
were like growing over the tombstones.
It's almost like, give the illusion
that the tombstones were sinking
because roots were starting to grow over the top of them,
they were getting shorter and shorter.
- Yeah, so a storm. - But I didn't know it fell down,
so what is it?
- A storm took it out, but they've left,
there's a big fence around it at the moment,
they're working out what to do
and which way to restore it,
but yeah, that is literally a bit of art/architecture
by Thomas Hardy, as you say,
you saw it when it's full place,
and God, just generally, by the way,
what an extraordinary cemetery that is
with such notable people.
Mary Wollstonecraft is buried there,
who was the mother of Mary Shelley,
and there's this story which all academics
think is almost definitely true,
it's one of those ones where it's like,
"There might be a tiny grain of untruth."
It's where she used to go and sit and read
her mother's books against the tombstone,
and it's where her and Percy Shelley first had sex
on the tombstone, literally.
- That's the kind of thing they would have done.
- Yeah, but so. - Dofts, man.
(all laughing)
- I don't think that's fair.
- I'll highly recommend it, though.
(all laughing)
- Of course, you would,
and you recommend all sorts of stuff.
- I'll be going to the cemetery.
- Dansex Advice podcast.
It's gonna go down like a live balloon.
- But also, incidentally,
one of the people who were buried underneath,
supposedly, all those tombstones is the writer
who wrote The Vampire, who was part of that weekend
with Mary Shelley. - Oh, God.
- Poladori. - Yeah, Poladori.
- Poladori, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Can I shatter your allusions, though,
about that lovely concentric circle gravestones and tree?
Tree has nothing to do with him.
- What?
- Yeah, everyone calls it the hardy tree.
There's no evidence.
It was planted in his life, like,
by him when he was an architect.
There's no evidence.
It was, they think it was planted
about 50 years after he died.
It only started being referenced in the--
- Oh, so he just made the circles--
- He made the circles, I thought.
- He, all we know, I'm pretty sure,
is that he was indeed employed
'cause he was low down in the architect's firm.
So the architect said,
"Could you dig up all these bodies?"
So he did dig up the bodies.
And he, in fact, he remembered later in his life
when they were digging up the bodies,
opening one grave that had two heads and one body.
And that was a fun--
- Wow. - One memory for him.
And he said some of them were just skeletons
loose in the ground.
Some of them, like, crumpled apart.
- He was digging them up personally.
- He was there overseeing it,
and other people under him were digging them up.
- Two heads, one body.
- Yeah.
We don't know he made the stone circle.
We just know he dug up the body.
- It sounds like he just littered some gravestones.
- He just dug up the--
- The story is losing the bodies in fact.
- A tree grew and turned them into a perfect circle.
It's, like, a naturally, like, a natural phenomenon.
Some poor person, probably a woman,
came after us and said,
"Hey, it would look nice if we did this."
And then everyone's gone,
"Oh, it was Tom Hardy, didn't it?"
- That's classic, Tom.
- Yeah.
- Can I, guys?
- How interesting.
- Can I give you guys a quiz?
- Oh, yeah. - Sure.
- Okay, so we all know Tom's Hardy,
and we all know about Kiss Me Hardy.
- Yeah.
- And we all know about Tom Hardy, the actor.
- So, which Tom Hardy--
I've renamed these headlines,
so they'll all say Tom Hardy,
so that's not a clue, right?
Which Tom Hardy are these about?
- Yeah. - Okay?
Goldfish removed from Tom Hardy pond to protect nutes.
- Which Hardy is that about?
- The actor.
- Author.
- Author. - Author.
- You're both right.
Sorry, Dan.
- I was a bit loose calling him Tom.
- I've changed the headlines.
I've changed the headlines,
so they all say Tom Hardy,
so that's not to avoid being a clue.
- I see, sorry. - Because people only say
Tom was or Tom. - Yeah.
- Tom Hardy fuels James Bond rumours.
(all laughing)
- Well, no, actually, yeah.
Let's go back to when the first James Bond was written.
Let's do the dates a lot.
- Fleming was a port bearer at the order, too,
so I'm locking that in.
- Author.
- No, I'm so sorry, Dan.
That's about the actor Tom Hardy.
Last one.
Tom Hardy wins Jiu Jitsu contest in Milton Keynes.
(all laughing)
- I don't think it's any of them.
That's just a different bloke.
- No, it's the actor.
He, last year, he just turned up in Milton Keynes.
The Brazilian Jiu Jitsu Open Championship
held at a school in Milton Keynes
and kicked everyone's ass.
He won.
He was champion in his--
- Held at a school, but it was adults.
(all laughing)
- He was turned up and going,
"This should be important to God."
- He absolutely went through year eight
like a dose of salt.
No, he has a blue belt in Jiu Jitsu
and just destroyed everyone.
Cause it's quite intimidating if you turn up
and see Tom Hardy, you know,
- Yeah, no shit.
- being mad at Max.
- Are you allowed to just wander in?
Surely you have to have entered in advance.
- He did enter in advance.
- He registered.
- Oh, he registered, okay.
- He just registered like a normal person, you know.
- And I bet someone who's worked at that school
who was organising the whole thing,
read it and went, "It won't be that Tom Hardy."
(all laughing)
- He was like, "Fuck, yeah."
- Terrifying.
- Do you know, I just want to bring up
the second wife very quickly, Florence Dugdale.
So that was her name.
She was an author herself, published author.
And there was, as you say, huge age gap.
Apparently they got on really well though,
according to friends who also said
that the first wife and Thomas didn't get on.
She wrote a biography of him and he didn't burn it.
It was called "The Early Life."
- Is that 'cause he died?
- No, it's 'cause it turns out he actually wrote it
mostly himself and it was published under her name.
- Oh my God.
- That's the sort of thing you do
if your first wife released a book saying,
"You're a piece of shit."
And then you go, "Hmm, how can I protect my reputation here?"
(all laughing)
- Isn't that astonishing?
- That's really, and has that survived?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Because a lot of stuff didn't.
A lot of stuff was burnt.
A lot of his correspondence was burned
almost immediately after his death,
which has really vexed a lot of biographers, obviously,
because so much burning of books
went on back in the day, didn't it?
Like they were constantly burning books.
So he burned most of his own diaries, I think,
as well as burning his wife's diaries.
She burned, like his second wife,
burned the courtship letters between him and his first,
or I think maybe his first,
and everyone was burning letters and books
left around center.
Why don't we do this anymore?
- I do.
(all laughing)
I do, I'm so fine.
So many letters on this and I'm like,
"All of your wife's diaries."
But maybe they'll go in the fire.
- There you were criticizing my carbon footprint.
(all laughing)
- Burning every book he's ever read.
Paul Bearers, obviously,
celebrity Paul Bearers, very cool.
- Oh yeah.
- There's a modern version of it, I'd say,
of having lots of, well, not famous people being Paul Bearers,
but something cool to do, which is Tupac.
You know, there's about Tupac in "Tupac's Dead."
Then Tupac's gang members smoked his ashes.
- Oh! - No way!
- Yeah, as was requested in a Tupac lyric,
he said in the lyric, "When I die, smoke my ashes," basically,
in slightly different words that I won't use.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I've got a question.
- Yeah?
- How can you smoke them if they're already ashes?
- Well, exactly. - You know what I mean?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Like, he wasn't made of tobacco.
- Well, I did say smoke his remains,
but I'm doubting there's like an arm.
(all laughing)
- Did they smoke the ashes?
- You did a very big fire pipe to get an arm into, wouldn't you?
- Yeah.
- No, what was ashes?
I don't know, I guess they're just...
- You just shove it in with, like,
- Mix it in with some tobacco, love.
- Mix it in, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And all the things. - And other things, yeah.
- Yeah, I don't think it was tobacco.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the UK literally have fashion police.
Quite literally.
- That speaks a guy who's just been arrested
for that choice of hoodie.
- So it turns out that one of the things,
there's a lot of things that happen
within police work with forensics,
and a very important bit of it
is trying to identify when a body might,
you know, if you find a body,
how long has it been there?
Diagnosing all that stuff.
And one of the things that might help you with that
is the clothing that the person is wearing.
And so there's this fashion historian called Amber Bouchard,
and she basically goes around,
and she worked for Beyond Retro,
and she was a fashion historian.
She liked to find where products were coming from,
at what point they were using certain materials and so on.
And there was a police forensic investigator
who saw what she was doing after hearing her
on a Radio 4 show and thought,
"I wonder if that's gonna be interesting for me
"in terms of trying to diagnose how all the body is,
"or just give us a bit more detail."
So that's what she does.
She goes around for the UK police.
She'll go to a murder scene,
and she'll look at the exact fabric that they're wearing.
And obviously, as we know, like, you know,
if you were gonna die today,
you might be wearing old clothes from--
- I was gonna say, me and Andy gonna look like
we're from the '50s,
because we just have never bought new clothes for ourselves.
- Exactly, yeah.
That's the issue, right?
- But I suppose it just plays into a bigger picture
of what they're doing.
So there's one story, which is a bit upsetting,
but an old lady passed away
and they found a body that was wrapped up in a bra,
and she was able to look at the bra
and work out exactly when the bra was from
to be able to say,
"So it must have been this year that the body was in there."
And she does it, by the way.
There's a lot of amazing archives of clothing,
and one big one is M&S have a massive archive of clothing
that she can look through and find the history of items,
'cause a lot of Brits are gonna be dying in M&S clothing.
Sorry, just a quick--
- I hope to one day, I hope to.
(laughing)
Actually, I don't mind when the day comes,
as long as I'm in my trusty M&S.
- That's what people say, isn't it?
Yeah, it's like, people often,
how they wanna die, they often say,
"In my sleep, or in my M&S cookbook."
(laughing)
He does fine with me.
- Yeah, and we should add that this is also not a sponsor
that we're doing right now, yeah.
- I reckon there's certain items of clothing
where I could tell you when that person dies.
- Oh, yeah.
- Buried in a Von Dutch cap, I'm going 2001.
Straight away, Liv's strong band.
Come on, you're getting a five-year period.
- Yeah, okay.
- What about the cycles of fashion, though, every 30 years?
It could always be the B, like, you know,
it was last year or 31 years ago.
- So it has to be, yeah,
so it has to be something that hasn't yet come back.
- Okay, so you know--
- Yes, right.
- Oh, it's not retro.
It's like, white guy, dead in a Wu Tang 36 chambers top.
- Sure.
- '97, '98.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
- So, well, I've always won flares.
Sometimes, I would have confused the hell out of police,
at other times, it's perfectly acceptable.
- I don't know what phase we're at now.
Are we in a flares phase?
- Yeah, we are, actually.
- We are. - Oh, there we go.
- I think often she just goes,
"Wow, what we have here is a time traveler."
(all laugh)
- I recruited a bit of help by this.
I wrote to an expert.
Val McDermid, the author, a.k.a. Queen of Crime.
- Holy shit, that's a clang.
We thought the old curling team had a clang earlier.
- Unnamed curling team.
(all laugh)
- No, I just, I know her very slightly,
and I just asked her about this kind of stuff.
She's written a book, as well as all her novels.
She's written a book about forensics.
- Oh, all right.
- And she said that natural fabrics decay when you're buried.
As in buried in the woods, you know,
that kind of thing, if you've been killed.
But labels are usually man-made fibers,
so they survive, right?
So they can provide a clue
if it's foreign label or a designer label or whatever.
So she says, "If you're planning a murder,
"go for mass produced cotton and snip those labels
"when it comes to dressing your corpse."
(all laugh)
- It's nice, very helpful.
- Yeah. - All right.
- Thank you, Val. - Yeah.
- That's good, 'cause you can tell
how big the person was,
even if the whole body's disintegrated, right?
You can still be like, "Size eight, size 14."
- This does feel like this story feels most like,
you know, Netflix are on the phone buying the rights
to this series, surely, of like the person
who solves crimes based on labels you're wearing.
- Oh, yeah. - Yeah.
- Sorry, I thought you meant buying the rights
to this podcast, which is so far.
(all laugh)
- They are available. - They are available, yeah.
- And she's cool.
Amber, if you see a photo of her,
she dresses like someone from Beyond Retro would, right?
Like she's got like old school clothing.
She looks like she could be
in a sort of Agatha Christie view.
- She'd be a vintage detective.
What could we call it?
- What, the series?
- Yeah, series called--
- "Drop Dead Gorgeous."
- Yes. - "Dressed to Kill."
- Brilliant. - Oh, yes.
- Yeah, yeah. - Yeah.
- All right, we've got two films.
(all laugh)
- Have you heard about this thing
of the principle of interchange
or the principle of transference?
So one of the fathers of forensics
was a Frenchman called Edmund Lockhart in Leon,
and his basic theory is that any two objects interacting
will leave a trace.
So when you commit a crime,
you will leave something behind that wasn't there before,
like a bullet in a person,
and you will take away something
that was there originally, right?
So that's just like the founding principle.
So all you have to do is work hard to find those.
- Well, so that you'll take away
like a bit of dust or something.
It's not like you're always--
- Exactly, yeah, or a fiber on your shirt.
- No, it's super near. - Whatever.
- Yeah, no.
- It's always gone off the finger.
- Yeah, yeah.
But this, now we are so good
that that sometimes makes things difficult
for forensics people.
So for example, if I hug Rhys,
and then I am murdered,
Rhys will have my DNA,
or sorry, my body's tested,
it'll have DNA from Rhys's clothes on it,
despite the fact he had nothing to do with it.
So that suddenly means that he might have to be questioned
or involved or whatever it is.
So that's the extent to which forensics
is advanced these days.
It's so good now.
You can recreate so much stuff.
- Yeah, so surely it's got to the point where it's so good.
Now the list of suspects is way too big
and makes this way harder.
So it's defeated, it's sort of eaten itself.
- It's sort of, yeah, like those detective clothes,
room things, it's only like,
it's 5,000 people going to the room.
- Yeah, probably all of them are just like,
"Oh, you need it."
(all laughing)
- It's obviously they've got good methods
to winnow it down.
- Yeah, sure.
- And you'd probably be released with that charge
after a day or two, Rhys, but--
- I don't know, I'll give up a voice.
(all laughing)
I've got those sort of eyes.
- The motive's there.
You've spent two hours with him now, so,
we'd all understand.
- I would be cool.
I mean, I've got, I've read about how cat hair
is like one of the main things, right?
Like murderers who have cats.
Getting caught quite quickly, because if anyone,
if any of you've got a cat, you know,
that you basically constantly have cat hair on you.
- Right, right.
- And so everywhere you go, you're just,
you're molting like a cat and cat hair is coming off.
- But then--
- And I have a ginger cat, so, you know,
that's just the most visible one, basically.
- But do police now go around, someone's murdered?
Are they now going around everyone's house,
testing not only other people in the house,
but their cats as well?
You're getting off the door, say.
- Maybe, maybe that's a double match.
You've got you and your cat.
- Right, we're looking for a British short hair.
Great fair, yeah.
- Do you know you can catch people by different prints
that aren't fingerprints, various other prints.
- Tongue?
- So, tongue prints are the thing you could,
'cause that's individual, although I'm not sure
how many people lick the murder scene before leaving.
- Oh, you said tongue, I thought I heard time,
which time prints would be as well?
- Time prints.
- Time print, do you leave a time print?
- Yeah, if you, your mobile phone leaves a signal.
- Oh, yeah, of course. - That's a lot of modern
detective work. - Is that a time print?
Did he leave a time print?
- Well, I thought that's what Rie said
and I was just trying to help.
- It's cool, I like the sound of, yes.
- And if you punch in and out,
like you would at a work factory, for every murder,
you'd let some of the time stand,
but you know, there's no way they have to check
into a building to find a record, you know what I mean.
- There's the comments book on the way out.
(all laughing)
- Died lovely, really easy to kill, thank you.
- He had the two star review, that's terrible.
- That's a real crime, crime goes, there's a lovely hotel.
- None of this is, is what I said.
- Prints. - Prints, glove prints.
So-- - Wow, what?
That's the whole point of gloves, isn't it?
- Yeah, that's brilliant, this context.
- No, right, first of all, you hugged Andy on the way in
and you're wearing gloves, none of this can work, Rie's.
So, yeah, people can take glove prints
and because people think what you guys think,
which is that wearing gloves, I'm safe,
they leave a lot more, they're much more cavalier
than they are with fingerprints.
But now there are various police forces
that have made databases of glove prints,
so if they can match it to another glove print
found at a different place,
then they'll know that it's the same person.
- Just fibres that come off the gloves or?
- Yeah, from the fibres that come off the glove
and the pattern that the glove makes on,
you know, it'll make an imprint and even--
- That's so clever.
- And it's even, it doesn't matter if it's the same
brand of glove that I'm wearing compared to you, Andy,
because I'll be doing different things with my glove
to what you're doing with your glove
and so it'll wear in a different way.
- Stop it, how interesting.
- It's absolutely nuts, what can be done.
- Ear prints, someone was caught in France
by their ear prints 'cause they'd been listening up
against the keyholes of lots of student halls doors.
- Wow.
- That's incredible.
- That's amazing.
- 'Cause that, yeah, footprint or shoe prints,
I imagine, as well, would be a thing.
You would see a size 12 Adidas,
you might have certain muds and stuff that you can,
yeah, but ear print, that's like, yeah, eyebrow print
or, that's so neat.
- Can we say you can get a bum print?
- What do you mean get a, what, do you sit on a photograph?
- But don't you, you have a bum print.
I just wonder, I mean, I just wonder
if that's what's been used.
- Sorry, everyone's-
- Well, you're sorry, you're not trying to,
you mean if you put, if you the murderer
would put their bear off or something at the scene,
they could go, oh, we know who the bum that is.
- Exactly.
- It's a classic calling card for a lot of people.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's the police line up for those.
- Yeah, turn around.
- An amazing sight.
(laughing)
Can bum number two move around then, please?
Have you, this is a very cool thing.
Have you had a forensic ecology?
- Forensic ecology.
- This is a, I read an interview
with a woman called Rosie Everett.
She uses materials found in the natural world
to solve crimes, right?
So, specifically micro fossils.
- Oh.
- There are these things called diatoms.
We've spoken about them, I think ages ago.
Basically, they're microscopic single cell algae
and she can use these, the presence of these
to come up with a profile of the soil in an area
which can then solve a crime.
So, there was, there's a castle
in Cheshire called Beast and Castle, right?
Which is a protected area.
And there were some metal detectorists,
night hawks, dirt sharks who'd gone and nicked
at like bronze age artifacts from the soil around there.
And when they caught, they just say,
oh, we found them somewhere else.
Can't prove anything, you know.
Except for Rosie Everett, who came up with the,
a profile of the soil based on the microscopic algae
found there and proved that's the soil
they've been taken from.
- Oh.
- What, looked at the objects and went,
hey, this soil's the same.
- Yeah, there was a bit of soil found on the bronze age
artifacts they'd nicked from there.
And there was a bit of soil around the castle.
Like, just so difficult.
- Wasn't one of the ways they caught Ian Huntley
from nettle disturbance.
- Really?
- So nettles, he trampled nettles
that meant that they were now growing outwards
in a way they don't naturally.
That sort of proved that he was there
in the woods at that time or something.
- Well, so it's next generation nettles
still affected by the previous?
- Yeah, it's like months later they had grown
in a certain like, 'cause they would've been,
and then they went out instead of up.
- Yeah.
- Or something like that.
They was like, yeah.
- That's incredible.
- That's mad.
And slightly less, I'll just quickly tell you,
a slightly less technologically advanced one
of this guy I read about who got caught
doing a crime after he got the crime scene
very in a lot of detail tattooed on his chest.
- Oh, gosh.
(laughing)
- So he literally, it was like,
he'd like murdered someone outside a liquor store
or something.
And so he got the liquor store like a painting
on his chest with him doing the murder.
- No, no.
- And above it he says the name of his gang,
which was Rivera, he said Rivera kills above it.
And it was like a revenge killing.
And he had that on his chest.
And one day the police were just like,
flicking through a book of gang tattoos apparently.
(laughing)
And they were like, wait, that's that liquor store.
We've been trying to figure out where that guy,
who killed that guy.
That's that guy killed that guy.
And then he was just trying to then.
- That's brilliant.
We've spoken about in the past how the Yakuza
would be busted because they all have
very individualistic tattoos.
And if they're on the run,
they might show up on Instagram,
sort of like, you know, topless.
- Yeah.
- And you'll be like, hey, that's him, that's the guy.
Like tattoo spotting is a big way of busting criminals.
Did you say your one, Andy, happened in Beeston?
- Yeah.
- Well, that was when we did our first book of the year.
There was a crime there committed,
which was thousands of bees were stolen from Beeston.
I wonder if she can solve that crime now
using this new technology.
- Wow.
- I just, I'd sort of forgotten that,
but as soon as you said we'd had it in our book,
I thought we'd all have been a story about bees,
won't it?
(laughing)
That's the level we operate at.
- We put it on the back.
It's Sue, it's our burp.
That was our leading fact.
- Of the burp.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that parents of newborn penguins
take thousands of naps per day.
- Lazy.
- Absolutely slackers.
- Yeah.
- And I'm taking very short naps.
These are chin strap penguins.
So they live in the Antarctic and around the South Pacific.
And they, they were scientists studying them recently
on King George Island,
and they found that they nap over 10,000 times a day,
but they only nap for about four seconds at a time
on average.
(laughing)
But still, it gets them something.
And I mean, they managed to tot up 11 hours of sleep a day.
- That's insane.
- Amazing.
- Which is a lot less.
- It's basically really blinking.
It's basically, every time they blink,
they do it for four seconds and fall asleep.
- Yeah.
- It's like when you fall asleep at the cinema
or the theater, you know?
And you have that kind of,
(gagging)
- Yeah, or train them, jolt.
- Yeah, yeah.
I've never left one of those occasions
feeling noticeably rested.
- No.
- Despite doing that kind of semi-sleep.
- But I wonder if you had a thousand of them.
- Yeah, true.
- Yeah.
- You just haven't been to a long enough play.
- Oh, I'm sorry.
- You know how you get those sort of rise and grind
influences these days.
So all about, you know, getting up at five AM,
doing a gratitude journal.
You've got to like circadian rhythm
and all that sort of stuff.
And you've got to get sunlight before coffee and all this.
I mean, do you think if they read this pretty soon,
everyone would be like, no, no, no, don't go to bed.
Just stand there.
(laughing)
- Just a long blink.
- And then four seconds at a time.
And you just feel perfect.
You'd say you'll never sleep.
- Rejuvenate it.
- Hustle never sleeps.
(laughing)
- It'll become a thing.
And so yeah, and they go into deep sleep,
which I'm not sure we're very good at doing
within four seconds,
but they looked at their brainwaves.
- Wow.
- Really?
- Yeah, so it was quite difficult.
- It's like a bungee jump into sleep and then back.
- Yeah.
- You just feel so rapid to get there.
- Yeah, deep sleep.
- But yeah, they go into slow wave sleep.
They really rigged them up these penguins.
It's amazing they could sleep at all.
There was this researcher, Wong Young Lee,
who I think was leading the research.
You said it was exhausting for them
'cause they had to catch 14 penguins
and they had to get equipment on their brains
to measure their brain activity.
And then they had to get accelerometers to see how fast,
to like record their muscle movements,
see how fast their muscles are moving and their positions.
And then they filmed like whether their heads start nodding
and then jumping again.
- So is it possible that the penguins actually
sleep completely normally,
but when they're manipulated by scientists,
they can't sleep at all?
- I think so.
They did say this is probably serving the purpose
of meaning that they can guard their young.
So it's when they guard their newborn children
because one parent will be off getting food,
the other parent has to look after the kid.
So it's like, so you never sleep for so long
that the kid can get in trouble.
It's like having a baby monitor.
And they said it's probably 'cause of that,
but it could also be because you know penguins,
when they're looking after their young,
they hang out in these massive groups
of just thousands of them and it's really loud and busy.
Like these researchers said we couldn't sleep
'cause it was just so hectic there 'cause so many penguins.
- These researchers are complaining a lot
about their own sleep.
I have to say, 'cause someone has to study
about something else.
(laughing)
- Four seconds, I wish.
But they said it could just be that the penguins
can't sleep for longer than that.
They might be able to sleep eight hours in a row,
but it's just that they've been woken up
every four seconds 'cause it's so noisy and bustling.
- Right.
It is crazy.
There are lots of animals in the world
that do, when they've had a baby,
are forced into a position of just being awake.
Like dolphins, for example, are awake for like a month,
a full month.
They just can't go to sleep
'cause their baby dolphins can't sleep.
So they're just awake the whole time.
- For a month.
- Yeah, for a month.
And they basically, they just have to be awake
and with them, part of the dolphin not being asleep
as a baby, as they keep movement,
they're building up blubber,
they're building up all the things
that they need to make them into a bigger dolphin.
That's like, and then after like a month or so,
they all start sleeping again.
But the mum is just solidly awake.
- But don't they do the half of their brains at a time thing?
- So I'm not sure that, that's what I tried to find out,
but I couldn't find anything that said
they go to half asleep.
'Cause yes, dolphins shut half their brain asleep.
- Yeah.
- As far as I could see, that wasn't part of any of the--
- They don't sleep at all, they're not either half.
- Yeah.
- Blimey.
- I don't know about all bears,
but don't polar bears do a similar thing
where they basically just attach the children
to them for the whole time.
So the children don't really walk around following them.
Like you see elephants, you see them following
and stuff like that, but polar bears is just like,
you see a picture of a new mum in the polar bear community,
there's just kids just like strapped.
- And then do they have a walk on a swing to them, is it?
- They're just like clinging on.
I think they, yeah, I don't think they have papoos.
(laughing)
But they're just like grabbing hold of them
and they just have to walk around with that
and then just do everything from there
until they like sit down again.
- That's so crazy.
- 'Cause they just don't walk.
- Tassels, it's got a lot of baby tassels.
- You know, elephant seals.
- Yes, which is a huge, great, massive big things.
We got Santa fact, actually, by Victoria Pierdadi.
So thank you for that, Victoria.
Which is that sleeping elephant seals,
they fall through the sea as they nap.
So they are mammals, they do not have gills.
They can last up to about half an hour underwater,
but sometimes they will just nap.
And it seems like they just spiral downward
through the water asleep.
- Wow.
- That happens in my brain quite a lot.
We've got to get to sleep.
You know, when you jolt away
'cause you felt like you were falling.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Well imagine if you woke up
and you had actually jolted into the sea.
(laughing)
- 'Cause it is fast, they drop 400 meters in 10 minutes.
Which if you can, that's like,
we're talking the highest buildings in the world.
That's like the full height of them, almost.
And it takes quite a long time.
You know, if you go to one of those skyscrapers,
the lift takes about that long.
- Yeah. - Sometimes.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So they're going that fast.
- Exactly.
If you wake up when you've only got three minutes
of oxygen left, that's presumably quite stressful.
- I would have thought so, yeah.
- What's the protocol?
What do they do?
- You can't really do that dancing
of faking that you weren't asleep on the sofa
during a Sunday afternoon movie.
You know, dads will always be like,
"I was asleep, I'm watching, I'm watching."
- I'm resting my eyes.
- Dad, you're at the bottom of the ocean.
(laughing)
- Does anyone, have you ever met a penguin?
- Oh.
- 'Cause I've got another clack.
- Here we go, here we go.
Which of your winter sports were you taking part in
with the Olympic team?
- Well, I did do the skeleton,
which is basically how penguins travel.
- Oh, yes.
- Did you?
- They go, you know, it's like the head first one.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Holding through the, yeah.
- That looks terrifying.
- Well, I did it, they train on just, on a track.
So just on wheels on track rather than on ice.
- Right.
- And this is the context where,
so there were penguins doing penguins.
- No, I did meet penguins actually.
- Oh, this is just a bracketed anecdote.
- But I did, yeah, yeah, because you mentioned
the Winter Olympics and that was penguin adjacent.
I met a penguin in Australia actually.
- Okay, right.
- Man, I can't, I was a child, there are photos of it,
but I'm trying to get my head around what it was,
because from memory it was like in our hotel,
like where the various pools were,
there was different pools,
but it was presented in a sort of like,
go over to this section,
it was like a quite kid-friendly hotel,
'cause like this section is meant to be the Arctic or whatever.
And then in between two of these pools on the walkway
were just like this bit where these penguins were.
- Right.
- And they would do like feedings at a certain time
every day, and you could go and hang out.
And then I was a penguin of my favorite animal.
I was obsessed with penguins as a kid.
Penguins is actually one of the many nicknames
I tried to start for myself as a child.
(laughing)
- That's a child, you were 23, weren't you?
- That's a child in some communities.
And then like I got picked as the volunteer
for this sort of penguin feeding.
And so I was like doing the whole,
you know, I was chucking the fish.
- Wow, that's great.
- And I shook his fin.
- Shook the penguin fin.
- What do they have there?
- Wing, wing, wing, yeah, wing.
Shook his wing, fin.
- Shook his fin, yeah.
- Shook his wing, yeah.
- That's lovely.
That's very cool.
- And now your DNA is on that penguin.
And if it's murdered.
- If that penguin goes missing, I'm absolutely shocked.
My cat's also a suspect
because there's definitely cat hair on that penguin's hand.
- Have you seen the penguins at the zoo, the London Zoo?
- No.
- Oh, well, I recommend.
Is there any nearest penguin to us geographically?
I don't think you can meet them as far as I'm aware.
There was something about them, wasn't there, though?
There was something, isn't there, isn't there enclosure?
It's the only grade two listed.
- Oh yes, it's got that amazing
we talked about before.
- I was in a Harry Styles video.
- Is it?
- I think that rings a bell.
- I can't get this from different angles.
- That enclosure that is grade two listed
but that spiral thing in the middle
is where the as it was video is filmed.
- Has it?
- He's like stood on that thing
and all these women are sort of circling.
- Right.
- Are they dressed as penguins?
- No, they're wearing tuxedos.
- I wonder what they did with the penguins
when they were filming that video.
- I know, right?
I think a lot of people on the internet
were wondering that as well.
I mean, supposedly it's just a time
when they weren't using it.
- How can they not be using their main home
in enclosure?
- The album is called Harry's House.
So it does feel like you're marching and we're like,
this is Harry's House, let's get out.
(laughing)
- Something that sleeps quite weirdly is spiders.
And they actually are unique in the animal world, I think,
in that they don't have the right body clock.
And they're the only things we know about
that don't have the right body clock.
So you know, we're all basically 24 hour body clock,
although sometimes when people go and live in caves,
they sort of stretch to 25 hours or 23 or whatever.
But mostly we-
- So there was such a dismissive role of the air,
like there's a thing that's personally inconvenient
to you on more than one occasion.
- Those caves are always late.
(laughing)
- The man is waiting outside the table for two.
God's sake.
(laughing)
- Time, it's a cadian with my arse.
- Yeah.
- So mostly even bacteria operate on a 24 hour body clock,
but spiders don't.
And we don't really know why except that they're fucked up.
So they have the shortest body clocks ever known.
Some spiders have been found to have 17 hour body clocks.
But this should really mess with them
because so spiders left their own devices.
And these are specifically trash line orb weavers,
which sounds-
- Slam.
- Yeah.
- I mean, rows of it or what?
(laughing)
- They're actually called that
'cause they hide in their webs in a pile of crap.
So they like will put dead bodies and feces and dirt
in their web and then they hide amongst it.
- Wow.
It's not dissimilar to my room.
(laughing)
- And that's how you catch flies.
Anyway, they need to wake up at night
and get super super active in the dark.
And they spin their webs at nighttime.
And they erect this big pile of trash to live in.
And then in the daytime, spiders fall asleep still,
which is why when you see them in daylight,
they're usually just motionless.
And then they go nuts at night in the dark.
But it turns out if you subject a spider to full darkness,
it starts waking up and weaving its web,
web many hours before night would actually fall.
So it wakes up like on the 17 hour mark
rather than on the 24 hour mark.
So that means they're constantly kind of jet lagged, right?
- Right.
- They're constantly, their bodies are going,
hey, we've got to wake up now.
And then it's like, no, no, no, you've got to stay asleep
'cause it's not night yet.
And then night comes and then they have to go to sleep
and they're wide awake.
But they manage to just reset themselves every day.
- Do they get cranky?
- Well, maybe that's why they're such bastards.
And they're always eating each other
and hanging out in the corner of the room
to deliberately scaring people.
- Oh, I feel for them.
That sounds very rough.
- Doesn't it?
- But apparently you can't catch up on sleep anyway, right?
There's a myth, the whole idea of like,
I only got six hours sleep last night
so I'm going to now have 10 hours sleep or whatever.
It's a myth.
- Is that a myth?
- You're better off just having seven or eight every time.
So you can't, it's impossible to catch up on sleep.
- What, you'll always be a bit more tired?
- No, you just don't, yeah, so I don't mean,
it's impossible to go, this economy,
it's bloody impossible to catch up on sleep.
I just mean that it actually makes it worse.
- Really?
- So it's like, it's not a cult or tally
for the week where you're trying to get us.
It's like, no, just every day try and get seven or eight.
- Oh, I did not know how to improve it with ten.
- 'Cause the way to avoid being underslept
is then just have seven or eight hours, rather than-
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, 'cause I assumed it was the other thing.
- Me too.
- That there's a ratchet and it only gets worse for your life.
- Exactly, but it's not like there's a certain amount
of hours you must sleep in your life.
And if you're not getting to the total,
like you're filling it in like one of those thermometers
and at school when you're trying to get donations.
- Well, you can actually trick yourself
into thinking you've had more sleep, can't you?
Remember we did that thing about the placebo sleep
experiment that was done in America
where they told people that they'd had more sleep
than they actually had and they performed better in tasks.
- I always use this as a life hack
to try and tell myself every morning
I've had loads of sleep if I haven't.
- Do you?
- It hasn't worked yet, yeah.
- All right.
- You need someone else to tell you that.
In order for you to actually believe it, right?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause it was work.
- 'Cause you know what, yeah.
- But how can you ever do that?
'Cause if you're employing someone to do that,
you would also know.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- It's like, if your phone told you, I'd believe it.
- Yeah, those apps sleep apps should just lie.
- Exactly, they should just lie.
- And everyone gets so much more done.
- Maybe they are lying.
'Cause they wouldn't tell us, would they?
'Cause that defeats the object.
So perhaps that's what they're--
- I bet if you have it and you work for the app,
it always tells you that you got loads of sleep.
- Yeah.
- Just so that you're more productive in the day.
For everyone else, I think, do what you want.
And if they know from your phone
that you work for a rival app--
- Yeah, if you work for someone--
(all laughing)
- They just go, "Sorry, mate, that was terrible."
You're knackered.
(all laughing)
You look awful.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media sites.
I'm on Instagram, on @Shrieberland.
Andy?
- On Twitter, @AndyHunterM.
- Penguin.
(all laughing)
- @Penguin.
- And all the forums.
And @ReaceJamesy on Instagram.
- Yep, or if you wanna get through to us as a group,
where can they go, Anna?
- You can go to @NoSuchThing on Twitter,
or you can email podcast@QI.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our website,
which is NoSuchThingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there,
as well as links to Club Fish
and various other bits of merch.
Do check it out.
Otherwise, just come back again next week,
and we'll be here with another episode,
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)