- Oh, yeah.
- [speaking in foreign language]
[theme music]
- Hello and welcome to No Such Things A Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from the queue.
I offer this in Covent Garden.
My name is Anna and I am here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Anne Miller.
Once again, we've gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite maps that we found in the last seven days
and in no particular order.
Here we go, starting with you, James.
- My fact this week is that Anna wants to be like
with Donna and known by just one name.
[laughing]
- What is that all about?
- Did I, I couldn't work out if normally we do two names
or one side mix it up?
- I thought it was casual and friendly.
Like, don't enough podcast now.
- I thought it was power mad.
[laughing]
- I thought it was maybe that you could work out
to pronounce your old surname.
[laughing]
- It might have been that dance confused me over the years.
- I'd like to be known as Lightning from now
and I'm this podcast, please.
- All right, that's fine.
- You've already got three calls.
- So I'll introduce you all again.
My name is Anna and I'm joined by Lightning, James and Anne.
[laughing]
- I'm followed.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 1758,
there were two camels on display in London,
one with a single hump and one with two humps.
They were advertised as the surprising camel
and the wonderful camel.
[laughing]
- Yeah, which was it?
- I think the one with a single hump was surprising
and the one with two humps was wonderful.
- I think they're all surprising to start off with.
- Yeah, I agree.
- And then a difference in humps is also surprising.
So I think they're both surprising.
- Are they?
- I think it was wonderful.
- Yeah. - Let's not do camels down there.
- I agree with Lightning.
[laughing]
I read this in the London Review of Books
and it was a review of a book called "Managerie"
by Caroline Griggsson.
I haven't read that book yet, but I am going to read it
'cause it looks amazing.
There's some really good facts in that review.
- I read a really good book about the history of London
and zoo a couple of years ago.
My favorite thing in the whole book was that London zoo
used to be at the Tower of London
and when it was there, you could get in for free
if you brought a dog or a cat to feed to the lions.
- Nice.
Was it entry for one or was it for a family?
Or did you have to bring kittens
if you wanted your children to go and see the lions?
- I think if you were bringing a family,
you had to bring a surprising camel.
[laughing]
- So one other thing that I saw 'cause yeah,
that book does look incredible, doesn't it?
And one other thing that I really like that she spotted
is that this was in the age where it was very fashionable
if you're a wealthy person to bring
back lots of exotic animals from various places
or descend agents off to get them
and apparently one London merchant asked his agent
to send him two or three apes,
but he forgot the "R" on "Or"
and so he was delivered 203 apes.
[laughing]
- Where did he put them?
- I don't know.
Apparently the first cargo of "80 apes" arrived
when the legs are promising them more.
[laughing]
- There was one other thing in there
that George the Fourth had a giraffe at Windsor
and the giraffe didn't flourish very well
because it was in Windsor
and not where it's supposed to live in Africa.
- Which is a Sandriggum.
[laughing]
- And when it got sick, they put it down to sympathy
for the King's gout and load of peon nonsense.
- sympathy for the gout, that's outrageous.
- You can say that or in an alternative fact universe,
you can say that maybe it was feeling sad
'cause the King was sad.
- Maybe it was sad.
- Do you know they have camel wrestling festivals
in Turkey?
- Is that camel's wrestling against each other?
- It is camel's wrestling against each other.
Yeah.
- But how does a camel wrestle?
- Yeah, they're on all fours.
- Well, with great difficulty.
- Yeah.
- It's the odd joke.
They, I don't know if they do it with camels,
but often they do it by showing
the two competence, a sexy lady insert animal here.
So they might bring on a sexy lady camel
and then remove it and then the two blokes remaining
say, "Well, I want it, well, I want it."
And little did they know they're not gonna get it.
- Do you know what constitutes a beautiful camel
since you mentioned a sexy lady?
- Long eyelashes.
- Yeah, of course, the eyelashes.
- They do, have lots of wine lashes.
Although maybe in the camel world
'cause that's so common then short eyelashes,
lovely lady humps.
[laughing]
So I've been reading about Omar lately
'cause we're researching for the O series
when they have camel beauty contests in Oman.
And they're put on by the government
and it's a milking and beauty contest.
And a beautiful camel apparently should have
a well-proportioned body and face,
a long garib, which is the area between the hump and the neck,
a clear and huge hump.
[laughing]
It needs to have...
- This was written by men, wasn't it?
[laughing]
- Firm ears and pouty lips, big whiskers,
and a fur shimmer.
- Right.
- Yeah, and he's good posture and it needs to be huge.
[laughing]
- That kind of makes sense, all that stuff.
- That does sounds quite attractive, isn't it?
- Is it of both sexes?
As in, the male camel's compete against female camels
that just has to be a beautiful camel.
- Yes.
- Really?
- Yeah.
I don't think you can tell a male a female camel apart
by looking at it.
- I bet you can.
[laughing]
- Where you're looking.
- In the 18th century, there was a collection
of camels on display on the strand,
just around the corner from us.
So it was at the toll but in in the strand,
and it belonged to a man called Richard Hepenstool.
And so that's exactly where
all the tube station used to be,
which I think is just a little bit, isn't it?
He tried to lure women in to view his herd of camels,
because at the time women were afraid
there would be a bit dirty and a bit spitty and a bit smelly.
So he advertised them as having breath as sweet as a salz,
which is weird, 'cause I didn't think a salz
is having particularly sweet breath.
But apparently, soon afterwards,
there was a journal article or a newspaper article
that reported that the ladies are especially charmed
by the camels and express great satisfaction
at the sweetness of their breath.
- See, that's quite high-risk, because I read
that when a camel spits at you,
it's also kind of bombing at you,
'cause the content of their stomach comes up as well.
- Yeah, it's not a spits, is it?
- Yeah, really?
Oh, it's just spitting, no.
Maybe that's what generated such sweet breath, though.
[laughing]
- Do you know what you could get from a camel?
- What? - If it spat at you,
a cold because one of the four common cold viruses
originated in camels.
- No.
- Really?
- And spread to humans.
- This is according to the German Center
for Infection Research.
Yeah, and there are four global human,
they're called coronaviruses,
and there are also things called rhinoviruses,
rhino-meaning nose.
- They come from rhinos.
- Yep.
[laughing]
And so one of these, one of these main ones,
apparently, has made its way over from camels.
At a long time ago, I don't know if you could still
get the same virus inhabiting both,
or whether it's come over, and now it's only humans.
Not sure. - Wow.
- Yeah, still.
- I didn't know that.
Firstly, camel can drink as many as 30 gallons of water
in 13 minutes.
Okay.
Which sounds impressive, but I worked that out,
and that's 3.25 seconds per pint,
and I can drink a pint in less than three seconds.
- Right.
- So I can drink faster than a camel.
- It's shortened long fur longs, though, isn't it?
[laughing]
- Well, I would be ahead after the first pint,
but then by probably halfway through pint two,
it might overtake me.
[laughing]
And then by pint 240, be struggling a little bit.
- So you just have to pick your race
when you're challenging the camel to the drinking contest.
- Yeah.
- So when you say to the camel, I want a drinking contest,
and he says, okay, let's do 240 pints, you know.
Well, let's start a one and see how we do that.
And don't do double our quits on the next 239.
[laughing]
- I didn't realize that there are three kinds of camel.
I thought dromedary and backtrune were the only kinds,
but the wild backtrune's probably
where I'd have different chromosomes.
- It's got three humps.
[laughing]
- Yeah, they did a DNA sequencing on it,
and it's different species.
- Well, so we've mentioned before
the Saudi Arabia imports camels from Australia,
because for me, but actually now,
have you heard that they're trying to rescue camels
from Australia?
So Australia's got too many camels,
apparently they're becoming a bit of a pest,
and they were threatening to coal.
I think 6,000 camels a few years ago,
and there was a big campaign set up
in Saudi Arabia and internet campaigns,
saying send the camels to us instead,
and we'll look after them.
- Yeah, but Australia has a million feral camels,
so 6,000 is pretty small beer, actually.
I think we've said before, they shoot them from helicopters.
- Yeah, they do, apparently one.
I think this was in the Australian.
Apparently camels in Australia,
smash water tanks destroy fences,
come up to houses and antagonize people.
[laughing]
I don't know how a camel antagonist is.
- That's just trying to blend in.
[laughing]
[upbeat music]
- Okay, onto fact number two,
and that is Andy's back.
- Lightning's factor, then you'll find.
[laughing]
Okay, my fact is that before they are launched,
London sends all its trains to Austria to be beaten up.
[laughing]
So there's this wind tunnel,
which is called the Rail-Tech Arsenal.
There's a huge article on wire about them recently,
and the article describes them as train torture chambers,
so you can put a whole 330 foot long train in this tunnel,
and then they basically simulate extreme weather conditions
and see how the carriages stand up to it,
so you can see what it'll be like for passengers,
if the train gets stuck in boiling sun,
or snow, or what a huge wind conditions are.
- That must be very confusing for the train,
because normally when he goes in the tunnel,
there's no weather.
[laughing]
- It's like a Thomas getting fucked up.
About a CIA.
[laughing]
- Are we in danger of anthropomorphizing trains
a little bit, yeah?
- Well, they shouldn't draw those faces on the front,
are they?
[laughing]
Yeah.
- They do simulate conditions that they wouldn't necessarily
come across in this country, don't they?
Don't they go down to a ridiculously low and high temperatures?
- Well, the London ones, they only test to minus 13 Celsius,
which is very, would be very low for London,
but they can set it to minus 50 Fahrenheit.
What would that be?
It's, that's cold.
- That's really cold.
[laughing]
So trains from Kazakhstan get sent there as well,
and they'll have lower temperatures, probably.
- Is everyone's trains go to this tunnel?
- Loads of Germany, America, Kazakhstan, Saudi Arabia,
they all, the article described as the Eaton College
of the train testing world.
- Well, you got beaten up already, I guess.
- You shoved the train in a toilet for a minute.
[laughing]
- You think if all the trains had to go through this tunnel,
wouldn't it make sense for all the train factories to be in Vienna?
- Yeah, I guess it would, but we've got,
I guess once you've built a train factory in Derby.
- And how do you reckon they go,
are they allowed to go on the train tracks to get to the tunnel?
Or do they have to go on a lorry because they're not pass safety?
- Yeah, I think they get voted over.
- They do, they get seven of them.
- Train some votes.
- Yeah.
- You get trains which you can put cars on, don't you?
I think we have one or two of those in Britain,
but you get them especially abroad.
- You put cars in the Urester.
- I would just love to have a car on a train, on a boat.
[laughing]
- I'd probably put like a bike rack on there as well.
- Oh, also they've got, I think it was in the news this week
or last week we've finally got a direct train service
from Britain to China.
I don't know why I say finally like we've all been
just pretty wasteful.
- We've all been stunned on the platform,
but I've been here already a minute.
- Southern.
[laughing]
- But you know, I think that's amazing.
It takes 18 days, it's a freight train,
so you have to be a piece of freight.
[laughing]
- You're a piece of freight, right?
- But it goes to Yuwu, which is in East China,
and that's the place that provides 60%
of the world's Christmas decorations.
And so I think it's like the new Santa's sleigh
and it goes direct from China to London,
but that has to actually be lifted from one track
to the other sometimes 'cause different countries
have different gauges. - Wow.
- Just on train testing,
do you know what the new measurement train is?
- No. - No?
- This is this train that's constantly in operation
around the country, and it's to test all the tracks
and it runs 125 miles an hour,
and it has various means of testing the track,
so there are no passengers on it.
It was made in response to Hatfield,
so that was the year 2000, wasn't it?
And, but it's got this amazing technology,
so it can test tracks as people would have to
at a walking pace, but at 125 miles an hour,
by for instance firing lasers at them,
and it measures contact with the rails,
and it measures the electrical supply,
and you know in some places you need to have a tilt on trains,
it checks that the tilt isn't too much,
so it won't crash into a cliff next to it or something.
And these are going running around the country at all times.
- So there are 100 mile an hour trains
going around the country firing lasers at things?
- Correct. - It's so cool.
- They're really cool, yeah.
- Have you heard about Operation Smash hit?
- Is it about 1970s pop stars?
(laughing)
It's very well-known.
No, it was an experiment that in 1984 in July,
by the British Central Electricity Generating Board,
and what they did was they got a train,
and they set it to smash at 100 miles an hour
into a flask of nuclear waste.
- What?
- A flask.
- And they televised this flask of nuclear waste.
- Yeah, so they had these new ways of storing nuclear material,
as it does material in these flasks, right?
And very strongly built flasks.
And they set one of these up on a track,
and they sort of wedged it into concrete.
And this is an orbit of testing track,
and they didn't need to use any more.
And they got an old train, they didn't need.
And they set it going at it at 100 miles an hour.
And then they put it on TV.
Millions of people watched it all around the world,
and it was to show how safe these nuclear flasks were,
'cause it didn't break.
- Oh wow. - They barely lost any of its pressure at all.
It was, and this was the final of a series of experiments
they did where they like engulfed them in flames,
these flask, and they dropped them from a big height.
- Amazing.
- And they did like all these loony tunes experiments
just to show you cannot break into these.
It was to reassure the public.
- And it's high risk though, 'cause one of those goes wrong.
Sorry we just wiped out the country.
- So France has had problems with trains lately.
And I think it's important that we smash the myth
that France is the train king of Europe
because in 2014, it's the train king of Europe.
- Yeah, come on then.
So who is the king of trains, the train king of Europe?
- Well, I think we should enter ourselves
into the contest, 'cause France is out, right?
In 2014, I think we've mentioned before,
they made those trains that are too wide
for their stations, do you remember?
- So they built, they spent billions.
- That's pretty embarrassing for the train king
of Europe to do that.
(laughing)
- So this was, they'd spent 15 billion euros
on these trains, they were too wide.
So they had to amend thousands of platforms across France
so they fitted them.
And then the following year, they made trains
that are too tall to get through tunnels
to take them into Italy.
- Wow, so who's gonna be your new train king of Europe, Hannah?
- Well, like I say, I think we're in with the shot, guys.
- I would've thought Switzerland,
but I was on a train in Switzerland last week
and it got cancelled and I had to walk across
to another platform.
- You wouldn't think that in Switzerland, would you?
- No, you wouldn't.
- For me, they were always the train prince of Europe.
(laughing)
- I have a nomination, I nominate Sweden
because I went Stockholm a few years ago
and the train there was so amazing.
It was really lovely, it felt like first class,
it was a standard class and I had a sign up saying,
"If you're more than two minutes late,
"will we fund you in full?"
- Two minutes, yeah.
- Wow.
- It wasn't the airport express train,
but I was a pretty good deal.
So I nominate Sweden for a train king.
- Okay.
Look, these nominations have all been accepted
and we'll be duty-consuming.
- I'm a train Republican.
(laughing)
I think we should put all the trains in a shed.
- We should move on quite soon.
Has anyone got anything else?
- So in Vienna, also in Austria,
they had an escalator reopening in 2015
and 14,000 people signed up to turn up
to this reopening of an escalator.
In the end, a good few hundred people turned up
and the party just got out of hand
and police had to be called to calm the crowd down.
- Did someone have to say,
"Well, that escalated quickly."
(upbeat music)
- Okay, moving on to fact number three and that is--
- And facts.
- My fact is that the oil company shell used to sell shells.
(laughing)
- And it's not a coincidence
that you know when they're selling the shells
or the two things related.
- They were different generations.
So Marcus Samuel in 1833 started
had an antiques business and started selling seashells
and then they got very popular.
So they started having these trading rates
for import export all over the world
and then his son Marcus Samuel Jr.
expanded the business, different goods
and then ended up doing oil.
- Oil is more lucrative than shell selling, isn't it?
I guess they clapped onto that.
- A bit riskier though.
- Yes. - For the world?
- Yeah, I think so.
- But also you can't power a massive industrial economy
just grinding up seashells.
(laughing)
So I'm glad.
- Actually seashells used to be used as currency.
Many, many years ago.
- What, not in Britain?
- No, before Britain existed.
Like I'm talking about thousands of years ago.
I think they were cowrie shells.
I'm going off memory a bit here
and they were used around Africa I think as currency
but then they found a new bay
which had tons and tons and tons of cowrie shells in
and then people just went and collected loads and loads
of them and ended up completely collapsing
the very early economy.
- Did you know that shell is revisiting
at shell based routes?
- Really?
- In that they are helping to return shells
to their natural environment.
So they're sponsoring this nonprofit organization
which collects shells from restaurants
and then puts them back on beaches and in areas
where oysters can cling onto them
'cause apparently oysters like to cling
onto other oyster shells.
So there you go.
They're collecting shells again.
- So I was really impressed with this fact
and I thought it was brilliant.
My husband already knew it
because there is a cart file song from the 30s about shell.
Did you notice?
- And it's married to a 101 year old man.
(laughing)
The whole song is about, in Margate,
there was a promenade and a man was selling shells
and his song comes along and turns the business around
and ends up being this big thing
about how it's a complex come out of oil
in the United League of Nations.
- From the 1930s.
- Wow. - That's kind of cool.
- He used to write songs about very different things
in the '30s.
(laughing)
- The first ever oil company was founded to harvest
just oil that was floating on water.
'Cause that was the first people knew about,
obviously you don't know oil in the ground.
- You said it. - Yeah.
- Yeah, so they sort of saw it.
It was in Pennsylvania in 1859
and they said, oh, maybe there's more oil underneath here
and they started drilling down and they struck oil.
But I think that was the first time that oil was actually struck.
- You know that just speaking of oil floating
on water, so bitumen is like, it's more solid oil.
It's made of the same stuff, but it's like more compressed.
And so I think the first ever oil kingdom
that made its money from oil was the Nabatians
who I love.
I'm never researching them for the end series.
So in the four days.
- You were always trying to shoe on the Nabatians.
In fact, Anna was actually sure for Ann Nabatians.
(laughing)
- I'm even older than Ann Sonsland.
- No, this is incredible.
They made their money 'cause they were near the Dead Sea
that so they base their kingdom around the Dead Sea.
And they noticed these lumps of bitumen floating
in the Dead Sea and they were islands of tar
and the Egyptians liked to buy tar
because they were used in the mummifying process
for embalming and they were also used
for waterproofing boats.
And so the Nabatians went and swam out to these islands
on the Dead Sea, easy to swim in it, 'cause you're flown.
And they collected this bitumen, sold it to the Egyptians
and that's how they got so rich
and that's how they had the biggest kingdom of that time.
- That is great.
- That's cool.
- That's really good.
- Love the Nabatians.
(laughing)
- Do you know someone who wrote about seashells
was Edgar Allan Poe, did he?
He wrote a book called The Conscientogist's First Book
and it was his best-selling book.
- Is it?
- Yes, and also he didn't write it really.
The original author said, can you rewrite this
and sort of remix it in a cheaper way?
But like don't tell the publishers that you're doing this
'cause the publishers didn't want the author to do this
but the author wanted to make extra money.
- Like a spark notes version of the original book.
So Poe needed the money, so he re-ordered the picture.
He wrote a preface.
One of his biographers, Jeffrey Mayer's, said,
"Pose boring, pedantic and hair-splitting preface
"was absolutely guaranteed to torment and discourage
"even the most passionately interested schoolboy."
(laughing)
- Do you know when the best time to buy petrol is?
- When your car is like 50% at least.
(laughing)
- It's the winter, actually, because petrol gets more dense
when it's colder, and so that means you get more for your money.
So if you make sure you go and buy a capetra
on a cold day, then more of it's gonna come out.
- Like how?
- 'Cause it's measured by volume.
- Like how metal expands when it's hot
so bridges change in length.
- Yeah.
- You get a different volume of petrol.
- Bridges don't expand that much in length.
- It's a bit.
- Oh, we've been on this bridge for ages.
(laughing)
Well, it's a very warm day.
- earliest oil drilling platform.
Do you guys know when it was?
Was it the Nabatians again?
(laughing)
- That was collecting, not drilling.
It was not, it was Chinese, obviously,
as all great inventions seem to be.
This is the third century BC,
and they drilled down 800 feet for oil,
and they siphoned it up through bamboo poles.
And the reason they did it was because salt was very valuable,
and they used oil to create fuel,
to create heat, to evaporate brine, so they're left salt.
And they had oil pipelines underground made of bamboo.
They were led from one like salt well to another.
- Come off it.
- Isn't that incredible?
- Bamboo pipelines.
- Apparently.
- It does not compute.
- It was in a real book,
and I'll look it up again later to check
that it wasn't crazy facts about oil by Mr. Muppet.
- Dan Schreiber.
(laughing)
So if you defecated at 650 degrees Fahrenheit
with a pressure of 3,000 pounds per square inch,
- It would burn.
- It would, and your poo would turn into oil.
So oil is made through organic material
which is pressurized,
and that would give you the same effect by doing that.
We've all had curries like that, haven't we?
- It doesn't mean we could take everyone's poo,
because it would be horrible,
but if someone collected everyone's poo
is going to put them in a hot, pressurized room.
- Yes.
- So why don't we do that?
- Well, the reason being that the energy
that you would need to create these conditions
is a lot more than the energy you would get from oil.
- It was a thermodynamics.
- It's called hydrothermal liquid faction,
and it's a report by the Pacific Northwest
National Laboratory, where they...
- Did they say the defecation thing?
- That was that of the Harkin Spin.
- That is, yeah, that is a Harkin Spin.
But they said if you put feces under these conditions,
that would happen through a pipeline.
And what is pooing apart from feces going through a pipeline?
- That's true.
- We should move on to him,
but has anyone got anything else?
- Oh, I was looking at other businesses
that originally saw different things,
and my favourite, which kind of makes sense
to me when you think about the name,
is American Express, do you know what they might have done first?
- Travel or transport?
- Sort of, so post.
They were, because in those days,
so they were founded in 1850,
and the post, US Postal Zeros was sort of not
as, as it is today,
and you could only post things as big as a regular letter size envelope.
And so anything bigger, you'd go through an express company,
so sort of horse guys on horseback,
and so on and forth from a transport that was around there.
- Like the pony express.
- Yeah, and they would just take things.
And American Express found out
that they did a lot of business for banks
and carrying things like stocks, certificates, and currency
was a lot more lucrative than carrying big bulky things,
and so they specialised and made their own products.
- Oh, that was really cool.
- Because American Express, it makes sense.
- Yeah.
- And my other favourite one is still the same product,
but the guys who invented YouTube thought it was going to be
a dating site to people that upload videos,
like for what they were looking for,
and you see what they were like.
- And then it turned out, no one is very camera friendly.
- And we all like cats, but not in that way.
- Yeah.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, we should move on to our final fact.
And that is my fact, which is that when Mozart first performed
in Naples, he had to stop to take his ring off halfway through
'cause the audience complained it was a magic ring.
(laughing)
- A magic ring through which he was producing oil.
- Oh, yeah, that's 650 predators.
- Oh dear.
(laughing)
- That's disgusting, but it wasn't that kind of ring
they were referring to.
- But Mozart would have liked that, wouldn't he?
'Cause he had a dirty mind.
- Yeah, he had a sense of humor.
- He was right about his fights and things.
- He was obsessively scatological actually, wasn't it?
And I think people have really tried to analyze this
and work out why, but he, so he wrote to his cousin
quite rude letters very often, and one of them, for instance,
was, "Well, I wish you good night.
"This is a swear warning for any listeners."
He said, "Well, I wish you good night,
"but first, shit in your bed and make it burst.
"Sleep soundly, my love.
"Into your mouth, your ass, your shove."
- What?
- And then he wrote another one saying,
"I pull on your nose so it runs down your chin."
(groaning)
(laughing)
- He also wrote a lot of really good stuff, guys.
- Like some of the good stuff.
- Yeah.
- He wrote enough music that it would take you
two hundred and two hours to listen to all of it.
- Wow.
- It's pretty cool.
- I think they might.
This brings above classic FM.
I think they might have just released
the complete Mozart 200 hours.
- Two hundred and two.
- Two hundred, maybe they skipped off the last two.
That was all the poo stuff.
- Yeah, it was the best-selling CD of last year, wasn't it?
Or more CDs?
More Mozart CDs were sold than any other artist last year.
- Mozart loved poo.
- Yeah.
- It's possible that poo loves Mozart.
There is a sewage treatment plant in Switzerland.
And in 2010, they started playing Mozart to the waist.
- No.
- Yes.
- And what?
- I don't know if he's seen Flava.
(laughing)
- They claimed that the music's vibrations
would help the organisms, the microbes in it,
to break down the waist and the cadences
and all of these things.
So they developed a process to play it.
And the man who ran the place is a guy called Anton Stuckey.
And he said he wasn't actually a fan of Mozart.
They had to convince him quite strongly
that it would work to do it.
I don't know if they're still doing it, but they did start.
- Interestingly, if you take human eggs in IVF,
they grow better if you play techno music to them.
- Really?
- Last week in some study or other.
- Wow.
- So is this vibration we're thinking?
- Yeah.
- That's vibration, yeah.
- I'm just really like to have an adjective explain my fact
'cause you all derailed me with your scatological--
- Sorry, magic ring, yeah.
- Magic ring.
So he was doing this concert in Naples.
He was 14 years old and it was in 1770.
And at rumour been spreading anywhere
that he was using magic powers to play.
That the audience refused to be entertained.
So they refused to applaud and they just didn't see it
as impressive 'cause they assumed his power was coming
from this magic ring.
So halfway through his performance,
he had to stop and take off his ring.
And at that point, apparently,
the audience gassed in astonishment and fear
while crossing themselves.
- I went onto the Wikipedia for magic rings, there is one.
And it starts off, a magic ring is a ring,
usually a figure ring.
(laughing)
- I wonder what these magic cock rinks are.
- Oh my god.
- It's a toe ring, James.
- I don't know about toe rings.
- Toe ring, or earring, it could be, I guess.
- No, the way my mind went that.
(laughing)
- Yeah, magic ring is a ring, usually a figure ring
that has magical properties.
- Great.
- Makes a lot of sense.
I should say I found this fact in a book called
Time Keepers by Simon Garfield and it's amazing.
And you should buy it, I'm loving it.
I'm about quarter of the way through.
He's brilliant.
- So I didn't know, I knew most of it was a child prodigy.
I didn't know quite how much of one he was.
So he could play the harp in the violin
at the edge of about three, or he started playing that.
When he was five, he was quite good.
And then his father took him on tour, age six,
for three and a half years, playing across Europe.
And with his sister as well, who doesn't get as much credit.
- Was his sister better?
I read somewhere that his sister was a better musician.
- I don't think so.
- I start off with, 'cause she was older.
- I think, didn't she trans, 'cause he would play,
I think she would transcribe.
And there's some thought that she had more influence
since he was given credit for.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, and he could, I read this.
I can't, I don't know if I believe it.
He could write music before you could write words.
- You can sort of believe it.
- It's easier to write blobs on manuscripts
than it is to write actual letters.
- Yeah.
- It is very interesting psychologically,
because he is the original child prodigy.
And you've got to wonder what effects it had.
So when I was listening to, I used this podcast
as an excuse to listen to my genuinely favourite podcast,
which is the Radio 3 composer of the week podcast.
- Second, second.
- It's the genuinely favourite podcast.
- Second favourite.
- Radio allows my favourite.
(all laughing)
And yeah, he was, and people were amazed at him.
And it must have affected him hugely.
And apparently, when he got older, he was very angry
that people didn't treat him with the same kind of
amazement and deference, 'cause once he was a grown-up,
he was just an incredibly talented musician and composer.
But as a child, he was like this magic genius.
So he used to get very annoyed.
- But it's really rough.
- Because he will be a better player than he was
and he was a kid, but rather than be admired
for being better at more skilled.
- Oh, everyone's gone, oh, you're not cute.
- Yeah.
- It's like someone who's absolute best year
was the first year of university.
And they can never quite get back that magic again.
- That is the story of my life.
(all laughing)
- So Mozart's first name was John.
Johannes, Chrysostom, Wolf Gangus, Theophilus, Mozart.
And he was named after St. John Chrysostom.
And I was reading about the story of St. John Chrysostom.
And it's quite good.
He was living in the desert.
And then a princess came to his cave
'cause she was being attacked by animals.
And he didn't really want her to move into his cave
because he was worried that he might have sex with her.
And so what he did was like some kind of 1966 sitcom.
He drew a line in the middle of his cave
and said, "I'll stay on my side of the line
"and you stay on your side of the line."
And then despite this, the synophonication was committed.
- Ah.
- And in a tent to hide it, he threw her off a cliff.
- What, I just tell her to keep it quiet with her friends.
- That's her off a cliff.
- It was a different time.
- It was a bit of the '70s.
- '70s. - '70s.
- '70s.
(all laughing)
- Then he went to Rome to beg for absolution,
which was refused.
- Only for the murderer for the sex.
- For the murder, really.
- I'd like to be absolved from murder, please,
but with a sex chaser.
(all laughing)
- At the beginning when he said a princess comes into his cave,
I was thinking, "Oh, it sounds a bit like
"the beginning of Notting Hill."
(all laughing)
- 'Cause that's where the celebrity comes
into Hugh Grant's bookshop in Notting Hill.
Like a very famous wealthy person
comes into the life of an ordinary man.
- I've not seen Notting Hill.
Does he then throw off a cliff?
(all laughing)
Anyway, so then he lived like a beast, crawling on all fours
and feeding on wild grasses and roots.
And then the princess reappeared alive
with the saint's baby.
- What?
- Okay.
- And the baby miraculously pronounced his sins
to be forgiven.
And that was the miracle that made him into a saint's.
- Very forgiving of the baby.
- Was she brought back to life by God,
or was she, did she just survive being thrown off a cliff?
- We don't see that.
We don't see that.
- The haven't asked it off screen.
- Yeah, you have to infer it from yourself.
Like it's one of those stories where it could be one
or it could be the other.
Like the end of inception.
(all laughing)
- I thought you could only become a saint
by doing three amazing things.
I didn't realize you could just get a baby to forgive you.
- He's done three amazing things.
He's had sex with the princess.
He's lived like a beast.
(all laughing)
- And he's been to Rome.
- He's been to Rome.
- And he's got a talking baby.
It's basically not in Hill, mixed with inception.
- Looks like he's talking.
(all laughing)
- And that's the story of Mozart.
- Mozart got a lot of bad reviews, interestingly.
Even during life, probably used a magic ring one star.
(all laughing)
- Fake.
- And so these were phrases that we used about him.
Too strongly spiced, impenetrable labyrinths,
bizarre flights of the soul, and overloaded,
and overstuffed.
- Really?
- Yeah, so it wasn't all completely positive.
I was not saying he was bad at music.
(all laughing)
- He was one of the haters.
- He may have died, this is interesting.
He may have died because he got too little sunlight.
- Pretty.
- Yeah, 'cause he died so young.
He was 35 when he died.
And he was very nocturnal towards the end of his life.
And where he was living, he died about three months
into the winter.
And there's a theory that a contributory factor
was lack of vitamin D, 'cause you can't make vitamin D
if you don't get sunlight.
So, and there are so many other theories though,
there are about 20 theories at least of what killed him.
- He was also rejected in other ways,
so he was rejected in love.
By the first woman he fell in love with, actually,
a loisier Weber, and he ended up marrying her sister,
but he fell in love with her at first.
And when asked after his death why she'd turned him down,
she just said, "I did not know.
"I only thought he was such a little man."
Rejected 'cause he was too small.
And then another person, the print select of Bavaria,
once heard him play, and then afterwards said,
"Who would believe that such great things
"could be hidden in so small a head?"
So he obviously had a smallness problem
that perhaps he was trying to compensate for.
- He must've been hard for him to play music
with such small hunts.
- And he ran up and down the keys, like big.
(all laughing)
- Maybe there's anything about him not getting
if he was indoors and not getting up with him in D
'cause you need that to grow, right?
- Yes.
- This is a cracking theory.
This is the kind of thing that bullshit science studies
get written about, was Mozart too small
'cause he didn't know enough with him in D?
- Okay, we should round up pretty soon.
Has anyone got anything else?
- Oh, I just have one thing, which I'm not sure is true,
but I like it so much I wanted to say.
Mozart probably had a fear of trumpets
and I read somewhere that to cure him of this,
his father hired someone to follow him around
with a trumpet and blast the noise and raise him.
I don't care if it's not true 'cause I really like that, yeah.
I can kind of know what I know about Mozart's father.
I can totally imagine that.
- Yeah, I can totally imagine that.
- Is he a slave driver?
- A little bit, I think.
- If it is six-year-old on tour for three years.
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- And his son liked him.
- Stunned to his grave.
(all laughing)
- Okay, yeah.
- He's deliberately shrunk his own son.
Like, honey, I shrunk the kids.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, we should have finished on the election and reference.
That's all of our facts for this week.
We'll be back the end next week with another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish.
And in the meantime, you can get in touch with us
at our group Twitter account,
which is @Qipodcast or individually.
You can get in touch with Andy at...
- @AndrewHunterM.
- James @EggShaped.
- @Miller_Anne.
And you can email me at podcast@QI.com
to hit any of our previous episodes.
You can go to No Such Thing as a Fish.com.
Thanks for listening.
See you again next week.
Bye-bye.
(upbeat music)