[Music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to
you from four undisclosed locations in the UK. My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with
James Harkin, Anna Tyshinski and Andrew Hunter Murray and once again we have gathered around
the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order
here we go. Starting with fact number one and that's my fact this week, my fact is that the
world's longest golf putt took 26 seconds for the ball to reach the hole. In that time it covered
a distance of over nine miles. So Dan, I've just done some calculations just before we came on
and I reckon that means they must have hit the ball at about just over 1200 miles per hour.
And is that good James? I know you play golf. Well I've just been watching the open just
before we came on as well and Bryson DeChambeau who most people think hits it the hardest and
fastest of anyone can hit it at a maximum of 140 miles an hour so what the fuck's going on?
Okay so yes you are correct in your calculation but incorrect in how this record was set.
This was set aboard Concorde. Yeah so it is a cheat. I was talking to our good buddy Jason
Haisley and this came up in conversation. He mentioned that a record had been set by someone
who had basically used the idea that the distance that you would travel on Concorde matched with
a putt that could travel the distance of Concorde into a hole would set the record. So the record
that is held currently is by a guy called Jose Maria Olathalbo and he's a golfer who in 1999
was on the Ryder Cup's team Concorde flight to the United States and during the whole trip he
spent most of the time in the aisle trying to break the record for longest putt ever. Right.
And so the putt that he achieved was 26.17 seconds long so it covered the 150 feet of the cabin
but as a result of the distance traveled by Concorde that was 9.2 miles that he traveled.
I can only imagine how hard it was for the poor bloody air stewards to serve the drinks
around this golfer. The other thing is when you're playing golf it's always more difficult to play
over water but presumably this whole shot was over water. Yes exactly but also you know I'd
mention he tried to break the world record. This isn't the first time that someone has set the record
of longest golf putt done on a Concorde airplane so a couple years before in 1997 there was a guy
called Brad Faxon and he set the record. Now what's interesting is I managed to find a blog
about the story of how this happened and I think it's a cheat his record setting because
as opposed to this other completely legitimate. Well as far as I can tell the current record
holder did it by hitting it and getting it into the hole on his own but in this blog about Brad
Faxon it sounds like he hit the ball and then all of the passengers were putting their hand
and feet in the way navigating the ball. That doesn't count. Exactly that doesn't count.
I have a question Dan. How did they make a hole in Concorde? In fact that made it easier to sink
the ball because everything was being sucked towards the massive hole in the fuselage of the
plane they just drilled. Is that what happened? No I think it must have been a cup on its side.
For such an important record the scant detail. Such an important record.
World changing record was set today. As far as I could tell the first person to ever hold the
record was not a professional golfer but was Suggs from the band Madness who initially did it
and what did you mean the longest putt or do you mean on Concorde? On Concorde the longest putt
on Concorde. No wonder Concorde went out of business the number of golfers just queuing up
taking up valuable spaces for people with their bags. The longest golf shot ever or what was often
claimed or speculated to be one of the longest happened on the moon right? I think we've mentioned
before Alan Shepard did a golf shot on the moon and it was it was never a record breaker or anything
but everyone always just said god that must have gone miles because obviously gravity on the moon
is a sixth of what it is now so you should be hitting it six times as far and there's the I
think there's the footage and when he hit it this is on Apollo 14 1971 he missed it the first one
which we've mentioned before hit the second and disappeared out of shot and he was like wow god
I reckon that's gone a long way he actually said about 200 yards which still is not as far as
professionals will hit it but they recently analyzed the videos of his golf shots and zoomed right in
and they worked out where he was standing because they saw his footprints and where the ball landed
and he hit the ball 40 yards which in earth yards I guess that would be what like seven
seven yards he basically hit at the equivalent of on earth wow wow var has really ruined more
things than we realized yeah as someone who once lost a cricket ball throwing competition
aged about 15 or 16 to a seven-year-old girl I don't think we should criticize this guy too much
but cricket ball throwing yeah it was a cricket ball throwing competition it was in Germany
and why why were you representing the UK the world cricket ball throwing championships
that's a fair point I guess they didn't have much interest from elsewhere yeah oh god amazing
anyway speaking of sport of the sports what sport do you reckon has the fastest ball of not being
played on concord just generally what about squash squash faster for sure okay it's not going to be
table tennis it's not ping-pong no the answer is pilota you know that game that they play in the
catalan region of spain oh yeah yeah I'm so excited about the pilota world cup coming up soon well
apparently you're representing the UK and that's all I think I don't know if you know it's basically
a game where you you have these gloves but they have like a slope on them and so you catch the
ball in midair it's a bit like squash and then you flick the ball using your hand and with this
slope and it really gives it a massive speed but I thought that's about 180 miles an hour the best
tennis serve about 160 I thought maybe quidditch but the quidditch broomsticks apparently according
to the internet I haven't read the books at all so I might be wrong about this only 150 miles an hour
the fastest brooms go so my pedestrian sport really but then if you throw the um I want to say
snitch from a broomstick no no no no no no come on let's throw the snitch come on come on a broomstick
if you catch the snitch the game ends your team gets 150 points right sorry well you're throwing
some sort of balls presumably you might throw a quaffle or a blusher it's a quaffle yeah right
so you quiff the quaffle off the broomstick while going at 150 miles an hour you give that some
extra speed yeah it's like shouting a torch out of a car exactly no hang on that's still the speed
of light it's exactly unlike shouting a torch in actual fact you've chosen the one thing light
which doesn't act like a ball you know a hole in one uh the phenomenon of a hole in one I did not
know this you can get a hole in one insurance if you own a golf course what do you mean basically
lots of golf courses offer prizes you know huge prizes if you got a hole in one on this hole
we will give you 50 000 pounds and that's obviously quite risky for a golf course in case someone just
turns up and does it so there is special insurance and you pick a main hole and you can also get
optional prize cover for five other holes in the policy I read I'm sure they vary but yeah I just
had no idea that was a special insurer that's very cool yeah so you're um encouraged to get
insurance if you play golf because you're hitting balls quite often in the wrong directions in areas
where there are people but part of your insurance will often be hole in one insurance and that's
because when you get a hole in one you're kind of supposed to buy everyone else in the club a drink
and so if you do get it and you pay for that then your insurance will pay for that round of drinks
really that's brilliant so that's kind of stingy isn't it people are saying even on that day when
presumably they're winning this massive prize from the golf course anyway they're not going to buy
the five other blokes in the golf bar a drink the poor people at Aviva who are dealing with two
competing claims one for 50 000 pounds for one for the biggest round of drinks ever
wow that's amazing well you say things golf balls often do get hit in the wrong direction
right and one particular group of people who is prone to doing this are American politicians
so i think maybe the record for the most disastrous misdirected hit is held by Spiro Agnew
so this was 1971 i think so he was former former vice president this is thank you i was going to
say just for the just for the younger listeners he explains who Spiro Agnew is
come on if you've heard his name once which you probably have you never forget that name
so no one needs to contextualize it's the bob hope classic tournament in 1971 this is like a lot of
celebrities took part in this a lot of presidents have played in it and i think he might be the
only person to hit three people with two shots so he hit one shot and it hit a husband and wife
couple both so rebounded off one smacked into the other he paused went up to apologize how embarrassing
for me i'm a public figure went back down put it back on the tee and thwacked another woman
who had to go to hospital no my god yeah did he then continue oh yeah he absolutely nailed it
after that you get your bad shots out the way that's amazing and i think was he working with
Gerald Ford he was at the time wasn't he who also once hit the same woman twice from the same tee
you're kidding did she move did she move in between shots one and two that's a really good question
in which case you think it's her fault because obviously he's not going to hit it to the same
place i don't think i'm sorry i don't think i'm saying it's her fault i'm just saying it would
be interesting if she moved and that implies that he was drawn towards her somehow okay i guess if
she didn't it also could imply that she could have been wearing like a giant flag on her head
yeah he thought she was the whole she was actually she had an enormous hole um in the middle of her
diaphragm okay oh that's who you guys know who the number one female golfer in the world is at
the moment type of recording no no come on guys it's not sexist because i don't know the number
i don't know either yeah fair enough the number one female golfer is a woman called Nelly Corder
the number 13 golfer is her sister Jessica Corder and you might know the name if you follow
tennis because their brother is Sebastian Corder who is currently the 46th best player in the world
and was the first player born in the 2000s to reach the fourth round of any grand slam event
wow imagine that family the father is Pettacorder who was a former number two tennis player in the
world and an Australian open winner and their mother is Regina Corder Ney Reichstover who
was a former tennis top 30 player as well wow imagine that family at Christmas their grandfather
was Concorda who invented it shall we talk about concord yeah yeah concord was absolutely amazing
it says kind of sad that it's defunct i i love the fact that i had a wiggly nose yeah which i didn't
really know because you see photos of it looking slightly skew if the nose they could genuinely
from the cockpit control where the nose was and it was simply so they could see the runway because
when the nose was in its up up position the pilots coming into land couldn't see the runway nearly
as clearly obviously advantage to see the runway so they just had a boom and you could see it tilt
down and they could see the runway at land and it made that noise didn't it yes absolutely it's probably
noise yeah oh i've just lost my sex drive sound effect do you guys know the oldest person ever
to fly on concord um gosh i don't was it um what who's old you do you mean old now because all of
them are fairly old well that's a good point yeah okay i'm gonna say this is a trick question
i reckon your like a mummy was transported from ancient egypt or something like that's classic
and oh it's bound to be that what a great lucy the ancestor of all the um homoerectasis yeah
some primordial soup was brought on board and served would you like the chicken or the fish or
the primordial soup poor andy he now just has to tell us it's a 61 that is very true well there's
been a few all these on there the queen mum celebrated her 85th birthday by going on concord
and sitting in the cockpit she's not the oldest person ever the oldest person ever was a woman
called eve woodman okay she flew on concord in 1998 and she was aged 105 born in 1893 and what
i really like is this when she went on the flight it was only the second time in her life she had
left bristol wow isn't that incredible that's amazing did honor waiting for the right moment
she would have been 11 years old at the time of the first flight of the right brothers
she was born at a time when cars were pretty bloody surprising
that's true concord was maybe not used to transport mummies but concord was used to transport body
parts which i didn't realize so the actual speed of concord had served a genuine purpose medical
purpose and apparently ba concords were quite often used to transport organs that needed to be
quickly relayed to somewhere else to be donated and there was one incident according to concord
magazine where french concord had to ship a really rare anti-venom to someone who'd had a snakebite
somewhere in africa oh my god and yeah and and because you've got such limited time it was
literally like if they'd just gone aboard a normal ba flight then wouldn't have made it in time but
the person survived because it whizzed over there so fast but concord doesn't fly to africa does it
well i think i suppose it flies to wherever the person gets bitten by the snake if it's
it probably wasn't a scheduled flight is what i'm saying do you mind if you could get him from
sudan to amsterdam then yeah we'll give him the antebellum no i think it diverted paul mccarney
once ordered a pizza to be flown from new york to london by concord yeah i don't get that i i
i'm trying to find out more about that was it a cooked pizza was it like a sainsbury's it would
be cold wouldn't it it would be i think it was from his favorite pizza place hmm i you'd imagine
it would be rather he wouldn't have got it from dominos in new york if there's dominos in london
would he he might have had vouchers for the one in london that he couldn't trade in in new york
well yeah was he misled as to how fast concord was it is possible if your delivery arrives after
two and a half three hours it is still going to be lukewarm at best i wonder if the pizza got its
own seat and stuff i wonder that i do wonder that um i would like to think it did there was
a thing where you could save money by being a courier and so if there were sensitive documents
that had to be delivered you would get a cheaper ticket on concord so maybe the pizza had its own
special courier yeah that's interesting i imagine if the pizza just comes out at the other end and
there's a guy with a sign which just has a pizza on it there were quite a lot of famous people that
did travel concord that have led to stories like this like phil collins famously with live aid
played in london and was able to fly to america to play for the end of the day uh over there and
there's a story of urie galler being on the plane and he visits he visits the captain in the cockpit
get get him out of here he's going to bend everything in sight interestingly the nose was
completely straight until he got him he went into the flight deck and he said i can spin the compass
on your instruments and thanks urie thanks a lot fucking don't yeah because presumably he's doing it
with a hidden like um you know magnet or something right it's got to be a trick so why are you letting
him on with that exactly so the captain said i thought at 37 kilometers a minute are we being
wise to allow this man to fiddle with the navigation and he did he let him he let him do it um i think
though he did it on the standby compass which is still you need it it's a standby compass sure and
he said sure enough it whizzed around i've never seen anything like it and uh when it stopped i'm
pleased to say it went back to show it accurately where we were going what a surprise just like what
would happen if you bugged it there yeah exactly okay it is time for fact number two and that is
Anna my fact this week is that some fish use sharks as scratching posts
brave fish yeah and also like my cat uses scratching posts to kind of get her nails down
and fish don't have nails so what's going on oh yeah what's no but they do have parasites
and so they like to rub themselves off against rough surfaces to get rid of those or scratch
that itch and the adrenaline junkies among them scratch up against sharks and this has been
documented in lots of places underwater so i first read about it there's a photographer who
spotted a crowd of jack kind of fish enveloping a massive bull shark and found out later this is
what they do they rub up against them and it seems to happen everywhere so i found a picture of
mackerel rubbing up against a great white very bold very bold and uh even sharks rubbing up
against other sharks sometimes there are silky sharks rubbing up against whale sharks to scratch
themselves wow so it must be harsh to like sharks it's not their fault they got this rough skin and
they've just become kind of everyone's using them right and they're so rough aren't they i i didn't
really realize this because i've never obviously touched a shark but um shark for example can
destroy human skin with their own skin so sometimes people who try to rescue sharks
which have washed up on land uh if they handle them they end up with shark burn where basically
their skin is just so rough that they destroy your fingers in your hands yeah wow what like classic
gray smooth sharks because that just looks like that's such a smooth surface the amazing thing
about them which is just so cool is they're basically made of loads of teeth aren't they
so their skin is loads of these tiny tiny teeth called dermal denticles and if you zoom in they do
look like kind of layers of oval overlapping teeth and they literally are jaws they are very nice
they're entirely and they're as hard as granite um and as strong as steel and they're made of
material called appetite oh wow and also here's a thing um sharks do lose their appetite sometimes
because they get dandruff which means bits of their skins the dermal denticles kind of fall off
and what's really useful about that is we can go into the bottom of the sea and find these
bits of shark dandruff and it can tell us quite a lot about the number of sharks that lived in an
area over many men because it doesn't it's really hard stuff it doesn't really degrade very much
so it's all there from hundreds and hundreds and thousands and millions and years of wow it's really
helpful if you're looking after coral reefs for instance you can work out how many um sharks
were there how a stick the water was all that kind of stuff and people are using this shark dandruff
to do that oh so cool that's amazing the shark that was mentioned in this article was a bull shark
and bull sharks very fascinating sharks they have this incredible ability to swim in both salt and
freshwater uh so do i so do i yeah hi uh yeah sorry let me let me rephrase that they can live
underwater in salt or fresh water those things and um as a result these sharks can be found in
really odd spots and one place in particular that bull sharks are found in is a place called
carbrook golf course in queensland where following a flood where the golf course was flooded bull
sharks swam into the local lake that's in the golf course and then stayed there once the flooding
went down so they're permanently there these giant bull sharks as part of the the golf course
someone's got to break that putting record by putting it onto the back of a shark which swims
the entire length of the lake deposits on the other side whale sharks that's a kind of shark
they're absolutely huge they have remora on them the sucking parasitic creatures but they make a
lovely meal these remoras for birds however how do you get from the bird to the shark underwater
it's really cool what they do is there's only one bit of scientific footage of this happening i believe
the cormorants will dive bomb into the water they will swim down once they're underwater
and then once they get to the surface of the whale shark they will peck away at the remora on the
surface basically try to chisel it off because it's stuck on you know with really strong adhesive
and pry it away from the surface of the whale and they do this you know losing oxygen all the time and
then swim back up and they got there they got the meal the remora are amazing aren't they when you
see have you seen photos of them this little suction pad i've never heard remora i must say
i've never heard that so they're quite a big fish and they're they're different in say like pilot
fish that pilot fish will swim alongside the shark and they will eat parasites along the way and
clean up around them and hence the symbiotic relationship but the remora literally on the
top of their head have this insane suction pad and they just rock up to the side of a shark
and they just go and suck themselves on with their head the right way up and they just get free
transport along the way and they're really important to some of these sharks to the point
where the shark will put itself in danger to help the remora suck on but they live off shark poo
don't they i think some of them they now think they thought they lived off like they feed off the
parasites on the shark and live off sort of scraps of food falling out of the shark's mouth which is
a kind of ignominious existence but now even worse they eat shark poo some of them we think and that's
what they get there so it's no it's no kind of life because there are these fecal plumes that
sharks produce and really big sharks produce thousands of liters in this plume you know it's
30 feet across whale sharks they produce this huge great plume but if the shark is swimming i don't
actually know how the remora manages to eat that maybe it detaches and swims around them yeah they
detach i think they're they're only attached for great travel so they they travel and then they
pause and i think they disattach and eat you know they they parasites off their faces and so on and
that's tough though that's like being driven to a restaurant you jump out the car but the car
continues driving on and then you have to catch it up after your meal yeah it's like a drive-thru no
not like a drive-thru no that's it unless your your parents hated you they drove you to the drive-thru
and then just drove away i like it look it was a fun game and it didn't do me any harm
i grew up well adjusted um greenland sharks you know we've mentioned those guys before the
really slow swimming dance favorite shark yeah they are often partially or completely blind
because they have these copepods which are tiny crustacean like creatures attached to their eyes
but the great news for the greenland shark is that they're swimming in such deep water
that the sharks don't care because it's so dark that they don't actually need their eyesight very
much well but there's also a theory which is not yet proved but that the copepod might be
bi-luminescent and because of that it's attracting prey towards the greenland shark which travels
at one mile an hour it's the slowest shark in the world top speed is two miles like we could
out swim this shark basically so in the greenland shark version of jaws the music doesn't speed up
at all it just stays forever exactly and so the idea is that the copepods are attracting prey to
eat that and it's basically bringing food to the face of the greenland shark nice so it's again
symbiotic is the theory because what that makes sense because i've read recently that 90 percent
of creatures in the ocean are glow-in-the-dark a bioluminescent and we and they're just sort of
discovering this and realizing all these all these animals deep sea animals that are glow-in-the-dark
lantern sharks they glow i think they're luminescent underneath and so that if you look at them
from underneath it looks like it's just the bright sky and you don't realize that there's a shark
there's camouflage yeah that's weird having a light that is also camouflage that's clever yeah
if you lived in blackpool with all the illuminations and you wanted to kind of camouflage
yourself there then it would make sense to cover yourself in lots of bright lights right absolutely
it all depends where you live no no completely but what a terrifying
version of a serial killer you've just thought of James who goes around covered in christmas lights
but only in blackpool
we've never talked about the shark murder case in sydney which just feels like if people don't
know about that you need to because it's such a good story this is basically 1935 there's an
aquarium in sydney there's a tiger shark there are loads of people admiring it and suddenly it
vomits up a human arm and this thank you good sound effects and this launched this massive
murder investigation so it was an arm which when they studied it it obviously been cut off
by someone as opposed to eating by the shark it had a tattoo on it which was identified as the
arm of this kind of boxer cum criminal it actually turned out the shark hadn't eaten the arm the shark
had eaten a smaller shark and that smaller shark had eaten the arm wow what a tangled web this is
this is incredible wow it was awesome it's never been solved to this day this crime because this
guy got accused uh this guy called reginald holmes and he denied it all he got really really drunk
and got his boat out into sydney harbour i think he tried to shoot himself in the head to get away
from the um accusation but instead the bullet flattened against his skull knocked him into the
water whoa did he have a skull made of iron or what like how does that work what the hell i don't
know what reginald holmes is made of but this bullet was flat and his skull was fine he got a
mark and cushion what he climbed back into against his skull a lot of this story was
unbelievable that put that bit in particular so okay so he's in the water he's got a bullet made
of jelly yeah and he's got his skull made of iron and he climbs back into his speed boat and there's
a police chase around sydney harbour which lasts for a few hours and eventually i'm amazed that it
lasts a few hours given that he's been shot in the head by himself shortly before this he's hard
cool maybe he's that guy from james bond with the metal face anyway jules yeah jules yeah the other
jules so then he says okay fine i am involved he says his business associate had killed the victim
this guy called smith and had dismembered him cut him into pieces and he turned up at reginald holmes's
door because they had beef between them and he'd waved this severed arm at him and said look if
you don't do what i need you to do then you'll end up like whoever this guy was and he'd left the
severed arm with reginald holmes so holmes just tossed this arm into the water didn't really know
what to do with it and anyway then he was murdered the day before he was supposed to testify and the
case was never solved because even though they kind of knew it was the guy who holmes had said it
probably was it was determined that no one could prove anyone had been murdered because actually
a severed arm does not constitute enough of a body to suggest that anyone's been killed in the first
place the threshold of proving a murder in australia seems to be remarkably high
okay it is time for fact number three that is james okay in my fact this week is that 46 percent
of masai men have become friends with someone who got the wrong number and mistakenly called their
phone how fat are their fingers how lonely are the masai more importantly if i get a wrong number i
never try and befriend the person who's called me so i think i don't know anything about the
mechanics of how they use their phones so i can only answer andy's question really but basically
the masai these are traditionally nomadic people but their lifestyle is evolving quite a lot
like a lot of places around the world as the expansion of western society kind of globalizes
itself and there was a 2021 study about masai men who live in kenya and tanzania and it found that
because they work in big big areas and they don't see many people from day to day but it's really
really important for them to have these social networks because it means that you can sell your
goods better it's you know it's really important to kind of see people and speak to people they
have found this way of making friends where whenever anyone accidentally calls them and they're
speaking the ma language which is the language that they speak they automatically just start going
oh how's it going i don't suppose you want to buy any cows or some grain or whatever i don't you know
and they just basically start up a conversation so bizarre one of the mechanics for why they
miss call sometimes is it's to do with the fact that there's not great access to electricity
in many areas and so if you were in an area and your phone died but you wanted to call someone
you would borrow someone else's phone and in that case you'd have to manually put in a number off
memory and it's during the memory of it you would miss dial i didn't see that that's really interesting
i should say this is specifically men that they found this in there has been a study on
masai women by a woman called kelly summers who comes from virginia tech and she found that the
men are often using their phones to talk about people outside their social circle to try and make
contacts for selling things especially um whereas the women are mostly talking to each other other
people in the family unit in this in the local unit yeah so that's quite a gender line as far as
mobile phone uses in the masai yeah there's another division that is being created in
masai society not a serious division but according to a 2017 study people with mobile phones which
are dumb you know non-internet enabled as it were they call smartphone users because they
have the ability to download weather forecasts and if you're nomadic or a cattle herder weather
forecast is very important so this is basically a new system of being a tribal elder opening up
which is you know have you got an iphone or the equivalent that's very funny wait so they just
call they'll call loads of random numbers until someone picks up and they say hey are you on an
iphone and then they say great can you tell me no they'll know if one specific person has an iphone
they'll call them say can you download the latest weather forecast exactly yeah so that person's on
the phone all day long basically just delivering the weather god it's like being a being a weather
man or woman but instead of being on tv you just have to deliver the weather to every individual
person yeah that's hot yeah it's like being the speaking clock isn't it really yeah yeah
i'm never being so surprised when i was in kenya i went around kenya in tanzaneer in 2005
and i was on like a matatu one of those buses and there was a big masai guy and it's so tall most
of them sitting directly opposite me our knees were touching and i remember feeling kind of awkward
um and then he delved into his sort of coat and he whipped out a mobile phone and this was kind of
when i just got a mobile phone that was when you finally decided to get one wasn't it Anna it was
like you know what i thought yeah it is time but he was on a bus with you right yes like he's already
engaged in the modern world well he's on a matatu going into town to sell some uh meat i guess
did you have the meat with him uh yeah the rest of the passengers on the bus were all cows actually
have you guys heard of the masai spitting customs again i don't know if these are now
completely out of date and i suspect covid might have rendered them a little bit passive yeah it
doesn't sound very covid friendly does it no there's lots of spitting belief it's a bit considered
a blessing uh spitting so uh parents and friends might spit on a newborn baby to wish it luck
and health that makes sense absolutely yeah during masai weddings a father might spit on his daughter's
forehead and breasts as uh again as a as a blessing weird we're so weird to marry into that if you're
not aware isn't it yeah i'd take that as an insult and they do the classic uh spit on your hand
for a handshake as well which is often done as a sort of blood brothers with spit kind of thing
you spit on your own hand so yeah you spit on your own hand and then shake uh but that's that seems
to be a normal sort of handshake again as you say handy it might be out of date now but yeah
yeah god i like the idea though that andy you would spit on someone else's hand in a spit shake
i'm going to start suggesting that you hand out and you have to project sit onto their hand
there was a traditional way of preparing mead in the masai uh and that was that a man and a woman
would live in a hut and keep away from the rest of society while they're making the mead and while
you're doing it you have to abstain from engaging in any sexual intercourse it lasts about six to
seven days but if you don't follow that rule then it means that the mead will be undrinkable
and all the bees who produce the honey will leave the village forever
imagine if you had broken the rules just nervously presenting your tainted mead to the rest of the
tribe and seeing if they guess yeah i'm going hey where are those bees going no they're just
popping out they're popping out that would be a great masai game show you know what the mead makers
dirty mead yeah it's a panel of masai judges who have to work out whether the couple of mead
makers have had sex during the production prices of the mead it's like anti love island basically
we're just watching people try not have sex oh wait there is a new network show
i believe is that is that that's the premise is it yeah yeah well you're not allowed to have sex
right to protect the mead it's not they've actually they've cut the mead element from the
netflix show which i think is a huge blunder big mistake big mistake how's that gonna work
i mean i hope they haven't cast long married couples because that's just the girl for years
and not be a challenge for anyone the masai have now created their own intellectual property trust
because they're so second tired of big global companies using the name masai or using traditional
masai designs and so they are creating a body of intellectual property trained elders and they hope
that they'll be able to negotiate with firms on behalf of the masai obviously it's tricky because
you've got lots and lots of people who are you know very dispersed and it's hard to negotiate on
behalf of all the masai but they are trying to persuade firms to recognize the masai trademark
over their own name for example yeah because isn't there an estimate that over a thousand companies
use masai designs basically it's that sort of red check right and the beads you see those beads
everywhere belts and so like louis viton calvin kline yeah and obviously it's hard it's hard to
trademark beads for example but particular designs you might be able to or there are sometimes
voluntary codes of conduct which some native american groups have struck so that now it's
seen as an industry standard that if you use and guess you have to kind of get permission or or at
least talk to the people involved and there is somewhere you can go which has been the first
company to start paying them for their trademark called koi clothing so ko y which i was looking at
and the items for humans are very expensive but you can get a dog collar for 25 pounds so
some stuff on wrong numbers oh yeah yeah elon musk has an old phone number which he doesn't
use anymore but which lindsay tucker 25 year old skin care consultant does use oh no so she
regularly gets phone calls and text messages for elon musk one guy sent her a blueprint for a bionic
limb another guy in south africa have sent her a text message asking if he can buy 1000 trucks
and the irs called her asking about her tax amazing what did you say her job is she is a skin care
consultant oh well so that first one sounds quite useful what was the first call bionic limb that's
the one place you don't need skin care you need just the wd 40 yeah look if you if you get something
you say i'll try to fix your skin your cold soles on your leg and then it's like i've really screwed
that up i'm so sorry i had to amputate but on the bright side got a bionic limb i can see how that
would look it's unlikely yeah god it must be tempting some of the offers she gets she must be
really tempted to pretend to be his representative i'm sure she'll be caught pretty quickly but
according to the article i read she takes it in in her stride and she says that um if any of you
ever call elon musk or text him and you don't get a reply then don't feel hard done so you probably
rang her number and she doesn't get a chance to reply to everyone saying it's that so it's not
elon's fault and but it was it was npr and they did ask elon musk about it and he did say that
that was his number he can't believe that it's still in use it's so old that's amazing she should
start selling musk oh that's such a good idea great idea capitalize on it start selling elon's musk
the skin does he have that as a perfume company elon's musk he must do right he should he must
defeat i mean the exciting thing here at her is we could literally call this lady up and you
picture the idea right let's do it we've got her number no no the number wasn't printed at the
story because that would just make matters worse yeah it would be irresponsible journalism yeah
this person gets loads and loads of dodgy calls but here's her number anyway he just gets she needs
to know do you guys want to hear the greatest wrong number of all time yeah in my opinion okay
it happened in 1992 it was happened in dover there was a man called jason pegler he was walking
past a phone box right and it rang he answered the phone and the person ringing that phone box
wanted to speak to him the person making the call was a colleague of his who was ringing trying to
get through to jason asking how to work the office fax machine they hadn't phoned his phone number though
they had accidentally looked up his sheet at the company and phoned his employee number at the
company which happened to be the same as the number for the phone box and was he able to help out
with the fax situation i don't know you bastard i have no idea that isn't it i mean do you do you
buy this because it does sound unbelievable well yeah you're absolutely right it does sound
unbelievable it's collected by david spiegelhalter of cambridge university who has a website where he
collects unbelievable coincidences and this is one of them so i don't know what verification
he does but i think it might um i think it might be true actually i think it is legit i think i've
heard him be asked about it before the guy who answered the phone i bet he was loitering outside
that phone because he spotted that years earlier i suppose it's like the law of big numbers isn't
it you have enough billion people in the world and enough things happen that eventually more of them
will be an amazing coincidence exactly that it's exactly that i found another just with silicon
valley tech billionaires one who's i'm not sure if he's a billionaire but steve wozniak the creator
of the apple computer with steve jobs so he used to have a phone number which was very similar to
panam's reservation number and people in silicon valley if they failed to use the right area code
they would get steve wozniak instead who loved pranks we've spoken about before on the podcast
and so he would play up to it and what he used to do is if someone was trying to make a reservation
he would tell them that they were the millionth passenger on panam and as a result they'd won
free lifetime travel on panam and then what he would do is halfway through collecting their
personal information he would hang up leave them confused and the obviously thing would be they would
spend the next however long calling panam back going no i swear to god someone was offering me
lifetime i'm a millionth guy harsh real harsh really cruel such a dick move in 2015 there was
a woman called betty barker who got a phone call and she picked up the phone and the person said
hello is this planet earth and so she thought that's a prank call or this person's drunk
and the phone call ended i actually i don't i think either the person cut it off or she cut
it off and it only came to light the next day i think when tim peak tweeted from the international
space station i'm so sorry for the wrong month number i called yesterday from space i was trying
to get through to my family that's so good isn't that great our similar story our friend poli adams
got a call from the international space station one day so she's the daughter of
douglas adams and it was the 42nd mission to the international space station so 42 is a big
number in hitchhiker's guide to the galaxy so the whole mission was themed to that so poli was
told that she was going to receive a call from the astronauts but um her phone when the when it rang
had a area code of texas america which is where it's rooted from and she thought well that's not
space so she let it go to voicemail it called a couple of times what did she think the area
code of space was going to be she i don't know it might have just said space or universe um so she
ended up having to receive a voicemail going hi poli um it's just the astronauts up in the
international space station trying to get through to you if you could give us a call back okay it
is time for our final fact of the show and that is andy my fact is that halfway through the first
world war the british government bought nearly 400 pubs in an attempt to stop people drinking
how was that helping surely that just gives the members of parliament way more options
and what did they just close the pubs are they didn't close them they they close some of them um
but actually a large number of them were not only kept open they were substantially modified um
basically they were very worried about people going to the pub and how this might affect the
war effort because there were lots of factories making munitions uh where you had workers turning
up either hungover or maybe still drunk but it was it was a real problem especially if you're
making very delicate uh bombs and things like that bombs aren't delicate you know what i mean high
explosive devices there's probably some delicate parts of a bomb they probably are aren't they yeah
yeah the embroidery on top actually it's very hard to get that right okay um and so they they
really were concerned about this and as an experiment in june 1916 kind of the height of
the war it's really crazy to imagine but they bought nearly 400 pubs over an area of about 300
square miles uh quite near the city of carlyle it was called the carlyle experiment this this
campaign they bought some more elsewhere but that was the main area and they said we're going to do
it for as long as the war lasts and do you mean they sold them back afterwards or i think we get
onto that later but they initially just sort of bought them and said we have to do this and they
basically took all these actions to stop people drinking but in a pub environment so they brought
in really strict hours uh they encouraged the sales of food and non-alcoholic drinks uh they made it
more attractive to women and families they introduced table service you know all of these
moves were basically designed um to slow down drinking and make pubs nicer and my why is the
attractive to women and families going to slow down drinking i would have thought you're just
doubling your cleantel there very good point i guess it stops mad bingeing it stops like people
just going in just to drink isn't it like just drink those pubs right exactly yeah get on their
best behavior if only women had the same impact now when they walked into a pub suddenly everyone
is a complete gentleman insight into your childhood anna that you think children are part of the
drinking problem don't let them in they're out of control but it's basically gastropubs i think the
british government kind of invented the gastropub yeah it was called um disinterested management
wasn't it the um the idea where you would give your landlords big commissions if they sold soft
drinks or if they sold food um but you wouldn't really give them any commission if they sold alcohol
and it started the idea started with private temperance people started buying a few pubs to do
this and then the government thought oh that's a good idea right wait and we should say it it did
expand out of carlyle presumably or was it just the poor people of carlyle who couldn't get a drink
anywhere it was mostly carlyle i think i think it was across the country that the laws were passed
that limited things like ours right so you were only allowed to drink um between 12 and 2 or between
6 30 and 9 30 yeah it's interesting that they wanted to turn it so that more women and children
were going in because i did read that women were a big problem for the drinking in 1916 so there was
a magistrates that dealt with a case with a guy called captain oversby that said he said in the
opinion of the committee the great increase in the number of women visiting public houses during
the past year has demanded drastic treatment and they all wanted to put in place things like this
is the quote partitions snugs and other obstacles likely to facilitate secret drinking be done away
with so they women were just a big problem for the for the people of england apparently because
they kept going getting pissed at the park i think it was basically there was like these factions
wasn't there like a lot of people temperance was kind of a thing and um people were trying to stop
people from drinking in general and obviously the war helped that argument but then obviously a lot
of other people were thinking not so when um they decided that they would allow or try and get more
women into pubs there were 37 000 female signatories in birmingham of a petition demanding that women
not be allowed in pubs until a certain age yeah that's incredible wow keep women in the home
and out of the pubs there were lots of um changes that were made also two pub designs because there
were structural things in the building that you could do to slow down drinking bizarrely so pubs
used to consist of lots of little rooms and those were all done away with inside it became one large
space inside which could be more easily supervised so snugs that were you know potential for naughtiness
and and binge drinking and there were snob screens you know these no snob screen you will all have
seen one because it's this etched pane of glass right and um in some very old classic victorian
pubs you will still see them to this day and it basically is erected between two bits of a pub
you can see through it kind of one way the middle class drinkers have their own space
which you can kind of see through you can see through to the working class drinkers next door
but the working class drinkers can't see back at you and so it gets called a snob screen yeah and
those were done away with as well in loads and loads of pubs and they they've survived in some
there's one right by Oxford Circus which still has snob screens but we don't have snugs anymore
which is so sad I think you get you get a few snugs in Ireland still but they sound so great
sometimes the snugs could be entered just from the outside but you couldn't get into a snug from
inside the pub and these were like like Andy says they were for people who didn't want to be seen in
the pub so if you're quite a classy chap or women often like Dan said like women didn't want to be
known as drinkers so you enter a snug from outside sit in the snug no one in the pub can see you
and then the barman just has to wheel around a tray of drinks and then you pull it in through
like a little letterbox in your snug sounds really fun can I ask Andy these um snob screens in you
said there's a few in London I've been to I would say most of the pubs around Oxford Circus and I
never seen this does that mean that they've put me in the working class bit yeah and I just get
unaware of it or I've been breaking the code here forget everything I said James I don't think
any of them have them anymore okay I think I said before or maybe I didn't about how they made the
beer weaker obviously to stop drunkenness and there was a song by Weston and Lee in World War
one which was very popular because it was about this and some of the lyrics are really good so
have you read it seen what's said of it in the mirror and the mail it's a substitute and a pub
statute and it's known as the government ale and it goes on blah blah blah oh they say it's a terrible
war oh law and there never was a war like this before but the worst thing that ever happened in
this war is Lloyd George's beer so for some people the whole thing that was happening with the war
it was the weak beer that was the real killer I'm going to bet that those were two guys who
had not been to the front and beer never fully recovered after the war what do you mean it's
hardly remembered these days yeah it apparently after the war it was pretty much remained about
19 percent weaker so it used to be slightly stronger before the war and never quite climbed back up
there unless and obviously now we're in London you get all these Ponzi craft beers like last night
I was drinking a Ponzi beer I'd bought and I tasted a bit weird and I realized it was 11 percent
so we are gradually gradually recovering the percentages Jesus Christ but generally yeah
suffered there is a pub that I'd love for all of us to go to when we're back in pub land and then
it's the Dolphin Tavern and it's not far from our offices in Covent Garden it's up in Holburn
and the initial pub that was built on the site was bombed to the ground on the 8th of September
1915 and it was completely destroyed rubble everywhere and they decided to rebuild it so
in the process of moving away the rubble they discovered one of the remaining surviving things
was a clock that had stuck at 10 40 p.m the exact moment that the bomb was dropped and crashed down
on top of it and ruined everything and so the Dolphin pub to this day has that clock sitting
with the exact time that it was bombed in 1915 on the wall for you to see that's very clever
because also it always gives the impression that it's about to be last order yes oh Dan does it
have a snob screen if it has a snob screen I'll go well but then we won't get to hang out with James
I'll be by myself in the have you heard my accent I'm getting behind that snob screen
you'll be in the snug with the other women I'm afraid actually like it was until relatively
recently it was quite unusual for women to go to pubs especially drinkers pubs you wouldn't
see that that often and it was only the sex discrimination act of 1975 that meant a lot of
places would start allowing women and even there was a pub called the grill pub in Aberdeen that
famously had a sign outside that said no ladies please and wouldn't let any women in at all and
in 19 in fact it was in 1975 no it was in 1973 that a group of women ripped the sign off the door
and went into the pub and demanded to be served and the police had to come in and actually the I
think the police escorted them out of the premises but they refused to leave until they finished their
drinks and eventually obviously this act came in in 1975 so there was nothing they could do
they had to let these women in but they didn't install a female toilet until 1998 well I bet
they regretted that when the cleaner had to do a serious job on the floor every night
isn't that amazing there was a pub called El Vino which was a big journalists pub and there's a
book by Helen Lewis called difficult women which is all about history of feminism and the
opening of it is about the fight for women to get served at El Vino because you weren't allowed
to go to the bar as a woman and this was after the sex discrimination act this was in 1980 this
was in the early 80s so several years later and the courts were just not upholding it because they
said well this is too trivial to uphold or whatever and if you went in you weren't as a woman you
weren't supposed to wait at a table and the guys would go up to the counter that is true and it
was the early 80s like you say and a lot of places you'll see that will say on the internet that it
was still legal to not serve women in pubs until 1982 because it was this case when eventually it
was a solicitor called Tess Gill and a journalist called Anna Koot and they went to cart and they
won which meant that there was now a precedent there was already the law but now it was a precedent
which meant they had to be served they said that I think the pub management had justified it by
saying well look if you allow women to stand at the bar they're going to put their bags down
and that's going to create absolute chaos okay there'll be no room at the bar for people because
it's going to be full of bags and what Tess Gill genuinely that was their argument and what Tess
Gill and her colleague did was they got a couple of male friends to go in put their briefcases down
on the counter clearly taking up space when the pub was very empty so clearly that is a breach of
the rules that the pub is trying to say only applies to women and the men kind of gathered
evidence that way and that's one of the ways they won yeah wow so I actually think the greatest
contribution that Tess Gill and Anna Kootz made obviously women are allowed in all pubs now but
also I'm guessing those little hooks under the bar because of them too right oh yeah I can't tell
you how grateful I am for those hey Dan you asked earlier about what happened to the state management
scheme the Carlisle experiment you know because it was going to be for the duration of the war
plus one year afterwards right so that would have been 1919 they kept the pubs until 1973
that was when the last ones were sold off it was I know it was a serious success and I read a website
about the state management scheme the official name of it which asked why this thing lasts so long
there were two reasons it lasts so long number one it made a profit every year for the government it
was so profitable and number two the economic and political problems facing Britain in the
20s and 30s that ultimately led to the Second World War and the rebuilding problems in the 50s
and 60s were far more politically urgent than dealing with state management of pubs in Carlisle
I don't know if you guys have ever been out for a drink in the Carlisle area but I am not that
surprised that they did that but one of the other reasons is because at the start of World War One
there was a bit of a rise of Irish nationalism in Ireland and a lot of the workers who came over to
the munitions factories in Carlisle were Irish and there was a worry that if the rise in nationalism
in Ireland kind of spilled over to Carlisle it might not be just that they struggled to work
because they were hung over but also that it might cause like political discontent in that area
well speaking of Ireland we've made a big deal about British pubs but really we've got nothing
on Irish pubs they're they're the big global expert aren't they and I was wondering why it was like
when did they get so big how long have they been around I reckon they date back to the sixth century
which is quite a lot older than us but I think I've been to some Irish pubs with some old boys in
there that bit versus the sixth century um so in the sixth century there was a law pass that said
every single local king and there are about 140 in Ireland had to have their own personal brewer
and the brewer had to keep a never dry cauldron which basically and it was called like a brugu
that's amazing the cauldron by law had to serve free food free alcohol and free entertainment to
anyone who passed by just in case it was the king and there were loads of rules they had to be on
the crossroads they had to have torchbearers all around to give passers by a welcome and invite
them in whoa whoa it was so good and if you were caught running a brugu and you couldn't provide
free booze free food free whatever entertainment then by law the sort of state of the official
poet of the region had to write a satire about you a poetic satire to publicly humiliate you
so good oh my god hey just modern day london pubs again another one i'd love to go to is the grapes
in london which is well for one main reason they have a pub quiz there and sometimes it is supposedly
run by gandalf sree and mckellan what really yeah he he bought the pub yeah he owns a pub it's called
the grapes he bought it in 2012 and if you don't know the answer and you want to pass does he say
you shall not pass is that a joke about lord of the rings i don't know yes it is yeah god that's
like seeing someone score a basketball hoop while blindfolded considering you've never seen it yeah
it's like a lady from bristol on her first cold claw flight she doesn't know what she's doing
yeah it's he he does the hosting sometimes apparently he mentions it on his twitter occasionally
who loves pub quizzes come to our pub quiz let's do it but we won't be allowed to because james
will be running for making bad jokes that he doesn't even understand about lord of the rings
it's a hard pub quiz there are a lot of um shadow facts shadow facts is the name of your house
horse and fact it sounds a bit like facts see that shows true knowledge yeah weirdly though andy wouldn't
be allowed in for a very different reason which is that was just fucking weird i would say andy
wouldn't be allowed in because at the end i think you have to throw a ring into a volcano but andy
would have to get a seven-year-old german girl to do it for him okay that's it that is all of our
facts thank you so much for listening if you would like to get in contact with any of us about the
things that we have said over the course of this podcast we can be found on our twitter accounts
i'm on at schreiberland andy at andrew hunter m james at james harken and anna you can email
podcast at qi.com yep or you can go to our group account which is at no such thing or our website
no such thing as a fish.com all of our previous episodes are up there do check them out also
we're back on the road baby we're going on tour in october nerd immunity is the name of the show
and we're going to be hitting up over 20 venues across the uk and ireland so check them out see
if we're coming to a town near you and please come along it's going to be great fun otherwise we'll
just be back here next week with another episode we'll see you then goodbye