(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing" as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covern Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber, and I'm sitting here
with Anna Chazinski, James Harkin, and Andrew Hunter Murray,
and once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the Icelandic version
of Agatha Christie's Lord Edgewear dies,
took over 10 years to complete,
because the translator couldn't work out
how to translate two words.
- Firstly, spoiler alert in Lord Edgewear dies.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- You know what, I don't think you understand crime fiction, Andy,
it's not like you have to wait till the end
for the big reveal about who dies.
(laughing)
- What were the two words, Dan, do you know?
- I don't know, so the reason I don't know is
I read this in an article on the Guardian by the author,
the translator of these books called Ragnar Yonneson,
and I think for the reasons of not wanting
to do the ultimate spoiler alert,
he's not included the two words.
- Because they're like the ultimate words
in the whole story of it.
- Yeah, so this is the thing.
These two words are, it's a bit of wordplay
that Agatha Christie used in the book.
It's the clue, basically, to solving the murder.
And in Iceland, he just couldn't work out how to do it.
And he's been translating Agatha Christie books
since he was 17 years old,
and he started with Endless Night.
The reason he picked it was 'cause it was the slimmest volume,
but he convinced the publishing house
that that was a really good one to start with.
But it was actually, it was just really short.
- He's quite a famous author in Iceland, I think.
He is, yeah, Ragnar Yonneson, was it?
- Yes.
- And his books have been translated into English
by a guy called Quentin Bates, who's also a writer,
but I couldn't see if any of his books
have been translated into other languages.
According to him, the hardest thing about translating
from Icelandic into English is punctuation,
because full stop in Icelandic isn't necessarily the same
as a full stop in English.
And I think that's really interesting
'cause you think it's all about the words
that you have to translate,
but if you have to translate the punctuation as well,
that's pretty good, right?
- Yeah, yeah.
Do you know what a full stop is?
- I think sometimes it can be a comma,
or even a semicolon.
- My pet peeve is people who put commas
instead of full stops,
and that Icelandic's are just doing it all over the shop.
- Well, I think it's part of their actual language.
- I'll allow it.
- I can't believe we're not finding out these two words.
Is the reason you didn't look into what they were,
that you didn't want the spoiler?
- I thought we couldn't actually mention it on the podcast.
I thought the words would be.
- Edgeworth is dead, is that it?
- No, I think that's translatable.
- Okay, fine.
- Maybe it's Edgeworth Road,
and the pun is that he's on a horse,
but it also sounds like a tube stop.
'Cause that'd be quite hard to translate
into Icelandic.
- Yeah, it would be really hard to translate.
- Well, this is the interesting thing about translating, though,
or simultaneous interpreters.
Sometimes, if they have a speaker
who makes loads of jokes,
they find it really hard to do,
because puns obviously are a nightmare for them,
and they hate it.
And one interpreter wrote in an academic article
about interpreting puns based on a single word
with multiple meanings in the source language
should generally not be attempted by interpreters
at the result will probably not be funny.
- I think often puns in your own language,
you should not attempt them,
'cause the result won't be funny.
I'm not targeting anyone specifically,
but that case, I'm not gonna say anything
for the rest of the podcast.
One of my favorite translations is the Asterix books,
and they're full of puns, aren't they?
- Yes, yeah.
- So they were full of puns in the original French,
and then they were translated into English,
and all the puns kind of still work.
They all have names at a puns, basically.
- Like get a fix.
- Get a fix is the druid.
So it's like getting his fix from him.
Anyway, what I didn't know is that that was translated
by two people, Derek Hockridge and Anthea Bell.
An Anthea Bell is the sister of Martin Bell,
the politician and broadcaster,
and also the daughter of Adrian Bell,
who was the first time's cryptic crossword setter.
- Wow.
- And you can see the wordplay really working in that family.
- Yeah.
- That's amazing.
So, guess what the most translated work is?
- The Bible.
- The Bible, you're absolutely right.
- Guess what the next most translated work is.
- Or who is by?
- Little Prince by Santac Superi.
- Oh, that's really close.
Okay, that one is in the top 10.
- Ah!
- Okay, I read recently that that got translated
into its 300th language, that's why I say that.
- Yeah, you're right, yeah, okay.
The next three books after the Bible
that are most translated in the world are all
by the Jehovah's Witnesses, the Watchtower Society.
- Oh, they go way out.
- Seven out of 10 of the books
are by the Jehovah's Witnesses in the top 10.
The only secular ones are the Little Prince
and the UN's Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
- Right.
- Which is a Zinger.
- I don't count it if then, are they selling them
the Jehovah's Witnesses or do they just thrust them on people?
- Look, they're translating them into different languages
and that's what counts.
- I don't think people are buying those.
- No, but it's not sales, it's just physical translation.
- No, no, I know, but, you know, if you get a free Bible
every time you get a church.
- Yeah, that's true.
The Bible should be classified as your heart too.
- No, no, no, no, no.
- No, church roofs are all falling down.
- On Translators, I read in an article I was reading that
when Obama was president, the US State Department
received a message for him
from the King of Bhutan and it was in the language,
'Jonka', which I think is how you say it.
And they needed it translated and so they went to
the third Zonga translator and said,
this is in the King of Bhutan, can you translate?
Well, this message says to Obama,
we need to know what the message is.
And the translator says, no, I can't possibly translate that
because it's in the royal version of the language
and my eyes are not worthy to see it.
- Oh, I know.
- They had to look far and wide for another translator.
Turn out the message was to wish him a happy new year.
- It could have been a major diplomatic incident.
- I think Thai has a royal language as well, don't they?
But they tend to be not that different
from the actual language.
I can't remember if it's like that in Bhutan.
- But even if it was only one tiny bit of difference,
it's the fact of setting your eyes on it.
- Yeah. - There will be a crime.
- You know, it sounds like he could have read it, right?
- Yeah, he could have read it.
- He totally could have read it.
- His eyeballs weren't worthy enough.
- They would have exploded.
- You know, happy new year by Abba,
I wonder if they have a special version
for the royal family in Bhutan.
(laughing)
The only layer out of here.
Does anyone know about the Icelandic translation of Dracula?
- No.
- So it was translated into Icelandic in 1900
by Vladimir Asmonson.
And it's a completely different book
than the actual Dracula.
And it sounds 10 times better.
- Yeah. - How was it different?
- Well, they have secret half ape vampires
who sacrifice young maidens in the basement
with lascivious glee.
- Yeah, apparently it's much sexier.
- We only discovered this really recently in 2014, I think.
- But the Icelandic people have known it for ages.
They've had the book, yeah.
- But they haven't been reading the original genre.
- No, yeah, yeah.
- So this is only when someone went back
to check something in 2014, this Dutch historian.
And he was like, this is completely different.
He said, I want to check something
in the original text, please.
- Oh, right, okay.
- So I was saying that no one Icelandic in English
had ever had a conversation in the last 115 years,
where they both said, I've read Dracula.
What did you think?
Well, I like the half ape vampires sacrificing maidens
in the basement.
- I think it's not.
- You know when you're a bit ashamed
that you've forgotten most of the book that you've read,
you're really like an idiot when you go, oh no.
- Oh, yeah, I love those.
- Yeah, I thought it was really good.
- Yeah, that's my best bet.
- Yeah.
- But yeah, apparently sexier and much less tedious
and punchier.
- Well, Dracula is quite sexy already.
This is sexier.
- Yeah.
- I mean, I had to read the original
with a cushion in my lap.
(laughing)
- But what's interesting about it
is that they're trying to work out
how much involvement Bram Stoker had
in the translation of the book.
- And I think the implication is this translator,
I couldn't have written something this good,
in must have been an early Bram Stoker version.
- It was the alternative that the translators
had made it up.
- Yeah.
- In certain things.
- Pretty much that he took the original story
and thought, I can make this better.
- Wow.
- But this guy's saying, no, no one except Bram Stoker
could have the imagination to come out
with a half ape vampire in must have been him.
(laughing)
- I think you should read it, Andy.
- I will.
- Just think of all the cushions you'll need.
(laughing)
- So Iceland books generally, really interesting.
They supposedly read more books
and more books are published there
per head than any country in the world.
So one in 10 Icelanders are gonna write a book
in their lifetime.
- Yeah, I've read that fact loads of times
and everyone says it's true
and lots of really proper places say it's true
and it almost certainly is true
but I still don't believe it.
- I know it's hard to believe, isn't it?
- Yeah, in 10.
- Well, there are only 300,000 of them.
- Yeah, I think it's quite plausible.
And you can get some real crap published these days
and if you checked out the Sunday Times bestseller list.
- Well, the BBC, they did a feature about Iceland's book world
and they interviewed one novelist
called Kristen A.Rick's Gdartier
and she said, it is difficult,
especially as I live with my mother and partner
who are also full-time writers.
But we try to publish an alternate years
so we do not compete too much.
- But they're in a constantly stressful household
with people up against publishing deadlines.
- I guess so.
- So I guess they hate each other anyway.
- Yeah.
- That's where we're gonna be when we publish our book
in two months' time at they hate each other stage.
- So it makes sense slightly of this Icelandic publisher
which I'm sure we all know about Tunglio.
So Tunglio, these are the ones that they publish
their books only on a full moon, the night of a full moon.
They publish in batches of 69
and if there are copies that are left over at the end
of the night, they burn the copies.
So it's this odd publisher where it allows for people
to sort of get their book out
but also not crowd the market.
They say they take a lot of care and respect
with the burning of the books.
They fuel the flames with French cognac
and it's all done very classily.
- Always fully depending on your perspective.
- There's a hate cognac as much as they hate books.
(laughing)
- Did you know George all well
when animal farm was translated into French?
It was called Les Animaux Pactoux
which is animals everywhere
but he wanted it to be called
Union des Republiques Socialist Animal
which is what it sounds like I guess
through a public of socialist animals.
That's because it would be shortened to U-R-S-A
which is French for bear
and of course that would be a nice
another reference to the Russians.
- Oh, that's so clever.
- But they didn't go with it.
They went with animals everywhere, exclamation marks.
- We just sounds like a fun romper.
- It does.
- It sounds like a kids book
where there's a mistake at the zoo
and animals get everywhere.
(laughing)
- Yeah, is there a bear in animal farm?
- No.
- It's mostly farm animals.
- Yeah.
- Is there a half ape vampire?
- Lots of those, yeah.
- It goes landing version.
You can't move forward.
(laughing)
I've one final thing about translation.
It's really tangential though.
But there is a thing called
the crew and equipment translation aids
which is on the International Space Station.
It's a miniature train.
There's a miniature train on the outside
of the International Space Station.
- What?
- Yeah.
I know.
And it's also called the mobile transporter
and that's to say that it is simultaneously
the fastest and slowest train in the universe.
- Wow.
- It's because it's spinning around the earth.
- Exactly.
- And the slowest because it takes 10 days
to get to the next person.
- Yeah, it moves at one inch per second, top speed.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- Well, have they not heard of Southern Rail?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is out of the 360 million
common bears made every year less than 1%
are actually common bear.
- Hmm.
That's not the fact I've got down here.
- No.
- For what you said.
- What have you got?
- Out of the 360 million wheels
of camembert produced every year,
only four are actually common bear.
Well, that would be less than 1%,
but it would be a lot less than 1%.
So this, that was my original fact admittedly.
(laughing)
And I read it in the independent
and I think when they said just four are true common bear,
I think they meant four million.
(laughing)
- Yes.
- The disappointing discovery we all made this morning
is we started research.
- I would have thought unbelievably expensive cheeses
on the market every year.
- Yeah.
- If you just have four small wheels of camembert produced.
So what it is is the French have a protected designation
of origin label which they put on real camembert.
And in order to be a real camembert,
you have to have used unfiltered raw milk.
Your cows can only be fed grass and hay from local pastures.
You're not allowed to move the milk more
than a couple of fields before you make the cheese.
You need to ladle it by hand
and the milk has to have a fat content of at least 38%.
And if you don't follow any of those rules,
you can still sell camembert like cheese,
but it's not the official camembert stuff.
And I thought when I first read it,
that only four cheeses managed to do that,
but actually it seems about four million,
which is still only 1%, which means more often than not.
If you're buying a random camembert cheese,
it's likely to not be the real deal.
- So is it, would it somewhere on the package subtly say that?
- So the, the stuff which doesn't have that label
is usually labeled camembert fabric on Normandy.
- But it is cam, it is like a lot of places,
you know, you can't use the actual name of something
unless it's made in the place it was made or in a certain way.
But it is camembert, all this other stuff,
it's just not made the Normandy way
that camembert makers in France think camembert should be made,
the proper way, right? - It's not the real deal.
- It's not the real deal. - Yeah, yeah.
- I can't believe cheese generally in shops isn't the real deal.
- No idea until I started looking into this.
- What do you mean? - It's all ham.
- It's some ham.
- The sort of regulations of what can be labeled as cheese
means that only 51% of the product needs to be cheese.
- Wow. - The rest of it can be something else.
But if 51% of it is cheese, then you can call it a cheese.
- So what if we just sell smaller blocks of cheese
just next to some wood?
- 'Cause people wouldn't buy that, would they?
- I guess they wouldn't.
- I don't know.
- That's why my little shop closed down.
(laughing)
- There was a kind of cheese war
over the camembert thing in 2007.
When I say a war, I mean a minor legal dispute.
But all the big producers wanted to say proper camembert
is the stuff we're making.
Even though the milk is pasteurized
and the cows actually have come from elsewhere
and they're eating grass from somewhere else still
and all of the stuff and there's not 38% fat.
It was a big legal dispute.
The courts came down on the side of the little guy
who was only making 1% of the cheese.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Good for the courts.
They were always the good guy, the courts.
- Yep.
(laughing)
- Do you know there was only one family making camembert
until around the 1870s and they were the direct descendents
of the lady who invented it, supposedly Marie Harrell.
- There were good PR people.
So I think her grand son,
oh maybe grandson in law, met Napoleon III
and brought a big wheel of cheese to a show.
So then he became the imperial supplier.
So then camembert was a big deal there.
And they also made it in 1813.
They made it an honorary citizen of the city of Cayenne.
- The cheese. - Yeah.
So camembert became an honorary citizen.
- The pepper must have been pretty pissed off
if that hadn't been the--
(laughing)
- Give it the cheese to the city.
- Very good. - Nice.
- Yeah. - Yeah, strong.
- Guys, have you heard of the Mondial du Frommage?
- No. - Okay, strap in.
- This is the world's greatest cheese mungering competition.
- Oh yeah.
- This is to be the best cheese munger, okay?
It happened in France and this year
the first ever American got a medal.
I think an American came third in the competition.
But it's held every other year and it is so hard.
It starts with a 20 question written exam.
Then there's a blind taste test.
You have to get the name, how it was made,
the region, the milk used, and how long it was aged.
- Wow.
- Then you have to cut four identical 25 gram pieces of cheese
by hand with no measuring tools.
You have to cut four identical size pieces of cheese.
Then there's a five minute speech
where you have to present a cheese to the judges
and say why it's good.
Then there's a swimsuit round.
(laughing)
That's the first morning.
Then there's more in the afternoon.
And one 2015 competitor said the afternoon
is the four hardest hours of cheese.
You couldn't have had it.
(laughing)
You have to make a cheese plate for the judges
and then do a carving out of cheese
and then do a large cheese board.
And you have to justify all your decisions.
- And what do you get at the end when you've done all this?
- I don't think there's a big, yeah,
there's probably a small medal or a cash prize
or not a big cash prize.
But you just get the honor of being
the greatest cheese munger in the world.
- That's right.
- Yeah.
- Sounds really fun.
- They take it very seriously, don't they?
They've got a brotherhood of the Knights of Camembert
tasting, which is like a Mason society
for Camembert tasteers.
And they all have this huge fancy dress festival
once a year where they dress up like Mason's
and they have this like really solemn.
- Come on.
- Yeah, you were thicker.
- You were thicker cheese.
- Yeah, of course you were.
- You can't go as a bit, it's a serious festival.
- A fancy dress.
- It's a fancy dress, a fancy like Mason's dress.
A fancy dress brackets, but be a Mason.
- I'm not about you to our fancy dress party.
(laughing)
She's come as a Mason again.
- Which cheese would you go as James?
- I think I'd go as a baby bell.
- That's a good one.
- What would the wrapper honor off?
- Half on actually.
- In hot wax.
- I would paint my face red, half of it.
And then I'd shave my hair.
And the top of it would like be the open bit
of the baby bell and the button bit would be the close bit.
- So it's just your head that's the baby bell.
- Yeah, and the rest of my body
I'll shape like a plate.
(laughing)
- Well that's a good idea.
- This is one of the rounds in the Mondialdi firmware.
(laughing)
- I think I'd go as a Swiss cheese.
- What'd you?
- Yeah.
- How would you make the holes?
- I'd fill a sheet with holes and I wear the sheet.
A yellow sheet obviously.
- Would you wear anything under the sheets?
- No.
- You'd be very careful where you put the holes.
(laughing)
- What would you go as Anna?
- I don't know, I can't think of any cheese string maybe.
- Cheese string.
- Yes, like peel bits off myself as the evening went on.
- That's great.
- You could put all your hair up straight
and then slowly like take the strands off of it.
- Make it down.
Yes, 'cause I was actually thinking of panning
to peel off my entire skin,
which would have been a real asshole as sacrifice.
- Dan's gonna get a lump of cheese,
which is 51% bigger than him.
- Yeah.
- You just stand next to him.
- I was gonna do.
- Now I was gonna go as a leg of ham.
- Just really.
(laughing)
- Charlotte Goal once said,
"How do you govern a country
which has 246 varieties of cheese?"
(laughing)
What was the answer?
- It was a rhetorical question.
- Oh, one of those.
- But the answer is you sought out
the massive competition to work out
who's the best cheese monger.
- And actually, you just reduced the numbers of cheese.
So they've got far fewer cheeses than when he would have said that.
I think they've lost 50 cheeses in the last 30 years.
- No.
- And there's something called the Slow Food Organization,
which is trying to save endangered cheese
and other endangered food stuff, actually.
But yeah, it's like lots of artists and cheeses have disappeared.
- Britain has more cheeses than France now, don't we?
- Yes.
And they're better.
- Well, I don't know.
- I don't like any of them.
- Got, so are they actually extinct cheeses
or can we reproduce them as in have the recipes been lost?
- Oh, no, the recipes will be there.
It's just like how everything when it starts being done
on a large scale, the little artists and producers get lost.
- But the other thing is a lot of these rely
on certain strains of bacteria.
So it could be that those strains have gone.
- Oh, yeah, they might have gone extinct.
You're right.
- And even if you get it back,
you don't know whether you've got exactly the right one anymore.
- Unless there's like a super old guy in the village
who remembers the taste of the extinct cheese
and you bring it to him and you let him sample.
- Yeah, I think there is one of those
in every French village, actually.
- They just keep one old guy.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Cheese taste, sir.
- Do you guys know about the world's most dangerous cheese?
- Oh, no.
- Is it the cheese rolling people,
'cause they're always injuring themselves, aren't they?
In Gloucestershire, they always run down a hill after some cheese.
- Oh, yeah, and you're saying that cheeses,
the world's most dangerous one, they're chasing after, yeah.
- It's not the cheeses fault, admittedly.
- That's like saying foxes are really dangerous,
'cause a lot of people get injured on fox hunts.
You know, it's not actually the foxes fault, is it?
- No.
- Anyway, it's not that.
- Is it something that's not pasteurised and might make you sick?
- Oh, is it the one that's full of maggots?
- It is one that's got, yeah, cassoumazu.
Have we talked about that before?
- Oh, I think so.
- It's great.
So it's from Sardinia, it's actually illegal.
I think the EU banned it a few years ago,
but you can still get it on the black market.
And yeah, the way you make it is
you infest pecorino cheese with maggots,
with these cheese fly maggots.
And they eat the cheese and then they excrete it
while they're inside.
And that's what adds the flavour.
So apparently it's really kind of creamy,
'cause their excretion of the cheese
and the way they processed it is tangy and aromatic.
- Do you have to eat the maggots?
- You do eat the maggots, yeah, 'cause they're inside.
- You have to.
- But it's quite hassle picking them out, I think.
- They jump out at you if I remember rightly.
- That's what people say.
You have livery all these maggots.
- I don't know.
- You've got to be careful of not getting hit in the face.
- So why is it dangerous to people die?
- Well, on the EU decided on hygiene grounds.
I don't think there have been any deaths related to it.
So it's probably just health and safety gone mad.
- I would be the fast-pot sitting there
picking out every single maggot.
- You could just eat around the maggots.
- Yeah, I just want to eat the maggot excrement.
Thank you very much.
- I think I'd go for a slightly less flavour some cheese,
but without the maggots in it.
I'm willing to put up with a slightly less flavour.
- I think that's a good idea.
- Yeah, I like cheddar.
I'll just have cheddar.
(upbeat music)
Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is Andy.
My fact is that Norway's coastline is so long
that if you took a piece of string along it
and then stretched it out,
it would run around the whole planet two and a half times.
Okay, so it needs to be quite a long piece of string.
- Yeah, you don't get balls of string
that big, I don't think, in your local hog restaurant.
- You would buy a few and then tie them together.
- Yeah, I was dreaming about this last night actually.
- Weirdly, it was genuinely in my dream.
I thought what if you had a long enough string
that could go around the world,
which would be shorter than the string you need for Norway, right?
'Cause you need two and a half, two and a half of those.
If you managed to get that kind of string
and you tied it to the coast of, let's say England,
and you just set off, could you wrap the world in that string
if you went completely around?
- I suppose in theory you could.
But here's something for you.
Imagine you added three feet of string
to that one that's going all the way around the world
and then you made it tight.
How much above the surface of the earth would it be?
- Oh, you know what I mean by that?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Hold on, so you could lift it a bit loose if you had three feet.
- Dan's holding a piece of string.
I carry it all the way around the world
and then give him the other end.
And then we add an extra three feet of string to it.
How much higher would it go?
- I would say it will basically not be higher at all.
- Yeah, like a fraction of a minimum.
- That's what you think.
The actual answer is 5.7 inches, about six inches.
- Wow.
- And it's basically maths and the circumference of a circle.
And this six inch difference is the same
whether it's the size of the earth
or whether you just put it around your stomach, for instance.
- No.
- If you had the three feet, it would just move out
by that amount.
- Wow.
- That is amazing.
- That is really cool.
- That is an old paradox which was originally,
the earliest I found of it was 1702.
- Oh, cool.
- Book by William Whitston.
- I don't really understand that, but I'm very impressed.
- Yeah, it's super cool.
- So just on Norway quickly.
This was sent to me actually by a guy on Twitter called
at YPLAC.
He used work for a ferry company in Norway.
- For a string company.
(laughing)
- He's got shares of that.
And he said that he learned if you took a piece of string
and ran it along Norway's coastline,
you could run it from London to Bangkok and back again.
But that might have been before,
there was a recalculation of the coast of Norway
by some geographers in 2011.
And the basic point is that Norway
is one of the most complicated coastlines on the planet
because it has all these fields
where instead of going straight north to south,
it goes in for a hundred miles
and then out for a hundred miles again.
So you've added 200 miles to the coast
even though you're only 50 meters further along it.
- Yeah.
- So Norway's unbelievably crinkly.
- Yeah, I think they added,
if you leave out the fjords it's 1573
and if you include them it's 18,000 miles of coastline.
- Wow, it is unbelievable.
- But that's, I was looking into the biggest coastlines
in the world by numbers and Canada's number one.
- Yeah.
- But what Canada you'd be able to go around the earth five times?
- Yes, yeah.
And what kind of shock to me was that
Japan is ahead of Australia,
which doesn't make sense when you think about it
because if you look at the sizes of the two places,
Australia's got way more coast,
but what Japan has is all these tiny islands,
which constitute being Japan.
So when you add all of them up,
they're ahead of Australia.
- Yeah, it's nuts.
- Yeah, this is why this fact is strange, right?
Because actually every list could be different, right?
In terms of the longest coastline
depending on the way that you're measuring it.
So a coastline can be infinitely long.
So imagine you've got a meter long ruler
then you're only measuring a contour every meter.
And so it's going to be much, much shorter
than if you go around with a one centimeter measure
and you'll measure much more lumps and bumps.
It's like if you've got a 30 centimeter ruler
with some lumps and bumps in it,
and then you actually ran a string
all the way in and out of the lumps and bumps,
that piece of string would be much longer than 30 centimeters.
So actually, Norway's coastline could theoretically go
to the end of the universe and back.
- Well, it's not quite infinite because there's a minimum length
that you can have, which is a plank length.
You can't measure anything smaller than the plank length,
but that is really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really,
20th century when and the first person to really work it out was a guy called Lewis Frey Richardson
who wanted to work out whether the likelihood of two countries going to war depended on the length
of their border. Okay, so he looked at a load of different borders and for instance when he looked
at the Spain Portugal border he found that Spain thought it was 987 kilometers but Portugal thought
it was 1214 kilometers. They immediately went to war over the world. Why did Stalin 300 kilometers of
our border? And then it was picked up by Mandel Brotton, all the mathematicians who did all this
fractal stuff. Yeah, he was amazing. So I hadn't really heard of him before this but he was a
mathematician and he wrote an academic paper which was called How Long is the Coast of Britain
and he said it's impossible for the same reason that the closer you look the more crinkly something
gets. But Norway is special so Norway has a larger what they call a fractal dimension than other
countries. Really? It just is more crinkly. Yeah. Yeah. Okay, so on the fjords, the fjords,
the deepest fjord, this one was actually also said to me by @whyblack, the deepest fjord is so deep
that if you got to the deepest point of the deepest one, right, you know the Burj Khalifa,
the tallest building in the world, you could strap the Empire State Building to the top of the
Burj Khalifa and drop the whole thing into the deepest fjord and it would still be more than 100
metres from the surface. It's a lot of effort just to prove that point, isn't it? You won't be able to
see it because it's underwater, so I don't know. I think I just believe it. And also the Burj Khalifa
is very pointy at the top but actually you should probably put the Empire State Building at the
bottom and then the Burj Khalifa on top. No, because you've got a very pointy bit at the top of the
Empire State Building as well. They're both pointy at the top. It's not going to work. Are you counting,
are you counting the pointy bit at the top of the Empire State Building? You know the bit that
they used to attach blimps to. All right, it's probably 96 metres from the top. If you don't count
the bit these attached blimps to. But you could, if you put the Empire State Building at the bottom,
then you could use the spike to impale the other one on top of and that would be how you welded
them together. You could do the same the other way around though. You could impale the bottom of the
Empire State. Yeah, no, you're right. It's a thank you for coming up with the solution. Yeah,
I think it's a good idea. I think we should do it. I reckon just like normal measuring equipment
like Sona might be better. Yeah. I'm so sorry for reading out a fact that someone sent me,
which is a very I think visually creative means of telling you the depth of a fjord. Imagine if
we did measure stuff using skyscrapers every time we had to measure something new. We had to take
down the skyscrapers and drop it in an ocean. If we measured the coastline of Norway with the
Burj Al Khalifa, it would be a lot shorter. Yeah. That's a very good point. So we should do it.
Just one more thing on Norway's amazing engineering feats. There's a little town called Rukken.
It's R.J.U. K.A.N. How does it say? Right, you can. Right, you can. Oh my god.
Yeah, there's a little town called Rukken. And it's got 3,400 people there and the problem that
this town has had forever really is that it's in amongst the mountain range and it's constantly in
shade. So for a lot of the year, they just don't see sun. They can see sun at the top of the mountain,
hitting the mountain, but they're just covered in shade. It's been a massive problem and there's
been tiny things to sort of try and fix it like a service, a cable car service was started. So you
could pay a small amount. Go up the cable car and just experience some sun and then come back down
again as a little ride. So they've recently fixed it. This is a few years ago now. An engineer came
up with an idea of creating three massive solar powered mirrors that now reflect the sun
into the valley and now they live in sunlight again and it tracks where the sun is going throughout
the day. So the mirror moves towards it to make sure the sunlight is always pushing down. So
this town that was in permanent shade is now sunny all the time. It's now being constantly
fried by trying to be concentrated beams of heat. If you want to kill an ant, go to Rukken.
That is amazing. It's cool. I mean, what a solution. But then you also think why build a town there
in the first place? Yes, exactly. I guess it's easier than moving the town to the top of the mountain.
Yeah, but it's not like 50 years ago that town would have been in the sunshine. No, you're right.
Maybe the mountain's grown. You know how Everest has grown a bit or shrunk a bit. Perhaps the
mountain's grown by 100 meters or so. Everest is shrunk by one inch. So perhaps the exact same
thing is haven't except in reverse and to a much greater faster extent. Also, my lawn is growing
at the moment and the bit of it isn't growing very well because it's in the shade a lot because it's
next to the vents. So where can I get these mirrors? A mirror store? I'm guessing. Oh, you want the
solar powered ones? Yeah, really. I mean, that's going to be better, isn't it? I need to go to Rukken.
Yeah, steel one. The lich has been left in darkness due to one Englishman's whim.
Okay, it is time for our final, we say fact.
And that is Adich Zitsky. My facts this week is that, now prepare yourselves for this, you've got
to focus. Beef stroganov is named after the great grandson of the person who brought human
chest to Russia. That's a great fact. It's a stroganov part of beef stroganov we're talking about.
Not, not, it's a beef. It was constantly getting into fights with people. His
crest was a big cow in the worst. What's your beef? It wasn't beef. It was a stroganov family. So
this was a big noble family in Russia from, I'd been thinking about the 16th century, but certainly
under the 19th and early 20th century. So there was Count Alexander stroganov, who in the very
early 19th century decided to turn his townhouse lawn into a chessboard, a giant chessboard for fun,
and he had his servants beat all the pieces, and he dressed them all up as a different pieces.
And then he had the game be orchestrated by chess players. So there was one that was, there were two
grandmasters at the time, or I don't know if they had grandmasters, but players of the time
called Count Ivan Osterman and Lev Nalyishkin, and they told the servants were to move and they moved.
And that was introducing chess to Russia. Human chess. Human chess. And then, fast forward a hundred
years, his great-grandson is called Pavel Sergeyevich stroganov, and he apparently had a chef
who came up with stroganov the dish and named it after this family. And there are some stories
that say that it was his grandfather, Pavel, who initially inspired it, and it had been the
family for years. So maybe it was named after the chess guy's son, but our first mention of
stroganov that we have is from the 1880s, 1890s, and named after Pavel. I think we think that probably
isn't named after him, right? It's probably named after the family. Yeah, it'll be named after
the family, yeah. Anyway, I just love this connection. Also, I just spent a long time reading about
the stroganov family. It is a connection between two things that you wouldn't say a
household item really. It's not like the guy who invented the fork is the grandson of the guy who
invented dogs. I play human chess. The fork came up with a dog. I'm saying it's not that. It's the
other way around. The grandson of the guy who invented the dog who invented the fork. Wow.
I have a couple of human chess pieces in my house. Do you mean humans? Yeah, I do. So actually,
you know, I just call that a household item. That's good for you. I didn't really think much about
it until starting researching this fact. I didn't realise that it was a big thing in, for example,
Russia, and there's a festival in Italy. It's not a big thing. It's not a big thing. Actually,
I don't think you'll continue thinking about it after we've researched this fact. Yeah,
but it is a thing that happens sometimes. So there is a place in Italy which has one massive
match every two years and they dress up in historical costume. And I think they actually act out a
particular chess game. Oh, yeah. Yes, they do. It's one that was written about in a novel. This is in
Maro Stiecker, isn't it? Yes, it is. Isn't it the story of a famous match played between two
knights who were both wanting to court a princess and the winner was allowed to court the princess?
What? Yeah, I think that's the story behind it. Well, neither of them could get to it because they
could only move two steps forward or one step to the side. Wait, hang on. That's the story of how we
got a human chess. No, the story of the game that's played every two years, the exact game.
In Maro Stiecker, that's what they're celebrating. Supposedly, the original game that they were
following, the moves of were played by two knights. We've played a game of normal chess. And it's
written about in a fictional story in the early 20th century. Yeah, and none of it's real.
Have you heard of chess city? It's in Russia? No. Okay, it's in one of the southern provinces.
It's southwest Russia. And it's in a town called Elista. And there's an enclave in that town,
which is a mini chess city. And it was built by our old friend, Kirsn Iliongenov, who
until 2010 was the leader of this province. And he is also the head of the International
and Chess Federation. He's the one who claims to have been abducted by aliens. And he thinks
that Sweet Corn and Chess are from outer space or something. Exactly. And in 1998 to host the 33rd
Chess Olympiad, he built Chess City, which has a chess museum, a large open-air chessboard,
and a museum of Buddhist art. Wow. Because there are a lot of Buddhist living in Elista.
Mars, incorporated are one of the biggest pet food companies in America. They might be the
biggest, actually. And they make beef stroganoff for pets, for dogs, specifically. Why didn't they
call it beef dog enough? Because that would be, like, cannibalism. Yeah, that's confusing.
You don't want to eat, like, an Andy Lasagna, do you?
But they use Tigray and Murray. Anyway, these kind of things, they make $100 million in annual sales,
these kind of human-like pet foods. Wow, that's so weird. I really want to verify this. There are
books on chess history that say that Charles Martel, who was Charlemagne's grandfather,
is a person who invented human chess originally in the world. And they claim that he played a
game of living chess, I think, in the eighth century, when he was at war with Arab forces and they
introduced chess to them. And he had his servants play it. If anyone has any first-hand evidence
that happened, I'd really enjoy reading it. First-hand evidence.
I want Charles Martel's exact words. This is actually one really old guy in every French village
who was part of that game. My grandfather was a pawn.
Okay, that's it. That's all of our facts. Thank you so much for listening. If you'd like to
get in contact with any of us about the things that we've said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts. I'm on @Sriberland, James, @XshapedAndy, @AndruHunterM,
Anna, you can email podcasts@ky.com. Yep, or you can go to our group account, which is at
QI podcast. We can also be found on our website. No such thing as a fish.com. It's got all of our
previous episodes up there. It's got all of our tour dates up there. And it's also got a link
to our book coming out in November, the Book of the Year. We'll be back again next week with another
episode. We'll see you then. Good bye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]