- Hey everyone, welcome to this week's episode of Fish.
Before we get going, we have a very exciting announcement.
Anna?
- Thanks, Dan.
Our announcement is that our esteemed colleague,
Andrew Hunter Murray, famous podcaster, comedian galore.
Does one say that?
He's also a published author.
I'm sure you've read his first two novels,
which were brilliant thrillers.
He's written a third, which is so much fun so far.
I'm only about a quarter of the way through,
because look, he didn't send me the proof on time,
but it is fantastic.
It's called a beginner's guide to breaking and entering.
It's really fun.
It's got elements of comedy.
It's got elements of thriller in it so far.
I really love the main character
'cause he's doing something
that I can really imagine myself doing in life.
Don't just believe us.
It's been complemented by The Guardian,
which says it has a propulsive plot,
an ingenious narrator and lashings of intrigue,
making it a genuine and thoroughly enjoyable page turner.
The Sunday Times has called it hugely entertaining,
laugh out loud funny and impossible to put down.
Dan Shriver, what do you say?
- Well, I actually am a third of the way through the book.
And I can say-- - All right,
and I need to break? - It absolutely gets better
after the first quarter.
So if you want your books great in the first quarter
and then accelerating to an even better place,
you gotta get a beginner's guide to breaking and entering.
It is the story of a guy who breaks
into the second homes of the wealthy.
He lives in them.
They don't know it.
He steals nothing, but one day,
after he accidentally bumps into a group of people
who also do the same thing, they witness a murder
and they get embroiled in a thing that they can't escape.
And it's one of those comedy capers
that just gets further and further into the chaos of it.
If you've read Richard Osman's
The Thursday Murder Club series,
this is the perfect accompaniment to it.
It's comedy, it's thriller, page turner, you're gonna love it.
- So go to your local bookshop or any online bookseller
or Amazon, look up a beginner's guide
to breaking and entering by Andrew Hunter Murray now.
- Okay, on with the podcast.
- On with the show.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
James Harkin and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that children's author,
Margaret Wise Brown, died from doing
an over-enthusiastic can-can kick.
- I think now having read up on her,
she would like that we laughed just then.
- Yeah, I think so.
- Definitely.
- So is there an under-enthusiastic can-can kick?
Is there such a thing as that?
- Oh yeah, yeah.
I've been to the Moulin Rouge a few times
and asked for my money back.
Barely got above the knee.
- You've got your protractor out in the front row.
(laughing)
- That was disgusting, I mean.
They really looked out at that.
So Margaret Wise Brown is most famous
for a children's book called Good Night Moon.
She's written lots of others, but this is the biggie.
What I liked about this is in this podcast,
the number of times I've got a book out
because we've talked about that author
and I've got about 25% of the way through it
and never finished that one.
This is probably the first time
I've got through the whole book.
- Oh, you finished it?
- I managed to finish it.
- All 140-ish words, right?
(laughing)
- I thought you were going to say pages then.
I was going to say, no, that wasn't the book I read.
Yeah, it's a very short book.
Actually, the first, maybe the first of those board books,
you know, that you give to children,
apparently it was the first of those.
But she unfortunately died in 1952.
She just had emergency surgery on either an ovarian cyst
or an inflamed appendix, depending on what you read.
And she was ready to leave the hospital
and be carried, as she said,
in a sedentary by four of the village boys
to a hilltop estate where she would convalesce,
but to show the medical staff that she was in good health.
She kicked up her leg, can-can style,
and she had a blood clot, dislodged it, blacked out,
and never died again.
- According to what I read, died instantly.
- Yeah.
- Like, can-can kicked and just out.
It's sad, obviously, but that's how I would love to go.
- Can't, can't, can't, can't, can't.
(laughing)
- It's a good way to go, I think,
if you've got to go at that age.
- Yeah, I mean, she was so young, she was 42.
And she was, the other cool thing about this,
she was on her way to meet, I think, her lover,
one of the junior rocker-fellas,
who was going to pick her up in a boat
and sail away to Tunisia with her.
- Yeah, he was on his way, on the boat.
- Yeah.
- So sad.
- I think that was maybe the saddest thing,
is that she'd had a very unlucky love life,
and she'd met this guy sort of the year before, I think,
and I was reading a bit of a biography of her
that he wrote many, many years later,
and he was so, obviously, so in love with her,
and she had finally found the love of her life.
And then, yeah, bam, he was nicknamed Pebble,
but it was a still, James Stillman, rocker-fella junior,
and he was junior, he was 24.
- Yeah. - Oh, wow.
- Toy boy.
- He later married a descendant of the Carnegie's.
So it's a real powerhouse couple of that,
the rocker-fellas and the Carnegie's.
- Yeah.
- Carnegie's. - Carnegie's, I would say.
- Carnegie's are the ones who come up to you in the bar
and say, "That's a shit shirt."
(all laughing)
- That's not how you neg.
The neg is a compliment, and then a backhanded compliment.
- What? - What should I be doing?
- You should say, "I love your shirt.
"I saw six people wearing it earlier tonight."
- Oh, that's good, that's a true better than mine.
(all laughing)
- But yeah, Margaret Was Brown was a absolute legend.
- What a gal.
- She was, and she sort of, the fact is,
is that she's often referred to
as almost like a Hollywood dame.
Like she was going around in high-class parties,
she was doing the weirdest of stuff socially.
She took all the-- - Oh yeah.
- She had things like the Bird Brain Club,
which it was a club where the decision was
anyone who was part of it.
If they said on the day, "It's Christmas,"
you have to go over and celebrate Christmas.
- It's a fun idea.
- It's a great idea. - I got an idea.
- Oh, it's a tiresome idea.
It's a fun idea, the first two times you do it.
And even by the third time, it's annoying.
- I think it was used wisely.
- I'm sure some people were kicked out
of the Christmas club or whatever it was.
- Bird Brain Society. - Bird Brain Society.
She could run as fast as a dog?
- There we go. (all laughing)
- Which dog?
Not a Greyhound.
- No, you're absolutely right.
Well, I've written in my notes, she was a lifelong beagle.
She was actually a beagle-er,
which is where you trace hairs on foot,
and you have a load of beagle dogs with you.
And supposedly she was noted for her ability
to keep pace with running beagles.
- Her relationship with rabbits gets intense
when she's an author, because she published a book
which was called Little Fur Family.
The illustrator was the same guy, Gareth Williams,
who did the illustrations for Charlotte's Web.
She had a first print run of 75,000 copies for this book,
and each edition of it was wrapped entirely in the fur
of a New Zealand rabbit.
- No. - Yeah, I don't believe you.
- And were they all ones that she caught herself
while being a beagle? (all laughing)
- Yeah, I have no idea.
- It's amazing, isn't it? - Sorry, no.
- Apparently it was because of a surrealist artist
called Meret Oppenheim, who you might know this,
it's like a teacup with rabbit fur on the inside
and the outside, actually, you don't know that.
It's in the Museum of Modern Art in New York, is it, I think?
And it was the first surrealist thing that they bought.
But yeah, she decided she would do her own thing
with books and make them really furry.
- But it's 75,000. - 75,000?
- Yeah, it's mad.
- Dan, you mentioned that you haven't read Good Night Moon,
so you won't be aware, as I am,
as someone who reads it every single night, my daughter.
The main character in that is also a rabbit.
They're both rabbits, so having read this about her,
I look at that completely differently now,
every page where you see this old rabbit in a rocking chair.
- It's a fantastic book, we should say.
- It's so good. - It's so good.
- It's pretty good, it's like one of the first ones
that just was slightly weird and just rhyming stuff.
- Yeah.
- It's just a little bunny going to bed,
and it's all the stuff in the room,
Good Night Blocks and Good Night Socks and all that.
It's just very gentle, sort of lulling for child.
I'm sure I was read it lots, I think.
- But she also didn't like children,
as well as not liking rabbits.
It's kind of weird to make a book about rabbits for children,
if you don't like either of those things.
- Yeah, 'cause she also did another book,
which had a print run of 80,000,
which was entirely wrapped in the skin of five-year-olds.
- She said in an article for Life Magazine,
she said, "I don't especially like children."
And in another note to someone,
she wrote, "How many children have you got?
"I have 50 bucks."
So I think she saw the bucks as her.
- All right, they are less trouble.
Have you seen all the Easter eggs in Good Night Moon?
This is just what happens
when you have read it over 100 times now.
- I don't know how to read it again.
- You are.
- There's so much you start to discover.
- Don't tell me it's the same with Les Miserables,
'cause I'm not reading that again.
- As long as you've got the illustrated version.
Well, I won't give it away so you can discover it,
but if you do have a copy,
look at the clock on every page and look at the moon.
- To go backwards?
- No, it doesn't.
- Oh, like memento.
- That would be so much better.
Why didn't you, it just goes forwards.
Just goes forwards.
And so you know that it takes an hour and 10 minutes
to get this rabbit to sleep when you want to go forwards,
which is actually a long time.
And look at the book on the bedside table.
What do you think the book on the bedside table is?
- Is it the book itself?
- It's the book itself.
- Is it?
- That's surreal.
- It hasn't met her.
- Good Night Moon, still innovating all these years later.
- She wrote her book, she said,
in a sort of 15 to 20 minute period.
That's the first draft.
And then the second draft.
- This is all about your books, isn't it?
(laughing)
- So it takes a 15 to 20 minutes for the first draft.
And then it takes her between one and two years
for the second draft.
- Oh, and that's where you go and rub no second draft.
(laughing)
- Oh, the edit is hard, the edit is hard.
- Can we talk about the great thing she did
with the royalties?
- Yes.
- It's bizarre.
Margaret Weisbrand gave the royalties
to every single one of her books,
basically in her entire estate.
She said, I leave it all to this little nine year old boy
who lives next door, who I'm friendly with,
and you know, I'm 40.
Nothing's gonna happen to me.
I'll probably change the world
when I gain dependence or whatever.
Anyway, she then dies.
- Two years later, right?
- Two years later, she dies.
So, and also Good Night Moon was on the,
it was not selling big anymore.
It was probably gonna go out of print shortly.
Obviously it's never been out of print.
It's sold millions of copies.
And he was called Albert Clarke.
And by the time he was 21, there was $75,000 waiting for him.
Unfortunately, he had become a bit of a tear away.
- Oh yeah.
- A bit of a, a bit of a.
- A bit of a rogue.
- Bit of a rogue, burglary, joyriding, vandalism.
He's a very, very, very naughty boy.
- Kicked out of school for five,
saw that sort of.
- Yeah, and he had this bizarre life
where he was always broke and getting into trouble
and being arrested and banged up.
And then every year, publishers would say,
right, there's another two million quid waiting for you.
- It's like the lotto lout.
Do you remember him?
- No, I don't.
- Do you not remember him?
He was like, when the lottery first started,
I'm sure he's a very nice guy.
So apologies if you're listening,
but he won a load of money on the lottery
and then just spent it all within like two years or something.
And he was in all the tabloids as being a bit of a rogue.
But it's like that.
But then if then, once he spent it all,
he won the lottery again.
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, exactly.
So the first initial batch of money that he got,
he gave a lot to his parents, which was nice.
He gave $35,000 to his parents.
He spent $4,000 on clothes for him and his two brothers.
He had two brothers.
And then he bought a Chevy Impala.
As soon as he took it out of the shop,
got smashed into, immediately dented it.
- That's not his fault.
- No, no, but I read an interview with him
where he was sort of saying, look, yes, I've done bad things.
But also just like, bad things just happen all the time
that throw me into situations of such weird details.
It's like he had a dented car
and 14 pairs of alligator shoes.
That's all he had in life.
And then the next check comes in.
And the only thing he's kept with him wherever he goes
is the will.
He keeps the will that she wrote.
- And the alligator shoes.
The naked man wearing alligators on his feet,
collapsing and weird.
- Isn't it weird?
Like she was putting rabbits on her bucks.
He was putting alligators on his feet.
This is like the least vegan fact we've ever done.
(all laughing)
- I just mentioned her love life earlier,
which was, again, not something you imagine
when you're reading it,
'cause you picture this old lady.
He's writing these books.
- Also, her name sounds old, doesn't it?
Margaret Wise Brown.
It doesn't sound like wise, yeah.
I suppose in the 1920s, that was a really sexy name.
- Margaret is now a more old fashioned name.
I think that's fair.
Is that fair to say?
- Well, my mom's a Margaret.
- There we go.
- And she's very cool.
- Yeah.
- Coming every weekend.
(all laughing)
- She had an interesting love life.
- Oh yeah.
- She had his mom.
And so did Margaret Wise Brown.
And she went out with a woman called Michael Strange,
confusingly, who, I like the LA Times in 1992,
described Michael Strange as a writer and performer
of limited gifts and voracious ego.
And she did seem to be not a great partner
for Margaret Wise Brown,
but they got together in 1940
and pretty much lived together
or lived in next door apartments
until Strange died in 1950.
- They did share a butler.
- The two ladies.
- Yeah, so they had an apartment opposite each other.
So in the corridor,
the butler would just sort of go out the door,
go through the next door and sort of just--
- Wait, did they know?
Did they know that they were sharing a butler?
Or was he doing a sort of--
(all laughing)
- This is terrifying.
- Take the mustache off, yeah.
- You don't need to take the--
- Yeah, why would you do that?
- 'Cause they're dating.
- Oh, you're right, yeah.
- Oh, yeah.
How's your butler?
Well, he's still without a mustache.
- He must get one.
Mine looks dashing.
- That was pretty fun.
That's a great thing to do.
- I looked at a few other kids' authors.
Well, basically I went through my daughter's books
and googled all of their authors.
And I was looking at the tiger who came to tea.
- Oh, yeah.
- Which is by Judith Kerr.
And Michael Rosen, who was the children's laureate
and the writer and stuff,
he has drawn parallels between the tiger who came to tea
and Judith Kerr's early life.
'Cause Judith Kerr's father was on a death list
from the Nazis.
And they had to leave Nazi Germany
when she was nine years old.
- Wow.
- And Michael Rosen said that maybe the tiger
is based on the threat that they faced
when they were children,
because it disrupted their life so much.
They took everything that the family owned,
like the tiger who came to tea drinks all of the water
and eats everything in the cupboards and stuff like that.
And Judith Kerr has said
that the tiger represents nothing more than a tiger.
(all laughing)
- Well, I believe Michael, though.
- Yeah, I love you too.
- It's got a very weird ending, the tiger who came to tea.
- Yeah, well.
- Doesn't the tiger just leave?
- No, I think daddy comes home.
And it's really annoying because, you know,
the tiger's had all his, like--
- Drunk all his beer?
- Drunk all his beer and had all the food for tea.
- Yeah.
- So then--
- He says, "I've got a very good idea.
"We'll go to the cafe and have sausage and chips
"and ice cream."
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah, daddy takes them all out for--
- Meanwhile, there's a drunk tiger feeling that.
- The tiger goes unaddressed, exactly, yeah.
- No, because then the next morning,
they buy loads of food to fill the pantry up
and they buy a tin of tiger food in case he comes back
and he never did.
- Oh, really?
- Hmm.
- Interesting.
- I think if I was a dad walking back home,
I opened the door,
I see my three kids and my wife sitting by a table.
No, no, just like in my story.
And in the corner is a drunk tiger.
I do think my first instinct is to not make a deal of it.
Take kids, we're going out now.
- Okay, so, Dan, the tiger's already left
when daddy comes home.
- Oh, I thought you said he was drunk in the--
- No, so the daddy comes home and all the food's gone.
All the water's gone, there's no water in the tub.
- Oh yeah, wow.
- And Mummy and Sophie tell daddy what's happened
and said the tiger came in and ate all of the food
and drank all of the drinks and all of your beer
and took all the water out of the taps
and then daddy goes, let's go to a cafe.
That's how it works.
- It sounds like daddy doesn't believe a word of this.
It sounds like it's happened before.
- Yeah.
- And all the beer's gone, has it?
Oh, the tiger, right, yeah.
- Someone's turned the water off, have they?
- Okay.
- And the water bill over here, that's not been paid.
But the interesting thing about that
is when they walk to the cafe, it's nighttime,
so all the street lights are on
and all the cars have their headlights on,
but there's a little cat that's walking by
near where they live that looks exactly like a tiger,
but it looks like a cat long.
- It's acknowledged as a--
- No, it's not acknowledged,
but it's obviously like what inspired her lies.
- Yeah.
This drunken, reprobate lady's lies,
she booses up on her husband.
- I wish.
- Here's what we're gonna tell daddy.
(all laughing)
- Tiger.
- He's never gonna believe it, man.
- I wish I'd been able to,
'cause I was on a sofa with Michael Rosen yesterday.
- Were you?
- Yeah, but it was such a long sofa
that I couldn't ask him about this.
It was an enormously long sofa.
- Well, he wouldn't have heard you.
- Honestly, he wouldn't.
I would have had to get him and walk
to the other end of the sofa.
- Oh, wait, did you genuinely think,
ah, I'd love to talk to this man,
this legend of literature?
Ah, the sofa's too long.
- He had picked the absolute opposite.
He had picked the furthest other part of the sofa
and so on.
It was very clear to me
that he wasn't looking for a pal.
- Right.
- Well, you were DFS.
(all laughing)
- It was a call-as-o for as well,
so I could have walked the hypotenuse.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the city of Matsuyama
has over 90 post boxes specifically for mailing haiku.
- Mm-hmm, lovely.
- Or, as you could say, Matsuyama
has over 90 post boxes for mailing haiku.
- Brilliant. - Is that right?
- It's right. - It's right.
- It's right. - It's amazing.
- Well done, Anna. - Why?
- Why?
Why?
- Why did you bother making that haiku?
(all laughing)
- That's bloody easy to make, aren't they?
This is the capital city of Shikoku Island,
which is one of Japan's islands.
And it's because the city sort of calls itself
the home of haiku because very famous haiku poets
lived there.
And so the first post box was installed in 1968
to commemorate one of these poets' births.
And now they're all over the place.
They're like monuments and baths, public baths,
and they're really beautiful as well
and lots of different designs.
And every three months,
the local haiku poets go to the post boxes
or they send an envoy and they empty them out
and then they judge all the entries.
- Oh, yeah. - And the winner
gets published on the city's website.
- It's so good. - It's so great.
- I hope there's a walking trail.
There is between them, which is called the Taker Haiku.
- Lovely. - That would be good.
- Nice.
- But there is a walking trail.
Sorry to jump in on your joke.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, I didn't see it coming.
- You should be able to see by now that long,
that distant look in my eyes,
but it shows something's brewing.
- The fact he's been silent for two minutes done,
that should have been a clue.
- Yeah, no, they do in this place as well,
the Matsuyama area.
They have certain haiku bars that you go into
and you go up to the counter and you write a haiku
and the cocktail they make you is based on your haiku.
- No. - It's just, you know,
they love a haiku, they love a novelty thing to do there, yeah.
- What do you say?
Gin and tonic, please.
(all laughing)
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
- Is it Bashou who was from this place
or is it someone else?
'Cause he's the most famous haiku guy.
- He is, yeah, there seem to be sort of four kings of haiku
and he's like the king of kings.
But no, it's Masaoka Shiki who was the person
who rejuvenated haiku in the 19th century.
So it basically sort of died, it was really dying
and he lit a fire under its arse and--
- Redamed it as well.
- And gave it its name. - Gave it its name haiku.
It was called like Hoku or something before.
- Oh, so it didn't change it much.
- No, he just put a stamp on it.
He just, yeah, this is the Shiki stamp.
- It's really interesting what Shiki did
'cause he was obsessed with haiku.
He failed his exams at university,
partly because he was writing so many haiku
and reading haiku and he was engrossed in the world of haiku.
He sort of added to the rules about haiku
and the first, the most important thing
about haiku as we know them
is that it's an observation of what's around you.
It's an observation of nature.
So that's a key element to haiku.
- So actually what Anna did at the start was not a haiku.
- No, it was a culture.
- It had the right number of syllables in
but it has to have something to do with nature
or something to do, it has to have a word
that's something to do with one of the seasons.
So for instance, there's a really famous one
by Bashou who I mentioned earlier
which goes an ancient pond, a frog jumps in,
the splash of water.
In Japanese it works as a haiku.
But for him, it's the word frog refers to spring.
It's a spring word.
And so you need one of those.
And so unless you're using the word postbox to refer to-
- Yeah, it's a classic autumnal word, postbox.
It's in the glossaries.
- I get it now.
So I read that earlier, that one.
And I thought, you know, it was like,
this was one that he published and became famous.
And he was like dining off it for years.
Like, "Where in that haiku was insane?"
And I didn't find it impressive at all.
I didn't make the spring and the frog connection.
That's wonderful.
- And now are you wowed by it?
- I do like the punnery in the kind of double meaning.
- Are we saying it because frogs jump?
- No, no, no, no.
- No, that's not it.
- Oh, then I just like it again.
I thought that is what was going on.
- Sorry, that wouldn't-
- That wouldn't work at all in Japanese.
- Please, no.
- No, it's just that frogs come out in spring.
That's in their barn in spring.
So they're associated with spring time.
And it's supposed to you read it
and it just puts you in that position
of being in a garden in spring.
The frog jumps in, you know exactly where you are.
You know what's happening.
You're one with nature.
That's it.
- Do you get it now?
- I get it now.
Listen, it's no good night moon.
It's like-
- What it's meant to be is like,
it's like a shot in a film almost.
It's a shot that crystallizes something
and expresses something.
I really like them.
I did not know they don't have to be five, seven, five.
- No.
You can be a bit flexible.
- And actually I was very interested
to message my Japanese friend after I'd read about this
'cause yeah, people who write about haiku properly
and who know about it say,
look, the syllables thing,
it's a misinterpretation in English anyway
'cause it's not syllables, it sounds.
And she wrote me a few haikus at random,
I think, while she was sitting on the toilet.
And none of them had the right number of syllables.
And I was like,
sorry, I don't know if she would have wanted me to share that,
but I have-
(laughing)
- She said an ancient toilet.
- And turds jumps in the splash of water.
(laughing)
- And she said,
the only thing I think a haiku needs
is the seasonal reference.
So there you go.
And it is, they have done these glossaries
that you have to stick to, don't they?
You can buy a glossary, a haiku glossary.
- Dan, could you maybe say some words
that you think might be summer words?
- Summer words?
- Yeah, like a word.
- Sun.
- That might do it.
- I reckon.
- Although you do get sun in the other, you know.
- True.
- A nice bright.
- You get it in most seasons.
- Winter sun.
- All year round, don't you?
The old sun.
- Harvest.
- Sorry.
- That'll be an autumn one.
- Bikini.
- Beach.
- Yeah.
- Bikini.
- Yeah, yeah, that's a classic.
It's in the list of summer words.
- Blockbuster.
(laughing)
- So summer could be insects,
autumn, scarecrow,
resentment,
winter, tangle, twigs, empty fields.
- Oh, lovely.
- I really like it.
Can I show you the prop I've brought along?
- Yes.
- I like a related prop.
- Hang on.
'Cause I don't know if you guys know this.
- You're not on the news.
- Sorry.
I don't know if you guys know this.
- You've got Michael Rosen in your bag.
(laughing)
- I brought the sofa.
- Okay, so there's a British Haiku Society.
- Oh, yeah.
- Do you guys find that?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Because of your research?
Well, I'm very proud to announce
they've gained a new member this week.
- Oh, no way.
- I joined up.
- Yeah.
- Have you stopped your subscription
to the Lighthouse Society?
- The Association of Lighthouse Keepers
have lost a member.
(laughing)
- Is it like having citizenship?
You're only allowed to be a member of one or the other.
- I think it's lapsed now,
'cause I haven't received a copy of Lamp Magazine
for a while, and I was a big fan of that.
- Lights out.
(laughing)
- I am now a member of the BHS.
- Yeah.
- British Home Stars.
- That's right.
And look, I've got the journal here,
which is called Blythe Spirit.
- So Andy's holding an A5 white book
with Blythe Spirit written on it.
Does it have a lot of haiku in it?
- Absolutely jam-packed with really good haiku.
It just randomly pick one.
- Yeah, give us a good haiku.
A spring one if you can.
- You're not gonna believe this.
This is by Philip Murrell.
Called home, I scrape away moss to find his name.
And you can see why I signed up, 'cause he was full of this.
- I like the way you pretended that was just random,
but actually--
- It's fallen open to this page
because the spine is so cracked.
All right.
A baby shower immersed by cherubs, Botticelli.
- What do you guys, I admire the idea
of haikus, I really like them.
It doesn't do anything for me.
Certainly something like reading through a book like that.
Just, I imagine if I was sitting in nature
and then someone sent me a haiku about the area,
that would be really nice and poignant.
But do you guys get something from haiku?
- I have done, having done research for this,
I would say until that I hadn't,
until I understood what it was,
I didn't really get anything out of it.
But I like the idea, they have these clubs
where a hundred people will go to a beautiful place
in nature and they'll all just write as many haiku.
- See, I get that, I get that.
- And you're just kind of like,
you're trying to capture one moment
where you're with nature
in just this kind of slightly formulaic,
but you can go out of the rules if you want to way.
I kind of, I do.
- Oh, it's a lovely conceit, definitely.
I like it.
- Yeah, I really like it.
As James says, reading about it, the analysis of it,
as with any kind of poetry or art,
'cause I'm not smart enough to understand it face on.
But when you read the analysis, I think you get it.
And maybe you could be lured in by the punchline element.
You know, often you'll do a comedy set
where at the end it's got a big reveal.
And that--
- Or haikus have them.
- Haikus, exactly.
There's supposed to be this moment of realization, so.
- That's why I thought the spring with the frog thing.
- Sorry, not that kind of thing.
More like the one I read that I really liked was bass,
picking bugs off the moon.
And the way it was explained was,
you have bass, it's a type of fish, it's plucking bugs,
and then it's off the moon.
'Cause suddenly you realize, to them,
they think they're picking bugs off the surface of the moon
'cause they're always looking up at the moon.
- Oh, that's lovely.
- To us, they're picking up the surface of the moon.
- And all of the haikus would have like a word in it,
which is kind of hard to translate into English,
but they're like a surprise
or they call them a cutting word online a lot.
And it might be, aha!
Or--
- Sorry?
- Yeah, it's almost like an exclamation point.
- Oh, okay. - Do you know what I mean?
- My favorite haiku that I found is,
and I hadn't heard of this,
and I really think this is beautiful,
the idea of the death poem.
- Oh, yeah.
- So the death poem is a Japanese tradition,
whereby if you know that you're about to die,
let's say an execution is gonna happen,
'cause this has been going from centuries and centuries,
this death poem idea.
You are encouraged to write your final poem,
and that can be presented in sometimes as a haiku.
So there was one that was written by a guy
called Moriya Senan,
and his was, "Bury me when I die
beneath a wine barrel in a tavern,
with luck the cask will leak."
Okay, so that's his thing.
What's really nice is the line,
hopefully the cask will leak or the cask will leak,
the Japanese wording for that is Moriya Senan,
which is his name.
- Lovely.
- Oh, that's clever.
- Is that wonderful?
Yeah.
- That is clever.
- No one else can do that, can they?
No one else has a chance in that competition.
- Hey doctor, watch this.
I'm doing a big kankam.
Uh-oh, oh shit, shit.
(laughing)
- Beautiful.
- Yeah.
- Really good, where's the seasonal reference?
(laughing)
- Did you guys hear, hear tell of?
- This is now he's a member of the Haiku Society.
This is how Andy speaks.
- Everything has to scan.
- Did you hear tell of the 2014 Haiku artist
who operated out of Sainsbury's in North London?
(laughing)
This was the board baker who smuggled complaint poems
into the Sainsbury's treats that he was bagging up.
So for example, enjoy your cookies.
Each bite is a minute, I'll never get back.
(laughing)
It's a nice one.
Anyway, he was identified and immediately fired.
- Sainsbury's apologized to customers
and said it should never have happened.
- I love it, come on, I love it.
- I liked it.
- You'd be delighted if you got it.
It's like a fortune cookie, isn't it?
But instead of your future, you get some abuse.
- This city is Matsuyama,
which led me to read about Hideki Matsuyama,
who was the first to have a Japanese professional golfer
to win a men's major golf championship.
- What year are we talking?
- 2021.
- What, wow.
- That's the first time.
- The first time a Japanese man
at least has won a major golf championship.
And he was once disqualified from a competition
due to Tipex, riddle me this.
- Yeah, okay.
Just qualified for the competition.
- It's famous in the golfing world.
- Painting his balls.
- Painting his balls with Tipex,
where they're already white.
- But does it add weight to it?
Or some kind of grip that you wouldn't have?
- You're getting really close, but it's not the balls.
- Did he Tipex over his score on the board?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Different score.
- It's the club.
He would put it onto the club itself on the...
- So he put like a little target on the club
so that he could see where he wanted to hit the ball
or with Tipex, and that's allowed.
You're allowed to do that.
But he put too much Tipex on it,
which made it slightly raised,
which would change the grip that when the club hit the ball,
it would change the way that the ball flew.
And they measured it,
and it was like a millionth of a millimeter too thick.
- How amazing is that? - From a competition.
- Gosh.
- The forensic down to the millimeter.
- Yeah. - That's so pedantic.
- Like someone said, "Yes, you are allowed to put Tipex
"on your club, but only a bit."
(laughing)
- And he exceeds that bit. - How much is a bit?
Yeah. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Wow.
- So that's just me shoehornin' some golf into this bag.
- I love it.
There was an exciting thing in the world.
This is sort of, he was the first Japanese golfer
to do this. - Yeah, yeah.
- There was an exciting thing in the world
of Haiku in 2017 when a very prestigious competition
was won for the first time by a non-Japanese person.
- Really?
- And it was Gracie Starkey,
who was a 14 year old school girl from Gloucestershire.
- Wow. - Oh, wow.
- And she was learning Japanese at the time,
and her teacher encouraged her to enter it.
I think there were 18,000 entries.
- It doesn't say much for the entire population of Japan,
does it?
(laughing)
- It doesn't. - It's girl who I'm sure is great,
but has only just started learning the language.
- Yeah, it shows that the bar to entry is low for Haiku,
I suppose.
- Like, I can't imagine her winning the Japanese open
golf for instance. (laughing)
- And her poem was printed on millions of,
there's a green tea drink company that was sponsoring it,
so her poem was printed on millions of these bottles.
And the coder to the story is that Gracie then decided
to drop Japanese for GCSE,
(laughing)
saying the Japanese language is so hard.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that in the early 1900s there was a debate
over whether cinemas should be dark or fully lit.
(laughing)
- Do we think they got it right?
- I think they did get it right.
- For me, yes, I think dark is better.
- For the screening purpose, yes.
For the rest of society, maybe not.
- Mmm, go on.
- Well, this was the brainchild of a guy
called Roxy Rothafell, early cinema entrepreneur,
and he announced in 1910 that he had perfected
what he called daylight pictures.
He said they were absolutely flickerless,
they wouldn't tie the sensitive eyes of the audience out,
and you could see everything in the room.
And that was a kind of crucial point,
'cause he was a big part of making cinema
socially acceptable, whereas, you know,
before it was fairgrounds and peep shows,
and it was a bit raucous, and it was dark,
and you couldn't see what was going on,
and people might be, you know, getting up to hanky-panky,
and men and women were sitting next to each other in the dark.
You know, why have we allowed this to happen?
And he basically said, "Look, here's a lovely bright,
"nicely lit screen," and he said,
"You can see the picture perfectly,
"but you can also see the room,"
and it's just a nice, more sociable way of watching.
- But actually, even the very, very,
very, very earliest cinemas,
so when Edison's Motion Picture Patents Company
was first sending out projectors,
they said that you should install ambient lighting
to deter misbehavior.
So even from the very first moment of cinemas,
they were saying, "Let's not have it too dark
"because you never know what's gonna happen."
- Exactly. - Imagine, if they'd stuck to it,
I wonder how many children wouldn't have been conceived
in the back row of a cinema.
It could have done damage to the population of the world.
- Seaved as well. - No, it would have ruined
a lot of people's cinema experiences,
wouldn't it, in their use?
- There's a cinema that's reopened in Leeds recently
called the Hyde Park Picture House,
and they are gas lamp lit,
and they basically were saying that the reason
that there were gas lamps in there
was to stop the groping,
not necessarily hanky-panky,
but actually attacking women in the dark
sitting in the cinema.
And so as they were restoring it,
they've been putting up photos online
of all the things that they're finding,
like sort of under the floorboards
and the seats and stuff,
and one thing they're finding is giant hatpins.
And this used to be a suffragette thing,
where it's suffins. - Hatpins.
- Yeah, you would have,
they had to legislate the length of hatpins
because they were being used as weapons,
but in the cinemas, women would bring hatpins with them
because guys would come and letch onto them,
and no one could see it,
and they would start poking them
with the old hatpin. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Nice.
- 'Cause it was a thing that you had on you anyway,
like you could say,
"Oh no, this hatpin, it's not for stabbing people,
it's for keeping my hat on."
- But if you're a pervert,
and the woman you were perving on tap fell off,
you knew you were in trouble.
(laughing)
Get out of there, it's my advice.
- It's really cool.
If we ever get back to Leeds for a live show or whatever,
you know, the cinema's back open.
It's the only gas-lit cinema in the world now.
It's pretty cool. - Wow.
- One of the things about the darkness in cinemas
is that you know how if you go to the theater,
or the opera, or you know, whatever, it's dark.
Well, that wasn't always the case either.
And it mostly came through Gustav Mahler,
who decided everything should be dark,
and he was probably inspired by the cinemas.
So I think it seems that in the early 20th century,
he insisted on dimming the auditorium.
And actually, when he did so,
the audience were protesting,
because if you go to the opera in Vienna,
in the early 20th century,
you're wearing all your best clothes,
you want everyone to see you.
- Oh, yeah, you didn't go to see the opera.
You went to see your rivals, didn't you?
- Exactly.
- And the box over the other side of the audience.
- Well, you didn't want it to be dark,
and you have to concentrate on the opera.
'Cause as we all know, opera is incredibly dull.
(laughing)
- It's literally just a filler to go and make people stress.
- Yeah, that's great.
I didn't really like it.
I'd love to have visited back then
just to watch the social situation.
I didn't realize it was literally social gazing, basically.
- Oh, people went like that.
- Every night of the season,
and they were not concentrating on the play
beyond night one.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Wow.
- There's a thing now where there's a lot of controversy
about when the lights should come back up
in a cinema at the end of the movie.
- Well, I think it's useful, right?
Because if the lights haven't come up
and the credits are starting,
that's probably 'cause there's an end Marvel thing
at the end, right?
- Yeah.
- That's usually what happens.
- Do they do like a little scene at the end?
- Yeah, like all the Marvel movies
would have a little scene at the very end.
- And there's never ever a horse to Marvel movie,
and I respect that.
It's like that.
- But they wouldn't put the lights up,
so you kind of knew that was coming.
- Right.
- That's very clever.
- So what's this red-hot debate
about when the lights go on?
- What the red-hot debate is,
it's a health and safety thing, right?
Most people, when the credits start rolling,
want to get out of the cinema as quick as possible.
Maybe they need to be somewhere.
If you're in--
- Just hate seeing the names of people who've worked.
I think it's just not like, "For fuck's sake, guys,
you've done the job.
I don't need to know about who's the best boy."
- Oh, it's the bragging.
- So they want to get out of there.
That can be very dangerous.
They can fall over, trip hazards, all that sort of stuff.
The issue is modern cinema uses its credit sequence now
as part of the film.
So there's one film where basically the final scene
is happening as the credits are rolling.
But you don't have the old-day projectionists
in most cinemas these days.
Let's say in modern cinema,
they get a hard drive,
and it has stamped throughout the hard drive.
This is when the credits arrive,
so they'll pre-program the lights to come up.
So a lot of people are missing the end of movies
in terms of the Atmos because lights are coming up.
And so, yeah, it's a raging debate.
- How many films are running their credits
over the final scene?
That feels very avant-garde to me.
Dan, have you ever been,
I ask you this 'cause you're Australian.
Have you ever been to Broome?
- No, haven't actually, no.
- 'Cause it's a very long way away from the rest of Australia.
It's in the Northwest,
and it's got a cinema called Sun Pictures.
And it's one of the first,
it's a very early cinema.
I don't know if it's Australia's first,
but it's very old, 1916.
It was, I just like it so much
'cause every night, the cinema at Broome was flooded
by the tide, it was on the coast,
and there was tidal flooding.
And most nights, the street would be submerged.
And apparently some old-timers who remembered it
back in the early days said you would be able to catch a fish
during the screening around, under your feet.
- That's so good.
- Yeah.
- Great if you're watching Titanic or something.
- Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
- It was more fun when projectionists
had a bit more control on the day, wasn't it?
'Cause people, you almost had a relationship
with your projectionists.
And actually, even,
I think momentarily when you're in the cinema,
you could say, you know,
put the music on louder in Nickelodeons or whatever.
- Oh, yeah.
- Or in 1939, a newspaper in Newcastle reported
on a really exciting innovation that it said
is gonna take off in cinemas,
where in musical films, of which there were quite a lot,
I kinda like singing in the rain or whatever,
after one of the good songs,
they'd bring the lights down to black,
and then that was the cue for the audience to shout encore,
and if they shouted encore long enough,
then you rewound the song and you played it again.
- That's great.
- Oh, that is good.
- That's really good.
- Could you say, I didn't quite, who's this?
Can you play that better again?
Is she married to him?
- Yeah, we've been incredibly annoying
watching it with a granny or a child or me.
- You mentioned Nickelodeons.
So that was in America, right?
And it was, you paid a nickel to get in,
and it was like usually the shop or something like that,
and they would pull all the blinds down,
make it really, really dark,
and you'd be able to watch one of these old movies.
And obviously very dark, and it was very cheap,
so they attracted the poorer classes,
and so it was worried by higher class people
that they'd get pickpocketed or whatever
as soon as they went in.
So again, the darkness was thought to be a problem.
But in the UK, we had our own version of the Nickelodeons,
and they were called Pennygaffs.
And obviously the difference being that in the UK,
there were one penny to go in,
whereas in America it was a nickel.
But the problem was a nickel was worth 2.5 pennies.
And so the people who were making the Pennygaffs
were making two and a half times less
than the Nickelodeon people.
- They just did it for the catchy title.
Call them Topnygaffs.
- I guess it was like the smallest,
although they didn't have pennies in America, didn't they?
So they could have done pennies as well.
But yeah, it was just, I suppose they thought
that it was the only price they could charge.
But there was a worry at the time.
I read some newspaper articles saying
that young children were robbing from their parents
so they'd be able to attend the Pennygaffs.
- Always, always social worries.
Any new technology, it's so interesting.
Just how is this going to ruin the youth?
- And the other thing that they did is
'cause these Pennygaffs were in shops.
So it was a normal shop and they'd be like,
"Okay, we'll put a load of chairs up.
We'll charge people a penny to come in."
But there was, people tried to shut them down.
And one way they did it was saying
you don't have a music hall license.
'Cause there was no cinema licenses
'cause cinemas didn't exist.
And so loads of them would play the movies
in complete silence.
And so you would go in, it was completely dark
and it was completely silent.
You'd be watching the moving pictures,
but there'd be no music.
- And that 'cause usually you'd have a piano or something,
wouldn't you? - Yeah.
- You'd be played live along with it.
- Exactly, but they couldn't do that
because if they did, they'd get closed down
for being a musical.
- To be fair, I think that's fine.
I mean, most of you are watching a silent film,
you're not watching it for the piano music, are you?
- Oh, no, the lot of music was composed specifically
for the reels, so they'd be handed the sweet music.
- Of course, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Ambience matters.
- Well, I don't think it matters as much as
with a film with dialogue, for instance,
where you wouldn't know what was happening.
If you're watching a silent film,
you still know what's happening.
- I would like more ambience in my movies, you know.
Do you think Star Wars, which has dialogue,
would be as good without the score?
The less experiment.
- So you should try that.
- Completely music-free or Indiana Jones or whatever.
- Also, I need something to drown out James going,
"Who's that?"
(all laughing)
- When did they marry?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that one of the oldest diving clubs
in Ireland is the Muff Diving Club.
- And?
What's so funny about that?
- Nothing, it's interesting because it's how old it is.
It's one of the oldest.
- How old is it?
- We're talking a good like three decades.
- Wow.
- Oh my God.
- Yeah, no, this is the Muff Diving Club.
Yeah, it was just set up by a group of guys
who obviously spotted a good gag and they wanted to do it.
And they've not only been pushing for it
to be an old, long-lasting diving club,
but they want it to be the largest,
the biggest membership of any diving club in the world.
And so you go to their site, you can buy t-shirts,
you can buy, you can get a membership card.
- There's a lot more t-shirts selling
than actual diving in this club, I think.
- I'm finding it so hard when I'm looking into it
and I still haven't got to the bottom of it
if any diving happens at all.
- What is a diving club?
What is a diving club?
- What do you get?
Diving instructors teach how to dive and scuba diving.
- Yeah.
- Oh, I thought it was high diving.
- Did you not even see the logo, did you research this?
- I did not follow the link you said.
I've tried, but I've got a child look on my computer.
- How interesting.
I mean, you could have a high diving club as well.
People who like to high dive might get together
and practice together.
- But if all your facts are about high diving,
then you are going to be lost for the next half an hour.
- I've gone purely Muff, actually, and Muff Directional.
- Well, me too.
I went to the Irish version of companies house
to see how many other Muff companies there are in Ireland.
Muff Engineering, Muff Service Station,
Muff Soap, Muff Direct.
- Muff Direct.
Is this all in Muff?
- These are all real, they're all in Muff.
Muff after school, and--
(laughing)
- I didn't know, you can't let other parents
send your kids to that.
- It's just like an after school place where kids go to,
like, while the parents are still working,
and the Muff Liquor Company.
- No.
- The Muff Liquor Company, this is really interesting.
I went on their website,
and it doesn't seem to be a joke at all.
In fact, if you go on their website,
it looks like they haven't realized
that Muff Liquor could be quite rude,
because it's a proper, like, it's a vodka company,
and they've got a history of this guy,
the grandfather of the owner who started it
all these years ago, and it's a--
- So there's no sort of sly wink at the fact
that this is an amusing phrase,
like that salad company called Tost.
- No, unless I've completely missed it.
- I think they've just gone deadpan.
- No, I think you're right.
I think it's just, we're in Muff, we make a liquor,
let's put it out.
- Well, fair enough.
- They do know, but they've gone, we're above that.
These fucking Muff Divers next door,
we don't need to stoop to that level.
We'll put it out there, we'll let people chuckle
to themselves, and we'll sell them some vodka.
No t-shirt necessary.
- I was reading an interview where a lady called Caitlyn
was over in Australia, and she was on a TV show,
like a Family Fortunes kind of thing,
and she was from Muff, like, you know,
it's not got a big population Muff, but she was from there,
and the guy couldn't believe that she was from there,
and she said she went to a school that was called Holly Bush,
so that was a nice, another connection,
and she says that when you come, when you're driving in,
that there is a sign that says you are now entering Muff,
and I've not seen that online, I've been looking--
- Seems plausible.
- It does seem plausible.
You can say, you see welcome to Muff,
but I haven't seen you are now entering Muff.
- House prices are struggling in Muff.
- Oh yeah. - Yeah, apparently,
the prices are lower than you might imagine.
- I'm just waiting for the other shoe to drop on this joke.
I can't tell what it is. - It's not joke, it's not joke.
Well, it's for a slightly different reason you might think,
so you would find, like, people who live on shit house,
laying or whatever, they're always complaining,
and the newspapers are like, "I can't sell my house,"
or whatever. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But in actual fact, the reason that they can't
sell them very well is because they're on the border
between the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland,
and Brexit has meant that the bottom
has dropped out of the Muff market.
- There we go, there we go.
I knew, I knew something was coming.
- Was it worth it?
- It was worth it. - It was mortgage news
from Muff. - I was not a written joke.
(laughing)
- You were on the phone to a local estate agent.
- So if I say this, am I technically right?
(laughing)
- Do you want to buy the house or not, it's dark in here.
- Oh dear, shall we talk about muffs themselves?
- Yeah, let's do wet muffs. - Actual fur muffs
that people would wear, hand muffs, as it were,
how you keep your hands warm.
They used to be completely gender-neutral.
Men and women alike would wear muffs,
it was just a thing, 'cause it was really cold,
it used to be a lot colder.
(laughing)
- What, what, what, big guys?
- It used to be a big colder, but also they were more common.
- In the 16th century, people did not have
well insulated homes, and clothes were,
you didn't have lovely puffer jackets.
People needed to keep warm, wearing fur muffs
to cover your hands, really useful.
- Furry muff. - Furry muff.
(laughing)
And I think it came from muffulai,
which is a medieval Latin term,
which describes these big leather winter mitts
that you'd wear in muffulai.
And there was a great article all about
the history of the word muff,
on the Oxford University Press website,
by Anatoly Lieberman.
And it's all these different words come from muff,
so Danish moth means clown,
and Dickens uses muff to mean something,
like an annoying person or a fool or whatever.
German has muffeln, which means sulk,
miff, might come from muff.
- Miff, miff. - I'm feeling a bit miffed.
- Oh, miffed, right.
- You might really be actually muffed.
- We say muff, we use muff in American football,
it's a term. - Do you?
Oh, you've muffed it?
- Yeah, that's what it means basically.
As in someone kicks the ball to you,
and you try and catch it, and you don't quite catch it,
but the ball's still in place,
so someone else can get it, that's a muff.
- Oh yeah, that's quite a technical term.
'Cause I would say, yeah, you've muffed it to mean sort of,
oh, you just messed it up.
- You do say that, and I actually checked
all my WhatsApp messages,
and you're the only person who's ever
WhatsApp'd me the word muff.
- No. - Really?
- Yes. - And to mean muffed it up?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Oh, that is interesting.
I'm gonna search my WhatsApp.
- Well, no, not now.
- Oh, okay, yeah, I'll do it later.
- Yeah, so be it.
- For a work.
(laughing)
- But muff is also slang for a woman's vulva.
- No.
- What?
(laughing)
- No.
- I know, it's so weird.
- What? - Yeah.
- Wait a minute, so what about the muff diving club?
That would be- - So I think that could be,
that should be a euphemism.
- It sounds like Cunningling Dist, doesn't it?
- What about the thing that James said
about the bottom dropping out of the muff market?
(laughing)
- That's even funnier than it was originally.
- I thought it was just funny
'cause James said the word bottom,
which is a bit funny.
(laughing)
- No, it's actually true.
But also it's been- (laughing)
But it has been slang for that for so long.
I like how quickly we turn this into slang.
So it started meaning a hand warmer in the 1590s.
And by the 1690s, it meant a woman's pubic area.
Because I suppose you carried it down there,
it's big hairy things around your crotch.
So of course.
- It's 100 years.
That's a long time for it to make the leap.
- Well, it's first written down there.
- Yeah, I bet they've been saying it for decades.
- Yeah, you can get muff warmers.
- Is that to warm your muff or?
- Yeah.
- I thought muff was a warmer.
- That's to warm you.
- Yes, but the muff warmers warm the muff.
- I think you put your hand in the mouth.
- But who warms the muff warmers?
(laughing)
- They were little ceramic things
that you would fill up with hot water.
And I imagine actually that you'd leave them in the muff.
- Yeah, you would.
- And then when you're going out.
- That's clever.
- You warm the muff up.
Maybe you're going out on an hour.
You say, well, pop the muff warmer in the muff.
Then you come to go out.
You just get your muff as lovely and warm.
- Andy. - Yeah.
- Idea.
Have you got any money to invest?
- Yeah.
- Good.
Okay, so a mannequin.
- Yeah.
- But it's heated and you put your coat on the mannequin.
And then when you go out,
you can take a nice warm coat and put it on.
- Oh, yes.
- Ring the dragons.
(laughing)
- That's great.
- Or if you're really wealthy,
you just have a human coat warmer.
Someone who wears your coat for half an hour.
- Yeah.
- Before you go out.
- I see that.
- Oh, yeah.
- Mine is just a one-off purchase
whereas yours is more of a subscription one.
(laughing)
- Very much so, yes.
- Yeah, I do see that.
- I mean, when you get into bed,
it might be nice to,
I mean, a warmer bed is not,
I know you two are weird as you like cold beds,
but I like getting into a bed that's slightly warm
on a winter's night.
- Yeah.
- Do you do like they used to do on the grand tour
where they would put a live pig in their bed
before they went to bed to warm it up
and to get rid of bed bugs?
- Is that a real thing?
- Yeah, that's what they used to do.
- On the grand tour.
You saw the Clarkson show.
(laughing)
- Wait, what were you talking about?
That's what I thought you were talking about.
- I was talking about when would it have been
in the 18th century when you would go around Europe.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Have you heard of Muff Boutiques?
This is great.
- Uh-huh.
- Okay.
- Okay, not a company in Muff.
- No.
This was a thing.
It's from a book by a 19th century dandy
called Octave Ouzanne
and he was an admirer of ladies' accessories
and he wrote a book which was called
L'Hombre Legante Le Morgant
which means the parasol, the glove, the muff.
And he said that in Renaissance Italy,
there were Muff Boutiques
where you could either go in and buy a Muff
or in the off season when it gets nice and warm,
you don't need your Muff anymore,
you go and you store it in the Muff Boutique
and they delouse them.
I mean, if true, that's very funny.
- It's a brilliant book that, isn't it?
- It does sound great.
I've only read second hand about it.
- There was a, it's actually quite,
it's all available online and it's quite short.
So I did read it and yeah,
there's the Sunshade, the Glove, the Muff
and it was published by this guy
in response to the previous year's
incredibly successful The Fan
which was his history of The Fan.
- Oh, that was great.
Yeah, yeah, I know that book.
- Really?
Published in 1881.
Were you there for the first?
- No, I know a modern one.
Someone wrote a whole book about.
(all laughing)
- No, it's great.
The Sunshade, the Glove, the Muff.
And he tells, my favorite story from it was,
he says there's an account in the late 1500s
of towers being besieged
and at the front line of defenders
who are defending themselves from the siege
is a woman with muffs and a halberd in hand,
a halberd being a sort of poke sticky thing.
- Spear.
- Spear, thank you.
(all laughing)
A woman with a muff defending the city.
- Why?
For a reason.
- Keeping her hands.
- Keeping her hands warm while,
'cause you gotta be quite dexterous
to operate a spear, I suppose.
- Absolutely.
- You can't prod a haldane with cold hands.
Can you?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Very difficult, yeah.
- There were muff chains
which were to hang your muff, I think,
when you're not using it.
Your hands out of your muff,
you just put it on your muff chain around your neck.
- Oh, right.
- Muff pistols.
- Okay.
- I don't think--
- To shoot your muff.
- To shoot from your muff
if you're approached by footpads.
- Oh, I see.
They weren't like the sex pistols.
(all laughing)
It was like a female sex pistols.
- No, that was just a tiny gun for ladies
to protect yourself if you were out and about
and someone approaches you to rob you.
- One place in Ireland
that would have used the muff divers,
I think, quite usefully,
is a town where the first transatlantic telegraph cable
was laid in the 1880s.
- Oh, yeah.
- So that was there, that was in Ireland.
It was a little place called Spunkane.
- Mm-hmm, yeah.
- That's where the first transatlantic cable was laid.
- Spunkane.
- Sounds great.
- Okay, here's another fact.
The word spunk also can mean ejaculate.
- No.
- What?
- But that's a really funny name
for a place to start the cable.
- I thought it was just like a good-looking dude,
you know, spunky, you know?
That's disgusting now.
- Spunkane, and the town of Muff,
where the original fact was,
is where Amelia Earhart landed
when she did her first solo flight.
- Cool.
- Not our last one.
- No, unfortunately, we don't know exactly
where she landed that time.
But her first one, she landed
just outside the village of Muff.
- Oh, wow.
- The man who composed the theme music for Gladiators
is called Muff Murphy.
(all laughing)
- Gladiators of the TV show.
- Yeah.
- Ah.
- That's a good name.
- Muff Murphy, yeah, Muff is a name.
It's a man's name.
- Muff, I don't know any Muffs.
- Or maybe it's a Nick name as well.
- Yeah, I don't know any Muffs.
- I'm not familiar with the name Muff.
- The brother of Spencer Davis,
who obviously founded the Spencer Davis group.
- Obviously.
- It's called Muff.
- Really?
- You know the Spencer Davis group?
Gimme some lovin'.
- Is that band?
- Oh, it's a band.
- Yeah, it's a band.
- Gimme some lovin', that one.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Oh, hang on, is that, I've always thought it was
give me summer loving.
- No.
- I have thought it was give me some Muffin.
(all laughing)
- James has inserted a Muffin there.
Anna has thought it was a haiku.
It has to be a summer reference.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this show,
you can find us on various bits of social media.
I'm on Instagram.
You can get me on @Sriberland.
Andy.
- I'm on Twitter @AndrewHunterM.
James.
- I now have 400 followers on TikTok.
(all laughing)
I'm now saying this, James Harkin,
despite the fact that I have no intention
of posting anything on there.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, and if you wanna get to us as a group,
Anna, where did they go?
- You can go to Instagram,
which is no such thing as a fish,
or Twitter @NoSuchThing,
or you can email podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, if you wanna find anything else about us,
go to our website, nosuchthingasafish.com.
There is the links to get you into the world of Clubfish,
which is our secret members group,
and there's a great Discord that you can join
and lots of bonus content
that we put out through Clubfish.
Or you can just get access to all of our previous episodes,
as well as bits of merchandise
so you can get your hands on there.
Otherwise, just come back here next week.
We're gonna be back with another episode,
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)