Hi everyone. Just before we started this show, we wanted to remind you of something that you
should already be well aware of, which is that our esteemed colleagues and co-podcasters,
Dan Treiber and Andrew Hunter Murray, have both written books and they are truly fantastic books.
So, if you have anyone in your life who is a fish fan, who, God forbid, thinks that Dan and Andy
are the superior half of fish, perhaps that person is you, then why not get them for Christmas,
a book by Dan and a book by Andy. Dan has written the theory of everything else and honestly, when
I read it, on every page, I thought, "How have you been hogging these facts for this book rather
than sharing them on the podcast?" It is so selfish, but it's made for a brilliant book,
stunning revelations on every page. Andy has written the last day and the sanctuary. They're
both thrillers. They're real page turners. They're a fantastic twist and turns and of course,
they're making some very intelligent points about society today. So, get both of those for
anyone you know who's a big fan of Dan and Andy. But Anna, what if the people listening to this
prefer this half of the podcast, the James and Anna half of the podcast? What are those people
going to do? Oh, you mean the 95 other percent of our listeners. Oh, I don't know, James. Have we
done anything interesting lately? We have indeed. I don't know if you recall, because it was before
you went on maternity leave, but we wrote a book called "Everything to Play for the QI Book of Sports"
and it is another book that is jammed full of facts. Do you know why ancient Egyptian athletes
removed their spleens? Why pool balls no longer explode on impact? How bum slapping improves
team performance? All that and more, you can learn in our book, which is called "Everything to Play for
the QI Book of Sports". But the truth is, if you or anyone you know is a big fish fan, these are
the perfect things to get them for Christmas. Who doesn't love opening a present at Christmas
and getting a good old book that they can read? Read. If you too like to do this strange reading
thing that Anna does, then go to Noticesthinkasafish.com/books and you'll be able to find all the
details of those three books, but they're available wherever you buy your books. Get them all, get
them for everyone you know for Christmas. Get them now. On with the show. On with the podcast.
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hobart. My name is Dad Shriver. I am sitting here with James Harkin,
Andrew Hunter Murray and Anna Tyshinski. And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days. And in a particular order here we go. Starting
with fact number one, that is Anna. My fact this week is that your brain contains a tender mother,
a tough mother and a spider mother. Is that just Dan we're talking about here?
Yeah, and it explains everything. It does. Are these like multiple personality traits of like I
have a tough mother that comes, is that the idea of it? Oh, I love that idea. What would the spider
mother be? Well, I assume there's something that they do in the wild where they make webs. I hope
they like eat their children. Yeah, eating each other. The spider mother actually eats the tough
mother and the tender mother. It's actually neither of these things. They're just fun names
for things in the brain. So these are meninges that in your brain and spinal cord. And they're
basically a three layered envelope that protects your brain and spinal cord. And there's a delicate
inner layer, which is called the peer meter, which means sort of tender mother or soft mother
or pious mother. And so that wraps around the brain and spinal cord a bit like cling film.
And then there's a really tough outer layer, which is just under the bone of your skull. And that's
a dura mater, the hard mother, tough mother. And then there's a middle layer, the arachnoid
mater. And that's like a network of tissues and the tissue sort of spread out like a spider's web.
So really, it should be called a spider web mother, but it's not. The meninges is, you know,
a baby at the top of their head, they have like a gap where the skull hasn't covered them up. Oh,
yeah. The meninges is the kind of tough stuff that covers their brain, which means that at least
the brain isn't sticking out of the head. That's interesting. I don't know that. And also that
little hole there, that is what the company baby gap is named after.
I was just looking at sort of things that happen in the brain, unusual processes and things like
that. Yeah, I really like this. Your brain is so fast that you can judge whether someone is
trustworthy or not, even if you haven't seen them consciously. Okay. So they tried this thing where
they showed people images for it like a fraction of it, like a millisecond, a couple of milliseconds,
right? Too fast for people to consciously register they had seen a face. Yeah. They were either faces
that were, you know, untrustworthy looking or trustworthy looking or whatever. I don't know
what the criteria were. What is that? Is it like one person they've got, you know, a fag out the
corner of their mouth and a big overcoat on? And a bag-tank swag. Yeah. No, I have no idea. Maybe
they had to assess from people what they found trustworthy or untrustworthy first. Because
some people might only trust people who look like sort of comedy burglars from the 1980s.
But when they showed them those images, even for a fraction of a second, they didn't consciously
see them. But the bit of their brain, the amygdala, which processes strong emotions,
particularly in relation to whether you trust someone or not, fired up. Wow. It's not weird.
Wow. Do you know what the amygdala means? Ormond. Yeah. The brain is just full of
weirdly named stuff because it's like a structure and people could look at it hundreds of years ago
if they took out someone's brain after they died and like name the bits of the structure. It's just
got all really old fashioned, odd names. Like almond. Seahorse. Indeed. Oh yeah, the seahorse.
Because like if you are looking at someone's brain and you're like, which bit do I need to take out?
And they say, well, it's the blood, blood, fontanelle or whatever. You wouldn't know what it was. But if
you say the seahorse, you can look at it and go, oh, that looks a bit like a seahorse. I'll take
that bit out. Yeah. And the martyr, the pia martyr and the other martyrs, they're named after the
facts that they kind of cover things like a mother might hold her baby. They come from the Arabic.
Wow. I wondered with the speed that you were talking about a second ago, Andy,
the like, I was just thinking a quiz show, right? How quickly does the answer come to you
prior to your finger, the information getting to your finger and you pressing a buzzer, right?
If you were able to hook up your brain to the bit that lights up that says you know the answer,
how quick could it be? Are you pitching a quiz where no one actually asks the questions and
people just buzzing and say, no, no, you need the question. Are you thinking like you're going
university challenge, everyone else is using their fingers like absolute noobs and you've
got something attached to your actual brain. Competitive advantage. You've got your head on
the button. Exactly. That's it. I look like I'm keeled over, but no. Shriver Australia.
The only flaw in your plan is that you actually wouldn't know any of the answers anyway. So
it doesn't matter how you're pressing the button. I've genuinely never got an answer right on a
university challenge. No, I think that's good. But they show you the question for a millisecond
at the part of your brain associated with Turkmenistan fires, then it's actually a team of
neuroscientists who answer the question for you. But like several days later after the analysis.
But is the kind of thing your brain does and mostly I associate this sort of thing with
that, you know, there's that split brain operation that used to be done on epileptic
people. It was like, it was a revolutionary operation. And you basically cut the brain
in half down the corpus callosum, which is a bit that splits the left side from the right side of
the brain. And it was amazing because it stopped people having epileptic fits when nothing else
would work. They did loads of experiments on these people whose two brains were working fine,
but they couldn't communicate with each other. And so the reason I thought, for instance, of that
university challenge thing was that someone who'd had that operation, they would be shown a picture
of a face to their right eye, which goes into the left hemisphere. And they're asked what they've
seen. And they can say face. But if it goes into the other eye and into the opposite hemisphere,
because it's going to the wrong hemisphere that doesn't process language, once they're asked
what they've seen, they can't say face, but they can draw a face. I mean, the language is still
completely fine. But they'll just say, I've got no idea what I've seen. But their hand will draw a
face. Here's my pitch. Yeah. It's a cop drama, right? And there's a witness to a crime, but you
only saw it with one eye, the eye which doesn't know what. But he can draw it. And you've got a
cop, but he's only got the other eye. Yes. And it's basically Pictionary, Pictionary cop. That's
actually really good. And that can be a sequel to Dictionary cop, which is... Oh, right. I thought
you're going to be like Buckaroo cop, Mousetrap cop. Jenga cop. He's got two hours to stop this
building falling over. Yeah. It's not got any mortar. It's just bricks. But you know, fine.
It's a dry stone building. And one of the bricks has got a bomb in it, but he doesn't know which
one. So he has to keep removing the bricks to find the bomb without the building falling down.
But it's in a very congested area. So he can only put the bricks on top of the building at the top.
This is quite good. Dry stone wall is probably set at the Cotswolds. So he's had some lovely
location filming before the... Yeah, yeah. This is bloody good. Jenga cop. There is just one
other possible spy film, follow up, where you can basically get people to say things that they
don't know they've said, I guess, because there was another guy who'd had his brain cut in half.
And they asked him the question to one side of his brain. They flashed the question,
who's your favourite girlfriend? He was a little boy. Oh, right. Who's your favourite girlfriend?
And then he was asked, do you know what question we've asked you? And he was shrugged and was like,
no, I haven't seen anything. I didn't see anything. But then he giggled, said no,
and then spelled out Liz in Scrabble Tiles with his other hand. How awful is that? You're just
giving stuff away. Scrabble Tiles, 10 points as well for the Zed. He put on a triple hurt score
as well. Well, it makes you a follow up. Scrabble cop. Scrabble cop. That's good.
Have you guys heard of hemmy neglect, which is kind of in the same sphere here? Hemmy neglect.
Hemmy neglect is when this is people who have had a stroke. There's a bit of brain damage that
goes on whereby they only experience basically one side of their visual field. So if they've gone
to shave, they'll shave off half their face, but leave the other side because it's just not
part of their field anymore, right? If they're eating on a plate, they'll eat the right side
or left side of the plate. They'll eat just one side of the plate. So it's not just that you can't
see presumably, it's that your brain refuses to acknowledge that. Your brain is refusing to
acknowledge that. Yeah. But this is what's amazing. They started looking into hemmy neglect within
memory as well. So they managed to find a group of people where all of them had been to Milan.
So they asked them the exact same thing, you're standing in the major plaza in Milan,
recall as many stores and streets around you as possible in the square,
and they could only remember the stores and the streets that were on the right side and not the
left. Probably good memories though. He asked me to name a shop, you know, on a square I'd lived on
for about 20 years. I probably couldn't do it. I could name a shop in Milan in the central square
but yeah, because they recently got their first Starbucks and it was some controversy because
obviously Milan, the home of coffee, good coffee, and there was a Starbucks there. It was very nice
Starbucks too. So that prompted a bit of local discussion. Or according to these people, there
was a Bucks. Yeah. All of our brains are smaller than they would have been 3,000 years ago if we'd
been born then. We've lost about four ping pong balls worth of brain. Whoa, that's a lot. It is
quite a lot and it's not exactly clear what caused it because we invented agriculture 10,000 years
ago as a species. It's not that. Writing dates back several thousand years and it might be something
to do with that. It might be that I keep part of my brain in all of your brains.
I wonder what that was. No, but like if you have lots of division of labor and you have a complicated
system, you sort of divide up the cognitive tasks and you need a bit less brain space. Yeah. I think
there is a theory that domestication makes your brain smaller because it works with animals for
sure. So am I domesticated? Well, I think humans are domesticated, aren't we? Well, no, we're the
domesticators. But who's domesticated us, aside from cat, according to some interpretation.
The man. The man. Society has domesticated us. To be fair, I don't think I would thrive in the
wild. I don't think you would either. I concur. Dan, anything to do with you? Do you contradict that
statement? No, I think well, I'm going off getting some berries and Anna's going off killing a wild
cat. And you are trying to think of some cop dramas. I don't know which of us is going to be the most
useful in the group. In the future, we will need cop dramas to survive. We'll need that hope that
comes from like, will you find the bomb? Yeah. Okay, brain fart. Yeah. Like when you have a moment,
you can't remember something, right? Yeah. Yeah. This podcast has been a 10 year long one, for
instance. Sure. Yeah. What about a brain squared? What is that? Brain squared time. It's where you
try and think of one thing, and it just shoves out tons of different things. It's like, someone
says, what's the capital of Malawi? And all you can think of is every other capital in Africa.
Oh, good. Yes. No, I was saying, yeah, that's probably closer than to mine, which you would be
saying things that sounded right as a ramble. So like a quiz question like that. But you genuinely
went, it's Michael's, no, Sarah, Joey, Chandler, right? Mums do when they're trying to remember
your name. They always run through, don't they? John, Katie, Claire, Hannah, James, James, come over
here. It's just a feeble or abortive attempt at reasoning, but it dates back to the 1650s.
They're cool. Really? I'm having a brain squirt. It was also, this dates back to Old English,
your brain locker. What is that? Brain locker. Brain locker. It's someone who looks at a brain
in South Africa. It's my brain locker. It's just your head. I was going to say, it's your skull.
My brain locker. My brain locker. Crazy that we had a word for that. It's like one little hack. I was
reading a lot of neuroscientists saying how you can hack your brain to make sure that, so if you're
someone who forgets things a lot, or you have something important that you need to remember,
and you just don't, you can't find it, write it down or anything, take something, take an object,
and just place it somewhere it shouldn't be. So if you're leaving the house, for example,
and you're like, oh, why is this, you know, flute here? Yeah. It'll make you go, ah, yes,
I've been meaning to do that thing. It's a way of associating with a physical object. So that's
just a great hack. I feel like, you know, I do that with my hair bands. I put one hair band on
the other wrist if I need to remember something. I'll be the second one on the other wrist if I
need to remember a second thing. And then I put one back on the first wrist if I need to remember
a third thing. Oh, shit. Okay, it is time for fact number two. And that is my fact. My fact this
week is that at the 1984 US Grand Prix, it was thought that Ayrton Senna crashed into a wall
on the 47th lap. But it turns out it was actually the wall that crashed into him. This is another
case of a Jenga cop, I feel. This is an amazing story. So Senna is one of the greatest Formula
1 drivers ever. His career was cut short, because sadly, 10 years later, he did have a crash in a
Grand Prix, which he died. So basically, he was in this Grand Prix, and he's heading on cutting a
corner, very tight to the wall as he had done on previous laps. He nicks it. So afterwards,
they're talking about it, and he says, "There's no way I hit that wall. I'm a precision driver."
And he was very cocky, Senna. "I'm a precision driver. That wall came into me." So they went out
just because, I guess, you know, they thought, "Well, maybe he's right. Let's check it out." And
they noticed that the wall had moved. And the reason was, is because a car-
Is a human dressed as a wall, wasn't it? Who was hiding from the Jenga cop?
But it was also saying anti-Catholic propaganda at the time, wasn't it?
Cool. Back to last episode, everyone. So basically, these walls were giant,
concrete blocks. And on a previous lap, a car had also hit this wall. And what they'd notice
was that it hit it with such force that it had knocked the back of it. And so the front bit
jutted out a tiny bit, but only by 10 millimeters is what they were saying that he was so precise.
He was so precise that that was enough. He knew exactly where he needed to take it.
And so he nicked the wall. And this is how he is sort of known. He's known as this guy.
He was the best. I believe so. I mean, there's countless arguments in Formula One fans, but
for me, he was the best. There you go. You heard it here first.
So tragically, because he was cut off in his prime, we don't know where he would have taken it to.
He won three world championships. He's been surpassed by Schumacher and others,
but that's because of the longevity of a career. So yeah, hard to know where he would have gone.
I didn't know why it's called Formula One. And it's just the whole point of Formula One is that
there is a formula. And it's this set of rules that you have to adhere to. And they change the
rules every, I don't know, every year or every couple of years. And then everyone has to build
entirely new cars and it's a nightmare. And that is the formula that everyone's complying with.
And that's about the weight and the aerodynamics and the blah, blah, blah. And I used to know,
what I do know, someone, a friend of mine, used to work on Formula One doing the kind of modelling,
the computer modelling of the aerodynamics of the cars. Basically, you just do that hundreds of
thousands of times and modelling the airflow over a car to work out what's going to be best.
And then they change the rules and then you have to adjust everything in a fraction of a millimeter
in all of this. It's amazing. And try and push it slightly further than everyone else is pushing it.
Yeah, because there must be one perfect car, theoretically. Oh, right. That would be the,
have the perfect aerodynamics for these rules. I don't know. And they all cross the line at the
same time. That's when you have to bring in some variables like Mario Kart. The Red Shells. The
Benefit. Rainbow Road. A bubble that you drive into. Blop, blop, blop. I mean, it would all liven up
what is sometimes quite a dry sport to watch. It is very, this is, I think, true of quite a lot
of sports, which is if you're not really into them and you watch them, they seem quite boring on the
outside. And then as soon as you start reading about them, it's like, oh my God, this is incredible.
Yeah, that's definitely true of everyone, isn't it? Otherwise, it is just people going round and
round at a thing. But yeah, you can't make the cars too good. And obviously, there are rules to
stop you doing that. Partly for safety, because if you go too fast, it's very bad. And safety has
massively cracked down the last sort of 30 years. But there have been great cars made in the past
that they've had to change the rules to stop happening again, like the six-wheeled car.
Do we have the six-wheeled? Yeah, it's so cool. It's amazing. Was it designed by Homer Simpson?
Yes, it was. No, this was in the 1970s. And it was Tyrell, one of the teams,
raced a six-wheeled car. Realised that there would be an advantage to it, because if you have
four smaller wheels at the front rather than two big wheels, then I think you increase the amount
of contact with the ground. So you've got more grip on the road. More traction on the corners.
Honestly, that is like, they've got someone in from the outside who's never worked in
Formula One before and said, look at this. How can we improve this car? And they've gone,
"More wheels?" Imagine being in that meeting, though. They were looking through it. We've
looked through the manual 30 times now. There's nothing which says the maximum number of wheels
is for you. You can do it. That must be something in the rules, something. That must be every other
car ever. They didn't think of putting it in the rules. It's like saying you can't have a crocodile
driving. They didn't think of that. There is no rule about the number of wheels, largely because
they did this. And at the time, there were various slight problems with it, because they hadn't
perfected the technology yet, because they'd only just invented the six-wheeled car. They did get a
few podium finishes, I think, for that car. But the FIA banned it in the end, because they worried
that we'd just get to a place where people were putting more and more wheels on cars. You just
have 100 wheels on a car. I think they did win. They won one Grand Prix with the Swedish Grand Prix.
What a vindication that must have been. What a moment.
Are the cars longer? Because that's an advantage as well, right? For tight finishes. If your car is
suddenly 10 metres long. I think of one problem is when you go into the pit stop to change your
tyres. If you have to change 200 times, it's going to take ages. Oh, those are... I love the pit
stops. Yeah. Those are the... Because that's a matter of variation in the race, isn't it? And they
used to have a lollipop man. Yeah. It's so sweet, really. It's really sad that they don't anymore,
I think. Because they always build the tracks next to primary schools.
But I do wonder. You just got a little old lady and a smart... He's chatting to some of the mums
and all the drivers and going, "Can I cross? Can I cross?" This pit stop has now lasted 18 minutes.
So their job basically was to know when everyone had finished their jobs and then they
lift up the lollipop and they could drive off. But now everyone just has a button. When you've
done your job, you finish your things and your lights change. Just rubbish. And that's... Oh,
that must be stressful as well. Because I can readily imagine fitting the wheel in 0.4 seconds
and then forgetting to press my button. Yeah. Well, if you had your head bugged on your left wrist,
here's a crazy pit stop thing that you're not allowed to do anymore, which is... And do you
guys remember ages ago, Lewis Hamilton, there was a bit of controversy about one of the races where
you have your team. So he's... What's his team again? He's with... Mercedes. So he'd be on the track
with another Mercedes rider, part of the same team. It made more sense for Lewis to win. So there was
this big controversy that the guy in the lead slowed down and let Lewis take the win for the
points for the team, basically. It is fine, but it's seen as... It's not sport, basically. It's...
They should be trying. Yeah. But they do the same in cycling, don't they? I thought they
happened to have one. In cycling, it's basically the whole spot. Yeah. I think in Formula One, it's
obviously taboo because it was a big controversy at the time when Lewis did it. Yeah. But so what
you used to be able to do in a pit stop is, let's say you have damaged your car. Yeah. You could
come in and they've called over the number two because you're the lead driver and they would
just give you his car. Wicked. So he would be out of the race. So your number two driver, you would
want them to be pretty much exactly the same as you, right? If you're six foot three with a very
spindly arms, you need another six foot three with spindly arms. Well, so you don't have to factor
around adjusting the seat and then changing the air con. Oh, radio one. But that is the thing,
isn't it? Because they all get weighed after the race. The driver and the car are weighed
because if you're too light, it might be dangerous and drivers lose about three kilos during a race
of hydration, of water weight. Because it's so sweaty, right? Yeah. It's so sweaty. It apparently
gets so hot in there as well. Like that's what's, you know, it's sweaty, it's hot, it's boiling,
and Damon Hill, there's a story. I couldn't find a good source for it, but it's claimed in a bunch
of places that he brings in, for some reason, a thermos of cold black tea and the heat of the car
makes it a nice piping hot tea for it to drink. I heard that. That's very funny. The safety stuff
is just nuts in the cars these days. It's so impressive. So these days, every single driver
has a monocoque. It was when they used to have two cars, there was so many deaths. It was tripping
over a lot. It's getting in the way of the levers. No, it's a cocoon, basically. It surrounds the
driver and it's sort of the core of the car. And it's like the, I want to say a very hard bag.
Like, it surrounds the driver and it keeps them safe even if they crash. So they get into a bag?
They didn't know. I'm misoldering dramatically. It's just like the sort of central command pod
of the car, which actually encases the driver. If you can imagine the meninges of the press,
it's almost like the meninges of the driver. Exactly. It's like the very toughest mother.
Only they called it that. I would have thrown it straight away. Yeah. And the, you know, the helmets
are amazing. They have to be subjected, the helmets have to be subjected to 800 degree heat for 45
seconds in case there's a fire or they have to be hot tea or hot tea.
The boss has really taken a pattering. Every time you blink, you lose 20 meters of road.
If you're going in fast Formula One car. So you have to be careful when you blink.
Yeah. They've measured it and like drivers always blink at the same part of the course.
It's really interesting. Yeah. I read that one thing that if you play the sounds of the cars
on a Formula One track to a Formula One driver, they'll be able to tell which track it is just
from the sounds that the cars make. Wow. Isn't that amazing? That's incredible.
You need a special driver's license? Oh really? Perhaps, unsurprisingly. You need a super license.
That's what it's called. Really? Yeah. Is that right? So does that mean if I took part in the Las Vegas
Grand Prix starts this weekend? Yeah. If I flew over to Las Vegas and took part in it, I'd get
points for not having the right license. I think you probably will get points. Yeah, yeah. Wow.
Do it anyway. I'll try it. Shall I try it? In your electric car as well. They accelerate like
that. They do accelerate well, but I'm not sure I could get around all the laps without retouching.
He's now had a lovely coffee at the Supercharger. I wonder if, you know, psychopaths is that idea
that they don't blink. I wonder if that would make you a better, there's one way apparently of spotting
a psychopath according to people who look into it is they blink much less than a regular person.
That's why they're forced to kill and kill again because they're so annoyed about their dry eyes.
I just wonder if you blink less. Are you a better driver? Are they all psychopaths? Is that what
you're saying? All these F1 drivers? Well, Senna, just back to him very quickly, sounded a bit
sort of like he was in an odd mental place a lot of the time. Well, as in like, whenever he arrived,
his friend said, he'd never said hi. Like if he was coming to a race, he was just in a zone. He was
just always kind of like angry. That's like rude. God, I said hi to you this morning and it was an
effort, frankly, but I didn't. I think that's really normal. Like I would say if you're racing,
I can imagine not saying hello to anyone like you've got to be so in the zone. Yes. How many
people are you having to say hi to? Because if it's just one or two people who are welcoming you,
you're like, oh, yeah, great. You have a nice chat. But if it's like all the 50 members of the team
are saying, hello, I like the big mascot in the silly suit. This is according to someone who works
for the catering operation, Lindy Redding. She said she said he would never say hi if he was in the
zone. But when he did say hello, it was very genuine. He used to kiss us and hold our faces,
which was hugely intense, but absolutely lovely. You know what? Let's do the not hello next time.
This is great. That's the greeting equivalent of doing the washing up so badly that they never
asked. Speaking of motor racing drivers, have you guys heard of Hella nice? Hella nice.
Hella nice. Yeah. It was a person from the 1920s. Real name Mariette Ellen Delong. She was an exotic
dancer who danced at the Ritz in Paris. And then she had a skiing accident and couldn't dance anymore.
And so became a racing driver. And she raced in five major Grand Prix in France. And she was in
an accident. This is why I was reading about her because we were talking about safety. She was
in an accident where she was in an Alpha Romeo and she's somersaulted through the air. And she
wasn't wearing a seatbelt because she didn't have to in those days. Her car went into the crowd,
killed four people. But she survived because she landed on a soldier who absorbed the full
impact of her body saving her life. Did he die? No, he didn't die. Sorry, did she
fly through the air or did her car, her car went one direction, killed some people.
She went in the other direction and luckily landed on this very pliant soldier. Wow. And they later
married. I don't think they did now. That's amazing. It's incredible what you can survive. I mean,
now they really saw extraordinary crashes because of the safety. But even when you look back in the
day, I mean, in 1993, have you seen the quite a famous crash? Two teammates actually who were
called Fittipaldi and Martini. They were quite near the back. But one of their cars was like just
behind the other. And I think the left wheel, front wheel of one car nicked the back right
wheel of another car. And it sent the front one into a full in the air backflip. Oh yes, yeah.
Just does a backflip, happily lands, skates over the finish line. It's absolutely stunning. That
showboating. It really is, yeah. To begin with the headline, Martini shaken not stirred.
It should have done. Here's a little quiz moment for you all. Okay. Who is the guy who I think has
done more Formula One races than anyone else? I'm 90% sure. He's done more Formula One races
than anyone else on the planet, more Grand Prix. Grands Prix. Okay. So someone we must know of?
No. Is it the Michelin man? It's not the Michelin man. Anna, I feel like you might have the answer.
I've just got my hand up. I'm bursting. Are you talking about the safety guy? The guy who drives
the safety car. Yeah, so good. He's been doing it for nearly 25 years. Yeah. He's done more than 450
Grand Prix. I can't believe it's the same guy. I just couldn't believe it's just one bloke
doing every single Grand Prix. So what does he do, sorry? When there's an incident on the track.
Yeah. There's an accident or like there's a horse ride out on the track, whatever. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
School day finishes. Receptions run out, lady car ladies already.
The safety car drives out onto the track and kind of regulates the service. Everyone has to
drive slowly. Yeah, he drives around at 20 miles an hour and everyone has to just slowly go behind
them and you're not allowed to overtake anyone. Yes, of course. Yeah, yeah, yeah. You know that
feeling when you're driving and someone's kind of coming up your arse? Imagine that like times a
million. This is what that guy's going through every single day. Someone coming up his arse times
a million. That is a tough job. That was work today, darling. Well, 20 men coming up my arse.
Want to sit down? No, it's alright. It's alright. After 25 years, you're kind of, you're hard into it.
Okay, he's a professional racing driver. He's called Burt Maylender. That's great though. That's
really cool. I mean, I guess he's not had any accidents himself over all that time. So
I guess it's quite stressful and he says the most, can you guess the most stressful person to have
behind you? What is in which racing driver is? Yeah, because I said they're quite aggressive
sometimes. It must be Schumacher. It's actually Lewis Hamilton, he says. Lewis Hamilton's really
up in your face or I'm like zigzagging everywhere, like really pushing, going up towards you.
What was the point? You have to stay behind them. No, you keep your tyres warm by zigzagging.
I think it's the most precise sport in the world. You guys have just written a book about sports.
The big book of sports. Everything to play for, the QI book of sports. But surely this is the most,
this is where the most thought has gone into the most tiny differences of like,
yeah, it is amazing. Technologically for sure. Right. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Like even in the formula,
there are even limits on the amount of data you're allowed to use to simulate the car aerodynamics.
You're limited to 25 teraflops of computing power when you're running the computer simulations
of air flowing over a car you haven't even built yet. And then after all that stuff,
like literally last night in the warm up for the Las Vegas Grand Prix,
someone hadn't nailed down one of the manhole covers properly, just smashed into the car.
Oh my God, I heard about that. They get sucked up. Yeah. Why do they keep building manhole covers
on the F1 tracks? Well, because it's it's in the actual streets of Las Vegas. And they have to
nail down every single manhole cover. I think they might not even use nails. They might use
like concrete or something. God, you don't want to be sort of a sewerage work who pops up at the
wrong one. Oh fuck. An escaped convict. Yeah, yeah. That's it, isn't it?
Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is Andy. My fact is, there is such a thing
as a ghost pond. Oh, splash. Yeah. This is a, so we're all familiar with ponds. Maybe just give us
a just for the people not from the UK. Well, no, actually, then, because, you know, what is a pond
and what is a lake? So it's a very large hill with just matter on it. Oh, no, it's the opposite
of that. It's a small indentation with water in it. That's right. Sorry, I always get those mixed up.
Oh, you caught me there. You have me going. But basically, there are these things all over,
particularly the UK, but I'm sure in other countries too. In fact, all over Europe, they
do know that. And they, like all the farms in England used to have ponds, like fields would
have a pond here or there in them, and they would either provide water for cattle or they would,
you know, they're just useful things to have. But then over the years, they got abandoned
and lots of them dried up. Oh, maybe they got choked by fallen leaves, you know, and all these
ponds are now missing from the UK. There used to be twice as many ponds as there are today in
the 1970s. Double the ponds. Yeah, I know. Like, why is no one marching? Why is no one superglaring
themselves to Heathrow Airport to bring the ponds back? Well, I think it's important that they're
like ponds are great because so many animals and plants just. They want to.
That was Dubai. Yeah.
That's right. I've got a pond. Have you got a pond? Anyone else got a pond?
I want to. It's on my list of things I'd like to do is to dig a pond. Very easy. Just dig a pond,
put some lining in it. Yeah. Sorry, can you just tell us what these ghost ponds are there?
Well, okay. So ghost ponds basically are about my pond.
Just tell us anything. We're passing the pond in a minute.
But no, basically, they're huge biodiversity hotspots. You know, you get you get plants and
species and dragonflies and beetles and all sorts of stuff where before you just have a field and
you know, they're really important for that. And basically the mud remembers. It's really weird.
So all of these ancient seeds might be left in the indentation that used to be a pond and they
can survive for over a century. And all you have to do if you have that little dip in the ground,
you refill it, expose it to sunlight and these old species just spring up and they come back
with a vengeance. And it's kind of staggering. So there's a team at UCL, the pond restoration
research group led by Carl Sayer, and they've been going around Norfolk restoring these ghost
ponds. And suddenly, bang, life, biodiversity, really important stuff, which is really under
threat at the moment. They reckon there's 600,000 that are hidden still waiting to be restored
in the UK alone. It's amazing. And it's longer than that, isn't it, for seeds? I'm sure we've
mentioned and I can't remember the exact number, but like the oldest seed ever found that can still
be, you know, watered and sunlit and grow is many thousands of years old. And so yeah, these can be
many hundreds. And what I really like is that you can sort of see a ghostly evidence of them,
can't you? Like from above, you can see it as like a slightly damp depression or it's a bit where
crops don't grow as well, because it's always been a bit too wet, the soils never dried out.
And I think often farmers, when they're expanding their land, rather than drain them, because that's
a hassle draining a pond, they just dump a load of earth in them, wouldn't they? Or a
load of plant matter, which doesn't stop them being wet. So they have left their little pond
prints. So cool. But also I think ponds, they kind of have like a life duration, don't they?
If you have a pond, like a pond farm, as you dig out a pond, right, because you're a farmer,
if you just leave it, after about 100 years, it'll just cease to be. Oh, really? Yeah, they just kind
of, they slowly silt up and silt up and silt up and then they die. And it could be just like one
really heavy rainstorm. A load of silt comes down, they're not a pond anymore. They're just like these
ephemeral things that kind of come and go. They have to be kind of maintained, don't they? A little
bit. They do. You clear out the leaves and you know, if they've got trees over them, that's a
nightmare for a pond, apparently. Sure is. Can I tell you about the leaves that have fallen into my
pond? Yeah. How big is your pond? Like the table that we're recording on. Okay, the one that no
one can see. It's about half the size of that. Oh, nice. Okay. James would describe something
the size of a basin. It's small. It's a small pond. But you know, it's just for animals to come and
drink stuff. You're not going to get a deer, are you? A lion kneeling down. I don't think there
will be wildebeest of lion sipping at my pond in North London. You're not that far from the zoo.
That's true. A catastrophic breakout and suddenly James looks out a watering hole.
Humans make ponds. What else makes ponds? Aliens. Yes, the equivalent of crop circles,
pond circles. Oh, lovely. Yeah, no, non-human animals. Non-human animals. Yes. I reckon like
if you're a hippo and you sit down in some mud, then it might create a pond. Good point. Whether
or not that would be intentional, I guess would be debated. I'm saying deliberate pond makers.
Oh, beavers maybe. I guess they're damning things up. It's not really a pond. It's not quite. No.
So, Andy, if you want to get a pond in your backyard, but you can't be bothered digging,
buy yourself a Goliath frog. Oh, great. Yeah. So, Goliath frogs do this. It's a really interesting
thing where they move rocks, giant rocks, basically their own weight and they get it so that they cut
off water and they build their own ponds so that the eggs are more safe in there. They can keep
attention to them, make sure the tadpoles and so on are all in place. They're their biggest
frogs, aren't they? The Goliath frog. If for the people at home who can't see it, there's a glass
of water in front of them, they're probably about two or three times bigger than that. Yeah,
they're massive, really big. And they think one of the, you know, there's always theories, but one
of the theories is that their size is to do with mating, to do with the best rock movers and, you
know, that's partially why they may be that big, specifically because they build ponds.
Do you know what else makes ponds? So, this is a subset of humans. Oh, okay, I was about to say
elephants. And schoolgirls. Subset of humans. That wasn't what I was thinking of. That can
as a subset, though. That's a subset of humans. Why? Are you questioning whether or not they're
humans? I wasn't sure what subset meant. I thought it meant it had to be like people
from, you know, the southern hemisphere or like, I thought it was bigger than just saying, you know,
slipknot fans, you know. Yeah, just a group of humans who make ponds. You used to be a schoolgirl.
I was trying to think of what a subset of humans would be. Oh, okay. I was just wondering if when
you were a schoolgirl, you dug ponds and that you had inside knowledge that I wouldn't have had.
No, we got taken to ponds. So, we got told about newt. So, not schoolgirls.
A subset of humans who make ponds. Is it a profession? No, it's more of a ideology.
Zen gardeners. Oh, okay. That is true, undoubtedly. Not who I was thinking of.
Communists. Oh, the opposite. Oh, fascists. Nazis. Yes, you got it. So, there's quite a lot
of bomb craters around Europe. And if you drop a bomb, it makes a big indentation and that indentation
can then collect water and become a pond. Wow. So, that feels like a silver lining.
It is, really. And possibly a reason to start more wars.
No. I mean, well, just the Nazis were pond making, right? The Allies were pond making as well. We
were all pond making. A lot of ponds in Dresden. Right, right, right. But yeah, a lot of ponds made
by both sides. And the thing is that they've done some studies on it and they did this in Hungary
in particular. And they found that they found 274 species in ponds made by bombs. And they included
like, for instance, an algae which has previously only been found in Chilean salt lakes.
And a furry shrimp that had only been recorded twice in the last 25 years in Hungary. And they
were in these ponds made by bombs. That's amazing. I mean, this is what they find with these ghost
ponds when they rejuvenate them. You get species that you haven't seen for many, many years. And
it's such a mystery, I think, how stuff turns up, how nature knows. And particularly, I think,
in slightly bigger ponds than maybe James's garden pond. But you'll find, no offense.
I can't even imagine a pond bigger than James's garden pond.
Please don't write in for me taking the piss up, James, having a small pond, okay?
Okay, here we are. New name for this podcast. Don't write in.
I was the eels.
James Harkin's podcast. Do you reckon?
Yeah. Come on, give us that. You will need a bit more detail, but I'm interested.
Okay, first episode, guess what leaves are falling in my pond?
Are you having a guest to your pond each week?
Yeah, but they'll be an animal, so they can't talk.
First episode of Dragonfly, and they just go...
Monaco. We have to guess what animal is at your pond chat that week.
Yeah, that's great.
It's almost always a snail.
It's never the world of bees, guys.
So I always have eels in ponds, because how did they get there?
Oh, yeah.
And all we know is that eels can move across sort of...
Not dry land, but across land.
That's moist, because they can breathe through their skin, not just gills.
So gills require some pressure for the water to be forced in,
but they can actually breathe through their skin.
So they must just flop out of a river,
but then how do they find their way to someone's garden?
Everyone's looking at me just to say no eels in my pond.
Oh, that'll be a big, big episode.
All in my hovercraft.
I think it's not an idea that sometimes things get in ponds because they're dropped by birds.
Can I tell you about one of the most interesting ponds in the world?
Please.
This is called Don Juan Pond in Antarctica, and it's really weird.
It's quite... It's very big. That's not the way of thing.
It's full of water. That's not the way of thing either.
Well, it's in Antarctica, so being full of water is unusual.
Exactly. That is the way of thing.
And it's because of what this water is like.
It's really dense and really syrupy, and it's full of calcium chloride.
It's kind of salt, right?
And the water remains liquid, even 50 degrees below freezing.
Even 50 Celsius below zero.
What's that all about?
Well, it's because it's the most salty body of water in the world, isn't it?
Exactly. And they don't know where the water comes from.
I read an interview with a scientist who said,
"We've been studying it for 60 years.
We're pretty sure it's fed from beneath, but we're not totally certain."
And what does the cold feel like if it's gone beyond the point of where it freezes into a block?
Oh, I imagine it's very cold.
I bet, right?
Yeah.
You need a wet season.
Well, let's say you're swimming in regular water.
It freezes, right? So you can't dive into it.
It's a nice block. You can't get in there, right?
Yes. I know what you mean, but you will have been outside
in the air temperatures lower than zero.
Yeah, but... Oh, yeah.
No, I'm just curious what water, just the feeling, the sensation of the...
It's really, really cold.
I think it's just the only way anyone can...
I don't think anyone...
But no one must have ever jumped into this pond, because they would have died.
There we go.
Here's what's interesting about that thing is you would be able to lie down in there
and read a newspaper like in the Dead Sea, because it's so salty, I guess.
Oh, because you float right on top of it.
Yeah, yeah, you wouldn't sink.
Could you concentrate on what you were reading for how fucking cold it is?
Some trickier Guardian articles might be able to stretch.
Like the long read, you wouldn't get through.
That's some quick bites in the sun, it'd probably be fine.
You know Vespasian, the Roman emperor?
He heard about the Dead Sea, and he heard that people just float in it,
but he didn't believe it, and he didn't want to try it himself,
so he just got prisoners thrown into it to see what would happen.
Oh, wow.
And they floated.
They floated, yeah.
I will say, in case you're just going to book a trip,
that probably don't A, right now, but B,
in case you were going to book a trip to the Dead Sea to float, disappointing.
And a sank.
That was quite sinky.
It's a nice review.
One star sank.
You had a big lunch.
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show, and that is James.
Okay, my fact this week is that in 1912,
the woman with the most perfect feet in America was devast
because her husband was jealous of all the attention she was getting.
Really?
It's relatable.
James, can I just say?
Is that because you got such amazing feet?
Or because you want to deposit your mind?
Can I just say, James, this was an impossible fact to research.
When you Google "nice feet" or "perfect feet" in America,
oh my goodness, there's a lot of stuff to get through first,
before you find out about--
Yeah, he had--
Tell us about this woman.
Well, she just had really nice feet.
It was a stunt by the Caropedists of the USA to find the perfect foot,
and they eventually managed to find it on the end of a leg
of a woman called Miss Clara Smith Houston,
who coincidentally was also a Caropedist.
Yeah.
Anyway, so--
Suspects.
Feels a bit rigged to me, doesn't it?
It does feel a bit rigged.
I don't know.
You might get into an industry because your feet are so nice.
People have complimented you your whole life.
They thought, yeah.
Well, anyway, this story made it into some newspapers,
just as the Caropedists had hoped.
But the husband of Miss Smith Houston was not impressed,
and he sent her a telegram, like really divorced by text,
saying "friend, wife," not a great start.
"Congratulations on putting your best foot forward."
Nice pun.
"Nothing like notoriety, no matter how cheap."
"Send your picture to the Pink Journals and call on me for cash,
with which to advertise yourself further, full stop, your husband, full stop."
And then Clara was later quoted in another newspaper saying
that she decided if a man was so jealous,
he would not even allow me to boast of a perfect foot,
then I best give him up and all the luxuries
with which he provided me.
Except the one thing, happiness.
Here, here, here, here, Clara Houston.
I agree.
I get the luxuries.
Can I just--
So his message, when he's saying advertise yourself in a newspaper,
is he saying 'cause you're single now?
What's that second, what's that look?
I think he's saying just 'cause it's--
Oh, you're now a foot person, are you?
You know, you're now just sort of like trading on your feet.
I think he was also implying that she was living off his money.
And he was like, "Well, if you want more money,
just to advertise yourself to the world for your awesome feet,
then fine, full stop, your husband, full stop."
Those agro-full stops.
So the question here is, what is the perfect foot?
What did Clara have?
And she had--
Seven toes.
She had seven toes.
I guess having seven toes.
So she had nine inches.
They were nine inches long.
Do you know what size that is, though?
I just know.
I've just read it from this.
So you've just written down nine inches,
but you don't know how big or small that is,
presumably for a woman's foot.
'Cause I don't know--
At least Dan goes into the shoe shop
and he says, "I reject your size existence.
I'm going to give you an inches.
You can work it out."
256 barley corns, my good Dan.
I'd like a shoe that's about the size of a glass,
which I dragged from the other day.
I want a shoe that doesn't fit in James' con.
Well, for the listener, it's size 3.5, which is fairly small.
And what is the--
Why is it saying 10 inches around the instep?
The circumference, I suppose.
Yes.
OK.
Nice.
So very small feet, 3.5.
I mean, not freakishly small.
No, but that is small.
It's exactly 1/7th her height in accordance
with the Greek rule of sculpture.
Oh, that's interesting.
Yeah.
OK.
This is from the Day Book, where this was all published.
And it's an amazing blog, by the way, that you found, James.
Yes.
Second Glance History.
Yeah, it's absolutely brilliant.
And it was really nice,
'cause they had the cuttings of all the newspapers and stuff.
Yeah.
So I didn't have to go digging for them myself.
And then they found that there was a new perfect foot found in 1916,
which belonged to a nine-year-old girl called Mary Boca.
This was found in Chicago.
And Mary's mom said, "Mary had very pretty feet when she was a baby.
I felt nature's gift must not be marred.
I began massaging her feet with cold cream
to make them strong and smooth
and rubbed them carefully to preserve the natural outline."
Yeah.
And so her mom realized when she was really young
that she had really nice feet
and then put special stockings on her
so that she didn't damage the feet and all that kind of stuff.
It's like the William Sisters' dad, isn't it?
I bet they made a Hollywood film about her in the '30s.
I just don't get the whole feet thing.
I know lots of people really like feet.
20% of men, I believe.
Only 3% of them.
20% of straight men.
I think it was that.
Or maybe it was 10%.
What do you mean, really?
I feel like I...
Fetishize.
Right, okay.
Oh, really?
'Cause there's a website called wikifeet.
Oh, yeah.
It features a great number of feet.
Features greatly in your search history after this week.
It does now.
There are only three rules on wikifeet.
Only five toes.
The rules change constantly.
Updating their feet.
No, so you have to be...
It's normally people posting pictures of women's feet.
I don't think the men section on wikifeet is enormous.
It's sort of women over 17 who are listed on IMDb.
So you have to be in the public eye somehow.
No copyright breaches and no adult content.
But there are people who complain a lot.
They get in rouse with each other on wikifeet.
They'll post on a photo NFS.
Which means no feet showing.
Which is a point.
I know it is, yeah.
That is weird.
But I think if it's if someone's wearing...
Maybe if you've got a welly on.
This is pointless to me.
I think if you've got a welly on, you're on the right side.
My friend has a page.
It's a mutual friend.
I won't say her name, though,
'cause it is a bit of a weird site.
But she has a page on there.
And it has ratings.
So she has three out of five.
Three.
Yeah, which is okay.
She's got okay feet.
You wouldn't get in the Uber, would you?
If I had a three out of five.
I think it's a bit...
I mean, obviously it's pretty odd stuff.
And I think you can, if you say,
take my pictures off this website, they do.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, they seem quite nice.
There was a journalist who writes for the...
Well, I read an article in the cut anyway.
So she writes for the cut and all the other things.
And she was going out with someone who said,
"Hey, do you know you're on wikifeet?"
And she said, "No, I don't."
And so saw that she had indeed been uploaded.
Her feet had been uploaded
'cause they get it off like public Instagram pages,
for instance.
So they were pictures of her on the beach on Instagram
and someone's taken her feet.
And she said, "Okay, I'll get in touch."
So she got in touch with the person.
And so she interviewed this guy who posted her feet.
And she was very fair, I have to say.
And I thought he did seem a bit odd.
And she did say at one point,
"I've noticed that sometimes within 10 minutes
"of me posting an Instagram story that shows my feet,
"the screenshot is up on wikifeet.
"How does that happen?"
And he said, "Look, I don't just sit there looking for it.
"If I happen to see it and I like it, I'll put it on there.
"But I'm not sitting there all day and staring."
It's like, it sort of started off quite nice.
And then he obviously, you know,
he kept on saying what beautiful feet she had.
- I read an article that said that the incidence
of fetishism increases as a response to epidemics
of sexually transmitted diseases in history.
- Interesting.
This was a guy called Dr. James Giannini
and his colleagues who did the study.
And they look back as far back as the 12th century.
And they found that when there was a spike in STIs,
people preferred feet.
And it might have been that they were just less interested
in penetrative sex because they might get diseases.
- So your feet are a bit safer to fancy?
- I guess so.
- Yeah.
- Because what's the worst you can get?
Athlete's cock on your cock.
(laughing)
- Athlete's cock.
- Yeah.
- And then they went all the way up to the 80s
and they found even in the AIDS epidemic
that when that happened, then the numbers of foot oriented
and foot fetish pictures in kind of porn magazines
and stuff shot up there.
Because yeah, so preservation, I guess.
People are thinking, well, where else can I go?
- Can I tell you about Hogan Fukunaga?
- Yeah.
- He was arrested in the year 2000.
- Oh no.
- I know.
Along with 11 acolytes.
That's a bad start, isn't it?
(laughing)
When you and your acolytes have been picked up.
- So he was the head of a cult in Japan
which offered followers analysis of their spiritual
and mental health entirely based on their toes.
- Right.
- So followers would pay 600 quid to have their feet stroked
and then looked at by Mr. Fukunaga.
- Consenting adults.
- Consenting adults with more money than sense.
And no, consenting adults with maybe too much money
on their hands and who fell for the story
that, oh, I can predict your future through your toes.
- It's like a pedicure cum fortune teller, right?
- Yeah, it's like cross my foot with silver.
(laughing)
The predictions were all very suffering based.
They predicted, oh, you'll die of a horrible disease
or you'll fall into debt.
So that wasn't nice.
But you can avert your problems if you sign up
for one of our lecture courses
or if you buy a pinch of Buddha's ashes
at a mere 120,000 pounds.
- Okay.
- They were running this cult for about 15 years.
They made 500 million quid out of it.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
And then he claimed later on
that he had been simply obeying the voice of heaven
but that he had since forgotten what the voice had said.
(laughing)
- RIP a lot of people off, maybe.
- I think so.
- It feels like in this cult being called
the head of the operation is the wrong title.
(laughing)
That should be the junior role.
- Yeah, you're absolutely right.
- Yeah, he was the big toe.
When you have an enormous interest in feet,
I believe it's called podophilia,
which means there is a word that should be coined
for people who have an abnormal interest in podcasts.
So when I have Harkin's podcast,
you might have Andy's podophile cast.
- No, I'm saying that-
- Would all your acolytes be called podophiles?
(laughing)
You can get badges made.
- I'm a podophile, I shouted the mob out like my house.
(laughing)
- No, but there should be a word for people
who like podcast lots
because podophile is taken by the feet people, right?
- Let's call them feetophiles.
- Yes.
- We'll take their word back.
- But you know, there should be something.
- Audio file.
- Audio file, that's good,
but it's quite confusing 'cause it's also an audio file.
- Yeah.
- Oh, that's what makes it so perfect.
Sorry, it's actually better than a confusing, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- So famous names who love a foot include Elvis.
- Are we really doing this?
- We're really doing.
- There's a lot of people who have admitted
to loving feet and having been a feet.
- It's quite, it's just quite a turn for us, isn't it?
Like celebrity toe suckers.
- Yeah.
- Apparently the podcast is now about.
- It was a story, but apparently Elvis really loved it.
What's interesting is there is obviously
quite a lot of famous stories about, you know,
his henchmen would go out into a crown after a gig.
- Good henchmen and cut off people's feet.
(laughing)
- And they would bring them back to the volcano
where the Elvis had his Graceland.
- His foot soldiers, yeah, they would go out.
- And they would, so they would, you know, go,
you, you, do you want to come meet Elvis?
And obviously it was, you know,
to bring women backstage.
And apparently they screened their feet.
Is, is what is up with that?
- Were they crawling around on the floor in the gig?
Just looking for feet.
(laughing)
- I dropped an earring.
Presumably most women went to the gigs wearing shoes.
How are they doing that?
- Don't, I, I, you know, it's just a rumor.
- What, it's just a rumor?
- We know that he loved feet and the, the story is,
is that that was part of what it, you know,
the screening is what would go on and I'm lucky.
- Story is.
- Can I, can I steer us back towards karma waters?
- Sure.
- I think about corns.
You know, you get corns on your feet.
- Yeah.
- Oh, okay, yeah, yeah.
- Can, can you, can they transfer to your pain?
(laughing)
I don't believe so.
- Cock corn.
- But they used to, it used to have street corn cutters,
right?
That was the thing.
- Oh God, really?
- Yeah.
I mean, it was, you know, it's sort of pretty,
and it's, it's obviously, if you have corns,
they're really painful.
- What would you do?
- Like filing a nail, like that kind of material.
- All sorts of procedures, basically.
- But the weird thing is, I just like this,
I was on the blog Foot Talk,
which is another great foot based blog.
- Oh yeah.
- I really recommend it.
But there used to be jingles.
They would advertise themselves by singing jingles
in the streets.
And the weird thing about this is that sometimes
celebrity composers would write jingles for corn cutters.
- Really?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Like how celebrity are we talking?
Mozart's, God is.
- Well.
- Irving Berlin.
- I'm gonna say the name Orlando Gibbons.
- Oh yeah?
- Oh my God.
- Yeah.
- Not Orlando.
- Wait, I mean, so he.
- Wow.
- He was famous at the time.
He, you know, he was the organist at Westminster Abbey.
He was eventually named Virginalist to the King.
(all laughing)
- That was a storm, he was kind of like that, wasn't it?
- A virtual being, a kind of piano, obviously.
- Do we have the song then?
The jingle one?
- Sadly, I don't think we do.
They're pretty sure that he came up with jingles
for corn cutters as well, as a kind of sideline.
I don't know if it was lucrative or something to do.
- You guys are just reminding me.
Wilf, my son, he used to love corn on the cob,
but he always used to call it corn on the cock.
That was the phrase that he used.
- Can I tell you something about horses feet?
- Yeah.
- Which I love.
Is that horses feet are always giving you a middle finger.
One big middle finger.
Every horse's hoof is what we call a horse's foot.
It's just a big middle finger.
And this is because they once had five toes on their feet.
Many, many, many years ago.
There are actually kind of three of them still visible
'cause you've got two little vestigial ones.
If you know, horse's legs,
they're kind of a bit out of the leg.
But the hoof is just the middle finger.
And there's actually a biologist called Catherine Cavana
who recently was sorting through preserved horse embryos
for reasons she didn't go into.
And she saw that in the very, very early days
of horse gestation, they have five fingers
on each foot.
- Wow.
- And then you see it in the cells
and it's like they're about to grow
and then they decide not to grow
because they've evolved out of it.
- So let me ask you this.
If a horse with five toes rocks up to the Grand National,
are there regulations to say?
- No rules against it.
No rules against it.
- No rules, no rules.
And it's five times faster.
- Yeah, ridden by a crocodile.
(laughing)
You know that the women of Chicago
have been famous throughout America
for abnormally sized feet.
- Big or small?
- Big.
- Okay.
- In the early 20th century.
So this perfect foot, the second one was in Chicago.
And everyone was surprised
because people in Chicago usually have massive feet.
- What a funny key shape to have about it.
- It's amazing.
And I looked in the newspaper archives
and sure enough, if you look like before, you know,
the 20s and so it's for big feet Chicago,
there's all these articles are going,
"Yeah, they all got big feet."
And then you get people in Chicago saying,
"Yeah, we do have big feet,
but actually that also means we have big intellect."
- Wow.
- Yeah, sure it does.
- Is it just the women or is it the people in Chicago?
- It's the women of Chicago.
- Is it so that they can like walk out
over the Great Lakes and distribute their weight better?
- Oh, that would be good, yeah.
- I thought maybe 'cause it's the windy city, isn't it?
And it would help you not to get blown over.
- Great shouts.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it's got all these uses.
- That's evolution.
- That is such funny.
Is there any evidence behind it?
As it is, is it true?
- No, I can't be true.
I mean, I'll be honest, I haven't gone to Chicago
and measured all the women's feet.
But it can't be true.
- Get Elvis's henchmen to go and do it.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @Shrieberland, James.
- My Instagram is no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy.
- I'm on Twitter and now Blue Sky, @andrewhunterm.
- Yeah, and if you wanna get in contact with us
as a group, Anna, where do they go?
You can go to @nosuchthing on Twitter
or you can email podcast@qi.com.
- That's right.
You can also go to our website, nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
If you'd like to check them out, there's also some merch
and lots of other fun things.
Do check it out, but otherwise just come back here.
We'll be back again with another episode
and we'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]