(upbeat music)
Hi everyone, welcome to a brand new piece of bonus material
that we are, well, that I am calling
and no such thing as a quiz
'cause I don't have any other name for it so far.
What this is going to be is I have a story from history.
It's the kind of thing we might use on the podcast
but all the way through I'm gonna have some questions
that I'll be testing these guys on
to see if they can help me along as I tell the story.
There is one rule and that is
that there is a big question at the very start
and if you get that right, you get 100 points.
And if you get it right at any stage like Quidditch,
you know, if you catch the golden snitch,
you just get 100 points automatically
and you probably automatically win.
But apart from that,
there'll be smaller points awarded throughout the show.
- Well, they add up to more than a hundred.
- I shouldn't think so.
- Okay.
- We might work on the scoring system
as the series progresses.
- Yeah, the incentive structure is pretty messed up
right now.
- Yeah, well, you might realize that this is quite apt
when I tell you the main question.
And the main question for today's harking quiz
is what was the terrible slogan
that was used by the man who coined socialism
for his utopian community?
Now, you can guess at any time the answer to that question.
- You're gonna get one guess.
- No, no, you can keep guessing.
- Okay.
- So if you can think of some bad slogans now, in fact,
you might just stumble upon the answer.
- Less stuff for everybody, socialism.
(laughing)
- It would be more stuff for some people
with knit socialism.
Like the bottom of society would get more stuff.
- Well, that's why it's such a bad slogan.
- I thought that was why it's such a...
I think that might have been the point.
- Okay, well, if you think of any answers
to that big question all the way through,
then just stop me and you might get some points.
- Okay.
- So anyway, this is about a French philosopher
called Pierre Leroux.
He was born in the same year as Mary Shelley
and Franz Schubert.
Who can guess what year that was closest gets five points?
- Oh, okay.
- I don't want you thinking.
I want fast.
- 18, 21.
- 1792. - 1792. Andy, what did you say?
- 1796. - Holy moly, 1797.
(laughing)
That was so good.
- Here it goes.
- Nice.
- Oh my God, you were once on Osman's birthday game.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Annoyingly, they asked about Nick Knowles
rather than Mary Shelley.
(laughing)
- Well, Pierre Leroux was born in Paris,
which was a very exciting place to be alive at that time.
In fact, when he was a baby,
he might have seen the first use of an invention
by André Jacques Gannarin,
which was made out of silk.
What might that be?
- Parachute.
- A handkerchief.
Oh, and parachutes.
- Dan's got it.
Parachutes.
- Was he the guy who jumped off the Eiffel Tower?
- No, he wasn't.
You just lost some points.
- Damn it.
I moved tower in 1790, whatever.
- I was a quick-looking thing.
- Yeah, yeah.
You got some points,
but they were wrestled away from you
by saying something not true.
- That's harsh.
We weren't warned about this.
All points can be reflected straight away.
- I'm making up the rules as I go along.
It might not be clear.
Gannarin was a friend of the MacGolfiers,
and he went up in their balloons quite a lot.
And in fact, the next time he went up in the balloon
after the parachute jump, which he did,
he did something even more shocking.
And it was so shocking that he had to appear
in front of officials at the Central Bureau of Police
to justify his project.
So what did Gannarin do in balloons
that was incredibly shocking?
- He's gotta be having a wank.
(both laughing)
That's his experiment.
- Having a wank was not the right answer.
- So it's something he did in the balloon?
- It's something that he plans to do in a balloon, yeah.
- Plans to do in a balloon, okay.
- And they stopped him from doing it
because they heard about his plans.
- Shagging?
Oh, someone went up with lots of animals in a balloon.
Was it shagging the animals?
(both laughing)
- I think roll it back slightly 'cause you're close.
- Having a lady read a novel.
- Roll it back even more.
- Just putting a woman in the balloon.
- Putting a woman in a balloon.
- I feel like I should get some points of that.
- I'm gonna work out the points at the end.
I'm gonna re-listen to the whole show
and then work out how many points you did
and then do a retake of the number of points.
So you lot will never know who wins.
You'll have to listen back.
- This is as corrupt as the QI's face.
- Anyway, anyway.
So LaRue was born on the South Bank of the River.
- Send?
- Points.
In a bar run by his parents
and he went to Charlemagne College,
which was one of the biggest old schools in Paris.
It was founded by Napoleon
and loads of famous French people went there.
So first person you could name any French person
who went to this school.
- Victor Hugo.
- Victor Hugo, no.
- Napoleon III?
- No.
- Jacques Lacocque, the famous clown.
Jacques Cousteau.
- Hang on, have you got all the people who went there?
- All the famous ones.
- Charle Gaule.
- Jacques Chirac.
- No.
- Inspector Clouseau of the Sainte.
- Go for Victor Hugo.
- Oh, okay.
- But then.
- Oh, it's Jules Verne.
- Someone else in his family.
- Victor Hugo, senior.
- So close.
- Victor Hugo, junior.
- Correct.
- Victor Hugo's son, Francois, went there.
Bolzac, Carnot and Gérard de Neval
were the other famous people.
Anyway, so he went to further education,
but his father died.
This is La Rue we're talking about.
And so he worked in his cousin's printers,
eventually founding Le Globe,
which was a publication which became the voice
for Saint Simeonism,
which was a philosophy that came out of the French Revolution
and was started by a guy called Henri Saint Simon.
And they thought that instead of relying on religion,
society should be shaped by something else.
What could it be instead of religion?
- Oh, a big blob from Mars.
- A blob from Mars.
- Close, actually.
- Okay.
- Oh, astrology.
Astronomy.
- Closer, but be both vague.
- Ouija, spiritualism.
Seeing ghosts and listening to what they say.
- Paranormal.
- Sorry, astronomy.
Did you say astronomy?
- No, we said it weirdly.
What did you say?
Because I'd said astrological.
- There are no rules.
There are no points lost for saying things weirdly.
- Yeah, and also saying things weirdly.
Fuck off, Dan.
Eight years in.
So what's vaguer than astronomy?
Looking at the sky, just...
- Even more vague.
- Just looking around.
- Looking around?
- Less vague.
The answer is science or technology.
So they thought that society should be shaped
by science and technology and not religion,
because they got most of their ideas during the terror
when there was a huge anti-religious upheaval in Paris.
He was arrested, actually,
the Saint-Simeon during that time
for his plan to profit from the terror.
So it's very anti-religious.
How do you think he wanted to profit from the terror?
- Well, sell all the heads that have been chopped off.
- So close.
But think about how anti-religious was and he was in Paris.
- Selling off the church properties.
I'm gonna give it you.
He wanted to buy Notre Dame Cathedral on a knock-off price
and sell all the lead on its roof.
- Oh.
- Anyway, LaRue, he became a big name
in this Saint-Simeonism.
And there was him and a guy called Bartelamy,
Prosper and Fantin.
And they ran something that was pretty much like a cult.
One thing they did was they always wore cloaks
that were buttoned down the back.
Why would their cult do this?
What did it signify?
- Is it because you're all acting as a unit?
So only someone else can undo your cloak,
so it goes second night. - 100%.
- She's right, she's right.
She's on the gun, I've got it.
- I'm a big sharer.
- Lovely, that's lovely.
- Yes, so if you needed to dress or undress,
you needed help.
I suppose there's a woman.
- I was about to say, as a lot of women's clothing,
less so male, has a zip on the back for dresses and so on.
- Yeah, you can usually do the zip up the back.
The buttons all the way up the back
would be more difficult.
You'd have to be a serious gymnast.
- But if you're bursting for the toilet
and one of your friends isn't around,
that's presumably a bit stressful.
- Yeah, they're cloaks.
So maybe you can just lift up the cloak.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Anyway, so the group split in 1832
and LaRue gave up on philosophy after Enfantin did what?
So they were in a cult together.
They're kind of quite a brotherhood of cults.
- No, it started sleeping with all the partners.
- I'm gonna say he did a sort of cloak prank
where he buttoned it up all the way around
and LaRue couldn't get out of the cloak for days.
- He went himself.
- Let's see who was closest.
My answer is he advocated free love,
called himself a messiah,
and sent his acolytes out around France
to find a female saviour with whom he could have sex
and give birth to a new god.
- Bo, bo, bo.
- Yeah, Dan went down.
- Dan was definitely a classic cult.
So LaRue was also friends with Georges Sond,
the novelist who at the time was bigger than Bolzac
and Victor Hugo put together.
Today she's probably most well known by people like us
for the fact that she wore trousers in Paris
without a permit, which wasn't allowed at the time.
And what two official reasons did she give
that she was wearing trousers?
- Bad legs.
(laughing)
- Those are the two reasons.
- Left, right, right, right, right, right, right.
- A health thing, maybe?
- She's got the bottom of her skirt, it's wet.
- No.
- And the rain.
- This is quite an easy one, I think.
- They're on the laundry.
- Pockets.
- I'm gonna give it to you.
Practical was one of them.
- Oh, okay.
- Okay, and more affordable.
- And cheaper, yeah, perfect, very good.
You guys are pretty good at this quiz.
What other thing did Georges Sond do in public,
which was very bad form for a woman at the time?
- I'm gonna go back to my earlier answer
having a wanker to the loop.
- It's gonna be right one of these days.
This is not that day.
- She did quite a lot of dodgy stuff, you know?
She was, she didn't like religion.
I think she spoke out against that.
- She did.
- She shagged Chopin, but I don't think she did that
in public.
- Drinking alcohol in public.
- Getting nude, I would say.
- Getting nude, I'm not sure she did that.
She was wearing trousers, we've already ascertained.
Smoking cigars.
- Oh, yeah, she loves cigars.
- She did.
So Sond was the great, great granddaughter
of Augustus the Strong of Poland.
Well, she was the illegitimate offspring of him.
And he was famous for two things.
So famous for fox tossing
and for having lots of illegitimate offspring.
And there are two points available here.
How many illegitimate offspring did he reportedly have?
And how many foxes did he toss on one day in Dresden?
And to give you a clue,
you can have to the nearest 100 for each.
- Okay, whoa.
All right, 700 kids, 900 foxes.
- Okay.
- 200 and 350.
Whichever way round is correct.
- I think 100 kids, 200 foxes.
- It was 647 foxes that he tossed.
And either 365 or 382 children.
I'm not sure any of you got any points there.
- 365 is neater, isn't it, for the children?
- Yeah, I think that might be why they said it.
- One for every day of the year.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It's a lot of birthday parties, isn't it?
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- You would only need like 50 children to,
on average, two of them would have the same birthday.
- Yeah, I think it's less even, isn't it?
I think it's 23. - It's 1823, man, like that.
- No points for that, because I got it wrong.
- So, Georgetown came from money, actually,
because she was a great granddaughter
of this Augustus Estrung, the fox tosser.
So, she financed LaRue's ideas and he started a new magazine
and a commune for his staff to live in.
The idea is they would farm the land for their food
and they would print the magazine.
And he wanted like a money-free society,
but he had to collect tax in some way
so that everyone paid into a collective pot.
And what did they pay instead of money?
- Compliments.
(all laughing)
- Pogs.
- What's that?
- Pogs in 1800s.
- Is it salts?
People always love collecting salts, actually.
- To say, they're growing crops.
- Yeah.
- Okay, I'm gonna go on a limb and say urine,
because everyone produces it
and it can be used in industrial processes,
so maybe-- - Yeah, very good.
- Okay, well, we'll see if that's right.
'Cause around the same time,
there was a scientist called Busingo,
who had some ideas about fertilizer
and there was a big boom in the fertilizer industry
around that time due to--
- Gonna be poo.
- Guano.
- Guano, points.
And he wondered whether a single animal
could create enough poo to grow enough food
for that animal to live.
Sort of a perfect system.
And so he got a cow
and he worked out exactly what it ate,
weighed all of its poo
and did a load of calculations.
But this experiment didn't go very well,
so what was the problem with the experiment
and what did he do to improve it?
- It was a, it wasn't a cow.
(laughing)
- It was two people in a cow situation.
- It was a pantomime act.
It was too embarrassed to reveal what's really going on.
- Collected the poo from the back
and also halfway down.
- Yes, it was handed to the cat guy,
but then had to pretend it was then coming out of his anus.
- No, the problem he had is just that cows are too big
to do this experiment.
You could do it with any animal,
so he started doing it with turtle doves instead.
- Did it work?
- Well, it didn't, in that there was a theory at the time
that perhaps you would be able to create enough poo
to create enough fertilizer for your crops.
Turns out not quite to be true,
but LaRue thought that it did.
And so he had a community in France
which where everyone paid their tax in poo.
- Oh.
- Close enough of your, and I reckon.
And the motto for this utopian community was.
- Spread the shit.
- That's the shit.
- Shit, you're so fridge.
(all laughing)
- The answer which I'm afraid none of you thought.
- Poo topia.
(all laughing)
- Okay, I'm going to give points for the best answer,
but the actual answer that his community had the slogan,
make bread with excrement.
(all laughing)
- Okay, so that's the end of the quiz.
I will tot up all the scores when I get home.
You guys will never know who wins.
People at home, stay tuned because you're about here.
Who's the winner?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, I'm home.
I have totted up the points.
And for the people who are really bothered,
because let's be honest,
the points are not really that important in this game.
The winner was Andrew Hunter Murray
with 16 points followed by Dan Schreiber with 14
and Anna Tyshinski with nine.
Hope you enjoyed this little quiz.
We probably will do it again sometime,
but this little club fish extra bonus material,
it's really a sand pit for us
to try all sorts of different things.
If you enjoyed the show or you have any questions
or comments about it,
then do drop us a line at podcast.qi.com
and we will read all your messages there.
Hope you enjoy the rest of your week.
We will see you again next week.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
you