(upbeat music)
- Hi everybody, Andy and Dan here.
Welcome to this episode of No Such Things As A Fish.
We've got a very exciting guest today.
- We do.
We have the brilliant Deliso Chaponda.
Deliso, some of you will know from being a finalist
on Britain's Got Talent a few years ago.
He's an amazingly funny standup comedian.
And we were very excited that he was gonna join us
on the show 'cause he's a big old nerd.
He's written a sci-fi set of short stories
that you can buy on Amazon and other online stores,
but he's going on tour as well.
- He certainly is.
His show is called Topical Storm.
You see, 'cause it's about the devolved news
and it's about the news.
- So that's a good title, that's what you're saying.
- It's a really good title.
And it's a really good tour
and he's going all over the place with it.
Where's he going?
Let's see, he's doctored on T, he's Chipping Norton, London.
- And various other places of roughly the same size.
- Yeah, and it's happening now.
He's on tour right now.
- He certainly is.
- So do get your tickets,
'cause you don't wanna miss out on it.
He's absolutely brilliant.
His website is delisochuponda.com.
Now, you're probably also thinking,
God, be great to see deliso,
but dammit, we'd love to see fish live as well,
but you're not doing any shows.
- Absolutely.
And what about a live show involving Anna?
- Who?
- Anna Tajinsky, when she's back very soon.
Well, have we got a surprise for you?
We're gonna be doing a live show this August
in Lund, at the Lund Comedy Festival in Sweden.
- Yeah, that's right.
We're really excited for it.
It's gonna be a live show recording.
If you have spare dodge to buy a plane ticket,
why didn't you come from the UK as well?
'Cause it's gonna be a great night
and it's the live return of Anna Tajinsky to the stage.
Tickets are on sale now.
You just need to go to nosuchthingasaffish.com/lund.
- That's right, Saturday the 29th of August at 7pm.
Come and see our impression of the Swedish chef.
Live.
Oh dear.
(laughs)
All right, yeah.
Watch us be booted out in the country.
Anyway, on with the show.
- On with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
(funky music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thingasaffish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and Deliso Chapponda.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Deliso.
- So my fact is in 1981, more than 1 million
bibles were smuggled into China by water.
- In one go.
- In one go?
- No. - No.
- 'Cause normally you smuggle things, you know,
bit by bits.
- No, also usually you're smuggling cocaine
or raisins, but bibles, that's what I love most about it.
- The way they smuggled it, it didn't go in the bum.
- It didn't go in that way.
You'd have to have very small bibles, if you could.
- Yeah, there would have been major theological chats
about what that implied if you did that.
- You could do it nowadays though,
because now the USB sticks.
- Absolutely.
- In each bible.
- Yeah, but when I put the USB stick in my bum,
I always put it the wrong way around.
That's what I'll end then.
- Very strong.
- But no, so they submerge tons of bibles.
Literally, I'm not using the metaphor tons.
It was they weighed tons of bibles,
and then they submerge them underneath a boat
which was called Michael.
Which I think is honestly the least sexy sounding name
for your clandestine.
- And in fact, Delisa, you say tons.
There's 139 tons in weight.
- 139 tons in weight.
- I know.
I believe there were small bibles,
as in they weren't the huge, big desk ones,
'cause obviously when you are smuggling size matters,
but this is because Christianity was suppressed at the time.
- Yes.
- That's right.
- And owning a bible was in the fence at the time.
- They were a few bibles, but it was being repressed,
and so they weren't a lot of,
it was after the cultural revolution,
and religion is the opiate of the masses.
- It's very vague exactly what the penalty would be
if you had it, but there were no bibles,
so they have to sneak them out.
- Well, people go to jail.
You still get people who are going to jail
and being released back to,
so they're being smuggled over from Hong Kong and so on,
and so they'll be sent back after a few years in jail.
So you will get jail time.
It kind of depends on the moment,
but this was a huge operation.
This was Open Doors, which is a smuggling industry.
This extraordinary thing that was started by one man
called Andrew Vanderbile, who used to smuggle
all of these bibles into different countries,
and then this was the ultimate project.
How do we get all of these bibles into China?
- Can you tell me more about exactly how it works?
So did they put it underwater and drag it along,
or what, in a submarine or?
- Well, so they built a special barge in the city of Shan two,
which was designed to sink.
So you do get submersible ships.
- Yes, right.
- We've talked before about when you need to give it,
let's say you've got an oil carrier that's broken or something,
you can get special ships which approach sink beneath,
sink underneath and then lift up again.
They're fantastic.
And this was a similar principle.
And the bibles were all in watertight packaging, obviously.
- Yes, and I ranked on them.
- And I'm fairly confident there were loads of believers
who were on the beaches and waded in,
submersed up to their necks,
retrieving these tons of bibles and carrying them off.
But also, some were believers and others were businessmen
because there was a scarcity of bibles.
Bibles were very expensive.
So there were other people who were in it
because you could sell them to Christian.
- That doesn't sound very Catholic.
- And it sort of went wrong on the night.
A lot of the authorities saw what they were doing
and were arresting people and a bunch of the bibles
swept away into the ocean.
So they thought, okay, that's it.
But then fishermen, this is the story.
There's so many weird stories about this.
One of the stories goes that fishermen saw on the surface
these bibles gleaming like fish that they brought them in.
And then they realized, oh, we've got all these bibles
'cause they were watertight.
So yeah, so the bibles found a way.
- And then even we was like,
some of the authorities grabbed bibles
and they flung them into like sewage.
And then believers climbed in right afterwards
and retrieved them.
- How interesting.
And this guy, so he's called Andrew van der Beil.
And he wasn't just China.
He did all of, beyond the Iron Curtain, right?
So it was Eastern Europe.
- And there were a lot of volunteers
because I heard about this
because I do a lot of, like religious shows.
And I was doing Green Belt Festival in Cheltenham,
which is like a religious kind of glass timbre.
And in the audience, there was one of the people
who had volunteered for one of these project roles.
- In China or in Eastern Europe?
- In China.
- Wow, amazing.
- So gosh, I think he was doing a talk about it.
But I was like, wow, what story.
I read that he would pray to God
when he took his bibles across.
And let's say he's going to Eastern Europe,
he might take them in his car.
Okay, so he's driving through the Iron Curtain
and people would check his car.
And he said he would pray to make seeing eyes blind.
And the border patrol people would be searching his car
and couldn't find the bibles.
Even though they were just sat there running back seat.
- And he said, that was because he prayed to God.
- That's somewhat in miracle.
I'm surrounded by skeptics.
I believe the man.
- He's dressed as a Bible because if you're dressed,
you know, yeah, it's in plain sight.
- It's also like, it sounds like nonsense,
but there's also a level where they're looking
for weapons and things.
- Yeah.
- So they'll just see a pile of books
and they'll go past it.
He, what, do you know what I mean?
Like, even though they are illegal,
I wonder how high up on the border patrols,
radar, bibles are because they're looking for weapons.
- In the cultural revolution, I think it was, right?
And I think in Soviet Russia, it was as well.
So do you guys know Vitaly Vitalev?
- Yeah.
- He met him, you met him.
So he used to work on QI for a little bit
and he left Russia during the Soviet Union,
but he did cross the border a few times.
He said when he was on a train and he would cross the border,
people would come down the train shouting,
"Bibles all pornography, bibles all pornography."
- Oh, that's great.
It's like a personality test.
- You're the one, are you?
And if you're both the Bible's pageant of the stock together.
- I'm sorry, I'm sorry, that's terrible, that's terrible.
- And that was like, you had to hand them in when they said that.
- Yeah, right.
- I really like the sound of this guy.
Purely just the adventure.
So he wrote a book.
- And he wrote a book.
- Yeah, he wrote a book which was called God Smuggler
and it sold over 10 million copies supposedly,
translated into 35 different languages.
And every country seemed to bring in its own new
Mr. Beanish moment.
In Albania, he used to do sort of drop-offs
where he would just sort of put the Bible down and walk off.
And you know, and then people would find it
and chase after him, go, "You're Bible, you've left your Bible."
And so he was just constantly outed
by people returning his lost property.
- Yeah.
- But I also think like, despite them trying to repress Christianity,
it grew in China in these years.
And I actually think part of it is, if it's forbidden
and you happen to smuggle in Bibles,
it becomes more elaborate.
But like, it becomes like, "Oh, this is the truth
"because they don't want us to read the truth."
And so places like the UK where you've got dwindling attendance,
ban it, ban it for a while.
- Yes, that's not by the, exactly.
- The happy moments in the UK
where people have been arrested for smuggling Bibles,
isn't there?
So William Tendell, and his mate who was called Mummeth,
but I can't remember his name, but Humphrey Mummeth.
So we're talking quite a long time ago.
We're talking Henry VIII times,
but the thing was that these Bibles were written in English.
And so they're in the vernacular.
And so that you're allowed Bibles as long as they're in Latin,
but if they're in English, you're in big, big trouble
because the church wanted to control
what was in the Bible.
They wanted you to only hear what the priest had to say.
They didn't want you to read it yourself
and make your own ideas.
- So Tendell was executed for this at the time crime.
The man who smuggled the men, the Humphrey Mummeth,
who was a cloth draper, he was smuggling the men in his ships.
He was briefly imprisoned.
But within a few years,
every church in the country had one of these.
And the King James Bible,
which is maybe the most significant English translation ever,
is one of the most beautiful.
Our language is full of phrases from the King James.
80% of it is Tendell's translation.
It's the absolute underpinning of the Bible in English.
I have recently read a smuggled book.
And I wasn't aware of,
I wasn't aware of when I picked it up and looked at it,
that this was illegal.
But I've just finished a book
which was punishable by death in Italy
at a certain point in history.
And it was smuggled in.
It's called The Moon Is Down by John Steinbeck.
And he wrote it explicitly as propaganda.
He was working for the US government,
early days of American involvement in the Second World War.
It's a tale of a nameless European town
where a nameless army invades
and takes over their collaborators.
And it's a story of the invading army
being resisted by the population
and then slowly cracking up as they realize
the awfulness of this war and what they've done
will, you know, they'll never be forgiven for it.
It will never end all of this
and the people will throw them out.
And in Italy, if you had a copy,
you could be punished with the death.
I've been to the Museum of Band Books,
which is in talent, I think, in Estonia.
It's really cool.
It's just a very small place run by one guy.
It's basically a bookshelf, to be honest.
And you can buy all these books
that have been banned everywhere else in the world.
And I think there's one book
that even he doesn't keep on displaying.
He keeps under the counter.
- Really? Do you remember what it was?
- If memory serves, I think, is it?
Oh, I forgot what it's called now.
Is it the anarchist's handbook?
- The anarchist's cookbook.
- Cookbook, that's it, yeah, yeah.
- Well, that tells you how to build bombs.
- Yeah, yeah, so.
- I was at home last year, I think, maybe the year before.
And I was, I can't remember now.
It's just this is reminded me.
You go home all the time, Louis.
- No, it's once or twice a year.
I kind of say hi to the kids.
I was going through some boxes.
And I found a box of books that were given to me
by a friend who moved overseas and I opened it up.
And in it was the anarchist cookbook.
- Wow.
- I didn't know that that was a smuggled book
or that it's illegal,
'cause it is still illegal to own it in this country.
So that night, on Instagram, I posted a picture of me
reading this book, going,
sitting down to a nice book and a glass of wine
and upholding it, and I posted it.
And I went to sleep, I woke up in the morning
to about 20 DMs saying, take that down immediately.
This is an illegal book.
People have gone to jail in the UK for up your bum right now,
mister, and dived, dived, dived, yeah.
So I had to get, I didn't know if I had to go to the police
to give it to them.
- I don't do that.
- That's embarrassing.
- I know right.
- That book, it's cause, it actually tells you how to make weapons.
But a lot of books which are banned,
it backfires because it makes you want to read it.
So I read this satanic verses when I was a teenager, right?
It's an extremely difficult book to read.
It's extremely dense.
You need to be a university student,
but because it was banned, we read it with our dictionaries
and tried to figure it out.
And I actually think, you know,
the banning of it made it more--
- Absolutely.
I still haven't finished.
- It's the satanic verses.
I've just started it as of last week.
- Oh, how odd.
And can I just say for anyone listening,
I've never read it.
I had to do not get to read it.
- Well, there's an amazing book called Joseph Anton,
which is Salmon Rushdie's whole experience
of what happened once the fatwa was put on him.
And he was saying that the book is known as something
called the page 15 club because most people
can't get past page 15 of it.
So you're part of a club if you've started
and you've never gone further than that.
But yeah, exactly, more dangerous
because of the banning of it.
- The banning of it.
- Yeah.
- Can I tell you my favorite book smuggling incident?
Okay, so Cold War, we've mentioned Eastern Block.
There was a lot of book smuggling into the Soviet Union
because there were a lot of banned texts.
And the CIA had a program smuggling in works
which they saw as spreading freedom democracy,
that kind of thing.
Things like 1984, the Guardian Weekly,
try to find rather nice.
(laughing)
'Cause the Guardian did a weekly magazine.
- Yeah.
- And it was all sort, you know, they smuggled in miniature books
in tampon boxes and sugar packets.
I mean, I've presumed tiny.
- Yeah.
- But I just love this wonderful detail
of the CIA operation.
In one instance, Alexander Solzzynitsyn's The Gulag Archipelago
was carried on to a plane to Warsaw in a baby's nappy.
- Oh, wonderful.
- I know.
- Wonderful.
- In our family, whenever my daughter needs to be changed,
she would say she's done assaults in Nitsyn.
(laughing)
- My favorite one is in Romania.
So in 2013, there were people started smuggling books
into prisons.
- Okay.
- And this is really interesting.
So they changed the law in 2013 that meant if you were in prison
for like a white collar crime, let's say,
you could get 30 days off your sentence
for every book that you wrote.
- 30 days.
- That's you wrote.
- Wait, wait, wrote?
- Yes.
So if you wrote a book, Andy, let your knock your books
off into you.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- That's why he's back out so quickly.
(laughing)
But if you wrote a book, then you'd get a month off your sentence.
- Wow.
- So a lot of like people who are in for fraud or tycoons
or former politicians or something suddenly started knocking
out books left, right in the center.
Now, have you written a book of short stories that which I have?
And it takes a long time.
- I did.
- Like that you did those over years and years.
- Over years, yeah.
- So what they did is they would get like experts in a subject
to write a book, then they would smuggle them into the jail
and then they would just copy them out and then put by whoever
and then say, written 30 days off, please.
- Oh, they copy their homework.
- So for instance, there was a former politician called
Georgia Koppos who wrote about the matrimonial alliances
of medieval Romanian rulers.
- Did no one write him like that?
I mean, you should be writing all this from memory,
Georgias.
That's very impressive.
- I called really Neelupse who was a pop singer.
(laughs)
He went to prison for fraud who wrote a book about stem cells
in dental medicines.
- And he's already in prison for fraud.
- Yeah.
- Do you think they'll be like, "I'm not sure you're under
"the nut."
- Isn't that amazing?
- That's so incredible.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for fact number two and that is Andy.
My fact is, Lake Malawi contains a thousand species
of the same kind of fish, one lake,
a thousand different species.
- Big lake.
- Very big lake.
- Big lake, they're waves.
- When I first went there, I didn't know
lakes could have waves.
- Oh, really?
- Is it like breakers, like surfables?
- They're smaller waves, but I'm sure they're times
of the year when it's larger, but it has waves.
- Wow.
- And I always thought a lake was like a glorified pond.
- Oh, it was a big, yeah, yeah.
- It's got beaches, it's got, yeah, it's huge.
And it's got a lot of sick lid fishes.
- Wow.
- More than a thousand species.
So this is absolutely bizarre.
I mean, they arrived in the lake, you know,
one species arrived in the lake, maybe three million years ago.
Some billions of years ago.
Why are there so many now?
- Well, okay, it doesn't think like,
you have a type of mouse, right?
Comes into an area and then some of them are bald here,
some of them are born here, and then there's something
goes in between them, some kind of barrier,
which means that the ones on one side
can't mate with the ones on the other,
and eventually they become new species, right?
In a lake, how does that work?
Like I know there's waves and everything,
but like what is stopping them from mating?
- So there was a study of this, and it's a theory,
but it's reasonably convincing.
There are a few different ideas.
One of them was a team of scientists
led by Christopher Schultz, who looked at this,
and found that historically, the level of the water
in like Malawi, it's about 700 meters deep,
I think at the deepest, but it has gone up and down
and up and down and up and down,
and it's plunged by at least 200 meters,
more than 20 times over its history.
And so every time that happens,
things change in the lake, the shoreline moves,
the pH levels change, and sometimes it even splits
into smaller lakes before the water's rise again,
and it's reunited.
So if the lake is split into smaller lakes,
those fish in each of those smaller areas
will split off from each other, spend time,
specializing at breeding in among themselves,
then suddenly when the lake is reunited,
you've got different species.
- That makes sense, that makes sense actually,
but I envision a kind of reverse tower of Babel,
kind of situation, where the fish were trying
to borrow their way down to the almighty,
because almighty was like, no, and they all speak
different languages now and different languages.
- Well, that's not been tested fully,
but it's a strong, yeah, it's strong, it's good.
So we should say it is massive this lake, right?
It's a fifth of Malawi is this lake basically.
- It used to be called Lake Niasa,
because when British arrived in Malawi,
they called it Niasa land,
and then after independence, we became Malawi.
- It's also called the calendar lake,
which is quite a cool name.
It's because, roughly, it's 365 miles long,
and 52 miles wide at its widest, so it's a calendar.
- Oh, it's a calendar?
- Yeah, 365 days, 52 weeks, and they say,
and I couldn't prove this,
but 12 main rivers flow into it as well.
So it even breaks down into lovely, yeah.
- But it's probably there's like a few more.
- Oh, that one doesn't go out.
- And I think they're the main rivers.
- They've been seen, but that one, that one's a trick-a-treat.
- And I think there are a few miles
that they're shopping off as well when they measure that.
- The fastest swim across Lake Malawi
was seven hours, 42 minutes, and 47 seconds.
What do you think was the fastest swim from top to bottom?
- So it looks like an exclamation mark, isn't it?
It's 50 miles across, but 36, like the country of Chile.
- Yes. - So seven hours.
- So seven hours.
- So some maniac, so maybe it was 49 hours.
- It was 63 days.
- Oh, you can't swim from that.
- I know, it was in stages.
- You're just stopping it.
- And it was by Martin Hobbes from South Africa
who I'm sure is not a maniac.
- He's a maniac, he's a maniac.
Like all of these people, like I've met Eddie Azard,
and I was like, you're a madman.
- Yeah.
- Like what are these people swimming across things
for no reason?
- Well, there's no crocodiles in it, like Malawi.
- That's it.
- It has hippos.
- Oh, that's worse.
- Neither is good if that goes.
- Okay, so this is the thing is,
if you are near a hippo's child, a hippo's worse
than a crocodile.
But if you leave the hippo alone,
and there are no children present,
a hippo is a very...
- Once you really have to look out for his,
the hungry, hungry hippos.
- Oh yeah.
(laughing)
- They're absolutely worse.
He, I read about him, James.
The Martin Hobbes guy.
- Oh yeah.
- So six years before he swam from the top
to the bottom of Lake Malawi,
he had never swam a mile.
- Six years before.
Okay.
- And he just started.
- He started.
I think he had an injury.
I think he was already a sportsman.
- Yes.
- And then he had an injury,
which meant he couldn't do his original sports.
- Right.
- And then he took to swimming.
But isn't that, just imagine six years from now,
we could all be on the northern shore of Lake Malawi.
- Race.
- Ready to surf.
(laughing)
- And the fish that are in there,
there are some pretty wild varieties.
- Yeah.
- There's one which is called the eye-biter.
We heard of the eye-biter.
- And how does it get that name?
- So.
- Basically, they found eyes in its stomach
and they think that it,
they don't know if it's eating the eyes as nourishment
or if it's taking the eyes out of the predator
or the one that it wants to eat.
- What is that fish?
- Yeah, of the other fish.
So it eats fish, eats the eyes,
therefore has a better chance of killing it all together.
- Right.
- So you start with the eyes.
- You start with the eyes.
- And this leads to the joke,
doesn't it?
What do you call a fish with no eyes?
- Yes.
- What do you call a fish with no eyes?
Dimmidochromus compresses eps.
That's why I call it.
- There you go.
- There were eyes in that.
- It should have been the promise.
- D-E, it should have been D-E-M, D-M, D-M.
- Yeah, but that behavior's never been observed
in the wild I've had.
- Exactly.
- So we're right.
- It's a theory.
- It's an unfold.
- They have found the eyeballs.
- They've seen the eyes,
but they've never seen the--
- Yeah, exactly.
- It's supposed, you know,
Attenborough has no time to go film them aloud.
(laughing)
- Here's another one, the sleeper sick lid,
which you get in Lake Malawi.
It does a thing called thanatosis.
And thanatosis is where you pretend to be dead.
But they do it in a really awesome way.
They lie down on the bottom of the sea
and they can change the color to like a blotchy,
very sick-looking fish.
And so the other fish go past and go,
oh god, he looks a bit sick.
And like, he obviously was feeling terrible
before he died, and then they go close to him.
And then he goes, ta-da!
Not dead after all.
And then probably bites, all right.
- This is awesome.
- I'll tell you, I wasn't afraid of Lake Malawi,
but this episode would be like,
"Why do I swim in there?"
- There's also the Malawi squeaker that I found,
which is a type of upside down catfish.
- Right.
- Another question.
- What's an upside down catfish?
They swim upside down so that their mouths
are at the top of the water
and they can eat bugs that are on the surface, yeah.
- I thought upside down catfish
is they actually look better than their fish.
(laughing)
- And it's called the Malawi squeaker
because when you take it out of the water,
it goes, "Squeak, squeak, squeak, squeak, squeak."
- Oh, that's amazing.
So I've read that it's very clear in like Malawi.
So you've swam in it.
How far have you seen giant fish?
- No, no, no, you swim.
Like when you go to the ocean,
you only swim in the shallow area.
You don't go away out there.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So I've swam in it,
but I've never been more than 50 meters out here.
- This is so big.
Does it feel like you're in the sea?
- It feels like when the ocean is not salty.
It's, it's, it's, it's, yeah.
- I'm interested.
- I read that it gets waves up to six meters high,
but that's, okay.
- That's huge.
- No, yes.
- Exactly what I mean, like,
if you felt like, if you knocked me out,
I would think I'm at the ocean.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- You have special things, it's something called
the Moira Wins that come every year
in November, December and January
that made it basically fish them
and can't go out that time either.
So it's lots of people go fishing there,
but you can't go in those times.
But like at the start of November
or the end of January,
you kind of can do a little bit,
but it's a bit dangerous.
But if you go out fishing them,
no one else is doing it,
so you can sell your fish for way more.
- Oh, that's kind of something I'll take care of.
- It's gonna reward.
'Cause those were the other names that it was given.
David Livingston, who was one of the first people
to describe it for the West,
certainly, he called it the Lake of Storms
and the Lake of Stars,
because you would see all the light
of the fishermen in the distance.
- And we have an annual festival
called Lake of Stars.
- Ah.
- Anyway, all these musicians come
and keep those smoke weed in it.
(laughing)
- Oh, this is a fact.
Malawi has the best weed in Africa.
- Really, Malawi Gold, it's cold.
- Really?
- Everyone goes on about Malawi has no minerals,
but we always say, "We've got Malawi Gold."
(laughing)
- We should say that you grew up in Malawi.
- No, I was refugee, so my blood is Malawi,
but my dad had to flee Malawi
because of our dictator.
But when I was in adolescence
and the dictator was gone eventually,
we went back to Malawi.
- And so you've got family there, still.
- I've got family there now.
- Amazing.
- But parents are there.
- And my one brother.
- Dileesa, you may not know.
One of the things I do in this podcast,
is I find any link I can to the first or second world wars,
no matter what we're talking about.
- Okay, so they were some Malawi soldiers sent.
- Well, first naval engagement of the first world war, guys.
- Oh.
- Lake Malawi.
- No. - Really?
- Wow.
- So exciting.
There were at the time,
roughly two Western boats on Lake Malawi.
Unfortunately, one was English and one was German.
(laughing)
So it was a colonial time.
And the borders of Lake Malawi,
it's a few different countries around it, aren't it?
- Yeah.
- So basically, a British steamer named HMS Gwendolyn,
which was named after the daughter of the Marquis of Salisbury.
- Okay.
- Lovely name for a ship.
- Very nice.
- It had one gun on it, I think.
And there was a German steamer,
which the captains were friends.
They were drinking buddies.
But the English found out the war was happening slightly
before the Germans.
So the English just sailed up, opened fire, one shot.
The German captain yells, "Roads, are you drunk?"
He said, "His friend, who's just overvar on him."
One shot battle roads,
then just confiscates the English captain,
confiscates the German gun.
And no more is said about it.
And that was the first naval battle of the First World War.
- Wow.
- I know.
- No more was said about it.
You've shot.
This is the first time anyone else is hearing about it.
- No, no, it's podcast.
(laughing)
- That's like finding out if you were just sitting
in a cafe with your friend,
and he happened to be German,
and you read the news before,
but you just popped into the air.
(laughing)
- The battle over.
- That's amazing.
- So, what's the name that keeps coming up
as names of towns and so on in Malawi is David Livingston?
- Yes.
- Who obviously was the missionary?
- Yeah, and it sounds like a lot of place names
that were colonially named have been changed,
but the Livingston ones seem to remain.
- Well, it's because Livingston is remembered positively.
- Yeah, right.
- So he came, he brought bibles and stuff.
- How did he bring them in?
(laughing)
- But, honestly, the tales of him is education and medicine,
so he's, there was not a hurry to rename his stuff,
but like the road stuff where it's associated with,
as being oppressed and being, that's all been renamed.
So, a lot of the Livingston names.
- Yeah, because he's fondly remembered.
- Blantaya, which is known as the New York of Malawi,
that's where Livingston was born in Scotland.
- And there's a Blantar in Scotland, yeah.
- Oh, are they twins or?
- They're not really.
I mean, on their Wikipedia,
which is where I had a brief look,
it said that it's twinned with many places,
but not with that town.
- How interesting.
- But there is a statue in Blantar in Scotland
of Livingston fending off a lion attack.
And it's designed by Ray Harryhausen.
(laughing)
- Is that the monster guy?
- Yeah, wow.
- So we should say,
he designed this special effects
for all the amazing old films, like,
what was it, the Jason and the Arctic Arch.
- Jason and the Arctic Arch.
- The Titans, yeah, those are fantastic.
- Apparently, he was married to a descendant of Livingston.
- Wow. - Yeah.
- And so, he did the statue. - That's amazing.
- There's also Livingstonia in Malawi.
He's got quite a few places, instead of named after him.
- Speaking of old sci-fi films,
I was reading about someone called The Terminator,
who is responsible for the annulments
of 3,500 marriages in Malawi.
- Oh yeah.
- So this apparently is someone called Theresa
catching them up.
- Oh, this is the child marriage.
- Yeah.
- No, no, she's actually absolutely amazing.
- Isn't that amazing? - Sorry.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, no, so essentially,
there was a practice of marrying very underage people.
And so she campaigned against her whole life
and I'll rescue these women, it was amazing.
- And then educated people in the area
about what to do in future and stuff like that.
But yeah, known as The Terminator,
because she terminated so many of these marriages.
- That's great.
- And whenever she terminated a marriage,
she'd be like, "I'll be back."
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the first ever British space suit
designed included a cape and a walking stick.
- Yes. - Yes.
- Yes.
- Wow, this was for floating in space.
- This, yes, how else are you gonna fly?
- Yeah, it's fantastic. - In space.
It's an extraordinary design that was showcased initially
in the '40s and 1949.
There's a replica that you can go and visit.
I've got a picture here at Deliso.
Do you want to sort of describe for the listener
what it looks like?
- It looks like a salon from Battlestar Galactica.
It's absolutely glorious.
- I don't.
The listener's perhaps, I think it looks like space shredder
from Ninja Turtles. - Okay, space shredder.
- But this is even younger than that, maybe.
- Okay, the helmet looks like a night's helmet,
and then the actual baggy suit.
It's a cross between a space suit and a washing machine.
- Yeah, yes.
And there's a glorious silver cape over the shoulder.
It's like a, it's a sort of steam punky,
but also the walking stick is very short.
- Yes, but because it's a practical walking stick.
Now here's the extraordinary thing.
If you saw a picture of this, you would think,
my God, this looks so ridiculous.
What were they doing?
Everything that was designed for this suit
was incredibly practical.
So to give the background of it very quickly,
this was designed by a group called
the British Interplanetary Society, the BIS.
It was founded in 1933 by Philip Cleeter in Liverpool,
and it is still to this day
the oldest existing organization voted
to the promotion of spaceflight.
So there's been older ones, but they're no longer around.
So this is the longest lasting.
- But it's an amazing sounding,
the British Interplanetary Society.
- It sounds insane, 'cause we're not used
to Britain being a major part of the spaceways.
As indeed, it turns out we were.
We may yet, we may yet, but this space suit was really fabulous.
So this suit has an airlock inside the chest.
So you can pick up a moon rock or whatever it might be,
pop it into the airlock, then inside your suit,
kind of take an arm out of the space suit,
reach in and open the airlock once it's pressurised correctly.
So then you've got it in whatever reason inside your suit.
- It's just such a cool idea.
- It sounds a bit awkward.
- It was a bit awkward, probably.
That did not make it to the space suit design,
but I think some of these elements were useful,
and they were established way before
most other space exploration outfits.
- They were thinking about how we do this
in a practical way.
- Well, that's what's so exciting about this.
Every single part of this suit dealt with
what was the hypothetical situation
of what you would have on the moon.
- On the moon.
- Yeah, so it was designed by two guys, Harry Ross and Ralph Smith.
And for example, the moon has very different temperatures
when it's dark and when it's light.
So either you design a day and night suit
that you can change into.
- Oh, lovely.
- Which is so British.
- Yeah, well, you need something for cocktail hours.
- Exactly, yeah.
- But what this suit is, what they went for is the all in one.
So the cape is not some silly British superhero.
- Yeah.
- What that was is to help with the temperature regulation.
- I actually think England just needs this
to start being reissued because on any particular day
we have all the weather.
(laughing)
- It needs to make a comeback.
- That's a great idea.
- Yes, yeah, exactly.
So Dileesa, you'll see here there's this sort of aerial
that's up here, that's for radio.
- Yeah, for radio.
- So that's how you could radio back to the ship
when you're on the moon.
- That's stunning.
- It's got like a 1.5 kilometer, I think, distance.
- It's brilliant.
- They were solving also, so they designed a lunar spaceship
as well in 1938 and they proposed a crew of three,
a multi-stage rocket.
Like lots of things that ended up happening in 1969.
- I think it's like a big what if, isn't it?
Of like, basically what happened is
they were gonna start doing experiments of rockets,
but there was a thing called the explosive sacked of 1875
that meant that private individuals were not allowed
to test rocket fuel.
And because that was in, they weren't allowed
to do their experiments.
But if the government had said, okay, you can do it.
There's every reason to suggest
that we could have gotten into space before anyone.
- Well, I mean, at least they had practical plans.
Zambia, which is a country next to Malawi,
they had a misguided attempt to join the space race.
Very bonkers guy, I'd have to find his name,
but he started training astronauts by putting them
in barrels and rolling them to get them used to be weightless.
And it was a really hilarious event
where he believed that Zambia could beat America
and Russia with this event.
- So we're talking 50s, 60s that this would have happened.
Wow.
- Yeah, and I should just quickly explain
that the walking stick, when I said it was practical,
is because if you were walking up mountainous bits
of the moon, if you were needing to sit down,
the suit's not very practical for it.
- So that is one of those, you turn into a sort of,
yeah, a little seat.
- Arthur C. Clarke was a member of this society.
- Yes.
- You know why we have capes and comic books,
like superheroes?
- Oh.
- 'Cause you don't need a cape to fly, do you?
- So it doesn't make sense at all, like you need wings.
- Yes.
- Basically, the reason is a comic book is just a drawing
and you need to show movements of someone flying
through the air, and what's the best way
of doing that, having something flapping?
- Something that flaps, doesn't make sense.
- Brilliant.
- Right.
- The first real space suits, like that were actually used
were the Soviet ones, I think.
So, CH1 or CH1, or CH1, I suppose it would be.
So this was used in the 1930s,
and it was 'cause they were going to very, very high altitudes.
So they weren't going into space per se,
but they were getting balloons really, really high.
And this suit, made by a guy called Chertovsky,
it had no hinges in the elbows or the knees,
and it was basically just, it was almost a barrel, really.
It was a barrel with a helmet on,
and you would just sort of open a door and walk inside it,
and you wouldn't be able to really move or do anything.
- Stole the idea from Zahambia, of course, isn't it?
- And then the first actual space suit,
so the ones that the Soviets used in space,
so what Gagarin might have used, for instance.
Oh, actually, this was a bit before him,
'cause it was a design.
It was known as the Scafander Cosmichesky,
which meant a diving suit for space.
And again, it was mostly to protect the space present,
it wasn't really that useful for doing stuff,
but one of the groups of people
who were really against the space suit
were the people who designed the spacecraft,
because they said that our spacecraft is so good,
that actually you don't need a space suit.
- Right, Gagarin will be absolutely fine.
- Risky, isn't it?
- And for anybody who wants to find out more
about what I mentioned, it was 1964.
Edward McCulloch was the one who formed the Zambian space program
and would train astronauts by rolling them.
- Wow, okay, gosh.
- Was it the Ferro Islands had a space suit?
I think it might still have a space agency,
but they expressly say we are not trying to get into space.
We're gonna maybe try and talk to some satellites
or they expressly say we are not trying to get to the moon,
we're not trying to get to Mars,
but it's useful to have this funding
because you never know what technology's gonna come from it
and stuff like that.
- Yeah, that makes sense.
The Smithsonian, you know, they're Washington-based.
Well, they're all over America.
They've got a lot of incredible collection.
- It's got a big space museum there.
- A huge space museum.
And in Maryland, they have a facility
which contains a space suit morgue.
There are a hundred...
- Field designs.
- Successful ones, actually.
- What a successful one.
- But just the spaces are not being used anymore.
And they have read a write-up of it which sounds so creepy.
- It's got 150 spaces in there.
They're all lying on bunks face up.
They all contain soft dummies.
- Oh, okay.
- So, I read about the...
- It should be the setting of some horror.
- It's fantastic.
- Absolutely.
And there's a woman who looks after them
or she did certainly 10 years ago.
She was called Amanda Young
and says she plays mummy to them.
And she says, you know, there's Neil and there.
- You know what?
- And you know what?
- And me.
Like last week, we had Nina Conzi on the show.
I don't know if you know any of that.
And, but she told us about, or actually down told us,
but she knew about this place where they had
all their old ventriloquist dummies.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Like, yes, someone has died.
- That's creepy.
- Yeah, but I think there's definitely something
where you go and visit all these
different really, really creepy places.
- Yeah.
- You're right.
- That should be it.
- Pitching it right now.
(laughing)
- The least such a ponders, creepy-ass places.
- Yeah?
- How'd you do it?
- Okay.
- 20%.
- Yeah.
- There are still developments happening
in space who, well, so right now,
something is being worked on, which is very sci-fi-based.
It's to solve the problem that, at the moment,
if you do a spacewalk, you wear what's called
a maximum absorbency garment, which is,
fancy we're saying, a nappy, it can take two liters
of urine, which is a lot.
- Wow.
- How much salt sinets and can it take?
(laughing)
- Well, of copies of the guleg I've felt like, yeah.
But it's really uncomfortable to wear one of those,
especially if you're out there all day working on something
on the outside of a space ship.
You know, so, and it can give you a rash.
It can leak.
Astronauts say that at a certain point,
they can no longer tell if it's urine or sweat
in their suits.
- Wow.
- Because it's really, it's so uncomfortable being out there.
It's a incredibly harsh environment.
- Not as glamorous as you think, is it?
- It's not as glamorous as you think.
And you weed loads in space,
because, well, the gravity difference means
that the fluid moves differently in your body,
and it's physically very demanding and you're sweating,
and we, and just, it's, oh, it's awful.
Okay.
Wait, though, they're working on a suit now,
which is going to be drinkable water
from urine in practically real time.
- Oh, okay.
- I would argue still not that glamorous.
(laughing)
- Your brain has to go around that hurdle.
- Oh, yeah, it does.
But this is basically like they have in dune.
You know, in dune, they have a still suit,
and it gives you, oh, sorry, good point.
They were, it's like in Battlestar Galactica.
No, okay, it's, it's a,
- That, yeah, is, if you make a suit,
which takes every bit of water
from your sweat, urine, everything,
and instantly turned into something that you drink.
- Yeah.
- So you can walk and be in the desert for a very long time,
or it needs to be. - Exactly, and this is,
they've now got it so that half a liter of urine
can become water in as little as five minutes.
So they add some, I would put a little bit of cardio in there,
at least. - I'd take like,
just to say the answer. - Yeah.
- And then you're like, that's white yellow.
(laughing)
- I'm excited.
- Yeah, that sounds very good.
Well, that was one of the,
just to bring it back to this original suit again,
it did everything.
It had extra mittens that you would put on.
They sort of everything.
The one thing they did not think of
was to add anything that dealt with feces or urine.
And so there was absolutely nothing
as part of the dis designed.
- I think in Britain, we don't need to worry about that.
That was kind of things.
(laughing)
- Yes, the due novels are very silent
on what happens to the feces in your still suits, really.
- Well, I mean, I'm sure someone will email
podcastacure.com. - You don't need that chapter.
No one needs that chapter.
No one was meeting, and I was like,
that's what's missing.
- I just amazed that he did any edits in a toll
when I look at those bugs.
- The other thing about spacesuits is they often don't fit.
- Right. - Because they have to make them,
and they don't necessarily, or certainly in the olden days,
they didn't make them for each person,
'cause you didn't know who was gonna do the trip.
So Neil Armstrong's spaceuit was made
for someone Neil Armstrong-ish.
- Yeah, this is why Vin Diesel never became
a successful astronaut.
- Sure. - You wanted to be one, did he?
- Oh no, I'm just saying.
- Oh no, it was a joke.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- This was like a little thing, we don't know.
Is he particularly differently shaped?
- He must be quite mussely, mustn't he?
- Is he.
- Yeah, I'm thinking of the rock.
- I meant to say the rock. - I think the rock, the rock would work.
- Vin Diesel's big as well, no, I'll jump in.
He's a muscular type.
- He's no the rock though, so he's a big-spector. - No, you're thinking of the space rock.
- Please. - (laughing)
- But this is really interesting,
that I think called the Jaggedness Principle.
And basically, if you take like, okay,
I gotta work out how big my head is, right?
Okay, it's this many inches, and my nose is this long,
and my shoulders are this big,
and my little fingers this big,
and my big toes this big.
When you put all those different things together,
no one is average, 'cause everyone's unique.
Okay, I've got you. - Yeah, exactly.
And so, they did a thing in the 1940s
where they were looking at the cockpits of pilots,
and they took 10 body measurements
from a population of 4,000 pilots,
and found that zero of them were in the average range,
but absolutely everything. - Wow, interesting.
- And so, some of them would have been like,
oh, this seats a little bit tight on my bun,
and then some of them were like,
"Oh, this cockpits a little bit low,
"I can't really feel anything here."
And that's something that you have to deal with all the time.
- Yeah. - That's interesting.
- Roll Dull writes about being a pilot of very elderly,
maybe biplanes, I think it was Gloucester Gladiator,
he was flying, and he was six foot four,
and you were meant to be about five foot 10 to fly these things,
and he just had, he was just like an accordion folded up
in the cockpit.
He just writes about being so uncomfortable in the cockpit.
- 'Cause what do you say about you Andy?
You've got a, is it a long torso or a...
- No, I keep my legs, my legs.
- You keep your legs. - You keep your legs.
- I tell these guys every week,
so they never listen, they never remember.
- This is what you have in common with the rock.
- Absolutely.
- He's too mussely for airplanes.
And you keep the height, where do you keep going?
- I keep my height in my legs.
- In your legs, so yeah.
- For some reason, he's not written back about my double-axe,
a buddy comedy idea, yeah.
- Muscley and legs.
- That's really strong, one guy's got big legs.
Not big legs, just long legs, really.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- What a crime-fighting team we would make.
(laughing)
- Don't even have you are listening,
please do get in touch.
- I need to lift up this car from this baby on the floor.
Oh, well, I need to step over that gate.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the last queen album
released while Freddie Mercury was alive,
was named after his favorite words to play at Scrabble.
- Amazing.
- Fantastic.
- Bohemian Rhapsody, no.
(laughing)
That wasn't an album, was it probably?
So I was looking for Scrabble facts
because Deliso, I read an interview where you say
that you rarely lose at Scrabble.
- I'm very good at Scrabble, I'm a Scrabble maniac.
- Yeah, I always play Scrabble.
- And even I was mentioning earlier that like
when I did Brune's Got Talent,
they were like, oh, you have African.
We should have a big African background for you,
you know what I mean, like, and we'll design like,
I was like, no, no, no, that's nothing to do
with my personality.
Scrabble, I literally have a Scrabble board
with my name on it as my background
because I'm such a stripper.
- And also in Scrabble, there's only one letter X,
so you can't get the three X's.
- Ah, very smart.
(laughing)
- Thank you.
- Oh, you're so rarely sad about this podcast,
really, so thank you.
- You've got talent, yeah.
- So I was looking for Scrabble facts,
and I found that Queen likes to play it
or likes to play it when they were on tour,
and also that the games used to get quite heated.
- They're not quite as rock and roll as you imagined,
you know what I mean?
- No.
- Backstage activity playing Scrabble,
even heated is very like.
- But you've got to do something after the co-came wears off
and after the orgy has wound down,
as you know, it's gotta buy the time.
- Yeah. - Absolutely.
(laughing)
- It's true, yeah, what's the orgy's of wound down?
- So I was reading a biography of Freddie Mercury
called A Kind of Magic by Mark Blake.
And in that, he said that Inuyendo
was one of Freddie's favorite words to use,
presumably 'cause it has lots of vowels in it.
- Yeah.
- And that was what gave me that.
- But I was like, I can't imagine it comes up a lot.
- Inuyendo?
- Oh, that's it, what?
(laughing)
- Well, no, actually, so before we came on out,
we were talking about our different Scrabble techniques,
but you said that you have a special rule for your Scrabble.
- Oh yes, when I play with my close friends,
if you put in a dirty word, any sexual word
or any word that can be used in a dirty context,
you get double points.
- Right, that's it.
- And so, but how do you have a dictionary of dirty words?
- No, no, no, you just have to explain
to the other person there's a dirty,
'cause most of them are nonsense, stuff like that.
But if you put in a word, which is debatable,
whether it's dirty, you have to use it in a sentence
to explain why it's actually dirty.
- Very good. - Yeah, it's nice.
- Do you guys know, as your Scrabble heads,
what you would get, numbers wise, points wise,
within your endo, if you didn't land on any triplet,
just those points, feel like it'd be quite low scoring,
'cause the vowels are low.
- I think the D must be worth two, is it?
- It isn't.
- It's gonna be one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine.
- Nine is correct.
Now, in your endo, isn't the only Scrabble word
that is a queen album that you can use?
- Oh.
- Because there's two other queen albums.
There's queen, they're self-titled first album.
- Now would be a lot of points.
- That is a lot of points.
- 14. - 15, 14.
- 14, but the one that's gonna get you most
is their album Jazz.
- Yes. - Oh, very nice.
- But you'd have to use a blank for that,
'cause it's only one Zed.
- Oh, is there?
- Interesting.
- So, but Jay is eight, is it?
- Well, yeah, that'll be what, 19?
- Pretty good.
- And it would be 29 if you can't as you say,
use the second one.
Now, interestingly, as well.
- Oh, also, actually, jazz mics have sexy people in them,
so it's double points.
- Double points.
- I don't know if that would work.
- Jizz would work, but Jazz, it wouldn't, it wouldn't be double points.
- Yeah, okay.
- It's very big.
- Here's another thing.
Here's another thing for a band that loves Scrabble.
Now, if the four of us were playing Scrabble right now,
not single one of us has a name that is a Scrabble word.
However, three of the four queen members were Scrabble words.
- Were they?
- Oh. - Freddie Mercury.
- Mercury. - Mercury.
- Mercury is a word.
- You've got Brian May.
- May. - May.
- May works, and then the bass player Deacon.
- Oh, yes.
- A Deacon. - A Deacon intro.
- Oh, in church, yeah.
- Down there's a word, the A.M.
This is Belton and martial arts.
- Oh, great.
- Is that a Japanese word?
- I think it's an addictionary.
- Okay.
- Unless you're the thing about Scrabble is actually,
in the official rules, it says before you start,
you have to decide what dictionary you're using.
- Yeah, right.
- So you can use any dictionary you want.
If you want, you can use green's dictionary of slime
to just have your words.
- Yes, yeah, Mike Schreiber would be in a German game
that Scrabble would be applicable.
- Yeah, in a British context.
- Yes, if we use your middle name.
- Yeah, that's right, yeah.
So anyway, Mercury is 14.
You've got Deacon at nine, and then you've got May at eight.
And then unfortunately, Taylor, who is Roger Taylor,
doesn't apply because it's not spelled.
And it's spelled with a line instead of an eye.
Unless you accept place names, in which case,
there is an American town called Taylor,
and then that could apply.
But again, it depends on your rules.
- There is an extra queen album
that you haven't mentioned, Dan.
- Oh, yeah.
- Freddie Mercury's Stamp album, which was another of his hobbies.
- Oh, he collected stamps.
- He collected stamps.
It was bought by the British Postal Museum in 1993.
- Really?
- Yeah, he was a big stamp collector.
As was John Lennon.
I mean.
- Wait a minute, isn't there a fact about them being on a stamp?
- Yes, there is.
- Like Brian May was the only living person.
- It's Roger Taylor, the drummer.
It is the only living person to appear on a stamp
because you have to be dead in order to be on a stamp.
So Freddie is in the front of it, and there's, yeah.
- Oh, no, no, no.
But when the queen was alive, wasn't she?
- Sorry, although the role of the role of the role of the role.
- Oh, I didn't know the role of the role of the role.
- Okay, sorry, yeah.
- Sorry, I've been pedantic.
- But yes, I see.
- So in a very vague, misty way,
you can see Roger Taylor in the back,
and so he's the only living person to make an auspicious stamp.
- They've loosened it a bit, haven't they?
They do special things.
- Oh, probably now, yeah. - Yeah, yeah.
- Nothing's like he used to be. - Cool.
- And. (laughs)
I read an interview with Martin Eiman,
who was the first British player
to ever win the World Scrabble Championships.
- Okay.
- He used to be the observer.
And he said that every week he hears
about some other celebrity who plays Scrabble.
So Robbie Williams, Sting, Christine Raghulera, Avril Lavigne.
And Martin Eiman said there should be a celebrity Scrabble.
So I'm thinking, the least outch upon this celebrity Scrabble.
- I would have. - Yes.
- I'm in, I'm in, but I'd want to play.
I'll tell you, this is the problem is
you get invited on all these shows
and you think you're there to play
and they just want you to do silly stuff.
And I'm like, I want to play.
I was invited on the countdown.
Now it's ready.
I've spent the whole week training myself
and getting better, that no, no, no,
we just want you on library corner.
And I was like, oh, let me play.
(laughs)
- Oh, that's a show.
- Nurtie Rockstars?
- All right, yeah.
- Once you get very famous,
let's say if you're a rock star,
you have a lot of money.
You're often out of a lot of space.
You have a lot of time because you're on,
you do one stage at an end.
- And also, because you've spent your childhood
in your bedroom on your own,
learning how to play guitar,
you're often quite nerdy.
I think, like quite a lot of the musicians
that I know, for instance,
are kind of on the nerdy side.
- Absolutely.
- Well, Bruce Dickinson of Iron Maiden,
who you're familiar with, James, you know, fences.
- I know he does.
- It's once ranked.
- And that's fences in the tent.
- But I isn't necessarily nerdy.
It's a weapon.
- No, and also Bruce likes to fence with a lightsaber.
- Okay.
- You know, that's nerdy.
That is really, and you're gonna get caught in the nerdy.
- You're gonna get caught in the nerdy.
- And then it was an epay, that's not it.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So there's four official swords that you can use
in modern fencing, and it's the epay,
the saber, foil, the foil, and the lightsaber.
- The lightsaber's now official.
- It's official, yeah.
And Bruce got one of the--
- I need to start watching this.
- Bruce got one of the first, like, official lightsabers
that you used to consist of.
- I watched Bruce's fuller side,
but I watched combat juggling.
If you ever have a chance to see this,
it's two jugglers facing off.
They have to constantly juggle,
but they can knock each other's bettiles out
with another batross, and they can distract.
It was amazing, and it's a whole big sport.
It was in like a, it was like in a high school arena
kind of thing, and I was just like,
this sports, you didn't even know it existed.
- Okay, what am I talking about here?
Rod Stewart's is enormous.
Neil Young has a special name for his.
Pete Waterman has displayed his in Chester Cathedral.
(laughs)
- And Jules Holland's stretches from London to Berlin.
- So serious.
- I think I know, because very famously.
- Yeah, they have enormous pieces.
- Is that all of them?
- Yeah.
- See, I know the first one I got it as well.
- Model Railway.
- Oh, Model Railway.
- Yes, yes.
- Wait, but how can you have a model railway
which stretches from one place to another?
- Well, the model is a model of the journey
from London to Berlin.
- Oh, the model of the journey.
- Yeah, but Pete Waterman who's the producer
behind Kylie Minogue and Rick Hasley.
- Steps.
Yeah, the Biggies.
Recently built a 20 meter model railway
for Chester Cathedral.
I just find it so he spends hours making fake trees.
He has a massive model of Lemmington Railway Station,
which is where he trains spotted as a boy.
I just think it's so charming.
- Yeah.
- I love it.
- Speaking of Pete Waterman, you just mentioned.
Do you know who is an absolute Scrabble Fiend?
- Oh.
- Kylie Minogue.
- Really?
- Yes.
- And this is according to Salman Rushdie.
- Who?
- I would love to see this game.
- Yeah.
- That's actually on page 16.
- Salman Rushdie is Kylie.
(laughing)
- On page 16 of Salman Rushdie versus he goes
into a game to Scrabble with Kylie.
- Yeah, she's fantastic.
- Apparently he plays Scrabble with her
or certainly did for a while.
He tweeted about it.
She wrote rematch as a reply to his tweet.
He used to hang with her apparently.
The room is that Salman Rushdie used to play
Twister with Kylie and Danny Minogue.
- Wow.
- But he said, "I never played it.
I would just watch as they play it."
- He said, "I should be so lucky."
(laughing)
- That is amazing.
- Good grief.
- Sorry.
- Yeah.
- What?
- So Kylie's obsessed with Scrabble.
- Fantastic.
- She plays Scrabble a lot.
- No, we were thinking of the other thing.
- Right.
- Yeah.
- Twister?
- I suppose you've got a while away
the long hours in hiding, huh?
- Yeah.
- I think it was in that period as well.
- During the fight, why?
- I believe it was.
I haven't--
- What a way to assess that Salman Rushdie.
- He should have been.
- Also, that's what he should have told them.
The people who had the fat on him.
This is what I'm doing right now.
- Yeah, yeah.
- No!
- But we've got to work out where Salman Rushdie is
because we want to assassinate him for the satanic verses.
- What's the least possible likely thing imaginable
he could be doing?
- Well, he could be playing Twister
with Kylie and Daddy Menok.
- No, no, no, no.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found online.
I'm on @Shriberland on Instagram, James.
- My Instagram is no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy.
- At Andrew Hunter M.
- Yep.
Deliso, are you online?
- Yes, I'm on everything.
I'm africancommedian.com.
And Deliso to palm down everything else.
- And you're on tour right now.
- I'm on tour.
I'm doing a show called Topical Storm.
The show changes every week
'cause it's updated with the headline.
- Fantastic.
- And so, yeah, so go to your website,
go to your Instagram and so on.
They'll be able to find the dates.
Where are your flat, it's all across the UK.
So go check it out now.
You can also write into us as a group.
Podcast@QI.com.
Send us all of your favorite facts that you've discovered
because we will cherry pick the best of those
and bring them to our Monday show, Little Fish,
where we get to read them all out.
Or if you send us just general feedback
about the show, interesting experiences you've had
and so on, those will be taken
to our behind the scenes show, drop us a line,
which is part of Club Fish.
Club Fish is a Patreon place
where you can do multiple different tiers.
There are lots of different rewards.
We have a quiz coming up for the highest tier.
Friend of the podcast, April 14th.
So join if you want to be part of that
and just check it out generally.
Otherwise, just come back here next week
'cause we are gonna be back with another episode.
Thank you as ever to our team, Leigh Engley
and Ethan Ruperelia, as well as the bigger Fishbuster crew.
And we'll see you again next week.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)