(phone ringing)
(upbeat music)
- Hi.
- Hi, Andy.
- Hey, buddy.
- Hey there.
- Oh, hello, Anna.
- What?
- Yeah, I've been on the podcast
for a couple of weeks now, guys,
and I'm surprised that you're all surprised.
- This is the first time you've been on Drop As A Line,
and I like to go into a different mind space
with Drop As A Line,
so this is like the first time I've seen you in months.
- Oh, right.
- Dangerous of this.
- In a different mind space.
I'm in the same mind space.
- James is in his own mind palace.
He's being very modest calling it a mind space.
He's actually a...
Damien is a mental yurt.
(all laughing)
- I'm a mind share.
It's like those wee workplaces.
(all laughing)
- Oh, well, welcome back, Anna.
And now let's go through a load of emails
that relate to shows that you didn't take part in.
- Brilliant, at least the complaints.
- You'll probably have thoughts.
- Well, maybe you can judge whether we were wrong or right.
- Oh, yeah.
- For the ones that--
- I would love to do that.
- You've had things like Spicy Meat Corner
and Get Yourself Off the Hook
and The I'm Actually of the Week.
- It's interesting, isn't it?
'Cause I sort of blank out everything that happens
in shows anyway after I've done them.
So, no, I wasn't.
- These are just format points that I've invented
that I've been having, frankly,
a pretty sticky time getting to take.
- I am.
Yeah, no, I wasn't here for any of those.
- Two of those I haven't even heard of
before, if that's how it is.
(all laughing)
- Okay, do you want a correction?
- Yes, please.
- All right.
Sally writes, big fan of the podcast,
but couldn't let this one go for a second episode.
Houston, Texas is pronounced Houston and not Houston.
- Who said it, Houston?
- Well, I always bring that up,
but presumably that's cut out
just because it's too, it comes up too much,
but Andy always says Houston,
and I always say, why are you saying it like that?
- Well, apparently I'm saying it right,
according to Sally.
- Oh, she's saying it's Houston, not Houston.
- No, she's saying it's Houston.
- Yeah, like everyone pronounces it.
- Houston, and I'm saying Houston.
- Yes.
- But her surname, she's called Sally Klaus,
and I actually don't know whether it's Sally Klaus
or Sally Klaus.
- Wow.
- Sally Klaus.
- I think we did keep in one mention
of Dan complaining about Andy's pronunciation of Houston,
and that might be why Sally's written in, perhaps.
I think it's been in once.
- I feel like I get an easier time on the pronunciation
because I pronounce quite a few things wrong, but I don't.
- You do, let's go through those.
How do you pronounce those small primates
that live on Madagascar with ring tails?
(laughing)
- They're zebras, aren't they?
- No, they're primates, Andy.
- Lima.
- Limia.
- Limia is what Andy used to say about that.
- I find you pronounce a lot of things oddly,
but I would never say wrong,
but maybe this is just the bias towards the male RP,
but I find you just have like quirky pronunciation.
What is it?
- Well, can I ask, Andy, if you're in America
and you're an early settler
and you're right at the edge of where settlement is,
but you're not quite there yet.
What would you say that edge is called, beginning with F-R?
- This is wild that you say this.
- Front it, front it.
(laughing)
Hey, hey, hey, let's press on and have another email, shall we?
- Davey Crockett, King of the Wild,
as Andy would say, Frontier, but it's Frontier.
- And you say Frontier, Frontier.
- No, he keeps saying Frontier.
I mean, it's not really incorrect.
- My dog's got three years.
A left ear, a right ear and a wild Frontier.
- Exactly.
- Right, I'll just, that's how I remember it.
Close to the home, we said right in
if you're from Martham in Norfolk.
- Oh, yes.
- Yes, I was there for that.
- You were there for this.
- Martha, mm.
- We had a lot of people right in who were not from Martham.
We had someone from Norwich, Katie Walters.
- Someone from Leeds.
(laughing)
- Holly Davis, who lived there as a teenager.
- Doesn't count.
- Katie Walters points out
that Martham has a thatch chip shop.
(laughing)
- That's really cool.
- It's like cool.
And that the car's dangerous, doesn't it?
- Yeah, you're right.
It must go up every year.
The carved village sign featuring a Viking
and a traditional Norfolk sailing wedding,
just kind of boat, was made by Harry Carter,
the nephew of the Egyptologist Howard Carter.
- Wow, interesting.
- However, he made over 200 signs,
so maybe that's not so interesting.
I think that is interesting.
- That is interesting.
- And Holly points out that Martha
and his point of West Flag,
which used to be an island when the Romans were here.
And then, really excitingly, we hit the jackpot,
Tilly Holland writes,
"Hello, my boyfriend has just played me a clip
"from no such thing as a captive willy episode."
Very excitedly, "I am from Martham."
Martham is a strange village, she writes.
Well, she goes into a lot of detail about it.
They've got some extraordinary stuff.
Three churches.
- Do you think on our next tour,
we could do a gig in Martham?
- Well, we could play one of the three churches
or one of the two co-ops.
- Or the chip shop.
(laughing)
They've also got a library and a kebab shop
and a Turkish barbers, which have the same owner.
My brother has been having a haircut
in which the barber has had to run back to the kebab shop.
(laughing)
- That's great.
- I imagine they cut your hair
with one of those huge knives
while you're rotating on your chair.
(laughing)
- And a library, did you say?
- I think that's a comma thing.
I don't think the Turkish chip shop,
a kebab shop owner also does a library.
- That would be confusing where you've got one job
where all you do is talk to the customer
and then you have a job.
(laughing)
- So don't silent.
Oh, that's really funny.
That's really good.
And she also says that Bradley Walsh's brother
reportedly lives in the village.
- Is that right?
- So one of the villagers must know.
- Well, in the past, Bradley Walsh has been spotted
at one of the annual fairs on Martham Green.
- I see.
- Huge.
- That's great.
- I bet that I used up the Martham Evening Mail
would have been headlined for a year, wouldn't it?
(laughing)
- My head chopped off my bum.
- And in the bottom, Bradley Walsh's seam.
- Oh dear.
All right.
Claudia Murdoch writes,
I recently listened to your episode, question mark.
And you mentioned the Wellington Shanty Club.
- Okay, so that, yes, that was me.
And that was when we had Lou Sanders on it.
It was our live show.
And I mentioned that the guy who did the sea shanty.
- Bingo.
- Yeah, or she mentioned, I think it was seasick.
- Well, you stated that this was the only Shanty Club
in Wellington.
And I just wanted to let you know
that this is actually incorrect.
- I couldn't listen to any more of the episode.
(laughing)
- There are two Shanty Clubs.
- Oh my God.
- The other one is called the Salty Wailers.
- Nice.
- Salty Wailers.
- That's great.
Huge apologies.
That's great.
- Imagine that.
Getting that wrong.
- Did you say, I shant be listening again?
(laughing)
- That was a missed opportunity by Claudia there.
Raise your game, Claudia.
(laughing)
- Here's a nice bonus ball from Anne from Canberra.
I was prompted to write after hearing David Mitchell's fact
about Steven and the white ship disaster
as there's a great link to one of your facts
in an earlier episode.
- Oh, lovely.
- This is cool.
A bit of like intra-episode tunneling.
- Yeah.
- Like this.
In episode 490, Andy spoke about wool
and its adsorbent quality, right?
Which is where it sort of has water within it
and it's not absorbing it, but it's kind of taking it on.
- Sounds like an Andy thing to talk about.
Wool being absorbent.
- Adsorbent.
- So not an Andy thing then, sorry.
(laughing)
- I was reminded of this when David Mitchell
was talking about the only survivor
of the white ship disaster, barrel the butcher.
There is a theory that the reason the butcher survived
was that unlike the other noble passengers
in their fancy silks, he was wearing coarse woollen clothing
which was water repellent and preserved heat even when wet,
which wool does.
So Andy was quite correct when he said
that if you fall in a river.
- Oh my God.
(laughing)
- This is all Andy is quite correct.
Every single email ends with that.
And he gave us one or two at the start,
just little fun ones and it was all leading up to this.
- We move on to the Andy is quite correct section.
- No one in real life would ever say
Andy was quite correct apart from you.
That's what gives it away.
- What was, what did you say that if you fell in?
- Oh, you didn't finish that sentence.
Sorry, if you fell in a river that's freezing cold
and then you get to dry land, you should be wearing wool
'cause it'll help you, it'll help you stay warm.
Okay, meat, lot of meat, meat judging in the inbox.
- Okay, so we had a fact about professional meat judging
in America that it's a thing you can do in college.
- Yeah, yeah.
Leah McConnell just writes to point out
the meat judging is pretty big in Australia as well.
- I think we mentioned that, yeah.
- I do be okay.
- My husband's grandfather was a meat judge,
meat, meat's there and meat judge.
- Wow, that's cool.
- Yeah, for any I've been on the show.
- And he's in, he would have been in Australia, so maybe.
- That's great, yes, Australia.
- Lisa Sackreiter is a high school agriculture teacher
and says they do lots of it
through the Future Farmers of America, the FFA,
along with poultry judging, livestock judging, dairy products,
dairy cattle judging, turf judging and others.
- Is that judging how anti-
- No, I don't think it's that, T-U-R-F.
(laughing)
- Oh my God.
- Oh dear.
Now, there's a serious message about the meat stuff
which is from Ben Lidgate.
I've been listening to your most recent episode
in which Dan talks about retro-clat.
- Oh yes, yes.
- So this is backwards talking for Butchers.
- Yeah, he said it is Butchers Talk Convention
in Australia in the 1960s and it angered me so much
that I felt compelled to write in for the first time ever,
despite having listened to you guys
since your very first episode.
- Thanks for listening.
- You can also thank Dan, as it also finally inspired me
to join Club Fish in the hope that I might hear this email
read out for some great, what a great idea.
So, just putting a few little mistakes every episode.
- New business model, it just pissed people off.
- Wow.
- Why do you think I've been saying it Houston all these years?
- Is this why people like Piers Morgan exist?
So they all got spin-off podcasts
where you're allowed to write and then complain.
They pissed people off solely to get subscribers.
- So should I tell you what Ben says in his,
why he's so angry?
He says, "I'm a fifth generation butcher."
- Wow.
- "Fifth gen."
And the reason that this fact, heavy quotes,
angered me so much is that Butchers Backslank
has been in use in Britain
since at least the early 19th century.
Not only was it not invented in Australia,
I'd be very surprised if they only started using it
in Australia in the '60s,
as it more than likely came over
with British settlers earlier than that,
unless it came over with the 10-pound poms in the '50s.
But even then, he's about 10 years out.
So really thorough demolition problems.
- Who's this person?
- Ben Lidgate.
- Okay, Ben, I think what we should actually do
is discuss this on the next episode,
which goes out next month.
So if you want to hear any more about this,
then make sure you keep subscribing for another month.
- I love it.
It's so weird, because effectively,
he was so furious with what I said that he had to write in.
Yet, it's such a great email that I just can't be upset.
- It's nice.
- It's really nice.
I love these letters.
- There you go.
- Yeah, thank you, Ben.
You weren't like this one.
Raquel Moss writes, "Dear fish."
Raquel Moss, yeah, made up.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- I'd like to just ask about Addy's novels.
It's been a few months since you've mentioned them.
- She writes to say, "Just checking in to confirm that yes,
Dan does give off big wife guy energy."
(laughing)
- Come on, come on, Moss.
- It is a black and white.
As does James, which is completely understandable,
because his wife seems rad.
A helicopter pilot.
- Wow.
- Wait, wait, I'm going.
Not that Dan's wife isn't rad.
- I'm sure she is.
I just don't know the details of her radness.
- Dan, do you want to tell us how rad Phen is?
- She sucks.
I hate it, I hate wives.
- Classic bro.
- I hate wives.
Raquel says, "Andy, you're a bit more of an enigma,
but I'm sure you're quietly a wife guy in your own way."
- I'm not.
(laughing)
- All right, so thank you, Raquel.
I'm going to sort of do like a--
- By the way, just to say,
we got a bit of husband girl energy
off Anna a few minutes earlier with the,
my husband's granddad was a meat judge.
- No, I didn't really do enough.
38 husbands, me and Joe Brandt,
not a good word to say about husbands between us
to know what you're talking about.
- You're never normally mentioned that you're married.
- No, that was made up that fact a minute ago.
I had a fictional husband.
I just really wanted to have something to say
about meat judging.
- Anna knows that it's only one butcher
who listens to this show
and a bunch of pseudonyms that you've created.
(laughing)
- I've been single-handedly maintaining
our ad revenue, Dan, don't.
(laughing)
- It's exhausting running a million salt puppets
every week.
- Oh my God.
- Have you had to actually subscribe
for every one of these salt puppets?
- I'm spending 90 grand a month
(laughing)
on Clownfish alone.
It's exhausting.
- Well, he should not get any adverts.
(laughing)
- Grace Jist writes.
- Just give us the general, you know,
(laughing)
you don't need to read the whole thing down there.
- Sorry, we're back to meat actually.
'Cause her email is head subject lined all caps.
Meat judging isn't a sport.
She says, you'll almost killed me
with embarrassment and laughter
on my drive to work this morning.
Meat judging isn't a sport,
but a competition for kids in FFA,
Future Farmers of America,
or 4-H who are interested in livestock farming.
Never did it myself,
but I did do a bit of other livestock judging as a kid.
It never gets old listening to a handful of Brits
try to understand American things.
- Well, that's interesting.
- Keep doing it like the idiots we are then.
- I would say it is a sport.
- They do it in college.
- Yeah.
- It doesn't sound like a sport to me.
I think sport has to have some physical exertion.
- Chess is a sport?
- No, it's not.
- Yes, chess is a sport.
- I would say that's what makes chess not a sport.
- Yeah, but Anna, what makes you an expert on sport?
- Oh, James, I'm so glad you've asked.
Well, I happened to have written a book recently
with my good friend and colleague, James Harkin,
called "Everything to Play For".
It's the QI book of sport.
- Excellent.
- And chess doesn't feature.
(laughing)
- What if the pieces are so heavy
that it is physical exertion to lift them?
Is that then a sport?
- Yeah, maybe chess is a sport for you.
- Chess boxing.
- Yeah.
We've, Caroline from Svalbard has written.
- No.
- Yes.
- Very interested in that.
- It is so cool.
We can get emails from all over the world, it's lovely.
- I think we have one from,
I can't remember where the other was,
somewhere equally far from here.
Anyway, cut that.
- Leads.
(laughing)
- It's from Leads.
- It's far away, you have the long year,
by and where you're not allowed to die,
- Well.
- Currently, 'cause it's too cold.
- You've fallen right into my trap,
you little fool.
(laughing)
- Caroline writes.
- Subject line, episode 11.
(laughing)
- I live in Longyear Bayen.
- In Svalbard, and I was listening to old episodes
while out training my dog team.
- Oh God, you're cool.
- So a very long overdue correction
and some related info on door handles and bears in Svalbard.
Number one, it is not illegal to die here,
but you cannot be buried here.
Not because you freeze,
but because the permafrost in most cases
will bring you back up.
- Yeah.
- I think that's what we've said, isn't it?
- Well, maybe.
Maybe we said that in episode 12.
(laughing)
You can get cremated and bury your ashes here.
- All right, number two, doorknobs.
I own a cabin outside town,
and like in many cabins here,
the door opens inwards and the handle upwards.
The first is to prevent you from snowing in,
and the second to make it more difficult
for bears to get in.
However, the bears do not always use the handle.
Again, see picture.
And the picture is just of a door
with a huge panel missing where.
- Oh wow.
- The bear has just gone in.
- Wow.
- Yeah, anyway, Caroline, Caroline,
thank you so much for writing.
- That's awesome.
- Love that about the handles going up.
- I'm excited.
- I know.
- David Crundwell writes.
- Good name.
- Great name.
I'm a huge fan of the show,
and as of this week,
also a proud card-carrying clubfish member.
- Yeah.
- This isn't a correction,
but I thought it may be of some interest
that the opposite of the word February,
as discussed in episode 502,
is in fact the word February.
- Oh.
- As the opposite of the song Wonderwall
is also the song Wonderwall.
As James correctly mentioned,
active noise cancelling in headphones
works by receiving an audio signal,
inverting the phase of this signal,
a pattern of compressions and decompressions
in air pressure over time,
playing the inverted signal into the speakers,
cancelling out those compressions and decompressions.
So Dave actually attached a file
of him saying the word February,
duplicated it,
inverted the phrase,
played them one over the other,
and the result is silence.
And I watched the video of him doing it,
and it sounds like this.
- That was a really good impression.
- It was really good.
(laughing)
- So Dave actually did the work,
and I'd just like to thank him.
I'd also like to thank Riffles,
who claimed to have sent the sound
and just sent the file that was called
"Five Seconds of Silence".
- Oh, that's clever.
- The effect was the same in both cases.
- Yeah, and Swifties will know
that Taylor Swift made it to the top of the charts
with basically a silent track.
- Ah.
- Oh wow.
- It was an accidental release,
and it was just basically, effectively--
- That sounds rude, doesn't it?
- Sounds like a fart.
(laughing)
- Kind of an accidental release.
But it was silent at least.
(laughing)
- But it was also deadly, so--
- That is what you would call a Swiftie as well.
(laughing)
- Yeah, I think it was either it had white noise
or it was something basically that was a non-track in it,
and it went to the top of the charts
because it was attached to the name.
- You can do a lot of interpretation work on that.
What does she mean?
- Yeah, exactly.
- Yeah.
- Brilliant.
The Incess Zone we're entering now,
which we've been in for a couple of months
on Drops of the Line, Anna, sorry.
This is about Iceland and the Incess app, you remember?
- Oh yeah.
- And we mentioned it,
and some were going to say, "No, that's not true."
- Well, it's not true that there's the app.
- No, we don't have an app that we check our dates
for Incess Tone.
ElsaAntons.io writes, "I'm writing regarding an email
"you read out on Drops of the Line,
"where a fellow Icelander,"
I think the name was Asgurthur,
but struggled to understand the pronunciation,
which is devastating 'cause I asked an Icelander
and I practiced.
- Yeah, we praised you.
- Yeah, okay.
Said, "The genealogy website was not a dating app.
"It is true that it is not intended as a dating app,
"but it is still used for the purpose Lusanda said,
"I have on multiple occasions used it
"to check my Tinder matches
"to see how closely we're related we are."
- Oh, interesting.
- This is huge.
- That's huge, so.
- So the way I understood it is
that they had this genealogy website,
and then they had a competition
to see who could find the best way
of utilizing this data,
and then one person came up with the idea
of doing the dating app where you bump two phones together
and it will tell you if you're related,
and it was kind of a joke,
and if a load of people downloaded it kind of as a joke,
but it was never really a proper, proper thing.
But this actually goes against that evidence, doesn't it?
This is actual anecdotal evidence of people using it.
- Well, no, that could be true as well, right?
Your thing is true, the joke thing,
but then this person's actually used it, not as a joke.
- So thank you, Elsa, vindicated.
- Love it.
- Yeah, so we'll say that in every episode from now on.
That happens.
Okay, Aaron Hung writes,
"In episode 498, you, Dan, James, and Hannah Fry
"had an interesting conversation about conversation.
"There is, in fact, a whole field of study
"called conversation analysis,
"which focus on the rigorous, in-depth study
"of mundane, everyday conversation,
"trying to tease out rules that people follow
"when talking."
So, for example, since you discussed ending conversations,
there's a chapter attached here on that very topic.
He's said a chapter.
"The too-long-didn't-read version
"is that a conversation usually closes
"after a series of steps or pre-closing sequences
"that signal a wind down to the conversation.
"This is arguably why you're abrupt by,
"at the end of your drop as a line, is so amusing."
(all laughing)
- Has it subversed those rules?
Has it subversed those rules?
That's why it's so amusing, guys.
- So, we've gone away from,
"Andy, this is why you're right,"
to now, "Andy, this is why you're so funny."
- We're gonna move on to,
"Andy, this is why you're so attractive,"
in a minute.
(all laughing)
- Fearless Bueller writes,
"I was so excited this morning to hear you talk
"about one of my true loves, Roller Derby."
Derby?
- Derby.
"I was so disappointed to hear you not mention
"the creative genius of one of the all-time
"best names that Derby has brought to the world.
"Twat Rocket has been on my list of favorites
"since I saw her skate years ago
"and heard the crowd chant her name
"to the sing-song tune of the hot-pocket commercials
"that haunted my childhood."
- I don't know that commercial.
- Me neither.
I thought, I found the name in my research,
"Twat Rocket," which I thought it was,
but it turns out it's an American skater,
she's called "Twat Rocket,"
'cause that's how they pronounce "Twat."
- Is this why on Twitter,
the other day, you asked a lot of Americans
how you pronounce--
- "Twat."
- Do you pronounce the word "Twat," "Twat?"
- Yeah.
- Or "Twat," and people just replied to you,
just saying, "Twat, twat, twat, twat."
- And it's so nice that finally there was a reason
for them to reply to my tweet saying that.
Yeah, but apparently, the hot-pocket,
do you know the hot-pocket?
- I guess, I think it's a pop-tart, isn't it?
- Yeah, pop-tart, right?
- Did you, can I ask?
Did you look onto YouTube to see
what the hot-pocket advert was?
- I did watch it, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Could you sing it?
Can you sing it?
- Like, we wanna hear it, basically.
- Oh, no, I couldn't do it justice.
- So we get an idea of what "Twat Rocket" would sound like.
- Hot-pocket.
- "Twat Rocket."
- Yeah, it's good.
So, that's Fearless Bueller, thank you for that.
All right, and last one.
- Yes.
- Holly Gittins writes.
- Yeah.
- She writes in very kind words,
and then she says, "I wanted to say how refreshing
"I was recently to hear an episode of Drop As A Line
"recorded early in the day.
"I often listened to the podcast
"while driving to work, still slightly bleary.
"I hope not too bleary to drive a car.
"It's a great way of waking up in the morning,
"but it was a lovely change to hear Dan and James
"feeling as irritable and generally confused
"as I often do by the first few minutes."
- I actually think our morning ones
are some of our best work on Drop As A Line.
Have any of you ever had this?
When I used to work in a nice five job,
and I used to drive in the rush hour every morning,
sometimes I'd be at my desk at like 10 o'clock,
and not remember how I got there.
- Oh, you're an autopilot.
- You're an autopilot the whole way,
and you're like, "Oh, last thing I knew I was in bed,
"and now I'm here, how did that happen?"
- Yeah, that's a bit freaky.
I think I have had that sometimes.
It's when you're driving very boring routes.
- Yeah, it's the same route all the time,
and it's car to car to car,
and you're doing it for 45 minutes or an hour.
So it's just to say, you don't do anything,
you're just like behind a car.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Get the radio on, mate.
- So Holly has a query, she asks,
"Have you considered a rolling schedule of recording times?
"A late night post-pub recording,
"live audio of you all waking up at 2 a.m.
"to record for no good reason,
"or even recording immediately after a 40-hour flight
"would all be greatly entertaining?"
- We did a podcast the night after a British election,
can't remember which one,
where we did it on the morning of.
I remember my fact or something to do with the Yeti party.
That's all I--
- I think it was 2017, I think it was election special.
- Yeah.
- So there was a big--
- We got in early so that James could edit it,
presumably that day, so he could get out that night.
The one we recorded, we basically recorded a podcast
at every single hour of the day,
'cause we've done the Comic Relief special
where we recorded for 24 hours, right?
So we've just ticked your box.
- Yes.
- So yeah, this was, Holly was it.
- Holly, yeah.
- So Holly can just listen back to the 24 hours,
all on YouTube.
- Yeah.
- And then you can compare how we were
all those different times.
- I was pretty tired by the end of the Comic Relief thing.
- I remember I was as well,
but I remember Anna and Dan really carrying
the last two hours, that's my memory of it.
- We're morning people.
- I can't remember.
- We had like a three minute break
in between each 35 minute recording.
And I remember I had my routine so down by the end.
I'd like, run, put a kettle on, have a pee.
Pour cattle into, I'd tell us more of it.
(laughing)
- On topedus.
Pour cattle, pour you more of it.
On topedus, wake up, scream.
(laughing)
Have straps on the throat, I'll just scream.
Yeah.
- I was stressed up.
I didn't get those breaks
'cause I had to do the ads in between.
I had to sit there and--
- You did ads?
- Yeah, yeah.
- What are you advertising?
- I was just a little side bunny.
- Side bunny?
- Side bunny.
- Bye bye you book, the theory of everything else.
My dad's tribe are available in all good bookshops.
- Are you a Desert Rogers child
in a poor corner of the world?
You need some entertaining.
(laughing)
- Hey, really quickly, just,
you know how sometimes people recognize us
by our voice on the street?
'Cause, you know, not many people know what our faces are,
but they will hear our accents and sometimes get it.
And Andy, you said that this guy actually wrote in
off the back of this incident.
But I was in South London with Jamie
from my dad wrote a porno.
And we were walking down the street
and I was telling Jamie about the fact
that's gonna be on the episode
that we just recorded about Senna.
And so I went, I literally said the words to him.
Yeah, so my fact this week is that in 1984,
and this guy just turned around
and went, Dan, no such thing.
And as a kind of like, 'cause I've walked past podcasters
and had a bit of sort of like,
whoa, that's pretty exciting.
To hear a podcaster use literally the words
that you hear in an episode.
- Are you sure you're not everyday?
You sort of pay Jamie to take you out
and you just spend all day walking around going,
my fact this week, is there anyone,
can you see anyone looking around Jamie?
No, okay.
- Let me do that a bit.
This one was accidental.
- Yeah, very funny.
And then we got Neema from that block.
- Yeah.
- Oh, really?
- But apparently not worthy for the show.
No.
(laughing)
- 'Cause it was saying how nice Dan is.
- I actually have a filter set up for those emails.
(laughing)
- Bye.
(upbeat music)
- That does work.
- Wow.
- I can see it now.
- It's really funny.
- I've subverted the norms of conversation
with that abrupt ending.
But I now spoil the joke by saying,
thank you for listening.
And we will be available.
We're in the inbox.
We're waiting for you.
We're in there.
So get in with us by emailing podcast@qi.com.
And we love hearing from you.
And bye.
(upbeat music)