[ inaudible ]
Hello, and welcome to another episode of "No Such Thing as a Fish"
a weekly podcast this week coming to you from the Northwall Art Center in Oxford.
My name is Dan Schreiber, and please welcome to stage Andy Murray Anichesinski and James Harkin.
[ Cheers and applause ]
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favourite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go. Starting with you, Chuzinski.
Yep, my fact this week is that the world's only Cornish Pasty Museum is in Mexico.
[ Laughter ]
These planning permission things are cool. So why and when did it go up?
Well, so this is because there's actually a significant like Cornish diaspora in Mexico,
because Mexico needed miners in the early 19th century, a bunch of Cornish men emigrated out there,
and they brought their pasties with them, and pasties have been a delicacy in Mexico,
and it's particularly in these two areas. It's in the municipality of Real Del Monte,
and yeah, and a place called Pachuca. Pachusa. I don't know. Is there any Mexicans in here who
are going to correct me on that? No, cool. But yeah, it's 4,500 miles away from Cornwall,
and it is a Cornish Pasty Museum. It was set off about five years ago.
What's in a Cornish Pasty Museum? I feel like the clue is in the title.
Some medieval helmets and a viking ship. It's actually miss me.
I mean, once you've seen a Cornish Pasty, I'm Andy.
You have not seen a Cornish Pasty.
Yeah, it seems like it's partly a culinary school disguises a museum.
There's a pasty-making lessons, and in fact, so recent, I think, in 2014,
a team of Mexican bakers took a trip to Cornwall so they could pick up some new tips
about how to make pasties, specifically the art of crimping, which is, you know,
getting that little handhold bit on the side, right? There is actually going to be a Cornish Pasty
Museum in the UK soon. Where will it be? Orkney?
No, this is a guy called Malcolm Ball. He's hoping to open what he's calling a planet Hollywood
with a Cornish Pasty twist. And he said he started to research whether there's any visitor
attractions in the UK focusing on the Cornish Pasty, and that was absolutely staggered
to find out that there wasn't a single one.
Is the twist on the planet Hollywood thing that it's got no celebrities, no memorabilia,
and is just Cornish Pasty? There's going to be memorabilia, but it'll be pasty memorabilia.
Pasties. Yeah, yeah. So if anyone listens to this in a year, I wanted to say, please don't
write in and say my fact was wrong. It just will be wrong in about six months' time because
there is going to be a second pasty museum. But, yeah, the Cornish had a really big influence
in Mexico. So they also imported football in the 1890s, I think it was about, set up the first
football team in Mexico. And in fact, FIFA's only football hall of fame is now in Patroosa,
in that little town in Mexico. Wow. Yeah. I was looking into the history of Cornish Pasties.
And in the early days, both husband and wife would initial the husband's name onto the end of
the Cornish Pasty so that they knew it was their lunchbox effectively. So you could go, that's my
Cornish Pasty. Look, Darren is written on it. And then also to test whether a good Cornish Pasty
is good as it can be, is that they would drop it down a mine and if it survives, then they're like,
that's a damn good Cornish Pasty. They dropped it down a mine. They didn't drop it down a mine.
So are the internet. People do say that. That also implies that a good way to test for a good
Cornish Pasty is try and bite into it. And if you can't, then it probably is good. The fact of
dropping a Cornish Pasty down a mine is much greater than biting it. So if it does survive, then it's
inedible. Yeah. I read the other day that it's impossible to tell if an apple is ripe without biting
into it. But I'm not sure anyone's ever thought of putting it down a mine. Yeah, just drop it down a
mine. Yeah. The thing with the, with the initials on the Pasty, what they used to do is they used to
hold it kind of, kind of upright and they would keep the initial at the bottom and then we'd eat
it from the top. And so you would always kind of have the initial at the bottom for the whole thing.
And then once you got down to the bottom with the initial, you would throw it away. And you'd throw
it for what they called the mining gremlins. Oh, they called them knockers. Did they? Yes. They were the
sort of little people in the mines who, if they, you gave them a bit of food, they wouldn't give you
bad luck. You also, some people say that they didn't eat the, the reason they have that handled
bit, the crimped handled bit was to hold on to. And that was discarded at the end because so Corn
was the, it had the largest tin mining, but it also had the largest arsenic mining. There's a lot
of arsenic down there. And so these miners hands were covered in arsenic, which they didn't want to eat.
So I think they chucked away the bit they held on to. Mind for arsenic. Yeah, apparently Corn was one
of the country's biggest providers of arsenic. Do you not get your arsenic supplies from Cornwall?
We, I do, obviously, I do. And also they're throwing the food down into the arsenic mines before
they eat it. Yeah. Just pick it up, three-second rule, brush off the arsenic. They'd have a different
second rule. It takes a long time to get there. Right. You know the chant that goes oggy, oggy,
oggy, oggy, oggy, oggy. Yeah, there you go, but not in that tone of voice in like a different tone
of voice. So that chant is thought to come from the Cornish word for pasty, which is hoggan or
hoggan, and it's thought, and this again is probably just missed. It's been passed down the generations,
but at lunchtime the wives would come to the top of the mines and they'd shout out oggy, oggy, oggy,
and the miners downstairs would go, oh, oh, oh, oh, and they'd be like, all right, he wants it.
And then you do the drop test. And then you drop them. Countless miners were killed by their
rock hard pasties. Goals of death, lunch, lunch, lunch.
I read a dictionary of slang from 1811, the gross dictionary of slang, and the only thing for pasties
that I could find is that to deliver a flying pasty meant to take a poo, wrap it in paper, and throw
it over a neighbor's wall. You didn't get that from a dictionary. I was going to mention I
thought it would be a bit to like just juvenile to do, but since you bring it up, I read a story about,
it was about a someone's housemate who got evicted from the house because they found them eating a
pasty full of poo. And they said, yeah, so here's the thing, he wasn't feeding it to anyone else.
He was just mining his own business, having a pasty on his own in the kitchen, and then they said,
we don't want someone eating poo. He said he wasn't feeding it to anyone, but she did make the good
point and she didn't want to use the oven afterwards, which I think is totally fair. Something else that's
disgusting that goes into college pasties. They used to put jam at the bottom and meat at the top,
didn't they? And so that was so that you could have a full meal, you'd have your first boss there,
and you're putting at the end. But there must have been a bit in between that was kind of jammy meat.
That was sorbet. Yeah, it's a nice palette cleanser for the gourmet miner.
We're going to have to move on to the next bag. Soonish, if you guys have anything else?
Okay, can I just say a thing about museums? I found this thing the other day. Apparently in 1846,
a snail arrived at the British Museum. As I read that, and they said, you're late, where are you being?
Yeah, someone sent a snail into the British Museum, and it was stuck onto a piece of cardboard,
and then they noticed four years later that the card was slightly discolored. They put it all into
some warm water, and it turned out that the snail wasn't dead, and it woke up, and it became really
famous, and it was like the most famous snail in Britain in 1850. That's not a composition in that year,
1850. 1850, that was. It was so famous, it was painted by John William Waterhouse. What kind of?
I just like that that there was a most famous snail in Britain, and Waterhouse I like as well,
because he painted pre-Raphaelite style, but like decades after everyone's lights. He didn't really
want to do it anymore, so he was like a post-pre-Raphaelite. I think they just call them "Raphaelites."
Have we got any more on this? I think a good thing to look into if you fancy or researching more about
Cornish pasties is the British newspaper archive, where I was reading up on other 19th century pasties
stories, and there were a couple of good ones, so one of them was a travel writer in the Leeds Times in
1861, a visited Cornwall, and said of the pasties, "The name is generally applicable to anything that by
any stretch of the culinary imagination could be conceived as existing under a crust."
So he wasn't a fan, and in 1889 two Cornish miners got trapped in a mine, so they were stuck underground,
and all they had to eat was four pasties that their wives had given them before. They got
trapped underground. They were trapped underground for four and a half days, and they didn't even
finish the pasties, because they were unfit to eat apparently, so yeah. This one's been in
the ground for four seconds because of the Leeds. Okay, I'm going to move us on to our next fact,
and that is James Harkin. Okay, my fact this week is that 20% of people wake up wearing fewer
clothes than they went to bed with. Do we know who's removing them? Do we know who's taking them on?
We don't know. Well, we think probably them. Okay. All the clothes fairy. Well, there is one theory
that if you wake, if you go to bed wearing pajamas and you wake up not wearing them, you've been
abducted by aliens. There's a website called Abduct Anon, and it says, "How to tell if you've been
abducted by aliens?" And that's one of them. If you enter bed wearing pajamas and you woke up
nude, that's one of them. The other one is electronic appliances behave strangely when you pass by.
Another one is you have an uncontrollable urge to take vitamins. Don't really understand that one.
Three out of three so far. And the other one, I really like this, the scene of your
abduction has been staged to look as if nothing happened. So if you ever wake up in the morning
and everything looks exactly the same, it's aliens I'm afraid. I was really that when aliens do
abduct humans, I don't believe it, by the way, but when they when they say they adopt them, the abductees
say that when they get up there, the aliens do some probes and they often have to do it in a sort of
slightly inappropriate kind of sexual manner, they try and transform their bodies so that they look
as if they're comfortable sights to you. So it just feels like, "Oh, this is this is quite a nice
scene." And the list of things that they dress up as body-wise is the Pope. That's the thing that's
most likely to put something up your ass. The other is a deceased relative and that's what they say
will make you feel like, "Well, this is a pleasant experience." I do this. I do this. I do what they say.
I'm drawing this. I can't bring it back to the conversation before. I wake up sometimes not
wearing, if I have socks on, when I go to sleep, I wake up not wearing the socks. Yeah, um, 13. I'm so
uncomfortable telling you that as well. I feel like you've all been left in now. You're not wearing
the sock on your penis, are you? Look, my room is drafty and cold. And I'm a real man, I don't
wear pajamas. Oh, god. Do you actually wake up with no socks? Yeah. Thank you. What did you say?
I've got a friend and supporter in tonight. So anyway, so this was a, it was a survey by a memory foam
mattress company called Ergo Flex. And they said that socks are the most commonly removed item
with 31% of people who remove things saying that they don't keep them on at night. So you're in,
you know, a good company. One of the other things I found is that the average length of time
men wear pajamas before washing them is 13 nights. And women, it's 17 nights.
Whereas we all know the correct answer is you're in for one night and then you incinerate them.
And you buy a new pen. So when you say you're a real man, you don't wear pajamas.
Are we so glossed over that? I think whether that's a thing because there was a survey done
into who wears pajamas and who doesn't and far, far fewer men wear pajamas than women.
So I think it was something like 13% of men wear pajamas and about 30% of women do. So is this
something in the male community that sort of is emasculating? I think it's thought of as being not
the act of a room and where I've got six pairs of soap operas, I'm fine. One sock. In the survey
they did, people were asked what they wore in bed and one percent of people said they had no opinion.
The aliens look after that stuff to be honest with you.
The idea of doing things while you're asleep is called parasomnia. And there have been examples
of people doing various things. Texting while asleep, eating while asleep is a bad one because
you can put on a lot of weight. Driving cars while asleep, there's one or two people who've done that.
And there was one sleep doctor who described how he treated someone who dismantled
grandfather clocks while asleep. There's, you know, you used to be able to text in their sleep.
Yeah. There was a, the first example of someone using the internet while asleep was in 2008.
And this was a 44-year-old woman who in her, in her sleep, she got out of bed, she went over to her
computer, she logged in and she fired off three emails. One of which read, "Come tomorrow and
sort this hellhole out. Dinner and drinks 4pm. Bring wine and caviar only."
Awesome dream, was she?
There's a really cool thing as well that they've noticed in recent times when they've been doing
studies that anyone playing video games and so younger children and really cool awesome adults.
They have ability, they say, in their dream to suddenly take charge and control the dream
as if they were playing called duty or something like that. So they don't have nightmares because
nightmares for them are a challenge where they can then slaughter dragons and sort out, I don't know.
Yeah, it's called lucid dreaming, right? Yeah. The idea is that you keep looking at your watch
during the day and then you start dreaming that you're looking at your watch and you realise that
it's not moving and then you can realise you're in a dream, as soon as you realise you're in a dream,
then you can start doing things in there. And there are quite a few people who can do it.
I've done it a couple of times, but only a couple of times my whole life I can remember having a lucid dream.
Wow. It's really cool. Yeah, I bet. I just fly. Just a quick thing on pajamas.
I was looking for information on astronaut pajamas, what they were in space, whether they were
wear pajamas, whether they take them. And so I googled do astronauts immediately type in wear
pajamas. And the first thing that came up is do astronauts masturbate in space? So I clicked
on that instead. There's a website called Quora where people write their own answers to questions,
people post up. And there was an article on Quora which gave an answer and I just wanted to read it out.
This is the answer on Quora. This is at least the tenth time I've answered a question about sex,
masturbation, or romance in space. Please search before posting. And it goes on, it gives the answer.
He says, "Yes, each astronaut has a private sleeping area." No, there isn't a space just for masturbation.
No, the guy's a NASA would have built that into a station.
Well, we've got the sleeping quarters, the masturbatorium.
Sorry.
There was an article in the Daily Mail which said, "I should have really looked into whether this
could possibly be right." But it said it had interviewed an independent sleep expert who said that
"Resist the temptation to strip off at nights when you're hot and muggy. It's actually cooler if
you wear pajamas because the pajama fabric draws sweat away from your body and will make you feel a
lot cooler and more comfortable." So, doesn't that imply that whenever you're too hot, you should put more
clothes on? Can that be true? I don't know. It doesn't sound very true, does it? It really doesn't.
Speaking of things that happen while you were asleep, a 64-year-old man has told how he passed out
after a heavy night's drinking and woke up to find that his penis was missing. Neighbours of
Gerardo Ramos claimed that he was attacked by a dog as he stumbled around the Dominican Republic
naked while drunk. He has decided to stop drinking. Sounds like a good decision.
It sounds like a bit of a stable door and horse-bolted decision to be honest.
We're going to have to move on very soon. Okay. In China, people were pajamas quite a lot. In
their evenings, people will just go out wearing pajamas. In 2010, they had pajama police in Shanghai
to stop people from wearing pajamas because there was an expo in town and they didn't want people to
think that they were sluvinely or whatever. So, they tried to stop anyone from wearing pajamas
and they even had celebrities on TV saying that the idea of going out in pajamas was backward
and uncivilized. But what's the definition of pajamas? I just think that's really hard to police.
But I think they do like in Japan. So, in the survey that was down asking if people wear
pajamas or wear something else in bed or sleep naked, the Brits love to sleep naked, actually.
We're up there in the top naked sleeping countries, 30% of us, only 12% in the US. In Japan,
in the survey, it wasn't even a zero percent. It was just not applicable. I think the Japanese
were just like, "I'm not going to answer that question." That is disgusting. So, yeah, they're not
up for it. Okay, should we move on to our next panel? Okay, it is time for fact number three and
that is Andrew Hunter Murray. My fact this week is that there are people who mine for jeans.
They literally go into mines looking for jeans. Yeah, this is really amazing. So, it's basically
back in the day when people were doing mining, they would bring their jeans down, leave eyes were
made kind of specifically for mining. And then for some reason, this is the bit I haven't worked
out in the story. They would come up without their jeans. And so, you know, it's warm, isn't it?
You've got to, yeah, but there are lots of things left down there. There are loads of silver mines
in the American West, which are just completely abandoned. And so, there is a thriving trade already
in people who bring up old whiskey bottles because they were left down there when they'd been finished
and collectors will pay for them so you can go down looking for them. And then there is a guy.
There are several of these guys. One of them is called Michael Allen Harris and he found some old
scraps of denim and he realised that a collector of sort of antique denim might pay good money for that too.
And he has had an amazing run of going down with his father-in-law into these abandoned mines.
He's sold one pair of jeans he found for $30,000 to a collector. And his father-in-law,
it's really, really cool. He found the oldest ever pair of leave eyes that are from 1873,
which is the first year of production. I don't think they've sold them yet,
but those can sell for over $100,000, an intact pair of original, they were called waste overalls back then.
I think he hadn't offered, didn't he? And he said he doesn't want to sell them.
Yeah, he doesn't. He said I do have two daughters to put through college so I might reconsider,
but now I'd rather own a really old pair of jeans that have $100,000.
This still doesn't answer my question. Why were they going down to the mines and coming back
up without their trousers on? Well, I think the heat is one reason, actually,
but I think another reason is if there was like a pipe which had kind of leaked or something,
they would take them off and tie them around pipes and stuff like that, because they
were such a durable material. They were kind of useful for anything, really.
Right. Maybe bring down an extra pair of jeans, that kind of stuff.
Maybe that's what they did. Yeah. We don't have photographs of miners emerging
and just like naked from the waist down. I do, but we'll talk about that later.
There are people trying to mine asteroids at the moment. That's a big thing, isn't it?
There's a load of metals in asteroids, and I think if they could somehow capture one and get up
there and get all the metal out of there, then they'll be able to make a load of money.
Yeah. Three quite big ears.
Well, they reckon a single asteroid will be worth $60 trillion if they could mine it.
It's a company called Planetary Resources, which is backed by James Cameron,
the film director, and they're going to try and do this.
And I worked out that if they managed to get this asteroid, then he could remake Avatar every day
for the next 1,000 years. So fingers crossed, everyone.
A famous movie made in one day.
So another thing about mines and miners, this is very cool.
There are some miners who are called ghost miners in South Africa, in the mines there.
They live underground and they're not official mine employees, but they sneak into the mines
when security is distracted. And then they then live underground.
And they just look for ghosts.
Ah, I've misexplained very poorly here.
So yeah, they live underground and their skin goes gray because they don't ever see the sun again.
And there's this whole economy because they can mine sort of extra dangerous bits which have
been abandoned by the main body of the miners. And so where a loaf of bread might cost one dollar
above ground to smuggle it into a mine, you'll pay $12 underground for it.
So this whole secret economy going on underground in these mines.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, that's out. Well, I mean, just in terms of underground economy, we talked about this, I think,
on the podcast, ages ago, the large Hadron collider is actually used for smuggling fruit across
from one country to another because apparently it's cheaper to buy fruit.
And they fire it through the ludge.
Never makes it through.
That's how smooth these are made, just to put that as smashing into each other.
It's amazing they're so cheap really, isn't it?
How expensive is fruit in France?
How many Higgs boson false positives did they get? Which turned out to just be a pair, do we know?
Can I do something on jeans very quickly?
Yeah, of course.
Okay, a hipster's skinny jeans have filed a group of would-be thieves because they were
unable to remove his belongings from his exceptionally tight pockets.
German cents 27 told the New York Post they couldn't even get a finger in.
Oh my god!
Even though they appeared to him and the guys of the Pope.
And they, the squabbling thieves gave up after two minutes.
So they were two minutes trying to get in there.
Wow.
The hips are just starting there going, yeah, I'll tell you the time, I know I'm safe.
There was a thing like that in Cuba, in post-revolutionary Cuba, there was a thing called the lemon test
where you would be stopped on the street by gangs of revolutionaries and they would, to make sure
your trousers weren't too tight and cool and American looking, they would try and get a lemon
through your waistband and down through your trousers to the, to the, the hem of your trousers.
Really?
And if a lemon would pass through then you were okay and if a lemon wouldn't pass through then
you got some on the spot tailoring.
Yeah, they were very popular in Cuba and you're not allowed to wear jeans in a North
career at all because they're a sign of American capsules Monday.
But actually that being too tight thing defeats the original purpose of jeans because
so the word jeans is from a genoa where they were first designed and they were worn by fishermen
and they were worn specifically, they were designed to be easy to remove if a fisherman fell
overboard. So the point of jeans was meant to be that you could whip them off in the air in order
that you didn't drown, yeah.
Why is he trying to take his jeans off?
I think they get waterlogged and weigh it down.
Oh, okay, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, but try to swim in jeans, it's very difficult.
I've never tried to swim in jeans.
Actually I have, you did that survival test when you were at school.
When you took jeans.
I know that you have to go in pajamas but Andy was just wearing one sock.
I ace that test.
And then I went back a second time to get the sock.
We're going to have to move on very soon to the final fact, anything before we do.
This is the most bizarre case, the world's most expensive pair of jeans in a way.
Do you guys know about these? The Pearson versus Chung jeans?
Right, so this is a lawsuit that was launched in 2005 when this judge called Roy Pearson,
who lived in the US, took his jeans to be cleaned for $10.
And he took them to a dry clean as it was owned by South Koreans,
Key and Jin Mann, Chung, and they lost the jeans and he claimed that they owed him $67 million.
That was for things like the emotional damage, the mental anguish,
the legal fees he had to pay to launch this court case.
And the 66 million pounds he added his pocket.
And this went on for years.
So it was only settled in about 2010, I think.
At one point, so Mr. Pearson, because he was a judge,
represented himself in court and at one point he broke down in tears
and had to take a break from testimony while questioning himself because he grew too emotional.
Also, they said, so at one point, about a week after he launched the court case,
they were in court and the Chung said that we found the jeans.
Okay, they were just in the back of the dry cleaners and they brought the jeans into court.
And they were like, these are your jeans, aren't they? These are your trousers, aren't they?
And he said, he insisted, these are not my pants.
I have in my adult life with one exception, never worn pants with cuffs.
But we don't know what that exception was.
All right, I'm going to move us on to our final fact.
Time for our final fact of the evening and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that Jesus had a monobrow.
No way.
Well, okay, yeah, good point.
As a fair point.
So basically, there's not many descriptions of Jesus out there.
We don't have any first-hand accounts.
We have one description which it turns out was written by someone who never existed.
And that's quite a classic, quite a classic description.
But there's a guy called Tom Schivers and he's on Twitter,
so highly recommend checking out because he has an amazing blog and he writes a lot about this stuff.
And he was looking through a lot of descriptions of Jesus
and various different texts over the years and ancient texts.
And he found this constant line that came up which was with eyebrows meeting.
So it happened in at least three texts that there was the the Coptic Acts of Paul and Thachler.
And Paul describes him as a man small and size, bold-headed with eyebrows meeting.
And there's a monk who also put it, it's just counts accounts.
I say countless.
Three accounts, that is round.
But potentially, Jesus had a monobrow.
And I think that's a cool thing, yeah.
We don't, so the Bible doesn't really describe Jesus' appearance almost at all, does it?
There's one account in the book of revelations, I think, where it says that his feet were like
onto burnt brass, who knows what that means.
His head and his hairs were white like wool and white as snow.
This vision is usually considered to refer to Jesus in heavenly form,
not his appearance during his earthly life in that he had a completely white head.
I guess, but that's the only description I think that comes straight from the New Testament.
Yeah, there are a bunch of those descriptions where they say that his face
was like the appearance of lightning and all these descriptions.
And I did think at the time, you know, if you were trying to describe what someone
looked like to a police sketch artist, that was very unhelpful.
Had hair like wool, face like lightning.
You were attacked by a collage of weird random things.
There was a first century historian called Josephus who wrote that Jesus
stood three qubits high and a qubit at the time on average,
because it was a variable measurement, but it was about 18 inches.
A three qubits is 56 inches, which is 4 foot 8.
So I think it might have been Yoda all along.
The gospel of Luke, this is like a gospel.
It was written obviously a long time after Jesus died.
But there's someone called Zaccheus trying to see Jesus preaching.
And he says, and he sought to see Jesus, who he was.
And he could not for the crowd because he was low of stature.
So I think with Zaccheus, he was a small guy because he climbed up a tree to be able to see Jesus.
But he might have only had to climb up the tree because Jesus was so sure.
That is an excellent sign.
I think it's not even specified, yeah.
Yeah, that's a good pipe.
Much more detailed descriptions of Jesus come from Islam, which obviously was much later.
But in Quran and Hadith traditions, they have lots of physical descriptions of Jesus.
Because Muhammad, I think, met him when he went up to heaven.
And there were various other descriptions.
They often they contradict each other.
So at some point he's curly head and at some points he's straight head, although he might have had like crimpers or something.
Also, he doesn't have a beard in the oldest portrait that we have of him, which is a Syrian one in 235 AD.
So he didn't have a beard until about the fourth century in depictions.
He was based on a sort of classical Roman gods for the first few hundred years.
Wasn't he, and he has a curly blonde hair and completely well-shaved face.
I just think it's amazing how quickly we were told this is the image of someone from history
where it must be quite hard to have known exactly what they look like.
And we just accept it and we never question it.
I mean, Shakespeare, by all accounts, mustn't have looked like he does.
Because the people who drew that of him, they didn't meet him.
He'd been dead for a long time.
Jane Austen, we only have one picture of her drawn by her sister,
who everyone said throughout her life was a crap drawer.
So it's just obviously not going to look quite like that.
She's going on the bank notes pretty soon.
The one that they, the picture that they've chosen is a very purified later Victorian
representation of Jane Austen.
And it's not anywhere near like the picture that her sister drew of her.
So yeah, it's very, very inaccurate.
Another person who you one necessarily think looked as they did.
John Wilkes Booth, who shot Erlingon.
He was described as the handsomest man in all America.
He wasn't that tall, but people said that it was made up for
by his extraordinary presence and magnetism.
Whereas English political activist John Wilkes, without the Booth,
he was famously ugly.
He had a sloping forehead, hanging jaw, bad teeth, bad breath, a severe squint.
And he was advised never to risk showing his face to a pregnant woman.
Oh, my God.
But he didn't kill anyone.
That's true.
Oh, my God.
Was he able to that sentence?
But he's my son, and I love him, and who did say that about it?
I think it was probably one of his detractors.
His detractors, they've never got a good word to say about you.
Do you want to hear some cool stuff about eyebrows?
Yes, please.
Oh, yeah.
OK.
Well, this is more about facial expressions than eyebrows.
But there's an author called David Eagleman,
who is a great writer about science and neuroscience.
And there's a fact in his latest book, which is just out,
that when people have had Botox, they find it harder to recognize
facial expressions in other people.
What?
Yeah.
So they've tested people who've not had Botox treatments,
and they've tested people who have had Botox treatments.
And if you have, it's hard of you to mirror their facial expression.
And it's hard of you to--
literally, if you recognize what you're looking at on someone else's face.
So if Dan looks baffled like you do now,
I would kind of copy what you're doing,
and then I would empathize in your baffled.
Exactly.
But this is the other cool thing is that married couples
start to look like each other over time,
because they are constantly mirroring each other's facial expressions,
and they get the same patterns of wrinkles.
That is excellent news for me, but terrible news for my wife.
[LAUGHTER]
Also, I was reading eyebrows.
Eyebrows are the most essential bit of your head generally.
I mean, I'm going to go close second after brain.
Eyes, mouth, ears.
Your eyebrows are the 19th most essential bit of your head.
This is why I read.
And no, they were saying because for communication,
the eyebrows, actually, they do the talking when they're talking.
If you're talking to someone--
Not if you've kept your mouth on the tick-bolt sheet.
[LAUGHTER]
If you were talking to me, and you said,
oh, can you believe this?
I, with my eyebrows, would go, whoa.
So if I shaved my eyebrows, you wouldn't know what I was thinking.
Yeah, I think that's similar to the Botox thing, I guess, right?
I read somewhere that eyebrows evolved partly
because they aid in sex differentiation in humans.
So people kept on accidentally trying
to procreate with the same sex.
And so they gave men slightly thicker eyebrows.
That did seem to be what they were saying.
And you just look at one of those two things.
[LAUGHTER]
But here's the weird thing about that,
which I thought that was weird, but apparently,
computers can determine someone's gender, 96% of the time,
just by looking at the eyebrows and nothing else.
So why?
Kind of makes sense.
So we've kind of assumed that Mono-Brow is a negative aesthetic
feature on Jesus.
Oh, you haven't.
No, I think that's great.
I think people with Mono-Brow's
are the great heroes of planet Earth.
They constantly--
Wow.
Again, a bold claim.
Well, it is the most essential bit of the head,
and don't forget that.
Who here has seen someone with the Mono-Brow
and hasn't just stared at the Mono-Brow,
the entire conversation that they've been having with them?
And that says more about the person with the Mono-Brow
than it does you the person staring,
because it says to me that they're going,
I know it's here.
I know it's here, and I love it.
And that's what I really like that.
I think that the bravest humans alive.
Well, so in--
I can't see fire, I can't see fire, I like it.
I'm going to call point of information on fire,
but it's weird.
My old list of best humans was one.
People with Mono-Brow's, too, Jesus.
Now Jesus has made his way to the top of the list.
It's very amazing.
So in Tajikistan, Mono-Brow's are attractive
and sought after, aren't they?
So in women, especially, and markets in Tajikistan,
you can buy this herb, uzma, which women will buy.
And you can rub it on your brow to make sure you turn those two
eyebrows into one.
And this is a desirable thing.
And I think there might be the only country in the world
where the Mono-Brow is genuinely desirable.
Well, there may be a turning.
So at the moment, in the NBA, one of the biggest stars.
And we're talking at someone who's
in the kind of level of Michael Jordan
and of modern day.
It's a guy called Anthony Davis.
And he has a monobrow.
And he has trademarked.
Basically, he's turned his monobrow into a business.
His monobrow has catchphrases that you
would not allow to repeat on any product.
It's fear of the brow and raise the brow.
And he's turned his monobrow into an actual business now.
And I didn't know that you could trade mine.
I mean, the quote from him is, I don't want anyone else
to try and grow a uni-brow because of me
and then try to make money out of it.
What else is suspicious is this man of other humans?
What would Jesus have said if he had that?
But I kind of-- I slightly like the idea of trademarking.
Because when I realized you could trademark a simple thing
like that towards a facial feature or something,
I thought, well, who else has done that?
And there's a guy, Michael Buffer.
He was a boxing announcer.
He was the person to say, let's get ready to rumble.
That's his trademark.
He has made, since he trademarked it--
since he first set in, trademarked it-- $400,000
American Dollars from movies using it, from TV shows
using it songs.
Yeah.
There's a little more.
How hard is it to come up with a different phrase that
means basically the same thing?
And then not have to pay this guy $400,000?
Just say, let's get ready to tumble.
And then--
It's washing machine noise.
Thanks, Carl.
We're going to have to wrap up really soon.
We've got any final facts.
We want to throw in.
The tactical name for the monobrow
is Sinophrous, just so you know.
And the founder of criminology, Cesare Lombrazo,
thought that Sinophrous was a sure sign.
You were a criminal.
And that's the founder of criminology.
One other thing as well.
You can tell if dogs like you, because when they see you,
they lift the left eyebrow upwards half a second
after they first see you.
And that was a study done using high-speed cameras.
So that's one way to speak.
They don't greyhounds.
And as they pass the camera, they sort of give a little--
Hey, how you doing?
Why high-speed cameras?
Just so that, because actually, it's
a very, very microscopic little life.
You can either see if its eyebrow is very slightly raised
or you can work out if you are the person that provides
its food every day.
And one of those two things will tell you
if a dog likes you.
If a dog doesn't like you, it bites your penis off.
[LAUGHTER]
No high-speed camera necessary for that one.
OK, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you want to get in contact with any of us about the things
we've said over the course of this podcast,
you can find us on Twitter.
I'm on @Sriberland.
James.
@X8.
Andy.
@AndruhunterM.
And Chazinsky.
You can email podcast@ky.com.
Yep.
And if you want to hear any of our previous episodes,
head to nosuchthingasaffish.com.
We will be back again next week with another podcast.
Thank you so much for being here, guys.
Really appreciate it.
And we'll see you again next week.
Goodbye.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You