Hey everyone, welcome to this week's episode of Fish. Before we get going, we just want
to let you know that we have a very special guest on this week. So James is away on holiday
at the moment, doing, you know, classic Jamesy things. I'm sure you're going to hear about
it on a future podcast when he's back. He's probably eating, you know, weird testicles
and living in a cave, that sort of stuff. Classic Harken holiday. Anyway, in his place,
we have the brilliant comedian, Shaperak Korsandi. Shaperak's a really good friend of ours. She's
been on Fish before. She did the comic relief marathon, and that video is up on YouTube
if you want to watch it. But she's here for an actual episode this time. And she's not
only a comedian, she's a brilliant author as well. She's written three books. Her latest
book, which has just come out, is called Kissing Emma. It's a novel for young adults, and
it is a modern fable of the untold story of Emma Hamilton, who is Lord Nelson's mistress.
So if you have a young adult in your life, do get the book for them, but also do get
it for yourself because it is for adults as well. And Shaperak is such a great writer,
so funny, so interesting. It's going to be a great read. Anyway, that book is available
online and in stores now, so do get a copy. But until then, enjoy Shaperak on no such thing
as a fish. Here we go. Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from four undisclosed locations in the UK. My name is Dan Shriver.
I am sitting here with Anna Toshinsky, Andrew Hunter Murray, and special guest, it's Shaperak
Kossandi. And once again, we have gathered round the microphones with our four favorite
facts from the last seven days, and in no particular order, here we go. Starting with
fact number one, and that's Shaperak. So hello. And my fact is that a doctor in India,
Ashok Aswani, would prescribe DVDs of Charlie Chaplin to his patients to convince them that
joy and laughter was the remedy to their malady. Does he do it if he's run out of medicine
for that day? It's interesting. I mean, look, we say doctor, but he was, and this is a new
word that I've learned, you've vedic medicine. So it sounds like you've called him a dick.
You want to say that again? I have a dick. I have a dick. Thank you very much. Is that
homeopathy? It's lots of different things. Yeah, it's traditional medicine. There's
breathing and there are dietary things and there's herbal treatments and that kind of
stuff. That's Ayurveda, I think. Yeah, I think 80% of people in India roughly would practice
Ayurvedic medicine. Yeah. But yeah, it's what we would say is alternative medicine. Exactly.
Or mindfulness, you know, I think that it's the practice of looking after the self and
your body and being connected with yourself. But let's be clear, if you're going for your
COVID vaccination and they run out of Pfizer, do not accept the gold rush as a substitute.
Absolutely. Likewise, if you've broken your leg, the kid will do nothing for you. Just
to clarify, even though we're talking about Ayurveda medicine and how it is alternative,
actually Aswani prescribes chaplain for mood disorders, right? And psychological problems.
So it's people who come with anxiety or depression. And that doesn't seem completely out of this
world for some of those issues. And so there's a lot of science that says the old GSOH is
associated with living longer. I think there was a study in Norway that it took like 54,000
people and it looked at how good their senses of humor were. Don't know how they did that.
And then it went back 15 years later. And the ones with the best senses of humor were
more likely to have survived. Wow. So maybe this guy knows what he's into. I think there
is something to it. I think, you know, we've spoken about this on the podcast before where
when people were put under pain and duress, when they put their, I think their hands were
in ice buckets, listening to Billy Connolly made them feel the pain less.
They did show Charlie Chaplin films in hospital. They screen it on hospital ceilings for casualties
of World War One because Chaplin was such a massive star that his very silhouette would
make people feel overjoyed and happy. How do you get the mustache into the silhouette?
You've got to do sideways aren't I suppose? No, he's iconic outside. You're not looking
at the cane bent with the hat going, who is that? Who is that? Who is it? Well, there
is someone else that could have been because you know how he, one of his most famous films
is called The Great Dictator and he was satirizing Hitler. I didn't know this. He and Hitler
were born four days apart. That doesn't mean they have the same silhouette on the ceiling.
Well, some say that Hitler copied Chaplin's mustache, but was that mustache the fashion
that then the way big beards are now amongst the young and her suit?
Yeah, I mean, Hitler was a fashionable guy. And yeah, I don't think there's ever been
evidence, but there is someone who did copy Chaplin's mustache overtly. And that is Marcel
Proust.
Why did Marcel Proust copy it? Was it a direct tribute to Charlie Chaplin?
Yes. And because he was the biggest thing ever. I mean, at the time people were saying
he was the most famous person who had ever lived, which was probably true in about 1915,
16, wasn't it? Because, you know, movies had just become this global thing. He was the
Mr. Bean of his time. He could transcend all language in that he did not rely on language.
And in fact, he resisted the talkies when they started talking films. Chaplin was like,
oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, this takes away the purity of what we do. And this is just
a passing fad. And it took him a good long time to make a talking film. I think I've
watched "The Great Dictator" even more times than I've watched "Grease".
Wow.
Really?
One of those films I know off my heart.
But we do need to know how many times you've seen "Grease" in order for this fact to have
true punch.
Oh, I think I watched "Grease" every Saturday for about four, five years.
Okay, now that's the great dictator thing. That throws it into an entirely new light.
That's amazing.
Well, you know how a lot of people during their sort of darker times in their teens
will listen to music. I would just watch "The Great Dictator" over and over again. And I'd
make my friends watch it. And I lost quite a few friends with my obsession with that
particular film.
That's amazing.
We should say "The Great Dictator" because this is a movie that a lot of listeners might
not know the plotline of or aware of its impact. This was a movie that Charlie Chaplin
made in 1940. This was a movie that basically satirized Adolf Hitler and showed exactly
what his plans were and his hatred towards the Jewish people of the world and how he
was putting them away and how he wanted global dictatorship. And this was at a point where
not everyone was really ready to say that that's what Hitler was doing. And Charlie
Chaplin got in a lot of trouble for it. But this movie came out while Hitler was really
at the beginning of what he was about to do. And it caused huge ruckus. Hitler saw it
twice.
It's astonishing that this movie was made.
How many times did he see Greece? We need to know that for context.
You better shape up was apparently one of his favorite songs. It bellows my mind that
Hitler saw this. How can you be Hitler and watch that final speech? Don't fight for these
machine men with machine hearts and machine minds. You are not machines. You are men.
You are the love of humanity in your heart. How did that not cure Hitler?
He thought that was the satirist. That's the problem with satire. It's too ambiguous.
That must have really hit home interestingly in your family as well because your dad is
a satirist and you effectively had to flee Iran because of his direct satire towards the
power there, right?
Yeah, I think my father was a huge reason why I fell in love with Chaplin. That scene
in The Great Dictator when he's on the roof with Paulette Goddard and they're literally
escaping with the shirts on their backs and then he sees his barbershop blow up because
the Nazis have blown it up and he's like, "There goes the barbershop." That simple little
line, "There goes the barbershop. There goes everything I have, everything I've worked
for, just gone. Now we have to flee everything we know because of these guys," which is exactly
what happened, of course, to our family. It's a horrible thing. Chaplin, of course,
was exiled from America. Yeah, it was a McCarthyism, wasn't it? And he was understandably criticised
it and then had to leave and move to Switzerland, I think.
Well, he didn't originally move back to Switzerland. He was on his way back to England and then
they told him on board the ship, "By the way, you're not going to be allowed back into
the States unless you appear in front of the immigration authorities on charges of political
and moral turpitude." So effectively, he couldn't go back.
I went to his house in Vervet. Did you? Really? The extraordinary thing about it is the Alps
are just looking down at you, like wherever you look. It's just this art of beauty. And
it was, for someone of his wealth, it wasn't an opulent place at all. It was just a lovely
family home. Yeah, I mean, I would live there if I was on route to the UK, but I chanced
upon this place in Vervet. There was this huge problem when he was on his way, which is
he had a million dollars buried in his garden. Really? And the story is, and I think there's
debate about how much of it is true, is that he asked his wife to get a spade, go to the
garden, dig it up, convert it into $1,000 bills, sew them into her mink coat, and then just
bring them to Switzerland. That's a big ask, isn't it? You've got to, I think I'd go
over to Vals over that. Did she make it? Well, I mean, they lived together in Switzerland
until his death. So yeah, she did. Did she bring the millions with her? I think that has
been, a veil has been drawn over that, so we don't know. Let's dig up his old garden
for God's sake. They might still be there. Don't dig up Charlie Chaplin because that's
exactly what happened to him after his death. This is the weirdest element of his story.
He was body snatched. Yes. By these two guys who wanted to bury him under where he was
buried, right? His corpse was stolen really shortly after he died in the 1970s. '75, yeah.
'75. And it was these guys who wanted to basically extort Una, one of his last wife,
and said, "Give us all this money because we've stolen your husband's body." And
they traced the cause and they caught the guys. And the guys basically said, "We didn't
really mean anything by it. We just wanted to dig him up, bury him a bit beneath where
he had been buried before, so it looked like he was gone. And then we had to leg it and
bury him in a cornfield." No. I mean, that is the worst alibi I've ever heard. They
wanted $600,000 or the equivalent of $600,000 today for his return. And the police did this
incredible sting operation. They launched surveillance operations on 200 phone booths
in the area when they were waiting for the call to be made, which is, you know, substantial
effort, I would say. They did never claim to be fair to them that they weren't trying
to extort the wife. They just said, "We weren't going to steal the body. We were just going
to hide it." And they did apologize to Una afterwards and she did forgive them. It's
what he would have wanted. He was a comic. He would have got the joke. It's just a bit
of slapstick. It's amazing that this happened in 1975 as well, isn't it? Like, that's pretty
extraordinary. Why? What do you mean? Well, because he died in 1977, so. Oh my God. I thought
her sounded early. I'm so sorry. Why have I written that down? Because I'm wrong. Wait,
what year did Greece come out? What year did? Oh, Greece come out. Oh, I don't know. 78.
It came out 1978. Are we pretending there's no connection here? Are we really going to
sit there? Well, I didn't come to the UK until 79, so I missed Chaplin's death. The stars
of all the lights, you see? I came in time for Thatcher. Well done. You timed it right.
Her films were rubbish. Can we talk a bit more about the insane early popularity of Charlie
Chaplin? Because we talk a lot about his later career with The Great Dictator, but his early
films, when he moved to the USA, because he grew up in England, incredibly poor, moved
to the USA. In his first year there, he made 36 films in 1914. So I read his obituary in
the New York Times, and it's full of these unbelievable details about the Chaplin mania,
the craze. So for example, I'm quoting directly here from his obituary, one New York theatre
played his films continuously from 1914 to 1923, stopping only because the building burned
down. That was how popular he was. I know, I know. But at one point he went to the ballet
in Los Angeles. And again, I'm quoting directly, it's dancers spotted Chaplin in the audience
and halted the show for half an hour while they embraced him. Wow. Imagine that. It was
a disease. You know, going back to the original theme, it was called Chaplinitis. And literally
from 1915, basically as soon as he become famous, people were reported Chaplinitis,
and he was everywhere, like from China, Africa, Russia, in Japan, he was referred to as Professor
Alcohol because of the way he swayed, which is like mad level of global fame for that
time. But he always wanted it. I hadn't realised he was so fame crazed. Yeah. On the boat over
to America, he basically said, I'm coming to conquer you. Every man, woman and child
shall have my name on their lips. And you know who he is on that boat with, who I believe
witnessed that moment of him saying I'm going to conquer America was Stan Laurel. Tim Kardashian.
Yeah, Stan Laurel, who was part of the British group of comedians that they were with, they
both went to America together, they lived together for a while as well. And he was like, yeah,
this guy was insanely ambitious. When they were living in America, obviously they weren't
successful. As soon as they arrived, they lived in a flat together. And apparently they weren't
allowed to cook in the flat. That was one of the rules of the tenancy or whatever. So when
they were frying pork chops, Stan Laurel would fry the pork chops and Chaplin would
play the violin incredibly loudly to mask the sound of sizzling meat.
My favourite Chaplin fact is that Jackie Coogan, who played the kid, I don't think I've ever
sobbed so much as when I saw the kid being put on the cart and taken away from Chaplin
and outstretching his arms. And in that film, that line for all of this horrific treatment
of women in his life, that beginning line where he says, a woman, I cry when I even
say this out loud, a woman whose crime was motherhood. Such a simple thing to say at
a time when so many unmarried mothers had to abandon their kids or put them up for adoption.
And that to me was such a support, early support of single motherhood. Of course, his mother
was a single mum, so he had a lot of compassion for women in that predicament. Anyway, Jackie
Coogan went on to become Uncle Fester in the Addams family.
Yes, in the Addams family. Yes.
What?
Yeah.
That cute, cute little kid that went around with the tramp smashing windows turned out
to be the gruesome bald headed uncle Fester.
Can we quickly go back to the man of who this whole fact was born from?
Oh yeah.
The doctor.
The doctor, Ashok Aswani. He's such a great character and it's wonderful when you have
people championing other characters as their whole life's mission. So he discovered Chaplin
when he was very young and he fell in love with him and he tried to get into being a
performer himself off the back of Chaplin and doing mime and so on, but it didn't work
out for him. And so he went to become this doctor and just while being a doctor, he continued
his love. So he used to dress up as Chaplin in the streets. He went on to set up a big
festival and when I say big, I think there's something like 300 people go to it every year.
But it's a tiny town in Gujarat. It's not a big place and people from around the world
come to visit it and they dress up as Chaplin and they cut a Chaplin cake.
Imagine trying to find your friend in that crowd. Imagine even worse, him being your
doctor and you having a severe case of Chaplinitis booking in to see him. He turns up dressed
as Chaplin and gives you a Chaplin DVD.
Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is my fact. My fact this week is that no one
really knows what order the Chronicles of Narnia should be read in, not even C.S. Lewis knew.
Is it actually the wardrobe, the witch and the lion? And there's been in a wrong order
all this time.
So basically this is something that's been bubbling away in the background amongst academics
who love C.S. Lewis and just fans of the Chronicles of Narnia where they don't actually know
which order to read the book in because there's been various publications over the years that
have them put in different orders. So there's a book that appears quite late in the series
called The Magician's Nephew which is actually a prequel to what is thought to be the first
book, The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe. So when certain publishers have republished
the book series they'll make The Magician's Nephew book number one. But people argue that
no, that should be later on in the series like they were originally published. And so the only
thing that we really know about C.S. Lewis' preference came from a letter that he wrote
to an 11 year old boy in 1957 who said that he thinks that it should be read in the chronological
order but his mother thought it should be in the original publication order starting with
the Lion, Witch and the Wardrobe. So he wrote back C.S. Lewis saying "I think I agree with your order
for reading the books more than with your mother's. The series was not planned beforehand as she
thinks. When I wrote The Lion I did not know I was going to write any more. So perhaps it
does not matter very much in which order anyone reads them." So even he was like "I'm not going
to settle on a side." And as a result that letter has been analysed so many times by different
academics who use it as him with that final line saying it doesn't matter what order and then the
other academics go to the top of the letter and say no he thinks he agrees with the boy's order
and so we just don't know. Christ, which academics are analysing and re-analyzing this very brief
letter from C.S. Lewis? It's not Don Jowen is it? He said it doesn't matter. Just accept it and move
on. Yeah and also you don't know how busy he was when he was writing this letter. Like he might
have been like "Oh honestly it doesn't matter. Leave me alone." He just had a thing that he had to
respond to letters and he just said something flippantly and didn't really analyse it himself
because they all stand alone books aren't they? Yes. So you're a fan aren't you? Have you read
them all? No I haven't read them all but I'm a massive fan of The Lion, The Witch and the Wardrobe
which I've just started reading to my daughter actually as of last night. I'm such a dipstick
that years and years into my adult life having been obsessed with The Lion, The Witch and the
Wardrobe all my life I had to go on a television programme and talk about it and there was a Q&A
and someone asked me about the fact that it was a Christian allegory and I didn't realise
up until they asked that question. I went "Oh yeah!" That's brilliant. Absolutely clueless. There was
very little religion in my life as a child and I just thought this resurrection was coincidental
with what happened to Jesus. But why would you? I mean there is no reason why you would know as
a child and it must be interesting reading it as an adult because I read all the books in
the order that they came in the box set, Magician's Nephew first and when you're seven or whatever
you're not really looking for the message and in fact even if the message is round down your
throat you're likely to miss it because you're excited by the idea of going into a cupboard.
C.S. Lewis, he was a serious Christian in lots of ways and in fact I think he was described in his
obituary as more of a Christian thinker. One of his main obituries in the New York Times didn't even
mention the lie of the witch in the wardrobe, didn't mention Narnia, described him as a Christian
apologist and... C.S. Lewis, oh come on that is wantonly highbrow to a really pretentious extent.
It was his biggest hit by a long way. C.S. Lewis, it was his biggest hit yeah but he converted to
Christianity. I really like this fact on a trip to Whipsnade Zoo and specifically in a motorbike
sidecar en route to Whipsnade Zoo. C.S. Lewis, what? C.S. Lewis, I think he went with his brother or
brother-in-law and he wrote later on "When we set out I did not believe that Jesus Christ is the
Son of God and when we reached the zoo I did" and the journey was on a motorbike and he was in
the sidecar so he had a conversion to Christianity in a motorbike sidecar. C.S. Lewis, oh wow what
happened? What possibly happened in that sidecar? C.S. Lewis, I mean I think it was probably the
culmination of a process. It wasn't as though they saw a burning bush en route and he just thought
"oh okay". C.S. Lewis, the parrot the zoo told him. C.S. Lewis, do you know that we know the population
of Narnia exactly? It's 19,252. C.S. Lewis, is that including the squirrels? C.S. Lewis,
oh that's a good point. Human population, sorry. C.S. Lewis, is that because there's a real place
called Narnia. Narnia exists. It's in Italy. It's called Narnie these days but in classical
times it was called Narnia and C.S. Lewis saw it as a young man on a classical map which was written
in Latin and it just labelled it Narnia and the name just stuck with him. C.S. Lewis, imagine it
could have been Chelmsford. C.S. Lewis, I don't know if that would have caught his eye in quite the
same way, maybe. C.S. Lewis, I looked into Narnia in Italy and it didn't look as if
they had done anything specifically to capitalise on, you know, you could quite easily turn yourself
into a tourist town, couldn't you? C.S. Lewis, yeah, I think they've probably got the dignity to resist
it. It's my hunch. Do you think? C.S. Lewis, yeah, it's Italy. It's not some coastal town in the
north of Ingalls the Italians were talking about. They've got really nice places they don't need to
nix C.S. Lewis, I think. I think they're missing a trick. Yeah, because if that was in Britain,
they'd be selling little Mr. Tumnus key rings. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, even just some sort of like
carpentry cupboard shop that has a tie in, you know, do something, use it. What cupboards were the
false back? That's a good idea, actually. That could be really fun. Well, Dan, I know you're always
looking for a pilgrimage to go on to see great places associated with great people. You can see
the wardrobe. The wardrobe is in Illinois for weird reasons. It's the Lewis family wardrobe,
which was at his family home in Belfast for years. And then it got moved to his adult home. So it's
definitely the wardrobe. And it was auctioned off and taken to a place called Wheaton College.
And it's there these days with Tolkien's desk. So they're united even in death.
And I bet that's the place that's capitalising on the connection. I suspect Illinois is making more
of that. You know, the first time walking through a cupboard, it wasn't in the line
The Witch and the Wardrobe. It was in a 1946 essay that he wrote called Different Tastes in
Literature. Wow. Yeah. Not as catchy a kid's book, no. That's the he uses it as an analogy of the
experience of reading poetry, you know, you walk through a wardrobe into another realm. And he
uses that in that book. So, you know, recycled a lot of his ideas. Did you ever try to get into
Narnia as children? Yes. Oh, my Lord. Yeah, like pushing through the. Yeah, just going if I if I
just do it, maybe this way, maybe if I just close my eyes, I'll be in Narnia hours I spent in the
cupboard. It was very controversial for him when he was writing it, because he wrote about the
cupboard, the wardrobe. And then he sent a draft of the book to his friend Owen Barfield, whose
daughter was Lucy. Lucy was C.S. Lewis's goddaughter, after whom the character of Lucy is named.
And anyway, Lucy's mom, Owen Barfield's wife said, Well, this is really dangerous. You can't
have this Pete. Kids will start locking themselves in cupboards. That's really dangerous. Lucy's
going to lock herself in a cupboard. And then so you'll notice he added all these amendments to
the text. There are four or five references in the text. So yeah, do you remember that? Absolutely.
Saying burnt in the cupboard, leaving it open just a bit because it is very foolish to shut
oneself into a wardrobe. And he said that repeatedly. Exactly. Very sort of like rammed in
to make sure. And that probably saved you from locking yourself in a wardrobe multiple times.
You know what? To this day, whenever I climb into a wardrobe, I'm careful to leave it open just a
little. Okay, it is time for fact number three. And that is Andy. My fact is that the only dog to
have been to both the North and South Poles was not a husky nor any kind of adventure dog, but a
small Jack Russell terrier solo mission, solo mission. No, slightly accompanied, slightly
accompanied by being Ronald Fiennes's dog, which did help the odds of getting there. Sure. Well,
Randolph and Virginia finds his dog. So we've spoken about Randolph finds before. We haven't
spoken about Lady Twisselton Wickham finds known to her friends as Jenny, who was his wife.
And the dog was called Bothy. And this was the trans globe expedition they were on,
which we've mentioned so briefly in passing. But basically it was the mission to cross Antarctica
and the Arctic Ocean and to go to both poles on the same trip, which had never been tried before.
With the dog, do we know? I mean, why the dog? Was the Jack Russell going to come in useful? Was
it a backup food supply? Was the Jack Russell pulling all the sleds? Do you know how expensive it
would be to put it in a kennels for all that time? Well, exactly. I think that they just loved the dog.
And Jenny said, Well, this is going to take three years. I'm not leaving the dog at home for three
years. And she and the dog were very, very close because I think she'd lost her previous terrier.
I think it had some awful ending. It's sort of drowned in a slurry pit or something. It was
really, really traumatic. She was absolutely inconsolable. So then Rannell got to this new
dog, Bothy, and they were inseparable. And she said, Right, we're going to take him
all the way around the world. And they did. So up until this point, I've known Rannell Fiennes as
this extraordinary explorer. But I have to say, Ginny Fiennes is the coolest person I've read
about in years. She's a legend, isn't she? What's your favorite feature? Your favorite Ginny feature?
She kind of ran the show. And no one really ever acknowledged that she would organise the
entire teams that would go along with him. She would set up the camp and she would have the
radio going where she would sit and monitor, listening out for Morse code for days on end,
like listening and then having to organise whatever weird request. I need a whalership
to pick me up in two days. Okay, I'll just do that then, shall I? Sitting here in my cardboard box,
which she did. She sat in a cardboard box most of the time. Hang on, hang on, hang on.
Yeah, I've gone too far, as always. Your enthusiasm carried you away. There were cardboard, though.
She designed cardboard huts, laminated cardboard huts, which were for when they needed to stay
for the winter in Antarctica. It's not the first material you think of, is it? When you think,
what am I going to buy? The wise man built his house out of cardboard? That's not a problem.
No, you're absolutely right. And then they got covered in snow. And I think that's what kept
them warm. I guess they were light and easily transportable, which is a good thing. And they
had tunnels in between the huts. And the other little piggy built their heart out of tin.
Thank God there are no wolves in Antarctica, that's all I could say. No, just Bothie the dog,
who apparently repeatedly, Bothie was a terror. Bothie shat in the snow tunnels between the huts.
Randall Fine said it's impossible to teach Bothie the difference between outside, outside,
and outside, which is a snow tunnel between the huts. And even on the ship all the way down,
Bothie was leaving little presents in everyone's cabins. That's a nightmare. But it was very brave,
according to Ginny, and all dog owners are biased, but apparently was only afraid once.
And that was when he came across a bowl shaped Antarctic sort of snow bowl. And he barked into
it. And then it barked back because of the echo and freaked the hell out. But aside from that,
very brave dog. Yeah. Yeah. My dog is a bit of a hero. And also I'm a little bit appalled at myself
talking about Ginny in the Antarctic with her dog, because all I thought about was I hope Ginny
cleared up after her dog in the Antarctic and didn't leave little green bags of dog poo all over
the snow. No, it's really, that is a very good point. I actually don't know if they did tidy up
and they have banned dogs from the Antarctic now. Because you see, ruined it for everyone.
Because Ginny left such a mess. Yeah. Exactly. No, not Ginny, not Bothie,
not Ginny. We don't know about either. So Bothie, Bothie the dog. Yeah, no, but that's probably
means that no dog after Bothie will ever go to the Arctic and Antarctic again. If the rules don't
change. There might be a generation of kids in the UK that are aware of Bothie, even though they
don't realise it. Bothie used to appear on Blue Peter a lot. And there was a book that was written
by Randolph and Ginny about Bothie the dog. Not by Bothie, I thought you were going to say.
Bothie won pet of the year, I believe, in 1982, I think after the expedition. And then he was also
invited to present a prize at the 1983 Crufts. I don't know how. He turned it down on moral grounds,
didn't he? He doesn't agree. She did win prizes as well. Ginny, she got the Polar Medal in 1987.
I think she was the first woman to get it. And that was because she did important scientific
work in the Antarctic, mostly with her radio stuff. She was pioneering. And she was the first
woman ever to be invited to join the Antarctic Club. Chopra, have you been part of any kind of
expeditions? I feel like it's a celebrity comedian thing you get invited to. I would love to. I would
love to do that. But no, I haven't. I've only done I'm a celebrity. Get me out of here where we just
really stayed put, apart from the occasional jumping out of a helicopter. But no, the Arctic,
I mean, who doesn't want to go there? It's like my dream to do a trip like that. And just hearing
you guys talking about Ginny and her tech work and how she pulled the whole show together makes
me feel like such a knob for taking almost an hour to even get on this call with you guys
and wasting all of your time. So I think that was that was your equivalent of an intrepid journey.
Like that was, you know, what that was, persistence and grit. And I think it shortened my life in
some ways. I mean, Ginny also, she's definitely suffered for her work. She once got in the Antarctic,
she got glued to a lavatory seat because it was minus 50 degrees Celsius outside. Once she went
out into the snow and she had a cigarette lighter, metal zippo lighter in her pocket,
and it burned into her thigh. It burned the shape of the zippo and the lighter into her thigh because
of how cold it was out there. I mean, it's not the same, but I had a similar experience and I'm
a celebrity, get me out of here because I got glued to the wooden toilet seat because I went in
after several of the blokes. And it wasn't the sort of seat that you can flip up. It was horrific.
Yeah, because they would we in the dunny, you couldn't flip it up. And then you couldn't really
wipe it either. So their pee would just soak down into it. And there was no getting away from it.
And there was a limited amount of loo paper. It was horrific. Oh my God, did this make, did this
fact make it to air? Or is this you giving us exclusive content about? This is exclusive content
about the unhygienic. Who's pee? Who's pee? Name names? No, God, Dan, no. Legally, no. But I will
tell you that Stanley Johnson and I had to share a towel for the entire time because they wouldn't
let us have fresh towels. And my towel had got so full of debris, like there's so much woodchip,
it was unusable. And so we had this situation that we never talked out of ever again of just we
were never sure whose towel was who. You see, I think that is hardship. I think that is qualified
for some kind of, not the entire club, but something. I think you deserve a polar medal.
Thank you. I mean, compare that to having a Zippo branded onto your thigh. I think me having to
share towels in Australia's Gold Coast was a lot worth. With Boris Johnson's dad, we should say,
for foreign listeners. Yeah, just back to Ginny for a second. Before she was doing these adventures
with Ranoff, she had amazing adventures in her own right. One really bizarre one, which is in 1972,
she was commissioned by Woman's Own Magazine to go and live with an Omani shake in a village
for two months, the idea being that she would be his third wife. And there was a very, very strict
understanding between all parties that there was going to be no hanky-panky, that it was just purely
her living the life to see what the life was like. And she did it. She went out there and she lived
with them. And she basically fell in love with the family to the point where she decided not to
submit the article because she wanted to respect their privacy. And then in that area, it's where
she then, with Ranoff finds, went and found a completely lost city to time. Oh yeah. It's just
amazing, the lost city of Ubar. They'd heard rumors about it. No one could find it. Ranoff and Ginny
obsessed over it, spent years and years looking for it. And eventually it was solved when we started
getting aerial shots via satellite that they were able to spot something in the sand, and they uncovered
it and they found it. It's completely lost city of Ubar. The frankincense city, I think it was
where they did all the frankincense trading. So it must have been this incredible, rich, scented place.
Do you think they smelled it out? I'm sure. I'm probably buffy. And she did all this stuff without
being, you know, she wasn't physically tough. So for example, she could do two laps of a running
track and then she had to lie down. She wasn't a strong woman, but I mean, but she still went on
this 35,000 mile transglobe expedition. She had to take a hot water bottle to the Arctic because
Ranoff like sleeping with the windows open, which I find completely. Jesus Christ. I mean, what?
Yeah. And sometimes when they were, you know, overwintering, this is at the other end of the
planet on the Antarctic, she wouldn't answer the radio. And twice Ranoff came back to the
cardboard hut and found that she was unconscious from carbon monoxide poisoning. What? And I know.
From what? Oh, God knows, a bit of the equipment going wrong or, I don't know what exactly caused
it. But yeah, there were just so many moments of near total peril and failure on this expedition.
And she took it all pretty well, didn't she? She was clearly very hardy. She sounds formidable,
I think is probably the word you would use. So everyone was kind of terrified of her.
Like your most respected, but strict headmistress is how I imagine her. I think when she heard
that Ranoff had to have his fingers amputated, you know, he had to amputate the ends of his
five fingers. It was through frostbite, right? Yes. But then he sawed them off himself at home.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Her first response was, oh, damn, we'll be short-handed on the farm now. Not a lot
of sympathy. Is that a short-handed joke because his fingers are literally shorter because he sawed
them off? I don't think it was an intentional pun, but it obviously has that other layer
that you can enjoy. Great. That's how good she was. She won. One kind of really amazing fact
about Ginny is that she died, I think, in 2003, although Dan, you may well tell me it was actually
2005. But it was 2004. You're kidding. Unbelievable. You know what? I'm going to start writing days
down. All right, she died in 2004. I think she may have been diagnosed with cancer in 2003.
She found out about her illness when Ranoff, her husband, was away. He was running seven marathons
on seven continents in seven days. And she didn't mention it to him in case he abandoned the attempt
and changed it if he wanted him to get on with it and finish it. And I think that is a sign of the
kind of woman she was completely. That strong spousing. Yeah. Extremely brave. Guys, can I tell
you about the first all-female expedition to the North Pole? Because it's a really fun story.
This was in the '90s. And basically, this woman, Caroline Hamilton, who was a financier, she hated
all forms of exercise, never done really any in her life, decided, I'm going to take a bunch of
women to the North Pole. And she put an advert in the newspaper, in the Telegraph, I think, saying,
"Hey, are you a woman who has no hiking or exploring experience? And do you want to come
to the North Pole? Get in touch." And all these women did. And it's the coolest story. They went
on a trial weekend somewhere in the UK, which was quite rough. I think it was in Dartmoor,
an induction weekend. And there was this woman called Ann Daniels, who was a mother to Toddler
Triplett, who I think his marriage wasn't going that well. She was not sportier outdoorsy at all.
She cried her way through the induction weekend. And it was all sorts of women like this.
And they did it. It was five teams of four who were selected, just from ordinary women.
And it was sponsored by McVitties. So they had 7,000 biscuits to get them through the trip.
7,000 biscuits. 7,000 biscuits. Yeah. Nothing else. And yeah, they made it. And now
there are a bunch of them are explorers. So Ann Daniels is one of Britain's leading explorers.
She's done 10 polar exhibitions now. She's amazing. Yeah. When they got back from their first trip,
they must have had a lot of diplomatic receptions and things to go to. They must have done a lot
of hobnobbing. That has cured all my ailments. Thank you. Dr Murray. I had mild eczema on my thumb,
and it's just disappeared. Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show. And that is Anna.
My fact this week is that the character of Don Corleone in the novel The Godfather was based
on the author's mother, which is great. Because when you watch The Godfather,
it's Marlon Brando. So it's a completely different character. But this is the guy who
wrote the book, Mario Puzo, said that he'd never met a gangster. A lot of people assumed because
it was kind of such a real portrayal that he'd been embedded in gang life for years. Never
met a gangster. And so he said, whenever The Godfather opened his mouth in my books, in my own
mind, I heard the voice of my mother. And he describes his mother as having the wisdom, the
ruthlessness, the unconquerable love for her family and for life itself. But his mother,
he was from an Italian immigrant family and lived in New York. And his father was committed for
schizophrenia quite early on in his life. So his mother raised seven children on her own,
and was clearly this another formidable woman. The side that he relates as his mother being similar
to is things like when the father was committed to the asylum, he could have returned. But the
mother made the decision not to let him out. Puzo said that she thought he'd be a burden on
the family. And he says that's a very mafia decision that she was like, no, keep him away.
Puzo also said that whenever he heard Brando speak the lines, he could hear his mother's voice.
He was like, ah, it's mum again. So like properly even in the movie interpretation of it. Yeah.
Okay, the other really, really weird thing about Mario Puzo, The Godfather was the second novel
he wrote based on his mother. He wrote one called The Fortunate Pilgrim. That was his second book.
And the main character in that is the woman called Lucia Santa. And he said that she is based on
his mum as well. Yeah, there was a publisher who read The Fortunate Pilgrim and said, look,
didn't really love the book. But that one tiny gangster character, that was good. Do you think
you could expand that? That's amazing. And he just went away and wrote The Godfather because of that.
The amazing thing was just how successful it was. Because his first two novels in total had earned him
$6,500. So his lifetime earning from books at that point was six and a half thousand.
I'm so glad things have changed with books.
It was really interesting his career because he had written these failed novels and he desperately
wanted to be an author. And it was only into his 40s that he then started writing The Godfather.
And that's where his life changed. And he knew that this was the last attempt. And if it didn't
work, he was going to do something else. And he tried to work for other people. Like he worked for
Stan Lee at one point when Stan Lee was doing comic books. And he was almost a comic book
writer, but he just couldn't make it work. But we could have had Mario Puzo Spiderman.
I'm happy with Mario Puzo, Godfather. I'll stick to that.
Yeah, I don't think being bitten by a radioactive horse is as thrilling.
We did have Mario Puzo Superman because he is the screenwriter behind Superman One and
Superman Two with Christopher Reed. Of course. Yeah.
But there's this great story that when he was writing screenplays post Godfather One and Two,
he sort of got anxiety realising, you know, I'm an author. I've adapted my books into
being screenplays. But I don't really know how to do this. So he bought a book on screenwriting.
And he said he had to stop reading it because in the first chapter, the book said, "Study Godfather One."
It's the model screenplay.
Sheprack with your novel, because he's used characters from real life in the latest one,
Kissing Emma. Are any family members going to look at that and go, hang on a sec?
No, I've written two novels and absolutely none of my characters or events have been based on
any persons in real life. Sheprack, why are you reading that off the card?
No, of course I have. What is it? They say that when there's a writer in the family,
there's a traitor in the family. There's a really grim part in Puzo's book that didn't
make the film. I can't remember how old I was when I read the book, but I was a kid or a young
teenager that absolutely mortified and distressed me. And it was a very early clue of what the
Hollywood scene was like way before Harvey Weinstein and all that. Do you know the part I
mean where there's a famous Hollywood producer and it's a tiny little blink and you'll miss it
detail where he sleeps with a very young girl of about 12 or 13 and it says, "Since his wife died,
his heart's been so broken that he can only get aroused by very, very young girls who were taken
to him to sleep with by their mothers in the hope that he'll put them in a film." And it describes
the scene where this young girl is being held up by her mum. That then makes you feel better about
the gruesome way that this producer is then treated. And obviously they left that out of the
film because it's not there. But even in the book, that's a part of it that when I first read it as
a young girl myself that really stuck with me. Is that what they do? Is that what happens in
Hollywood? It's just really interesting how that bit was really bypassed, but it was a massive
clue. And I wonder how much Puzo did know about the industry and how common knowledge that was.
I think we've blown this open in that Puzo had some kind of amazing prescience or psychic
powers because he was not involved in Hollywood at all, so he would not have known. But he could
see, he could see into gangsters, he could see into Hollywood. He saw this. Yeah, it's the
Nostradamus of the crime world. The cousin Nostradamus. Nice. They were pretty heavily involved
in the filming of The Godfather, The Mafia. It's this crazy story. They only allowed The Godfather
to be made on the grounds that the word mafia was never spoken. So this was because they wanted
to film in New York. They had to film in New York. They couldn't use a set. It wouldn't look real.
And the mob boss in New York at the time was this guy called Joe Colombo,
Sr. And he basically said to the producer, Albert Ruddy, "Okay, you can't mention The Mafia because
The Mafia doesn't exist, mate. We don't know, it's not a thing. And you're just going to give
Italian immigrants a bad name." This was while he was running the head of one of the biggest
gangs in New York. So he said, "Don't mention The Mafia. And also, we want all the proceeds
from the film premiere. Just the premiere." If we don't get them, something bad could happen.
Terrible. Well, it works. It works. And Albert Ruddy, he actually promised all the premiere
proceeds. Oh, my God. And awfully, the studio then went back on that promise, which must have been
a terrifying moment for Ruddy when they said, "We're not actually going to pay them."
And I'm going, "Okay, what's going to happen to me?" Good news is, we no longer need die for
the red carpet. It's just going to be naturally red, actually. So the thing I love about the
book as well is that Puzo wrote it from research, didn't know any gangsters, but he met gangsters
through the success of the book, who flat out refused to believe that he'd never been a gangster
himself. And then, mafiosi themselves, they started doing the cheek-to-cheek kisses based on the
movie. No one called each other a godfather before Puzo did. And then that became a mafia term.
The mafia basically are a tribute act to the novel The Godfather these days.
And if they've heard this, Andy, you are in serious trouble, tribute act to a movie.
Something else that came up in his book, which didn't make it in, did you guys read about this?
Well, you will have read it, Shabrak. This is the subplot about Connie's, so you know,
Connie, the daughter who has the wedding at the start, her maid of honour, Lucy Mancini,
who has a vagina that's too big. Yeah, absolutely bizarre plot. She's going out with Sonny,
if you remember the character of Sonny, but he can go out with her and it works because he's
quite well endowed. And then he doesn't last the first film even. And I think she struggles.
Anna, that's I forgot about that bit until you just said. And now, of course,
the memories of how I felt reading that, of coming flooding back to me. And I'm thinking,
perhaps I was probably too young to read that book, because she was she was a gorgeous woman.
She's described as a gorgeous woman, this big baggy Fanny. And it was it was so graphic.
It was like Bukowski style graphic. How funny that as a bloke, he sat down and he created this
character that needed a lot anyway. It's not it's not a female author, is it? Once you get to that
bit. It is not a female author. That woman has written that. What a bizarre subplot.
Thank God it wasn't relevant to the storyline. He didn't have to keep it in.
Doesn't seem like he could keep it in, frankly. I really hope you know how his publisher read the
previous book and spotted that tiny mafia character and went do a whole book about that.
I really hope you saw that character with that big Fanny lady. That's the next book.
Okay, that's it. That is all of our facts. Thank you so much for listening. If you would like to
get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts. I'm on @Shrieberland. Andy.
At Andrew Hunter M. Shaperak. At Shaperakor Sandy. And Anna. You can email a podcast at qi.com.
Yep. Or you can go to our group account, which is @NoSuchThing. Or you can go to our website,
NoSuchThing, asafish.com. All of our previous episodes are up there. Do check them out. Also,
do go to the website to find tickets to our upcoming tour. We start October this year.
We're going to do November and January. It's going to be a big old UK tour. See if we're coming
to a city near you. But most importantly of all, do go out and buy Shaperak's new book. It is called
Kissing Emma. It is out now. It is in shops. It is online. Okay, we'll be back again next week
with another episode. We'll see you then. Goodbye.