- Hi, everybody. - One, two, one, two. Oh, sorry, Andy. I was just testing my mic.
- Were you really good to test? - That's funny, because this happens every time we
do this show, isn't it? - Weird, isn't it? Yeah, it's as if it's a systematic campaign
to undermine me. - Or perhaps Andy should wait for us to test
our mics. - All right. Maybe I'll just wait forever.
And I won't read any of the juicy, juicy stuff we've got in the fridge.
- No, read it. We love it. We love it. Come on.
- Hello, everybody. Welcome to Drop Us Align. This is our audience feedback/microphone testing
segment. And we've got some cracking stuff. We've had Christmas in the inbox, so it's
been very festive in there. What are you guys, do you know what? What are you guys fancy
starting with? Do you fancy a correction? - Complaint. Complaint, please.
- Oh, great. Okay. Here's an eminent correction to start. This is from Noah Trudeau.
- Whoa. How closely related to the now disgraced foreign president?
- He doesn't say, but he is the assistant professor of economics at Troy University.
Is that in the 51st state of America? Or is it in... - It's in... It's in... It's actual
Troy University. So most of their studies are about, like, should we take this big wooden
horse in? Will it have a good effect on the city's economy? Long term, yes, probably.
No, no. Troy, Alabama. I didn't know that was Troy, Alabama.
- Oh, sorry. It's in America. No, I didn't know that.
- Well, Noah says, "Long term, listen, a first time emailer, always thought my first
email would be regarding economics, as I am a professor of economics. However, this is
about riding a television." - Oh, my God. Oh, yeah.
- Right. Now, I have waded through a lot of this in the fin box. In episode 563, Brisbane,
one of the facts related to the NEI-SS data from the United States, mentioned an injury
sustained by a person who, while riding on a TV, when he ran into a turkey, lost control
and ran into a tree. As someone who grew up in rural Alabama, this has to be a clerical
error. I've had multiple friends involved in ATV, Brackett's all-terrain vehicle accidents,
but have yet to account for anyone who has ridden a television into a tree. And amazingly,
so we got a lot of emails about this. He's the only one who found the original report
from 2014 and tracked down the specific entry about the 21-year-old man who was treated and
hospitalized after fracturing a vertebrae. - Well done, Noah.
- Very nice. I do remember, because on the night in Brisbane, when we did this, I was
reading this out, there was a bit of debate from the front row about whether or not it
was a TV or an ATV. And that didn't make it to the edit, but I since, when I got back,
I sometimes have dreams now about my facts and I wake up and I just have to get my phone
out and double check things at like 3 a.m. And the article I got it from was either a
Guardian or Independent in the UK, and it very specifically is ATV, a television.
- Wow.
- Yeah, so I read what I'd sourced correctly, but I should have gone to find the 2014 article
where a boy broke a vertebrae. - Wait, hang on. So the thing you read, it actually
put a space between A and TV and the Guardian article. That is the Guardian, isn't it?
- Well, one of those, I can bring it up while we're on here.
- The Guardian for international listeners is renowned for their typos in print. And
they're nicknamed the "Groundy Ed" and it's very funny.
- Very funny.
- Here's some.
- And I just quickly, I just, I really don't want to write in. I just casually dropped in
about Justin Trudeau being the ex-president and I don't want anyone to write in and explain
that he's the Prime Minister. I get it. Okay, it was just, I misspoke momentarily.
- Yeah, and can I also say my 51st state joke was just a bit of satire. I don't actually
think that America should take over Canada.
- Well, we don't know though. This doesn't go out for another week. It might be by the
time this airs.
- Maybe by the time this airs, Noah will have been installed as the kind of puppet vizier,
all right, Canada.
- I quite like that Noah studies at Troy. You've got a famous wooden object going into
Troy and then you have a man who built a wooden structure to, it's, it's, it's a lot of, there's
a lot going on there.
- He probably, he probably gets that all the time. I sometimes worry we're too obvious
with our jokes about people with great names. I don't think he will get that one all the
time. That's brilliant.
- All right, here's Amelia Brownstein. Brownstein, Brownstein. It's Amelia, right?
- Is it Brownstein?
- It's not Brownstein. Although this is relevant to the, to the subject of Amelia's email.
She said, I have worked in veterinary medicine for some years and the key takeaway from this,
I want to make clear, do not pull string coming out of your animals butt.
- Oh.
- Oh, okay. Good. Public service.
- Yeah.
- Did we say that you should?
- Do not pull string.
- So this is the other thing.
- I always thought, like my cat doesn't meow very much, but I thought if there was a string
there that I pulled, she might go meow, meow, meow, meow, meow, like a toy.
- Was that the thing on the show? Did we talk about a dog swallowing tinsel or something?
- We talked about a dog swallowing tinsel and Dan wondered whether there has ever been
an instance where a dog had tinsel coming out of its mouth and its rectum at the same
time.
- That's right.
- And you could turn it into a spit roast.
- Well, no, just you can put the dog on the tree and say, that is the tinsel.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah. Well, anyway, look, Amelia makes very clear.
This is really bad. It risks bowel strangulation, necrosis, gut contents leaking through the
body cavity, which is bad news bears, she says. So don't do it.
- So are you just supposed to leave a string hanging out of your dog's arse for its whole
life?
- No. You're meant to contact a professional who will, I think, deal with it, which goes
into a lot of detail about, you know, like twisting bowels and rather upsetting stuff.
But basically, if you are lucky enough to have access to an endoscope, you always, always
need to palpate the entire bowel. So just remember that. I think that's the take away.
Palpate is a massaging along the length of something, you know, a bit like palpitations,
but not quite. So anyway, be very, very careful.
- Okay.
- Noted.
- I reckon if you own an endoscope, you probably already know all this stuff.
- Yeah, you're absolutely right. Can you do a self-endoscopy? I bet you can, can't you?
Of course you can.
- Well, in theory, it's possible for sure. But...
- Is it recommended?
- No, I don't think so. I think get a professional, I would say.
- Have they ever done a TV show where it's an endoscope going all the way through someone's
body? Like, it's the journey of a piece of food?
- I think it feels like that has been done. Yeah. I think that would be good.
- Wasn't that what the Millennium Dome was? Do you remember in the Millennium Dome, you
went through a whole, a person's digestive system, didn't you?
- Did you?
- I thought there was, I think you could go through the whole human body. That's like
an endoscope.
- Yeah, you did. But that wasn't the same as what Andy was saying.
- No, I'm pitching a TV show.
- It's not exactly the same, no.
- I think Endoscopy Live is a good TV show. And I think we all know TV is in the doldrums
and need to make cheap TV these days.
- It's in the shit.
- It's in the shit. You could do a different episode for every species. That's, like, immediate
100-year commission.
- All right.
- Who would, which would be the human you would go for? Because if you're doing one
episode for each species, you only have one chance to choose the perfect human to put
a camera up.
- That's got to be Atombrough, right?
- Atombrough.
- What? He doesn't eat the animals he observes.
- That's the misconception, Anna. He does. He says, "I have to know."
Okay. Here is an email from Andrew Conlon. Listen to the most recent bonus app. This
is Drop the Line on Drop the Line.
- The bit about specific tannoy instructions in M&S.
- Oh, yeah. Code 4.
- Someone stood a poo in the changing room? Was that it?
- Yeah.
- Yeah. It reminded me of a specific code we had in a call centre. When we trained new
staff, we had to give them the specific hand gesture to use if someone called the phone
line with a bomb threat. I can't remember exactly the gesture, but it evolved standing
or making a fist. It was presumably quite confusing because it makes it look like you're
celebrating.
- Yeah. You've just landed a deal.
- Yeah. I didn't give it much thought. I just assumed it was something all call centres
did. Only listening to last week's bonus did I tweak it. It might be because we worked
in Northern Ireland.
- Oh.
- Big fan.
- Oh, God.
- There you go.
- There's a chance.
- Yeah.
- What gesture would you use, Andy?
- For a bomb.
- Let's say we're on a call right now. We're on a Zoom call. I don't think it's too much
behind the scenes to say. If there's a bomb threat and you need to let us know, but you
can't tell anyone out loud because you don't want to scare the other elves because you're
in the QA office, what would you do?
- I would do the classic. I would do my head exploding.
- Yeah. But the problem is you work at QI, and that people do that all the time when
they're told that you're right.
- You're right.
- I feel like Andy's the worst person for this because he also comes from an improv background.
So he would just be, I need to, you know, he'd be trying to use all the tricks that
no one would know.
- A suggestion for a kind of explosive, please.
- Well, we didn't have to keep it secret, but we have had a bomb threat interrupt us
during a recording, and it ends, it ends one of the fish shows from very long ago. And so
what happened there was Alex just came through the door and went, we need to leave, there's
a bomb.
- With a belt strapped for himself, he said, I want to be on this show more.
- I think what happened there, was it not that someone rang up and said that there's
a bomb threat in your streets because they'd seen it on the news or something. And Alex
looked out of the window and sure enough, there was no one there, apart from a load
of police. And then he came and told us.
- Yeah, it was all cornered off. And we just, they, they was...
- It wasn't a real bomb.
- It was a car that had been left there for a while.
- Yeah, because my old, my old, my other, private eye, we have had a World War II bomb at the
end of our street. And again, the whole street had to be evacuated and, you know...
- Who did you upset? Go ring.
- Yeah, yeah. We're up to the minute with our sasa. We're constantly having to go with
that girling guy.
- Carina Diazza writes, great name. Just a quick one to add to the story of one of your
listeners told about becoming sleepy when listening to fish. What a beginner. I've been listening
to fish every single night since 2015, which awarded me the incredible skill of using the
podcast as a general anaesthetic. So much so, Carina writes, I listened to it during
the labor and birth of both my children when I am at the dentists and I use the Stephen
Fry episode in particular to manage my fear of flying.
- Wow. We could sell this to the NHS then or something.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Cool.
- That's a good idea. That can go with endoscopy live.
- They're, I don't know that they would work. Distraction does work against pain. There was
the thing about if you swear a lot, then it stops things being as painful. So if you put
your hand into some really, really cold water, you can keep it in for longer if you're swearing
all the time. So maybe the person who listens just really hates us and is listening going,
that was fucking easy. That's what gets rid of the pain. I don't know.
- That's true. There's the Billy Connolly study we spoke about once as well, where people
were played Billy Connolly while their hand was in ice cold water, I think something like
that as well. And they could resist it for longer.
- He's very sweary.
- Well, they were distracted.
- Oh, sorry. They were distracted. It wasn't that he was swearing like a proxy swearing.
Him swearing makes it easier for them to stand the pain. No. Okay. Got it. Got it.
- Wait. So James is saying that you put your hand in ice cold water to withstand pain. And
then you're saying you have to listen to Billy Connolly so close.
- No, I'm saying this.
- Is that ice cold water?
- I'm saying there's two different...
- So you have to listen to Billy Connolly.
- There's two different...
- What?
- I don't know. I know. But we're saying that basically if you're in pain, you have to put
your hand in ice cold water.
- No, no, no, no, no.
- If you're able to do that, you have to listen to Billy Connolly.
- No, no, no, no.
- Does that know what you were saying?
- No, I wasn't. So the way that you... If you're in an experiment and you want to put someone
in pain, you can't punch them in the face. So the way that you do it is you put their
hand in ice cold water to make it painful.
- I see. I thought you were saying that could distract you. If you're in labor, dunk your
hand in ice cold water and that pain will distract you from the coming birth pain.
- You look up, you look up, doctor takes off his mask. It's Billy Connolly. That's a good
distraction from the pain, but it's hard to roll out nationally.
- It is, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah. Anyway, thank you, Karina. She says she does also enjoy the content while conscious.
Here's this very medically themed show. This is an anonymous email. Just with the relevant...
Actually, it's not irrelevant. It's just a good anecdote, but they have to remain anonymous
because of the nature of the anecdote, which is what drew me to it.
- This one really needs to stay private, says the writer. Don't even mention my forename
if you read it out.
- My son donated stem cells to a cancer patient, a woman in her 60s. The donation process was
anonymous, but after her recovery, she requested to meet my son.
- Okay.
- When they met, she asked him if he has a seafood allergy because she has developed
one since the transplant.
- His part is, we don't know if he has a seafood allergy or not because we are strictly
kosher. So not only do we not know, we likely never will.
- That's interesting.
- That's so interesting. I'm surprised you didn't have to check a box or something on
a form when you fill that out.
- Yeah, I guess it's not.
- As far as I remember, because I read a story about how someone inherited a peanut allergy,
so you could basically transfer that, and they weren't 100% sure what was going on.
It's like a science that's being looked into at the moment. It's my memory of it. Maybe
they know more now.
- I think that's right.
- Do you remember one of you guys was sitting at the table with me in New Zealand when a
lady came up and told us a story about her daughter having had a transplant, and is this
ringing any bells? It's like a blood transfusion, which meant that when you do a test on her,
she has different DNA.
- She comes up as a different gender, I think, isn't she?
- Yeah, she comes up as a different gender.
- So that's usually a bone marrow transplant.
- That's what it was.
- Yeah.
- How fascinating.
- That's good. We've had loads of emails about the... Do you remember we did that section
on the Spanish language, and they don't have a word for the differentiate between afternoon
and evening?
- Sydney Opera House, that was.
- Parade.
- Yeah.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Did the Opera House.
- Oh, yeah.
- As Dad would say.
- Dad does his sexy stuff.
- Dad does stop saying it like that.
- Well, we've got... Honestly, we've had almost as many emails about this as we did about
writing on ATV, and that was a lot. But these are more varied. So Enrique Duran writes, "You
didn't mention the hilarious and useful concept we rely on. Tare de noche." So Tare day is
afternoon slash evening, night is noche. And that sort of means evening, because you say
nos vemos por la tarde, and you don't know... You can't do the afternoon, but you can do
the evening. But you can say, "You're solo puede por la tarde noche. I'm available in
the afternoon evening."
- It's funny how that Spanish accent started off really good, and then went west country
right at the end.
- Tare de noche. Oh, yeah. So that's a loophole there. You could just say the afternoon night.
- Yeah.
- We'll say, "Oh, it's the evening." But Malen Unden from Sweden writes, "We're equally
disturbed that in English you call everything before lunch the morning. Whereas for us,
there is a split between morning, morgon, and for noon, formidag."
- Again, the west country came out there at the end.
- It felt like the ringzish morgon.
- For morgon, formidag. So morning is morgon, and for noon, formidag.
- Well, presumably that's just a few hours before noon. Like, when's the casting?
- Right. I think that must be it. I don't know where the gutter goes.
- It's probably, this is in Sweden, right?
So in the summer, their mornings start really early so that you might as well split it up
into more sections, whereas no one here gets up before nine o'clock.
- What time do they get up there, Anna?
- In Sweden?
- Yeah.
- I don't know, but if the sun comes up at three, you're probably going to get up at
3.30, aren't you?
- You've got paradins, don't you?
- Well, I mean, if you don't.
- No, they don't.
- Yeah, they don't.
- You've got the Swedes.
- It's weird.
- And Malyn just adds this little final kick. Another issue with English is that you lack
separate words for thin and warm socks.
- Oh.
- Not necessary for us, mostly.
- I mean, you could just use the adjective, cut you.
- Yeah.
- Well, yeah, yeah.
- I guess that's what they say about afternoon and evening, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- You could just use the afternoon night adjective to distinguish night from afternoon night.
- We all manage, don't we?
- That's the new code.
- Everyone gets by. Yeah, yeah, yeah. But I do think that's cool. Actually, I tried
on our socks. Do you remember the fan made us some socks recently?
- Oh, yeah.
- But I wore my moss green socks. They were fantastic.
- Were they?
- They were so good.
- Mine are really good.
- Yeah, really cozy.
Anyway, we've had something about Dan. Do you want to hear this?
- Yeah, sure.
- It's good. Jamie Lerner Brecher. Loving the Taub Recordings. On the most recent episode,
you all, as usual, made fun of Dan's accent and called his Spanish accent racist.
- Can I just say, I think it was the general feel of the room
of 3,000 people in Sydney who thought it was racist, rather than us individually.
- Yes. Whereas I thought it was funny. So, yeah, but you do think racist things are
funny, aren't you?
- Well, that's not the point of the email, I guess.
- When Dan does his actually racist accents, we cut them out. That's the thing.
- Don't do that.
- We wouldn't have left it in if it was one of his really racist ones.
- That's true.
- That's not true.
- It's not true.
- Sorry.
- I can't say that's true.
- That's not true. To clarify, that's a joke.
- Really funny one.
Jamie writes, "As someone who speaks Spanish, you are really missing out on making fun of
Dan's actual Spanish accent. When he gave the translation for 'tos', 'de los pies',
I had to listen to the English translation to figure out what the hell he was saying.
I had literally no idea what he could possibly have said in Spanish, and I speak it. I think
for something to come across as racist, there has to be a sort of idea of what culture or
race the person is making fun of, and I can say in full honesty, I would have had zero
idea that Dan was trying to speak Spanish. I played this part of the show back for my
mum, and she had a good laugh about it too.
- Exaggerated.
- It goes on. Before now, the worst Spanish accent I had heard was from Giles Brandrith,
but Dan brought it to new heights.
- Your Honor, I couldn't possibly be racist because I'm completely ignorant about the
race I'm talking about.
- So there you go. Off the hook.
- That's great.
- Thank God I got my accent lessons from Giles Brandrith.
- Oh, dear. A bit of sad news now, I'm afraid. We've got Sad Fish Corner. Emilia Victoria
writes, "I was just listening to your 500th episode and went to look for pictures of Cassius
to find out the awful news. Do you remember Cassius?"
- The crocodile.
- Bingo.
- Oh, yeah.
- He was a big, big crocodile.
- Big one.
- Yeah. Biggest ever. Or no, we didn't know how old he was. Is that right?
- That's right.
- Or how big he was.
- We didn't know how big he was because he was so big, no one could get close enough
to measure it.
- Well, we now know how big he is because he's died, sadly.
- That was on the news, wasn't it, when he died quite extensively, I think.
- We were on tour at the time, so I missed it.
- How big was he?
- He was very big. He was 5.48 meters long.
- Wow.
- And apparently they're waiting on necropsy results to know his age.
- Was he the one who was in Crocodile Dundee?
- I think, I don't know.
- I can't remember.
- I can't remember. Or was he in Live and Let Die, where, you know, Roger Moore jumps
over the crocodile. I don't remember.
- He doesn't jump over. He walks on his head as a stepping stone.
- Oh.
- Have you seen that scene, James? It's one of the greatest movie scenes ever.
He needs to get across a lake of crocodiles and all their heads are sticking out.
And he literally, like a Takashi Castle style challenge, runs across their heads and gets
to the other side. It's incredible.
- So were they both real crocodiles in that scene?
- Yeah, they're real.
- And it was real Roger Moore?
- It wasn't real Roger Moore.
- Oh.
- Roger Moore was in his mid-70s by the time this film was filmed.
It's a very brave stuntman.
- Am I right about that, Andy? That scene?
- Yeah.
- I feel like I'm making that up now.
- You can see the outtakes where the crocodiles are lashing around and they nearly get him.
- And he falls in at one point, doesn't he? Yeah, he kind of goes down.
- Does he actually stand on real-life crocodiles?
- Yeah.
- Oh, okay, but it's different time, isn't it?
- He's moving quickly across the... Oh, come on. You're not saying you wouldn't film that today, would you?
- What? Stomping on crocodiles?
- He's walking across their backs. They're very big and powerful.
- They like it.
- It's not a monster.
- They like it. The oldest excuse.
- Maybe you wouldn't today. Maybe you wouldn't today.
- They were asking for it. Did you see what they were wearing?
- Okay. I think we need to move on quickly.
There's a little bit of parish business from Gina Chadderton who created the Zine that we talked about a few episodes ago.
There's a little magazine of us. And she said, "I'm very glad you weren't all horribly offended by the Zine."
I think you were, Anna, but that doesn't matter.
- Oh, well, I've quit. Yeah, I handed in my notice. It's three months.
- And we gave it a little shout-out. And anyway, she has popped a free to download digital version of the Zine on her website.
So it's georgerexcomics.com. George like the name George. Rex like Rex. Exactly.
And it's on there and it's free to download. And it's good. It's funny.
- Yeah. It'll let you do a little quiz to decide which member of NoSageSingersFish you are.
- Yeah. And there's an episode name generator. It's brilliant. It's really good. So thank you very much, Gina.
We've had an email from a record holder who had a record that we talked about a few episodes ago.
Oh, you guys actually, this is one of the ones I sadly had to miss. This is from Colton J. Proveas.
Colton is a previous record holder of the longest baton.
- Oh. Wow.
- Set in Mountain View, California by the Googler Orchestra. And the baton was 4.92 meters.
And that was the one that was broken, I believe. And they apparently are determined to get it back.
The guy who made it Emmanuel Pacheco. Pacheco.
- What happened to it? Oh, get the record back. Sorry. They didn't have the baton stolen.
- Oh, sorry. He says we likely won't challenge the new one that Brown have won.
- Okay. That's confusing. That's a confusing pair of bits of information you gave us.
- No, sorry. I hadn't read. Sometimes I don't read all the way to the end. I like to surprise myself.
Although apparently Emmanuel does have an extension long enough to regain the record.
So it feels like that's just something to wield.
- I mean, if you just get two of these really long ones and sellotate them together, is that not just going to win?
- I think it would be fine. It just has to be used to conduct a piece of music. It mustn't break during the performance.
- Oh, there was all things about the bend. You know, there's a lot of details.
- That's true. Yes, but he does say it doesn't need to be a single solid piece.
The one we use broke down into multiple pieces so it could be shoved in a ski bag and carried across the US-Canada border.
- Smuggle them. Your ass would not be.
- When you say US-Canada border at time of recording.
- Sorry. Yes. That's obviously a historical border which used to exist.
There's also Dave Taylor writes, "I know the subject of this email scenes worrying and believe me it is.
I hate to open old wounds, but this is in regards to bassoon gate."
- Oh, Jesus Christ.
- Jesus. I do love it.
- Go back to the first drop of the line if you need. Anyway, context.
In 1999, the pianist Maria-Juaul Perez. I presume you're a fan of Dan.
- Yeah, I've seen. I've watched her.
- Have you?
- Well, I know. This is a thing that I use as evidence where she can't remember the piece, right? Is that what's going to be around?
- Oh my God, have you? Have you?
- Andy. Andy. Dan is now the world expert on this subject.
- Absolutely. The amount of correspondence he's had.
- I'm so sorry, Dan.
- You're absolutely right. No, sorry. It was an open rehearsal. So it was like a rehearsal with an audience.
And she had prepared a concerto, but the orchestra started it and she realized she had learnt the wrong piece.
And after a moment of panic, she managed to play the correct concerto completely from memory.
And Dave writes, "This is evidence that classical musicians can perform complicated pieces of music from memory just as long as they put some bloody effort in."
So there we go. So that's evidence on your side, Dan.
- It's really worth watching, by the way, everyone listening. She's panicking like crazy and the conductor's next to her talking her down,
just going, "You know it. You know this piece. Come on. You can do it."
And then the moment comes and she just has to lean into it and it comes out perfectly. It's really beautiful.
- Wow.
- Yeah, it's great.
- He pulls an enormous baton out of his ass.
- Oh, dear. Thank you so much, everybody, for writing. We love getting the emails.
It's podcast@qi.com. If something has happened in your life or you have a bit of bonus information that's relevant to what we've talked about,
please do write in because it's great fun to chat.
Bye.
- Great.
- Did you tell them where to send the emails?
- I did say podcast@qi.com. Glad to know you've paid scrupulous attention.
- Sorry. You know what? There was a little bit of butter on my wire and I wondered where it came from.
And I remembered that I had a slice of toast before we came on.
- That is nice to know. It is also a bit tragic to know how easily the audience's attention can be rested away from me.
Like a small piece of butter on a wire. It's sufficient to...that'll do it.
- I've been in constant pain for 12 years and nothing you've said has helped it.
- That's because you've got Tinsel coming out of your arse, James. You've got to stop pulling it.
- Eventually I'll reach the end. It's like the worst magic trick ever.
- Your clowning show is very, very blue, isn't it?
Right. Bye.
[music]