(phone ringing)
- Hey, I don't want that.
I don't want that.
(upbeat music)
- Hi.
- Hello, Man.
- Hi, guys.
Welcome to Drop of the Line.
And welcome you to Drop of the Line.
Patreon's and Apple subscribers,
because you're all hearing this,
and some of you are able to see it too.
- Yeah.
- So there might be some physical bits of business
we throw in, and it might take a shirt off,
and it might, so welcome to Drop of the Line.
I'll fortnightly audience feedback special.
We've been promoted.
(laughing)
- This is huge, the network won more of us.
- It's great stuff.
- Wonderful.
- I mean, we did the promoting.
- Who do we have to sleep with together?
(laughing)
- Each other, it turned out.
- The worrying thing is when we get canceled.
- Oh yeah.
(laughing)
- I don't you worry, there's plenty of stuff in here
that is going to get us canceled.
- What would you say about the mailbox this month?
- It's been absolutely bulging.
- Right.
- I've had to print two separate documents.
- A bunch.
(laughing)
- Has anyone ever told you about copy paste?
You can put two things in one document.
- Yeah.
- There's just so much.
- Have you heard about font sizes as well?
- So hello, welcome to Drop of the Line.
We're going to do the audience feedback,
and we got some great stuff.
- Yeah.
- Let's do it.
- Let's start off with just with an,
and I'm actually, actually this is off the back
of last month's Drop of the Line.
You and Taylor writes, on the October Drop of the Line,
James stated that he did not think
that the song Chocolate Salty Balls
got to number one in the charts.
Just to correct this, it was indeed a number one single.
It missed out on the coveted Christmas number one,
1998.
- This is by Scales.
- With.
- To become one.
- Goodbye.
- Okay, bye.
(laughing)
- However, it would reach number one,
the following week, where it remained for just one week
before being knocked off the top spot by.
- Oh, good grief.
- What year are we talking?
- 1998, and now maybe 1999.
- Smash mouth?
- Steps.
- Oh, I said I've got it.
Okay, 1998 steps.
Oh, stump or chain reaction.
- I can't beat a slash tragedy.
- Really?
- Oh, wow.
- Huh.
- I'm verified.
- I'm verified this.
- And how did Smash mouth do?
- You and doesn't relate, I'm so sorry.
So there you go.
It was the biggest selling Christmas number two
since Wams last Christmas.
- Wow.
- And Christmas number two brings us to Mr. Hanky,
the Christmas poo.
- Perfect.
- There we go.
- No, I do remember, like I remembered very clearly
the time of Chuck the Salty Balls when it came out.
I was working in a hotel and it was lots of Christmas parties
and we used to play it every single night.
And I remember really hoping that it would get to number one
and then being beaten by the Spice Girls for Christmas.
And then of course, no one really cares
about the first week after Christmas number one.
No one really thinks about that much.
- What a shame.
- It's sort of like the new year.
It's like this bringing in the year.
- Yeah, but what happened?
- The 12th night number one.
It's very important.
- What happens is everyone,
the amount of money people used to spend on singles
the week before Christmas,
it clips every other week in the year.
And then when you got to the first week in January,
quite a lot of sort of rock bands and indie bands
will bring singles out because they knew
that no one was buying music then
and they could get higher in the charts.
- That's the time.
- Done with the days of sales.
- Family days.
- Yeah, they were.
- Happy days, well.
- Apologies, you and.
- Yeah, sorry about that.
- I'm sorry about that.
And in fairness, Dan, you actually messaged me
and said, yeah, you got that wrong James.
- Well, and because it was part of the last duel.
Yeah, so the issue, and this is just for all the listeners,
sometimes if we get something very slightly wrong in a duel,
you know, what do you do, chop the whole segment?
That was a big segment or callbacks all the way through.
And so I knew someone would write in
that we could readdress it on a further one.
So, yeah.
- Very clever.
- Yeah, it was an unfortunate one.
I don't ever want to do that again.
- Look what's happened.
James is having a sit here, defend himself.
- We're daggers drawn.
- No, I don't know if you remember.
We had Ella Alshamahi on a few weeks ago.
- Oh, yeah.
- Of course.
- How would we forget?
- I don't know.
- I don't know if this tickles the old brain bug.
(laughing)
We have one of dad's old friends and someone we've all known
for many years.
- She won.
- She was great.
But she led to a lot of correspondence.
- Okay.
- So about half the correspondence from that show
is about Hobbits.
- Oh.
- 'Cause we mentioned the homo floresiensis
who are clearly Hobbits.
- They were giving the nickname Hobbits.
- Yeah.
- And yeah.
- So I'm gonna jump in here and suggest
that the correspondence might not be so much
about the ancient hominids and more about the tedious novels.
- It is universally about the tedious novels.
(laughing)
So correction, this isn't, I'm actually from David Spraklin,
who writes, the idea that Hobbits have big feet
is a fan idea not supported or rejected really
by Tolkien's actual words.
So he's just silent on the size of their feet.
They are hairy and the only one whose feet are mentioned
is smegol, but he was likely a store
which isn't a race of Hobbits from the Shire.
Those would be half-fits and fallow hides, okay?
So can we just please put this to bed, this myth.
- That they had big feet.
- Yeah.
It just doesn't say, but apparently it's just a fan idea
that's taken off.
- Did the novels say that they had big penises
and people have said, you know what?
They say about people with big penises.
(laughing)
- Tolkien is very clear in his concerning Hobbit section.
- Yeah.
- They're all packing.
- It's a lot dirtier than we realized.
- We've had a couple more.
We've had one from Dan Connolly,
who writes about the lawsuits over the word Hobbit,
which is, you know.
- Yeah, 'cause it's okay.
So the guy who effectively discovered the homophlerentices,
or however that's pronounced,
then called it Hobbit and went on a tour
and the estate got in touch saying,
you can't call it a Hobbit.
- So that's right, isn't it?
- Yes.
- Well, the people who did Dungeons and Dragons,
those books, they had to change,
they put in Hobbit and End and Balrog and Warg,
and they had to change all those.
- 'Cause the estate, I presume, was still pretty active.
- It's interesting,
'cause all the words have been invented prior to,
or at least Hobbit was certainly used prior to--
- This is what Dan Connolly says.
- The Hobbit is in a list of fairies from the 1850s,
that Warg, only Balrog of those,
is an invention of Tolkien arguably.
And that list of fairies includes names for Will of the Wisps.
- You know, the sort of,
phantom lights in marshes, or whatever.
Names for them include Melch Dick,
Sponks, Dicker Tuesdays, and Meg with the Wads.
- That's very funny.
I must have said this on the show,
but Sponk used to mean just any kind of light.
- Hey. - Oh yeah.
- Because in Ulysses, I think,
or at least in one of James Joyce's books,
I was reading it, and when my daughter was born
to try and stay awake, which did not work very well.
But it says that he created a Sponk and passed it to me
or something like that when he's lighting a cigarette.
- So Sponky does feel like you're saying
you've got like a bright energy about you.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
Sorry, why don't you try and keep yourself awake
when your daughter's born rather than trying
to desperately claw back every second of sleep?
- Because my wife was sleeping at that period,
and I needed to stay awake to make sure
that my child didn't die.
And so one of us was always awake.
- And you thought I'll read one of the most
legendarily difficult and boring texts.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it was a mistake.
What am I going to say?
- Were we doing that fact, that week?
- No, no. - Right, we just had it in the shelf, right?
- No, I'm the same.
When my first child was born,
I read the phone book to try and keep myself awake.
It just didn't work.
- It's so night.
- How is your child, Aaron?
(laughing)
- Aaron A. Aaronson.
- He's doing great.
- So another thing on the Hobbit Penguin thing.
You remember there were giant penguins and tiny cows
and miniature people and all that.
We've had an email from Thomas Halliday,
the paleontologist.
- Oh, yeah.
- I know.
- Of the author?
- Yes.
- Of other lands?
- I don't know which books he's written, but it might be, yeah.
But no, it is him.
- Yeah.
- He says, yes, there were big penguins in the past.
And he emphasizes were.
And frankly, they could have given Kylie a piggyback.
- Oh, okay.
- As we said, they were about the height of Kylie,
the giant penguin.
- Yeah, yeah.
So that was a little bit of a mistake, I would say,
but I know of a generalization,
which we said that they were the size of penguins,
by which we meant they were 1.1 meters tall,
which is about the same as a giant penguin,
or an emperor penguin,
which is the one you think of when you say penguins.
But actually, of course, there's loads of different types
of penguins and they come in all sorts of different sizes.
- And I think Kylie Minogue is taller than 1.1 meters,
but that is really, really, really small, isn't it?
- That would be small, yeah.
That's in fact the height of my three-year-old.
- She has been 1.1 meters at some point in her life,
Kylie Minogue.
- Yes.
- She's been all heights up to at least five foot.
- Up to where she is now.
- Yes.
- And maybe a bit beyond,
because as you get older, you do shrink a bit, don't you?
- What a great,
'cause she started so young in her career
that is an actual unit of measurement,
Kylie Minogue in 1976.
You know, Kylie Minogue in 1993.
- No, she did start as a three-year-old though.
- Even when she came on neighbor, she was a teenager, right?
So she would have been relatively adult.
- Yeah, that's true.
- She'd have done the bulk of her growing.
- Okay, you know, the Olsen twins, you know.
- They'd have had to throw it in as a plotline otherwise,
like, "Oh, Kylie's getting bigger isn't she?"
- You know.
(laughing)
- That's true.
- We have had an email complaining about you saying Kylie Minogue.
- I know, I know.
- But I say stay true to your lights.
So anyway, thank you Thomas.
It was a good point.
Oh, there was the largest ones are estimated
of being about two meters.
- Oh wow.
- But they're just based on fragments.
So you've got to scale up from the fragments.
There's a bit imprecise, but.
- Okay.
- And also he answers, "Why there aren't giant humans?"
- Oh yes, I've always wondered this.
- He says, "We are the giant humans."
- Oh yeah.
- 'Cause all the others are little.
- Oh, we're giants.
- Yeah.
- We are the giants.
That's very cool.
So the next time you feel, you know, disempowered.
- Yeah.
- Just remember, you're actually a giant.
- Does that mean, in a million years' time,
all the humans will be hobbit sized
and they'll find our bones and think,
oh, they used to be giants.
- Yeah.
- Interesting.
- They might have been giants.
(laughing)
- It was a band.
- It's a band.
(laughing)
- How does they do in 1998?
- It's the perfective version of the imperfective.
They might be giants.
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- They will have had to be giants.
It's their future perfect.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- They would love that.
If they're listening, they'll love that.
'Cause they're very clever band, aren't they?
They're always doing clever things.
- They are, very clever.
- They're very cool Thomas Aladay, he's a great author.
- Yes.
- Well, and actually, while we're on height,
but still in the Ella episode,
we talked about sci-fi, Elliot Boyd Smith writes,
as a six foot nine inch, 16 year old,
who will likely grow even more,
I am very used to the multitude of comments
about my height in almost all aspects of my life.
However, as an avid fish fan and club fish member,
I did not expect to be so viciously attacked
by the members of my favorite podcast.
- Oh, because Ella said that all the tall people die.
- Oh, okay.
- In episode 601, while discussing mundane sci-fi,
Dan, quite randomly, shared the fact
that the writer of Jurassic Park was six foot nine.
He then proceeded to call him a dinosaur,
sparking Elliot to tell me I'm going to die
earlier than everyone else.
(laughing)
I'm sure all your other freakish listeners
were just as shocked by the unprovoked attack from Dan,
especially considering most of us are literal bigfoot's.
(laughing)
Thanks from the tall community, Elliot.
- There you go.
- One light the hobbit.
(laughing)
- I feel that in, it wasn't a random fact.
It was connected, we had mentioned dinosaurs earlier,
and so I was, I was relating to that.
- But, I thought that was, come on,
Michael Crichton comes in the room,
taller than the velociraptor in the movies.
Are you kidding me?
- He struggled with the door handle
from it on the outside, but he just couldn't imagine.
- Your glass of water is wobbling.
Oh, Crichton's on his way.
(laughing)
- Well, you've done it again.
- This is a polity corner, not come up with extra jokes.
We didn't think of last time cornering.
(laughing)
- My point is it wasn't an attack.
There's no attack on the people.
- Can I, and this is a possibility
that we can put a photo up that's on my phone.
- Oh yeah.
- So we did a show with Richard Usman recently,
and we got a member of the audience to come up on stage
and be against him in a quiz, okay.
Now, Richard Usman is six foot seven, yeah.
The member of the public was also around six foot seven.
You two are taller than me.
You're above that six foot six, one, something like that.
I'm about five, 10, five, 11.
So I'm not that small, but I'm just an average height.
But something about the photo where you two are in the front,
and then Usman and this guy are stood right next
to me, I look like a literal puppet.
I look so small in that photo.
- So funny.
- I've seen that one.
- I've seen it either.
- They put that up.
- That's great.
- I got measured last night, and full body liked, yeah.
I thought that I was six foot one,
and this lady last night said that I was six foot.
And it was a real...
- Well, as you get older, you do shrink.
- So in your four days, do you shrink?
- Oh yeah.
- Have I prematurely started shrinking?
- I think, I saw this fact on Oprah when I was about 12,
so it's probably not true,
that every year after you're about 35,
you shrink a sixteenth of an inch.
- Right.
- Okay.
- Really?
- How interesting.
- Yeah, and again, like heavy, heavy quote marks around me.
- Well, I haven't measured myself for a while,
so maybe, 'cause I am considerably over 35.
Maybe I am that small.
- Right, yeah.
- So maybe, why are you getting so...
- We had to, I mean, for now we had to get our medicals done
for a thing for the house.
We were doing a remorage, so...
- All right.
- So she did my height, she did my weight,
she asked my my trouser size, so...
- What kind of mortgage device are in this?
- Sorry.
Before we work out whether you are on a 5.5% or a 6%,
can you tell me if you dress to the left?
- On the right, so...
(laughing)
- Yeah, sorry, you fall for another local apartment.
It just happens time and again.
Well, she was very nice, me and my wife both liked her.
She was a fiora, lovely lady.
But she said, so she got all my measurements,
and now I was in the room with Ben.
And she said to Phinella, so she did her height,
did her weight, and then she said breast size.
And Phinella went, "Oh."
And then told her, "Fold her a brass size, right?"
I won't say what it was, but she just told her a brass size.
And this woman staring at her, just went,
I said, "Dress size."
(laughing)
Breast size is the next question down matter.
Right now, breast size.
(laughing)
- Thanks so much, I'm not a mortgage thing.
My very nice mortgage device,
that David has never once asked me for my inseam.
- I'm sorry.
- Okay, I'll have to check that out.
- You too.
- Yeah.
I gave him my urine.
(laughing)
- I'm sorry, she said.
- You did when she told you what you'd be paying
for the next two years.
(laughing)
- What's actually happened here is that Phinella
has got a life insurance policy out on you
and told you it's a mortgage thing.
- Really wearingly, she has three out on me.
It's absolutely true.
And you know me, I'm the kind of guy
that's gonna die in a really stupid way.
It's just gonna look like she had me killed
and she's gonna go to jail.
It's just gonna look suspicious as hell.
- Damn.
- Stunning.
- Anyway, it's absolutely stunning.
- A bit of protein in my urine.
Gotta get that checked out.
(laughing)
Do we have more?
- We've got more.
- Cool.
- This, oh, this is another room actually.
Do you remember we talked about wasps?
- Yes.
- Need more.
- We talked about wasps.
(laughing)
- These small yellow insects.
- Okay, yeah.
- Yes, we did.
And it was also on the yellow show.
- Yeah.
- And we discussed how they were different from bees,
for instance. - Yes.
- And Andy said that in the summer,
they switched from going after ham to jam
or the other way around.
- Ham to jam, ham to jam.
- So this is, I'm so sorry James,
I think this might be something you said.
This is a lovely email from Aspen Kennedy.
- Great name.
Aspen Kennedy.
- Yeah, it's a really good name.
- Pretty cool.
- Yeah.
- A long time listen, a big fan of the podcast.
I do want to pull you up on one thing you said
in this week's episode, however.
You said.
- Love that.
I love it when that just isn't.
- Yeah, I'm putting the tone in there.
But anyway, you said that mud-dorber wasps
present a hazard to airliners
as they build nests in the engines.
- Yeah.
- Which is not correct.
- Oh.
- A wasp nest would have zero impact on a jet engine.
They're designed and tested to be able
to ingest whole frozen chickens
and still function correctly.
The wasps actually cause a problem.
This is pedant of the week, I think.
- Okay.
- When they build their nests in the pitot tubes,
which are used to measure a plane's airspeed,
there are these tiny tubes on the outside of the plane.
They have a little revolving thing in them, basically.
- Yeah.
- They have a little thing which measures airspeed.
- Okay.
- Or it might be to do with pressure differentials, I think.
Anyway, that's because on,
they do this by measuring the pressure of the air,
I've got to read these emails before I read them out.
They do this by measuring the pressure of the air,
rushing through the tube
and comparing it to the static external pressure.
If wasps build their nests in the pitot tube,
it might either cause an erroneously low airspeed reading
if minimal air is entering the tube
or an erroneously high one.
If the mud is blocking the air from escaping,
this then causes issues with various other computer systems
in the plane that are relying on 40 readings.
It might even cause the pilots
to respond to the incorrect speed
and slow the plane below stall speed
in the belief that it's going far too fast.
- Yes, yes.
- 'Cause they just get this reading saying
you're doing a thousand miles an hour, slow, slow, slow.
And then they slow down and actually they're slowing down
to a hundred miles an hour and then they crash.
And there was a flight,
Bergen Air Flight 301, which crashed shortly after takeoff
from the Dominican Republic
after the pilots incorrectly responded
to the erroneous speed readings.
- Okay.
- What have we done to fix this issue?
- Plains on the ground have covers placed over the tubes
to prevent this.
You just put a cover over there.
- Yeah, there you go.
- So James, I would say basically right.
You just said engine instead of PTO tubes.
- Well, you know, the number of times
I've made that mistake when I get
to the mechanics just look at my car.
I think it's a problem with my PTO tubes.
That's a sorry, it's your engine.
Oh, okay, no fair enough.
I didn't know all that extra information,
which is very interesting.
- Really incredible.
- I once heard, oh, you should never get maggots
in your PTO tube and I've always remembered it.
Such a precise thing to remember
like under the beard of advice.
- Where's your PTO tube on a...
- I don't have a PTO tube.
- Oh, okay.
- On airplanes, you mean?
- Yeah.
- Is it an exclusively...
That cars don't have a PTO tube?
There's no...
- No, no, no, no.
- They don't...
I don't think they need to rely on external pressure sensors
to work out the speed.
- I just don't know the multiple uses it might have.
- I suppose, because how do cars measure your speed?
By the wheels going...
I mean, the wheels on the bus go round and round, don't they?
So you just measure how far the wheels have...
How many times the wheels have gone?
- I actually don't know how that works.
- No.
- Well, yeah, they used to, I mean, Roman times,
there was the first invention of a pedometer, I guess,
would be the turn of a wheel, right?
So no matter how far you're going,
the turn of the wheel will turn the wheel.
- A turn of the wheel, we would call that at school.
- Oh, yeah.
- Try not to...
Do you have a turn of the wheels at school?
- No.
- How did you measure things that were one meter in length?
- Probably, we used that.
- They're not talking about town's body, yeah.
- We used our lifestyles currently, but no poster.
(laughing)
- Chop a head off, that's meter, yeah.
- So yeah, I guess that could work in theory,
although it seems like an odd way of doing it.
- It does seem like a very...
As I said it, I thought that can't be how they do it.
- Because if I attach my Google Maps to my car,
so it's using Google Maps as a satnav,
that can tell me how fast I'm going as well.
And that must be using satellite.
- That's using satellites, but the car won't be doing,
and what no modern car might do.
- Yeah.
- Pito tubes.
- If you know how to speedometer's work, let us know.
- It's such a risk saying stuff like that James.
It's such a risk, 'cause I might get one email,
which is brilliant and Chris, where I might get 400.
- Okay, if you are the world expert on odometers,
they're right into Andy.
- That's it, there we go.
- If you kind of half know how it works,
or you just go on Google and check how it works,
don't write it to Andy.
- He said right in.
James Delce, just finished off the wasp chat.
- Mm-hmm.
- Do you remember I was banging on about that book,
Endless Forms by Professor Sarian Sumner,
which is all about wasps.
- And he hates bees.
- Very good book.
- Yeah, she actually.
I wonder whether Professor Sarian Sumner
of wasp ham and jam fame is in any way related
to Gordon Sumner of police and sting fame.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- Yeah, really a bass player?
- No, guitarist?
- No, he stings, he stings.
- Oh, Gordon Sumner, of course.
He has the singer to take a songwriter.
- I think that's the best joke we've had this month
in the inbox.
- Yeah.
- I'm gonna give James a preliminary, J-O-T-M.
- Jotum, is that what we're gonna call this?
- Jotum, Jotum, Jotum, Jotum, the month, yeah.
- Yeah, okay.
- Jotum, we're doing it by weekly.
So is it two episodes worth of Jotum?
- Jotum.
(laughing)
- Jotum, the fortnight, yeah.
- Yeah, great.
Let's have another.
Spoons.
- Oh yeah.
- We talked to Richard Osmond about the masked spooner.
- Oh, yeah.
- And we've had an email very pleasantly
from Cindy Forkel.
- Brilliant.
- While you've been joking.
- Thank you, Cindy.
And do you remember, I tried to get that
Spoon's quiz off the ground.
- Oh, yeah.
- The Spoon, Idiom Mean.
- Yes.
- How's that going?
(laughing)
- It's in development.
I've had a lot of interest.
- Yeah.
- It's from major broadcasters.
- Thought you would.
- Yeah, about Ms. Forkel could be a host.
- You're absolutely right.
- That's gonna turn the dial of the commission, isn't it?
- You can see it in Andy's eyes.
I'm gonna email them right after this.
- When you sent us this pitch first,
we were a flat-note.
(laughing)
Hearing that you've got Forkel involved.
- She hasn't said yes yet.
- Oh no.
- I'll imply she has.
- I know how a pitch works.
- Forkel, like instead of being a TV show,
you could sell it to the New York Times
as like a daily quiz.
- The New Forkel Times.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- But you know, like you have word-o and stuff.
- That's forkel.
- Yeah.
- Go on.
- Well, it's a different cutlery idea every day.
- Yeah.
- That's really okay.
Actually, this is really good.
- Oh, it's like a crossword where the first three letters
is the same, but then it trails off into three
different options to end it.
- Yeah.
- So you can have fork, fore, and foreskin.
- Perfect.
- There you go.
- We've got, right, puzzle one.
This is gonna make our millions.
She just adds that the idiom to hand over the spoon.
- Oh, yeah.
- Is that a new one?
- Well, I said to stick one spoon in the wall.
- Yeah.
- Means to die.
- The German language has then lothal abgabin
to hand over the spoon.
And that means to die.
- Oh, I don't think when we put it on Instagram,
we had someone saying in South Africa, it's a phrase too.
So it's a thing.
- Yeah.
- It's a phrase around the world.
It just happens not to exist in English anymore.
- It's not weird.
- Love that.
- Right, here's a controversial one.
And it's from the Poundland section we did
with Richard Osmond.
- Oh yeah.
- Tiana from Queens, New York.
- New fork.
- New fork, new fork.
- Right.
Just wanted to give my two cents about toilet lights.
They are fantastic.
(laughing)
- Oh dear, okay, for new listeners.
This was the fact that in Poundland,
was it Orinalde or somewhere you could buy these lights
that go on the inside of your toilet.
And we supposed what kind of video might need that.
Because who turns the light on when they go to the toilet?
- Yeah.
- Well, we're the kind of video James,
'cause we don't turn the light on.
- Absolutely.
- Yeah.
- Where he's turned the light on.
- And who wakes up in the neighborhood?
(laughing)
Who are kind of powerful lights do you guys have?
You live in lighthouses?
Like what?
(laughing)
- It's jet crash onto the rocks
'cause for the critical seconds of the lights
it's good.
I'd be in James standing there, like a piss.
(laughing)
Tiana just wants to say, they're fantastic.
I've never been to Orinalde,
so I've not experienced the Isle of Shame,
but boy do I love my toilet light.
The one we have cycles through 16 colors and is motion sensitive.
So every time I walk into the bathroom it's a party.
(laughing)
Even with the toilet lid down and the bathroom light on,
this thing is bright.
Standing.
Our primary purpose for owning and using this
is not for providing light for middle of the night trips,
though it certainly does do that job well.
Mainly we use our toilet light to bring some joy and wonder
to the bathroom experience.
- That's what I get there.
- It's a great conversation starter when we have guests
and becomes even more thrilling
when certain substances have been consumed.
- Be true.
- Asparagus?
- Asparagus.
- It sounds like drugs.
It sounds like hard drugs.
- Oh, I don't know.
(laughing)
- I don't know.
I don't know, I might be wrong.
But it does show up everything.
So you do need to be quite as serious with cleaning the lid.
- Oh, really?
Yeah, yeah.
- So I know, thank you, Tiana.
Great review.
- Yeah, great review.
- I feel like Tiana is part of big toilet light.
She's trying to make this a thing now that everyone buys them.
She's got shares.
'Cause it goes in under the thing.
- Oh, is it like an LED strip that you put in?
- I assume so.
But how would it be lit up?
- It would be the lid opening.
Sorry, I thought it needed a jet of urine
in order to light up.
But then how do you get it on target in the first place?
- Hmm, anyway, Sarah Crocker, right?
Crocker can go with forkle in the, in my show.
(laughing)
Long time fan of the show and a club fish member.
So hello, Sarah.
I was listening to your latest mail bag show earlier today.
I was chuckling over your comments about Eric Carmen.
- Oh, right, yeah.
- Oh yeah.
It's a musician.
- Yeah, or by myself.
So the Richard Osmond episode as well.
- Right, right, yeah.
- I'm currently retired and living in Bucket,
Bucket Day, Panama.
But I was born and raised in Cleveland, Ohio as was Eric.
In fact, we dated as teenagers.
- No!
- Oh!
- Oh my gosh.
- When he was in a local band called The Harlequence.
It was clear he had talent as a musician, singer,
and songwriter, even at that age.
And I was so enthralled to be his girlfriend.
Well, until he broke up with me.
- And you were all by yourself.
- I'm pretty.
(laughing)
- I genuinely thought that's where that was going.
- No, actually he didn't do it all by himself.
He had a mutual friend called to break up with me.
- That's so funny.
- What a dick.
- What a rutter.
- Oh my God.
- I think I cried straight for about nine months.
I was a teenager after all, then decided he wasn't worth it.
Good for you, Sarah.
- Wow, he uses other musicians to write his songs
and he uses other people to break up with his girlfriends.
- Hi, it's an act man and off here.
(laughing)
- My friends tell me to tell you something.
- Superb.
Oh, so thank you very much, Sarah.
That's a brilliant, brilliant email.
- That's awesome.
- Elliot Jeffries writes, "Hello, fish folk.
On the matter of fish lines,
making their way into common parlance,
I frequently use the phrase "friend of the podcast"
to refer to people frequently discussed with friends.
For instance, Oscar Wilde, J.S. Bach,
and Richard Armitage are all friends of the podcast.
None of my friends who I've said this to understand it,
but have accepted it.
- So that's nice.
- There's one name on there that I couldn't work out
who it was.
- J.S. Bach.
- Yeah.
- It was the Richard Armitage.
- Armitage.
- Who was Armitage?
- I can't remember.
- He invented the Armitage Shanks toilet.
- Now available with light up bowl.
(laughing)
- Do you know who Richard Armitage is?
- Look at filmmaker.
- Is it?
- Should we look it up?
- Yeah.
- There's someone with a similar name
who's like a forced racing goner.
- I'll check.
- But I don't think that's him.
- Oh.
- Richard Armitage, English actor, voice actor and author,
his role as Dorf King and leader in Peter Jackson's film,
The Hobbit.
- Oh, give me a break.
- No.
- No way.
Oh my God, look at the size of his feet.
(laughing)
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- Friend of the podcast.
- Well, friend of Elliot Jeffries's personal podcast.
- That's great.
That's really funny.
- What are the odds?
- We've had a controversy bit.
- Oh yeah.
- Daniel from Wagger Wagger.
- Right.
- Wow.
- I know.
- A truly a global show.
- So good, they named it twice.
- That's right.
(laughing)
- Just catching up with some special episodes.
As I do, when I have the occasion for long drives,
where does Wagger Wagger do?
- It's Australia.
- No, no, come on.
- It's right in the middle, isn't it?
- I can't actually remember, yeah.
- Is it in the bit where they have quiz questions
on the road to the road?
- Well, it sounds like if there's long drives,
that's gonna come up is where the road goes through.
I'm guessing.
- Well, Daniel, in fact, Daniel,
you might be listening to this now,
because Daniel says, "Always have special interest
"in the clubfish extra content."
- There we go.
- Hey, Daniel.
- You're probably hauling a road train right now.
- And we're gonna get to that.
(laughing)
- But Daniel asks critically,
how did Dan's fridge go bad?
And he didn't know it was unplugged.
Surely the light didn't work if it was plugged in.
Something doesn't add up.
- What?
- Okay.
- Your fridge went bad.
- Oh!
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And it turned out it was turned off at the wall.
- Yeah.
- And he thrown away all your delicate wagyu steaks
and everything had gone green and moldy.
- Yes.
- Wagyu wagyu.
(laughing)
- Absolutely, absolutely.
- So, sorry, I got lost in what you were saying,
repeat the point.
It was that how did you not know your fridge was unplugged?
Because surely the light wouldn't have worked.
- Well, you see, you and I,
when we get up in the night for a midnight snack,
and we go to the fridge to get some cheese,
we open the fridge door.
It's very obvious that the light sun,
but damn, turns all the emumination
and it's entire house sun.
So, he can't tell the difference.
(laughing)
- There we go.
- Yeah, I don't know an answer to that.
- No, I've got an answer, Dan, for you.
- Sorry, Daniel.
- If Dan's fridge, if the light wasn't working,
that's an extra reason to assume your fridge is broken.
Do you not mean?
- Yeah.
- Like if the light's not coming on,
and it's clearly gone all warm.
- Yeah.
- The fact is, how did you not know
that it was unplugged in the wall,
but you frequently can't get to the socket.
The real mystery is not, how did you not know it was unplugged.
The real mystery is how did it become unplugged?
- Yeah.
- Or turned off at the socket.
Like what is going on there?
Because the socket is in excess, I'm presuming.
- It was pretty hard to get to.
- It's pretty hard to get to.
- Yeah.
- What or who, or whom?
Turned off your fridge.
- So, I, has anyone got three life insurance policies on you?
(laughing)
- 'Cause it fell over on you, didn't it?
It was so strange.
- It's very weird.
- You normally don't.
- Yeah.
- You normally not the very stable things actually.
(laughing)
- Yeah, there's a lot of mysteries going on
in the house of the man.
- I'm sure we were with 32 C breaths swing.
(laughing)
- Oh, dear.
Shall we come to the sausage parlour?
- Yeah, we should.
- All right, we're getting close to shutting up shop.
On this week's drop of the line.
But don't worry, we'll be back again in two weeks.
- We will.
- With plenty more corrections,
including lots of corrections about things we said about Australia,
where Mel Bracewell was on the show.
They have been rolling in,
but I want to give the flood more time to build up
before releasing the pressure.
You know what I mean?
- Yeah, yeah.
- So let's just have some light emails about sausages
to round us off, okay?
(laughing)
- Gareth Taylor writes,
"You might be uninterested to hear."
(laughing)
- Well, disinterested.
- No, I am uninterested, actually I'm afraid.
- Because of some hearing loss,
I find F and S sounds very similar.
And in particular, the names of the letters themselves
sound virtually identical to me.
So when my partner reads me crossword clues
and says what letters we have so far,
she will say fish rather than F and sausage rather than S.
- Okay. - Oh, that's good, too.
- I can't remember why we chose those
as the substitutions,
other than fish and sausages are both great.
Well, episode 6-0-1 has just arrived,
and it's called no such thing as sausage by Chanel.
I wondered how many sausages you have given us over the years
as it's a familiar, fishy word.
So Gareth has done a quick look at which words
occur the most often in episode titles.
- Oh, sausage has to be, has to be the winner.
- Wow. - Oh really?
- And there's one coming up.
(laughing)
- Oh, I know, that's gonna be.
- There was one where we were in,
we were sat in a queue, signing books,
and someone said, "What will the title of this show be?"
And I said, "I don't know, we'll just make it up
when we do the show."
And they said, "Can you call it this?"
And I said, "Okay, so it's gonna be..."
- It's a sausage thing, it's gonna be sausage thing.
- Nice, I remember her, yeah.
- So you took out no such thing as,
and drop and line and all of that in, you know,
all the little words like "the" and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
- And joint ninth place tied with "with" is sausage.
- In ninth.
- Yeah.
- So it's one of the top 10 most frequent words.
- So we have the top 10.
- I would have put it absolutely number one.
I'm really surprised.
- Can you give us some clues?
This is a great game.
- Oh, sorry, if you take out A, the in and of four on and and with.
- Yeah, yeah.
- The next word is sausage.
- Oh, okay.
- It's the most common, proper word.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
- Oh, wow.
- I actually use the word sausage as a conjunction.
(laughing)
- So, okay, here's one.
Can you name any of the next five most common words?
- Pope.
- Oh, nice, not far off.
- Vatican?
- No, there is a title, Jesus.
- No, I wouldn't do that.
Oh, like Queen.
- Queen, brilliant.
- Okay, so Queen is one, King.
- Nope.
- Some kind of animal, maybe?
- There are no animals in there.
- No, a couple of adjectives.
- Oh.
- Oh, no such thing as a hairy.
- It's not hairy.
- A sausage, or, you know, big.
- No.
- No such thing as a.
- I'll give you one, yeah.
- Yeah, sexy.
- Really?
- Oh gosh.
- Okay.
- You've got three more to get from the top.
- This feels like a--
- Give a slight clues.
It's a kind of--
- Magic.
(laughing)
- Give a slightly more extreme clues, please.
- Queen.
(laughing)
- Crazy little thing called--
- No such thing as a magic love sausage, is there?
(laughing)
- No such thing as the Queen's magic love sausage.
- Once we've done that, we've just done it.
- That's the final episode.
- No, it's the final episode.
We won't even announce it when that pops up.
- There's one more, which is, what's a good example.
Blank.
Huh?
- Blank.
- Check.
- No.
- Blank.
- Blank, man.
- As a movie with--
- It.
- I think Taylor Swift.
- Blank.
- Kelt Travis Kelsey.
- Blank Space.
- Space.
- Oh, okay.
- She doesn't think of Blank Spaces, is she?
- I don't know.
- I don't know either either either.
- All right.
(laughing)
And those are the five.
Sex Eat Love, Space, Queen, and Magic.
- Great.
- Wow.
- I know.
- Good, thank you very much, Gareth.
- Yeah.
- One final one, Todd Norbury writes, subject line,
with regards to your sausage conundrum.
Way back in episode 471, no such thing
as a toying costs bracket's classic dam.
You spoke about the time--
(laughing)
Can you spoke about the time you returned?
- Okay.
- I forgot about that.
(laughing)
- You spoke about the time you returned
to a takeaway shop to complain about a spicy sausage.
- Oh my goodness.
- Was this the genesis of spicy meat?
I didn't, I wasn't complaining about a spicy sausage.
I bought a spicy sausage
and I was unhappy with the quantity I've received
for the money.
- Yeah.
- Guys, don't bring this up to you.
- Sorry.
- Todd writes, "I was lucky enough to travel to the UK in July
and I also had a sausage moment.
I have attached a photo of the menu
and the nine-quid hot dog.
It caused a bit of chatter on the fish cord at the time.
I should have done what you did and complained
but the group was in a hurry
and I had to down it with copious amounts of water
to smooth the way.
No facts, just a shared sausage experience in the UK.
So I just wanted you guys to look at what we've got here
and say whether you think this is worth nine-quid.
- Okay.
- Oh my God.
- Where's the sausage?
(laughing)
- It's underneath that turd.
- Oh, good, is it?
- We're looking at, it's a sort of open bun
with a sort of dark void.
- I think to me, it looks like it's probably a vegan sausage
that's overdone.
- That's very unkind.
- No, it's just me like it doesn't have the,
it's kind of very cylindrical
like often those fake meat sausages are.
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- That's amazing.
- That looks like, have you ever looked at the hole
where Anish Kapoor did his van to a black?
(laughing)
That's what I feel like I'm looking at.
- Yeah.
- And what a reference that is.
- And if you understood that reference,
you are in the right place.
(laughing)
- Oh, so there you go, I'm so sorry, Todd.
- Yeah, so you've absolutely been diddled there.
- I know.
- Do you never know where you get with the sausage?
- No, that's true.
- That's a beauty of it really.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- The next one will be better, you know?
But he came from New Zealand to the UK
and that was the sausage we gave him.
I just feel a bit about, you know, I feel a bit sort of,
oh, come on Britain.
Yeah, we can do better than that.
- We can, yeah.
- We can.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
(upbeat music)
- Well, that's it for this episode of "Droppers Aligned".
Thank you so much for listening.
If you enjoyed it, well, no matter whether you enjoyed it
or not, you'll be back again in two weeks with another one.
(laughing)
Yeah, thank you so much.
Thank you for all these emails, they're brilliant.
We're going to have plenty more next time
and we'd love to hear yours too.
If something we've said has affected you,
there will be a hope line available
and the sausage help line.
- The sausage help line.
The help line is podcast.ky.com.
So just write it there.
Thank you again.
Thank you so much for listening.
Thank you to those of you who are watching today.
We'll see you next time.
Bye.
(upbeat music)