(upbeat music)
Hi everyone, just before we start this show,
I wanted to let you know that James and I
are going to be doing a talk chat,
a lecture at the Hay Festival in Hay on Y,
next Wednesday, the 29th of May,
and we are gonna be chatting about our new release
of the paperback, A Load of Old Balls,
which is all the most interesting facts
and things we learned about sports.
It's for sports lovers, it's for sports haters,
it's for sports skeptics,
you've got Mary Queen of Scots football in there,
you've got Michael Palin's Concord Tournament,
you've got lacrosse games involving over 100,000 players.
There's something for everyone.
Do come and listen to us.
Hay is such a fun festival anyway,
so to get tickets for that,
go to knowsuchthingasafish.com/live,
and while you're there,
obviously buy tickets for our tour,
if you haven't already, which you should have.
On with the show.
(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber,
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin, and Anna Tyshinski,
and once again, we have gathered around the microphones
of our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the coroner
who did the autopsy of President McKinley
injected part of him into a dog.
So, he was autopsied by two doctors
called Harvey Gaylord and Herman Matzinger,
and Matzinger wanted to find out
whether the bullet that killed McKinley
had been poisoned or had some bacteria on it,
like a biological weapon.
And so, the way he did it was he took samples
from the wound and he injected parts of it
into some rabbits and a dog,
and wanted to see how the rabbits and dogs reacted,
because if there was poison on the bullet,
maybe they would die and that would be evidence
that he'd been poisoned as well as shot.
- And?
- And it turns out that the thing that killed him
was the bullet that went right through his body.
- Yeah, the dog was fine, wasn't it?
In the notes that were given, sort of said,
he was acting fine, doesn't mention the rabbit.
- No, it doesn't mention the rabbit.
It said that he was acting well, the dog,
but his body temperature was around 104 degrees Fahrenheit.
- Is that good or bad for a dog?
- It's bad for a dog.
It should be a bit lower than that.
- You can react badly to an injection,
I certainly do at any time.
I get a raised temperature.
We should say this was 1901 as well,
just for anyone who's not up on their presidents,
President McKinley around 20th-ish.
- 25th, I think?
- He was 25th president, that's right.
- So why am I talking about this today
if it was something that happened around 1900?
Well, we don't talk to us anymore.
(laughing)
- This is a new feature.
- Well, in the news this year,
there was an auction site called the Raab Collection
and they found the personal papers
of this Dr. Herman Matzinga
and that gave us all of this information
about him injecting the president into the dog,
which we didn't know until this year.
- That's very cool.
- He was actually, no wonder he liked animals
'cause he was a buffalo doctor.
And when I say buffalo doctor,
he was a doctor who lived in the city of Buffalo
in New York. - Who's that Matzinga?
- That was Matzinga, yeah, right.
I just thought I'd try and trick you guys there.
- Good trick.
But he wasn't the first man
to even look after McKinley when he came in.
That was a different man called Dr. Mann
and Dr. Mann, Dr. Matthew Mann,
and he wasn't even a proper surgeon.
He was a gynecologist.
He was a gynecological surgeon.
- Oh no.
- This man has no vagina.
- It's all going into openings, isn't it?
When someone's been shot.
- That's true. - What a comforting thing to hear.
Dr. Anna says you lie on the operating table.
Look, it's all just stuff going in places.
Don't worry.
- It's all holes in the body.
- Let's inspect your chest vagina now.
- Oh, the exit vagina is a lot bigger.
- But the weird thing is
Thomas Edison gets involved at this point.
- Of course he does.
- He sent to Buffalo a new X-ray machine,
which is exactly like first ever episode of the podcast,
James Garfield's shot.
In that case, it was Alexander Graham Bell
sending a proto-metal detector.
Basically all new technologies were at some point
just being tried on presidents who have been assassinated.
- So basically if God forbid the American president
gets shot in the next couple of years,
they'll probably send a chat bot.
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- That's amazing.
So autopsies have come a long way
since the days of injecting stuff into animals.
And I didn't know really about body farms.
- That sounds grim.
- And yet it is.
(all laughing)
So they were basically invented by this guy called Billy Bass.
I remember that singing fish.
- No, not Billy.
- Bigmouth Billy Bass is singing fish.
- Wait, so he did body farms
and then he did novelty singing fish?
- Fairly so.
Or it could be that they are different.
- People.
- So this guy called Bill Bass
was a forensic anthropologist in the 60s and 70s.
And he realized that we didn't know much
about what happens to bodies when they decompose.
And so he kind of bought up some farmland
and decided to collect loads and loads of dead bodies.
And it's still going today.
And there are now a few body farms around the world
and they're extraordinary places.
- It does sound like an excuse, doesn't it?
When the police come and they say,
why have you got hundreds of dead bodies buried in your field?
- Well, also 'cause they're buried in really odd scenarios
'cause they're stored in the boots of cars, for instance.
- Oh yeah.
- In pools of water, buried under rubble and in concrete.
- No, this is my body allotment.
I want one day to have a whole farm,
but I've only got one so far.
- Yeah, they're incredible.
And we've learned so much about forensics from them.
And yeah, they do things like,
you'll be walking through a field
and you might not see any bodies,
but you might see pipes sticking up out of the ground.
And that's 'cause there are bodies underground
and they're connected to pipes, which are collecting gases
and the gases will determine what bodies smell of
and that's so that we can develop machines in the future
that can detect them by smell.
- That is stunning. - That's classy.
Leaving your body to science like that
is a really good thing to do.
As in, well, I hope I have the gumption to do that.
I felt that we established
you won't have any body remaining
after we got to it from last week's episode.
It's a fun little callback
if you haven't listened to last week's episode yet.
Find out what's gonna happen to me
when these three get their hands on me.
- So the father of autopsy, what people call that
is a guy called Karl Rokitansky.
And he came up with the idea of like looking
at the internal organs to diagnose disease on the outside.
He personally performed 30,000 autopsies
and supervised another 70,000.
- Sorry, 30,000? - Yeah.
- That's one a day for like ages.
(laughing)
- It's one a day for a hundred years, isn't it?
- Yeah. - Wasn't it?
- Yeah, he did more than one a day.
It's the way he got through that.
- Clever.
- It's weekends, that's evenings, that's your birthday.
Maybe you do more on your birthday.
I don't know if you're the father of it.
- So I got a question.
I think Andy's the best one to answer this.
- Okay.
- But Dan might be able to answer
and Anna definitely won't.
- Interesting.
- So it's guy's stuff.
- He's called Karl Rokitansky.
And where do you know that name from?
- Karl Rokitansky. - Rokitansky.
- Rokitansky.
- What are you guys both into?
- Something that I associate with both of you,
which is shit movies.
- Oh.
- Was he in?
- Adam Sandler's real name.
(all laughing)
- Actually, it's unfair to call this a shit movie.
It's actually a classic,
but it's the kind of movie you two would like.
- Pacific Rim 2.
(all laughing)
- He gave his name to Max Rokitansky,
who is the main character in the film series Mad Max.
- Oh. - That's amazing.
And that's 'cause George Miller, who directed it,
he was working as a doctor when he was getting funds for it.
- What, George Miller?
- That's amazing. - That's very cool.
- Yeah, George Miller's career has been amazing.
He's done Mad Max.
He did Babe 2 Pig in the City, Happy Feet,
and then more Mad Max.
- Yeah, this weird fund.
What was it called, the latest one?
- The one's second to last.
- Fury Road. - Fury Road.
- He's like in his 70s radies
when he comes out to make that again.
Like he's-- - And the new ones out shortly?
- Yeah.
- Anyway.
- So why does he--
- This is why I thought these two liked this answer.
- I have actually seen Mad Max uncharacteristically.
I thought it was very dystopian.
I'd rather be locked on a body bath.
- Yeah.
- You know what?
The plot was not lost on you.
(all laughing)
- Oh, dear.
James, I have a different father of autopsy.
- Oh, yeah, go on.
- Mondino De Liuzzi.
- Oh, I can't hear this again.
- Is it?
Can we hear this again?
- Who is the father of autopsy and me?
- Don't do that, look.
- Most episodes.
(all laughing)
- Mondino De Liuzzi was the Restorer of Anatomy.
He was Italian, if you couldn't tell.
(all laughing)
At the University of Bologna.
And Anatomy was a band,
except for once every five years you could do a dissection.
- Wow.
- Dissection.
- Is this like what's that film where sort of every 10 years
or something, you can all kill each other?
- The Purge.
- Yeah.
This is basically the Purge.
- Oh my God, Anna.
You are in your dystopian worlds today.
- I am, yeah.
- Amazing.
- So De Liuzzi, he became the first person
to do a dissection, document it and publish his findings.
And it was the first documented public dissection
in 1700 years.
- Right.
- Amazing.
But weirdly, senior people like him,
they would not do the actual dissection themselves.
So there's a picture of this happening.
And it was in the 14th century.
Senior people like him, they wouldn't do the dissection.
He would sit on a big elevated chair above the action.
- Like a tennis umpire.
- Exactly like that.
And he was reading aloud from a book.
I'm bringing him a book of Anatomy.
- No balls, please.
(all laughing)
- And he was commenting on,
he was reading Galen's Anatomy to the audience and saying,
look, now you're gonna say,
there was just a sort of barber surgeon
actually doing the procedure.
And also, do we ever mention the ostensor?
That was basically someone with one of those pointers
whose job was to just point out the bits
that were being autopsyed or examined or whatever.
- Separate to the guy on the chair.
- The guy on the chair is talking you through it.
- 'Cause he can't reach,
he'd need a very long ostensor.
- Exactly, I mean, they can go very long, those.
That's true.
The ostensor is just there going,
"Vada, there's the pancreas, uh-huh, front door."
- Yeah, they became really popular,
didn't they, dissections in Italy especially.
Around the time of the 16th century,
they were so popular, you could buy flap anatomies.
And a flap anatomy was like a book with flaps in it,
you know, like a kid's book,
where you could lift up the flaps and say,
"Oh, look, there's the gallbladder."
- Oh, yeah, so cool. - Isn't that cool?
- Wow.
- I can't believe that technology is that old.
- I don't know.
- Well, I mean, the technology is quite basic for a flap.
(laughing)
Literally just a piece of paper.
But I don't know if there were any kids books
that did that before then, I can't imagine that would have.
So I think the original kids flap book was probably this.
- That's great. - Wow.
- Have you heard of vampire autopsies?
These are very weird.
These are a real thing that used to happen.
There was concern that if you were dug up
and you were very well preserved,
you might be a vampire.
And there was this big superstition
that tuberculosis was an inherited disease.
So the dead could drain the life of their descendants.
Actually, those people had TB,
but the idea was that they were kind of being drained
by the people who died.
And there was a theory that the body of the dead person
had to be destroyed to protect the health of the living.
The last one of these happened in 1949.
- What?
- I know.
- Was it to kill them,
to stop them vampirizing other people in 1949?
- Yeah. - Right.
- Very weird.
We should have done my spooky voice for that.
- Yeah. - Come on.
- I read about a very interesting autopsy
that happened in 1533.
And it was an autopsy that was done on two children
who were infant twins who were conjoined.
And the question was, are these two children,
two children with two souls or one soul?
And the autopsy was to determine that to work out,
is there one soul between two kids?
- How many souls did they find?
- They found two.
- Oh, did they?
- Yeah, they found two because there's a Greek idea
that the soul resided in the heart
and they found two hearts within the conjoined twins.
Therefore, that was the answer that they were given.
But that was like a very theological specific autopsy.
- I think the important part of that was
that these children hadn't been baptized,
but they would baptize people after their death,
wouldn't they?
And so, if they only had one soul,
they'd only have to have one baptism.
But if they had two souls,
they'd have to have two baptisms.
- Surely, less effort just to do the double baptism.
You know, just let's do two, cover up.
- Yeah, but if you baptize twice,
then that undoes the effect of the first baptism.
- Absolutely.
- Yeah, it's like being bonked on the head
by something, losing your memory.
- Oh, right, the second bonk brings it back.
I see.
Another autopsy, which was quite amazing,
was a little bit later on in 2010.
And this is the amazing stuff they can reveal now.
So this was a robbery in Oregon
and it was two men in masks
who tried to rob a cafe or coffee kiosk at gunpoint.
And the guy who was managing the kiosk
also whipped out a gun 'cause it was America.
And he managed to shoot one of the people
who was robbing him,
but the other one got away.
Now, they did an autopsy on the one robber that he'd shot
and they looked in his belly
and there was a still intact French fry in his stomach.
Now, we know about how much French fries degrade
and how good I digest.
So they knew that he must have eaten a French fry
sort of in the last hour.
Not only that, but someone doing the autopsy
managed to identify it as a Wendy's French fry.
- Come on.
(laughing)
- Give me a break.
I think I could tell the difference
between a Burger King and the McDonald's one for sure.
- There you go.
- Someone tasted it.
They drew straws.
- Yeah.
- So it's a Wendy's fry.
- Wendy's fry.
So they just looked all the nearby Wendy's restaurants
'cause there couldn't have been more than an hour ago
he ate it.
And they looked at the security footage
and there was one within an hour.
And they did indeed find the pictures of the two people
on CCTV and found the other guy.
- Wow.
I'm gonna hear how they know it was a Wendy's fry.
I'm sure, I mean, I believe it.
I just, I'm just curious.
- Yeah.
- We don't have Wendy's here.
So we don't have, if you can let us know
if Wendy's fries are particularly,
maybe they're S-shaped or something.
- Moral of the story is always chew your food.
- That's a really good point.
Why is the fry intact?
- I mean, he's literally inhaled that fry, hasn't he?
- Oh my God, I'd be so easy to autopsy
if I committed a crime.
All my food enters my body and completely intact.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is Andy.
My fact is that England's worst ever pennies
are worth 350 pounds each.
- Hmm.
- Well, they may be some of the best.
These are coins called the Tealby pennies, right?
And this is a story of a man.
Well, why am I telling you this fact today?
Well, I'll tell you.
(laughing)
- Is this gonna be a new feature now?
I'm gonna start finding it quite tedious, I think.
- Basically, there's a man called Tony House,
which I love.
He's a metal detectorist and he was out
and detecting away and he found a stash of pennies,
ancient ones, they're from the 12th century.
He found one and then he found 600 more.
(laughing)
- That's like if you see one and two in your house.
- Exactly.
(laughing)
And they're worth about 350 quid each.
And the thing about them is they're really,
really low quality coins.
They are badly made, they're hard to read.
The image is just hopelessly stamped.
They're from the reign of Henry II.
They're named after Tealby in Lincolnshire,
which is where 5,000 of them were found
in a huge cache in the 19th century.
- Ah, cache.
- And they're just really ropey coins.
- So why are they worth so much,
just 'cause they're old now and rare?
- Rare, maybe?
They're old, they're pretty rare.
- I thought they were quite a lot of them.
- Well, I was on a numismatist website called Numsock,
which was really good.
It says this coinage is renowned for its ugly appearance,
bad craftsmanship and careless execution.
To collect Tealby pennies in the first place,
it grounds you as a little strange.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Right, to be strange in the numismatist world
is truly strangeness.
I kind of absolutely love numismatism, in fact,
even though it's really hard to say.
And I love coin research because, A, it's so reliable.
It's such reliable history, there's no spurious,
oh, what was this used for?
Because all the information that you need is on this coin.
It's like, there's a date, there's a face,
it's a physical thing.
And people--
- You're saying we have no mystery coins
that we don't know the stories behind?
- Oh, yeah.
I mean, we will have some mystery coins.
Don't worry, Dan, there are the alien theories out there,
I'm sure.
- Good, 'cause all my research.
- But people are also so obsessed.
I was on a Reddit thread,
which was started by someone who said,
"I ranked all the Roman emperors for their coinage
"based on its artistic value, variety,
"collectibility and historical value.
"Feel free to ask me about the rankings."
And everyone did.
(laughing)
- That is really tragic of no one else's life.
- Oh, don't you worry.
- Anyone?
- Thousands.
I can tell you that Claudius wasn't high enough.
And Claudius, of course,
was responsible for the return to realism
instead of the vaguely Hellenistic idealism
on previous coins.
So he should have had at least an A rank,
according to one person.
(laughing)
One person just said, "I feel insulted
"you ranked Nero as high as Augustus."
And this is not as an emperor,
this is his coinage.
(laughing)
- Right.
- You were saying about there being no dubious coins,
Anna, which did backtrack on Inferness, but--
- I guess, yeah.
- I have an interesting thing that I found,
which is about rainbow cups.
Don't know if you guys found this.
- Was it related to the moon cup?
(laughing)
- In the fact that they're cup shaped, both.
- Okay.
- Only.
So these are coins that are cup shaped,
and you find them, especially in Germany,
and you'll find them in fields.
But these are often found after it had been raining,
but then it was sunny straight afterwards.
Because not only are they kind of pushed forward
by the muddiness,
but also water gets into the cup-ness,
and it shines, and they're really easy to find,
because the reflection of the light comes off.
And people associated them with rainbows.
And according to Discover Magazine,
which is usually a pretty good source,
this is the reason that we have like a crock of gold
at the end of a rainbow.
- Oh, no.
- People, whenever there was a rainbow,
they would find these cup shaped coins.
- Very good.
- That's awesome.
- And apparently there were tribes of Southern Germany
that were Celtic tribes that moved up into Ireland,
and that's why the Irish associated with leprechauns.
- I love that.
That's amazing.
- Isn't that cool?
- Yeah, that's really cool.
- That's great.
I've got a favorite coin.
- Yeah.
- You've got a double eagle.
This is an American coin,
and it was a $10 coin issued in 1933.
Half a million of them were struck,
but they weren't issued as legal tender.
'Cause in 1933, the Great Depression, blah, blah, blah,
banking crisis, gold coins are outlawed as legal tender.
It is now illegal to own a double eagle one.
- What?
- Yeah, they're all technically U.S. government property.
- Because they never put them out.
You can't have accidentally got one in your change
and own it.
- I see.
- If you have one, it must've been stolen.
I think there is one, isn't there?
- There's one, so there are two in the Smithsonian,
which is kind of different,
but then there's one which is not illegal to own.
I can't work out exactly why that's the only one
that's not illegal to own,
but it was sold in 2021 at auction for nearly 50 million
pounds.
- Wow.
- What happened was a few of them were stolen
and found their way into private hands via a jeweler
called Israel Svit, who was from Philadelphia.
And when they came to light, they would just get confiscated
'cause you weren't allowed to have them.
But one of them got sold to King Farouk of Egypt.
And he wrote to the Treasury Department said,
"I have this coin, is it okay if I keep it?"
And they hadn't discovered the theft at that stage,
so they didn't realize that they'd been stolen.
And so they replied to him saying,
"Yeah, you can keep it."
- Wow, that's good.
- And that's the one.
That's the one that if it ever comes up,
is the one that gets sold at auction.
- Amazing.
- Wow.
- So that's, I think, unique.
- That is.
- Yeah, that's really cool.
- Just while we're on American coins,
in 2007, there was a coin that was minted
which had an image of JFK on it.
And if you pressed a button on the coin,
it played a short excerpt of his Iqbin Einbilina.
So it had little technology in it to do that.
- No, I don't believe that was legal tendancy.
(laughing)
- Do you know where that was minted?
What country that was for?
- Germany.
- Sounds it right.
Mongolia.
(laughing)
- Lovely.
- Do you guys know that the first book written
about the history of the coin
was called the Ass and Party Bus?
- The Ass and Party Bus?
- Is that right?
Is that a Latin book?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I see.
- It's actually the ass at Party Bus.
So I have translated two of the words.
- Of ass and--
- Party Bus means like parts of.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Ass was like an old Roman coin.
- Oh, that's great.
- Published in 1514 by Huiam Boudd,
and to be honest, is quite boring.
(laughing)
- But you read the whole thing, presumably.
- Yeah, the first 10 pages are about
the etymology of the word ass.
Then it goes on about--
- I bet you read that so voraciously.
- Yeah.
- That's brilliant.
- Come on, come on, come on, come on, come on.
- They were big.
- One actually amazing thing,
speaking of Romans and coins,
is that coins are the reason
that we're still discovering Roman emperors.
Which I, sorry, I just still, I didn't know.
- Wow.
- We discovered our latest Roman emperor in 2022.
- No, no, no, it's true.
- Who were we missing?
- This is--
- It's not a biggie.
It's not like in between Nero.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, to Augustus actually.
It only came to light.
No, this is the great Sponsienus.
(laughing)
- Yeah, yeah, that sounds like a legit one.
- Hi, I'm doing it.
Oh, would you like to sponsor my anus?
(laughing)
- This is from, well, we think it's from the disaster century,
whatever it's called, the crisis century in the Roman period,
which was like the third century,
when it was all falling to pieces
and there were sort of 1900 emperors.
But the reason he's only just come to light
is because there were these coins found
in Transylvania in the 1700s,
which were assumed to be fake,
and people looked at them and said they were true.
- Andy, sorry, can Andy,
can you say these coins were found in Transylvania, please?
- These coins were found in Transylvania.
- Yeah, that seems to add to it for me.
- Yeah, you're absolutely right, yeah.
They were found in Transylvania in the 1700s,
and they had a picture of this bloke,
and it said Sponsienus under it, and--
- Sponsienus.
(laughing)
- It just doesn't work when you do it down.
Anyway, it was decided that they were fakes,
and it was only in 2022 that analysis of them
actually concluded they were probably real.
And so we've literally just found out
that there was a Roman emperor
at some time between 248 and 253 AD.
- Okay, wow.
- Very much a sort of Liz Truss style.
Lincoln, you'll miss him.
- Yeah, I think it was in and out, job.
- And just one coin so far, did you say?
- I think there are a couple.
I believe there are two coins.
- Did you hear about the Eid Ma Aureus?
So there's another Roman coin.
Is this the, like after Caesar was killed?
- Yes.
- This is a coin that celebrates the assassination
of Julius Caesar, minted by Brutus,
and it has the inscription, "Eid Ma,"
which is, "Eids of Mars."
And it has their daggers on.
Brutus and Cassius' daggers are depicted.
- It's crazy.
It's like immediately after, almost, right?
Like it's like merch.
- That's kind of what they did, though, wasn't it?
It was like, "Get rid of the old emperor.
How do you do it?
Well, let's just mint a load of coins."
- Yeah.
- It doesn't matter how you do it.
- Interestingly, Julius Caesar was the first known autopsy
that we have ever done stuff.
- Yeah.
- Was that required?
- Well, they found out that he was stabbed 23 times.
- Right.
I mean, that, yeah.
- But was that poison on the dagger,
which was the actual cause of death?
- I can't deal with this many vaginas.
(both laughing)
- But they wanted to find out
which of the stabbings was the one that killed him.
- No, how did they, no offense to the Romans.
How did they think they were gonna be able to do that?
Surely it would have been some combination
of the 23 that did it.
- I could tell you, because most of them were
either in the face or the groin.
It was found.
- Oh, they were in the face.
- I didn't know that.
- Wow.
- And it was just one or two.
And I think one of them went through
is the side of his arm and into his arm's room.
- Right, okay.
- So they decided that that was it.
- Wow.
- Anyway.
- Blimey.
- And the groin, was that deliberate?
- Yeah.
- Doesn't seem inadvertent, does it?
- Going for a crotch.
- Coin villain, Henry VIII.
- Really?
- Yeah, but the numismatists foe.
So he wasted lots of money on wars
with foreigners, basically.
And he specifically, he debased the currency.
He issued new coins where he'd put copper
in the silver coins just to make the silver
go a bit further, basically.
And it caused mayhem.
People were hoarding their good coins
from the before times, which were still worth
every bit of silver in them.
And they left the bad ones in circulation.
Foreign bankers refused to accept English money.
They were asking for gold instead.
It just, it was a disaster.
And then a few years after he dies,
Elizabeth I came to the throne 15 years later,
she had to recall every single coin in the kingdom
and melt them down and reissue proper coins.
- You have like a coin amnesty.
Everyone come and hand your coins in at the forum.
- Pretty much.
- They had those, you know, those machines
where you pour all your coins in
and it gives you a little slip, they had those.
- Not the ones with the tray going back and forward.
Is that what they're doing?
They're collecting my coins.
- Well, they are collecting your coins effectively.
You know those things, by the way,
they were invented by, I can't remember who it was now,
but they were invented and the person who invented them
thought that they would only last one year
because it's been quite a few of these kind of amusements
that had come and gone really quickly.
And so they invented them, they didn't patent them.
They made a load of them
and then they became really successful.
And now you could just make them without any patents.
- I didn't realize that.
- Yeah. And the original one had the big hole in the middle
which your coins would go in so they would make money.
Whereas now the holes are hidden.
So when the coins are being pushed,
there's holes on the side that you can't see
and that's where the coins kind of fall into
and that's the cut that the machines are.
- So I'm not aiming, I don't want to get into those holes.
- No, so think about it.
- I want to get into the big hole in the middle.
- Every coin you put in, in theory,
is going to come out again, right?
So how do they make money?
Well, the way they make money is they have hidden holes
where the coins fall down and go into the bank.
- Wait, why would every coin in theory be coming out again?
I just thought they'd got more and more and more coins
until the whole thing exploded.
- Until the whole thing was full of coins.
- Yeah, exactly, someone's going to go to those machines
and they're just crowned.
- You've never seen one of them fall to top.
- I think it's like, you fill them with coins
to start off with because you've never turned up
to one of those and there's no coins in it.
- Just a little sign saying please.
- So they fill them with coins
and then in theory, everyone you put in
is going to push another one out.
- I did not know there were side things.
I just thought they built up and then at night
people came by and siphoned out and stacked them artfully
so they never stayed, none of them would fall in the hole.
- That might happen as well.
- Those machines are great.
I love them so much.
- I spend so much of my money on them.
- Yeah, they are amazing.
I love them as well.
You know those penny collection machines actually?
- What do you mean?
- The one where you get all of your money
that you've been keeping in a jar for the last 10 years.
- Oh and you tip them in and you turn it into cash.
- Do you know what the most
that anyone's ever got out of this?
- Oh great.
- Oh God, how much?
So I think I mentioned on the show once
that I did it in Australia
and I think I got three or $400 out of it.
- What, how much?
You were pouring in coppers into a machine.
You got $400.
- What's an all coppers?
There's some 50 cents.
- Right.
- What Looney Tunes bank robbery had you just done
to have $400 in spilled coins?
- It was all of Bean's money
they'd been collected over the years.
- Well remember, he just spills change everywhere,
never picks it up and I was unemployed.
So I thought I'm gonna try and contribute
to this little domestic economy.
Go on, who's beating my record then?
- Yeah, what is it?
2000, I'm gonna say.
- No, the record is $13,084.59.
- Wow.
- I don't mean behind that person.
(all laughing)
- There was a man in Alabama
and he had to have all of his coins delivered
to the bank to do this
because obviously there were so many of them
he couldn't carry them
and it took seven hours to count them all.
- Wow.
- And his collection weighed more than 4.5 tons.
- Goodness.
Why did he stop?
- The fool.
(all laughing)
- Yes, what a weird again.
That's an inside out logic.
I would have gone for, why did he stop?
- It does feel like perhaps
there was someone else in his house
who asked him to do it.
- Yeah, fair enough.
- I don't know.
- Have you guys heard of Christopher Ironside?
He was the designer behind the first decimal coins
that we had in 1969 in the UK, right?
And so, he designed the 50p.
That was the first thing that he designed all of the coins.
- I'm so sorry, I think it was 71?
But maybe he designed them early?
- No, there was some that came out early.
71 was decimalization,
but there were a few earlier decimal coins.
- Right.
- That's confusing.
- That is confusing.
- I mean, the whole decimalization thing
sounds confusing to be fair.
You would have loved the Daily Mail in 1971.
- Why are there 240 anymore?
- But so there was sort of an announcement
that Britain was going to be heading this way,
but the Royal Mint didn't say who was designing the coins,
but they had picked this guy, Christopher Ironside,
and he had to do it in secrecy from 1962 all the way to 1968.
Now, you would think they gave him an office
to go and do it in, that he could do it in secrecy
if it was such a big deal, they didn't.
He had to do it in his house.
He had his mother living in the house.
He had a daughter living in the house.
He had two young kids on the way.
He had a small house, so he had nowhere to do it.
- And they're constantly at risk of discovering
the big secret, which is that he's working
best after this time.
- But he's designing.
All you need is a desk.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- There's the voice of Big Mint over here.
They could give him a room in the building, I would say.
- Exactly.
- I'm not saying they couldn't do that,
but I'm just saying that the fact
that he's working from home, like many of us does today.
- Yeah, yeah.
- But if I was working from home
and I couldn't let my wife find out
that I was working on a podcast,
it might be tricky.
- Would it?
- Yeah.
- What's this microphone for?
(all laughing)
- Well, she's at home
'cause she's got two kids on the way.
- And she's finding drawings of 50p coins around the place.
She's saying, "What's this?"
"Uh, nothing."
- So I think she gets into it
because she becomes the model for Britannica
on the back of the 50p coin.
Her name was Jean.
And we were talking last week
about Uma Thurman's grandmother.
Well, we now know who was basically the model
for Britannica. - All right.
- But he had to hide it from all his friends
who would come over and so on.
So he had a big cloth that he would put over his desk.
- What kind of claim he was doing?
Did he say he was a spy?
And actually--
- It kind of felt like it, but--
- It just doesn't feel hard
to hide drawing a picture of Britannica.
- No, he was making the molds.
He was doing all the molds.
- Still?
- Do you know how big a coin is?
- Yeah, totally.
But like, you know--
- James, I think this guy had a rough time.
I do, I've got to say.
- I want to know why it took him six years to design.
- Yeah.
- What, like five coins?
- Because he was constantly trying
to hide his tiny molds everywhere.
- I think it was, as he reports into the office every quarter,
"No, sorry, my mother-in-law came into the room."
What they had to do--
- Just as I was making the molds.
I had to throw it out of the window into the garden.
- And then someone walked past the garden
and they had to go and bury it in the garden.
- Then a fox dug it up, you see, that was the problem.
So I will need another three years.
I'm afraid to complete the molds.
- They had to delay one of the coins
because he found his daughter at the desk
putting into the putty her knife or whatever
and it completely ruined the coins.
They had to redesign the way.
- His whole family, I imagine,
was just going, "Darling, we don't care.
"It's something to do with the coin.
"We couldn't care less.
"It's dinner time."
- Oh, that's so good.
That's hilarious.
- Just very quickly before we go,
crypto coins that exist include the Yeti coin.
- Brilliant.
- The golf coin.
The Mossland coin.
The egregious fish token.
And the AP wine coin.
- Get out!
- What?
- For me.
They've minted a coin for me.
- It's a crypto coin.
I'll explain later.
- All right, yes.
- Just send me your back details.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that, in theory,
you can get a peanut allergy transplant.
- Oh, good.
- Why would I want that?
- You wouldn't be asking for it.
This would be an accidental transplant.
So there's numerous papers out there.
The one that I read was to do with a 31 year old woman.
She had liver failure.
So she had a liver transplant.
And then after the operation,
she was kissing her partner
and he had just eaten a peanut butter chocolate.
And as a result, she rashed up and she said,
"That's weird, that's never happened before."
They went to the doctors
and they worked out that she now had hypersensitivity
to peanut, hazelnut and pecan.
And they believe that that was new from post-transplant.
And then there are the multiple examples
of people who have been claiming
to have had a peanut allergy post-transplant.
- That's very cool.
- Yeah.
- Paying the arse for those people.
- Peanut allergies.
- Did you say peanuts?
- It was definitely, it was either peanuts or peanuts.
- Oh, peanuts.
Sorry, no, no, no, I still want peanuts.
There is a day of the year where in Canada,
peanut allergy cases, which trigger anaphylactic shock,
rise by 85%.
Can you work out what that day of the year is?
- When they eat a lot of peanuts,
Super Bowl, no, Canada.
The World Series, baseball, the hockey.
- Hockey, it's not sport.
- When's a day when certainly everyone eats a lot more peanuts?
- Christmas.
- Christmas, it's the Canadian peanut Christmas.
- When they all take flights and get them for free.
- That's right.
- When they go to the cinema,
do they all go to the cinema one day of the year?
- Canadians only go to the cinema one day a year
because it's quite sinful.
So they try and limit it.
- It's a national peanut day.
- What's Charles Schultz, was he Canadian?
- Oh, these are such good guesses.
Okay.
- Is it really obvious?
- It's not really obvious.
Peanut-based confectionery gets eaten a lot more
on one day of the year.
- Halloween.
- When they do dribble treats.
- Halloween, thank you.
(laughing)
- It's Halloween.
You get children going house to house,
having a lot of confectionery.
Maybe they didn't know they've got a peanut allergy
or maybe they are, you know, they're just excited
and they have some unfamiliar confectionery
and they already knew about it.
But yeah, that's 85%.
Easter is 60% rice.
- Really?
- I guess chocolate-containing peanuts.
- Yeah.
- It's amazing how much it's changed
over the last 20 years or so, isn't it?
- It's bizarre.
- The number of people who are allergic to peanuts
just 20 years ago is so much lower than it is today.
- Really?
- So much and no one really knows why.
- No, 1995 to 2016, there's been a five-fold increase
in the UK in peanut allergies and more in other places.
And yeah, as James says, we're not really sure why.
It's much more industrialized countries.
Could be to do with the fact that we are
not getting as many parasites, they think.
And I think the immune system uses a similar mechanism
to fight parasites as it does to flare up in allergies.
- Yeah, we just don't know, but it's rocketing.
- It is, and definitely like the more that you live
in a city, the more likely you are to have it.
- Really?
- So seems like it's something to do with not being exposed
to natural environments, possibly vitamin D sunlight.
Apparently people with a vitamin D deficiency
are 11 times more likely to have a peanut allergy.
- Really?
- But that might not, but that might be just that
the two things are related to a third thing.
We just don't know.
- Yeah.
- One way of stopping getting allergies
is to desensitize yourself by having small amounts of it,
right?
This doesn't work in all cases,
but it's a very common way of treating them.
And for that reason, there's a new kind of toothpaste
that's been invented, which has got little tiny, tiny,
tiny bits of peanut in it.
- Ah, that's brilliant.
- And the idea is that you have this toothpaste
and it desensitizes your immune system to the allergens.
- Nut paste.
- Nut paste?
- Give your kids nut paste today.
- I think we can go back to the branding drawing bar
before we start printing the packets.
- Ironically, they all just get stuck in your teeth.
So then you need to use an actual normal toothpaste
to get rid of it, presumably.
- Yeah.
You can be, of course, allergic to peanuts.
- Penis.
- Penis, yeah.
- Oh.
- Post-argasmic illness syndrome
is where you get flu-like symptoms,
rashes, itching, after sex.
But it has been caused, in a few cases,
by men being allergic to their own semen.
- Their own.
- Their own semen.
- Yeah.
- Oh, no.
- There is a cure.
Thank God.
- What is the...
We'll be back to nut paste, basically.
(all laughing)
- We are, I'm afraid.
- No.
- It's multiple subcutaneous injections
of the semen in question.
- I think I'll just stay all for life,
thank you very much.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, so you get very, very tiny bits of the semen
and you would inject it under the skin
and your body would learn to do well.
- Not on your toothbrush.
- No.
(all laughing)
- Wow.
Scientists get allergic to the thing
they're researching quite frequently
'cause you're exposed to it, day after day.
There was a great piece, I think it was the Atlantic,
about a scientist called Brian Fry.
He studies snake venom and has since become allergic,
not to venom, but to snakes in general.
- Really?
- Yeah.
And apparently there's a huge chance
that if you work with something all the time
you develop an allergy, 40% of vets,
45% of people who work with lab rodents
get an allergy to them.
There was a leech scientist called Danielle DeCurle
who uses herself as bait
when she's trying to catch leeches out in the field.
You know, she just walks through a swamp and gets them.
She now, after a year or two, couldn't do it anymore
and her hands started swearing up massively
if she was trying to feed a leech in the lab on her blood
and she had to feed them pig blood instead.
- That's weird though, isn't it?
Because obviously you're supposed to sensitize yourself
up until a certain point.
But maybe you can be overexposed.
Like if I'm eating peanut butter on a daily basis
and a lot, does that mean I eventually might then become
a leech scientist?
- I read the article and it said 25 to 60% of people
who work with insects become allergic to them.
So people who work with bees might come out in hives.
- Right.
- Hey, lovely.
- Now I think about it, people keep telling me
'cause I love milk and I drink milk a lot
that I will become allergic to milk
by the amount of milk that I drink.
- I don't listen to those people.
- You know who told me it was Ash Garner.
- Oh, did he?
- Who did our theme tune for anybody who doesn't know
who stopped drinking milk because he thinks
he became allergic from drinking so much as a kid.
- I think I'm right in saying that.
- There's an interesting thing where people who think
they are allergic to things in double blind tests,
quite a high percentage of people turn out not to be
allergic to them after all.
- Right.
Just on the quickly jumping back to allergy transplants
and just the idea of things being transplanted
when you take in a body part from a donor.
I read an article from a lady who said
that her personality changed after a kidney transplant
where instead of reading celebrity trash
and watching celebrity trash,
she started reading Jane Austen.
And that was purely off the back from the kidney.
She said she got a brain-y kidney.
- She said there's a pseudoscience theory,
which is the idea that you inherit traits of a person
that you might take something off.
And there's so many exact,
there's a guy called Dr. Hagen who's an ER doctor
who claims that he inherited a love of avocados
and barbecues after he got a transplant.
- I don't know maybe if your digestive system
responds to certain food stuff seems more likely
than liking trash magazines compared to Jane Austen.
- Yeah.
- To be fair to the ER doctor.
- Yeah, fair enough.
He got in contact with the family
because it was like a murder trial that she'd been killed in.
He went to the trial and the family took him in
and they did prayers together.
And then he went back to their house
and the sentence reads,
"He learned she loved avocados and barbecues."
- Oh, and there's such unusual things that people like
they could only possibly have come from this ridiculous idea.
- Well, he never used to cry during movies as well.
As a surgeon, you're trained not to cry.
And then after surgery, he kept crying and kept crying.
And as well as learning that this lady
loved avocados and barbecues,
she was also an emotionally passionate woman.
But there's a doctor who believes that
as a patient's about to go into surgery
to receive the transplant,
a few bit of details might come out
about the person they're getting the transplant from.
And they embed that in a really emotional moment
before they're about to go down.
And it goes into their psyche
rather than it being a physical transplant.
- Imagine, by the way, the kidney that you're receiving
comes from someone who loved avocado.
Okay, go on down.
(laughing)
There is a lot that we obviously don't know at all.
Like we've talked about fecal transplants before.
- Oh yeah.
- And how you can actually transplant unexpected things
in them, it is thought.
And then we're in very early days of fecal transplant.
- What changes with my personality
if I get someone else's poo in me?
- Depends who's poo you get.
Which one of our poo do you want?
And then I'll tell you what you'll get.
(laughing)
We'll save that for our therapy session after the show again.
- Now you kind of think Andy mentioned on the show
before that a mother who received a fecal transplant
from her daughter suddenly became obese.
And her daughter was obese.
And 'cause we really don't know--
- Okay, well, that makes sense.
'Cause it could be the microbes causing that, right?
- That's right.
There was someone else who received a fecal transplant
who had had alopecia and not had any hair
since there were six who suddenly grew hair again.
And I suppose this is all micro climate.
There's a lot still to learn about it
and who knows what little things it's affecting.
- Yeah, I buy it.
I buy it a lot.
Okay, here's a way.
If you are a parent and you have a baby who has a dummy,
you can protect them against allergies.
How do you do it?
- Never let them take the dummy out
so no food could get into their mouth.
- That's right.
That's right.
Can anyone think of a second method?
(laughing)
- I know the answers to this
'cause I've accidentally been doing it all my three kids.
- I've seen you doing it as well.
- Oh, well, that must be you sucking on the dummy as well?
- Yeah.
- Is it really?
- I didn't like to admit it, but it's, no, it's.
(laughing)
- Oh my God.
- Oh my God, Dan.
- For the lesson that Dan has just got a dummy
out of his pocket and popped it in.
- We assume it came out of his pocket.
We can see where it came from.
- It certainly came from below the table.
That's incredibly, Dan, wow.
- That's really disturbing.
It's weird how disturbing that is to see.
- Well, I didn't know I had it in my pocket
until I was coming in this morning
and I felt it and I was like, oh, I've got kids dummy.
- What's he got of yours?
(laughing)
- Where's my research notes?
- That one explains so much.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the largest parasite
in the world is a Christmas tree.
- Feels a bit political.
Feels like you're saying Christmas is rubbish.
- Okay.
- It's like it's feeding on ordinary families,
trying to make them spend the money on Christmas.
- Basically, it's capitalism and capitalism
is a parasite on the working-
- Good point.
Christianity actually organized religion of any form
is a parasite on our society.
- Yeah, man.
- All right, put down your joints.
(laughing)
- Put down that old wacky backie.
- Welcome to the dad car.
(laughing)
- This is a different kind of Christmas tree
to what you might be thinking.
It's the Australian Christmas tree
and the Australian Christmas tree is different
to our British Christmas trees.
- Upside down.
(laughing)
- It's not upside down.
It's actually very beautiful.
It's also known as the--
- All the baubles are made of cork.
Sorry.
(laughing)
- They're not used as Christmas trees.
We should add in Australia.
We use the classic Christmas tree in Australia.
- Yep, you do, you Australians are saying
do use the classic Christmas tree.
These are known as mungi or mood jar trees as well
but they get called the Australian Christmas tree
because they flower in December
and they're endemic to Noongar County
in Western Australia
and they're really beautiful actually
and they grow in very barren landscape
and they're bright yellow flowers when they flower
so they're like fires all over the desert
but they are also parasites and it's so amazing.
So their roots can steal from other plants
that are up to 110 meters away
by slithering under the ground to this other plant
and then the plant root wraps around the other plant's root
and then injects a spike into it
and can just suck out all their nutrients.
- It's extraordinary. - It's amazing.
- It's so cool.
- It's zombie stuff. - It's actually,
it's tipped me over into believing in plant sentience now
because you're always so skeptical about that.
- I've been on a fence, I've been on the line
but this is just extraordinary what it does.
The thing that tipped me over is that
it's a beautiful looking tree.
So even when they are cutting down areas
where this tree grows,
they'll cut everything down but this hot tree
that just looks so cool
and then it feeds off the grass.
That's basically what it is.
It's like, that's a sexy tree.
We're keeping that up.
It's evolved to be, I assume,
a good looking tree to the human eye.
- No.
(laughing)
- You assume wrong.
- But it is amazing.
- It's striking what it does.
It's pretty spooky stuff if you don't mind me saying so.
(laughing)
It's so aggressive, it's yet another bit of evidence
of like the Australian version of everything
is much more lethal than the non-Australian version.
So it'll attack power cables.
It can cut, slice through power cables
because it's so powerful, this wraparound organ it has.
Sometimes I read it steals juice from its own roots.
- Yes.
- It's wild.
- That's embarrassing.
- That was a big one.
- What it's trying to do is get the juice
from the power cable because it thinks that's a root.
- Yeah.
- But actually it's just--
- It's not just trying to contact its friends
on the phone on the other side of Australia.
- Well maybe it would be trying to contact aliens
because there was one time there was a space tracking station
in Western Australia, which was connected
by underground cables and it got into those as well.
- Wow.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Getting it from its own roots is an accident as well.
- It is an accident.
- You just find something else.
- So I don't know if you guys had or the listener has
but I'd never heard of parasitic plants before
as in I didn't really recognize
that this relies entirely on stealing other juices
from other places.
- I suppose the most famous one is mistletoe.
Of which this is a type of mistletoe, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- So yeah, mistletoe famously just grows on other trees.
- It grows on other trees.
Photosynthesis is not a thing for it.
So it just relies entirely on it.
But just the idea that this needs other living things
to live is extraordinary.
- It kind of, it can expose your year nine biology
when you learn about how plants survive.
When actually there are thousands of plants
that aren't doing any of that shit.
They're not bothering with all this complicated
chemical equation with their leaves.
They just jab into other plants.
- Yeah.
- I think there are 4,000 species.
- Have you guys heard of Hydenora Africana?
- No.
- According to one website I read and I quote,
"No plant looks more like a labia than the Hydenora Africana.
"This flower not only has teeth-like traps to lure insects
"to leaving or picking up their pollen,
"but emits a feces-like sense to attract dung beetles."
- Gosh.
- I just love that sentence.
"Nothing looks more like a labia
"and it has teeth that smells like feces."
- That's quite, that is a good riddle to ask.
- But yeah, this one sort of likes to attract dung beetles
with its smell and a lot of those ones
that are like really, really smelly plants,
they are also parasitic.
- The dodder is amazing as well.
Did you guys read about that one?
- Yeah.
- That one's extraordinary.
- It's a bit unstable on its feet, isn't it?
But it's pretty extraordinary.
- Yeah, so this is a plant which is,
it's got no roots or leaves and it's sort of yellowy looking.
It sort of grows on other plants
and it's only got a lifespan of five to 10 days
without a host, right?
So it needs to find a host in that time and it goes--
- Which is when the seed gets dispersed.
- Yeah, sorry, when the seed gets dispersed
and it can sense where the closest best host is
through the air, which is mad.
And then goes that way.
- Yeah, that I can see when--
- It's really sinister.
- Sentience!
- So sinister, Sedona.
- No, it is 'cause we don't understand
a lot of how they do this, so it is extraordinary.
- It is amazing.
- And it's weird how pretty so many of them are.
It's like if you came out--
- Almost like they evolved just so that humans
would like this.
- Thank you, James.
- I love them.
There's one which lives entirely inside the stems of plants
and this is a genus, pylostyles.
Nicely described in 1948 by Australia's government
botanist who was called Charles Gardner.
- Right, very nice.
- And it's so pretty, so it just lives entirely inside a stem.
You don't notice there, it's just little threads.
And then plops out for about a week of the year.
Again, like the one Dan described.
And it's so pretty and these white flowers come out
all over the stem of a plant.
So you'd think, gosh, this plant's looking so pretty
and actually it's diseased.
- It's another plant.
- It's so weird, I love it.
Did you guys hear about the logical pine dwarf mistletoe?
This is another, so this is a kind of mistletoe.
Most mistletoe seeds are dispersed,
almost kinds of mistletoe, they're dispersed by birds.
Birds eat the berries and then they fly somewhere else
and then they poo out the seeds
and the seeds have a new environment to grow in.
Not the lodgepole pine dwarf mistletoe.
It spreads by explosions.
- Oh.
- Basically the seed, each fruit has a single seed inside it
which is covered in this very, very sticky stuff.
And then as the fruit matures,
the pressure builds and builds and builds inside it.
And then eventually it just goes, blah.
- I've seen these exploding cucumbers in Greece.
- Yeah.
- So it was growing almost like a weed and some steps,
but I noticed it and it looks like a tiny little gherkin.
And then if you prod it enough,
it just explodes and the seeds go everywhere.
And they're really cool, but they don't go that far.
- But then it apologizes and says,
sorry, that's never happened before for me.
- Do you know why mistletoe seeds are sticky?
Because they are when they're dispersed.
- No, what is it?
- Partly it's because they have to grow from up a tree,
which is kind of cool anyway, so to stick to the tree.
But as you say, they're dispersed by birds,
pooing them out and then wiping them on trees.
So what it requires is for the bird to poo,
but this annoying sticky seed gets stuck to its anus.
And so this bird's going,
I've got this seed on my bum,
I just need to wipe it on something.
And they wipe their bums on the tree branches.
And that's what sticks into it.
- And also because they've wiped their bums on the trees
and their bums had poo on them,
then they have their own fertilizer.
- Lovely.
- So it's like the perf, if you're a seed,
you know, you're being flown to the top of a tree
and you're being put exactly where you want
with a load of fertilizer, it's a dream.
- So I just said, when you said that, I went, clever.
But I realized that's obviously humanizing it.
Like, what is it?
What is that?
If it's not clever, what is it?
- Just the evolution is amazing.
- It's just what it is.
It's just a random thing.
- It's just over millions and millions of years.
Maybe even before humans existed,
different things have been tried out.
And this is a lot of work.
- I don't think we invented sentience.
I've not played with humans for a long time.
- Is Ivy parasitic?
- No, that just, that just grows on stuff.
- If it just grows on something,
it's not technically a parasite.
It has to be stealing its resources like it's sad.
- So it doesn't steal resources.
- It might not be particularly good for the thing
that's growing on, but it's not parasitic.
- Yeah, it could weaken a tree and make it fall and so on.
Yeah, but okay.
- Do you know what is, which makes people really angry,
is orchids.
- A parasitic.
- In fact, all orchids are parasitic.
- No.
- Another beauty.
- But another beaut.
But this is something that is vigorously denied
by the American Orchid Society.
(laughing)
Again, it's so weird.
- That's brilliant.
- They're a slightly different kind of parasite.
They parasitize mycorrhizal fungi,
which are those threads underground,
those fungal threads underground.
So all orchid seeds start off by parasitizing the fungi
'cause they're not born with the resources
to grow properly, so they steal from this fungi at first.
Many of them do it for their whole lives.
So the parasites, and yet on the FAQs page
of the American Orchid Society,
there's a question, are orchids parasites?
- No, no, they're not.
Go away.
Stop asking questions.
- It is absolutely not of the approximately
20,000 species of orchid.
Not one is parasitic.
- So how are they, how are they claiming that?
Are they claiming that because it's hosted by the fungus
that it's different to being hosted by a--
- I think that's the assumption.
They don't address much like hearing
a politician interviewed on the Today program.
They're really very much just repeating this one point.
- I don't think anyone wants to talk about parasites.
No, people want to hear about the good work
that I'm doing for the people of the underground.
- Exactly.
- I think I've been buried down on sentient plants
throughout this, but I do think fungi are evil.
(laughing)
- Oh yeah, that's a good point.
- So there is a mushroom called fusarium xyrophylum.
This is amazing.
So it will find a plant called the xyros plant,
and it will sterilize it so it can't make flowers.
But it will then make its own flowers
that look exactly like the normal ones,
but they're made out of mushroom.
- Wow. - Wow.
- That's amazing.
- Oh my God, like a tofu alternative.
(laughing)
- Exactly like that.
- Plant replacement food.
- So you might think you're getting a nice bunch
from Interflora, but actually all those roses
and lilies and whatever, they're all actually mushrooms.
- That reminds me of the show, is it cake?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- There should be a show called, is it mushroom?
- It looks like a sofa.
(laughing)
- It's a mushroom.
- And then the final episode,
it turns out the host is a mushroom.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It's a format.
- You might think I'm the host,
but in fact, I'm a parasite.
(laughing)
- That's so funny.
I read just related to that.
This 2024 Bolton, where I'm from in Greater Manchester,
has been named the town of culture for Greater Manchester.
But also this week, it was named as the moldiest town
in the whole of the UK.
And it just feels like they got the wrong meaning
of the word culture.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @Sribeland on Instagram, James.
And my Instagram is @NoSuchThing as James Harkin.
- Andy.
- I'm on Twitter @AndrewHunterM.
- And Anna, where can they get us all as a group?
- You can go to Twitter or on @NoSuchThing
or Instagram @NoSuchThing as a Fish,
or you can email podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, or go to our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
We've got all of our previous episodes up there.
We have the doors to the secret club known as Club Fish.
We put lots of bonus material up there.
It's a really fun place.
There's a discord where all the listeners
get to chat to each other.
It's really worth checking out, do that now.
And as you will know, we are back on the road
with our new tour, Thunder Nerds.
We are gonna be coming to a bunch of cities and towns
around the UK, and then we're going down
under to Australia and New Zealand,
get tickets now before it sells out,
or otherwise just come back here next week.
We'll be here with another episode,
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)