(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
where we were joined by the brilliant Olga Koch.
Now, if you remember the last time Anna was on maternity leave,
Olga came on the show and she absolutely blew us away.
She was one of our favorite guests in that run,
so we were so delighted to have her back.
I'm sure you're gonna really enjoy this episode.
And when you do, you're gonna want to find out more about Olga.
Now, the best way to do that is to go to her website,
it is rock n' roger.com.
I'm gonna spell it, ROCK N R O L G A dot com.
If you go to rock n' roger.com,
then you will find details of her new tour,
which is coming up, it's called Fat Tom Cruise,
and it is playing all over the world.
Well, it's certainly playing in the UK and Australia,
that's for sure.
So do go there and see if Olga is coming to a town near you
and get your tickets.
Don't forget that if you want to hear more from Olga,
then you can go to our Patreon and get the Excel version
of this show, along with a whole host of other goodies.
There are three different tiers there.
They have extra material, they have video content,
they have merch, there's all sorts of stuff up there,
really recommend you go up there.
And of course, by joining Patreon,
you are helping the podcast, but actually, you know what?
By listening to the show and telling all your friends
how much you enjoy it, that is helping as well.
So, do enjoy this week's show with the incredible Olga Koch,
on with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
Hello, and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing as a Fish", a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here
with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray, and Olga Koch.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in a particular order, here we go,
starting with fact number one, and that is Olga.
- My fact is that TLC held the head of their recording label,
Clive Davis Hostage, in order to renegotiate
their recording contract.
(laughing)
- Brilliant idea, brilliant.
- As they should.
- As they should if, this is an amazing story, isn't it?
- Have we, so before we go anywhere,
have we decided how much you're being paid for this podcast?
(laughing)
- I have logged the doors pre-empted.
So, apparently, basically, there are albums sold
something over 10 million copies,
and they made $75 million off of it,
but each of them, the trio, got paid only 50K.
- Yeah, so who are the trio?
- Well, the trio at TLC, so you've got Lisa Left Eye Lopos.
- She's the L. - She's the L.
You've got Chilly, who is the--
- From Bluey?
- Yeah, so for all you two, turning into a talking dog,
Chilly was there, and then there was T-Bos.
I think she was called T-Bos.
- Yes. - I believe so.
- John Watkins.
And I didn't know, I thought I didn't know who TLC were.
And then I realized they did that song.
- What's it called? - T-Bos?
- No.
- Creep?
- Scrubs on those grubs.
- Oh my god, those grubs, yeah.
- Those grubs, which I do like.
But I'd, no, I don't think I know what's full.
♪ Don't go chasing waterfalls ♪
♪ They took to the rivers and the lakes they flew ♪
- Welcome.
Welcome to our friends at PRS again.
(laughing)
- Yes, that's a brilliant song.
Oh, well, great.
- Yeah.
- Harmonized so well.
It actually identified as the actual record.
- That was quite something.
I was ready for you to come in with a snare drum or something.
- You was gonna do the rap.
- We just didn't go long enough.
So yeah, TLC.
TLC, that generated $75 million.
They got $50,000 each.
They thought, "Uh-uh, no way."
And so they went into Clive Davis' office
and they brought lackeys with them.
- They stationed them outside the room
and said, "No one in, no one out."
- And I gather that lackeys were from when Lisa
had been in the big house.
- Yes, and she made some friends.
- Yes, and she had been on court-mandated rehab.
And that was after she burnt down her boyfriend's house,
I believe not on purpose.
- Yeah, completely accidentally.
- She had put a lot of his, not completely accidentally.
- She could end up in prison.
That doesn't suggest accidental, does it?
- What had happened was, she had alleged
various things against him like assault.
And I think she'd found him cheating on her.
So I would say quite a vexed relationship.
She had put a load of his sneakers in the bath
and set fire to them.
Now unfortunately, the bath was a low quality model
because she had also burned down his previous bath.
So he'd, the previous time he'd annoyed her.
- You don't know any TLC songs, and yet here you are.
(laughing)
- This is what the research papers were.
But basically, they'd had a marble bath
and she'd put a lot of stuff in there and set fire to it,
which had damaged the bath.
So her boyfriend had replaced the bath
with a cheap fiberglass model, which was a bit more flammable.
So the next time she pulled the,
I'm gonna put some of your stuff in the bath and burn it,
routine, it burnt down the whole house.
- It melted the bath in the fire spread.
So she didn't mean to do it.
The first time it was all the teddy bears
that he had given her as presents.
So she did some time and then when she was led out,
TLC formed, they released two albums,
Crazy Sexy Cool, which is the album we're talking about,
which has Waterfalls and so on, second album,
went ballistically huge and so yeah,
they went and held him hostage
and they maintained a good relationship afterwards.
I mean, you know, these women brought guns.
It wasn't like just a nice little hostage taking.
You know a nice hostage situation.
When I read this fact,
I thought, oh, that's probably just a publicity stunt
and they probably didn't really do it.
- Yeah.
- Well, that's not the case.
- No, they've spoken about it quite a few times
in interviews and they try and play down the gun element to it.
They say, it's like, I never took the gun out.
(laughing)
- But there was a gun there, lovely.
- I'll also say it's like '94, around '94, right?
- '94.
- Obviously there's been endless boy band documentaries
made about this, but record labels were really
predatory at the time, right?
'Cause they would essentially give you all this money
in advance and then you'd have to pay it back.
So, I think sometimes violence is,
well, I don't know where I'm going.
(laughing)
- And I was looking at some other historical musical contracts.
- Oh.
- Actually, my research for this came from
the latest series of "I'm a Celebrity Get Me Out Of Here,"
- Okay.
- Which I watched for the first time in about 20 years.
And Jack Osborne was on it.
And he talked about his grandfather called Don Arden.
And Don Arden apparently got the small faces
to work for him 'cause he was an agent
by dangling them upside down out of an upper floor balcony
by the ankles until they signed.
- What?
- And Jack Osborne said this on "I'm a Celebrity."
And I checked in.
I think it is mostly true.
Don Arden in his biography said that he didn't do it.
It was a group of thugs that he'd hired.
- Oh, well, that's a different story.
(laughing)
- Who overstepped the mark, he said.
- That would be Sharon Osborne's.
- Sharon Osborne's father.
- Don Arden, born in Manchester.
And he had a little phone box in Manchester
where he used to work in.
And he was such a gangster that no one would go in
to make a phone call because they knew that
if they went anywhere near his phone box,
they'd get the shit beat out of them.
- Wow.
- Yeah, he's like a real gangster,
like probably the most gangstery
of all the record boxed buses.
- Gosh.
- He also invented the coworking space.
- Yeah.
- We had people like park up on a Starbucks
for hours on end.
- Yeah.
- Was he working full time in the phone box?
- Well, that's what I'm asking.
- That was his office.
He would send people that phone number
and they want a speech when they'd have to ring
his phone box.
- Okay, that's incredible.
- Wow, that's incredible.
- That is incredible.
- Flex.
- Yeah, that is.
- Oh, got you a fan of Ray.
- What do you mean by that?
- She's a singer.
- Oh, yeah, Ray with an E.
I couldn't hear the E when you were a singer.
- Where the hell is my husband?
- What a song.
- She kept me going, I asked.
When's your album coming out?
And she'd say, oh, you know, and then in 2021,
she got asked the question and she sort of snapped
and she posted online.
I've been on a four album deal for the last seven years.
But the record label keep on not allowing me
to release an album.
They say, oh, you're not ready and I'll not yet,
you know, sometimes the person signs you up for a deal
and then they leave the company.
So there's no one inside saying, right, where's the Ray album?
So yeah, all the label doesn't want to find
that to campaign.
- Wow.
- I think she did eventually get out of it, right?
And then she self-released 21st century blues.
- Yeah, so it's still sort of going on
that you sign up and then you don't get.
- Yeah.
- The other big one is New Jeans, isn't it,
who's like the massive K-pop band.
And it even went into like South Korean parliament
was talking about whether they should be allowed
to get out of the contract.
I think it still hasn't been started yet.
- When in K-pop, it's even harder because obviously
they start like 13 and it's like basically a boarding school.
So how long are you technically paying them back
for the services that the label provided for you?
- And I don't know if it's in K-pop
'cause they don't listen to that much, but in J-pop,
like the bands will, they'll have the members
and then the members will leave
and then new members will come up.
So it'll be the same band,
but then maybe it'll just be completely different people.
And it's like all the shipathesis.
- Yeah.
- The trigger's broom, pick your metaphor.
But is that, so I was thinking about there's that band,
is it AKB 48?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Are they Japanese?
- From Akia Bura.
- And they're like 48.
- They're about 48 of them give all take.
- Exactly.
- I was thinking that they were famous years ago.
And it's like teeth, isn't it?
- It's like shark teeth.
- You lose, well you lose a tooth.
- Yeah, but when you get to human teeth,
you only have two sets of teeth.
- What?
- Oh, I've been so kind of late.
I've been waiting for these new ones
to come through for ages.
- I guess it's like S Club Juniors,
but if it was all one band.
- Yeah.
- It's like if S Club Juniors came through
and became S Club again,
and then S Club babies came along
and became S Club Juniors a mess.
- So good.
- I would like to say that what just happened is
you said Ray and I did like a cool young reference.
I mean, I can go even younger.
Do you know K-pop?
(laughing)
Anyone want to be more angry at you?
- I would just say that the surprise biggest girl group
of 2025 has to be Huntrix.
- Well, are they from Demon Hunters?
- They, sorry.
- Oh yeah.
- They got nominated for like every Grammy.
It was crazy.
- Yeah, well, and they're probably gonna get
an Oscar nomination.
And they, they're now a traveling band, basically,
because it's been so successful.
They had a number one still word, sorry.
Old person here.
What?
- An animation was released earlier this year
on Netflix called K-pop Demon Hunters,
which has just absolutely dominated children's parties
and Netflix streams, like nothing else.
- And it has a specific song in it called "Golden"
that I would say that the success of "Golden"
is only comparable to, you remember when Frozen came out
and it was let it go and at first it was just kids
and then it was everybody all the time.
That's what happened to "Golden."
- Interesting.
Have you guys heard of Duran, Duran?
Can we just hold the conversation back around Duran?
- Duran, Duran, of course.
- Yes.
- Of course.
- I heard you the first time.
- I was looking at problems between bands
and their fans as well, like breaches of contract
as well as breaches of contract.
In 2014, they were reported to be suing their own fan club.
- No.
- With a love.
- And they, it's great.
They signed an agreement with this fan club company
called "World Wide Fan Clubs."
Which, Duran, Duran will get 75% of the profits
from the fan club, but these guys will run it
and they're alleged that it hadn't been run properly
and they hadn't been collecting membership pieces.
It became an incredibly boring and technical story,
but I like the idea of suing your own fans.
- I wonder why as a person who does our inbox.
(laughing)
- I was looking at some of the oldest sort of contracts
from music and the first person I think to get a royalty
was a guy called Albert Chevalier.
Have you heard of him?
- No.
- Oh, I love his, I love his second album.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- He got one shilling, which is five pence
for every dozen records sold.
This was in 1891.
And he's also famous for inventing or popularizing
the phrase "watcher."
- Really?
- Which means like, hello.
- Yeah.
- Was that in his songs?
- It already existed, but it wasn't that popular,
but he had a song called "watcher" knocked him out
the old Kent Road.
- Right.
- Oh, that's where that really took off.
- Well, speaking of "watcher,"
did you know the word "hello" was popular
as by the song "hello" my baby, "hello" my baby?
- No, really?
- Before they wanted to use a "hoi" to pick up a phone,
and "hello" was people mocking people picking up the phone.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I really hope this is true.
- Wait, so we need to research this.
- So did that song come before the phone?
- No.
- Okay, so the phone happened.
- A "hoi" was being used.
- Yes.
- Someone sent a grand bell once he'd say, "a "hoi" "hoi"
- Yeah.
- That's right.
- And then "hello" was like slaying at the time,
and "hello" my baby, "hello" my darling.
- Wow.
- With them making fun of people using "hello" on the phone.
Isn't it a while?
- When you think of time travelers who would come
to our present day, the things you wouldn't expect
would blow their mind.
- You're using "hello" as the greeting.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- That was like fifth version of how you would do that.
- It was like minor slang.
That's wild.
You know within the world of TLC,
they basically fell out at one point.
Lisa left "I Lopez" got a big beef with the other two,
and they started sort of cussing each other
within articles.
So Lisa in "Five Magazine" called them out,
saying that everything's going terrible,
then in "Entertainment Weekly," T. Bos and Chile,
said, "Well, she's manipulative, she's evil,
"she's a bad person."
So then Lisa left "I Lopez" replies
in "Entertainment Weekly," saying, "Okay,
"we've got three albums left on our contract
"with this company.
"Let's release an album that is three CDs long,
"but each of them are solo albums,
"and we'll let the fans decide who they think
"the best solo album is."
But hang on, is this a randomized controlled trial?
Is it a blind listen?
'Cause you have to, if you're gonna get it--
- You can recognize them from the voice, sure.
- Yeah, well, that's what you'd have to do.
You'd have to get someone else to sing them all, right?
- To sing them all, right?
- We could do this scientifically, or are we not?
- Yeah, we just--
- When the IRA are on TV,
and they have to get someone to do the voice over.
- They all have to be done by Jerry Adams.
- That's it.
- And that was the plan, so...
Jerry Adams then wrote to Entertainment Weekly
and said, "Well, I'm Keen, what about you guys?"
So it was meant to be called The Challenge,
and that was the idea, three CDs,
which would then finish their contract,
'cause that's how many albums to go.
- I like the idea, but it's pretty bold move, isn't it?
Someones gonna come last in that competition.
- Yeah. - Oh, yeah.
- Please never do this on fish.
- No, we never do that, 'cause Anna is just gonna get it.
I'm far the most wizards.
- Yeah, we'll be get squashed by her.
Just while we're on things, the home office
might have been interested in Jerry Adams.
(laughing)
The home office used to have its own boy band.
- Did it?
- What?
- Yeah, they were called Mr. Mina,
and it was three, sort of, I think, teenage lads,
and they would go around schools up north
as part of a government initiative
to deter Islamist extremism.
So they have various songs about things like 9/11,
or the sort of, the temptations of going down
an extremist route.
It's unclear whether they knew they were being funded,
'cause there's quite a secretive home office program,
which does a bit of cultural outreach,
and I'm not clear whether or not they knew you.
- It was a lot of that wasn't the back of the day.
Like, there was talking about it.
(laughing)
- Well, during the Cold War,
there was lots of people who became really big,
and were sort of traveling around the Eastern Europe,
and they thought it was all because how great they were.
But actually, the US government
was just paying for everything.
- Exactly, see?
- Scorpion's wind of change vibes?
- I don't know what that means, but yeah.
- Oh, okay, never mind.
I'll take that back.
There's a co-rumor that winds of change
it broke the Soviet Union, the song.
- Oh, I bet it is that song.
- The song, right.
- Well, there was a lot of CIA stuff going around.
- I often wonder, 'cause at the time of recording,
we're number one in Apple's comedy podcast charts.
And I always think that's so mental
that probably the government are doing this,
and probably they're kind of training us
to take over some country out of the Syops.
- Wait, you're telling me
that a bunch of teenage boys, singing about 9/11,
didn't realize that they were
(laughing)
- We said, "Nonsense."
- That's what came out to you about instead of,
"Wait, are you telling me this piece of shit
"is the number one in the comedy podcast?"
- No, no doubt about that.
- I mean, we know that a lot of our lessons on fish
do come from voxels, specifically,
just next to voxels stations.
- Right, yeah, that's true.
- Like, hundreds of thousands every week,
just from there, yeah.
- I thought you were talking about the gay sawdust.
(laughing)
- Yes, but the gay sawdust at my five funded.
Sorry, just to be completely clear.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the height
of the world's third tallest structure was picked
because it worked as a pun.
- Love it.
- Nothing.
- So this is better, so better be good.
This is the number one comedy podcast town.
Don't send a spiraling back down those charts.
(laughing)
- So this is the Tokyo Sky Tree,
which is 634 meters.
It's the tallest free standing tower in the world.
- Where is it?
- It's in Tokyo.
(laughing)
- And yeah, it's height was picked very specifically
because the area that they were building this on
was part of an old region that was known as Musashi
and Musashi and she broken down are Musashi,
Sa, three and she, four.
So Musashi is the exact height that they decided on.
- Brilliant.
- And interestingly, there are different ways
that you can count in Japan,
as in the way that you say the words,
'cause there are old Japanese in those a few dollars.
So, Mou is part of an old version.
- Yes, it's Jini-san, she go Roku.
- Exactly, so it's not Roku, but Mou works as well.
Just for anyone wondering why that's the case.
- Yeah, so they deliberately did that as a pun.
- Very clever. - And it's lovely.
- It's very cool.
- Does that happen much in the world?
(laughing)
- I've been imagining it as you know what I thought of
when you sent this, was it the crystal palace,
which was 1,851 meters in all yards in length or feet
in length because it was opened in 1851.
- That's brilliant, I didn't know that.
- That's cute stuff.
- It doesn't help when you don't remember the unit.
(laughing)
- Gotta be feet. - Yes, yes, yes.
- It's about 600 meters, like a mile punch.
- Yeah, yeah.
This kind of gets to happen a lot in Japan.
So, this is part of a tradition of Japanese puns
called Guru Wase.
So, it can be associated with people, ideas.
It can even be associated with Pai.
- That's in the number?
- Yeah, so if you say 3.14159265 in Japanese,
those all are numbers that make words.
And that comes out as a sentence that means an obstetrician
faces towards a foreign country.
- Wow.
- They just like finding all these little patterns
within that world.
If you do 18782 plus 18782 equals 3756.
So, there's a calculation.
That comes out as bad person plus bad person equals massacre.
When you translate it into Japanese words.
- It's three, three, six, yeah.
- We have wide at six, eight, seven, because seven, eight, nine.
- So, you know, we've got our own version of that in our culture.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's a classic.
That's the first joke my daughter led.
- Yeah, yeah, wow, that's bizarre.
- Yeah, it's very cool.
- It is very cool.
I'll just mention two others just in case.
There's a famed admiral, Yamamoto,
whose given name comes from the older pronunciation
for the word 56, which was his dad's age when he was born.
So, Yamamoto 56, yeah.
And then there's a baseball player, quite famous in America,
called Icho Suzuki, and his jersey number was 51,
which in Japanese is Go Ichi, which is his first name.
- Oh, fine.
- Yeah, so it was Go Ichi.
- That's really fun.
- This is all really good stuff.
I wish I could refining, you know,
normally we kind of just bad sort of these,
but I just like hearing them.
- Yeah, yeah, it's really cool.
- Yeah, Ichi was an amazing baseball player.
So, he was an outfielder and whenever he called a ball,
it was seen as like really well done.
So, that area was known as Area 51.
- Oh, that's, wow.
- So good.
Oh, God, I love that.
- Yeah, so that's a thing that happens in Japan, quite a lot.
- Love it, yeah.
- The only thing that the entire time was like,
and sometimes when I tear a misu, I say, I tear a misu.
That's the one pond, the only pond
that was just circulating around my mouth.
- You say it to the food?
- I say it to the food, because it sounds like misu.
- Tokyo, have you been?
- I did go to Tokyo a couple of years ago.
I wrote a whole show about it.
Basically, I met a guy at a wedding.
We spent an unforgettable night,
and then he lived in New Zealand and I lived in the UK.
So, we decided to meet three months later in Japan.
- Lovely.
- And it was a disaster.
- Oh.
- Yeah, we absolutely hated each other's guts.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- But what a beautiful city to hate each other's guts at.
- Did you find that out early on in the trip?
- 45 seconds at night.
- Yeah.
- And then you say goodbye or did you hang out the trip?
- Oh, baby, we planned too much to say goodbye.
Non-refundable train tickets, restaurant reservations,
guided tours.
- Did you go out this guy tree?
- Well, we went up a building of some sort.
- Do you think if he'd have told you all of Don's puns
and things might have gone better?
- 100%.
- Maybe I would have tire missed him.
(laughing)
- That's beautiful.
- Yeah, the entire time.
I was like, I wish I had those in my pocket
to fill the silence in.
(laughing)
- Not.
- Wow, that's extraordinary.
- Yeah.
- It's one of those things where everybody sort of always
wonders what would happen if they did such an impulsive thing.
And I'm here to tell you,
this is why you don't do that.
- Do you remember who was it?
- Was it I way, way, who did that thing where
they got two people to walk along the whole of the--
- I think it was Maria.
- Maria.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
So she walked all the way along the Great Wall of China
and then met someone halfway and then kissed and then--
- They broke up?
- It was her, yeah, it was her both artistic partner
and her partner in life.
And they both started on either end of the Great Wall,
met in the middle and broke up when they met in the middle.
- Did they always plan to break up?
Or did they just remember they hated each other
when they got there?
- I think, yeah, 45 seconds until we're done.
It's only remembered.
- What I mostly remember about Tokyo is how busy it is.
Like, because we live in a city, London, right?
And you think, oh, it's really busy.
And then you go to Tokyo and it's just like
a million times busier.
Of the 51 busiest train stations in the world,
all but six of them are in Japan.
And the top three are in Tokyo.
- Wish.
- 51!
(all laughing)
- Go wish you.
The most busy.
- Sorry, but who else?
Who makes the top 51?
(all laughing)
- So shy.
- I don't see the chart that does the chart 51.
- It does feel like once you get to 52,
then they're all in a different country.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But the busiest railway station is Shinjuku.
And they had, in 2022, the average number of daily passengers
was 2,704,703, which is the equivalent of every adult
in Uruguay passing through the station every day.
- Oh.
- That's just one station.
- Thank you for putting into terms and numbers
I had to understand.
(all laughing)
- I can't picture that many people.
Can you keep it?
- We all know the entire adult population.
The population, the adult population.
- Yeah.
- The kids of Uruguay.
I'm gonna have a field day where the grownups are away.
- You'll thank us in five months' time
when you're in Uruguay meeting some Australian
from the other side of the world.
(all laughing)
- The chat runs dry.
- Wow, I had no idea.
Uruguay was so small.
- Yeah, it is small.
- That's a small population.
- It's much smaller than you think,
but it's just that tiny little bit in South America, isn't it?
It's not a very big country.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Do we have any listeners in Uruguay?
- Podcast@QI.com.
- Ooh, nice.
- Lovely stuff. - Throw this.
- Send us some freight bantos.
- Yeah.
- This Tokyo Sky Tower is a radio and television tower.
Now, we spoke about one very recently, the BT Tower.
So it's a hot topic on the fish world right now.
- This one is amazing.
I've been reading a bit about it.
- Oh, yeah, give us some.
- So guess what they did for the 10th anniversary
to celebrate it?
- Was it a pun?
- It was, no, it wasn't.
It was, okay, what's the famous Japanese cultural thing?
- Godzilla.
- More artist, even more artistic.
- Anime?
- Even more artistic.
(all laughing)
- AKB48.
- Kabuki theatre.
- Oh yeah. - Okay.
- Oh yeah.
- You know, this is the ancient centuries-old form of theatre.
And they have really famous actors,
and it's quite dynastic as well, isn't it?
So sometimes you'll do it because you're, you know,
great, great grandfather, et cetera, didn't it?
So for the 10th anniversary of the Sky Tree Tower,
they got a Kabuki actor called Inchikawa Ibizo the 11th
to perform his famous glare from the top of the building.
(all laughing)
- That's incredible.
- It's so good.
- There's a famous glare called the Nirami,
and it's done by moving each eye in different directions.
- Oh, that's cool.
- Which is good.
And also that means that Inchikawa Ibizo the 11th
could qualify as a fighter pilot,
'cause I believe you have to do that to be a fighter pilot.
- So you're also looking to different directions at once.
- I think you have to have one eye on the mig who's up ahead,
and you have to have one eye on your instruments.
So I think you need to be able to,
I think Prince Harry can do it.
- Wait, is this a thing that you can make yourself do?
- No, you can train for that.
- So your brain can take in two different...
- Yeah.
- And Harry's really good at doing those magic eye pictures.
- Definitely.
- It's incredible.
- All day outside of Thina, like I used to do.
Trying to see if he can get a book of those
and just go through them.
That's a tiger.
That's a butterfly.
That's a waterfall.
He can just do it.
- Wow.
- Okay.
- Anyway, there you go.
- Olga, when you went to Tokyo,
did you go to the Gotakuji Temple,
which has got all those sort of cats
that wave their arms?
Do you know those ones that you see in Chinese restaurants?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Well, there's a temple just outside,
it's just outside Tokyo, actually, where they have these.
And the idea is that there was a guy,
some priest or other was walking past
and a cat let him come into the temple
and then that became the sort of lucky cat.
And if you go there, there's thousands of them outside
and you can, you know, pay 100 yen and get your own one
and then write a message on it and stuff like that.
- That's really cool.
- So is the cat waving you in as opposed to waving hello to you?
- Yeah, it is.
- Right.
- And also, actually, probably they evolved
from waving penises, we think.
So probably this story is like a new story
and where they actually came is that they were used
in brothels and they would have these lucky talismans
in the shape of penises that weren't beckoning people
into the brothels.
There were things that evolved into the cats.
- I don't want to, I don't want to assume anything,
but wouldn't the average person not be going
to a brothel for a penis?
- No, but I suppose you just need to some kind of symbol
and it's hard to make a vagina wave.
(laughing)
- You tried.
- Good Lord.
- I could tell as I started, that said,
since I was not going to ed them all.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- Yeah, gosh.
But answer a question I did go and there's a tiny little cat
at that temple that just says, "Please help."
(laughing)
- I have found, certainly for anyone who's not living in Tokyo,
possibly the most famous musician that they have.
Certainly, their songs is known more than most songs out there,
right?
- So what you're saying is they're really famous in Tokyo,
but anyone else wouldn't have heard that.
- Yeah, and possibly in Tokyo,
they might not even know the name of the person,
but they will know the songs and be able to sing.
- Okay.
- The songs are there as impossibly any other composer.
- Are you gonna forget something?
- I think it's Mr. Meena, the home office funded.
(laughing)
- And given his boy band, they're huge in Tokyo.
- It's got to be the music in the underground, is that?
'Cause whenever you go on a train,
whenever you get into a station,
they play a certain song in every station.
- There you go.
- That's what it is.
So it's not what they call it, Mr. Meena.
- Mr. Meena, I've just heard the joke in that name.
Mr. Meena.
- Yeah.
- Mr. Meena.
- Yeah, that's good.
- Because that more mean.
- No, I think terrorism is Mr. Meena.
- I think it works at three levels.
- Get out.
- Wow, wow.
- This is huge.
- Arguably extreme terrorism is more than a Mr. Meena, isn't it?
- Mr. Meena.
(laughing)
- God.
- We took that, damn tell us.
- We were talking about joke.
- It's not Mr. Meena, it's Mr. Minoru.
- Brilliant.
- And this is Minoru Mukaya,
who is the underground train composer.
Every train station has its own unique jingle
for when a train comes in and goes out,
and he's done over 110 of them,
and he will visit each one,
and he will watch as the train comes in
and try and invoke what kind of feeling it gives you.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, I thought they were just random.
- No, he does it station by station,
and every single one will be like,
is this a historical area?
I'm gonna use all Japanese instruments.
Is this a new area?
We're gonna use synths and electron.
- Oh my God, so they're not even on the same style.
- No, exactly.
- That's so cool.
- That's a different song and different instruments.
- And it's not that it's useful for, say, blind people
who need to hear where they are.
- It probably is.
- We're recognizable.
- I gotta say, when I was in Tokyo,
we actually stayed near Shinjuku,
and whenever we got in, I would recognize this.
Like you would just recognize the songs
as you moved along,
and you would know, oh, our stations come in.
It's not always that easy with the different,
kanji and stuff, I guess.
- That was fantastic.
- What would you like for a whole burn?
- Ooh.
- That's a good question.
- Is it your theme tune?
- Yeah.
- There we go.
- For sure.
- What about Margate?
- Margate.
- Oh, God.
- I do like to be beside the seaside.
- Yeah.
- Absolutely.
- Also, the Libertyens live there, don't they?
- They do.
- Oh, yeah.
- There you go.
- Yeah, no neighbors.
- He's a friend.
- He's a teen.
(laughing)
- He's a light man.
- That's really light man.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that one idea
to block Russian expansion in Eastern Europe
is to create a 500 mile long bog.
- That's, it's so such a cool idea.
- It's a amazing idea.
- Well, I'm a big fan of Pete and bogs.
- And the big enemy of Russia.
(laughing)
- I'm favor a blocking Russian expansionism
seems we've had a bit of that here.
- Well, actually, like this is kind of one point of it.
So this is an article that I read in the week,
this week, and it's, it does two things
that the EU is really trying to do at the moment.
And that's number one, stop Russia from going west,
but also to stop climate change.
And bogs can do both of those.
- Yeah, 'cause if you get rid of a bog,
it releases a lot of CO2, doesn't it?
- Yeah, so if you make one, it stores CO2 back.
- So is this an extension of like trench warfare?
So you do a sort of World War I style trench
and then you fill it with Pete?
- It's kind of-- - How are we doing this?
- But you don't put any humans in it, I guess.
But basically, there's already a bog there.
- It's a kind of, it's a kind of phantom bog.
- It is a phantom bog. - It's a phantom bog.
- Well, it's, it kind of exists,
but it doesn't exist as much as they want it to.
So at the moment, if you go from,
let's say you go from Helsinki,
all the way down past the Baltic countries,
and then towards Poland and wherever,
if you go on that line,
there's a huge sort of boggy area that goes down there,
but what they're gonna try and do is make it more
and more boggy. - Can I ask who they are?
- NATO. - NATO, so it's NATO,
but it's also the governments of Estonia,
Latvia, Lithuania, and Poland.
And what they're trying to do is put more and more water there,
more and more peat there,
so that if anyone tries to come across, it's very difficult.
And that's something that's happened in history in warfare,
that you basically, you water a log an area,
and so just can't get past it.
- And what's really lucky is it says by chance almost,
all of these boggy areas are on the border,
but they're on NATO side of the border outside of Russia.
So you've got, as James says,
Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, it's all running down,
but they wouldn't have to go into Russia in order to build these bogs.
So what sort of they can just do it?
- I love how we go friendly this is.
This is cool. - Yeah.
- And even better, Kaliningrad,
which is like this little X-clave of Russia,
so it's still part of Russia, but it's not attached.
And Belarus, which is like a real ally of Russia at the moment,
there's a big old bog in between those places as well.
So it's like a really different,
that would be a really obvious place for an attack to happen
because you could put your troops into Belarus,
and you could go through Kaliningrad,
but actually there's a bog there, so you can't get through.
And dare I say, maybe this is going to sound very stupid,
but it almost makes you think that that's why the borders
were drawn there in the first place?
- You're probably right. - Yeah, okay.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Maybe here.
- It's not a coincidence that the bog is up there.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - It's almost like
in the head going down it.
- Damn it, it's an idiot.
- But it's really fascinating,
'cause lots of this land, the reason I say it's a phantom bog,
is that it's been drained.
There are ditches that have been cut,
and then the wet, watery mass of this land drains away,
and the bog dries out. - 'Cause they try to reclaim it
for years, for centuries, I'm saying.
- For agricultural purposes, you know,
it means you can expand your farming land.
And so all you need to do really is to stop draining them,
and block up the drainage ditches,
and then a couple of years later, you have a bog,
and there are all sorts of arguments going on about,
well, the farmers won't be very happy with this,
and they might need some kind of subsidies,
so I don't, it's not being hugely enacted,
but one of the guys proposing it is a guy called Hans Yuston,
who is known as the Peteland Pope.
I just like him so much.
- Yeah.
- Is that, is our bogs a solution to every problem?
- It's pretty much, yeah, yeah.
- Have we considered a bog?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, so it's fascinating.
And this was done at the start of the war in Ukraine,
as the Ukrainian army, they blew up a dam,
which turned the whole of this Irpan river basin
into a massive expanse of bogs and marshes,
and it turned the area into what one defense consultant
called an impossible turd.
It just means you cannot drive a tank through that, right?
And actually also Russia did the same in, in Zaporizia,
and they blew up another dam to stop the counter-offensive
of Ukraine, so both sides are blowing them up,
and also both of those dams were also blown up during World War II,
when Germany attacked and went towards Russia.
This exact same thing happened where they tried to stop
the Germans by blowing up these two particular one
on the Dnieper and one on the Irpan rivers.
- Can I ask, why are bogs not defeatable to most modern armies?
- The tanks can't get through them.
- Yeah, they can't support the wage.
- No one's invented a thing that can just go,
let's ride over the bogs.
- Erroplanes?
- Erroplanes.
- We have not considered an airplane.
(all laughing)
- No, like, you can get through the bogs,
but it just slows you right.
- Yeah.
- And when you're being slowed down,
you're more of a city duck.
- Yeah, and it forces you into a narrow path through the bog,
for example, and then your enemy can just focus
their fire on that narrow path.
- Yeah.
- So you sort of canalize your opponent.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, it's pretty amazing, isn't it?
- It is, and the bog might be a huge contributor to this.
- And like Andy says, it's like,
it's not really happening that much in the moment,
but in Finland, there isn't in Poland, it is.
So Finland have started reclaiming their bogs
for this specific reason in Poland as well.
So yeah, it is happening.
- And it's also just from a sort of purely philosophical
perspective, always very comforting when the solution
is like organic, as opposed to, it's like,
you know what's gonna defeat AI, bogs?
- Yeah, yeah.
It's like for the whole of 20th century, it was barbed wire.
But we had bogs all along.
- You're absolutely right.
Do you know what percentage of greenhouse gases
going into the atmosphere are due to degraded peatlands?
- Oh my god, Andy, I think you're gonna tell us.
(laughing)
- I guess you're guessing.
- Welcome to Quiz Corner, Andy.
So this is one of your quizzes,
so let me just guess another two more than 100, isn't it?
- Yeah, I'm gonna say 38%.
- Oh.
- Because 38% is my official number now
that that was the answer to a quiz question
about how much urine was in the international space.
- I'm gonna go it, she's 51%.
(laughing)
- To be completely honest, I was gonna say 51 as well.
Can you ask the question again?
- What percentage of greenhouse gases
going into the atmosphere?
- I think it must be much lower than
- I do to degraded peatlands.
- And I'm gonna be honest with you, I'll go.
- If it was 38% or 51% of all greenhouse gases
being due to degraded peatlands,
I think we might have got more of a move
on to solve the problem before now.
(laughing)
- You've gotta realize that in these quizzes,
sometimes callbacks is more important
and getting answered, right?
- I'm so sorry, and I think that's an unfair clue
to the final person in the quiz.
Olga, would you like to guess maybe the 80%
of all greenhouse gases due to degraded peatlands?
- I'm gonna throw in 11.
- Well, you're closest.
It's 4 to 5, not 45, otherwise 51 would have rocked home.
- Yeah, but it is double flight.
It's double all flights happening around the world.
All hundreds of thousands of flights happening,
you know, every day is due to degraded peatlands.
That's crazy.
- And you know what's bad for it?
- What, mushrooms.
- Is that so?
- I do not like mushrooms.
It has been long set on this podcast,
but in the UK.
- May trip.
(laughing)
- In the UK, the mushrooms that you eat
are made using peat that has been dug up from peatlands.
They have to basically put the peat on top of their,
like little bodies of mushrooms
and that's what helps them to fruit
and that's what helps you to get them.
And the UK mushroom industry
gives the equivalent emissions
of more than 2,600 cars.
- Okay.
- Someone took down the UK mushroom industry.
- Big mushroom, yeah.
- I will say quite a small number of cars, is it?
- Well, all mushrooms.
- I only have one car.
- Yeah, no, fair enough, fair enough.
- No, but like, obviously it is bad
to take peats out of areas
because it takes a long time to get them back.
So I think they are looking to find other ways
to make mushrooms rather than using peats.
- That's great.
- Am I correct in thinking
that they used to use it for whiskey and they stopped, right?
- They did that, I think they might still use it.
- I think it's now a significantly smaller amount
from what I, yeah.
- Interesting, 'cause everyone's gonna go peat-free
in terms of compost for your garden.
You can still buy peat stuff,
but there's been a big campaign saying,
"Can you use some peat-free?"
- Yeah.
- Comprehensive, you can't get.
So I didn't know that about the mushrooms.
- That's very cool.
- Have you guys heard about the 40 acre bog?
- 40 acre bog.
- Yeah, no.
This is in Lake Chippewa, which is in Wisconsin.
So this was a lake that was created in the 1920s.
They flooded a swamp in order to do it.
And as a result of it, this bog formed, that's 40 acres
and it sort of sits in the middle of the lake,
but it moves around.
- A bog in the middle of a lake.
- Yeah, it's pretty amazing.
So it's got sort of mud plains underneath it.
And on top, it's very grassy
and it's got a few trees like thin trees sticking out.
- I have seen this.
- Yeah, it's pretty amazing because it's transient.
It moves around all the time.
So what happens is there's a bridge
that goes over the lake
and this bog keeps coming towards the bridge.
And so what they do is they get all the boats
and they line up against the bog
and they shove it back out of the way.
They all drive the bog.
- Yeah.
- It's like an annual thing.
They have to do, they have to push the bog.
- Yeah, and it's not consistent.
They have to check every morning
that the bog isn't making its way back over it.
- How's that even work?
- I know, it's wild, isn't it?
If you've seen images of it, it's pretty cool.
- It's stunning.
- It's absolutely stunning.
- So it doesn't, I assume it doesn't go that deep
into the water if it's movable.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, it's not very far down.
- It's just floating, Pete.
- It's floating matter.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- That is so cool.
Does anyone know where is the world's biggest bog?
It's somewhere that's been mentioned
on this podcast already.
- Okay, okay.
- It's okay.
- Will it be somewhere,
I'm gonna guess somewhere in Eastern Europe,
somewhere like Belarus.
- You're close.
It's Russia.
- Okay.
- It's the great.
- I mean, if you have that much land mass,
statistically speaking.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- It's the great Vazugian Maya, it's in Siberia
and it is twice the size of Wales.
- Goodness.
- But again, to Russia, that's nothing.
'Cause they've got areas, the size of Wales coming out.
There is.
And it comes from melting permafrost, basically.
So the water, melts from the permafrost,
goes into this area and becomes a marshy land.
And the worst thing about it is the flies and midges
that live there.
If you ask locals, they say that there's so many midges
they can drink enough blood from a random traveler
that they will die of midge bites.
- Oh, the traveler will die.
Not the midge dies of.
- No, they'll have in a great time.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- But yeah, that's what they say.
And there is no doubt there is a lot of midges there,
but whether they can actually drain you
of all your blood, I think probably not.
But anyone who works there has to wear
like hazmat suit solvast or like beekeeper suits
so that they don't get bitten.
- Oh, not for me.
- Man.
- No, not for me.
I don't even like one midge.
- Now, we all know Ireland.
- Oh, I love him.
- Yeah.
- How many Walesers is that?
- They've got vast piti areas.
- They do.
- Okay.
- But how many Irish people, according to the latest census,
heat their homes by burning peat?
- 51.
- Okay.
- 38.
- Two.
- It's 68,000.
- Wow.
- 68,000.
- And I would have thought.
- Yeah, for sure.
- I thought we were doing percentages.
I don't think.
(laughing)
- Sorry.
- Well, there's one percent of the population,
so you're not far off.
- Is it really?
- Yeah.
- They've got these raised bogs.
- Thank you.
- But there are some bog bastards as I'm calling them.
- Bogdas.
- It's okay.
(laughing)
- Is that an official tab, or is it?
- For majors.
- That's an AHM original.
But those are people who aren't
sneakily cutting special conservation areas of bogs.
Because a lot of these bogs are now protected.
- From a scientific viewpoint,
why would I burn peat over wood?
- Is it, does it burn longer?
- I think just there's loads of peat around.
- Oh, okay.
- I think it would burn longer.
- Oh, would it?
- I think so, yeah.
- Right.
- I think it kind of turns more carbon, doesn't it?
- Mmm.
- I'm pretty sure.
- Those bogs in Ireland is where you would find
Tories speaking of bog bastards.
(laughing)
- I don't know.
- So Tories, I think as we've said before,
was an old sort of word for an outlaw in Ireland,
especially a Roman Catholic one.
They would call them Tories.
And then eventually it became,
I can't remember how it became a word for conservatives,
but it's always that word's from.
- Yeah, it's originally--
- It's fascinating.
- But yeah, they would live in the bogs,
these outlaws, and then they would come
and attack your sheep and stuff.
- Wow.
- We've got peat and Margate.
- Happy?
- Yeah, peat talkative.
(cheering)
- A lot of annoying me all the time, eh?
- Yeah, here we go.
- That's number one comedy podcast.
(laughing)
- In the end.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is, when the first ever online pizza delivery
was made, a hundred journalists turned up to report on it.
The driver got lost.
It took an hour to deliver,
and the pizza was long cold.
- Wow.
- So this is something that was printed in the LA Times
in 1994, which I love to read.
- Well, only a few months before TLC released
Crazy Sexy Cool.
- It's the 1994 podcast.
- Yeah.
- It really is.
- Clive Davis was the one to order the pizza
to sort of try and get out of the hospital situation.
- Please help.
(laughing)
- It's typing.
- Yeah, there was this article headline,
online pizza idea is clever,
but only half-baked, brilliant.
And it was by Pizza Hut, giants of the scene.
- Oh, they always do stuff like that.
- They always do stuff like that.
- But this one was genuinely an innovation.
So they launched the thing called Pizza Net.
It was in Santa Cruz,
and I think this was hosted at the University
of California, Santa Cruz.
Basically, no one had really tried,
not many people had done e-commerce like this,
especially not with a pizza.
- It was not in 1994.
- This is so long ago.
And you had to put in your stats.
You had to put in your order.
The data was then sent to Pizza Hut HQ in Kansas,
quite a long way away.
It was relayed via a modem to your nearest Pizza Hut branch,
who would then phone you up to check
that you weren't pranking them.
And then eventually, after that had all been gone through,
then they would start making you your pizza
and deliver it to your home.
And they got a hundred journalists in
to report on this.
- People had the internet by them.
I reckon it was about them.
I went to Georgiaal Bank,
which is a big telescope in the north of England.
And that was the only place that had the internet.
- Yeah, that's like, I've never seen the internet.
- Did you go online?
- Yeah, what did you do?
I searched, I was really into fantasy football at the time.
So I searched for the word fantasy
and got as a 14-year-old boy.
- Uh-oh.
- A lot of knowledge that I didn't wish previously had.
- Oh my gosh.
- Nice.
- Did you have a Georgiaal Bank?
(laughing)
- Anyway, yeah.
- It is early internet, isn't it?
And 94, that's when Amazon launched.
- Yeah, 95 is when eBay launched.
It's way older than I realised.
- There was almost nothing on the internet back then.
Newspapers would run articles saying,
"Here are the best websites to go to."
Which I love.
I think we could do with that again.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause the internet's been sort of,
it's like there are now only about what four websites now.
- I'm always looking for a new website.
I love a new website.
- What do you mean?
- I want new cool stuff.
- It used to be when I started working at QI
that you could search for carrot facts
and you would get a page of someone
who really liked carrots, writing 20 incredible facts.
- That's what I want.
- Really well solved about carrots.
- In comic sands with like a sort of my spacey
background of carrots.
- No, you put in carrot facts and AI goes.
- Did you know that carrots are all green?
And you're like, "Oh right, are you sure?"
I think they're orange.
Oh yes, they are.
Orange, I'm sorry about that.
- Wait, you guys are extremely smart.
This is unrelated to anything.
But can someone explain to me,
I'm the one, the quote unquote tech person here.
Why can't it say I don't know?
And second, well, why can't it tell me where it got its knowledge?
- 'Cause it's stolen from somewhere else
and they don't want to reveal it?
- Yeah, that's fair.
- I'm sure I can Google this.
It would just be so much more reliable
if it said I don't know.
- Wouldn't it be great?
- But I'm not interested in making a better product.
Never mind.
- But don't you think that?
That's just true of humans in general, right?
So many people, if you ask them,
especially people on the internet,
if you ask them something,
they'll just pretend they know the answer and say,
"If we all learned how to say I don't know a bit more,
then wouldn't the world be a better place?"
I don't know.
Grubhub, have you heard of Grubhub?
- Love Grubhub.
It's like delivered food for Americans or something.
- Yeah, I don't really know.
- Are we overpeats a hunt?
I just have one more thing to say,
which is I had assumed that hiring Gorbachev
to be in one of their ads was the coolest thing
they did in the '90s.
- Wow.
- Essentially, it's Gorbachev
enjoying pizza at Pizza Hut.
And then different people at the restaurant
are debating whether he's a good or bad guy.
- Right.
- And the ending is, well, he's the one who brought pizza Hut.
So I guess the conclusion is that you can't beat Pizza Hut,
but it was more nuanced in terms of where people were standing.
- Wow.
- Then you'd think.
- Pizza Hut in our times.
That's a joke about pizza in our time.
- Yeah.
- Which was something that Gorbachev didn't say.
- That was another table in.
I felt us literally just moved to number two
in the comedy challenge, so I said, I don't know.
Did you guys feel that?
It's like a shudder pizza Hut in our times.
(laughing)
- Ooh.
Meanwhile at Parenting Pal, they're like,
"Oh, did you feel that?
"I just felt like we lifted you up."
I think we've just done a terrible job.
- In my house, we grew up with a giant painting
of Gorbachev on our lounge room wall.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Again, I'm gonna say lie.
- Is that true?
- Yeah.
We had one of him and one of Chairman Mao.
- What?
- Yeah, so it was knockoffs of Andy Warhol's collection
of Pop Art, and they bought it in a market somewhere.
But I grew up with Gorbachev on my wall,
wondering, who is this guy?
Is he good or bad, you know?
- Interesting.
- Do you know the pizza?
- We grew up with this.
- Things had resolved that.
- Yeah, all you had to do was watch the ad.
- We grew up with a series of Russian leader
themed matrioshka in my house.
- Ah, did you?
- Yeah, you know the Russian dolls.
The one on the outside was the biggest one.
- I have a name.
(laughing)
- Lovely.
And we're back to number one.
(laughing)
- That's good.
- The big one was it Stalin on the outside.
- The big one was the newest one
who was Yeltsin at the time.
- Yeltsin.
- And then it was going all the way back to London,
I think.
- Grubhub is a food delivery system online, right?
It was started by a guy called Colin Wallace
and he was a school child
and he wanted to get a sandwich to his classroom
without the teacher noticing.
And so he created a computer program
which took a text from his phone,
sent it to a fax, which was delivered to a restaurant,
and then they would send the sandwich to the classroom.
- Right, amazing.
- That's genius.
- And then eventually sort of turn that into a much bigger thing
and then got bought out by some squillianaires.
But yeah.
- Okay.
- Are you the origin stories?
- I don't know if you guys do business ideas here.
- Oh yeah, we're doing, we're doing.
None of them has taken off yet.
- Okay, but like you know how there's like the founder movie,
right, which is like for the MacDonald's founder movie,
like that type of thing.
Imagine with that, it would be like a Disney channel
original founder movie about like a guy in school.
- Yeah.
- Oh, that's a cute idea.
- Wouldn't that be so cute?
- So you've come up with an idea for a cultural thing.
- Yes.
- A movie pitch, don't worry, we do those too.
- Okay, sorry, I take it back.
It wasn't a business idea.
It was a business idea for us to make money off this movie.
- Yeah, it's a great, yeah.
That's really good.
- Like a kids founder movie.
- It's like capitals for kids.
- So what's it called?
Grubhub.
- It's something about sandwich, something about fax.
- We can do this.
- We can definitely do this.
Come on guys, number one.
This is why we're number one.
(laughing)
- Breadie steady go.
- No.
- For kids film.
- It's like, yeah, it's gotta be like something about
recess, school, a detention, but with bread in it.
- Just put the word bread into the word detention.
Yeah.
(laughing)
- Depredution.
- The new number one, I don't know if you've got it.
(laughing)
- It's good to have something to be asked about
in interviews on the press round.
So how do we say the name of this?
(laughing)
How's it pronounced?
- Depredution.
(laughing)
- Podd you see?
- It's gonna be huge in Japan.
(laughing)
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- I'm so sorry.
- That might be the one that takes off.
(laughing)
- Yeah, last week's Google for Smells did not go anywhere.
So we're up for different ideas.
- Can I tell you guys about Jane Snowball?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Okay, she was a 72 year old British woman
and she did the first ever online grocery order.
In what year?
- 1951.
(laughing)
- 1938.
- You've got a real chance to score the triple here.
(laughing)
- Okay, I'm going in '96.
- '96, it's 1984.
And this is insane.
- Wow, but you said she was in her seventies?
- Yes.
- Wow.
It was simply the end user of the product.
She had very little to do with the development.
(laughing)
- I'm sorry.
- But I still think in your seventies at that time.
- That's true.
- It's gonna be tough to use new technology.
- Absolutely.
- No offense to anyone in the seventies,
but like it's become more difficult
to get older.
- But she's 72.
This is 1984.
This is a long time ago.
- Well hang on.
- That's when I was born.
It's not that long.
- It is a lot.
- Imagine that.
- No one has the internet in their homes.
- Yeah.
- You know.
- Basically.
- It's my entire time we're speaking.
I'm trying to put the word sub into CEO.
(laughing)
- Is it fitting?
- Sorry.
- Keep working on it Olga.
But it's, I'll tell you.
- If I look distracts.
- I'll tell these guys.
But basically, she lived in Gateshead.
She had a bad hips.
She couldn't get to the shops.
And there was this thing being run by Gateshead Council
called the Gateshead Shopping Experiment.
And this developer, Michael Aldrich,
set up a thing where she could use
her TV to get access to every huge number of shops.
- And I could tell it actually.
- It's something.
- Kind of.
I'm slightly struggling with how exactly it worked.
'Cause I don't think she was pressing her screen.
She shouldn't have been anyway.
But it allowed her to go through every product
that the shops had and order via her telly.
It was unbelievably advanced at the time.
- Do we now have a name for the boy?
- For what?
- The boy in the film.
- Yeah.
- He was called Colin Wallace.
- Wallace.
- Greg's Wallace.
- I don't know if it's like Walson Grame,
but the grame has to be bread.
- Wallace and Grubhub.
- Grubhub.
- Wallace and Grady bread.
- No, keep going.
- Grain Hill.
- 'Cause it's Grange Hill.
- He's good.
- He's actually good.
- School-based thing.
- We can go on that.
- No, no, no.
- So sorry.
- We'll get it eventually.
We would usually move on, but it's such a good idea.
(laughing)
- Podcast@QI.com, send in your titles for
The Bread Based.
- Disney Channel Original Movie.
- What's it about?
Oh, the Grubhub.
- Yeah, CEO.
- Teen CEO of Grubhub.
- Inventor, yes.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Should we wrap up soon?
- Yeah.
- All right, here's a quiz.
What was the first thing sold securely on the internet?
It's also 1994.
- Yeah.
- It's about 10 days before the pizza idea was launched.
- The first thing ever sold on eBay
was a broken laser pointer.
- Very good.
- I know that.
- But this was before that, right?
- Yeah, it's the first time anyone bought anything
that was properly with secure data.
So previously, people had used our penet
to buy and sell weed, things like that.
But that was just arranging a meeting place.
That's not properly an online transaction.
- Was it an OASIS album?
1994?
- It's an album.
- Oh.
- Okay.
- It's not CLC's crazy sexy cool, is it?
- No.
- Is it someone from the '90s?
- I'd say so.
He's still alive.
- I know the answer to this,
I'm bowing out of the course.
- Oh, okay.
Brian Adams?
- Oh, good guess.
- Good answer.
- Good guess.
- I'm just transporting it to '94.
- Not bad.
Who else is?
- Meatloaf.
- British?
There's no way of saying it without you immediately.
- Else a job.
- He likes having sex for a really long time.
- Rod's doing?
(laughing)
- With his wife, Trudy Styler.
- Yeah.
- Is it stink?
- It's stink.
It was Sting's album, 10 Summoner's Tales.
And it was a guy called Phil Brandon Berger.
Phil Adolfier.
- This weirdly, this fact unites all of our facts today.
Because it was bought in 1994.
- Yeah.
- That's TLC.
It was the first major hit he had since his previous hit,
which was called "Rushens."
- Uh-huh.
- Very nice.
And the title of the album, what was it Andy?
- 10 Summoner's Tales.
- It's a pun.
- Is it a pun?
- His surname is Sumner, isn't it?
- His surname is Sumner, and it is a pun on the Canterbury Tales
of which there was a character called Sumner.
So it's got a pun, it's got Russia,
and it's got 1994, the release of TLC.
- Damn, and the show now, that's amazing.
- That's like, that's a bravier.
That's a now-you-see-me-three level.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Oh, bravier.
- And that's a compliment.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
- If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can all be found
on our social media accounts.
I'm on @Shrybeland on Instagram, James.
- Come find me on TikTok.
No, so you think it's James Harkin?
- Andy.
- Instagram @AndryHunterRab.
- Yep, and Olga.
- Everywhere at Koga 300.
- Yeah, nice.
And you've just announced a tour, haven't you?
- Yes, I'm touring my new show, Fat Tom Cruise,
all around the world.
- You're so good at titles.
What the hell happened in the show?
(laughing)
- Goodbye, take us to my tour at rock and rollga.com.
- Lovely, cool, yeah, and if you want to get through
to us with anything that we've said
as a group on this podcast, podcast at QY.
- Guys, dough, dough is money.
- Oh, yes.
- But dough is bread.
- Yes, dough boy.
- Dan!
Oh my god.
- So boy.
- Oh my god, that's so good, sorry.
Oh my god, last second.
(laughing)
- No need to write it now.
- Yeah, do not write in any more.
(laughing)
Olga saved the day.
But if you want to talk about anything else but that,
they're shaking hands to see, you know what it is.
The deal has been done.
(laughing)
- Podcast@QY.com, send us all your stuff there.
Andy goes through the emails.
He cherry picks the best of them
and he brings them to our special club fish,
which is our private members club,
secret, extra bonus show, so secret.
(laughing)
It's called Drop Us Align.
Anyway, we read all that stuff out there.
If you want to be part of club fish,
go to no such thing as a fish.com.
You can find all details there.
Find any details about upcoming live shows.
You'll find all our previous episodes.
Just check it out.
If not, just come back next week
'cause we will be back with another episode.
We will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)