Hi everybody, Andy here.
Just before we start this week's episode, wanted to introduce you to our special guest.
This week's guest is the brilliant Stevie Martin.
If you haven't heard of Stevie, you are in for a treat.
She is a fantastic comedian.
Everything she makes is good.
She makes wonderful sketches.
She's in shows.
She's on stuff.
And if you want to hear more of her after this episode, which you will, check out her
podcast which is called "Nobody Panic".
It's a great show.
It contains advice about absolutely everything in the world.
How to do your taxes.
How to brush your hair.
Some even funnier things than that, can you believe it?
And it's a great show.
I think I did an episode recently which is coming up for release, but just start listening
to that now.
Once again, it's called "Nobody Panic".
Hope you enjoy this show.
On with the podcast.
Hello, and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing is a Fish, a weekly podcast coming
to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Andrew Honto Murray, Anna Toshinsky, and Stevie Martin.
And once again, we have gathered round the microphones with our four favorite facts
from the last seven days, and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Stevie.
My fact is that Australia is wider than the moon, except technically it's not.
What?
Hello.
You can't row back row back.
I did some verification.
I think you're absolutely right.
Come on.
Back myself more says my mom, but so it is, if I was looking at it, it would be, but
if I was like taking into account surface area, perhaps, and the fact that it's a sphere,
that's all right.
That's not what you said.
Yeah, man.
Why does?
We moved Australia, so it's in the place of the moon.
Yeah.
It would be, it would cover it from left to right and then some.
Like an eclipse.
Like it could, you could move the moon and it would block the sun, possibly.
Would it?
Australia, yeah.
It may not be tall enough.
I don't know.
Is Australia quite flat?
Is it a flat boy from the top to the bottom?
It's white.
I think that you would get bits of moon poking out.
I don't think there's any Australia arrangement that totally covers the moon, but it's definitely
wider left to right.
There's no doubt.
You might be able to cut bits off or move Tasmania, for instance, to one of the poking
out bits.
They'd love that.
Politically controversial plan already.
Feels like they probably had to put up with a lot.
I don't know.
I don't know anything about it.
So the moon is about three and a half thousand kilometres across and Australia's about, when
we look at it in the sky, Australia's about 4,000 kilometres.
Yeah, it's about 4,000, yeah.
Did you know that the smallest moon of Jupiter, which is so small, it's called, just called
Jupiter, L-I-I, it doesn't have a name, is the same size as Vatican City?
Is it?
Yeah.
It's almost not worth it.
It's not worth it.
Do we know it's a moon?
Does anyone know what the smallest amount has to be for it to be a moon?
Oh, there are all sorts of...
Is it the Vatican City?
Is that it?
That's it, yeah.
Yeah.
If it can have a pope, it's a moon.
It's a moon?
That's it.
It's hugely contentious.
That question's hugely contentious in that world.
Okay, we'll get emails, just dozens, hundreds of emails now that you've asked it.
Wait, yeah.
Doesn't the moon have a bishop?
I'm sure we've vaguely said this in the past, that there is a guy whose role is a bishop
of the moon.
Oh, yes, yeah.
When they tried to claim it as theirs, yeah, and they got given its own bishop.
I mean, I think self-proclaimed.
Is that like when I was 14, my mom bought me a little plot of land on the moon, and
you get a little deed.
So I got a deed.
Oh, no.
You did that.
So there's any mineral rights in maybe a centimetre square somewhere on the moon.
You'll get none of it.
I will get none of it, because it's not legally binding, because I'm sure she bought it like
a paper chase.
But the bishop thing, I think, checks out.
Imagine if there was a bishop in my bit.
That's it.
Well, that's why the Pope Mobile has that dome over the top, the bubbles.
Because people own it.
It's so that if he needs to, he can operate in a lunar environment.
Yes.
I also own a small square of the Pope as well, so I got my 15th birthday.
Wouldn't it be crazy for the UN or whoever it is to say, right, we are going to divide
up the moon, but we've decided that paper chase are the people who are going to administer
this system.
You do need people to do admin.
You do.
They might have put in the best bid.
You're absolutely right.
I don't think that's too far a crazy idea.
They've got the paper to make the certificates.
I think it's a really...
It was high GS ads.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It was.
Here's an interesting thing.
So the space between the moon and the earth, right?
Yeah.
So that is roughly, because it changes all the time, but like it's furthest.
It's big enough that you could take all of our planets in the solar system and you could
put them next to each other in one big row and they would all fit between the space,
between the earth and the moon.
No.
Yeah, that is weird.
How?
It's not extraordinary.
Sorry.
I forgot to mention, I'm not true to it.
I always think we don't make a massive enough deal about the coincidence of the moon and
the sun and the fact that we can have a full eclipse, right?
Because the only reason we can have a full solar eclipse is the fact that the moon and
the sun look exactly the same size to us on earth.
And that's just a total coincidence.
It's just proportionally the size of the moon and the distance of the moon from us
makes it the same size to us.
And then in a million years, when the, because the moon's moving away like a few centimetres
a year, we won't have full eclipses anymore because it'll be too far away to cover the
entirety of the sun.
Yeah.
And the chances were just infinitismally tiny.
And I think that is evidence for a higher power.
If ever there was it, the fact that they're basically the same size to us.
I like the idea that in the future, when it's, when the moon is smaller and it goes across,
it'll make the sun look like a bagel.
Oh, yeah.
A really stingy bagel, though.
Why don't you get your bagel that thin with a huge hole?
Yeah.
I like that.
Can I tell you about the first Australian person to go to space?
Oh, yeah.
Paul Desmond Scully Power.
Cool.
It's the first ever astronaut.
I'm calling him.
Nice.
I did try and find online if anyone's used that.
I don't think anyone's says astronaut.
Maybe because...
Trade market now.
It happened to one guy.
Also, it could be like Austrian as well, so it's kind of confusing.
Oh, yeah.
That'll lead to heaps of confusion.
Yeah, sorry.
I was confused.
Duns and duns.
But he was also the first astronaut with a beard.
Wow.
Yeah.
In the grapity, his beard would be flip more of the place like he was a wizard.
Exactly.
Was it like my beard or we talking Gandalf?
It's in between...
He didn't have a Gandalf beard, very sadly.
I think even NASA did try and make him shave and he said, "No, it's fine."
So they tried to make a joke, they said it won't form an airtight seal and presumably
Eula's Fixie-8.
And he said obviously it'll be all right and it won't make a risk.
She'll be right.
He is so Aussie, it's brilliant.
He said going to space was just one of those things that happened because he started off
as an oceanographer and then he liked surfing and was studying maths and then he got into
the Aussie Navy and then he exchanged over to the US Navy and they said, "We need someone
to do a naval study, an ocean study rather from space."
So do you want to get on board?
And he did.
He's founded a drone company called The Ripper Group.
He's created Shark Finding AI.
Oh my God.
He's just like...
It's in his contract conforming to stereotype.
Really?
We'll only let you up there if...
I know.
As the shuttle was about to take off, you know, you're sitting like, I guess you're facing
the sky so you're sort of lying on your back beneath the chair, right?
What did he do?
He fell asleep.
No!
Okay.
And he was like, "He like barbecued something."
Exactly.
He stood in a surf position as he went up.
And his beard was sort of parted as they went...
That's all you could see is the rocket left the atmosphere, two strands of beard.
Anyway, what a guy.
What's he named?
What's he called?
He's called Paul Desmond Scully Power.
What a great name.
Yeah.
Paul Power.
That's brilliant.
There's just, speaking of the moon and Australia, I found a really cool thing online and it's
an interactive page and it's created, is this website that's created by the people who wrote
a book called Cosmos, the Infographic Book of Space, which I think has loads of really
cool infographics about space in it, as you'd expect.
Whoa!
So, Shane, they couldn't nail that onto the camera somehow.
They needed me writing their subtitles.
Your Amazon reviews of books are so shit right now, they're so bad.
Anyway, they've also got a website and they have this whole interactive section and one
of the interactive sections, which I strongly amend that you Google, is you can see how
high a human or a kangaroo could jump on various celestial bodies.
So they'll drop down, you can select human or kangaroo, no other things.
Because they're the two main ones that would go into space and then, yeah, you can see
how high they jump.
So, on the moon, we could jump three metres, pretty good, kangaroo, eleven metres, better.
It's always better than kangaroo.
That's good to say.
It's relative, isn't it?
It's really fun.
Quite a lot.
It really tricks you and I've wasted a lot of time because it has things like some of
the tiniest moons in the solar system and it'll do see how high you could jump on this
and you click jump and then you sit there as it goes up and up and it doesn't really tell
you if it's going to go on forever or if it's going to stop at some point.
So I did sit there for about eight minutes watching it go up and up thinking, I wonder
if I'm coming back down and sometimes you don't.
Really?
Yeah, well, it's a bit sad, don't jump from asteroids and stuff.
You know how the moon looks too big, it looks bigger than it is when we look at it.
Too big.
When you look at the moon and the nice guy, what a beautiful moon, then you take a photo
and there's a dot.
Yes.
Oh.
I did that this morning.
Right.
Yes.
And it's really weird, it's a weird effect.
Yeah, why is that, though?
Well, we sort of prioritise it more with our eyes, but there are various reasons why, sometimes
the moon looks very big near the horizon because it's closer to things that we recognise like
houses or trees or whatever, you sort of see it in reference to those and you think it's
bigger than it is.
But wait, are you saying that it takes you so long to grapple to get your camera that
by the time you've taken the photo it's actually moved up into the sky?
No, because even when you look at it in the night sky it looks bigger to our eyes than
it does on a camera.
Okay.
Cameras are telling the truth.
But there is a way of negating the effect of the moon, this effect of it looking too
big, which is look at it upside down.
Oh.
Yeah.
How do I turn my head up?
I do a headstand.
You go to Australia.
You put your head between your legs as you're standing there and it looks the right size
again.
Really?
Yeah, this was studied by two Japanese scientists.
They wanted an ignoble prize for their paper.
That's for telling people to put their head between their legs, look at me.
Perceived size and perceived distance of targets for you from between the legs.
I almost want to disagree with them, but it's a fact.
You haven't tried it.
True.
But next time you're out on a romantic night time stroll and the person you're with says,
"Look at the lovely moon."
You can say to them, "No, look at it between your legs and we'll see it."
That works.
You know, like sometimes, I think it was the last year, you could see Jupiter really well
next to the moon and yeah, I looked at some planes, but then I also did see Jupiter.
So if I looked between my legs, it would look like Jupiter.
Yes.
It brings it closer.
Oh wait, no, it's a make it smaller.
It looks smaller.
It looks smaller between your legs.
Oh, for God's sake.
So I want to be opposite.
Okay, fine, Ryan.
Could we have a leg stream ahead?
It'll bring it for Ryan.
Okay.
Good, thank you.
Check this out.
I don't fully understand the science of this, but I find it amazing because it's true.
And that is that on a rainy day, if the moon is overhead, it's going to rain less.
I know.
Yeah.
That frightens me on a very deep level.
On a rainy day.
Yeah.
If the moon is overhead, it's going to rain less.
So if the moon, rather than like sometimes you see the moon, which is like closer to
horizontal.
On the horizon.
Yeah, exactly.
And then you get high in the sky, right?
The moon.
Yeah.
Different spots.
When it's there, let's say it's a cloudy day and it's raining, it's going to rain less.
But it's already.
Is it the gravitational pull?
Is it sucking?
Yeah.
Sucking in the rain?
So the rain goes off in the air towards the moon?
What are you saying?
Space rain is what happens.
Upside down, space rain.
Okay.
Well, it just doesn't, it just, it stays within the atmosphere.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Close.
So the gravitational pull with the moon, it's all to do with the kind of pressure that
it's creating around in the air as well.
So the pressure can suck up the moisture that's in there.
So it's just kind of, it's not, it's not weighted so that it falls down.
But so it will still rain, but by less.
It does.
It does make sense.
It would be freaking bizarre if it just didn't rain in a Truman show way.
Yeah.
But it's less by 1%.
That's a lot.
Oh.
It's not a lot.
Contrary.
Sorry.
That's a really relevant.
There's a lot of rain.
I was about to leave my umbrella at home before Dan said it's 1%.
I think I'll take it anyway.
Yeah.
But you can drill a hole in your umbrella that's 1% the size of it.
And then as long as that's in the right position, then it won't matter.
Are you fine?
Yeah.
It's a thought.
They did this.
Science.
They studied it for ages.
They were looking at reports.
And then they looked at meteorological reports.
They go all the way back to the 1800s.
And they found that on the days where the moon was in those positions.
1% less rainy.
I just love that fact so much.
Australia's got its first ever moon rover.
It was getting its first ever moon rover.
Okay.
This is quite cool.
Yeah.
It's going to go on.
Why?
Why are they doing that?
It's just being included on a future mission.
I think Australia has a space program.
Ask Paul Power.
And it's going to be included.
But I'd just like to see, can you guess the name?
There were 8,000 suggestions.
Oh, okay.
Of the name.
And one winner.
And it's gettable.
And it's an Aussie.
Is it Mooney McMoon face?
It's not Mooney McMoon face.
It is something actually Australian.
And you're going to kick yourselves right up the arse.
Big old moon spider.
That's good.
It's a rover.
It's a car.
It's a rune rover.
You're so close.
This is agony.
What did you say?
I'm going to give it to you.
Roover is what its name is.
What?
I was way closer.
What did you say?
Rune rover.
Yeah.
Absolutely not.
That was a shock.
Wait, say it again.
What is it?
Roover.
Come on.
You should put kangaroo in front.
She said kangaroo.
Kangarova.
It was closer than rune rover.
I had to say it.
Not saying anything.
Just being like, mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Anyway, it's going to be called Roover.
And it will weigh about the same as a western grey kangaroo.
Cool.
Or four wallabies.
Is that deliberate?
That's deliberate.
That's integral to the design.
Four wallabies by wallabies.
OK.
It is time for fact number two.
And that's my fact.
My fact this week is that as a child,
Roald Dahl was used as a guinea pig
for a chocolate factory.
Cool.
That's very on the nose.
Yeah.
Makes me wonder about all the other books as well.
Like, did he have a big peach one day?
Was he a twit?
Yeah, no.
So he went to the school called Repton.
And at Repton, there was a local Cadbury's.
It was either a factory or it was just a base
where they were sending chocolate out for it
to be tested around the country.
Either way, what they used to do was they used to
ask for kids from the school to apply to be guinea pigs
in order to test out these chocolates
and see whether they were fit for the market.
And Dahl happened to be there at the time.
So he would have been like 13, 14 years old at the time.
Yeah, he spent four years at this place.
And it had a huge impact on him.
He did think off the back of it,
what's going on inside these chocolate factories?
I bet it's a marvellous incredible place.
And it was the seed for what then became Charlie
and the Chocolate Factory.
The pod.
It was a lot of injuries.
But Charlie was there.
My chocolate had a finger in it this week.
Marvel.
Wow.
Do we know if any of the kids in that classroom,
when the teacher said,
"Have we got any volunteers to test out chocolate
in a chocolate factory?"
Was there a single child who didn't put their hand up?
Yeah.
It's like a dream for a child.
Oh my God.
Yeah, it's a dream gig.
Professional chocolate testers are a thing.
But not again, not many of them.
And it's not as good a gig as maybe Dahl made it sound.
You get quite sick, wouldn't you?
You also develop an incredibly advanced palate.
Oh, so nothing satisfies you.
You're ruined.
Basically, you get chocolate that's a few hours old.
It's ultra-fresh.
And it's delicious.
And you're always thinking whenever you eat anything else,
you're ruined for your keys, basically.
You can't just taste like trash to you.
But one thing they do is,
real chocolate experts and testers,
they listen to the chocolate.
Okay.
What's this thing?
What's going on there?
It's like a phrase.
Like wine has a nose or whatever.
It literally is.
They listen to it.
They listen to the snap sound it makes.
When you break a piece of the chocolate,
they'll give it a listen to make sure.
Is there a thing like with cheese where once I went to a party
and someone was like,
"Oh, we've fridgeed the brie for too long."
And they were like panicking.
Did you like fridge chocolate or not?
You know, because if you put it in the fridge and then you snap it,
it goes...
Lovely snap.
But would they hate that?
Probably.
I'm sure they would hate all sorts of things.
I'm sure the refrigerator chocolate is probably a deep no-no.
It probably is.
You'd be sacked immediately.
If you knew anyone who'd ever done it, probably.
Yeah, that's true.
But they do.
Actually, someone I know went on a chocolate expert in for the day.
Great.
As a team building exercise,
I think they did a chocolate tasting.
Oh, okay.
Just to the house.
Yeah, good things.
And the chocolate expertier came around too.
I want a chocolate expertier.
This is going great.
Right?
You know, all these quite serious business people who work in finance.
And they all had to...
They were all sitting there listening to their chocolate.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Like a tuning fork.
Wow.
Yeah, they do.
Jobs don't come up much sort of publicly for chocolate factories.
But occasionally, Cadbury will sort of say,
"We're looking for new taste testers."
And they did that at one point where they put a sort of open audition out.
And there's so many, 4,000 applicants.
Everyone went.
And they made the point of saying,
"This isn't going to be easy.
This isn't just you sitting and eating chocolate saying,
"Wow, how yummy."
Like, it's really intense.
They had to go spend two and a half hours a day having their taste buds
put to different chocolate tasting tests.
They had to sit in a soundproof booth.
They had red lasers going around so that they could see the type of...
Why they had a soundproof booth?
To hear the chocolate.
I guess it was a sensory booth rather than soundproof.
But it's a similar thing.
Sorry, you said that they said,
"Oh, it's not just about eating loads of chocolate all day."
But the first thing you said was they had to sit
and have their taste subjected to loads of chocolate for ages.
I mean, that was just eating loads of chocolate.
No, no, but I think, yeah.
Intensely, though.
But it's intensely.
I think they're slightly trying to SAS what is quite a nice job.
You obviously have to write down quite a little detail, I guess,
about what you're tasting.
Because they don't like work.
They don't like if you say,
"Mmm, caramelly."
They're like, "No, no, no.
We want the components.
We want the makeup of this.
We don't need to say anything."
They should know what to do already.
They shouldn't be required to retro-engineer their chocolates for them.
No, no, no.
I should be saying if I like it or not.
No, because you want to be able to say,
"Oh, that hint of nutmeg is really speaking to me."
You know, they want to...
They don't like it.
The extra bits.
You see what you mean, yeah, yeah, yeah.
You don't want to just go, "Wow, that's caramelly."
That's...
My one was shaped like a tiny seahorse, and I love that.
A keyard.
I once did a...
for Aussie shampoo.
I went in and tested their new scent.
Oh!
I just remember smelling one and being like immediately,
they were like, "So what are the components can you smell?"
And all I could think of was like, "It smells like a man one."
"It smells like a musky, like a musk man one."
And they were like, "Yes, because of why?"
And it was like, "Because it's like other men's shampoo."
And then I didn't lose anything for the rest of the hour,
because I was like, "I actually can't smell."
That's what I discovered.
Unless it's like, "Yeah, a man one."
Sounds like they pay you in advance for that job.
They do pay you in advance for that job.
Yes, thank God, otherwise it would have, yeah.
Well, I think it is nice enough that employees at the Cadbury's Factory,
and this was established about 10 years ago, so it may not be a true now,
but they can still eat as much of the product as they like,
and they do tend to put on half a stone in the first 10 days of their employment.
10 days?
Yeah.
And then I imagine you pair back.
I don't think you keep on gaining half a stone for every 10 days.
I would have thought they'd have a bucket.
You know, you spit your chocolate into the bucket.
Like tobacco, like a cowboy, or a bit joyless, yeah.
Maybe they do, but then you can eat whatever you like from that bucket at the end of the day.
Like a fondue.
Yeah, because I assume they all just have no teeth, right?
Yeah.
But then you guys come in again, and they're like,
"We want to be careful about the first 10 days."
You do put on weight, but you save weight because your teeth aren't quite a lot.
It feels like a great job.
So, hey, Cadbury.
That was the biggie.
That was the thing that started chocolate off, basically,
in terms of this big global Willy Wonka-esque world.
Well, for me, that's Cadbury's always been the global brand.
And so it started by a guy called John Cadbury.
I was looking into him.
He was born in Birmingham.
He's the son of Richard Cadbury and his wife, Elizabeth Head.
Very sad that they didn't take on the double barrel surname,
because you would have had Dickhead Cadbury.
That would have been a lovely name.
And then, check this out, his second wife.
Actually, his middle name was Tapper, so that's good anyway.
Dick Tapper.
Would you like a nice fruit and nut Dick Tapper?
What is his wife called, Ballant?
So his second wife was called Candia.
He married a Candy.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
So he was an amazing guy, John Cadbury.
He was very into animal rights.
He set up the Animals Friends Society,
which basically is what led into the RSPCA eventually coming about.
It was sort of the forerunner and sort of molded into that.
And then he passed his company on to his sons,
and they set up this incredible place, because they were Quakers.
And so they've got this little place called Bourneville,
which was given its name because it sounded French,
and therefore would sound really kind of upper class.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
So they just gave it--
They didn't fly for some reason.
Welcome out in the mayoral dickhead town.
And it's a model village.
It's a model village, and it's still going to stay.
I find the terminology model village quite confusing,
because it means two quite different things.
You're right.
He didn't set up a village of tiny houses that you can--
That's what I thought it was.
Wow, what a great hobby.
For all the oompa-loompas.
Yeah.
So he set up just like a nice small village?
What's a model village?
It was for the work-- it was for Cambry's workers,
and it was basically--
it was a village of houses that were built
along new architectural lines.
They were designed to be, you know,
a development from the horrible slums that you've got--
Oh, I see, right.
--in one of the urban centers.
Every house had a garden, and every house had a fruit tree,
and things like this.
And, you know, people were encouraged to live
basically clean, healthy lives.
These were all quite teetotal places as well.
That's the downside, yeah.
It's boring.
Unless it's changed recently,
and there's been quite a few people that have been trying
to buckle it, it's a dry town, which is nuts.
It's because the Quakers were--
Quakers were behind all three big chocolate companies,
which were Cambry's, Fry's, and Roundtree.
Yes, it was.
And they weren't-- at the time,
Quakers weren't allowed in the professions.
There could be a doctor or anything like that.
And they weren't allowed in public office.
So they were in--
If you can't do those two,
you've got to go into sweets and confectionery.
Also, I suppose if they're not drinking,
they've not got a lot of good stuff going on.
So, like, there's absolutely canitch on the chocolate.
Yeah.
That's the vice.
You're actually missing a fourth Quaker chocolate,
and I've got a product of theirs here.
This is by a different company now,
but I'm holding it in my hand.
It's a Wonka Bar.
And the Wonka Bar was created by Quaker Oats.
You know Quaker Oats?
Yeah, they funded the movie.
They put $3 million into the funding of the movie,
and they had a deal that they would have the chocolate
merchandise that would come off the back of it.
And that's where we started getting Wonka Bars.
But they had a huge problem,
because the movie didn't take off to begin with.
It was doing fine, but it didn't go massive.
Really, this is the one with Johnny--
Not with Johnny Depp, sorry, with Gene Wilder.
And the chocolate itself,
they produced at the wrong temperature,
as in the melting point of the chocolate,
was so inaccurate that when it was being transferred,
it would melt in the trucks and so on.
So they had a few problems,
and they sold it and sold it to different companies.
But it was set up by Quaker Oats.
So we've got a fourth Quaker company.
Wow.
Did you know that Cabry's once
reverse shop lifted a bunch of their cream eggs?
So they sort of snuck them into shops?
They snuck them in, yeah.
I couldn't quite work out why they went to these lengths.
This was in 2018.
You might remember, they did a kind of Willy Wonka promo thing
where they hid a thousand,
about a thousand white chocolate eggs in cream egg wrapping.
Oh, yeah.
And I think if you opened a cream egg,
there'd be a golden ticket in there,
and it'd be a white chocolate egg,
and it was really exciting.
And then you could win 10,000 pounds.
But the way they did it was,
when they made the eggs,
they didn't tell anyone in the factory in Bourneville
that they were making the eggs,
and they didn't tell any of the people in the shops
where they were planting the eggs.
They just got this crack team of spies
to break into the factory overnight
under cover of darkness, go in,
make these eggs, smuggle them out,
and then kind of in disguise,
sneak into shops and slip them onto shelves.
How many, do we know how many they made?
They said they made about a thousand.
You can do that in the course of a night.
That's insane.
I think it might have been multiple nights,
but also, I think a chocolate factory
can churn out, yes, even a thousand eggs.
They make hundreds of thousands of cream eggs a year,
just for a tiny season.
I know, you're breaking in,
you've got to turn on the lights.
I'm sure they created a pretext of an away day.
We're all going on a chocolate listening course,
and so no one needs to come to work tomorrow, you know.
And if you notice any white smears around the machinery,
just disregard it, get on with your work.
So who were the people who were sneaking them
bit onto the shelves?
That's such a cool job.
I suppose you have to be very high up in Cadbury
to get that gig.
But also inconspicuous looking.
Very inconspicuous.
Like you've got someone who looks
just like a normal person, I guess.
I would invent a sleeve that allowed me
to drop off an egg.
Lay an egg with your arm.
Exactly, exactly that.
So I would pick up an egg,
so no one would notice,
and I would go and buy an egg, you know.
But no one's noticed the one I've secretly
glayed in the egg tray behind me.
Can I tell you like a real life, Willy Wonka?
Yeah.
This is a guy, have you heard of Forest Mars?
No.
Was he responsible for Mars Mars?
He was.
Wow.
Forest Mars.
Also Maltesers invented those.
Okay.
Also Pedigree Chum and Uncle Ben's Rice.
But those were like huge though.
Wow.
Like solo albums of his main career
was in the confectionary world.
Did he hands-on invented all of those?
I don't know how.
Invented Rice?
There was a technique with Uncle Ben's Rice.
In a pouch.
I don't know how on his hands were on Pedigree Chum.
But it's a big deal.
Yeah.
Huge deal.
And he did, I think he did with Maltesers.
He took this tiny pellet of dough,
this pea-sized pellet of dough,
and then put it in a vacuum oven.
You know, exploded it in a vacuum,
and then you cover that in chocolate,
which is how they made today.
They made the vacuum.
Anyway, very cool.
But Forest Mars was very eccentric.
As in, he was a bit of a tyrant.
He would get his executives on their knees
praying in meetings.
He would lead them in prayers,
saying, "I pray for Milky Way.
I pray for Snickers."
What?
For the success of it,
or like literally for a bar of...
[laughter]
For the success of it.
So what about...
He was a tyrant, I think, domestically as well.
His adult son, John,
once asked to miss a sales meeting.
So Forest Senior said he had to spend the entire meeting
on his knees in prayer.
So I think...
It's very interesting to make people just get on their knees
and pray or something.
A lot of praying is a theme.
A lot of praying going on.
He was so secretive about his life
that when he died in 1999,
Mars wouldn't even confirm that he died.
Gosh.
I know.
So there is a bit of a...
It's quite an odd biography.
Someone once saw him in an airport
and shouted out,
"Forest, Forest Mars!"
And he marched over and he...
He made them get on their knees and pray.
[laughter]
That's right.
It was more conspicuous, actually.
He marched over and he said,
"Don't ever call my name out in public."
She was so concerned about being recognised
or spotted or any of that.
Yeah.
I mean, really an unusual guy.
Why have you called your biggest product
after yourself?
[laughter]
Uncle Ben!
[music]
Okay, it's time for fact number three
and that is Anna.
My fact this week is that the thumbs up emoji
is contractually binding in Canada.
[laughter]
Be careful, Canadians.
And this was as of this year.
No, as of last year, 2023.
We're now in 2024.
But this is because of a legal case
in Canada, in Saskatchewan.
And they have the system there
where a legal case will set legal precedent.
That will be the one that they refer back to.
And there was a legal case where a guy
called Kent Mickelbrough,
a grain buyer,
who wanted to buy some grain.
So he texted a bunch of farmers
and said, "Anyone got any
flax to sell me?"
"86 tonnes of flax I want at..."
86, why 86?
Kent, is it called Kent Mickelbrough?
Kent Mickelbrough, that's right.
It's a pretty cool name.
Frankly, he wasted on a flax buyer.
[laughter]
Careful, buddy.
This guy's litigious.
[laughter]
Flax buying is the coolest career.
Sorry, yeah, yeah.
He needs the 86th ton for whatever reason.
He wants 86 tonnes, exactly.
Precisely 17 Canadian dollars a bushel.
And one farmer responded, Chris Achter.
That's A-C-H-T-E-R.
Chris Achter responded.
They chatted on the phone.
And Kent was like, "Cool, I'll text your contract."
Kent texts him the contract saying,
"Please confirm this is the grain you want to buy.
You want to sell at this price."
And the farmer responded
with a thumbs up emoji.
Fast forward a few months.
Grain doesn't arrive.
Kent's like, "Where the hell's my grain, mate?
You agree to this contract?"
Farmer says, "No."
I was just saying, "I've received the message."
I wasn't agreeing to the contract.
Confirming that he's thumbs-uping that this is the contract.
That I am that man.
Yes, that's me.
But he's not signing.
No.
I understand that.
Like, I get that position.
Like, I've received this contract.
Thank you, but I never signed it.
Well, so these were the two positions that went to court.
I think I'm on Chris Achter's side.
Well, let's argue it out
as they did in the Canadian courts.
You also had lost, I'm afraid.
And he had to pay $82,000 Canadian dollars in damages.
Because it was determined that thumbs-up,
because the guy said in his text message,
you said, "Please confirm this is okay."
And then with a picture of the contract.
And I'm with you.
A thumbs-up can just be like, I'm really lit.
I can't be honest to respond now,
but I'll do something to put them off.
I think it's an incredibly...
I don't want to weigh in with an opinion here,
but I think it is quite a passive-aggressive thing
to do a thumbs-up emoji.
I tried.
I sent you one earlier this week, Dan,
as an experiment to see how it felt.
Oh, yeah?
I didn't feel great after sending it.
Oh.
You know.
Really?
You felt like it's a bit of a thumbs-down?
I feel like it's a bit of a...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Whatever, mate.
Jog on.
You know, it's sort of a...
What was a weird response to me
telling you my dog died?
Jog on, mate.
I like, instead of a thumbs-up,
I've started doing a top hat.
Oh, that's nice.
A jaunty, just like a...
Yeah, cool.
I've got my glad rags on.
I think is what I'm saying there.
No, I like that.
I would feel a bit special receiving a top hat
from Stevie, you know?
Yes, that's what I like to do.
But also, as a...
When my driving instructor,
I have to formally confirm,
contractually over text,
and he'll say, like,
"This time in this place,
confirm," and I just put a "why,"
and that means that is, like,
if I...
Wait, why?
Like, why?
And a top hat.
And he doesn't seem to think that.
No, why for yes.
Right, okay.
And when I do that,
I am in this obligation
to not cancel within seven days,
and I did have to because I got COVID,
and I was liable for, like, 250 quid.
And, like, so it...
But also, isn't it because, like,
if you...
What's the word?
This has turned into more of a personal complaint
about your driving instructor's cancellation practice.
Because I read about a while back,
a long time ago,
but maybe in 2019,
about how, like, emojis are used in court
for, like, someone sent their partner
or ex-partner a gun emoji
and actually got sentenced for threatening,
because people do use them in terms of words.
So if you're gonna,
you've got to, I suppose,
come down on one side of it.
You can't just go,
"Well, if it's a threat, yes,
but if it's a thumbs up because of flax, no."
Like, I suppose it's quite tricky.
You can see, I'm just excited that
you have firsthand recent experience
of this actual fact.
Yeah.
You said legal precedent.
You and your driving instructor.
Top hat means yes.
Do you want to give it a quick, please?
Oh, God, yeah.
It is an interesting point, though,
like, what if he had sent a heart,
for example, in response, you know,
what would be, where's the boundary
of the early flax?
I love flax.
And you.
Yes, you're right.
I think his thumbs up has that meaning.
Yeah.
I can sort of understand why it went that way as well.
You know, like, it's a sort of...
It's a yes.
It sounds good.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And actually, in fact, that was a thing
that was brought home in court,
because the defence raised concerns that
what if you send a fist bump?
Is that a contract?
Or is that I'm going to punch you,
and that's a threat, and then you go
to prison?
Exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
Or that Lady Tango dancer in the red dress.
Yeah.
I would take that as an absolute yes.
Like, we are, we're on, we're going.
You're sending twice as much flax as they've asked for.
We're dating now.
That's a...
Dating the flax.
Yeah.
No.
But I think the judge says,
"Don't be silly.
This is about a thumbs up."
And that's, that's all it is, you know.
Well, they, just to Andy's point
about the thumbs up, actually, in China,
you'd be right.
Apparently, the thumbs up emoji in China is bad.
Oh.
Amongst the youth, because it is...
But they asked some Chinese people.
More like passive-aggressive?
Yeah, I think.
Basically, Jen Zeds in China said
that if someone said them a thumbs up,
it means, "I don't like talking to you.
I want you to go away."
It reads like, like, okay,
and no punctuation.
That's what it reads like.
Okay.
You're like, you're angry.
If I ever said, "Okay, I'm a full stop."
That's as angry as I can possibly express myself.
Like, that's absolutely a white-hot with fury, you know.
Yeah.
You know the Gagas cave paintings and the Pyrenees?
The ancient...
Intimately.
Yeah, yeah.
No, can you explain?
No, no.
Sorry, yeah.
But there are these cave paintings and the Pyrenees
in the Gagas caves.
Yeah.
And they're very, very, very old.
They're between 20 and 40,000 years old.
They're quite hard to date, but like, they're old.
And they're all stencils of hands, right?
Okay, yes.
And there are...
There are amazing images of them.
They're beautiful.
There are sort of dozens of hands overlaid on each other.
I have seen this, yeah.
I think they made them by putting the hand on the cave wall
and then spitting ochre paint.
Really?
Yeah, it says, yeah.
But the weird thing is, about half the hands
would be injured or mutilated.
You know, they're short a finger or two,
or some of them are short all four fingers.
And there's a theory that...
It's a language about hunting,
or it's an indication of something or another.
But there is a theory that that could be the first thumbs up.
It's either someone who's been tragically ritually mutilated
with the loss of all four of their fingers,
or it's the first ever thumbs up.
Or it's an emoji.
It's an emoji.
Yeah.
That's fun.
So that's...
It's hard to know.
A Egyptian hieroglyphs like emojis.
They are, because they're open to interpretation.
Yeah.
And they're pictures.
Great.
Thank you.
(ALL LAUGH)
Do you think they actually had a writing system,
but it just got so popular with the emoji side of things?
(ALL LAUGH)
Because that's where we're heading, anyway.
They were really frowned upon at first, the hieroglyphs.
Among the older generations.
Hieroglyphs are past ag.
Dumb it down.
(ALL LAUGH)
Right, where does the word emoji come from?
What does it mean?
Oh.
Emotion and something Japanese.
Exactly.
Bang, you fell right into my trap.
It's nothing to do with emotion.
Oh, and it's so weird.
So it's from the Japanese words for picture and character.
Oh.
So air is picture, moji is character, right?
That's weird.
It has nothing to do with emotion.
But weirdly, do you remember the emoticon?
Yes.
Like a colon and then a closed bracket is a smiley face.
Yeah.
That is an emotion icon.
And that came first.
That's so weird.
But then emoji came second and it has nothing to do with emotion.
This is like the sun and the moon being the same size coincidence.
This is all falling into place.
It's like a lot of emojis that have got nothing to do with emotion.
Like a suitcase or like Easter Island hat.
Exactly, yeah.
So that does now kind of check out, doesn't it?
Yeah.
I like what they decide to add each year.
So like there was a big uproar because there was no avocado for ages.
Right.
And I think there wasn't a seal for a long time and that really got me down.
And I think it got me down.
A seal like when you seal an envelope.
No, unless a sea line.
I'm right.
Again, Anna, we're getting more of a glimpse into your communication style.
And mine.
Well, wax seal.
There was no wax seal.
Let's send it by seal.
That's what I do.
Do you know what the least popular emojis are?
Because I really look this up because when, you know, when you go to send one and you
see this vast selection and you think, God, none of these must ever get a look in ever.
And there's actually a Twitter account called at least used emoji,
which kind of sandy for it doesn't seem to have tweeted since 2020.
But in 2020, the same one had been top of its list for 264 days,
which I guess is when it gave up and thought this is the ultimate loser.
And he guesses.
What am I doing with my life?
Even bots get depressed.
Okay.
Is this gettable?
I don't know.
I mean, I guess it's one that you won't have seen very often.
Is it an object?
No, it's a flag.
You'll never get it.
I've just realized the least used one is the symbol that is an ampersand,
an equal sign, a musical note and a percentage sign.
What is it?
They come as one.
What does it mean?
Well, I suppose no one's ever known.
Which is why.
Because you don't really get package emojis.
Like that's like four really unpopular ones that have got together in a supergroup
to try and bump themselves up.
Yeah.
It's the opposite of a supergroup, isn't it?
They thought they would be the traveling wheel breeze and they, yeah.
Also the tramway symbol.
I really thought, Andy, that you can't have been on Line March in 2020,
given that that was the joint lease popular.
Yeah.
An aerial tramway symbol.
Oh, I, I've already talked about that.
And it was a, it's a sort of hanging railway.
It's a suspended railway.
Yeah.
And I saw someone claiming that there's only one suspended railway
and widespread use of the world nets in China,
which is why the emoji is not used.
Actually, there is one in Germany, the Wuppertalsch Weberbahn,
which is a very popular suspended railway.
Great.
I just can't believe you won.
And that's, I'm stupid now.
That's where the train's like underneath the track.
Yeah.
Right.
So I think it's that an emoji before and been like, why, what's that?
But that is actually real.
I didn't, I didn't know.
Go to Wuppertal.
And you'll have a whale of a time.
It's, it's a really good, I think they put an elephant in it once.
I've just had a memory that.
Oh, it feels.
Wow.
Unnecessary, doesn't it?
I can't.
Can they?
Oh, to prove that it clings to the top.
Like you can even put an elephant in it.
I think.
You know, really, I know.
Really.
I'm really doubting myself.
I've got to find out.
I'm not sure what you do.
You go quiet for a bit and then go, oh, did you put an elephant in it?
Supposedly they put an elephant, they did put an elephant in it.
They put an elephant in the Wuppertal Schraberbahn in 1950 as a stunt either to promote the monorail
or the circus.
Both.
Why not?
And it fell in.
The panic had broken out in the carriage, which apparently also had passengers in it.
Oh my God.
This is bizarre.
This is insane.
I'm just on the Wikipedia for it now.
It was called Tuffy Was Fine and survived another 39 years.
I thought you meant he was fine.
I was going to be like, this is not his fault.
I haven't paid for a ticket, mate.
Right.
I'm glad he was okay.
I'm famous in 1950.
Oh, it was she.
She actually accidentally, obviously, fell from the Wuppertal Schraberbahn into the River
Wuppa.
Oh, no.
But she survived.
Yep.
For 39 years.
Yeah.
I'm going to keep that in mind.
How did she thought did they not shut the doors?
Well, what it says here is that she was put on the monorail as a publicity stunt, tick.
Elephant trumpeted wildly and ran through the carriage, broke through a window and fell
12 meters down into the river, suffering only minor injuries.
A panic had broken out in the carriage, naturally, and some passengers were injured.
That's right.
Big-ass window.
Yeah.
It's a big window.
Or small elephant.
Small elephant.
Not African elephant.
It depends how you're looking at it.
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show, and that is Andy.
My fact is that there is a fish that spends its entire life upside down.
Is it trying to make the moon look smaller?
That's right.
This is a fact.
It was sent in, actually, by Kate Glyzinski.
So, thank you, Kate.
It's about a kind of anglerfish.
Sorry, that does sound like a pseudonym for Anna.
Kate Glyzinski.
Yeah.
Absolutely right.
This was sent in by Anna.
So, anglerfish are the ones which they have a tentacle and they have like a fishing rod
sticking out of their head, and then they use the end of the rod.
There's got a little glowing ball of light on it, and they use that to attract prey to them.
It's pretty incredible.
We say it casually.
It's amazing.
But you've got a light bulb hanging off your face.
Absolutely amazing.
Well, and it's bacteria that is lighting it up as well.
It's not like an actual light bulb.
It is an actual...
Hang on.
You've got to feed the rod for them to...
It's so weird.
Yeah.
It's genuinely amazing.
And sometimes they accidentally chew their own tentacle sort of thing.
Because they close their mouth and they go, you know, and then they obviously sometimes
they trap themselves.
Ow!
Anyway.
Like biting your tongue, basically.
They're light.
So this is the whip nose anglerfish.
And for years it was just assumed that it went the right way up.
It just went around the right way up.
Yeah.
People assumed that.
Because we've only seen dead ones, presumably, with anglerfish, right?
You don't obviously see them in the wild.
Yeah, because they live very, very deep in the deep ocean.
And it was assumed to be upright.
An upright fish.
Like all fish.
But they got some camera footage in 1999 of one of these swimming around the ocean,
upside down with the fishing rod dangling down beneath it.
Very weird.
They thought, what a weird...
What a weird one or fish.
But they keep finding these, like deep sea drones, keep filming these anglerfish swimming
around upside down.
And it appears they spend their whole life swimming upside down to attract prey.
But apparently it is better for it so that it doesn't bite itself.
That's in part of the description of the whip nose.
Yeah, it's just helpful.
It just gives it a tiny bit more of an advantage.
It's quite cute.
They're very cool, anyway.
They are weird anglerfish.
Anglerfish are insane.
They do this thing, and I know I always get too surprised by this, but evolution.
What a great idea.
So one of the things is that it's bioluminescent in that rod.
But also it will eat a lot of fish that are bioluminescent.
And an anglerfish has a really elastic kind of tummy, very rubbery.
So it can eat things that are almost twice its size.
And so it goes quite transparent, except it doesn't, because there's black lining on the inside.
So you can't see the bioluminescence inside it.
So it can't attract predators if there's something inside swimming around that's still not dead.
Kind of like a car that has tinted windows.
You don't know what's inside the car, but you can...
It is on purpose so that it's not gone transparent.
Like I went to the gym once and my leggings had gone see-through and everyone could see my knickers and butt.
That's the opposite.
If I was an anglerfish, I could have just made my leggings more opaque, for example.
One of the many reasons to want to be one.
That really puts it in context.
It really brings it down to earth, or up to earth.
This one that you mentioned, Andy, the whipnose is a classic anglerfish in that it's just the females you're talking about.
It's pretty much whenever anyone talks about cool stuff with anglerfish, it's just the ladies.
Because they are way bigger than the males.
So in the whipnose ones, then the females are like half a metre and the males are two centimetres.
And I think there's another kind of anglerfish which has the Guinness record for the biggest dimorphism between males and females.
And this I find so hard to believe, but Guinness says that the females are more than 60 times the length of the males and half a million times as heavy.
That's crazy.
The mating is very wild.
The mating is odd.
I think the mating is...
Basically, the male sort of latches onto the female, just kind of bites the side of her.
And then fuses and then dissolves into her.
And all that's left is a tiny pair of testicles.
Oh my god, that's incredible.
That's basically it.
Their skin and their organs all fuse together.
And for a long time, I think they assumed that there wasn't a male in the picture at all, right?
They just thought it was female.
Actually, you're looking.
That's him.
Testicles!
I know those testicles anywhere.
This is great.
We all know couples like that.
I wonder if that's what the perfect distance is.
Kind of like with the eclipse of a moon and the sun, that you could have the male anglerfish near you and the female.
That they will appear to be the same size.
Yeah, yeah.
Do you get females, don't you, which have lots of pairs of testicles just hanging off them?
Yeah, you get six or seven males will have been fused into one female at once.
Really?
Yeah, yeah.
And it's just like, you know, have you had many previous boyfriends?
No, actually, you don't need to tell me.
Oh, it's like a brownie sash with your badge just that you've collected.
Yeah, exactly.
That's how you explain this to your five-year-old.
That's really brownies.
Oh, no, they're brilliant.
They're so good.
They are.
Yeah.
And they do, when they're lava, they look really cool.
And there's not enough focus on this in the anglerfish world of chat.
They, when they're lava, they're surrounded by this jelly egg.
So that is transparent.
And so you'll see this tiny little anglerfish and then it's got this big see-through pile of jelly around it.
Like, absorbing.
Like, absorbing, exactly.
Really?
Yeah.
That's very cool.
All absorbing.
You guys have seen an anglerfish in person?
No, not in the flesh.
Not in the flesh.
I've met one.
Get away.
Yeah, yeah.
I met one.
I met a very famous one.
I met the one that basically was in Blue Planet that was discovered by all your celebrity anecdotes.
Names dropping.
So exhausting.
Are you a close personal friend of this anglerfish?
I was at a cocktail party with her.
We got chatting.
I don't even remember you, Dan, okay?
How many testicles did she have on her?
No, so years ago I got to work with Alistair Fathergill.
He came on Museum of Curiosity and he's the person who found the hairy anglerfish.
So he went down and he filmed it.
They, so you filmed it for an a half, isn't it?
Did he show you his hairy anglerfish?
Fly me.
So they brought it back up and it dies in the process.
Oh, when they died, did their lights go out?
Like a Pixar.
It might do.
But they would live on, wouldn't they?
They would.
That's even sadder.
This is the nuts thing.
It's that they're bacteria.
And I was reading a thing.
How do they get these bacteria?
Yeah, yeah.
Because normally when hosts have symbionts, you know, things living on them that rely on them,
they either find them in the local area or they, um, or they inherit them.
Bacteria wants to live on your nose.
Um, no, but they sometimes inherit them from their parents with other animals.
But anglerfish never have any contact with their parents.
It will be insane for them to.
His dad's been dissolved.
Come say hi to your father.
He's like, what?
Give him a little jiggle.
It was a real male role model.
Um, but no, they don't get their lure until much later in life, even.
So they must find them in their area.
They must pick them up from around the place and they have them on the end of their nose.
What if they, like, didn't find enough?
That would be like a Pixar film, like the anglerfish that couldn't find the bacteria.
That's a good one.
That's good.
Don't maybe edit that out so I can write it.
Yeah.
Please don't.
I will never write that.
Yeah.
Um, I found something that swims, but it can never be upside down.
Ooh.
What are they doing to me this?
Okay.
What could that be?
Something big and flat like this.
My vision.
Like a manta ray?
Maybe they're big and flat, but they can't.
They swim, but they, no.
No.
Right.
A starfish.
Not a starfish.
Stupid.
A ball.
A ball has no upside down.
A boat.
Do they swim?
Oh, okay.
A water boat.
- Yes, you probably are.
- The answer is the word swims.
- Smooth.
- Swims is an ambegram.
You flip it upside down and it's exactly the same.
- I've got my hot.
- Wow, with arousal.
- Yes, I'm incredibly aroused.
- That's amazing.
- I love that stuff.
- That's really good.
That is great. - That is great.
- That's really lovely stuff, Dan.
- That's a good riddle.
- Who would have thought?
- The riddle. - The riddle.
- Finally.
- You can stay.
- You've passed the audition.
- I said a boat.
- What the fuck are you saying?
(laughing)
- That's why I'm hostess podcast.
- They don't swim and they can be upside down.
- Namely.
- Just another thing on how fish swim.
Do you know how to tell if a fish is depressed?
- Oh, no, don't.
- Is that too sad?
- Okay.
- 'Cause we've got a cure.
- Great.
- There you go.
- What a roller coaster.
- I know.
(laughing)
- So you only said the fact yet, please.
- That's the cure.
Come on, the podcast.
It'll raise your spirits right up.
- What's the cure?
- Well, antidepressants.
And we only have a cure because we've trialled
human antidepressants on them to make them better.
But, how do you know that they're depressed?
- So they swim at the bottom of their tanks.
So depressed fish swim low and happy fish swim
at the top of the surface of the water
or the top of their tanks.
And this is actually really useful
according to scientists who do trial antidepressants
because it's a really obvious sign that they're depressed.
So we can trial antidepressants on them
and we know if they're working.
And they--
- They just go higher.
- 'Cause they just get higher and higher.
So you go, "Oh, pros out.
"That's doing the trick."
Look, it's like in the air.
- It's out of the water.
(laughing)
- Is it true or have I just made this up in my brain
that goldfish grow to fill their tanks?
If you actually give them a bigger tank,
they just keep going.
- That is true.
- And that's so sad in retrospect.
Because when I was growing up,
we had just a little tank with three fish
and you're like, "God, we were sort of shrinking off the tank."
- That's a thing when people throw them into the wild
into little lakes and so on.
They just turn into these turbo sharks.
- Exactly, you were doing a public service
by keeping them from, you know, taking over.
Upside downness?
Sure.
This is a very weird thing.
Which is better for a rhino to be?
Upside down or not upside down, lying down?
- Is it in the circus?
- It's not in the circus.
- It's not.
- Okay.
- Let me take you to the Vupetage favor button.
No, okay.
It's better for a rhino to be upside down
than it is for it to be lying on its side.
Isn't that weird?
- How does it get there?
Why?
- Well, I think we might have mentioned a while ago.
- We've done this about the rhinos.
- They transport rhinos to new areas
by putting them in a helicopter,
stringing them up by their ankles.
- No, not in the helicopter.
(laughing)
- No, they hogtie them.
- Right.
- They lift them up upside down
and then they fly to the new nature reserve
where they have to get them to.
It's the easiest way to transport them.
- Okay.
- It takes like 10 or 15 minutes.
It's really fast.
And no--
- What depends on the distance?
- Regardless of where they go.
(laughing)
- And on traffic.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But they're normally not taking them
like from South Africa to Tunisia.
You know, it's not like a short journey.
But nobody had checked how their hearts and lungs
actually cope with this journey.
And a team of scientists,
led by Robin Radcliffe from Cornell,
realized oh, we should probably look into
whether or not they're--
- Yeah, they're like--
- Incredibly upset.
- Oh my gosh.
- Yeah, yeah.
And so they held 12 rhinos upside down by their feet
for an experiment from a crane.
And they're also dated, obviously.
But they were just testing their heart and lungs.
And it turns out that it's much better
for it to be upside down.
Because when a rhino's on its side,
their lungs are a bit distorted.
You know, the gravity means--
- Oh yeah, yeah.
- The lungs are not getting equal amounts of oxygen
for the air exchange and all of that gas exchange.
But when they're upside down,
it is equal because they're just upside down.
- Lovely.
- So--
- When they sleep, they go upside down.
- They go upside down, yeah, yeah.
- Like on their backs.
- Liners, yeah, yeah.
If you go for a walk in certain bits of Namibia,
you'll look up in the trees
and you can see hanging from the trees.
- Stop it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- I just want to be wrong on the back.
It's all I'm meant for.
- I don't think they like it.
- They should.
There are like rhino articles on the web.
You've been sleeping all wrong your whole life.
(laughing)
- There is another fish that swims upside down.
- Ooh.
- Well, it's not actually a fish.
It's krill, not technically a fish, I suppose.
(laughing)
- Forstalling the letters, very nice.
- Antarctic krill swim upside down in the Antarctic
when the water's covered in ice
so that they can graze like cows on the underside of the ice.
- Gorgeous.
- And they eat algae that grows
on the underside of the ice.
And they live such a weird life.
They migrate, quite weird migration, but up and down.
So they graze on algae swimming upside down
and then they get quite fat and heavy from it.
And then they sink 'cause they're too heavy
and they have to fan themselves out like a parachute
and they sink about 50 meters down
and then they think, oh God, I'm really hungry again.
So then they've used up all their food supply.
So then they have to swim up to the top again, eat
and then sink and that's their lives.
And they do about three times a day for their whole lives.
- Wow.
- And then they die.
- I go to the fridge more than three times a day.
I'm just saying I empathize.
That's my life too.
- It's like your whole life upside down.
- Go back and forth for a food source.
Yeah, it kind of is when you think about it.
- You're so right.
It's what we all do, isn't it?
- I'm at work, I then go downstairs, I guess food.
And he's always got a plate of something
that he just comes up with something on the go.
- Oh, I thought you Dan were saying
that is kind of our light and philosophical way.
- Oh, I thought you were saying that.
- Yeah, I thought that.
- And I was just saying yes too.
- The only reason they don't have a podcast
is it's too wet for all the equipment.
(all laughing)
That's fine.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter, our Instagram,
our threads, our any Facebook.
There's so many options that you can find us on.
I'm on @Shrieberland.
Andy.
- @AndrewHondaM, various.
(laughing)
That's Stevie.
- Mastodon only.
(laughing)
Now I'm on Twitter and Instagram @stevm.
If the S is a five, I regret it.
- Right.
(laughing)
And if you wanna get to us as a group, Anna,
where do they go?
- You can tweet @NoSuchThing
or email podcast@QI.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing.
All of our previous episodes are up there,
so do check them out.
Also, lots of bits of merch,
and also there's the clubfish entrance point.
Join us, get access to all those fun things,
like Drop Us Align,
all the extra bonus shows that we do.
That's all there.
Anyway, otherwise, just come back next week.
We'll be back with another episode,
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[MUSIC PLAYING]