(upbeat music)
- Hey everyone, welcome to another episode of Fish.
Before we get going, I just wanna quickly let you know
about two very exciting global live streaming events
that we are gonna be doing
on the fifth and sixth of September.
So we're gonna be playing the London podcast festival
and as well as playing to a live room full of people
at Kings Place in London,
we will be live streaming the event
so that you can watch it from wherever you are in the world.
So for those who have never made it to a live show before
and always wondered what it's like,
this is the full experience.
This is a sort of warts and all version
that you'll get to see.
It's all the bloopers, it's all the extra bits
that end up getting edited out.
There's all the admin at the top of the show.
Who doesn't love admin at the top of a show?
Imagine getting to see that.
It's gonna be a great night.
Also, as Anne is now off on maternity,
we're gonna be joined by some really fun guests.
We've already sort of announced one of them on Instagram,
but if you didn't see that video on the sixth of September,
we are gonna be joined by one of the UK's best-selling authors
of all time, Richard Osman.
That's gonna be an awesome show, that's on the sixth.
We'll be making another announcement
for who will be joining us on the fifth soon,
but in the meantime, if you wanna get tickets,
they are available now.
Just go to knowsuchthingasafish.com/live
and get your live streaming tickets now.
All right, last thing to say before we get into the show
is some very exciting news back at QIHQ.
The Lunchbox MV podcast has been picked up by BBC Sounds.
So if you happen to listen to your podcast there,
do type in the words "Lunchbox MV now"
and you'll be able to get access
to the most quite interesting food-based podcast
there is in podcast land.
Each episode deals with a different kind of food.
So the episode that went up a few days ago
was all about cheese,
where they answer the big cheese questions,
like, you know, how do they put the holes in Swiss cheese?
Who eats the world's hardest cheese?
Why do people put Parmesan into a bank?
All the biggies.
And there's over 30 episodes you can access now,
everything from pastry through to butter and chocolate.
You must check them out,
but specifically do check them out now at BBC Sounds.
All right, let's get into the show.
On with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
James Harkin, and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that
if you are 20 years old now,
there is a chance that your great grandparents
might have met thanks to computer dating.
- That's wild. - It doesn't make sense.
I had to ask James to explain this,
even after we'd said this would be our fact.
That doesn't work, James, and he proved it.
Go on, prove it.
- So for the hard of thinking who are listening,
this is an article that I read,
was written by Adrian Covert in Gizmodo,
and it's about a guy called Lewis Altfest.
And Lewis saw a Pempal machine,
which let you fill down his questionnaire,
and then it fed it into a machine,
and it found you the perfect Pempal.
And he decided that he would do the same with dating.
So he called up his friend called Robert Ross,
who worked at IBM, and they made a computer program
called TACT that stood for Technical
Automated Compatibility Testing.
They did that in New York, and it was in 1964.
So, for instance, if your great-grandparents
got together due to TACT in 1964,
your grandmother could be born in 1965.
She could have had your mother in 1985,
and then your mother could have had you in 2005,
and you would be 20 this year.
- Yeah. - It's stunning.
- It was great.
- It was amazing at the time.
It was such like everyone thought computers
would know the answer as well.
It wasn't the best at pairing people.
It did at one point match an older brother
with his younger sister.
(all laughing)
- They have a lot in common with it.
- And I turned out fine.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, that actually weirdly, I think shows it does work.
Shared interests.
- It just, you haven't put in the anti-incest layer
into the program.
- You haven't clicked that button.
Most people would click that button.
(all laughing)
- He was crossing his fingers, that guy.
- So, is this the one, 'cause I read about
one of the very early computer dating services,
and it asks clients to pick from the dislikes,
and the dislikes were, I'd say, very much of their time.
- Yes, this is the one you're talking about.
- From one to six, it was,
what do you think about affected people?
I think that's a really good question.
Like, I'm a bit affected, you know?
- You mean like people who have affectations.
- Exactly, a bit pretentious.
I presume, and that still means they've been affected
by an event. - Oh, okay.
I thought it wasn't a typo for infected, 'cause that--
(all laughing)
- But who's saying I love those?
Are there people going--
- Well, after '60s, some people had affectations
in the '60s, and that was cool.
It was the New Age, man.
- But I think like, it wasn't that you only picked
one of them, you kind of picked them in order.
- Oh, okay. - That kind of thing.
- 'Cause two through six that you might dislike were,
birth control, foreigners, free love, homosexuals,
and interracial marriage.
But it never says sisters, so.
(all laughing)
Yeah, that was true.
So you paid $5, basically,
and you would answer loads of questions.
You would also, the men would be asked
to rank women's hairstyles.
Women would be shown pictures of men in different settings.
So there'd be a man chopping wood, a man who was painting,
and a man who was in a garage working with a drill.
And you had to say which of those you fancy the most.
- The drill and the chopping wood are very similar, aren't they?
What are the two different personality types?
- Well, some people are more discerning than you, Anna.
(all laughing)
- That just sounds like outdoorsy versus indoorsy to me.
- I suppose, drill is indoorsy.
- I think like chopping wood shows muscular strength,
whereas drill shows more kind of industrial ability.
- DIY maybe. - Yeah, yeah.
- And these things, they started off,
and they were kind of thought of as a gimmick.
So for instance, this guy at Altfest,
he just gave up in the end on his tact.
But actually he met his partner due to tact.
- Did he? - Yeah, so he married a reporter
who'd come to interview him
about how terrible his machine was.
(all laughing)
And they hit it off.
- Yeah, they were funny.
There was another one in 1965 in New York,
which was called Operation Match.
I was reading the memories of someone who went on one of those
and had three very unsuccessful dates.
But the way all these things worked, I guess,
is you sent in a bit of money
and you filled out a questionnaire,
which could be very long.
So Operation Match was 75 questions.
And then they took your questionnaire
and they tried to match it up with others
using a computer algorithm,
which is why it was computerized or computer dating.
But the questions were,
I couldn't look out why this one existed.
So there was a question in this one,
which was, I'd considered dating a woman as young as,
or a man as old as.
So if you're a man, it was a woman as young as 17 or whatever.
And if you were a woman,
it was like I considered dating a man as old as that.
- Yeah, right.
- But you wouldn't ask a woman,
I considered dating a man as young as.
Did it just assume that women could,
would date men who were infinitely young?
- The cougar had not been invented.
That's what we're saying.
- Yeah, I think that is what we're saying.
Yeah. - Yeah, I suppose so.
- Very weird.
And then are you sexually experienced or inexperienced?
And also, what does this mean?
Is extensive sexual activity preparation for your marriage?
Yes or no?
- Answer, see previous questions.
So Operation Match was invented by Jeff Tarr and Vaughn Morrill.
Jeff Tarr met his wife,
not by going on and doing it himself,
but someone who was using Operation Match said,
"Oh, I know someone who you'd be good with."
So they met up, they got married.
They had a daughter called Jennifer.
She goes on to marry the co-founder of OKCupid.
- No.
- Yeah. - Whoa.
- Yeah, so. - Tasty.
- Yeah.
- So dating apps are declining a lot, right?
In the UK, I think users are dropping.
- Oh, really? - Of the really big sites.
Things like Tinder.
And it's because people get exhausted
and they get burned out with them.
And it's just this endless array of new faces.
You can start thinking everyone's the same.
And it's also, it's very sort of private.
So the pool of dates is massive,
but you don't have any friends in common.
So people often behave badly,
they don't get back in touch or whatever.
- I see.
Yeah, so if you date someone who's a friend of your friend,
then you kind of feel like you can't be an asshole
because it will get back to you.
- There's a shame mechanism there.
Whereas you can absolutely just go
to some random person you've met once and all that.
Anyway. - Oh, thank you.
- I don't know.
But I found this claim that some sites
are saying things like, if you pay a lot extra,
like if you pay 45 quid a month,
you'll go on three times as many dates, right?
- Okay.
- So, this is just to say, yesterday I said to my wife,
I'm downloading Hinge by the way,
'cause I wanted to test if there are special offers on.
But what I forgot to say was that I was doing
this as part of podcast research.
From her perspective, I just said, I'm downloading Hinge.
I want to see if there's got special offers
on right now.
- Okay.
- Let's not put out this fact ever.
And then she'll never have caught to believe
that's what you were doing.
I really, I think my favorite thing is Love Getty.
Did you come across this gadget?
It, 1.3 million was sold.
So it was quite popular.
- Is it Spaghetti?
Love Spaghetti.
- It's just for people who love Spaghetti, yes.
- Is it not people who just love John Paul Getty?
- It's neither of these things.
- Or Getty Images?
Is that the--
(laughing)
- Any further guesses?
It's like, Get You Love, Love Getty.
It's a love getter.
- Got it, yeah.
- There we go.
And this was a thing in Japan in 1998.
Basically, it was a thing that you kept in your pocket.
And if you saw someone who was a bit fit,
then you turned it on.
And it meant that if they had the same gadget,
then their gadget would buzz.
Or you keep yours on all the time.
And whenever you were within 15 feet of someone
who had a gadget that was also turned on,
it would buzz and you could be like, oh my God,
something's buzzing.
- Can I just say,
so what you do is when you see someone attractive,
you start fiddling in your pockets.
(laughing)
I mean, yeah.
- It was a small vibration.
- I don't think you need a buzzer.
I think people are gonna know what you think immediately.
It's such a bad idea.
Like it's a stalker's charter.
- But also the flaw seems to be that,
let's say I'm looking across the room at Barry,
and I think he's hot, and I turn my thing on.
And Barry doesn't have one of these love getties,
but Norman on the other side of the tube carriage
does have one.
His goes off, and then he's looking at me,
thinking she fancies me.
- She's fiddling in her pants.
- She's fiddling.
- Is that a love getty in her pocket?
(laughing)
In Spain at the moment,
if you go to supermarkets after seven o'clock,
you might not be able to get a pineapple.
- Okay.
- Is this research for this part?
- Just to complain from my last holiday.
No, so this is a TikTok video that's been going around
telling people that if you're lonely
to go to your nearest Mercadonia supermarket
to take a pineapple and put it upside down
in your shopping cart,
and then see if anyone else is doing the same,
and if two upside down panapples see each other,
then they might get together.
- So that's just like the love getty.
It's a slightly more basic version of love getty,
but at least you've got deniability.
Whereas if you've got a love getty, it buzzes.
Whereas if you've just got a pineapple,
you could say, "Oh no, I'm just--"
- It's upside down, though, isn't it?
- It's just all that way.
- I'm making a pina colada, whatever.
- Well, the problem is that basically,
the trend has taken off a little bit in Spain.
Police have been called to unruly crowds
of people trying to find pineapples.
And employees of Mercadonia are so sick of it,
they've been hiding their pineapples at five to seven,
so no one can get them.
(laughing)
- It's a huge pain, people just walking around the shop
with a single pineapple in their basket.
Like, you're a business here.
You're trying to sell other goods.
- Do we not think they buy the pineapples at the end?
Do you think some people probably just do it,
get their date, and then put the pineapple back?
- I think if you don't get the date, you would do that.
If you do get the date, probably you want to show
that you're not a skin flint and that you can afford
to buy pineapples. - That's a really good point.
I'll get this, darling.
(laughing)
- Does that happen here, or is that just in Spain?
- Just in Spain, the supermarket chain Mercadonia
has yet to get into the British market.
- But next time, Andy, you're in a supermarket
with your wife, just make sure it's the right way up.
Bad and hinge combined, something's definitely going on.
- Well, do you remember, actually, Madison,
the cheating website?
- No.
- Do you not?
(laughing)
- Damn, that was so impossible.
- What, website?
- Well, that's a list of hacked email addresses
that's different.
(laughing)
- Okay, let's move on.
Type it back on there, too.
- No, no, no.
This is amazing, right?
So it was an affairs website, okay?
It marketed itself to mostly blokes who say,
"Hey, you want to have an affair?"
Then join Ashley Madison.
They were hacked into by some disgruntled staffers
or former staff or something.
And ha, ha, ha, it turned out 95% of the members
of Ashley Madison were men, right?
So that was the headline that went around the world.
It was quite a big story at the time.
The really interesting thing is,
a journalist called Annalyn Newitz looked into it,
found something much more perturbing.
It was that the parent company,
who were called Avid Live Media,
had made 70,000 fake women bots.
They would just say things like, "Hi, and what's up?"
And the men thought they were talking to real women.
Like, there were 11 million interactions in the database
between human men and bot women,
and the men were paying for every message.
- Right.
- And the company was paying workers
to generate these fake profiles.
So it was basically real people interacting with bots,
having no idea about it.
That's quite, that's the really sinister thing, you know?
- And let's talk about our level of sympathy for these men.
'Cause I suddenly feel really bad for them.
But I suppose they had gone on a website
to cheat on their wives.
- In a way, they're doing something good, aren't they?
This company, because this hypothetical man
has gone on the website to cheat on his wife,
but they're just putting a fake thing up
that he can chat to.
So he's not gonna be able to have the affair.
What is sin?
- I think it's what we're asking.
He thinks he is sinning, so is he?
If I'm just talking to a chatbot, that's for God's sake.
- I remember years ago when there was the rise
of niche dating places when I was single,
I went on to, I think it was like a ghost hunter's
dating site.
- Of course you did.
- Yeah, and I got on it and it's just all men.
But--
- The ghost dating.
- Yeah, but their profiles with their blurb came up,
and all of them sounded so interesting.
So I actually messaged a couple.
- No.
- Yeah, just to say like, hey,
can you tell me about ghost hunting?
'Cause I'm not actually interested sexually.
I'm just like, you sound really interesting.
- Ooh, it's like to me.
- I've got one last example of someone who made it big
in the world of creating online dating,
a guy called Gary Kremen who created match.com.
What's impressive about him is he seemed to just
cleaned up on domain names early on, right?
'Cause that's where he's made a large fortune from.
So he owned sex.com.
Can you imagine owning sex.com, yeah.
And there was a big case where someone forged fake documents
so that the domain name went over to them,
and he had to fight them for years and years,
and there's now an outstanding bill of 65 million
that is owed to Gary Kremen,
which has not yet been paid by this person.
- What's on sex.com, is it porn, I guess?
- He was gonna use it in the way that he was using match.com,
but match.com just flew into huge success immediately.
So it was just kind of sitting there dormant.
He also owned computer.com, which he sold for 500,000.
But he set up match.com, and even his girlfriend
found a partner on there, which wasn't him.
She joined up and met someone else and left him.
Yeah, and he said, "Look how successful it is."
- What are you hoping for if you buy computer.com?
It's just old people going on Google
and typing computer.com, 'cause they think
that's how they turn it on.
- It's very much like Donald Trump saying
everything is computer now, it's a bit, okay.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that one of the original
57 Boy Scout badges was the invention badge,
which required kids to not only invent something new,
but obtain a patent for it too.
- It's so hard.
- I mean, it's a lengthy process
to get a patent in America for an invention.
- Is it hard?
'Cause there's so much random shit that's been patented
that you see.
That never went in here.
- I always seem it's piece of piss, actually.
- Yeah, I always thought you could just draw a picture
on a beer mat and just send it in
and then give you a patent.
- I think it works like that.
This idea of yours for a beer mat is incredible, so.
Not as easy as it looks.
- Is it quite a process?
- Well, I think it costs.
You got to pay in order to have it accepted
to the submission and so on.
Like, yeah, it's a lengthy process.
And basically they dropped the badge largely
because no one was really achieving it.
So the invention badge,
it's part of the American Boy Scout specifically.
There were 57 original merit badges that you could get,
like archery and swimming and so on.
And invention was part of it.
So that launched in 1911 and they took it out by 1914
and only 10 scouts in that time managed to get it,
which I think is a very high number.
- Actually, only nine got it in that time.
One person got it in 1915
'cause he'd already started with his invention.
So they were like, oh, well, I guess you can have it.
- That's apparently one of the rules
with a badge that's been stopped.
If you've started the process
trying to get it, you can finish it.
- And the inventions have not survived.
Most of them have not survived.
We don't know what was patented,
but we do know one by Graham Thomas Smallwood,
which was a scout's uniform with a removable sleeve
to stop your Boy Scout badge arm getting dirty.
- I think it's a great idea.
It's really good.
- Is it?
- Yeah, it's not just that.
You could take the sleeve off
and use it to sew badges onto it.
You can carry on wearing the rest of your Boy Scout thing.
- Just take the whole jacket off, mate.
- Yeah, we must have another shirt.
- I think you still had,
from what I could see on the drawing,
you still had an underneath sleeve.
It was a sort of on top.
So it's not, you didn't look like
someone had just ripped your sleeve off.
- Well, there was a few different things you could do.
You could do that.
And then you could also put a secondary sleeve
on top of your other sleeve.
- Okay.
- So it's like a prophylactic sleeve.
- Was that so it matched the other side?
- No, it stops you getting dirty.
Stop shirt, sleeve getting dirty.
- And we've all got these things these days.
- So like you're walking down the street
and you lean on some wet paint
and everyone laughs at you
'cause you got paint on your arm.
You go, "Haha!"
And you pull off your fake sleeve.
- Amazing.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Incredible.
- Richly deserved patent and badge.
- I can't believe he's not famous.
- The horrific badges back in the day.
Other discontinued Boy Scout badges
on the Wikipedia for them is top drawer reading.
There's beef production.
- Yep, that's good.
- Lost until 1975.
You get a Boy Scout badge for beef production.
Blacksmithing, nut culture, hog and pork production,
taxidermy.
- Interestingly, hog and pork production
was discontinued in 1958.
So I wonder what the difference
of the discrepancy between pork and beef is.
We must keep the beef scouts going.
- Is it, well, there are a lot
of nine-year-old farmers in those days.
- No.
- To get the pork production badge,
you needed to confer with meat market men
and from their instruction, draw a diagram of a hog
and mark and name the parts for butcher classification.
- It's so good.
I think our children should be learning that kind of stuff.
- I love those details.
All the things that they had to do.
Like a farmhouse and planning
was one of the merit badges you could get.
And as part of that,
you had to present a drawing plan
of sewage disposal for a country home.
(laughing)
- Amazing.
I mean, these are the skills of the future.
- I don't know.
I don't like that element.
It reminds me a lot of Duke of Edinburgh.
I don't know if anyone did that
where basically you thought it was just going
on a fun walk when there's all this background stuff
you also have to do.
So all the badges still, there's the family life badge,
which is quite nice.
It basically means being a good little boy
or girl to your parents,
but you have to write this full proposal, don't you?
At the start and make lists
and then submit various essays on it.
- It doesn't mean anything to be good to your parents
if you're doing it just to get a badge, does it?
- Yeah.
- I think whatever, whatever works.
- Whatever.
(laughing)
I agree.
Stalking badge was another one, by the way.
- Stalking.
- That had to go.
(laughing)
They just renamed that as tracking
just to make it more acceptable.
- Do you know what the rarest badge
that anyone got in 2024 was?
Again, this is all American Boy Scouts.
We should say.
In fact, I think pretty much everything we've said
is American Boy Scouts.
So, okay, I would say in 2024,
'cause there are some old-school badges
like Hog and Pork production,
but there are new ones.
- That's not there anymore.
- There are new ones like being woke or whatever.
Is it one of the new or the old-school ones
that was the least caught on?
- Oh, it's old-school.
- I reckon.
- Is it motorboating?
'Cause I think that--
(laughing)
- Popping your head between women's boobs.
- Well, that's the thing.
I think that's got connotations now.
It is a badge, but I bet a lot of people
are doing the wrong thing when they try to get it.
- I see what you mean.
Only one kid actually drove a motorboat.
The others all just went, "Maw, maw, maw, maw."
And they get it. (laughing)
- My God.
- It's not that. - Okay.
- I'm trying to think if this actual thing
could have any sexual connotations.
- Is it like a schooner construction?
- I mean, it's a very difficult thing to guess, really.
It's something that you might associate with the army
as opposed to the scouting movement.
- Okay.
- Something that one person in an army regiment would do.
- Oh, only because I've read through the big list.
Is it bugling?
- It's bugling, yes. - Oh, wow.
- I don't know if that is another sexual term.
It feels like it probably should be.
- Certainly could be, couldn't it?
- But yeah, the least common are bugling, surveying,
stamp collecting, drafting, composite materials,
and then it goes on.
- We've lost so many of our traditions.
- And the top three.
Oh, top one, top one badge in 2024.
- I think pioneering, 'cause it's so classic.
That's one with ropes and building.
- Not where you put a pioneer ear.
(all laughing)
- Got to get off over dictionary.com.
- I just hope to God, Anna,
you never be a young boy scout
who tells you they're doing a motor birdie.
(all laughing)
And you're gonna go on.
Go on, mate.
(all laughing)
- Show me your skills.
Don't mind my mate with the poisonous ears.
(all laughing)
He's just going for his.
- So pioneering, that's your guess, right?
- This is easy to get, I reckon.
- Is it like helping a person?
- Geocaching.
- Helping a person, but in a very specific way.
- Helping old women cross across the road.
- There's no badge for that.
- First aid.
- Correct.
And the biggest gain in popularity in 2024.
This one went from the 121st most popular badge
to the 81st most popular badge.
And it's something that one of us
round this table enjoys.
- But it's a skill.
- It's not, so it's weighing on
about electric cars or something.
(all laughing)
- Thank you.
Was it being a lush, James?
(all laughing)
- Being weird on ghost dating websites.
- I wasn't being weird, I was being friendly.
- It was.
- It was a friendly ghost.
- The wife guy badge.
- No, no, it wasn't, it wasn't, it wasn't.
- It was the golf badge.
- Oh!
- It was the biggest cake.
- Clever.
- It was a twist, it was him.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, we were looking at the,
that's very good, that's very good.
There is this really big thing of like,
oh, all the badges, they've gone all woke, blah, blah, blah.
And it's a very, very tiresome talking point
because there are things like, there's a money skills one,
or you know, or there's Scouts Digital Citizen,
or you know, or there's, actually loads of them
are just absolutely straight down the line,
like athletics, air researcher, angler, caver, climber,
they're just absolute route one classic scout stuff.
- Oh yeah, they're all the classics,
except one of the really early classics,
the Swastika badge, which I don't think was on my list.
- No.
- Baden-Pound loved the Swastika badge.
- What?
- He thought it should be like the defining badge
of the Scouts, he said.
- So what are you talking about?
- In 1921, he wrote quite rightly
that the Swastika is a symbol used in every part of the world,
in the ancient world, in the modern day,
but now it stands for the badge of fellowship among Scouts.
And how you used it was, if you're a Boy Scout,
you always carry around a collection of Swastika badges.
And if someone did you a good turn,
like gave you a leg up or a pie,
then you gave them a badge and you said, always wear this.
And that means if a Boy Scout ever saw you,
they have to offer to do you a good turn.
- So are we misunderstanding the Nazis?
- They just did a lot of good turns for the Scouts over the years.
- I think that was it, yeah.
- It was actually just a big sponsored march into Poland.
(laughing)
'Cause Baden-Pound,
'cause that was obviously when the Swastika
had not been adopted by the Nazis.
But he was a bit fascistic.
So in 1937, he wanted to form close ties
with German youth movements.
He wrote in his diary in 1939 that "Mine Camp"
was a wonderful book with good ideas
on education, health, propaganda, organization, et cetera.
- I would agree on the propaganda front.
- Well, it did work, didn't it?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, obviously he could have known how it would turn out,
but...
- Yeah, wow.
That meant that puts the shows the Swastika thing
in a whole new light.
- I don't want to say...
By the way, I'm not saying he was an out and out fascist.
He was just a complicated character,
very old fashioned these days,
but had amazing ideas about like getting young people
organized and working together,
helping each other, all of that,
like raising good citizens for that.
- And it impressed the world.
So the reason the American Scouts started,
there's an origin story,
which is such like, it's like King Arthur.
It's just like total bullshit,
but it's a guy called W.D. Boyce.
And W.D. Boyce is one of the five co-founders of the Scouts.
- Scouting for Boyce.
So you got Baden Powell,
who obviously is the British originator,
but in America, you then had W.D. Boyce,
you had Daniel Carter Beard, James E. West,
and then you had Ernest Thompson Seton.
The audio was that W.D. Boyce was in England.
He's an American newspaper guy,
and he was walking through a foggy street at night.
Couldn't really see anything.
Went out through the fog, came a Boy Scout,
and said, "Let me help you across the road,
"and let me get you to where you need to go."
And he thought, "Wow, this young man with impeccable behavior.
"What is this?
"Oh, you're a Boy Scout.
"I must do that."
And he got taken to Baden Powell,
and immediately said, "I'll set it up."
Now, we know that it wasn't even foggy that day
that he was there in the UK.
- Well, who thought to do that research?
- Well, people who try to work out.
- People who meet urologists.
- Because there's a lot of sort of questions
about who actually is the original founder
of the American Boy Scouts.
- So often it's raining outside,
and I look at my phone up, and it says it's not raining.
And that's like literally happening right now.
I don't trust this stuff.
- Yeah, I mean, who knows?
But that's the kind of the story
that was created, the mythology behind it.
The other guy was Ernest Thompson Seton.
There's a great fact,
I read in a Margaret Atwood book about him,
which is when he turned 21,
his father handed him a bill charging him
for all the expenses associated with his childhood,
including the fee for his delivery at birth.
Just hand it to him.
- Right, he's one of the founders of the American Boy Scouts.
- I will not do that for my daughter,
just to say, 'cause she was on the NHS.
(all laughing)
- They and Paul, yeah, he married a woman called Olaf Sones.
He was 55, and she was 23 when they got married.
And the wedding present for those two,
the Scouts were each encouraged to contribute one penny,
and a hundred thousand of them did it,
and they bought him a car, which is quite cool.
And then in 1929,
to celebrate the 21st birthday of the Scouts,
they all did the same again.
But at this stage,
there were four million Scouts and guides around the world.
And so they bought him a Rolls-Royce.
- Oh, that's great. - That's great.
- Isn't that cool? - Long Con, you know?
(all laughing)
- They started emitting girls in 2019,
the Boy Scouts of America.
And who did this piss off?
- Oh, the Daily Mail readers.
- Was it someone in the Baden-Powell family?
'Cause he, I mean, he--
- Very much so.
- His sister ran the Girl Guides, though,
when they started.
- Well, that's, it was the Girl Scouts.
- Right, right, sorry, Girl Scouts, yeah, yeah.
- So yeah, they are furious about this,
because they now call themselves the BSA
to try and take the boy out of their, like, name.
And the girls basically said,
the whole reason they've done this
is to help with their massively plummeting membership.
They're trying to steal Girl Scouts from our movement,
from us, and they're suing them, the name change.
- People who want their children to join the Girl Scouts,
they might just Google Girl Scouts
and get the girl members of the Boy Scouts.
- Yeah, absolutely, so there's beef.
- If it's called the, there's beef.
- There's a lot.
- Not since 1968, there is a--
(all laughing)
- It's gone off now.
- Lovely.
- So hopefully they'll fight, and then who do you back?
- But they're called the BSA now.
- I believe so, yeah.
- Boy Scouts of America, yeah.
- What was the B-Stand for, if not for boy?
- Well, you don't know the--
- Well, you're hiding it, aren't you?
That's the whole point.
Why did the girls start letting boys in?
- Yes.
- Yeah, I can see how that's the logical daily mail
commenters' response.
(all laughing)
- Sorry, I thought that was the work response.
You're trying to get your work badge.
- Let me knock down the Girl Scouts,
'cause it's about time someone's done a peg or two.
They, according to a blog called Waity Matters,
are saddling America with a huge amount of obesity.
Thanks to the Girl Scout cookies
that they sell every year.
So according to this person on the blog,
they worked out that the Girl Scout cookies
that are sold every year accounts
with three quarters of a million pounds of trans fat.
That's 3.5 billion teaspoons of sugar
that they add to the American food supply.
- Well, that does sound bad,
but we need overall figures, I think,
because that's a bit,
if it can't just be the Girl Scout cookies.
- Oh, no, there's other stuff going on.
(all laughing)
- But it doesn't help.
- It doesn't help.
- They're trying to fatten up the boys,
make them easier to defeat.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that one of London's oldest windows
is made of cow horn.
- The window itself.
- The glass, as it were.
The glass substitute is cow.
- Can you see through it?
'Cause if not, I say that isn't a window.
- Well, judge for yourself, James,
'cause I've got a photo here of me this morning
at the cow horn window.
- I can see you, but you are in front of it.
- Yeah, but you can see through it.
It's very see-through-able.
So, horn, it turns out, is a fantastic window material,
beaten maybe only by glass.
(all laughing)
This is in London.
It's a place called Guildhall.
So, there's a separate thing called the City of London,
which is different to London, right?
The City of London is the sort of ancient body.
It's--
- It means part of London, really.
- It's right in the middle of London, definitely.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, you're still in London.
But, the actual Guildhall itself,
the town hall of the City of London,
dates back to the 14th century.
Like, it's the oldest non-religious building in London.
You know, there are a couple of abbeys and cathedrals
and things that are older, but it's really old.
And this window dates back to the 15th century.
So, it has survived any manner of stuff.
All the other windows in the place have been replaced.
Like, there's been the Blitz,
there's been the Great Fire of London.
This window is still there all these years later.
It's kind of amazing.
- Come on, kids, go and play football outside.
(all laughing)
- I dare you.
- And it's made of cow horn.
So, you pop the horn off the cow, you slice it up,
you heat that, and then you can mold it
into this amazing, really pretty transparent window material.
It's stunning.
- So cool.
- And is it incredibly strong?
Is that how it's survived this lot?
- Oh, no.
- Okay, so that makes it all the more amazing
that we've still got it, right?
- It's not only not--
I mean, it's decent.
You know, glass from the time is not incredibly strong either.
And until the 18th century,
cow horn was used largely for translucent sheets
to go into, like, lanterns.
The word "lantan" comes from lanthorn, you know,
'cause it would have horn--
- That's it.
- The sides of it were horn.
- I don't think it does.
I think, 'cause I was like,
"That's why they always spell it weird in old books."
'Cause obviously, you know, you read old, like,
Shakespeare will say it, "lanthorn."
In the old 19th century novels,
sometimes you see lanthorn.
So I was like, "That explains it."
But actually, lantern just comes from Latin,
like, meaning light.
But people then did the old got confused.
Lots of their lanterns were made out of horn.
So they went, "Should we shove a horn on the end?"
And I read a quite annoyed encyclopedia entry
from about 1803, saying lanthorn
is a completely incorrect spelling of this
based on the misconception.
So that's just the idiots from the 18th century.
- But it is based on the fact
that lanterns were made of horn.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- Which they were.
- Yeah, right, yeah, yeah.
- That's really interesting.
- It's so cool.
I mean, basically, in the 15th century,
they had the equivalent of laminated menus.
There were the horn books that students would use
where they would have all the alphabet on it.
You've got, like, wooden frames
where you've got horn that's written on
with the alphabet to learn from and things like that.
But you've also got ancient books
which have a square of horn on the front
to protect what's beneath,
like a very valuable old bit of parchment
or vellum or whatever.
So the horn window covers that.
But it's quite delicious for insects.
So a lot of the very old ones
are just nibbled away at all around the edges.
- The alphabet books that Dan was talking about
are called horn books.
And the horn book is also the title of a book from 1889,
which is thought of as the principal work
on sex technique in the English language.
- Oh, good Lord.
- It's basically 1889.
- I didn't think.
- Yeah?
- I didn't think they had that then.
- Well, that's why it's interesting.
Where do you think your great-great-great-great-great-great-grandmother
came from?
(laughing)
So it's like the Kamasutra, basically,
but for Victorian England.
- Wow.
- And they had sex techniques.
Number one, The Ordinary.
(laughing)
- End of book.
- What was that then?
Was that actually in 1888?
That was upside down and back to front.
- Here's some more.
Number five, The St. George.
(laughing)
- What, 'cause you're sort of prodding a dragon.
- Number nine, The View of the Low Countries.
- Oh, that is good.
- Number 48, Waste Not Want Not.
- Oh, dear.
- And number 63, The Sack of Corn, Backwards.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- None of these say much about the people involved,
do they?
- No.
- There's much more.
- Wait, what was the connection to horn, sorry?
- It's called the horn book.
- Oh, that's it, sorry.
- It's like, if you Google, I'm just warning people,
if they Google horn books to get these alphabet books,
they might accidentally get this one.
- Do be careful if you're on horn.com.
(laughing)
- There's a cleaner horn book fact, which I quite liked,
which was a poem was written in 1622,
which said, 'cause they were the thing you went to
for your learning your first letters, and it read,
"Even so, the horn book is the seed and grain
of skill by which we learning first obtain,
and it was written by William Hornby."
- Oh, that's really good.
Can I give you another one like that?
- Please.
- The largest brothel in Europe is situated on Horn Street.
- Okay.
- Is it?
- Yeah.
- I was trying to raise the tone.
- Well, it's gone straight back down again.
It's in Cologne, and it has 120 sex workers working there,
and it was Europe's first high-rise brothel.
- But how many of the customers are going looking
for alphabet books for their kids?
- Most of them, yeah.
- I think the architectural thing
is not the interesting thing there,
as I've stayed in the largest hotel in Thessaloniki,
and it's not a guarantee of quality.
It turns out, when you just say Europe's largest brothel,
it doesn't mean best.
- That's true.
- Oh, my God.
- They basically had a red light district in the town center
and decided to do away with it
and get this huge multi-storey building and stuff.
- Right.
- And it advertises money-back guarantee
in the case of unsatisfactory service.
- No.
- Yeah.
- It's so awkward to complain, isn't it?
- The sack of corn wasn't backwards at all.
(all laughing)
Have you guys heard of the worshipful company of Horner's?
- Yes, I know someone who's connected.
- Get out.
- Well, 'cause London has all these guilds,
which are the worshipful company of,
and then you insert very old-fashioned trade.
- So this is the thing, it dates back to 1284,
and it was a guild for people who worked with horn people,
and it was a huge business at the time, obviously,
'cause all the people needed lanterns and windows
and horn books and other uses of horn, there are thousands.
Now, they declined, obviously, when pesky glass,
stupid glass, took over the window industry,
and they were in the doldrums for centuries,
but they came back,
and he guesses what they sort of re-imagined themselves as.
- Oh, buglers.
- It's not buglers, though.
They just can't get enough buglers through the door.
- I'm just thinking, like, if they're still called the Horner's.
- They're still called the Horner's,
but they took on another industry
related to what they did in the first place.
- I read this early today,
and I just couldn't believe I never made the connection,
but shoehorns are made of horn.
- It wasn't, yes, that's true.
That's not the gigantic industry they put on.
- Come on, globally, everyone's got a shoehorn.
- Absolutely.
- Is it microchips?
- No, it's plastics.
- Oh, right.
- Horn was the original plastic.
You heat it, you can mold it.
So these days, all the members
of the worshipful company of Horner's
are from the city, from the plastics industry.
They sponsor the Polymer Apprentice of the Year Award.
Big deal in plastics.
- It's huge, it's a scout badge.
- Yeah, that's amazing.
- Yeah, that's really cool.
- Do you know that actually being a Horner
is pretty tricky today?
- Is it?
- If you're a true Horner,
not one of these plastic people,
but you're a person who wants to make things out of horn,
it is difficult because of breeding
and modern farming and feeding
has changed what horns are like.
So the material is not as good for molding
as it used to be.
And it'll quite often retain what they call its memory.
So you kind of flatten it
and then you put it into whatever shape you want it to be,
but it kind of remembers that it was horn shaped before
and you can't get it flat properly.
- You come down to your new car window
and it's just back in the shape of a cow horn.
- It's a cow there instead, you ride it to work.
- So did you read about the Abbey horn, horn works?
- Go for it.
- We've said the word horn so much, I just love it.
Anyway, sorry, it's on the edge of the lake district.
It's the only horn works left in the UK.
'Cause it's an endangered craft these days
'cause there are only about 10 to 20 horn workers left.
And I think most of them work at Abbey horn.
It's been there for nearly 300 years
and you can get some bloody good stuff there.
I was going through the website
and just, you get a horn moustache brush,
some bloody good shoe horns, Dan, you'd love it.
- Okay, send me that link.
- Some absolute foot long monsters.
And actually, James, as you were saying,
'cause horn has changed,
they get some of those from like,
I think it's African cattle called the ankle
'cause they have massive great horns.
And you might wanna buy it at the novelty drinking horn
if your partner is into being a Viking or whatever.
- How is it?
Are you allowed to buy and sell this kind of horn
compared to obviously ivory you're not allowed to
and lots of other rhino horns you can't.
- It's fine, it is fine.
Because all of these cattle that they're buying the horns of
were bred for farming
and they certainly weren't killed for their horns.
- On drinking horns, obviously a huge use of horn.
And Vikings really did massively popularize them.
It was kind of the Vikings that brought them to the UK,
although they'd been used before.
But did you know that they also bought
such a drinking culture that got so bad by the 10th century
that King Edgar, who you all know,
it was the late 10th century English king,
said that every village had to be limited to one ale house
and every single drinking horn that any punter drank out of
had to have pins inserted at certain levels,
it's a bit like you have measures on cups a day.
And whoever drank beyond those intervals in one week
had to be severely punished.
- Whoa. - Right.
- Which is a tough to monitor as a bar person.
- Policing that, yeah.
(laughing)
But is it because it's a little bit of a drinking culture,
I think, because you can't put it down.
- Yeah, that's the idea.
- It's like a cocktail party where there's no table.
It's a nightmare.
You fill up your horn and you just stuck around holding it.
- Yeah, I must say the Vikings coming to Northern England
in the 10th century is just like you going to a cocktail party.
- There's no to put it down.
And often you lose track of your own horn.
And what's good is to put a little hairband
around your own horn.
(laughing)
- Well, you're the only one who comes with a horn holder
to make sure you can put it down between sits, so.
- Can you think of another use of the word horning
to be horned?
- Oh, I'm thinking of horning in on a situation.
- Oh, like horning in.
- No, it's sort of where you interrupt.
Oh, here Anna comes horning in on our conversation.
- Oh yeah. - Whatever.
- No, not that.
This is in a kind of sport.
- A very old-fashioned European sport.
- Marrying the Habsburg Queen.
- That's a sport, very good.
No, it's in bullfighting.
It's when you get gored by a bull.
It's called, it's known as a horning.
- It's been a horning in the morning.
- Yes.
- Morning horning would be a good royal rumble thing
for bullfighting.
Just in case the bullfighting people are listening,
wanting to rev it up a bit.
- The record for most hornings
is by a guy called Antonio Barrera,
who has been horned 23 times.
- Is that a good record?
Do you want that guy on your team?
- The guy from Guinness is saying,
"I'm so sorry, I missed the 16th morning,
"so we're not gonna gather a record."
- Wait, how many of those were the same occasion?
- They were all different occasions.
- Oh, blimey.
- The most common place to be horned by bull.
- Spain, I imagine.
- Are you a buddy?
- That'll be in Boston.
- In the ring. - Is he running away?
- In the ring, now in the upper leg.
And second place is the perineal area.
- Second most popular, that's a show.
Do they have guards?
Do they wear boxes?
- No, they don't.
- Bullfighters.
- No, no, they were very tight trousers, don't they?
- If only there was some system
where there could be some kind of clown in the ring,
who was able to distract the attention of the bull.
- Well, some rodeo clown idiot.
- I guess you'd call them that, yeah.
Have you heard of the German island of Borkum?
- No.
- This is a place that has a Christmas festival
called Klassholm, right?
Or Klassholm.
And they had this tradition for many, many years there
where men dress up in elaborate costumes
and spank women with cow horns on the bottom.
And this led to controversy recently
because a lot of the women said,
actually, we really don't like this.
- Stop using the pointy end.
- Well, I mean, we don't like being spanked,
or, you know, we're being spanked without permission
on Christmas.
But last year there was a huge crackdown
on cow horns spanking on Borkum.
And it passed without any spanking
and without any complaints.
Certainly without any complaints.
There may have been private consensual cow horns spanking.
- I think that's fine.
- Absolutely.
And in fact, when there was this big protest,
like loads of the women saying,
can you stop hitting us with cow horns on the bum
every Christmas?
This is not fun.
A couple of hundred women did launch a counter protest
saying, we love it.
It's our way of life.
This is our tradition.
So there's definitely debate.
But for the moment,
it appears that the involuntary cow horns spanking is over.
Why don't the women just spank the men back?
Or, I'm sorry, is that the Daily Mail comments
coming out again?
(laughing)
- I think that takes the fun out of it.
It's like giving someone a wedgie.
It's not as fun giving someone a wedgie, is it?
If you have to say beforehand,
is it okay if I give you a wedgie?
- Are we saying, Anna,
that consent takes the fun out of things?
'Cause I do think we're on thin ice.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is Anna.
My fact this week is that Jack Kerouac
wrote his most famous novel on one long scroll.
- Was it sold in scroll form ever?
- Yeah.
- The audio box started, oh, yay, oh, yay.
(laughing)
- That's an interesting question.
It sort of is today, but not at the time.
- It has, as in that scroll has been sold.
- I think, yeah, that scroll, you're right.
You can go and visit it.
I can't remember what, it's in a museum somewhere.
- It's owned by, or it was owned.
Unfortunately, he died this year.
Jim Erse, who owns the Indianapolis Colts
American football team.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- Obviously, that's where it, who it would be owned by.
(laughing)
- Yeah, no, he's a big, maybe we'll talk about it later.
Let's get into the fact that he was a huge collector
of this guy.
- Oh, cool.
- Yeah, I've got a big old list of other cool things he has.
- All right, well, excited to skip ahead to that.
But first of all, Jack Kerouac.
Yeah, he wrote on a long scroll
and basically he got annoyed
'cause he was a writer who typed very fast
and it all came flowing through him
and out of his fingertips.
And he thought you should never have to pause or stop
or have your flow interrupted.
- Or think, or think at all about the next sentence.
Maybe I'll put a main verb in this one, that kind of stuff.
Why would you think about the next sentence
considering it's about five pages away?
(laughing)
Which we should say if you read any Jack Kerouac,
it is very stream of consciousness.
- Yes.
- It's interesting.
Maybe we'll also get into a big debate
of who likes his style and who doesn't.
I think I know around this table who's gonna be the fan.
But he didn't like to reload his typewriter
with bits of paper.
So he got this massive scroll.
It was made of like teletype paper,
kind of like tracing paper, thick tracing paper.
And he taped it all together.
And then he made a 120 foot long scroll.
This was in 1951 and he was writing on the road.
- That was the name of the book.
- Sorry.
- Sorry, yeah.
He was writing in his bedroom, but on the road.
And when he was finished, he marched into his editor's office
who was a guy called Robert Giroux.
And he was unspun the scroll across the floor
like you would unroll a rug.
And Giroux just said,
Jack, don't you realize that's not how authors
present manuscripts?
I can't do anything with this.
Take it away.
- I think he did know
that that's not how you present manuscripts.
Also, it is often presented as if he did the stream
of consciousness he handed it over.
And that's it.
That's not the case.
He spent years and years editing it.
It's a very highly edited document.
- Not that it seems like it, but yeah.
- Should we say who Jack Kerouac is?
Briefly, like American part of the beat generation,
post-war counter-cultural writers
who were rebelling against the way America was.
You know, that was the basic movement.
And Jack Kerouac was a huge part of it with On the Road,
which is extremely famous, you know?
- Yeah.
And what's interesting is he influenced a lot
of these people like Ken Kessie,
who wrote One Flew the Cuckoo's Nest,
Alan Ginsberg, the poet.
- William Burroughs.
- Yeah, if he gave the name to William Burroughs'
probably most famous novel, Naked Lunch.
That was something that he came up with.
But when he wrote On the Road,
he did spend all those years trying to get it published
and editing it.
And in the meantime, everyone who was influenced
by reading copies of it got their own stuff published.
So it ended up looking like Kerouac was copying off them,
when in fact he was the influence for this whole generation.
- Yes, 'cause it only ended up being published in 1957,
we should say.
So he proposed it in 1951.
The editor said, "Take it away and tie it into a proper book."
And so he then did type it out on normal pages.
But no one would take it.
All the publishers said,
"We think this is kind of a work of genius,
"but no one's gonna care about the subject matter."
- And the subject matter is?
- It's basically a big old road trip.
It's none of his books and novels,
and I hate it when people refer to them as that,
'cause they're all completely true to his own life.
They're his autobiography, basically.
And this was a bit of work.
- They're exaggerated autobiographies, aren't they?
- Yeah, so it's him traveling around with his mates.
And they all put each other in each other's books,
don't they, Ginsberg does and Burroughs does.
He also, incidentally, named Ginsberg's most famous book,
Howl.
So he named the three most famous books
of the B-generation.
- His real skill was naming books.
(all laughing)
- All these books that he did,
which were semi-autobiographical and with all his mates in,
the liars of his publishers made him change all the names
for obvious reasons.
There was lots of stuff happening in those books
that they might object to.
But Kerouac's intention was towards the end of his life,
he was gonna get all of his old books,
and he was gonna republish them all
as one enormous scroll from start to finish,
but then change all the names back
so that we got all the people's names out.
- Oh, that's good.
- But then he died quite young, I think.
- He died really, yeah, he died in the late 60s.
- Sorry, can I just say that has been done now,
just to make sense of what I said earlier,
I think Viking Press in about 2011
released the original scroll,
which is with all the original names,
and it's with no paragraph breaks and written--
- I've got it at home, it's a beast of a book.
I haven't read it, I mean, just no way, but it's--
- And there you go, that's the fan reveal.
- But I'm a fan of the counterculture,
I've not actually read Kerouac,
because it's a difficult read.
- Yeah, a stream of consciousness is harder.
Can I give you one more version of that meeting
with Robert Giroux, who was one of his previous editors,
and then he'd written short stories and things like that.
He turns up at the office with the manuscript,
with the scroll, throws it on the floor,
and this is according to Robert Giroux.
He was very excited, this is Kerouac, I think he was high.
Anyway, I bent down to look at the thing,
and after a few moments, I looked up and said,
"Well, Jack, this is going to have to be cut up
"into pages and edited and so on."
Jack just looked at me and his face had darkened,
and he said, "There'll be no editing.
"This book was dictated by the Holy Ghost."
And the book then went to a different publisher.
(laughing)
- You met him on a dating site, didn't you?
- Yeah, I think he was off his face quite a lot.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- He was on Ben Zatrin when he did this,
which is an amphetamine that a lot of people were on
at the time.
It was like a nasal spray, like a kind of pseudo Fred thing,
but then it made everyone, gave lots of people lots of energy
'cause it's basically amphetamines.
- It's not very cool though, is it?
It's not like-- - It's not cool now.
- The jazz guys trying to find a new vein for the horse.
It's like, if it's a nasal spray,
I do think that's an uncool administration
for a mind-altering drug.
- Yeah, I guess so, but it was cool at the time.
- Yeah.
- And then it kind of did go out of fashion.
- And he went out of fashion within his own circle as well.
That's one of the tragic things.
But he did die young, I think he was 47 when he died.
And even his friends, his closest friends,
like Alan Ginsberg, didn't want to know him at that point.
He had turned from this amazingly magnetic character
that basically defined this whole movement
to someone who became very bitter, very angry.
- He used to write newspapers about Boy Scout badges changing.
They got quite right-winged in the end.
He was always quite racist.
- But those letters to the newspapers,
they were so long, they couldn't get in.
- They were all on little scrolls, so sad.
You know, the original On The Road,
a dog ate part of his homework?
- Yes.
- Yeah, genuinely.
- Really.
- It was auctioned some years ago,
and the condition notes noted that the final 25 pages,
or equivalent of, had been chewed and torn away
by a dog belonging to Kerouac's friend
in April or May, 1951.
- But the thing is that no one who read it
ever got up to the last 25 pages,
so no one ever noticed.
- On The Road was published in 1957, was a huge hit.
And immediately he couldn't handle it.
He just like, he sort of had a breakdown.
His publisher said he ended up like lying
on the floor staring at the ceiling,
not knowing what to do, became terrible alcoholic.
- I think we said that he went to a lookout tower,
didn't he?
Was that after that as well?
- Oh yes, that's right.
- He kind of just lived on his own for months and months
in the middle of the forest looking for fires.
- Did you find any?
- No, he didn't, but apparently he did leave behind him
a column of feces about the height and size of a baby.
- Why, what an upsetting simile point.
For your column of feces.
There's so much else you could compare it to,
like a melon or a melon.
- A melon?
- Melons are smaller than babies.
- How big are your melons?
- Excuse me, how small are your babies?
(laughing)
Alan, we're not getting into motorboats again.
- Do you know the only reason he became so famous
and it all ruined him anyway?
It was because of one review he got in The New York Times.
So if the review had not been printed,
he would have probably stayed a small time.
He was a small time before it came out, right?
But the main reviewer, a guy called Orville Prescott,
hated him, hated his stuff, but he was away on holiday.
And so there was a different reviewer
who just got drafted in for holiday cover
called Gilbert Milstein.
And he gave it the biggest smash hit review
The New York Times had ever given anything.
He said, "It's publication is a historic occasion.
"The writing is of a beauty almost breathtaking."
And this gave the book absolute rocket fuel
that made it a huge success.
Prescott, who was the main guy in charge of reviewing,
was so angry about this.
He almost didn't allow it to go in.
And then he fired Gilbert Milstein.
He was never hired again to write The New York Times
because he loved this stream of consciousness,
hard to read, beat generation thing.
- Yeah. - Wow.
- Love it, all you hate it.
- Well, listen guys, I can hear the audience at home.
Script, well, I can hear at least my mom screaming.
Tell us about the collection that Jim Ersey had.
- Ah, yes.
- In which.
- Can we scroll this content?
- Why not tell us who this guy is?
- So he was the owner of the Colts,
the football team in America.
And he bought up the scroll.
And it's part of this big traveling collection that he has.
So he has the big book,
the original Alcoholics Anonymous book,
the first manuscript that was ever written.
- Oh, I thought you went with everyone's names.
(all laughing)
- It's Alcoholics Not Anonymous.
- That's the Compromat book.
Just one guy is allowed to know who you are.
- No, this was the original book
that William or Bill W. Wilson had written.
- Actually, wasn't that the Holy Ghost
who gave him that as well?
- He was, you're right.
You're right, it was a huge episode
for the Holy Ghost, this one.
(all laughing)
He has two tickets from the performance
of our American cousin for Ford's Theatre,
the night that Lincoln was assassinated.
He's got a rocking chair that was used by JFK
inside the White House.
- I should just say, he did die this year.
- He did die. - He keeps saying he has.
- Sorry, he did, he died just over a month ago.
- Well, he'll be getting a chance
to chat to the Holy Ghost, won't he?
That's exciting.
(all laughing)
- He has the greatest collection of guitars.
- Yeah. - In the world.
Or he has, I should say, again.
It was called that in the Guitar Magazine in 2021.
And every famous guitarist you can name, he has.
- Eric Clapton.
- George Harrison. - Jimmy Bage.
- Django Reinhardt.
- Oh. - What the fuck?
- I just don't think
you've written them all down.
- No, I haven't. - I bet he does though.
- I think Betty does have a Django.
- Yeah, I'm sure he does.
'Cause I was really hoping that you would just name
any of these 20 names that I have on my list.
- Give us one or two.
- Oh, okay. - No, I mean,
Elvis, George Harrison, John Lennon,
Paul McCartney, Jerry Garcia, Prince Les Paul,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
- Kurt Cobain.
He has Kurt Cobain's Nevermind guitar.
It's like one of the most iconic grunge guitars you've ever had.
- Just the guitar he brings out at a party
and they say, "Oh, for fuck's sake."
Nevermind, nevermind, nevermind.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
- I'm on Instagram under @Shrieberland, Andy.
- I'm on Instagram at @andrewhunterm.
- And James.
- I'm on TikTok, no such thing as James Harkin.
- And if you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- We are on Instagram @nosuchthingasafish
or on Twitter @nosuchthing or email podcast.qi.com.
- That's right.
Or you can go to our website, nosuchthingasafish.com.
We have all our previous episodes up there.
You can check out things like Club Fish,
which is our secret members club.
Do join that, get bonus episodes,
ad-free content, all that stuff.
And we're gonna be doing a couple of live gigs
in September at the London Podcast Festival.
Tickets are available for that now.
Go check it out.
Otherwise, just come back here next week.
We'll have another episode waiting for you.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)