[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to Meet the Elves which is another one of our
favorite features on Clubfish where we meet one of the QI elves who you might
not have met before and today we're gonna speak with Leigh-ing.
Hi. Hi Leigh-ing, how you doing?
Hi, yeah I'm good, enjoying the sun.
Oh yeah, we're in London in our new offices in Holborn and it's beautifully
sunshiny outside. Dan, anything to add on the weather?
No, I was just curious how you said Holborn because I've dropped the L from my
pronunciation, but I kind of saw you snuck it in to yours.
Well I told you not to put the L in Holborn, but you say it with an L.
Yeah, because I'm not from London you see.
I'm not from London. I pronounce it Covent Garden so anyway, Leigh-ing.
Nice to see you and you've brought a question for us I think and we're gonna
chat about it and try and answer it and maybe learn a bit more about you along
the way. Sure. So what's your question?
My question is, how do you pronounce it?
Why shouldn't you use the pink toilet in Christchurch Cathedral?
Oh, okay. What a great question. It sounds like a euphemism doesn't it?
Christchurch, is that an Oxford or a Cambrian?
New Zealand? Oh yeah. My first thought was New Zealand, is it?
Was it? It's not in New Zealand. You were right the first time, it is the one in Oxford.
Christchurch is a posh college. Is it?
Yeah, it is. It's one of the ones where people at the other colleges go, oh Christchurch.
Because to me, they're all posh. What is the, you know, on the scale of poshness?
It used to just be called church didn't it? And they went, oh Christchurch.
There is a kind of, I'm not gonna say a social dividing line, but basically
colleges made of stone tend to look down on those made of brick, you know?
Is that right? What about those made of straw?
All the little pigs have been eaten in those. It's very tragic.
No, as in just if your college is made of stone, it's like it's 700 years old
and it can withstand a medieval siege and it's probably there for the Civil War and all this stuff.
Whereas if you just made a brick, it's either like late 19th century or early 20th century.
So did you not talk to it? Because you went to Oxford. How could you go?
I thought we were dancing around the subject there. I thought we'd just lay it down.
Did you go to a brick or a stone? I went to a brick because I'm a blue-collar guy.
- Flame, did you go to university? - I did go to university. I went to Durham.
Oh, that feels like a stone to me.
- That's a good question. - It feels like bonds to me. Durham.
- It's nice and countryside, isn't it? - What? Durham, isn't it? - It's a city.
- It's a tiny city to be fair. - But it's quite medieval, isn't it?
It is gorgeous. I didn't go to one of the old posh ones though.
- You know what I'm talking about. - I do, I do.
- We tried ourselves on being relatable. - Durham.
- It's our college, our college. - Durham is a lot of posh as well.
It's like St Andrews as well. St Andrews is incredible. They've got three streets and everyone's got 15 names. It's very posh.
What was Exeter like? That's where you went, isn't it, James?
- No, I went to Sheffield. - Oh, sorry, Sheffield. My wife went as well, weirdly.
- Oh, yeah? - Yeah, yeah, yeah. What was it like there? Was that...
- That was great. - Sorry. - Why does a wolf have a little goatee?
It was alright. I went to Durham only once in my life, as in stayed there, and it was when I walked from Durham to Lindisfarne.
- Oh, gorgeous. - I did a pilgrimage.
Were you briefly in training for a monk to be a monk?
I feel like there was some point in your life where you could have become a monk.
I want you to carry on with this, because it is a complete falsehood, but I want to know where you're going to go with it.
No, I just thought that you'd be into it. I was an altar boy.
- That's it, and you were educated. - Does he just give off monkish vibes?
It's the tonsure that does it.
Yeah, that's why he's got a hat on.
But it's the... You went to a seminary. You were raised Catholic.
- I thought you went to a seminary. - I didn't go to a seminary. I actually don't know what that is.
I think of it as being a bit like a kind of training wheels monastery.
I went to a Catholic school, which was run by nuns and priests.
Right, so there must have been a point, the last possible point at which you could have become a monk.
I think it's still open to me.
You're absolutely right. There's no age limit in monks, is there?
Actually, famously, a lot of them are very old.
Yeah, you're right. You're right. Sorry, if you're listening to this and you think you're becoming a monk, don't give up.
Never too late.
Ling, have you ever considered the religious life?
Well, interestingly, both my parents are vikers.
- Are they? - Yeah, both.
So my mum and my dad are both reverent.
Andy was shocked a woman was allowed to be a viker in that.
No, I assume Ling had two dads who were both vikers.
Can I just say that must be difficult because I'm sure I'm wrong about this,
but I would have thought they would have to stay in their own diocese or parish.
And so it would be difficult because one of them would have to work in one town and the other one would have to work in another town.
So my dad is a viker, but not in the Church of England and my mum is a viker.
It is an Anglican viker, but that's irrelevant now anyway because they've moved to Hong Kong.
So my mum is a viker in Hong Kong.
Wow, which church?
So she used to be at St Andrews on Nathan Road.
- That's where I used to go. - Did she?
- Yeah, my whole childhood. - In Jinxatui, right?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Oh, my God. Wait, where? - In Jinxatui, TST.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
But I would have gone to that because I used to live near that area.
- So, wow. - Yeah, by Jordan and TST.
That's not well, she's not there anymore, but she used to be there.
And then now they've moved to a different church.
- I mean, that would have been amazing. - That would have been incredible.
I'm kind of sad that you backed off that.
I just sort of thought for accuracy, but yeah, I would have been there.
I would have prayed there.
You famously went to all the churches in Hong Kong, didn't you?
You've got to try them all out to see which one fits.
Sadly, it's made of brick, not stone, so...
- Right. - I know.
I just remembered the format.
- You had a question. - Pink toilets.
So Christ Church is like, it's got a big bell, which is called Old Tom.
That's one thing I know about Christ Church.
- Oh, I didn't know that. - And they've got the longest dining hall in Oxford.
- Is that where they filmed Harry Potter, their dining hall? - I think it is.
And I think my college had the second longest dining hall in Oxford.
- Oh, that must have hurt. - You couldn't add just a bit of wood.
- It was built later. - Why didn't they just make it?
I think mine was built later, and they did deliberately make it
by about six inches, the longest dining hall in Oxford.
You know, when they're trying to build the tortoise building,
they just add an extra spire on the top.
- They just chuck an extra table in the end. - One brick.
- This is a difference between my education and your education, Andy,
is that my university had the longest bar in England,
and I think it still does have the longest bar in England.
- Wow, it's very nice. - Bar one in Sheffield.
- Bar one? - Yeah.
- They couldn't remember bar two. - Is it an actual toilet, Leigh?
- No. - Oh, okay.
- Wait, let's have the question again then. - So why shouldn't you use
the pink toilet in Christ Church Cathedral?
- It's not an actual toilet. - It's not an actual toilet.
- Oh, and it's a cathedral. That's the other mad thing.
The reason that everyone thinks Christ Church College is so posh
is it has a cathedral on the premises, as in that's uncommon.
Like, colleges might have a chapel, or a little, you know,
because they're all religiously, they've got religious origins,
all of them, you know, so a chapel normal.
A cathedral? - Ah, so--
- If your little college, which has about 300 students,
you've got a cathedral, it's crazy.
- Is it a confession booth that's been called the pink toilet?
And-- - Oh, my God.
- Right, so Dan, I'd like to ask you a question.
Why is your confession booth called the pink toilet?
- I'm actually not taking questions right now, Andy.
- But it does, like, a confessional booth
looks a bit like a stall in a toilet.
- Yeah, absolutely. - Yeah.
- You've got the guy in there taking a mess of shit.
He's been in there for hours.
- 'Cause they have a little seat you sit on,
and they have a hole in the wall next to you.
- The trouble is-- - And there's a blow coming up
inside. - It would be incredibly circular
if the confession booth was a toilet, and you use it as a toilet,
and you were stuck in the confession booth add-in,
so confessing that you just shat in the confession booth.
- Yeah, it's got another confession booth if you do that.
- Imagine being the priest waiting for the next confession
to start, but then you just hear this--
(laughing)
Sorry, is there someone-- - No.
- Is there-- - No.
- There's no toilet paper there, is there?
(laughing)
- No.
- Oh, well, I've definitely sinned.
Forgive me, Father.
- That's when they open the little hatch
and just pass the-- (laughing)
- Pass the lever all through.
- Give it five minutes before you confess your sins
in there. (laughing)
- Oh, my God.
- Oh, no.
- There's nothing to do with confessional booths.
- Nothing to do with confession, apart from anything,
because Christchurch is an Anglican cathedral.
- Okay.
- And confessions, and correct me if I'm wrong,
I think they're Catholic, is that right?
- I don't know if there was ever a tradition of--
I think, I mean, they are Catholic, for sure.
- Yeah, so I think that's-- - Okay.
- All right.
Okay, so it's not a toilet.
That's what we know.
It's a big toilet, but it's not a toilet.
- Is there any kind of little clue that you can help us
along our way?
- Sure, it is a depiction of a toilet.
- Ah, okay.
- Of course.
Well, in that case, if it's a painting,
you should never shit on a painting.
(laughing)
I think, is that the answer?
- It's not a painting.
- Oh, not a painting.
- It's not a depiction, depiction.
Could be a mural, could be a gargoyle.
- Stained glass.
- Stained glass toilet.
- There is a stained glass toilet.
- No.
- In Christchurch Cathedral.
- Brilliant.
- Is there?
- Yes, and it is bright pink.
- Wow.
- Okay.
Who's, is it an, is it a?
- Is it quite modern?
- Yeah, it's modern.
- Because you would think like pink glass
would be difficult to get.
- Yeah, it's actually from the 1850s.
- Okay, wow.
- Yeah, so it was added by Edward Burn-Jones,
who became a pre-Raphaelite,
but it was in his pre-Raphaelite days
(laughing)
that he designed this stained glass,
and he was 24, 25.
- Wow.
- And they think that he was pretty excited
about the advent of flushing toilets,
and he added one into a panel in Christchurch Cathedral.
- That's so crazy.
- Wow, so it's a modern,
I didn't know when we got flushing toilets,
so that's quite exciting.
- Victorians.
- Yeah, great.
- When Victoria arrived on the throne,
they wouldn't have had them,
and by the time she died, they definitely would.
- Okay.
- So that's.
- That's about the right time.
- Yeah, so they think that he probably
would have used, you know,
the communal toilet on his street kind of thing.
- Right.
- But basically, this bright pink flushing toilet
is in a panel that he designed
that depicts the life of St. Frideswide,
who is the patron saint of Oxford.
Frides, well, so.
- I think it might be Frida's Wider.
- Well, Frida's Wider.
- Is it?
- I'm not sure.
- Frida's Wider?
- I thought that was a patron saint of Stockholm.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- I'm not certain,
but I don't think it's Frideswide.
- Well, that is what I was going to say,
which I find really interesting,
'cause I was mentioning this to Tara, who's.
- Don't use the pink toilet, Frida's Wider.
Don't be naughty.
- So Frida's Wider or Frideswide,
what's funny is that this is a town and gown divide,
I think, because my brother.
- Okay, town and gown.
(laughing)
- My brother went to,
his high school was called Frideswide School.
- Right.
- And everybody called it Frideswide School.
- Oh.
- And there's a square in Oxford called Frideswide Square.
- Well, they make all sorts of shit up in Oxford,
don't they?
- Oh yeah.
- They call Magdalene Maudlin.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that's true.
- There is a magazine about the patron saint of Oxford.
I think it's called Frida's Wider's Digest.
(laughing)
- Very nice, very nice.
- Are you a Frida's Wider Wider?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Well, Frida's, Frida's Wider, Frideswide.
- Frideswide.
- Whoever we're going for.
It was a panel depicting her life,
and this is the very, very last panel,
was Herb on her deathbed.
And behind her,
she just has a little on suite.
- Toilet.
- Cool.
- Lovely.
- She's got a little curtain.
- Made it.
- And you've got the toilet with a flushing handle
and everything.
- Wow.
- It's extraordinary.
- That is incredible.
- Yeah.
- I had no idea that there's two crossed over,
the stained glass in there.
- I suppose if you're making a church now,
they rebuilt the one in Christchurch, New Zealand,
didn't they?
- Yeah.
- After the earthquake.
What would you put into the stained glass?
- That's true.
- That's the modern equivalent of the toilet.
- Oh, it'd be like a mobile phone.
- Someone getting a good signal.
- Yeah.
Or a rocket.
- Or a working printer.
- Yeah.
- I've been to a Buddhist temple in Wimbledon,
and it's quite, like it's a surprising Buddhist temple.
- He'd be looking for James in his monkhood.
(all laughing)
But in it, they've got depictions
of all sorts of modern things.
- Okay.
- Whether it's spaceships or planes or whatever.
I mean, they're painted rather than stained glass,
but it's one of these incredible,
like all-round painted rooms.
I can't remember the name of the temple.
It's quite a famous Buddhist temple.
- We spoke on the pod a bit ago.
I can't remember how long ago,
but there is a stained glass window
that's now at Westminster Abbey,
which was designed by Hockney.
- Oh, yeah.
- The one that looks like it was made on Microsoft Paint.
- Well, it was made on an iPad.
- An iPad, yeah.
- He sort of designed it on an iPad.
- Oh, yeah.
- So stained glass is still alive.
- I went to the Hockney exhibition
in Granary Square in Kings Cross this weekend.
And someone who isn't a massive fan
of the new Hockney stuff, it was really good.
- Cool.
- You're like in a room,
and it's on all of the walls,
all of his paintings,
and he's talking about it and stuff like that.
And these things that look not particularly brilliant
'cause they're done in an iPad on a wall,
suddenly when it's the whole room lit up
with all the lights and stuff, it looks incredible.
- Nice, yeah.
- Yeah, it's really awesome.
- It'd be a cool escape room as well.
- Yeah?
- Like David Hockney's locked you up,
and you gotta get out.
- David locked me.
(all laughing)
- And there's the poster.
Have your name.
Hockney, we'll split it 50/50.
We'll see you there.
(all laughing)
- James, on your question
on what you'd put in a church nowadays,
I think it depends as well
on what we think Edward,
or why we think Edward Ben-Jones
put the toilet in the glass to begin with.
- See, I thought 'cause he was celebrating it, maybe?
- Yeah, so there's different ideas about that.
I'm curious what you guys think.
So one of them is this,
that he's excited about this new invention.
There's another idea that he might be actually making
a bit of a political statement
about the importance of sanitation.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, so because in 1858,
that was the year of the big stink.
So, you know, where all the, you know,
parliament had to be evacuated.
- Because, yeah, the sewers were emptying into the Thames.
It was a really hot summer.
- Exactly, exactly.
And the year before,
he had had a really awful, awful fever.
He nearly died.
And apparently, Frieders-Weeder,
slash, fried-eyed, had also died of a fever.
- Frieders-Weeder died of a fever.
(laughing)
- There is a thought that he's trying to make
a bit of a statement of, you know,
if only she'd had proper sanitation.
- Okay, that is, yeah, great.
- Yeah, so I don't know if you could, you know,
add some kind of political statement into your church.
I don't know what it would be.
- Hmm, well, it'd be a climate change thing,
I guess, for a lot of people these days.
You'd sort of have Attenborough sinking.
- Yeah, like a solar panel.
- I would want to see Attenborough
in a, like, depicted in stained glass.
- What, drowning?
(laughing)
- A stained glass solar panel would look really cool.
- Yeah, it would look cool.
- But wait a minute, the light has to pass through
in order to light up the cathedral,
and the solar panel has to-
- Yeah, you're right, you're right.
I put someone not playing the music out loud
on a portable speaker.
- Oh yeah, how would you, how would you depict that?
Someone not doing something?
(laughing)
I think actually this person who did the other one
has already put that in his-
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's all stained glass windows,
showing people not using portable speakers.
(laughing)
- Okay, well, thanks very much for your question, Leigh-Ink.
I think, did we get it right or not?
I think Andy maybe got the correct answer.
- Yeah, I don't want to say glass.
- Eventually.
All right, well, that's the end of the show.
Thank you very much, Leigh-Ink.
Thanks for bringing your question.
Hopefully we get you on this again quite soon.
And that's the end of Meet the Elves.
We'll be back again with another elf.
(singing)
- You remembered it!
- It's my, yeah.
- I'm impressed.
- I wrote it for this show.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)