(WHISTLE BLOWS)
(MUSIC PLAYING)
Hi!
Hey Andy, how's it going?
I'm really invigorated because we just
be talking about Dunstable.
Yeah, exactly.
The greatest show that we ever did.
I know.
And it was a great show.
It was a really fun show.
Wonderful.
Dunstable.
Look it up.
If you're watching internationally,
or listening internationally, check it out.
Check it out.
Get along there.
Yeah.
But enough about Dunstable.
We've got a show to record.
We do.
Can I ask a very important question before we get into it?
I think the entire audience is screaming to get an update.
How's my leg?
How's the leg?
It's still not 100%.
I have to say, but I've been going to rehab
to 20 minutes on the excise bike yesterday.
A little bit stiff this morning.
Legs not so good either.
Are you glad you asked?
Can I say the name of the show?
It's OK.
Welcome to Drop Us Align.
The audience feedback show.
My name's Andrew Hunter Murray.
And these two schmows that I'm with,
are Dan Schreiber and James Arkin.
Hello.
I'm thrilled we're here.
The inbox has been chocker.
It's been chocker block.
Has it?
Let's get slewson.
You ready?
I've written kick off with a nice email from Thomas Talba
from Austria.
Lovely.
Let's hear from Thomas, who says, first off,
thank you for going through our emails on a regular basis.
I'm finding the ones worth reading out, Andy.
Shame on James and Dan for not thanking you ever.
There I said it, heart emoji.
Thank you, Thomas.
Well, I edit this show.
So Thomas, you didn't make the cut.
Thank you for editing the show, Dan, by the way.
You are welcome, James.
These guys, of course, say thank--
well, they say, even though they're saying thank you,
they're appreciative.
I can tell from the way you're silent,
I can tell that you appreciate it.
Did Thomas say anything else?
He did, but that was the main--
Interesting.
So really, he's taking his time to write this nice email.
And all you've done is taking the bit which praises you,
and then you've ignored the rest of it.
I would say that what he said was a whole lobster's claw,
and I've extracted the small filament of meat
from the inside of it that was the most important.
Interesting.
And we've all enjoyed that meat now.
I'd argue it's more like a shrimp or a prawn,
and you take out the poo trap.
That's got to be removed out of eating.
I didn't know about that.
Oh, dear.
There's a little-- you see a little brown line.
That's their feces.
That's their bum tube.
It's only before you cook it.
If you're going to a restaurant, it should already have been done.
OK.
I'm going to stick with just a green salad, I think.
You don't need to remove the bum tube from a lettuce.
Anyway, new section, fish life.
Fish life.
Yeah. People living their best fish life, right?
Yeah.
I suppose it's a bit of a pan on fish knife or fish wife,
but neither really.
What does it mean?
People living their best fish life.
Yeah, but what does that mean?
Question.
People living in a way that is a fish appropriate
for people who've been inspired by fish in their day-to-day life.
So, for example, Jay Joah writes,
"I forget what the name of the section of Dropper's Align
where you talk about romance spurred by fish is..."
Do we have one of those?
I thought it was romance, but the row is spelled
like the eggs of a beluga.
Get in.
Romance.
Well, Jay writes,
"My fiancé, Umi and I got engaged last year,
and we're due to wed this June,
for much of the course of our relationship,
your podcast has been on constant rotation on our car journeys."
So, to honour this, we've included the podcast
in our pre-wedding photo shoot,
and Jay has sent a couple of photos of them in the car,
listening to fish.
When do we have to go for this photo shoot?
We are invited to the wedding.
Oh, which is in June.
Oh, I'm busy in June.
Oh, that's shame. Where's the hublin' cup, son?
Oh.
It's in Brunei.
Oh, I'm not so busy, actually.
I just realised it's only the group stages.
I'm not really bothered about those.
Is it one of those invites where it's sort of like all paid for?
Or it's not paid for, and it's evening only, but you are.
You have to leave on a flight by midnight.
Yeah.
But we wanted to ask if we're the first people from Brunei to write in,
or at the very least, the first love story
from Brunei involving fish.
I think this is the first Brunei correspondence we've had.
I think so.
The only fact that I can think of about Brunei
is that Geoffrey of Brunei had a yacht called Tits.
Who's Geoffrey of Brunei?
He was like a member of the Royal Family.
Wow. Wow.
It's Geoffrey. It's called Tits.
That's cool. Cool, yeah, that's a cool guy.
Wow.
When are you turning 14, Dad?
Because I don't want to be there for the party.
I hope you go laser questing.
Anonymous writes, "I am a judge in a superior court in Location X."
I've redacted that out of their request.
Yeah, very nice.
And I have placed my certificate from you,
friend of the podcast certificate, on display in my chambers.
That's really cool.
Wow.
I don't have my diploma from law school,
my certificate of my call to the bar,
or my certificate of appointment to the bench up,
but everyone who comes to the office knows
that I am the proud custodian of the fact that's (beep)
and the judge has attached some photos of their certificate.
That should we say what the fact is
because at some stage on Little Fish we're going to name
who owns that act.
One name who owns it.
Oh, that's a kind of jigsaw identification, isn't it?
Yeah.
Should we bleep that or blank it out?
Well, the thing is about super criminals is
they're going to be able to work that stuff out, and they...
Arguably, it doesn't matter.
How come they've asked to be redacted?
Yes, they have.
It matters, sorry, it matters to them.
(laughing)
Oh, it only matters to them.
I don't think you lose your gun and your badge
as a judge for having us certificate.
You're a judge.
You're a wigan, you're a guffal.
Exactly.
That's a weird judge.
He comes with a gun.
(laughing)
He's Judge Jerry and executioner.
Matthew Little writes, "Love the podcast, guys, big fan."
So much so that over the years,
I have had more than a few dreams
where I have been a guest on the program.
These dreams all go the same way.
The banter is excellent, and we all have a fun time.
I even managed to...
Not very realistic.
(laughing)
So he's not a guest that droppers alive.
He's a guest on an edit of one of our shows.
Yeah.
I even managed to get everybody chuckling
with a few little quips of my own.
That's nice.
Until the awful moment when it comes to my fact
to bring to the table, and I realize with dread,
I have come to the show with absolutely nothing.
This is a recurring dream that Matthew has.
What, do you guys have an anxiety dream like that?
Like most people do have like a recurring anxiety dream
where they just can't quite do something.
A lot of people, it's like running, but you're in quicksand kind of thing.
Yes.
For me, it's like putting a golf ball on a tee.
You know, a little tee hook.
And I just can't get it to stay on the tee peg.
Yeah.
Like that's my anxiety dream.
That's fascinating too.
That is because you play a lot of golf.
So that's the thing you do lots in real life.
But you don't find it difficult, I'm guessing.
I don't, but every now and then I'll put it on
and it'll fall off and I'll be like, oh my god, am I dreaming?
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
So it does go lucid at that point.
You wake up in the dream because it's so...
No, I've never been able to do lucid dreaming.
Right.
I've done it once or twice and it's amazing.
But not much.
Yeah, I've done it a few times.
Yeah, I have a recurring nightmare that I am bidding
on a Monty Python holy grail toy on eBay.
And I've driven it down to the last few seconds
before submitting my bids.
So that's the person in the lead thinks they've got it.
You're sniping it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But you can't quite find the bid button.
I'm pressing it, but it's not reloading the page.
And then, and then someone else wins the Terry Jones.
So yeah.
Because I imagine your anxiety dream is the end
of a drop as a line episode.
What you're trying to say goodbye,
but just can't fight, get the words out.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah.
I have this nightmare every two weeks.
Time slows down and I have our palpitations.
Yeah, yeah.
So thank you, Matthew.
Thank you.
Fish dreams is pretty exciting.
Fish dreams is cool.
Yeah.
Dreams.
[LAUGHTER]
Dreams can.
We said dreams.
Yeah.
Be dream.
[LAUGHTER]
Things can only get wetter.
It's very good.
Thank you.
A little bracket section.
Helping audience.
We've helped our audience in one way in the last fortnight.
This is really nice.
Tom Rosedale writes, "You talked to a little fish a while ago
about how almond extract does not come from almonds,
but instead from peach pits."
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Well, you have turned my wife's life upside down.
She developed an allergy to almonds and hazelnuts
at the age of 25.
For the last seven years has lived a life
devoid of bueno and marzipan and lots
of other nutty goodness, tragic.
However, having listened to the section about almond extract,
we are pleased to say she is now able
to eat Mr. Kipling's Battenberg.
Oh, that is huge.
That's amazing.
As the marzipan surround does not contain almonds.
It's just almond extract, which is made of peach.
Yes, lovely.
Previously, we hadn't even looked at the ingredients.
Why would you?
It's marzipan.
Brilliant.
It's really good.
I imagine that.
You're welcome, Tom.
All that time with no battenberg.
Next up, Extreme Fish.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Extreme Fish.
Yes.
Sam Koopland writes, "It's definitely possible to shoot out
a candle flame, which was what happened."
Oh, that's what happens to the guy who wrote "Bed her."
Lou Wallace.
And supposedly the friends of Billy the Kid
shot out his candle.
And I said, surely no one can do that.
And then Dad said, well, maybe Clamacy Jane,
but probably no one else.
Oh, that's still trying to think of Clamacy Jane.
One of my shooting clubs--
Oh, yeah, one of them.
Sam is a serious shooter here--
has a Christmas shoot where you have five lit candles.
And you're at 25 yards prone.
And you have to extinguish them without hitting the candle.
No points if the candle is damaged.
And one or two people each year manage it, and I've done it.
Mind you, this is with modern Olympic style target rifles,
and there are no Victorian novelists
potentially getting in the way.
So you have modern rifles.
You have a club full of presumably entusiasts of whom
only one or two can do it each year.
I'm still standing by the fact that that's pretty tricky.
There's pretty tricky.
And this is at 25 yards.
It's quite reasonably close.
But then there's someone's front garden.
You know, you're at the other end of the front garden.
It's manageable.
But apparently the trick is to get the bullet
to pass through the flame and the associated rush of air.
Very nice.
How cool is that?
Yeah, really clever.
Because the bullet travels at 700 miles an hour.
So that little whiff of air just blows it out.
Yeah, stunning.
I don't know where else you'd be shooting, though,
to put it out.
Well, like I thought, one version might be you shooting the wick.
And then it breaks the wick in half.
And then the bit that some fire sort of falls off.
Yeah, interesting.
John Wick.
Is the name of a--
That's just a name.
He's called Wick.
What do you want?
Something that works.
Yeah.
We can't just say people are always trying to shoot at John Wick, though.
Ha.
And no one's ever managed to actually lots of people do it.
Although it's through those films, he's constantly being shot.
But they've never managed to snuff him out.
I think I've made it work.
Actually, I want to apologize.
That was very good.
Let's have some get yourselves off the hook.
OK, this is what we're actually here for.
This is why I want some stuff about things we've said on the show.
OK, well, good job.
Jacob Valkin writes, "It was really cool to hear you guys read my
fact on the latest little fish.
However, he's not going to debunk himself, is he?"
However, my email was a loan of all books.
However, your follow-up contained an error.
Rolled Amundsen and his crew did not eat their dogs.
Did they eat their dogs?
No, it is true that they brought twice as many dogs as needed.
But the grizzly truth is that it was their dogs that ate the other dogs.
Is that right?
Yeah, so that is...
No.
So this was the Michael Paling episodes, I think.
No, it was from the body of the young old man.
There's a recent little fish about how they all put on weight
while they were doing their hunger thrust.
That's really interesting.
I can only go off what this person writes.
I know, I know.
But if that is true, that is a piece of general ignorance that I have
because I did think that was true.
All right, Vinny Cobb says, "In the most recent drop of the line,
it was mentioned that James is associated with the phrase,
"If you put a broom up my ass, I can mop the floor
as an idiomatic expression of being overworked."
Yeah, all right.
"Why would anyone mop the floor with a broom?"
I thought you'd deliberately done that.
No, I just messed it up.
One would sweep the floor with a broom.
If one mops the floor with a broom,
you would only move the water about.
I suspect the phrase ought to be,
"If you put a broom up my ass, I can sweep the floor
or if you put a mop up my ass, I can mop the floor."
I am sure you have had thousands of emails about this.
Honestly, I thought that you knew what my saying was
and you deliberately mised it for comic effects.
You do me too much honor.
That was why I did laugh at it at the time.
No, far from far from.
How interesting.
Okay, fair enough.
So thanks a lot, Vinny.
Yeah.
Vinny says, "Keep up the good work.
Drop a lot of those, become my favourite fish section."
Quite hilarious.
Oh.
It's nice, isn't it?
There it is.
We all get credit for that.
Yeah, but what about the main show?
Doesn't say.
Vinny says nothing about the main show.
Right.
Can we only do feedback from now on?
Just to remember my idea for a podcast.
What was it?
You have one every day.
Basically, well, this is my main idea, right?
Yeah.
So you say episode one is going to come out on a certain day.
But it doesn't come out for a week.
And some people send you a letter complaining.
And then the first episode is responding to those complaints.
And then the second episode is people complaining about episode one.
And the third episode is people complaining about episode two and episode one.
And basically, you never get to the point of the podcast.
Fantastic.
Let's do it.
What's it called?
It doesn't matter, really.
That's a good name.
It's called a normal podcast.
The idea is that you give it some kind of really overarching name like it's, you know, brain
surgery for rocket scientists or something.
And you say you're going to do something, but actually you never do that thing because you're
always responding to it.
Yeah.
I think that's a really good idea.
I like it.
I love it.
No, a Motelson.
In the drop of the line episode, what section is this again?
Andy coins the section name bonus bone with the justification that all fish have bones.
You've forgotten parts about the cartilaginous fish such as sharks.
You wish.
This disregards the cartilaginous fish, which are the main reason there is no such thing as
a fish.
Phylogenetic is speaking.
Get your facts straight.
Thanks Noah.
Yeah.
Absolute.
Don't like, can't be that great point.
Very good point.
Back to the podcast names, starting really fast listeners on the planet.
Also the most annoying, some fish are bones.
Oh my God.
I only wish I thought of it at the time.
Now we come to Both Finn's experts.
Yeah.
This is always fun.
Because we think this is my favorite part of the show.
Sounds so.
I think so, yeah.
That's great.
You love this.
Johnny Singer writes in.
Johnny writes in from the MCC, the Marleyburn Cricket Club.
Johnny is a Laws of Cricket Advisor.
Very good.
Johnny sits on the high council of Cricket and says, I presume is a judge and does the Laws.
This is our second judge of the episode.
Oh yeah.
Johnny writes, there are two ways, traditionally, of notating the score in a Cricket match,
right?
You have scorers in Cricket.
Linear scoring, as you might imagine, records the balls in order as they happened.
Yeah.
But there's also box scoring, which most people think of as normal scoring, which is noting
everything down in little boxes.
So there's a box next to the baller, there's one next to the batter, and there's a box
for the score.
Is that right?
Yeah.
Despite overwhelmingly using boxes as its method, the box method is actually named for its
inventor, Charles Box.
No.
Is that true?
Yeah.
That is amazing.
I wondered where you're going for that for the longest time, because I was like, we've never
mentioned this on the show.
I was like, is Andy Saltsman been on the show?
I don't think so.
Oh, it's cheeky.
You set us up with a different section and then went into the names named after things that
it shouldn't be named after.
I can't do it in non-clatuna anymore, because it's too obvious.
It's too obvious.
It completely deadens any sensation that we'll all get from it.
So it's got to be coming as a surprise.
It's good.
Yeah.
So be on your guard.
We need to be on our toes.
Absolutely.
Well, that goes your favourite section.
No.
There is another amazing one.
We mentioned on a little fish, James, your fact about 3D printers, what they had invented
a 3D printer.
They're printed 3D printers.
Yeah.
So that was a very old fish fact, in fact, and we gave custodianship to someone, but yeah,
we brought it up again because of that.
Exactly.
And Vic Oliver from Masterson in New Zealand, writes, "I was one of the people working with
Bath University on this project."
Oh, man.
You wondered where they went, and why we're not need deep in 3D printers.
Well, we designed it to evolve, Vic says.
Most of the 3D printers you see on desks today are its children.
The children of their original 3D printer.
Wow.
Like, they designed it to be changeable, I suppose, until it's so cool.
And he just includes a couple of other amazing facts.
One is that the entire 3-year project was funded for less than a cost of a single industrial
3D printer of the day.
It's amazing.
Cool.
And also, there's a special thing called PLA Filament, right?
PLA Filament.
Which is biodegradable, is made from plants, and we wanted people to bury the leftovers in
a hole, which would lock up the carbon for 100 years.
But if it escapes or ends up in something living, it will buy a degrade.
Okay.
And Vic adds, "I know this because I invented PLA Filament."
Wow.
God, that thing that we all use every day.
We all do exactly what it was, even after you'd explained it, we still not quite sure what
it is.
It's very cool.
That's incredible.
That is.
It's very cool.
I think so.
Thrills to hear from someone who was involved in that project.
It's really cool.
Would you like a bonus bream, bonus bass?
Bonus bone.
Or bonus balls.
I'm going to try calling it last time.
Let's go for a bone.
They're all the same, aren't they?
The emails weren't changed.
It was going to be a name of someone anyway, so I'm just giving it up.
I don't have a terribly complicated tree, our system.
If they say bonus barracuda, I'll read Luke's email next.
Luke Kines writes, "So we talked about Chicago being raised up by a meter."
Seattle went through it twice, says Luke, in one year.
First, it was raised to the ground by a fire, and then it was raised an entire story, just
up one level.
Wow.
All of Seattle just went up one level.
Really?
You can get an underground tour of what used to be the street level, but it's now under
the streets.
That's amazing.
Cool fact.
Yeah.
It's incredible.
Very cool fact.
And Alex Hirn says, hopefully I'm not the person to say this, you're not Alex, you're
the first.
But the raising of Chicago and the reversing of the Chicago River were planned by the
same person.
Oh, are they?
Ellis Sylvester Chisbrough.
Chisbrough.
Okay.
Have we come across him before?
Oh, I don't know.
I feel like we might have done.
Interesting.
She's Ellis Chisbrough.
Well, she's not the guy who invents him.
Absolutely.
It's not him.
Okay.
But, huh.
Anyway.
Yeah, interesting.
Yeah.
And Alex has Chicago as an excellent architectural city, which makes it all the more tragic
that the Dave Matthews band dumped their shit over our beloved architecture.
But they dumped it in the river in fairness.
True.
That was the most unaware fish conversation that you guys just had.
We're going, it's not Chisbrough who invented both at the same time, the Vaseline.
Absolutely.
And quickly move on.
I was going to say we were the only place in the world where two people could have a discussion
where both would know who invented Vaseline by him.
They're probably a few others.
Yeah.
Probably Vaseline HQ.
They'll be slipping on the slide and about all over the place.
But they'll be stopping to chat meetings must be fun in Vaseline HQ.
Patrick writes, I recently listened to an episode of Little Fish examples were given
of family members playing on the same sports teams.
Oh yeah.
Professional teams.
I'd like to bring to your attention the National Hockey League's Sutter Brothers.
Okay.
In the National Hockey League in the 1980s, Brent, Brian, Darrell, Duane, Rich and Ron
all played in that league.
Incredible.
At one time there were as many as five brothers active in the league at the same time.
On March 30th, 1983, there were four Sutter Brothers playing in the same game.
Great fact.
That's very good.
Yeah, really nice.
Duane, we did a headline fact once about the football, a lower tier football team that all
had the same surname.
Yeah.
And they were all cousins and brothers and so on.
We did.
It was the entire team, wasn't it?
Yeah.
Called Car Member.
It was like it was a Serbian, Turkish name, yeah, Eganishvili or Dashvili or something.
That'd be charging.
Those names.
Obviously.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
It's amazing how you can feel stupid, but not knowing the Serbian structure of a country I've
never been to.
Oh, so sorry.
This is why I have no friends.
No.
You've got two.
You've got two great friends and they're right here.
Who's it?
Oh yeah.
No.
No, I have to say that now before I get back.
Absolutely.
Speaking of two, Ben Tudik writes back, oh, I'm so sorry, Ben.
Welcome back.
Ben Tudik says, always a treat to be included in droppers of line.
Otherwise, I suspect my surname may have got that email over the line.
I'm really sorry because I watched that back and I thought, you just caught me off guard.
I know.
But Greg Bunk hasn't written back.
So maybe we've lost it.
Lost a list of that.
I don't know if Greg's a member of Club Vist though, but Ben says I should have tied the
two together myself.
But people so rarely laugh openly at my surname these days.
I have almost forgotten it is inherently amusing.
At secondary school, I was quickly given the name Four Balls and I know what was ever
said about this.
It's good.
That's fantastic.
You know what?
Kids can be so creative.
You're a genius.
That's a brilliant nickname.
Thank you, Ben.
Oh, wonderful.
And welcome back.
It's the first time we've ever had the same correspondent in two separate, two consecutive
editions of droppers of line.
Yeah.
Definitely referring to the previous one.
Yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
Okay.
Good.
We earlier didn't include something I should have done, which was in the fish life section.
Okay.
We came back into that.
That's fine.
But we're heading towards the naming section and it's kind of relevant to that.
So actually, I did the correct thing.
There is method.
Oh, there's method.
Right.
Ashley writes, on a recent episode of Little Fish, you mentioned two football players that
had the same name.
Okay.
Yeah.
And so this is slightly, we're in the right area.
I thought you might like to know a little fact about my husband and I.
We are both named Ashley Field.
We have the same job.
We're both mechanics.
We own our own business and work together.
Wow.
Hang on.
No, no.
I'm standing in front of the mirror.
Apologies.
Disregard.
Love your stuff.
I love the way that because you're standing next to someone in the mirror, you have the same name.
Well, it's on the mechanic badge.
Yeah, but it would read back the, well, they're dyslexic.
It reminded me of Michael Fields, the, um, was it the poet who was actually a woman in
her aunt?
Oh, yes.
Michael Field.
Yeah.
Whose real names were Bradley and Cooper.
Oh, yes.
Bradley Cooper.
Yeah, we said that.
I made a joke at the time.
Yeah.
It was a good joke.
Thank you.
Thank you, man.
It was better than, yeah, better than what John Wick.
Are we allowed to do drive-by some jokes we made half an hour ago?
Is that fair?
Yeah.
I was, I was corded.
I was just trying to get out.
Absolutely.
Fortunately, you had a terrible joke I'd made at your fingertips.
It was, it was no hesitation.
You had to swallow it back before I pressed you on it.
Yeah.
So you're right.
It's your fault.
I wasn't even going to mention it.
Yeah.
Ashley says, my maiden name was Davies and I changed my surname without too much thought when
we got married.
This is called various issues from opening each other's male, medical results, medications,
mixed up, etc.
The worst was being pulled aside by immigration in the UAE for travelling with passports with
the same name.
Oh.
For clarity, I'm female and have a middle name, but I didn't really use it.
My husband is male with no middle name.
Yeah.
And our friends and fur to us is Mrs. Ash or Mr. Ash, which makes sense to me, actually.
Good.
Right, next up, Rob Davis writes about the recent Hungarian elections.
Oh, nice.
Because the guy who won the election is Mr. Peter Madjar.
Yeah.
And Madjar means someone from Hungary.
Hungry.
Yeah.
That's called Hungary.
His name is Mr. Hungary.
And now he is Mr. Hungary.
Yeah.
Hungary Hungry happens.
Again, just a series of words with no real joke attached.
But we.
Wow.
We.
Yeah.
Do you know what I'm doing?
Technically.
Games.
I'm doing a little professional broadcasting track called "Filling Airtime".
We always over record.
We literally don't need to fill airtime.
Okay, then I'm doing another trick called "Grist for the Edit".
Okay.
Good news, though.
That often going out.
Very good news.
Yeah.
So that's a bit of a nice news.
Liam Figgit Lee sends in a urologist in Brisbane, Australia that specializes in erectile
dysfunction called Mr. Erich Chung.
Erich Chung.
So.
Oh.
Erich Chung.
He's maintaining his Erich Chung.
Yeah.
I bet when they like tell him his funding has got more like he's got more funding for a few
more years, they'll say we're maintaining our erich Chung.
Erich Chung.
A bit of a stretch.
Very nice.
That would be a successful.
Yeah.
Anyway, four separate people have sent that in.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
That was popular.
People like sending in number term.
Such as Tom, who writes about the mayor of Cookshire in Queensland, which has one of the
highest rates of crime per capita in Australia, the mayor is called Robin Holmes.
Yeah.
Nice.
That's really good.
Yes.
Very good.
Anna Maltzi writes about a place in Antarctica where over 40% of the world's Emperor Penguins
breed, and it's a bit of Antarctica called Mary Bird Land, but it's named after a lady
called Mary Bird.
Richard E. Bird's wife.
Yeah.
No.
That's really good.
Stunning.
Right.
I like these ones that are like, I think I've seen that name probably on a map.
But also, I know that lots of Emperor Penguins live around that, and I know that they are monogamous,
but I would never have put those things together ever.
And I love those where people have had an insight that makes something more of a non-determin.
Yeah.
Those people are going to go up very high in the running order for the book.
The book is coming together.
I would say I've got 50 things for the book now.
Yeah.
So I've got 950 to go.
You're right.
Yeah.
That's the number you've given me.
Oh, yeah, of course.
A thousand and one.
A thousand and one to cut.
Yeah.
You literally can't think of any more.
Say, oh, well, let's do something else.
Call the publishing house.
Council the launch.
Tell Rushdie, no, we won't be needing him to do the song at the launch anymore.
The song.
No.
Tell him to.
He could take his twist to set up.
His song.
You idiot.
You booked Rushdie to sing and Kylie Monota play Scrabble.
What are you doing?
[LAUGHTER]
Is that a lot of-- because I've never read the Satanic verses.
Is it just a song but?
Yeah.
[LAUGHTER]
The Satanic choruses is much catchier, isn't it?
That's what I like doing this show.
I just had some rubbish.
And you guys have turned it like alchemist into something.
That's incredible.
Where were you when I said hungry?
I'm drinking a piece.
[LAUGHTER]
Oh, dear.
We're plowing.
We're cruising to a halt now.
Yeah.
The inbox is nearly drained, I would say.
Yeah, we got through formal pages of email at the cat.
Are they all names?
No, no, they're not.
However, Sai writes in, "I've been listening to old episodes."
[LAUGHTER]
There you go.
I was thinking Gagnon's style.
It's very different to what you and I think of when we have the word Sai.
Sai has chosen to be slightly anonymous here without Sai.
They were anything.
I've been listening to old episodes the past few weeks and just heard you guys talking
about company's house and their list of rejected company names.
I don't know if you remember that.
Oh, yes.
Yeah.
Episode 289.
Gosh, it's lunch time ago.
It's just seven years ago.
One of the rejected company names Anna mentioned was Anus Beauty.
[LAUGHTER]
And I think I know where it might have come from.
Anu is a fairly common girl's name in India.
So my guess it was supposed to be Anu's Beauty and maybe they missed the apostrophe.
Yeah.
I'm not sure that was the reason they proposed that business name.
I'm not sure.
OK.
We may never know.
Could be though.
It's plausible.
In India, there is a trend of women bleaching the skin, isn't there?
Oh, yeah.
So try and have lighter.
Right.
Anu's bleaching has done any business.
Might well.
Well, today's been very blue.
You always say this.
Oh, this has been a very blue one.
Ribbled with blue.
I had to stop myself saying ribble because I thought it was too obvious if I say it too many times.
Rafael Alvarez writes with a great suggestion.
Hey, Andy, and the rest of the fish team.
Thank you.
I'm just listening to all the episodes and on the December 2024 drop us a line, you talked
about how all of the people who listened to the podcast to sleep mess with the metrics
for tour ticket sales.
OK.
This gave me an idea for your next tour.
I love it.
A bed or recline the section for people who usually sleep to the podcast, maybe at a premium
price.
I think that's a great idea.
Like, for instance, let's say one day we managed to play the Royal Albert Hall.
Yep.
A thousand seats would have to sell, but if you have a recliner, that's basically three
seats worth, right?
Oh, we don't only have to sell 1,700 beds.
That's a great way of dealing with that.
Yeah.
OK.
Or maybe a gig at a mattress store.
Yeah.
Food for thought.
This is Rafael.
And then if we sell out, bunk beds.
Brilliant.
Yeah.
It's quite a good idea.
Well, look, anyway, that's it.
That's your lot.
But I've had a really good time.
I've had a wonderful time, actually.
And I'm sure you guys have too.
Yeah, I really enjoyed it.
Yeah.
Anything more to add?
No, this is usually your bed.
Yeah.
We respect it.
We sit back and we let the magic out.
Well, listen, if you've enjoyed this show and, you know, we've got, we've got a, the inbox
is hanging limp and empty and we need it filled up again.
So just please, please email us.
Even if you're not grateful, it doesn't matter.
I'll keep doing it.
I can't be stopped.
I will kill again.
Podcast@qy.com is the email address where we receive your emails, buff them up, addition
back out to you, the, the baying public.
So we're really excited to do that again in a couple of weeks time.
Might be, I'm away next week, so it'll be, I'll be a bit more tanned when you see me next.
Oh, yeah.
Oh.
Going somewhere nice?
Well, I'm, the bit of me that I'm getting tanned won't, won't be on display for the
cameras, but you tend to wear a burger, but with a little cut out around the crotch, don't
you?
I've got it at the point of booked in an A-news beauty and very ribbled.
Bye.
[Music]