Hey guys, just a quick announcement before we begin this week's show which is that we are going on tour
We are going all over the country and there are tickets available now
We're gonna nodding him. We're gonna Manchester, London, Lester, Dunstable, Birmingham, Coventry
Yeah, and there are more dates coming up, aren't there?
There are indeed, but we're not allowed to say where they are yet
But there'll be a bit further from the center of England than those places that Dan's just mentioned
Yeah, it's gonna be so much fun. We're putting together this whole fantastic first half full of stupid games and extra
bits and interactive bits, and in the second half we're gonna record an episode of the podcast
Yep, so if you want to see any or all preferably all of that then go to qi.com/fishevents and you can get your tickets there
Okay, on with the show
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden
My name is Dan Schreiber and I'm sitting here with James Harkin, Anitzenski and Andrew Hunter Murray
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones of our four favorite facts from the last seven days
And in no particular order, here we go
Starting with you, James
Okay, my fact this week is that in 1966 the Chinese press reported that a 73-year-old German Mao had swam 15 kilometres of the Yangtze River in 65 minutes
That's twice the speed that Michael Phelps has ever swam
75, imagine what he could do at 40
It's amazing that you're given a number and you just remember a different number
No, I confused it with 65 minutes
So I took the seven from the year and I took the five from the minutes
Wait, may I have 73 kilometres in 15 minutes?
I don't know
He swam 1966 kilometres and 65 seconds
Okay, wow, can you say the numbers again?
Yes, year 1966, age 73, distance 15 kilometres and time 65 minutes
And the thing is, I've read about this and it's possible that he might have been carried along
by some very, very strong currents
Right, but then I wonder if that's really swimming
It's not, it's because it could be floating
But he had floating bodyguards with him
Yeah, he did
And huge portraits of himself
So there's a picture of him floating along with these six bodyguards around him
And then these giant pictures of Chairman Mao floating alongside him in front of him
But wait, when you say they were floating bodyguards
What were they?
They were swimming, too
And they managed to keep up with the fastest swimmer
And maybe that's why there were six, they were positioned strategically further up
And after the river
An improvement to Olympic swimming would be to have a giant raft with the swimmer's face on it
Going behind it
Because often when the water you don't know who it is
But if there's a massive raft with Michael Phelps' face going behind it
Yes, that's great
It's interesting he spent so much time in a body of order because he never bathed
Chairman Mao
In order to wash himself he would have servants wipe him up and down with towels
Yeah, yeah, so just wet towels
In fact, and this is a bit early in the podcast to be going into this territory
But he claimed to wash his body in the body of his women
That was his
Wait, in the body, he washed his body in the body of his women
Yes, I think what that's saying is he liked to have sex with a lot of women
And he thought that that was enough of a cleaning process
It really wasn't there, was it?
No, no, no
That's a wipe him off with towels afterwards
I had to go for that really long swim to really get it off
Well, he is the most polluted river in the world, isn't it?
It's unbelievably dirty
So I suppose it suited him
What I think, I think it's got rivals in now
Maybe it was completely cleaned before he got it
Mao used to suffer from very bad constipation
And apparently if he actually managed to get a bowel movement out
It was like a cause of celebration amongst the staff
It was seen as a great way
It would be celebration if I was a towel guy
That's true, that's true
He used to have two to three animals a day
Wow
Maybe when he was saying, "I'm surrounded by enemies"
He was actually saying, "I'm surrounded by enemies"
And the whole cultural revolution was a big mistake
So there's a lot of work for Mao lookalikes at the moment
Because in Chinese television, there's a lot of things you're not allowed to do
If you want to write a screenplay
I think we might have said before you're not allowed time travel
And you're not really allowed word play and puns and stuff like that
They have a lot of things you're not allowed to do
But one thing you are allowed to do is historical dramas
And so basically if you're a talented screenwriter in China
You just write historical dramas
And usually about Mao because he's like the most famous historical figure
And so 44% of all Chinese shows produced in 2013 were historical dramas
Wow
You say that, I would be surprised if I was the same on the BBC
No
That's just what you watch, I know
Oh yeah
And so because a lot of these have Mao in them, there's a lot of work
If you're a Mao lookalike, it's one of the best jobs you can have
Wow, remember there's that Chinese guy who's an Obama lookalike?
Is he
Yeah, so he gets a lot of work in TV shows and stuff
Is he Chinese?
Yeah, he's Chinese, but he just looks a lot like Obama
And he gets hired out as Obama
He's not like exactly like Obama
Well, he's a lookalike
He's a lookalike
Just on crazy claims made by dictators
Oh yeah
In 2006, a North Korean publication called Nodong Simmon
reported that Kim Jong Il had mastered the art of teleporting
and that he could move so quickly that American satellites could not track him
Hey, have we ever mentioned the ex-president of Turkmenistan?
Almost certainly, what...
Feel like we must have the ears of?
Yeah, the ears of, yeah
He's just, he was one of those characters as well
Claimed crazy things, did crazy things
He changed the names of the days and the months
in the country to the names of his family members
Didn't he name Bread After His Mother? Was that him or something?
He renamed Bread to his mother's name
Yeah, very cool
Just on on Mao
So a statue of Chairman Mao was unveiled in 1993
And it was a really big deal
It was to commemorate him
It was the, I think it was 120th anniversary of his birth or something
Okay
That makes sense
And it was in December
So and it was in the Hunan province
So it's cold and dark and it's constant rain and sleet
And you can now, if you go to China, you can buy photographs of
The moment where the sheet was pulled off this giant statue
The 6-meter-high bronze statue
And at the same time the sun suddenly came out
And the moon came out
And they both shone upon the statue at the same time
Wow
And if you go, I mean
Do you look very, as if you're believing it?
Well that's, I mean that's possible, isn't it?
It is plausible, I think it was just the
Fortunatousness of the event
I don't believe it
I don't believe it at all
Sun and the moon coming out at the same time
But the sun and the moon are always out at the same time
But half the year they're out at the same time
That's not always
No, but it bears credence that this might have been in that half of the year
And I just think it sounds suspiciously like a propaganda quote
Rather than, I think you guys are
And also, it's very trusting
No, but also this is what, last year, or the year before
I mean China has a lot
Ninety-nine-two-three
Ninety-nine-three, okay
Sorry, 25 years ago
Regardless, China has been scientifically
They would know basic things like when the sun and the moon's going to be out
And like time it
Also, don't forget the Trump, when he was doing his inauguration speech
And the rain just mysteriously stopped
Actually, yeah
I'll start it, I can't remember
I'll start it, I'll start it, yeah
No, he very clearly remembered afterwards it a bit of sunny day
So that's nice
Just quickly on Mao, he initiated a campaign where you were supposed to murder all the sparrows
It was called the Four Pest campaign
He started it in 1958 and the idea was to exterminate mosquitoes, flies, rats, and sparrows
And it was really, really successful, so lots of people went out there
And were supposed to form these kind of people's armies to try and kill them
It was successful in the sense that it achieved what it was supposed to achieve
And then it caused enormous problems
Like these things do so, for instance
The sparrows all been gone meant that there was a plague of literal plague of locusts
Which now weren't being scared off by the sparrows
And they, all the crops, and had incredibly devastating consequences
Where many, you know, millions of people died
And as far as what it was trying to do was get rid of pests, it didn't really work
No, it worked as in it got rid of those pests
But it's just such a strong lesson in how we definitely shouldn't be just trying to randomly wipe out something that's annoying us
Yes
Also, if you're on the side that's telling you to go out in massacre the sparrows
It feels like you know that you're not on the right side, don't you?
Do you?
The others are quite bad, rats, mosquitoes, sparrows are so adorable
They're like the epitome of a sweet innocent
Not when they're eating all of your grain
Of course not, but the word sparrow
And the image of a little sparrow
If someone's telling you to trample it down
But without grain, how can you make a loaf of the president of Turkmenistan's mother?
[laughter]
Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Andy
My factor is that seahorses greet their partners every day to make sure they are still alive
Ooh
Top tip for all you couples out there
[laughter]
What does that mean exactly?
Because you'd greet them anyway, wouldn't you?
[laughter]
Every day
I know their intentions
Well, if you're a seahorse, you might not
You know
I don't like that, so I'm asking what do they, what do they, how do we know?
Because most likely a seahorse is going to say hi to another seahorse if they're married every day
[laughter]
I'm so much unclean
We don't need to do that, senders
[laughter]
I'm completely with Dan
You're joining the side of the lunatics, Anna
You're completely with that, are you?
So that the married seaharses, you're with him on that bit, are you?
Well, partners, it says
We just jumped in with both feet, and I just decided
When married seahorses get up in the morning, obviously they greet each other
How do we know it's to make sure they're still alive?
You're right, what they do is they do this courtship dance every day before dawn
for a while
Which is for two different reasons
One is to check that the other one is still alive
And the other is to also synchronise their mating
Because you know the male carries the young in his pouch
And then he sort of, yeah, he's pregnant
That's a thing that is, you've just said quite casually
But is incredibly amazing about seahorses
The male carries the child
Yeah, but apparently the ritual that they do, the sort of ritual they move around and sing
is designed to synchronise their movements
So the male will receive the eggs well
when the female deposits her eggs in his pouch
Okay
Because otherwise they won't dock properly
And just this keeping a live thing
Is it really common for them to die in their sleep?
They can't really drop in dead overnight
I don't know
I don't know, I don't know why it's so necessary
Well, I looked into the life span of seahorses
And in the wild between one and four years
In captivity, four years
And they say they just almost always make it to four years
They have a really consistent sort of oldest age a seahorse gets to life span
That's interesting
So you're not basically, when you're three years old
You know, you've only got a year left
That's good, you can plan stuff
Can't you? Like the pensions world is very stable
In seahors land
Because you know, roughly how long you've got
I did not know that they were fish
Yes, I don't know
Well, I thought there was something
Acquasty
Did you think they were horses?
I didn't think they were horses exactly
But you thought they were maybe like muscles and...
Yeah, I thought a lobster isn't a fish
You know, and so they're called hippocampus, which means horse sea monster
And they eat super quick
They have to use in order to actually see them eating food
Ice-peed cameras in order to catch it
Because they can eat stuff in like six milliseconds
Oh really, they're sucking, they suck it in, don't they?
Yeah
And also, they kind of flick their head
Because they got this horse neck
And they catch the culpods that they eat
About 94% of the time
Which the article I read said might be the most successful in nature
But we know that actually dragonflies are slightly better than that
We think dragonflies are 95%
But they're similar kind of...
But it very much depends on the prey
It's like, it's all gone tech
So, you know, a lion will be terrible at catching a copepod
But a seahorse will be terrible at catching a zebra
That's true
And if I was to go to McDonald's and I wanted to get a Big Mac
I would have 100% success rate
Yeah, so we are the best hunters now I suppose
If you're calling that hunting
And I would be not
That's when James and I go to McDonald's
We hunt for the burgers, we sort of tiptoe up
And make sure it doesn't see us coming
So, the copepods, which they hunt
The reason the seahorses have to be so good at hunting
Is because the copepods can flee unbelievably fast
They can move at 500 body lengths a second
Which is the equivalent of a human swimming at 2,000 miles an hour
Which is roughly as fast as chairman Mao
And seahorses swim incredibly slow
There's one that's called the line seahorse
If you put it into a bathtub, just your regular length bathtub
To swim that length would take five minutes
Seahorse racing would be quite a cool thing to watch
So, wouldn't it?
Yes, you could paint a little like a little ascot
Put little jockeys on top and tiny copepod jockeys
And they have to jump over things in the water
With these tiles and hedges and things like that
I think you want the jockeys to be the things that the seahorses are going to try and eat
No, you're right
You want the copepods to be going round like a hare in a greyhound race
Exactly
Yeah
That'd be amazing if in real horse racing there was a chance that the horse would eat the jockeys
Halfway through the race
And the Tories come off
And he's being eaten
James and I know seahorse expert, by the way
Yes, we do
Helen Scales
I know her too
I think we know her better
We probably introduced you to her once
Yeah, you did, yeah
Yeah, okay
I don't know her
Good
She's great
She's written the book called Beside and Steed which is unbelievably good
Yeah, I have a feeling most of the stuff that I'm saying right now is taken directly from her book
But it was stuff taken from her book by James and put it to a script which I've been just lifted
And I'd look through the script, by the way
So she was on our show Museum of Curiosity as a guest about six years ago, seven years ago
Almost even
This was the opening question we asked her in the show
Oh dear
Helen, as someone who spent the past 15 years learning everything there is to know that fish
Perhaps you can answer this for me
Is it true that there is no such thing as a fish?
Oh, the way
Yeah, that was our opening question
And what did she say?
No, that's rubbish
Yeah
I'm in 2009
There was a woman in Dorset who found a seahorse on her drive
And she lived three miles in land
Wow
And it was alive
How did it get there?
Well, they think a seagull dropped it
Seagull, I think
Over, right
It was a really rare endangered seahorse
Wow
It could be that thing, you know that riddle about the man who's found in a diving suit in the forest
It could be that someone was trying to put out a fire in her house by scooping up water from the sea
Into a helicopter
And then dropping it onto her house
And they scooped up a seahorse
Right
I was thinking of that one where there's a guy found hanging in a room
With a puddle of water
So I was wondering if the seahorse was trying to hang itself
And he was still on an ice cube
Yeah
Oh with that
Or a man arrives into town on a seahorse on Thursday and then leaves again
Friday, it's called Friday, the seahorse is called Friday
Yes
I think it's that a seagull dropped it
I just think that's amazing
Trying to get endangered animals
A lot of them are quite endangered
I read something I think it was on Mother Nature Network
Maybe saying that they could be extinct within about 30 years
Which seems radically pessimistic
But because they use so much in Asian medicine
So 25 million seahorses a year are used in traditional Chinese medicine
Or actually the seahorse trust claims that it's 150 million a year
So it's somewhere between those two
Which is a lot because they thought to help impotence, aren't they
Which makes--
Yeah, it's in China, yeah
Which kind of makes a lot of sense
No, it doesn't stop saying it makes sense
Yeah, it doesn't make sense
Yeah, killing them
Don't say that sentence
Seahorse grinding up
It doesn't make sense, it's a terrible idea
I can see where culturally it happened
Because as the only males that give birth
Perhaps that has some connection to the fact that men now think if they eat ground up seahorse they'll get fertile
It starts spewing out babies
I know it doesn't make a lot of sense
It doesn't make any sense, Hannah
No, it doesn't
Scientists tested seahorse relationships about 10 years ago
They did an experiment
Because everyone thinks that they're monogamous
And they wanted to see maybe they're not
And so they put little wire labels on them, colored wire labels
And sort of match them up with their partners
And then they asked the public to spy on them to see if they were sleeping around
And the scientists, one of the scientists responsible for it said
When people hear that this might not be true after all, i.e. the monogamy
Their curiosity is immediately aroused
And they seem quite happy to watch
For long periods to see if there's any hanky panky going on
Aroused, so they are an aphrodisiac
That's the big thing
Sorry, the fish this week is sponsored by ground up seahorses
They found out that they flirted with both sexes up to 25 times a day
So it's hanky panky all over the shop?
Oh yeah, it's quite a lot
There's a lot in going on
Every day
So yeah, it's a lot, i mean that's a lot
Wake up, check your partners alive down
Dab it
Well, might as well do a bit of flirting anyway
And their flirting is pretty intense, isn't it?
Their meeting rituals last for days and days sometimes
And the way they mate is they interlock their tails
And they just bob along together with tails interlocked for hours on end
Or they dance around a kind of invisible maple
And yeah, it's just very romantic kind of animal
It's very sweet, it's durable
It's weirdly sweet, yeah
The eyes move independently of each other as well
Which is actually much bigger than me
It's because they're trying to check out all the other male and female horses
It's got a roving eye, yeah, but they all do
Okay, it is time to move on to fact number three
And that is my fact
My fact this week is that falcon experts put on a special hat
When they want to collect semen
Basically falcons have been going extinct
Or endangered in the wild
And so that what they were trying to do was
To force them to mate with each other
They had to do artificial insemination
And this guy in America called Les Boyd
Worked out the best way to do that
Was to wear a special hat
Which he would then walk into a room
The hat would excite the falcon
Who would then land on his head
And hump his head
Until it ejaculated into this guy's hat
And then he would wait for the next falcon
So it's onto the hat really
Because I imagine that into a hat means
It's you turn the hat upside down
And ejaculate into the...
No, no, no, no
It's no, no, the hat looks like a waffle
So it's got all these little holes on it
And so I think what happens when the ejaculate comes out
It sort of seeps through the holes
Like Swiss cheese
We should say they're not wearing these hats are they
Because they're particularly sexually attractive to the falcons
The hats are specifically there to collect the semen
But why does the falcon...
I mean, this is an amazing fact
Why does the falcon want to have sex with the hat?
I think it is and correct me if I'm wrong
They introduced the falcon to the hat very early on in life
And it sort of develops a mother complex with it
It imprints it
And then when they see the hat come back in all those years later
It thinks I've got to have it and lands on it
But wait, are they introduced to the hat?
Because yeah, I think when falcons are raised by people
They are more attracted to people than they are to other falcons
Because they are imprinted, so it's whatever raises them
They both are attracted to
I thought it was the humans and then the humans put on the hats
Oh, wow
Did it introduce the baby falcons to the humans
So what happens if the human walks in without the hat?
Then they think they'll shine their heads
So there's a real debate in the falcon in community
Over whether it's better to buy a collecting hat
They call it a copulation hat
Or whether it's better to make your own
Because it's much cheaper to make your own
But sometimes you just want a professional hat
Don't you?
Because it looks better
I guess so
But I don't think anyone's wearing this for fashion actually
They're not very fashionable things
They've got waffle stuff on the top
And usually a bird shagging
You can see it being a hipster thing
Yeah, I can imagine walking around Shardich
No, I've just remembered that's what they do
They imitate the falcon's voice
So they imitate the falcon's vocalizations
To sound like a lady falcon
Yeah
I think that's amazing
Yeah, it's incredible
And you can see footage of this online by the way
They sort of land on the head
And they're just going at it, flapping their wings
This guy's head is just big jutted around all over the shop
And then it ends and he walks out
And then he takes it through a tube, doesn't he?
And he brings it to
To inseminate it into the female falcon
And that in itself is another whole process
What does he have to put on a special chest wig or something like that?
In the video that I saw
He also had what like a glove and God talks were mating on that
The copulation hat began as a copulation glove
I think because it definitely happened on the hand before
And I think some genius
Or wait a second
Yeah
What if I wear the glove on my head?
I think probably because if you have a falcon land on your hand
You can only stretch it so far
And they are moving about a lot
I mean it's a vigorous activity
And so you might get a wing in the face
So maybe that was a protection point
So that, yeah, yeah, possibly
But does that mean that they can be collecting
Gossalk on their hand and falcon at the same time?
Yeah
Do you know the other method to do it for doing this?
It's called stripping
It's a moral fashion method
None of this high tech
Digital equipment that he's using
So what you do is you get a little pipette
And you have to put it
It's a sort of tiny suction pump
Into the birds, the male falcon's
Khloeakka, sort of genital opening
And then you have to use an automatic pipette
To just, you know, you just put it one notch
And it just extracts a little bit of semen from the falcon
Right
Before the invention of the automatic pipette
What you would have to do is
Someone on the team would have to suck the open end of the pipette
To get the falcon semen going
And
This is from the book How Fast Can a Falcon Dive
Peter Kappai-Nolo had some experience performing this procedure as an undergraduate
Despite keeping an eye out for the rapid movement of semenal fluid up the tube
He occasionally learned the hard way
That while falcon semen looks like a nice lager
It tastes rather bitter
Because it's amber falcon semen
That looks so cool
But he discovered
And he's the co-author of this book
So does falcon semen look like beer?
Like if we went to the pub and I accidentally swaps duns beer for a pint of falcon semen
He might not notice
I if I saw the hat
If I was like
What are you doing wearing in that James?
It's just fashion Daniel
We are in shortage
Okay, I can definitely say they're being a beer in shortage called falcon semen
That's a really good beer name
Yeah it is
That should be our no such thing as a fish
Brewery
Yeah, release
But I put in falcon jizz into google in order to
To make sure that there is already a beer called falcon jizz
But what came up is that there's a
A club in America called falcon jizz which is what it would have corrected it
You have to wear this special hat to go in
It sounds like a really fun jazz club
And it's run by like this environmental scientist
And why is he running a jazz club?
I don't know
And his name is Tony Falco
So he's just missing the end to be Tony falcon
And he's in the falcon jazz club
And it's in New York
So if you're in New York
Go see the falcon jazz
And ask for a pint of falcon jizz
He should launch a beer there
Falco jazz presents falcon jizz
I think what's really interesting about this fact is it's the current method
Probably the most successful falcon breeder in the world
His name is Brynn Close
He specifically breeds falcons who fly incredibly fast
Because falcon racing is a thing that happens a lot in the Middle East
To buy an Abu Dhabi specifically do it
And the shakes and the super rich out there by these falcons
He is the number one breeder of these falcons
And that's how he collects the semen of all these of these different falcons
But anyone listening to this might remember ages ago
There was an image that appeared online of a commercial aeroplane
And it was the economy class of the aeroplane
And it was just packed with falcons
Sitting there
And to Brynn that's a very regular thing
Because that's how they fly all the falcons out to Abu Dhabi and Dubai
Was there a business class on the same flight for a few months
Or was it as people were coming in like yeah just this way so this way
Falcon you'd need to turn right
So airlines have specific rules for this right
There are a lot of airlines that will only animals that are allowing
The cabin are guide dogs for the blind and falcons for falcon racing
So Emirates is one of those airlines where it says they're the only two animals that are allowed
But if you buy a first-class seat you're allowed to falcons
So I think this is
One on the head one on the other
This is with Etihad that's what it's with
Yeah if you're going to Dubai or Abu Dhabi or something like that
You buy a first-class seat you're allowed to additional falcons
On the seat next to you
I get Etihad and Emirates a lot because my sister lives over in Abu Dhabi
I have never seen a falcon
Well you're never in first class then that's where they were hanging out
I thought you said you can have one in economy
You can't have one in economy yeah maybe
So just very quickly on brim close he raises these falcons in donkaster near an industrial estate
He's been doing it for years
He says that his falcons can get up to 75 miles an hour
The average falcon can get up to 60 miles an hour
So he doesn't know what he's doing right except that he knows that he's spending a lot of money
On their daily meals and so on in order to just build them up to be the strongest that they can be
And what's interesting is he lives in an industrial town
I read an article a year or so ago about pigeons which is that pigeons can fly faster
Through noxious air than they can through cleaner
If you get if you have racing pigeons they always go faster if you put them through horrible air
And no one knows why it might be because they just want to get out of it
Or it might be something to do I don't know
But that's the secret as what you're saying
Maybe maybe the donkaster air is the one secret
Maybe it's not anything else he's doing
Do you know how staff at marine parks get seeming out of a killer whale?
No, go on
They used to use a calvagina
They lost it
Some real and some artificial
Although where you would make an artificial calvagina I do not know
I could think the worst way
Wearing a swimming cap
Another marine biologist had his neck broken today
[Music]
Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show and that is Anna
My fact this week is that my and women had to prove they could make cocoa with the right amount of froth before men would marry them
This is something I was reading in the Smithsonian
And it's something that's claimed by this guy called Haze Lovis
And I've known if that's how you pronounce his name
But he's a cultural curator at the Smithsonian
And he said that early records of my own marriages in Guatemala
Indicate that in some places a woman would have to make the cacao
So she'd have to make the chocolate drink
And prove that she could make it with the proper amount of froth
Before she was able to marry the man
And this is the thing froth was incredibly important
So I hadn't realized that the froth on the chocolate drinks in
Mesoamerican civilizations was a bigger deal than the actual chocolate drink I think
And why for do we know?
I guess because it was part of just part of the ritual right? So you'll see lots of Mesoamerican art
Which shows the women making the froth
And they'd stand up really really high above the vessel that they were pouring the chocolate drink into
And they'd pour it in from really high above and it would splash down onto the ground
Like two meters high
And that would sort of froth it up and they'd do that a few times
So you just pour back and forth and back and forth
So it's just like a ritualistic thing
I guess it's just showing that you're not a complete idiot
Can you pour some stuff into a pot and then back and forth? Okay, well I'm angry, that's fine
Are you from quite a height?
I'd struggle, I would have been a spinster
I don't know
So Jose de Acosta who was a Spanish Jesuit missionary
He said that the scum of froth had a very unpleasant taste
I really
I think to European taste it wasn't that tasty because it's hot chocolate but it's not that sugar in
That'll pass on the chocolate, I'll just have some of that falcon seam and thank you very much
Much nicer
Because they didn't have cane sugar or anything like that
They could have put honey in it I suppose
But mostly it was a bitter and spicy drink, it wasn't sweet and
Yeah, they morphed with chilli in it, didn't they?
Yeah and yeah it was really really popular in spite of not being delicious and sweet like we now have
You know when old chocolate goes white, you know that?
No
Yeah when it goes off
When you leave chocolate for a while, you get white, do you know what that is?
No
It's called a fat bloom
So it's liquid from the cacao bean
Gradually moving towards the surface of the chocolate and breaking out on the surface like a rash
It's not bad
Yeah, I wouldn't eat it
I would
Would you?
Yeah
What about green bacon?
Yeah, I'd love it
No, sorry, no
Green bacon?
You know bacon goes a little bit off
Off that shimmery sheen on it
I think that's probably still all right
I still eat that
Yeah, it's nitrate burn that
It's the nitrates that they use to cure the bacon with and preserve it
That's just that reacting with the oxygen
Great
So does that imply that it's on the turn, right?
Yeah, but it's fine, it's still okay to eat
Good
Otherwise, I'm in serious trouble
I mean, if it's green and furry, probably not
They used to, the Mayans and the Aztecs used to use the cacao bean as currency
That would be their equivalent to money
Not exclusively, but it was, it was a traded thing
So and you would know what it was worth
So one bean might be worth according to this expert
Sorry, 200 beans might be worth according to this expert
The price of one turkey, for example
Okay
No, they think they know that, don't they?
Because so there, we can't, a lot of this stuff
We kind of have to guess that
Because we don't have written records
For a lot of these cultures
But they think they know that because they found counterfeit beans, right?
So
No
They have
They found the archaeologists keep finding what look like cacao beans
And then they go up close
And their little beans made of clay to look exactly like cacao beans
And they think it must be counterfeit currency
But or it could be, you know, they use them in
It's hot chocolate, tastes like shit
Is it their equivalent of chocolate money?
It's the non chocolate money
One of the suggestions was that the counterfeits
were to use in ceremonies
Because a lot of religious ceremonies involved cacao
Because it was such a valuable thing
But the point of religious ceremonies
Is to give offerings to the gods, right?
And you would have thought
If you're offering a god what looks like a cacao bean
But when he tries it
It's a bit of clay
Doug would actually piss the wall because ceremonial things don't you like
Like in ancient Egypt they would have made fake slaves
Or fake this or fake
Fakes slaves for the afterlife
For the afterlife
I'm sorry I thought I meant like
I saw you my slave
It's just a block of wood
And in China
Traditionally they would do paper
Versions of things you want in the afterlife
Because they knew that you couldn't necessarily take your iPad
To the next life
Because it's a solid thing
But you could take a paper one
And they still do that
It's amazing
Yeah, I think we have mentioned before
They do money
So you just burn money
And you burn items that you think they would like to take into the afterlife
It's amazing if you get to the afterlife
And you've got a paper iPad there
Oh, shit
I thought when I walked through this door
It would all chance for me to fail the egg
Everyone in the afterlife has all wondered how with paper iPad
Yeah, mine doesn't do anything either
It's ridiculous
We've no way of communicating to you
I know
Maybe that's what ghosts are trying to do
Bring my friends
So, I didn't know this
But Kakao bean
Stocks are running lower and lower
And all the crops are being converted to corn
And West Africa where they grow a lot of it
And chocolate's going to get way more expensive in the next few years
And Erika McAllister mentioned this a few weeks ago
Yes
But there was a guy in 2010
Because you get traders who buy and sell loads of Kakao beans
He bought 7% of the world's Kakao beans
658 million pounds worth, mountains of them
And he was nicknamed "choc finger"
Chocolate finger, it should be just...
I'm his real name's Anthony
He's just a trader who's specialised in Kakao his whole life
He knows all about the market movements
And you know, he's just spend his whole life buying and selling it
On what he thinks the market will do
Just on the Mayans very quickly, not to do with Kakao
But to do with those massive, amazing pyramids that they built
So back in the 30s, they discovered a pyramid within a pyramid
So is it in Russia?
Well, no
But what's amazing is last year
They've just found another pyramid inside that pyramid
Inside the pyramid
Yeah, and they think there may be a few more in sight
So yeah, it's like a Russian dollar factor that's going on
Very, very middle
That's the top of your own
Yeah, this is only last year that they announced it
That they found this new, smaller pyramid
I would have looked outside
Yeah
First pyramid for a massive pyramid
It could be that we're all living inside a massive kind of solar system size pyramid
And that one first one they found is actually the second one
Exactly
Yes
Why would you make the second Russian doll so much more
than the outside layer?
You just wouldn't, doesn't make any sense
Yeah, that's a huge scaling difference between
Well, they're faster than that
When they get that big
The first one took a lot of effort
And then the next one they're like, oh, we shouldn't make one that big
Just very quickly
We've never mentioned before that the first ATM machine
So the first cash machine was based on a chocolate bar dispenser
And so it was invented by this guy called John Shepherd Baron in the 1960s and '67
And he, I was really an interview with him
Well, I just imagine in like five of us on one of those chocolate machines
where it's just about to fall down
I think it's just quite fall down
That would be the worst thing ever, wouldn't it?
Yeah, and they wouldn't fall properly, I don't know
Yeah, it would be a nightmare
It was done with using checks in the olden days
So you'd write a check and it had a bit of, come off here
Like, even to get some chocolate out of a chocolate machine, you'd write a check
And six days later, once it's cleared
Who should I make it out to?
Just A9
Please deliver this check to A9
You're sincerely just a Baron
Don, you don't sign off checks, you're sincerely
I am so lost with what's happening at the moment
Clear up number one, no, you didn't ever put checks into chocolate bar machines
I'm sorry, give that impression
What I meant was, he based the cash machine on a chocolate bar machine
But to use cash machines in the olden days, you put a check in
And it had a bit of radioactive carbon, 14-nice atop
Which interacted with the machine
And he used to get in trouble and people would say
Oh, we reckon this is dangerous, it's radioactive
So he said, I later worked out that you'd have to eat 136,000 checks
for it to have any effect on your health
Okay, so, is it, you put, that's our cash machine used to work with radioactive
Yeah, a radioactive system that triggered it to give you some cash
That is unbelievable
But that's not how the chocolate, the chocolate dispenser works
Because it would melt, it would melt
You did used to get radioactive chocolate bars
When they first invented radium or discovered radium, they started putting them in chocolate bars
So technically, you could have actually put a chocolate bar into a cash machine and got a cash
But he'd have to get his chocolate from the original machine
So it's just the system that's just working back and forth
He still stopped between two vending machines
So this guy, this inventor, said he then moved up to Scotland to the coast
And the next thing he invented, and the only other thing he invented as far as I can tell
Is a device that played the sound of killer whales to ward seals off his fish farm
And he said to the BBC, he only succeeded in attracting many more of them
He should have put it inside a cow's vagina
Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts
Thank you so much for listening
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast
We can be found on our Twitter accounts
I'm on @Triberland, James, @X8, Andy, @UndrewHondaM
And Jizinski
You can email podcasts@QI.com
Yep, but you can go to our group account which is @QIPodcast
You can also go to our website, no such thing as a fish.com
Remember, our tour tickets are now on sale
Do come along, we'd love to see you there
We will be back again next week
Goodbye
[Music]
[BLANK_AUDIO]