We're going to go to the U.K.
Hello and welcome to another working from home episode of no such thing as a fish
a weekly podcast coming to you from four undisclosed locations in the U.K.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with James Harkin with Andrew Hunter Murray
and Anna Tajinsky and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite
facts from the last seven days and in no particular order here we go.
Starting with fact number one and that's my fact this week.
My fact is two days after receiving his latest book the author of annals of gullibility
why we get juped and how to avoid it lost hundreds of thousands of dollars in a Ponzi scheme.
He did admit that it was embarrassing he kind of thinks it's funny now you know with the
distance of time to look back at it but this is a guy called Stephen Greenspan and he'd written
this book and and it was meant to sort of help you to understand how not to be jubed by exactly
the thing that caught him off guard so he got caught off guard by the greatest Ponzi scheme
of them all which was the Bernie Madoff which set so many people around the world losing thousands
and millions in some cases it's the biggest of its kind and yeah it was recommendation via his sister
and two days after receiving his latest book he lost 400,000.
Wow in his advice as to how to avoid it did it include things like you know don't take advice
from ill-informed siblings and don't invest with people who have surnames that sounds especially
like the phrase made off. I think a revised edition was hastily issued with all this in there.
Don't come at his check is the Ponzi scheme basically a pyramid scheme where it's what it is
is you get in early investors and you get their money and when you bring in new investors you give
the money of the new investors a bit of it to the early investors so it seems as if they're
getting returned on their money and then you kind of thought that was a pyramid scheme basically.
A pyramid scheme is where you bring in new investors and they have to bring in new investors
and that money comes up to the people higher up in the pyramid it's slightly different.
Oh yeah see. So the Ponzi scheme is more flat it's more like a large plane on the deserts of Egypt
compared to the pyramid. A Ponzi scheme is the thing that we used to do as kids which I found
so thrilling do you remember where you'd get a letter that had a chocolate bar in it and you said
and it said send this on with no wait how would it work. I tell you no you're right you're doing
all right someone sends you a letter saying send me a chocolate bar but then you send the letter
to six people and then ask you ask each of them to send you a chocolate bar and then you get six
chocolate bars. It was amazing. That's a pyramid scheme. That's a pyramid scheme not a Ponzi
scheme but Anna if you've been investing. No a Ponzi scheme. It's pretty similar. It's similar
but it is there's quite a distinctive difference. So in a Ponzi scheme you would get a load of
Mars bars from loads of different people and then you would cut some of the Mars bars up and they give
the Mars bar back with another half of a Mars bar to someone who said you want Mars bar as they think
they're getting one and a half back but actually what you're doing is you're using other people's
Mars bars to do it and eventually you're going to run out of Mars bars. Do you have to re-wrap the
Mars bars once you cut them out? I feel like it's more different with Mars bars than it is with
money. It is when you get a monkey half a Mars bar through the bus. Is it different? They get in a nice
crisp 50 pound note. We're rich. We're rich. You know it's weird just in order to get ready for this
fact. I looked up what a Ponzi scheme was so I knew what it was. I now have no idea what it is off
the back of all these models. It's literally all it is is a pyramid scheme has one person at the
top ten people next, a hundred people next, a thousand people next whereas a Ponzi scheme has one
person at the top and then everyone else is flat. You actually did explain it completely correctly
Dan. We just started throwing Mars bars around. The first Ponzi scheme was basically invented by
accident, wasn't it by Charles Ponzi? He didn't quite mean to do it. He sort of meant it to be legit
so it was in the 1920s and he had the scheme where he was buying stamps or actually these things
called reply coupons and that was when if you wrote to a friend internationally you included a reply
coupon which I think essentially meant it was like doing a reverse charge call but on a letter and
it meant that they could write back to you for free. Anyway he bought them overseas for much cheaper
because they were cheaper overseas and then sold them for more in the US and he said to people I've
got this amazing scheme. Well I can make a massive profit on these reply coupons and he got people
to invest and they did and he hadn't factored in the fact that he'd have to pay for all the
ridiculous international travel to these places to go and buy these stamps in the first place so he
realized the scheme couldn't make any money at all but these people were investing loads of money
and you can see the reasoning where he started to think oh I still I'm receiving all this money.
Should I just keep keep going with this and not mention that it doesn't work? It's kind of working
well for a shot period of time isn't it I guess. It is until he so I think someone did the mass and
worked out that he was claiming to be buying and selling 160 million reply coupons and only 27,000
existed in the world. The Boston Post did an article in 1920 didn't they demonstration that
was completely impossible and when they did an audit afterwards they found only 61 dollars worth
of these stamps even though he'd said that he'd bought millions and millions of dollars worth.
So he did try he got a few. He got a few but when the Boston Post came up with
this expose everyone thought oh my god I've given him all my money I need my money back and so they
did a run on him to try and get all of their money back and he just completely fronted it out and
he just said yeah no worries you guys just queue up and I'll give you your money back and they
stood in the queue and he bought them sandwiches and coffee and people weren't sure whether he was
real or not still at that stage and so half the time they were cheering him and half the time they
were booing him no one really knew what was happening and then eventually the government got involved
and looked at his accounts and found he was three million dollars in the red and they later advised
it to seven million dollars in the red and he got arrested and when he got arrested everyone lost
her money. Oh wow. What was his long term plan that that queue outside his house? I just think
sometimes it's like maybe tomorrow it'll be fine. Yeah. If you're calm enough with the beginning of
the queue then the end will probably get bored and go away. Well that's what happened like because
loads of people started running on it but some people still trusted him so they became a secondary
speculation market where people would buy the Ponzi coupons on a cheaper price so that the people
in the queue would at least get something back and the people who bought it thought well this is
actually real it's for real so I'm going to get the full amount back so they became speculation
on the speculation. That's clever. That's crazy. And while we're on scammers have you guys heard of
Victor Lustig? I don't think we have ever mentioned him before. Is he the guy who sold the Eiffel Tower?
He's the guy who sold it twice. Oh wow. So he knew that Paris was broke. He was living in Paris and
he thought maybe the city would want to sell the Eiffel Tower off because it's been up for 30 years
it's a bit rusty and so he decided to forge some government stationery and he wrote to a load of
scrap metal dealers and he invited them all to an expensive suite at a hotel and he said hello
I am the deputy minister of posts and he said well we're looking for buyers but we've got to keep it
quiet from public opinion because there might be controversy and then one of the guys was tempted
and especially stupid dealer called Andre Poisson and Drew Fish and he said I'd really like to buy
the Eiffel Tower scrap and he paid a massive bribe to secure the ownership and unsurprisingly
the Eiffel Tower was not the sale but he got away with it. He was so successful Victor Lustig.
Was he never busted? He was busted later on for his Romanian box.
It was a box which would duplicate any bank note that you put in it. Obviously it wouldn't.
Okay well James Nanner I'm not going to try and sell you one but Dan you're looking interesting.
He had concealed genuine notes within the device and then as long as you only put in a selector
and I had all these buttons and levers that you press and pull and then another bank note would come
out and they'd think oh my god this is amazing. What's he inside making the noises?
He just made a complicated looking box basically and he sold the box for a lot of money to
various different people and then once there was a sheriff in Texas who realized that the scam
caught up with him in another state and then Lustig said oh you're just not using it right don't
worry it's okay completely persuaded him it was fine and then said look let me give you all this
cash to compensate you which was counterfeit money so you managed to pay his way out of it yeah
you're very cool. Like you were saying about how he said oh I'm not really supposed to talk about
this and so people trusted him Ponzi did that as well so when they said to him how are you making
this work because it doesn't seem like at work all these stamps he said oh yeah I've got a system
which I don't want to tell you because then the government will shut it down and then when
everyone did the run on him and started queuing up for money he said oh guys guess what I've come
up with a new system it's completely different it's not to do a stamps at all it's just really really
awesome and so this one will get you even more money so why don't you give me more money but he kept
saying I can't tell anyone what it is because if I tell you then everyone will be doing it and that's
what kind of suckers people in. Yes. Got to be adaptable. Do you know how you find out if someone is
gullible? Oh no. Oh well let me tell you my magic function. I don't know is it like a questionnaire
or something? It's exactly that there's a questionnaire but basically it is just asking are you
gullible? It's amazing it's a 12-question questionnaire some Australian authors came up with it
and it measures persuadability and insensitivity to untrustworthiness and but the questions are
really they're all things like my friends think I'm easily fooled do you disagree agree strong
you agree and basically if you answer yes to those questions or that you agree with them you're
gullible. Really? Which is weird because I would have thought gullible people wouldn't automatically
know it. No because as soon as you know that you're gullible surely you can start correcting your
gullipidacy. No I know I'm gullible and I can't stop it. If you guys decide to tell me some
bullshit on this show I will believe it until I see you the smile on your face. What do you think
about this? We are in the midst of a high frequency blossoming of interconnectedness that will give us
access to the quantum soup itself. What do you think of that sentence? I don't fully what's the quantum
soup is that like primary? Maybe you're not that gullible because apparently people who take that
kind of bullshit aphorism and think that it's quite deep are people who rate more highly on this
gullibility scale. Okay so I'm still gullible I'd be like the leader of the gullibles I'd be going
whoa whoa whoa whoa I know how that sounds guys but I don't think that's right. I've not had that soup.
You know that do you remember that old joke at school which was the gullible you know the world
gullible isn't in the dictionary? Did you know that OED published a special edition where they
took it out of the dictionary? No they didn't. Wait think of the labor involved in printing an entire
new edition of the dictionary just for one joke it doesn't stack up. I just want to point out that
Dan was the first one who spotted that and so I think well done you're not as gullible as we all
think well they're actually apparently humans aren't too gullible we all have this conception that
we're really gullible and more is falling for stuff but studies seem to show that we're actually
too skeptical and so there's been a bunch of things that so fake news is often used as an example
of how we're too gullible we believe this stuff we change our voting habits but all the studies
that have really been done on fake news over the last few years have showed that it didn't impact
elections at all because people only ever consumed the sort of fake news that already accorded with
what they believed so it wasn't like they were reading stuff and going oh my god Hillary Clinton
really is a lizard it was like they already thought she was probably a lizard it's just confirmed it
but actually we're too skeptical so there's a very famous psychologist called Julian Rotter
who died quite recently but he said that the more trustful you are the more successful you are in life
and the better you are at determining if someone is trustworthy or if something's worth supporting
because you've practiced it so people who are more trusting generally they practice it through
life and then you learn who to trust and who not to trust whereas the cynics who just think oh god
everyone's a liar everyone's trying to jeep me they actually have no idea and they lose out
because of that so Anna are you saying that me and Nandi are really great because we fell for your
dictionary prank sounds like it really smart and let me talk to you afterwards about a scheme I've
got up and running but Dan is the cynic and he's just like he's living in his barrel
yeah I'm like don't know oh god it always comes back to diogenesis isn't it um there was a dictionary
scam back in the day where uh Huxters would go around a pubs getting into uh getting money off
people with a dictionary based bet okay so the idea is three of you go into the pub you all pretend
you don't know each other you just start you know sit at different places it's quite easy for us
yeah three of us I've gone home um and then one of one of you guys will start repeatedly using the
word unfortunate okay let's say Dan keep saying it's really unfortunate about this and then James
or Anna will lean over and say excuse me I think it's unfortunate bingo exactly and then Dan will
say it's pretty unfortunate that you're such an idiot or whatever and you get into this
big argument I can only afford James I've also been quite drunk when I said that you get this huge
route and obviously you get everyone else involved and you start putting money on it and then Dan
pulls out his dictionary which does have the word unfortunate in it because it's an old version
of the word and then you get the money in it and then it works as other comments of this story
shall he she's the one with a dictionary I've been at the bar this whole time I got really bored
very early on in this chat and I went to talk to some people at the bar it must be the case that she
happens to be a dictionary salesman who has a dictionary for the wise what's about to be in there
that's even better yeah yeah that's the first one and that's the third person is just for audience
purposes to cheer people on it's sort of to get more people involved in the bed hey come and look
at the argument these guys are having and is there a whole history of that like is that a
gang that went round the dictionary gang yeah yeah this is a what-off incident no I think some people
have used it repeatedly but I don't think it was a massive because if it's the trend only lasts
until everyone has heard of it because there are hundreds of gangs going around the pubs
doing the unfortunate play oh man that's it during gang wars I wouldn't want to be in that gang
have you not watched gangs have blended recently there's one episode where the dictionary
gang comes along it's it's the least violent of all the episodes I have to say hey you could get
some pretty big dictionaries you could do some serious damage with the full edition of the OED
yeah kill someone yeah sticks and stones maybe yeah um I found um a gullible person who fell
for a scam have you guys heard of this guy in New York a few years ago sued a psychic for fraud
it's I mean it is sad but in 2015 he sued the psychic because over the years he'd given her over
$700,000 because he wanted her to make the woman that he fancied fall in love with him it's an old
classic Shakespearean tale he should have just given the 700,000 to the girl
she James women can't be bought I agree but it's worth a try rather than giving it to a psychic
that should have been his for at least the person you like has got a lot of dash yeah he was actually he's
walking down the street to New York thing this is really sad I've told the woman I really love her
and she said she has no interest in me whatsoever and he passed a sign saying psychic with a flashing
arrow and so you already know he's a bit gullible he walked in and this psychic just managed to convince
him for instance to fork out um $40,000 so she could do him a fake funeral to convince the bad
spirits that he had died so that they stopped plaguing him and let the woman fall in love with him
why don't invite the woman he fancied to the fake funeral and see if she was sad that he died
and then he bursts out of the coffin come on and then that is the woman he fancied I don't think I've
got another that is never gonna work is it in a romance that's how my wife and I got together
true story yeah I think you might risk the woman thinking you're a widow which this guy definitely
wasn't to be clear um he also paid $80,000 for an 80 mile long bridge made of gold to lure the
spirits into the other realm and then say that sounds like quite a good deal for a bridge made of
gold an incredible bargain yeah that's so cheap it is I think I the thing is the bridge made of gold
didn't really exist in this realm so you can never get the evidence that it has been built
a bridge yeah much cheaper than bridge much less did the guy did he not see the psychic
increasingly turning up in fur coats in matterities and all of this stuff and she's like I bought them
in the other realm it's much cheaper over there eventually I've been fucked up another 90 grand
for a longer bridge because the spirits weren't going over this one um halfway through this the
woman he was in love with very sadly died and the psychic thought quickly on her feet and said
oh well don't worry we'll just have to pay a bit extra for my reincarnation machine to be built
and so creepy no this is a terrible story it it it is awful and it was only when she said she built
this reincarnation machine and Michelle this woman you're in love with is now inside this new
woman you've just met and he said I met the new woman and I thought she doesn't seem like Michelle
at all and that was when I started to think the psychic wasn't who she was purporting to be
right god how did this guy have access to seven hundred thousand dollars in the first
nutman is now the president of the United States okay it is time for fact number two and that is
Anna my fact this week is that in 2011 former Paralympian Josh Sundquist who's missing his left leg
announced that he'd found his soulmate i.e someone missing a right leg with whom he can split pairs
of shoes I don't know how I sort of came across this but I was watching his YouTube channel so Josh
is a he was a Paralympian skier and now an author and a comedian and public speaker and he sort of
posted a video saying he's got these piles of shoes he's been saving up for years because obviously
you can't buy one shoe but he only needs one so he's got loads of right shoes and he'd been looking
for someone who could wear them and then he found living in the same city as him a chap called
Stephen missing a right leg same shoe size and crucially same taste in shoes so they had a lovely
meet-up well they did some swapsies that's great that's great it's a beautiful story although it was
quite I mean I think he might have been conned to be fair because he'd obviously been saving up his
right shoes over the years Josh and so he came with this giant mountain whereas Stephen wasn't
expecting the soulmate reunion so he'd presumably chopped away all his left shoes so he only gave
Joshua one shoe so it was sort of a one shoe and exchange for about 50 shoes there are charities out
there where you can so if you have lost a leg or lost a foot but also if you have a pair of
feet that are different sizes like we all do but some people much bigger than others
there are some places where you can you can match up with people with the opposite-sized feet to
you oh really yeah in a moment there's something called the national odd shoe exchange which is
nose NOSE and they put people together with mismatch feet and in the UK there's something called Joe's
odd shoes which is on Facebook where all you have to do is pay postage and packaging and they'll
send you a single shoe very cool it's a bit weird isn't it usually when you do those acronyms
it usually works out of something like foot it's a bit odd to get it for nose yeah absolutely right
they should well maybe they have this conversation footwear odd one out trading and it's
foot except foot is also the beginning of footwear so it's achieved apart from odd one out has got
three oz in a row so it'll be food so that's that's Josh great guy but I was I was sort of looking
into prosthetics and there's some really cool prosthetics out there that you can get so if you
guys heard of this woman called Sophie de Oliveira Berrata no she's got this thing called the alternative
limb project and she's basically an artist is in North London and she makes these bespoke limbs
and she was she was inspired to do it she had this client who was a little girl who had one leg
and every year she'd come for an upgraded leg because she was growing and she started asking for
she asked at first for pepper pigs at the top of her leg pictures of pepper pig eating ice cream
and so Sophie was like yeah sure whatever and then she came back the next year and asked for
a Christmas scene at the top which I think is very short termist and she's going to regret that
in February but whatever um and this woman Sophie thought well this is great what a good idea and
so she was inspired by Inspector Gadget because you know he makes yeah he makes gadgets yeah um and so
legs doesn't he sometimes exactly so she makes long arms and legs and special arms and legs
and so for one guy she made a hyper realistic foot that look really like his own foot and she got
hairs off the back of his neck and put them on the toes not many people in history have ever
looked at their toes and gone that isn't hairy enough can we put my hairs on that please
so the the I guess one of the next front is in prosthetic bone development is is how to incorporate
feeling and how to incorporate automatic responses so there's one recent development
research at Newcastle University came up with this it's got an AI camera inside it it's a hand
or an arm fitting and it can recognize hundreds of objects using the camera and when you move to
grab something with your prosthetic arm it automatically moves into the right position to grasp it
so if you're reaching for a pair of tweezers it'll move into a pinch position or if you're reaching
for a volleyball it'll move into a sort of spread hand position so you can pick it up like that
sounds unbelievable and it can be trained to you know develop more and more positions can you
can you sort of code it so that if it's reaching for your 10th toffee crisp of the night it will
be used to clap down on it or something and we don't have time for your toffee crisp problem
maybe if you had to send that letter to so many people you wouldn't have so many to get through
a toffee crisp no one mentions toffee crisp chocolate I agree they're the best they I'm not sure
I've ever had one what oh my god that's like me not what you'd eat Jesus Christ we we definitely
don't have time for the fact that you've never eaten toffee crisp they're the they are one of the one
of the very best are they I reckon even asthma would agree with that I was reading up about Aaron
Ralston you guys remember Aaron Ralston a 127 hours yeah I remember that oh yeah yeah so he was the
the mountaineer slash adventurer who fell down a little gap between some boulders a boulders
a boulder collapsed on his arm and he had to cut himself free and so he now when you see pictures
of him if he goes mountaineering he has a prosthetic that has a little pick on the end oh wow
they went back and they actually recovered his arm so it was stuck under this boulder they managed
to winch it out winch the boulder up and get his arm back and they cremated it there on the spot
and he scattered the ashes symbolically all over the area so that's really nice but the the little
fact that I really like that I've discovered about him is his current place of residence he lives
in a place called boulder cholera no one lasting on prosthetics I was I was amazed to learn about
there's a big comedian back in the early days of American comedy during the silent era called
Harold Lloyd and Harold Lloyd was at the time more famous than Buster Keaton and Charlie Chaplin he
was he was the one who was pulling in most money at the box office and what I didn't know is that
he lost two of his fingers he lost his thumb and his index finger when he was doing publicity for
a film of his called haunted spooks he stood in the photo with a prop bomb in his hand which
turned out to be a real bomb no yes for the fuse later minutes what kind of what kind of prop
department has two boxes one with prop bombs and one with real bombs and accidentally takes out
the wrong one how do you how do you end up in that situation now what we've done is we've labeled
the prop bombs with a key and we've labeled the real bombs with a lower case don't put them upside
down next to each other was that someone simultaneously in the middle of a battle somewhere throwing the
prop bomb yeah so it it's wet on his hand yeah it took off his thumb it took off his index finger
temporarily blinded him he took eight months to recover and then they built a glove for him which
had the thumb and the finger and the most famous surviving sequence or even image that will
know of Harold Lloyd as him hanging off a clock yeah face he did that with a prosthetic thumb and
and finger it was after that that is a public saying I'd never heard that yeah okay it is time for
fact number three and that is Andy my fact is that you can now diagnose a urinary
tract infection using a fidget spinner finally I can get all my old fidget spinners out
oh yeah that is worth a customized right customized fidget spinner don't go pissing on your
children's match of spinners oh what what do you mean children
adults as well where they don't piss on any fidget spinners whether they're the children's
addition to all the special adult fidget spinners that James owns the erotic fidget spinners
you can't I saw sorry to interrupt when you haven't even told us a fact yet but because I didn't
write this down because I didn't think it would come up but did you see that there was a you know
like they call pasties or pasties that erotic dancers put on their nipples and spin them around
pasties yeah cornered pasties yeah it happens mostly in Cornwall yeah the strippers do this but they
made one with fidget spinners didn't they which liked fidget spinned around when they twelped their
breasts gosh yeah so you can get adult fidget spinners is what you say yeah they're not the ones I have
though Andy what is the how does this work well this is a new scientific development basically it's
it's a it's a pain diagnosing urinary tract infections it can take sometimes days to get the
results back and scientists are always looking for ways to improve the process so this is a way
of detecting pathogens in someone's urine which might reveal if they've got an infection um so
and what you need is detectors that are cheap and simple and accurate and that's what this
new one is they custom made this team a fidget spinner um where you you pee in the spinner uh
no no yeah yeah unless your aim is phenomenal you pee in a jug uh and then the jug is yeah a bit of
it's poured into the fidget spinner and it it spins uh it spins around obviously and the the
centrifugal force pushes the urine sample outwards and it pushes it through a little internal membrane
inside the spinner and the membrane is is fine enough to stop bacteria which can tell you whether
you've got one of these infections and then all you need to do is add a little bit of a die which turns
the bacteria orange you look at the membrane a little bit later if there's orange on the membrane
you have these bacteria and you know that you've got the infection i would have that day to die which
is a colour that's less similar to the colour of urine yeah how orange is people's urine these days
more orange than it is purple James I know you're a sunny D for that too much look it's for adults as
well as children so do you know I mean yeah that would make sense to you I do I imagine that other
other dies are also available but the the good news is that it cuts the test times to under an
hour and it does also mean that people don't get diagnosed antibiotics unnecessarily maybe in the
interim while they're waiting for the results so doctors might say oh just take something's anyway
which is a bad thing because it leads to antibiotic resistance so yeah this is a good finally we've
found a use for the fidget spinner three years later is it commercially available can we all buy one
no no you can't it's just been invented sorry no and also I think you probably want a medical
professional to do your diagnosis of UTIs rather than just pissing on your own fidget spinner
oh yeah it's something I do that you could get it like a pregnancy test you know and you'd be
able to buy one and then piss on it and then maybe you could lay with it yeah I guess you could
I guess yeah or just they're issued to doctors who know how to administer the tests but either way
I think everyone should be their own doctor oh god it sounds really simple give it a spin pour the
dye in what are we what am I missing wow you've already got the slogan yeah one thing that they
think it might work for in the future is also viral infections so hopefully this technology in
the future you'll be able to use with saliva instead of urine and you'll be able to detect viruses
if you get your mesh fine enough your membrane fine enough then it will be able to find viruses so
it might be that if there's a viral infection going around then you'll be able to use something
like this to tell whether you have that that's great because fidget spinners have had a bad
rep and a lot of corners over the years haven't they they've been sort of banned quite a lot of
places quite love schools in America went through a phase of banning them for big really distracting
for kids there were lots of warnings that some of them were dangerous do you remember there were
various fidget spinners came out that were a bit like ninja stars that had sort of pointed ends
and there was actually this woman who was employed to test them a test a blade expert
apparently called Sarah Haynesworth who BBC Watchdog made her test these things to see if they could
penetrate skin or eyeballs and her job and only Xbox to attempt this was to get a fidget spinner
and stab a tomato with it which apparently represents an eyeball and then stab some pork skin
with it the represents human skin so interesting because I have some fidget spinners in my house
and I've also been trained how to throw ninja stars so I can actually try and I have some tomatoes
you're qualified do you say that anyone can do this Sarah well again I think everyone should be
their own blade tester as well as their own doctor so yes you should start stabbing tomatoes
awesome wow the trick is in the flick of the wrist at the end just in case you hold it like
between your thumb and your first finger and then you throw it and then you flick your wrist at
the last second and then it helps it to spin and hence it stick into things that's like flooring a knife
that's why Harold Lloyd could never have become a ninja after his terrible publicity accident
you did have two hands good point that's why Harold Lloyd would have had to be ambidextrous if he
was to realise his ambition of becoming a ninja it's ironic that the one famous thing about him
is he's on a clock which does have two hands wow that is such a slap in the face isn't it
we we wrote about fidget spinners at the height of their of their craves back in 2017 in our first
book of the year in james you found out this thing which is that of all the top 25 toys on amazon
dot code dot uk all of them were fidget spinners yeah and I went to check up amazon today just to see
where they sit in the top 100 and not a single fidget spinner has stayed in the top 100 really
but yeah and the top toy at the moment is a black balloon that's in the shape of a zero I think you
can get it multicolored but that's the image that you're met with that's quite a nihilist thing to
give to a child is black zero happy birthday but it did last longer than everyone thought so that was
2017 where it was at its peak but in 2019 fidget spinners still accounted for a fifth of all toy sales
what wow really it's amazing I was looking at other toys that can be used for medical uses
and I found a paper called a novel method for the removal of ear ceremony so that's ear wax
okay what time might be used to remove the wax okay yes yes yes I'm a yo-yo but a very small
yo-yo that you just got a dip in the ear it's a good first guess um okay quite right now um um so
something oh something absorbent or something with little scraping edge yeah you mean scraping
like a Lego man's hand you know you can go in with that pincer grip it's got a pincer grip on it
doesn't it that's good yeah oh oh silly putty just putting so much silly putty that the ear wax is
forced out so have you guys never had any issues with ear wax I think you haven't because you don't
seem to know what they actually use in real life you suck it out but I'm trying to think it's
something that you suck and that's a toy a straw one of those really fun straws they don't suck it out
my doctor's all have massive mouths and they just put their entire mouth around your ear
and it's a heavy hoover and they just stick it to your head and they have to stop before the
brain comes out um no it's going to be it's going to be a it's going to be a fake doctor's syringe
maybe exactly they syringe it out normally yeah and what it is is a super-sulka max D5000
wow um this is a guy who um he was living on an island and the child had real problems with ear wax
and he couldn't get to the um doctors to get a syringe quickly enough so he said the owner of a
super-sulka max D5000 was sought out after hearing an explanation of its intended application
he granted permission for its use verbal consent was obtained from the patient he then changed
into swimming shorts located himself on an ideal location on the deck and held a Tupperware container
product number 1611 slash 16 to the side of his neck the super-sulka max D5000 was filled with
body temperature water and then mildly pressurized using the blue hand pump the trigger was depressed
releasing a gentle narrow jet of water which was aimed along the posterior wall of the ear canal
and then after 15 seconds bits of wax started coming out and it worked I might do that that's great
I think don't do that this was a medically trained professional uh-huh and this is a thing that
happened then it is in a medical paper but I think if you do have ear wax problems maybe you should
consult a profession you guys are so boring don't piss in my fidgets videos don't
get the circus in my head um do you know what the best selling doll of 1976 was you'll be
surprised oh 1976 was it a rich Nixon doll was oh that was very that I was about to say very close
it's not very close was it a um when was star was 77 so maybe it wasn't yeah it wasn't
the blue skywalker oh I don't oh oh the exorcist didn't that come out in 70 oh nice okay well
you're all kind of getting closer it is it is a pop culture thing it was share oh what's it really
yeah there were sunny and shareholders and um the share one was very customizable had different
outfits and things and it was hugely popular really the best selling doll of the entire year was
share that makes sense yeah I am surprised Andy I just don't have I don't have any references that
I can make jokes about share no I'm just trying to think of a single share song shoot shoot song
is the only one I could think yeah the famous one with Sonny Bono what was that the duet I got you
babe I got you babe yeah yeah I was just imagining being a parent and having two kids and I own
one share doll and convincing them it was called share because they had to share it I'm sorry I
switched off and went there okay it's time for our final fact of the show and that is James okay my
fact this week is that Al Capone ran a soup kitchen during the Great Depression he served beef on
Thanksgiving in 1930 because there had just been a theft of 1000 turkeys nearby and he didn't want
the authorities to think it was him makes sense yeah and he had to do something with the 50 cows
even it didn't he that's probably more like it um so yeah um Al Capone Chicago gangster
public enemy number one um bad guy killed lots of his enemies uh especially in the St Valentine's
Day massacre in 1929 but like a lot of these people who were bad guys he had this kind of Robin Hood
reputation where he would give to charity in the local area and the idea I think sometimes is that
he's less likely to get ratted out if people like him although it has to be said that this soup
kitchen although it definitely existed he might have not paid any money for it because he could have
like leaned on some local businesses to donate their beef and whatever uh because obviously that
extortion was a lot of his a lot of his stick so he might have said to you guys you better give me
some stuff for my charity or else so that's a negative portrayal of Al Capone
on the other hand it was a soup kitchen it was a soup kitchen yeah and yeah they gave breakfast
lunch and dinner to um over 2,000 people in Chicago every single day uh and the newspapers kind of were
not sure about it because on one hand they thought obviously this is a good thing that people
are being fed but on the bad hand they could see him becoming like the mayor of Chicago if people
liked him too much and they thought if a gangster becomes the mayor of our city then we could be
in real trouble yeah he was sort of Dave facto mayor for quite a while wasn't he in the he ran
the city essentially well yeah he didn't really need to become there because he had a guy called
William H Thompson who was known as Big Bell and basically Al Capone funded him and made sure that
he stayed in place and Big Bell was um sometimes known as Kaiser Bell because he was very pro German
during World War One and in the 1920s he threatened to punch the British king in the snoot
mind you it's not the worst war in which to be pro German to be fair to him no there'd been
worse one since yeah I just I find Al Capone so amazing how it's like he conforms to all the gangster
cliches and the fact that he could just commit multiple murders and everyone know and no one be
able to do anything about it I mean he he's shot people in you know open public there was one of his
rivals he just went down into a bar and shot him in the head and everyone saw everyone knew he'd
done it but no one's going to say anything they were all distracted by an argument about dictionary
going on in the other car the newspapers reported it as an unfortunate
Anna I wonder though if you've got that right you're probably right but I wonder if you've got
that wrong in when you say he conformed to the cliches I wonder if Al Capone invented the cliches
yeah you're right yeah all the movies born off the back of his life and of all the gangsters of
that time or what inform us about the mafia yeah so he kind of invented clich yeah I didn't know
that he was called Scarface I mean I'm sure anyone who you know has read a bit about it didn't
know that but yeah I didn't know that he had the big scars and the first film called Scarface was
about him I don't know either he hated the name well so yeah yes he did yeah and he got he got the
scars on his face from insulting a lady the the brother of a lady was taken aback and slashed his face
but he used to claim that he got it as a result of some service time in the army because he didn't
want to just admit that he was you know lost a battle in the fight where he got scarred Al Capone
his brother James Capone kind of got in involved in it and pushed the guy who who scarred him through
a glass window because obviously he just cut his brother and he was so worried that this guy was
going to come back and get him that he fled the city and joined the circus and then he served in
World War One and then after the war he changed his name after his favourite cowboy and became a
prohibition agent and basically spent his whole time stopping people from moving alcohol around
which is where Al Capone got most of his money but he didn't realise that that happened because of
that time Al Capone wasn't really famous for that kind of thing and so he only later found out that
his brother who he'd left after that fight when he was 16 years old had become the greatest mobster
and he had become one of the big prohibition agents there needs to be a film that imagines the
meeting between them where he knows he's arresting this huge prohibition breaker and suddenly they
meet face to face he was called Vincenzo Capone wasn't he this guy originally and then he
he became Richard Hart but there were so many Capones I think eight or nine Capone siblings in all
and the last member of the family alive or she was alive in 2012 and no she is still alive because
she's on Twitter is Deirdre Capone wow the most harmless name Deirdre why no she defends Al Capone's
reputation which I think is an uphill battle and she's written a book saying he was a mobster not a
monster and she's written a book all about him which includes recipes like meatballs alacapone
wow but and and these days she's just retweeting you know like dogs and meditation she has a
Twitter account so weird that a Capone family member should be judged by your by your grandparents should
you really oh or your Twitter account I'd just like to make very clear he was quite a family man
though again as the cliches then played out he had that typical I've got a wife who theoretically
doesn't know anything that's going on but maybe she knows everything he was he really loved his son
so his son had hearing damage probably because it was congenital syphilus contracted from Al Capone
which he famously had and he spent a hundred thousand dollars fixing his sons hearing in 1925
when he didn't he bet didn't even really have huge amounts per se he was a family guy but his
syphilus was a much bigger part of his life than his gang time wasn't it I could can we say that for
short time wise total time okay my sorry it was a longer part of his life you're right okay say
biographers are always complaining why do they always focus on the gangster years it's more about
his rancid penis I think of myself as a syphilus patient who happens to be in the
well I think by the end he basically couldn't think of himself as anything he was it was so awful
I didn't sort of realize the symptoms of untreated syphilus but by the time he went to prison in 1930
he was starting to really suffer from it there's a theory that one of the reasons he was moved from
Atlanta prison to Alcatraz where he was famously sent it's actually that he was being bullied
in Atlanta the Atlanta prison because he was very weak and he was starting to lose his faculties
because of this syphilus and his cellmate had to protect him because you know everyone else
was bullying him and so he was accused of a special treatment because this cellmate was protecting him
so he was shifted but yeah by by the time he got to Alcatraz he was having problems he was one of
the first people ever to be treated with penicillin in 1940s for it yeah have you heard of his lawyer
or one of his lawyers I'm sure you know it's a cool time if it's Charlie Chaplin yes
he was called Hiram Mendo no no okay um so he defended him in a trial I think in 1930 which was when
they first nabbed him you know they eventually got him for tax evasion but they first got him for
unlicensed ownership of a gun or something anyway this is the earlier trial that was in about 1930
guess when Hiram Mendo retired okay so he must have been at least 30 then and he retire when he's
65 so he retired in 1965 he retired in 1994 yes he he died in 2001 aged 107 but he kept practicing
law until he was a hundred years old oh my gosh I know was he Donald Trump's lawyer he just feels
at the kind of guy he definitely must have been Donald Trump's lawyer at some point he wasn't he
was just amazing his working life he started working when he was six at the age of in 1900 and he
kept working for 94 years he wasn't working as a lawyer when he was six did clarify who would you
rather have the six-year-old liar rather one hundred year old liar there was he had another lawyer
who was called Edward O'Hare who testified against him in court not a good lawyer oh wow that's not
the kind of lawyer what and he's slightly a notable character not just for his connection to
Capone but his son is called Edward but show hair junior off which O'Hare airport in Chicago is
named after he was a yeah he was a Medal of Honor fighter pilot who single-handedly shot down
eight Japanese bombers so he was a hero for Chicago why did his lawyer testify against him though
that does seem like a bit of a rookie mistake I'm sure he wasn't representing him anymore at that
point I call to the stand me I'll capone the only time he got shot
was when he shot himself wasn't it he shot himself by accident 1928 it had a golf game
so James golf dangerous game you've got to be careful and playing on Saturday
well try not to put your gun to near your golf clubs in the bag because that's how he did it he
it's the details are slightly unclear but we think that after a round of golf he got into his car
and he opened his golf bag and fiddled around and he was keeping his gun in there as well
and he shot himself and he shot himself sort of multiple times I think through the groin and through
the why why why did he keep shooting off the first that doesn't stack up Anna it really doesn't
I think he had multiple wounds maybe the bullet went in and out and in and out kind of like a
sewing needle or if you press your finger on a trigger accidentally can it deploy multiple bullets
it's a machine gun it can yeah I wouldn't keep a machine gun in the golf bag if afterwards someone
said did you get a hole in one and he said a hole in one of my testicles yeah he wasn't he wasn't a
funny guy he I read it one coupon biography this thing that gang habit that gangsters had in the
20s that Brooklyn gangsters had which apparently they devoted huge amounts of time to so and this
is also in a book about Brooklyn gangs but I couldn't find first hand evidence apparently gangsters
devoted huge amounts of time to the look and the look is a threatening stare that you give someone
it was a deadly gaze designed to strike mortal fear into the heart of an enemy and it was more
frightening than any kind of violence or anything like that and so they they practiced it apparently
alcohol is very good at it it's the source of all is yeah so Andy's doing it sort of trying to do
it now you know you can't shake your fist James that is cheating probably that young gangsters have
it's just a stand in front of the mirror for hours on end each day practicing yeah Capone used to
think that he was very a well-dressed guy as well they had a look in the other way didn't he he had
the nickname snorkey which he much preferred to to Scarface so he's quite embarrassed by Scarface
and like if there were cameras on he would try and move the scars to the so they couldn't see them
on the camera but he wouldn't he wouldn't move the scars obviously he would move the scars but only
because they were attached to his head and he was moving his head but yeah he liked to be called snorkey
which in those days meant someone who was well dressed he looks a bit snorkey snorkey snorkey
something like a cartoon dog is much less threatening Al snorkey Capone yeah I read a thing in gentleman's
Gazette recently which was about Al Capone it said Al Capone was known as much for his sense of
style as he was for his psychopathic tendencies which I would dispute I think you're right I think it's
number one syphilis number two psychopathic tendencies number three style yeah I think that's
okay that's it that is all of our facts thank you so much for listening if you'd like to get in
contact with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast we can
be found on our Twitter accounts I'm on at Shriberland Andy at Andrew Hunter M James oh he's giving
us the look at James Harkin and Anna you can email podcast at qi.com yeah but you can go to our group
account which is at know such thing or our website you can go to know such thing as a fish dot com all
of our previous episodes are up there as well as links to bits of merchandise that we've released
over the years okay guys once again we hope you're staying well we hope you're safe we hope you're
family are doing well um thank you so much as ever for listening to us during this weird weird time
we will be back again next week with another episode and we'll see you then goodbye
and I can I quickly say at Deirdre Capone just because we mentioned her on Twitter and I don't know if
it's funny or not she's actually Deirdre Marie Cap what I don't know why she put it Marie had left
out Capone but there we go because Cap is a slang word for putting a cap in it for shooting
somewhere that comes from that comes from Capone part of Cap in your ass come on we just had a
gullible podcast dad I held that deliberately held back damn it up we're still recording
[Music]