[Music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to
you from four undisclosed locations in the UK. My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with
Andrew Hunter Murray, James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski and once again we have gathered around
the microphones with our four favourite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order,
here we go, starting with fact number one and that's Anna. My fact this week is that in India
you automatically get a government job if you qualify for the Olympics and if you win a medal
you get a promotion. Wow, does the size of the promotion depend on the size of the medal,
not the size of the medal, the material from which the medal is made?
Yeah, you don't get sort of giant gold medals do you? It does, yeah, essentially. I think the
level of promotion depends on how well you do generally and it's not just at the Olympics,
it's in various other sporting competitions. So this is a system which seems to exist state to
state, they have various different policies from one state to the next and it seems to also exist
at a federal level and the truth is that to train to qualify for the Olympics is basically a full-time
job and a lot of people can't afford to take time out of work, like where do you find the money
to support that? The athlete's diet can be very expensive and so the way the Indian government
and state governments encourage their citizens to get sporty is to give them government jobs,
which is like monthly salary, you can't be fired, you get medical care, you get a pension,
but they do actually have to turn up to work. So there's... I have a question. Yeah, go on.
Are the government jobs you get related to the sport that you do? So if you're a really good
high jumper, do they sometimes give you a job like turning on light switches on very big walls?
Oh, yeah, those really high light switches that are purposely beyond normal humidity.
I guess the reason they put them there in the first place is because they were installed by
high jumpers. Exactly, yeah, it's a vicious circle, it's the whole thing. Is it like that?
It's not, though, is it? No, it is the answer. It's exactly like that, yeah, it's a very good
question. They almost all work for the railways, don't they? Are a lot of them. Yeah, police force
as well. The biggest employers are the railway, the police force, the army, but various government
departments. So there's an air rifle world record holder called suma shiro and she got a job on
the railway, for instance, and she had to turn up to work sort of. No, I don't think every day,
but quite regularly and just did data entry and literally sitting at a computer doing data entry
in order to claim her government salary. Well, did she do it from a computer which was 10 meters
away from her because she's so good at air rifle? Well, she was shooting it. Like she has to shoot
each key. There was an old game called duck hunts which came out before any of you guys were born,
which probably would be quite useful for that. Exactly. Yeah, that's how she trained. I think
I stretched this beyond the point. But it seems like in some cases that it's the other way round,
they became athletes and tried to get into competitions just to secure a lifetime government
job. Wow. So because you get, as Anna said, the pensions, you get medical, you get lifetime job
basically. But surely that would be easier to just get the job than becoming an elite athlete,
considering how difficult it is to become an, you know, you have to get to the Olympics. That's
pretty hard. It must be easier. Some people are very bad at data entry, James, but naturally quite
fit. It's amazing how badly India does at the Olympics relative to the population size. So
they've won 28 medals total at the Olympics, which is the same as Michael Phelps has won.
Wow. Now, it's obviously Michael Phelps is very, very good at the Olympics, but India has roughly
a billion people. And in 2008, they won one medal per 383 million of their population.
So that's a low hit rate, basically. That's what people say, isn't it? Like it's not really fair
the Olympics because, you know, you might say, well, it's not fair that, you know, some countries
in the Eastern Bloc might have used drugs or whatever. But also it's not really fair that
the rich countries just get to do way better because we have way better diets, we have better
facilities, we have better everything in the Western world. So yeah, it's pretty hard to be
just a lowly born Indian person and get into the Olympics. And that's a huge amount of the population
are basically excluded because of, for financial reasons, from even ever having this as an option
in their life. So it's not really a billion people who are, you know, in the pool to be selected.
But they do, there's a stat that I read in an article talking about this, where they say that
there's more than 100 billionaires in India. That's a lot of billionaires, which mean there
must be a lot of millionaires, which must mean there must be a middle class that is good at
sport and have the facilities and have the training. That's true. They just don't do it for some reason.
Well, there's a saying, there's a popular Hindi saying, and this is the translation of it. It's
"If you study hard, you will live like a king. But if you play sports, you will ruin your life."
So it might be a cultural thing as well.
I think there's a bit of a disadvantage as well to the people who have grown up wanting to work
and get high up in the railway services. You know, imagine you're like, I want to kick ass and be
at the height of this job. And then you've suddenly got this Olympian who's won a silver medal,
getting promoted over you, because that's part of the... Like there's a guy called Sandeep Sejwal,
who he competed in Breaststroke at the 2008 Beijing Olympics. And he's never been to the office
because he's always training, but he's got this full-time job. And he says, "If you swim continuously
and win a medal at the Nationals, or just represent the Indian Railways at the National
level, you can get promoted. So I'm going to file for a promotion. Hopefully I get it,
and then I'll be the boss." He might be the boss of some guy who's worked his whole life to get
up the railway. It's mad. The system's crazy. I think we'll know when the Indian, entire Indian
railway infrastructure falls apart. It's because of this Breaststroke professional who's risen to
the top and ruined it. But it's good for the state departments, because what they get in return is
PR, right? So it's sort of seen as them representing the police, or the army, or the railways when
they go and compete. That's what they get in return. Also, the Indian Railway competes in
national championships of things. So you might have American colleges competing, or at least
on a semi-professional level they play. But the Indian Railway has teams that are in all of these
different spots. So it does give them, like Anna says, a lot of good PR. Have you guys heard
of Abhinav Bindra? No. He's great. He is an air rifle champ. India is actually really good at
the air rifle for some reason that countries just have to think that they're really good at.
So when he won, his training was amazing for it. So he ordered 10,000 specially Chinese-made
air rifle pellets, right? And he weighed every single one of them on the super sensitive scale,
and he looked at each one under a magnifying glass. And if there was any irregularity in it,
it went in the bin. Wow. You see, that's where the admin skills come in, isn't it?
Right. That's data rendering. He's got a spreadsheet with 10,000 pellets in it.
He, Abhinav Bindra, is India's only gold medallist, isn't he? He's the only individual to win a gold
medal. An individual, right. Yeah. So they won, basically, India's won a very large number of
gold medals in hockey. To be fair to them, they did really dominate. 1920 to 1980, they won 11
medals in 12 Olympics in hockey, and eight of them were gold. And the highlight was 1948,
and this really must have felt good, 1948. So immediately after independence for India,
when the final or the silver gold, you know, showdown over the Olympic works, was against
Britain, and they beat Britain 4-0. That must have been fun. Well, they had that golden period
where they were winning golds. It was 1928, 1932, 1936. They won the golds, and they had this one
amazing guy called Richard Allen, who was the goalkeeper for the team. And in that time,
in those three Olympics, he only conceded three goals. One of them was in 1932, when they were
playing in LA, they beat America, they beat the USA 24-1. And the only reason they scored the goal
was because Richard Allen was off field, signing autographs for Fads. No. He just sort of went
off to site. Yeah, and that's the only time that they got a goal. I would say that's bad goalkeeping.
That's amazing. At the 1948 one, the hockey team, when they won, would have got their gold medals,
but no ribbons, because this was the austerity Olympics. So this was held in Britain and was,
you know, rationing was still happening. Everyone was bit poor. There was that whole war thing that
just happened. And so as the austerity Olympics, medals were given without ribbons. I can't believe
that they made the saving on the ribbon. I can't believe they looked at the big gold medal and
ribbon. But you can't just give people a ribbon. So this rule in India, they've changed it slightly
this year. So there's more sports that you can do, which will allow you to get your government job.
So if you are in the tug of war, you can get it now. If you play roll ball, or if you play Malakamb,
so those are the three main new sports that have come in. Two of them are traditional,
well, two of them are Indian sports. Roll ball isn't traditional Indian. That was invented quite
recently. And that's kind of, it's like basketball on roller skates. And Malakamb is a traditional
Indian sport. And there was a Malakamb team who have already got Olympic medals. So Malakamb is
a sport where you get a big, huge pole and you have to balance on top of it while doing yoga moves.
Okay. So this is a really awesome sport in India. And in 1936, there was a Malakamba group who went
to Germany and they showed off their skills. And Adolf Hitler was so impressed that he gave them
all Olympic medals. Wow. I read a tiny bit about Malakamb. Is it true that the pole in Malakamb
represents the phallus of Hanuman, the Hindu monkey god? And did Hitler know that when he
gave out these medals? I think probably. Yeah. I do know you have to lubricate it before you get on
it. So you don't get any wood burns. Wow. That's fair. But a lubricated pole would not be a very
stable slip, wouldn't you? That's the sport, Dan. Yeah. Right. There's a different levels of
lubrications, I suppose. You can have like just covered in butter or you can have it just slightly
smooth so you don't like get any splinters. And I think it's closer to the second one.
Is it? Are they doing the yoga moves on top of the pole? Yeah, they're kind of balancing. So I
imagine a yoga move where you're on one foot and then your other foot is kind of wrapped around your
head or something. Well, you're doing that, but your foot on the ground isn't on the ground. It's
on top of a massive pole. And is there, on the top of the pole, is there a little platform you
can squeeze your foot on? Or is it just the end of a pole? It's the end of a pole. But it's kind of...
That's very difficult. Well, that's the least sport for you.
Again, I think probably easier to just do the exam to get into the government job.
I'll stick to data entry. It feels like it's a time with the pole vault that they should be able
to do. As in you start doing the pole vault, but of the way on when you get right to the top, you
just stay there. Oh, you're downward dogged. Yeah. That occasionally does happen with pole vault,
where they kind of get to the top and they run out of momentum. And they almost... It looks like
they're just going to stay there. And then what happens is the weight of the person kind of bends
the pole down and they get sprung off like a cartoon. That does happen on occasions.
They never get stuck at the top. That's funny. Eventually, the Olympics just goes home.
Okay, it's time for fact number two. And that is my fact. My fact this week is that the photo of
the Wright Brothers first flight was taken by a man who had never used a camera before.
So we're lucky it's not just a picture of someone's feet.
Lucky he didn't have it on selfie mode or something.
It's his first ever photo.
His first ever photo? I read that he'd never seen a camera before.
Yeah, exactly. Like every... Imagine the day for that guy, he's seeing a camera,
he's seeing a photo, a plane's flying. This is a big day. This is magic. Yeah. So this is a guy
called John T. Daniels. And he was working at the life-saving station at Kill Devil's Hill,
which is where the first flight took place on December 17th, 1903. And he was positioned with
the camera by the Wright Brothers, who were obsessed with cameras. They told him everything
he needed to do. And there's really a lot of risk when you think about it as well, because
they needed to position the camera at a place where they believed the plane was going to take
off, having never took off before on a plane. They needed to tell him the exact moment for him to
press this button that would allow them to capture the perfect shot. And they were giving it to a
man who, as we said, not only had not seen a camera before, but was about to witness flight,
man-powered flight. And so there was a genuine moment where he almost forgot to press it,
because he was so in awe of the historical thing that he was seeing. And at the last second kind
of shook himself and took the photo. And by some insane magic, we have the perfect shot. It
developed perfectly. It caught it perfectly in flight. And it's an amazing photo.
It's a cool thing to reflect. Actually, when you look at that picture, which I guess people have
probably seen before, to think how unlikely that was. So that was actually going to work. I mean,
how did they pick the exact spot? Because you can't swivel it around, can you?
Exactly. I don't think they had a turn. Even if they did, the guy wouldn't have known what to do.
And from the account of it, he was also that day involved in the first-ever plane crash.
Because after they landed it, after their flight, it blew away. Because it was a
really light. It was basically a glider with a little bit of an engine. And he got tangled up in
it. He tried to grab it as it blew away, just tried to stop it from blowing away. And he got
sort of caught up in it and had to be helped out. And he was injured.
Yeah. When he flipped over, he was holding onto a strut. And all the others let go, but he desperately
didn't want this thing to break. And so he flipped over with it. And he was a bit mangled, but he was
fine. But they let him keep the strut that he was holding onto, which he kept forever for the rest
of his life. And he would carry it round with him. And every time he told this story, this amazing
story of being the first person to be in a plane crash, he would take out a pen knife.
And as he was telling it, he would shave off a little bit of the strut and he would give it to
the person he was telling the story to. Yeah. You've got to limit the number of times you
tell that story. Towards the end of your life. I'm really sorry. I can't tell it today. I've
just got a bit of sawdust left, to be honest. Oh, just find another piece of wood.
Exactly. It must be like the crucifixion, you know, the true cross.
Yeah, relics. There's a billion Wright brothers planes worth of strut shavings out there now.
But you say so, he thought he was witnessing this incredible historic moment,
which he did. And I think there were sort of four or five people there who did think that.
But I hadn't quite realized that the rest of the world, A thought it was nothing,
what happened, and B didn't believe it. So they were completely ignored by the press for five years
after 1903, that first flight. Newspapers and journalists just didn't believe them. They told
newspapers on the day that this is what they were trying to do. And they basically thought these
guys were crazy crackpots. It's such a slam to say not only did nothing happen, we don't even
believe that nothing happened. I know. I know. Quite nicely, the only paper that did report on them
in that on that first day was a paper called the Virginia pilot by chance. But the way they got the
story was the Wright brothers once they'd achieved flight, they telegraphed their families to be like,
"Hey, mum, hey dad, we've flown." And so the telegraph operator said, "Oh, couldn't help but
notice that message you just let me give you a mum and dad. Do you mind if I tell the press?"
And they said, "No, don't want you to tell the press because they wanted the press in Ohio where
they were from to get the story first." And the telegraph operator ignored that, told the Virginia
pilot, but Virginia pilot knew nothing about it. So they completely made up what had happened.
And so they had them flying for sort of three miles. You know, I think we've said before,
they only flew for about 100 feet, 120 feet. They were like, they flew for three miles. They
were 60 foot in the air when actually they were 12 foot above the ground or something.
They said Wilbur was flying the plane when it was Orville. And so the first account of the
Wright brothers flight was total fiction from the Virginia pilot. I thought it was in a B magazine
that they were first reported in. It was Gleanings and B culture. So that I think those are the
later, because they kept flying. I don't know if you guys know that, but they actually did more
flights after their first ones. I'd say quit while you're ahead.
But they were doing these flights. Oh, where exactly was it? I can't remember if it was
still a killed one. In Dayton, though. In Dayton. Okay, yeah. And this was in 1904 and 1905 when
they were making flights up to 40 minutes long and nobody paid any attention. It was amazing.
I mean, it doesn't. But this guy, Amos Ives Root, he had kind of heard about it and he saw them flying
because they were out in the sticks. They weren't near a major population centre.
And he wrote to Scientific American and Scientific American didn't reply.
So he wrote it in Gleanings and B culture along articles, which are things like
beekeeping in the Southwest and midwinter flights of cellar bees. And it's just mixed in with that.
Do you think they got complaint letters from bee fans saying, I couldn't really see what
relevance your article about the first ever powered flight had? Amos Ives Root was so cool.
So he owned the first ever bicycle in Ohio. That makes him cool.
Definitely. Yeah, he was friends with them, wasn't he? And he had, I think he just had his own kind
of comment page in Gleanings and B culture where he was allowed to write about whatever he wanted,
even if it wasn't about bees. That's so cool. The first lot, what was the hill called, Dan?
It was called Kill Devil Hill. So Kill Devil Hill. And that was in Kitty Hawk, wasn't it?
That's where they did it. And the reason that they went there is Wilbur. Well, when you're flying,
you need like some wind coming straight towards you. It helps you to take off right.
And he wanted to find out where the best place in the US to go for that was. So he wrote to the
US Weather Bureau who sent him data on the wind velocity in more than 100 places around America.
And he settled on this place where he knew there was a hill. He knew that they had really good,
steady wind always coming in their favor. And then he went to Kitty Hawk because it was just
like a bit of nothing kind of marsh, not marsh ground, but kind of wilderness ground. There
was nothing there. There was like 50 households. They were all descended from sailors who'd been
shipwrecked there over the years. So they were all like it was like a sailing community.
And the richest person that lived in that town was a guy called Doc Cogswell. And he was the
richest because his brother owed him $15,000. That's the worst kind of wealth. I'm broke,
but I'm owed it. It sounds miserable when their conditions, when they were living there, because
they had to dig for water. They had to catch their own fish. One of them said that there
were so many mosquitoes, they almost darkened the sun. I know, it just sounds like really
unpleasant living conditions, but they went out there for weeks and weeks on end.
Yeah, only it's got such an ominous name. If I were trying to fly for the first time ever,
I would ask not to fly on a place called Kill Devil. I don't want either of those words
in the place I'm attempting to fly.
And it was a thing that people not only didn't believe it, but they didn't think it was possible
that we could fly. And there's a few, you got some famous quotes from that period before they
went up of people saying this will never happen. There was one bishop who was asked if he thought
that flying would ever happen. And he said, what a nonsensical idea, flight is reserved for the
birds and the angels. And that bishop was called Bishop Wright. And that was the father of the
brothers. Yeah, he absolutely thought there was no way. And once they did it, and after the years
of them doing it, he actually loved it. He used to go up with the brothers separately. He had a
rule they couldn't fly together. He didn't want to lose them both in a crash, but he would fly
with one of them and he'd go higher, higher, get me higher. I think he went up just once, didn't
he? It was the one day he allowed the brothers to fly together in 1910. It was that day when he
did that. They didn't all go up in the same plane though, because that would have been really
all eggs in one basket. You just got mum left. Not the bishop. But it wouldn't have been just mum
left because there were two other Wright brothers. And the Wright sister. Yes, they had more weird
names. The other brothers were called Ruchlin, Reuchlin and Lauren. And they just worked as
bookkeepers and they appear to have had no interest in flight. Whereas the Wright sister
is the reason that we kind of accept the Wright brothers as the first flyers today because
the Smithsonian, they thought that the first person to fly was a guy called Samuel Langley,
which he did in 1903, nine days before the Wright brothers. But what he actually did was fly his
plane for about maybe about half a meter before it smashed straight into a lake or something.
But they said they didn't believe the Wright brothers at all. And so they decided that this
guy Langley was the first person. But then for years and years, Catherine Wright, who was the
sister, it was her life's job to try and make sure that people believed that the Wright brothers
were the first people to do it. And she was super famous in her day. Wasn't she Catherine Wright?
Yeah, it was pretty much the three of them who were equally famous, it seemed, because the Wright
brothers were bad with the press. I think they were not good media personalities. They were very
shy, whereas Catherine Wright was very gregarious. And so she was like the front facing Wright.
And so she met the King of Spain and the Prince of Prussia and spoke with them at events.
She got the French lesion donner, which they gave the Wright brothers and Catherine at the
same time, the highest order of merit you can get in France. And yeah, she was great.
And she was the first woman ever to attend the Aero Club de France, because basically when they
went to France, which was when they became massive really, because in America, they were kind of
ignored, especially they tried to sell the plane to the military and the military just
weren't having it. So they said, fuck, it will go to France instead. But the French, they love kind
of aerospace. They loved the balloons. They loved their new gliders, things like that. And so when
they saw the Wright brothers, they absolutely loved it. And Catherine was the main face for that.
Very cool. She had kind of a sad end. So they were incredibly close. And they seemed to have had a
pact, Wilbur, Orville and Catherine, that none of them would ever marry. I think we think that's
what happened. And they made this pact very, very early on. And she stuck to it. She was incredibly
close to Orville. So Wilbur died in 1912, I think, but Orville, a long time, very close to him. But
eventually, 1926, age 51, she decided she wanted to marry her childhood sweetheart. And Orville
completely stopped speaking to her. That is mean. That is harsh. Very harsh. Childhood sweetheart.
If you've waited about 45 years to marry someone. It is harsh because they seem to have had that
pact where none of them will marry. But for Orville and Wilbur, it seemed to be quite an easy thing
to keep. Because they were particularly good with the press, but they just weren't good in social
situations at all. Were they? Whereas like Catherine, she was just everywhere. She was...
So were the two brothers just not sort of romantic people at all? And they've got this mega babe
sister. But they keep saying, no, no, no, we made a pact when we were all nine. Nobody will ever
get married. The brothers, they lived together, worked together, ate together. And they even
shared a joint bank account, Orville and Wilbur. Really? So yeah, it was kind of easy. And then
Catherine went on to become a suffragist, didn't she? And also the vicar went on the march with her.
Not the vicar. What was he called? The bishop. The bishop. Yeah, the bishop, sorry. And the bishop
went on the march with her. So he kind of... And that was when he was in his 80s. So he was kind
of like joining in with all of the kids stuff when he got a bit older. That's really fun.
He really embraces kids hobbies. What an amazing 80s he must have had just being a bishop your whole
life. And then you get to go on a plane, you get to go on a march. That's really cool. That thing
about how they only became successful when they got to Paris. So in Paris, Wilbur was the one who
went to Paris and Orville stayed in the USA. And Wilbur was a bit more of a showman. He was
better with the press than Orville really was quite reclusive and shy. Wilbur was put up in the
Hotel Maurice. Have you heard of this place? No. Oh my God, it's amazing. I got in a complete
distraction about this amazing hotel he was put up in. So it's very, very classy. He still exists
today. The lift was a copy of Mary Antoinette's sedan chair. That's how sort of lush this hotel was.
Everyone has stayed there. Awesome Wells, Rudyard Kipling, Picasso's wedding meal was there.
Salvador Dali stayed for one month every year. And he once ordered a flock of sheep to be delivered
to his room so he could fire his pistol at them. Blanks, it was blanks. Even so, if I were at the
hotel reception and someone asked for that and told me why they wanted it, I think I wouldn't do it.
I'd at least call my manager and say I'm not comfortable doing this. He might have asked,
he might have given you the other task, which was he asked staff to go to the Toulierie Garden and
catch flies for him for five francs per fly. When I used to work in a hotel, they used to say to you
you have to say yes to everything, basically. Unless it's illegal or immoral or whatever,
if they ask you for something, you always immediately have to say, yes, I can do that,
but it might cost a lot of money. You know, you have to agree to everything.
Wow. And just hope Dali doesn't check in.
Oh, you see the handlebar mustache coming around the corner. Oh, here we go, okay.
Just quick, hide the clocks.
There's one other thing about this hotel, which is that it's where the decision was made not to
blow up Paris. So in the war, Hitler really kind of went off the deep end towards the end, I would
say. And he, as the retreat was being sounded, he ordered lots of key bits of Paris, you know,
the Louvre, Eiffel Tower, the bridges over the Seine. He ordered them to be wired up with explosives,
which they were. And General von Choltitz or Koltitz was in the hotel. And it's there that
he made the decision. He was either persuaded, we think there are various different versions of
events, or he was trying to save his own skin. And that's the hotel where he said, actually,
maybe there's a lot. Let's not blow up the most beautiful city in Europe. Let's just leave.
That is interesting. But there is one other thing about the Hotel Maurice that you might be
interested in, Andy, because we have mentioned it before quite recently. And that is because they
had 148 pneumatic clocks in the hotel, one in each room that were attached to that air system in Paris.
Of course. Oh, I'd forgotten that. That's so cool. Of course they did.
I really hope that when Darlie did room service, he would save the crazy request
right to the edge so that the person would think they were getting away with it.
What can I get you, Mr. Darlie? It's just eggs Benedict this morning.
An orange juice, please. And is that it? One more thing. 7000 sheep.
And a gun.
Okay, it's time for fact number three, and that is James.
Okay, my fact this week is that on the French island of Ile-de-Raye, the donkeys wear trousers.
Sounds like the start of a kid's book, doesn't it?
Do they wear V trousers? What do you mean? Like, do they wear the trousers?
Oh, I see. As in are they in charge? Well, I would say with a donkey, basically the donkey always
wears the trousers, don't they? They don't do what you tell them to. Very wise. Not really.
These are originally working donkeys on this island. They used to work in the salt marshes,
and in the salt marshes, there are lots of mosquitoes, maybe not enough to block out the sun,
but there's definitely a lot of them. And so to stop their legs from getting bitten,
these particular donkeys, their owners would put little kind of trousers on, and they look a bit
like, you know, really old fashioned pajama bottoms, which they would tie around the bottom part of
their legs, and their butt is still exposed. So it's like pajama bottoms with a flap allowing
your buttocks to kind of hang out. And so these days, they still wear the trousers, even though
they don't work in the salt marshes, but they just give rides to children around the local park,
which no matter what you think about donkeys giving children rides, whether that's fair play or not,
definitely better than working in the salt marshes. Donkeys around the world, they do seem to have a
very two track career path. Either it's horrible backbreaking work, and they get really mistreated
all over the world, or it's working at the seaside, taking the children out for a bit.
They are quite, these ones are amazingly big, aren't they? Before you start feeling too sorry
for them having children on their back, I didn't realise a donkey could even qualify as a donkey
at this size. So the Baudet de Poitou is what they're called, I think. There can be 16 hands,
which is, that's like a big horse. That's a horse that you feel really high up when you're sitting
on it. 16 hands is a big horse. I think I might have met some of these donkeys. Because they have
them in the New Forest. Do they? Yeah, they do. They have a few of them in the New Forest. Was it
really fluffy? Like they're quite fluffy. They've got long shaggy hair, like a shaggy. It was very
shaggy. We met one right up close, although it wasn't 16 hands high, so maybe it was a younger one.
And presumably without the trousers on. It had no trousers on. Not by the time.
No, don't go there. That's really cool, because they're very rare. You've seen an endangered
species there. I may have just seen a normal donkey. I already regret. You may have seen a sheep.
It's possible. But they're less rare than they used to be, aren't they?
Yeah. They went really, really rare in the 70s and 80s, so much so that there were only a dozen
or so of them left that could reproduce. But now, thanks to some kind of bits of conservation,
there's a lot more of them in France, and they're starting to send them to other places like the
New Forest, I assume. New Forest, yeah. I think there's about a thousand, isn't there? Maybe just
under a thousand in the world. And you should look them up. They do look bizarre. They look a bit like,
you know, if you have an old English sheepdog, the really shaggy dogs, but they've got quite
a responsible owner who doesn't look after their coat, and it really dreadlocks. It's like that,
isn't it? They've got long dreadlocks. Yeah, exactly. Okay. What would you replace a donkey with on a
beach if you had to? I reckon like maybe seven ducks, and they have like a little carriage
underneath them that the child can sit in and then fly around. You know, I'm thinking Wright
brother's the kind of flight as a feature. I mean, that is nice. I'd go to that beach. That was
dangerous. Health and safety is never going to pass. Sorry, Grant. In 2016, Tall Bay Council
replaced their donkeys with three small trampolines, and there was outrage. Because it wasn't as much
fun. They said this is just not as good for children. All for the donkeys. The donkey keepers were
furious. Do the kids have to haul the trampolines along the beach then? And if you want a ride
along the beach, the trampoline's not going to cut it. Yeah, you could jump from one to the other,
but I think there are only three small trampolines. It's quite a short ride.
It's a quick ride, yeah. It's not getting far. In Iceland, when I went to Iceland,
every small town has like a massive trampoline in the middle of it. It's so weird. Yeah. It's
like, you know how in most, in like towns, you might have a park that kids play on with swings
and slides and stuff. In Iceland, they just had these massive kind of plastic kind of
tarpaulin things that appeared to be filled with air. I don't know what they were filled with,
because I never jumped on them much to my shame. But they were like, yeah,
just everywhere you went, it seemed like kids could play on these bouncy things like bouncy
castles. So a bouncy castle, right? James, is it true? I think I've read that they were initially
for defense as in you'd have to have someone guarding constantly jumping up and down,
landing out for an invading army. Yeah. I was, you know what? At the start of that sentence,
I genuinely thought that you were about to say something real. I saw you going along with it.
So donkeys, eh? Donkeys. Donkeys are cool. The word donkey used to rhyme with monkey.
Monkey. Donkey. It used to be donkey. Yeah. Nice. And it didn't really exist until the start of the
17th century. You would always say ass or ass instead of donkey. So in Shakespeare, there won't
be any donkeys. There'll all be asses. And in the King James Bible. Was it because that was,
it was also rude and an insult that they kind of borderized it? There is one thought that that's
it. The word probably comes from done meaning brown or gray. But I think that's why that the word
donkey became more commonly known is because of the association with bums. Like rooster,
because in America, they didn't want to say cock. So they said rooster instead or man chicken.
Man chicken sounds more rude, I think. Yeah. So the donkeys, donkeys in the UK,
they are big on the beaches, obviously. There are still lots of donkey rides.
So you know the donkey sanctuary, that's the one of the major donkey charities in the UK.
And they have, I'm going to say secret agents who travel around the UK checking up on donkey abuse
and making sure that they're not being badly treated or that their backs aren't being strained
at the beach. And they can turn up and they can, I think they have the power of,
they don't have the power of arrest, but they don't have the powers to take your donkeys away.
So is that if you're doing donkey rides on the beach and someone who looks suspiciously
like an adult but is dressing up as a child and claiming they want a donkey ride turns up,
but has sort of a notepad they're trying to hide, that's probably your guy. So they go undercover.
They're like, I think they do go undercover because if they phone ahead and say,
I'm bringing from the donkey police, then you'll just get out the nice donkey. Whereas if you,
if they turn up incognito, they see you've got your ratty old donkey and you're beating it,
then they'll intervene. Yeah. Wow. Good. Doing great work. It might be quite fun to be a donkey
in the US. If you're specifically, if you're pack borough racing in Colorado, which is a
sort of ancient historic Colorado sport and it's, it's in honor of miners who used to go gold mining
with donkeys. And the rule with pack borough racing is that a donkey can't carry a person,
but a person can carry a donkey needs be in it. And you basically have to run along with your
donkey. Right. Okay. Is it one man, one donkey in the one man on donkey. Okay. How often does
anyone actually carry the donkey though? Cause they're pretty heavy. They're heavy. I did,
I was reading one person's account of his pack borough race where he should have carried the
donkey and didn't. So I think they must be too heavy. This is a guy called Curtis Emory,
who's a veteran borough racer. And he was near, really near the end of a 15 mile race. And suddenly
his donkey called Jackson had to cross a wooden bridge. And as donkeys I want to do, he'd cross
the bridge countless times before suddenly stopped, like not doing that. Stubborn. And he,
and right at the end of the race, and he had to tie Jackson to the bridge, walk into town and return
with a winch equipped Jeep to pull the donkey over the bridge at which point. I don't think he'd
won the race anymore. That's amazing. But yeah, they do, they do freeze donkeys. That's the weird
thing about them. I hadn't probably realized that's what they're doing. Like horses, if you scare them,
bolt, a donkey goes stock still, turns to stone. Yeah. Right. Well, this is why people think that
they are stubborn. And this is some, some study done by the donkey sanctuary in the UK, which is
about people's perception of the donkey, which incidentally found their Britain's second favourite
farm animal. Pretty good. Can we guess the favourite? After cow. Got to be sheep. No one's, no one's said
the right answer yet. Chicken. Man chicken. No, Anna's got it right. It's a horse. It's a horse.
Everyone loves a horse. Anyway, sorry, that's completely irrelevant. Cow doesn't come into the
top two. Yeah. Everyone likes cows. Oh my god. Donkey is number two. Yeah. Because I think if you
are a kid and you have like a set of all your farmyard animals, very rare is there a donkey in
there, is it? Or it's certainly cows and sheep coming first. Are you guys suggesting that this
study conducted on behalf of the donkey sanctuary is in any way improperly done? No. But basically,
you know what? I just want to carry on talking about this. What they've done is they thought,
right, we need to make it seem like it's the best animal, but no one's going to believe us
if we say that the donkey is the most popular farmyard animal. So we're going to have to
put it in second place. That's what they thought, isn't it? It's like when, you know, Kim Jong-un
gets 97.9% in the election. It's like, no one will believe 100%. So I have to go down a bit.
Yeah. But 55% of people do think they're stubborn. And the donkey sanctuary explained that they're
not stubborn. They're just freezing. One in three people think they're affectionate,
and only 18% of people think they are charismatic. Yet they've ranked number two. This doesn't add
up. Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show. And that is Andy. My fact is that in the late 1960s,
the CIA considered assassinating people using lightning. Wow. Is that you bringing back your
old nickname and admitting that you were part of the CIA? I'm very glad that you've mentioned
my old nickname being lightning because I'm determined that it's going to make a comeback.
So this is something, there's a great article on Forbes about this, a journalist called David
Hambling, I found it, and it was a proposal in 1967 that was made seriously, but it wasn't carried out.
But the idea was developed. They thought, well, lightning, lightning is pretty powerful, isn't
it? And if there was a way of directing lightning, then you could get it. They used a real euphemism.
They said it would produce effects favourable to our purposes. I don't think you don't have to
read too much between the lines to realise that that's killing people with lightning, basically.
And yeah, the plan was basically to get a very, very thin wire, which would be only a
fraction of a millimetre wide, but several miles long to effectively drop this from an aircraft or
to use a kind of parachute to keep it up there for a long time. And then if there was a storm
happening above the person you wanted to assassinate, it didn't rely on that. That was the floor in the
plan. The person had to be in a lightning storm. But it wasn't also a flaw. They had to somehow get
this wire next to them. So like you've run over to someone and say, just hold this wire, will you?
Exactly. So it was those were the disadvantages. There were advantages, obviously, like cheap,
because you're not being getting an electricity bill for this. And also it would leave no evidence.
Yeah, but you can always have incredible advantages to something impossible.
That's true. I think we should go ahead with the impossible thing, because the advantages are
just so good. Yeah, that was, I mean, the disadvantages were big as well. Yeah.
I think there's contextual evidence. I think that if Fidel Castro had suddenly been struck by
lightning around that period, it would have been very suspicious. Well, if all the CIA's enemies
suddenly got hit by lightning, I think you can do it twice. I had a good luck to see if all that
there's a list of Wikipedia people who were killed by lightning to see if any of them
were possibly enemies of America at this time. I couldn't find any, I'm afraid.
Few sports, few sports people. One person from the American War who was the guy who invented the
phrase, no taxation without, what's that one? No taxation, yeah. It was, he was killed by lightning.
You're not a true believer in democracy, really, are you? What's the thing that we need for them to
tax us? I don't really give a shit. Yeah, so not unfortunately, yeah. That's a shame.
Was that, so those were the most notable people on the list? There wasn't really anyone,
there was a few people from the, you know, from ancient times who were killed by lightning. Not
that many famous people are killed by lightning, it turns out. It feels like if the CIA had time
travel and this thing, they probably still wouldn't use it. Just think of the advantages of time
travel though. Like, I know it's impossible, but just think of all the advantages.
Let's just do it. Wow, we're doing it. I can see, you know, anti-universal suffrage,
campaigner, politician, not liking the no taxation without representation. I think there's the
kernel of a conspiracy theory there that he was assassinated. Yeah, I was aiming for a conspiracy
theory and I was aiming a bit higher than this, to be honest. I was hoping that an actual, you know,
dictator from the Soviet times had died. Yeah, shame. They came up with some pretty wacky plans,
didn't they? Yeah. There was sort of a massive dump on all of us, which you might remember
in 2017. That's a strange weapon, isn't it? Yeah, a shit bomb. They just came onto me in
the street and said, "Hold this wire." And then before I knew it, I was covered in shit.
In 2017, the CIA sort of dumped 13 million pages of documents on us by putting them online,
and that was 800,000 declassified files, which useful journalists went combed through
and found the insane plans they had. Like, I think it came out that they interviewed Yuri Geller.
That's one of my favourites in the 1970s. They took an interest in spoonbender Yuri Geller,
and according to him when he was asked about it, he said they were afraid that there were people
like him in Russia who, I guess, would pose a threat by bending cutlery in the Soviet Union
somehow. And the way they tested Geller to test his skills was they shut him in a room,
and then the CIA taped to the wall outside his room a picture of something. And the way they
chose the picture was they opened a dictionary, they got a word, so they chose the word, for
instance, "bunch." And then they drew what first came to their mind, a bunch, and then they asked
Yuri on the other side of the wall to draw what he sensed the picture was. Was that a bunch of grapes?
Well, exactly. He drew 24 purple grapes. To be fair, there were 24,
so that's kind of impressive. But basically, the CIA's conclusion was he has demonstrated
his paranormal perceptual ability in a convincing and unambiguous manner, which I would say he
hadn't. You hear about it, you think grapes. But they didn't, did they tell him the word "bunch"?
Yeah, they said "bunch." Oh my goodness. They said, "We've picked the word 'bunch' out of the
dictionary. Draw the first thing that comes to mind." But he did draw 24 grapes, and they
had 24 grapes in their picture. Yeah, but I have to specify, they did this on him dozens of times,
and he only got a few of them right, and that was one of them. I would have drawn some flowers.
Yeah. A bunch of flowers. You know what? I deliberately went with grapes thinking it was
the wrong answer as well, because I was thinking it would be flowers. James, you are the new Yuri
Geller. What's more impressive is if you say that you've picked the word "Jiraffe" and it's
actually a dump truck, and he draws a dump truck, that's, you know... Yeah, that's true.
That's when you know you've got someone dangerous on your hand.
The most impressive thing that Yuri Geller did, and the most controversial, actually, was in Euro
'96. He was flying over Wembley Stadium in a helicopter, I think, and Gary McAllister was
taking a penalty for Scotland, which would have put them level with England in the game.
And if you watch the video back, the ball moves about one inch just before he kicks the ball,
and he misses the penalty, and then Gaza goes up the other end and scores,
and Yuri Geller claims that he made that ball move. No. But he doesn't claim it was the downdraft
of the helicopter. He says it was his magic powers. But I thought you were going to say
he dropped a bent spoon on his head, which is slightly concussive. Weirdly, I read a thing
just this morning about Yuri Geller, which is that in 1974, he was a paternity suit, was filed
against him by a young mum in Sweden. She didn't claim that he was the dad. What she claimed was,
is that his magical bending powers had altered her contraception coil, and it became inoperable,
and she got pregnant as a result. And as a result, he should pay for that, because he's the sort of
pseudo father. Wow, that's a really difficult position to put him in, because on the one hand,
he really wants to admit to having those powers. Well, it was the same with the football thing,
because he wants to claim that he moved this football, but actually he had 11,000 hate letters
from Scottish people after the game, saying, how could you scupper our chances in the European
Championships? Wow. Hey, I read a really cool invention by the CIA, which was used. It's called
the Skyhook. And the Skyhook was basically a way of extracting CIA operatives or anyone that was in
need of help, who was involved in the military in some way, from a location without having to get
on the ground to pick them up. So what it was, is that they would drop a package over to where they
believed the operative was, and the opera, the package had a little description on it. And in
it, they had a helium balloon that would lift the cable 500 foot into the air. And then the operative
would strap themselves to a harness that was connected to the other end of that cable that
went up with the balloon. And they would sit and wait until a very slow flying plane would fly to
where the helium balloon was. And it would hook its nose of the plane around the hook that had been
sent up. And it would carry the guy off into the air and back to safety. That is so cool. I mean,
if you timed it right, you could say, just so you know, all this time, I've been working
for the CIA and then bang, if you get that even slightly wrong, then you're just immediately
arrested. Yeah. Or if a lightning storm comes over and it attaches itself to the 500 foot wire.
He told us he was working for the CIA and then he just exploded. It's really weird.
Yeah, I can see why they didn't go with that. All sorts of any of their mad plans.
I wish someone one day had turned around at the CIA in sort of 1950,
just early on and said, you know, these crazy ideas we keep having that never come to fruition.
You know, the ones that always work, they're the ones where we just shoot someone in the head.
Do that from now on.
There was a guy called Edward Geary Lansdale and he was with the CIA and he was requested
by the president of the Philippines to come over. There was a United States military assistance
group to come up with ideas to fight the communist Hock Balahap, which was a regime that was threatening
the Philippines at the time. And he came up with this idea of convincing them that there were
vampires out in the woods. And the way that he actually tried to convince them that this was
really happening is they captured an enemy soldier and they drained the blood from his body and left
him making it look as if he was trying to flee and got caught by one of these vampires. So when
they found him, they believed the myth was real. It's bizarre. These little tricks.
Who benefits from this? Well, I suppose if you've got an enemy believing that there's
something paranormal going on, as well as an enemy who are physically real,
that just keeps you on edge. It keeps you psychologically all over the shop.
Because do you remember that fact that you and I both found out about in Japan,
they were going to capture some foxes and then paint them in luminous paints and then
release them into the Japanese countryside so that people would see these glowing foxes and
think that they were some mysterious kind of apparition. Yeah, that's right. They would
believe. And there was a thing where one was connected to some balloons. The idea was there's
a floating fox guard. You just see the balloons, wouldn't you? Not at night. And you would just
see the illuminated figure of floating fox. And again, is the idea that you sort of make them
all a bit edgy because there are these scary foxes around. Or that everyone thinks it's a
Pokemon and Chase is after it. Again, there's just always, you know, Killjoy Barry in the
corner of the meeting there going, "Guys, shall we just shoot them in the head again? I'm really
sorry. It's a great idea." But one CIA agent, maybe the most surprising one I found out about
was the Dalai Lama. Oh, yeah. Yeah. In the 1960s, his group was being given over a million dollars
a year by the CIA. And they did deny that the Dalai Lama was on a personal retainer of $180,000
a year. His organization have denied that. But that's because the CIA were paying for
Getty operations against China when China invaded Tibet. And so the Dalai Lama was an important
part of that resistance. So we don't know what his kill total is. Yeah. That's a great series of
novels to be written. The secret CIA adventures of the Dalai Lama. But that's another one where
Barry never gets what he wants. Because if you do shoot the Dalai Lama in the head, he just comes
back. That's so frustrating, isn't it? It's just a pointless assassination. He's on your side. You
wouldn't shoot your own agent. Maybe if you're playing a double bluff, maybe it's the Jason Bourne.
But think of it, the Dalai Lama can get to anybody. There's no one going to refuse a
meeting with the Dalai Lama on security grounds. No, that's true. Yeah. Yeah. True. True. A lot of
the people in the CIA are just massive nerds, right? They're kind of our people. So like when
WikiLeaks exposed a load of stuff that the CIA was doing in its hacking program, we managed to see
a lot of what the tools were called and what the programs were called. And they're all named after
memes or references to pop culture. There's one of them named after a World of Warcraft trading card.
There's another one that's named after some characters from Talladega Nights, which is the
Will Ferrell movie. And there was another document where a guy just listed a load of awesome tool
names he wanted to use at some stage, including awesome McTool name and starving weasel. And
the second of those is a weird Aljankovic song. And they're just like, we've got to invent something
so that we can give it this really nerdy name. Yeah. Yeah. Funny. Somewhere there's a dangerous
sniper CIA agent who's just heard James call him a nerd. What's that red dot that's just appeared
on my head? Actually, that's a myth, isn't it about the red dot because lasers go in a straight
line, whereas bullets don't go in a straight line. So there's no point having a red dot aiming at
someone's head because it's pointing straight from the gun. You need to be aiming slightly above the
person's head if you're a sniper. So in the film, it should be there's a red dot slightly above you
on the wall. Exactly. And that's when you know you're in danger. And if there's a red dot on
your head, you think, oh, I'm sorry. Oh, you don't. You think, oh, shit, they're going to shoot me in
the balls. Okay, that's it. That is all of our facts. Thank you so much for listening. If you
would like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of
this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts. I'm on at Shriverland Andy at Andrew
Hunter M James at James Harkin and Anna. You can email podcast at qi.com. Yep. Or you can go
to our group account, which is at no such thing or our website. No such thing as a fish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there. Links to bits and merchandise are there as well.
We hope you're doing well, everyone. We will be back again next week with another episode.
We will see you then. Goodbye.