(phone ringing)
- Hey, I don't want that.
I want that.
(upbeat music)
- Hi.
- Candy.
- Hello.
- Welcome to Drop of the Line, you too.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome to you.
- My name's Andrew Hunter Murray.
I'm sitting here with Dan Schreiber.
- Hi.
- Anna Tajinsky.
- James has got a week off for good behavior,
but he'll be back in the slava before long.
This is Drop of the Line.
This is the audience feedback show.
We've had quite the fortnight in the inbox.
It's been torrid.
- Yeah.
- It hasn't been tumbling in.
Good ones.
So let's get into it.
Let's get to the emails.
- Let's go.
- Let's start with some getting yourself off the hook,
bashing here from Ashley Smith
from the Washington DC chapter.
Quick correction regarding Twin Astronauts
Mark and Scott Kelly.
In your recent fish segment about twins,
it was stated one of the Kelly twins
had never been to space while the other one had,
rated the question of whether the guy
who hadn't been to space was even really an astronaut.
- Oh, yeah.
- In fact, both twins had been to space
at the time of the twin experiment.
Mark had flown four space shuttle missions
and his brother Scott spent a record breaking
340 consecutive days on the ISS.
- How annoying.
- That was pretty bad of us.
- Can I ask what's her name?
- I don't like the nitpick straight away.
- Ashley Smith?
- Ashley, would you mind re-listening to that episode?
Because I vividly remember,
because we all know, well, as I research the fact
and Dan knows all these astronauts inside out,
that both of them are astronauts who'd been to space.
- So I'm amazed that we claim that.
- Well, you know, the transcript.
- I think there was a catch up about it, yeah.
- 'Cause we were saying at the time,
how annoying it is that they're both astronauts
'cause either one could have gone,
so that's like even more annoying.
- Yeah, I'm pretty sure we got it wrong, Anna.
- You trust her, okay.
- Well, I've listened back to the balance
of the recording of who you're showing.
- Oh, thank you.
- Who made the claim, Andy?
- I think it was me.
- There we go.
- And what did you say about Ashley?
Could she listen back?
- Could she just listen back?
'Cause I was skeptical that we got it wrong.
- Well, we have another email here
from Ashley Smith, just to make one more correction.
This one is personal.
In your most recent episode of Little Fish,
Anna referred to the namesake of Ashley Pond,
which is in Los Alamos and it's named after
someone called Ashley Pond.
Anna referred to the namesake as she.
Ashley Pond was, in fact, a he, as am I.
We men, so you've misgendered Ashley,
and down to his credentials.
We men called Ashley are a dying breed, I admit,
but though we are a dying breed,
we are also a proud breed.
(laughing)
- So that's twice.
- This is awkward.
- I've disturbed a proud breed.
- I know.
- I've never poked a hedge and a angry badger's come out.
- I feel compelled to speak up for my tribe
as we slide inevitably towards extinction.
- Well, we haven't Ashley connected with fish,
just so this Ashley knows.
(laughing)
- I can't believe you're wondering who that is.
- Oh yeah, as well.
- I don't even know if you shortened it.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Ash Gardiner, the co-composer
and singer of our theme tune.
- Is he Ashley?
- Yeah, didn't know that.
- Yeah.
- So you've got a shortened it to Ash.
- It's like Lindsay, an America,
Lindsay is always a bloke, isn't it?
But it's very weird to us.
- Lindsay Hoyle, the speaker of the House of Parliament,
is a bloke.
- Is a bloke indeed?
Yes, that's a good point, so it shouldn't be weird.
- Lindsay Buckingham, is that the Fleetwood Mac player?
Could be, British or American?
- Couldn't say.
- I feel like you've opened a real kind of worms here,
and you're expecting us to mop up all the worms.
Lindsay, you've just sent Lindsay Buckingham,
that a person, British or American, male or female?
- I don't know.
- Go, I'm leaving.
- I've never heard the second part of opening a can of worms
that you're leaving someone to mop up all the worms
that are down at the ground.
- Yeah. - Very cool.
- I don't think you've mop worms, you see?
- Yeah, very odd choice.
- Sweep them up?
- So I think you'd sweep, yeah.
- Probably collect them, because sometimes,
they've got a grip, don't they?
The brush would go over them.
- Yeah.
- And they would just hang on in the ground.
- Yeah, they would just drag a slimy trail
across the floor.
- Would vacuum worms, would you?
- Certainly not.
- Oh my god, no.
- No, absolutely not.
Unless it led straight to a bird feeder.
- That would be an amazing contraption.
- A vacuum worm.
- Yeah, if you only had nuts and seeds and worms on the floor,
you could create a new kind of hoover.
- Yeah.
- We've got to plow on.
- Okay. - I hesitate to move us on,
because I think this is a very rich seam we've fallen into
before we've got to climb out of the seam.
Let's come now to bonus brim, very exciting.
And you know what that is.
- I've got a lot of this memory.
- Okay. - Go on.
- Gareth Tucker writes,
"I'm sure you've been swammered by people involved
in hairnet auctions."
(laughing)
- But I will add to that list
to someone to give the context, yes.
So you discovered the most ever spent on a hairnet
which was one sold at auction.
We all had a guess of how much it was.
I said 400,000, and I believed that it was Beyoncé's.
Anna said that it was Bruce Willis.
- Bruce Willis. - So funny.
- And you said, "What Bruce Willis?"
was ironic and then we could skip to the issue.
- The reason I'm giving you the details
is while I was away on holiday,
my youngest son Kit discovered that Instagram reel
where we had this conversation.
And for about seven days of my two week holiday,
he watched nothing but that on repeat.
I think he watched about 6,000 times per day.
- 'Cause he was talking about hairnet.
- Yes, yes, three.
- I tell you one thing you did.
He turned to me and went 50 pounds.
(laughing)
And then giggled his ass off.
- And so the whole holiday, any time he wanted it,
he'd say, "Where's Andy?"
(laughing)
And that's how we knew that he needed to watch his video for.
- Oh, wow.
- So that's how I know the details of that so well.
- I think he must have gone in so deeply
into his brain now that he'll know that for life,
but he won't know how he knows it.
- Yeah.
- When he grows up, he'll know
that the most expensive hairnet ever sold at auction.
- And he'll be surprised that not everyone knows it.
'Cause he'll be a business guy.
- He'll be just everyone's.
- Because they were kids.
- Just based knowledge.
- Okay, we'll get Garrett Tucker ads.
- In the mid, sorry, it's such a good email.
In the mid 1990s, I went to Longleet,
which is a kind of Safari Park.
- Okay. - Great Safari Park.
- Okay.
- And there was a Doctor Who auction going on.
We went in.
The first item was a red hairnet worn by Sophie Oldred
in the Curse of Fenric.
I wanted to bid, but I was worried it would go for too much.
To this day, I am gutted.
I didn't bid, as it went for a mere eight pounds.
Not challenging the world record, I'm afraid.
(laughing)
So that's just good bonus information.
- Thank you, Garrett.
- That's what we do this show for.
- That's why always bid, you never know.
- Right, we got a blow on.
Jack Wheatley, I'm really interested
in your response to Jack's email.
You just mentioned the Stapidius muscle, right?
We're talking about the smallest muscles in the human body.
It's in the ear.
It might not be as small, but it's neighbor.
The tense or tympany muscle might be the smallest
that can be voluntarily controlled.
Although only a very small percentage of folks can do this,
and it produces a kind of low rumbling noise when tensed,
I am blessed to be part of this hallowed group,
and I was surprised to learn not everyone can make
their ears rumble.
Are any of you part of this exclusive club?
- I am.
- I can make my ears rumble.
- So do it now.
- Oh, and what are you hearing?
You're hearing a...
- I'm hearing a rumble.
- Oh, so we're not supposed to be able to hear it.
- No!
(laughing)
- It's like the...
- You know.
If people, it would be like on the trade,
it would be very annoying if someone's ears are rumbling.
- Sorry, could you, I've got a fast.
- What would it be, like, 'cause your tummy rumbles
when you're hungry, what's that?
When your, why your ear is rumbling?
- When you're deprived of music?
- Yeah.
- Good chat.
- No wonder yours would be going.
(laughing)
- What the hell, can we just try and do?
I know it's not a good podcast content,
but can we try and do it now for a second?
- Yeah, yeah.
And sorry Andy, give us the instructions again.
You just sort of clench your inner ears?
- Yep.
- You should be able to hear the rumbling noise.
- No.
- Stunning.
- I thought everyone could do that.
- That's amazing, wouldn't an amazing revelation
for all the earwax that's out there.
- That's a show.
That's a show.
- It's what?
- What is...
(laughing)
- What's the problem, man?
- Wendy Lane of New Zealand Rights.
(laughing)
Wendy Lane of New Zealand Rights.
You put a call out for facts about wrinkled bird beaks,
and I knew my time had come.
Basically, O. Taroa, New Zealand,
has the only bird in the world,
which has a laterally curved bill,
which always curves to the right.
It also has a bird with lips.
- Yeah.
- I know, I looked it up and it's real.
There's a bird with lips.
- Like human looking lips.
- I mean, not, not.
- You wouldn't want to kiss it, you know?
It'll be like, it's got rubbery excuse if you did.
(laughing)
- A drunken evening.
It's the wio or blue duck.
It uses its lips to scrape its food off the rocks
among the water it lives in.
- Don't we all?
- It's got soft, rubbery lips.
- Is it on the end of a bee?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Is it instead of a bee?
- Oh, that's on the end of its bee.
- That's so funny.
- It's crazy.
- 'Cause that would look like it had just swallowed
a small human, right?
And the lips were the last thing it was about to take in.
I guess so.
- Yeah, I guess so.
- It's not the first thing I'd assume, actually.
- I think I think I reckon that's a bird with lips.
- That's what I've got lips.
- I think someone said it's not.
- Yeah, oh god, we've just come in my nose to the worst fit.
All right.
I've got a bone to pick with you, Anna.
- Okay.
- I go away for one week, two weeks of little fish.
- Yeah.
- And I tune in, I listen with great eagerness to the show,
which was brilliant, by the way.
It's so nice listening to one you, you know,
you haven't been in, but you just know will be great, right?
- Oh.
- And then towards the end of the show,
Anna pipes up and says, can I just ask
about cafe toilets?
- Oh no, yeah.
- And whether they have specials.
- Oh, good.
So, has someone in touch who works in the sewerage?
- Special sewage for the big turds that are coming down.
- We've had so much correspondence.
- Yes.
Okay, if we've got an answer, is there a special drainage system?
- So the excitement that you just displayed
is what this show was meant to be as a whole concept.
That's why we were here.
- Now we just get these little jams once every episode,
maybe, if we're lucky.
It's baggy now, isn't it?
- It's baggy.
- Do you know why I listened back recently
to the first drop as a line?
- Oh yeah.
- It's 17 minutes long.
- What is it?
- It might have been 12 minutes long.
It was short.
- Right.
- These things swell.
But.
- Too mess.
- Cafe toilets.
- Tell me.
- I'm just going to tell you the full range
and it gets more exciting as we go along, okay?
Van Brenner from the USA, and that's relevant, says,
restaurant toilets rarely clog because they use high pressure,
tankless flush valve systems.
So they use water pressure rather than gravity.
Combined with wider drain pipes,
commercial toilet paper that breaks down easily
and strict maintenance protocols,
they're engineered to withstand heavy repeated usage.
(laughing)
- Heavy and repeated.
- Very nice.
- That's what I'm talking about.
- That's the USA.
Ryan Loughgren is a plumber in Nova Scotia.
(laughing)
Canada.
- Yeah.
- Long time less than the first time writer,
Ryan says they probably don't have special toilets.
They may have bought high pressure toilets
or even pumps that grind everything up.
- How hard are your bees, Ryan?
- But that would be fairly rare most of the time.
- Right.
- Okay, so that's America, Canada, now we come to the UK.
- Okay, okay.
- Jamie Audrey writes,
"I can confirm, for the toilets and customer sinks,
"there is nothing special,
"just normal commercial toilets and standard drains."
The sinks behind the counter,
the sinks behind the counter,
are fitted with sediment traps
to catch the gloopy milk enzymes and ground coffee parts.
'Cause otherwise they'll clog the pipes and block them, right?
And there's a special horrible job of cleaning the trap.
I'm so excited about that one,
because Jamie Audrey writes to us
from Costa Coffee's HQ.
Jamie works in Costa's Global Retail Center of Excellence.
- Oh my god.
- Jamie, and this is what you're spending your time doing.
That's awesome.
- Well, it's like there's a royalty.
- I know, see.
- The Global Retail Center of Excellence.
- Yes.
- Well, I don't deny that they deserve that.
- I love the buzz and is getting off the show now.
- I know, yeah.
- It's like you get back into it, don't you?
- Get into it, get into it.
- What I've taken away from that is I need to start
shitting in the sinks.
- That's what I thought as well.
- Do you mean the sinks behind the counter?
- Yeah, right.
- Did I do that?
- Sorry, man.
That's actually, I know it's better at catching the gloop,
but it's not intended.
- I think you're right, I've got a cost of loyalty card.
We know that someone at HQ.
(laughing)
- Talk to Jamie, you know, if you don't mind.
- Oh, yeah.
Yeah, but I'm so excited about that
'cause I wrote a lot of my most recent book in the costa.
And the costa card is actually a key plot point.
- Did it?
- Yeah.
- I can verify that that is correct.
- Wow.
- Oh, I'd love that card in the book.
- Yeah.
- What an extraordinary product placement.
That was for some.
- I thought, both for costa and you.
Why do you think I subtly seeded?
Even when not on the show, Anna to mention cafe toilets.
I thought this all year, Jamie Audrian
from the Global Retail Center of Excellence.
- This is an interesting email
from an anonymous correspondent.
- Oh, juicy.
- I'm sure many hundreds of thousands of people
were risen in with this.
But according to a 2016 study,
cats who drink filtered water as opposed to tap water
have an 87% lower chance of developing kidney disease.
- Hmm, well.
- This is clear vindication for James,
giving his cat Evian.
And I think you all owe him a big apology.
- Huge.
- Can I also take this opportunity to say,
I don't care for the section naming section.
And I think the things that are named after things
that you wouldn't think about has run its course now.
Also, can I say, I am sad that James is not appearing
on this week's show.
And I look forward to his return next week.
- Hi, honestly.
- If it did, this is from James.
- Hi, my name is James.
- Who did it from?
- Busted and not keep me anonymous, it said.
I didn't check the email address.
But I suspect I know what it would go.
That's cheating.
You're not allowed to offer free hits into the tent.
You're not allowed to piss into the tent, right?
- Is that pissing into the tent?
- Is that another phrase?
- It's a phrase.
- Yeah, don't.
- You're out of the tent pissing in.
- Yeah, yeah.
We need this guy inside the tent pissing out,
not outside the tent pissing in.
Basically, the idea is this guy's got a lot of pissed to give.
- That's so nice.
- Have you ever heard that?
- No, but because I've, I've sat in a tent
thinking I was shitting out.
So that's, I didn't realize that that was an actual phrase.
Anyway, okay, I think we're going to come to that.
- I don't know what the metaphor is.
- What's the metaphor of shitting in the tent?
'Cause outside the tent pissing in is, yeah, don't.
- This guy outside the organization.
But like, yeah, James is outside the tent this week.
- Yeah.
- But he's now pissing in.
- And you're inside this week shitting, apparently.
- You thought you were pulling outside the tent,
but you were actually peering into the tent.
- Yeah, I mean, we don't need to go into,
yeah, I think let's not really hide that.
- We've got, we've got, sorry, what do you mean?
- Interestingly though, I sat on our friend Ashley.
So that's just a call back to that.
- That's horrible.
- It was by mistake.
- It's all, all is forgiven apparently.
(laughing)
Anyway, so how does, how does anonymous end this email?
- Clearly not James, not James.
I don't know, I did, you all sense me.
- No, there's no sign of it.
- There's no sign of it.
- Everard Dick Beale.
- No, no, no.
James, you've been seen and heard.
- Yeah.
- Okay, I've got some brilliant news from Dale Myers.
Hello, I'm quite late on this, but I'm sure
that Dan would be delighted to know,
even though he recently lamented that the poker player,
Dan Schreiber, was the day facto Dan Schreiber
according to Wikipedia, since July 2023,
Dan has in fact been the most important Dan Schreiber
according to Wikipedia.
- How?
- And I've checked, you are.
- How do you check?
- We just go to the Dan Schreiber page.
You go to your page and it's Dan Schreiber
and then there are the other.
- Oh really?
- Mine are Dan Schreiber's, but you are the Dan Schreiber.
- Oh, interesting.
- And Dale includes a link to the discussion of the change,
which I've had a look at, and it's reneboring.
(laughing)
- That's wonderful.
- No, people are discussing why you just don't
place that down.
There are a lot of people in the world aren't there?
- Right, oh my goodness.
- What a polite way of saying anything.
- There are a lot of people in the world aren't there?
- Great, thank you Dale.
- Yeah.
- And Louis has another email in this section.
I may have stumbled across an accidental record
that fish has.
- Oh cool.
- I've been a big fan for a number of years
and was recently diving into the archive.
In episode 15, Dan welcomes us to season two
of no such thing as a fish.
Implying that the first season was the original 14 episodes
and maybe international fact-ball.
That's a World Cup thing we did, many series.
Regardless, it now means that every canonical episode
fish since episode 15 is in season two.
As Dan has never stated that this finished
all started season three.
With 636 episodes to date, that means fish season two
is 621 episodes, the most of any individual season
that I can find.
- Oh, cool, isn't it?
- Yeah, it's great.
- To soap operas don't do seasons today or series.
They don't.
There are more episodes of these tenders,
but that's the completely different way.
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
Oh, how exciting.
- That is cool, 'cause yeah, I know people have pointed out
before that we were still on season two.
- Yeah.
- You haven't thought about that.
- What's in a good season?
'Cause I think it's a fine one.
(laughing)
- I don't know why.
- It's got a bit weird now.
- Yeah, we'll bring it to a close soon.
- I like that you never know how it will end.
You know when friends use to release seasons
and you know when the like 21 and 22
was coming up and that would be the finale.
But you guys will never know which fish
is gonna be the massive finale.
- Yeah.
- Whether we all shag each other
or someone gets pregnant from someone else's mum
or whatever it is that happens, close it off.
- And it today.
(laughing)
- If that's what we're saying.
- That's exciting.
- And if you'd like to mess on
which member of the four of us is gonna get pregnant.
(laughing)
- Yeah, no, you're right, you're right.
Like we operate in a kind of flux state
of low and nose what's going on.
- Yeah.
- No one knows, you know, is this any good?
We don't know.
- No, I mean, I think no.
- No, I think we know that, yeah.
- Okay, new section.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- And this is also this week's Radio Clan.
- So it's a subsection.
- So it's in a Radio Clan.
- Okay.
- The section is called, I need a better name for it.
- Yeah.
- Who is talking?
- Oh, okay.
Who is talking?
Like what?
- Blowing bubbles.
- Yeah.
- Bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble.
- That's not bad.
Bubble, bubble.
- Yeah.
- Toilet and trouble.
- Fish lips.
- Okay, it's cool.
- Flopping fish lips.
- This section is called fish.
(laughing)
- This is what we call a holding title.
- Holding title is even worse.
(laughing)
This section is called holding title, bullshit.
- No, okay, Isaac Wood writes in,
listening to the drop of the line
where some listeners were confusing
Dan and Andy for each other,
despite you having different accents.
I used to have the same problem when I started listening,
but now can mostly tell the difference.
I think the confusion is down to a few factors.
One, your voices seem reasonably close
in non-accent-related features.
- Hmm, I agree.
- Oh, that's just a great pitch.
- Over the course of a show,
Dan's accent might wonder
between Sydney, London and over the Atlantic,
but for short interjections,
he can sound a lot like Andy.
Whereas Andy, putting on an Aussie accent
as part of a joke or doing his spooky mystery voice,
is more Dan and Jason.
(laughing)
And of course, when either of you
raise pitch defensively upon having a fact questioned,
that's near indistinguishable.
- Oh.
- Top tip, if you're Australian,
listen for the one that sounds most familiar.
Otherwise, try and match interests and personalities
to what's being said.
EG Moss versus cryptids,
or a personal anecdote versus
I saw Andrew Lloyd Weber at the park.
(laughing)
- Just one of my anecdotes.
- I actually, so the last drop of the line
is up on the Patreon,
and you can comment underneath those videos, right?
And so someone has also tackled this Andy
and worked out another way to tell us a part.
They left it in the comments.
So, this is from Phoebe.
- Okay, sure.
- I can tell the voices apart,
but I'll admit, when I started to listen,
I matched the voices slash names to the wrong faces.
Anyway, I tell Dan and Andy apart now,
because Andy always sounds like he thinks he's in danger,
and instead of fight a flight, he is chosen flail.
So that's just another way, isn't it?
- Yes, just another way.
- Yeah, completely non-judgmental.
- We all need our ways,
and that's just another one.
- Wow.
- So we could use that in the section title somehow.
- I'm actually gonna go into the inbox now,
because there's an email I forgot to put in here,
and I think it's relevant.
- Okay.
- We've had a load of people writing and saying,
they just cannot tell the difference between us.
Right, here we go.
Callum Boland sent in a very funny email
about the Chow Chack Wing Museum,
which everyone thinks is like a wing of a museum.
Actually, it's named after someone called Chow Chack Wing.
Brilliant.
The absolute confusion this has caused over the years
makes me believe it as a primary
for Dan's list of assumed names.
- Ah.
- How dare you, Callum Boland.
- Oh, dear.
- Anyway, so we've had loads of stuff like this.
I mean, lots.
- Are you being trolled?
- No, I don't think I am.
- Okay.
- Anyway, yeah, David Ford,
two more for Dan's collection.
- Yeah.
- What is going on?
- Who is talking?
- That's the name of the section.
Right, enemy of the podcast corner now.
- Ooh.
- Okay.
- Lachy Falkena Boog.
Falkena Boog.
- Amazing.
- What a name.
- Great name.
- Yeah, very cool.
- While sitting the medical entry exam in March,
here in Melbourne, Australia,
they're not allowed to test any pre-medical knowledge.
So it's just a general exam to get into med school,
but it's not about medicine.
- Ah, okay.
- Bizarre.
- Cool.
- There was a question asking me to match
the meaning of the provided quote
to the meaning of four other quotes.
One of the possible answers was by none other
than enemy of the podcast.
- Mark Twain.
- Unfortunately, reading through the other options,
the quote from Mark Twain,
"I'm 90% sure was the right answer,
yet I couldn't bring myself to select it."
(laughing)
- You might be saying,
"Well, that's kind of silly to do in a very important exam,
but as any good doctor will tell you,
it's more important to do what's right than what's correct."
I believe, like, they like to dovetail both.
I think, like, the sweet spot is,
(laughing)
"You do what's right and what's correct."
- You're...
(laughing)
- What's the patient's name?
- Mark, too close.
(laughing)
I didn't die.
- He's been hit by a what?
A twain.
(laughing)
I'm not operated on this man.
There's a happy coded to this story.
Anyway, I ended up scoring quite high on the test
and start mencing next year.
- Lovely.
- Brilliant.
- Congratulations.
- Congratulations, Lucky.
- Almost certainly wasn't a Mark Twain quote, as well.
I will say, that's what I would have written on the exam paper.
Take a point.
It won't be Mark Twain.
- How come?
- Just as lots of misattributed Mark Twain.
- I see.
- Everyone says Mark Twain said a lot of things,
and sometimes, you know.
- Yes.
- Mark Twain, Abraham Lincoln, Winston Churchill.
- Yeah.
- There's this cluster of historical blocs
who get a lot of stuff attributed to them.
- I wrote one about in my,
I wrote a book called The Theory of Everything Else,
and there was a misattributed quote to a president
that was in one of the books
of the encyclopedias of presidents,
and it was a Dolly Parton quote instead of the president,
and it got pointed out by an academic,
and that's since been changed, but yeah, right.
- Do you even know what was the quote?
Was it, I've been working nine to five or something.
- Yes, that was it.
- It was just Joleen, Joleen, Joleen.
And I think it was his dying words, apparently,
the president, but.
- May I say it down?
That was absolutely masterful plug for your book.
- Thank you very much.
I mean, I was annoyed I couldn't get a big franchise cafe in there,
but I've got access to the inbox, you know.
Right, know what it's time for now?
It's time for...
- Extreme fish.
- Have I done one of these sunglasses?
- Come down, explosions.
Hot dogs.
Hot dog cannon.
- What's extreme fish?
- Extreme fish.
- Okay, do you have anything on that's a little bit more specific?
- It's fake, the explanation.
- Extreme fish is people listening to fish
while doing extreme things.
- Oh, cool.
- We're still on the hunt for an astronaut,
but we've had quite a few amazing ones recently.
So, Elsa Desmond.
I'm sorry to disappoint Dan.
I haven't listened to fish in space.
However, I did listen to fish while competing
at the Olympics.
- Hey, cool.
- I listened to your podcast between my first and second run
in the Women's Looge event
at the Winter Olympics in Beijing, 22,
as well as at over 50 World Cup events before and since
until I retired earlier this year.
- Wow.
- Cowabunga.
- And Looja, what a legend.
- Yeah.
- Do they help like jazzer up for the slide?
- Yeah. - Questionably.
Well, that's the question.
What is it doing?
Is it giving a mental break and you're just,
it's familiar voices and you're sort of zen-like?
Is it to get a laugh?
Is it to...
- I don't know.
I don't know.
- For tips, you know, we have a lot of useful facts.
- A lot of useful podcasts.
- Yeah, maybe.
- All right, I'm gonna show you guys a video now.
- Okay.
- From Alice Mwandro, your recent chat about volcanoes
reminded me that earlier this year,
I was listening to this podcast while hiking Guatemala's
volcano de Akate Nango and volcano de Fuego.
Fuego was erupting pretty loudly,
regularly interrupting the facts,
but you made great company all the same.
I've attached a video of the view I had
with fish as my soundtrack.
You ready?
(gasps)
- Wow.
- Oh, wow, we are looking at a real volcano.
Often you see a volcano and it's just a big ash cloud,
isn't it?
But there's real flames coming out.
- A crop of volcano.
- That's amazing.
- That cool?
- Not flames.
- Lava with smoke, that's very cool.
- Unbelievable.
- Wow, I've got an extreme fish.
- Have you?
- Yep.
- Very recently, someone was at the third largest
colosseum built by Rome and it's still standing
and was listening to fish in this place.
And it's in Tunisia and it was my son,
my youngest son who was still while we were out and about,
not even taking in this amazing spectacle
was watching Uncle Andy.
- That's so funny that he's in the sight of ancient majesty
and he's watching a clip, an Instagram clip of a podcast
talking about an Ina Sharple's hair next.
- Yeah, giggling his ass off every time we say 50 quid.
- It's the funny 50 quid.
- There are so many unlikely ingredients to that pie
of an anecdote that those are.
- Yeah, it's a good pie.
- Right, good pie.
We're all, nice try.
We've got a few more to go yet.
- Damn it.
(laughing)
- I just got that, yeah, yeah.
- Right, Emma writes in, subject line,
Andy has ruined my life.
- Okay.
- Hey, you and me both Emma.
(laughing)
- Are we still in extreme fish?
- No, we've come out of extreme fish.
- Where are we?
- You'll find out, you'll find out.
I just had the realization that Andy has ruined my life.
I was lying in my hospital bed.
This was nothing to do with me.
I was lying in my hospital bed
after having a benign tumor removed from my salivary gland
when they put me on a drip as my blood pressure
was bottoming out.
This sounds bad, right?
- Yeah.
- In my drugged up, woozy and pained state,
the only thing I could think was,
I wonder if a drip is called a drip
because it slowly drips into you
or is it called a drip
because it was invented by Mr. Steven Drip.
(laughing)
- Fantastic.
- So I googled why is a drip called a drip?
Imagine my surprise, when the result came back,
it comes from African American vernacular English
and originated in hip-hop culture.
- What? - Drip is kind of your stuff,
your cool clothes and stuff, I think.
- So how come it comes from that?
- Well, Emma writes,
probably should have left off the googling
until the fentanyl had worn off.
It turns out that's the wrong definition
and a medical drip is called a drip
because it drips the medication into you drop by a drop.
- That makes no sense.
- Thanks Andy for making me question the origins
of an obviously normal word.
(laughing)
- Imagine if the word drip came from me.
- What?
- Oh God, that was about a drip.
- I know, I know.
I'll just finish off by giving you one or two more
of my absolute favorites, which is from Tristan Shepard.
Oregon is apparently the home of this stuff
'cause we had Wank's Corner, the cafe,
which was named after Richard Wanker, the proprietor.
- Right.
- More entries for all of this stuff.
There's a place called Coffee Brewsters,
which is a coffee shop founded by Travis and Susie Brewster
and also a Fatt Schlag sausage.
- Fatt Schlag.
- Nice.
- Founded by Alan Schlag and one final just lovely email
from Gabriel, Gabriel Farrah and his mum.
Gabriel is 12 years old and his mum writes,
"We started listening to fish soon after he was born."
So, apart from the first few episodes,
he's listened to all of them.
His sister Lillie is 10.
She was forced to listen on our drive since birth
though she did recently admit she started thinking
the show was funny when she turned nine.
Welcome Lillie.
(laughing)
- Nine years of toil, Paul Lillie.
- Good on ya.
- Oh, anyway, here is Gabe's fact.
There's a warhammer 40,000.
You know, that's like futuristic toy soldier things.
There's a famous tank called the Land Raider
and a vehicle called the Land Speeder.
And they are named, not because they travel over land,
they're named after the legendary tech archaeologist
who discovered their blueprints, Arkham Land.
That's Gabriel's fact.
- That's very good.
- I used to like warhammer too.
- Great fact, he used to play Warhammer.
- Yeah, big time.
- Wow.
- But don't let that push you off, Gabriel.
- I know you're shocked, Dan.
You thought this guy was out, you know,
beating up nerds and kissing girls, probably.
- Whoa.
- Playing sports, smashing my neighbor's mailboxes
with a baseball bat from an open top car.
- That's not what the cool kids did.
- Andy grew up in 1950s of America.
Sitting at the milkshake bar.
- Sit at the milkshake bar with your best girl.
- Where are the sports jacket?
- Wimbledon is rougher than I thought.
- Making quarterback.
(all laughing)
- Yeah.
- Being prom king.
Yeah.
Yeah, but actually I was playing Warhammer mostly by myself.
- We should have prom king as a sort of award on here.
- Prom king.
- Yeah.
- That's good, prom king.
- What is it?
- No, hang on.
- No, you can't just, I get in trouble all the time
to say stuff and they're not defining it.
What's the prom king?
- The coolest kid on the podcast.
- Yeah.
- That week.
- That's great.
- Prom king.
- I always need to win round.
- You should be on Dragon's 10.
(all laughing)
- I'll invest.
I don't tell me all the product is I don't want to know.
But I'm offering you five million pounds
for no percent of your company.
(all laughing)
- Done.
- Prom king.
- Prom king and queen.
Like you'd have a prom king and queen.
- How do you qualify?
- I was just the most memorable.
The ones that have really stuck out.
The one, it's like winning an award.
It's just got a fifth based name.
- I, look, it's just the best one.
- Just the best listener.
- It's the best listener of the last three months.
- There we go.
- Prom king.
- All queen.
- Okay.
Okay, I'll get working on it.
(upbeat music)
- If you'd like to put yourself forward
to be the Prom king or queen.
- Wow.
- Then all you have to do is email
podcast@ky.com.
Thank you so much.
All of you for your emails, your complaints,
your clarifications, your corrections,
your abuse.
- No, not your abuse.
Everyone's been lovely.
It's a terrific place to fish in box.
And why not dive in by sending us an email
with your thoughts and corrections
and extra information?
I've done that bit.
- You can't do that.
You can't.
- Andy is doing the wrap-up sign to himself.
Let's know.
- You can't.
- It's a tough place, your head isn't it?
- You're not allowed to get bored of yourself talking.
Come on, Andy.
Bring this home.
So anyway, Dan and Anne.
Dan and Anne.
- Are you all done?
No, but I've been away a long time.
It's okay.
- Dan and Anna.
Would you like to say anything?
A question could be there.
- I'll just say.
- Good.
How does it go?
- Good bye.
- Good.
- And that's it from all of us here on Drop us a Line.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)