[telephone ringing]
You don't want it or who don't want it to be?
[upbeat music]
- Hi!
- Hello, Andy.
- Hey, guys.
Welcome to Drop Is Alive.
Welcome to all of you listening, or watching,
at home, or at your place of work.
- And nothing?
- No, no, Andy has said work or home.
- Oh, is that the only two places you're allowed to be?
- Apparently.
- The other places, a third space, stop,
and resume when you've got time to properly focus
on what's going on.
It's been a great, great couple of weeks in the inbox.
- It's been wriggling the inbox.
- Really?
- Absolutely writhing.
- Yeah. - Not bulging?
- No, no, no.
It's, it's, it's developed, it's got worse than that.
- Oh, it's, it's crawling.
- What's happened?
Why is it changed?
- Well, we've gone fortnightly.
So, you know, people have picked up the pace.
We've got people writing, now people,
a lot more people are sending in facts,
'cause we've lost the fact show, little fish.
- Oh yeah.
- So a lot more people are sending in their facts for that show,
which is great, podcast@QI.com.
If you've got a fact, or a bone to pick,
then send it our way.
- Great.
- Yeah, let's get to those bones now.
- Should we start with a treat?
- Yes, we are.
- Okay, 'cause we always start with the, you know,
maybe a quibble, maybe you've got it wrong,
and there's plenty of that coming out.
- Oh, no.
- Flenty.
- Should we not save the treat for dessert?
- I don't think you'll feel hungry anymore,
once I've read out some of the complaints I've got for you.
- Right.
- No, this is a really exciting thing.
I don't know if you remember.
We've got a bit of correspondence from Jodie,
little while ago.
- Oh, Jodie, yeah, I remember Jodie.
- Yeah, saying we're getting married,
and we're having a heritage rail themed wedding.
- Oh, yeah.
- That's right, Jodie.
- You're our kind of person, Jodie and James.
And they were doing small coal as wedding favors.
(Jodie laughs)
Just did it on my heart, 'cause we said ages ago,
what do they use for coal, on model rowers?
They use small coal.
- Small coal, yeah.
- Anyway, Jodie writes, as promised,
here is the candy coal we handed out as favors at our wedding.
It was a fantastic day.
The wedding went off without a hitch.
- Oh, 'cause your hitch carriages on Twitch are that.
(Jodie laughs)
- Okay.
- And all the guests were absolutely steaming.
That's my little drug.
- How is the train of her dress?
- Oh, yeah, beautiful.
- Oh, very nice.
- Really good, as was her carriage and he railing.
(Jodie laughs)
- Oh my god.
- It doesn't say in her letter.
- Okay.
- Brilliant.
But anyway, look, each of you has a little bag of candy coal.
- Dan, that's for you.
- Wow.
- Oh, no, look at this.
- Thank you.
- A little sack of coal.
Normally, it means you've been a bad boy,
getting a piece of coal.
- Yeah, but this is a mark of favor from Jodie and James.
So thank you so much.
- Okay, so what is this?
- This, I don't know.
- Looks, it doesn't look.
- It's edible.
- It looks like it could be heroin.
She does, actually, she encloses a spoon and a lighter.
And I think, right, here we go.
Oh my god.
- Oh, I love it.
- Just tastes like slightly stale chocolate cake.
(Jodie laughs)
It's been in the box for ages.
- It's got Oreo cookies, Oreo vibe.
It's very Oreo-coated.
Anyway, thank you so much, Jodie and James.
Welcome to Married Life.
- Yeah.
- If you're listening to this and you're married,
you two must send us tribute.
(Jodie laughs)
- No, that's brilliant.
Congratulations, guys.
- Right. - We're wonderful.
- Right, we're off the blocks, but we are on the hook.
- Okay. - Okay, dammit.
A lot of comments have come in about things
we said about the Second World War.
- Oh.
- It's an episode.
- And Alton. - Right.
- And great news.
It's all complaints about stuff.
Ben said nothing about what we said.
We're fine.
- Ben's in trouble.
- Okay.
Ben's in trouble with the people of Canada,
and Australia, and New Zealand, and also India,
for saying the Britain stood alone for a year
in the Second World War.
When, in fact, all of those countries.
- And the wider Commonwealth were very much on team GB
for that spell.
And contributing lots of, you know, stuff, food, supplies,
soldiers, all of that.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So Erin Thomas just wants to point out Canada
was there every step of the way
from the Declaration of War until peace was declared.
Mayor Brown writes, for a man who says he's read
an awful lot of books on World War II,
Ben Elton's egregious declaration that Britain stood alone
for a full year against Germany was patently false.
And Geoffrey Partiger has a little bit of extra spicy stuff
about a lances.
- Oh.
(laughing)
- So that was the fact, was your fact, wasn't it?
- Yeah, we had, the army was still using lances.
- Tell the first World War.
- Yeah, 'til 1927.
Your terrific guest, Ben Elton, expressed his doubts
regarding the use of lances.
But there's also an example of the miracle on the vestula
in the summer of 1920, so socket Elton writes Geoffrey.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- Yep.
There was a place, there's a thing called the miracle
on the vestula, which was the red army against Polish cavalry.
And it was, it was thanks to Polish cavalry with lances.
And in the same campaign, there were 20,000 men
on horseback charging each other with lances couch
at the Battle of Comorov.
So there you go.
So anyway, lances remain useful.
- And Canada also.
- And Canada also, mainly Canada,
but I mean, full credit, full credit to almost everyone involved.
- Yeah.
- Well, I'll cut this up and send it to Ben.
I'm sure he'll be very here.
- The dish is it out.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Yeah, that's a fact check.
Right, now I've got a new section for us.
- Oh, exciting.
- The, you said it wrong underground chamber of nightmares.
- Okay.
- Now entering.
- Is that a pronunciation thing?
- Sonny is.
- Is it done?
- It's, no, it's me.
- Oh, okay.
- Interesting.
- Oh, there's a bit for Dan later.
- On a previous drop as a line, I said
that Daniel from Wagger Wagger had written.
And I've had several Australians right in saying
it's pronounced Wagger Wagger.
- Oh, that's just your accent, Andy.
- That's just my accent.
- If you say it correctly, like Andy does.
- Why?
(laughing)
- Jeff Salfall writes, Australian and Melbourne here.
A friend of mine was briefly a DJ and Wagger Wagger
and was given strict instructions on how to say it.
So firstly, everyone in Australia knows it isn't said
for them as in hat, but as if it's spelled Wagger Wagger.
So I'm very sorry.
Dan, you didn't help me out there.
- Yeah, I mean, I've heard of Wagger Wagger.
They might have been a Wagger Wagger as well.
Like Australia's massive, it's got lots of names.
I don't know where we're always talking about.
- Fair enough.
- I'd be astonished if there isn't a Wagger Wagger,
a Wagger Wagger, a Wagger Wagger and a Wigger Wigger.
- There you go.
- I think we need to name check pronunciation
anything Australian now because our hit rate is pretty intense.
- Bad.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And we have a huge listenership there.
- Yeah, that's our third most listened to country.
- The nullable road train has kept rolling into the inbox.
But are we gonna stop doing it?
- If we discovered beforehand, it's not pronounced like that.
Yeah, we will.
- Okay, but apparently we even said Melbourne wrong last time.
- So...
- What did we say?
- I can't remember, Sydney.
- That's right.
- Well, just to go elsewhere,
we're still in the Chamber of Nightmares,
but Alex Tewski has written,
I listened to this week's episode of "Fish During a Long Drive"
during which I was amused by Dan's mispronunciation
of the University of Notre Dame in Indiana,
which is pronounced Notre Dame.
- Right.
- He said Notre Dame.
- Yeah, that feels like an affectation.
- I think so.
- Like Mordlin College and...
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- And Laffborough, and I just think it's clearly Notre Dame,
isn't it?
(laughing)
- Clearly Notre Dame.
- How it looks.
- Where's the hunchback from?
(laughing)
- The hunchback of Notre Dame is a funny idea for something.
- Yeah.
- It's his college years, I suppose.
- Oh, yes.
- That's good, and he's called a hunchback.
- This is...
- Sometimes things just write themselves instantly,
and here we are.
- It's weird how nothing good ever writes itself.
- No.
(laughing)
- It's always really weak puns that write themselves.
- Yeah.
- I actually dreamt an idea for a movie the other night,
which I wasn't gonna bring up.
- Oh God.
- Oh God, go on then.
- Okay.
And it's because it's a fish related thing, it's okay.
It's like a Guinness World Records jamboree day, right?
At a big conference center,
but the plot of die hard happens.
So like terrorists break in,
and they're trying to steal something big,
that's happens to be held in this big conference center.
- The world's biggest something, presumably.
- That's it.
- They're trying to steal the world's biggest.
- Oh, don't tell me.
- You're giving me a half bags idea,
and I'm gonna fill it out, aren't I?
- I'm giving you 10% J.
- It's a great idea.
- But how many people are gonna get it?
- I can see it's a great idea.
- So, okay, the main character
is the Craig Glenday editor figure, right?
Who doesn't have any special skills himself.
Apart from, he can stop a stopwatch exactly
at the time he needs to,
'cause he's been doing that all day.
- He's like Hawkeye from the Avengers.
- He doesn't really have any skills,
but he's quite good at one thing.
- But the stopwatch is his one skill.
So the terrorist break in,
obviously a Ragtag band of insane record breakers
has to drop water balance on their stomachs
and to feed them all.
- Oh, yeah, like you can see someone being stabbed
with a sword, but it happens to be a sword swallower
and it goes in their mouth, it does nothing.
- Exactly.
- To them, just like this is a,
I think a legitimately reasonable idea.
- Yeah, I think it's something that could clear a committee
of Hollywood brains.
Something's really high up, how are we gonna get to it?
Oh my god, the Guinness World Records
for the most cherished stacked.
- All the longest arm.
- Guys, I think it's a sketch.
I'm not sure we can squeeze two and a half hours out.
- I think it's a Friday minute long, so yeah, I agree.
This is the next Avengers.
The mediocre's.
- And it comes down to it, like the final bit is,
the bomb's gonna go off,
unless we can cut these wires at exactly the right time.
Up steps, the hero, Mr. Stopwatch.
- But that doesn't cut wires, right?
- Yeah, but he's timing when exactly to do it.
- Okay, right.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Like that's his skill.
- And then there's someone with the Guinness World Record
for most successfully defused bombs.
- He just has to cut the wire at the right time,
but he's quite poignant because he thinks he's not,
he thinks he doesn't have a skill, right?
And he's gone his whole life
surrounded by these amazing people
who have these bizarre talents.
And he's always felt a bit bad about himself, you know?
So actually, it's quite moving.
- Okay, it's really good.
I mean, what's it called?
- Ooh.
- Don't know.
Coming to one sketch of a new sketch show, here you.
- In fairness, that was a tough one
to put him on the spotlight, man.
- But you've got a lot in the dream, Dan.
A lot of work done in the dream.
That's great.
- It started in the dream
because I was flying a plane in the dream,
but it was about to fly into a shopping center
and I was thinking, oh no, we're gonna crash.
But then I remembered in the shopping center today
that I have a demonstration of the world's largest balloon.
Okay, so I'll just fly the plane into that.
And that'll save everyone.
It's a really good idea.
- Thank you.
- I mean, oh god, I started crying with laughter again.
I can't be crying with laughter this early in the show, you know.
- Do you know what I mean?
- Absolutely.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Okay.
- Okay, so it's noted, Dave.
- Yeah, it's the point I'm trying to make.
Which is another great movie.
That's another great movie.
The Hunchback Collegios.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Right, fan theory corner.
- Cool.
- Logan Emory writes, this is about dreams, actually.
I was listening to an old episode
in which one of you mentioned
that a lot of people listened to fish to fall asleep.
I don't know who said it or what episode it was
because I was listening as I fell asleep,
but it started me thinking about why that is.
I vaguely remember someone, Andy,
mentioning cognitive shuffling,
but that may have also been a figment of my imagination.
Stay with it.
Essentially, you think of a word, fish,
and then think of words that start
with each letter of that word.
- That's the way to get a sleep.
- Exactly.
So, friend, icicle, shortbread, honeybee,
would be fish.
The idea is that this replicates the sort of half dreams
you have as you're falling asleep.
You know, when images start to sort of flip around
in your mind a bit.
My theory is that the tangential associations
and scattered nature of fish,
I'll show, mimic micro dreams,
the same way that that technique does.
So, you can zone in and out
and get this collection of images and words
without thinking of them yourself.
Could be that, it could be just that we're really tedious.
Yes.
- Oh, good.
- It could.
- It's so horrific.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Now, I see what I see what he's saying,
'cause it means you won't get fixated on one thing
'cause we move around from that subject to another.
- Exactly.
So, I think that's a very plausible theory.
I like it.
- Yes, really good.
- Yeah, yeah.
And as we've seen, it comes up with that
major franchise ideas as well.
- 'Cause I sometimes fall asleep to the podcast
of Richard Herring playing Snookle with himself.
- Okay.
- Not a euphemism.
And then that really, it's the same thing
that happens every single game.
He misses lots and lots and lots of shots.
And then eventually all the balls get down.
Again, not a euphemism, but he does find that
100% of the time it will get me to sleep for a...
- For a 10 minute nap.
- Yeah.
- Are you needing help to get down for a nap?
- Well, yeah, that's harder to get down for a nap
than for a sleep, isn't it?
'Cause you're not necessarily tired.
- So this is our afternoon nap, we're talking.
- Yeah, I can nap very readily.
- Yeah, I can, but that might change.
You might need Herring on your side soon.
- Herring aids.
- Yeah, I like it.
- Anyway, we're going to a fun new place now
called Place Name City.
- This is a whole new show, Andy.
- I know.
- Okay, where's spicy meat?
- There's a little bit of meat later on.
- Does that's what people are chewing them for?
- That's true.
- Do you guys remember Zoe Hamburger?
- Yes.
- She was the first ever fact on Little Fish.
- Right, and you, James, said something about.
- So she was, oh, I see where we're gonna go.
She worked for McDonald's.
- Yeah.
- And I said that her name probably comes
because her ancestors came from Hamburg.
And then one of the other two of you said,
oh, we don't have that in the UK.
People whose names are from the place
where they're from, well.
And we came up with a couple of examples.
And I can only imagine that the audience back home
were yelling Tommy Fleetwood at the phone and saw.
- Who's that?
- He's a golfer.
- Of course.
(laughing)
- And is there a place called Fleetwood?
- Yeah, in Lancashire.
- I've never heard of Fleetwood.
- What?
- It's a relatively large town.
- Is it?
- Anyway, yeah, we missed a few people with names
that are also places.
- Okay.
- So Ian Dunn sends in Danza Washington.
- Oh yeah.
- I suppose also George Washington.
- At least slightly the other way around.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Irving Berlin.
- Yeah.
- Dion Dublin.
- So there's all great points.
Emerson Lehmann writes,
you all forgot about Michael York.
- Okay.
- Who?
- He was in Austin Powers.
He was, he was.
- He does alex position.
- Yes.
- He's a great actor.
- Tom Yark.
- I know heaven from Radiohead.
- Oh yes.
- He's Tom Yorky.
- Yeah, he's no doubt that the chocolate bar isn't here.
- He's not for girls.
(laughing)
- That's an old-eyed campaign for Yorky.
For international listeners, it doesn't matter.
(laughing)
- Sometimes it's just good to say,
if you're international listeners, don't worry.
- I think they do plus over
a lot of this podcast international listeners.
- Yeah.
- Well, I think they do it with love.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
- Yeah.
- Jack writes,
I have a colleague with the surname Pontifract.
- Oh, really?
- Okay.
- The last surname was Wally, Wally with an H.
- Like Wally Bridge.
- Wally in Blackburn?
Is that the same Wally?
- Maybe.
- So name I weigh somewhere.
- Which links Wally Blackburn,
whose Abbey was dissolved by Henry VIII.
With Wally being a popular term of derision in the '80s,
my family changed our name.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
- Tony Blackburn.
- I mean, they're everywhere.
- Yeah, Peter English gets in touch.
- Oh yeah.
- It's interesting.
- His surname is ink, the word English.
- Yeah.
- But he writes oddly and confusingly,
the name was not given to a person because they were English.
It's actually Irish.
- Is it?
- What?
- 'Cause I said, I mentioned Harris English,
who's another golfer as an example.
But yeah, maybe Harris English is family and not.
- This is crazy.
- So the story is that, Peter writes,
at the time when surnames were required,
some rich English people had estates in Ireland
and locals who were employed to work on those estates
were given the surname English.
- Is that crazy?
- Yeah, yeah.
- The absolute crown on this one goes to Dan Connelly,
who writes, he got inspired by our discussion
of Zoe Hamburger and says,
"I got thinking about the longest chain you could make
"of people named for places named for people."
And so forth.
- Okay.
- Give us an example.
- So for example, Bolivia is named after Simon Bolivar,
and he was named after the village of Bolivar
in the bar's country.
- Lovely.
- It gives a couple more examples.
And then the coup de gras, he needs a bit of help
with the end of it.
But Houston, Texas.
- Houston.
- Houston, Texas.
- I'm just saving emails.
- Sounds like Houston, you have a problem, mate.
- Is it?
- Yes.
- Okay.
- Where is Houston?
- Hugh, really, Whitney.
- Brilliant.
- Houston, Texas.
- Yeah.
- Extraordinary.
(laughing)
Is named for Sam Houston, whose name comes from Houston
in Renfrucia, it's called.
- Yeah.
- Which was named for Hugh, de Paduinan,
where Paduinan also refers to a place.
The bit I haven't managed to track down
as someone whose name is Houston,
after Houston, Texas.
Maybe Whitney, Houston.
But that will be a person named for a city,
named for a person, named for a town.
Name for a person, I've got confused.
- But it's great, it's very impressive.
- That's a really good research.
- Brilliant.
- Yeah, really good.
- The infinite loop, helical staircases.
- Oh yeah.
- Here we go.
We, just, it's not a problem, we didn't say anything wrong.
- No, I can get us for anything we said.
(laughing)
- But Nick Ladner writes, since you mentioned them,
you might like to know there is a double helic staircase
at the University of Reading in the chemistry department.
- Oh, that's very cool.
- Isn't that good?
- Yeah, that's awesome.
And if you flip that over, you'll see a lovely image
from Galicia, Alvaro Lomba writes,
at the Galician People's Museum, we have a triple one,
triple helic staircase.
- Wow.
- From 1700.
- Oh, it's beautiful.
- How good is that?
- Yeah.
- Stunning.
So thank you.
Dan Cloak, wicked name, that's great name.
- Points out that we have a triple helic staircase
in the UK, and in fact it's Hune, or Hune,
into the rock at Dover.
- Is that?
- Yeah.
- It's called the Grand Shaft.
This is for troop movements.
It's from the Second World War,
or it might even be from an older war,
like Napoleonic or something,
but it's to get troops down to the beach in case Napoleon,
or Hitler is turning up, you need to get three layers
of soldiers down at the same time
from the top to the bottom of the cliffs.
- Cool.
- How cool is that?
- That's very cool.
- And it's called the Grand Shaft, which sounds rude.
- Is that more or less complicated
than digging three sets of staircases down?
- Good question.
- So no, it's all less complicated than a big pole.
- Oh, that would not be fun.
- It would be good.
- It would be very good.
- Massive, massive, massive firemen's pole.
- Yeah, but if you go too fast above the guy below you,
don't want your lance to go through his head.
- Are they going down with lances?
- It feels like you should drop your lance off the top
before, which carries his own risks, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- We've had a serious comment from Stephen Chalena.
It seems as if Anna has been absent from the no such thing
as a fish podcast for several weeks now, is she okay?
Hope she's okay.
- Yeah, she's doing good.
- She's fine.
- I saw her last weekend.
- Oh yeah, how was she?
- She was good, she was a bit tired.
- Yeah.
- Because she's been listening to the podcast every week,
and you know, I get to sleep because it's so exciting.
No, she had her little baby relatively recently
and she'll be back next year.
- Excellent, excellent.
I just like to point out, Stephen adds,
I miss her.
Assemblance of sanity amongst a room full of oddness.
- Ah, now what you've done there is mistaken Anna
for someone else.
- Yeah, she's not saying.
- She's the least sane person I've ever met.
- She's loopy-loop.
- I don't know.
- Oh, that was a compliment.
What were we called?
- A room full of oddness.
- Yeah, love it.
- We are.
- That's the title of the film.
- For the Guinness World Records.
- Yep.
- Well, that's, challenge is involved in the royalties.
- He's on 10%.
- Okay.
- You're on 10%.
- You don't think of--
- Please, I have the whole saw down them.
- Yeah, don't know.
- You're on 10%.
(laughing)
- I feel that's for the triple X parody version.
- It's such a vote of confidence, James,
that you think we're going to get a scene remake spade.
That's thank you.
That's really nice.
And we should put that in the pitch too Hollywood.
It's like, we think we can, you know, broaden this out.
As it were.
Right, let's carry on.
Audience quiz of the week.
- Great.
- This is, I can't put it any more simply than that.
Sorry.
- Well, look, are we giving the quiz time again?
Sorry, I was the audience giving the quiz to us.
- Someone's written a quiz in.
- Someone's written a quiz for us to do.
- A quiz for us, yeah.
- Or is it a quiz that you've got for us about the audience?
- Okay, I could have been clearer.
I could have been clearer naming this section.
- So an audience originated quiz question of the week.
- Okay.
- From Ben Rushworth.
Thank you, Ben.
This is my first email since becoming a friend
of the podcast, who writes, which is a very proud moment for me.
I have always wanted to be considered alongside such luminaries
as Robin Thickey and Mark Twain.
- Or were those enemies of the podcast?
- Thickey, Thickey is us.
- He's an acquaintance of the podcast.
- Yeah.
He's closer than that.
He's family at this point.
- He's one of those uncles that you see at Christmas
that you're like, which of course makes his father,
Alan Thickey, our great uncle.
- Yeah.
- And Twain is definitely that enemy of the podcast.
- Twain is a part of the podcast, yeah, yeah.
Right, Philip Muir is our Mike Giggler of the month.
- Oh yeah.
- Who he writes, comedy gold was missed
in the last club fish.
It's fair enough.
And you guys are gonna kick us off up the ass
when you give us a set up and don't tell us what we missed.
- All right, let's see if we can get it.
- Okay.
- In the discussion on Forks, it was said,
Forkall, I think this was you James,
instead of being a TV show,
you could sell it to the New York Times as a daily quiz.
Oh, I think I then said New Fork Times.
- New Fork Times.
- New Fork Times has in the end of a Fork.
- He's done it.
- And so is that it?
- Yep.
(laughing)
- He's done it.
Yep, he says we got nine out of 10,
but if we'd said New Fork Times,
that would have been 10 out of 10.
- Yeah.
- So thank you, Philip.
It's good.
I like what you're saying.
- It's good, but I said it.
I can go back and edit it back into the show now.
- You'll have to.
- Yeah.
- And I'm actually, yes, how cars work.
- Oh, dumbeters.
We said on the show that we're not quite sure
how speed omiters work in cars.
- Yeah.
- And then we thought, we said right in,
someone cavalier said right in.
- You said right in if you're a world expert on it.
- Yes.
- Not if you half know the answer.
- Well, James, thank you for saying that.
And I was used at that because we've had one email
explaining, "Cristily Clearly"
from David Speedometer.
(laughing)
"Eventer of Such."
David Sander for rights.
I have been a technician of one variety or another
for over 50 years.
Put that in your pipe and smoke it.
For many years, the speed indicator in your dash
was driven by a cable running off a small gear
in the transmission, which is part of the car.
(laughing)
He doesn't say, "I'm just adding that in."
- All right, head repart.
(laughing)
There were several different gears for many vehicles
because tire size affects the speedometer,
of course, because if your tire is bigger,
once round actually means you've gone a bit further.
Today, the cable has been replaced by a non-contact sensor
that reads the speed of a gear turning in the transmission.
That signal is sent to the onboard computer,
which then sends a variable signal
to the speed indicator in the dash.
So there you go.
So you're seeing the speed of a gear in the transmission,
not the actual direct monitoring of the actual speed.
- Makes sense.
- And GPS can use that as well.
And that's a bit more accurate.
The average speedometer has a bit of a tolerance,
so there's a bit of error in there.
- So there you go.
- Great.
- Well, really good.
- Yeah.
- Aren't you a bit boring?
(laughing)
- Oh, I mean, it would have been nice
if there was a really exciting way that they worked that out.
- Oh, yeah.
I said, "Your couple is not with David's email explaining it,
"it's with how they work."
- Yeah, it's an awesome way.
- Oh, yeah.
- If David had written in saying,
"Well, what they do is you turn your radio on
"and the radio waves bounce off a wall
"and it could tell how far you've gone in that time."
- It tells you how far you are from BBC Radio Norfolk.
And then in a second it tells you how far you are then.
- Yeah, yeah.
- That would have been exciting.
But as it is, the actual answer is, you know, mundane.
- Quite mundane.
- But probably very useful.
- But so if you're writing in and it's with something boring,
just make something up.
Just make something really interesting up.
- Don't.
- And we'll read it.
- Yeah.
- Change your surname 'cause I'm in silly.
(laughing)
- Thank you, David, for your email.
We've got, I'm actually on none, urine.
- Ah, yes.
Okay, Ben Hilton show again.
- Absolutely.
- This is the fact that for fertility purposes,
nuns were donating their urine
in order to help people conceive.
- Well, Helen writes, listen to the recent Ben Hilton cast,
maybe think about the nuns who having never had,
I'm afraid, cover your ears, children.
You can't have relations.
- Yes.
- She says penetrative penis in vagina sex.
(laughing)
- We all have our ufusus.
- So we call it in our house.
(laughing)
- It's a bit of a mouthful.
- Oh dear, oh dear.
Well, those nuns who have never had that,
very rarely get cervical cancer.
And it was this fact that led to the discovery
of the HPV factor in cervical cancer,
leading to the vaccine for HPV.
- Very good.
- And she pointed to us by saying HPV is almost always
spread around by PIV.
- Yes.
- It seemed like a vagina.
- Yeah.
- So PIV, that's called new acronym.
- PLV, points of view.
- Yeah, but this is a slightly different point of view.
(laughing)
- God, you don't want to be dyslexic looking
for the PIV room and said good to the VIP.
(laughing)
- Oh dear.
I think if you went to the VIP room
and there was a mirror right next to the sign
that says VIP room.
- Yeah.
- So it says PIV.
- Animal.
(laughing)
- Oh, we've had some terrific non-determ.
- Great.
- I mean, really good.
Mollipair writes, medium time less than a first time emailer.
(laughing)
- My GP is called A Doctor.
Doctor A Doctor.
- I love it.
- If I didn't respect her privacy, I'd send proof.
- You've sort of broken that anyway, haven't you?
Doctor A Doctor, how many of those can there be?
- I don't think the doctor patient confidentiality
stretches to you not telling people
what your doctor's called.
- No, because you have to tell people
what your doctor's called, don't they?
On every form you fill in there.
- Yeah.
- So what's your doctor called?
- People must think she's filled it in wrong.
- Refused it.
(laughing)
- It says doctor question mark
and she just writes doctor next to it.
- Yep.
- She must think she's about to start a joke.
- Monty Cox sends this in.
Lindsay Newton, who then became a doctor, doctor Newton.
She then had a chance to marry a man whose name was sleeper
and she wasn't going to, but then she decided
she would take his surname.
She's now doctor sleeper.
- What kind of doctor is she?
- Euthanasia.
(laughing)
- You go for a very long sleeper.
- Hi, I'm gonna be your euthanasia today.
- I went for an eye test the other day, right?
And the woman, the ophthalmologist said,
you know, if you had any problems with your eyes
and I wanted to sell it that I'd had some migraines,
optical migraines. - Yeah.
- But I forgot the word for migraine
and that's accidentally said,
oh yeah, I've had a few comas.
(laughing)
And she's like, oh no, what happened?
And then I realized what I said and I was like,
oh no, no, no, cause a few comas.
It does sound like it's happening again.
(laughing)
- That was very funny.
- Tom Reed sent in a fairly uninteresting article.
His words, but it does feature a belfast tailor
called Chris Sutter.
- Lovely.
- Really good.
David Bella Squires sends in a piece about scarecrow's
by Mark Haye and a Portland dance founder
whose name is Sarah Slipper.
- Very good.
- And Michael Boulter writes about something you said, James,
about New Zealand's state librarians.
- Oh, apparently there was a flood or a storm surge
and they had to get all of the books out of the library
and so they took them onto the roof
and according to the people,
according to the talk guide of the library,
they did so in their underwear and no one knows why.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, for unclear reasons.
So, well, Michael Boulter just wants to write in and say,
"I can speak from experience through undertaking tasks
"in your underpants in the rain."
Early on a Sunday morning, my young kids and I were watching
a hail storm from our back deck.
The kids wanted me to collect some hail
and I could see a lot had accumulated on our trampoline.
I was in a bathrobe and jocks
and didn't know that I had time to go inside
and properly gear up for the wet weather
and rather than get my bathrobe soaked,
I derubbed and ran out in my jocks.
My wife took a video of the whole rigmarole
which I have omitted for your benefit.
(laughing)
- Yeah, because actually under you said
that it's quite good for people to get naked whenever it's raining.
- I think that's--
- To start their clothes from getting wet.
- I think that's a spider.
It's good to be chasing it around in your pants rather than in your,
you know, rather than it crawling into your trousers.
- Good climatic scene for your movie.
The Guinness World Record, they all are on the roof.
- Oh yeah.
- In their underwear, but we don't explain why.
- That's good. - Yeah.
- That's good.
Do you know what?
I think, 'cause we don't know what's going on there,
that makes sense to the film title, don't know.
(laughing)
- What I'm thinking from all this is maybe we start off
with the pornographic parody.
(laughing)
- And then we fill the dates and the Hollywood movies.
- That's a really good idea.
So yeah, Michael, thank you for that.
- Yeah, thank you.
- You know, very, very descriptive, you know, it's vivid.
- Send the video.
- Well, I mean, to listeners, you know,
what's the weirdest thing you've ever done in your pants?
- Is this the kind of email you're fishing for now, Andy?
- No.
- Is this what you're gonna start doing in each episode going?
And listeners, what's the sexiest picture
you've got on your phone?
(laughing)
- Oh God.
No.
(laughing)
- No, keep the inbox PG, please keep it PG.
Please.
Thank you.
'Cause it's great, and I just wanna keep it the way it is.
But we've, there we go, that's it.
That's your emails for today.
You too.
- Thank you.
(upbeat music)
- Thanks everyone for listening.
We are podcast@cure.com.
If you've enjoyed this show,
and we're gonna make another one
whether you want us to or not.
So just there'll be another one in two weeks.
- That's right.
- But if you want to contribute to it,
then email podcast@cure.com, I suppose that's the point.
And if you don't, then don't.
- I think you've covered all basis, yeah.
- He's bloody good at this.
I mean, he really is, isn't he?
Like, he makes it so easy.
- He's got a much more difficult job.
- Yeah, it's a tough wrap up.
'Cause look, why?
- It's hard to say bye sometimes.
(laughing)
- When that old phrase of, "It's hard to say goodbye,"
I didn't realize they were referring
to your wrap-ups of podcasts.
(laughing)
- Thank you, everybody for listening.
Bye.
(upbeat music)