(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast this week coming to you live
from Up the Creek in Greenwich, London.
(audience cheering)
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray, and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones,
but not with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
but with some of our favorite facts from the last 12 months.
This is No Such Thing as the news meets the book of the year
that we didn't get to do,
all smashed into a 30 minute podcast.
So, in no particular order, here we go,
starting with a fact.
(laughing)
- How's the jump in?
- I can jump in because we're recording this
at the same time as the World Cup semi-final is happening
between France and Morocco.
And I have a fact where 40,000 people in France
thought they were watching a World Cup match,
Germany versus Japan on YouTube,
but they were actually watching someone playing FIFA 23.
(laughing)
And apparently this is a group of people in Vietnam,
this is what they do.
They play FIFA, they pixelate it
so that someone watching the game
thinks that maybe they're watching
a pixelated version of the actual match.
And they make hundreds and hundreds of pounds
by just getting people to watch.
- Oh, 'cause people are, right, right,
'cause they add money or whatever, wow.
- That's the thing, they're genuinely,
I read this too, and it's amazing.
And what a letdown when you find out that it's not,
and how foolish you are.
I saw some pictures of the pixelated
and it does kind of look right,
but when they clean it up, it's very much a video game.
- Really?
- Oh yeah, I mean, it is a video game.
But I thought, I haven't played FIFA almost ever.
So I assumed it's like, could we do that
with the podcast?
Like if we sort of play a kind of slightly garbled version.
So it's like, there it is, there it is, like that.
- Yeah.
- People might listen to that.
- Does that mean there are people out there
who might think that, like, Wales won the World Cup?
- Oh yeah, 'cause you could totally rig it.
- Apparently they're not that gullible, it says.
(laughing)
Sorry, sorry.
- But they did, that's James who was pointing out,
they matched up the right match.
So everything was fine.
The thing that was the kicker
was it was a Vietnamese commentary, as you say.
And that's, but I don't think I would have noticed.
- But actually, that added sort of realism to it.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause when you go onto YouTube
and you're watching some hucky channel,
it might be in a different language.
So it kind of gave realism to it.
- Yeah, but another news story from the year,
the queen, queen died.
- Oh.
- What?
- Oh wow, way to bring her down on it.
- So just to cheer us all up,
let's remember the greatest tribute paid to Her Majesty,
which was by the London tourist attraction,
Shrek's Adventure.
Do you guys remember this?
A lot of companies jumped on the bandwagon.
Domino's Pizza said everyone at Domino's
joins the nation and the world in mourning.
Pizza Express went for a slightly different message,
but they also said the same kind of thing.
And Shrek's Adventure London said,
"Shrek's Adventure London joins millions of mourners
"around the UK and world in paying tribute to HM QE2."
Yeah.
- I went to Shrek's Adventure this year.
I thought you guys thought you went to see the queen.
- Oh no, the queue was shorted by just a bit
at the Shrek Adventure on the South Bank of London.
- Wow.
- Actually, I remember a few weeks ago,
I never used this on the podcast,
but I found out that the longest ever theme park ride
was eight hours long.
So you could have done that ride three times
in the time you'd have got to see the queen.
- Really, what was it?
What was the ride?
- It was the Hogwarts one at Universal in America.
- There's an eight hour long Hogwarts ride.
- It was when it first opened.
- What was like a broken motor or something?
Like what was the, why was it eight hours long?
- Everyone wanted to go there.
- Sorry, the queue was eight hours long.
Sorry.
You said the ride.
You said the ride was eight hours long.
- You said you could go on it three times.
- Well, let's see if I said that by the time
the edit goes out, shall we?
(audience laughing)
- Not knowing it was an eight hour ride when it got on.
- Ah.
- Sorry, I'm the queen.
- The queeny thing, yeah.
- So, you know, so you remember for the day
of the funeral itself, the queen's coffin
was carried on a gun carriage, you know,
that was the thing, and it was pulled
by lots of naval ratings, that was the thing,
hundreds of them all pulling it in front and behind
to get it exactly the right speed.
So that carriage, this is just an interesting thing.
That carriage has been kept in a sort of storage room.
That's not the interesting bit.
(audience laughing)
It's been kept there for 40 years,
and every single week its wheels have been oiled
and turned around one quarter, just in case gravity
affected and misshaped the wheels,
and then they wouldn't work properly
on the day of the funeral.
- But 'cause, I mean, gravity doesn't do that.
We've got other wheels in the world, haven't we?
(audience laughing)
And we don't turn them a quarter, I think.
- Yeah, it's not like I come back to my car
after I haven't driven it for a month
and they're all square.
(audience laughing)
- What's gravity doing to it, sorry?
- It's just, well, it's making it flat.
- It's a heavy carriage, it weighs tons, you know.
- I get that, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, and the wheels are obviously quite sensitive,
and you just want to, you just--
- So what, by shifting your wheel,
that's effectively an anti-gravity machine.
- It's not anti-gravity.
- No, 'cause you even out the effect of gravity over here.
- If you flatten out this bit,
if you shift it round a quarter turn,
you flatten out that bit, and then you flatten out that.
But it's like doing something culinary,
like dough or something.
There's a culinary metaphor in there,
which if I cooks, I'd be able to give you right now.
- Right.
Domino's pizza actually had--
(audience laughing)
- In anticipation.
- I just think that's an interesting example
of the extreme thought and preparation
that had gone into it over decades, you know?
- You were talking about the different things
that different brands did.
So Morrison's, apparently, it was said
that they turned off the beeps in their checkouts
in deference to the Queen dyeing.
But they denied it, and they said
they merely turned down the sound.
- Oh, okay.
- So instead of going, "beep," it went, "beep."
(audience laughing)
Although for someone who's dyeing, going, "beep,"
"beep," "beep," you don't really want that, do you?
- They should have replaced it with the Big Ben Bongs.
That would have been nice.
- That would have been great.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Bong.
(audience laughing)
- She caused confusion as a result of her death in Canada.
Don't know if you saw this, but in Canada,
there was not long after she died, like quite soon,
there was a citizen ceremony going on
where there were anointing new citizens of Canada
and doing the pledge and so on.
And it was all done virtually,
and there was 140 people there or so.
And they started doing the ceremony,
and they had to stop it and say,
"Sorry, we can't make you Canadians.
"We don't know who you're pledging to.
"Is it the Queen or is it to the King Charles?
"So they had to like go off and find out
"who the fuck's in charge."
- Does that mean it doesn't count?
If they said the Queen instead of the King,
it doesn't count?
- I think so, yeah.
- Really, 'cause quite a lot of the England team
in the World Cup matches would sing
"God Save the Queen" instead of "God Save the King."
So do you think we could get a rematch against them?
(audience laughing)
- Hey, here's a crazy stat that I read,
is that the Queen was,
she was obviously very old,
but was she 96 years old when she passed.
So that means that of all the people alive in the country,
only 100,000 people had been around longer than her.
So everyone else of us had her in our lives.
- That's still quite a lot, I think.
- 100,000?
I can't believe 100,000 people are older than 96.
- Yeah, it's filled a lot.
- Okay, it's gone the wrong way.
(audience laughing)
- You just needed to present that with a different term.
- Yeah, sorry.
- 100,000 people have been around longer than the Queen.
- Wow, that's a great fact.
- Oh, great fact.
(audience laughing)
- And that will make the edit.
- That will make the edit.
(audience laughing)
- Just on royals, we're not the only royal family
in the world, obviously the Saudi Arabian royal family
forgave Thailand this year for a really interesting thing.
I had no idea they'd been having this feud for 30 years,
but like there haven't been any flights
from Saudi Arabia to Thailand for 30 years.
There have been no ambassadors, anything like that.
And it was caused because 30 years ago,
a Thai cleaner who was employed as a servant
at the Royal Palace, the Saudi Arabian Royal Palace,
he was called Krankrai Tekhamon.
He stole $20 million worth of gems, and diamonds,
and precious stones. - Wow.
- Hid them in some vacuum cleaner bags,
'cause you use what you've got,
and like duct tape them to himself.
- Oh, he didn't accidentally suck them up,
and then... (audience laughing)
- That may have been his excuse in court, I don't know.
And he smuggled them out of the country,
and I love this, the way he smuggled them out was,
he got them to Thailand by putting them
in a big box of cargo, and then he knew
that the Thai officials at the other end
would check them at customs, unless he did something.
So he bribed them with an envelope,
stuffed with some cash, and with a note saying,
"Hey, in my cargo, I've got loads of really bad porn,
and I'd really rather you didn't search it,
'cause that would be really awkward for me,
so can you not?"
And they didn't.
- I really... - I would have thought
you'd go for something slightly less tempting
than that wouldn't you?
- You're right, they're very respectful,
the Thai officials at customs.
Anyway, this year, finally, Saudi Arabia forgave Thailand,
'cause it became this huge diplomatic incident,
people were shot dead because of it.
- Yeah, there were lots of back and forth, yeah.
- Yeah, that's terrible.
- But the blue diamond's still missing,
so check under your seats before you go.
- It's not Oprah, we're not Oprah.
(audience laughing)
- Just while we're talking about porn,
even though it was just a word,
I'm just gonna quickly grab that
and bring it over here.
There was a news story which in Manhattan,
a congressional candidate called Mike Itkis,
he's running and he has a sex positive approach
as part of his campaign.
So he thought, "I'd like to demonstrate
how positive I am about sex."
He released a 13 minute long porn video with himself
and a porn star that he filmed and put out
to say, "I'm a man of my words."
That's called Bucket List Bonanza
and it's with Nicole Sage, the porn star.
And yeah.
- Sorry, what party is he from?
- I would say wherever he is,
there's a bit of a party going on there.
There was someone called Alexandra Hunt
who ran in the third district for Congress
and she was a former exotic dancer.
But rather than hiding it, she decided to embrace it
and one of her campaign slogans was just elect hose.
The other one said, "I may have danced for money,
but I'm no corporate whore."
- Wow. - Isn't that good, isn't it?
- Yeah, it's quite good, yeah.
- There was a guy in Nebraska, Bruce Bostleman,
who apologized for repeating the rumour
that schools are accommodating children
who self-identify as cats
by putting litter trays in the corner of the classroom.
- Why are they putting litter trays in the corner?
- Oh, no, they're not.
- All right, okay.
So the premise of his accusation is flawed.
- Yes, he accused them of doing something
that definitely did not happen.
- Right.
- I've got a fact that was sent in by someone, actually,
like a couple of weeks ago.
Someone called Brain Blobs on Twitter,
so thank you, Brain Blobs.
This is a really thrilling thing, guys,
so this doesn't sound thrilling,
but there's been a general conference
on weights and measures and some scientists,
no, stay with it, because some scientists
from the National Physical Laboratory in the UK
attended that conference on weights and measures.
And obviously, I don't need to tell you
that that's the authority of the International Bureau
of Weights and Measures.
And so, anyway, we've got some new units to celebrate,
and that's really good.
So a measure of weight, a ronogram.
A ronogram is...
- It sounds like it's someone's birthday.
(laughter)
And you just send someone a run-around.
- Hello.
- What is it?
- A run.
Happy birthday.
- Oh, that's so much better than what I've got here.
(laughter)
So a ronogram is a one followed by 20 zeros, okay?
And I think the earth weighs six ronograms,
which is really good,
'cause previously we had to say it weighs
like 250 million blars,
and even that was the previous biggest unit.
- Okay.
- So you see what I mean?
Now we can just say it's six ronograms,
and that's a much more convenient way of putting it.
- Great.
- Yeah, that's good.
- That's very handy.
Yeah, 'cause people often ask how much is the earth weigh,
and you don't know any more units.
- Well, there's the ronometer.
- Oh, yeah.
- And the universe is--
- It's how you measure runs, isn't it?
(laughter)
- The entire universe is just one ronometer across.
- What?
- Oh, that's great.
- 'Cause it's very big, it's huge.
- You sound surprised,
but you haven't just heard that a ronogram is a large thing.
- It's massive.
- It's bigger than a gram.
- But I don't think that then helps you understand--
- Okay.
- Anything.
- All right, Dan, okay, Dan.
No, no, no, that's fair enough.
All right, it's fair enough.
- Correct me if I'm wrong, it's an expanding universe.
- Well, eventually it'll be two ronometers.
- Okay, here's, okay, better example, better example.
The other end of the scale,
they've added some very, very small things as well.
- Yeah.
- Right, so what about a quectogram?
Okay?
- Okay.
- There's a rontogram, which is the weight of an electron.
- Oh, this'll be the weight of a quark or something like that.
- Is the weight of something even,
so the weight added to your phone
if you get one extra byte of data on your phone.
- Oh, okay, right.
- That is one quectogram.
- Right, so that has actual weight?
- Yeah.
- I swear to God, I emptied my phone
some hours the other day, and...
(audience laughing)
- And it floated away.
- I'm not kidding, it felt so much lighter.
I was like, wow.
- Yeah.
- And so that's true.
- That's it, yeah, that's it.
- There we go, yeah.
- Do we think any of these are gonna come in handy
at Weight Witchers' Meetings?
(audience laughing)
- Maybe, yeah.
- You've lost a rontogram this week, that really is, wow.
Well, actually on the Earth, an universe,
worrying news this year is that our days are getting longer
and we don't really know why.
So there's this quite confusing thing
where in the very, very long term,
the days are getting slightly longer
'cause the Earth's rotation is slowing
'cause the moon's moving away from us.
That's over millions of years.
You don't need to worry about that.
But in the short term, like the last 50 years,
weirdly counterbalancing that,
they've been getting shorter,
which we haven't really known why.
And now suddenly, the last couple of years,
they've gradually started getting longer,
don't know if anyone's noticed here.
The extra--
- It's felt like during Andy's tiny bit, actually.
(audience laughing)
- So there's a new measure of time,
the Andy Graham is, before.
- It's only a matter of minutes, but you will age.
(audience laughing)
- But yeah, we think it might be
because of the Chandler wobble.
(laughing)
- The Chandler wobble.
- Could that be any more weird?
(audience laughing)
- Lovely, for someone who I know
has never seen an episode of Friends.
(audience laughing)
- Someone who's read the Wikipedia page of Friends.
- Halfway through, I was thinking I'm out of my depth here.
(audience laughing)
- Oh, you nailed it.
(upbeat music)
- Do you know whose time on Earth has been made longer
by one to two years, as of six months from now?
- Oh, yes, I think, I mean,
despite the way you phrase that, yeah.
(audience laughing)
I think I actually do.
- So it's South Koreans.
- Right.
- South Koreans have just extended their life
by one to two years,
and that's gonna happen between June of next year
because they usually, in South Korea,
the way that they measure your age is when you're born,
you were born one years old.
So they say that nine months is rounded up to
12 months, you are one, and if you're born,
I think it's like close to December,
then you become two because it just is a new year.
So you go, you're two, quite quickly,
if you're born in, let's say, November.
So that's been a thing where people have always found
confusing if they go overseas,
because their birth certificate or the passports,
we all carry our birth certificates, right?
(audience laughing)
Their passport will say an age,
but they'll say a different age,
and it's really confusing.
So now South Korea has decided to abandon
the whole thing of saying you're one or two when you're born,
and they're gonna be like the rest of the world's metric
or I guess the majority.
- Are they?
- Yeah, it's really sad.
It's a real shame.
- That's so sad.
- Well, I just think it's a cool, interesting thing to do.
- Yeah, it's an interesting cultural difference.
Yeah, don't do it, Korea.
Go back.
'Cause it would be cool if, as you claimed,
they're adding two years to their life,
and if that's how they've tricked them into it, then yeah.
- Oh, I think if I could, I'm 38,
if I could be like, I'm now 36,
I think that would make my day.
You wouldn't be, you would have--
- You're still gonna die on the same day.
- Yeah.
(laughter)
- Well, yeah, but--
- And it's soon, sooner than you think.
- But I will have died two years younger.
- Also, people, more people will say, "Such a shame."
- Yeah, yeah.
- They were too soon.
- There were only 100,000 people older than Dan Shriver.
(laughter)
- Can I drag us quickly back to sport?
- Oh, yeah.
- And well, actually, one thing I just wanted to say
about Southgate, which, go with Southgate.
- Sorry, yes, I'm not familiar.
I'd like to know a little bit.
- You were thinking the Tube station, weren't you?
- I was actually thinking a scandal.
(laughter)
- Southgate.
- Did you hear about Southgate?
- So, football manager for England.
- England's football manager,
and everyone thinks he's a really great guy now,
so obviously he was the bad guy in the '90s
because for international listeners,
he missed a penalty at the Euros,
bit of a crisis for his popularity.
Everyone loves him now 'cause he wears waistcoats
and England's a quite good team,
but I found out how he met his wife,
I mean, his ropey.
- Oh, what do you mean with ropes?
(laughter)
- It's actually not that bad,
but he saw a woman he fancied who worked in a shop in Croydon,
and so he, first of all, would like,
loiter around the shop pretending he was looking
at the clothes there a lot to try and talk to her.
- What sort of shop?
- Clothes shop, I reckon.
- Oh, yeah.
(laughter)
- A hardware store, he gets picked up.
He's picking up padlocks and going,
"I love this t-shirt."
- "I love this high-vis jacket."
(laughter)
- Okay, sorry, so he's hanging around the shop.
- He's hanging around the shop.
He finds out she's got a very serious live-in boyfriend,
but it happens, he goes to a restaurant one day
and her and her boyfriend are sitting nearby at the table,
and he senses that they're having a bad time together.
He senses this relationship on the rocks,
so when the boyfriend's not looking,
he sneaks over to her and drops a letter in her hand
with his number on it.
- A letter?
- A full review, yeah, yeah, 18 pages.
A note, I suppose a note,
and saying, you know, when this cocks up,
which clearly it's going to,
why don't you give me a call?
And she did.
- And she did.
- And they had their dates in Tesco Carpac for a long time,
'cause they had to be secret, I think.
- Oh, so she hadn't left,
they just started dating secretly?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Wow, this is a gossipy story, isn't it?
(laughter)
- A Tesco Carpac is not a very secret place, either.
It's actually open to anyone who wants to go there.
- I assume her boyfriend shopped at Sainsbury's.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, I guess so, yeah.
- It's the only safe place for them.
Anyway, so that is some hot goss from 30 years ago.
- 30 years.
- About Gagasasky.
- Are they still together?
- Yeah, the art's very sweet, actually.
- Oh, that's nice, well done, Gareth.
I got sports news here as well.
This is to do with the world of Badminton.
You'll all know this, I'm sure.
But just to remind you, four Chinese Badminton players
were put on probation for two years this year
after failing to try their best to win in 2018.
So the match happened in 2018, they finally had the thing.
Basically, the people that were watching the match
noticed that either side were sort of not really giving it,
they were just sort of like dicking about,
and that apparently is illegal in Badminton.
- They did it for a very good strategic reason, right?
- What, both sides?
- Yeah.
- Is it so they can play a different team
in the next round?
- Yeah, exactly.
- I thought you were gonna say
maybe they'd been paid to throw the match.
- No, I think it was because they,
if whoever won would be playing the better team,
and I believe it was two Chinese team, wasn't it?
Who, if they won,
were gonna end up playing the other Chinese team.
And so that was silly, 'cause they want China to win.
So it's pointless China playing China,
'cause they're gonna knock one of them out.
- Right. - And so they all won,
and then I think was the other one Korean.
- I don't know, apparently you know this way better than me.
- I'm just guessing.
I'm just like crystal ball.
Yeah, I think then the other team were like,
hang on, you're trying to lose.
We're gonna try and lose as well.
And then they got picked up,
and then the second half they kind of went for it properly,
'cause I think they realized we've been caught out.
- But now they're banned, yeah, for playing shit.
(laughing)
Which is amazing.
- In 2024, the Olympics are gonna be in Paris.
This is the fact about next year, I should say.
Because this year they unveiled the mascot
they're gonna have.
And everyone said the same thing,
that it looks rather like a clitoris.
- Oh.
- The woman who designed it, when they said to her,
you know, it's a bit weird
that your mascot looks like a clitoris.
She said, "I'm so happy after everything
"that's happened with feminism,
"that people can now recognize the clitoris."
(laughing)
- I saw the mascot, I didn't think it looked like,
I don't think at all.
- And they did find, I'm sure everyone saw this today,
they found the snakes clitoris for the first time, haven't they?
- Yeah.
- It's got two.
- Two.
- Yeah, 'cause they have hemi-penis, don't they,
like, double penises, so they have double clitorises as well.
- Oh, good for them.
(laughing)
- I got a few records.
- Oh yeah.
- Do you want a little quiz?
- Yeah.
- Okay, right, this record was broken in January.
By Laura Noonan of Sydney,
it's the most cartoon characters identified in one minute.
How many?
- 20.
- Okay.
- In one minute, 40.
- 106, come on.
- Wow.
- Imagine that.
- That's a lot.
- Yeah.
- How, identify what, like, by photos, or?
(laughing)
- I mean, yeah, some kind of pictorial.
- I thought it was a voice, I guess.
- Oh, yeah, I thought a voice maybe.
- No, I think it was pictures, you know,
Popeye, Betty Boop, Donald Duck, that one, you know.
- Question two, question two.
- All right, all right, all right.
February record, Franz Huber from Milan,
most swords swallowed while hanging upside down.
- Okay, I've seen, I reckon,
I've seen people swallowing around six or seven,
so I'll go for that, six.
- Okay, one.
- 100.
(laughing)
- Sorry, you didn't let me finish, 100.
- You're both right, it's 100 swords.
No, of course it's not, it's nine.
- Oh, okay.
- Although, is that, if you're upside down,
is it still swallowing or something?
- Yes.
(laughing)
- What is it, if it's not?
- It's just like, it's just sort of
pushing something up, isn't it?
You know, swallowing is where you swallow something down
and it goes into your stomach.
- It still ends up in your stomach though,
no matter which way you're orientated.
- Yeah, I think you've forgotten the definition
of the word swallow.
- Okay, well.
- You can't say, oh, I didn't swallow those diamonds,
officer, because I was upside down at the time.
(laughing)
- Please go on your way, sir.
We legally can't arrest you.
Okay, fine, fine, fine.
All right, final one, final one.
March record, this is Miyabi Kugimachi of Tokyo,
most socks sorted with one foot in one minute.
(laughing)
And I want an answer in pairs, please.
How many pairs of socks sorted?
- Half.
- Half of one pair?
(laughing)
James has low ball there.
- 30, 25.
- Pairs?
- 400.
- 12 points.
- Four, again, 400 pairs of socks.
- I half listened to the question.
- Eight pairs of socks per second.
(laughing)
- Final answer.
- I don't know or care who got it right.
I think it was Anna, I think it was 15 pairs.
- You think?
- No, no, no, I know, I just can't remember what everyone said.
- Oh, right, I know.
- I was so angry with you for guessing 400,
but I kind of forgot Anna's answer.
I think you guessed sort of--
- 25.
- Oh, there we go.
- Yeah, but I meant singles, so 12.5, I thought.
(laughing)
Wasn't this, I think I saw this,
and wasn't she known on YouTube for foot-related content,
anyway, I believe the person who won?
(laughing)
Or maybe I came across her in a different walk of my life,
but--
- Oh, right, okay.
- What is foot-related content?
I know it means sexual stuff, but what does that mean?
I actually don't know what that means.
Just sexy photos of feet?
- I don't know, I guess it's sorting socks with your feet.
I don't know, I've never--
- Sorting socks with your feet?
- Yeah, well, that's what she's doing.
- That's what this lady was doing.
- I didn't hear the question.
(laughing)
- Okay, I have a related fact on these kind of people.
It's about influencers who do strange things.
- Oh, okay.
- And this is Stephanie Matto, who sold farts in a jar.
- Oh, yeah.
- And she managed to get very, very sick
because she was trying to fart too many times,
'cause she got so many orders,
she was trying to make as much as possible.
And what that meant, because I found another story
in the same week, is that you can end up in hospital
if you fart too much, and if you don't fart enough.
Because there was a woman called Cara Clark,
who got extreme stomach pain
when she'd been holding in her farts too much.
And then this influencer, Stephanie Matto,
had been farting too much,
and she ended up in hospital as well.
- Were they in the waiting room at the same time?
(laughing)
- Well, what that says to me is there's an optimum amount.
- Yeah, well, if you read the uncut version of Goldilocks,
there is that scene where one of the bears in hospital--
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Why was the second woman holding in her farts?
- Because she had a new boyfriend.
- Oh, no.
- Yeah, she's fine now, they had a laugh about it.
- Okay, that's pretty good.
- So what you're saying is we're all walking
a kind of, quite a thick line of--
- Yes, I think so.
But Stephanie has now retired from selling farts and jars.
You'll be glad to hear.
Her family are glad to hear.
But she is now selling her fart jars as NFTs.
- Okay.
(laughing)
There's, can I mention one of the big stories of the year?
- Yeah, go on.
- The very infamous Chris Rock Will Smith moment.
- Oh, yeah.
- The slap at the Oscars.
I fell in love with this story because it was just
a very good example of how very quickly we all jumped
to insane theories to sort of justify
why it may have happened.
So there were two theories that came out immediately
after it happened.
One was that someone said that the slap is much less
interesting when you realize that Will Smith almost
certainly went through the Scientology courses
that tell you to unapologetically use slaps
and physical force to let a fellow Scientologist know
they've done something wrong.
So the idea is that in the training,
they just go kwa-pang on the side of your face
because they're bored or whatever.
And that's them letting you know that they don't want it.
- Can we introduce that to the podcast?
- Please, please no, please no.
(laughing)
I won't last one.
- Tell us some more unit facts, Andy.
- Pow!
(laughing)
- But yeah, so but then Scientologists,
including Ex-Scientologists,
jumped to the immediately saying, no, no,
that's not a thing.
My favorite one though of all the theories that came out
is that someone noticed just before Will Smith
came up to slap him on stage,
that Chris Rock had dared to say the word Macbeth on stage,
which you should never do.
The curse of Macbeth.
Oh, shit.
(laughing)
- Anna, you know what to do.
- But so just a few moments before he congratulated
Denzel Washington on his performance
on the tragedy of Macbeth.
And so now if you go to the Wikipedia page
for incidences after invoking the word Macbeth,
you will find Will Smith slapping Chris Rock.
- But isn't that only a viable theory?
And I can't remember his wife's name.
Maybe it is Macbeth.
- It's not Lady Macbeth.
- But it's basically what Will Smith's wife
would have to be called Macbeth.
'Cause I believe it was accompanied
with an explanatory words, wasn't it, by Will Smith?
He didn't want to leave us in the dark.
Didn't he say get--
- Keep my wife's name out of your mouth please.
- Oh, I see what you're saying.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And his wife's not called Macbeth.
So that's where that theory completely falls down.
But aside from that.
Well, that's the only reason he'd be annoyed
about him saying Macbeth.
- No, the whole idea of the Macbeth curse
is that it's out of your control what then happens.
So then he goes on to tell a joke
he thinks is gonna be fine and the curse takes over there.
- Oh, you're not saying Will Smith was furious
'cause he broke our rule.
- I thought that, yeah.
- The way you told it, it did sound like--
- Was it Will Smith?
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- The Scottish Blair, you dickhead.
Oh, the garb and tell him.
(upbeat music)
- On celebrities, another celebrity of the year
was Liz Truss.
- Mmm.
- And a chair of slight recognition in the room, wasn't it?
- Can you just, for any international listeners,
can you just say who?
- Yes, so she was the short-lived,
five minutes of fame Prime Minister of the United Kingdom.
- She still lives.
- She's still alive.
- She lives.
- Yeah, Liz Truss lives.
- She wasn't Prime Minister of the United Kingdom.
For God, how long was it, 37 days?
- 49 days.
- 49 days, actually, that's not too bad, is it?
(audience laughing)
But she, I learned this year that she was often
compared to Margaret Thatcher, obviously,
because she tried to compare herself
to Margaret Thatcher quite a lot,
and she actually played Margaret Thatcher
in a school play when she was eight years old.
- Oh, really?
So what was the school play, Macbeth?
(audience laughing)
Like, I was in a couple of plays at school,
and none of them featured a book without your character.
- It was a nativity.
- Nativity, yeah.
(audience laughing)
- It was, the school play was the 1983 election, so.
- Wow.
- It was a weird, they did things differently
and paisley in the '80s.
I think that Thatcher election was going on at the time,
and so they re-enacted it, and they asked people
if they wanted to be certain candidates,
and they said, would you like to be Margaret Thatcher
and try to get people on your side,
and then everyone would vote for who they liked best,
who was pitching their political theories,
and Liz Truss actually got zero votes,
not even voting for herself.
(audience laughing)
- Oh, because she was left-wing at the time,
because her parents were quite left-wing,
and she wouldn't have been a Thatcher supporter
until much later, even at uni, she was in a damn.
- Yeah, that probably was it.
What she said was she knew the Tories
were so unpopular and paisley at the time
that she couldn't be seen voting for Margaret Thatcher,
even though it was her in this instance.
- My school did the 1997 election,
and it's a good, fun thing to do.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Who did you play?
- Chubb Prescott?
- Well, we didn't do it as a play.
- Aw.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Actually, Michael Gove wasn't around then.
(audience laughing)
- Who were you?
- I was-
- No.
(audience laughing)
We weren't playing individual people,
it was just like it was done as like,
I can't remember, there was a talk about it or something.
- You played people talking about the election.
- No, it wasn't a play, for fuck's sake.
(audience laughing)
- It's not a play.
- We got to talk about the letters.
- The trust letters.
- The first letters, the letters that lasted longer
than this trust, but of course there's a big argument
between left and right on Twitter, like there always is,
with the right-wing saying that actually
there was some discoloration in the letters,
and maybe it hadn't lasted as long as Liz Truss,
but the Atlantic said that it was still usable in a salad.
(audience laughing)
So that counts.
- Do you know what happened to it in the end?
- Yeah, straight afterwards, for the next month,
it was doing personalized messages on Cameo
and it was 13 times.
(audience laughing)
- Are you serious?
- I'm serious, sorry, fine.
- That's really good.
- There was a really good quote about Boris Johnson
in The Times this year.
Boris Johnson for International List
is another Prime Minister that we've had this year.
(audience laughing)
This is around about the time when he was flying back
from his holiday to claim the title of Prime Minister again
and then decided against it.
And there was a school report written
by one of his teachers when he was 18,
and it was just so good and prescient.
So the school report said,
"Boris sometimes seems affronted when criticized
"for what amounts to a gross failure of responsibility."
(audience laughing)
And surprised at the same time
that he was not appointed captain of school for next term.
I think he honestly believes that it is churlish of us
not to regard him as an exception,
one who should be free of the network of obligation
which binds everyone else.
(audience laughing)
- All right.
- Cookie.
We were talking just before the show.
Do you guys remember the Sue Gray report?
This time last year, that wasn't out yet.
That's all happened this year.
- Oh, wow.
- We're getting some nose over there.
So we're gonna have to refresh people.
- Nah.
(audience laughing)
It's very boring.
- Another Boris-like person, Chair Bolsonaro, in Brazil.
He's been away from the public eye
for the last couple of months.
And no one's really known what's happening.
There's been a lot of rumors.
- What since the election?
- 'Cause he lost, didn't he?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
The vice president said that he'd had COVID three times
even though he denied it existed.
(audience laughing)
And he had a skin disease
which stopped him from being able to pot on his trousers.
(audience laughing)
And so he couldn't do any public events.
- Oh, enough.
- You can still do Zoom calls, though, can't you?
(audience laughing)
- That's amazing.
- We should think of wrapping up in very,
not just yet, but sooner.
- Can I say a science fact?
- Yeah, of course.
- So one thing that we've just been getting this year,
it's been in the works for years and years,
the James Webb Space Telescope,
which was launched, I think,
at the very, very end of last year.
And we've just got the first photos back this year.
It's amazingly exciting,
'cause we're seeing lots and lots of the universe
in completely new ways.
And I've just been reading a bit about it.
It's so sensitive, the James Webb Space Telescope.
It could detect the warmth of a single bee
that was on the moon from Earth.
- Okay.
- Wow.
- Isn't that good?
- Well, we don't have bees on the moon, though.
(audience laughing)
- Well, maybe now we'll find out
if we do have bees on the moon, then.
- Yeah.
- And do we?
- Well, no.
(audience laughing)
- That is quite amazing.
- Yeah, it's taking these pictures,
they get called the baby pictures of the universe,
because it's photographing light
from 30 and a half billion years ago,
really, really long time ago.
- So you can see what was happening
just after the universe was spawned.
- Exactly.
Well, that made me think that all of our baby photos
are still traveling out into space.
As in if you were far enough away,
you'd be able to see yourself as a baby,
you know, what you were up to.
- Yeah, as well.
- You'd be able to see your own baby photos happening.
- I guess so.
- James, you're a physicist.
- You'd have to be firing them out
somehow.
Like, for instance, broadcast stuff.
- Yeah.
- Something that's broadcast over the airwaves,
that would go into space,
and that could be seen for a long time.
So technically, no such thing as the news is still on.
(audience laughing)
We got cancelled on Earth,
but if you're on Alpha Centurion,
you can watch it live.
- Oh, wow.
- Do you think the owner of,
or the originator of the James Webb Space Telescope
spams their friends on WhatsApp constantly
with annoying photos of the baby universe?
- Yeah, almost certainly.
(audience laughing)
- Quite ugly, but they have to say something nice.
- I've got a bit of a silly story here,
which I just loved.
There's a guy in China, two guys in China,
that were picking pine nuts from a tree recently,
and the tree was a bit high,
so they thought the way we'll get to it is,
let's just fill up a hydrogen balloon,
and we'll attach ourselves to that.
So they go up in it,
and they're picking their pine nuts,
but then the balloon becomes untethered.
One of the guys jumps out.
The other one's too afraid to.
And he disappeared for two days into the air.
(audience laughing)
He went on a 200-mile-long journey,
really high in the sky.
They were monitoring as he went.
Fortunately, he had his mobile phone,
and he was constantly calling,
and running low on battery, going, "What do I do?"
And they had to navigate him to slowly let air out
over somewhere that was landable,
but for two days, he just fucked up, yeah.
- Wow, what an adventure.
- So funny, it's like up.
- So great, yeah.
- Have we got any last stories?
- In Nigeria, they seized thousands of donkey penises
because they were mislabeled as cow penises.
- Okay.
- There's a romance novelist who wrote an online essay
called "How to Murder Your Husband",
and she was sentenced to life for murdering her husband.
(audience laughing)
- The old double bluff.
It doesn't always work.
- And according to a recent study
at the University of Singapore,
the three funniest word pairs in the English language
are played by Parrot, Weasel, Penis, and Spam Skroton.
(audience laughing)
- We'll try them in the next episode.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts from the year.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter account.
So I'm on @Sribeland, Andy.
- @Andrewhunterm.
- James. - @JamesHarkin.
- And Anna.
- You can email porkcoast@QI.com.
- If you want to get in touch with us as a group,
we're on @NoSearchThing, or you can go to our website,
NoSearchThingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there,
so do check them out.
There's a bunch of other fun things up there.
Check it out too.
Thank you very much Up The Creek
for being here for our big end of year.
NoSearchThing is a new smash
with the book of the year, Bonanza.
And we'll be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(audience cheering)
(audience applauding)