(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of No Such Things A Fish, where we were joined by the legend.
The national treasure already, I think,
but definitely future national treasure, Tom Allen.
- That's right, Tom is absolutely fantastic
as you're about to hear.
He's a flanner, he's a man of out town.
Among many other things, you might not think it
'cause he's so dapper, but he's also a gardener.
- You might not think it 'cause he speaks so nicely,
but he's also a podcaster.
(laughing)
- And he has a new podcast out, it's called "Pottering" with Tom Allen,
and he gets a celebrity to his garden,
be it Nish Kumar, be it James A. Castor, be it Natalie Cassidy,
and they talk about gardening.
- It's lovely, and I think they do some gardening as well, actually.
- He probably has some Natalie Cassidy Bagonias,
get some Nish Kumar, Asperd Distras.
- Lovely, can James name a third plunge?
- Absolutely not, but if you want to hear Tom's podcast,
then go to wherever you get your podcast,
it's called "Pottering" with Tom Allen,
and it's absolutely fantastic,
but Andy, we have some more news.
- That's right, the other thing to say is that,
in a week's time, we're gonna be doing the first
ever Club Fish Quiz.
Now, this is for people who've joined Club Fish
at the top tier, the friend of the podcast tier,
we are gonna be doing a quiz globally, I imagine.
We suspect hundreds of thousands may be attending,
and you can be one of them, it's gonna be on Zoom,
or an equivalent streaming platform.
We've all been writing our questions,
we've been showing them to each other,
we've been coming up with silly games,
it's gonna be so much fun.
So mark your diaries or your calendars
for Friday, the 23rd of January, 7pm British time,
but if you're around the world,
we'd love to see you there as well.
- Gonna be so much fun, we can't wait to do it.
But anyway, please enjoy this week's episode
of "No Six Things A Fish" with the incredible Tom Allen,
on with the podcast.
- On with the show.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing" as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here
with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray, and Tom Allen.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Tom.
- In September 1945, a small booklet was discovered
in the main offices of the third Reich in Berlin,
or Reich, if you're from southern Germany.
In Berlin, it was a secret list of 2,820 British individuals
who'd be rounded up in the event
of a successful invasion, and Noel Coward found his name
on page 34.
- Oh, okay, why were they going after him?
- Well, firstly, I think anybody in an entertainment
would be annoyed that they had to go so far.
(laughing)
- Mind your own name.
- There's only one thing worse than being on the Nazis,
deathless.
(laughing)
- And that's not being on the, I can't believe
you're quoting Oscar Wilde in a Noel Coward section.
- Oh yeah, we'll get onto that.
- Well, they just kind of crossed over
in a sort of Dalai Lama way, yeah, yeah.
- Is that what was he?
- Very Dalai Lama way.
- Have you ever looked at who died just before you were born?
- No, I never had.
- Oh, that's a funny question.
- There was one of the popes, the one that was before
John Paul II, so I think it was, just before I was born,
you died, so I'm not saying anything else,
but I am Catholic, so.
- I think you could still do it as well.
- I can.
- Well, no, I've been excommunicated, as we've said,
but.
- But what a comeback story that would be for you.
- Yeah, and actually the Pope.
- I can change the rules if I'm the Pope.
- Yes, yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
- Let's get back to Noel Coward.
- I know, I like that.
I was suddenly panicking about who died in 1983.
- Yeah, lots.
- Mount Batson, no, that was '70, late '70s.
- Yes, Mount Batson was, I went straight through.
- I just got to see what this is.
(laughing)
- We should quickly say who Noel Coward is.
Noel Coward, very famous way around.
- Yes, I didn't bother to say that.
I just assumed all your listeners would know who he was.
- Yeah, but you know better than anyone,
'cause you're part of the Noel Coward Society, so.
- Well, I have been involved, but I, the, the,
Noel Coward, yeah, usually seen as a playwright
and a writer of songs, particularly Mad Dogs and Englishman.
He was also an actor, musician, and an author,
as well, he wrote a novel.
Well, he was wanted by the sinister Amst grubber,
V1, V1, G1, I don't know what,
I don't know what that looked like.
- I was like a music channel in Germany.
- Amst grubber, V1, G1, real common.
A department, it was a department
that evaluated intelligence material.
Well, he was a, it turned out, a British spy,
and his cover had apparently been blown,
and if the war had gone differently,
well, the man known the world over further,
the song "Don't Let's Be Be See to the Germans"
could have ended his days in front of a firing squad.
- Wow.
- So, yeah, and when the list was discovered,
amongst other people who the Nazis didn't like,
for various reasons,
and the author, Rebecca West, sent him a telegram
to say, "My dear, the people who were to be seen dead with."
- Which I thought was very cool, that's very good.
- This song, interestingly,
got him in a bit of trouble back home, didn't it?
- Yeah.
- What was it called again?
- It was called, "Don't Let's Be Be See to the Germans."
- Yeah, so, came out during World War II.
It was a satire.
It was--
- It was signed by the BBC.
- Exactly, because the satire didn't quite cross,
as well as he hoped it would.
They thought that he was actually genuinely saying that.
- I was excited about it, because I think it's the only thing
that Noel Coward has in common with the prodigy
I found there, songs "Smack My Bitschup",
which was also banned by the BBC.
- Can you imagine him reading "Smack My Bitschup",
Noel Coward, in his accent?
- He'd have--
I think he'd have gustyed up the lyrics a bit.
He'd have made them cleverer.
(laughing)
- But I always wondered how he got away with being a spy,
'cause he was so flamboyant, right?
It seems like, as a spy, you have to hide away a little bit.
- Well, Radio 4 did a dramatized version of what he was like.
I think a lot of it, as well, was propaganda work
in North America, obviously, the US.
I think to Ghana support for getting on board with the war effort,
which I know wasn't the case at the beginning.
So I think he was seen as sort of a special envoy,
I suppose, as much as anything.
I don't think he was going behind enemy lines.
- No, but I'm--
- Hamburg.
- He'd been recruited even before the war started.
I think there was someone called Sir Robin Vancetart,
who was running--
- Sounds German, actually.
- Yes, but he was at the foreign office
and he was recruiting various people
to go about their business in Europe, quite successful people,
and then report back on the national mood,
what people were saying, just sort of soft intelligence,
as it were, not, you know.
You don't need to observe this tank column
where it's going, this ball bearings factory.
It was just like what you're hearing in social conversations.
And I think Howard was sacked partly
because he was too public in his maneuverings,
and also because everyone looked at him,
and this is after the war started,
and they just thought we've just got to a load of parties
and man, happening, you're really letting the side down.
And actually he was doing the war work, like he was doing.
- He was, he was really completely shamed about it, I think.
- Yeah.
- I think the Daily Mail covered about it.
- Oh.
- And said like, they said outrage, going over there,
spitting all this money, with public money, going to parties.
- The Daily Mail, who's departed,
and all of that, so he's just before the war.
- Ooh.
- Well, it might be, yeah, I mean.
- Yeah.
- But I should check, I should check,
it was the Daily Mail that it's out there and I'm lovely.
- Well, he used to, again, trouble with the daily express.
- Yeah, and actually this is another war connection.
So he wrote the screenplay and started a movie
called In Which We Serve, which was a really good movie,
often got used to get them morale up
and show how the war was going.
And he kind of based the character on your past life.
- Not that.
- Yeah, so he consulted with him and that was largely part of it.
Can we say who Matt Baffin was again?
- Sorry, yeah.
- He was, oh, oh, Matt Baffin, I think.
- Oh, Matt Baffin.
- Lord, Matt Baffin, wasn't he?
- Oh, yeah.
- And he was, he was Prince Philip's uncle by loose connection.
I haven't researched it.
- By big, the brother of his mother?
Or, yeah, so it's kind of like loosely unclear to him.
- Is it like one of those uncles who's like,
just friends with your parents?
- I have a feeling if we're, yeah, exactly.
- And you were shocked at some point to find out
that wasn't your uncle.
I remember this when I was five.
I found out Uncle Joe wasn't my uncle.
And I was a bit outraged.
- Uncle Joe.
- Yeah.
- It was a cup of coffee.
- Yeah, so anyway, Matt Baffin was part of this thing
with Noel Coward.
And the daily express started ridiculing the production,
saying that how could you have Noel Coward play
a high ranking general in the army?
- He's a captain.
- A captain, right?
- In the Navy.
- Yeah, yeah, he didn't come across.
- Not above that, don't carry on.
(laughing)
- I feel like I'm going quite lost in it.
- Sorry, no, I'm barely tripping it up.
Well, I mean, I'm pretty sure he's a captain.
I haven't watched it before.
- I haven't seen the movie and you're a part of the system.
- You're being absolutely pancake
between Tom's love of Noel Coward
and my love of military rank.
(laughing)
- Sorry.
- Just bring a bit of golf into it.
- Absolutely.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- That sounds quite out of time to me, Noel Coward.
- I know his name and I know he's part of the plays,
but I do, you mentioned Oscar Wilde before.
I do play some as part of that era,
but he was in things like the Italian job.
- Yes.
- He was, you know, in the '60s.
- Yeah.
- That was his, I think, his last acting role.
- Right.
- He was born in 1899.
And he served briefly in the First World War,
which I didn't know.
'Cause again, I think of him as like,
he's wearing his pajamas, maybe dressed in gown,
he's smoking a pipe through a long holder,
he's writing brilliant dialogue,
he's writing plays like blindspirit and hay fever, you know.
- Yeah.
- Witt.
- But he served in this company called the "Artists Rifles."
- Just sounds awful, doesn't it?
I think it was so, yeah, I think it was a place where
maybe I don't want to be unkind,
maybe slightly less useful fighters were replaced.
And I think he wasn't ever put in any sort of position
where he'd have to do anything to practical.
- Well, he got himself out of it quite fast.
- And this was only in, I mean, he was born in 1899.
So I think he was signed up aged 18,
or maybe conscripted, I'm not sure.
He was discharged for Neurosthenia,
which was very much a catchal you've got nerves.
- Sort of tying a piece of string around his finger.
- Why?
- I guess it's sort of stress.
- I stress it.
- A stressful situation, definitely.
- It'd be a tick talk about it now.
- But I think part of the reason he got so involved
in World War II as a spy or whatever,
is 'cause he was a bit embarrassed by the fact
that he'd gone into World War I quite young
and then had to leave quite quickly.
- Yeah, his company suffered lots of casualties
in the last two months of the war.
I mean, hundreds, you know?
So I think, and that was after he'd been
invalidated out as it were.
So yeah.
- Yeah.
- I love the main thing about him outside of his plays
and his acting and his songs is the gossip.
He was Mr. Annicdote, basically.
He's like the Charles Brandrath of his day.
(laughing)
- Charles will be very happy.
- Charles Brandrath was absolutely in love with that.
(laughing)
- Oh my goodness.
What a Christmas breath of joy.
- Well, we'll clip this out inside of him.
- Yes.
- Oh, and so there's one great war Annicdote from him,
which is he said, he never forgot the sight
of Coco Chanel entering a Paris air raid shelter
followed by a maid who carried a gas mask
on a velvet cushion.
(laughing)
- That's wonderful stories.
- It was a time when people did,
well, I know there was a structure of class,
but I think if you did transcend those structure,
you would just end up being at parties with these people.
- Yeah.
- I don't know, maybe it would be the same now,
but I mean, just like--
- 'Cause his mother, I think, had some vague sort of connection
to the aristocracy.
- Oh, is that really?
- Maybe like an uncle or something.
(laughing)
- Yeah, she, like, feel martial hague
was a distant cousin of hers,
and her sister married the nephew of Sir Henry Ponsonby,
who was private secretary to Pequim Victoria.
- Oh.
- So there were kind of, like, close to high society,
but not quite in there until he became very famous
and really hot-knobbed with the--
- Yeah, 'cause I thought they were kind of,
like, pretty lower middle class,
grew up in Southwest London,
and very suburban, reasonably poor,
and his mum was a real stage mum.
- Yeah, she was the Mrs. Worthington, I think.
- Perhaps she was the real Mrs. Worthington.
- She pushed it.
- Mrs. Worthington is--
- Oh, is a song, don't put your daughter on the stage, Mrs. Worthington.
It's kind of a song told from the position of a producer,
I think, in an audition, but essentially,
kind of saying to this very pushy stage mum,
she's talentless, please stop moving in.
(laughing)
But Noel Carrot's career happened partly
because of a medium spiritual guidance.
So his mum went to a show at the Coliseum,
an American celebrity medium, Anna Eva Fey,
and his mum asked, "Should Noel, young Noel here,
"go back to school, or should he stay as a child actor?"
And from beneath this big sheet that she was--
(laughing)
- A medium, Anna Fey said, "Keep acting!"
- Oh, wow, I didn't know that.
- So that was a, I think, I suspect they probably would have kept him acting,
even if the medium had said, "Go back to school!"
(laughing)
And I suspect the ambition was strong.
- Still though, I haven't seen Blife's spirit,
but I think it's a very satirical about the spiritualism movement.
- Is that right?
Is that sort of parodying it?
- It was a big drive towards it.
It wasn't in the 20s and 30s, I think.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Where people would have--
- Yeah, I guess, I mean, that probably makes sense, doesn't it?
But my dad even remembers his grandmother having her friends around for like a say-on.
- Really?
- Which, isn't it?
- Like they'd go into the back room or something, yeah.
And all these women would come in and try and contact with dad.
- Yeah.
- But it was kind of seen as his thing that people do quite socially.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It was like a book club of its day.
- The book club of its day, exactly.
- Exactly.
His writing was extraordinary, the speed at which he wrote,
because there were so many knoll-coward plays, there was a story that in 1935,
in the summer of that year alone, he wrote nine plays.
That's how quick he knocked out a song called "I'll See You Again,"
which Frank Sinatra recorded while he was stuck in a taxi, in a traffic jam.
- It's similar to, I think, Elton John, in the way that he,
apparently writes his songs in five minutes.
- That's the tangents and tiaras.
It's something about that creativity.
It's something quite useful about actually not allowing lots of time.
- Yes.
- He also says the songs slightly come to him, he doesn't claim to have written.
- Is that Elton John now?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, Elton John will say that the songs sort of arrived to him.
- After the war, just to go back to his sort of post-war life.
He spent a lot of time with the Navy.
- And in fact, I bet he did.
- During the war as well.
He frequently would just hitch a lift on royal Navy ships.
- Really?
- Yeah, he would just...
- So he had to get on that.
- Well, how did he get off?
- He said, he spent a lot of his life as a tax exile because he was so financially successful
in the first half of his life that a lot of his life was just moving around to different,
low tax jurisdictions.
And he once joined a ship in Bermuda called HM Dragon, or HMS Dragon, maybe.
And the captain said, "What the hell are you doing on board this ship?"
And Coward replied that he was, quote, "exhausted overworked on the verge of a nervous breakdown
and had joined the ship in order to be nurse back to health and strength and waited on hand
and foot."
And the captain not only gave him a lift to Trinidad, he gave him loads more lifts later on.
- That's so nice.
- I became friends.
- This was just like...
- As well as a naval captain, you might be quite pleased that if somebody so witchy and
famous was suddenly on board.
- Oh, yeah, great.
- That's the entertainment.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Yeah, better than the inser or whatever.
- You say he was rich.
He was so rich.
He was making £50,000 a year.
The equivalent of which today that would be £15 million per year that he was making.
- In the late 20s.
And he was really burning through it, though.
So he had a lot of financial problems, hence moving to tax havens like Jamaica, where he
moved right next door to Ian Fleming.
- Oh, yes.
- Yeah.
- I love this spy.
- And there are stories that he turned down the role of Doctor No, that that was actually
offered to him for the first bond.
- He was just called Doctor before they offered it to him.
- So Doctor No, Coward, that's the original name of the character.
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that there is a Marvel superhero called The Gardener, whose superpower
is that he is insanely good at gardening.
So is it that he can grow things very, very fast?
- No, it's more that he is obsessed with gardening, and he is almost an immortal.
- Gardening is supposed to be good for you if you're getting older, like it helps you live
longer, doesn't it?
- Exactly.
- Well, yeah, and potentially forever.
- It is, it is.
- It is forever.
- You give enough time to it.
So he's part of this group called The Elders of the Universe, and basically the other
one who is really good at bowls.
- There's another one who is just really good at being racist.
- It's a really ruins Christmas, yeah.
- Captain Crossword, come and say.
- Yeah, okay, these are each of them with the last survivors of their own race, and these
were racers that evolved just after the Big Bang.
And the idea is that they have extended life spans, but not because they're immortal,
but because of a single-minded obsession with a hobby.
- Oh.
- That can be, I'll back that, there you go.
So his hobby was Gardening and Horticulture, and the idea is that he would go from planet to
planet, and he would spend sort of up to a year sort of terraforming it, making it greener
guys.
- Yeah, that seems like very, might come into his own actually, you know, environmentally
conscious age.
- There you go.
Well, he should be a bigger character, because actually in the original-
- I think I should blame him.
- In the original stories, he and the other elders all had the Infinity Gems, which is
what Thanos collects as part of the main Avenger storyline in order to wipe out all of-
- Oh, so he's one of the original holders of one of these?
- Yeah, because some reason when it came to the movie adaptation, the Gardner didn't quite
get.
- Pretty cool.
That's what I'm thinking.
- Yeah, I'm talking about that.
- Yeah, I love that.
- Yeah.
- The other thing with like a big wide-brimmed hat, you know, the sort of thing that old ladies
used to have.
- Oh, yes.
- Yeah.
- Gloves on-
- Obviously, floral gloves in one of those kneeling pads.
- I've got one.
They are very useful.
The best ones are when you've got a handle at the side to push yourself up.
- Ooh.
- Yeah, they give you those.
- It's like an upside-down piano stool, really.
That's really helpful.
- That's really helpful.
- And then you've got to just have a couple of beats to be like, "Oh, with my knees."
- Yeah, absolutely.
- We're talking to a seasoned Gardner here, I'm guessing.
- Well, I salty, maybe, if it's just about seasoned.
- You do have a Gardner, though, that you love to test.
- I've got an into Gardening.
I like to use the past tense of God.
And I've gotten into Gardening in the last sort of four years since having my own place.
For a long time, I lived with my parents, and I didn't have my own space then.
So now I do, and it's quite nice just to, well, just mess around, really.
I'm proud and obvious with it, but I find it really interesting.
- So on Famous Gardners, who's the most famous Gardner in the UK?
- Alan Titchfars.
- Correct.
- What has Alan Titchfars got in common with Elvis Presley?
- Ooh.
Okay.
- That's obvious.
- Both sex gods.
- Okay, I'll give you that.
It's slightly related to that.
- Poets?
- He writes poetry, Titchmush.
- It's not that.
- Okay.
- Very vintage ale.
- Well, Elvis had a song about it.
Titchmush was done up for years, wasn't he?
- Yes, yeah.
- That's why he has on his tattoos.
- Yeah.
- Come us them up for the show across.
- One for everybody.
- And he killed him.
- It's how he got into gardening, was burying the bodies.
- The answer is that the lower halves have been censored on television.
- Really?
- So Elvis, obviously, when he became big, they would only show him from the waist up so
that people didn't get too excited.
But Alan Titchfars has been...
- They were sent over the waist out.
- They have censored his trousers because he wears jeans.
And in North Korea, they don't like jeans being shown because it's a symbol of America.
- Oh.
- So they show his programs, but they blur out his trousers.
- Wow.
- But that means he's free to broadcast Winnie the Pooh style.
- Yes.
- So the North Korean networks.
- He's there.
- We have to paint his legs blue.
- I've seen Titchmush do karaoke.
- Have you, in person?
- In person.
- Wow.
- I don't mean to cling.
- What did he say?
- Something green-green grass.
- It was...
Oh, what's the one I killed the man in Reno?
- Gangsters paradise as well.
- Yeah, I don't remember the song, but it was, yeah.
- Wow, that's very cool.
Well, there's other reasons that Alan Titchmush is a sex god.
- Yeah, by the way, which is that as well as writing over something like 70 gardening books,
he's written a series of novels.
- Yes.
- Yes, they are.
- Are they seen?
- Are they?
- Yeah, in fact.
- Absolutely.
- I don't know if you remember, but we had Los Andres read Morrissey's contribution to the world of sex scenes.
- Tom, do you mind?
- I feel a little extra.
- Oh, here we go.
- Well, I think I have met Alan a few times and he's always very charming, as you imagine.
And he did say to me, because I was talking to him about audiobooks.
- Oh, yeah.
- And he did say he was very aware of his more intimate scenes when he had to sit in a booze.
- Oh my God.
- And read them out.
- To an engineer.
So as an example of what he might have been reading, there is a little bit here.
She planted moist hot kisses all over his body.
Beads of sweat began to appear on Guy's forehead for it.
As it became more entangled in the lissum limbs of this human bower constrictor.
For fully 15 minutes, their mutual passion heightened with groans, size, and liquid noises.
- Oh my God.
- Wow, I can't believe it.
- Can I just say, when you're describing lens, why'd go for the one out of all that doesn't have any lens?
- Oh, lissum.
- Lissum limb.
- I don't know what lissum means.
- What l'd say?
- I've never heard that word before.
- Lissum is kind of young and firm and strong, isn't it?
- Is it?
- Oh, sorry.
- I love that.
- Titch marshes.
- Too high brow for us.
- We don't know the vocabulary.
- I know.
I bet he learned.
- He's a very educated man.
- I like the way it begins with she planted kisses.
- Yeah.
- Like because obviously he's a gardener.
- Absolutely.
- Oh, every.
- Well, he.
- Yeah.
- So he was runner up in the 1998 Literary Review Bad Sex Awards.
And you're right.
He felt very uncomfortable reading them.
He said particularly with the sheet of glass between you and a very large bearded man twiddling
knobs as you say the words.
- Gosh.
- He found it uncomfortable.
- I think it's a bit unfair that bad sex thing because they go for slabs, don't they?
There must be loads of like not famous people who are writing worse.
- Absolutely.
- What?
- To be fair, the winner that year was Sebastian Forks.
- I was going to say bird song.
- Yeah.
- It's got lots of that.
That's very interesting.
- Bird song is very fruity, doesn't it?
- Very fruity.
- I remember reading that when I was about 17 and thinking, "Oh gosh, that seems like a lot
of effort."
(laughs)
- Can I ask you about a couple of things you might or might not use in your garden, Tom?
- Oh, yeah.
- Absolutely.
- Should we give it a go?
Right.
Do you ever use worm poo tea bags?
- No, I think I have heard of this sort of thing.
- So cool.
- Worms are very important, aren't they?
- Worms are vital.
- And obviously they eat soil.
They poo it out.
You know, they help.
- So do I.
- They do their aerate.
- They have all sorts of stuff.
You can get tea bags with worm castings, aerate worm poo, where you literally make a cup of tea
out of it for your plant.
And it really helps your plant.
- Really?
- Yeah.
Lion urine?
- Well, that's the thing, isn't it, because people say to keep away foxes or other animals
if you want them out of your garden.
- You need an apex predator.
- You need an apex.
You can't.
The people say, "Oh, just go and weigh in the garden."
And they're like, "No, they need men to weigh in the garden.
It's male urine," they respond to.
And apparently, that's not...
That's not going to do it.
Apparently, you need to go to the zoo and ask, "Yeah, I'm going to get a lion to
weigh into a cup."
Oh, you could get the piss off plant, have you heard of that?
- What's that?
- Piss off plant is a plant that's native to Southern and Eastern Africa.
And it is a plant that supposedly repels dogs and cats from coming near it because of the
eroma that it emits.
So if you had that in your garden, most likely, they would smell it and never come back
again.
- Well, I'll get one of those.
That's pretty good.
- That's a great idea.
- Do you have an ornamental hermit in your garden?
- No, I don't have anything like that was like a sort of a little house, wasn't it word
a little.
- Well, back in the 18th century, this was a real life human that you would bring into your
garden.
Yeah.
They would dress like a druid and they would just be sat and they would have a contract
to live there and negotiations for roaches and negotiations every autumn as the reproaches.
- Yeah.
Well, look, I'm not going to do this for another year unless you revise my terms.
- Yeah, it's been in 1797, there was a thing, the hermit is never to leave the place or hold
conversation with anyone for seven years during which he is neither to wash himself or cleanse
himself in any way whatsoever.
- Yeah, my agent's got a problem with his claws, right?
- Yeah, it lives a bit further down the garden, another little folly.
- Yeah.
- Do we know why people did that?
- Well, I think it's a kind of, it would be like landed gentry would have this person.
You wouldn't have it in your garden in that knee, would you?
- No, exactly, I think what it is is the hermit is a symbol of a wild and ancient way of living
and it's kind of they are reflecting on history and on humanity and on progress and the countryside
and the wilderness and I think that's why it's cool to have a hermit because they kind of
hark back to that.
- Yeah.
It's been that kind of sentimentality isn't it around that kind of pastoral?
- There was one place which had a hermit which turned out to be a mechanical hermit, genuinely,
I think it was the 18th century aristocrat, quite clearly it was just a hermit.
It was like a very, very, very crude model robo hermit that they had in there with those things.
- Here's another famous gardener.
So this is a king called Error Imiti who was in ancient Samar and what would happen in
ancient Samar is you would get people who would tell the future and if they saw a bad
omen, like maybe the king's going to die, you would put someone else on the throne for
100 days and then you take over again.
So this guy, Error Imiti decided to put his gardener on the throne for 100 days because
there'd been a bad omen and then he died after eating some hot porridge and his gardener
then reigned ancient Sumer for 24 years.
- Wow.
- Just because he didn't blow on it.
- I guess so.
- It's a good holy porridge.
- Yeah.
- That's incredible.
- I know.
- I guess it wasn't a successor in place who would not have taken over.
- Well, he's the king now, right?
- Yeah, you're right.
- So what are you going to do?
- That's so funny.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is Andy.
- My fact is, in 1920, the king of Greece died after trying to break up a fight between
a dog and a monkey.
This is the only royal death I've found which involved a monkey at all, actually, little
end of fight between a dog and a monkey.
This was King Alexander of Greece and he had a dog, he had a German shepherd and one
day he was having a walk in the palace grounds and I think a barberry ape, quite an aggressive,
yeah, not a titler of a monkey, you know, this isn't like bubbles.
- No, no, no, no, this is, this is proper-
- They're very naughty barberry apes, I can say, they only, yeah, it's naughty.
- They'll kill your dog.
- Like slaughtering your dog in front of you.
- Or your king.
- They have the man to brawl to them, they, and I went up there with a pusher, with my
daughter who is very young and basically they will just steal everything.
Everything that's not held down, they'll steal it.
- You got her back though.
- No, she still lives there.
- She is the egg queen now.
- That's why I'm about to put Brexit, I don't want it to be Spanish.
- Yeah, so anyway, this ape and this dog were in a fight, he was trying to separate them
at which point the apes wife turned up and sunk fangs into King Alexander's leg.
- Oh no.
- And I think some days later he died, he'd become ill and they had swithered over what
to do the doctors and so.
- So he died and this produced huge geopolitical consequences with Churchill later wrote, "It
is perhaps no exaggeration to remark that a quarter of a million persons died of this
monkey's bite."
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- Because they've spent the Greek Civil War.
- Well, it all led to a lot of unhappiness and conflict inside Greece.
They got back the previous king.
- Because what had happened?
The previous king was very pro-German and his son was pro-German, his eldest son.
So Britain and Russia and probably France got rid of those guys and brought in this guy who
wasn't expecting to be King.
He was just thought he was going to spend his days gardening or just having a lovely life.
- Having a lovely life.
- Yeah.
- And then suddenly he's King and then, okay, well now we've got our puppet who's in charge
but then he dies and then they bring the old people back and it all goes to shit.
- That's basically what happened, yeah.
He fought this war against the Turks which went disastrously wrong, hundreds of thousands
of deaths.
We've kicked out and then the European great powers just started picking the Greek royal family
and then eventually things got a bit more democratic and the Greeks in 1862 had this vote for
a new king, a kind of national referendum and they almost universally, they chose Prince
Alfred of England who I believe was one of Victoria's sons.
He won 95% of the votes cast against the Turks.
He said no, no thank you.
I don't want to do it.
- You used for the throne of Greece, yeah but imagine if we have a nice house somewhere
wouldn't it?
- I'm sure he's already got a nice house.
- You're right.
Well yeah was that?
- That was 1862.
- So this is not happening in the 1860s, wasn't it?
- Oh.
- Going on.
- Bucket.
- Was that unification of Germany around then?
- Yes.
- And then formation of Italy.
- Also my house was built.
- Really?
- So some major events.
- Major, major things.
- So your garden.
- That was laid out.
- The garden was created, yeah.
- By Prince Alfred.
- And the corner from me and Napoleon III came to live.
- Is that so?
- Really?
- Wow.
- So we've asked Tate a huge decade.
- Huge decade.
- But basically Alfred was pressured into saying no, because Britain, France and Russia had
all to creed.
Nobody's going to accept this throne.
- Yeah.
- Nobody wants it, get over it.
And every candidate said no until they got to Prince Wilhelm of Denmark of the Blocksburg
house and he had received six votes from the entire population of Greece and he was
then chosen to be the king.
- That is unfortunate.
- I know.
- The 18th highest voted person in that list.
- You came 18th.
- Yeah.
- But various people had just written a Russian king, please, or whatever they just selected,
like they just listed it.
So he came almost dead last.
And yet, he then was king for 50 years.
- King Elet kingface was there.
- Is it?
- Who they really wanted.
- Yeah.
- And then he lost it until 1913, he lost it 50 years.
- 1930.
- 1913.
- He was assassinated by either a socialist or a lunatic, and it's not clear which apparently.
- Oh yeah.
- Not necessarily.
- Not to get political.
- Yeah.
- A lot of assassinations happening around that sort of area, wasn't there that time?
- Oh yeah.
- Yes.
- He loved it.
- A vexed, a vexed period.
- A vexed period in the south-east of Europe.
- Yeah.
- I found another monkey bite death.
- Oh.
- Did you?
- It's an expect-to-find one, but I tried hard and I got there.
- Do you know the character Grizzly Adams?
- Grizzly Adams.
- He was.
- I wasn't like a vampire.
- No, no.
- So Grizzly Adams in America, I think he's quite a well-known.
Historical character.
So he was a Californian mountain man.
He was a trainer of Grizzly bears.
And he used to just do acts, you know, kind of like a Petey Barnum kind of thing.
So he made pets with quite a few of these bears that he thought were friendly.
- I can't see this going.
- Yeah.
- Can't see where this is going to go.
- And he was killed by a monkey.
- Yeah.
- So.
Okay.
Don't take your eyes off the threat of the monkeys.
- Yeah.
- So he got attacked by Grizzly in Sierra Nevada, in the monkey was one who set the Grizzly
on him.
- No, monkey comes in later.
So his scalp was dislodged in this attack and it left a silver dollar size impression in
his skull just above his forehead.
Then he had all these other Grizzlies that he made friends with.
Anyway, he was re-insured several times in the head and it opened up the wound which meant
a bit of brain tissue where it's exposed and then, as he's still going with the bears,
stick.
- He's still going with the bear stick.
- Okay.
- And then Grizzly added this on tour with a circus when a monkey that he was trying to train
jumped up and beat him in the brain, not in the head in the brain.
- Well, you don't have any nerves in your brain so you wouldn't even feel it.
- Yep.
- So anyway.
- No, it was happening.
I think.
- Okay, from behind is possible.
- And so he died.
October 25th.
- Oh, no.
- 1860.
- Yeah.
- It was another thing.
- It does.
- Another thing.
- How extraordinary does.
- If you hadn't said it was a monkey, I wouldn't have seen that coming at all.
- Yeah, I know, right.
It's a real plot twist at the end there.
- It really is.
- Wow.
Horrifying end.
Here's some people.
William III of England, Alexander III of Scotland, Prince Alfonso Portugal, Frederick
Augustus II of Saxony.
Matthew Jeffrey of Brittany is a Beller of Aragon, Leopold V of Austria, Louis IV of France,
William the Conqueror.
They all died the same way.
- Monkeys.
- Not monkeys.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- At what point do we start suspecting the monkeys?
- Araratus of the day.
- This is something that does away with lots of royalties.
- And it's very guessable.
- Oh.
- Or is it gouged or something?
- Yeah, gouged.
- Gouged.
- But that's a bit of a hog.
- Yeah.
- It's sort of explosion or some sort of, 'cause William the Conqueror did explode.
- He did explode his death.
- Yeah.
- He got rather a beef, I think, to me.
- Right.
They couldn't bury him straight away.
And so when the monks came to bury him in his concrete tomb, they sort of shoved him
in it.
- Oh.
- And then he exploded.
- Wow.
- And the Conqueror.
- I'm pretty sure, yeah.
- William the Conqueror, yeah.
He definitely exploded in the--
- Conqueror.
- Oh.
- It wouldn't be Conqueror, no stone, sorry.
- Oh yeah, okay.
- That's a bit of the story you wanted to pick up.
- The Romans had Conqueror.
- I know the Romans had Conqueror, but I wasn't aware that--
- Yeah, it was a brutalist--
- It was a brutalist coffin.
- I just went with something really silly.
- Anyway, the answer is, falling off a horse.
- Oh.
- That is a big old way that people died in the past.
- Yes.
- Alexander III probably was riding along a high treacherous coastal path, having drank
a lot of bodo wine, and just went straight off it.
- Right.
- I just jumped straight off it, yeah.
You would think the horse would stop, but yeah.
The problem is that quite often when these people die, there's a big sort of something happens
afterwards, like happened with this Greek guy.
So when Alexander III died, that started the first war of Scottish independence, essentially.
- Right.
- So you know, it's quite a big deal when these kings die, even though they're just people.
- But what point is anyone suggesting a helmet for horse riding?
- Oh.
- I just--
- You don't see that, I mean, apart from knights, you don't see people with like cycle helmets
in the past, do you?
- Yeah, but knights do have protection.
You just think that I get how many regal deaths do they have to have before they say, I think
we should say, if you're the king or queen, you have to wear a helmet on your horse.
- Yeah.
- Or how about seat belts?
- Horse seat belts?
- Yeah.
- Horse belts.
- Is that safer?
- You're not going to fall if you're really tied tight.
- If your horse falls over though, and your seat belt is on, I just wonder if there's five
reggae to come along.
- I feel like there might be a reason why the horse seat belt hasn't been invented.
Or maybe it has.
- Stirrups is effectively the horse seat belt, because it really helps you hold yourself in
place when you're in the stirrups.
- Look at you, you've been riding the horse recently.
- I've ridden one half.
- You've ridden one half.
- You're wearing it as Mr. equestrian.
- All I'm going to say is that go off any clefts, so, you know, despite how much border
wine you--
- Yeah.
- That's true, isn't it, how do people-- maybe this is a very graphic question, but how do
people die when they fall off a horse?
Do they get trampled in the legs?
- I think it's banged on my head.
- Banged on my head.
- Yeah, because actually you're quite--
- Someone who's ridden a horse, I would say, but you would know, that's why I asked.
- You're quite high up.
- Oh yeah.
- And they do, like, my horse, at once they saw a lady horse, and so I started galloping
towards them.
- Oh no.
- I'm going to tell you a little bit more shit in my angle.
- One advantage for a horse ride, if it mounted the feet up, and you just have to sit there
like a horse passenger.
- That's amazing.
You're riding two horses at once.
That's absolutely incredible.
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that one of the most popular celebrity tailors of the 1950s
was, ironically, called Newdy.
- This guy's a character.
- I reckon quite a few people might have heard of him, but I'd never heard of him before.
He was the first person to spot rhinestones on clothing.
So if you've ever seen one of those rhinestone cowboy suits that they wore in America, in
what, this 50, 60, 70s, he will have made it.
So he made suits for Elvis.
He made them four ships.
- Well, in Titch Marsh.
- Elton John, who we've mentioned before, Hank Williams, John Lennon, this is the who's
who.
- It's everybody.
- Yeah.
- Staggered.
- Liver Archie, I imagine.
- Oh, yeah.
- They never too much sure.
- It was sort of everyone.
In fact, I was thinking, because I, you know, the term rhinestone cowboy, Glen Campbell,
that was originally written by a man called Larry Weiss, and it was, it was in tribute
to Newdy.
- Really?
- That was a thing that all of these country music stars kept asking for.
They were like, "Newdy, more rhinestone, more rhinestone," when they were asking for their
suits to be tailored.
So that song was put in more of a sentence, though.
They just went, "More rhinestone."
"More rhinestone."
"Newdy."
- That was, it was a guy called Lefty Frizzle, who was more rhinestone.
But a few more rhinestone, "Newdy, put more rhinestone."
- The rhinestones are stones from the Rhine, by the way, just in case you didn't know what a
rhinestone was.
- I never knew what they were.
- I don't know about this.
- It's now just a piece of coloured glass, basically, but they were kind of proper rock
crystals.
- Apparently you just get these little colourful pebbles on the banks of the Rhine, and people
used to put them on stuff as decoration.
- Yeah, at these days, you melt them on to clothes with heat.
- Do you?
- So you have a little, you have a little glue layer, and then you just heat them up and
you just shove them on.
- But yeah, "Newdy," he was born, "Newter Cop Clierenko" in Kiev in 1902, and he moved to
America, but he was really into his tailoring, and then when he was processed, supposedly
according to the story, when he was processed through Ellis Island, they changed his name to
"Newdy," which I'm not sure how often that actually happened, and usually it was people
just changing their name to sell more American themselves.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And then he came to America, opened an underwear shop selling G-strings and pasties to strippers.
- Very poor brainies.
- West Cornwall wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- But they're called pasties.
- They are called pasties.
- Oh, okay.
- I just thought, okay.
He's going to get hungry, and they are quite handy, because that whole meal running through
them.
- If you've got one hand on the pole, and the other one is hold onto the cross.
- I think the strippers in Bolton do put pasties on their nipples, but.
- So they're all the more popular for it as well, people love pasties, they love pasties.
He then had surgery when he was in his 40s and lost all of his money, because he had to
pay for the surgery.
- And America.
- And then he thought, what am I going to do?
I'm going to make suits for celebrities.
And he got in touch with a guy called Tex Williams.
Tex Williams auctioned off his horse, and used the money to buy Newdy a sewing machine,
and they went into business together.
- Well, you wouldn't have got on with Tex.
- Yeah.
- Both love horses.
- I'm going to start coming to the ride stunts.
- Yeah.
- But yeah, I'd never heard this guy, and he was pretty big deal.
- Quite the guy.
Apparently, at the early stage when he was selling the pasties to strippers, he sold also
Taylor Mae's G-strings, which you don't, you don't them to not fit.
- Right.
- If you got round your knees.
- Oh, was that happened again?
I was just eating a pasty.
And the name Newdy became sort of synonymous with these amazing suits, and actually the Newdy
name is still alive thanks to his granddaughter, Jamie Newdy, who seems to have taken his first
name as her surname now, not quite sure how.
So now they do still exist, but they mostly make t-shirts and coffee mugs with the name
Newdy on it.
They don't really make so many clothes anymore.
- His cars were absolutely bananas, and I only say this, because I've seen one of them,
I think in the flesh, in the Nashville country music hall of fame.
- Oh, wow.
- And it's...
- When did you know that?
- I don't even know.
- I mean, just 15 years ago.
- I thought I'd heard every one of your anecdotes.
- No, no, no.
This is...
- Why do you keep telling us the same three then?
- I feel like we're having distracted from my fourth anecdotes on these facts anyway.
- Yeah, it's an insane car.
It's got 18 pistols distributed around it, and kind of built into the doors and things
like that on the inside.
It's got 1,200 silver dollars glued on at various points all over it.
My memory might be tricking me.
I feel like it's got a bison's horns on the front.
- Oh, wow.
- You'd have the Mercedes sign or whatever.
It's got one of those.
I mean, it's an absolutely loopy car.
- Well, you would plug in your electric vehicle.
- That's right.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- He was very obsessed with fashion as a lot of celebrities are.
Tom, you are one of the best-addressed comedians.
- Well, that's very generous to say fashion.
I've always liked shooting and tailoring.
I don't know.
I think it makes me feel a certain way, sort of stand in a certain way.
And I guess that's part of what tailoring has always done for people.
But yes, I do like to wear a suit.
- Yeah, I used to wear ties a lot.
And I've stopped in recent years and I feel less good as a human as a result.
So I think I might get back into it.
- Well, they're a flash of color, really, I suppose,
or a variation in the...
- Well, you always wore a black one then you'd have.
- Just black.
- With a white shirt.
- Yeah, so remember those days.
- Yes.
- Very Mormon.
- That was you.
(laughing)
- Safe time, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- So you don't have to change your clothes at the end of the gig.
You can just get out and fly the audio somewhere out and yeah.
- Pop the old badge on.
(laughing)
- I don't know those books.
- I do, whoa, what's interesting is I read a study recently.
Is apparently when you wear a tie, it stops your blood flow by 7.5%.
- Well, that gets me high.
So I like that.
- That's what I'm missing.
- That's what happened there.
- To your brain.
- Yeah, so you've been operating with constricted blood flow to your brain.
- For some years.
- They did MRI scans on 15 men who were wearing ties and 15 men who weren't.
- I'm actually going with the MRI machine.
(laughing)
- Very smart clothes.
- Should I pop my umbrella but I haven't.
(laughing)
- Yeah, and that's what they concluded.
So it is letting less, and it will give you headaches and dizziness and nausea if you wear
a tie more.
- Wow.
- And if you wear it to me.
- Right, yeah.
- I find now it's evolved into the work where if men going to work is rather
than suits, it is some skinny chinos, a quarter-zip jumper with a shirt underneath open neck,
and then a lanyard instead of a tie.
So people don't wear a tie because they're lanyards, which I think will evolve maybe one day
into something else.
But we've all become quite utilitarian, I think, in our clothing, I think we've all become
quite practical.
I think for a long time there was an air of flamboyance, about a lot of men's clothing,
which isn't afforded so much now.
I think if you went out, even me wearing a tie, people were like, "Oh, all right."
- Oh, yeah.
- Well, I don't know if you're having a wedding today.
- I'm literally just wearing the same thing as my dad might have worn, but you can't seem
like.
- Yeah.
- I was thinking to tight clothes or snug clothes and clothing innovations, because it's
really fun if you look in someone like new scientist for all the clothing inventions.
It's all like, "This is the clothing of tomorrow."
And so in 2007, Philips, the electronics people, they invented auto snug clothing, right?
Which is where?
The clothes with muscle wires woven through the fabric, you'd put it up to the power, and
it adjusts until your trousers are the exact right size for you.
- That's good.
- And then you know exactly what trousers you need from now on.
- Oh, yeah, I think that's good.
- I think that's useful.
I can imagine it going wrong, though.
- Oh, absolutely.
Yeah.
- To hundreds of people who were electrocuted very badly, very badly scorched during this.
But it's also, we have a tape measure.
We have the technology to find out what size trousers someone needs.
- It's not like until 2007 people were like, "This is like trousers, that's why I'm out."
- The other thing is, it's different in different countries, right?
So I bought a pair of large underpants in America and a pair in Japan, and I could tell you,
one of those, way too big for me, and the other one, I can't even squeeze them too.
- This is why James has his G-strings tailor in here.
- Look, you know of putting metal inside clothes.
That's what Lame is.
I didn't know this.
So Newdy in 1957 made Elvis Presley a $10,000 gold Lame suit.
And Lame is where you get your fabric, but then you put metallic fibers into it.
- Oh.
- I didn't know what that was.
Where else is Lame used in the sporting world?
- Gold being woven through-- - Or any metal woven through fabric, not horse-raining.
- Aerodynamics, stuff.
- Nope.
- I've got a wild theory.
- Go on.
- Is it tennis rackets?
- I thought you were going to get it, but no.
- For me, a one?
- No, it's not that.
It's used in fencing, because you need to, when someone stabs you with the sword, they
need to connect it, and so it's the threads inside.
So all fences use Lame suits in the same way that Elvis did.
- That suit of Elvis is amazing.
- Did you see that in your-- - I don't remember if I saw it, because they've got a pair
of the blue-sweight shoes, you know, they've got a load of costumes and outfits.
But that is, if you're listening to this and you want to know what that gold Lame suit
is, it's on the front cover of an album which gets referred to as 50 million Elvis fans
can't be wrong.
It's a very, very funny album title, and it's this mad gold suit.
- It's very loose.
It doesn't fit in with all well by a modern standard, but it's, yeah, I think about it.
I can't remember if I saw it there.
- If there was a lightning storm, wouldn't it?
- Oh, yeah.
- It'd be like, "Absolutely."
- Absolutely.
- At the road.
- I found a comedy play from the 1805 called The Taylors, which was shown at Covent Garden.
And it was kind of taken a piss out of young dandies at the time, and they were so annoyed
with it that they all turned up and started booing the actors and stuff.
And not only that, they decided to throw, not rot 'em tomatoes, but scissors and cutting
shears.
- Whoa!
- At the actors throughout the road, they roped 'em at night.
- Wow.
- Grizzly Adams is on stage too, and he has a terrible night.
- Isn't that mad?
- That's crazy.
- But how interesting to think of people who want to associate with sort of foppishness and
not being particularly agitated.
- Yeah.
- But young dandies is like, you know, muds, rockers, that kind of--
- But isn't it?
Yeah.
I know it's an obvious thing to say, but one realises that the things we see today have
all happened before.
- Yeah.
- Kind of protest all those kind of groups of people being, you know, people being outrageous
in their dress sense as a protest, or as an expression, and--
- Yeah.
- I've got a riddle for you guys.
- Oh, give it.
- Okay.
Carol Spencer was a fashion designer.
She spent 30 years working for the same client design encodes, but her clothes have never
been worn by a human.
- Riddle.
- Riddle means.
It's like a lacy.
- Well, it's up there.
- It wasn't a lacy.
- So it's nice.
- A horse saddle.
It wasn't a horse related.
- James would have got it in the bin.
- I think I've got it.
- God.
- I know my hit rate with the tennis racket.
- Yeah.
- Back and that up.
I think it's a living Madame Tussaud's wax work.
And with the fashion changing of the first--
- Like the sauna.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Exactly.
- They keep the wax work, but they don't.
- Oh, that's--
- And they change that.
- You're so close.
- Oh.
It's a model of a person, but it's not Madame Tussaud.
- Oh, is it the--
- Is it Lenin?
He's kept in the cabinet.
- It's not.
- Lenin's fashion.
- Yeah.
- It's a--
- Lenin's fashion.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Mr. February revolution.
- It's Lenin again.
- It's like the fashion show, where they're all healed out.
- Sherman L. Summer.
Look.
- Isn't the mannequin piece.
- It's not the mannequin piece.
- Right.
Shall I tell you all?
- Oh, I feel it.
We are close.
I'll tell you this one more clue.
- Okay.
- A client was only 11 1/2 inches high.
- Oh.
- She's fashionable.
She's got a lot of outfit changed.
- Bobby.
- Oh.
- We get there.
- I'm sorry.
- You know itching to tell us.
- No, no, no, no.
- To play the game.
- That was a bit longer.
- I'm so sorry for truncating in Brooklyn.
- No, no, no, no.
- I'm sure.
- We've all got homes to go too.
- For other people listening, we're like,
it's obviously Bobby.
- Is it Lenin?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
That's it.
That is all of our facts.
- Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found online.
I'm on Instagram, on @Streiberland.
James.
- Come find me on Tech Talk.
No such thing as James Harkin.
Andy.
- Instagram @AndruHunterreb.
Tom, where could we find you?
- My Instagram handle is @TomIndeed.
So do feel free to follow me there.
Or I have just started a visualized podcast.
I don't know if you're familiar with this idea.
And that is available from all podcast providers.
And also on YouTube at Tom Allen is the handle.
And it's called "Potering."
And it's about gardening and being in the garden with my friends.
- Oh, great.
So you're in the garden.
You've got your guests sitting there in the distance.
We see a carpet.
Just sort of wandering around.
- Yes.
Don't acknowledge him.
He's got another six years left.
- Well, yeah.
If you want to get to us as a group,
go to podcast@qy.com.
You can send us some facts.
You can send us some extra things that you want us to know about
that we were talking about.
Whatever you send Andy goes through these emails.
He cherry picks the best of them.
And they make their way to our bonus show called Drop Us A Line.
Now this is part of a secret club called Club Fish,
which you can find on Patreon.
If you go to patreon.com/nosuchthingasafish,
you can find all the details there.
And you can also send us your most interesting facts
of bonus show that goes out on this main feed called Little Fish
every Monday.
And we will be reading out the best of your facts on that show.
Otherwise, just come back here next week.
We're going to be back again with another wonderful guest.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]