*tongue outro music*
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covert Garden. My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with Andrew
Hunter Murray, Anish Zinsky and James Harkin and once again we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order here we go
starting with you Andy. My fact is that in the 19th century champion flowers were traded like
Premier League footballers. I don't know how exactly like Premier League football as it was but
it wasn't for like ten million pounds. No exactly, I think the sums were a bit lower but there was
a big thing where there were lots of plowing competitions in the 19th century where you had to
you had to plow up and down a field and one of the there are all these metrics in plowing about
whether you're doing it right or wrong and squires who had lots of plowmen would kind of pet them
against each other and then the winners would win a year's wages and then they might be transferred
could I just can I ask what a squire is because I associate that with King Arthur Times and this is
the 19th century where it started yeah so that's a kind of assistant to a nobleman isn't it okay but
in the late of times it's more of a kind of junior aristocrat sort of a slight landowner I think yeah
so for example you get the word squirearchy which is a word for quite affluent families from the
country is it is a not a very common word I think do you get the word I don't use it casually
pop conversation here's a less common word I think you used to get a squish it someone who was a
squire and a bishop that's great oh wow again don't use that in the normal conversation but that
is that do they just do that like Scorkman who delivers the milk but also a squire is that just
applies smashing the words and so it was landowners and they would get have these competitions so
that the land got plowed basically and so like for instance the first one ever in Kent was in
1867 on the first big one in Kent and that was run by a guy called Mr. Hart's Dyke who owned a massive
amount of land in Kent and who then later had children who had children who had children who
had Miranda from the TV Miranda oh wow and Tom Hart Dyke who we know yeah oh who he he was he's
still he works in in agriculture to an extent he he plants things yes so there's a massive garden
in Kent which he runs from his ancestral home which was where this plowing competition
wow isn't that so cool he got on the side now he got he was famous for being stolen or kidnapped by
gorillas out in the Dorian gap and they held him for months and they let him go finally and then he
went back to get directions and while he was kept by the gorillas they are the gorillas he
like I kind of you can't say yeah yeah well that damn pronounced it so profoundly like the word gorillas
I'm so that you clarify I'm slowly realizing we're talking about humans are not actual gorillas
the humans are talking so while he was kidnapped by these fighters he kept like a little garden
didn't he where he was kept and like he would ask them for plants and stuff like that to kind of
keep him sane a squirrella is someone who's a squire and the guerilla squire yeah so anyway I should
say that the way this comes from because it's a really good story it's a guardian long read on the
world plowing championship and it's an incredible read it's 5,000 words of plowing action and it's so good
so you there are all these things you have to do right basically you have to plow up and down
and plowing we should just say what it is it's turning soil upside down basically so you're
inverting it which means that you're bringing nutrients to the surface and you're plowing weeds
and other plants back into the earth so they break down and they feed the soil so the aim is
that you've prepared a field for planting yeah that's what plowing is yeah well I mean is it necessary
maybe we'll come on to that later yeah what's allowing us very controversial in this day and
it kills the soil yeah ruins farms now we've been doing it for thousands of years and now people have
suddenly started doing this thing called till free farming or no till farming where they've realized
you can just spread the seeds on unplowed land and they can actually get better yields it's a thing
this is why they've been doing it South America for years because their land isn't as robust as
ours and so they've realized that it's been really drying out and ring the nutrients because the idea
is that we suddenly disturb this massive ecosystem with this plow you dig down you wrench up all these
insects and stuff and you plop them on top and they don't know what they're doing well it's an argument
and the experiments are happening and they're getting kind of similar-ish results to plow fields
so might something in it I mean imagine if it turned out plowing have been totally pointless all
of these years well I mean it hasn't been there's been these amazing competitions going on
that's what you think about it and it's still and it's what they say it's the biggest event in Europe
the one that happens in Ireland in Ireland the outdoor event in 2017 291,000 people went along to the
plowing competition to see I read an article about it and it said that two thirds of the attendees
have absolutely no interest in agriculture whatsoever it's because it's a huge event you know
when you're someone's going to a village show because you're a bit bored of a Saturday it's like
a massive version of that it's like a festival kind of thing isn't it yeah and then how's
that attendance is twice as much as glass and brie here are some of the things that you can actually
see at it outside of the plowing there's a robotic milking machine that milks 40 cows so you can
watch that there's a pesteront which serves mealworms and crickets local locusts tractor football
so that's a that's one of the new chance yeah so it's teams of tractors push a giant football
around the field yeah and then they say there's there's the RTE tent where they have a very famous
commentator slash news broadcaster called Marty Morrissey and you can meet him and then they say
in brackets or his cardboard cutout yeah it's a massive deal and the same person has been
the head of the National Plowing Association which is the organization that runs it for 68 years now
since 85-year-old woman called Anna-May McCue who I think is a bit of a legend there basically
and so it's quite impressive that she's a woman because only about 2% of plowers who enter these
contests are women and she said I was reading an interview with her and she was saying that there's
this contest for farmer rats which are the female farmers and they sort of compete over who's
going to be queen of the plow and it used to be that the queen of the plow if you won that title
at the contest you were given a hundred pound dowry as long as you were married by the age of 25
wow yeah good right ancestor actually on that the the first farmette competition was in 1954
that was the first time they allowed women in and not many people were happy about it some people
said it was introducing Hollywood razzamatas at its worst sounds like it
they want introducing Mae Weston I also said that you were allowed to enter it if it was open this is
from I should say this is from Andy's article not your article but the one that you forwarded to us
which as Andy says is fantastic and so the farmette class was open to girls and women that were
single married or widowed which are the three I guess options of life generally but not divorced
you might be right um so that just while we're on plowing in sexism there is a really interesting
theory that plowing created sexism in the first place it's so good I wonder why you were so against
plowing gather so people plowing is invented with agriculture about 10 that roughly 10,000 years ago
10 to 8 and the original plows were called scratch plows so they don't turn the soil over they
just literally dig a little trench through it and you don't need too much strength to do it but you
do need quite a lot of upper body strength to do that and before that lots of women have been in
charge of fields in cereal growing because they were using hose and then when plowing has invented
and I mean hose smoking hose and then we're on the side of the sexism I thought you'd grab you've
gone later on to use to plant crops okay do you think that's where the phrase grows before
hose comes from but then when plowing is invented suddenly the men are in charge and in Mesopotamia
there's this flip from mother goddesses to male gods and this is the really weird thing it still
happens today as in the the effects might still be being felt so women descended from plow using
societies are much less likely to work outside the home or BMPs or run businesses whereas in
countries like Rwanda and Botswana and Madagascar which are mostly hoe using places and everyone's
giggling again but in those countries women are much likely to be in the labour force
because of but what's the reason that it drove women out is it the weight of the plow so it was
when people had to pull the plow or direct the animals exactly the first world plow champion
was a guy called Jim Eccles from Ontario and the only writer if I could find said that he was so shy
he only entered because his friends taught him into it and the second champion was Hugh Bar of
Antrim and Eccles only came eighth in this competition because according to the article I read he had
the bad luck of drawing a plot with a bump in it oh so it's all down to how lucky you were with
your little bit of field it's true and all the international competitors in that second one
which was in Ireland hated it because they had stony fields in Ireland and you didn't get stony
fields anywhere else around the world so you have to clear the stones out of the way I think before
you start so Richard Herring who's new podcast is about him clearing stones from fields is he
secretly training for the next international athlete now championship okay it is time for fact
number two and that is James okay my fat this week is that the American centre for disease control
has warned against kissing hedgehogs how come because they can give you illness they can give you
salmonella specifically and there have been eleven in January they said that there have been eleven
people in eight states who've got a strain of salmonella and in ten of the eleven cases the people
had reported recent contact with the hedgehog it's too much to be coincidence it's too much it's too
much I can only think that the eleventh person is lying this happened in Missouri in Minnesota in
Colorado main Mississippi in Nebraska Texas and Wyoming and we already knew that hedgehogs can give
you salmonella but it seems like it's a particularly bad strain at the moment in America it's so widely
spread across all the different states that it makes you think as though each state has one person
and they all know each other and they just have a hedgehog kissing club and they just like sending
videos around to each other or it could be just one widely traveled hedgehog who's just going
around attacking people is it French kissing that they're doing with the hedgehogs or is it just
it doesn't specify but I think it's nuzzling okay right if you imagine like a you could do that
if you had a small child with a hedgehog wouldn't you if I had a pet hedgehog I would definitely
kiss it at some point would you yeah okay I get attached it's edible right so they don't even have
to have snogged it some hedgehog come on just been near it and it's got in the dust between the
hedgehog and the cousin can do but it dies quite quickly in the air I think maybe you hold the hedgehog
and then you put it down and you suck your finger for the reason you like so you're bigger for any
reason yeah although you shouldn't uh incidentally while we're on giving advice about what to do with
hedgehogs you shouldn't have sex with them because in 2007 a Serbian man needed emergency surgery
after he had sex with a hedgehog on a witch doctor's advice she told him it would cure his premature
ejaculation and it actually just left him severely lacerated because they're covered in needles
any who sorry Salmanella yeah so other other animals in the US that can give you Salmanella or
that have given people Salmanella in the last few years include chickens ducklings guinea pigs frogs
turtles geckos and bearded dragons who have all given people Salmanella recently all from kissing or
from I don't know I don't know what kind of he's saying undercooked bearded dragons you know when he
is slightly undercooked bearded dragons you often feel sick afterwards uh turtle was in that list and
I was reading a story of um in China that was a man who made the news not too long ago because he
decided to get rid of his pet turtle so he was releasing it back into the wild and as he did so he
decided to give it a goodbye kiss um but unfortunately it was a snapping turtle and it grabbed onto
his lower lip and refused to let go um and you can see video footage of his face uh which does not
look good basically it kind of locked on and didn't come off um yeah so don't kiss turtles as
another thing just don't kiss other animals is that as well isn't it well there's a series a study uh
I think it was in 2015 and it was analysing you know how people kiss their dogs yeah yeah I mean I
include that in animals yeah no you're right but um it was at the University of Arizona and they
were trying to find out whether the microbes in dog guts might be good for humans okay and whether
they might actually it's like having a probiotic yogurt basically kissing a dog right um it is not
as delicious but this is really weird dogs and their owners end up having very similar gut bacteria
so it you end up with the same kind of microbiome and so the study was pairing people with dogs for
three months and testing them to see if there was any change yeah is that so does that mean it's a good
idea to kiss your dog because at least that you won't get a strange bacteria or it's kind of pointless
actually because you're not getting any new bacteria you didn't have already yeah I think they
were saying it could have good effects but also obviously it could have bad effects because what are
you for a piece of advice it probably means if you have your dogs bacteria in your stomach then it
would be easier for you to digest um dog food yeah come brexit do you guys know the what do you
think is the food stuff that most commonly gives people salmonella chicken eggs it's salmon or it's a
bit of salmon I used to think that I used to think salmon really salmon other yeah sorry it was just
found by a guy called salmon salmon no it salad or something it is yeah it's leafy greens um so I
didn't know this we don't give them enough stick it's cucumber and melon are responsible for
are responsible for 20% of cases of salmonella whereas chicken is only 19 oh what a stupid
hey it just overtook it the last minute I'm immediately going to go home throw away the balance
I replaced them with raw chickens anyway this is true and generally meat so chicken beef and pork
account for 33% of salmonella poisonings whereas leafy greens again a huge lead with 35%
um so we never talk about that and is I think the salmonella you get from salmonella you get from
the meats can be a more virulent strain so it produces the most deaths but really avoid salad I
think is the next big advice I think that's good advice um you said that it was invented it was
discovered by mr. Salmon um actually discovered by his assistant the abol smith uh Daniel
Salmon was the other guy uh and the abol smith was also the first person to discover that text could
spread disease and he also discovered anaphylaxis did you know oh he's quite a big deal that is a big deal
feels like he didn't get the credit he deserved there no smith anella is probably a hard word to say
you're right andaphylaxis is sometimes called the theobold smith predominant um but again don't
use that in conversation because people have no idea what I think if you're ringing 999 when someone's
having anaphylactic shock don't say he's suffering the theobold smith predominant sound clever
um hedgehogs yeah yeah there was a tradition in the Victorian times of having a hedgehog in your
kitchen to go around eating insects oh wow hedgehogs seem to make quite fun pets for some people so they
love running in their wheels didn't know there's a love running in their wheels more than anything so
like a hamster but more enthusiastic and I was on these sites which were saying which were giving
advice about how to keep hedgehogs they were saying you've got to take the wheel away as soon as
the hedgehog gets pregnant because they love the wheel so much that they'll keep running while they
give birth for instance wow they'll often then trample down the thing they've just given birth to
because they'll keep running no way they won't look after their babies because they're too busy running
in the wheel and sometimes they pick up the little hoglets so that's what you call the little hedgehogs
in their mouth to take them onto the wheel so at least they're with them but then they'll just run
over them it's like heroin it's like heroin yeah it's like hedgehog heroin that's another thing
you shouldn't indulge them while pregnant I believe a special advice that's amazing that's incredible
yeah pretty pregnancy they have very loud sex hedgehogs yep very loud sex especially with
the sleeping with a man from Serbia oh my god sake already
but they do have loud sex even when having sex with each other and there was a man in Germany
who called police once who's in his apartment he was reporting heavy panting happening under the
common stairwell in his house so we called the police saying can you stop these heavy panters
the police came round and they just found two mating hedgehogs under the stairs and as the police
spokesperson said we just found two hedgehogs loudly engaged ensuring the continuity of their species
and so they left them to it yeah because they last a long time which is why they could they were
still doing it when the police came round they can go on for hours which again I guess is why
they're particularly good it's more satirical
okay it's time for fact number three and that is my fact my fact is scientists have finally worked
out what time it is on Saturn and what time is it um it's well yeah uh we don't know it's we know
how long we we know how long that I can't tell you exactly right now what time it is on Saturn
I can tell you how long a day is on Saturn and that's what they've worked out it's 10 hours
33 minutes and 38 seconds now this is new from what we thought decades ago up by as the article says
several minutes it's it's a very interesting reason of how they found it out so Cassini which was
the spacecraft which has been taking all the images that we have a Saturn it's it was an incredible
mission that is ended now I believe that the Cassini is actually burnt up into Saturn's atmosphere now
but everyone was looking for how long it took to rotate um by looking at the planet and there was a
student of astronomy at UC Santa Cruz who started looking at the data about the rings of Saturn and
what they noticed that the rings themselves started taking impressions off them kind of like how if
you were having a earthquake on earth you could use seismology to work out how strong it was say
they were noticing that a similar thing was going on with the core of Saturn that was releasing
certain seismological waves that were being recorded in the rings so what the guy did was he made a
simulation of how fast the core would be turning by using the waves that were imprinted on the ring
on a computer simulation and by doing that was able to match it up with what the spin would be
and that came out at 10 hours 33 minutes and 38 seconds oh well when when they discovered the rings
it was a pretty confusing episode so Galileo the first person to observe the rings and describe
them poor guy this is in 1610 and he saw it with a telescope and he sent this cryptic message to
Kepler saying I've seen the highest triform planet and Kepler told King Rudolph and Rudolph said what
the hell you on about Galileo and he Galileo said I think it's three planets side by side because he
was sort of seeing it as three um but then so he wanted to have another look at it so he waited a
couple of years for some reason and then um after a couple of years what he didn't realize was that
he was observing them at the Saturn ring plane crossing so that is when Earth crosses like into
the exact plane of Saturn's rings so it happens about once every 13 to 15 years and at that point
because they're so flat if you're looking at them face on you can't see anything
so Galileo looked they'd totally gone and he was really freaked out he thought I have no idea what's
gone on them so so it seems like I've lied that's bad luck it's really bad how often does that happen
every 13 to 15 years god so it's the same thing of that timing you know if we didn't look again we
would assume that it didn't have it but it was just that little blip yeah where suddenly it just
doesn't to us yeah and then it's going again a bit later oh yeah yeah the second check how did
you know it was the same one I would have thought I've just seen a different one a different planet
yeah yeah I guess that's what astronomers do for living isn't it they could predict where
the planets were going to be they knew which was which yeah he was a smart guy Andy okay well
not that you're not but probably in different ways yeah I would like to see him improvising the
Jane Austen play I think we all would actually love that amazing I'd actually go and see
but the rings of Saturn they're 180,000 miles wide and they're only 300 feet high yeah
always that that's crazy isn't there 400 kilometers wide like the actual ring bit there so they're
that many miles across around the from one end of the ring to the very first on the other side
of the planet yeah yeah but yeah they are incredibly flat I think someone worked out that if they were
the equivalent of paper so if they were the thickness of paper then you need a sheet of paper that
was 1.7 miles across wow that's the equivalent there's a theory that I just saw in the new scientists
this afternoon which says that the planet Pluto might be a billion comets squished together
that's how all the planets are really aren't they they're just bits of rock and dust squished
together I guess I think there was an alternative theory but I have I literally just saw it as we
sat down so yeah it's not even even Saturn began as a pebble just begins as a pebble going around
and then another pebble squashes into it and then bigger pebbles bigger pebbles if actually you've got
Saturn that's quite that's such a nice fable you'll make a great dodgy your kids feeling a bit small
you can always say even Saturn was once a pebble that's great yeah look at him now look at him now
oh huh did you guys know just speaking of sort of time and space that there are two different days
on earth we have two different days there are seven in a week oh my god I've been saying that all wrong
oh my god what's half a juice day it's not Monday again
it's invigorating no there are two different types of day on earth so there's a solar day
which is the one that we know which is the 24 hour day actually the more legit day so if I asked you
what is the definition of a solar day how quickly we spin round yeah how many degrees have you spun
around yeah three six yeah in correct it's actually a tiny bit more than 360 so a sedereal day
is 23 hours and 56 minutes and that's how quickly the earth does one rotation of 360 degrees but
actually because we are also rotating around the Sun every time the earth rotates in order to get
from midday one day to exactly midday the other it needs to spin that tiny bit more because he moved
around a bit more so our 24 hour day is actually you're spinning around a bit more than 360 degrees
and I didn't know that how does that affect our working life and pay and stuff well so I think
what you can say is actually the day is four minutes shorter than you thought so you can go home
from work four minutes earlier than new plans great yeah let's do it yeah finished now
just stop this podcast four minutes before the end yeah yeah so do you know how long a day is on
the Sun how long it takes the Sun to rotate once on its axis yeah and as opposed to when it's
light which is all the time it's 24.5 earth days on the equator but 34 earth days at the poles and
this is always a problem isn't it because they're big gas things and things are spinning at different
speeds yeah so if you're on a holiday you would have your holiday at the pole of the Sun
because you get you get longer still hot this time of year yeah I don't know if you want longer I
think you want to shorten that holiday as much as possible if you're holidaying on the Sun don't you
well and I see you've got very good good factor good factor Sun cream yeah okay that's amazing though
it has two different days or three and it's different days okay yeah so Saturn the Saturn is a god
in Roman mythology right um so there's also Jupiter Jupiter all the planets are gods basically
not earth apart from earth all the power unless you can't guy who's Greek goddess
but Jupiter's far Jupiter the fifth planet then the Saturn the sixth Jupiter's father is Saturn right
right and then the next planet is Uranus and Uranus is the father of Saturn so Jupiter
next planet father next planet father the solar system is basically a big who do you think you are
yeah in some traditions Mars the fourth planet is the son of Jupiter so that so yeah it's like a
family tree going outwards that's a way you can remember and so is Uranus's father Neptune
I think we didn't know about Neptune and the father of all the gods is that cartoon duck
that is really cool that's really yeah Pluto knocked out because that just didn't work for the
system it actually is a planet but they're like okay it is time for our final fact of the show and
that is Chazinski my fact is that the first ever blood transfusion to be a scientifically recorded
used a goose quill to connect an artery in the neck of one dog to the joggular vein in the neck of
another and it was successful the dog was okay one of the dogs was okay it was half a success it was
a hot well the dog was okay that they wanted to be okay the dog that was receiving blood exactly
so it's actually quite mean this was done in 1666 by a guy called Richard Lauer or Lauer who was
from Cornwall and he traveled up to the Royal Society in London and did it in front of an audience
and he apparently got a medium sized dog I don't know why the size was that relevant but he severed
its jugular and blood it until it was approaching death and then thought okay cool now we can see if
we can save this dog and he did that by then sort of severing the artery of a secondary dog attaching
a quill between the two and siphoning the blood from the secondary dog into the next one but then
you need a third dog to save the second dog and indeed yeah they call that day the massacre of 500
dogs no don't you ever be the massacre of one it's only over the last dog on the congular
yeah could you not like put it in like a circle so that everyone gets everyone else oh yeah wow he
should have done that I don't know why he didn't do two gruse quills and swap them but no he didn't
he just bled you put in a second quill at the back end of the dog couldn't you one in the neck of
the dog and one in the bum of the dog don't think it works like that doesn't it and then you get the
blood just going round you know you've got two hearts you've got two circulatory systems yeah just
like a circuit I don't know that doesn't go for the head to the bum and the back end I think that would
work yeah you said the transfusion came to an end when the emittant dog which is the one who gave
the blood began to cry and faint and fall into convulsions and the last die oh yeah they weren't
the animal rights weren't as strong in the olden days yeah but it was successful which is kind of
weird actually because just like humans really when you're doing blood transfusions in pets it's good
to have the same blood type I think dogs have same blood type I know cats have a a b and b yeah I
think they're different a's and b's aren't they as in their different proteins on the oh are they
I believe so yeah but hang on would it would that's a I've never considered that would a great
day and have different types of blood to a scotty no so all dogs so all dogs can give blood to
all other dogs but I feeling they can't give its humans because of the pro the antigens on the
yes although I didn't know they could give it to all other dogs I think so it's the same species
isn't it it's just different yeah but all humans can't give blood to all other humans oh sorry no
yeah you're right yeah so it's the same as humans as in a scotty and a tie patient now the
yes yeah yeah yeah yeah if you're a bird any kind of bird then you can have a transfusion from
any other kind of bird wow so rubbing could donate to an ostrich but you'd need quite a lot of
rubbins that's incredible yeah so donating blood between animals they started you know injecting
blood from let's say a calf into a person that was a few a year later after this first experiment
and he died so it was banned for a long time the person died yeah but there was this weird
rash of cases in the mid 19th century where doctors just started saying well milk will probably
work just as well and putting milk into people's bloodstreams directly yeah yeah they thought because
it's got these little oily droplets and fatty droplets they thought well they might turn into white
blood cells and they just there were two doctors called bovell and Hodder and this is all from I found
this a journal called transfusion and this is the 1969 edition but they wrote up the whole thing
and their first patient was said to respond dramatically to 12 ounces of cow's milk
but two other patients who they transfused the following week died and people kept dying as well
when they say it was pondermatically and it happened and for 25 years at least
that people were just putting milk into your blood well they started that's how they started doing
it even in the 17th century so Christopher rendered a lot of this bizarrely before he got into building
cathedrals but he was involved with which allowed with his first transfusion and he used to inject
dogs with water, milk, beer, wine and opium to see if any of them were just blood transfusions.
He once said I have injected wine and ale into a living dog into the mass of blood by a vein
in good quantities till I have made him extremely drunk but soon after he pisseth it out
but also the idea of putting animal blood into humans there was a big theological debate about
what you would be doing if you were putting foreign blood into someone else's body because
supposedly the soul would be contained inside some of that blood so you're altering the whole
person so what they used to plan out was if they were going for someone who was a bit wild they
would get sheep's blood because that was a calm nurturing Jesus-like animal would then give
a sort of balance of a soul to this wild character equally if they had someone who was very shy
they might adopt an animal that had a bit more of a wild attitude and the idea was to inject
them with that blood although a sociable Jesus-like lamb lamb lamb lamb lamb of God okay yeah yeah
similarities there's a weird thing this is so on just taking blood and putting it into other people
we've said before you know the secret service in America they have several pints of the president's
blood type in his car which is pretty cool but I read this piece in the Atlantic about how the
secret service was protecting Barack Obama's DNA because you know we all shed millions of cells
a day yeah so the DNA is intact so if you let's say the president shook hands with you and you got a
few live cells or he sneezed and he threw away the tissue you could make you can now make cells
into other cell types so you could make synthetic sperm cells from the president's sneeze in a tissue
and then you can you know they can't fertilize eggs with them but you could say oh look we've
got evidence of this so they could what you could say they might clone Barack Obama or I think it's
not exactly that you'd make another president but you could one another but why do you want another
who doesn't want to know why stay you I'll take a sterile sperm cell of Barack Obama is president of
America but you could so you could fabricate evidence of an affair or you can or for example you
can analyze the genetic markers of diseases that you could say well he's more prone to outzymas
or to this heart disease and you could cast out on their legitimacy that way truth that he was
born in Africa yeah so yeah so these this is a real problem so presumably they have Trump's DNA as
well I think a lot of people have Trump's DNA in Japan a blood type is a super important thing
isn't it I don't think we've mentioned before I think we've done it on QI but it's on job applications
and stuff it's so related to thought to be so related to who you are and what you're like kind
of like how we see maybe star signs but much more believed in and invested in and yeah you'll have
to say on your application what blood type you are but they I mean saying horoscopes they in the
morning TV shows in Japan they have the blood type horoscopes they do do that and yeah and on an
Asian Asian countries on their Facebook profiles that tends to be a thing and you're about you would
have your blood type in there because it tells you a lot about who you are for potential you know I
didn't even know what my blood type was until earlier this year that's weird isn't it I still don't
know I don't know I don't know I always call my mom whenever I need to know it she knows it well
she's very deaf though so she always says hey thanks mom okay that's it that is all of our facts thank
you so much for listening if you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that
we have said over the course of this podcast we can be found on our Twitter accounts I'm on
at Shriberland Andy at Andrew Hunter James James Harkin and Anna you can email podcast at qi.com
yep or you can go to our group account at no such thing or our website no such thing as a fish.com
we have all of our previous episodes up there we also have a page of links to all the tour dates
that we're going to be playing in the next few months and look out for some European ones very
exciting we're going to a place called Europe okay we'll be back again next week with another
episode we'll see you then goodbye
[BLANK_AUDIO]