(upbeat music)
- Hey everyone, Andy and Dan here.
- Hello.
- Before we, yep, there he is.
So this week's episode,
which I wanna let you know is a live recording.
We did this a few weeks back at the London podcast festival
and as Anna is away on maternity at the moment,
we had a very exciting guest join us.
And that was Richard Osman.
- Yes, Richard is here, partly for the love of the game,
but partly because he's also got a new book out.
It is the fifth in the Thursday Murder Club series.
If you haven't heard of this, I'm amazed
'cause it is a global multi-million selling series.
It's absolutely fantastic.
I have read all four previous outings
of the Thursday Murder Club.
They're all great.
I cannot wait to get my tea stuck into the new one,
which is out right now.
It has just come out.
It is called The Impossible Fortune
and it's gonna be terrific.
I know it.
- Yeah, it really is an amazing series.
I like Andy.
I've read them all really excited for this one.
And on top of it, you know,
Richard arrives to do our show in the craziest of weeks
because not only is his book coming out,
but also the Thursday Murder Club
has been converted into a movie.
It's on Netflix.
It stars Helen Mirren.
It's got Pierce Brosnan.
It's directed by Chris Columbus of Home Alone
and Harry Potter.
Spielberg's got his name as an exec.
It's an amazing cast and collection of creatives.
So if you wanna check out the first book in movie form,
that's up now.
- Yeah, but Dan, speaking of all this book stuff,
are we going near any book world events anytime soon?
- I believe we are, Andy.
I believe we are back on stage live,
doing something similar to what you are about to hear,
except as it's in the future,
you can come and be in the audience for it.
It's the Cheltenham Literary Festival
and we are gonna be doing it live
with special guest, Rachel Parris.
- Yes, it's gonna be on the 16th of October,
8 p.m., Cheltenham, live, unplugged.
We will be plugged in.
There will be electrics.
It's gonna be so much fun.
You can get your ticket right now
at no such thing as a fish.com/live,
but hurry, tickets are going like hot books.
- Hot books?
- Yep.
Just go along with it, mate.
- All right, well listen, if you wanna see us live
and you'll get a little taster of it now,
go to the website as Andy says, book your tickets
and join us in the room for the recording.
So let's hear this one now.
It is Richard Osman.
We know such thing as a fish.
On with the show.
- Yay!
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast,
this week coming to you live
from the London Podcast Festival.
(audience cheering)
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin
and Andrew Hunter Murray and Richard Osman.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Richard.
- One nominee for best TV show at the first Emmys
was the masked Spooner.
It was like the masked singer,
except the celebrity was spooning rather than singing.
- So that was what year, Richard?
- 1949.
- And you've got to guess who's spooning you?
- Yeah.
- Which celebrity is spooning you?
- It feels like a format that wouldn't get made these days.
- Big spoon or a little spoon, do we know?
- Spooning is sort of a misnomer.
Nobody was cradling anybody at this stage.
Spooning was a mixture of spoken word and crooning.
So the masked Spooner, who is a, well,
we'll get onto who it was
because you had to try and guess who it was,
but they never told you.
And that's why the masked Spooner
I think didn't do quite as well as the masked singer,
because you'd have a whole episode.
And at the end, you wouldn't have Jonathan Ross going,
is it Bono?
And then you go, no, it's former home secretary,
Alan Johnson.
(audience laughing)
I should have sworn it was Bono.
Next week, I bet it's Bono next week.
No, it's someone from Emmerdale.
- Yeah.
- So he would essentially turn up at places
and he would sing to people in a mask
and you would constantly be asked who he was
and you would go, oh, gosh, I bet it's Alan Ladd.
And they go, no, guess again.
Oh, I don't know any other celebrities from the 1940s.
Well, unlucky.
But then at the end they go, see you next week.
- Wow.
- And that was the masked Spooner.
It won't surprise you to know it didn't win the Emmy.
- Yes, it did not.
Pantamime Quiz won the Emmy that year, I believe.
- I don't know, it didn't.
(audience laughing)
- That was a charades thing, basically.
So you would have two teams.
There were four people in each team.
Three of the members of one team would always be the same
and they'd have a rotating guest
and then you would have them acting out like charades.
And 1949, that probably was mind-blowing.
- Yeah, I mean, to have a rotating guest for a start.
(audience laughing)
They're like, they haven't seen that before.
- These are-
- Tied to a spit in the middle of the studio.
- These are, by the way, the other shows
that were nominated.
You had Armchair Detective,
which sounded really great, actually.
I don't know if you read into that,
but Armchair Detective-
- Can I guess?
- Yep.
- Every crime, every week.
Someone's been killed, but in a chair.
- Yeah.
- You're right so far.
- Oh, no.
- What, is he?
- Okay, so someone's killed it.
Great, just go with it, go with it.
- I actually, that was just a pun you missed.
You're right so far.
You're right.
I was just trying to-
- Oh my God.
- So it's, we're in Los Angeles.
The city of sin.
(audience laughing)
- You see, and that's how you do a pun, Dan.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Well, it sounds like an Armchair Cop.
- Yeah.
- It's sort of a very specialized unit in the police,
I would say.
- What it was is, it was a show where they would put on
a drama in which someone is murdered,
and you at home had a chance to guess who it was.
So, and they had a panel as well live who would sit there.
So you would watch the drama,
and then they would stop at a moment for you to deliberate,
and then they would actually show you what happened.
- Do you know what, there was an actual show on TV in Britain
about two or three years ago with the exact same name
and the exact same format
that Susan Kalman hosted, wasn't it?
- Correct.
- Really?
- Is there no such thing as a new idea, Richard?
- Well, I would say that the mask spooner at the time
was a new idea.
(audience laughing)
- But today, is it like a lot of the new formats,
the kind of old formats that are--
- Of course, yeah.
People want something that's a tiny, tiny, tiny bit different
to what they've seen before.
- Right.
- That's all you want.
Like when the Traders comes out, every single channel goes,
I tell you what people would like,
something that's a bit like the Traders, but worse.
(audience laughing)
And that's how TV has always worked.
When we did Deal or No Deal, my God, the next five years,
some of the worst television programs
in the history of the world came out,
where people just went,
"Oh, people just like random stuff, do they?"
"Okay, we'll do that."
And channel five did Heads or Tails,
which is a whole week of Justin Lee Collins flipping a coin.
(audience laughing)
And then Simon Kal did the same thing with Red or Black,
which was Choose Red or Choose Black,
and I'll give you a million pounds.
- Oh, that was Anton Deck?
- Yeah, it was Anton Deck.
It was a million pounds and still nobody watched.
- Really? - Can you imagine?
- Wow.
- I watched a clip of that earlier today
while researching this, and I found it compelling.
I really, like, if I'd known at the time,
I would have been hooked.
- Well, no, but compelling in that sort of, you know,
a Netflix documentary about a poop cruise,
rather than I would love to watch this live.
- Yeah.
- Have you got some more of those?
- Yeah, yeah, there was one called
"What's the Name of That Song?"
- Can you guess what that format was?
(audience laughing)
- God, I think you could do it.
- I love that.
- It was quite nice.
The first ever Emmys,
there was only about five awards that were given out,
but the special award was my favorite.
The special award went to Louis McManus,
who was awarded the Emmy for designing the Emmy statue.
- That's clever.
- For the Emmy. - Oh, that's easy.
- Yeah.
- Does anyone know why the Emmys are called the Emmys,
by the way?
- Named after a person?
- No.
- Oh.
- So we think, so the Tonys are named after a person.
The Oscars are sort of named after,
I mean, there's also several versions
of why the Oscars are called the Oscars,
but the Emmys, I thought maybe they'd be like M-E,
or something like musical entertainment awards,
but it's not, I'll tell you,
there are, you know, the cathode ray in your television.
They have the same sort of thing,
but in video cameras,
and there were two competing versions of this
in the '30s and '40s, right?
There was the RCA image orthicon tube,
that was the first one,
and then there was the EMI Emitron, okay?
So we've got the RCA image orthicon tube
and the EMI Emitron.
Now, you've been doing this show long enough,
but if I ask you the question,
which of those two were the Emmys named after?
(laughing)
What would you go for?
- I've got the Emitron.
- The Emitron, yeah.
- You'd be wrong.
(laughing)
It is named after the RCA image orthicon tube,
which they used to call an EMI.
So someone said, "Oh, we should call these the Emmys,"
'cause that's the industry we're in.
- Oh my God.
- Because the Louis MacManus made the statue into a woman,
they said, "Oh, why don't we call it EMI
"instead of EMI?"
So it became the Emmys.
- Brilliant.
- But named after the orthicon tube
rather than the Emitron.
(laughing)
Which, by the way, was made by EMI, which also--
- What it should have been called was the Dorothy,
because that's who Louis modeled it after, his wife.
- Oh, but everyone's always modeling after their wives,
weren't they? - Yeah.
- But all those statues, yeah.
- I think the Rolls Royce is a bit racier.
Isn't the Rolls Royce a mistress or something?
- Yes.
- Silver sprite figure on the front of a Rolls Royce.
- Yes, yeah.
- Isn't the Statue of Liberty like the face is his mother
and the body is his wife?
- Wow.
- There's something like-- - What?
- That is a very, very nice fetish, isn't it?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- And you know what?
I'm gonna make a 200 feet high.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- I'm just, I'm sure we'll move on
and talk about more TV formats and things like that,
but I have a little quiz for you of spoon-related slang.
- Oh.
- 'Cause we were on the Masked Spooner.
- The Masked Spooner.
- Actual spoons.
- Well, you'll see.
(laughing)
So part of the reason that the Masked Spooner
was a bit cheeky was that spooning,
to mean cuddling up to someone,
was dates from 1887, I think.
- Yeah, so he knew it was a double untied.
- He knew it was a bit cheeky, yeah, yeah, yeah.
And there are all these references.
It's also a cricketing term dating back to 1836,
meaning a weak stroke.
But anyway, it's spooning dates to 1887.
Now spoon me, Stirling stretched himself out
on the warm flagstone and the boy nestled up against him.
I don't know the context,
I just know that that's what was happening.
- Do you know what?
That's my favorite of your novels.
That is a bit cheap to promote it on the show, but...
- Okay, to stick one spoon in the wall.
What does that mean?
- Are they from Urban Dictionary or something, so?
- Are you sure it's not to stick one spoon in the walls?
Because that's an ice cream reference, that's easier.
That's much easier.
To stick one spoon in the wall?
- Yeah, to stick one spoon in the wall.
- Is it to try and do something that's almost impossible?
- No, it's very possible.
We all do it.
- Oh, we do?
- Yeah.
- Oh, is it like Shawshank Redemption?
- Oh yeah.
- Oh, it's older than that.
It's from the 19th century, so it's pre-Shawshank.
- Okay.
- Shall I tell you?
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's to die.
Oh.
As you're doing on stage right now.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- I'm not sure we even want round two.
I'm not sure we've earned round two.
- Definitely do.
I mean, good luck topping that.
- Yeah.
- I put the strongest one first.
(laughing)
- To stick one spoon.
I'd love it if a doctor ever said that you,
Mr. Hunter Murray, I'm ever so sorry.
We did everything we could,
but I'm afraid your mother has stuck a spoon in the wall.
(laughing)
- Oh my God.
- To fill the mouth with empty spoons.
- To fill your mouth.
- False promises.
- To waste your time.
- False promises, wasting your time.
- Wasting your time.
- Lying.
It's someone in the audience said it's just being hungry.
- Oh.
- Weird, these didn't catch on.
- Yeah.
- Well, a spoon can also be a second rate coachman,
a penis, a shovel, 1/16 of an ounce of heroin,
or a newly qualified prison officer.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- There's lots of times where you can say
stick in your spoon in the wall,
and depending on which spoon you're talking about,
it could mean something very true.
- Very true.
- Richard, just as someone who's created
some of the most defining quizzes of our time.
- And some of the worst, to be fair.
- Okay.
- Where does Andy's What's My Spoon rank on?
- I would say fairly highly up,
when I think of some of my stuff.
I mean, yeah, it feels like maybe,
I'm not sure it's a runner.
Like series two, I don't think people are going,
oh, I wonder what more spoon stuff
Andrew has for us this week.
- Yep.
- That sort of work.
But if you moved it out to other utensils,
so the first one is what the spoon,
second one, what the fork.
- Yeah.
- See, there's the fork.
- We've got ourselves something.
- It's not the end of your quiz, Andy.
- I'm afraid.
- Okay.
- I just want to quickly say a little bit more
about the Mask Spooner.
- Yeah.
- Because this was the kind of thing,
it started off as a bit of a meme.
So there was this guy who's going around like restaurants
and bars and he was always wearing this outfit,
which it's like got a mask on and he's got a hood.
You can't really see what he is.
And then all the Hollywood magazines started writing
about him and saying,
who is the Mask Spooner who's going around?
And actually it became a bit of a thing
where people guessing in magazines and newspapers
who he was.
And then the TV show was almost a spin-off.
- Okay.
- And yeah, and he got like,
he was getting marriage proposals from people.
And yet he never gave away the secret.
And in the end, it felt like he was kind of holding on
to give it away, give it away.
But in the end, everyone just gave up
and didn't really care anymore.
- Yeah.
- Do we know who he was?
- We do know now, yeah.
Because when he was going around to all these restaurants
and the newspapers were writing about him,
they heard about him from his friend called Jack Rook.
And Jack Rook would say,
oh, the Mask Spooner is going to be in the old bar
in Soho tonight.
And actually it was him.
- Yeah.
And here's the thing,
Jack Rook was big in his own right at the time.
He wasn't an anonymous character that you would just,
when you heard his name,
it was like Jack Rook,
it'd be like saying Richard Osmond,
he was a huge force in the world of entertainment in America.
He effectively created,
or at least popularized from massive scale, telephones.
And I think the word itself was almost coined
by Jack Rook, telephone.
- I think it was, yeah.
- The Mask Spooner invented telephones.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
- He also invented the political debate on camera,
on screen.
So when, was it Nixon?
I think it was Nixon.
- He did a big show with Nixon, yeah.
- Yeah, big Nixon fan.
- He did a telephone for Nixon
and raised loads of money for his election.
- Can I just say a sad thing about this though?
In 1994, Jack Rook finally stuck his spoon in the wall.
(all laughing)
- Yeah.
- It's gonna catch on.
- Isn't it a shame?
- I don't know how else to put it.
(all laughing)
- I was trying to find TV shows
which have where everyone is in a mask,
or someone is in a mask.
- Oh yeah, that's it.
- And there was an amazing TV show
that you may or may not have heard of.
It was called Mr. Personality, right?
2003, American, it's a dating show.
And there was one woman called Hailey Arp,
who was going, she was wanting to get married,
wanting to find love.
And there were 20 suitors, guys,
and they were trying to catch her eye
and she was wanting to be picked by her in the show.
But they were all wearing intense iron masks,
or sometimes like rubbery, quite gimpy masks,
throughout the series.
- And was that her thing?
- No, no, not at all.
- It wasn't their thing either, like it was nobody's thing.
- And it was-
- Apart from one of them, one of them,
was that your thing?
(all laughing)
So you go, do you know what,
I might not go for number seven.
He has been erected the entire series.
(all laughing)
- It was actually won by a man called Will Dick,
funny you say that, but.
(all laughing)
And they were only allowed to remove their masks
in a pitch black room and she would feel their faces
and then they put the mask back on.
Monica Lewinsky was the host, obviously.
- No.
- Wait, wait.
I would like, and frankly,
the second worst decision she's ever made
was to host this show.
And it was an absolute disaster.
- Amazing.
- The men didn't even know they were gonna be in masks
until they turned up on the first day of shooting.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So can you pop this on for the next five weeks?
- Right.
- Disaster.
- But they all would have said yes, they'd go,
yeah, okay, that's the thing where people can't tell you.
Especially in like 2003, anyone would have done anything.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- We pretended to send people to space.
The show called Space Cadets.
- Were you part of that?
- What was your show?
- I mean, I wasn't.
But was I part of it?
That's a good question.
What's your view on it?
(audience laughing)
No, I, with two of us, we're going,
what's the biggest practical joke you could ever pull?
- Yeah.
- And we said, I wonder if you could convince people
they'd ever been to space.
And any time when we pitched it, they said,
yeah, but sure, but you're not floating.
And you go, yeah, you don't float in space
'cause of the vacuum seal.
They went, okay.
(audience laughing)
I'm like two weeks late to go.
Is that true?
You go, no, but you believed it.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is Andy.
- My fact is, in 1990, most of the red kite birds
in England had arrived here by British Airways.
So this is about the red kite.
This is a beautiful bird.
And they're kind of all over the place these days.
In the '90s, they were absolutely not.
At the worst, I think they got down
to like five breeding pairs in Wales.
And you had to go to Central Wales
to have even a sniff of a red kite.
And they had this project, Mike Pionkowski was a guy
from the Joint Nature Conservation Committee
and his colleague Colin Galbraith and lots of colleagues.
They knew this bird was declining a bit across Europe,
but in England, there hadn't been any for about 400 years.
- It was about to put its spoon bit in the wall.
(audience laughing)
- Oh my God.
Oh my God.
- Andy, lean into it.
He's gonna get you a TV show under this.
- You're right, you're right.
And they thought, well, maybe we could restore them
in England and they imported maybe a dozen
from Navarra in Spain.
And they arrived on British Airways.
Amazingly, they were flown in the main cabin
with paying customers.
So as you got on, there was a load of boxes
on the seats strapped in.
Now that's a film, that's a film.
- What, boxed red kites on a plane?
- I think something happens, right?
- It's not--
- No, my film is about the conservation effort.
It's like nothing happens.
(audience laughing)
And basically, the population has grown
two and a half thousand percent since 1995.
And it's a massive--
- That's pretty good.
- Now they're reaching seagull status
in the rest of the country.
- I read that they're getting to the point
where schools aren't allowing the kids
to eat lunch outside because they're swooping down
and trying to steal their lunch.
- Is that right?
I read that when they did come over,
they spread initially along the M40 corridor
because there were so many dead animals
by the side of the road.
- And that's what they love to eat.
- Yeah, they're scavengers, aren't they?
- That's a lovely thought, isn't it?
(audience laughing)
- And the reason that there weren't so many of them
is because they were all killed, basically, right?
So they like to eat dead things,
but if a farmer sees them eating like a dead lamb
or something like that, they haven't killed the lamb,
but the farmer thinks that they might have done.
And so during the Tudor times,
there was a thing called the Vermin Act of 1566.
And that said that if you killed a red kite
and you could prove it, you'd get some cash.
And so people basically went out
and killed as many of them as they could.
And the idea was to help the farmers,
but of course we now know
that it didn't really help them at all.
Also, if you killed a hedgehog,
you could get up to four pence,
which doesn't sound a lot,
but that could buy you 20 pints of beer
in Elizabethan prices for one hedgehog.
- Really?
- Wow.
- Getting you a certain number of pints
means nothing to me recently
since I discovered weather spoons
because up until recently,
you could get a pint of Ruddles for 99p.
99p.
I could go to the bar with a 20 pound note
and come back with 20 pints.
- Or one hedgehog.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Danny, have you taken another advertising gig
on the side?
- No.
- But Ruddles is a fine, fine beer.
(laughing)
- And affordable.
- Wow.
- It's actually gone up controversially
to like a pound 49 now or something like that.
It's me and the other guys at 9 a.m.
and the weather spoons are furious.
(laughing)
Anyway, back to Red Kites.
- Yeah, sure.
- Yeah.
- That's the most animated I've seen Dan
in any other side of the world.
(laughing)
Finally discover what he's interested in.
- Do you know one other thing Red Kites do?
This is, no, there's been a big vote
for wild swimming, as I'm sure you know.
And a lot of people like to swim, oh, natural.
- Where's this going?
We know they can kill lambs.
(laughing)
They sometimes will steal your clothes
if you're wild swimming in a river.
They would nick your clothes to line their nest.
- Oh yeah.
- And then some Red Kite chick has a, you know,
lovely pair of white fronts.
- I've heard this.
They found nests with a teddy bear's head in it,
a tea towel in it.
And in 2006, they found a nest
with a St. George's flag in it.
It might have been painted in by a local.
(laughing)
But it was discovered less than an hour
before England's World Cup match against Paraguay.
And so it hit the newspapers
that this was very patriotic, Red Kite.
- Did we win that match?
- Against Paraguay, I can't, I think we did, yeah.
- Do you know what their Latin name is?
- Red Kite.
- Yeah, it's Milvus Milvus.
Do you know what Milvus means?
- No.
- Bird.
(laughing)
They're called Bird Bird.
Linnaeus called them Falco Milvus,
but then Milvus became its own genus.
And so then it got renamed
and Milvus was put in front of it.
So they're Milvus Milvus.
- That's very funny.
- Yeah, Bird Bird.
- Very good.
- It is a problem, we should say.
It's a great story of reintroduction
of a really precarious species,
but they are eating people's lunch,
and that is a problem.
Article this spring from the Henley Standard.
Red Kite stole my hummus.
(laughing)
Jeff Hay, 72 years old,
was having some nice hummus in his garden.
And got swooped on, predated, and scratched.
And it was the third time in five years
that a Red Kite has snatched food from him
while he was eating outside.
- He sounds careless.
- I got some stuff on things that have been on aeroplanes
that feel quite out of place.
I'm a big comedy fan, and Tony Hancock.
You must have loved Tony Hancock growing up.
- I mean, I'm not 70, but move on.
- When did he die, when did he die?
- I can't actually remember, I think.
- It certainly was before I was 10.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- No, sorry, I'm not suggesting that you saw it live.
- I think Hancock's half hour was on TV
when I was a kid for sure.
- Yeah, I think a lot of us grew up on Hancock's half hour.
- Yes, I don't think I grew up watching Hancock's half hour.
- Sorry to--
- No, good lesson to just say the fact
and not accuse you of a childhood memory you don't have.
So basically, Tony Hancock, for anyone
who doesn't know him apparently--
- Oh, Tony Hancock, I thought you meant Nick Hancock.
I'm so sorry.
- Tony Hancock was one of the great British comedians.
- He was the one who said, in the blood donor,
he said, you know, a pint that's nearly an arm full
or something, right?
- Yes.
- He was the one who had an affair, wasn't he,
with the wife of the guy he ran Oliver Bonus during COVID?
Have I got it right now?
- That's, yeah, you--
- Is that the right Hancock?
- Yeah, yeah.
- That's the right Hancock.
- I think, "What's My Hancock?"
Could be the next game show, I think.
- There you go.
(audience laughing)
- And it's called Hancock's Half Hour.
It's a half hour format.
- Oh my God.
- Yes. - Roll it.
- Roll it.
So, he was what?
- This had better be spectacular.
(audience laughing)
Given the investment we've all made.
- Yeah.
- If this was just Tony Hancock was once on a plane,
it's just going to be very disappointing.
(audience laughing)
- Tony Hancock was coming back from Australia.
He was sitting next to Willie Rushton who's another,
you must have grown up on Willie Rushton, Richard.
- See him, he, I did, he, I did.
- And so they were sat on a plane
and one of the stewards came over
and said, "Mr. Hancock, you belong in first class."
And so Hancock went to first class,
but Willie Rushton stayed in economy.
And the interesting thing about that is Hancock
was dead at the time.
So he, yeah. - Oh, what?
- He had sadly passed away in Australia.
He took his own life.
He was quite a depressed character.
And Willie Rushton happened to be in Australia
and he was cremated.
He was put in an urn and they bought him a seat in economy.
And an air steward came over and said,
"Someone would like to move seats to sit there."
And they said, "You can't, this is Tony Hancock."
And she said, "What the hell is he doing in economy?
"He needs to be in first class."
So she took him in an urn off to first class,
while Willie Rushton just had to sit to a random person.
So he went to pick up Tony Hancock at the end of the flight
and there was a red rose and a little note saying,
"Thank you for all the laughs on the seat next to it."
Yeah. - That was quite good.
That's annoying, isn't it? - Yeah, that was all right.
- Same thing happened to Eric Morkham, didn't it?
- Did it? - Eric and Urn, right?
Yeah, flight together.
- Come on guys, he's a guest.
- Yeah.
- Thank you, James.
- Do you know what the world record is
for the number of yaks on a Boeing 747?
- Wow.
- Eight.
- Oh, it must be more.
Nine.
- Even higher.
- Higher than a nine.
- 14.
- It's triple figures.
- No.
- Yes. - 116 yaks on a Boeing.
- Yeah, not for fun.
It was for a relocation program, but it was, yeah.
That was last year, so it feels like it's a beatable record.
Like it feels like it's innovation in the space right now.
- What's the fun version of that number of yaks on a plane?
- Well, I'm scripting something.
I don't wanna talk about it, but I...
- Did they go in the seats?
- Yep.
(audience laughing)
- Oh, did they go in the hold, I guess?
- I think they always have to go in crates
and custom-made crates and things.
When you're moving like Megaforna, you have to,
you have to do that.
- Yeah, when you're moving in Megaforna, James.
You have to...
Do you know what?
James is such an idiot.
- I am like that.
(audience laughing)
- My God, have I ever met a man who knows less
about moving Megaforna than James?
(audience laughing)
- Can I tell you something just to change the subject
about moving Megaforna?
(audience laughing)
- So there's a company called Cargo Lux.
It's a Luxembourg Guards company.
And they have the tagline, "You name it, we fly it."
And they fly...
If you need a big animal moving from one place to another,
these are the guys you go to.
And a couple of years ago,
they moved a beluga whale from China to Iceland.
- Okay.
- For fun?
- Or...
(audience laughing)
- No, it was very serious.
It was in a sanctuary, like an ocean sanctuary.
They wanted to move it to Iceland
where it could live in the wild.
And to cut a long story short,
they just put it in a big hammock
and keep pouring water on it.
- Yeah, okay.
- But they did, they kept it in very, very cold water
for a couple of months beforehand.
So it's blubber would get thicker for the journey because...
- 'Cause it's cold on a plane?
- Yeah, well, you have to keep your...
You have to regulate your temperature
and that's how they do it.
- Yeah.
And I guess it would be moving to colder waters as well,
if it's going to say...
- To Iceland, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's just a thing that happened, but...
And when they arrived in Keflavik,
the locals gave them a salute of water,
like they got hose pipes so that the plane could go
through them, which sounds dangerous.
Especially in Iceland.
- Yeah, true, yeah.
Just on reintroducing things.
- Oh, yeah?
- Would you guys like to see animals introduced to the UK?
Show of cheers.
- Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, which animals?
And now we come to the meat.
Okay, so animals that have gone extinct,
that used to live in England,
but have gone out of business here.
- Okay.
- Beavers.
- Beavers!
- That always gets a cheer.
- I know, and beavers against?
- Boo, no beavers.
- Who would like moose back?
- Boo!
- Did we ever have moose?
- We had moose.
- Did we?
- Yeah, we did.
- So lots of people want beavers and like birds.
37% of people want moose back.
37% want wild boar.
Can I have a cheer for wolves?
I think that's more than beavers or moose.
- That's a lot of people who don't live in houses
made of straw.
- But 31% of people would be up for wild wolves in the UK,
which I think I'm up for.
Okay, what about bears?
- And again, these are people who are not living
with the consequences.
- What about wasps?
- You see?
You know what I mean, they'd rather have bears than wasps.
Honestly, I think a bear would ruin your picnic
quicker than a wasp would, I think.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that this year at Poundland,
if you had one pound, you could buy a tin of Pilchats,
a water pistol, or all 825 UK Poundland stores.
- That's, yeah.
- So yeah, I mean, you wouldn't be able to go in
with your quid and say, can I have them?
There has to be some lawyers involved in stuff,
but the fact is that Poundland was sold this year for one pound.
- Wow, plus 10p for the bag.
- And this is the thing,
like it's a thing in UK law if you want to buy a company,
and let's say they have loads and loads of debts,
so they're not really worth very much,
but you want to buy the brand or whatever.
In theory, you think you could just pay nothing for that
because you know, you're taking on debt,
but in that actual fact, you have to swap something
between you in order for it to make a contract,
and usually when they do that, they do one pound.
And there's been lots of things that have been bought
and sold for one pound.
Ken Bates bought Chelsea Football Club for one pound
in 1982, and then sold it to Roman Abramovich
for 140 million, about 20 years later, so you know.
- That's a good investment.
- She is.
- Probably could buy half a defender with that, couldn't you?
- Portsmouth, Swansea City, Hull City, Bolton Wanderers,
and Notts County have all been bought
for one pound in their history.
Notts County, the oldest football team as well.
- Oh yes, Aston Villa, they were bought for a pound.
- Were they?
- Yeah, but if you buy a tin of Piltrons,
no one says that does come with 200 million worth of debt.
- Exactly, that is the difference.
So yeah, they were sold by a Polish firm called PEPCO
to a US investment firm called Gordon Brothers.
- Do you know what's really sad about this?
Is that I could buy 825 UK Poundland stores with my pound,
yet I wouldn't be able to buy a single pint of Ruddles
anymore because of this mad inflation that's gone on,
this just pisses me off more.
- That's devastating, yeah.
Poundland is very interesting.
The idea of setting up a shop where everything was a pound,
and it did have to buckle because things did go up,
so obviously things were more than a pound,
but just the very idea of setting up a shop
and going everything as a pound
is a pretty remarkable thing.
- Yeah, because a lot of things are a pound.
- Right.
- That's the clever thing about it.
- Yeah.
- You're going, "Oh my God, everything's a pound."
You go, "Yeah, but I mean, they cost a pound."
- Yeah, you're not selling iPads for a pound.
- Yeah, exactly.
- But Poundland was a bit of a Nepo store
because they were founded with a 50K loan
from a guy called Stephen Smith's father,
who had, he had a cash and carry business,
and he gave his son a loan so that they could sell
this new company.
- A loan of one pound.
- But in fairness, the whole family had come
from a market stall background,
and the business idea for Poundland came
because on their market stall,
they had a box where everything was 10p,
and people would just go in and grab something
and put their 10p in the thing.
They thought we could make this a big thing.
And actually, I think in the UK,
there's quite a lot of companies,
especially supermarkets, that began in the markets.
- Yeah.
- Didn't they?
Tescos, Morrison's and Mark's and Spencer's
were all originally market stalls.
- Right.
- There's a Poundland Museum as well.
There's a Poundland Museum,
and even better than that, you can buy it if you want.
You can buy it for 4.25 million.
So Keith Smith, who set up Poundland with his son,
he went off to the Algarve after Steve Smith
was building this thing,
and he and his wife came back to England
and bought a house.
I've got the name of it.
- Lutstone Hall.
- Lutstone Hall, and in Lutstone Hall,
it has the Poundland Museum in one of the barns there.
And it's on the right move right now.
If you look at Cleverley in Shropshire,
you can take a look at Lutstone Hall.
There isn't actually a shot of the Poundland Museum.
- But I feel like they're tricking the buyer
because it's not only a Poundland Museum,
it's also a Lutstone Hall Museum.
So you've got all these amazing bits of archeology
that they've dug up,
sitting next to Poundland items, right?
But they say you get the house,
which is unbelievably beautiful,
but they're gonna take all of the stuff
in the Poundland Museum and bring it to headquarters.
So you actually don't get the Poundland Museum.
- I bet if I've made them an offer,
and I'd said I'm buying it,
but I want the Poundland Museum,
they go, "Yeah, fine."
Because it's still for sale.
It's been selling for a long time.
- Yeah, they've had to halve the price.
- So if I'm saying to them, full asking price.
- Is it you and me on Zoopla,
just constantly looking at this house?
- One other person interested, it says.
- It started at about 9.5 million, right?
Then it was down to 7.75.
Not that I'm obsessed with white move.
Now, as you say, it's about 4.5 million,
and it's a really nice house.
It's got one of those swimming pools
where you can put a dance floor over the top of it.
- And they actually, they reduced the price
over a Christmas period for a while,
thinking that that would be.
- What is going on, Dad?
(audience laughing)
- I didn't know you were so into this.
But if you said I want all the pound land stuff,
they're not gonna say no.
It's really important to us that that goes to our head office.
- Listen, if you wanna go halves, I am.
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, right.
- If you wanna go, let's readdress that balance.
- Yeah, let's do it.
- Richard, would you give a TV show
to the concept of Poundland?
Would you think that's a good TV show?
- Would you think that's a good TV show to make?
- Sorry, what are you talking about?
(audience laughing)
I've got a format called PoundShop Wars,
which is all about rivalry
between different kinds of PoundShop.
- Okay, that's different to what you said.
When you walked, when you walked in the room,
which was, would you like a game show?
And it's about Poundland.
(laughing)
- Sorry, because there was a real TV show
called PoundShop Wars.
- Wow. - Okay.
- And it sounds quite fun.
So I'm just gonna give you a few episode pictures
and see what you think of it, Richard.
- So someone's already made this.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- So I might not buy it from you, but go on.
(audience laughing)
- When Poundland reduces its prices,
Pound World retaliates by launching the one-pound bra.
(audience laughing)
- Is that a weight thing or a price thing?
- It's a weight, a price.
(audience laughing)
- Rival stores compete for the crown
of best Halloween PoundShop in South Wales.
- No, I genuinely would like, I would watch that.
- Okay. - If I watched
the first two minutes of that,
it was on channel five, I think I even saw it.
- Oh, I'm not sure.
- Almost certainly with John Thompson doing the voiceover.
- Okay.
- It does sound good.
- Did they have any stuff about the 99p stores?
- No, absolutely not.
- No, really?
- No, that's good.
- I love it.
It tells you everything you ever need to know about economics.
You do not need to go to university.
You need to know that whenever a 99p store
opens next to a pound store,
it takes a lot of their business, right?
- Yeah.
- Poundland even bought the 99p stores
for 55 million pounds in 2015.
But then there was also when the 99p stores came out,
then you started getting 97p stores.
And in Barking in Essex, there was the 99p store.
And then on the same street opened a 97p store,
which had an introductory 95p sale.
- That's good.
- That's really good.
- Economics 101.
- Do you know who was the father,
kind of the father of all of this stuff?
So this is a guy called Frank Woolworth of Woolworth.
So he was the father of discount stores, basically.
- Where was he from?
'Cause you get that in multiple countries now.
- Yes, he was American.
Woolworth was a big brand in Britain as well
till it went bust, but he grew up in the States.
And there were already some budget stores in big cities.
And they were called Nickel and Dimes
'cause everything was either a nickel or a dime.
And he opened a thing called Woolworth's
great five cent store in Pennsylvania.
And it became unbelievably successful.
As in he had about a thousand branches.
No more, probably a couple of thousand
all across the States, went international.
And he took the opportunity to go absolutely bananas
with the money.
So he paid for the biggest building in New York to be built.
The tallest building in the world at that time
was the Woolworth building in New York.
And he paid cash for it.
He didn't muck around with mortgages or anything.
He just said, "I'm building, I'm commissioning this."
And then he became obsessed with Napoleon Bonaparte.
That was his thing.
So his private office, sort of 50 floors up here,
was an exact replica of Napoleon's private office
from his castle in France.
He would walk around his private estate
in an old Napoleon uniform,
like a legitimate old Napoleon uniform.
The gate of the estate is based on the Arc de Triomphe.
He bought Napoleon's old bed.
There was an old slave bed that Napoleon had had.
And there are rumors that he believed he was Napoleon.
- Okay.
- Towards the end.
- And you were saying he wasn't?
- I'm saying he--
- What evidence do you have that he wasn't?
Just out of interest.
- Do you know what?
He was also interested in time travel.
So that's a very good choice.
- He's here today.
- That's amazing.
- Frank Woolworth, just one of the most eccentric,
effectively pound-trop owners, you know.
- Do you know what is the biggest supermarket?
Fastest growing, let's say, grocery chain in the US today.
It's one you've heard of.
- Target, is that one in America?
- It's not Target.
It's one that's bigger in the UK.
And Europe, I should say.
- Lidl.
- Lidl's very close.
- Aldi. - Aldi is correct.
And so they're starting to learn
about the Isle of Shame now.
- Oh, sorry.
I thought that was Britain.
(audience laughing)
- For anyone who doesn't know the Isle of Shame,
this is the middle Isle of Aldi
where they just put some absolutely crazy things in there.
Basically, they do something called Overstock
where if a company has a lot of ironing boards
that they're trying to get rid of,
then Aldi will buy them all for really cheap
and then sell them in their shops.
So America is starting to find this.
And so if you go on the internet,
you get lots of people asking
what's the weirdest thing you've ever found in the Isle of Shame.
So things include bucket hats for dogs,
a light for the inside of your toilet bowl.
- Okay, hang on.
Let's pause on that.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- So what's going on there?
- I would give you 400,000 pound
for 20% of this company.
(audience laughing)
- If you want to go to the toilet in the night.
- I think that's a brilliant idea.
- You might need something to aim at.
- What runway lights?
- In an airplane.
- Exactly.
- You know the airports didn't used to have those.
- Then I can get rid of the guy
with the ping pong bats in my toilet.
- But hang on.
You don't want to turn on your main bathroom light?
- What if the main bathroom is right next to the bedroom
and you don't want to wake up with your partner or whatever?
- That isn't you don't have a door.
(audience laughing)
- Sorry, we don't have doors there, all right?
- If you get up to go to the toilet in the night,
do you turn all the lights on?
- I just feel my way to the bathroom.
- That's really selfish if you do that.
- Hang on, no, I'm sorry.
(audience laughing)
I don't turn on the main light.
- I bet you flush as well, don't you?
- I do.
(audience laughing)
What I do is I get out of bed,
I go right up to my wife's ear and I go,
"Where's the toilet again?"
(audience laughing)
Hey, you would go into the toilet, it's a separate room.
You turn the light on.
- I'm so sorry, what on earth are you using
your iPhone light for?
- That's very personal a question.
(audience laughing)
- You don't turn the light on at night.
- You guys are nuts, what are you talking about?
It's in a different room altogether.
- Oh, well, someone's doing your life for himself.
- Oh, but to me.
- Ew, I'm just going to the West Wing to have a wee.
Fuck it, ow.
- Some of us are still on
the old trusty ceramic bowl under the bed.
(audience laughing)
- It's honestly like sitting next to Prince Andrew.
- All right, what else is there?
- What else is there?
- So that's a good, that's a good,
I think that's not an insane idea.
- None of these, like people bought these things.
Dessert, hummus.
- Dessert, hummus.
It's made of chickpeas, but it's sweet.
- Oh, okay.
Are the red tights get pissed off
when they taste the difference?
- And then one person on Reddit,
when they asked what's the weirdest thing
you found in the Isle of Shame said,
"I work at Aldi, so my take is a bit different
"than the shopper, but the weirdest thing
"I have found in the Isle of Shame
"is a turd lying on the ground."
(audience laughing)
- And that's what happens
when you don't turn the lights on, so take it back.
(upbeat music)
- It is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that not long
after he released his song "All By Myself",
the musician Eric Carman was taken to court
because as it turned out,
he did not write it "All By Myself".
We all know the song, it was in Bridget Jones' diary.
Celine Dion covered it, it's a massive tune,
and Eric Carman put it on his debut album,
and he decided to incorporate
the second movement of a piece by Rachmaninov,
and he thought, because in America,
it was out of copyright,
that that would be the case globally, but it wasn't,
and so he had to give over 12%
of the royalties forever on,
and so Rachmaninov has a co-write credit on "All By Myself".
- Crazy.
I mean, it is in fairness, it is identical, isn't it?
- Yeah, and he wasn't trying to steal it,
it wasn't a plagiarism thing,
he thought it was out of copyright.
- Yeah, he was a massive Rachmaninov fan, I think,
and when they asked him about it, he said,
"I thought it's a crime that there are some spectacular
melodies in classical music
that the general public doesn't get exposed to."
But it turned out that the actual crime was plagiarism.
(audience laughing)
- The irony of the title, that "All By Myself",
and he didn't write it all by himself,
reminds me of the absolute classic case of Gary Portnoy.
- I grew up with him, yes.
Who's that?
- I know the name.
- You know Gary Portnoy?
You know Gary Portnoy?
He's the man who wrote "When Everybody Knows Your Name".
- Oh, cheers. - The theme tune to "Cheers".
Yeah, which one of the most famous songs in our culture,
but no one knows who wrote it was Gary Portnoy.
- Yes, that's great.
- There you go.
- That's really good.
- James didn't know his name.
- I've heard the name before because I've watched every episode
about 20 times and it comes up, doesn't it?
- Gary Portnoy.
- Does this work when you're on quizzes,
if you just say, "Oh, I did know it"?
(audience laughing)
- Yeah, if you're honest.
- Yeah, there should be benefit of the doubt points
at the end of every round.
- Oh, I was gonna say that.
Well, if you were gonna say it,
then I'm gonna give you the points.
(audience laughing)
- I'm taking notes for "What's My Spoon",
don't worry guys.
(audience laughing)
So this is a really big thing in lots of songs.
There are songwriters who will get sued later on
because some similarity has been found.
So one of the most famous recent cases of that
was the song "Blurred Lines", if anyone remembers that.
- Friend of the podcast.
- Right, T.I. for over Williams and--
- Robin Thickey.
(audience laughing)
They had to pay.
They had to pay $5 million of the proceeds of "Blurred Lines",
which I mean, I'm naive about how much
an individual hit earns you, clearly.
They had to pay $5 million to Marvin Gaye's estate.
Not because of a particular melody or anything,
it was because of basically the feel of the song.
- The vibe.
Like they had borrowed the vibe.
- To be fair, when you listen to it,
you can kind of see where they're coming from,
'cause it's like a kind of funky bass
and some cowbells and--
- Yeah, but I mean, that feels really harsh.
- I know.
- 'Cause they were going for a kind of old school funky hit.
- I think that one did feel like, that's an odd one.
'Cause there's very obvious ones where absolutely is the case.
- Completely.
- There was one that I read about, which was,
I don't know if you all remember,
but Louise Redknapp had a song a long time ago
called "Naked".
The lyrics are, I could feel your eyes all over my body,
I can read the signs, they're sexual,
I can read your mind, I can see you want me.
And basically, someone effectively ripped
the entire melody and the bounce of the tempo of the song,
and they sued them, and so the co-writers of "Naked"
by Louise Redknapp are now the co-writers
of "Pepper's Party Time" from "Pepper Pig",
who sang a song about jumping in muddy puddles.
- Yeah, and again, it does sound,
if you listen to the both, it is-
- It's pretty much for much, lyrically as well, yeah.
(audience laughing)
- I was listening to one, "Viva La Vida" by Coldplay,
which I love, that's a Roman cavalry choirs
are singing all that kind of stuff.
There's a song by Joe Sattriani called "If I Could Fly",
and I was listening to the first minute of that,
I thought, "This is nothing like it."
And then it gets to a bit,
you go, "Oh, that is exactly like that song."
So, but that's called "If I Could Fly",
and I do a very brief sidebar,
because instead of putting in "If I Could Fly",
I put in "I Wish I Could Fly",
which is the Keith Harris and Orville song,
if anyone remembers that,
which is "I Wish I Could Fly" right up to the sky,
but I can't, Keith says, "You can."
It's called Orville's song,
and so I Googled Orville's song.
I originally wrote Orville's dong,
but,
(audience laughing)
fortunately, it said, "Do you mean Orville's song?"
But, so, a lot of people know,
a lot of people know the first verse of Orville's song.
The second verse, I think,
might be the bleakest thing
ever written in any medium, ever.
So, the first verse is, you know,
you have sort of a roughy no ear going,
"I wish I could fly right up to the sky,
"but I can't, Keith, you can, Orville, I can't.
"I wish I could see what folks see in me,
"but I can't, Keith, you can, Orville, I can't."
Second verse.
So, Orville, "I wish that I had a mom and a dad,
"but I don't.
"Keith, you don't, Orville, I don't."
(audience laughing)
And here we go.
Back to Orville.
"I'd like to pretend my sadness will end,
"but it won't.
(audience laughing)
"Keith, it will, Orville, it won't."
And that was number four.
That got to, that was like a big hit.
- Wow.
- I mean, that's quite something, isn't it?
- It's quite something.
- Yeah, "I'd like to pretend that my sadness will end."
I mean, that's like Iris Murdoch.
- Good Lord.
- They're the only people who've ever been allowed
to confer on Pointless Celebrities,
Keith Harris and Orville.
(audience laughing)
Very nice.
They came on together, we were like,
"Yeah, but this is fine."
(audience laughing)
None of us saw a problem with that.
- How did they do?
- They did great, actually,
'cause they were up against Tommy Cannon and Bobby Ball,
who scored 600 points in the first round.
- Wow.
- Which to this day is a Pointless Celebrities record.
- Taylor Swift.
- Oh, yeah.
- Singer.
So she has a song called "Look What You Made Me Do,"
which is a great song.
It's an absolute banger,
but it has a single cadence,
which was pretty much the same as one used in
Wright said, "Friends, I'm too sexy."
- Ah.
- Which was a really bad hit.
Like it was great, but it was sexy.
- I'm too sexy.
- Come on, mate.
- Okay, all right.
- I mean, it's no deeply dippy,
but it's not bad.
(audience laughing)
But basically, the writers of Wright said Fred,
or Wright said Fred themselves, I suppose,
have now got a credit on "Look What You Made Me Do,"
'cause their cadence ended up in it.
And this is a really common thing.
Like if a big star has a hit coming up,
or a song coming up for release,
like they'll have people check over it and they'll say,
"It's quite similar to this existing thing.
"Do you want to change a few notes?"
So people actively make the songs arguably worse,
'cause they'll say, "I'll just change these songs
"so it's not like, I don't know,
"yesterday," or whatever it is, you know.
- 'Cause there's only so many notes.
- I feel like it's all fine.
I feel like it's all fine to do.
- Do you?
- A lot of them.
- Thank you, your honor.
(audience laughing)
- No, but it's an interesting point because
the line that often gets said
from the old generation of rock stars, John Lennon period,
they would say, "Steal from the best,"
and they did sometimes get busted,
but if you look at the modern--
- And busted are the best.
- Yeah.
(audience laughing)
And the modern crop, you've got Olivia Rodrigo,
who was sued multiple times for her debut album
by various people, but the old crop, Elvis Costello,
said, "No, go for it, this is great."
The strokes with their biggest hits,
that was a Tom Petty song,
almost literally ripped--
- Last night by the strokes.
- Yeah, exactly.
Did Petty, I don't think he ended up--
- I think he was called,
I think they came to an arrangement.
- Oh, okay.
- He was quite called about it.
- Yeah.
- So he wasn't, that's nice, he wasn't Petty.
Sorry, just to, like--
(audience laughing)
- Phil Manzanero, who was in Roxy Music,
every now and again, like he'd be sent a royalty check
for like 1.5 million pound,
and every time you'd have to go,
"Sorry, this is Ray Manzorak from The Doors."
This happens every now and again, so he sends it back,
then he gets a royalty check for 1.5 million dollars,
goes, "Sorry, this is Ray Manzorak."
They said, "Oh no, someone took a riff
"you did from a 1970s album,
"and it's on the new Kanye and Jay-Z album."
And so it was his money,
and he had just one of their kind of scouts,
found an old record, thought this is an amazing riff,
found out who'd done it, sent him the money.
- Wow.
- Yeah, it's worth having, isn't it?
- Yeah, that's great.
I found a really weird moment in pop history,
so Blame It On The Boogie was written by Michael Jackson,
a very different Michael Jackson,
who was also a singer,
who would trade under the name Mick Jackson,
but then it got taken to America via his people,
and it was played to a bunch of different people.
One of the people who heard it was the Jackson Five.
They recorded their own version,
and they released it in America.
Meanwhile, Mick Jackson is getting to release
his own version in England,
and no one knows who is who, because it's the same name.
BBC Radio One would only play the Jackson Five version,
whereas Capitol Radio would only play the Mick Jackson version,
and they were battling it out in the charts,
with people being confused about who is who.
- That's cool.
- It's just the most random name connection, yeah,
that you could get,
and he so happened to be an artist in his own right.
- Very cool.
All my stuff's about Rachmaninoff.
- Oh, let's hear about Rachmaninoff.
- He...
- Who did he rip off?
Doido.
(laughing)
- His first symphony, he played it to Rimsky-Korsakov.
He, like, went to the rehearsals,
and Rimsky-Korsakov said this,
"I do not find this music at all agreeable."
I was gonna translate it, this is shit,
but it was basically that's what he said.
Rachmaninoff suddenly thought,
oh my God, this isn't very good,
but he couldn't call it off,
so he spent the whole of the first symphony
hiding in a staircase backstage.
- Yeah, but then, like--
- Was it a success?
- Oh no, no, no, no, no, no.
It happened once.
The one reviewer wrote that,
"If the devil had written a symphony
"based on the 10 plagues of Egypt,
"and it was like Mr. Rachmaninoff's,
"then he would have fulfilled his task brilliantly
"and would delight the inhabitants of hell."
Three stars.
(laughing)
And Rachmaninoff refused to let anyone
perform it again in his lifetime,
and when he left Rush,
'cause he fled Rush and went to America afterwards,
and when he did that, he left his manuscript behind.
He just didn't want anything to do with it.
- Right. - Boy.
- Yeah.
- Was that the one that was used in All By Myself?
No, different one.
- No, no, no, no.
The one that All By Myself is his second symphony,
which is an absolute classic,
and which is regularly voted on Classic FM,
you know, our favorite symphony.
- But is that because most people listening are going,
oh, that's the Celine Dion song?
- Generally it is, I think it is, yeah.
Rachmaninoff, massive hands.
- Is that so?
- Yes, he can go 12 notes or something.
- He could do 12 notes,
but he could play a five note chord.
So it's not just reaching,
he could also play the first note.
- If he could play a chord.
- Yeah, he could play the first one,
and then the second one is 12 notes away,
and he could also play the three in between.
So that means your hand has to be even longer than the...
- But surely he's impossible to play then
for normal pianists with little fingers.
- Actually, I think that is a problem that,
like, people with smaller hands
find it difficult to play Rachmaninoff,
and also female pianists find it difficult
to play Rachmaninoff 'cause they, on average,
have smaller hands.
- Right. - Yeah.
- It's weird because this is, Richard,
you don't know the full history of our show,
but this is probably the third.
- I know the full history of your show.
- Okay, okay.
Then, as you will very well be aware of,
this is the third historical figure I found
who has massive hands.
George Eliot, the author.
Stonewall Jackson, the Confederate general.
He was convinced he had one giant arm,
so he used to go into battle on horse
with his arm in the air so he could distribute
all the blood that that was hogging
to the rest of his body.
This is now the third.
Rachmaninoff is in big hand territory,
big hand or not, the quiz.
- I got it, I got it.
They say that about Vladimir Putin.
Vladimir Putin, when he walks, you see,
he swings his left arm and he doesn't swing his right arm,
so his right arm stays absolutely by his side.
And for ages, people say that he's had a stroke,
something has happened with Vladimir Putin.
But you talk to anyone with any kind of knowledge of spying,
they go, no, that's KGB, 'cause that's where your gun is.
So you would never, you wouldn't be kind of doing that.
Always have your hand when it's your gun.
- No, fake arm, fake arm.
- No, no, it's real.
- No, shush, right hand is like holding the pistol.
And then you got the fake arm, and that happens.
- I'm with Andy, you see this all the time.
There's photos.
- But I don't think Putin has a fake arm,
that's what I'm saying.
- Well, agreed to disagree, but.
- I know he listens, so he probably can let us know.
- Guys, I was listening to the show.
I won't do the voice.
- That would be offensive, yeah.
- I think he's all right.
- Oh, I don't want to offend Putin, oh my goodness.
After all the good things he's done, no.
- We do need to wrap up, but you see photos now
where all the security detail that are walking around,
major prominent politicians and leaders,
have their hands just stuck in a position,
and it's because they're wearing underneath their jacket,
fake arms, while they hold a little gun.
- This is genuinely true.
- And it brings us back to Keith Harris, with Orville.
- He had a fake arm.
- Of course he did, because he's got one hand up,
Orville's, you know Orville wasn't real, right?
- Right.
- Yeah, you know it was Keith who wasn't able to pretend
that his sadness was going to end.
You know that, don't you?
- Are you saying that he was holding a gun inside or was?
- At all times.
- Was Orville working under duress?
- Yeah, I'll go on pointless with you, absolutely.
- Yeah, I wish I could fly right up to the sky,
you fucking won't in a minute, mate.
(audience laughing)
(upbeat music)
- That is it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our online accounts.
I'm on Instagram, I'm at @Sriberland, James.
- My Instagram is @NosexThingness, James Harkin.
- Andy. - My name is Andrew Hunter M.
- And Richard, you're online.
- I don't know why.
- Mr. Osman.
- Mr. Osman. - On Instagram.
- And September 25th, the latest book is out.
- It is The Impossible Fortune.
- Yeah, and if you-- - What could that be?
An impossible fortune, huh?
You'll have to read it to find out.
(audience laughing)
- And listen, if you wanna ask us any questions
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, podcast@QI.com, give us an email,
Andy reads literally every single one of those emails,
and if he finds them worthy to bring to our special club,
they will appear on Jewel Drop Us Align,
which is our secret hidden members' club episode
that we like to do, so do send it to us there.
Otherwise, thank you London Podcast Festival.
Thank you everyone who has been with us here tonight.
Thank you everyone who's been watching us
overseas on the live stream.
We're gonna be back again next week.
We'll see you with another episode then.
Goodbye!
(audience cheering)
(upbeat music)