(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Shriver, I'm sitting here
with Andrew Hunter Murray, Anna Tyshensky,
and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered round the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that it's a common misconception
that face mites don't have an anus.
- How common?
- Oh well, I know that I've blown it wide open
for all of you guys and everyone listening.
(laughing)
- If I, honestly, if I had a quid for every time
I'd heard someone on the bus saying,
you know that face mites don't have an anus.
- No, right?
- It's exhausting.
- So we did think they were anus-less for a long time?
- We did think they were.
- And also, sorry, face mites, what are they?
- Oh right, sorry, yeah, I suppose I better start
from the beginning of this story.
So face mites are something that almost everyone
with normal faces-- - Face mites, yeah.
(laughing)
- If you've got a face, you've got the mites,
probably about 90% of people, and they're very small,
about between 1/10th and 1/3 of a millimeter,
and so you can't really see them,
and they're living sort of like inside your pores
in the daytime, so you couldn't see them anyway.
But there's been this thing, and honestly,
if you look up face mites and you do a website search
of new scientists, of national geographic,
very reputable sources, they all say,
interesting thing is, they don't have an anus,
and so what they do is, they store all their fecal waste
in their bodies until they reach death,
which does only happen after a few days,
and then they just explode it all out,
and this is why they're bad,
because they explode feces on your face.
Now, this isn't true, and what's more,
we've kind of known this isn't true since the '60s,
so there was an electron microscope in the '60s
that did identify a face mites anus, but--
(laughing)
- No one believed him.
- I wonder, would you rather have face mites
on your face that had an anus,
and were constantly pooing on your face,
or one that only pooed as a one-off at the end of its life?
- Well, I think there was an idea, sorry,
that it's worse to have them storing up all the poo,
because this is where a lot of the bad rep
of the face mite comes from.
People will put various skin diseases
down to face mite infestations,
and it's partly because they'd say,
oh, do you know, they build up with poo, so much poo,
and then it explodes everywhere, and it's not true,
and actually, we don't really have evidence
that they do any harm to us at all.
- Although, I found one thing that they might be doing to us,
so they've got no protection from ultraviolet light,
which is why they have to hide inside the pores,
and they can't produce melanin,
which is related to tanning and so on,
but they do have the ability to eat our melanin.
So, human's grin secretes melanin,
and then they gobble it up.
- That's good, so basically,
they get a suntanth through eating,
as opposed to through sunbathing.
- Exactly, that's exactly what they do.
- Oh, that's great.
Imagine if we could do that.
It's like a biscuit that tanned us.
- They're eating our suntanths, don't you find that?
- Oh, they're eating away our suntanths.
- I think they're eating our suntanths.
- That's so interesting.
- And they're using our suntanths
to fuel all night sex sessions on our faces.
- I know, this is the most amazing fact.
- This sounds like a Tory party expose.
(all laughing)
- Can I ask about this massive poo?
Is it like fake tan coming onto your face?
'Cause it's what they've eaten, right?
- There is no massive poo.
It's all small poo.
- It's all small poo.
- So, let's just quickly mention
something you dropped in a second ago,
which is the fact that every night,
when we go to bed,
they crawl out of our little pores,
and they have a big old sex party on our face.
And this is happening every night
on our children, on our grandparents.
It's happening everywhere.
- It's quite a cool idea,
'cause nighttime is when humans often have sex.
So the idea that when you're having sex,
it's likely that loads of face mites are also having sex.
- Oh, so they're not even waiting for you to sleep.
It's just nighttime.
- I think it's just darkness.
- Yeah, 'cause they don't--
- Away from the UV, isn't it?
- Yeah, right.
But also they find that couples pass each other's mites.
So, while you're having sex,
you might pass a mite that's now having sex
with another you mite.
- I think that's quite unusual
for you to pass your mites onto another person, actually.
- Yeah, oh yeah.
- I think babies normally get them from their mothers.
- For breastfeeding, yeah.
- And I think any other way of me giving you one of my mites
is quite unlikely.
- Oh, really?
- But it is weird, the idea that our face mites
are basically our own.
Because, as you say,
mostly they come from either vaginal childbirth
or breastfeeding because you get face mites hanging around
sometimes in the genitals and the nipples.
And then they don't really change
unless you are living face to face with someone,
like cheek to cheek with someone for years on end.
Like, my colony is totally different
to your guy's colonies this stage, I guess, right?
- Yeah, that is amazing.
So, you'll have got some mites from your mother
from breastfeeding, perhaps, or vaginally.
And then they obviously won't live for your whole life.
They'll have children,
and their children will have children,
and their children will have children.
- The cycle of life.
- So, it's a circle of life.
- Well, it's more like a straight line of life.
Because by the time you die,
if you live to an average human age,
it will be 1200 generations from the start.
- Really?
- Okay, so the ones that are living as you die
will be the great, great, great, great, great, great,
1200 times from the ones that you got from your mother.
And that's the equivalent in humans
of when rope was invented and ovens were invented
and pottery were invented.
- So, why aren't they achieving more by the end of my life?
Why haven't they got many laptops on my face?
They're working on it.
- On the sex, face mites, is quite interesting
because their penis is on their back.
So, the male has to sort of get underneath the female
to have sex.
But his--
- So, give her a piggyback?
- Yeah, like a piggyback.
And it's really interesting because this is a gene
which has changed in the genome called the hox gene.
And if you, you know the facts which all mammals
have got nine neck bones.
- Yeah.
- Even a giraffe has got the same number of bones
as a shrew or whatever.
That's because of the hox gene.
And the hox gene is the thing
which tells you where all your body parts grow
so that your arms are here and your legs are there
and your necks here and all that kind of stuff.
And really, very, very few animals.
In fact, this is the first one I've ever seen
where they changed the hox gene
because it's really a hard thing to change
'cause you need all your bits in the right place.
- So, evolutionarily at some point,
their gene just changed and now their penis is on their back.
- Exactly.
- And are you suggesting that if we harness this power,
we'll be able to have penises wherever we like?
- We could, but then the problem would be
that our other body parts would grow in weird places.
- Okay, so we've got to find a way of isolating it
to give each other a very sexy piggyback, yeah.
- What changed for them when their penis went on their back?
- Well, actually, the mice have been in the news
in the last few weeks 'cause they've checked the genome
and they found that the genome has changed quite a lot
and the reason is because they are having sex,
but they're having sex with their own cousins
and brothers and sisters and stuff like that.
And what they're finding is that they're changing
in the way that I said,
but also in a way that they're losing lots
of their useful powers, if you know what I mean.
So, things that could save them from ultraviolet,
they might have had that in the past,
but they're losing it 'cause they don't need it
'cause they have such a nice environment in your face.
- They're basically becoming completely dependent on us.
They're very clingy.
It's like having a partner who suddenly,
they ditch their whole friendship group,
they can't even cook for themselves
and they're developing a completely symbiotic relationship.
- They do have a penis on the back though.
- It is worth it.
- I think the definition is they're currently
classed as external parasites on us,
but soon, if this process continues,
they will be classed as internal symbiotes.
- Yeah, and also, they might be classed as extinct
because if they lose all of these skills to stay alive,
then it makes it much more difficult
when they get passed on to the next generation.
- They also have a seven-clawed organ around their mouth,
which when they do eat your sea bum,
they kind of latch their claws,
these claws around their mouth into you.
- Right.
- Which is quite cool to imagine.
- Just when I was warming to them a little bit.
(all laughing)
- I love those called sea bum,
yet we have not seen bum for brilliant of these years.
- Mmm, how did I not realise that?
Yeah, yeah.
- So, just mites in general.
- There are five million different species of mites,
I believe, as in everything's got one.
Humans have their own.
- At least one.
Every kind of beetle will have its own mites.
Every plant, soil, ocean, any mammal.
- I have a favourite mites,
which is the Adactolydium.
This is so amazing, it's a life cycle.
It's usually found in the Middle East,
and they're basically born pregnant,
and they're born in order to die.
And so--
- Aren't we all, aren't we all?
- It's like human lifespan, but very, very fast.
So, basically, you've got the mother,
and she only ever eats one meal in her whole life,
and it is always an egg.
- Hard boiled, or--
- An egg, I think it's poached,
and it's specifically a poached egg of the Thunderfly,
or I think in America you call them a thrip.
And so yeah, it just eats one Thunderfly egg,
and then she, this keeps her alive,
and she, Insider, has six to 10 fertilized eggs
ready to go, and they hatch Insider.
So, all her offspring hatch Insider,
and it's always one male, and then all the rest are females.
And then, inside the mother, all of her offspring,
you know what's coming, we all know what's coming.
Obviously, the one brother shags all the sisters--
- A mucky pup.
- Impregnates them all,
and then once he's got all the sisters pregnant,
they eat their way out of the mother.
- Alpha heaven's sake.
- So, the mother gets eaten from the inside,
and then the kids are born already pregnant, obviously.
And then I guess they just start again,
being eaten from the inside by the pregnant kids inside them.
- There are some animals which are just too different to us
for us to have anything in common.
- Yeah, we wouldn't get along.
- No.
- Yeah, nothing to talk about at all.
- If one of them gained human sentience,
we just wouldn't like that.
(laughing)
- Is that the dinner party?
They start up their children bursting through their chest.
- At least at the dinner party, all they're eating is an egg.
- What egg?
- Are you gonna have that bread?
- All right, I'll have that.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that a robot version of the Mayflower
has just completed a human free void
from England to America.
It went really well, except that it took three goes,
had to be towed in manually,
and first hit land 400 miles from where the original landed.
(laughing)
- Still cool.
- Still wants for effort.
- Totally disastrous.
It was a disaster.
So this is a ship.
It was a robot ship.
It was built by IBM and an organization called Pro Mare.
I think that's how it's pronounced,
'cause it's Mare like the C.
And it was called the Mayflower Autonomous Ship,
and it was piloted by AI technology,
and apparently the technology worked perfectly.
But the really funny thing,
I just find it funny,
the original Mayflower voyage in 1620
took 10 weeks to get from England to the Americas.
And this was expected to take three weeks,
'cause they said this is so fast, it's so efficient,
it's so AI, it's amazing.
And it's first set off in, I think, June 2021,
and eventually landed in, I think, May or June 2022.
It took about 60 weeks, basically.
(laughing)
Any time longer than the original Mayflower.
- But I had to come back and start it again
at that point, right?
- Yeah, most of those 60 weeks,
it was just waiting to try again for a mechanic.
- In fairness, it was a research thing, right?
And in some ways, it's a way to prove
that you can do this for research in the future.
So the idea is that a normal boat, like the Mayflower,
most of the boat you're using to keep the people alive
who are on the boat.
So you need to keep food, you need to give them shelter,
you need all this kind of stuff.
But if it's an AI boat, you don't need any of that stuff.
All you need to do is get from A to B.
And so you have loads of extra space
to do loads of experiments and put loads of electronics in
and loads of scanners and all that kind of stuff.
And in that respect, I think it was something of a success.
They managed to get quite a lot of data out of it.
- Oh yeah, yeah, exactly.
And the whole thing is, what a cool idea as well.
Like, yeah, it took a bit longer,
it landed in the wrong spot.
Sure, my factory's not.
- Broke down a lot.
- Broke down a lot, cause nightmares,
but the boat has got--
- Absolute mess.
- Called pro mess.
- Oh, there we go.
- Sorry.
(laughing)
- But it's got a great website as well, should say.
- Well, it did crash three times.
And then you ended up on bbc.co.uk.
- The boat itself had microphones on the hull
with the part of the research capacity.
So it was listening for whales as it traveled.
And it also has a smart tongue.
It had a tongue on the bottom.
- That sounds like someone's Tinder profile.
Or--
- I got a smart tongue.
- No, that's too rude, isn't it?
- No, it sounds more like a mites penis.
- It's sort of migrated from the wrong side
to sort of under the keel.
- It was recording the chemical composition of the ocean.
So I think in that sense it wasn't the right place.
- Right.
(laughing)
So before we invented the stove,
there used to be sailors who would have to lay
at the bottom of the boat
(laughing)
with their tongue out through a hole.
- Scratch on.
(laughing)
Still salty, I would say.
- We're not in the river yet.
(laughing)
- I think it seemed like the conclusion of this voyage was,
AI works quite well,
but it turns out humans still don't know how to make boats.
Right?
- I think that's boats to call.
- Boats break down all the time.
- Boats break hard, yeah.
- Boats really crap, they're always breaking.
And this seems to be a problem with AI generally,
is that it can work very well,
but if stuff goes wrong around it, it can't fix it.
And it made me think next time I go on a ferry,
I'll have new fan respect for the people
I think are doing nothing.
'Cause stuff just, stuff just breaks all the time.
- So you'll stop telling them.
- I'll stop saying.
- Name and shame these people who you think are doing nothing.
- Are you talking about the people manning like the kiosk
for snacks, 'cause they're doing an important job,
keeping the people out of their lives.
- Like health and safety officers.
- They're crucial, the health and safety guys,
the mechanics aren't necessary.
- The guys in the car parking bit who are saying,
no, bring it in, left, left, left, left, left, left.
- No, no, that's my left.
- They're doing a really important thing.
- Reverse, reverse, oh, it's in.
- Those are some of the most skilled people on the planet,
I would say.
- Do you know what?
- People who can fill a ferry.
- That bit of the ferry where you drive into,
is one of my favorite smells.
- Oh, that oil. - It's oily and petrally,
and it smells like trucks.
- Yeah. - It's very petrally.
- I really like that smell anyway,
but it reminds me of holidays as a child and stuff.
- As a result of that smell,
the guys who were doing the car parking,
they're as high as cars for the whole time.
Like they're in an altered consciousness
where they can see Tetris.
- That's what the thing is,
I thought I'd run over this guy,
but it turned out he had his tongue
through a hole in the water.
(laughing)
- Did you guys see the picture of the robot Mayflower
when it was pulling in?
- Yeah.
- When it finally landed at Plymouth,
which it did eventually.
So it left from Plymouth, as the original Mayflower did.
- England Plymouth.
- England Plymouth, England, yep.
And then it ended up accidentally somewhere in Canada
where Halifax. - Halifax.
- But then it did get to Plymouth in the end,
but it looks so pathetic,
because it pulls in next to the Mayflower 2,
which is the exact replica of the Mayflower
that was built in the 1950s, which I didn't know about,
but that's obviously stunning.
It's got all this stuff, like, you know,
it's all got all the rigging, it's like triple-masted,
and then it's got this crappy,
it's like a cat moran, really, isn't it?
- It is. - It's a trimoran.
Outrigger, tiny thing, looks like Thunderbird 3, I thought.
- Yeah, they didn't make much of an effort, yeah.
- I think there was a suggestion before they made it
that, oh, should we make another replica
of the Mayflower and send it across?
And then they decided, no, let's try and do something
for the next few centuries.
You know, that's looking to the past
if we did that, another replica.
So I think it is a really, it's a brilliant project,
and you know, well done, everyone involved.
- It is really cool. - Yeah, it is really cool.
- The Mayflower 2, when that originally went out
in the '50s, they had problems as well on the way,
and they had to divert, and during the diversion,
they went across Bermuda, and they almost sank
in the Bermuda ocean. - Really?
- So it could have been a Bermuda triangle casualty,
but they didn't, and so it's not a good story.
- How almost are we talking?
- Oh, they just had, yeah, they had a bit of trouble.
- Like, they had to bucket out a bit of water.
- No, there was a big storm, and so it was, you know,
you could go.
- Oh, yes, there was, wasn't there?
- Yeah.
- That journey, it was in, it was in 1957, they went,
and it was this entrepreneur called Warwick Charlton,
was a great name, and he was full of crazy schemes,
I guess, all through his life, and he wanted to thank
the Americans for their help during the Second World War,
so he said, let's build another version of the Mayflower,
and sail it across.
And they did it in quite an authentic way,
so they had one radio only.
That was the only concession to modernity, I guess.
You know, they had no radar, they had no supplies dropped in,
they wore pilgrim outfits on Sundays.
- On their journey. - Just on Sunday, isn't it?
- Yeah, just on Sunday.
Yeah, they didn't want to do the whole thing as a cosplay.
- Yeah.
- And then, after it was arrived,
it was officially welcomed by Richard Nixon.
- Oh, that sounds so frustrating,
recreating it like hand forging the individual nails
with which they make it, hand sewing the canvas sails,
'cause that's how they did it.
They must have thought at some points,
is this, what the fuck's the point in this?
And apparently, according to the Wikipedia page,
and this is taken from a pamphlet
that's issued by the Plymouth Museum in Massachusetts,
which is where it is now.
When they built this replica in England,
they employed the skills of elderly, traditional workmen
so that they could build a vessel
that reflected the original.
- How old were they?
- That's interesting.
You look like you're alive in 16, 20.
(laughing)
- And do you know the one difference between the,
it's not the one difference, there are others,
but a difference between the Mayflower Original
and Mayflower Two.
- Oh, toilet facilities, I would guess.
- Oh, that's a good one.
- Yeah.
- Would you?
I bet the toilets weren't that much more up to date.
- Electricity.
- No, although that, I think there was a little bit
of electricity on the top of my mind.
- To power the radio, which I'm going to say is the other.
- So there were lots of differences.
One of them was, no women allowed on Mayflower Two.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, that feels a bit regressive.
- Well, I'm not--
- No, not allowed?
- Not allowed, wasn't.
Not allowed because the captain,
who's a guy called Alan Villiers.
- Bad luck, maybe.
'Cause they used to be thought that women on boats
was bad luck, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- Sort of, he basically said that we won't be
having any women because there's no place for,
this is 1957, but there's no place for glamour pusses.
And he said, "Look, the reason women came--"
- Llamour pusses?
- The women.
- Was the original Mayflower absolutely stuffed
with, you know, Raquel Welch and a fur bikini?
- Yeah, and that's why it ended up so badly
when they arrived at the other end.
They were all shagged out.
No, he said the reason the Mayflower original worked,
and they had women on board and it was fine,
was because back in those days, women were chattels,
you know, you just owned them.
And they're not now.
They talk back and you can't handle them.
No, no women.
- Wow, Alan.
So there were thousands of women who applied
to help sail the boat over,
and they were not able to go on the trip.
But aside from that, it was a really great mission.
- I found it amazing on the original Mayflower
that you had three women who were pregnant
and knew that they would have a baby on the boat.
- Yeah, which I think that's hardcore, isn't it?
'Cause you know how long it's gonna take.
It's gonna take you six months to get there.
You're less than six months pregnant,
or less than six months to go.
Would you do that?
- I don't know, medical facilities were so shit.
I think the further away you can get from them
in those days, the better.
- Middle of the sea is better than anywhere else, yeah.
- Really interesting, 'cause you might,
were any of the babies born on the new continent,
or were they all born on board?
- There was one that was born when the ship was anchored,
I think, in Cape Cod.
So they called him like the first baby in North America,
ignoring thousands and thousands of years.
- Waiting for them on shore.
- Hey!
- But yeah.
You would've thought that they might've said to the mother,
if you just hold on a little bit longer,
this'll be the first pilgrim baby born actually on.
- Exactly, a bit like how we tried to have our cesarean
on the 22nd of the 2nd, 2022.
- Yes.
- How'd that work out?
- When you say we, you mean you and your wife, not you.
- You and I, I was looking at you dead in the eye
when I said that, Andy.
Yeah, not me and my wife, yeah.
- Doesn't always work out, does it?
- I'm afraid not.
- But then, much like, I think you, you know,
named your child partly after the day they were born,
one of the children who was born on the Mayflower
was called Oceania, I think.
- Oh, cool.
- Oh.
- That is a cool name.
- After the Oceania. - That's a brilliant name.
- Yeah.
- Better than 14th of February that we called ours.
(laughing)
- There's been another Mayflower controversy recently.
- Okay.
- In 2019, in Devon, there was this group
which announced that they were planning to build
a 400th anniversary Mayflower, so in 1620, 2020,
and then they were gonna set it on fire.
- Oh yes.
- And this prompted a row in America,
people saying it's very disrespectful.
- I can see why.
- Yeah, yeah, you know, but it wasn't intended
as a disrespectful move at all.
It was this group in Devon who I want to go and meet.
They're called the Great Torrington Cavaliers,
and every five years, they build a big old structure
and then set fire to it.
- Right.
- They've done it with loads of different things,
and it's just their way of raising money for charity.
- Yeah, I saw a photo of it, 'cause they did do it in the end.
They did light it up, and yeah.
- And it had knitted rats.
They had a ye olde one-stop knob shop on board,
which I am pretty sure was an original feature
of the Mayflower.
- One-stop knob shop.
- One-stop knob shop, what's that mean?
- I don't know.
- What kind of knobs is it?
Door knobs?
- I imagine door knobs.
- No, it'll be old knobs, 'cause it's only one stop.
So for all your knob needs.
(laughing)
I'd like to buy a packet of hub knobs, a door knob.
- And Piers Morgan there in the corner.
(laughing)
- Anyway, they set it on fire.
- That was very cool.
- Another controversial one was the town of Horwich,
which is where the Mayflower was originally constructed.
So this is an Essex.
They wanted to build a replica Mayflower
and send it across again.
So this was in 2009.
They had a town meeting.
They said, "How do we commemorate
"this big 400th anniversary?"
Someone said, "Why don't we put up some bunting?"
(laughing)
And then another person, a dentist called Tom Daley,
said, "Why don't we rebuild the Mayflower
"and we send it across?"
And so they all agreed to it.
And they started raising money for it.
And it sounds like it was quite a doomed project
from the get-go because first off,
they needed to build a shipyard,
which they didn't have in order to build the ship.
And so that took up a lot of funds.
They raised millions and millions
in order to get this done.
They hired lots of interns to come and build the ship,
but they had no training.
So I think they went through hundreds and hundreds
of these interns that just didn't know
what they were doing.
- Meanwhile, the guy suggested putting up some buntings,
just watching the whole thing going.
- I told them, I told them.
- So what happened?
- Well, they just kept trying to,
they were investing the money that they kept bringing in.
They kept building up more money
and people were doing things like sponsoring ship bolts
so that they could have their own ship bolts on the ship
and so on.
And eventually they just ran out of money.
- So how much of the ship did they build?
- I think they did the keel and like the bow
and then that was it.
And then obviously all these people
that had these plans anyway for the big anniversary
couldn't do anything about it
'cause COVID hit.
And so all these plans got put into the back seat.
So even if they had their ship
it might not even, even gone at that point.
- Oh, that's quite good.
I feel like COVID conveniently disappeared
a lot of doomed projects.
You could just say, well, then COVID, you know,
also if that was a completely stupid idea in the first place.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three, that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that
when the first four minute Myla, Roger Bannister,
met his future wife Myra, she knew he was a runner
but thought he'd run four miles in one minute.
Many years later, their grandson bragged to his friends
that his grandfather could run one mile in under four seconds.
- This is like the Dan process of telling anecdote.
It's exaggerated beyond plausibility.
- I should let you know, I am his grandson.
- Holding that back for years.
- Yeah, so this is Roger Bannister.
- And it's very stupid wife apparently.
(laughing)
Come on Myra, you've run before.
- Four miles in one minute, that's pretty fast.
- That's silly.
- So Bannister was a medic as well as a runner,
wasn't he?
He became Sir Roger Bannister as well
because of the load of work that he did
for the sports council.
So he wasn't just a fast runner,
he was an all round guy.
I find it amazing that he wasn't even a fast runner
after the age of, I think it was 25 when he quit.
He just gave up, he said he wouldn't be taken seriously
as a doctor, he wanted to be a neurologist
and that's exactly what he became.
And the running he just completely left to one side.
- He said that it was only a small section of his life
and if he had to give one or the other up,
he would definitely have given running up
and would have carried on being a medic
'cause that was his main part of his life.
- It's amazing.
- Yeah, that makes sense.
- It's quite striking if you read any interview
with Roger Bannister.
- The pretty much the first thing he'll say is,
I hate it how everyone bangs on about my running.
I don't even care about that.
All I wanna be known for is being a doctor.
- Yeah, I should have just run a bit slower, shouldn't he?
- Yeah, that's pretty right.
(laughing)
- We wouldn't have been talking about him.
- Just had a few seconds on
and you'd be a complete footnote in his room.
(laughing)
- Nobody would care.
- So this happened in Oxford at a place called Ifley Road
and he was--
- So that's his four minute mile.
- That's his four minute mile that he ran
and the track that he ran it on
was actually built partially by him
when he was at university.
He helped lay that track down.
Yeah, when he did it--
- Seems like a bit of a swiss.
- It does, doesn't it?
It feels like something's going on.
- What do you think he's done?
Made it very slippery or something.
- Yeah, let it downhill part of it.
- Yeah, a little spring.
(laughing)
Lobs him forward.
But yeah, so he did this
and it was an amazing thing
that you can actually watch footage of online,
which is pretty incredible.
And they talk a lot about his legs,
which are very kind of weirdly spindly
and the sort of big strides that he takes
are really interesting.
And you can see how knackered he is coming into the end
as he does it.
In fact, there's a whole crowd waiting for him
as he comes right into the end
and he basically collapses into someone's arms
as if they knew that was gonna happen.
They're waiting there to capture him.
And then they all stood around to hear had he done it
and there was an official announcement
and the announcer went the time was three
and then there was huge eruption
because that's what they needed to hear.
- Yeah, it was in McWherter.
- It was, it was Norris McWherter,
the founder of the Guinness World Records
along with Hugh Beaver.
- Apparently we're in a pantomime.
(laughing)
- Norris McWherter is a very pantomime as well.
- And he nearly didn't do it.
That morning he said he spent,
'cause he was training to be a doctor at the time.
I think he was a junior doctor, a medical student.
And he, that morning was working
and said it was really, really windy.
And it was only at the last minute,
I think his friend about half an hour before said,
"No, you gotta do it, Rog, come on."
- And the wind went, that was the other thing.
- Oh, did it?
- Yeah, so he went and he went, "Let's do it."
But he did it in three minutes, 59.4 seconds.
So we've really taken it to the just under four minutes.
- In actual fact, I said he was the first four-minute miler,
I should have said under four-minute miles, right?
He didn't do it in exactly four minutes.
But there was someone a few years later,
Derek Ibbotson, who in a mile race at White City
ran in exactly four minutes and zero seconds.
So he became the first person
to do an exact four-minute mile.
- Would that still have been as exciting to break the record
or is the point that it has to be under four minutes?
- Yeah, it just had to be under four minutes.
It was this invisible barrier that people thought
that humans would never be able to get under.
But yeah, we got under it.
So getting four minutes, actually,
if Ibbotson had done that four-minute mile,
arguably he wouldn't have become famous
'cause he hadn't beaten the four-minute mile.
- Yes, yeah.
And it's pretty, again, when you watch the footage,
I do wonder it's the '50s here that we're talking about.
What sort of accuracy are we talking about
with the stopwatch?
'Cause it was so crowded.
What did they have?
It was a stopwatch, presumably.
- Yeah, I guess I would have imagined it was a stopwatch.
- I think that as well.
I was in quiz.
We accept this so blindly.
It's just all Norris sitting there jamming his thumb.
- Yeah, doubting.
Norris McWhorke.
- Good call.
- The first woman to run a five-minute mile, Diane Leather,
it was only 23 days after Bannister's record,
but didn't get any of the...
- Diane Leather's a very good name.
- Run Hell for Leather.
- Okay.
- Yeah, that is good.
- By those days, basically women
weren't really supposed to run middle distance running.
It was thought to be deleterous to their health.
- Was long distance running allowed?
- Yeah, they were only allowed to run over 100 miles
or under 100 meters.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, the IAF just banned them
for running anything more than, I think, 800 meters.
- I think we might have said,
did we say once in an earlier episode
about there was an 800 meter race in the '20s
or something where all the women collapsed?
- Collapsed, yeah, we've talked about that.
And so that put them off.
Just 'cause everyone collapses.
They collapse in the way
that everyone at the end of a long distance race,
like if you've ever seen Mo Farah or someone
get to the end of a race,
they fall onto the nearest person.
- Absolutely.
- They very often do.
And so these women kind of did some of them.
- The IAF, we should say who they are,
the International Amateur Athletics Federation.
'Cause they did exercise quite a lot of power at the time.
'Cause they still do the IAAF.
- So Panister was running as an amateur.
That was part of the point, I think.
And so after he'd run the four minute mile,
obviously incredibly famous,
now one of the most famous people in the world, blah, blah,
blah, he went to the USA on a kind of diplomatic,
you know, jolly, glad-handling celebrity trip.
He was sent by the foreign office.
But when he got there, the IAAF said
that if he was on sponsored TV,
that might risk his amateur status.
And therefore, you know, that would be in big trouble
and I don't think he'd lose a record or whatever.
And he was offered a trophy, which was worth 178 pounds.
But when he was in America,
'cause they wanted to reward him somehow.
And the IAAF said, absolutely not.
You can accept no gift worth more than 12 pounds
as a result of this becoming the most famous program.
- Yeah, like you couldn't even have expenses
to get to places.
- Really?
- Yeah, maybe a bit earlier that,
but yeah, the amateurism was really important.
- That was why most of the people
who were quite successful runners back in the '50s
were quite wealthy white men in Western countries.
'Cause you couldn't really afford to do anything like that.
- That's true.
And actually, there is a thought
that there were people who were running
sub-form minute miles before him,
but they weren't Oxford graduates
who had all the newspapers and everything like that.
So for instance, there's a guy called James Parrott,
who is a costamonger.
And he supposedly ran a mile in under four minutes in 1770.
And there was in 1796 someone called Weller who did the same.
And the reason that we think it might be true
is because they were bets.
So it was like this costamonger said to his mate,
"I bet you 10 pounds that I can run it
"under four minute mile."
And the other person paid up.
We know that they paid up.
So whether they did or not,
certainly the person they did the bet with,
you know, was happy.
- I couldn't say that they had, yeah.
- I didn't know that if we're not trusting
Norris McWhorter to stopwatch,
I don't know if I'm trusting whatever grandfather clock
they timed it by.
- But I'm so clever on these guys
'cause I think they're really interesting claims.
I love the James Parrott one.
And there was also, soon after him in 1787,
there was a runner called Powell,
who wagered a thousand guineas,
which is a lot of money.
Today that's nearly 800,000 pounds.
- Wow.
- That he could manage a four minute mile run.
And he claimed to have done it in four minutes '03
when he did this time trial.
It was near Hampton Court in London.
And it was five days before Christmas.
And the really interesting detail
is that he was naked at the time.
(laughing)
Most serious runners would have been naked when they--
- In the 1700s.
- It was kind of a harking back
to ancient Greek athletic culture.
But still.
- And so what happened?
Did he lose the money?
- I actually don't know if he lost or won the money.
I actually apparently didn't decide
it was worth writing down whether or not he managed.
- I did a similar thing.
The current record for what the four minute mile
can be running, I've got all the other details.
Got the guy's name.
Just have to bring down what time he did it in.
So does anyone know the current?
- It's about 350.
- Is that Al-Garouj?
- Yes, Al-Garouj.
- I don't know how much it was.
I think it would be less than that, wouldn't it?
- I think it's 340 something.
- 340.
- I know what he'd be banister by in meters.
As in, if the two of them were racing against each other,
how much of a lead he had on him.
- That's so weird for you to have collected that.
- Okay, well, tell us about that, Al.
- Yeah, try and work it out.
- How many meters was it?
- He beat him by 100 meters.
He would have crossed the line.
- Okay, well, if you think 10 seconds
for a really fast runner to run 100 meters,
they would have done it in 15 seconds, something like that.
So if you take that off four minutes,
then that's, you know, 345, 346.
- You made it a bit complicated
by mixing up meters and miles, obviously, but we can work it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But just a home, do the calculation yourself.
- Or just Google HML Gurush and find out, 1999 it was.
It seems strange that we haven't beaten
the world record since then.
- Yeah, century.
- Since 1999, a century.
- This century.
- Oh, this century.
(laughing)
But yeah, the reason, according to Peter Weyand,
who is a Southern Methodist University Professor
of Applied Physiology and Biomechanics,
he records that the reason it hasn't been beaten
is because the next year we started testing for EPO,
which is a banned steroid, which kind of gives you--
- What year was that, sorry?
- '99.
- Oh.
- And so the Olympics knew that people were taking EPO,
but they didn't have a way of testing for it
until a year later.
And El Gurush, I should say, has denied
that he's ever taken any drugs,
and he is quite vocal in the anti-drugs kind of campaign
in sports, so no suggestion.
- 'Cause all the other ones go, "Yep, I was definitely on it."
(laughing)
- But the really interesting thing I think about El Gurush
is that he was gonna be a football goalkeeper.
And as a kid, he was really, really good.
But his mum stopped him from doing it
because he would dive around in the mud,
and all of his clothes would get really dirty.
And so she said, "Oh, well, you know,
"I have to clean them all the time.
"Can you not do something that's a bit less dirty?"
And he went, "Okay, I'll be a runner instead."
And he became the best miler ever.
- Wow.
- Do you know who came up with the first steroid test
for athletes?
- Is it someone we'll have heard of?
- Norris.
Is it Norris?
- Yeah, you're really close.
- David Hartley.
- Oh, Hugh Beaver.
- No, it was a banister, wasn't it?
- It was a banister.
- Oh!
- Yeah.
It was banister who developed the first steroid test
as in 1973, 'cause he was big into, you know,
calling out people who took steroids in sports.
And other stuff he did, other medical stuff he did,
since that's all he wants us to know about him,
is he was into self-experimenting.
He was one of those doctors.
- Oh, really?
- Okay.
- Steroids.
(laughing)
- Yeah, later at the age of 45,
he ran out of two minutes.
(laughing)
- He, not steroids, with pyrogens, actually.
- Okay.
- Which are less fun.
They are chemicals that induce fever.
So he wanted to study fever.
So he injected himself with pyrogens,
and then he sat naked in a hot chamber for six hours,
which spiked his temperature to very dangerous levels
and turned him dark green.
- Wow.
- Dark green?
- Yeah.
- Do we believe that?
- We've got the story of the Accredible Hulk.
(laughing)
- And he said, I wouldn't perhaps recommend it.
- What, Bruce Banner, stirrer?
- We've passed.
- Oh my god.
- Oh, we blow this shit wide open.
(laughing)
- So long since we blew something wide open.
I'm so glad about that.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- Yeah, you'll see in a lot of his papers,
he'll refer to the study participant, R.B.
And it's always him, obviously.
- You mentioned earlier, Anna,
that he was quite tricky to interview sometimes,
because obviously he had two very different aspects
of his life.
So there was an interview by the Guardian,
I think in the early 2000s.
So he was getting on them,
but I just wanted to read you some of the--
- Yeah, go for it.
- Okay, he was asked a few questions.
Then he said, right, is there anything else
you want to know?
And the interviewer said, well, I'll be honest, sir.
Yes, what's your favorite biscuit?
Oh, I don't answer questions about biscuits.
(laughing)
Why not?
Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
I'm not into biscuits.
(laughing)
- Now, what is he hiding?
That's the question.
The interviewer says, everybody likes a nice biscuit.
He says, well, I'm not sure what the purpose
of that aspect of the interview is.
It's quirky, game showy, odd.
(laughing)
All right, fair play to the Guardian interviewer.
He perseveres.
Cheese or chocolate?
No, no, no.
All right, I think you've got more than enough there.
What about pie fillings, steak and kidney
or chicken and mushroom?
Banister just says, thank you so much.
All the best.
(laughing)
Ends the interview.
- That's incredible.
What year is this?
2004 it was.
- Okay.
I'm just wondering, is this like the era of like,
you know, Dennis Penness and Ali G
and everyone's been primed not to answer stupid questions.
- I think you just hated us.
- I think that's just the point that's questioned
from a journalist.
In that journalist, I can really imagine doing
what that journalist has done,
which is not be able to remember anything else
that you might have asked him.
(laughing)
I'm just happy to keep going on.
- Or just quickly looking at, you know,
it's going off.
Fuck, what's your favorite sandwich?
(laughing)
Would you rather?
No, that's not going to work either.
Have you ever?
No.
(laughing)
I was, I was saying to you guys,
bizarrely, my brother helped him write
his last autobiography a few years ago,
which came out.
I think it's called "Twinsumthings".
And he said he was extremely nice.
And actually, particularly his wife,
my brother absolutely loved Moira.
And she'd always bring them warm beer
and sort of cold cuts for lunch.
- Any biscuits?
- Well, I read through that book
and there was no mention of Garibaldi.
So we went, "What's the matter?"
- Every time she wore biscuits in,
he'd flip the table.
(laughing)
- I saw him once at a,
the QI used to have a building in Oxford
and he came to one of the parties in a QI.
- He just ran in, had a drink, ran out.
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
(laughing)
Yeah, but it was kind of like,
I don't know, in a weird way,
because he's someone who's a slightly obscure famous person.
It was sort of like spotting, you know, like a Bigfoot.
It was just like, "Wow, like look, a sighting of Bannister."
Quite exciting.
- I mean, he didn't like it,
but let's say he did like it.
Would you walk around even in your 80s
wearing your shorts and your like-
- Tank top thingy.
- Yeah, tank top thing.
- Carrying your record, what did he get?
- Medal?
- Must have got a medal or something.
- He was the year before you get
the Guinness World Records.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Poor guy.
- So he didn't even have the-
- Missed it by a year.
- No proof.
- Because his record was then broken, wasn't it?
46 days later by John Landy, the Aussie.
And they ended up having an amazing run together,
which was part of a race,
which was known as the Miracle Mile Race.
It had a few different names.
And they went up against each other.
I mean, how exciting.
Two guys who had the records
trying to see who could beat them.
- I suppose that does happen
in pretty much every race meeting in the world.
- I suppose, yeah, that's true,
because you're always trying to break a record.
I guess this was-
- Very rare, Mo Farrow just racing
a bunch of primary school children's sports day.
Do you know what?
You should try racing other good runners.
- Yeah.
- I think Bannister said his race against Landy
was the thing he was really proudest of.
- Oh, really?
- 'Cause it was watched by 40 million people
when it was in Vancouver.
- And listened by a hundred million on the radio,
apparently. - Listened to by a hundred million.
- Bizarrely boring.
Just bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang.
Is that what you hear when you listen to a race?
- Commentary, probably true, it probably be.
- Commentary.
- It's not a good commentator
if that's what they're saying the whole time.
Bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang.
So in that race, they were both, you know,
neck for neck the entire time.
And Bannister's behind him.
And-
- That's not what neck for neck.
- Yeah.
So he was kind of like putting his neck out,
touching the back of it.
- It's neck and neck, I think.
- Yeah.
- Not neck for neck.
- No, I've never-
- And neck for neck and eye for eyes.
- That's the Bible, yeah.
I think they were neck and neck, I'm sorry too.
- No, no, that's fine.
I would not make a good commentator either.
- Bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang.
- Yep, they're neck for neck.
- They were neck and neck in front of one in front of the other.
Yeah.
- So Bannister's right behind him and he's covered up.
And on the final corner, Landy looks over left
on his shoulder and as he looks over left,
Bannister takes over on the right.
And that was the famous moment where-
- He tapped him on the shoulder before he did it.
(all laughing)
- I wanna put a ghost on the running track.
I think we need to redo it.
(all laughing)
- So that was the big moment.
And this moment has been-
- Then he stole his nose.
(all laughing)
- And then his thumb came off and it was like,
"Whoa!"
(all laughing)
- Anyway, the prize money that Landy got
was retrieved from behind his ear actually.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number four.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that when the movie Ulysses
was released in New Zealand in 1967,
sensors were so worried about it
that men and women weren't allowed to watch it
at the same time.
So they literally had to be placed in different cinemas
if they wanted to go and see it.
And that continued on for years.
So there was a showing of it at a university
in New Zealand in 1972.
And even then they still had,
they allowed men and women in the same room,
but they had to sit on either side of the cinema.
- Okay, so is it because it's so sexy?
- It's sexy, it's sweary, it was just debauched city.
It was-
- You see, because I can see if it's sexy
that you don't want men and women sat next to each other,
right?
- 'Cause they might have sex with each other.
- They might, just straight like that, you know.
That's what happened when I watched.
Stop on my mom.
(all laughing)
- And you weren't on your own to sit on that movie,
so that poor person next to you.
- I could see half way through that sense
as that was going the other way.
But then like if it was a sweary part of it,
it doesn't make sense if they're in the same room, right?
- No, it was a mixture of the sexiness and of the swearing.
And in the room, there was a rope
that went down the center of the audience.
And so you had the men and women still,
there was one row, like one line down the center
where men and women could have had sex with a rope.
- Well, just like the rope was sort of,
there was no aisle between them.
They were literally in a seat next to someone, yeah.
- If there's just a piece of rope in between you
and a person, you can still have sex with them.
- It's a pretty weak barrier to ardor, I would say.
- Yeah, I got this fact, by the way,
from a brilliant book called "The Land Before Avocado"
and it's by a guy called Richard Glover,
who I've met in Australia when we were on tour there.
He actually, I went on his radio show.
So he's a big journalist and broadcaster.
He's written a bunch of books.
- What's the title referring to?
- Well, avocado is absolutely abundant in Australia
as a breakfast item.
And he's talking about the old Australia.
So avocado is sort of the new world of Australia.
- Got it.
- And the book is all about all the olden days
and how things used to be.
And Ulysses was actually banned in Australia,
which is where it comes up, the book as well as the movie.
- So this is James Joyce's "Ulysses", I should say.
- Yeah, James Joyce's, you haven't read the book,
now don't see the film.
(all laughing)
But yeah, so he mentions that it was allowed in New Zealand,
but then they had this segregation thing
between the men and the women.
- Very funny.
- And you said that it was the film as well, wasn't it?
There was one in Australia and South Africa, I think.
- Quite a lot of places, there was a band in Ireland.
- Yeah.
- The band in Ireland was only lifted in the year 2000.
- That was a long band.
And I think Ireland's justice secretary
sent his secretary to go and see the movie
and reported back that if this film was allowed,
it would discredit the Irish government,
so it can't be permitted.
- Yeah.
- It was the first film shown in Britain
to feature the F-word.
- Ooh.
- Spicy.
- Yeah.
- It's really interesting.
It was made by a guy called Joseph Strick
and he was a massive fan of the book.
So his initial pitch for making the movie
was he wanted to do it verbatim,
so it was gonna be 18 hours long.
He wanted every bit of dialogue
that was in the book.
- Marley, Marley.
- Got talked out of it,
so it eventually ended up being two hours long.
But then when it came out,
he was very angry about the response of all these bannings
in the way that people were treating the film.
And there was one famous incident
where they showed the movie in Cannes
at the film festival.
And this was at the 1967 one.
It had French titles along the bottom.
And during the film,
where it got to a particularly spicy bit,
they had, using their hands,
scribbled out the translation
in French subtitle of what was being said.
So Strick saw this,
thought, you're messing with my movie.
Ran up, ran to the projection booth,
where he was met by the committee of the film festival
who knew that he'd rush in there.
And then he was forcibly ejected, according to him.
He said he was pushed down the steps
and suffered a broken foot.
And so he withdrew the film from Cannes altogether.
- The reason that he loved the book
is that his father had smuggled a copy into America
because it was illegal in lots of countries
at the start of the 20th century.
And his father smuggled this copy into America
and would just keep it in the house
and leave it on the table
so that whenever anyone came around,
they would say, oh, that's that dirty book, isn't it?
Like Ulysses.
And then like, even though no one had read it,
they would still argue about it,
about censorship and stuff like that.
- Yeah, well, it was really,
so I think 1920, the very early 20s,
it was published, '23, I think.
And it was, you know, it was printed.
It was, 'cause he wrote it in '18, didn't he?
And it was serialized,
but maybe it was published in Britain in '23, do you mean?
- Well, 500 copies were burnt at Folkstone in 1923.
So I think that was an attempt to import it.
- It was published in France in 1922.
That was in Paris by an American woman called Sylvia Beach.
She opened a shop and she had these copies of Ulysses
that she managed to get.
And she sold them for 10 times more
than any other book in the shop
'cause she knew that everyone would want to get
the hands on this book.
But still they managed to get them,
still they paid for them.
And she removed the copy from the store window
'cause she thought that people would start throwing bricks
in her store and stuff like that.
- Still none of the buyers ever read it.
I think we can guarantee all of these places,
all of these people.
- Beach was really brave.
So the book was sued in New York
by the New York Society for the Suppression of Vice,
and it was convicted for being obscene.
- They were fun people.
- Yeah, but then after that,
Beach published it in Paris.
And part of the reason it was controversial
was when it was printed in extract in the USA,
even the printers themselves said,
this is outrageous, we're not working on this.
And then when she was in Paris,
French printers were obviously harder to offend
with English filth
because they don't understand the language
that they're printing in.
- And that'd be French, like Madame Bovary.
- Web it through, web it through, yeah, yeah, yeah.
They're used to this sort of.
- Madame Bovary's not that sexy.
- Are you joking?
- There's some shit in a carriage.
Come on, it's much more subtle
than what Ulysses sounds like.
- Pretty raunchy stuff, Madame Bovary.
- Okay.
- Andi's Bar is quite different to you.
- I'm still lobbying to ban Madame Bovary.
(all laughing)
- But so, Norsica was the chapter in America
that was seen from Ulysses.
So they were publishing these extracts.
And in the chapter that suddenly raised the concern,
Leopold Bloom, one of the lead characters of the book,
Ulysses. - He's the lead, I think.
- He leads the main guy.
- He's not sharing it with many people.
Maybe Molly.
- Yeah, I was thinking Molly.
So it's a scene in this chapter
where he's masturbating on a beach
while gazing at a 17-year-old girl called Goethe McDowell.
And that's what they took exception to.
Do they have scenes like that in Madame Bovary?
- It's not quite that much, is it?
- I don't remember.
- Or in fact, another scene.
And this is just saving anyone the trouble
of actually reading it
'cause we're just telling you
the couple of fun bits, so you don't have to bother.
But apparently there's one scene in a, I haven't read it.
There's one scene in a Dublin brothel
where Leopold Bloom transforms into a woman
and then gives birth to octoplets
before the brothel, Madame,
who then turns into a man
and starts auctioning off blooms
like prostitution services and demonstrates.
So Bloom's now a woman with a vagina.
And so the brothel, Madame,
demonstrates how good a prostitute that he'd make
by shoving her arm up his vagina.
- Yeah, okay.
- Also doesn't happen.
Oh, it shoves her arm up the vagina
and then shoves it into the bidder's face
to be like, look, how good is that?
- There's another line.
I actually started reading Ulysses at the start of the year
when my daughter was born
and I had a lot of time in the middle of the night
sat there with nothing else to do.
And I got through quite, no, not much of it,
but then I started listening to the audio book,
the RTE version, which actually I got through most of.
I didn't get through to the end.
And it gets really racy at the end.
So I'm a bit gutted that I haven't got there yet.
But anyway, there was this line,
and I did tweet this at the time,
which is, "Haines helped himself and snapped the case too.
He put it back in his side pocket
and took from his waistcoat pocket
a nickel tinder box, sprang it open too,
and having lit his cigarette,
held the flaming spunk towards Stephen
in the shell of his hands."
- What?
- And so that's-
- Sorry, when did the spunk come in before that move?
- The reason is that the word spunk
just doesn't mean what it means today.
- Oh, really?
- It meant like a little bit of flame
or a little bit of, you know,
if you like to match a little bit of flame
sort of flies away.
That used to be called a spunk.
- Oh, okay.
- Flaming spunk.
- I guess it is a sort of fly away thing.
It flies off and away.
- Yeah.
- I'm sure there's some etymological reason, golly.
- Do you know the day Ulysses was set,
which is famously one day, June the 16th, 1904,
is the day that James Joyce first got a handjob
from his wife.
- Is it?
- Yeah.
- Bloom's day.
- It's to commemorate that day, exactly.
- Really?
So that's why it's to commemorate?
- Yeah, he said it then.
It was their first date.
Is it to commemorate the first date?
Is it to commemorate the handjob?
Is there a difference?
- Is, I don't know, but also Sylvia Plath and Ted Hughes
married on that day.
- Did they?
- In commemoration of Bloom's Day,
not the handjob.
It looked more about when the day was set.
- Yeah.
- I wonder if she gave him a handjob
in proper commemoration.
- You may now kiss the bride,
and you may now...
Oh.
(laughing)
The person who banned the book in the UK,
this was in 1922.
It was the government that banned it,
but the person whose idea it was
was a guy called Sir Archibald Bodkin.
And he issued an official opinion
saying that it was a filthy buck,
and it should not be allowed to be imported
into the country, and the government agreed.
And I was reading about Sir Archibald Bodkin.
Apparently he was a man of unwavering Victorian sensibilities.
This is according to an author, Kevin Birmingham,
who was writing about Ulysses.
They said, "On the rare occasions that he told a body joke,
"he drained away the humour by delivering the punchline
"with a disapproving glare."
(laughing)
- Why are you looking at me, James?
I don't know what you're trying to say here.
- I love that.
- That's so funny.
- I'd love to see his live at the Apollo set.
(laughing)
- Furious when the audience laughs.
- Shut up.
- Just on films that are banned.
- Oh yeah.
- The Wikipedia film, which films are banned where,
is great.
So, 'cause it's quite nationally specific in lots of cases.
So, "Cuba," for example, has banned the films,
"Red Zone Cuba," "Cuba Crossing," "Red Dawn," "Cuban Love."
- Any movie would "Cuba Gooding Jr."
(laughing)
- Without Havana.
And finally, "Harold and Kumar Escape from Guantanamo Bay."
(laughing)
- Okay, that's understandable.
- There's one film called "Titanic" from 1943,
it's a 1943 Titanic of the original,
which was banned by the Nazi government,
despite the fact that it had been made
by the Nazi propaganda department.
- Oh, I remember that one, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Why, was it like a practice run
to check how well they banned stuff?
- I think Goebbels decided it would weaken morale,
because there was lots of bombing happening
in Germany at the time.
And Goebbels decided that, because this film
featured a lot of deaths on the Titanic,
that it would weaken morale in Germany.
So, there were some test screenings outside Germany,
but it was never shown in Germany.
It was also then obviously banned by the Allies,
because it was Nazi propaganda.
- So, there was basically nowhere this film
was allowed to be shown.
- Yeah.
- Do you guys do the film "Too Cool for Christmas?"
- No. - No.
- Not familiar with that.
- Do you know the film "A Very Cool Christmas?"
- No.
- Right, well, they're both the same film.
They're about a girl who wants to go skiing
instead of spending Christmas with her parents.
But in one of them, in "A Very Cool Christmas,"
the girl's parents are a female and male
heterosexual couple.
And in "Too Cool for Christmas,"
her parents are two male gay fathers.
- Right, okay.
- And it's exactly the same.
But the films are exactly the same as each other.
They just re-filmed every single scene involving the parents,
which I imagine is quite a lot of scenes.
- And they just show them in different parts of America.
- Or different parts of the world.
- That was pretty much exactly it.
It was for America, it was 2004.
And it's this director who is called Sam Irvin,
who's a gay director who wanted to do the plotline
about the gay dads.
But couldn't get the budget for the LGBTQ station
that he wanted to put it on.
So he also sold it to Lifetime TV,
a rather traditionalist TV station.
So he also got a mom.
- I want to go to like a traditional
Orthodox American family and show them the first film,
the one with the heterosexual couple,
and then show them the other one and say,
"You know what, they've done this for all the films."
(all laughing)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland,
- Andy, - @AndrewHunterM,
- James, - @JamesHarken,
- and Anna.
- You can email podcast.qi.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account
@NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThingIsAfish.com.
Check it out.
All the previous episodes are up there,
as well as links to any upcoming live shows
that we might be doing.
Our merch is up there as well.
But most excitingly of all,
is the new thing that you'll find up there,
which is a link to Club Fish.
Club Fish is our new subscription service.
It's a membership club,
whereby you can get access to ad-free episodes.
You can get all sorts of bonus content
that we're going to be popping up there.
Or you can just support the podcast.
You might just want to do that.
You've been thinking of doing that for a while.
This is your way to do it.
So whatever your reason for joining Club Fish,
we would love to see you there.
We hope you enjoy all the behind the scenes stuff
that we're going to be chucking up there too.
But hey, listen, if you can't join Club Fish,
don't worry, you don't need to,
because this podcast isn't going anywhere.
We are not going behind a paywall.
This will stay a free weekly podcast
for the rest of its days.
So the best way you could support us,
if you don't want to do Club Fish,
is simply just keep listening.
Just keep bringing your ears to the party
and maybe tell your friends about it too.
We want to be spreading these facts
to as many people as possible.
And the only way we do that
is by having listeners like you tell your friends about it.
We will be back again next week with a very special guest.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)