(telephone rings)
(speaking in foreign language)
(fun music)
- Hi!
- Hey Andy.
- Hi everybody, welcome to Drop us a Line.
Thank you for listening, thank you for watching.
We hope you've had a lovely break.
We're back, we're raring to go.
We're full of beans.
How's the inbox?
Bulging.
(clears throat)
It's stunning.
I've actually got a hefty bit of paper pile in front of me.
Any inbox-related New Year's resolutions?
- Ooh, for me.
- Yeah.
- I think just, I'm gonna keep reading everything
and that's my, I'm just trying to stay on top of it.
- Yeah, okay, great.
- Yeah, I'm gonna stay on top of it.
It's my resolution.
- Okay.
- I'm not gonna let it get like it did last year.
- It was an absolute shambles last year.
- It really was, it really was.
You have to just sort of pretend
you've lost those 10,000 emails, no, I don't know.
- Yeah, right.
- I do read them, and they're all brilliant.
You've been emailing in podcast@ky.com
and we've got a lot to get through, guys.
- Okay.
- Let's do it, let's go.
- Well, let's start with the business lounge.
- Oh, this is new.
- This is new.
(laughs)
- What is the business lounge?
- Well, it's where people pitch us ideas.
- Oh, business lounge, as in, this is a business idea.
- Yeah.
- Oh, I see.
- I can't trust it.
- Okay, well.
- This is a dragonfish dead.
- We're fish tank, fish tank.
- Yeah.
- James writes,
"While playing hungry, hungry hippos over Christmas,
"my entrepreneurial mind invented a sure fire.
"No such thing as a fish money spinner."
- Yeah.
- Okay.
"Swap out the hippos with faithful recreations
"of President James Garfield's buttocks.
"Hey presto, a fun and educational game for all the family.
"I'm looking for 450,000 pounds."
- Okay, in return for a 30% stake.
- Here's the issue.
I feel that what he ate through his anus
was largely soup based, which is--
- Yeah, eggs though.
- Sorry.
- Eggs.
- He had eggs?
- Yeah.
- Fried or--
- I think they were probably chopped up.
- Not just whole, it wasn't like a reverse chicken.
- It wasn't like a boiled.
- It's the reverse chicken.
- No.
- Okay.
- I believe they stopped giving him eggs
because it was causing annoying smells.
- Yes.
- So eggs could work.
- Eggs could work.
- I've got a question for James.
And that is, how do you differentiate
President Garfield's buttocks from any other buttocks
around the world?
How do we know that they're Garfieldian?
- I think you'll have to have a little mold of his face,
his upper half at the other end.
- I see.
- Of the hippo.
I guess you pressed down on his,
on the top of his head actually,
to make the buttocks leap out and grab some food.
Visually, that could work great.
- I think so.
- Yeah.
- Anyway, I have been into your bank accounts.
I'm siphoned off 150,000 of each of you.
I don't even know 149,000 pounds in the red.
Sorry.
- What's it called?
Because that might not be a problem.
I might be happy about that.
- There's not much you can do with hungry, hungry hippos.
- No.
This ass eats.
- This, well, kids, kids, time.
Where's grandma?
We're playing this ass eats.
- Quick.
- Yeah.
- And you can stop me watching that.
I hope those of you have been waiting for me
to cry at the sound of the sound.
- email one minute three, brilliant.
- Oh, so thanks James.
That's a great idea and the check is in the post.
All right, I've got some serious legal news.
- Oh, we had a business lounge.
- Yes, we are.
We're into plagiarism corner.
- Oh, yeah.
- Oh, wow.
- Yeah.
So Declan Costello writes,
"I am a very recent new listener to the podcast.
I'm very much enjoying working my way
through the back catalog."
Nice, perfect.
Listening to your theme music,
I was struck by the resemblance to the opening bars
of Kate Bush's "Wuthering Heights."
- Hmm.
- I surely cannot be the only person
to have commented on this.
Declan, you are.
You're the first person in nearly 12 years.
- Please suggest to me that they're not similar.
- Well, do you want to hear it?
- Yeah.
- Sure, well, I think you and I know.
- Right.
- I feel like I know "Wuthering Heights" as well, but.
- I thought I knew it too.
This is quite striking, I'm going to say.
Have a listen to this.
- So.
- It'll be an exciting, exciting 2026 for Fish
and we will see you then.
- That sounds nothing like Kate Bush.
Wait, okay.
That bit?
Yeah.
Okay, wait for it.
(soft music)
(singing)
- Yeah? - Not bad, yeah.
- I can see a slight resemblance, but not enough
for it to be legally challengeable.
- I can see why Bush's lawyers had to step down
when presenting their case, yeah.
- I think that's right, James.
I think legally there's not remotely similar enough
for that to be any chance of a successful action.
- Well, do you remember when Robin Thickey got
done for plagiarism and it was all on the vibe?
And I don't reckon that the vibe is the same there?
- No, I think we're a bit more mystical in the material.
- than Kate Bush.
- Yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- But anyway, so thank you, Declan, that's good
to keep us on our toes.
- Yeah. - Cool.
- That's great. - Let's see if you spotted something
that might financially ruin us.
The email address is podcasting.com.
Thanks very much.
- Well, we didn't write that feature.
- Yeah.
- No, no.
- That was written by Ash Gardner.
- That's true.
- Some time of this parish.
- Yeah. - Yes, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Hugo and Alan Betts as well, yeah.
- Empre yes.
- Yes. - If you want to go on Spotify.
- Yeah, it's on Spotify.
- Yeah. - It's a great album.
- Yeah.
- And Kate Bush is also available.
(laughing)
- Good.
Ellie Pearson writes in about a recent episode
we did with Lou Sanders.
- Yeah. - Oh.
- This is a telling off for me.
Hi Andy, I feel like a lot of people
might write in about this.
I'm afraid you're the first, Ellie.
So I apologize if that's the case.
I wasn't gonna mention it when you only said it once,
but then you said it five times and I couldn't let it go.
Okay, the pronunciation of Wyoming
has the inflection on the second syllable, not the first.
So it's Wyoming.
- No, it's not Wyoming. - It's Wyoming.
- Oh, I've done it six, six times.
It's Wyoming.
- And you said Wyoming. - Wyoming.
Five times apparently. - Okay.
- Wyoming.
- Yeah, Wyoming. - Wyoming, that's fair enough.
- I know it's a slight difference,
but I figure if the Australians are allowed
to correct pronunciation, so are the Americans.
Fair enough?
- One thing I've noticed very early in this year
is how many times people are apologizing to you
for writing in almost as if you've been saying
quite often on the podcast.
We get too many emails, guys.
You know what, James, this brings me,
you've actually precipitated,
I need to get ahead because we had an email from,
I think it was called Park.
Yeah, Park.
I hate when you all say don't write in.
It makes me feel bad,
even if I wasn't planning on writing in.
(laughing)
Like me saying don't write in is prompted him to write in,
so it hasn't worked.
So I'm really sorry, always write in.
Always write in, I do be genuinely loved.
- We love these. - Oh, we do, we do, we do.
- And if you don't want to write in,
then do write in and tell us.
- Podcasts of UI.com.
- Whether or not you want to write in, please write in.
- Right, thanks but no thanks.
- Okay, oh.
- No, thanks but no thanks.
- Yeah, okay.
Dan's unexpected anecdotes are always a real treat.
It never ceases to amaze me.
How frequently Dan is able to perfectly segue
into some personal experience
based on something other hosts have said.
From my family was featured in a friend's parking
in fraction photo and the tip off was a pumpkin suit.
- To, I was featured in a Hong Kong Karate magazine
for spitting on an opponent.
(laughing)
- There are hours of ready-made material
just begging to be collected and released as a special.
- Well, I think, you know, one day Bob Mortimer has to retire,
right?
And would I like you are gonna need someone
with ridiculous stories to come on the show?
- Yeah, I think you're right.
Yeah, the problem is, is they're all true.
So I would just, I would be caught out every single time.
- You get to make, what, no.
- I don't know if I can make up one.
I don't know if I can fabricate a life story.
- Yeah, in the moment.
- Try me.
- I'll try one during this episode.
See if it's on it.
- Okay, great, exciting, okay.
(laughing)
Now interestingly, Jim Dennis.
- My uncle's called Jim Dennis.
- Right, that's a lie.
- Correct.
(laughing)
- God, you're good.
- He's good.
- You're both good.
- Well, I'm not going on if he's going on.
(laughing)
- No, but you know, Jim, James, Dan, Dennis.
- You know, you can sometimes get Nick Mender, I do.
- Just a bit weird, isn't it?
- I'm just thinking that Lee Mack has to retire eventually.
- Right.
- They need some sort of Northern Chipper Lad.
- Yes. - Come on.
- That's very good.
- So we could be the future of what I like to you.
- We could be.
- David Mitchell.
- It's not going anywhere.
- Oh no.
(laughing)
- Dan, James, and David Mitchell
present their new project.
- That sounds good.
- Right.
(laughing)
- I was just thinking, you know what the special guest
comes on.
- Oh yeah.
- How do you know this man?
Well, he actually lost all of his money
to a game attribute to hungry hippos.
(laughing)
- Cool.
This ass eats.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
Okay.
(laughing)
- Well Jim Dennis says, in a recent episode at Christmas,
you mentioned James and Dan have lived really interesting
lives before no such thing as a fish.
Weirdly no mention of me.
(laughing)
- My suggestion.
Can I say, "Scree you, Jim."
(laughing)
- My suggestion will be his Andy and he's a friend of mine
who has no anecdotes.
(laughing)
- Rob Brighton's got to retire eventually.
- My suggestion will be an episode of no such thing
as a fish which focuses upon
either James or Dan.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- What am I?
- We could do you one week and me the next year.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that's great.
- We the listeners can find out more about you guys,
but also draw upon interesting facts from your past.
Facts built around an interesting life well lived.
Well Andy, I presume it just continues reading the emails.
(laughing)
- Can't believe I put that in thanks, but no thanks.
- Right, say thanks.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Good Lord.
- I can't believe you're getting bullied on email
from our fans.
- It's quite something, isn't it?
But not even bullied actively, bullied by a mission.
- Yeah.
- By Jim knew why he was doing that.
- Yeah, he was doing.
- He knew what he was doing.
- Yeah.
- All right.
Well, here's one from Sully.
Hello, any chance you could post a video
of James Harkin doing his Donald Duck impression
on Instagram.
I'd love to see what he looks like when he's doing it.
He's so funny.
- Okay, well, thanks.
PS Dance Terrific, too.
(laughing)
- Well, we're filming this, so I can quickly do it.
- We're filming this.
- I can quickly do it.
- Yeah.
- Good luck.
- Goofy's got to retire eventually.
(laughing)
- Cool.
- Guy.
- Wow.
- Yeah, pretty good.
- So, I'm pretty good.
- I don't know what I look like in any case, actually,
'cause I have face blackness, but it's true.
Like, I don't know what I look like there.
I assume I just have a slightly open mouth on one side.
- Yeah.
- No, it was good.
That's a very good impression.
So, thank you, Sully.
We now come to get yourself off the hook.
Okay.
And then we're gonna segue into this week's rodeo clown,
which is a different kind of get yourself off the hook.
- Yes.
- Unfortunately.
Ian Flower says there's one for me.
I'm so sorry, I imagine you're getting this a lot all week.
It seems as though the clock faces on the Elizabeth Tower.
Do show X's.
- Interesting.
- They're just in the Fractour font,
which makes them look quite a lot like F's.
- Yes, so, this is, I think they're right.
I forgot the name, sorry.
- Ian, is that Ian?
- Yeah, I think Ian is right about that.
But one interesting thing is,
if you go onto the website of the House of Parliament,
they specifically say that they're not X's, they're F's.
But when you look at it,
they're very obviously stylized X's
that Pugin just decided he wanted to do that.
- Yeah, look, 'cause I spent quite a long time looking at that.
Basically, what we said was, in case anyone missed this,
Lord Borwick wrote in and said that the X's
on the face of the Big Bang clock are in fact F's.
And there are some very weird Gothic fonts
where the X looks quite a bit like it.
But it's really tall with a sticky outfit at the time.
- Yeah, we looked at the pictures at the time.
- Yeah, it does look like it.
- Well, after we got that email from Lord Borwick,
I thought I wondered if we could run it on QI
'cause we're currently researching the X series on QI.
And we did some more work on it.
And I think we're not gonna run it for that reason
because we think they are stylized X.
- 'Cause it's not true.
- Yeah, just fair enough.
Well, but you must have loads of material for the X series.
- Oh, I wouldn't worry about that.
- Yeah.
- And thank you also to Salman,
long time listener from Riyad,
who wrote in saying the same thing.
And he claimed that a Lord wrote in
to tell him there are no X's.
He's a real Lord, what does he want to say?
The Lord is real.
- You were getting a kicking in this episode.
- For me?
- At your own hand as well,
'cause you select these emails to bring.
- Well, don't worry, Dan.
Your time will come.
- Will it?
- Uh, not sure.
Can't remember.
- Oh, here's another thing.
- Here's the last threat ever.
(laughing)
- This is why I failed my audition to play Fanos.
- And then that's Bonville and your time will come.
- Maybe.
- Anyway, I'm just gonna throw myself
into the shark tank now.
- Speaking of shark tank, Mr. Bond.
Have I told you my idea?
(laughing)
- So do you know the phrase this eats ass
means something bad, okay.
What if?
Okay.
Right, Dawn Heatherington
raced with something else that I got wrong.
(laughing)
I don't want to be dishonest.
I can't let a fact go wrong on the show.
- Absolutely.
- You know.
- No way.
- Yeah, he's gonna have integrity.
- Dawn Heatherington writes,
"My ears pricked up when listening to this week's podcast
"as I felt sure I had listened to an interview
"with the British author of the Jack Reacher books
"saying he no longer wished to live in America
"and he was returning to Britain."
So, I said he lives in Wyoming.
- Off the grid.
- So off-grid.
- End of a long drive.
- 10 miles from his own postbox.
- Yes.
- And 45 miles from the nearest grocery store.
Well, apparently he's moved back to the lake district.
- Okay.
- Oh, lovely.
- That's right, yeah.
- So he's back in the lake district.
And I looked up and he's done it.
He has been interviewed and said,
"Yes, I've moved back."
So.
- Having lived in the lake district,
I can say that you can often be a long way
from your nearest shop as well.
- Absolutely.
- So he hasn't moved to the hustle bustle.
- No.
- Well, those trains from Windermere are pretty unreliable,
aren't they?
- Yeah.
- Good stuff.
- Once an hour to Watson Home.
(laughing)
- I'll, you used to live properly there, didn't you?
- Yeah, yeah.
And that brings us to the rodeo clown.
- Okay.
- Ooh.
- Here we go.
- Now you'll see why I did so much preparatory
dunking on myself.
- Oh shit.
- Because I'm about to read out about 1,500 words
which backs me up on something I said.
- Oh, here we go.
- Here we go.
- Okay, sorry, right.
- Don't you worry.
Right, Shane Doran says,
"Your novels aren't that bad after all."
(laughing)
Shane Doran says,
"Regarding the point made by Andy about the train
"that requires zero energy to run,
"I would like to point out it is possible for this to work
"without requiring either magical
"any kind of perpetual motion device."
So this was, there's a train in Australia
which gets loaded up with iron ore at the top of the hill,
goes downhill, breaks on the way
to reach out its battery 'cause it's an electric train,
and then empties out the iron ore
and has enough extra juice from the braking
to get itself to the top of the hill.
- Yeah, and I think what the problem,
'cause Alice was saying that it might not be possible,
and I think I sort of said that as well,
but I think we didn't really take into account
the potential energy that you're adding
when you put the loads on,
which obviously you need to use energy
to put the loads on as well, right?
- The work is basically,
well, I'll read Shane's email basically.
If the train is loaded at the top of the hill,
the load has a large amount of potential energy
that can be used to charge the battery.
If the train goes back up the hill empty,
then there is less potential energy required
to drive it up the hill
than was available to drive it down.
This is just a slightly more convoluted version
of a water wheel.
So the rocks are descending in a controlled manner
and charging the battery.
I think Professor Alice owes Andy an apology.
(laughing)
- I think.
- Let's call her up.
- Yes, there we go.
- Now I think we, yeah, it was just the,
obviously you need energy to load it up.
- Yes, the work is being done at the top of the hill.
Like that is effectively another version
of a battery being charged
is filling a train up with these rocks,
which then, you know, once that mountain is empty,
then you won't be able to run an infinity train anymore.
Anyway, I wanna thank David Hopkins.
I thought you were not treated very well
when talking about the infinite train.
Nash Rochman.
James indicated this would constitute
a perpetual motion machine, but it would not.
Andy even summarized the mechanism
but was unfairly silenced.
Eric Samuel.
- Let's go, I'm not gonna go on.
- Please.
- We've had dozens of emails about it.
- When you're making up these names,
do you take two separate names
and bash them together to make a full one?
- Oh, let's see.
- Yeah, lie.
(laughing)
- No, thank you to everyone.
I'm really touched by your support, you wrote in.
- It works, the infinite train works.
I thought you said the mountain runs out though.
- Yeah, like in a hundred years
when they've emptied out this entire mine,
what is infinite to you?
- Oh my gosh.
(laughing)
- Stop.
Anyway, no, thank you everyone for writing
and about the infinite train, the theory works.
And the train is going, anyway, whatever.
I'm cool about it.
Right, now we move on to a really fun section,
a new section that I think we're lobbying for names for.
It's personal experiences that people have had
based on things we've talked about.
- Oh, okay.
And I can't think of a fishy pun for it.
- Right, Alexander Dudley writes,
"My wife, Jane and I just listened to the episode,
"little fish, this could tail off really quickly
"and we're heartened to hear our story mentioned."
"For I am the husband
"that cured my wife, Jane's treatment resistant
"by polar disorder with poo transplants."
- Come on.
- 2017.
- Okay.
- No way.
- This is, I'm Starstruck.
My wife has now been without bipolar symptoms
and off all medications for eight years, not one year.
Can't remember if we said that.
And we know of 18 other people who have resolved
their bipolar disorder
through this somewhat unconventional treatment.
- Can you give us,
can you just remind us the basics of the story?
- Yeah, so this lady had this problem of bipolar disorder
and they found out that by having a fecal transplant,
they changed the biome presumably, I forgot, and...
- How was that?
- It was a hominage fecal transplant.
It was administered at home the old fashioned way.
- And then the bit that we did was imagining
how you bring that up in a relationship.
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- But I'm amazed that these people are actually listening.
That's incredible.
- And Alexander writes, "Prior to the treatment,
"missing any of her three medications
"for more than 48 hours,
"mentally would be in a psych ward within a week."
And then since the treatment, it's now fine.
The treatment also began on my birthday,
but that was purely coincidental.
Suspicious.
- That is stunning.
- I know, because the post line of that was like,
"Maybe we could try it on my birthday."
- Yeah, exactly.
- That's amazing.
- I know.
- So there you go.
So thank you, Alexander.
- Oh, good.
- And he includes a lot more details,
but it was quite a long email
so we don't have time to read the whole thing.
But just stunning.
It's a new field of research and it is exploding.
He says, "Like the bowels of someone
"with clistradiodes difficile,
"which is presently the only disease
"the treatment is officially approved for."
Anyway.
- Incredible.
- That's great.
- I'm really, like you say, star stroke, genuinely.
Yeah. - Yeah.
- Yeah.
- Really cool.
- Can I give you a similar one,
someone who had an experience?
- Yes. - So great.
- So we said on a recent podcast
that Kanye West, on his rider,
said that they had to iron his carpets.
- Oh, yeah.
- Okay.
- Do you remember that?
- Yeah.
- I was giving some strange riders
and that was one of them.
We had someone who I'm not allowed to name,
but I can say that they worked on the Jewels Holland show.
And when they were working on that show,
Kanye had his carpets ironed
and that's where the story came from.
- Amazing.
- Now, the reason was,
is Kanye likes everything to be white
in his dressing room.
And the events team put a new white carpet on the floor.
So that's normal.
And then they steamed it because it needed to be clean.
But then someone walked past and saw it being steamed
and thought that he deliberately asked it to be ironed.
When actually they were just cleaning it
because you would clean it normally.
And then that person walked past,
sold the story to the sun.
And then it became folklore that Kanye West
always asked for his carpets to be ironed.
- So how this happens?
- When in fact, he just wants an all white dressing room
like any normal artist.
(laughing)
- That's brilliant.
- That's so good.
- Is that your celeb ghost that you said you heard?
- That is my spicy celebrity meat.
- I've got a friend who got to go on Jewels Holland.
I think it was last year or the year before.
And he's in a band and so the band was on there.
And it just so happens that Jewels Holland
is also his landlord for the flat that he rents.
So, sorry, that's really funny.
- Yeah.
And Jewels Holland apparently is really hands on
as a landlord because there's a problem.
If there's a problem, he really wants to sort it, right?
He runs over, "Hell, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh."
"Dishonel is your lullaby."
I will now fix the live-on.
So he didn't know that my friend was going to be on the show.
And so they play their song, and Jules does the ending.
He's like, "Oh, goodnight, everyone." He turns around, and he sees my friend,
and he's like, "Hey, it's me." And so you can see at the end,
Jules is talking to him, and what Jules is saying is, "The boiler, I'm going to fix it."
Someone coming in, I booked it in, he's doing house-maintored stuff in the credits.
Okay, what are we going to say, Andy? I think lie.
I think lie. I'm clearly followed.
We're going to say lie.
It was, in fact, true.
In fact, it was true.
Jules Holland was Dan's boiler buddy.
Now, Andy, what have you got for us?
I've got an anonymous poo expert who writes in an anonymous poo expert.
Who asked for their name to be removed?
Just to gently and very kindly, correct James Harkin, who said that, climbing Everest,
he would leave his human waste a couple of hours before collecting them, so they would freeze.
And I, at the moment, I have a dog that I walk every day, and I need to pick up his droppings.
I'm in Canada, where it's been minus 25 Celsius for the fast few days, and let me tell you,
turns freeze a lot faster than hours.
Knowing the top of Mount Everest gets to minus 19 on a hot day, I can safely say that James
would only have to wait a few minutes before being able to pick up his poop sickle.
What was the name of this person, sorry?
Anonymous poo expert.
Anonymous poo expert, I could say, "You don't know my diets."
Two Shay, two Shay.
Cool science fact from Eric Stafford, who was a cardiac medical device representative.
We mentioned Dr. Werner Forstman, who did the first ever heart catheteriser?
Oh, yeah.
Which you mentioned, I think, in that show.
Yeah, and he's basically the first person to put a catheter into his own heart, as a
sort of theory.
It's all very exciting.
Anyway, Eric adds just a fun little bonus fact.
In my world of cardiac electrophysiology, we now use a technique called pulsed field
ablation to treat heart arrhythmias, where the rhythm of your heart is slightly off.
But lots of the pre-human testing was done on potatoes, because this technology is also
used to make potato chips, and apparently there's this technique called electroporation,
which uses high-voltage bursts to use water molecules to rip tiny holes in things normally
potatoes.
Wow.
But they will occasionally do it on the human heart.
That's very cool.
How interesting.
There's a lovely fact there.
This correspondents called Dan James.
We had Jim Dennis earlier.
Yeah, it's Brian Wales Footballer, Welsh Footballer, Dan James.
He says, "Yes, just come off the back half of the line."
What?
Very good.
Yeah, it's the back half line of traditional football saying, because I really know.
I've just been having my orange at the half-time.
Yeah?
Yes.
Podcast@QI.com, and I will be apologising to each and every one of you.
Dan James, right, thanks to you all.
This is how my wife and I are seeing in 2026, and then send an image of the film, "Now you
see me."
Oh.
Lovely.
You've changed the year, but listening to "Now you see me."
Did they say what they thought about it?
Very enjoyable stuff, says Dan.
I mean, Dan James.
It's perfect for "Now you see me" viewer, as we know.
I've got to watch it.
Haven't seen it yet.
No, not yet.
I'm saying I'm waiting for 2027.
We've got an outrage of the week, but it's all in this personal experience thing.
Oh, have you guys thought of a name for the personal experience?
No.
Yeah, it's like a personal experience.
It's not good.
It's not good if a perch is kind of fish.
Yeah, no.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Exactly, right?
Yeah.
Anyway, outrage of the week, Lauren Philpot, my family and I were playing an interactive
version of pointless during our Christmas celebrations.
In real life, like real as in a...
There we go.
That's it.
Real life.
Real life, real life.
Yeah.
Lovely.
Lauren Philpot writes, "My family and I were playing an interactive version of pointless
during our Christmas celebrations.
And I managed to get through to the final part due to my random trivia knowledge, thanks
to your podcast."
Right.
Okay.
The final topic was history and the category was gunpowderplot conspirators.
I guess.
And I couldn't believe my luck.
Yeah.
I, of course, went with friend of the podcast, knowing in my soul that it would be pointless
and win me eternal glory over my family.
Imagine my heartbreak when I was told that I was wrong.
What?
The makers of the game clearly don't listen to your podcast.
So it wasn't even an option?
It wasn't even listed as an option.
I got to say, I mean, it's a tricky question for 99.99% of the...
Anyone, anyone other than Guy Fawkes is going to be a pointless answer, right?
Yeah.
But it just...
Isn't that outrageous?
Who else was there?
That you wouldn't...
No, I'm sorry for the other.
No, no, no, no.
It's not the top guy Fawkes.
And that's sort of...
Who else is there, you know?
Everyone did me.
It feels like it's a joke from the people who made the game, knowing that people only know
one of those things.
Yeah.
They just didn't bank on Lauren being able to get another one.
Didn't even bother to look it up.
Anyway, that's my outrage of the week.
Yeah.
Good.
Let's get on to Osmond.
Yeah.
I mean, he doesn't do any modesty.
Do you reckon it's because of this?
Yeah.
When they made this game, he probably saw that question and thought, "This is an outrage."
That's it for me.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
shocking. Jennifer Sokolov writes, "One of you mentioned that in 1935, a rabbi was
privy to the secret ingredient of Coca-Cola for the purpose of making it kosher. I have a rabbi
friend who works at the orthodox union, which is what they give Coca-Cola the kosher, Coca-Cosher.
Could we say that again? No. Kosher Cola? No, we didn't say either of those. Do you know what?
We did the first time. That's a little inside. We lost that episode and we had to do the whole
thing again. John Lloyd actually made that gag in the first one, but no one made it in the
second one. There we go. Anyway, Jennifer writes, "My friend told me once how Coca-certified
now so they don't have to reveal the secret ingredient to the certifying rabbi, which
I thought you might find interesting. This is so interesting. What they do is they put
a lot of ingredients in a room and the certifying rabbi checks every ingredient to make sure
it is kosher and can be included in the final product. But they put extra ingredients in
the room that aren't actually part of the Coke formula. That's so good. That's really clever.
I would love to taste what that Coca-Cola is if all of those things. Just out of curiosity.
But you can put in some bananas stuff, which is bananas. I'm guessing bananas are kosher.
There was actually, I said on that podcast, I think that we know you can basically work
out the ingredients of Coca-Cola. But actually, I think literally this week there was a YouTube
clip of some YouTuber had done probably the best ever version of Coca-Cola, where they'd
worked it out and this is completely indistinguishable. Amazing. Can you tell the difference in that
and Diet Coke? Well, yeah. Because I don't like to boast, but that's a little skill. That
is a callback and a half, isn't it? That's another of my, would I like to you, fun, crazy
stories about me? Samantha Jo. A lot of two named people we've had
writing in today. So Jim Dennis, Dennis Jim and Dan James. And there have been several
more. Right. Anyway, rights. There was a thing about breach babies. You said about breach
baby being massaged? Yeah. We had someone write in telling us about the massaging that can
happen, yeah, with a breach baby. Yes. That was the same person, though, who claimed
that they'd seen a big, giving another B or all sex. Yeah. Anyway, Samantha Jo hasn't
add on to the breach baby bit, which is that your organs can be moved into place via massage.
Okay. A family member had their gall bladder removed several years ago through laparoscopic
surgery, keyholes, isn't it? This family member also went to see a massage therapist regularly
at the time. On one visit after surgery, the massage therapist could feel that my family
members' organs were not with, they should be because the surgery requires extra room to
be made. So the organs had slipped out of place. Luckily, the therapist was able to massage
their organs back to their proper positions. I mean, this is what the masseur told them,
right? Yep. That's wild. But apparently your organs are not stitched into place. But
so could could arguably a masseuse completely rearrange you? Yeah, of course. I don't think
that's possible. And have you checked this? I feel like most of your organs are generally
speaking held in place. Yeah. That's a good shout. All right. Samantha, we'll need internal
photos. I'm afraid. But I know I don't have Google in front of me. So maybe it's true.
I think it's quite nice thing about this format is we're largely flying completely blind.
You know, we're flying on own. We're off instruments. Yeah. We're only using horizons.
I'm going to change your wife's. Is this absolutely she does. And the one thing that you
should never do is ignore your instruments. Oh, dear. Even if what you're looking at
doesn't look right, always trust your instruments. Okay. Well, let's see if you believe the email
I've had from Tom Brockington, because we're on, you know, just loving your new podcast,
Tom says, it's to be going for 11 years. How long is it taking you to get through these
emails, Addy? Horrible. That person who let themselves be stung all over by bees. Oh, yeah.
Michael Smith. Is that so? Schmidt. Schmidt. There's a couple of them, I think. However, they
missed the area. I got stung by a beyond. Oh, can we guess when was the big giving him
all those little sex at the time? You can have a guess, but I'll be surprised if you get
it, but please. Well, my first thought is this a seat. Is it right up there? Oh, it's
not below the belt. It's not below the belt. As tonsils. Oh, that would be so sore. Yeah,
exactly. Right. That's going to be somewhere not quite accessible. It's on the head. It's
on the head. Okay. Well, after I had a massage, my gallblad is on my head now. Yeah, about 10
years ago, I was walking through the park and a bee stung me on the ear drum. The pain was
absolutely blinding and the ear drum ruptured, so I was also impaired with balance and movement.
I did ask him how did the bee get in there? And he says, I do not know. Wow. The pain was
indescribable. I could hardly even see the pain was everywhere. I ended up having a new
ear drum part grown from taking skin from the side of my head. So I also had five years of
incredible ear infections and pain. Oh, my blessed. I know. But luckily, I'm fine now and
can still scuba dive. Oh, that's good. That's an important thing. However, there is a little
hole left in the drum. So when I equalize the pressure while diving, bubbles come out of
my ear. People who are like, when you do that, like ruptured your ear drum, this is obviously
a datesit, but people used to like, they would smoke pipes and then blow smoke out. Really?
Wow. James, I'm so glad you said that Tom finishes. I have tried to blow smoke out of the
hole, but it has not been observed working. That is a pain. Like the description of that
pain is unlike anything. Yeah, I feel like I've heard before. That's bad. That's bad.
Okay. We'll do a couple more. Yeah. All right. Morris E. Corner. Ah, lovely. Alexander
Andrews writes, I can confirm that not only with the audience frisked for meat, but venue
staff were also searched. Wow. I worked in a college with someone who moonlighted at
a venue he played and they were forewarned that they would be searched. However, I was
also moonlighting as a chef. I happened to be working that weekend at the hotel he was
staying at. We provided a full buffet breakfast, including a whole side of smoked salmon and
me cooking every man out of pork product under the sun. The smell didn't seem to bother
him. Oh, more spicy celebrity meat. The spicy celebrity corn. Yeah, it's really exciting.
Yeah. That's incredible. Yeah. Well, Thomas Patanoster Howe has more stuff. What a middle
name. Oh, it's double-barrelled. Tom Patanoster Howe. Wow. Yeah. Hello, Andy or your minion.
I dream. Tom of having a minion. On the subject of very veggie pop stars, Paul McCartney refuses
to even sit on a leather chair. My sister used to manage a club that he came to and she
had to get him a non-lether chair to sit on. Yeah, he's very. But apparently he wasn't
being prissy about it. He was willing to stand, but he said no, we'll get you a chair.
Okay. Well, I don't think we have a problem with people's beliefs in that respect.
Yeah, exactly. Like Lisa Simpson is a veggie because of him, right? Yeah, absolutely. Yeah.
Like he's done a lot for promotion of that. Completely and I fully respect it. Willow writes.
Okay. This is important. For a long time, fish has been telling the world digital rectal
massage. It's the only scientifically proven method for stopping hiccups. Absolutely. Yeah.
So the other day, when my spouse started hiccupsing, the path seemed clear. I hope it was
a birthday. It was just another day in a typical nerdy lesbian house in Wellington as we prepared
our supplies. Uh-huh. The insertion was textbook and the massage went well, but the hiccups
did not cease. With my spouse still hiccuping, I went straight to the medical journals. It turns
out that often the cases that it works on are considered the intractable hiccups rather
than the pedestrian form that we all get. I was dismayed at the lack of research there
is on this. And then I had my dear, the fish audience are a nerdy lot. And my guess is many
of them are down for some digital rectal massage in the name of science. I'd like to propose
a new segment, fish medical to be kicked off by asking the fans to give DRM a go for hiccups.
No. No. I'm sorry. We will not be held responsible for any medical procedures that we mentioned
on this show that I've then done by our listeners. I think that's really sensible, James. I think
that was really, I had to even consider the legal bit. We look great. We're thinking that
this person's partner didn't cure their hiccups. That's right. But perhaps they just liked
the DRM. True. And then fake some hiccups afterwards and said we're going to have to try
that again. Oh yeah. Yeah. Yes. That's a good point. It's a good way of doing that. Darling,
I feel some hiccups coming on just a new netflix and chill, euphemism. I mean, the hiccups.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Bye. That's it from this episode. What? You normally get a bit further
in than that. That's it for this episode of Drop us a line. Thank you so much for listening,
for watching and for all your fantastic emails. Keep them flooding in. They're brilliant,
podcast@ky.com. But for now, bye. But for now, bye.
Better? Warmer? But for now, bye, bye. It's goodbye from these guys. Bye. When can
you buy from me? Bye everybody. See you next time. Here on Drop us a line. It's always
good to have 16 possible endings.
[Music]