[mechanical beeping]
[phone ringing]
[suspenseful music]
[upbeat music]
- Hi, Andy. - Hello, Andy.
How you guys doing?
- Very good. - Not bad.
- Welcome to "Drop us a Line." - Oh, no, I feel better.
- Yes. - Yes.
Welcome to "Drop us a Line."
Whether you're listening to this,
whether you're watching it... - Whether you're performing it.
- Whether you're performing it. Hello, friends. - Hello.
- Friends! - Colleagues! Colleagues!
- No, it's on tape. It's on video.
This is the worst case for you.
[laughter]
- Thank you for coming today.
- I'm trying to put things back on a professional footing,
but caps out of the bag now.
Thanks, guys.
We've had a lot of great correspondence.
- Yeah. - The inbox has been bulging.
- Beautiful.
- And let's open it up
and have a fiddle around inside
and see what we pull out.
- Okay, okay.
- One of the weirder interests I've ever done.
- You can see the point where you should have stopped.
- Always. - And then...
- You just keep going.
- Well, it's because I assumed
that one of my fellow trapezoartists will catch me.
- Nope. [laughter]
- We're busy loosening the net underneath.
- I'm just swinging back and forth
and talking rubbish for ages.
- Okay. Well, let's start with some corrections.
'Cause we've got a few to get through.
- Actually, let's not.
Let's have some whimsy.
- It's the new year.
- Absolutely.
- When it goes out.
- Let's start. Like it's a fresh, exciting start.
- Yeah.
- Let's have some whimsy.
Okay. Well, Matt Bush sends a brilliant fact about Scurvy,
which I'm afraid of.
- Oh, thank God.
We're on those whimsical subjects straight away.
How many millions of people died of Scurvy?
And we've mentioned this before, so I'm sorry.
It's not any use to us.
But Matt also sends this, which is why I read out his email.
And a side says Matt,
"I officially began listening in the mid-200 episodes."
- Okay.
- "And for the longest time, I thought Andy was Japanese."
[laughter]
- Okay. That is interesting.
And does he give any reason to his supposition?
- Yes. Can you guess why?
- One of the time I think I was Japanese.
- Well, you had been to Japan around that time.
- Been to Japan.
- And because I remember there was a time when you sat down
near one of the stations and counted how many people
were wearing face masks.
- Yes, that's right.
- You talked about working on a writing project out there,
which would sort of suggest that maybe you could write
Japanese as well.
- I can't, but that didn't matter,
because the sitcom was in Norwegian.
- Yes.
- Which I also cannot speak.
- Right, okay.
- I wrote it in English,
then the Norwegian cast translated it every night
and then we filmed it in Central Tokyo.
- So it's not those?
- It could have been your burgeoning J-pop career.
- Oh, these are all, but none of these are right.
- None of these are.
- It's Dan's fault.
- Oh.
- Matt says, "You see, Dan's accent made the pronunciation
"andrew" hand to "murei."
- Which, and those are the characters there.
- Okay, what does that mean in Japanese?
- I don't know what it means,
but they're all, I guess, Japanese sort of syllables.
- Oh, okay.
- And I was even more confused when I finally
sort of pictured the group,
and he was nowhere to be found.
(laughing)
- How was he saying, "I pronounced your name?"
- "Hand to "murei."
- Which I don't think.
I think we'd have picked you up on that.
- I think more than Chazinsky,
that would have got people writing it.
- Anyway.
- So if you have a fun theory
that's been disproved about us,
please do get in touch.
podcast@ky.com.
- Yeah.
- Yeah. - We're off the blocks.
- Wow.
- Catherine Birch says,
"In episode five of Little Fish,
"you were wondering how many people on Earth
"haven't had the chance to write an escalator.
"There are only two escalators in Wyoming,
"or four, depending on how you count escalators."
- Interesting.
- Yeah, as in there's two that go up and down.
- Two up, two down.
- Yeah. - Yeah, yeah.
- And they're both in banks in the city of Casper.
- Yeah, that is true,
and I have long tried to prove that false,
I think there's probably an escalator somewhere
that someone hasn't thought of.
And I've looked like at all the airpods.
There's not many airpods.
There's a few airpods there.
None of them.
They're all one layer.
All the different moles that I could think of in Wyoming
to see if there was another one.
And I've never been able to find another one.
- Interesting.
Well, Catherine says there hasn't been a new one built since 1979.
- Yeah, and I think all sorts of the ones in the banks
are not for the public.
I think there might be for people working there.
I think.
I might wrong about that.
- So she says there's probably a significant section of the Wyoming population
who have never seen an escalator assuming, of course,
that they don't enjoy banks or traveling out of the state.
- Also, the population of Wyoming is extremely low.
- Is it? Yeah.
- Right.
- They will have watched movies.
- Yeah, but that's not true.
- I don't think they've seen one in the flesh.
- I know, but they probably don't think of it
as some sort of futuristic invention that we don't have.
They know how it functions.
- Yeah, but if you haven't seen one out close,
you've no idea of the majesty.
- I was in Harris the other day and I went on that first ever.
Well, I think because it's really a small one that you think
why an earth is an escalator here.
- Yeah.
- So it goes from a mezzanine to an actual floor.
- Yeah, so exactly.
- So I think it must have been the first one that was put in there
where they give everyone some brandy when they came off.
- Amazing.
- I've always thought of that as a two-floor stretch.
- That might be wrong because I didn't Google it or anything,
but it just happened to be there because I was in town.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, I do.
- Are you going to get your milk in Harris, don't you?
- I get the cat's water in Harris.
- Have you seen inside of an escalator when they have to open
and up if you're ever on the tubes?
It's quite exciting, right?
- Yeah.
- And if you've been on the London.
- I've seen that.
- Oh, okay.
So I've seen it a few times on the London Underground
because they're always fixing some of them.
- Yes, because he says.
- Yeah, it should be just down there.
It's a book of crouching marks on the same.
- It is signed, so.
- Second edition.
- It's definitely second or third edition, so I don't want to.
- I shouldn't have put it in there, but I wanted to see what would happen.
But I've seen it a few times.
One thing I hadn't seen until about a week ago was the inside
of where the bowling balls come out when you're waiting.
- Oh, that whole contraption where it comes out?
- Did you fail to let go of the ball?
And so you just got through, flew along.
- And you ended up in the thing?
- You did a whole circuit and came back out.
- Yeah, yeah.
- No, I was at a children's party.
- They come off, don't they?
It's like got a little cover that lifts up.
- Exactly.
- Can I go enough memory?
Because all the bowling alleys that I go to,
they still have pinboys there, so.
- In Wyoming, they only have pinboys.
I don't know enough of that Wyoming.
I've realised.
- No, me neither.
- Fascinating.
- I've been.
- It's where the old faithful geezer is and stuff.
Yellow stones in Wyoming.
- I think.
Hope I'm not wrong now.
But it's like extremely empty.
The whole place is just like, there's hardly anyone there.
- Wow.
- It's such an iconic American.
- Smells of thoughts.
- Does it?
- But who's, if there's nobody there, who's doing the thoughts?
- All right, Confucius.
- Right, we better.
- Let's get on, let's get on.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Oh boy.
We've had some corrections about the age of James Bond.
- Oh, trust me.
- All right, my light Arctic quiz.
- Yes.
- Who was the oldest Bond?
- And who was it in the end, Roger Moore?
- For Paul?
- Yeah.
- I followed by Daniel Craig.
- Exactly.
- Yes.
- Ding ding ding, everyone gets it right.
And then I recorded it.
I recorded before that little fish, a separate thing saying,
look, I know Sean Connery was in a later one when he was old.
But that wasn't an official one.
- Yeah.
- Well.
- Thank you to all the Bond nerds who dropped us a line.
- Yep.
- I got a couple of things wrong.
There is a 1967 version of Cassina Royale,
which is a spoof where David never--
- David, never.
- Place James Bond at the age of 57.
- Absolutely.
- Andy McElfresh wrote that in.
Thank you, Andy.
Charlie Tuff makes that point.
But also says that the second oldest official James Bond actor
at time of retirement from the role is in fact Toby Stevens, of course.
- Okay.
- James Bond's was 55 when he stepped down from doing the audiobooks.
- Oh, come on.
- No, you know, it's official.
And he's also the only person I think who's played both James Bond
and a James Bond villain, again, in one of the audiobooks.
- Okay.
- So there you go.
Bit of Bond trivia.
- Yeah.
- That play.
- I think we put the constraints on it being the movie franchise
when we did it.
And Cassina Royale was not a part of the official broccoli movie franchise
until Daniel Craig came along.
Never say never again was not part of that.
- Yep.
- That's all we were doing.
We were just trying to live our lives.
- We were just, you know, two escalators or four escalators.
Who knows, you know?
It's that same problem.
- I don't understand any of this.
I only said that you'll Craig because he's the only one I heard of.
- Oh, we did have someone write to him about George Lazenby.
- Oh, yeah.
- Amy Cox.
- Oh, so in this episode, Andy alluded to an anecdote about George Lazenby,
which we never broadcast.
In fact, you never even said because we were worried that he's still alive.
- He's a light sewers.
- Yeah.
But my old painter and decorator thinks he was not a great guy.
- Really?
Oh, my gosh.
- Well, you'll liberator.
- Look, that really is a club fish park, everyone.
That is what you get behind that paywall.
- Absolutely stone-cold celebrity gas.
- I'm really sorry.
- That's the worst edit.
I was saving that one for Graham Norse and I'm so annoyed.
- Amy Cox writes,
"Talking of Bond, James Bond's, and particularly when Lazenby was mentioned,
we will remind it of our own spicy meat Lazenby story."
- Oh.
- We attended an event here in Perth, Western Australia.
Brilliant, hello Perth.
"Of the night of Bond music performed live, interspersed with a Q&A with Lazenby."
The link below, I think, says it all.
And I'll just say, we really enjoyed the portion of the event
with the singers and the musicians performing Bond's songs live.
They at least were fantastic.
- Oh, no.
- Anyway, she's appended a link.
I'll just read you the key words from the link,
because I clicked it, I have read it.
But former James Bond star, George Lazenby,
asked from National Music Tour after homophobic comments.
- Oh, no.
- It's not clear.
It's not clear what exactly Bond said, but I believe an apology was later offered.
- Right.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- There you go.
- Matthias Panzenbach.
- I do start to wonder, and it's obviously this will be Matthias' name
and do apologize for that.
But there will be a stage where people will deliberately put wacky names
in so that they get read out.
- Have you been checking in with David Bergaman recently,
who has also written this week?
- Yeah.
- Is that a bad Zoe hamburger?
- It's not.
- Oh.
- Matthias Panzenbach, I think that's a fair point, James.
- Yeah.
- I'm doing that's a fair point.
- I think Panzenbach is a proper name, but--
- Absolutely.
- Just not from round the ear.
- But Matthias writes.
- All right, George Lazenby.
- Oh my gosh.
- Matthias writes, "Because you had a fact about the Mall of America
being heated with body heat."
- Oh, yeah.
- It was something about newly built houses in medieval times
being dried out by letting poor people live in them.
Of course, once dried, they had to leave.
I can't find info about it now.
My Google food is not good about that.
I'm also not sure if I saw it in English or German.
- That's a great fact.
- That's a great truth.
- Yeah, I know.
I mean, it's 'cause I guess you'd have sort of wet plaster
on the walls and--
- Yeah.
- And you want to like put the heating on,
like the cooker I mean.
- Yeah.
- And it would make sense that you wouldn't want your
pusho to do that themselves.
- Yeah.
- Is it true that the queen used to have people who would try
out her shoes before she wore them, like break them in?
- I can't believe it.
- I do know something about the queen,
which is something you guys, as fans of now,
you see me will enjoy.
- Queen Elizabeth II.
- Yeah.
- If you did a contract for her as a magician,
she would get a lady in waiting to actually take the card.
- Really?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Why would the queen, why can't she hold the card?
- Busy.
(laughing)
- Rating of us.
- Yeah, I'm fair enough.
- Doing important constitutional work.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Probably.
- Also, those Lizzy hands cut.
(laughing)
- Really good grip of the cut.
- She just sticks her tongue out.
(laughing)
- Sorry.
- Outrageous.
- I know.
- Who's not too soon?
- No, it's fine.
- I think we're able to say that, Lizzy.
- I don't think so.
No, I was gonna mention that.
Remember, there was a story, and I don't know if it was ever debunked,
but in history, in ancient Egypt,
it used to be the idea that the Pharaoh would have someone beside them
if they were in an area that had lots of flies who was just soaked in honey
so that the flies would come towards them and never touch the leader.
- I think that was, it was someone like Pliny writing about it.
I think who said that that happened.
But yeah, it's definitely attested that it happened,
whether it did or not.
- That was amazing.
- Yeah.
- All right.
- Time for a bit of extreme fish.
- Ah, is this where someone listens from an odd place?
- Yeah.
- Okay, cool.
This is really, this is actually someone doing something that could be life-threatening.
- To themselves or to someone else?
- To themselves.
- It's a killer.
I love killing while listening to fish.
It really gets me through those difficult kills.
- Oh my god.
- This is so cool.
- It's Caleb Cole writing it.
I've been listening to the podcast for many years.
You've mentioned several times that people often listen to it to fall asleep.
I do that.
As well, however, as I live in Montana, I'll also regularly listen to it
while I'm on solo hikes to ward off bears.
- Oh my gosh.
- As they don't like the sound of your podcast.
They hate it.
- What?
- No, I'm making it up.
They like off-menu, which they find funny and sometimes talks about salmon.
No, he doesn't say that. Caleb says they don't like the sound of people talking bears. Yeah, I've heard that. So either you have to constantly Yammer away, but if you're on a solo hike, you either have to talk to yourself for hours now, or you just play a book. So there's a boom box along with him playing the sound. Yes, you're right. It wouldn't work. It was just.
Why did they eat me?
Wow, that's amazing. That's incredible. I know. And Caleb adds I mostly use it in place of bear bells, which I didn't know were a thing in high-bear density low foot traffic areas.
I like the multiple people talking excitedly. I on fish as bears are especially wary of groups of people. I'm very close to Wyoming as well.
Montana. I believe they're the neighbors to each other. I went to them both in the same trip. Right.
And in Montana, I saw the biggest American flag I've ever seen in my entire life. Wow. It was like it was in a hotel, but it's a very tall hotel, lots of escalators. But you know, sometimes in a hotel, like the lobby will go all the way up to the ceiling.
It was a high trim. And they had a flag that went all the way from the top all the way down to the bottom. It was insane. It was like six stories high.
If you did that in the UK, people would think you're having a breakdown. Yes. It's just a completely different flag attitude that we and they have.
Thank God you didn't go hiking on your own in Montana, because the bears probably really hate us. And they're like, finally, one of them's on their own. Let's get them.
Yeah. Yeah. That would have been bad. Yeah. But they wouldn't have known that it was James's voice. Why not?
Because you, unless you were talking to yourself, which I regularly do on my walks, do you?
You would have survived because I'd got up to you and gone, no, he's not Japanese.
Keep looking.
So thanks Caleb and stay safe out there. Yeah. Avoid those bears. He adds, I, of course, always carry bear spray as well.
Not hairspray, but bear spray. Pleasing. Very nice. That is just to double down on that. So cool to hear that we're being played out in the mountains of Montana.
We're playing bears. That's really cool. We listen to the depths of the ocean. We haven't had space yet. But someone must have listened to us on a plane once.
We have. Yeah. We were sat next to someone who was listening to us on a plane once.
Do you remember? No. When we flew from, probably from Perth, actually, to somewhere else in Australia, we were chatting. And there was someone sat next to us who was listening to the show on the headphones.
We were still talking. That must have absolutely broken their mind irretrievably. Do they just have a complete meltdown there and then.
Because you think you were going mad, wouldn't you? I think they worked out quite quickly what was happening when they turned around and thought, well, half of those six efficient and non-Japanese.
Oh, dear. Well, I was in Tokyo, actually, on the trains. You know, they've got the amazing trains.
I sat next to someone who was watching QI really on his phone. And it was a question I had written or was a script I had written. I was really excited. And I think I told you this before.
And I tapped him on the shoulder and I said, that's me. I wrote that. I did that. I got off the next stop. It just wasn't interested at all. Okay.
Wow, that's pretty cool. Jam Rainbird, regular correspondent, says in today's dropper's line, not today's one we're doing now, the previous one or two.
You discussed the phenomenon whereby, pedantically correcting someone else's fact puts you most at risk of yourself being corrected.
Down then went on to wonder if this was a variant of Murphy's law and James claimed this new law is his own Harkens law. Yeah. Interestingly, I saw this law mentioned on a TV show recently. They called it Muffery's law, not to be confused with Murphy's law and stated it in the context of spelling, grammar, etc.
If you correct someone else's, your correction will always contain an error itself. Anyway, you guys should give the show a watch. I think it'd be really up your street. It's called QI.
If you want to serve, I wrote that. I wrote that. Okay. We need to go. That is episode 12. Oh, wow. Thanks. Jam. You know what? This is an example of Stigler's law of eponomeny or whatever it's called, which is that the law is always named after someone who didn't invent it. Yeah. So that's an example of that. If we call it Harkens law, then we're sticking to Stigler's law. Right. Yelka Ludolfi. I think I've got your first name, right? Yelka.
Probably with a J. Anyway, Yelka writes with your latest episode. I've been noticing a bit of a pattern. The podcast has really been on a spree of episodes with celebrity names in the title. Oh, apparently so. Well, you do the names, James. Can you think of any we've had?
I've got this gracious Bible six. Yeah, really. I can't even think of a single one within the last few weeks. You've had Dwayne Johnson. Oh, yeah, Johnson's hair. Yeah, Gordon Ramsey. Oh, yeah, cookbook. Oh, yeah, some book Lily Allen. Oh, she's a proper friend of the podcast though.
I don't want Bessie. Training the definition of celebrity. I could have gone runny pickering for that. Yeah. And Chanel. Well, that's not a celebrity. What? With honorary mentioned to the teletubbies.
Okay. Yeah. No, I see that. I wonder why I can. Well, Yelka has a theory. Okay. I can only imagine this is part of a strategy to trick the algorithm into hitching your popularity to theirs. Or is there's a way to ingratiate yourself with the Hollywood.
And Yorkshire putting elites for when fish eventually makes the lead to movies and the Andy's dreams cinematic universe. Yeah, I can say. I mean, there is an argument that if we called every single episode, you know, no such thing as Taylor Swift and Sabrina Carpenter's picnic. Yeah, then we probably would go up in the algorithms. Yeah. All right. Time for fish love corner. This is new. Yeah. Very nice.
Peter Teplitsky writes, hello, I have a fun fact for you. During COVID, I send a fact I heard on fish to a girl on a dating app. Yeah. That girl is now my fiance. Wow. Yes. And we guess what the fact is. He can't remember. Oh, it must have been about that woman who faked a prolapse.
It was probably the pro-laptop spectrum. Probably that's always got me laid that fact. No, I asked Peter and he can't remember exactly what the fact was. And I think he's claimed he claimed he can't find it in the app records anymore because probably he's not even on the app anymore.
I should congratulate you.
Oh, yeah, that's really nice. I remember there was a survey saying that QI was one of the best things you could pretend to watch that people find you more attractive.
It's like a cultural aphrodisiac. Yeah, like it makes you seem smart, but not that smart. Yeah, you watch comedy panel shows, but you watch a sort of more intellectual.
Whereas if you say I listened to round Britain quiz, someone's going to think you're insufferable. Yes. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, it's a good good quiz that that was it. Is it? I've never I'm too hard for me. I don't understand it. Yeah. Like in our time already. It's not for people like you. No.
I'm happy watching a just a stream of colors and shapes appear on the screen.
I sometimes find the magic roundabout a bit much plot-wise. Have you ever seen boo snoo? No, boo snoo is amazing. It's a little red ball.
Yeah. It's a seven minute show of a little red ball just rolling and some little things happen in the background. There might be some, you know, weighing scales and it goes on one side and then it weighs up and then it rolls off again or it might go on a seesaw or something.
But it's literally that's just the whole thing. I love it. It sounds like the advert for cats that we covered a long time ago. Yeah. But it's real like toddlers love it. And also I think it's for people with sensory issues.
Because it really is a lot of like textures and stuff. It's like catnet for kids. Fantastic. But I love watching it because half of it is CGI and half of it's real and trying to work out which bits of real and which bits of CGI.
Try to be right. I'll check it out. Anyway, it's the new like if you're a student and you're off your face. Yeah. Then it's probably the best thing you can watch right now.
If I got boost new for you. But that's really cool. Congratulations Peter. We scare off bears and we find you love. Find you love. Yeah. Yeah. Just brilliant. Matt Underwood writes just listening to little fish.
Read the list of funnily named things which James read out. I have another for you here in Cornwall. There is an animal park called the screech owl sanctuary.
Perhaps reasonably you would assume this would be a sanctuary for screech owls, but no. It's named for its founder Caroline screech. That's really good. That's very really good. Very funny. Let's have a couple more. Yeah.
I'd rather like this. We were having a chat recently about the origins of spicy meat. Right. Because James you I think in particular. I don't understand any of it fear and dislike all of this my cool categories for our stuff.
I indulge you, but it's through gritted teeth. Yeah. I'm talking about things like the buffins. Yeah. All the fish love from this week. Yeah. That was new. That won't be coming back. No. Well, actually if you're in a relationship. Thanks to no such things official. Always tell us. Please. Yeah. Especially if there's a good story behind it.
And even if that story is I send a girl a fact and I can't now remember what the fact was, but we're engaged. I think that clears that for me that clears the bar very ably. Yeah. Agreed. Yeah.
That couple you got married and had minutes of coal at their wedding. It's good stuff. Anyway, James. Yeah. I've got news for you because air and hung has found that someone around this table was the first to use the phrase spicy meat on no such thing as a fish's drop us a line section.
Oh, okay. What's obviously Harkin? It was James. Does it? I doesn't sound like me. Andy. Anyway, let's get on to the meat of Pete's message. James. Pete's meat. And that sounds like me. Andy, Pete's meat. Here we go. Then we keep going for a bit. And we thank Pete. Dan says and your meat.
It doesn't hold up quite so well when you read it out like this. I was sure that was very funny when we said it. But as it is, it sounds like three middle age men with no sense of humor.
This is the court stenographer's version. Yeah. What we do. Andy, okay. I quite like the procedural stuff. There's another procedural question. Oh, yeah. But this is a spicy one. James. Spicy meat. There you go.
Okay. Well, me a culper, I guess. Absolutely. You later tried to row back and suggested get to the meat. Then Dan, you suggested meat cute. Both of which I love. But no spicy meat was born that way. So thank you Aaron for keeping us honest. Yeah. That was about two years ago. And the two years have flown by. There've been two years of very happy spicy meat for me. Very nice.
Meat cute works for anyone who has fallen in love. It does. So we could bring that in. Have you ever split up with someone over no such thing as a fish?
You know, that would be good. That'd be great. I thought you had a meat pun connected to that. Nope. No.
Bye. Is that it? That's it. Well, okay. On that spicy bombshell. It's time to say thank you and goodbye. Thank you to all of you for listening or for watching. Thank you.
All performing. Thank you to everyone who's contributed in any way to all of this. If you'd like to send us an email about anything we've said. We love reading them. We love reading them out. The email addresses podcast at qi.com.
But there we go. Down and James. It's goodbye. Say bye. Goodbye. Bye. And we'll be back again in the fortnight with another one of these. And it'll be a bit better run next time. I think we can agree that. Don't make promises you can't keep up.
You always look at us when you do these out troves with fear such fear in your eyes. Have you ever seen a dog driving a tractor? I don't know what I'm doing. I don't know what I'm doing.
Someone's going to get hurt real bad because I'm here and in charge. Stop me for my own sake. Stop, Andy. Bye.
[Music]