(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
Anna Tyshinski and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that when Socrates lost feeling
in his penis, he asked his friend to sacrifice a cock.
- Wow.
- When you say sacrifice is cock, does that mean
he swaps it over for Socrates as well?
- Like a battery swap, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Have you rubbed it?
- Yeah, have you put it in the right way around?
- It's like a literal auger donor.
- This is very immature wording of a very serious story
about someone who had to commit suicide.
So it's 399 BC.
- Wow, I didn't actually read the story.
- He was executed by himself.
- Yeah, I think that is a difference.
- It is so bizarre, the, yeah,
I don't know if we do this anymore in any countries
that the state sentenced him to suicide,
which I don't know if you can call it suicide
when the state, but they gave him the hemlock and he took it.
Anyway, and the effect of it,
because he was so hardcore, Socrates,
and he was so, had his shit together,
hemlock usually had quite violent effects on people,
but according to the people around him,
with him, it just made him go numb gradually
from the feet up, it crept up his legs,
and as it reached his groin,
the numbness of the hemlock as he was killing himself,
according to Plato, he spoke his last words,
which were, we owe a rooster to a sclipius,
we owe a cock to a sclipius,
don't forget to pay that debt.
And then he died.
- And a sclipius was a god,
this is not a person he had borrowed a cockerel from.
- Yes, sorry.
- And we should say we're in fourth century Athens.
That's the other thing we should say.
- BC.
- In context, BC, sorry, fourth century BC Athens,
a sclipius was the god of healing.
- Yeah, and the idea is that whenever you were sick
and you got better, you sacrificed a cockerel to a sclipius,
but he saw his death as a recovery from life almost,
like he wasn't scared of death was the point.
- It's been cured of the sickness of living.
- It's very cryptic.
Like, and also you can't ask him,
what did you mean by that exactly?
Because he's just, he's literally just died.
So there are a few theories of,
or maybe he's making fun of the Pythagoreans
because they saw cockerels as being sacred,
or maybe he was alluding to something else.
But it seems likely that exactly he was saying,
actually, life is the illness.
- Yes, nice.
- Real chin stroker.
- Well, he was a funny man, wasn't he?
- He was a funny guy, yeah.
- There's a big theory that he didn't die of hemlock really.
I mean, he had died of hemlock,
but it wasn't the hemlock that made him go numb
because hemlock doesn't make you go numb.
- No, but as I said, he's a very special man.
- I think the-
- But then there are other theories.
- The suggestion is that he had a lot of opium
mixed in with it to kind of take the edge off a little bit.
- Okay.
- Because there was a guy in the 18th century
described the effects of hemlock.
And there was a guy called Fergus Cadd,
and he was living in the village of Talisca,
and he mistakenly ate some hemlock roots
thinking it was carrots.
And he said, his eyes did roll about,
his countenance became very pale,
his sight had almost failed him,
the frame of his body was all in a strange convulsion,
and his pudenda retired so inwardly
that there was no discerning
whether he had been male or female.
- Okay, out.
- But it was quite funny,
it would make you convulse and stuff.
- Was he all right in the end?
- This guy actually got better.
They basically, they gave him loads of stuff
to make him vomit and make him shit himself
until it all got out of his system,
and he just about survived.
- What about his pudenda?
(all laughing)
Did they reinflate?
- Not recounted.
(all laughing)
Don't get the wrong, the important stuff.
- That's interesting about the opium
because that kind of suggested
it's like the equivalent of a last meal
when you're on death row.
It's like, you're gonna be drinking this,
what would you like as your mixer?
- Yeah.
- What do you want in there to make it go down nicely
at the end?
- Can I have a hemlock and opium?
Oh, we've already got Pepsi, is that okay?
(all laughing)
- Opium Max, unfortunately.
- Well, we should say what he was sentenced to death for.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- So.
- Corrupting the youth.
- Corrupting the youth and also impiety.
And he'd been teaching young people critical thinking,
which he was frowned on,
and he'd also probably not been taking religion
completely seriously,
and Athens was a very religious society.
And also, the other sort of context is like,
Athens had had this really rough time.
It was sort of, it was in the golden age of democracy,
but they'd just been really walloped in a war
by the Persians, and it was a very rough time.
And there's a theory that people were willing
to put up with Socrates,
who famously asked provocative questions,
didn't accept the established version of things,
like he was a provocateur, he was a thinker.
And there was a theory that when it was going fine
for Athens, people were willing to put up with that.
And then when Athens was really doing badly,
people said, "This is subversive now.
"So you're gonna have to knock it off."
- Interesting.
- He was tried for that, you know?
He was tried by a jury, and it was a massive jury.
It's not like you're a classic 12 angry people.
It is 501 jury members.
- The Levi's jury.
(all laughing)
- Absolutely.
And it was, the one extra is so that you don't get a tie
when it comes to the fighting.
- It'd be bad luck to get 250 all, wouldn't it?
(all laughing)
- Exactly.
He ended up with a close margin, 280 voted,
that he was guilty versus 221.
- It's not that close.
- Well, I guess it's--
- It's thump it in a modern democracy,
that's a resounding mandate.
- Okay, well he got thumped.
Well, what's even crazier is that he lost it, 280 to 221.
That was just to find him guilty.
Then there was another vote to see
what the sentence should be.
He said, "Well, I think you should give me
"free lunch for life."
Like he was a joker, right?
That pissed off the members of the jury,
including jury members who said that he was innocent.
And even they voted for the death sentence,
because I was so pissed off by that joke that he made.
- Yeah.
- I think it's a weird thing to ask the newly guilty party,
what do you think your punishment should be?
It's a bit like asking a toddler, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- But maybe that was a little bit like twist,
playing your own game, Mr. Socrates.
You're the one always asking us bloody questions,
rather than giving us answers.
Well, we'll ask you a question.
- Did anyone vote for the free lunches for life?
(all laughing)
- To be fair, he did get free lunches for life, probably.
- Oh, yeah.
- I mean, I don't imagine he had to pay
for the hemlock and opium.
- Maybe it was his clever way of saying,
I think I should be put to death in a couple of days,
but that I should get the food in the prison in that time.
Like, there was his clever way of saying,
yes, put me to death.
- Yeah, it's gotta be a clever way of saying something,
'cause that was what he did, wasn't it?
- Well, actually, like, you know what?
He was sentenced to death,
but then his mates bribed the prison guards and said,
we'll get you out of here.
And he said, now you're all right.
- Yeah.
- I'll just take my punishment.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- And his idea was that the law of Athens
didn't protect him all the way through his life.
And so it would be inconsistent to say,
well, now I think that because the laws are against me,
I shouldn't follow them anymore.
- Bit ungrateful.
- That is good.
And he was 70 as well.
So going on the Lamb would probably,
I mean, just surviving in ancient Greece,
outside Athens was probably hard.
- Yeah, he must have been in terrible shape.
Ancient Greece aged 70, 71.
- Tom Cruise is 63.
So let's put this in context.
Socrates was only a few years older than Tom Cruise is now.
So Socrates's method was really good.
You know, you'd say,
so what do you,
you just get somewhere into a conversation.
So what do you think about this matter or another?
And they'd say their opinion.
And then he would slowly unravel them.
- Oh yeah.
- And anytime they said something,
he said, well, hang on,
you said just a moment ago that this other thing was true.
So how can those both be true?
And you would end up with both of you
in a state of aporia,
where neither of you can further define the idea
that is under discussion.
And there are lots of anecdotes written about Socrates
getting into conversation with people who end up just saying
to him, sorry, I have to go.
I don't, I don't, I have nothing, I have nothing more to say.
- I want my way to work.
- He's basically like a charity mugger outside the station.
So just one minute.
- What do you think of free speech?
- Did he get punched too much?
Was he, was he ever?
- I can imagine you're in the groceries
and you're behind Socrates
and he's questioning the seller, you know.
- Would you punch someone for that?
Maybe try to engage Dan.
- You should see him in the 10 items
off your line.
- What is an item?
That's a bunch of grapes.
Is that one item?
Is that 12 items?
- He did used to cost people in the gym quite a lot
when they were exercising,
which maybe isn't a good idea
if you want to avoid being punched.
- If he was in the gym causing ruckus and starting fights,
I actually think he would have held up on his own
because we do picture Socrates
as this older philosopher walking around barefooted.
- You know how I picture him?
Exactly how he is in Bill and Ted's excellent adventure.
- Yes.
- And I also pronounce him Socrates
because of the time.
- Socrates, yeah, exactly.
We picture him as this philosopher,
but actually he was a decorated military hero.
He went all the way up to 48.
He was still going to battles.
He was still in front line.
And I just didn't know that about him at all.
I've just had this old man philosopher in my head.
- But it does raise some questions
because so the three main people in his life
he wrote about him were Aristophanes, Xenophon and Plato.
So a huge amount from Xenophon.
And I hadn't realized he saved Xenophon
in the middle of battle.
So in the Peloponnesian Wars Xenophon was dying.
It's a little bit like the two little boys story.
Xenophon's lying there dying.
He trots up says, "Do you think I'd leave you dying?"
Tosses Xenophon over his shoulder
and carries him out of battle with one hand
while fighting people with the other.
- I thought they both had a wooden horse or something.
- Yeah, that's the Trojan War you're thinking of.
(laughing)
- No way, did you just make that joke?
That's incredible.
What is the two little boys' story?
- Yes, they start off with a wooden horse
but you've obviously never made it to verse two
where they go into real battle.
- Yet they grow up, do they grow apart
and then they come back together
and one of them saves the other's life.
- Yeah, it does ring a bell now.
- It's a tear-jerker.
Anyway, then Xenophon wrote loads of really
obsequious shit about him for the next 50 years
but of course he did, he saved his life.
- And we also got a lot from Plato
'cause these are all his students, right?
And Plato writes all the really smart things
that Socrates thought.
But actually, it kind of starts off like that
but then towards the end, it's just whatever Plato thinks.
And he's like, oh, yeah.
Yeah, Socrates thought that Tremera the best team
in League Two this season.
Yeah.
So he's just like, you never know where Socrates ends
and where Plato starts.
- Is it right that there's no written stuff by Socrates?
There's no record of any of that.
- He hated writing.
- He was against it.
- He thought it would ruin people's memories.
- So it has proved.
- And the well done hit, called it.
- In fact, that's the reason that a lot of historians
apparently really love the Bill and Ted movie
because in it, you can't understand what he's saying
and that is very on point with the fact
that we don't know anything that he actually said.
- Right.
- So it's a perfect representation of Socrates.
- Okay.
- I haven't seen it, but I am gonna counter the claim
that it's a perfect representation of Socrates,
nonetheless.
- Yeah.
- Is that fair?
- No, not fair.
- Okay, sorry.
- Most triumphant movie.
- Was there a Mrs. Socrates?
- Yes, there was.
- Yes.
- She was called Zanthipe, saying it right.
- Very useful for us at the moment
'cause we're researching the X series of QI.
- Right.
- As is Xenophon, actually.
- Yes.
- So they had three boys and they lived in near poverty
while Socrates went around the city
asking people weird questions.
Does this remind you of anyone?
(laughing)
- Dad Shriver.
- Three boys.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, near poverty.
(laughing)
- You're always just going around
asking people weird questions while Fenn is saying,
we need to sort out this or that.
- Yes.
- If Dad's the great philosopher of our time,
we are really.
(laughing)
- Just another Zanthipe thing.
This is a mystery that I got too deeply into,
so I'm gonna drag you down.
Zanthipe was the original Shrew.
She's known throughout medieval history.
She's the Shrewish wife.
She's mentioned in the Taming of the Shrew as the archetype.
And then a Shrew was discovered in the late 19th century
and it was named Zanthipe's Shrew
by the person who discovered it.
Obviously after Zanthipe.
But get this, its other name is the yellow-footed Shrew.
Now, as I'm sure you all know,
Zanthos in Greek is yellow, golden yellow,
and Podes, Pe, Pe, is like feet.
So Zanthipe sort of means yellow-footed
and it's got yellow feet,
but it's named after Zanthipe the woman.
What's going on?
- That's amazing.
I got lost halfway through.
- Has anyone followed?
- So they named it after Zanthipe,
the woman yellow-footed.
- No, 'cause she's a Shrewish woman.
- But if you twist the words a bit,
it sounds like it's got yellow feet in Greek.
- Exactly. - That's crazy.
That's really good.
- Thank you, Andy.
- Are you the first person to make that link?
- I think I might be.
- Wow.
- Yeah, this is going to blow some stuff open.
- Yeah, let's get in touch with our PR.
Let's get that out there.
(laughing)
- We don't have a PR.
- Danny Express though, if you're listening.
- I have a favorite Socrates sort of thing that he did.
It's the Socrates freeze.
Did you read about this?
It's written about, so Plato writes about it
in the Symposium.
Basically, he used to get stuck with ideas in his head
that he really needed to think about.
And when he did, he just stopped or moved himself
to a convenient out of the way spot
and just remained there completely still
no matter what he was on his way to.
So in this, he was on his way to a dinner party
and he suddenly had an idea.
He just stands on the porch and just stays silent.
And that's how he lived his life.
When I walk into a room and can't remember why I went in,
I do the exact same thing.
- You just stop.
- Just stand there and look around and go,
what was it I came in here for?
- Right, maybe you are the great philosopher of our time.
- I think we all know that's true.
- I think that's probably true.
- But you're saying Socrates is standing on that porch
going, who the fuck's house is this?
- Yeah, that's what I reckon.
My favorite Socrates is the--
- I know who it's gonna be.
- My favorite Socrates, who is it, Anna?
Do you think?
- It's gonna be the other famous Socrates in history,
the football player.
- The footballer.
- Oh, nice.
- From Brazil in the '80s.
He was known as the smartest player
in the Brazilian football team.
- Question, was he known as Socrates
before people thought he was smart?
Or was he called Socrates and then people thought he was--
- He was known as Socrates from a very young age.
People in Brazil, they'll often get a nickname.
- But I think actually his dad was a self-taught,
very poor but self-taught guy,
and he named him Socrates after the philosopher,
'cause I think his brothers were called Sophocles
and some other very lesser Greek person.
- Yeah, so his dad was a philosopher,
like he studied philosophy, and he had lots of books.
And basically he was quite sad actually,
'cause there was a coup d'etat in Brazil,
and when the army came in,
they forced everyone to burn all their books.
And Socrates as a child, the footballer,
he watched his dad burning all the books in his library
and imagine how painful that was for him,
because that was what he loved, he loved his books.
- And did that then turn it onto football?
He said, "Well, if I can't read 'cause of this coup,
"I'm gonna become a footballer."
- No, he was just a great footballer really,
'cause he also had a medical degree.
- Which he got while he was playing football.
- Yeah, he was super smart.
- He was amazing.
- And then when he got towards the end of his career,
he got into politics as well,
and he said, "If this military dictatorship doesn't leave
"and if they don't allow free elections,
"then I'm gonna leave and I'm gonna go and play in Italy."
- And what happened?
- He went to play in Italy.
- All right, that's so good, so what a letdown.
I thought you were gonna say, "And the government, back down."
- So in fairness, they did back down,
eventually he played one year in Furentina,
and then the next year they did back down and he came back.
- But they didn't just abandon the dictatorship
because it's to get him back into the country?
- No, they didn't, but he was quite instrumental.
- He was influential, yeah, he was such a big campaigner
for all that, he was such a great guy,
and he made them all wear shirts saying,
"Democracy" in their big,
this is when he played for the Corinthians,
which is also really cool because obviously the Corinthians,
great allies of Athens, allies of Socrates,
the Socrates fought with them
and the Peloponnesian Wars.
- Anna, have you taken Dan's coincidence pills?
This is insane, this is insane, I love it.
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Andy.
- My fact is that a lot of people in the UK
have their heating controlled by BBC Radio 4.
- That is amazing.
- Seem unlikely, doesn't it?
- This is mad.
This, I should say, was sent in as an audience fact,
it's sent in by Bill Welch, so thank you, Bill.
Right, so you will have electricity in your homes, right?
- Not me with my poverty situation going on.
I'm out on the streets anyway, so it doesn't matter.
- So, your electricity is controlled by a meter,
and it might be a smart meter if you've had it upgraded,
or it might be an old-fashioned one,
which measures the current going into your home
and you pay for the amount you use,
but you also pay maybe a different amount
at different times of day.
You know, at night, there's more electricity
that's going unused, and there's more wind turbines
going around, so there's lots of cheap electricity available.
Some old-fashioned electricity meters
can switch between different tariffs,
different rates they're charging you,
and the way they do it, switching twice a day,
is that they are set up to receive a signal
embedded in the BBC Radio 4 long-wave radio, so it's nuts.
Twice a day, Radio 4 sends out this message from Droitwich,
which is in the middle of the country,
and it's a transmitter that can reach the whole country,
and it just goes, "Blip!"
And hundreds of thousands of homes across the country
switch onto the new tariff
that they're paying for their electricity.
And this system, it dates back, I think, about 40 years.
It's only meant to last another month or so,
and they're meant to be shutting it down in June 2025,
but still, they've got hundreds of thousands of homes
where they haven't switched over the meters yet, so...
- We don't know what's going to happen.
- No. - Yeah.
- 'Cause at a time of recording,
they're still going to cut it off.
- I know. - But good luck.
They are trying to switch people over,
but they have to accelerate pretty fast, too, right?
- Yeah, switching people over at several thousand a day,
or they're trying to. - But it's hard, is it?
- It's hard, yeah. - And there is a petition,
just in case anyone's listening and thinks,
"Hang on, I don't want this to happen on change.org."
Do check it out, 'cause it's...
Like, I think it's gonna happen.
I think there's time.
- Yeah, and if you're listening to Radio 4
and you're listening out for this noise,
you're not gonna hear it. - No.
(laughing)
- Because it's not a bloop, not really.
It's the signal is sent by the phase information of the wave.
So you've got this radio wave sort of pulsing
through the country, and it's always the same frequency
so that you can pick it up on your radio.
But if sometimes they put little changes
in where the peaks and the troughs are in this wave,
and those tiny changes are the things that it picks up,
and your radio would normally strip away
any of those differences.
Any radio that you own, you would never hear this.
Now, in theory, you could build a radio,
like a ham radio, that would pick it up,
but even if you did that,
it would just be the tiniest little hum
you would have. - Right.
That's interesting.
So if you are at home, and your radio is off,
you've turned off Radio 4,
that's, it can't get through the radio, right?
Like, that's it, no.
- That's not how radio works.
- Then you pay loads of extra money for heating.
It's such a stupid system,
so you don't have to use their radios on all night.
- Your electricity meter is a radio.
- It contains a tiny little rod with iron in it,
and that's an antennae,
and that can receive 198 kilohertz radio waves,
and any signal that comes in on that radio wave
will be picked up by that little rod,
and so that is kind of acting like a radio.
- But you can't get a test match special
through your electricity meter.
- Okay, so if I lean up close,
I won't hear the arches theme tune.
Okay, that's good to know.
- A test match special isn't played on radio for anyways.
- No, it's all right.
- Isn't it?
- They got rid of it a few years ago.
- Okay, oh my God.
- I think that's the saddest part of all this stuff actually,
the test match special isn't on radio for anymore.
- Right, not even long wave.
'Cause the reason they put it,
like we should say,
most people listen to FM all probably now digital, right?
But long wave was 'cause there were about 90,000 homes
in the country which couldn't get FM radio,
and you would have to carpet the country with transmitters
to make that signal available absolutely everywhere.
So for those homes,
they just had the long wave signal,
which it's different that it'd get anywhere.
And also if you then have a program that lasts
for five days like test match special,
you just shove it on long wave.
So you don't have to stop all other radio for for a week.
- But this is why the heating has had to be stopped, right?
It's not about the heating systems changing over.
It's about radio for saying no one's using long wave anymore.
So also this will be probably news
to maybe five people after the country.
They're stopping broadcasting over long wave.
And this is just the knock on effect
where these guys are going,
"Hang on, that's gonna stop my heating."
Although it doesn't really affect that many people.
For instance, if you go to Curry's and try and buy a radio,
I think of all the radios they sell in the entire country,
there's only one of them
that will pick up long wave signals these days.
- Really, is that true?
- We're shooting ourselves in the foot
by turning off long wave.
What about when the internet stops, when it breaks,
we're gonna need a good reliable backup system
and that can be long wave.
- Yeah, well, that's probably there, right?
For us to still use.
- No, it's not.
This is the weird thing.
The whole point of it
is that they can't get these handmade glass valves.
There are these big glass valves
which make the long wave signal work.
And the BBC bought the entire global supply some years ago,
which was 10.
(laughing)
You need two of them
to make the transmitter work, right?
- How long did they last?
- Well, between one and 10 years.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- You know, so then down to their last two now.
They've got like, they've got no spares in the cupboard.
They're using their last two valves.
When one of those goes, the system goes.
- Yeah.
- One interesting thing about the long wave,
especially this thing in Dritewitch is,
you have to send out a frequency,
and it has to be exactly 198 kilohertz, right?
But how do you make sure
that the frequency is always the same
when you're sending this signal out?
- Yeah.
- I don't know.
- Well, they used to have a thing called an SN ring,
and it was made of quartz.
And if you apply voltage to quartz,
it vibrates at a very precise frequency.
And you had to, it had to be in a perfect ring,
and you had to sort of hang it up by nylon threads.
(laughing)
- It's so cool, the technology we used to have.
- And one of these existed inside the Dritewitch thing,
so that you would always have the exact frequency.
And now they do it with rubidium.
So they get some rubidium atoms, like a gas.
And rubidium atoms, rubidium 87, the isotope,
they always transition between two energy levels.
This is quantum physics now,
which are exactly 6.834682610 gigahertz apart.
And that's basically an atomic clock.
That's what that is.
- Yeah, 'cause this is how we used to keep time in Paris,
wasn't it, with the quartz before they came up
with the better version?
- Absolutely.
That's how my cassio works.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- Actually, I'm not even joking,
it has a small piece of quartz in.
That's how a digital watch.
- So yours works in the same way
that the SN ring would work.
Obviously, you don't have rubidium atoms in there.
- I didn't spring for that.
I saw it on Amazon as an option,
it's like, but it was three quid more.
And I thought, no, stuff that.
- But the atomic clock inside Droughtwitch,
not lose more than one second every 3,000 years,
if it was a watch, which is pretty good.
Although we're now up to with atomic clocks,
ones that won't lose a second in 30 billion years.
- Yeah, we've got two perfectionists here, haven't we?
It's like having to find the next digit of pi.
- Yeah.
- Who cares?
We've gone far enough.
- A second every 3,000 years is still,
if you'd started that when we invented farming
and came to now, it would still be within three seconds,
which I think is good.
I think that's good.
- Socrates would be almost a second late
if you had a meeting with him.
- It doesn't matter, he's frozen half a mile
down the road anyway.
(laughing)
- I had to refresh my memory from the old GCSE
in physics of how on earth all these waves bloody work.
And so, in case you need it, long wave hugs the ground,
which I just like the idea that that's why it can get
to all of those places is that,
like some sort of weird cartoon character
just clings just above the ground
so it can gallop over mountains and humps and everything.
- So if you're in a valley, you still get it?
- Exactly.
- Is it bouncing off the sky?
- Sometimes it is, but more important
with the bouncing of the sky.
And I think this is the very cool thing,
is short wave reception.
So short wave relies on the ionosphere,
which is the ring in our atmosphere of charged ions.
And the reason they're charged is because the sunlight
bashes into atoms in the daytime in our atmosphere
and it causes them all to react with each other
and lose electrons and they become ions.
So it's all very electrically charged.
And we use that ionosphere short wave
to bounce radio signal up and then back down to us.
What I quite like about that is that that means
that you'd get much better reception at night on the radio
just because of how the ionosphere works.
So basically in the daytime,
the ionosphere has been all charged up by the sun.
So it's lots of ions, like free electrons,
wandering around looking for a partner.
And so the radio wave goes up,
like someone going into a ballroom full of dancers
looking for partners.
- The sexy stuff, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
And it's harder in the daytime to get through that ballroom
because the dancers keep on trying to dance with you.
They're these free ions being like,
"Hey, pair up with me, pair up with me."
But in the nighttime, they all chill out,
they recombine with their normal partners
'cause the sunlight's gone away and stopped stirring them up.
So the radio signal of your short wave radio
can just go straight through the dance floor
without anyone assaulting them for it.
- Which is all well and good,
but you can't play cricket at the nighttime.
So the terrible irony is you can never listen
to "Test Met Special" with a good signal.
- And that is the ultimate point is it's pointless.
What good radios on a three in the morning?
- "Droit Witch" played a part in D-Day.
- Did it?
- Yes, it did.
- The D in D-Day stands for "Droit Witch" day, yeah.
The date of the landings was broadcast
from the "Droit Witch" transmitter
because there were people in France, the resistance,
they were getting signals from Britain
and how do you send a signal all the way to France?
Well, it's pretty difficult
unless you have a big old tower that can send long wave.
And so they did and they could pick up
the BBC French service from there
and they played like a poem by Paul Vellan, I think.
And when they heard that poem,
they knew that this was the time to,
basically what they did was they would kind of cause ruckus
with the Germans and like, you know,
just be a pain in the arse.
- If you're gonna block the roadways,
blow them up now.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
Just keep them occupied in various,
oh, ironically, you're the one who's occupied,
but keep them occupied while we're going onto the beaches.
- So the signal was like, create a distraction.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Cool.
- Can we say what the line was?
It's so cool.
So as you said, James, it was a poem by Paul Vellan
who was a 19th century, quite avant-garde gay poet.
Like, he was quite--
- Was he the one who had an affair with Rambo, I think?
- I think he did.
- Not Rambo, the--
(laughing)
- That's looking interesting.
- I was told me more.
Who's Rambo?
- Arthur Rambo was the poet as well.
Yeah.
- Oh, God.
- They were like the romantic poets of France.
- Yeah, they were terrific.
- That's a disappointing movie night
when I've rented that movie.
- Rambo, First Blood.
(laughing)
- Actually, Total Eclipse starring Leonardo DiCaprio
as Rambo is a great film, Dan.
- Wow.
- Yeah, there you go.
- And so the poem starts.
(speaking in foreign language)
"The long sobs of autumn violins
"wound my heart with a monotonous langer."
Very poetic.
So when they broadcast the first half,
that was a signal to the French resistance.
Invasion's gonna be within two weeks.
You've got two weeks to get ready.
- Right.
- And then they broadcast the second half of that line,
which was, you've got 48 hours.
Like, the French service broadcast all of these phrases,
some of which were meaningful,
like, "Molas's tomorrow will bring forth cognac."
That just went into France,
as it might've been done in Morse code,
but it was- - Okay.
- And then, "John has a long moustache."
And some of these phrases were meaningful to the resistance,
and a lot of them were nonsense,
just to confuse the Germans, basically.
- How interesting, right, cool, that's clever.
- And the Germans knew the significance
of the Verland poem.
There was an officer, a German intelligence officer,
who said, "Okay, the invasion's coming within 48 hours."
And he passed the message on,
but it did not get through to the army
who were actually in charge of Normandy,
and trying to man the beaches.
- Did he go shortwave?
- I didn't. - Grewed it up.
- Yeah, the warning wasn't passed on.
- That's mad, really.
- It's huge, that's a big counterfactual.
- Well, the amazing thing is also the Germans
sent some signals from Droitwich as well.
- Did they? - They had someone on the inside,
and so they could use the Droitwich transmitter
to send their own signals to people in France.
- Right, there was a German spy in Droitwich.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- They don't know who it was,
they assume it was someone working at the BBC or something.
- That's crazy. - Wow, that's cool.
I like that Longwave can go through water as well,
and that was submarines would use Longwave
to get their radio, their Radio 4,
they would literally use to get it.
- I think they still do. - Yeah, they still do,
but obviously at the end of this month, they weren't, right?
- What are they gonna do?
- I don't know, I don't obviously got a new thing,
they're gonna swap too, but that was the thing,
I'm sure we've said it, where in wartime,
you would make sure that England was still there,
basically, while you were under water,
if Radio 4 was still going.
- They've probably gone BBC sounds now.
- That's true, they probably pre-download before they go.
(all laughing)
I do love codes in,
I feel like we should do this at some point,
there's a whole period of an American radio
where they would put a code for the listener
at the end of a radio show,
so it would be like a little bit of Morse code,
and you had a decoder at home as part of the fan club,
so we would give little teasers for what's happening
in the episode that you were gonna hear
the next day or the next week.
- That's a really good idea,
'cause we know that you listening to this
almost certainly stop listening
before we say our email address is at the end,
'cause we've seen the figures,
we know when the drop-off comes.
- Are you saying we should put them in Morse code
at the start of the podcast?
- No, I'm saying we put something special at the very end,
so people are forced to listen to us saying,
I'm on Instagram.
- All right, we're gonna do it,
we can just tell people we'll put something special in.
- What should we put?
Crossword?
- That's the most, that's the most fun,
I think I've ever heard of.
- What about Sudoku?
- A Sudoku.
- So I'll do the first box, blank.
(all laughing)
You're gonna listen next week.
- In just 81 episodes time,
you've made your own Sudoku credit.
- That's great.
- This'll get people listening.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that Andy Warhol
would regularly have his wig cut by a barber
and then return the following month
wearing a new longer wig.
- Sorry, annoying for that barber.
- Yeah, how did the barber react?
- Well, this is Andy Warhol we're talking about.
He, as well as being an artist,
was an art piece in himself,
and the barber would have known
and would have enjoyed what they were doing.
- And actually, at the moment, if you're a barber,
you have to sit there waiting
for your customers to grow hair,
but if they just come in and buy some hair for you to cut,
it's giving you more work.
- Yeah, that's a good point.
- Yeah, was it so that his friends
would kind of slowly see his wig get longer and shorter
so it looked more realistic?
- Yeah, I think as well,
like this is one of the most photographed
socialites in America at the time.
He wanted to make sure that his look was ever changing.
It was sort of in fashion.
The wig was a huge part of his life, by the way.
- 'Cause his wig is a very obvious wig,
Andy Warhol's, isn't it?
- Yeah, it's silvery, isn't it?
I know you had hundreds of wigs.
- But iconic, so he basically started going bold
when he was in his 20s, and he really didn't want this.
And there's a lot of early art pieces
where it clearly is playing on his mind.
There's a piece that he did called "Bold?"
Question mark, where he just showed
someone gradually becoming bold in sketches.
And so he took it very seriously.
And there's a huge collection of Andy Warhol wigs
that are out there now.
They were all very nicely made by a man
who was called Paul Bokiccio.
They were iconic wigs.
- Yeah, you could buy one in 2006 at auction
for $10,800 at which time it was
the most expensive wig ever sold.
- Oh yeah, has it been overtaken?
- Three times, do you wanna guess?
- Oh, yes.
- Who's Big Wigs?
- You can get them all.
- Big Wigs.
- Marge Simpson?
- Oh my God.
Let's try some real life people.
- Okay, okay.
- But Big Wigs is a good name for when I turn this
into a channel five format.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- I'll take my usual 10% fee.
- Yeah, I feel like we might struggle
after the first episode.
In fact, after the first question.
(all laughing)
- I'm struggling now, I think I'm really famous.
So I'm thinking of people,
I'm thinking of iconic weird artists like
Salvador Dali.
- I think I'm more famous, very famous.
- Edna Everage?
- Edna Everage.
- Really good call.
Michael Jackson.
- Michael Jackson in at one, $75,000.
- Where's his wig?
- He did wear wigs later on.
So he was in a commercial for Pepsi.
- Yeah.
- And there was a fire or he burnt his hair basically
and he had to wear wigs for a while after that.
- It was pyrotechnics that went wrong
during the advert recording and his head lit up.
He didn't even notice.
You can see the footage where he's still dancing
and his head is just in, yeah.
Oh, so that's number one.
- Are the famous wig wearers, so?
- Go for more famous people who might have happened
to have worn wigs at a certain time.
- Dolly Parton.
- Close, but no.
- Give us one, like one clue that's sort of like.
- The most famous woman of the 20th century.
- Marilyn Monroe.
- Marilyn Monroe and Elizabeth Taylor.
- Oh, double.
- Yeah.
You kind of spoiled the format by getting them so quickly.
Fill another 24 minutes of the show.
But it was Elizabeth Taylor's wig in "Clear Patra"
went for $16,000 and Marilyn Monroe's wig,
she wore in "The Misfits," which was her last film.
I went for $30,000.
- Nice.
-  Da, da, da, da, da
- Come back next week when we'll desperately be hoping
for some big news in the wig world.
(laughing)
- So he kept hundreds, didn't he, Andy Warhol?
In boxes and--
- Yeah, he was a huge hoarder.
- He collected everything in his life.
There's a weird, massive art.
I think there's an Andy Warhol museum somewhere.
Maybe it's in Pittsburgh, which is where he was from.
- Yeah.
- But it's got, wherever it is,
it's got 50,000 of his things or 100,000, you know,
sort of many floors of ticket stubs and old.
- He basically, at the end of every day,
he would get a big cardboard box
and anything that he had left over,
like half a sandwich or a smoke cigarette or something,
he would just pour it all into that box
and with market time capsule
and then just put it to one side.
- It's a good idea.
- And the Andy Warhol museum has hundreds of these
and I don't think they've all been opened.
- No, so back in 2007, there was a journalist
who was invited to see some of the boxes being opened.
So they had 600 boxes of these things.
I think only like 80 of them had been opened at that point
and they had just no idea what you'd find in it.
So he was there as they opened it
and they found an unopened Lionel Richie CD
and you know, but then they found things
like a mummified foot that he bought at a sort of sale,
you know, like a garage sale and that he kept in.
- This is a format James, I'm sorry,
but like when the wig show comes to the end
of its natural life after many seasons,
I think Andy Warhol's big box open is a good,
it's like storage walls where you bid against each other
for what's in a box and you might get a half-eaten sandwich
or you might get millions of flies, you know?
That's a fun concept.
Are any of them like moving or ticking or?
(laughing)
- It's very much something you can get away with
if you're a very famous artist.
But if I did that as an ordinary human being,
my friends would think I'd gone completely mad.
- It's unsustainable for all eight billion of us
to do this with all of our things.
- But also the wig became its own thing in his life
where it could act as him.
So there was a whole tour in colleges
and instead of going, he sent an actor.
I think the guy had his own hair,
but he cut it and he colored it to exactly Andy Warhol.
So iconic that look and he wore dark glasses.
- Can we say what he was called?
- Yeah, absolutely.
- He was called Alan Midget.
- Yeah, Midget.
- I'm so sorry for mispronouncing
something for comic effect.
(laughing)
- Alan Midget.
- He had an E at the end, but he put that E on.
It didn't have the originally.
- Yeah, thank you very much.
- And basically people were very annoyed with Andy Warhol
when they found out that he'd sent Alan Midget in his place
just like sunglasses in a wig.
- Yeah.
- Did they know straight away when he came up
or would they see the whole tour?
- Basically they screened an incredibly boring film
that Andy Warhol had shot.
And then Andy Warhol's shtick
was that he didn't answer any questions.
So you'd have a question and answer session
where you'd say like two word answers.
I think people did get pretty quickly.
- They eventually did get it.
And it was a bit confusing.
And the people around Andy would say,
isn't it fascinating?
Some people who'd even met Andy
would then meet Paul Midget and say,
wow, Andy, lovely to see you again.
And he was like, if enough people around a person
believe it is the person,
then they get confused into thinking it is.
And that was the case.
Andy said they got a better deal
because actually Midget gave more answers at the talks
than Andy would have.
He was more personable.
He was more likable.
- Supposedly he was caught
when he ran out of silver hairspray.
Alan Midget, I don't know if that's true.
And people were so annoyed about this when it was discovered
that one Oregon college made Andy Warhol swear
on a Bible that he was Andy Warhol
before they let him do the event.
'Cause it was to students, these talks, basically.
And I think people had...
- But it feels better to see the double
because you're seeing an Andy Warhol work of art.
As Dan says, Andy Warhol made himself a work of art, didn't he?
So it was like everything he did, you had to appreciate.
And some people didn't get it.
- This guy is the Socrates of the 20th century.
I'm sorry, he's going around irritating people.
- Not answering any questions, only asking them.
- Yeah, he was a weird guy.
He did a lot of art, which was about replication
and uniformity.
And so one of his most famous things
is the paintings of Campbell's soup can.
- Yeah, that's what made him famous, really, yeah.
- But this was 1962, and it was his first big solo show.
So it was his debut to the art world.
It was not a success.
He sold five.
- Really? - Yeah.
In fact, I don't even know if he sold five.
Like a few of the, two were sold and a few more,
someone said, "Yeah, keep that back for me."
You know, it was a failure, I would say.
And the gallery owner then said,
"Actually, I'm not going to sell any of these.
"I want to keep the series together."
But I think it's interesting
that Campbell's didn't know about it,
because obviously he wouldn't have worn them or anything.
But then people started wearing Campbell's soup clothing
because this work of art had become popular.
And then Campbell's soup gave him a commission
to paint a can because their chairman was retiring.
So they've got this weird relationship.
Then they threatened to sue him later on.
Then they made their own dress out of soup can labels.
If you sent them $1 and two labels,
they would send you a dress
that looks like Campbell's soup can labels.
- Oh, so it was for anyway, it wasn't like high fashion.
- No, no, no.
It was just a sort of an offer.
But it was based on-- - Oh, $1.
That's a great value of dress.
- And two labels.
(laughing)
It's still a great value of dress.
But he just sort of dragged this perfectly innocent soup company
into the world of high art.
And then they started engaging with it off the back of it.
It was very much. - You may ask,
you might not know this,
but if that was such a failure,
at what stage did he become not a failure?
Do you know what I mean?
- I think it was very soon after that.
- I think it was almost the day after that.
- I think it's connected, yeah.
- A lot of people thought all the soup thing don't know.
And then a few critics said, actually, this is great.
- Actually, it's pretty good, yeah.
- Yeah, which I'm still on the fence about.
(laughing)
Some other people who don't appreciate his art,
people from his original village.
- Oh.
- 'Cause as you say,
I think he was born in something like Pittsburgh.
But ethnically, he was Russin.
Not Russian, Russin.
Which is this really tiny ethnicity
from the Carpatho-Russian Mountains.
And it's between Poland, Slovakia and Ukraine.
And that's where both his parents were born
before they emigrated to America.
It actually, so he's from a place called Ruthenia,
it's also called, which existed as a nation for one day
in 1939. - What?
- Yeah, it declared independence
and then immediately was invaded by Hungary.
- Oh, that's bad luck.
(laughing)
- Or was there a connection?
- There was a connection. - Oh, sorry.
- It wasn't that they were thinking,
when should we do it?
Let's wait, no, we'll wait.
Should we do it today?
No, no, let's wait.
Okay, finally.
Let's declare our independence.
Oh, fuck.
- Go on forward the chances.
- There was stuff happening in 1939.
I'm not sure if you're aware of that.
- I understand.
- But anyway, he's got all these cousins
still there in the area.
And they kept in touch with Andy Wall's parents
when they were in America.
And the parents wrote back to their cousins in Slovakia
saying he's a painter.
And people were interviewed saying until the late 70s,
they all thought he just painted houses.
They were like, oh, there's a house painter.
And then there was some good interviews.
Like he's got a cousin.
I think a first cousin called Julia Vasholova,
who's from there, still lives there.
And she said, semi-recently,
in America, you don't really need to be good at something.
You just need to be different.
Warhol was just really good at being different, wasn't he?
- So he's called Warholah.
It was an A originally.
But isn't it, I think it's in Slovakia
that they have the second largest collection
of Andy Warhol art now and memorabilia.
So there's an actual museum there that's outside of Pittsburgh.
But how are you going to compete
with 600 boxes of mummified feet, right?
Like you're not going to come first.
But yeah, so they've obviously embraced it now.
- Well, a little bit.
The person who set up the museum embraced it,
but he did go around trying to tell everyone
to get into it, him and a lot of his family
and people there were like, we don't get it.
We don't like it.
- Right.
- Whatever.
- And then he was shot.
- By Valerie Solanas, who he put in a few movies.
She thought she should have been in more of his movies.
- He shot me and then I shot him.
- Yes, I guess so.
- He took the task, isn't he?
- I think she had a few issues.
But basically she was a member of a feminist organization
called the Society for Cutting Up Men, or SCUM.
And she walked into his factory
'cause the place where he worked was called the factory.
And she just walked in, shot him and walked out again.
And then a few hours later,
she kind of went to a policeman saying,
I think the police are looking for me.
I am a flower child, arrest me immediately.
And they arrested her.
- And he survived, just 'cause if you don't know his story,
that sounds like he died, but yeah.
- Oh yeah.
- It was 168, this all happened.
I thought that the reason she shot him
was because he had lost the script of a play
that she had written called Up Your Ass, which,
and apparently--
- Or is that where he lost it?
(laughing)
- But I mean, she went to jelly the way, yeah.
- Yeah, probably for a few years.
- Yeah, he was declared.
- She was declared.
- And to be honest, I don't know.
But the episode of his shooting is insane.
It's the kind of shooting you'd imagine
in Andy Warhol's mad life.
Two friends there, his friend Mario Amaya
was also shot on the bullet,
went all the way through from back to front,
didn't get any organs,
but then they called an ambulance
and it took half an hour to arrive.
And in that time, more mates turned up,
found this blood-soaked scene.
Mario was running around going,
"Is there a bullet in my back?
"Is there a bullet in my back?"
And then Andy Warhol's lying dead
and he was literally declared dead.
- Really? - Yep.
- In one of those youth here that was a fact
and you think, "No, surely not."
But he was taken to hospital.
He had no signs of life
and there was a sort of vascular surgeon in the room
who said, "Hang on, I quite like the soup cans thing.
"I'm gonna really try and sew this guy up."
- Not true, the doctor didn't know who it was.
They thought he was a random tramp.
- Oh, I thought they thought he was a tramp at first
and then they were told he was Warhol
when they were operating.
Although I'm not saying
he wouldn't have operated on the random tramp.
- No, Giuseppe Rossi was the name of the surgeon.
What a guy.
This is an artist, okay?
Boy, he did.
Serious.
Warhol's been shot, I think, twice and really badly.
He's in very, very bad nick.
He's dead.
- He's dead.
- But Rossi opens Andy Warhol's chest,
massaged his heart, took out his spleen
and he puts it in order for 12 pints of blood.
And he's like, "We can do this."
- And he did it.
- Yeah.
- And Andy Warhol thanked him
by giving him 10 posters of Campbell's soup.
- Well, thanks.
- Hang on, that's gonna be worth so much.
- Yes, they were sold after Rossi eventually died.
I think his widow then sold it
'cause I imagine they kept them for life.
- Yeah.
- You know, yeah, yeah.
- If I gave a doctor 10 posters, that's an insult.
- What would you pick?
Posters of what?
Fish tour posters?
- Yeah, fish tour posters.
- This is Fanella's dream.
We've got to give away 10 of my posters.
- Brilliant, I've got them ready, Dad.
- Poor surgeons at home after a very hard day's work.
So I was like, there's a life-sized model
of Groucho Marx outside.
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week
is that when Stansted Airport was being planned,
locals, complaining to maintain the area's natural beauty,
often met in a village called Ugly.
- Lovely.
(laughing)
- So initially this was a fact that I found
about the Ugly Women's Institute.
We were gonna do an Ugly Women's Institute fact,
but that's kind of on the internet a fair bit.
And when I was researching that,
I found this campaign about Stansted
and they were deciding where to put London's third airport.
And it turns out that quite a few of the meetings
to stop the airport from going around there
took place in Ugly Church Hall.
(laughing)
Because Ugly is a village in Essex.
- Yeah, and we should say Stansted is an airport.
It's an airport for international listeners
who have not been.
- It is not a great place to spend time.
- It's not a beautiful place.
- It's one of the big three.
Gatwick Heathrow, Stansted.
- But yeah, they had lots of meetings
at this Ugly Church Hall.
Some of the Ugly residents were pro.
So the Ugly Youth Club (laughing)
wrote a letter to the Preservation Society
saying that it will bring some life into the area
that according to them had little around but farming.
And they said that a lot of young people
were moving out of the area.
And if you brought in this big airport
with all the jobs it created,
then maybe it will keep the Ugly Youth around.
And Councillor Jay Luckey's responded saying,
it's a feeling that the youth has
that they're being brought up among squares.
- Oh.
- So yeah, so it was, you know,
it wasn't everyone was against it,
but it is quite a beautiful part of the world actually.
- Is it?
- It is.
- Ugly is really nice.
I've been looking at photos.
- It's lovely, as they will tell you.
Understandably, they'll get defensive.
It's very beautiful.
Ugly Church is not ugly.
- Yeah, ugly green, ugly village hall.
There's an ugly farmer's market
that happens every now and then.
- I went on to company's house.
There's an ugly coach house.
And until 2023, there was a company called the Ugly Indian
and it was based in Ugly.
And I can't find that what it was.
I assume it's a restaurant.
- Yeah.
- Right.
- It's not gonna be a single person, right?
- But there is.
- There's a group called the Ugly Indians in India
that kind of clean up potholes and stuff.
- Really?
- But it's not that.
- Oh, that's cool.
- No, that would be a terrible base
for much to clean up bottles and in here.
- I really liked the very first mention
that we have of ugly written down is in 1041.
And it had a different name.
It wasn't called ugly then.
- Oh yeah?
- It was called ugly.
(all laughing)
- Oh, you're spelling that?
- U-G-E-L-E.
- Nice.
- Ugly.
And actually the locals there,
the locals there don't call it ugly.
The posh ones who are living there,
they like to call it ugly.
- Stop it.
- No, they don't.
But there's not a single one.
- This was told to a reporter called Laura Fiddler
who was down there trying to find out
all the most interesting things about ugly.
- Laura Fiddler's misunderstood the jokes on her.
It's five kilometers north of Stansted Airport.
So Stansted is named after a town called
Stansted Mount Fitchett,
which is just outside where the airport is.
So it's not inconceivable they could've called it ugly airport.
- That would've been terrific.
- Other nearby villages include Little London,
Mole Hill, Maggots End, and Hope End.
So Hope End Airport would've been a good one.
- That's good.
There is a nearby village called Nasty,
which is 12 miles away.
It's a long running.
I think it's just a joke.
Reputedly there was a newspaper headline once,
"Nasty man marries ugly woman."
- I suspect it never happened, sadly.
- The evidence isn't bad.
- Quite near to another little village called Matching Tye,
which is a great name.
- Oh, it's such a good name.
- It's T-Y-E.
Have you guys of Danor and the heard of Matching Tye?
- No.
- I'm really surprised you haven't
because Rick Mail lived there until he was three years old.
- Oh!
- That is a real gap in our knowledge, Dan.
- Yeah, we're gonna have to send in our badge
and our gun back to Rick Mail.
So I think they shouldn't let us have a gun.
- I thought you had a badge and a big frying pan.
(all laughing)
- More Essex place names, just as we're on those.
There's Shallow Bowls.
Shallow, not Shallow, really.
Shallow Bowls, Wiggly Bush Lane,
Burnt Dick Hill, Dancing Dick's Lane,
and the best of all, Fingering Ho.
- Hopefully.
- Come on.
- Fingering Ho.
- Ho.
Yeah, you've said it three times now.
We've heard it, I think we understand why it's funny.
(all laughing)
- That's great.
- Speaking of Dicks, Dicks related names,
there is an Ugly Women's Institute,
and there was, well, it was certainly reported
in the late '50s that they decided to change
to Women's Institute brackets, ugly,
but then by the '80s,
they were back to being the Ugly Women's Institute,
and their president in the late '70s was Mrs. Dicks.
Mrs. Dicks was president of the Ugly Women's Institute.
Yes.
- You know the most famous person to visit ugly ever, I think.
- Oh, just like passing visit.
- Yeah.
- Daphne and Celeste.
- No.
- Think more German.
- German.
- Daphne and Celeste.
(all laughing)
- Tomorrow German, well, Ahets, Adolf Hitler.
- You know what?
Right period, right cabinet, in fact.
- Gering.
- Okay.
- Hitler.
- It's another.
- Can we just pause on the fact that James has a nickname
for Hitler?
(all laughing)
- We go way back.
- Ahets.
- We're just reading it off his tattoo there.
(all laughing)
- I couldn't fit the full name on my penis.
- Oh my God.
- Wow.
- Oh, dear.
- It was Joachim von Ribbentrop.
- Oh, is it?
- Yeah.
- Try fitting that on your penis.
(all laughing)
- Of Pactfame.
- The moment when Ribbentrop was Russian and German.
He was the foreign minister.
I think this was before his time as German foreign minister.
He visited Orford House, which is just outside, I think,
but it's still in the sort of parish boundaries.
And of course, later he was the first man
hanged for war crimes after the Nuremberg trials.
- He was, yeah.
I think he might have been the only person
who's been too ugly, who was hanged
as part of the Nuremberg trials.
- And what was he?
- I believe.
- And what was that?
Like why was he staying at a hotel
the night before a flight from Stanstead?
(all laughing)
- It was a beautiful house that I think was owned
by a local toff who invited him over probably.
- And he loved England.
I think it was Ribbentrop who kept on trying
to get him to invade England
'cause he thought all of it was so beautiful.
Loved Cornwall.
- Yeah.
- Right.
- Yeah, probably loved ugly.
- So there was a big argument about Stanstead Airport
when it came in.
So we had two airports in London.
We had Gatwick and Heathrow,
and they thought we're definitely gonna have
to build a third one.
And the decision that we were gonna need
was starting about the '50s and '60s,
and they didn't actually build Stanstead Airport
until the '80s.
I think it finished in '85, something like that.
Because actually, Stanstead in the end was,
they just did up an old airfield.
Like rather than building like
a whole big massive new airport,
like is what they were planning,
they kind of rolled back on that idea a little bit
and went for the smaller version,
which was what Stanstead was.
But everyone obviously got really upset about it.
- People don't like airports near them, do they?
I understand, please.
- And it wasn't even, like during the war,
during the Second World War,
it was the ninth largest American air base in East Anglia.
Like it might not have been the obvious choice, actually.
They were bigger ones.
After the war, it was used as a base
for German prisoners of war
who were gonna be sent back to Germany.
And actually--
- That's a good idea, isn't it?
- Well, if you get a Stanstead now,
they've really preserved that sense
of what it must have been like.
Yeah.
- And they nearly built the third airport
in a place called Wing in Buckinghamshire.
Yeah, there was locals there weren't happy about it,
either informed the Wing Airport Resistance Association.
But that was gonna be a really big airport.
And it was after the oil crisis in the '70s,
they decided that actually we should do a smaller one
and that's when they went to Stanstead.
So we could have had a Wing airport.
And actually where the airport was gonna be,
there's now, they put some trees there
and you can go and visit that sort of patch of forest
of where there should have been an airport.
- Is that a big tourist hotspot in Buckinghamshire?
- Just nimbyism in general.
- Oh yeah.
- You know, there's a nimby not in my backyard.
This is what people say when they don't want to think.
The alternatives are the banana people
and that is built absolutely nothing anywhere near anything.
(laughing)
It's good.
- That's brilliant.
- And there's an idea in,
I think it's more of an American thing when it's cave,
which is citizens against virtually everything,
which is another good idea.
- Nice, that's really good.
- But maybe the paradigm example of this,
this was something that happened in Medway in Kent.
So not far from Essex, three years ago.
Medway Council, they really wanted to add solar panels
to their headquarters.
It's kind of a post-war, like modern initial block.
It's not sort of, it's not incredibly exciting to look at.
They thought let's stick some solar panels on there.
So the Medway Council put in an application
to Medway Council to put solar panels
on their own headquarters and they were shocked
that Medway Council turned down the request
by Medway Council saying, no, this is not appropriate at all.
The weird thing is it already had solar panels on it.
They were just like, can we put some more on there?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can all be found
on our social media accounts.
I'm on @Sribeland on Instagram.
- Andy. - I've joined Instagram.
Ooh, I'm @AndrewHunterM.
- James.
- Well, I might leave Instagram then if Andy's there.
I'll go for TikTok, nosy fingers James Harkin.
- Yep, and Anna, if they want to get to us as a group.
- We're on Instagram on @NoSuchThingAsAfish
or @NoSuchThingOnTwitter
or you can email podcast.qi.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of the previous episodes are up there,
so do check them out.
There's also links to our upcoming live shows.
We've got one in Belgium in a couple of weeks,
and then we're gonna be in Sheffield.
It's part of the Crossed Wires Festival.
We've also got a link to Clubfish, our secret club,
where there are bonus episodes
and lots of fun things going on, so check that out.
Or you could just come back next week,
'cause we'll be back with another episode.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)
(harmonica music)