[music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from four undisclosed locations in the UK. My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
James Harkin and Andrew Hunter Murray and once again we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in a particular order here we go. Starting
with you, Andy. My fact is that after his death Anton Chekhov was brought back to Russia in a
refrigerated railway car labelled Fresh Oysters. Wow. So was he your nice? Oh I don't know if he
was actually all nice. I know that he was he was pre-chilled for that. I think he was he was
chilled because the last thing before he died was he had some champagne which would have been cold
as well. Oh yeah. So yeah this is a 1904 he was 44 years old very young to have completely you know
revolutionised Russian literature and he was in a spa in Germany because he had tuberculosis
and the doctor arrived and when the doctor arrived because things were nearing the end
his tuberculosis was really bad at this point. He sat up straight and he said to the doctor
Ich staube which is I'm dying and the doctor just said let's have some champagne because there was
this German medical convention which was that if you can't do anything for the patient you just get
them some champagne and that means they know what's going on and so do you. Okay that's interesting
but he didn't really speak very good German right? Tol Chekhov and so I find it quite interesting
that he'd picked up this one he must have known that he might need that phrase. He didn't know
he was going to die so he said before he boarded the train to Germany he said to his friend I'm
off now I won't see you again I'm going to Germany to die so I suppose he was prepped to check out
the I'm dying phrase. Yeah he was a medical doctor wasn't he so he sort of his whole life was sort of
he saw the little hints of what was going to happen in his near future he thought he would try
and go to the spa to sort it out it didn't work out but what's amazing is he got given this big
flute of champagne and he downed it all in one go and then he sort of laid back and after a few
moments that was it he was gone what an ending. Yeah well they say that but I mean you don't down a
massive flute of champagne without there being at least a little burp at the end do you?
Probably just before he went there would have been a big belch I reckon. Yeah the account that
we have is from Olga Knipper his wife then widow and she sort of says it was very calm and very
peaceful and he sort of laid down turned his head and passed away but there are other accounts
that were written that didn't come out for years and years afterwards by another kid who was in
the room who was assisting the doctor and as James said there was a sort of great burpy groan.
Oh really? Yeah knocks out the poetry of Olga's account. Oh the Olga declined to mention that.
She was one of Dennis the menace's pets wasn't she? Well his body then went to Moscow in this
train which said fresh oysters on it but when he arrived in Moscow station there were people
kind of waiting for his body because he was a big famous you know hero in Russia but apparently
this is what I read when he came back there was another person who died the same time called
General Keller and the state had organized a big sort of fun for for his body returning
and a military band and a parade and stuff and so a load of Chekhov's fans just started following
General Keller's funeral procession thinking it was Chekhov which he was in the refrigerator
railway car next to it labeled fresh scallops and there was a bit of mayhem. It's a comedy it's
a faulty tower style comedy mix-up where you want Basil faulty to expose at the end what he thinks
is a pile of oysters and is actually the corpse of Anna. So weird that you mentioned that because
I was thinking about faulty towels already for a different reason related to Chekhov's death
which is that after he died they put him in a laundry basket which is kind of like the episode
The Kipper and the Corpse. And what was his wife's surname? Kipper? The Canipper and the Corpse.
The Canipper and the Corpse. Oh my god. Yes. Are we blowing shit wide open again? Oh no let's
let's have a week off blowing shit wide open. Too late! Too late! The Canipper and the Corpse.
That's got there's no such thing as the Canipper and the Corpse. But they but they couldn't fit
him in properly because obviously he was um he was a little stiff by the time they tried to
fold him up and laundry is more flexible than Chekhov and so he was in a half sitting position
in the basket. Oh my god. Pretty undignified I know and it was it was to hide him from the other
guests basically. It's a bit more dignified than you know how you fold laundry by two people holding
each end of it walking towards each other. You can't do that with Chekhov can you? No way.
It's really nice as a witness account as someone accidentally passing them as they were trying to
sneak Chekhov out. No. In the laundry basket. Yeah and he said I walked behind the man carrying
the body light and shade from the burning torches flickered and leaped over the dead man's face
and at times it seemed to me as if Chekhov was scarcely uh perceptibly smiling at the fact that
by decreeing that his body should be carried out in a laundry basket fate had linked him with humor
even in death. Oh that's so nice because I was just gonna say I reckon Chekhov would have loved that
way the worst thing because he was kind of a comedy loving guy. He would have really enjoyed
that and I suppose that that guy saw the same thing. Yeah yeah. He started out as a comedy
writer really didn't he? Well he thought he was a comedy writer at the very end as well but not
everyone else agreed with him. Yeah very confusing is that the thing where like with the cherry orchard
he was insistent the cherry orchard was a comedy and the famous director who put on the first
production was Konstantin Stanislavski who insisted it was a tragedy and staged it as such
and it's kind of sad because it's the last thing that was put on before he died and Chekhov was
furious. They hadn't been interpreted as a sort of a farce. I think it's amazing because you have
Chekhov who's like one of the great short story writers and playwrights of history
and then you've got Stanislavski who's one of the great theatre producers ever and you know he's
where the Stanislavski method comes from and you know when American actors are doing the method
that's basically the Stanislavski method that they kind of brought over to America. So you've got
two greats who came together and Chekhov wrote this play and on the front page it says comedy
it says a cherry orchard a comedy and then Stanislavski writes back to him going I think it's a
tragedy mate and it's like how can you say that to the writer how can you say I don't think it's a
comedy yet I think it's amazing. And then Chekhov wrote when he first saw this play he wrote how
awful it is an act that ought to take 12 minutes at most last 40 minutes he has ruined the play
for me and Stanislavski wrote the blossoms had just begun to appear when the author arrived and
messed everything up for us. So it's like these two greats and they just couldn't agree I think it's
amazing. That's incredible and then in between there is Olga Knipper who acted in all of Stanislavski's
versions of Chekhov and that is how yeah that's how Chekhov eventually so it would be a situation
where he probably didn't want to see the plays but he had to see the plays because he was madly
in love with this girl and get closer to her and because they eventually married after she'd done
I think four of his plays or so. That must have been so awkward because I think the cherry orchard
was after they were married and she must have been so torn between these two people. I mean do
you think she would do one scene serious and one scene comedy or yeah maybe when Chekhov came into
the room she'd put on a red nose and some big things. She was bizarrely she acted in the cherry
orchard in 1904 she was madame Ranevskyer who's basically the main part controversy over who
is the main part so 1904 and then she did it again 1943 same part. That's got to be one of the longest
gaps between the same role. She was 36 for the first and 75 for the second. She outlived him by a
really long way because he died in 1904 and she died in 1959. Do you know what I find the weirdest
thing about Chekhov is that as we were saying before he's this huge author and he's today he's
still considered to be one of the all-time greats. I kept reading in a few places that
just he's sort of under Shakespeare as the person with the most film adaptations and plays that are
on and I can't I haven't seen any of his stuff and I can't think of a single short story and I just
find that fascinating that I read a lot I see a lot of things yet this guy is second to Shakespeare.
His plays got put on a lot I would say and definitely in London you would get it. We had
tickets to watch the Seagull just before lockdown we never got to see it in the end with what's
the name from Game of Thrones Amelia Clark was it? Oh yeah yeah but yeah his plays are excellent
I love those but honestly Dan and anyone he was in my top three favourite writers I would sometimes
say as my favourite writer his short stories are heaven. You'd sit down and read one of those
before you read Cloud Your Way Through the Merry Wives of Windsor. Definitely and good news they're
quite short Dan. I read log books. I read just for this I read what's it called the the woman and
the dog. The woman with the dog. The woman with the lap dog or whatever. Yeah and I've tried to
read it in Russian because you know I'm learning Russian a little bit and I'm kind of okay and
the standard of writing is it's quite simple it's quite easy to read it's like he has lots to say
about the human condition and about you know love and the way that people react with each other but
actually it's in really nice easy to understand writing. I can read big words. I can read big
words James. We should say that not everyone respected him quite as much so Tolstoy hated his
stuff. Tolstoy said that Chekhov is an appalling playwright but at least he's not as bad as Shakespeare.
But he also have really hated Shakespeare. Well actually they were good mates but they
Tolstoy and Chekhov. Yeah they were. I think he said that right to his face he was like I hate this
but at least it's not as bad as Shakespeare. And he loved his short stories so Tolstoy used his
daughter Tolstoy's daughter said that Tolstoy used to make them read the short stories aloud at
dinner and his early funny stuff and the daughter said that Tolstoy my father was usually a good
reader but with Chekhov he was often quite unable to go on so infectious did his helpless fits of
laugh to become and he was sort of laugh until he cried and he I think he was on the people who
said why doesn't Chekhov understand that he's just a great comedy writer you know stick to that.
And he just knocked about as well that's what I love about them. He decided he wanted to be a
writer because he needed to support his family and he just it was only over about 20 years that he
wrote all these things like 700 short stories or something and they were all literally just like
okay we'll get this out to the to the Moscow Times to the St. Petersburg Times every month or so you
would have at least two or three of Chekhov's stories in there they'd be all under different
pen names he didn't know they were all from the same person. Well someone who I've become a bit
obsessed off the back of Chekhov now is a lady called Constance Garnet. Now this is just what
a remarkable story so it's really thanks to her that we have Chekhov in the English language as
well as Tolstoy and other great Russian writers. She sat down with a Russian dictionary having
not spoken a single word of Russian until the age of 29 and she translated all of these books
and that is how the English speaking world got introduced to all of these people and just a
remarkable person. She is she's such a weirdo she just randomly decided to withdraw and devote her
life to that and yet changed 20th century literature I guess because all literature was then influenced
by the Russian greats and she churned it out too she did like hundreds of Chekhov stories all of
Turgenev all of Tolstoy's novels almost all of Tolstoy all Dostoevsky. Oh my god I hope she started
with Chekhov. Yeah ease her way in and the reason she started is because she had a difficult
pregnancy in 1891 where she was kind of confined so she thought nothing else to do except learn
Russian and she did and then 1894 she just abandoned her husband and her toddler went to Russia
and hung out with Tolstoy for a bit and so like can I can I start translating your novels please.
Amazing. Yeah and she and she didn't start easy you know one of the first translations was a
religious and philosophical piece by Leo Tolstoy which was called the kingdom god is within you
I mean a really hardcore first thing and she had terrible vision at the end so she kept translating
sort of into her late life but she would have someone sitting there reading it out
while she translated so she sort of had assistance alongside her helping her to do it and the reason
that they became so popular around the world is because she was she was it from a publishing
family her husband worked in publishing as well and she was able to press them as really cheap
books so people could afford them and they could just get out there into the wild in a in a way
that people could could buy them affordably that's that's the real reason that they into the attraction
into the wild novels galloping through the rainforest. I tried to find if there's a single
removals firm in the UK called Uncle Vanya and I can't find one Jesus and I think what a gap in
the market that is yeah yeah what about a um is there like a really happy tree surgeon called the
cheery orchard that's good yeah so many gaps in the market everywhere are these gaps in the market
are just terrible jokes I'm sure I would trust a removals firm called Uncle Vanya I think these
guys are going to look after my books okay his nickname in the UK was Willy Wetleg
really why Florence nicknamed him Willy Wetleg because um Willy Wetleg just I don't know why
it's but audiences in the UK were not wowed by early jack-of-plays because they didn't like the
lack of obvious plots or clear meanings some of them some of them are quite you know
non-committal and there isn't a definitive answer that's right I read a review in the Daily Express
from the time which said that the cherry orchard was a silly tiresome boring comedy there is no plot
the orchard is for sale and certain dull people are upset because it must be sold wow it's a decent
summary of the plot oh is it um so this is coming from someone who as I say doesn't hasn't read any
of Chekov was the idea that it was all character studies and just amazing dialogue and sort of
insight into the human condition I mean there's quite a lot of social commentary a lot of stuff
about um kind of aristocracy can we spoiler the can we spoiler the cherry orchard are we
going to get in trouble for that I don't think I don't think we're going to go for the ending
this big messed up family is having crazy philosophical debates and then shagging each
other and um getting angry and making up stuff like that you know it's like neighbours we haven't
even mentioned Chekov's rifle or Chekov's gun oh yeah it's impossible to find out if Chekov actually
owned a gun because whenever you google the phrase Chekov's gun it only comes up with the dramatic
principle that he kept saying which is if there is a gun hanging on the wall in the first act it
has to go off uh in the second pretty and he said different versions of it but that's broadly it
don't introduce a plot element that's a big heavy thing and then not play it out but I kept on trying
to find out if he did have a gun yeah why have what why why try and find that out yeah I think
that's interesting it's relevant did he have it Chekov's gun was it real yeah was he you know
could he really talk about guns or had he never seen one in his life and he's you know exactly
was he bluffing yeah sorry for trying to do my homework Dan sorry sorry yeah I don't know why
I questioned it no I was just curious if there was an extra thing about it that I didn't realise
there was absolutely nothing here's a pointless um here's a pointless fact about Chekov uh the Seagull
in russian is um Cheka it's called that's russian but it's not russian for seagull it's just russian
for gull uh because actually the play is set in the middle of ukraine or russia nowhere near like
thousand miles from the sea and so yeah we just translated it as seagull but really it should be
gull that's probably bloody constant it's garnet isn't it bringing her seagull base i think
see that's a good fact to look into Andy this kind of thing you should be focusing on that will
absolutely delight or mythological fans because of course there is no such thing as a seagull
yeah and there's no such thing as the seagull either there you go nice yes did you guys spot that
thing about the theory that he didn't die of tuberculosis and how they've been looking into
they've reopened the case they've reopened the case i've got them into it come on this this was
a thing whereby did he drown in a bed of oysters suffocated in some laundry basket
he um he supposedly died of a brain hemorrhage and this was this was scientists took some proteins
that were on his shirt and they analyzed it and um they they think what showed up sort of
suggests that the tuberculosis was a lifelong thing that he had under control that it was
manageable but actually he was suffering from huge pains of a brain hemorrhage and yeah so they
they just analyzed this is and this is only a few years ago that they managed to get these samples
and that's the theory they dig them up again together it's a good question it was on his
clothes so i assume that maybe the clothes must have been saved it's relics yeah got it it's not
what you want when someone says of a historical character he actually didn't die this way what
we want is he was murdered by his furious lover by his by a gun which may or may not have belonged to
him if they accused his wife of killing him and she didn't really she could say i was done up like
a clipper okay it is time for fact number two and that is james okay my fact this week is that
earlier this year a woman reported that she was bleeding from her eyes whenever she was on her period
wow is it i euphemism no is that okay none of that sentence is euphemism you wouldn't say eyes
plural would you um that's mental yeah so does i mean so many yeah i'm just waiting for the
questions and then i'll tell you but okay can you buy i tampons you cannot buy i tampons no oh well
then i feel really sorry is it the same is it the same blood that's kind of traveled through the body
and up out the eye okay if you if you squeeze her by the tummy that started off as a reasonable
question so i'll answer it so there is a thing um that it that can happen called vicarious menstruation
and it seems to be a kind of hormonal thing we're still not exactly sure why it happens
but it means people can bleed from different parts of their body when they're on the period
so people have been documented as bleeding from the nose that's quite common like nose
bleeds the nipples the intestines the skin things like that it's extremely extremely rare
but earlier this year this is a report in the british medical journal there was 25 year old who
visited an emergency room and she was having blood coming from her like near from her tear ducts
when she was on her period and there's also a thing called hemo lacrea which can make blood
come out of your eyes there's lots of different things that can cause that so that could be caused by
you know abnormality in the sinuses problems with the tear ducts there's lots of things that
can cause that but the doctors went through everything that that could have been and realized
it couldn't be any of those things and they think that this is vicarious menstruation
and hemo lacrea put together and this is the first time that it's ever been reported in any
medical journal now it seems to be quite benign they can't see any other problems from it it's
just the thing that happened they gave her some hormonal therapy and it has gone away so it seems
to be a hormonal thing like the vicarious menstruation would be but that's it this is a thing that
happened extraordinary so it's not her womb wandering around her body we're not about to
say Aristotle was right we're not saying oh that would have been the biggest shit to blow wide open
of all everything parent i've read that there was a 1995 study that found that 18 percent of fertile
women do have some blood in their tears is that right trace amounts of blood yeah seven percent
of pregnant women eight percent of men 18 percent of fertile women and then postmenopause no women
have it oh i see so it comes study but interesting so you can cut down that phrase blood sweat and
tears you can just say blood and sweat or tears and sweat yeah that's good that's going to save
us all some time well i did also say that some people can sweat blood due to vicarious menstruation
so you could just say blood oh great much easier if anyone ever says to you blood sweat and tears
just go to autology mate do you think uh i'm sure you don't uh that groups of women living together
start to experience synchronized menstruation oh it's what people say but i think i've read
things that say that that's not true but anecdotally so many people whenever i've said to them and said
well it is true so i don't know what you're talking about yeah that's i saw that as well
medically according to the reports not true i know so many women who've told me that that's
what's happened with them so who do we believe yeah i think the larger more recent studies
which say it doesn't happen i thought i reckon that's what they were that's what they were saying
to baristotle back in the day weren't they they're saying i've spoken to lots of women and they say
that their wombs do not move around their body you're like nope nope this is what the scientists
say studies have shown um yeah i think the largest and longest studies have found no evidence for it
there is plenty of random overlap that might be seen as synchrony if you look at it through a
shorter time window so there are plenty of reasons why you might think it is happening but
but no i think it's confirmation bias i think it just overlaps enough that every four months
that happens and they go oh my god we must be synchronizing right okay but it does
happen with lions that's the key so maybe everyone you've asked has actually been a lion in this
do you guys think and i don't think you do but do you think that bears are attracted to menstruation
are attracted how just as in section come closer to what yeah yeah well finella's finella's cousin
was once told to escape a forest because the the guide found out she was menstruating it was like
you got to get out of here now and they just left to run her own to just yeah she had what she had to
leave the wood at her at her husband's stage and she was like never found again she's now living in a
gingerbread house wow really that's amazing and what did you get attacked by a bear don't know
no because i have a feeling james is about to say that that's a myth well it is a myth but i'm
still a bit worried about this guide at all where they just say anyone who's menstruating get out of
here now and you're on your own there was a study relatively recently done uh where 15 used tampons
were presented to male black bears that were feeding in a garbage dump uh and they found
there was no uh reaction uh from the bears i mean at least at least they had the courtesy
not to go oh get out of my face but all this study says to me is that bears prefer garbage dumps
to use tampons it doesn't necessarily mean that but yeah it could be the second best thing on the
menu yeah the um a lot of different tribes think that periods will attract dangerous animals i think
the warry people of brazil uh the women wouldn't be allowed to go into the forest when they were on
their periods because jaguars would be attracted to them and they weren't allowed to have sex either
because then jaguars would be attracted to the men who were out hunting because they'd have sex
with someone wow it's like it follows it's like cracking film and a niche reference that some
people will get that's but they also have another really cool practice uh these guys or this is
actually a thing i was reading in the 60s about them so it might have changed but whenever a mother
was on her period her whole family her husband and children all painted themselves with red food
coloring wow that's amazing that is such a good idea weird right i think we should bring that in
kind of a hassle a bit messy you could make a lot and food coloring only comes in those tiny tiny
vials yeah so what you could do is paint yourself in the new pantone shade uh called period um which
they brought out relatively recently um it's it's very red it's very very red it's not blood red
it's just red red um but they brought it out uh according to them um to so people can own their
period with self assurance to stand up and passionately celebrate the exciting and powerful
life force they are born with to feel comfortable to talk spontaneously and openly about this pure
and natural bodily function and by having some red paint that will help us to do that but i think
if we all painted ourselves red we'd definitely be able to do that yeah yeah i feel liberated already
paint my wall in period that makes a big difference if you go to a property website and they say
well this of course is a period property uh a lot of period features oh my word um sharks also don't
go for menstruation they know they they like fish it turns out and they like it i mean this was a
thing that this is a thing that is also thought i think like the bears you know they've got a great
sense of smell sharks and um you know if uh you are menstruating then and you're in the water
maybe you're going on a swimming with sharks experience it might lead to trouble it turns out
really they're like the chemicals in fish blood and they have good enough nose to detect fish from
human blood um and also menstrual blood is mostly not blood it's it's mostly you know the the lining
of the womb it's secretions there's trace of blood but it's not uh yes yeah so feel free to go swimming
with sharks if you're if you're hanging out on the edge of the water worried about it don't be
has anyone heard of the sanitary products known as sphagnikins?
no no they sound a bit scandy no okay it's not scandy um the name comes from what they were
made of sphag sphagnikins sphag sphag swags oh like sphagnimos then sphagnimos so they used to have
the sphagnimos girls um which were images that they used to advertise sanitary products made from
andi's favorite material moss wow there you go the sphagni the the the moss girls yeah they were
known as the sphagnum moss girls wow when were these ladies around uh it was the middle of the 20th
century is that i can't can't do is that there's nothing moss can't do lovely um one thing that's
of quite a hot potato in a lot of countries is the tampon tax and um in germany in 2019
there was something that was actively done about it in order to raise awareness so
it's taxed as a luxury good this is in 2019 at 19 percent um which is ridiculously high in comparison
to so many other things say like books which are only charged at seven percent so there was a brilliant
book that was released called the tampon book which had inside of it 15 tampons which was sold
so you could buy them for much cheaper than you would a normal pack um of tampons uh in the tax
sense and um they sold 10 000 copies once they released it so it was sort of becoming a best
selling book in its own right but yeah tampon tax has been a horrific thing that we've still not
solved in the uk just passed something though which yeah i think they have just passed it haven't
they in the uk i don't know i know you get free sanitary products in schools out of very recently
in the uk now you do have to be a pupil i say this for a better experience all right
have you got any moss does anyone got any moss just standing on the school gates
or on the school roof scraping on
okay it is time for fact number three and that is my fact my fact this week is that
touch screens can now be operated using muffins oh wow finally well okay so this is a discovery by a
scientist in belgium called florian heller and he realized that the electrical field of a capacitive
touchscreen could be altered by using different materials so usually it'd be your finger or it'd
be a type of metal hence styluses um and he discovered that if you used a fresh out of the oven
muffin that the moisture was enough and the humidity was enough that it could be electrically
conductive to this particular type of screen okay so we can recognize it being touched and
that's the kind of one that you have on your phone most of them will be yeah yeah i did then spend
most of my research time going around my bedroom seeing how many objects work me too but actually
not around your bedroom around my house i did wonder what you were doing in here um there was
nothing surprising it's not very exciting i mean it's obviously stuff that you know conducts electricity
you know you're although i was quite excited that my spider plant does wow so if my spider
plant became conscious it could hack into my phone okay let me give you some examples and see if you
can guess whether they work a great yes yes yeah all right uh plumb yes no oh i think you're kind
of right as a group because it did work but it didn't work very well um a piece of alpaca poo
no oh my god you opened up our trophy in order to test this um a year or so ago we got an award
in Vienna which was a small vial of alpaca poo i opened it up and took up one of the little
currents of poo and tried to use my phone with it did it work or did it not work uh i'd say yes
there was a current with your current yeah it did not work oh it didn't work to try an egg
which bit of the egg the shell yeah just an egg just an egg from the fridge oh no no way no not in
shell not in shell you're right uh damp egg no i don't think that i'm gonna say yes oh definitely
put a bit of water on the egg and it works so anyway um thanks for listening to my tab talk
that's things that wow what an insight to your brain that you went from egg to damp egg like most
people would have moved on to the next object but one thing that's really interesting and i did try
this in my house but actually i read it on the internet is a battery so if you try and use a
battery to um operate your phone it will only work if you use the negative side of the battery
and if you use the positive side of the battery it won't work uh and that is the explanation really
of how these things work because you have a tiny little electrical difference in your finger uh
and that's what the phone can tell you know it's very very slightly charged your skin and that's
how it can tell the difference and so there's not a current it's not like there's a current
obviously running from the ground through you to your phone no it's like you know if you have static
electricity yeah um because you've been walking on a carpet or you've been rubbing a lot of balloons
against you or something then that you get a little shock um well that shock actually happens
all the time you always have that kind of tiny difference in electricity in your body like the
inside of your body is positively charged and the outside of your body is very slightly negatively
charged and that's what the phone can tell yeah so it's just connecting a circuit it's like putting
the crocodile clip on the circuit when you're at school your finger is literally connecting
that little circuit slight putting the damp egg on the on the stop saying damp egg so but is this
so when when you don't have you know when because some people or sometimes your finger
doesn't work on your phone it's really annoying and that is that due to your having more dead skin
for example so if you've got really thick skin does that damage it yes andy do you have zombie
fingers some people have this i don't know but if i was a lumberjack for example i might do yes
you're working for my company cheery archard exactly you'd need to get yourself a stylus
what is zombie fingers at her uh well it's for lumberjacks it's a particularly suffered by
lumberjacks and guitar players as well have it and yeah as if you've got very callous fingers
they're very dry so they're not conducting as well uh the recommendation is lick your finger
or if you are one particular woman let's use a damp egg just use a damp egg you can't quite get
because it's not very pointy is it um one woman got a refund on her chromebook because she insisted
that it just did not respond to her fingers wow okay so i didn't know this this is really cool
when they were making the iphone they still didn't have the keyboard touchscreen worked out the year
before it was launched and they developed this technique to work out what you're going to type
next to kind of predict it so if you hit t on your phone yeah the phone they they know that you're
likely to hit h next because of the word for example and there are all these probabilities
they can work out so when you've hit t what they call the hit region around the letter h on your
phone keyboard it grows a bit so that so it stays the same size to your eye and on the screen but
beneath it the technology knows that so there's this hit region around h which swells a bit and
then once you've hit t h the hit region around e will swell a bit so there's this quivering pulsating
map that we can't see what if you wanted to write tug or something like would it does it mean you're
more likely to make mistakes with more unusual letter pairs i think that's what it means but
fortunately we don't write tug much so i can't there are no words other there are no words
that they give tg i don't think uh no i might try typing tg on my phone now what if you were
typing the word cat gut that's got a tg brilliant brilliant why i should type that more often than
the word the technology it should have brought it up do you know who invented the touchscreen
it was a man called bent stumpy um no what stumpy what a first name for mr mr stumpy
he was an engineer at CERN and he was working with someone called frank beck uh and frank
beck asked bent stumpy um to solve the problem of to build some uh hardware for an intelligent
system which in just three console units would replace all the conventional buttons and switches
sorry i was just reading that but basically they wanted to get rid of all the buttons and
switches and replace them with a new system uh and bent stumpy went away and a few days later
he came back with three different solutions um one was a tracker ball one was a programmable
knob don't know exactly how the knob was programmable uh and the other one was a touchscreen
wow yeah he should be the steve johns of the time they probably said to him listen we'd love
to make you global famous but the name it's just not going to work mate no one's going to buy this
product and he wouldn't give it up he wouldn't give up the name no stumpy is s s t u n p e i think
it's stumpy it could be bent stump i'm not sure i think that's much better that was the only option
he offered them he was like okay i'll make it bent stump my final offer the first time that was used
was in air traffic control right when when that came along and then it just wasn't using anything
else for 30 years so it was in 1960 literally the mid 60s 1965 um and air traffic controllers used it
and they called it a touch wire display and it must have been so advanced in 1966 as an air traffic
controller there was one wire that's attached to a computer that's getting into information about
when all the planes are landing and what time and what platform um or whatever runway platform
and then the other end of the wire would connect to the screen and then the bottom of the screen
that wherever you touched it would touch a specific bit of wire that would transmit information back
and forth and they were doing this for 30 years and yet it wasn't until really the 80s the LA 80s
90s that it was incorporated into other tech it's amazing to think that jimmy henricks could have
used a touchscreen if he had worked in air traffic control but he couldn't have because he was a
guitar player so they wouldn't have worked for him. Oh my god! Brilliant yeah um stuff on muffins
or that? Oh if you've got yeah um so the british museum might have been established as a result of
a muffin. What? So you might know that the british museum was established by Sir Hans Sloan uh after
he died all of his collection were put into this new museum um because he had been collecting
these loads of weird things like antiquities rare books all sorts of stuff he kept them in his house
and then when it got too much in his house he bought a house next door and put it all in there
and he had loads of friends loads of famous friends who would come and like have dinner with him and
have a look at his amazing stuff um but once he was visited by Handel and Handel apparently put a
buttered muffin on one of his rare books and Sir Hans Sloan was absolutely furious about this and
he was like I can't have the place where I have my dinner parties in the same place as the place
where I have all my rare stuff so he bought a new place out in Chelsea and he put everything in there
and it became a little museum of its own rights rather than a house and then it was all the stuff
from there that became the british museum wow that's awesome yeah do you think Handel was just
being very ahead of his time and trying to operate what he thought was a kind of amazing touchscreen
muffin okay it is time for our final fact of the show and that is Anna my fact this week is that
in 2012 Southwest Airlines agreed to fly a single butterfly 2000 miles after it overslept and missed
its ride oh it's adorable it is what a good service to have offered this was uh this is a
problem with this butterfly spotted by a woman called Marilyn Manos Jones she was in Albany New
York and she saw in her garden a monarch butterfly and she happened to be a butterfly expert so she
knew that it was well she was watching it from like metamorphosis stage and she knew it was
metamorphosing too late so often when the caterpillars go into their chrysalis stage
they'll sometimes wait it out too long emerge late they'll emerge a bit damaged a bit unhealthy if
they're slow to develop she expected it to be like this and a lost cause but it came out
big hearty healthy she said and she knew that its swammates had already flown south because that's
what they do for the winter to get some warmer climate and so she panicked and she thought well
this guy isn't going to survive the winter up here in New York so she rang up Southwest Airlines
obviously and she said can you carry this guy to Texas please where it can cross the border into
Mexico and join its friends and they agreed so what did they they didn't give it a seat and you know
I think they made it share her seat which is I guess you do that with babies don't you yeah
you can put them on your lap if there's a problem with the flights when you're flying you have to
put your own gas mask on before you put your butterflies gas mask on that's absolutely right
would have been hell to put gas mask on it because it was wrapped in about 17 different layers so
they packed it up in this like glass scene which is like very light transparent paper and an envelope
made of that with a damp piece of cotton then they put it in a Tupperware then in another container
with an ice pack to keep it cool and calm stop it panicking and then they put that container into
a bag that was padded out with layers of newspaper and towels and it sat on her lap and flew all the
way down to San Antonio and then popped out joined its friends and flew further south into South Mexico
do we know it made it or did do we just have records up to the point at which she released
this butterfly and then it got eaten by a bird immediately yeah she released it and then we
believe it probably survived although we don't have confirmation it hasn't sent any postcards
but did she have to find the swarm in this bit of America so she just let it off assuming that it
would cross the border on its own and finish the it knows where to go it's a big risk no I get I get
that but it's sort of not seeing it to its you know it's if you're trying to return it has to be a
missing there's to be a point at which you give up on this story and you give up on the like this is
not practical you can't fly all the way to the swarm it's like one of those easy jet flights
sometimes to get to Barcelona you have to go to an airport that's 200 miles from Barcelona
everyone knows that yeah I think I'm with you Dan she's lazy you've got it you've got to see it
through he could just be dropping up a bar in Texas still I think she's actually gone above and
beyond what was required and I think if we all did this it would you know forever it would
exactly what Greta Thunberg would say you know we're talking about one single instance where
she did three quarters of the trip yeah and has no idea if it paid off there's no end to this story
I don't think she should have done it either dad no I know so I do three quarters it makes no sense
I think that this is a wonderful heartwarming story that Pixar needs to get on immediately
you know the butterfly that's left behind in cold new york and has to get to sounds yes yeah it
has a champion who says I'll get you there but then only gets them three quarters of the way
there and says all right off your part wherever you want that's a twist halfway through that's the
low point yeah most of the way through the film in all those films there is a low point like where
Paddington leaves his family temporarily in Paddington one or when Paddington is sent to prison
in Paddington two or I could go on um you can get we must have said before that you can get
butterflies that drink tears of animals but also humans but you also get blood feeding
sweat feeding and tear feeding butterflies so for these butterflies that woman who was
bleeding out of her eyes it must have been it's a banquet it's a banquet it's a three course meal
it's one of those world buffet grills where you have 20 different cuisine styles all served at
the same buffet exactly um the blood ones are quite interesting um because they will actually
pierce your skin like to get your blood uh generally not with humans um generally with
other animals although it can happen with humans and it what they think is they evolved from
fruit eating moths and butterflies and they would pierce the skin of the fruits to get at
the juicy stuff inside and they evolved into blood drinking moths and butterflies so will
they just be drinking the blood of little ants and stuff usually they'll drink like proper they'll
drink proper mammal blood for sure uh it's only the males who do it uh and it's same with tears
actually only males will drink the tears of animals and that's because they're trying to get the
sodium from the animal which can be in the blood or in the tears but the females they get the
sodium directly from the male during mating so they don't need to get it from the from the
other animals they get it through the yeah second hand they get second hand sodium yeah cool um I
read this amazing thing about monarch butterflies which astounds me and this is part of actually
their big migration that they do uh when they're going south and it is the fact that they have to
one point in this huge journey they have to cross lake superior and lake superior biggest lake in
the world it's it's ginormous and that is a huge moment of the trip where they really have to go
gung-ho on it and this really odd thing happens that biologists have been looking into for quite
a long time which is they all fly in this sort of straight line and then out of nowhere they take
a turn to the east and they fly east for a while and then they turn back flying south again
and they they haven't known why and they're still not completely sure but the latest theory
is that it's a memory of the past from old days when they were traveling down
and there used to be there must have been a jutting out mountainous bit in lake superior
and it's a memory that this is where we take a right I remember when we used to go on holiday
when I was a kid and my dad would drive us many many hundreds of miles to where we were going
on holiday and he'd always be driving around going I'm sure there was a service station around here
exactly so they think there was something there that was blocking the path for generations and
generations and then it went but they still in their head go oh this is where we take a right
to get away from the blocky thing even though nothing is there there would be evidence wouldn't
there that there had been a mountain here or something yeah I mean there would be right
you'd think but they can't explain they just don't know why they take a right there that's
amazing yeah wow that's so cool the species evidence of a previous mountain that must have
been missing for a while now it must be some thousands of years where's it gone yeah that's
very cool I wonder who's in charge of the sat nav there who's jabbing the muffin at the I don't like
jabbing the muffin at all that's a phrase so how many butterflies do you think there are in the
natural history museum dead ones I mean okay um I guess three thousand come on three thousand three
twenty five fifty thousand fifty thousand you're gonna have to go quite a lot higher than that
oh 500 000 keep going keep going 100 million oh no yeah you went too far there are eight million
712 000 dead butterflies and moths in the natural history museum uh there in the glass-fronted cases
that if laid out on the floor they would cover around 30 football pitches which is about 10 times
bigger than that ship that got stuck in the Suez Canal oh my word which at the moment is a very
on-topic reference but probably in two weeks time everyone will have forgotten it the collection
began with Walter and Charles Rothschild uh who were amateur entomologists and they gave
more than two million butterflies and moths to the natural history museum it's too many you don't
want that many it well maybe but Walter Rothschild used to say that of the two million more than
two million butterflies he didn't have a single duplicate in his entire collection oh come on
what it can't be true right I've got like packets of football stickers with a duplicate in the same
packet it can't be true two million with no duplicates amazing wow that's so good rubbish
some of them have bullet holes in them don't they this is how this is how they used to collect
butterflies in the olden days yeah even at the turn of the 20th century even though we're still
doing it so the specimen that the natural history museum has are for instance the largest butterfly
in the world um was collected by shotgun in 1906 by a guy called Albert Stuart Meek who sounds not
very meek if he's going around machine gunning butterflies down how big was it Anna because
that you can get quite big butterflies right this one has a 20 centimeter wingspan and the biggest
of its kind has a 26 centimeter that's big that's very big it's a biggie um still thinks like feels
like a shotgun would obliterate it they use special ammo I mean I'm sure you could just get a net it
feels like um using a sledge ammo to crack a nut but they use special butterfly friendly ammo not
friendly to the butterfly itself but friendly to the shape of its wing oh there are people who um
aim to wipe out butterflies like the New Zealand government oh they are the first New Zealand is
the first country to eradicate a butterfly within its own territory deliberately a single species
or a single species called the great white butterfly which uh they eat the rare crests of
New Zealand I didn't know that was a problem in New Zealand but get this out of 79 Kiwi crests 57
are at risk of extinction and these bastard butterflies were eating them so the New Zealand
government said no we are going to destroy this butterfly in New Zealand because it's it's plenty
for us around the world so they conducted 263 000 searches they offered a bounty for of ten dollars
for every dead great white butterfly you turned in what if you don't like bounties uh then you get a
galaxy or a twirl um and they released wasps that hunted them and they did this for about four years
this savage butterfly hunt and they found no more they declared that they had uh won
oh makes them sound like really bad guys and I'm happy because the New Zealand government
has got a lot of good press the last year and a half and it's about time someone brought them down
as butterfly murderers yeah what's this is this pre-jocinda or is this going to be a stain on her
career no this is 2010 to 2014 I think that the campaign was happening so it didn't sound very
jocinda it's not a stain it's the rare crests think of the rare crests that are on the verge of
extinction rest of all the fucking things you can kill a butterfly ball some crest I got a
so plus some egg sandwiches without just very quickly back to the original fact 2012 was when
this story happened when the butterfly was taken by plane it was a bit of a big year for taking
singular animals that were migrating and were left behind on uh in the news so there was a story in
England this also in 2012 a cuckoo was found badly injured in a garden and was transported by British
airways along with the person who found it to churrin to join the migration of the other cuckoos
that had already set off and they knew that it was the last of the cuckoos to fly away because it
was tagged so while the butterfly was being flown almost to Mexico this this cuckoo was being flown
to churrin to meet up with the migrating cuckoos and then over in Russia again in 2012 there was
a migration of endangered Siberian white cranes that weren't quite finding their way so Vladimir
Putin got into a motorized hand glider and dressed up in garb that sort of emulated the white crane
and tried to steer them unsuccessfully unfortunately but he was flying above them trying to get them
to follow him and start migrating but then Putin said you crane and then they misrepresented
it and ended up going into Crimea very strong animal okay that's it that is all of our facts
thank you so much for listening if you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the
things that we have said over the course of this podcast we can be found on our twitter accounts
i'm on @shriberland james @jamesharkin andy @andrewhunterm and Anna you can even podcast at
qi.com yep or you can go to our group account which is @no such thing or you can go to our website
no such thing as a fish.com all of our previous episodes were up there also check out all of the
videos from our 20 hour comic relief marathon they are now all online all 35 videos have a watch
and please do donate to the cause if you can comicrelief.com/fish is where you'll find our just
giving page um it will really help some people out all right we'll see you again next week guys
with another episode goodbye