(mechanical beeping)
(speaking in foreign language)
(electronic music)
Hi, Andy.
- Hello, Andy.
- Hey, guys.
Welcome to Drop us a Line.
Welcome to you at home.
Welcome to the viewers.
Welcome to the listeners.
Welcome to those who are experiencing this
solely through touch or smell.
The astral plane.
Welcome to those shooting it from the astral plane.
Yeah, right.
Let's have some emails.
We've had some great ones.
Thank you for sending them in.
Podcast at qi.com if you do want to send one in.
Let's start off.
Jonas Beederman from Basel, Switzerland.
- Basel.
Is it Basel?
- Or Barl, if you from the French speaking part.
- Sorry.
- But yeah, not Basel.
Which is how Americans pronounce Basel.
- I'm absolutely gutted because I was really,
I checked about Beederman and how you pronounce that.
- And I tripped over.
- I mean, I met people in Switzerland
might ride to me, but I have been that.
- Basel, yeah, yeah.
- Basel.
- There's a famous football team from there as well.
- I stepped over the rake and then I tripped
over the safety pin.
They're so annoying.
- Jonas, sorry Jonas.
Right.
I am a long time club fischer and fervent admirer
of Andy's sections from the evergreens
like spicy meat and thanks, but no thanks,
to the more short-lived cult classics.
(laughing)
Like the sausage parlor, Russian droppers of line,
and of course, the incest zone.
(laughing)
Which I think we have, we've done all of it.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yes.
A while back you mentioned getting stings slash jingles made
for the various sections.
I'm sure you have already been inundated
with fan creations that you quite sensibly refuse
to play on the show.
We haven't really, Jonas.
It was a call out.
We got a couple of them.
- I remember it.
- Yeah.
- But here is some more.
- Great.
- No AI was harmed in the making of these,
though I did use virtual sampler instruments
for some of them.
- That's allowed.
I'm proud to say that I was able to play
the bassoon sections entirely without sheet music.
(laughing)
So I thought let's lead in.
Let's have a cup.
Let's sprinkle these through the show.
- Okay.
- So can you guys earphone up?
I've said them too on WhatsApp.
You haven't heard them yet.
So just have a little, set yourselves up now.
Okay.
I'd like you to play now the one that's labeled
extreme fish.
- Okay.
- We'll play it at home.
Okay.
Ready?
One, two, three.
(upbeat music)
- Time for minutes.
It's extremely fish.
(laughing)
- That's very good.
- It's very good.
- Isn't it?
- Is that me doing the raw?
- It is.
- It sounds like me.
- Yeah.
So yeah, very metal.
- And by leather sampling.
- Yeah, really good.
- Why have I not been sampled?
Am I not metal enough?
- You might come up in a...
- Oh yeah.
- It was soft fish or something.
Stinky old fish.
(laughing)
'Cause I'm probably the one who's been
to a Metal gig most recently out of the three of us.
- What did you go for?
- I went to watch ice-nine kills.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
- So they're a metal band who they take horror films.
- They're great songs based on the horror films.
- They're very cool.
But way too loud and shouty for my ears.
- Well, so anyway, thank you Janice.
That was the, well, you're the metal aficionado.
That's the...
- Yeah, I thought it was as far as metal music goes.
Nine out of tab.
- Right.
Well, Christie from the Gold Coast in Queensland
has some extreme fish for us.
- Okay.
- Great.
- So in Reason Drops of the Line,
you heard from Caleb in Montana
who plays fish out loud while hiking
to scare away bears.
- Yes.
- You remember this.
He also mentioned Bear Bells,
which are these jangli little alarms.
I don't think there's an actual cloche.
The jangli little alarms,
I guess you use to let bears know humans are nearby.
So this just struck a chord with Christie
because my partner and teenage kids
recently went skiing in Japan.
I suggested they invest in Bear Bells,
but their Japanese friends confirmed bears
have been a big problem this past year,
especially in northern Japan.
- Wow.
- Kind of there's been a bad acorn harvest
and they've been sort of looking in towns
for food basically.
- Right.
- So it does in deaths, lots of injuries.
- Oh dear.
- On hearing my suggestion,
their friends Mum put me in my place.
She warned us that curious bears
are now being attracted to Bear Bells.
- Oh really?
- Instead of human nearby,
they now hear room service.
So hikers are basically being told
that to be loud and boisterous instead.
- Yeah.
But then eventually the bears will get used to that, right?
Because presumably what happens is they hear the bell
and then one bear goes up and finds,
actually I got a kick-cat from that person.
- Yes.
- So then the future they go again,
but then they change it to podcasts.
But then eventually they'll start getting attracted
to podcasts and they'll have to find something else.
- Yeah, you're right.
- Maybe that's a music.
- Yeah, you're absolutely right.
Well, Christy Finishes,
the Japanese member of your team,
hand-to-moo-ray,
might be able to tell you more.
(laughing)
- We got it out.
- Yeah, that's Christy.
- It was wonderful.
- Yeah, so Bear Acorns,
that's the surprising bit of the diet
for a bear that I didn't know about.
- No.
- Yeah, what did you think they at Picnic baskets?
(laughing)
- I'd like jars of honey
that they can have. - Chas of honey?
- Chas of honey?
- Have they been lying to us in these great cartoons?
- No, that's very cool,
'cause you would think you would solve that immediately
by importing a bunch of acorns
and helicopter-dropping them over the areas
that Bear has live in.
- I guess so, I guess, for whatever reason,
that's been rejected as an idea.
- Oh, no one's thought of it yet.
- 'Cause there's been a bad acorn harvest.
Where are you getting these acorns from?
- The countries.
- Bring 'em in. - Bring 'em in.
- Bring 'em in.
- We have them coming out of our ears
in London, the acorns.
- Who's the leading Avelace about trees?
- There we go.
- So what we need to do is helicopter some,
I guess you'd use long distance,
you'd use a plane for the first leg
of the journey, wouldn't you, from bringing to Japan?
- Yeah, I don't think I'm saying it just to get anything wild.
- No.
Jonathan Negus writes,
"Can I just check James' thoughts on reflection
"of the phrase?
"You don't have any nerves in your brain,
"so you wouldn't even feel it."
This was about a month you biting you in the brain.
- Absolutely.
- And so my understanding is that
if someone touches your brain, you can't feel it.
Now, I was going off memories, so maybe I'm wrong.
- Well, I think there's a middle path here.
Jonathan writes, "I'm but a lowly orthopedic surgeon
"spending my days replacing worn out Australian knees
"in Sydney, but I believe the brain is in fact
"mostly made up of nerves."
- Oh.
- "I'm presuming he meant sensory or pain receptors."
- Yep.
- It's a technicality.
(laughing)
You see, I don't want to be the person on this show
that just fights back against the audience
to see what a bullshit email too often.
- No.
- And so when I occasionally think that in my head,
I kind of hold it back, but actually in this case,
I didn't, did I?
- No, but it's nice that you occasionally,
I think you can't just be, you can't just roll over every time.
- No.
- You've got a reputation to maintain.
So I think it's fine.
I think it's fine for you to do that.
- Okay, now fair enough.
I guess.
- Yeah.
- Don't fight.
- Really good fight.
- I think it is pretty amazing that a monkey could
bite your brain and you wouldn't feel that.
- That is pretty astonishing.
- You know, it was happening.
- You'd probably, there would be other signs.
- It's very rare that a monkey bites someone's brain
in a controlled environment where they're screened
from the monkey and the top of their skull's been taken off
by a surgical tube and then a monkey's got into the brain.
- Somehow made it into the ring.
- So I was, where was this in the pole
and I was sat by some river and I'm just sort of sitting there
with my bag by my side and reading my book
and the monkey's kind of got really close
and tried to get into my bag
without me even noticing they were there.
- That's pretty good.
- So if the back of my skull was open
and there was something, you know, they were hungry for brain,
then I can actually imagine them getting relatively close
without me noticing.
- Wow.
- There you go.
- It's a good point.
- It's an if, if the back of your brain was open
but you've been allowed to go on holiday.
Anyway, yeah, we'll finish the operation
and the bet is to harking but it's five o'clock.
So it flights to Kathmandu leaves.
It's just half an hour, you better get out there.
- It was it was irresponsible of you
to book the holidays so close to your major brain surgery.
- It's actually good to air it out
before we close it up.
- Don't pick it.
All right, just let it get a nice air ring.
- Yeah.
Are you going to any monkey infested areas
just to carry us any?
- Right, I've had one.
You've had one.
Rachel Bobo writes in for Dan.
- How do you spell Bobo?
- As it sounds.
- B-O-B-O, great.
- Wow.
- Of clown fame.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It just makes so much sense
that my one's from someone called Bobo.
(laughing)
- She writes, sniff my flower.
- She doesn't.
- I imagine you've already received quite a few emails.
Hopefully not rodeo clown numbers
about Elvis Presley's birthplace.
As my cat phrase on this show, Rachel,
I'm afraid not you are the first.
But as a local, I felt my duty to correct Dan.
Elvis was born in Tupelo, Mississippi,
not Memphis, Tennessee.
Not sure about Alan Titchmars, though.
- I don't recall this.
- I'm afraid I don't remember saying that at all.
I must have, obviously.
- I know.
- Yeah, apologies.
But there you go.
He moved to Memphis to pursue music
when he was in his late teens.
- Interesting.
It must have been in the Tom Allen show.
- Yeah.
- Because that's when we met mention that.
- Yes.
- And we were talking about, yeah, the dancing.
- Oh, I see.
That was what happened.
I said he had something in common with Alan Titchmars.
And Dan, I think, said,
"Oh, they were both in prison or something."
Or maybe you also said they were both born in Memphis.
- Yeah, maybe.
- Yeah.
- So it was a joke.
- Sounds like it.
- It doesn't, I mean, it doesn't sound like it, but yeah.
(laughing)
- Sounds like a really good one.
- That's fair enough.
Right, we've all three had one.
- But there's a bonus hook.
- Oh, it's a whole hook lurking in the water.
Dan Latham writes, "Long time listener, first time nitpicker.
"I was listening to no such thing as an Eton Oyster."
Oh, the release at the end of December.
And in it, I believe it was Andy who said
that the Chartres recipe is known by only two monks.
- Oh, yeah.
- I felt it was my duty to correct you,
especially as I've now been living in this part of France
for five years, and I've been on the tour
of the Cav de la Chartres twice,
which are the not caves in the English,
they're sort of sellers for making it
where they aged the alcohol.
My correction is there are in fact three monks
who know the recipe.
(laughing)
- And what's happened is the third monk come in
and...
- He's walked it out.
- He's walked it, he's burst in
while they're having their secret weekly meeting
where they go over the ingredients.
(laughing)
- He says to avoid stalemates in arguments.
- Oh, yeah.
- Oh, maybe.
- They just need a third.
- I don't think they're allowed to change the recipe.
I don't think if you know the secret recipe,
you could just put any old shed in it, no.
But apparently on the tour,
a downland that in order to protect the recipe, what?
- They can't fly on the same flight together.
- They're not allowed to travel together.
- Is it?
- Yeah.
- But now when there's three of them,
presumably two of them can go on a nice
caravan holiday or something like that
because the third one's still there.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- So that's maybe the reason why they got a third person.
- They can go monkey spotting in the pool.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so thank you, Dan.
- Can I do a thing where it was an error that I said,
and I want to send you a WhatsApp?
- Oh, great.
- So this is Dan mentioned on the podcast.
Why has a football team never had a sponsor
on the inside of the kit?
So that when you score and you put your share over your head,
you can see the advert.
- Yeah.
- It's really good.
(laughing)
- And the person called Andrew Vazano
wrote to us with this catafi kit.
- Incredible.
- Where they're sponsored by Burger King.
And when you pull the shirt over your head,
you can see the Burger King face
where your face would normally be.
- So good.
- I wasn't aware there was a Burger King face.
- Well, you know.
- No, I didn't know that that was one part of the.
- I didn't know that was the King.
- Yeah.
- So it's the actual Burger King.
So Macdonald has Ronald Macdonald.
This is the King of the Vegas.
- Wow.
- Well, yeah.
- Brilliant.
- I think it was from the '90s.
- Wow.
- Bring it back.
- Oh, cool.
- Brilliant.
We now come to our regular section.
Apologies to the armed forces.
(laughing)
Merlin Lewis.
- We've had another Merlin race name.
Maybe it was the same one.
- Yeah.
Merlin's coming back as a name.
- Or it did 30 or 40 years ago.
However, this Merlin shell Drake
is a big selling answer at the moment.
- Yeah.
- No, it's huge.
- You shout Merlin on in any crowded night club.
And it's a nightmare.
- You go to the one's I go to.
- Yeah.
- The Druid Society in Morgan.
- Merlin writes, "I'm listening to you talk with Tom Allen
"and would urge you to reconsider your position
"on the artist's rifles."
- Do you remember this?
- Oh, yeah.
- Okay.
- So Noel Coward.
Noel Coward briefly served in this regiment
in the First World War.
And then he quickly sort of got a bit ill.
- And Tom said that actually it was a place
where you put the less useful people
because they were in the arts and they went straight in there.
And actually I'd read that as well.
And I thought it was true.
- Quite the reverse it turns out.
'Cause they're better known these days as 21 SAS.
- Okay.
- The artist's rifles was Merlin writes
an extraordinary regiment in which imaginative
outside the box and sometimes flamboyant individuals
were embraced by the army to allow genuine innovation.
And it started in 1860 and all sorts of people.
Ed Woodburn Jones, William Morris, Frederick Layton,
Holman Hunt, all sorts of really famous artists were in there.
And then they were sort of disbanded
and then became the SAS in one of those weird ways
that regiments kept us banded and then reformed
and murdered all that.
But basically the artist's rifles
is now a historical way of referring to the SAS.
So they're quite tough.
- Okay, well, come at us.
- Merlin or the SAS?
(laughing)
- Yeah, but anyway, so they sound very cool.
I'm gonna read up more about that.
- Yeah, really good.
I hadn't heard that.
- Time for some real life.
- Really?
- Real life.
Matthew Price writes a quick clarification
inspired by James Harkin, not a telling off.
In episode 577, he joked about the idea of getting a barge
with his wife in Venice.
Do you remember that?
It was very funny.
- Yeah, we were talking about getting a gondola
and he was like, oh, we got a barge, you know.
It was funny.
It was really good.
- I'm a funny guy.
- Yeah.
- Sounds like a joke.
- It was a good joke.
(laughing)
- We were talking about barges
and then James joked about getting a barge.
It was great.
- Yeah, to be there.
- I can't believe you guys have forgotten that.
It was so good.
I'm delighted to report, writes Matthew,
that a hotel barge does operate in Venice.
- Is that so?
- So he never say never.
- It's fully licensed.
And Matthew is a certified deckhand.
And you wondered, I think,
a hundred episodes before that James,
whether it was a good thing
that people had stopped learning how to barge.
And Matthew says, I feel duty-bound report.
The barging is still very much taught across Europe.
- Is that true?
- Yeah, complete with exams, salty instructors
and the traditional shouting at lock gates.
(laughing)
- So good.
And he works as a tour guide in France
on a British First World War munitions carrier
that has been converted into a floating hotel.
- Wow.
- Yeah, I love barges, really.
I don't know why I've been so down on them over the years.
- Apparently you have.
- Yeah.
- And Matthew's kept the receipts.
(laughing)
- And he invited us to do an episode of float on this barge.
- Where is it again?
- France.
- Sounds good.
- It does sound good, doesn't it?
- What about the one in Venice?
- He doesn't work on that one,
but it does also sound good, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- We could just do a barge tour.
- That'd be great.
- Oh my god.
- How many people do you think you can feel on a barge?
How many?
- I think I looked at the one,
and it's about 20 people on the one that we've been saying.
- Okay, well, to be honest, when we played Paris,
it wasn't that many more than that.
(laughing)
- They won't be swarming the gangplanks trying to get on board.
We might hit 15 to 20 tops.
- Oh, that was because in our European tour,
we had a tour booking company who booked it all,
and we know we're all of our listeners up.
We know where you are.
- We know.
- Because we can see our stats, right?
- Yeah.
- And they said we don't have many listeners in Paris,
and we were like, oh, we really want to go to Paris.
There's a great expat community there,
and it turned out they were absolutely right.
- Yeah.
- Paris and Berlin, and we were like,
how is that even possible?
- There are two flamboyant cathedrals, you know.
- Yeah.
- Well, there's hands out.
People don't have better things to do.
- Yeah.
- Kevin Edge writes,
(laughing)
- I've been in YouTube for many years,
and no one has ever asked my first name.
(laughing)
- Me either, it says Darrell Bono.
- On your latest podcast,
you seemed to know whether spoons quite well.
Good and bad, I think this is pointing at you mostly, Dan.
Did you know there is a whether spoons top trumps?
They were on sale before Christmas at my local
Colwyn Bay picture house spoons.
The sort of properties of the things include
year-opened pub size, and of course,
number of steps to the toilet.
(laughing)
- It's famous whether spoons for,
usually the toilets are an absolute trek away
from the bar.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, and lots of them.
- I've not heard that.
- I don't know that.
- Maybe it's ones in a North that are like that.
- No, no, no.
It is, think about it now.
- Yeah.
- But, I mean, surely number of steps to the toilet
is a movable property.
- Yes.
- If you get there nice and early,
you can get the table right back right by the toilet.
- There are no toilets by the,
there are no tables by the toilets, right?
You can get a table by the bottom of the stairs,
but they have to walk all the way up the stairs
through a load of corridors to find the toilet.
- Oh, just a pristine table for Valentine's Day love.
(laughing)
- That sounds great.
So it's for two, yes.
Do you have anything a bit closer to the toilets?
(laughing)
- I'd be willing to make it worth your while.
We're gonna be drinking a lot of ruddles.
(laughing)
- And yeah, okay, so thank you Kevin.
- Well, I don't know if weather spoons
are a friend of the podcast or an enemy
of the podcast on this show.
- Yes.
- I think we've got no official position on weather spoons.
- Well, I think Dan has a very positive position.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And the absolute sanders and other members of the team
have a more negative position.
- I feel I have a position on the owner,
who I'm not a fan of.
Anytime I go into one, everyone's very nice in there.
So I feel rude saying anything against them.
And Ramsgate happens to have an extraordinary one
on the beach, and so it's worth it for the location.
- Yeah, yeah.
We have talked about it a lot over the years, haven't we?
The carpets, remember, they've all got
at the spot of the interesting carp design.
Is that on the top trump card?
- It must be.
- Yeah.
- Maybe it would be on the back of the card.
Oh, that's nice.
- 'Cause then everyone would know what cards you had.
- Doesn't matter in top jumps.
- Does it matter if everyone knows what you've got?
- Oh, yeah.
- The only thing is that you keep on winning
and getting more, yeah.
Anyway, thank you, Kevin.
- Much like capitalism in that way.
And so probably why the guy who wants weather spoons
likes it so much.
- Come at us Tim Martin.
Michaela Comperi writes,
you mentioned recently in the last drop of the line
that Tim Hortons doesn't have an apostrophe.
- Yes.
- 'Cause of Quebec language laws.
- That's right.
It might have been in little fish actually.
- Oh, you might be right.
And it reminded me of my favorite
French language law story.
A comedian took out billboards in Quebec
that said, quotes,
"For Christmas, I'd like a complaint
"from the office de la langue from says
"within 48 hours he received the complaint
"and had to change the science
"because you're not allowed to put up big signs
"in English, I suppose."
- Oh, okay.
- "I had to change the signs to Pornowel,
"get a complaint de la langue from says."
- Do we know who the comic was?
- No.
- Michaela Michela has sent a link, which I haven't followed.
- And is that to get publicity
basically for the show in the long run?
- I guess so.
- Yeah, I guess so.
- Is that what I've been in the newspapers?
- It's an interesting practice.
I used to work somewhere and I won't say where,
but they tried to constantly get MPs
to sort of ask for the banning of a specific comedy thing
in the House of Lords so that it would make the papers.
They would actively pursue them to talk them into doing it.
- Oh, we think, James.
Truth or lie?
- How interesting.
I'm just trying to think of all the people
I know where you've worked over the years.
- I know, I can't.
- I can't.
- Yeah.
- It's been two places, QI in here.
- Right.
But basically, and Evan from Vancouver,
we've had a lot of correspondence from Canada
about the Quebec language police,
the Okwuf, office quibikwa, Dilla Longfran says,
'cause they've done a lot of stuff over the years
that's been a bit too outsiders, bananas.
- Bananas.
- Very good, great point.
They find a restaurant called the pub Burgundy Lion
because it was not French enough,
despite pub Burgundy and Lion all being French words.
They told an Italian restaurant they needed
to translate pasta into French.
- I know a French people call like a bar la pub.
I've seen that in places,
but I would still say that was an English word, really.
- I think so.
I think you can't have the word part of France.
But basically, one last anecdote that comes from a friend
of mine is wife used to earn a shop in Montreal
and she does not speak French.
She received a violation notice from the Okwuf.
However, she did not know what she violated
since they will not correspond in English.
(all laughing)
- It sounds very entertaining.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So thank you, thank you everyone who wrote in about that.
That sounds great. - Very good, very good.
- We've got, we've got ham fish now.
New section.
- Ham fish. - Oh, new section, okay.
- Ham fish did.
- Oh. - Like as in,
you do something that's really good.
- Is that what it's about?
- Is this in relation to McKellen
or the oldest ham?
- It's in relation to the oldest ham.
- Oh, I see.
- So we mentioned the oldest ham.
Charlie Tuff has updated us on the oldest ham in Oxford
that we talked about, which is not the other oldest ham
we talked about, but we did talk about the one
in the covered market in Oxford.
- And we were wondering whether it was still there.
- Yeah.
- Well, the butchers who displayed it,
emfeller and daughter,
closed their shop in the covered market back in early 2023.
I can't find any online presence for the butchers after that.
The fate of the ham is currently unknown.
- Wow.
- So let's start a ham hunt.
- Yeah.
If you know where that ham might be, drop us a line.
- 'Cause we need to get us out some press, guys,
and I'm thinking if we find the oldest ham,
surely that's good for something.
- I think we put it up in Quebec
with a sign saying oldest ham in English.
(laughing)
- And get down to mention campaign against it
in the House of Lords.
- Yeah.
Interesting.
Yeah.
- Yeah.
- I imagine they just threw it out.
- Do you?
- I do.
- I don't know.
- No.
- You're crazy.
It's not gonna be an historical ham.
Submitted to a museum, surely.
- Oh, damn.
I can't believe you've not been in the inbox, still.
- What?
- No.
- Okay, 'cause this is so exciting.
And in fact, this is the big Marmalade dropper
of this show, I would say.
- Okay.
- Ben Murray.
- What is that?
- Marmalade dropper.
- Yeah.
- Is it like an exciting news story?
Have you not heard of that?
- No.
- 'Cause you're eating your breakfast and you've got what?
- Yeah.
- It's a newspaper term for a great story.
- That's great.
- You would probably call it a cocoa pop splasher.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Whoa!
(laughing)
- Well, Ben Murray writes, long time listen
at first time emailer, I've just heard today's episode
of Little Fish and was extremely surprised to hear the fact
about the world's oldest ham only being dated 1902.
- Oh yeah.
- This is because I look after museum collections
in Hampshire, Hampshire, and have both seen and smelt
what I believe is a much older ham currently sat
in one of our stores.
- Wow.
- Please see the picture attached.
Our record for this ham states that it was one
of a pair of ham's cured in 1875,
one of which got eaten to celebrate Queen Victoria's
golden Jubilee in 1877.
- Yeah.
- No, 1830 golden Jubilee, 1887 would have been, yeah.
The other made its way to the Hampshire museum service
in 1971, and here it is.
- I mean, it's a very old ham.
- That's an old ham.
- Ben writes, I thought it was worth correcting this fact
from years ago because I believe the world deserves to know
about factually correct old ham's.
- I think you should go there and do a video
like an Instagram video.
- I'd love to.
I'd really love to.
I hope it, I hope it's still there, of course it's still there.
(laughing)
- I'm so sorry, we just, we just had it.
- Honestly, it was a bit stale.
- Glad to be with Broken D.
(laughing)
- Who ate the oldest ham?
- Oh dear, anyway, thank you very much, lovely.
So that's the ham fist section.
Right, now, get those headphones back in.
We're going back to Jonas.
Who has produced a rodeo clown jingle.
One, two, three, go.
- Okay.
- It's rodeo clown time.
(upbeat music)
- Right, it's good, we're rodeo clown.
rodeo clown of the week.
- Yeah, I mean.
- No, no. - No, it's Yihar.
- Is that me?
- I think it's you.
- Am I just making sounds?
- All the way through.
- All the way through, I podcast, I'm not aware of it.
- I mean, James does the edit.
I'll defer to him on this.
- Again, interesting that I'm not at all.
(laughing)
I do want the Yoda Siff.
You've had some forgotten about a member of the team.
A crucial member of the team.
(laughing)
- That's true.
- He doesn't say in his email.
I've tried to cover everybody.
(laughing)
- I don't think you not being in it
is worse than me being the guy who just goes,
"Are you hot?"
(laughing)
(screaming)
- Showing our episodes.
(laughing)
- You've got to give Yoda something to work with, James.
You need to make some silly noises.
'Cause it's easy for me,
'cause I'm the guy who says rodeo clown.
So he's got a sample me.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Ham.
That's for a future one.
- Right.
- He's really good.
(laughing)
I'll be honest, guys.
I'm not sure how frequently Ham fished it.
It's going to be part of the regular lineup.
I think it's going to be more like the incessant zone,
which is an occasional friend.
Does anyone in your family listen to this show?
- They do, and it's why I've stopped telling those stories.
(laughing)
- I mean, they're not stories, sorry.
It's why I stopped making up fake.
(laughing)
I think that's going on further with this.
- It is, in fact, yet again, true.
(laughing)
- Right.
The rodeo clown of the week is about
something we said in the Newdy Code, was he called?
- Oh yeah, yeah.
So again, this was the Tom Allen episode.
And Newdy is the guy who made suits.
- Yeah.
- Rhyne stones, he put rhyne stones on clothes.
- Rhyme, also.
- The song Rhyne Stone Cowboy is off the back.
It's a tribute to Newdy Cohen and the clothes he designed.
- Can you guys remember what he said?
He started his career doing.
- Lost right?
- Oh, I know what it is.
I said, because I'm from the north, that he made pasties.
- Selling pasties to strippers?
- Yeah.
- Well, Mabel Syrup writes.
- Maybe not a real name, I guess.
- Thrilled to hear you talk a bit about rhyne stones
and pasties, both topics close to my heart,
but I need to clarify, is definitely pronounced pasties
when you're referring to the nipple covering.
Although you wouldn't be the first to notice
the glorious possibilities of pasty themed pasties.
- Micredentials, seven years of wearing pasties
as a burlesque performer.
Do let me know if you'd like some fish-themed ones.
- Yes, please.
- Obviously.
- Or any tips on twirling.
I'm sure I could make that happen.
- I think we could get a lot more people to our French shows
if we all came up wearing burlesque.
- Yes.
- Absolutely.
- Yeah, my friend Chris Buddle, he wrote to me saying,
he'd made a lot of pasties in his time
and that we pronounced that wrong, yeah.
Well anyway, this has been the Radio Canal of the Week.
Thanks also to Indiana Split, another burlesque artist
who said it is pronounced pasties
and is a big faux pas among the burlesque community
to mispronounce it.
- Oh really?
- Fair enough.
Big shimmies, Indiana Split.
So thanks to Lizzie B. Elaine, Mary, and Colorado
and John Petra, who have all had the moment in the inbox.
- I do like, we get to discover
not only you love locations of people.
- I love locations.
- I love a location.
I love a territory of work that we suddenly have
a huge fan base in that we might not know about.
So burlesque dancers as a merge now is,
that's really cool.
We should say more wrong things about people's industries,
just so we can discover who's listening
to us through the complaints.
- Good to hear that.
- Great idea.
- If you are from an industry that we mentioned,
but you just want to write in and say,
we got everything right,
then that will be equally fine.
- That happens, but it's more rare
than people writing in saying,
I'm a sailfish farmer and you said it all wrong.
Yeah.
Right, I'm gonna ask you one last time to put your,
put your cans on because we've got another section coming up.
And I'm excited for you guys to hear this one.
Okay, I'll count you in.
Ready?
Three, two, one.
- Spicy.
- Here's how we get to the spicy meat.
- That's just meat.
- This is spicy, spicy meat.
- Yeah.
- If you're spicy meat, Ali.
- All right.
- Spicy, spicy meat.
- This is a spicy one, spicy meat.
(laughs)
- Spicy meat.
- Spicy, spicy meat.
- I'm still not sure what spicy meat is.
- It's like, I don't need to explain this.
- Spicy, spicy meat.
- Maybe there's some spicy meat.
- Looking at it.
- Spicy, spicy meat.
- I mean, see how spicy you think there's meat is.
- So someone that's using that to their sex sound track.
- That's quite spicy.
- Oh, that's all we've got time for on today's job.
- Brilliant.
- It's great.
Works for incess corner as well if we need it to.
(laughs)
- That's the only one I'm not on board with, I'm sorry.
- But you're in it.
(laughs)
- If you want to buy it, you can't be pleased.
- I love it, didn't you hear that the sizzling bacon?
- Yeah, no, I didn't like that.
(laughs)
- I thought it was brilliant.
I thought it was sonically brilliant.
- I like it, yeah.
- I thought it was powerfully sexual.
- I think that was my main problem with it.
- And that's my main, that's the thing I like about it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I just thought that was stunning.
Stunning work, thank you.
There's also an email.
And this is to do with fish love.
- Meat cute.
Liz writes, "I was merrily laughing along
"to the recent drop of the line,
"do bears like listening to fish
"and towards the end you invited stories
"of anyone who has split up on account
"of no such things as a fish.
"I can supply an anecdote for the new segment.
"Fish empty love in or dead meat."
- I like that meat.
(laughs)
- Dead meat, that's good, that's good.
- Right, there's some details have been changed,
but not many.
My ex and I attended a live performance of fish in 2024.
The show itself was wonderful, thank you.
- Thank you.
(laughs)
- A few months before, I had ordered a book,
which was one of those books you order from sites
where you generate an avatar of each family member
and it creates a personalized book.
- Yeah, okay.
- You can also encounter each of you.
- Yeah, nice.
- I chose features relevant to my ex-husband
who looks very different to Dan.
However, the book inexplicably arrived
with a likeness of Dan on the cover instead of my husband.
- That's the picture.
(laughs)
- That is you, Dan.
- Wow.
- As you can see from the image, it just generated Dan.
My ex didn't even wear glasses.
I thought it would have been brilliant
for Dan to sign the book.
My ex didn't think this was funny, he was wrong,
and didn't endorse the signing, so I didn't attempt it.
This incident was far from the singular calls
of our seven year relationship breaking down,
but it really didn't help.
The story has a very happy ending
in that I've been gleefully single for more than a year now
and co-parenting is going as well as can be expected.
- Okay. - Wow.
- So that's our first fish divorce.
- I don't think we can be blamed wholly for this.
- Not wholly.
She says it's only part of the,
she says it was probably the straw that broke the cows.
- Honestly.
- No, no, no, no, I'm paraphrasing, but like.
- But we didn't create this.
The only input we have at all is that Dan has
quite a generic male face with glasses.
Like that's all we can be held responsible for.
I know it looks like that.
- Dan's hacked his way into this company
that makes personalized books,
and it's on hundreds of thousands of books
all over the world now.
- He's like, you know when they find like a sperm doughnut?
- He's been (laughing)
giving the sperm to like thousands of different people.
It's like that. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Well, I'm glad she's thriving in her new life.
- Sounds like it. - Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, I'm very sorry.
- Yeah, and I'm happy to sign the book, you know,
if she wants to send it in.
- So there you go.
Congratulations Liz.
And thank you for listening to the podcast.
- All right, now it's time for a few quick fire,
nominative determinism corners.
- Oh great.
- Finley Chope writes in,
re German chocolate cake.
- Yes, made by someone called German.
- Yeah, from Germany.
- Finley writes,
I have another thing that sounds like it's named after something else,
but it's actually named after a person.
Don't remember whether you come up with the name for that.
I don't think we did actually have a specific name for that.
Anyway, there's a snake native to my,
and Dan's homeland of Australia.
It's the children's python.
(laughing)
Well known for its dose of nature
and a great choice for any child wanting a snake for a pet.
It's actually named after John George children.
- Brilliant.
(laughing)
- It's not good.
- I really like it.
- And I looked it up and I think you can keep them as pets.
- Really, yeah.
- You can, yeah.
- Anyway, so that's a great, that's a great, yeah.
- That's very good.
- Very nice.
- Okay.
- It's a lovely show.
- Yeah.
- Nice show.
- Let's see how the ending goes.
(upbeat music)
- Well, thank you everyone for your emails
to the podcast@QI.com address.
And we'll be back in the format with another one of these.
And I think that's all there is to say on the matter.
(laughing)
- It's good.
- Thanks, thanks everybody.
Thank you, bye.
- Thank you, bye.
- Thank you.
(laughing)
- It's so unclear when something's going to end, isn't it?
- Actually, that's what the word buy is really helpful for.
(laughing)
But I tried that and then you people forced me into another.
- We're not doing nothing and nothing.
We're just sitting here watching you hang yourself
(laughing)
- See you in two weeks, podcast@QI.com.
Bye.
(upbeat music)