(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Anna Tyshinski,
and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is My Fact.
My Fact this week is that a lot of the Daniel Day Lewis movie,
My Left Foot, was filmed using his right foot.
- What are you saying using?
Is that, we're operating the camera with his right foot?
- Yeah, that's what it sounds like.
- While he filmed his left foot.
Yes, and when I say a lot, I also mean some.
So let's just put this into context.
This is a movie about an Irish writer
and painter called Christy Brown.
He was born with cerebral palsy,
and by the time he was an older kid, he didn't walk,
he couldn't do much, and he only really could operate
by moving his left foot,
particularly the big toe on his left foot.
As he grew older, he got really excited
by the idea of becoming an artist.
He started to learn to paint,
and then he started to write a book
by using that left toe on a typewriter.
It was a massive success,
and this is what eventually became a biopic,
which starred Daniel Day-Lewis.
Now, for anyone who knows Daniel Day-Lewis,
he's a method actor.
He loves to really immerse himself,
and in this case, he operated most of the movie
from a wheelchair using his left foot.
- Yeah, and when you say method actor,
he basically lived as this character
throughout the whole time, right?
He stayed in the wheelchair the whole time, pretty much.
Like he had to be carried places.
- Yeah, made the cast and crew feed him.
- Well, he just was trying to stay in character,
but here's the thing.
The movie involves some quite intense stunts footwork-wise.
Okay, the movie is not,
I'm sorry, I watched the film yesterday.
It's a terrific film.
Stunts is not a good way to play it.
- Yeah, yeah.
And when you say this movie contains footwork,
it's not like Ginger Rogers.
(laughing)
- So there's a couple of scenes where he,
as an actor, was unable to do it
by manipulating his left foot into the right positions.
- But so the scenes are basically
he's holding a paintbrush or a pencil.
- Or writing.
And the first shot of the whole film,
it's just a shot of a foot.
And it's taking a vinyl record out of the sleeve.
- Yeah.
- And popping it off the turn.
- So what you're saying, Dan,
is that he did that with his right foot
instead of his left foot.
- Exactly.
- Now my question is,
how did we not tell the difference in the movie?
- He has them switched around.
It's really the opposite way around.
- That's the method.
He had to speak seven and then reversed.
(laughing)
- That's exactly it, Andy's got it right.
It was mirror filmed.
So the detail is a bit actually quite hard
to work out if they flipped the film itself
as in they did a mirror image
or if they filmed through a mirror.
- Right, okay.
- Has anyone else seen it?
- Yeah, many years ago.
Good film.
Weirdly, I read the book about 20 years ago.
It was also a great book.
- Did you, right?
- Yes, apparently he's a brilliant writer
when the book came out,
which bizarrely was when this guy Christy was,
Christy Brown was only 22.
He was so young to be writing about your experiences
so far, but I think it was in the 50s.
And when it came out,
someone said, I think the Irish standard or something,
said that it was the most important book
since Ulysses in Ireland.
- I think that might have been the subsequent book.
- Sorry, you're absolutely right.
That was his magnum opus.
Yes, what's it called?
Down on All Days?
- Down on All Days.
But I mean, they were both absolutely massive.
And he was from a family of 22 children,
not all of whom made it to adulthood.
- I think 11 did.
- 11 did, yeah, imagine that.
Good grief.
- That's from the birthdays.
- That's the candles.
- That's true.
That's the candles.
- Oh yeah, I was gonna say you could reuse them,
but no, you can't reuse them.
- No, well, you can.
- Oh, it depends how quickly you light and blow, right?
- But most birthday candles are so thin.
Maybe they had a very strict lighting and blowing policy.
Maybe in the--
- You'd have to.
You'd have to.
Anyway, it's a very--
- Is that in the book?
- It's like, it's been 20 years, I can't remember.
It's definitely not an overwritten book though,
because he's typing it with one toe.
So he doesn't go for the incredibly long sentence,
quite a lot of the time.
- It's kind of the reverse Ulysses, isn't it, in a way?
- Yes, it is, absolutely, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- That was good.
- And it was a big book, right?
So when it came out, it made Splash internationally.
He actually got no correspondence
with this American woman called Beth Moore,
and he eventually went over to hang out with her,
and she was married, but they had an affair.
And this is where he wrote his magnum opus, this novel.
And she basically is the reason he got it done,
because at this point,
he did have a bit of an alcohol problem,
and it was preventing him from getting on with stuff.
She basically said, "You're not allowed to drink
"until the end of the day,
"after you've done a full day's of writing,
"and then you can have that."
And that's how he got the novel done.
He dedicates it to her.
He goes back to Ireland,
and then they have more correspondence saying--
- Is he married as well at the time?
'Cause he did marry a couple of times.
- No, he wasn't married at the time.
- No, 'cause he's not married.
- He's not married.
- Yeah, so, but she tells her husband,
"I'm gonna marry Christy."
And just as that's about to happen,
Christy meets his wife and gets married,
and then Beth is stuck.
- So, bit of an asshole, actually.
You know, people don't really focus on this bit, do they?
Abandoned poor Beth for his new woman,
who's the person I think in the film,
which I haven't seen, but he goes off with a woman
at the very end of the film, I think.
It looks like it's going to be happy.
But actually, that's the person he went off with.
And it seems like, based on his life,
Beth, who helped him write his great novel,
was a lovely woman, and he ended up with this other lady,
who I think a lot of his family didn't like,
who turned him into a bit of a recluse.
She was an alcoholic herself, I believe.
- There were allegations of abuse,
so he passed away, quite sadly, at 49.
- Really young, yeah, yeah.
- He was choked while eating, but, yeah, on his body,
there were sort of unexplained bruises all over,
with the abuse. - Yeah, wow.
What about Daniel De Lewis, eh?
- Oof. - Well, not that guy.
- He's a character.
(laughing)
- Well, more often than he is himself, yeah.
- So, before this podcast recording time,
I had never seen any of the films with Daniel De Lewis in.
- Is that right?
- Not one. - That was so cool.
Not one.
- Wow.
- I thought he was in "Backman Forever",
but it turns out that was someone else.
(laughing)
- Don't spell kill them.
- No, spell kill them.
You're thinking of Jim Carrey.
(laughing)
- So, I've never seen any of the interests.
- Have you just watched them all?
Have you seen, how many have you seen now?
- I've now seen one and a half way through two others.
- Which two?
- Gangs of New York, have you watched that?
- No, I haven't.
- Oh, that's a brilliant movie.
- It sounds great.
I've started, not on "American Werewolf" in London,
but "The Last Mohican", sorry.
- Yep. - Oh, yeah.
- I started "The Last Mohican", terrific.
Was watching that in the small house this morning.
And I'm also watching "Stars and Bars",
which is a goofy comedy he made immediately
after "My Left Foot", which appears to have been
the only film for which he's never done any method work,
whatsoever.
- What was his character in that?
- The premise is just like,
what if a goofy British guy went to the deep South of America
and it is so bad?
(laughing)
- I've managed to watch the only time they know this film,
which is not like five-star.
This will change your life movie.
- Well, in "The Last Mohicans",
he caught and killed all of his food.
- Brilliant.
- Apparently, I had to get into that character.
- Yeah, he lived for a whole month in the wilderness,
didn't he, in order to fully immerse himself.
- He was in "The Crucible"
and he didn't bathe for the entirety of "The Crucible".
Now, I'm not sure, is that about the witch trial?
Sorry, is that about Snooker?
(laughing)
- It's the happy marriage of the two.
- He bathed, but he kept one foot on the floor at all time.
(laughing)
I think my favorite one,
'cause I don't ever heard of him as like this,
incredible that he lives the role.
My favorite is the unbearable likeness of being,
I'm sure you guys all found this,
which is based on a Czech novel by Milan Kundera,
and he learned Czech,
learned to speak Czech almost fluently for the film,
despite the fact the film is in English,
all of his lines are in English,
and he said, "Yeah, but I can't just do an accent."
I need to know where that accent comes from, great.
So he put all of his lines through the Czechy New
and then back into English to do the accent, I mean, insane.
- And do you know what people who speak Czech,
and particularly British people who now live
in the Czech Republic,
say that it's a really bad Czech accent?
- Oh no, he says nothing like a Czech English.
- If you learn how to speak a language,
that doesn't mean you learn how to speak English
in that accent, but that's the one problem
when you learn a language is you can never nail the accent.
- Yeah, I also really want to find out how fluent he is,
'cause there's so much allegation about this,
and apparently, according to the Foreign Services Institute,
which ranks languages by difficulty,
Czech is in the fourth out of five hardest languages.
So I mean, it takes years and years and years to nail.
So how, I mean, was it,
do you think it was like primary school, French level?
- I always wonder that,
whenever you see like a top footballer or a basketball player
going, I speak nine languages to you.
Did you Kobe Bryant, did you really?
- Well, did you just learn how to say,
oh, I got that three points today?
- Exactly, 'cause as that fact we did ages ago
about umpires and tennis,
do you need to learn all the swear words
in multiple languages or something on the same?
Maybe it's just that.
I mean, obviously some of it is myth-making,
but I love it, I just love it.
Like he played Lincoln, President Lincoln.
So he actually-
- He got assassinated for that one.
- He got assassinated, he had himself made President first.
And then, so on the set of Lincoln,
it was just totally a period appropriate.
So supposedly, nobody was allowed to tell that
wearing a T-shirt with a logo on.
Like, I presume all the like thousands of electricians
of people who work on the film had to be in front coats
and things like, it's addressed to like union soldiers.
No shorts, no paper coffee cups.
Lincoln wouldn't have had a paper coffee cup.
I imagine it's more for Daniel Day-Lewis
than it is for everyone else.
- But you've got to slightly create the scene around him,
haven't you?
I mean, like in there's a famous thing in Gangs of New York
when he was filming,
where first of all, Stephen Graham,
who is very famous and brilliant British actor,
said that he was such a great guy to work with
and they became friends before they started filming
and they did the training together,
some martial arts training together.
And then the first day on set,
Daniel Day-Lewis walks on the set
and just touches him on the shoulder and says,
"From now on, I call you Shang and you call me Bill."
And then moves on.
So cool.
- Bill the butcher.
- And then indeed-
- Is that his character?
- Yes.
- I read that he worked as a butcher for some time.
I know I read butchers were flown over to the set.
- It was one butcher.
But I've got a theory about this butcher.
I don't think he's a butcher.
- Okay.
- I think this butcher is the ultimate method actor.
He's a guy called John Dell.
Look him up.
He's a butcher who runs W, head and co-butchers in Peckham.
- Sounds like he is a butcher.
- Well, no evidence of that online at all.
- Oh.
- There's like one little company record
of it once existing.
John Dell.
- How many butchers have websites, though?
Especially at the time that Gangs of New York
was the 2002 film, it's early into there.
It wasn't required that a butcher
had to have a buzzing online presence in 2002.
- Everyone's Google reviewed something.
- Oh, come on.
- I couldn't find nothing.
He was an amazing character, though.
When he was interviewed, first of all,
he was asked by the producer who lived in Peckham
and he knew him.
And he was like, this guy's a legit butcher.
He knows how to slaughter a pig.
So-
- He's an avatar worker.
You could clearly, yeah.
If your butcher's killing the pig,
that's a problem with the sourcing.
Butchers don't normally kill the animal.
- No, sorry.
- No butchers.
I mean, butcher the animal.
But he was very good at butchering pigs.
So he trained Daniel Day-Lewis in how to butcher a pig.
And they got along really well.
He said Daniel Day-Lewis could butcher a pig like no one else.
He'd never seen anyone else with the knife skills.
He'd never seen anyone else
with the natural feel for cutting meat.
- And this is a man who presumably
has known a lot of other butchers.
- I reckon 'cause they hang out together, don't they?
- Yeah.
- I love the sound of Daniel Day-Lewis.
He sounds like a really nice bloke.
And when he's interviewed about it,
he sounds quite normal.
- Yeah.
- Because I'm just trying to get into the head
of the character so that when I put it on film, it's real.
- I think he's a big old liar.
- No.
- You think he's just not doing it?
- I genuinely do.
I think some of it's true, but I think there's some.
And actually, I think a lot of the lies
are made up by people around him.
But there was the famous thing where he walked off stage
'cause he thought he saw his dad in the wings
when he was doing Hamlet.
- That's right.
- And then later on, he did an interview saying
that's what happened.
And then later on, he went, "No, it didn't really happen."
- He said he was just tired.
He said he was just exhausted
and you're doing a play for every day for 18 months,
whatever, that's really exhausting.
- But you can imagine if Daniel Del Luis says,
"I saw my dad father in the wings,"
you're gonna believe that, aren't you?
- Absolutely, yeah.
- And it was, he's never done theater since.
- But he explains, actually,
he prefers the medium of film and so on and so forth.
- I kind of agree.
It's sort of like if he was less sort of thespian-like
and had so much integrity, he's Brian Blessed.
Like all these stories are just tall tales.
Apparently on my left foot, he broke two ribs
because he was hunching over so much
while he was in the wheelchair,
but they just snapped under the weight of his hunchback.
- I just don't think that breaks your ribs.
- I hunch over my laptop all day, every day,
and never have I broken a rib.
- You're not committing to the work
like Del Luis commits to his work.
No offence, Anna, I'm sorry.
- But he is a very, very successful actor,
Daniel Del Luis.
His Wikipedia, he doesn't have a separate Wikipedia page
listing his movies, 'cause he's done so few movies.
I think he's done less than 20 or around 20.
- Wow.
- But he does have a separate page listing all
of his awards.
- Just 'cause he's won so many.
- Yeah, he's done around 20 feature length films
and he's had 212 major nominations and 139 wins.
- Wow.
- And not one of them will have been for "Stars and Bugs".
I guarantee it.
- What I worked out is if each episode of our podcast
was as successful as each of his films,
then we'd have more than 4,000 awards.
And if they all weighed the same as an Oscar statuette,
the total weight would be about the same as two elephants.
- Oh my God.
- So that puts it into perspective.
- Yeah, it really does. - That's brilliant.
- Tells you a lot about Daniel Del Luis, that.
- Yeah.
- Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is Andy.
My fact is that some French unions have special barbecues
that can be used to cook sausages while on a protest march.
- Brilliant.
They do like a strike in France.
- They love a strike and they love a saucy song.
And they found a way of combining the two.
And this does the rounds every now and again.
But Snopes, the brilliant people at Snopes,
looked into this picture.
You can find it online.
There's French people, they're very clearly French union workers.
They're in their hives and they're pushing along
this mobile barbecue, which is in tram tracks.
- Yeah. - Oh.
- So they're going the tram route, I presume.
Oh, they're French train workers who were on strike.
- It was in Nice.
- Very annoying if it's French teachers on strike
and they're confined to the tram route for the whole process.
- It's 'cause they were doing some reform of the SNCF.
- There was some probably mild change
suggested to working hours and I was like,
"Everybody out now, we leave Nice to Rock for a year."
- So it's really cool though, isn't it?
There's actually video footage.
It's like one second of video footage
from what I saw where they're just pushing it down.
It's a massive grill going over the two tram tracks.
- It's very cool. - And they're pushing it along
and they're, you know.
- So why do they put it on tram tracks
rather than just putting a barbecue on wheels?
- Good call.
Good point.
I suppose they were marching the route of the tracks.
I mean, I suppose they were only walking the tram route
to make a point about whatever beef they were having.
With their bosses.
- Maybe it makes the point more emphatically
if they're like, "We've even made a barbecue
"to make our point."
- I mean, we're talking about them now.
This was several years ago.
- It's worked. - So, you know, it's worked.
- Their wagers will probably shoot up
now that we've discussed it.
- You're welcome.
- Yeah.
I didn't actually know the knees had trams.
I've been to knees, but clearly I wasn't paying attention.
So, you know.
Is that an all new low in terms of my anecdotes?
It's 'cause I cycled into knees, that's it.
Now we've hit the rock bottom.
There we go, there we go.
- You know, the barbecue I have is a Weber or Weber barbecue.
- Okay.
- And that is a, it's like a circular one.
It's almost like a ball and some legs.
- I think of that as a classic.
- It's a classic garden barbecue.
- It's like War of the Worlds, the tripods.
- It is. - Like this is all with a tripod.
- The terrifying aliens leap out of it
if you want to cook the meat.
- Sort of.
Will they climb into your body
and then they leap out several hours later?
- Yes.
- Well, they were invented in 1952
from two halves of a steel boy.
- A boy?
- You know, a boy.
- A boy. - Ocean boy.
- You know, those things that float to the ocean.
- Yeah.
- Well, yeah, they decided they wanted
to make a new kind of barbecue
and they thought, wouldn't it be nice if it was circular?
And what do we have that's circular in our iron works?
Well, we have some boys.
- Boys. - Cool.
- That's brilliant.
- And the guy used it in his garden
and basically all his neighbors called it a spaceship
and laughed at him.
But it turned around.
- And it took off?
- It did.
- So was the previous barbecue not around like a bro?
- No, because in America where the barbecuing started,
that's not really what barbecuing is.
It's more like roasting meat for 24 hours
until it's really, really, really soft.
Isn't it? - Right.
- That's low cut.
- 'Cause in the, I should say to any Americans listening,
in the UK, a barbecue is you sit in the garden
when it's raining and you put burgers on a grill.
- You go into the house and put them in the oven
if it's really raining yet.
- As far as I'm concerned, a barbecue is a metal tray
that you buy from Tesco Metro on a sunny day
and then take to the park.
- You cramp.
- You three bottles of white light in.
- Yeah, delicious as well.
- I discovered that I spell barbecue differently to you three.
- No, you spell it wrong,
which is what I noticed is a document
where we put a tag or a search.
- Are you spelling it with a Q, Dan?
- I'm spelling it with a Q,
which is the Australian way of spelling it.
That's the actual way of spelling it in Australia.
Yes, it is, and New Zealand as well.
And also, ah.
- But you pronounce that barbec.
- Barbeque.
- They pronounce it Barbie, as we know.
- Oh, we have a Barbie, but yeah, barbecue.
And in Sydney, there's a thing.
- If it was, sorry, if it was meant,
if you were spelling it like it was pronounced,
but you wanted to include the Q,
you'd have to end it Q-U-E-U-E.
That's how you do Q.
- Join the barbecue.
- Yeah.
Well, no, I'll bring that up.
And the next time I'm at the Australian Embassy
and they're asking me for my international opinions.
- They've constantly got a barbecue
on the go at the Aussie Embassy.
- They do, exactly.
- But this relates to a really interesting
etymology of barbecue,
because there's a kind of mythic folk belief
that it comes from a French phrase
from barbecue, which means from beer to tail.
You're eating the whole pig.
Jokes on you, that pig is Daniel Day-Louis in disguise.
He was method acting.
You're in big trouble now.
You've cooked and eaten him.
- Was he in Babe?
- What was the movie?
(all laughing)
- 'Cause the word Q in English as in to stand in a line
comes from the French for tail as well.
- Right, right.
- But you're saying this isn't correct.
- It's not from that.
In fact, we very briefly mentioned years and years ago
that it's from a guy called William Dampier
who was a privateer, sailor, pirate, roaster.
- The original Robinson Crusoe, I want to say.
- He was a buccaneer and a buccaneer is a pirate
who cooks meat.
It's basically the etymology of buccaneer
comes from that as well.
- Yes.
- It's all Caribbean languages basically.
So there's a barbacao,
which is from the various Caribbean peoples who got it.
So it's from the Americas, the word in the first place, yeah.
- There's a fun phrase in Argentina
where barbecuing is huge and it's called asado
in place like Argentina, Brazil,
other parts of South America.
And then you get asado al disco, do you know what that is?
- A circular.
- Revolving, yeah, rotating.
- Oh, the disco gets so hot that you feel like you're cooking.
So they're a ball full of meat.
- Thank you.
I was looking for some disco stuff
and then I could say no,
it's about the first things that you guys said,
but a disco is the disc from a plow.
So a plow has like very sharp discs
that it cuts the crops with.
And once they've worn out, then in Argentina,
you take that off the plow and you cook on it.
And it's basically like a wok, a giant wok.
And that's Apollo al disco
is using the disc from a plow to barbecue.
- Yeah, a barbecuing is very common around the world.
And one thing that's quite interesting
is it's very common for men to do the barbecuing
almost everywhere that you go.
So like we think of it in the UK at least
and probably in America as like,
the dads go and do the barbecuing
while everyone else does something else.
- That's right.
And the men obsess over it and they talk,
Lou, what charcoal are you cooking with these days?
You know that kind of stuff.
- But yeah, Levi Strauss, the anthropologist,
he says that yeah, basically if you look all over the world
from Amazonian tribes, people in Africa,
it's often the men's work for the barbecuing.
There was a book called the complete barbecue book
by John and Marie Robertson who put it,
they said that the man who does the barbecuing
takes on a somewhat god-like stature.
As for the ladies, well, they're virtually your slaves.
I feel like John wrote that bit, not Marie, probably.
- Who is it?
- Anthropologist of food rides called Calvin Trillin
records that if you want to be a good barbecueist,
you have to be basically a mishandthrope
because you're going in the garden on your own.
You're not really talking to anyone else.
Your friend is the meat, as opposed to the--
- Oh God, it's such a lovely chance
not to have to fulfill your social obligations
and just stand there feeling used to it.
- I would say in Australia,
I don't know what it's like here properly,
but it's the water cooler.
It's everywhere when it hangs around the barbecue.
- What are you driving these days?
Yeah, that kind of thing.
- Exactly that kind of thing, yeah.
- But then this guy says that actually it's quite good
as a hobby because golf and sailing and fishing,
these are also things where men sort of like to go
just a couple of men on their own
and not see anyone else misanthropically,
but at least in this case,
everyone gets some food out of it at the end.
- That's true, I'm not guaranteed with fishing.
I'm very rare with golf unless you really hit something.
- Yeah, I think misanthropically,
for activities like fishing,
which is so dominated by men,
we need to replace the word misanthrope,
which has a kind of coolness to it with unhelpful,
because that's all it is.
That's just men pissing off and not helping out, isn't it?
- So when my wife says to me,
"Why have you not taken the bins out?"
I could just say, "Oh, it's been misanthropic."
- Yeah, exactly.
The male thing is interesting though,
and going back to French barbecues,
a green politician in France got in trouble in 2022
'cause they were saying obviously meat,
very bad for the environment,
20% of our greenhouse gases still come from the meat industry.
And she was saying,
"We have to change our mentality
"so that eating a barbecued Andracot
"is no longer a symbol of virility."
And basically people said,
"You're blaming men for killing the planet."
- I don't think I've ever heard someone say the word
"Andracot" and think that is a virile person.
- France is a very different place to Bolton James.
The interesting male thing about barbecuing a meat
is that men just do eat more meat,
and actually we don't know why,
but around the world, in almost every country--
- It must be cultural, it can't be biological.
- Well, a lot of people think it's biological,
so there are arguments that female hormones suppress
the desire to eat meat around your period,
or when you're pregnant, which sounds very implausible to me.
There's another argument that says
men behave in more risky ways.
So evolutionarily, they need to eat more protein
to make their bones stronger, more meat.
- But also cooking a sausage for three minutes a day,
I was probably fine, that is a risky behavior.
(laughing)
- But it's really interesting,
and also there was a study looking at 23 countries,
and the wealthier and more gender equality we have,
what would you think, as you get more gender equality,
which tends to happen in more developed countries,
does the gap between men and women's meat
seem to get bigger or smaller?
- Well, you think it would get smaller.
- You think it would get smaller and it gets bigger?
- It doesn't, 'cause men are trying to cling
to something to show their blokes, is that it?
- We don't know, but I like that's a nice interpretation.
- Have you heard of transglutaminase?
I'd be really surprised if you had, no.
- Some kind of molecule.
- It's a molecule, all right, it's an enzyme,
and it's a thing that gets called meat glue.
- Oh, that's not the answer.
- And if you buy a big piece of steak, you may notice,
it might be skewered, and if it's skewered,
there's a good chance.
This is in America, this stuff is not legal in the EU,
that it's been had meat glue sort of painted on it,
and if you paint meat glue on it and squish it all together,
you can make a big, expensive looking steak
out of several pieces of small scrap meat.
- Oh, cool.
- And that's how it's not cool, it's really horrible.
- No, but it's cool that you could bring
a dino burger basically, right?
- Yeah, it's like the Power Rangers,
they combine their forces.
- Yeah, yeah.
- If you're listening to this after the Trump tariffs
have forced us to do a trade deal with America,
then you two could be eating one right now.
- We'll eat these days.
- Yeah, I was looking at sort of out-of-place barbecues,
like the one on the tram line,
and there was a really cool thing I found,
which is there used to be a tour
called the Vans Warp Tour.
It's basically a festival that you would have like 20 bands,
and they would go from city to city together.
So not like class and regis or what.
Yeah, and they came to Australia in 1998,
and I remember it being a big deal.
So they had big bands,
you'd get people like Blink 182 and No Effects and stuff,
but then they would also give opportunities
to younger newer bands.
And one of the conditions of being on the Warp Tour
was you could be the barbecue band.
You get a slot on stage, but when it's done,
you go backstage and you're in charge of the barbecue,
and you cook for everyone.
And so that's the condition,
the trade-off of you being on the tour.
- Don't we know any bands that went on to be massive,
having begun as barbecues?
- Yeah, the Dropkick Murphy's, Art of Shock,
Gorilla's, Gorilla's, Gorilla's.
- Yes. - Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Was he in it?
(laughing)
- I was in it.
- I think Gorilla's is what belongs, isn't it?
- Oh, you mean, I think. - Damon Aldon, you mean.
- Yeah, Damon Aldon.
- Yeah, well, it's a good one.
- Damon Aldon, I mean, he belongs on a farm anyway.
(laughing)
So you know, there are these rubs.
- Yeah, meat rub. - It's a big thing.
- Meat rub. - Meat rub.
- Yeah.
- So it's basically a load of spices
that you rub over your meat to marinate it.
- Exactly, exactly.
And there's a shop named Me,
which stocks something by what's called
the Gentleman's Rub Club.
And I have tried to,
and I've tried to find any evidence that it existed online
'cause I remembered it running up to this podcast
and they're nowhere.
- The thing is, it's a bit like Butchers in the 1980s.
You don't necessarily have to have a massive online presence
if you're a rub club.
- But the fairly the first rule of Gentleman's Rub Club.
(laughing)
But this just got me off onto like,
so it got me off onto, got me onto grilling awards,
barbecue awards.
So I was looking at the NBBQA,
National Barbecue and Grilling Association,
'cause they have an awards of excellence every year.
I think it's an American thing.
So they've got beef rub, pork rub, poultry rub,
seafood rub, spicy rub.
And I just, I wanted to read a few of the prizes
from the latest awards.
They're terrific.
Barbecue apparel category.
First prize, a t-shirt reading, wanna see my rack.
- First prize. - First prize.
- Third prize.
- Well, they try and encourage women to get into it, aren't they?
- Second prize, wanna see my sausage.
(laughing)
- Third prize, t-shirt reading, I got sourced.
Fourth hat reading, my dad's barbecue.
But there's a barbecue book of the year.
- Oh yeah.
- A barbecue, badass backyard cooking.
- Oh, dear.
- Oh, cool.
- There's even an award for best barbecue audio series.
There's barbecue podcasts.
Could we put this section up for it?
- I think so.
If we wanna dethrone the smoking hot confessions
of the BBQ podcast.
- Well, I definitely wanna check out my rack t-shirt
or whatever it is, so let's do it.
(laughing)
They're massive, the barbecue contest in America.
They're all run by the Kansas City Barbecue Society
and it's trained over 15,000 judges to judge barbecues
and the rules are very tight.
So, judges are not allowed to eat with utensils,
but you're also not allowed to lick your fingers.
Why?
No one knows.
You just have fingers covered in like,
- I do? - Barbecue meat the whole time.
- How can you eat some ribs
without licking your fingers?
That's unnatural.
- Well, I think it's not a challenge.
- Maybe you have wipes.
- Gloves?
- Yes.
- I don't even like gloves.
- They've got the glove culture they want.
(laughing)
- Like a snooker referee.
- I need another 20,000 pounds of linen gloves please, yeah.
- The scores are on a scale of one to nine,
but there's no three and four, weirdly.
(laughing)
- Come on.
- Five.
- What, one, two, five, six, seven and nine.
- That's so funny.
- Yeah, five is poor and then two is inedible.
Nothing in between.
- That's very funny.
- There are various rules.
To judge a brisket as in a big chest of a cow,
you have to be able to manipulate it like an accordion.
- Wow.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
- Wow, what a sentence, horrible.
- I think it's all, I think it's useful.
- I'm surprised, yeah.
- Are you?
- Because, well, I could play the accordion, right?
And so you have to move it quite a lot, right?
And to move a rib cage,
I don't feel like that would be possible.
- Yeah.
- Maybe the rib cage.
- That's a terrible cheer.
But if a couple of the rooms have already been broken,
let's hope because Daniel Day Lewis
has been living as the cow.
(laughing)
- Tank, I'll ask you a question.
- Yeah.
- Australia.
- You're from there.
- Yes.
- Have you ever seen a coin operated barbecue in the past?
- I was gonna mention this before I was cut off
for my terrible spelling, which was not terrible.
In Sydney, we actually have not even coin operated.
You have free barbecues on most of the beaches
that you go to.
So we would go down to Clairville on the weekend.
You would just press a button and it gets going.
And your only thing is to just clean it up.
- Wait, is it like gas,
or do you have to bring your own charcoal?
- Oh, no, no, yeah, just goes up.
- Isn't it unhygienic?
- No, you clean.
So there's a raw sausages on there.
- I kind of think the thing with barbecue
is it doesn't matter if you drop it in the mud,
'cause you're cooking it on such a massive, massive heat.
- It's a thousand degrees.
What's surviving on that?
- There's a real pride thing, by the way,
of you leave it ready for the next person.
Yeah, it's a thing that is sort of just part of the way.
- I see, I see, that's national culture.
Well, supposedly even some zoos have free barbecues,
which I feel is open to misuse.
- What, do you think that's a bit scary
for the animals just sitting around?
- Have you seen the wombat?
Where's the wombat?
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that epileptic fits
can be triggered by thinking about toothpaste.
- That's wild.
- Yeah, not widespread, don't worry.
- Do you have to have a specific condition
already for this to happen?
Epilepsy, I'm assuming.
(laughing)
- It is more common epileptics, yes.
But you ask all the right questions, Andy.
That's why we love to have you in the class.
This, I just came across this paper from 2006,
which reported on a patient with epilepsy.
Came across a paper from 2006,
which reported on a patient with epilepsy
in which seizures were induced
both by tooth brushing and by seeing
or thinking about toothbrush and toothpaste.
- That's amazing.
- It's extraordinary.
- Is that someone who is stressed
about the idea of brushing their teeth
and then the stress brings on it?
Like, what is bringing it on?
- I don't, well, it's very mysterious,
and I don't think it's quite that.
It's a type of reflex epilepsy,
which is epilepsy that's triggered by something,
and this type is called thinking epilepsy,
and it's where thinking about something,
and I don't think it's necessarily something
that causes you stress,
but thinking about a certain thing triggers it,
so there was other cases reported on
where someone, when they thought about food,
whenever they thought about food,
which is quite debilitating.
- I read about one who, every time they tried to do Sudoku,
they got an epileptic fit.
- This seems to be a thing, puzzles, crosswords, Sudoku.
- Oh yeah, I hate a Sudoku.
- Yeah, but it's not about hating it.
I don't know, do you have the lying epilepsy?
- I'm starting to feel like I might.
- But is it because there's a particular location
in your brain where the neurons for toothpaste
or Sudoku or whatever, or food are kept,
and there's a crossed wire in there?
That seems logical, doesn't it?
But I don't think anyone really knows.
- No, no, and it is rare, but it is amazing,
and some people can think themselves into an epileptic fit.
It just sounds like the most awful thing,
'cause what is the only thing you can do
when you're told not to think about something,
obviously is think about something.
If you know that you can't think about this,
there was a guy who was taken to hospital,
and he had a brain lesion, I think,
and he had an epileptic fit,
and the only way you could characterize it was,
if he started to feel enthusiastic,
he would then have a fit.
- Oh, interesting.
- Can I wonder if you have that?
I know we probably never know.
- Me.
(all laughing)
That's why, actually, I play it safe.
- So it could be anything, you just got to identify it.
- So he's not allowed a hobby?
- He's not allowed a hobby that he likes, no.
He can do Sudoku to his ask and death, actually,
but they actually made him induce one,
which does feel quite mean.
They were like, "Could you try and replicate the feeling
"when you have one so we can have a look?"
So he was like, "Okay, I'll make myself feel enthusiastic.
"You ready?" - Wow.
- Toothpaste?
- Yes, please.
How do the stripes get in?
(all laughing)
- Oh my God, the ultimate question.
- Why don't I know?
- I believe there's a couple of different ways of doing it.
- Yeah, they got a couple of them.
- But my understanding is that the main one,
there's a little thing near the nozzle or something.
- Oh, it's a paintbrush.
- It's disappointingly technical, the explanation,
but knowing that it's not like--
- Is it not through the back door?
- What do you mean through the back door?
There's one rope of toothpaste that goes into the tube.
- You've got the nozzle at the top,
and then you've got the bottom.
Maybe that's not closed up when the stuff's put in,
and then you seal it up.
- What you're saying is that one long string
of toothpaste is put in,
and it comes out in the same order
that it went in the other end.
- No, I'm picturing it a bit like Mr. Whippy.
- What if you get it wrong and squeeze it the wrong way?
- How does it work the opposite way round, though?
'Cause it would mush inside.
- It's white on the inside, up to near the nozzle end,
and then the color, or colors,
this is one way of doing it, the colors are up at that end,
and it's a very thin pipe.
So as you squeeze from the back end,
the white goes up through the nozzle,
but the color bit is also pressed out
through the holes in the sides,
and joins the main white bit.
- Cool.
- And the main bit is white,
and the other colors then are the garnish.
- That's fantastic.
- I love it.
I never knew that.
- So if you don't like the colors,
if you get a bit perturbed when you spit it out,
and it looks like your mouth is bleeding,
you can cut your toothpaste tube in half,
and then just use the bottom of it, and it's just white.
- That's what I do.
Think of someone who could have had a tube of toothpaste,
right, a famous person in history.
- Margaret Thatcher.
- She could, yes, even more impressively,
even further back on that.
- Jim Callaghan.
- Julius Caesar.
- Yes, Jim Callaghan, no, do this.
(laughing)
- Wilson.
- Harold Wilson, yep.
You're just doing PMs.
- Yeah, just going backwards.
- I think even before Balfour,
she could have had it, yeah.
- I don't know if designing quiz formats is for you.
- Lord Salisbury.
- Oh, God.
- No.
- Was it between Disraeli's first term
and Disraeli's second term?
- No, it's after all of Disraelian Gladstone.
Campbell Bannerman probably could have had, who?
- Wow.
- He was a turn of the 20th century Prime Minister.
- Atlee.
- Yeah, we must say that atlee could have done, James.
You're not catching up.
You're not playing the game at all well,
which is surprising to me, 'cause it's such a good game.
(laughing)
- What's your point toothpaste
that was invented 100 years ago?
- How young, Joan Rivers?
- Let's trust him, yeah, all of these people.
So what I'm trying to say is that the squeezy toothpaste tube,
the collapsible toothpaste tube,
was invented in roughly the 1880s, '90s.
So Queen Victoria could have had a tube of toothpaste,
which just makes you think, doesn't it?
- What does it make me think?
- Well, it's just the tube of toothpaste
is older than we might think it is, you know?
James thought Clement Atlee was the earliest
Prime Minister who could have had one.
But actually, 1880, a dentist from Connecticut,
confusingly he was called Sheffield, launched it.
And then it was launched in York,
confusingly the place in 1896.
So other people who could have enjoyed it
include Adolf Sachs, Friedrich Engels,
William Morris and Rutherford B. Hayes.
- Goni women there who cleaned the teeth in there.
- Queen Victoria, I think was the opener.
- I stopped him.
- Queen Victoria, Queen Victoria, great.
Here's a worrying thing for toothpaste, possibly.
Do you know that sails have dropped by a lot?
Some say almost half since the late '90s.
- What?
- Yeah, now riddle me this.
- Is it that people used to have much bigger toothbrushes?
- You got in one, electric toothbrushes.
- Oh, wow!
- Electric toothbrushes have such a small little surface area
if you put it on that you're not squeezing as much.
And also the rise of the two for one
or three for two promotion
has absolutely knocked out sails for them as well.
But it's literally that we're using it
almost half the amount that we usually would.
- I'm so surprised, 'cause I don't think a high proportion
of people use electric toothbrushes.
I'm surprised that it's half.
Do you guys?
- Well, so the promotions as well, the promotions.
- I don't, but I tend to just cover my whole flannel
with toothpaste and rub that round my mouth.
- Well, do you know--
- So I'm probably keeping the industry going.
- That would work.
And this is his, you don't need to put it
on a brush or anything.
And this is something that will really send
toothpaste sales plummeting.
If they were worried before about this drop,
it's totally pointless.
- What's happened to your teeth, Adam?
- Toothbrush.
- Toothpaste.
- What?
- So, study after study.
If you're looking at removing plaque,
study after study, like dozens and dozens of studies,
very, very reliable, broad studies,
look at the difference between toothbrushing
without any toothpaste and toothbrushing with toothpaste,
and there is absolutely no difference.
- Your teeth are gonna be stronger if you use fluoride.
- So the only thing is, the fluoride in toothpaste
is in the long term, good for your teeth,
only if you do the thing that I've always known
you should do, but can't bring myself to do,
which is not rinse at the end.
Do you guys all not rinse?
- I do now, having learned this,
'cause we talked about this from QI coming up.
- Oh, did we?
But yeah, it is quite interesting,
'cause I think, and there are so many ingredients,
but it is literally the only thing
is fluoride that does anything,
unless except like breath-smelling of mint.
'Cause you get a fluoride-free toothpaste,
which I do have friends who use,
and I'm not judging them, 'cause they're my friends.
- Yeah, but you can't invite them to the barbecue
'cause they can't get through the meat.
- How is RFK?
Is he all right?
It's so interesting how we got fluoride in toothpaste,
and in fact in water.
In 1901, there was a young dentist called Frederick Mackay,
and he moved to Colorado Springs in America,
and he found that people there had a thing called,
have you heard of Colorado brown stain?
- Well, I wouldn't buy that toothpaste, Brad.
- Isn't that one of the spots, team,
the Colorado brown stains?
- Yes, that's right.
- Go brown stains, yeah, yeah.
This is insane, 90% of children had it.
Almost no one in the rest of America
had Colorado brown stain, or any kind of brown stain.
The water was tested.
Turns out the water was very high on fluoride, right?
Particular towns of particular water sources
had awful brown stain, but the good thing was,
they did some experiments, Mackay and Et El,
and they found that basically this water-borne fluoride
changed the color of your tooth enamel,
but it also made this mottled tooth enamel
that people have was very resistant to decay.
And so they started thinking, okay, we pop a little bit,
these kids have rock hard teeth, basically.
And they thought, if we put the right amount
of fluoride in the water, you won't get discolored teeth,
but you will get strong teeth.
And the year after the first place,
Grand Rapids in Michigan got fluoride,
the number of cavities dropped 60%.
It's one of the most effective
health interventions ever made.
It's like that thing in Switzerland,
where everyone had goiters on their neck,
and then they started putting iodine in the salt,
just overnight changed it.
- Well, and bizarrely, we don't do it everywhere in Britain,
which I actually didn't realize until recently.
- Not everywhere, no.
- And lots, in fact, in most places, we don't do it.
But does that mean we should actually,
or good teeth, mottled brown teeth?
Like really, if we want super strong teeth,
why not triple the fluoride?
- I think you can have too much fluoride.
- You definitely can, there are advisory levels.
And people go a bit nuts about it, obviously.
There's lots of stuff online about it.
When it was installed in Grand Rapids in 1945,
lots of people said, "This fluoride,
it's giving me sore teeth and sore enamel,
and it's really bad."
And they were told,
"Yes, we haven't actually put the fluoride in the water yet."
That's happening in a few weeks, yeah.
- So we know now that there's no toothpaste
before Campbell Benjamin.
- Well, there's no tubes, right?
- It's usable tubes.
- Yeah, okay.
But what did the Romans do to keep their mouth nice
and healthy, what they use as mouthwash?
- Oh, like urine.
- So there is this sort of factoid
that Romans used urine from Portugal as mouthwash.
(laughing)
And it is put across by lots of popular historians,
but it's really probably not true.
Like if you look for any classical evidence,
there is a mention by Catalyst, and it's a poem,
but he's mocking someone and he's saying,
"Oh yeah, you're in Spain, you've been to Spain,
so you probably wash your mouth with urine."
- Oh, okay, right.
- And it might be that maybe some people in Spain did that,
but this is a satirical sort of taking the piss.
Really, they didn't do this.
- You mean not only not Portuguese urine,
they probably didn't use urine in general.
- Probably not, nah.
Otherwise, why would you take the piss out of someone
for doing it, having just been to Nigeria?
- Yeah, yeah, that makes sense.
I thought you were saying like,
it's a myth that they imported large quantities
of Portuguese urine, and actually,
they just used good old fashioned Roman urine.
(laughing)
But you're saying no urine was probably involved.
- No, I don't think there's any urine involved.
- There's only often they introduce the urine tariffs,
of course, starting getting good at making their own.
- There's a lot of old methods to clean your teeth
and alleviate toothache before it was a paste.
It was powder, so we were all using powder toothpaste.
One of my favorite ones, if not my favorite,
is you would use the ground up ashes of a wolf's head.
But what you say is when you find that dead wolf
and you get its head in order to mash it up and use that,
it is a well-known fact too,
that there are bones generally found
in the excrement of that animal.
These bones attached to an amulet
are protective as well.
There's a lot going on.
- It's an undertaking, isn't it?
(laughing)
- It's laborious every night, I guess.
Yeah, you gotta add a toothpaste.
- Honestly, compared to,
'cause I've literally been to the dentist two days ago,
and compared to that, I'll take the wolf crap.
- You'll follow a wolf run until it does a shit,
immediately kill it, turn the shit into a necklace.
- Rather than an hour and a half of drilling,
yeah, I'll go for it.
- Fair enough.
- My dentist said, "Mr. Harkin, you have a very strong tongue."
(laughing)
- Wow, wow, would you like to join my gentleman's rub club?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that things
that French newspapers were censored
from mentioning during World War I included,
any use of the word peace without the word victorious,
any mention of the cold weather,
in case it reminded people about the shortage of coal,
and any reference of a meeting
between the president's wife and a wild ape.
- I mean, what twist?
- And did that reference a specific occasion,
or was it just in case anyone--
- It did, it did, yeah, there was an incident
involving Henriette Poincar,
who was the wife of the president.
And on the Wikipedia for the Alise Palace,
it says in 1917, a chimpanzee escaped
from a nearby menagerie, entered the palace,
and was said to have tried to hold the wife
of president Raymond Poincar into a tree,
only to be foiled by the guards.
And-- - How strong was it
that he could have held her into a tree?
- Oh, what chimpanzees? - I know chimpanzees are strong,
but that's bulky.
- A teenage girl chimpanzee would beat you in an arm wrestle.
- I don't doubt it, I don't doubt it.
- I know you've been bulking up.
- Thank you, I think a teenage human girl
would probably beat Andy in an arm wrestle.
Oh wow, it's going there, are we?
- Can I celebrate strong women, Dan?
I'm sorry you don't.
(all laughing)
- Wow, in the metaphorical arm wrestle,
but in this discussion, you just got slammed.
- I got beat shitless, yeah.
- So I read this on Wikipedia,
and I looked for some contemporary reports,
and I found this mention,
actually this was from the 1930s they mentioned it,
it was in the London Diary,
and it was things that you were not allowed to mention
in 1916 in France in World War I.
So that seemed to be that it might have happened,
but then I went further back
and found some reports in 1916 in the American press,
and this definitely did happen.
And the Baron Henri de Rothschild
had a place near the Elisae Palace,
and he'd been to the Far East,
which means that maybe this might have been
an orangutan, we think.
He brought it to his home near the Elisae Palace,
and it had escaped.
- Oh my God.
- And I read one account in the Oldie magazine,
a bit more recently, that said,
"The ape wrapped her in his embrace,
took her by the waist,
and attempted to carry her up a tree."
- That was like King Kong.
- It is King Kong, that's it.
- And then apparently, Poincar, the president,
he apparently put the orangutan up
against the firing squad.
- No, according to one article.
- Which is still King Kong.
That's the exact quote.
- So I mean, whether that's all true or not,
like it definitely was reported in 1916 when it happened.
- 'Cause it's really hard, isn't it?
'Cause it was censored from the French press.
- Yes, you've picked a really hard factor, especially.
- But it was mentioned in the world press around the time.
And apparently, President Deschanel, who came after him,
he was so impressed by the ape
that he took to jumping in trees during state receptions.
- Oh, wow.
- But he was the one who went a bit crazy.
- He was very mad, wasn't he?
- Deschanel was the manic pixie dream president, wasn't he?
He was, he was the one who woke up on a train,
opened the window, fell out of it,
as it was going 35 miles an hour.
They didn't know until the next morning that he was gone.
And he was found by a local rail guy who,
he was saying, "I'm the president of France."
He goes, "Sure, mate, sure, okay."
Brings him to his home and they just keep him there
until he convinces them that he is, yeah.
- And then later on, he left the palace
to go into the gardens and started chatting
to a park worker, but he had no trousers on.
And then he stepped into an ornamental fountain
thinking it was a bath.
And then he resigned.
- Yeah, he was in the stress of the job.
- No, in fairness, like we think now
that he had some sort of really awful
sort of sleep deprivation illness.
- Help in a syndrome, I think it was called sleep.
Sleep drunkenness is a, yeah.
- But yeah, it was basically he would never,
he couldn't go into REM sleep or anything.
So even when he slept,
he just wasn't getting his brain refreshed.
- Oh boy, what a pain.
- It's so weird 'cause he lasted a long time being fine.
And then as soon as he became president.
- Maybe the stress did do something for it.
- Yeah, his wife was called Jermaine.
And I just think I've blown something open
but I don't quite know what because she's,
so Jermaine Deschanel was there.
She was a society lady.
She looks like she would have been so good at entertaining
'cause your whole role as first lady then
was throwing big parties and she was brilliant at that.
So such a shame he only lasted about a minute as president.
But she's called Jermaine.
They were married in St. Jermaine church
and he first went mad in St. Jermaine forest.
- All right, so what's your theory?
- Well, I was throwing something open
but I don't know what it is.
- Is this like the Peckham Butcher?
Do you think she doesn't exist?
- Well, she is the devil or something
who she drove him mad by embodying a forest
and then a church.
- I think it's a very Jermaine theory.
- Oh yeah.
- And there's the missing piece.
- Yes.
- The pun.
(all laughing)
- You need for any conspiracy theory to be the pun.
- So this original president's wife,
the one who bumped into the orangutan
was Madame Poincar, right?
She was, so Mr. Poincar,
her, him indoors, was Raymond who was president,
very presently, president for the whole
First World War and some years on either side,
PM three times as well over a longer period,
like really, very imminent.
- And then came back to be president again,
I think, afterwards.
- Wow.
Yeah, I mean, so like amazing political career.
So he would have had tube toothpaste.
- Right?
- He would have had tube toothpaste.
- Yeah.
- So his cousin was Henri Poincar,
mathematician, who James, you might?
- Oh, of conjecture fame.
- Of conjecture fame, and I'm putting big quotes on that.
- Poincar, conjecture.
- So he's, yeah, he's really famous, right?
- Oh yeah.
- In maths world.
- In maths world, yeah.
- So I just love this, this is a slight sidebar,
but he was in a picture, Henri Poincar,
which is known as the most intelligent photo ever taken.
- So there are lots of smart people in it.
- Exactly.
- More than that one from the Oscars
with Ellen the generous in it.
- Amazingly, no, that one,
that was not the most intelligent photo I've taken,
but this was in 1927.
So it was the previous record holder.
Can we guess who's in the photo?
Would we know?
- Let's say Einstein.
I'll give you a clue.
- Neil's bar.
- Can I give you the clue?
- Wait.
- Proust.
- Please wait.
- Marie Curie.
- Hugo.
- I mean, you kind of hit all of them.
- The 1927 Solvay conference on quantum mechanics,
which was held in Brussels, attracted,
there were 29 people in this photo,
17 of whom got Nobel prizes.
- Oh my God.
- The photo was stunning.
So you said Einstein.
You said Marie Curie.
You said Dirac.
Someone said Paul Dirac.
Neil's ball, Max Planck, Heisenberg,
Erwin Trdinger, August Picard.
Like everybody, 17 of them got no bells.
And just Picard.
- Wow.
- I know.
Yeah, Picard, yeah, yeah.
But there's just one photo of the,
maybe the most intelligent conference
that's ever happened.
- It wasn't in the.
- And Poincar was in it.
- Oh, he took it.
He was in it.
- He was one of the.
- Wow.
- There were people in it.
- And that's lots of nuclear physicists
of that period as well, right?
- Right.
- 'Cause I wonder if the phrase,
"If an atomic bomb dropped on us right now,"
would have been used.
- I'm afraid the atomic bomb hadn't been invented.
- No, no, no.
Okay.
Well, a bomb.
- Is there a phrase that says,
"If an atomic bomb dropped on us right now"?
- No, I was just adding that to the bomb.
If a bomb hit this.
- If a bomb, right.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- If a bomb hit this recording studio we're in right now,
no effect on global history.
(all laughing)
- Do yourself that.
- Although next year's top barbecue podcast
might be short one candidate.
(all laughing)
Can I just ask quickly the censorship over that story,
is it because it wasn't so much that it was embarrassing?
It's just that no matter what interview they gave,
the journalist was just desperate to say.
- You know what Dan?
Like I really, I did a lot of very, very in-depth research
on this and it's very difficult to research,
but I think it was because they were trying to keep morale
up in the country.
I can't think of anything that would improve morale more
than if I found out what's the name Starmer
that was attacked by a cheetah
in the background down on the street.
(all laughing)
- Well, I think also like it could denigrate his authority.
- Yeah, right.
Like they're quite good about,
well rather they're quite strict about private lives
in France in particular.
- Yeah, that's true.
- But you're right.
And it's sort of a leading industrialist as well.
It's like if Alan Sugar's pet Komodo dragon
had temporarily abducted Mrs. Starmer.
- And Starmer's had it shot by a firing squad.
- Yes. - Lovely.
- She, Madame Poincar, she was quite controversial.
In fact, the Queen of England was very snobbish
about her, Queen Mary.
They did an official visit in 1914
and she refused to be seen with her at first.
- Sorry, that's just grinning away
at the thought of Queen Mary
using some collapsible toothpaste tubes.
- I was about to say, how did you know?
- 'Cause I had the same thought then.
(all laughing)
- I don't know the state of her dental hygiene.
All I know is I'm trying to make the serious point
that the English, the Brits were very snobbish
because Madame Poincar, she was very old when she married.
This wasn't why they disapproved.
This is sort of why I disapproved when I read about the story.
She was in her, she was 46
and the primus was a bit younger.
So Queen Mary refused to share a carriage with her
because she was divorced and her first husband
was a cab driver who was still alive.
- Oh, okay. - Unbelievable.
- It's showing because they could have run
with the headline Cougar attacked by chimpanzee.
(all laughing)
- Very good.
- I mean, that mirrors current prime minister,
sorry, Brigitte Macron.
- The French are into it, yeah.
- And they're also into presidents
having lots of mistresses all the way.
Franois Hollande, he had four children
with his long-term partner,
but then when he became president,
moved in with his mistress, Valrie Truvile.
But then he cheated on her with an actor
with an actress and it was really funny
'cause he went off to see this actress
with a motorcycle helmet on his head
thinking that no one would be able to tell it was him.
But he wore the same pair of socks
that he'd been wearing at a recent international visit.
So the photographers took a photo of him
and went, "I recognize those socks."
- Whoa. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- That was bad luck.
- What does the sock say, president of France?
Like what was-- (all laughing)
- It must have been quite distinctive.
- I think it must have been
'cause most socks are just quite plain.
- Most male professionals wear plain black socks.
- That's why I always wear plain black socks
is so I can get away with being a cat.
- What socks I'm wearing?
- Just a shagger on your socks, James.
(all laughing)
- I'm wearing part of a girl's socks,
which I reckon if, oh, look at Dan's.
He's got bright yellow ones.
- James, you must be the only man
in London wearing those socks today.
- I know, if I have an affair.
- Yeah, you're screwed.
- Dan, what's that?
- It's blast skateboards.
It's their logo.
I am the only man wearing this in London today,
but because of them, I will not be having an affair.
- I think the same applies to James.
- Show you mine, plain black.
- Lovely, lovely.
- If you see a man having an affair
and playing back socks, you know it's not me or Dan.
- No, and if they've got a little garter
and they're tighter than me, you'll know it's me.
(all laughing)
He is not, I don't mean to be rude about him,
but he's not David Gandhi.
- Oland, who's saying?
- Oland, yeah.
He's an example of power being a great aphrodisiac.
You know, he's sort of just a very average-looking dude
who happened to be the president of France.
- He's not David Gandhi, is that the best?
- Yeah, I don't know.
Is that Mahatma Gandhi's brother?
- He's Mahatma Gandhi's, yeah, yeah.
Mahatma Gandhi had taken his well-man pills.
He would have looked like David.
- David's one of my top-end model, male model.
- He's an underpan model.
- Right. - Oh, yeah.
- Okay, yeah.
- Is this the first ever modern popular culture reference
that Andy's ever said on the podcast?
- I think it might be, yeah.
- Maybe that none of us have, well, I've got it,
but like that you two haven't heard it.
- I can't believe you haven't, Hannah.
- He's sort of a famous guy.
- You think I know a lot of male underpan models?
- He might get a magazine or something, I don't know.
- Right, yeah.
- But Jack Chirac, President of France?
- Yeah.
- He muddled the pants.
- Well, he might as well have done.
I mean, he certainly showed his pants off a lot.
- Did he?
- He, when he was mayor of Paris in the 1980s,
he ordered the city council to buy him a coat
fitted with a bedroom so he could meet lovers
on official engagement.
- Oh, wow.
- Sorry, a coat fitted with a bedroom.
- Coat.
- Coat, right?
- Coat like a bus.
- Like a national express.
(laughing)
- Like a mega bus.
- A really mega bus.
- Was that so he could have lots of affairs
not just so he could sleep between?
- No, it was specifically so he could meet lovers.
- Did he say that?
- Well, he had his private jet when he was president,
had a room that was for trists.
- Lovely.
He has the weirdest thing, which made me sort of warm to him.
So Jack and Bernadette, his wife,
brought a Vietnamese refugee to live with them
and sort of adopted a Vietnamese refugee.
And it was on a whim.
So this woman was called Anne Dow Traxel.
She was actually about 20.
But she'd escaped from a refugee camp in 1979
when the Vietnamese were having a not very good time.
And she was crying in the corner of an airport in France.
And Jack Shorak saw her, approached her,
and said, "Don't cry, my dear,
from now on you'll live with us."
- Hmm, okay.
I've got a special bedroom on the jumper.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Can I tell you one French heroine I found out,
she wasn't First Lady of France or anything,
but just in the course of researching her,
so I found out about her, 'cause she was amazing.
Her name was Valerie Andr.
She died this year in February.
She was the wife of President Peter Andr,
wasn't she?
- She was.
And she was a mysterious girl.
She died this year.
She was 102 years old, right?
So she lived 1923 to 2025.
She was, in this order, a brain surgeon, a parachutist,
and the first woman to fly helicopter missions
in combat zones, and the first French woman
to become a general in their army.
- Wow.
- She would do parachute jumps into combat zones
if someone had been wounded, right?
You know, she would either do parachute jumps in
or she would fly a helicopter in herself,
pick up a wounded soldier in the helicopter,
fly them to hospital, and then she'd say,
"Hello, I'm gonna be your surgeon today,"
and do the operation on them.
- That's amazing.
- I just think I was like, imagine that.
Imagine you're pilot then becoming a surgeon
halfway through and patching you up.
Just crazy.
- I think I would feel less confident in her in both roles.
(laughing)
- I think you're not putting your full life
into being a helicopter pilot or a surgeon, are you?
- Would you say that before she made the first incision,
or would you maybe wait until?
- I'd be like, do we not have someone
who studied their whole life as a surgeon
who could do my surgery, please?
- Looking at gift horse in the mouth, or what?
(laughing)
- That's so funny.
- I'm not gonna sign this consent form.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram.
You can find me at @triberland.
James.
- My Instagram is @no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy, I'm on Blue Sky at @andrewhubtureb.
And if you wanna get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can go on Twitter at no such thing
or Instagram at no such thing as a fish
or email podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, or you can head to our website,
no such thing as a fish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
There's also links to an upcoming live show
that we're doing later this year in Sheffield.
It is part of the Crossed Wires Festival.
That's happening on the 6th of July.
Tickets are available.
We also have a lot of merch that's up there.
We have the entrance to our secret club,
which has bonus episodes behind the scenes stuff.
It has extra compilations of all the outtakes.
From our show, it's called Club Fish.
- Is it still $2.99 then?
- At the moment, but I am on the brink of changing
that, James.
So get in quick, get in while that lasts,
and yeah, otherwise just come back
'cause we will be back here with another episode next week
and we will see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]