(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Shriver.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
of our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that shortly after writing an essay
on why writers shouldn't publish anonymously,
Anthony Trollett published a book anonymously.
- Oh, it's called out a mere 130 years from later.
(laughing)
- Not a moment too soon.
I've just sort of inherited from a friend
who decided he was never gonna read them,
the complete works of Anthony Trollett.
And he's giving them to me in bits
and he seems to have given me
the three least known Anthony Trollett.
So this is an introduction to Nina Bellatka, which was...
- If you wanna get into Trollett,
I would say probably don't start with that one.
- It's not an entry level, no, no.
Anyway, this fact, Nina Bellatka in the introduction,
it just mentioned that he wrote an essay in 1865
and he said a man should always dare to be responsible
for the work which he does
and should be ready to accept the shame, rebuffs, ridicule,
or the indifference which will attend bad work.
And it's all about how, you know,
put your name to something
and then he didn't put his name to Nina Bellatka and...
- I do have some sympathy, but if your name is A Trollop
that you don't wanna put it on every big video.
(laughing)
- Who here has read Trollop?
- I've read the start of Barchester Towers.
- Okay.
- Did you read it in preparation for this book?
- I certainly did. (laughing)
- Read the first 50 pages.
- Nice.
- Like I've done quite a lot of books over the years
just because of this podcast.
- Yeah.
- Just kind of started reading, got an idea and gone,
well, I think I've got an idea
of this guy's entire earth right now.
- How have you got to the end?
You don't know about the robots in it.
- What?
So Anna's read some Trollop, Andy, you must have done.
- I'm actually a Trollop virgin.
- Honestly, I said to my wife last night
that if anyone likes Anthony Trollop,
Andy would like Anthony Trollop.
- Is it because he writes about ecclesiastical
matters in the 19th century?
- Yeah.
- I think I will.
- It's right up your street.
- I don't know if it is.
I think that's a missed call on Andy.
- You think?
- Yeah, I do.
I think I slightly prefer that kind of literature.
- It feels like it's in between what you would like.
It feels to me like it's halfway between Dickens
and Jane Austen.
- It is, but the thing about Anthony Trollop,
he's not as widely read as I think he should be.
He's frowned on in a lot of circles
because he was just a machine.
- Yeah.
- Of output, wasn't he?
47 novels, loads of stories.
His routine was getting up every morning,
5.30, writing for three solid hours.
He put a watch in front of him,
made himself write 250 words every 15 minutes,
and he didn't have word counts that time.
So he must have incorporated counting the words.
- He must have counted the pages
'cause he just had so much stuff.
- I love it.
I think that's exactly how I would write
if I was writing novels.
- I actually thought reading about him,
and this is not a negative thing at all.
I thought there's quite a lot of you in him.
- He's quite annoying.
We all write books.
As someone who, you know, footles around a bit,
toys with the margins.
As you know, and you just see,
in the time you've spent footling around with the margins,
Anthony Trollop will have written 16 pages in prose.
He had a portable desk made.
I love this.
So he could write on trains.
And if he was going on board a ship,
he would meet up with the ship's carpenter
to arrange proper writing conditions.
- That's pretty ritzy.
- Wow.
- That's cool.
- But the reason he had to do it was 'cause he was,
and I'm simplifying here, postman.
(all laughing)
You are simplifying.
But he wrote in the morning
'cause he had a full-time job at the post office
for about, what, how long was this?
Decades.
- Yeah.
- And he was quite 60s.
- He was really senior.
He was really senior in the post office.
- Yeah, what if you worked there that long?
- And it's that really cool fact,
which is the only thing I knew about him,
which is that he's basically responsible
for the reason that we have post boxes all over the UK.
Possibly he's spotted in in France.
I don't think he ever claimed that he invented it,
but he certainly recommended it to the government.
And they used to be green, but now they're red.
- That's the thing though.
Like he is responsible for that, I suppose,
but they did exist in France.
They did exist in Belgium.
The stamp had been invented about 30 or 40 years earlier.
It feels like we might have got there anyway,
even without him.
- Maybe totally, but he's the one who did, yeah.
Hey, here's a cool quote just to sort of really hammer home
what a workaholic he was.
He said, "There is no human bliss equal to 12 hours of work
"with only six hours in which to do it."
- He was a bit like bankers in 1990s in the UK
because his motto was, "No day without a line."
- Hey.
Can we talk a little about Fanny Trollop?
- Sure. - Yeah.
- His mum. - Yeah.
- Yes, please.
- So his parents were very interesting people.
Just briefly, his dad was a complete failure in life.
Sounds harsh, but it is true.
- It must have been someone in a podcast
in 200 years saying that about you.
- I know, I know, and they will.
I hope they will, I dream of them doing that, you know.
But his father had law work which had failed
and a farm which had failed.
And he decided finally to write, I think,
called the Encyclopedia Ecclesiastica,
which would define all the ecclesiastical terms
that had ever existed.
And by the time he died,
he was still only on the letter D.
- Ah, to be honest, church is quite a long one.
- Oh, huge, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, it was R-Men.
There's another biggy guy on the top.
Chassable.
- I mean, you can see why he-- - Chassel.
- You can see why he struggled, you know.
- Christian, Catholic.
- Oh, baby Jesus, starting with David.
(both laughing)
- Yeah, yeah.
- Anyway, that was his dad, tricky time.
But his mum was a successful author and mega successful.
And she made her name by writing a book
called The Domestic Manners of the Americans.
'Cause she'd gone to America, set up this business venture
which had completely collapsed and been a disaster.
And, but then she wrote this book,
which was basically just incredibly rude
about everyone in the USA.
It was very, very, very snobbish.
And it became a massive success.
- She said of people living in New York,
that they were bullying, struggling, crafty,
enterprising, industrious, swaggering,
drinking, boasting, and money-getting.
But then enemy of the podcast, Mark Twain.
- Thank you.
(both laughing)
- He really loved her and he was like basically saying,
well, you know, she's telling the truth.
That's what we're like, fair enough, fair play.
- So he liked her, so I now don't like her.
Great, okay, thank you.
I'm sort of keeping my beef going throughout the century.
- One thing I noticed from reading the first 50 pages
by Chester Towers is how hackish he is with names.
- Oh, really?
- I don't know if you notice the same with the ones
that you've read before.
- I've only read the way we live now.
- Well, like the first two,
a couple of the first characters are,
I think the policemen and they're called
Landon Mew New and Omicron Pie,
where he's basically just taken Greek letters
and turned them into names.
- Right.
- So what he used to do quite a lot is do that thing
where, I suppose Dickens did it a bit,
where you just take whatever attribute your character has
and just call them that.
- Oh yeah, Dickens is, yeah.
- Right, yeah.
- So in his novel, Miss Mackenzie,
it's about a young woman who's pursued by three men
who are called Handcock, Rub and Ball.
- What?
(both laughing)
- And there was another man.
- Handcock?
(both laughing)
- And there's another man in it where he's not a suitable
suitor for this woman, and he's called Mr. Frigidae.
- Wow.
- I mean, they're so on the note.
- It takes a bit of the suspense out of it, doesn't it?
- Yeah, I think so.
I wonder if I can give you some names of characters
and you can tell me what they did in the novel.
- Oh, okay, yeah, great.
- So Dick Rabbit.
- Ended up in prison.
- So, Shaggy Rabbit, obviously, yeah.
Had lots of kids, breed it a lot.
- Nice.
- No, he was the leader of a hunt.
- Okay.
- Yeah, good.
- Samuel Nickham.
- Policeman?
- Police, yeah, yeah.
- Kind of.
He wasn't a policeman, but he found evidence against
some people who've been poisoning animals.
- I was going to say shoplifter,
and I've only just realized that nicking him
is something that shoplifters do, and policemen do.
I nick him.
No, I nick him.
We're on opposite sides.
How confusing.
- Gosh, yeah, food for thought.
- So, Oliver Crumblewit.
- Stand up, stand up comedian.
- Yeah.
- Someone who thinks they're funny.
So, like, this is on a dad joke
to call back to the previous episode character.
- No, he was a phrenologist.
- Crumble.
- So, just like, witless person,
I guess he was slugging off phrenology.
And Joe Thurabug.
- Thurabug.
(all laughing)
- Proctologist.
- No, he was a brewer, of course.
- Oh, very nice.
- Brewer, I was going to say the bunghole in the sherry.
That's right.
Did you, sorry, just while we're quickly
on Barchester Towers, have you ever got to a bit
in the book where he injects himself as a narrator?
Because that's something he apparently loves to do.
So, he does it twice.
- He pops in.
So, for example, there's a sentence
that comes in that book where it says,
"How easily she would have forgiven
"and forgotten the Archdeacon's suspicions
"had she heard the whole truth from Mr. Arobin,
"but then where would have been my novel?"
- Oh, I didn't notice that, I love it.
- And then right at the end, he says,
"The end of a novel, like the end of a children's
"dinner party must be filled with sweet meats
"and sugar plums, obviously alluding maybe
"to a nice happy ending."
- Yes, followed by tears, someone being sick,
people being dragged home, screaming.
- Nits being spread.
- Yeah, he does do that self-consciously a little bit.
Yeah, sometimes we'll be like,
"She's my favorite, actually, she's lovely."
- I think that's good.
I mean, Jane Austen does that all the time,
just sort of pops her head around the curtain
and says, "Hello," and then pops back.
I like it.
Have you heard of his novel, The Fixed Period?
This is very weird.
So this was his, I think, only venture into sci-fi
where it's set in 1980 on a fictional island
in the southern hemisphere called Britannula.
And the main point of the story is that it has
compulsory euthanasia for anyone
between the age of 67 and 68, that's the idea.
It also features a futuristic cricket match.
- Bit harsh, you can't get to the best age.
- Right, yeah, yeah.
- Maybe he was sick of all the innuendo.
- Right, there's a steam tricycle
which can go at 25 miles an hour.
So it's still rooted in the 19th century.
But, get this, Trollope died at the age of 67 and a half.
- Did he?
- Dun, dun, dun, dun, dun, dun, dun, dun, dun, dun, dun.
He didn't do much on the sci-fi,
but basically, I think his novels were essentially
a Marvel marvel.
- Marvel?
- Marvel, sorry.
- Andrew Marvel.
- An Andrew Marvel universe.
- 17th century Laureate.
- Yeah.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- That's so funny.
- It's how they, but world enough and time,
they would, is that him?
- Yeah, very good.
- And then they would have written a Marvel comic
because he basically did that.
He created a universe.
- Ah, right, oh, lovely, yeah, yeah.
- And I think this kind of explains why he was able
to churn things out so much,
as well as the fact that when you read them,
there are a lot of extra words.
But like the passage of chronicles,
oh well, you can lose a lot.
- Have you ever read, sorry to, this is a digression,
but have you ever read the Wumble books?
- No.
- I was reading the Wumble books to my daughter
and all the way through, it's like,
and then the Wumble went to the park
and picked up some litter.
They picked up an umbrella, a bag of crisps,
like this, and they just fill up all the sentences
with just lists of nonsense.
- That's your word count for the day.
That's Trollup thinking, right,
I put in 16 adjectives to describe this table.
That's fine, I can knock off for the next five minutes.
- Can't believe you're reading the Wumble books.
'Cause I thought it was just a TV show.
You're the guy who's like, you know,
the books are actually--
- The novelizations of the Wumbles
are actually really, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think the books came before the TV show.
- Oh, sure they did, yeah.
- Anyway.
- So it's the Trollup Cinematic Universe.
- The Cinematic Universe, so it embosses shit.
It's really fun, so I've only read one
and actually it's The Way We Live Now, which isn't the universe,
but my husband happens to have read quite a few more
and he says it's fun 'cause characters pop in
from other places.
- Lovely, I love it, I love it, I love it a lot.
- So that Vick who was quite annoying when he was 25
is now 40 and he's a bit wiser.
- I reckon that he had hyper-fantasia.
- Oh yeah.
- Which is, so I have a fantasia,
which means I can't imagine things,
but some people have hyper-fantasia
where you really can't imagine anything.
It's like just an incredible story going on in your head
and sometimes you don't even realize that it's in your head.
And he used to say that his main work that he did was
when he was daydreaming.
So, you know, he would churn out these words,
but actually the rest of the day he'd just be thinking,
"Oh, I wonder what my characters would be doing now."
When he came to write them down, it was pretty easy for him
'cause it was just, this is what I remember them doing.
- I think he almost says that the plot
is kind of not even really important.
It's just, it's about the characters exactly, as you say.
- I want to know what his legs were like
'cause I think he might have had a fantastic pair of legs.
- Okay, go on.
- Well, he was all over the UK
for his work for the post office.
It was sent to Ireland, first of all,
which is where he started writing.
And basically he had to work out the routes for postmen
and he rode across the countryside.
He did about 40 miles a day riding across the countryside.
- It feels like the horse would have a good leg.
- No, you're right, sorry.
He'd have a great bum.
But he was a member of a thing called the Tramp Society,
which was a ramblers club across Southeast England.
They just walked huge distances every time they let up.
Yeah, so I think, I think his lower half
might have been incredibly fit.
- Well, in support, I think of that.
Do you know what the hardest day's work
he ever did in his life was?
And that's a high bar for Truller.
- Oh, no.
- It was walking.
And it was when he was posted to Glasgow
and he wanted to review postman's jobs, basically.
And postmen in Glasgow were having to go
up and down tenement blocks,
sometimes to just post a letter to one person.
And he walked the full Glasgow postman's route
up and downstairs on his beat
and came back to the post office and none of them was like,
"Hey, those guys have it really rough.
We need to sort it out."
- Yes.
- His second-ever novel sold 140 copies.
- Okay.
- Yeah, it did not sell.
- What's that one?
- They were both set in Ireland, his first two.
I think he saw a picture of them and published them out.
Oh, I don't know.
But the publisher had a resort to advert saying,
"Do you know who this guy's mum is?
This guy's mum is Fanny Truller."
- Fanny Truller, which is so embarrassing
as a young debut novelist, you know.
What a quote for the front of the book.
"Do you know who his mum is?"
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that in 2008,
a TV channel spent the day rescheduling shows
so that millions of people in India
could continue to watch a live broadcast
of a man trying to kill another man
using nothing but his mind.
- Okay.
- And it took longer than expected.
Is it like when a football match goes into extra time
and you have to cancel the news afterwards?
- It's like that tennis.
Do you remember, it was at Mahut Isner?
- Mahut Isner.
- Which went on, it was a Wimbledon several,
like 10 years ago now, and it went on,
they played like 70 games each.
- Yeah, it was something like that.
- It was something like crackers.
- Yeah, it was kind of that.
- And Mahut Isner, I imagine, got closer to death
than the person who was trying to be killed here.
- Well, not quite, actually.
So, okay, at that time, there was a politician
who said out loud that she thought
that someone was attacking her mentally
using Tantric powers, which is, you know,
when we talk about Tantric sex and all that,
there's a side of it, which is to do with the mind,
and you can supposedly attack people
if you're using the dark practices of it, right?
So, as a result, there was a TV show
where skeptics and Tantra practitioners
were brought together on the show,
it was called Tantric Power versus Science.
And while on the show, this guy who was called
Pandit Srintheshama claimed that he could kill someone
within minutes using nothing but his mind.
Now, the person who was sitting on the panel with him
was a guy called Sinal Edamaruku.
- Is he representing Science in this?
- He is the president of the Rational International Group.
He says, you can't do that.
You think you can do that?
Do it to me now.
And the guy says, okay, fine, I'll do it to you now.
- That's annoying when they call your bluff like that,
isn't it? - Exactly.
So, he says, do it now.
So, they say, all right, let's do this.
The host of the show is going, all right, let's do this.
- Legally, very tricky water for the channel
and the program to be in. - Exactly.
- 'Cause I'm thinking about all the forms
we have to fill in on QI if you just, you know,
strike a match.
- You very rarely use dark tantra on QI.
- So, basically what happens is, is this guy, Sharma gets up
and he starts focusing his mind on him.
It's clearly not working.
The rational guy is sort of giving laps and so on.
So, Sharma comes over, he starts sprinkling water on him
as an intimidation tactic.
He starts ruffling his hair.
- Oh, the big guns are coming out now.
- He covers his eyes.
- It was all that stuff.
But then, and this is where it gets a bit desperate,
he suddenly presses his fingers down onto his forehead
and steadily really pushes and pushes
and he has to be called out because basically,
you will kill me 'cause you're trying
to crush my skull, basically.
So, he has to go back to his seat
and he has to do it with his mind.
Now, at this point, the show's meant to be ending.
But they say it's not done yet.
So, the show continues and the next show is canceled.
And at this point, word is getting around.
So, people are tuning in and tuning in.
After a couple of hours, the guy's exhausted,
Sharma's exhausted and he says,
"But I'm not done yet.
"Let's meet again this evening.
"And this evening, I will do the ultimate destruction ceremony
"and kill you."
What is going through his mind when he's saying,
"I'm gonna do that?"
I'm sure I can think of an ultimate destruction ceremony
in the two hours between the broadcast.
Like, what is his plan?
- But then, I think his plan probably is to not turn up
and then go, "Oh, sorry, I was killing some other person."
They go to another school, you wouldn't know them.
- Yeah, so they do it at night.
It's performed under an altar in an open night sky.
They've got all the cameras there
and he tries and tries and tries.
And obviously, the guy who's the rational guy
is laughing his ass off the whole time.
So, it didn't work out.
But this, just to remind you, is 2008.
And this was broadcast live.
And according to many reports,
some say hundreds of millions,
obviously a huge population in India.
But millions tuned in to see a man killed live on TV,
probably knowing he wasn't gonna be,
but wanted to see what happened.
- I have a question for you guys.
If you were on that TV show
and you were next to a tantric master
and they said, "I could kill someone with my mind,"
would you have the courage to say,
"No, you can't do it to me."
You definitely would.
There wouldn't be a tiny bit of doubt
that like, I'm pretty sure you can't.
- Once he started, I'd shit my pants.
But yeah, I would probably call it.
- I would feel fairly confident
that that wouldn't happen.
- No, but you can't be fairly confident.
- Okay, I would be 100% certain
that that wouldn't happen.
- You'd be up for it.
- I would be pretty confident,
but I would think to myself,
"I'd be so annoyed if I have a heart attack and die."
Unrelatedly.
- When I went to, I was in Bhutan
and I went to the tiger's nest monastery.
And there's a little bit where you have to jump
from one bit to the other
and you're going over a sheer drop of thousands of feet.
And the step is basically just a step.
It's a step that you do every single day
and it's no problem.
But all the way through, I was thinking,
"If I fall now, what a fucking idiot.
"What an idiot I am to be doing that."
And I suppose it's that kind of thought.
- And the pressure of the TV cameras
will make you think, "This is a very public forum."
I can understand, I'm very impressed by the skeptic.
- You'd feel embarrassed for him.
You'd start wanting to die.
- Yeah, yeah.
- You'd fake it.
- Do you think you'd fake it, Dan?
- I'd fake it.
- Well, it would be really fun
to draw the death Tantra dude out
by pretending to die and then like, "Aaah."
And that would be great.
- That's a good point.
- I've never heard of this.
I think of Tantra as primarily a sexual thing.
Now, I'm thinking about Sting.
- Yes.
- Who proclaimed, I think, in the 90s
that he could have sex for five hours because of Tantra.
Just Tantric skills.
- He says he never said that.
- I don't know if he does now, but that's--
- Right.
- He says, "Bob Geldoff spread that rumor."
- Yeah.
- And then he said, "Oh, I said five hours,
but that includes dinner and a movie
followed by some begging."
You know, he's got some very funny jokes about it.
Yeah, yeah.
But that was--
- No movie is.
- Lord of the Rings.
- The entire trilogy.
- No, but I don't know anything about Tantra, really.
Although the idea of Tantra,
and I gather it's more of a philosophy
or a set of philosophies.
And it's from lots of different--
- Very complicated.
- Lots of different religions have elements of Tantra.
- Definitely, yeah.
- That sort of spread across all these different schools
of thought.
- There's no one thing.
And when I say the dark side or whatever,
that's so rare, it's not really even a thing.
We'll get letters, people saying,
"That's not a thing."
- Right, right, right, yeah.
- Well, there's space in Hinduism.
- Yeah.
- When we say lots of different religions.
And it's not its own belief system within Hinduism
as far as I can tell.
It's like a series of practices
which seem to exist in lots of strands of Hinduism.
- Yeah, it's almost like non-Orphodox Hinduism.
- Yeah.
In fact, I did read things saying the whole point of it
was to subvert Hinduism and encourage lots of things
that Hinduism does not.
Like, I think there's one where you're encouraged
to have the special Tantric fivesm,
which is like eating meat, drinking wine.
- Right.
(all laughing)
- Have you ever had a fivesm?
Yeah, I've had a bit of meat and a drink, a bit of wine, yeah?
- Coming to the party to make it.
- I didn't have--
- Wine's everyone in there.
- Yes.
- God, that looks delicious.
I've had a foursome.
I didn't have the sherry at the end,
which would have been, you know.
- To be fair, sex is the last one.
- Oh, okay, okay.
So it's like a date.
We're not describing a date.
- Are we describing a date?
- What are the previous four?
Is there an order?
- Netflix.
- Sorry.
- It's drinking, eating, movie, begging.
(all laughing)
Sex.
- So the five are alcohol, meat, fish, grain, and sex.
- Okay.
- You're very full at that point,
so it's not very pleasant.
- We do that five at home,
but the fifth one is always headache.
(all laughing)
- I'm really annoyed.
- But the idea is violating all these Hindu taboos.
- I see.
- And I think that's called left-handed tantra.
So there's left-handed tantra and right-handed tantra,
and left-handed tantra is the sex one.
- I'm left-handed.
- Well, that doesn't surprise me.
- No, no, no, no.
It's all starting to come together.
- I always do left-handed tantra,
'cause it feels like someone else is doing that.
(all laughing)
- There's no thousand-year-old tradition
we can be trusted with.
(all laughing)
- Other things that are done in tantra traditions
that are non-sexual for the right-handed,
living in cemeteries, if you want that,
and smearing cremation ashes on your body.
So these are all agori rituals.
- And do you say agori?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause it sounds quite gory.
- Oh yeah, agori tradition, yes.
- I was just missering.
- No, that's very good.
Maybe it's a fun play on words, 'cause it is very dark.
They smoke a lot of marijuana,
not too dark, they drink a lot of alcohol,
and they meditate on top of corpses.
- I got some good news for you, Dan.
- Yeah.
- So they're meditating on a corpse.
There are quite a lot of rules
about the kind of corpse that you can meditate on.
Ideally, it would be someone who died from drowning,
lightning strikes, snake bites, something like that.
You are allowed to kill the person
before you meditate on top of them,
but you shouldn't really meditate on top of a man
with a beard or on top of a wife guy.
- Anyone who's hand-packed, you shouldn't be doing.
- Really?
- Wow, Dan, you're in the clear.
- I am safe and sound, guys.
- Wow.
- But what about a clean-shaven bad boy like me, James?
Am I in the firing line for getting meditated on?
- Oh dear.
- That's amazing.
- I read an amazing way of if someone,
if so, let's say we are on that show
and we have said yes, consenting to Sharma
trying to kill us with his mind.
One way of getting him out of your mind
and shaking off the bad juju that's inside there
is something that was practiced
by a guy called Viktor Kortchnoy, who's a chess player.
- Yeah.
- Now, we spoke many episodes ago
about a very famous chess championship in 1978,
and there were two Russian grandmaster chess players,
Karpov against Kortchnoy.
And basically, Kortchnoy, as he was sitting there,
had a guy in the audience who was mentally trying
to ruin his game, get into his head.
It was the weirdest chess game ever, right?
Kortchnoy eventually brings in two people
who practice the idea of all this mind power stuff.
And he genuinely did this during the course of the game
to get rid of all the bad thoughts that were in his head.
You do a handstand so that you can shake it out
using the gravity that's pulling down to the earth,
all the bad vibes.
So, if ever you're in a space
where you think you're being infiltrated in your mind,
do a handstand.
- If you believe, though.
- Yeah.
- I mean, we're sort of skirting around the psychosomatic thing.
If you believe that someone is in the crowd
getting into your head.
- Which he did.
- Then they're already in there.
- Yeah.
- And he was in there.
Like, that's exactly it.
He believed that was in there.
- Did he win?
- He lost.
Only just by one game.
He was down, and then he did the handstand thing,
and he came back for like a few games.
And then he lost the final game.
- Didn't shake that last bit out, did he?
- This just reminded me of another interesting Hindu sect,
which I've been fond of for a while, the Nagasadhus.
- Okay.
- Which, we've talked about the Naked Sadhus,
which who are just naked all the time?
- Sadhus.
- Naked Sadhus, yeah.
So, a lot of this is about asceticism
and renouncing everything.
And they have very strict exercise routines.
So, they're very fit, but they have long beards,
but they have no clothes.
They also smear themselves in ashes.
I think this seems to be a thing.
But they were great fighters back in the day.
So, they've been around for many hundreds,
for thousands of years.
And they were military men.
So, in 19th century reports,
they wore nothing but a belt,
and they'd have ammunition and flints and guns
hanging off their belt.
- Wow, like Batman.
- Yeah, but nude Batman.
- Yes, 'cause he normally is wearing
the full Batman outfit.
- He's in fact a bit too covered up, really.
- Yeah, yeah, but I'm just mean like the utility belt.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
- They've got the utility belt.
And that's all you need, really.
And they were great military leaders.
And in fact, there was one in the 18th century
who commanded over 20,000 men.
In fact, quite a few of them commanded that many.
And in the battles that the British East India Company had
when they were trying to colonize India,
they played a huge role.
And bizarrely, they were often mercenaries.
So, they often fought for different sides,
which is weird given that they renounce all possessions.
So, I don't know what you're using,
all that money you're getting paid.
- Oh, you gotta, you know, there are,
there are incidental expenditures and you, you know,
you want to have something for a rainy day.
- You want a really nice belt.
(all laughing)
- That beard oil's very pricey, um.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
And that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the last thing
that British soldiers going to the Crimean War saw
was Queen Victoria throwing a shoe at them.
(all laughing)
- And stay out.
- No, this is a good luck thing.
It's been a good luck thing since the 16th century at least.
And Queen Victoria, when she got married,
she had shoes thrown after her.
So, she obviously had this idea that it was good luck.
And there is an 1854 sketch from Punch Magazine
that shows her throwing a shoe at her soldiers
as they go off for the Crimean War.
- It's very, I'd never heard this tradition at all.
Shoe-trucking for luck.
I've just never, ever heard it.
But she did it a lot.
She did it in 1855.
She chucked shoes into Balmoral Castle again for luck.
And that was a.
- And is it she takes one of her own shoes off
or does she take an extra shoe in her handbag?
- Great question.
- Good question.
- Don't know.
- Yeah, so the first one she's throwing it off
from where she's, she's standing on a balcony.
- That's right.
- So, okay, so she's at home.
She's probably in slippers anyway.
So, she could do that with a shoe.
- And you don't want to chuck a really heavy shoe
in case I hit someone.
- Yeah.
- Well, it's from a balcony.
It seems quite risky.
- That's gonna be my question.
Do we know where the shoe is?
'Cause I couldn't, I couldn't find it.
- The shoe?
- Yeah, the shoe.
- I don't know how many of you have been victorious.
- Yeah, shoes are forever.
- Yeah, but the shoe, lots of shoe traditions.
Hiding shoes in the walls of your building.
That was not the big one, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- Is that for good luck?
Or just for a rainy day?
- To ward off evil.
- Ah, evil hates shoes.
- Yes, the Northampton made all,
basically all the shoes made in the UK
came from Northampton.
- Really?
- Yeah, 'cause it was Chewtown.
- That's why the football team's called the Cobblers.
- Oh, is it?
I didn't know they were.
But they've got a thing called the Hidden Shoe Index
at the Northampton Museum.
- I read it was called the Concealed Shoe Index,
which made me wonder what CSI Northampton would be like.
(laughing)
- Very strong.
I don't know which is the true name.
It goes back to the '50s though,
but the oldest shoe they've got or found in a building
dates back to 1308.
- Wow.
- That was concealed in a building, yeah.
- That's not gonna be wearable, is it?
- No.
- Is this related to,
I mentioned cats being found in buildings.
That's the thing, isn't it?
That people would bury their dead cats.
- Yeah, war-lover's cat, frogs as well.
- Frogs, yes.
Presumably that was for good luck.
- I think it's to also attract or distract or deter witches.
We're back to the evil thing.
- Distract.
Is that what I kept?
(laughing)
That's what I was doing.
Maybe one of the most famous shoe-throwing incidents
is when George Bush had two shoes thrown at him, in fact.
It's in 2008 by an Iraqi reporter.
And actually, I was rereading what George Bush said
when he was asked about it afterwards.
And I thought, you know,
there was a lot of criticism of George Bush
at the time, understandably.
But he said, "I know I wasn't offended.
"We're in a democracy.
"This is freedom for you.
"You're allowed to do this kind of thing."
Which is very mature of him, well done.
- The guy was then imprisoned
and I think beaten very badly.
- He asked a lot of tea, I think.
- I think it was by the Iraqi authorities,
rather than by anyone else.
But yes, it was a sentiment bang on.
- They did a massive shoe statue, didn't they?
Statue.
- Didn't they?
- Yeah.
- Nice.
- Wait, who's in Iraq?
- In Iraq, yeah.
But it was done, I think it was done at a university
or something and they had to take it down
'cause it was seen as being political.
- When they tore it down,
did they run over and beat it
with miniature statues of Saddam Hussein?
(laughing)
- I love that the museum in America
that has, as one of its exhibits, a replica of the shoe.
- Oh, really?
Not even the shoe?
- No, the shoes were destroyed by the CIA.
- Right.
- Sorry, I've never sounded more conspiracies
and winged that whack-off.
Sorry, but they actually were,
because I think they didn't want the shoes to become martyrs.
- Do the CIA need to be drafted into destroy shoes?
I reckon you get the intern.
- Maybe it was the FBI.
- Or the Secret Service, maybe.
- It was the Secret Service, sorry, it was the Secret Service.
But it became big business as well.
All these rival cobalas in the area started claiming,
"Oh yes, that's our shoe."
- Really?
- Yeah.
And the thrower, Mundar al-Zaidi,
he was offered a couple of hands in marriage
by various people who said,
"I'd like you to marry my daughter."
And then, in 2009, he was doing an event,
the year after he did the thing, guess what happened?
- You got a shoe thrown at him?
- He got a shoe thrown at him.
Yeah, it was a real circle of life thing.
- Come up and buy Bush, or?
- Not buy Bush.
(all laughing)
- But Bush has had more shoes thrown at him since.
There's a whole, I mean, it became a thing
post that event generally.
So there's a whole Wikipedia page
where it's a shoe throwing incident, it's called,
and it gives you a big timeline,
and it really picks up after old mate Bush was attacked.
There's a famous incident as well.
Queen Elizabeth, the late Queen, in Australia.
- Second?
- Yeah.
She threw a shoe at Philip when they were in Australia.
It was one of the only moments where a fight,
I think in fact, the only incident in which a fight
was seen between Philip and the Queen,
she threw a tennis racket at him as well.
- A tennis racket?
- Yeah.
- The Aussies were filming from a distance,
and they were like, "Geez, what did we just see?"
'Cause we've never seen anything like that before.
And so one of the PR people had to come out for the Queen
and say, "What are you guys doing?"
With a British accent, they're like, "Oh, the Nazi accent."
And then the Queen came out, and she apologised,
and she said, "Where do you want me?"
As if to say, "Please don't use that.
"I'm here now as an embarrassing apology
"for you witnessing that."
But possibly she was wishing him good luck.
(all laughing)
- Or whatever affair.
- With a lucky tennis racket as well, yeah.
- All of your lucky clothes are out on the lawn.
(all laughing)
- That's so funny.
- Wow.
James, have you ever seen...
I'm asking James specifically this for a reason.
Have you ever seen a panty tree?
(all laughing)
- We know the reason, panty tree.
- No, but I think I can guess what it is.
Is it a tree where people leave their pants?
- That's right.
- Why would I have seen it?
- Why would you specifically, isn't it?
- Is it common in Bolton?
- It's not a Bolton thing.
- I bet it's a golf thing.
- Oh, it's a sporting thing.
- I thought it was just because James makes a habit
of visiting all the weird places in the world.
And it sounds weird.
- And it's a pervert.
Or maybe I'm like Tom Jones and wherever I walk,
people just throw pants at me.
- That's it.
- Whenever I'm walking in the forest.
(all laughing)
- You are the panty tree, actually.
- No, the reason I asked is 'cause I know James
has been on a skiing holiday.
- Yeah.
- But I think you, probably all of you guys
in metropolitan elites are always skiing.
But no, apparently it's a thing on for a ski lift
because your ski lift goes very high, doesn't it?
And it passes over some trees.
And in some ski resorts, there are trees
where people chuck their panties onto the tree.
- I've seen that.
And I thought it was a Mardi Gras thing.
But there were loads.
And there was lots of sparkly, bras-y, panty.
Oh my God, and that's a thing.
- That's a thing.
I think they don't love it, the skiing authorities.
- Why do they care?
- I don't know.
(all laughing)
- Sorry, I don't know.
- What's their problem?
- It's hard to get your neck.
- Literate.
- Yeah, it is, yeah.
It must be hard to get your knickers off
on a ski lift though.
Like, that's a tough.
- I don't think they're doing that at all.
(all laughing)
- 'Cause you're wearing like your ski suit.
- Exactly.
- And you've gotta pull them off
and then pull them all over the ski.
- Exactly.
- I don't think it's possible.
- And your skis as well.
(all laughing)
- You have to take your skis off, they're gonna fall.
- Yeah.
- No, I reckon it's a spare pair of pants
situation in the pocket, isn't it?
- Very interesting.
- Probably is it.
- Yeah.
- I occasionally have dropped a ski pole
when going up on a ski lift as I'm sure many people have.
And obviously we hire our skis
and then we went back and we said,
"We dropped our ski pole, can we pay for the ski pole?"
They said, "Oh no, don't worry about it."
Because at the end of the season,
when all the snow melts,
someone goes up and collects all of the ski poles off
and then they just distribute them between all the shops.
- It's no way.
- That's amazing.
- I don't know if that's true.
- That's what they said.
- That's amazing.
- This was in Italy.
- It was fine, just give us your panties.
Give us your panties, mate.
- In 2016, MPs in the Egyptian parliament
attacked each other with shoes,
or one attacked another with a shoe.
Which I think is quite sorry.
- It's a big drop down from a mass shoe wall.
- No, it wasn't.
The other one wasn't quick enough off the mark
taking his shoe off.
He was actually suspended,
which I don't know why I sound surprised.
I suppose you probably would be from our parliament as well.
- Did they run with the headline,
S open brackets, C closed brackets,
Andal.
- Ssss.
- Ssandal.
- Oh yeah.
- Gosh, that took us all a long time, didn't it?
- That was, yeah.
- No, 'cause I suppose it would have been written
in Turkish, so.
(all laughing)
- But yeah, it sounds like a very exciting moment.
Tolfik Okasha was the MP who got attacked by a shoe
because he'd had the Israeli envoy round,
and one of his fellow MPs objected to that,
and got angry and hit him with a shoe,
and had to be escorted from the house waving a shoe.
I just thought that's a fun addition
to parliamentary goings on if we want to try it out.
- Yeah.
- There's a bit of an irony about Queen Victoria
showing the shoes at the Crimean War soldiers,
which is that they had very bad shoe situations
when they got to the war.
- Oh, nice.
- Wow, I froze there badly.
- They should have kept that one shoe.
- Well, yeah.
They had awful boots, and they got trench foot,
their feet swelled up in the cold.
The clothing was completely awful.
Sometimes the sole of their shoe would just stick
to the mud as they lifted their foot up,
and the rest of the shoe came,
and the sole was left behind,
'cause the mud was very thick and sticky.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Really bad, yeah, yeah.
They had a horrible time.
- Yeah, it was a tough one.
- It was a tough war.
- Oh.
- It was many of them are.
- What were the years, the Crimean War?
- 1853 to six.
- Yeah, as Anna said.
- Three to six.
- Three to six, yeah.
- 1853 to six.
- Yeah.
- Sorry.
- Right.
- And it was a very complicated war.
- Yeah, it was basically a blue sash orange
about the West trying to limit Russian expansionism,
wasn't it?
- It's basically the Ottomans coming up
to the North, the Russians coming out to the West,
Britain and France having colonial things
that they didn't want to lose,
trying to keep Russia as quiet as possible,
and decided to get on the side of the Ottomans,
and then attack the underbelly, which is Crimea.
- Yeah.
- And also there were a lot of Ottomans
living in Crimea at the time,
so it was a bit of a powder keg anyway.
- It was a very, very complicated situation.
Anyway, it started over rights of access
to the Church of the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem,
which I think we talked about.
Isn't that the one where they have the disagreement
over the ladder?
- It is.
- Yeah.
- And this was the same thing, basically.
The Ottoman Sultan gave the Catholic priests
a key to the Church in 1852.
And from that point on, you know, it was like,
well, we have to have a war over this.
Basically things escalated from there.
And then suddenly you have got the charge
of the Light Brigade happening,
and it's all going disastrously wrong.
- Yeah.
- And Florence Nightingale's having to organize
a lot of stuff.
- I mean, lots of famous things came from it, I suppose.
Florence Nightingale, Mary Seacull,
charge of the Light Brigade.
- Three items of clothing.
Balaklava, the cardigan.
- Cardigan, Earl of Cardigan,
very heavily involved in the Light Brigade.
- It's gotta be a boot.
- You're not gonna get it.
- Go on, what is it?
- The Sebastopol hat.
(laughing)
- It's the Raglan sleeve shirt.
- What's that?
- It's got a different color of,
the torso is a different color to the sleeves.
It's a baseball jersey.
But General Fitzroy Somerset, the first Baron Raglan,
was not wearing a baseball jersey,
but it didn't have a Raglan sleeve shirt named after him.
And he was the one who was responsible
for the charge of the Light Brigade going so badly wrong.
- Right.
- He was very old and he was half deaf
and he was not really with it.
And he said, oh, the Russians are taking some guns over there.
Can you go and stop them taking away the guns?
And the order was then carried to someone else,
the Earl of Cardigan,
who could not see the guns
'cause he was somewhere completely different.
And he said, well, those guns,
and pointed at this incredibly well-defended gun in place,
but at the end of a long, narrow valley,
just a disastrous place to attack.
And he said, okay, this isn't gonna go well,
but fine.
- Don Yacardi's.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Here's the exact words where,
here goes the last of the Brudenells
'cause he thought he was just riding straight
to a certain death as a lot of the people in that charge were.
- Here's another thing that wasn't invented,
but someone tried to invent for the Crimea,
which was a entire city destroying cannon.
This is a massive cannon.
It was 10 meters wide.
The shot is 10 meters wide.
- No.
- And it would weigh 550 tons.
And the idea is that once it landed,
it would demolish an entire city.
And it was to be called the Saxo Cannon.
- How are they gonna transport that anywhere?
- Yeah.
- It's a wacky racer's Acme Roadrunner-style cannon,
they're making.
- The inventor was a solid inventor.
- Was it not Adolf Sax?
- It was, the inventor of the saxophone came up
with a city destroying cannon,
which he really wanted to build.
- He was such a weird guy.
He would just invent these things
and then just call it the Sax something.
- Exactly.
- So never, it didn't take off.
- No, didn't get past the planning stages.
- No.
- That's what we wanted to do.
- Take off, very nice.
- Something else the Chromium War gave us is,
I think the earliest war photography,
or some of the earliest war photography,
very famous photo of the Valley of the Shadow of Death
by Roger Fenton in 1855.
I think it's one of the earliest pictures of warfare.
Basically, there are two photos
of the Valley of the Shadow of Death.
And they're both of this extremely barren landscape,
very near where the Charger Library was,
and gravel, little valley slopes on each side.
One of them has some cannonballs on the floor,
one of them doesn't,
and the famous one is the one with the cannonballs.
And it's the, you know, sort of tragedy of war
and the emptiness of the landscape with these war weapons.
But there's been so much debate over the last 150 years
over whether he faked it.
Like, where did the cannonballs come from?
- Well, Sax, I think, prototypes.
(all laughing)
- His marbles, weren't they?
And we don't know, 'cause it might be
that the second photo is after they'd cleared it up.
So then they just took another one of it clean.
- Right, or he might have deposited.
Ooh, tricky.
- The thing was, 'cause he took a lot of photos, right?
He had a horse and carriage with him,
which was like a portable photo developing booth
that he had with him.
He had lots of glass slides that he had
with him, multiple cameras.
And everyone's saying, oh, he staged a lot of photos.
I think it's more than just the cannonball one.
And the problem is, of course, they were staged.
Everything had to be staged.
- 'Cause you needed a long exposure time.
- The exposure was like 30 seconds.
- It's actually why the charge of the labricade
was such a disastrous, 'cause they had to wait
for half a minute for the photo.
The team photo at the start.
- And someone was blinking.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is, there is a chameleon in Madagascar,
which is effectively extinct for several months every year.
This fact is incredible.
- It's insane.
- Yeah, it's really good.
- I think it's not true.
I think if you're extinct, come back three months later,
you're not extinct.
- Let's debate the case.
(all laughing)
And first of all, thanks to Kate Wood,
who sent us in, in the email, "the fish in the box."
- If I knew it was from you, as opposed to Andy,
I wouldn't have poo pooed it.
- No, no, no.
This is the Labord's chameleon, and it is crazy.
Right, so, November, the chameleon hatches out.
- Yes.
- In Madagascar, in the forest.
Then they grow to sexual maturity very fast.
In about two months, they are grown up, ready to breed.
They breed, the females lay some eggs in the ground.
Then in March, they all die.
- Not the eggs, the adults.
- All the adults die.
There are then, the entire species exists in egg form,
basically, for most of the year.
In November, eggs hatch out, on they go.
- It's so weird, it's so weird, for most of the year,
yeah, they're not extinct exactly,
but for most of the year, the species lives in,
as an egg.
- Must be weird for the first person to come out of the egg.
- Yeah.
- Every year.
- Oh my God, yeah.
- They learn nothing from their elders?
I just think these are bizarre.
These were discovered in 2008.
I think their life cycle was first reported.
I think since then, they have found that
if you keep some in captivity,
or maybe under very specific conditions,
one might make it through a year.
But it's really, really rare.
So it's--
- What a year 2008 was.
Over in India, you had someone being killed on TV
with mind power, or not, or not.
- In Iraq.
- You had a chameleon being extinct, or not.
- In Iraq, George Bush is getting a tooth run at him.
- Wow.
- What?
- What was Anthony Trollup doing that year?
(all laughing)
- No, and they're amazing.
And I think it's 'cause they die to avoid the dry season,
which is very harsh and very, very hot in Madagascar.
And they just, some species hibernate,
they just decide to die.
And lots of chameleons on Madagascar,
I think they've got about--
- They've got almost half, haven't they?
- Almost half, what's the percentage of something?
- Yeah.
- Extraordinary variety of estimates
as to the number of chameleon species.
Given that it feels like a very small, countable number,
I read anywhere, and all from very reputable sources,
anywhere between 134 and more than 217 species of chameleon.
- Well, they're different colors, aren't they?
It's very hard to tell, you know?
- Yeah, yeah, that's a good point.
- Well, this was a green one before.
(all laughing)
Or is it a different one?
- They're great.
- Yeah, they don't change their color to match their background.
I actually didn't know that
until reading it for this podcast.
- Right.
- They change their emotions.
- Yeah, no, I think that's amazing.
An amazing misconception.
It's one of the biggest ones we've debunked on QI.
You know, sometimes we debunk things that you think,
yeah, come on, that's a bit.
- No, we never do that.
- No, we never do that, we never do that.
- There's an amazing thing.
If you were watching the UFC of chameleon battles, right?
Two competitors enter the ring.
If you were betting, you could probably bet
in the last few seconds, if that was allowed,
on who was gonna win.
- Do they change color based on whether they think
they're gonna win or lose?
- When they pass each other in the street,
two males were often changed colors to sort of be like,
kind of like if you're walking poolside
and you tuck your tummy in and walk in that kind of thing.
So yeah, so they found when they were studying it
that the chameleon that was brighter
and changed more rapidly was the one who was gonna win.
And they just found that that on average
was the way that it happened.
Yeah, or above average.
- So what a useful way, if only we could tell them that,
then they never have to fight, right?
- They can always just go up to each other and go.
- Stop the match.
- Oh, okay.
- Throw the towel in, yeah.
- Exactly.
- Wow.
- If you were a chameleon in a boxing ring or something,
'cause you normally wear a little dressing gown,
don't you, into the ring.
And as soon as you take your dressing gown off,
you look down, you were confident
until you saw how bright and stripy the other guy is.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I should just quickly say, this was in 2013,
it was a guy called Russell Ligon and Kevin McGrew,
and they did 45 encounters that they monitored.
And that's what they discovered from it.
- That's very cool.
- Yeah.
- They've got amazing anatomy.
I didn't know about the shape of their feet at all.
And they are bizarre.
They are described often as looking like salad tongs.
- Oh, yeah.
- And they do.
So there are two pads opposite each other.
And in fact, they're the only animals who aren't birds,
who are zygodactylists,
which basically means that they have three fingers,
opposite two fingers in a certain way.
And they're not the same kind of zygodactylists,
really, as birds.
They're their own special thing.
And essentially it's to grip trees.
I don't know why more things don't have this.
So it looks like a sideways claw
that just clamps onto trees.
It's very clever.
But I did find out that you can also get
pamperodactyly, anisodactyly, and schizo-dactylies as well,
which are in primate schizo-dactylies,
grasped with their second and third digits.
What's we're doing instead of thumb and finger?
- Like doing scissors for a rock paper scissors.
- Exactly.
- Does that free you up to hold something, like food?
- Or do you like a thumbs up at the same time
as holding onto the tree?
- I think that's the idea, yeah.
- And you can hold a can of paper
between fingers four and five.
- Yeah, perfect.
- No, they are, they're great.
I know someone who's got a peck of media.
- Do you?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Is that the end of the Alec Dope?
- I think it is.
- I'm rummaging for more, but that really is about it.
It's called Roy.
- Oh, there was more, there was more.
- No, and that's the end of the Alec Dope, yeah.
- If you were sitting on a chameleon's tongue
when it ate something.
- Food for thought, yeah.
- You would die so badly.
- No, no, it would just not be able to eat anything
because you're way bigger than a chameleon.
If you're sitting on its tongue,
it's not gonna be eating anything.
- Sorry, you're right.
You have to imagine that you're the size of a borrower
or maybe even smaller.
- Oh, okay.
- Of an ant.
Oh yeah, sorry.
Well, we'll see if you sit on a chameleon's tongue,
it'll just crush its tongue because you're human size.
- No, but like, you know, if something bites you,
a bite could have venom
and I thought the reveal was gonna be the tongue would.
- Sorry, it wasn't.
It was the acceleration of their tongues.
I should have made clear that you've been shrunken
like honey eye shots with kids in this.
- Yeah, I think that was a big central bit of that story.
- It was.
- Yeah, Anna, you've clasped at this one.
This is it.
(laughing)
- Should I?
If you were really, really small
and you were sitting on a chameleon's tongue
and it stuck it out, then you would definitely die.
The acceleration of their tongues are amazing.
They're actually the highest acceleration
and power output, like amount of power generated
for any movement of a reptile, bird, or mammal.
- It is the same.
- Yeah.
- The power output is 14,000 watts per kilogram.
- Incredible.
- Okay, now, Jonas Fingard or Tade Pagaccia
who are the best cyclists in the world in the Tour de France
say if they're going up a mountain,
they can max out at about seven watts per kilogram
and these guys are doing 14,000 watts per kilogram.
- It's a lot.
- I almost can't compute that.
That's amazing.
- It's like, so the G-force is, I think,
the maximum G-force we can survive
is maybe nine or 10 for a few seconds by the pilots
and the G-force on their tongue would be 264 G.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- Your face is being distorted by that.
- That is so cool.
I did read a bit about what's inside their tongue
'cause they have these things called
intralingual sheaths, right?
So the tongue has bones running along the core of it,
which is weird in itself.
I guess they don't, not very big bones,
but those are covered by these intralingual sheaths
and those are covered by an accelerator muscle
and what the chameleon does is
the chameleon spring loads the sheaths
and packs them into each other like a telescope.
- That's like, there was a toy that used to do that
that you flicked it when you were younger
and it was telescopic and they expanded out, wasn't there?
I've got a real memory of that.
- I don't remember that.
- I was just playing with the chameleon's tongue
when I was younger.
- You would get like those pointers that teachers had
and they would go like that, wouldn't they?
- Yes.
- I got one of those last year.
- For Christmas.
- I got one myself at a non-holiday time
and God, they're good.
- Yeah.
- The pointers.
- Do you just point at stuff?
- Yeah.
- Just walk down the street going, there's a fancy tree.
- It really, it gives you a kind of authority
that is extraordinary, you know.
- You've never dared use it here.
- No, no, no, but if I'm in the supermarket
and I want to put it something on the conveyor belt
and say, make sure you apply the discount on that radish,
my good man.
- I'm gonna bleep this one next.
- I'm so confused about why you asked people what it is.
- I'm so confused because all of this sounds so plausible.
- Yeah.
- We're just missing the one detail.
- We're sort of playing what I like you now, aren't we?
No, I think it was a couple of years ago.
I bought it for a show.
But I cannot remember the context in which I have
and I've just ended up with a pointer,
which I'd love to get out occasionally.
- That's right.
- So chameleon saliva.
This was another fact in the inbox actually.
So not only did Kate Wood send the original fact,
that Robert Harding writes,
chameleon saliva is the opposite of custard.
- It's disgusting on treacle time.
Is that 'cause it's non-Newtonian, but in a different way?
- Bingo.
- Yes.
- So custard, if you run across custard,
as you apply force to it, it gets harder.
- Very good.
That's it, it thickens on impact.
A chameleon saliva is thick in the mouth,
but when the tongue strikes the insect
it's trying to eat or whatever,
that blob becomes very malleable for an instant.
- That's clever.
- And then hardens right again.
- Right.
- So the prey is then glued to the tongue
and then it gets pulled right back into the chameleon's mouth.
- That's clever.
- Isn't that amazing?
- I found a chameleon who was a chameleon
before chameleons were chameleons.
- What?
- Keep talking.
- I got a headache.
You know I got a headache and this is not helping.
- There used to be a philosopher called chameleon.
- Really?
- He was a disciple of Aristotle.
- Was he the guy who came up with the idea of karma?
(laughing)
- He, we don't know anything about him.
- He's just gonna go straight up.
- I'm just, you're ill, you don't know what you're saying.
It's just helping you out here.
Yeah, no, he is a disciple.
We know virtually nothing about him,
I guess with us, as with a lot of people then,
but he did write a lot of pieces
that we do know of his names attached to,
like a piece called "On Drunkenness",
a piece called "On Pleasure",
but virtually nothing is known.
But so he lived, he would have died in 281 BC
and the word chameleon came about
in roughly the 14th century, mid-14th century.
- Okay, interesting.
- To describe the lizard, presumably.
- To describe the lizard and what's interesting is,
Aristotle wrote about chameleons,
but we just didn't have the word
and he wasn't writing about his mate.
- So did he always have to say,
"You know that thing that kind of changes color,
"looks a bit like a gecko?"
- Looks like my mate, my disciples, yeah.
- Can I give you some animals
that were thought to be extinct,
but then aren't.
- Yes.
- The Canterbury, Nobdweevil.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- I might just stop there actually.
- No, more, more!
- The cloaked bee, the dinosaur ant,
the terrace skink, the Batman river loach,
the painted frog, and the Machu Picchu,
arboreal chinchilla rat,
which was found in a tree near Machu Picchu.
- Right.
- When they un-extincted it.
- Wow.
- So these are just all things,
was there one big find, one day out,
where they're just all hanging out
in the same playing cards for a while?
- It's some sort of like support group
for the extinct who aren't extinct, yeah.
- There's also the Confusing Rocket Frog.
- That's a great name.
- And they found it in 2019,
and it's called Confusing because it looks a lot
like other frogs, but it's the Confusing Rocket Frog.
And the interesting thing about this is,
it was thought to be extinct in 1985.
They found it in 2019, but luckily it was in a place
where they were about to do loads of mining
and logging and stuff like that,
and it meant that they couldn't do any of it.
- Brilliant.
- I think it's in Ecuador.
- That's great.
- Well done, Little Rocket Frog.
- The Painted Frog, was that one that you said?
- Painted Frog, yeah.
- Which just sounds like someone forcing
chameleonism onto animals.
(all laughing)
- That's very interesting.
- There's a type of fish that was thought
to have gone extinct 66 million years ago,
and then it was found in 1938.
And it's the Sealocanth.
And do you know the story of how it was rediscovered?
- Is it?
- It's so cool.
- Was it in 1938?
Was it found by a submarine?
- No, no, just found by a normal fisherman in South Africa,
caught a weird fish, got back,
gave it to this woman who ran the museum,
who thought that's weird.
So she sketched it.
- Oh, I remember, yay.
- It's amazing, so she sketched it,
and she sent it to Professor Smith,
who she knew would be able to tell her what it was.
Professor Smith received her sketch, no straight away.
This is the Sealocanth.
It's been 66 million years, we thought it was gone.
And he goes and he visits it,
but it's kind of disintegrated by that point.
So he can't confirm really that lots about it,
or where it came from.
And he devoted the next 14 years
to finding a second specimen.
He was desperate.
And eventually there was a guy on the,
one of the Comoros Islands off Mozambique in 1952,
who found one.
And Smith was managed to convince the South African government
to get a military plane to fly him
to off the coast of Mozambique.
He had to have a conversation with the Mozambique authorities,
saying, "Hey, we're flying military planes
"over your airspace, really sorry."
They were like, "Why are you doing that?"
They said, "We're just going to pick up a fish."
- I remember reading that story,
and I think the woman who found it in the first place
and knew there was something up,
I think it was either Smith or someone else said
it was evidence of women's intuition.
The greatest evidence we ever had of women's intuition.
- Really?
Marjorie Courtney Lassmer, really?
- That's what I said, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- What, just 'cause she sensed that this is a weird...
- She just knew there was something going on.
- Yeah. - Wow.
- Just proving two things with one fish,
that's pretty cool.
Not only do we have the fish,
we now know about women's intuition.
(all laughing)
- Happy day for the world.
- I'd love it if his paper, which eventually came out,
was about women's intuition, not about the fish.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, just use Shriverland.
James.
- I'm on Twitter, just use @JamesHarken.
- Andy.
- I'm on X at @AndrewHunterM.
(all laughing)
Sorry.
- And Anna, how can they get through to us as a group?
- You can just use the email address podcast@qi.com
or the Twitter handle @NoSuchThing.
- That's right.
Or you can head to our website,
no such thing as a fish.com.
All of the previous episodes are up there,
so do check them out.
Otherwise, come back next week,
'cause we'll be here with another episode
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)