- They don't want it, I don't want it.
(upbeat music)
- Hi, welcome to Dropper's Align.
Welcome to the audience feedback show
as part of Club Fish.
Welcome to all you Club Fishers,
whether you're listening or watching.
We've had a huge emboss--
- I don't think anyone's watching or mute.
I think the people are watching are also listening.
So whether you are watching or listening
or merely listening, is that all right?
- Yeah, there could be captions actually,
it could be subtitles.
- It could be, also I saw a comment from someone saying
they love just looking at our three heads.
(laughing)
So if you're watching from some kind of
I imagine mental health institution,
we've had a very, very full inbox.
- How full, it's bulging.
- Yeah, exciting.
- It's, it's heaving.
It's, it's riving, the inbox.
- Yeah, it's separating.
(laughing)
- Let's clear it out, let's do it.
- You're right.
Let's start with an email from Matthew Acorn,
a book with an H in the middle.
- Acorn?
- Yeah. - Hey John.
- Could be, hello Matthew.
We mentioned a thing about literary characters
whose names clearly say what they like.
Like Dickens does and like Joe Rowling does.
- Exactly, exactly.
- And I always say it's massively hack,
even though a lot of very, very great writers have done it.
- Yeah.
- What's that I can't actually think of an example
right now?
- Tony Old.
- Is that a dickens?
- Well, no, but it would be it.
If I was, yeah, yeah.
- I've got a book coming out next year.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Tony Old is the main character.
- Is that what the old curiosity shop is?
It's his shop.
- Right, yeah.
(laughing)
- The club Cratchit is Cratchin' around in the ground.
- Mr. Bumble.
- Yes.
- Bumbles around.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- That kind of thing.
Anyway, there is a book called Snowcrash.
- Hmm.
- The novel Snowcrash has a character called Hero
with an eye, as in Japanese name.
- Hero protagonist.
(laughing)
- That's really good.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I love that name, Hero.
- Yeah, me too.
- Great name.
- That's from Matthew Acorn,
who lives in a place called Trophy Club in Texas.
(laughing)
- Isn't that unusual?
- Yeah.
- And I looked it up.
And it's James, you're going to love this.
It's centered around a country club.
It's basically a golf horse.
- Golf horse, now that is what I want.
Those golf buggies are so old-hat.
I want a golf horse.
And then you can play like Polo, but with golf clubs.
- Has anyone done that?
Because you've got two sports so close to each other
in terms of the item.
- Why on earth wouldn't you use a horse as a caddy?
It just makes perfect sense.
They fertilize the green.
- That's true.
- Which is what you want, isn't it?
- And you can ride them.
You can't ride your caddy in golf.
- No.
- It's frowned on.
- You know what, I rode a horse for the first time
a few weeks ago.
- Did you?
- Yeah.
And I found it absolutely terrifying.
(laughing)
- Well, you're a long way up.
- Yeah.
- And they're unpredictable.
- I will never do it again.
'Cause I felt like it was a bit unfair on the horse, really.
- Why?
- Because you were inexperienced.
- No, because I weigh 90 kilos.
- Right.
- Then you think Harry, heavy, heavy, like burdens.
- Well, I don't think that's fair, I bet.
(laughing)
- I don't think we've got a complete difference in our opinion.
I think it's absolutely fine to put them through hell.
- And you know what, that ride in the horse,
it wasn't the most uncomfortable I was that day
because I also went for my first ever massage.
I've never been for a massage before.
- What a day for you.
- And I went for a full naked massage.
- Oh!
- Like a time massage.
- Yeah, right.
- It was my birthday.
- What a birthday.
- Did you get, were you naked on the horse as well?
- No, no, I wasn't wearing my birthday suits
all the way through the day.
- Did you have the massage after the horse riding?
- Actually, no, I did it the wrong way around.
'Cause it was a sunset horse ride.
- So now that you're totally relaxed,
like a boneless jelly,
let's get you on a horse where you have to,
you know, maintain perfect posture.
Did you have, were they, did they walk all over you?
- That kind of massage.
- Oh, I switched out.
(laughing)
- They also fertilized my back.
I've got a lovely hairy back now
after all that fertilizing.
- What a day for you, James.
- Yeah, it's my birthday.
And you know what, the very next day,
I went straight back into my comfort zone
and I don't intend to leave there
for another 360-poil day.
- Yeah, that's just quite something.
I can't imagine you having a massage.
You're just such an unmassaging person.
- I'm just, I'm really ticklish.
And I don't like people touching me.
- And you thrive on tension.
- Yeah.
- So did you like it or not?
- No, I was extremely uncomfortable
all the way through.
- Make it is a big step to go.
You should go to a, like a step one massage first.
- Well, you're in like hazmat suits.
- Yeah, like you just take off,
you just really reveal one flap of skin
and let me rub you through that.
(laughing)
- Tealers choice.
Or like an airport chair that you put coins in,
like one of those ones.
- Oh yeah, I've been in one of those.
- You've done that, right.
- How exciting.
- You've done that massage in years.
You were a massage guy.
- What do you think?
- I think every morning.
(laughing)
- I'm often late for things.
- You're in like a mini kimono.
I can see you.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Here are protagonists watching.
(laughing)
Cracks his fingers.
- Right, should we do some emails?
- Yeah, sure.
- Right, let's go to a rodeo clown.
rodeo clown of the week.
- Okay, boy, oh boy.
- I feel like having ridden the horse for the first time.
I'm able to comment on these now.
- Yeah, well, you're about to get bucked right off this horse.
Ruth Tiffin writes, right name.
Oh no, Andy.
The amount of emails you're about to get
about everyone's pronunciation of null-ar-bore
is going to be off the chain, Loll, and Ruth was right.
And it was followed by, I'd say, 15 to 20 emails, say.
- Do you remember when we went to this place in Australia?
- Yeah, yeah.
- So it's where there are no trees.
- It's where there are no trees.
- Exactly, from the Latin, nullus and arbor.
- No trees.
Well, in terms of the Australians have formed
their own unique way of pronouncing that name,
and they're very interested that that's the correct way.
- I think that's fine.
- Yep, absolutely.
It is fine.
The Romans are long dead.
They don't get to say it's pronounced anymore.
But my goodness, Mel Brayeswell was on as well, wasn't she?
- Mel Brayeswell.
Having moved to Australia two weeks earlier,
would have been able to tell us that.
- Absolutely.
- How do you pronounce it?
- Null-ar.
- I'm so terrified now to say it.
I think null-ar-bore.
- Null-ar-bore.
Null-ar-bore.
Leah Bridges says, "Dang claims to be Australian.
Come on, mate."
But throws in a fact about null-ar-bore.
- Right.
- If you're driving from the eastern states,
you can't take fruit, vegetables, or honey
into South Australia or Western Australia,
but you can take onions and garlic
as long as you peel them first.
- Pre-pit, wow, pre-peeled.
- That's a good fact.
- Peeling garlic, yeah.
- Cool.
- All right.
Marcus Jakes writes, "I have listened to nearly every podcast
you have done.
I look forward to Friday when I get a new one,
but ep604 was a disaster."
Can't pronounce Melbourne.
Do we say Melbourne wrong?
- Melbourne.
We've talked about Melbourne.
That's not Melbourne.
That's a different thing.
Can't pronounce Melbourne or Null-ar-bore.
Terrible description of a road train, not even close.
I have more, but in my disbelief, I've forgotten most.
Considering Melbourne is the city with the most NBA number one
draft picks since 1981.
We deserve more respect.
Excuse me.
I don't know what that means.
I thought I was going to hand over to you.
- I can't.
- What?
- In Australia, of Australian NBA people.
- Yeah, it must be of.
- Because there would be a lot more people in LA or--
- Just America, generally.
Well, I don't know what a draft pick is,
so I'm very happy to just hand over to you guys.
- Do you want to know or--
- We'll just assume everyone does know.
Yeah, yeah.
I can't think of who it might have been,
but, okay.
- That's a top basketball player, not all Australian.
- It's a really idea.
- Here's a funny idea.
- I do.
- I mean, Mark, she's my thing, so I'm sorry,
sorry, Mark.
- But one of the Aussie basketball players
who was massive in the NBA was part of Michael Jordan's
Chicago Bulls team was Luke Longley,
who is brother-in-law by marriage
of our guest, Ben Elton.
- Recent guest.
- Is that right?
- Yeah.
That's good.
- Actually, on draft picks, just from the Ben Elton show,
we mentioned William Shakespeare, the NFL player.
- Right, yeah.
- And I was like, I know the name,
and the reason I knew it is he was the first ever draft pick
in American football.
So, I mean--
- Right.
- So he's an American football player?
- Yeah, yeah, but I was like, how do I know the name?
'Cause you said, I said, oh, I've known that name,
and you said, oh, he's from 1950 something,
or 1960 something, so I was like,
oh, well, I didn't watch American football back then,
but that's how I know it, 'cause he was the first ever draft pick.
- Look, I'm just gonna say it.
There's college basketball, there's college football,
they graduate, and the NBA and the NFL get to bid on them.
- You know what, I've never put knowledge out of my head.
So quickly, except when I've met someone
and they've told me their name, that's like--
(laughing)
It was that fast, I was like, actively having to slap it right out.
- Wow, okay.
We also, in that episode, managed to fluff road trains,
apparently, and this was me.
- I'm on the hook.
- Yeah, absolutely.
You were the one who said it.
- Oh gosh, I'm so sorry.
Thomas Wyndham writes, "I feel like a better job
"could have been done explaining road trains."
That's true.
It's a single vehicle with lots of trailers.
- Okay, right.
Now, what I said was, it's--
- You thought it was like a convoy.
- I said something.
I said something really, really wrong.
In Australia, if there's a main vehicle pulling one trailer,
that's a semi.
Sorry.
But--
(laughing)
- I'm done as semi, but it's like 18 feet long.
- I wouldn't have made that joke
if you just didn't giggle for the last 30 seconds.
- There we go.
- But road trains, it's one prime mover,
as they call it, moving two or more full-size trailers,
and they're really long.
And apparently, even the shortest road train
is as long as three and a half London buses.
- Wow.
- So you know how you felt about draft picks?
- Yeah.
- I'm experiencing the exact moment right here.
- In Australia, you should be all over the road train, Stan.
- That was a dorkin--
I was sitting reading Mark's brothers in a bedroom.
- I wasn't into it.
- Okay.
- Well, you may like to know, Thomas adds additional,
they might have additional locomotives in the middle
of a big long road train.
It might be an extra engine in the middle,
providing more power.
- That's pretty cool.
- Wow.
So there you go.
Bryce Clark writes, this is absolutely huge.
Do you remember we mentioned one of the most famous
Australians of all time?
- Oh, Lenbedel.
- Lenbedel.
- Yeah.
- Right.
Bryce Clark writes, I know Gary of Gary Highway.
So Lenbedel was the Australian road builder
who named all of his roads after members as family.
- We all know that.
- It's only Mal, who didn't know Lenbedel.
(laughing)
And so Bryce writes, I know Gary of Gary Highway.
He's got good dental work.
'Cause Lenbedel would take out the teeth of--
- Oh, they're crews building the roads of the desert.
Gary is a well-respected piano technician in Melbourne.
But I think his sister-- - Sorry, what?
- Melborn.
But I think his sister does bush tours
around the areas their dad worked.
- Right.
- Bush, 'cause all of his books,
you remember beating around the bush too long in the bush?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Bushbashes.
- Yes, bushwhackers.
- Bushwhackers are a very big band in Australia.
The bushwhackers, yeah.
- Interesting.
- They wrote the song, "I am you are we are Australian."
If you know that song.
- That's how Australians learn grammar.
(laughing)
- So I know that's huge news that we allow
two handshakes away from Lenbedel, basically.
- It's huge.
- Is he still alive?
- I don't believe Len is, no.
I think so. - So that'll be a bit
of an awkward handshake.
- Certainly with some digging required.
- Oh, dear.
And David writes, "Pubquizzes, do you remember
"Pubquizz Roads in Australia?"
- Yeah.
- This is a big thing.
Well, the Western USA also has miles and miles
of nothing but miles and miles, writes David.
And during the heyday of America's love affair with cars,
we had Burma Shave signs,
which had humorous limericks on them.
- So a razor company?
- Yeah.
- Right.
- It's got to be.
It's Burma Shave has to be a razor company.
I did look it up, I think it is.
- And then we just put random limericks.
- Yeah.
- Very nice.
But David says, "Since we Americans are not as intellectually
adept as Brits, we had humorous limericks
rather than quiz questions."
- I'd like to hear an example of the limericks.
- I don't have one, I'm so sorry.
- Sorry.
- Must end in like shave or...
- Razor?
- Taser, laser.
That's not for a limerick.
- It has to begin with the once was a man
from Australasia.
(laughing)
- Who tried to shave with a laser?
- Yeah.
- He burned off his face.
Wanted to disgrace.
He should have used a Burma Shave razor.
- Brilliant.
- There we go.
- We should have gone into advertising.
- We do been bloody good.
- Maybe all our ads going forward are in limerick form.
- That's a very good idea.
- Look how quick that was.
- Yeah.
- And we'll have the royalty rights of the lyrics.
- The royalty rights?
- Oh yeah, you mean, when they make a song,
when Kendrick won the harmonics a song.
- Yeah.
- With one of our limericks.
- Yeah, exactly.
It could happen.
Chas and Dave got used in M&M song, remember?
- How many rhymes are they for VPN?
- Then, men.
- Hen.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Come on.
- Biscuits in New Zealand.
- Biscuit tin was what we were talking about.
The fact that Parliament has a Biscuit tin
that they pull out policies to discuss.
- Yes.
- So in that fact, John, from Parliament,
the British Parliament, writes in.
This is exciting.
- John there, come.
- I can't say.
We've got a few secret squirrels today.
- It's too late.
- People who can't reveal their true name.
- Major?
- Location.
- It's John Major.
I was listening to today's episode
and you talk about whether the division bells
still work in the pubs around Parliament.
- Oh yeah, I'd be interested in to know that.
- Well, I've got great news, James.
You're about to find out.
- We should re-explain what the division bell is.
'Cause it's so interesting.
It's basically if a vote needs to happen immediately,
bells start ringing and everyone dashes towards
to make their vote,
but because they're all spread around in places
like pubs around the area.
Sometimes there's telephones that ring
and the division bells are ringing and they play it.
So yeah, it's a big thing,
but we thought a lot of it went extinct in modern day.
- Well, I work in Parliament, says John,
and I can say that they don't ring anymore.
The system, I believe, broke over COVID
and as it was being phased out,
they didn't bother to fix it.
It still works inside the building.
That's good, but not in external pubs.
Oh, it still goes off in the on-site bars.
There you go.
- There's three bars, isn't there?
- Yeah, yeah.
- And because of the sound of the division bells,
John adds, it means the fire bell must be different.
So instead of a loud noise,
it's a pot of voice saying warning,
warning a fire has been reported in your vicinity.
(laughing)
- That's good.
- When my daughter was born,
we, it was in the hospital opposite the Parliament.
- Oh, across the town.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, St. Thomas's. - St. Thomas's.
- And we were in a room overlooking Parliament.
- Wow. - So we could see the people
and obviously when your child is born,
you're awake all night.
So we could see the people with flashlights,
you know, looking for fires
that they do that every single night.
- Yeah, 24 hours a day.
- Yeah, like every couple of hours,
someone with a flashlight would be looking for fires outside.
- You're worse in the bed saying,
James, I can appreciate.
A bit of, I need a bit of help with the boat.
You're saying, wait, wait, it's been an hour and 57 minutes
and I just, I wanna check my theory.
- That's terrific, that's so cool.
- That is cool. - That's spooky.
Right, here is, get yourself off the hook for James.
We've both had a real showing so far with this whole.
- Okay, no, I'm ready.
- Nullabor thing. - I'm ready.
- Nullabor, yeah, yeah.
Simo Sarn writes, in episode 604 at 5119,
well, I'll just, over to you, James.
- Oh, no, I see, so that's right near the end.
- Yep.
- Number 614. - 604. - 6, oh, right, sorry.
- That's the, it's still the Mount Bracewell show.
We're talking about, yeah.
The last section, James says that pie is infinite.
- Oh, here we go.
- And doesn't repeat, meaning it's irrational,
thus all series of numbers are in there.
Then Simo says the latter called normality
actually doesn't follow from the former.
It's a separate property which hasn't been proven
or disproven about pie. - Yeah.
- So, you're on the hook. - Well, I'm about to say something,
which will go directly into both your head
and then directly out of it straight afterwards.
- Okay.
- But yeah, pie is not a normal number as far as we know
or it might be or it might not be,
which means that it might be that all numbers are in there
or it might not be.
Now, I said that it might repeat,
but what is definitely true is that it doesn't repeat
at the end, you know, like one third is 0.3333333
and it just keeps going forever.
Pie definitely doesn't do that.
It's not like a repeated set of numbers
that just keeps going on like that.
What is possible is that there is some pattern inside of pie
as in it's not at the end, but it's inside.
Like it could be, it could go 1, 2, 1, 2, 3, 1, 2, 3, 4, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
That's a pattern and it's a repeating pattern,
but it isn't repeating numbers.
- Hmm. - Right.
- And what was very difficult to part across
in the comedy show that we were doing,
was that quite advanced math,
at which I did at university
and which, in fairness,
I haven't completely remembered all of it.
- Yeah. - And I did flub it a little bit.
- I think he slightly fudged it though at the time.
I think he said it might or might not be.
So I-- - I definitely fudged it.
It's slightly inexcusable because I do know it all,
like all that stuff, and I did study it,
but at the same time, yeah.
- So I think you're off the hook.
- I don't think so.
- Well, we've got to the end of it either, have we?
- We haven't, but we know for a fact that it doesn't do that
'cause then it would, you would be able to express it
as a fraction, which you can't.
- I forgot about the fraction.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- There you go.
- Okay. That was very interesting.
- Thank you, James.
- I think the show does have to be serious sometimes,
drop us a line.
- What do you think?
- I think it can't all be hilarious.
- It can't all be limer eggs.
- It can't all be music limer eggs.
Josh Jones writes, long time listener, clubfish member,
hello Josh, and first time message guy.
I was listening to episode six, I fought with Mell's Forfax,
and you spoke about the digits of pi.
Listening to her recite pi to 50 decimal places.
- That's very impressive.
- It was astonishing.
- It's amazing 'cause what she actually did was just say
all 10 numbers, and I put them in the right order.
She doesn't know, actually,
she didn't even know the first thing.
- That's a great edit.
- Yeah. - She's amazing.
- I don't think we knew she knew that as well.
That kind of just came out, didn't it, in the show?
- I astonished. - Yeah.
But it reminded Josh of something here
a few weeks ago.
He says, I work in a hospital with a surgeon,
brackets gynecologist, who just a few weeks ago
set a new Australian record by reciting pi to 10,640 places.
Can Chana, once a purer, is his name
from Ballarat Base Hospital in Victoria, Australia.
So that's pretty good, isn't it?
- That's very cool. - That's amazing.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- It is 10,000.
- That's a lot, isn't it?
- Imagine he's just muttering away down there.
- What are you saying?
- 3,640. - What are you measuring?
(laughing)
- I'm just doing the circumference,
and then I could have divide it.
(laughing)
- Bit of ribbled humour.
We've had emails from the Australian Bureau of Statistics.
- Oh, yes, we mentioned a fact about them.
- 'Cause it was about pie charts and pies and bakers in Australia.
So Mel Aitan, Aitan, has sent over a bar chart on bartenders,
also things I've included here.
A line graph on line markers and a histogram on historians.
(laughing)
- It's very nice. - This is altered by the Aussies.
- This is all the Aussies.
- Sorry, very good. - Very good.
So it's just a bit of fun, really.
- Really like that.
We should mention something quickly that actually,
I've had a few messages about,
which is the fact that the Mel Bracewell episode
was the first episode we have ever done,
where the facts were entirely from the guests that we had on,
one person bringing the facts.
There was a lot of theories about why that happened.
- She insisted.
- She insisted? - Sever.
- Yeah.
Yeah, no people were saying like,
"Oh, did they have no time to get it together?"
And then she just brought the facts.
So just for clarity, 'cause why not?
We basically received five facts from Mel.
We couldn't pick one we liked most
because we thought they were brilliant.
And I think it was you James, just one.
We just do all the facts.
When that be fun, that it was just Mel's facts each time.
And then he resisted it.
It was so there was some resistance
from more traditionally minded members of the group.
But yeah, and you know what?
I'm gonna say, Mayor Culper, I was wrong.
Well, don't, don't Mayor Culper.
I mean, it's not my fault.
But I was wrong, so resisted.
I thought it was a very fun thing to do.
- But never again.
- Never again, never ever again.
But it was really fun.
They were all great facts.
- Right.
- Here's a, do you know the name, if I say Mike Giggler?
- Mike Giggler?
- Yeah.
Mike is maybe a private, I think.
It's like when someone writes an email in that's amusing,
deliberately amusing.
Sometimes people just think of extra jokes.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So is Mike, it's not a slam on the email.
- It is a bit of a slam to save Mike.
- It's a bit of a slam.
- Okay.
- To say, oh, there's a bit of Mike Giggler email.
Someone's saying, I've thought of a joke
that you didn't at the time.
But we're operating in a live fire environment.
There's not time to think of every joke.
You know, sometimes you mess something and it's,
- Sometimes you say a joke and I cut it out.
- Exactly, those are the most painful of all.
It's where like, someone's like, I can't believe
you didn't make this incredibly obvious
low-hanging fruit joke.
And I'm like, I did make the most obvious joke
and I'm like, I did make the most obvious joke.
I'm a James Cunning.
Anyway, this is not, this is a bit of a Mike Giggler,
but I'm very grateful to Caleb M for sending it.
Thank you, Caleb.
You remember we talked about ghost sharks
and they've got these weird things on their head,
made of teeth.
- Oh yeah.
- They used to grip on during sex.
- This is in the Sarah Pasco show.
- It certainly was.
Sorry, show change.
There we go, we're on the Pasco show now.
Anyway, Caleb writes, ghost sharks use their teeth
to eat prey and love.
- Oh, that's a really good joke.
- Yeah. - To be fair.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Well done, Mike. - Oh, we go.
- Caleb, no, no, I don't.
- Oh, I'm sorry.
(laughing)
- Lauren Payne writes, "I was listening
to this week's fish podcast
and the mother of a friend of mine is a nurse,
named Nurse Doctor."
- Nurse Doctor. - Brilliant.
- Based on central Kentucky.
- 'Cause you said, Andy, that Paul Nurse is a doctor.
He won their Nobel Prize for Physiology.
- Oh, yeah. - And there was another
doctor called Nurse,
but you'd never found a nurse called Doctor.
- There we go.
"And my friend is considering going for a PhD
to become Doctor Doctor."
- Very good. - It's gonna be great.
- Which was Sarah Gertons.
- Wasn't that the name of President Garfields,
one of the doctors?
- Doctor, Doctor Willard Bliss.
- Yes, his first name was Doctor, that's right.
- So, Doctor. - Oh!
- There's been an amazing email from Dragon.
Dragon. - What a great name, can't you spell?
- Dragon, but with another A instead of the O.
- Are they from Serbia?
- They don't say, is that a Serbian name?
- Uh, I know some dragons from Serbia.
- Really? - Yeah.
- That's pretty cool. - It's a footballer
called Dragon Steak of It, I think, as well.
I'm not sure if he was Serbian.
- That's a great name.
- It's very strong.
Anyway, it's the Blade Runner plot title explainer.
Now, just look at this half of the sheet of paper.
That's very important.
Don't turn it over. - Oh, okay.
- So it basically shows,
and we'll put it on screen as well,
where the title comes from, where the plot comes from.
It just makes it so clear.
- And he's made this for us?
- Dragon.
- We should explain,
'cause some people won't have heard the episode.
The very basic thing is,
"Do Android Stream of Electric Sheep" by Philip K. Dick
was being adapted into a movie.
The people making the movie didn't like the title.
So they call it Blade Runner,
but in order to call it Blade Runner,
they had to buy the rights to another book,
written by William S. Burrows,
to take the title, but just the title,
and apply it to the Philip K. Dick book.
- That William Burrows had taken the story
from another book called Blade Runner,
and turned it into a movie adaptation,
which was never adapted, but then was later adapted.
- Yeah, and that book was by someone called,
I think it was "Alone Nas." - "Alone Nas."
- Anyway, so it does not make it clear?
- Yeah, although it's just very complicated, isn't it?
- Yeah, although someone on the train the other day
was reading "Do Android Stream of Electric Sheep."
Coincidence? - Yeah.
- Pass it back.
- I tell you what, if they were reading the "Alone Nas" book,
which is quite obscure, I've been really surprised.
- Yeah, I might have had to intervene at that point,
or if they were reading the final book
in this little image here, of the novelization of the movie,
Blade Runner, which is not "Do Android Stream of Electric Sheep."
- That can't have sold well.
- Can't have done it. - Do you want to read
the book of the film?
- Yeah, well, there is one, you know?
- Anyway. - Yeah.
- Right, "Discussed."
William James writes, "We talked about being disgusting."
- All right, not the past of "Discussed."
- No, right.
- Although we, I suppose we did "Discussed."
It was "Discussed." - Yeah.
- In regard to Sarah Pasco's fact, regarding "A Rousal,"
reducing people's "Discussed" response.
- So this was Dan's idea that if he arouses his wife,
he could get to take up the bench.
He's one of my favorite lines ever in any podcast we've ever done.
- Really pulling pain to the wife guy thing, as well.
(laughing)
James, folks, the idea of a restaurant
that shows "Soft Cool Pawn" to entice people
in tweeting "Medio-Coffoon."
- Yeah. (laughing)
- Though it doesn't show "Pawn" per se,
I believe there is already a restaurant chain in North America
operating on this basic principle.
I believe James has invented Hooters.
- Yes. (laughing)
- I believe I have.
- Yeah, congratulations.
Like that's a huge business.
- That is a big business.
- Yeah, but it exists, doesn't it?
What am I gonna do?
- Yeah, I know, that's the only,
but you could be the first Hooters,
I don't think Hooters exists in the UK, does it?
You could franchise Hooters.
- Spring Fellows, is that Hooters in the UK or not?
I don't know.
- I think it's just a big chain of like,
not very good restaurants, though,
so there is definitely a gap in the market.
- I think they've tried, maybe.
- Well, the advantage of my version is you don't have labor costs
'cause you just put the TV on and show some Soft Cool Pawn.
- Yeah.
- You don't have to pay the waiters on waitresses.
- It must be niche, like we're for geeks.
Like a cypher, oh, like Dr Hooters.
- Dr Hooters and all of the people there
have three boobs and they're alien like, I mean, yeah.
- Where's the doctor, Pa?
- A doctor who?
There's a cypher.
(laughing)
- Some steps went on in your head there.
- Absolutely.
- And you really need to elucidate.
- Why so cypher?
That's a cypher.
- Sorry.
- Dr Hooters.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Bigger on the inside boys.
- Oh my God.
(laughing)
- Four, five, seven, nine.
- Oh, we've got very blokey since Anna went on matter.
I think it's really, it's ribbled now.
- Yeah.
- That's the second time you've used ribbled today.
- Has it get away?
- Yeah.
- What a bad vocabulary I've got.
But you know where you know one fancy word.
You're constantly.
- Was that your word of the day that you've read?
- Oh my tear off calendar.
(laughing)
- Ribbled, hmm.
Don't mind if I do.
- Oh, yeah, that's very embarrassing.
- All right, let's move on.
Sophie McCook writes,
- Ah yeah.
- I don't often know a fish fact before I hear it
on your podcast, but the news of the great raft spider,
mmm, Norfolk spider.
- Yes.
- It can run across the water.
- Lots of it, yeah.
- It lives in the Norfolk broads and things like that.
Great spider.
It was already fresh off the press for me
because the fact is currently being used
as an excuse by my mother.
(laughing)
She lives in a small cottage in Beckles, Suffolk.
And holiday rents out a smaller cottage in the garden,
right on the river, Waveney.
The cottage, she rents out,
seems to be a popular spider congregating place.
They're all sizes and favor the walls, ceiling and bath.
My mother doesn't want to hoover them all up,
spiders are friends.
So she's printed an extensive guest information pack
all about rare Suffolk spiders,
especially the great raft spider,
and she hopes this will act as an information to pay
that will stop visitors leaving poor reviews.
- Hmm.
So what we've got here is a holiday cottage
that is absolutely, sounds like absolutely coated in spiders.
(laughing)
- Imagine in a Ragnaphobia if you go to,
you know that movie, you go there,
but there's just a big sign saying spiders are our friends.
(laughing)
- You know what, this reminds me of,
I was driving back from somewhere,
I can't remember what it was,
somewhere in Gloucestershire maybe the other day,
and I drove through Beesden.
- To you.
- Wow.
- Was that, and I've taught me a different way,
'cause it was like a problem on the roads,
and then suddenly I was like welcome to Beesden,
and it reminded me of one of our favorite facts.
- Yes, full of Bees.
- Full of Bees?
- But he's still.
- Like 10,000 Bees were stolen from Beesden.
- Yes, that was the, that was getting it now.
- Look at the year.
- 2,000 Bees were stolen in Beesden.
- Yeah.
- I almost stopped off and tried to find the Bees,
but lucky that would be stupid.
- Yeah, well, they'll all be dead now.
(laughing)
- How's the search going, guys?
- 2,000, it does sound like a lot, but for Bees, that's.
- No.
- Highval two, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Very cool.
- A good book to write, though, and fun to read.
- Yeah.
- Right.
We've got a lookalike.
This is really exciting.
- Mm-hmm.
- Luke McNeil writes this.
I noticed an uncanny similarity between Dan Schreiber
and Don Music from Sesame Street.
- Twin separated at birth, perhaps?
Now, I was thinking, come on.
Is this, like, a Sesame Street character?
This is not gonna look like that.
- That looks like Beaker, doesn't he?
- Oh, from the Muppets.
Don Music, I would say, looks even more like Dan.
- All right.
- I'm just gonna turn the paper over for you now.
Your time starts now.
(laughing)
- No, that's Louis Theroux, isn't it?
- It's quite Dan, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- We prepared for how much, like, Dan.
(laughing)
- Hey everybody!
- What's he called?
- Don Music.
- Don?
- I'm clear why.
- Oh, he sounds like a twat, doesn't he?
(laughing)
- What?
- Don Music.
- Sounds nice.
- No, right now.
- With that head?
- With that face?
- I mean, don't be too harsh about it,
because it's your face, okay?
- I need to say, I reckon Don Music probably does music, right?
In the same way that Dan Schreiber,
it does the German for writing.
- Yeah, that's so very true.
- I think it might actually be based on you.
- Wow, I know.
So I've got that guy from Dender Dan.
- Yeah.
- And Don Music.
- Maybe you're the guy with an incredibly recognizable
copyable face and head, unlike me.
- No, you have just a face, but Dan has a face
which is very similar to other faces.
- Yeah, mine is generic, Dan's is repeated.
- Yeah.
- I got it.
- Like Pie.
(laughing)
- Please don't, please don't.
- No, then we're gonna do draft picks again,
and I won't be able to hack it.
Extreme fish.
- What's that mean?
- What do you think it means?
People doing extreme things while listening to fish.
- Oh, great.
- Yeah, so we have the guy who went fishing.
(laughing)
Okay, we'll get this.
I think this is unbelievable.
This might be email of the week.
- Okay.
- Duncan Pierce writes, "In the September of Drops of Line,
"you said descendant pictures of you
"doing extreme things while listening to fish.
"I'm not sure if this counts as extreme,
"but efficient counts as extreme,
"and this probably does as well."
(laughing)
Fair.
This summer, my friend Dante and I did our explore a belt.
Okay, a scout expedition similar to the British Duke of Edinburgh,
but it's for Swedish scouts.
And it involves being dropped off in a random city
in another country and having to hike 160 kilometers,
at least over 10 days without paying for lodging
or ready-made meals.
You just get dropped somewhere with a letter
with your destination and some challenges and 200 quid.
That's it. - Cool.
Sounds great.
I'd love to do that.
- I know.
Dante and I did this in Scotland.
We were dropped off in a small village called Ecclefecan.
(laughing)
- The locals are having you on there.
That is not a real place.
- Ecclefecan.
- Ecclefecan, yeah, yeah.
And they had this lovely time and he says,
the scouts were incredibly kind and people would let them
sleep in their gardens or whatever it was
and sort of be very hospitable.
- In Scotland, you're allowed to sleep in any field, right?
- No way.
- I think so.
I think, unlike in England,
if you want a camp, you need permission of the Londoner,
but in Scotland, I think you're allowed.
- Wow.
- Starting.
Okay, well, they did a bit of that.
They did a bit of camping.
And he says, "No such thing as a fish was our soundtrack."
We listened to the drove effects while walking
on the old drove road.
- Very good.
- Yeah.
And also, it's made it's called Dante.
What a name.
- I know, Dante.
- Duncan and Dante.
And they saw the great Polish map of Scotland.
Have you heard of this?
- No, it's the largest physical map in the world, apparently.
And it was made by some Poles living in Scotland
during the Second World War, as a thank you present.
I looked it up, it's absolutely massive.
There's massive map of Scotland.
Very cool, very cool.
- I know.
So there was some, just stunning stuff.
That's an extreme fish, I'd say.
Would you like to hear a bit of non-determ.
Quick old blast on that, please.
Flute, lovely.
Dennis Walker of Dumf, oh, I'm gonna say this wrong.
Dumfurlin, Dumfurlin.
- You got it right, the second time.
- Dumfurlin, yeah.
- Right, on nominative determinism,
I have always been amused by this book,
a book about chocolate by Sophie D. Coe
and Michael D. Coe.
- Coe coe.
- Oh.
- How good is that?
- Very good.
- I like it when people have,
they make you work a bit for your non-determ, you know?
- Yeah.
- There's not an immediately obvious spot.
- There you go.
- I wonder what he does for a job,
because his name would lend itself to non.
- Dennis Walker.
- Yeah.
- What are you thinking?
Line painter on the roads.
- Or just, he walks a lot.
He's a, is that a job?
- Can be.
- Tour guide.
- Yeah.
- Line painter on the roads, and I said.
(laughing)
- But has he said?
- No.
- I want right back in, Dennis Walker.
- Yeah.
- For God's sake.
- Please, in future emails, please include your profession.
You know, it's important.
- It is.
- It is important.
- Finally, email.
Nate Booster from Eugene Oregon writes.
- What do I name?
- Thank you for the hilarious and data rich show.
- Thank you.
That's nice.
It's a very nice compliment.
And Nate adds a bit of nominative determinism.
My last name is Booster.
And I spend a good chunk of my work day at a pharmacy
giving people vaccines.
- Very nice.
- Brilliant.
- That's awesome.
- But what do you do for a living, Nate?
- Oh, I'm sorry.
- That's great.
- Yeah.
- So there you go.
- Lovely.
- Anyway, that's it for this episode of "Crops of Line".
It was a good one, Andy.
It was, it's always fun.
And we'll be back again, now in two weeks.
- Come on.
(upbeat music)
And if you have anything to say about anything we've said,
please write to podcast@ky.com.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
See you next time.
Bye.
(upbeat music)