(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to a brand new episode
of No Such Things as Fish.
First things first, let me tell you
about our very, very, very special guest
and that is Phil Dunster, the brilliant actor
who plays the character Jamie Tartt
in the unbelievable TV show, Ted Lasso.
I don't know if you've watched Ted Lasso,
if you haven't, it's definitely worth checking out.
It's on Apple TV right now.
They're about to show the final episode
and if you don't have Apple TV,
I'm pretty sure you'll be able
to get a free trial somewhere and it's well worth it.
There's loads of good stuff on there
but especially Ted Lasso is such a good show.
Phil actually does listen to fish
so he came well prepared with loads and loads of facts.
It was such a fun show to record
and we all had such a great time.
Few more little bits of news.
We have some live shows coming up
in the Soho Theatre in London.
There are still tickets available for that
although some of the dates are now sold out
so you wanna get in there really quick
to get tickets for that
and those tickets can be found
at knowstichthingasafish.com/soho
and apart from that, join up to Club Fish.
There's loads of fun stuff happening there all the time.
There's bonus episodes, there's Discord
where you can chat to fellow Fish fans.
You'll learn about live tickets first.
There's all sorts of bonuses for signing up to that
so do that and apart from anything else,
if you're listening in a place
where you can follow knowstichthingasafish then do that.
We taught some industry bots the other day
and they said that is very important
that you click follow if you like us.
Anyway, enough about that.
Really hope you enjoy this show with Phil.
I'm absolutely certain you will
and all I can say is on with a podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of knowstichthingasafish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin,
Andrew Hunter Murray and Phil Dunster.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Phil.
- My fact this week is that the Shakespeare's Globe Theater
is the only building with a thatched roof in London
since the great fire of London in 1666.
- Very cool.
- Andy is very excited right now.
- That's so excited.
- Thatched roofs, are you kidding me?
- Yeah.
- This is brilliant.
- This is your thing.
- Jonish.
- Is it a fetish?
- No, I wouldn't say fetish.
- Would you like to have sex underneath the thatched roof?
- Everyone's got a bucket list.
(laughing)
- Anyway, look, the Globe Theater, sorry.
- So what's the story, what's going on?
- So Andrew Hunter Murray had sex inside the Globe Theater.
(laughing)
'Cause it had a thatched roof.
It was fascinating, it was originally built in Shoreditch.
It was called the Burbage Theater in 1576.
And the land was owned by this bloke called Giles Allen.
And when the lease on the theater came up,
he didn't want to renew it.
And so the Chamberlain's men,
which is Shakespeare's company of actors,
they decided that they will just literally upsticks,
take all of the timber from that theater
and hide it in someone's shed for a bit.
(laughing)
And then, whilst Allen was away at Christmas,
they built it a few hundred meters away from
where the current Globe Theater currently is,
is where they built the original.
- So that one was thatched,
the sort of proper original South Bank.
- But that will have been
before the Great Fire of London will it?
- That was Shakespeare's time.
- Yeah, it didn't hang around for very long.
It was 1599, I think, was when it was built.
And then it was actually burned down itself.
It didn't need no Great Fire of London to burn itself down.
- Wasn't it a cannon during a play?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think it was Henry VIII?
Was it?
That bastard?
(laughing)
- I think it's one of the least good histories.
I don't wanna--
- Well, they don't play it very often, do they?
- They don't go down the Globe and see Henry VIII.
- No, well, I think there must be a reason for that.
- Yeah, but last time they performed it,
the whole fucking thing, probably on the band list.
So did Shakespeare do his stuff in Burbage's Theater
up in the East London side?
- Sure did, yeah.
- Oh, really?
So was anything ever performed in his lifetime during--
- Well, yeah, Lightfill says they moved the Globe down to--
- And Shakespeare went along with it.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I think they rebuilt it within his lifetime,
even though it burned down quite closely.
He died in 1616, and I think it burned down
not long before that, but they rebuilt it,
and they're still showing new Shakespeare plays there.
- Well, that's really good to know,
because whenever I pass it, I think,
oh, this is just a replica.
It's not got any kind of original meat to it.
Shakespeare was dead by then, it's just a fake.
But if he was alive while people were performing--
- Well, the modern one is a new one.
It's completely new.
- It's an even more new one.
- Yeah, so the modern one was built in the, what, '80s?
- '90s.
- Something like that, in the '90s, yeah.
And that was by, what's he called?
- San Juanemaker.
- San Juanemaker, and that's the one which has got thatched now.
- That's right, yeah.
- Right.
- Yeah, it's pretty much the same.
It uses green oak, and it has wooden postings,
or whatever, doweling, or whatever it holds it all together.
They tried to make it as close
to how it would have been made at the time,
using all of the techniques that the builders would have used,
but they had to use stuff like modern scaffolding,
and they had to increase the amount
of fire escapes and exits and all that sort of stuff.
- They got sprinklers.
- They got sprinklers, yeah.
- I read them, I was reading the newspaper articles
from the time, and as late as 1988,
the papers were saying that there wouldn't be thatch,
and it would be tiled, and that was due to fire regulations.
And then sometime around 1990,
they kind of changed their mind and said,
"Yeah, we're gonna be allowed thatch after all."
- That's cool.
It's got some cashmere in the walls.
- Is it?
- Yeah, 'cause they used,
they made proper old-fashioned plaster,
as in 17th century plaster.
Wattle and Dorb is the name of it,
and it includes cashmere goat hair,
which is an ingredient of the plaster, so yeah.
- And the thatch roof that they have now
has a hidden set of sprinklers all the way through it.
- Oh yeah, nice.
- Just in case.
- Just so you know that they learned their lessons.
- I found a company that made the thatch,
they were called TAS, and there was an article about them,
and apparently the globe wasn't the biggest-ever contract
that they had.
They had one bigger contract for thatch roofs,
can you guess?
- Oh, my God.
- It was, oh, I've given it away, it's multiple roofs,
multiple thatch roofs.
- Did they redo a whole village or something?
- In a way.
- In a way, okay.
- Phil, I'll edit out all these silences, by the way.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Oh, an Olympic village,
but like an old fashioned Olympic village.
- That's right, yeah, it was a 2012 Olympics.
Everyone lived in batched houses.
That's why they were all having sex all the time.
- Right, absolutely.
- Was it for like a Game of Thrones sets?
- Okay, not Game of Thrones.
- Harry Potter.
- Lord of the Rings.
- No.
- Hobbit.
- Ted Lasso.
(laughing)
- I think, I don't know when this,
I think it was '90s, so it's a similar era, this.
- "Zena, the Warrior of Princes."
- Film came out.
- "Matrix."
- Yeah, okay.
- "Matrix," stop it.
- Was it "Historical" for?
- Oh, no, Shakespeare in love, Shakespeare in love.
- No.
- But that would have been--
- That feels good, that feels good.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Do you feel it?
- It's gonna be a bit of a downer now that I tell you.
It was Robin Hood, "Prince of Thieves."
- Oh, okay.
- No, you were there tracks.
- And they had to do the entire kind of village
and they put thatch on all of them
and that was the most money they ever made
and the globe was the second most they ever made.
- That's incredible.
- His movies are expensive, man.
- "Waterworld."
- Kevin Castle, yeah, that's "Flood the Earth,"
you know, for that one.
Kevin Costner, these huge sets.
- "Dances with Wolves,"
they had to teach all those wolves how to dance.
(laughing)
- You know the globe?
- I do, yeah.
- When they rebuilt it, it then shrank.
- Oh, riddle me that.
- Oh, okay.
- Okay, they built it in the summer and then it got cold.
- What kind of, just the timber dries out.
And it takes years and years for timber to properly dry out
and it dries and it hardens and it shrinks a bit.
- So it gets stronger through time, which is amazing.
- That's cool, that's really good.
Do you know where they got the timber from?
- No.
- I think it might have been the 1987 storm
in the new forest knocked down loads of trees.
But it's certainly a big storm in the late 80s,
knocked down a load of trees in the new forest
and they got all of the timber from there.
- That's really cool.
- Yeah, and also the Duke of Edinburgh offered wood
from one of his oaks at Windsor.
- Lovely.
- That's great.
- Good bloke, good bloke, yeah.
Do you want to hear another fact
about the Royal Family in this, by the way,
while we're talking about,
well, let's not say good blokes for this one.
So they crowdfunded it quite a lot of the money for this
because, you know, they need a load of money
and they need to get it from somewhere.
So they went to America and they had an event
called UKLA88, a celebration of British arts.
And according to the Desert Sun newspaper,
the real stars will be Fergie and Prince Andrew.
So Prince Andrew's partly responsible
for the building of the globe.
And the British consulate said,
"When you think of Britain,
"we don't want you to think about
"fatched cottages and bobbies,
"but of Concord, microchips and Phil Collins."
(laughing)
- I don't love to see Phil Collins perform at the Glow Theater.
- Concord's not even going anymore.
- No.
- Microchips, do we make many microchips?
- In the UK?
- Possibly.
- I don't think so.
- Huge centre of friends.
- Phil Collins is still going strong there.
- That's a good point.
- Yeah.
- He's the one part of Britain that's left.
- Yeah, have you played there, Phil, to look like?
- I haven't played there.
I've been to see quite a few productions there.
I was a poor student when I went.
And so I was standing.
I was one of the groundlings.
- Ooh.
- And I was, I mean,
I've got a pretty bad attention span as it is.
And being stood there for like three and a half hours,
I was like, "Oh, fuck this, man."
But--
- Do you remember what you were seeing?
- I saw "Midsummer Night's Dream" there.
And they were all great productions.
But this is my, listen, I'm working on it, I'm working on it.
But they have another space,
which is called the Wanna Make a Playhouse,
which, again, is made like a Playhouse
would have been back in Dere.
And it's fully lit by candles.
And you can just imagine that, again,
the schematics coming along, and they're like,
"Right then, Globe Theatre, what do you got for us today
"after all the thatched houses and all this stuff?"
Oh, a fully wooden theatre, and it's only lit by candles.
- The way you just said Dere,
just then a second ago, back into Dere,
apparently, if you see Shakespeare,
you weren't here to be or not to be,
you're here to bear or not to bear.
- Is that right?
- Well, this is what I read.
So apparently, the Globe Theatre has a tradition now,
these days, of making sure that the accents
that are spoken while Shakespeare plays on
is the accent of the time.
And so David Crystal, who James, you and I met years ago,
he's a linguistic guy, he studies all types of language,
and no one really knows how people spoke back then fully.
He kind of clobbered together an idea
of how to speak, and to be is to bear.
- To bear?
- To bear or not to bear.
- Okay.
- That was a classmate.
- It's quite Brian Butterfield there.
(all laughing)
- Oh, did you have any snacks when you were there?
- This is relevant, I promise.
- A beer.
- You had a beer, okay.
- A beer can't as a snack as more of a refreshment,
isn't it, a beverage?
- It's still something from the theatre.
- But it was very of today.
- Okay, so it wasn't, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It wasn't brewed in there.
- I have a beer.
(all laughing)
- To bear or not to bear?
- Exit, pursued by a bear.
(all laughing)
- I just wondered, 'cause archaeologists have done lots
of digging around under the sights of the old theatres,
and they found out what the snacks would have been
in Elizabethan times.
- That's great.
- Yeah.
- Okay, so what, go on.
- Well, they're slightly limited by what remains,
as in what rots and what doesn't.
- Of course.
- But they have found thousands and thousands
of oyster shells.
That was a huge thing.
And because oysters were not the food for the posh,
they were just a sort of standard snack.
Just get a few oysters when you went to the theatre.
So that was a big thing.
- Yeah, that's very cool.
- Just go back to the accent thing.
There was, because it was such an amalgamation
of different accents that were in London,
and they hadn't really sort of formed a London accent yet,
I guess, at that time.
It was such a hodge podge of different accents,
like a sort of Irish, British, West Country,
Lancashire, Geordie sort of thing.
And I could give it a bit of a go.
- Yeah, do it.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Nobody can tell me I got it wrong,
because no one remembers it.
Something like, "Two our souls, both alike in dignity,
"in failure of a rona, will we lay our sin,
"from ancient grudge break to new mutiny,
"where civil blood lay civil hens unclean."
Something like that.
- Wow.
- So that's great.
- That's great.
I did just get hit in the head before I said that.
(all laughing)
- Could you do the rest of the show?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
(all laughing)
- There's a lot of, if you go to the globe,
there's a lot of things on the floor,
which are the names of patrons,
basically help to fund the new globe and so on.
And so there's lots of very famous names on there.
And two in particular, which are exciting to see it,
John Cleese and Michael Palin, which is very cool.
- Mm-hmm.
- Yeah.
- Michael who?
- Michael Palin.
(all laughing)
No, Michael Palin.
- I'll stop it.
- Because according to the story,
John Cleese only agreed to donate to the theater
on the condition that Michael Palin's name was misspelled.
- And so on the floor, you can see it.
It's P-A-L-L-I-N.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- What would you have done if we just politely
glossed over it?
I was so nearly dead.
- I would hold it on, go, come on, guys.
Someone, someone call me of this.
It's a problem when you pronounce everything wrong.
- The thing is that Dan's such a big fan of Michael Palin.
I was thinking maybe that's how it's pronounced.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But yeah, so the globe says that this is the story.
When you go on the tour guides, they say this is the story.
There's no solid, you know, John Cleese needs to say it out loud.
- Okay, but it is misspelled.
- Yeah, it's misspelled.
Yeah.
We need to move on in a sec.
Does anyone have anything before we do?
- I've got some stuff on Rich the Third, but that's--
- Yeah, do it.
- So a lot of archeologists found that the old theater
buried underneath a car park not so far away.
And as was Rich the Third found under in a car park.
And obviously was one of Shakespeare's
big villain protagonists.
And Dr. Joe Appleby at the University of Leicester
looked at the bones and saw that Rich the Third
got fucked up when he got killed.
- Oh, right.
- That he was, they see from his bones.
He had a glancing blow to his cheek.
He had a wound from probably a halberd,
which is like big stick pike with a sort of axe thing.
It was potentially the fatal blow.
The back of his head, a sort of chunk was missing there.
And then they think that they didn't want to do too much more
to the face because Henry the Seventh
needed to parade this dead body around to be like,
"Look, this is definitely him."
- This is him, not just some pulp.
- Yeah, and they saw what they thought
would be some post-mortem injuries to his rib
and to his spine as well.
And then one up his bum, they reckon.
There's a sort of a mark like this one.
- Was that after he died?
- Well, this is it.
- This is it, this feels like a month.
- That's the question.
(laughing)
- That's a different play, Dan.
He's my kingdom for a horse.
My kingdom for a horse with a very soft saddle.
- Yeah.
- Wow, that's amazing.
- Yeah, poor old Blake.
- That was in battle, wasn't it?
That he was killed?
- That was in battle, battle of Bosworth.
- Yeah.
- Who was the last king killed in a battle?
- Was he?
- I don't think anyone since then has been.
- Cowards.
- Yeah.
- Come on, Charles.
- Come on.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that when residents of Greater Manchester
were recently asked,
they identified four distinctive accents in the region.
Mank, Lancashire, Wigan, and Posh.
(laughing)
- Brilliant.
- Yeah, it's like a good version of the Spice Girls.
(laughing)
- Wigan, Spice.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Mank, Spice.
- Wigan, Spice is eating a pie all the time.
- James, do you, when you see that there's these four,
does that make sense to you?
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, for sure.
I would say my accent began as Lancashire
with a bit of Wigan,
'cause I went to primary school in Wigan,
and now it's Posh probably.
- Right.
- Like, I've lost a lot of my accents
since I moved to London,
so I think people in Greater Manchester
would say I was in the Posh bit.
- You do, I notice when either you're around family
or people from the North,
you do slightly slip back into it.
It's like the wording, like, Tintinet.
I don't want, like, you know, have that sort of word.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- That's my New York true.
But you miss out, like, certain words sometimes.
- Oh, I did, I did it on purpose.
I did it when Phil came in,
and then he opened his mouth,
and I'm like, "Oh yeah, you're not Jamie Tartt."
(laughing)
- Always disappointment.
- What's Tartt's accent?
Is that from--
- It's, well, it's sort of new,
most in sort of the way.
- 'Cause the people who did this research,
one of them was called Dr. Rob Drummond.
He listens to fish.
It turns out, and I emailed him
and sent him an example of your accent
and asked him if he could place it.
- Oh my God, oh my God.
- So this is an academic.
And he said, "No, it's shit."
No, he didn't.
(laughing)
He was like, "No, it's really, really good."
And he says you do a great Manchester accent,
and it's all about the letter vowel and the happy vowel.
And apparently, when you say let her,
as I would say it,
if you're in Manchester, you say let or,
which Jamie Tartt does.
And happy, as I might say it, in Manchester,
they say happy.
But anyway, he could take your accent,
and he reckoned he could pinpoint
it's a pretty much central,
or just north of central Manchester.
- Wow.
- From Seoul, kind of, Smedley, that kind of area.
- That's so cool.
- An academic.
- That's a good report card.
- Three years later, that's the relief.
- It depends what series you watch,
'cause I think the first series, I was like,
"I don't really, I don't know if I'm doing this right."
But it was an American show, so I was like,
"No, they won't care."
- We should name the project, shouldn't we?
It was called Manchester Voices,
and it was a three-year research project
at Manchester Metropolitan University.
- Yeah, Dr. Rob Drummond, who checked out Phil's accent,
he is a listener, he listens to fish all the time
with his daughter, Cassia,
and he has a new book coming out called You Are All Talk.
It's not out yet, but if you wanna pre-order that,
you can.
- Ooh, they had a really cool thing.
They had an accent van, which drove around,
and they bundled people into the accent van
and recorded how they spoke.
Bundled.
- Yeah, they wrote it, there was consent.
(laughing)
- They had hoods, they had cuffs, they...
- That's so funny.
- And so the specific questions that they asked
were things like, "Oh, I'm curious,
'cause you're from Bolton, James.
So, if they said, "I've never heard you say,
"instead of bottle, Bockel."
- Bockel, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Or Lickle, instead of Bockel.
- Lickle, yeah, that is a Bolton thing,
but I don't really speak like that now.
- School with two syllables.
- Skewel.
- That's more of a Wigan thing, you would say skewel.
- Okay.
- So, the word Bocke, as I would say it,
10% of Boltoners say Bucke, instead of Bucke.
And 71% of Wiganers say that.
- Wow.
- So that's how you can tell the difference.
And 30% of Boltoners say buzz instead of bus.
And I actually do say buzz instead of bus.
- Did you, just with all those words, James was saying,
when you were doing your accent,
is it something that you studied?
Or is it one of those things that once you start speaking
in an accent, you almost naturally find
the way that they would pronounce it anyway?
- I guess studied, watched documentaries and whatnot.
- Yeah, okay.
- My agent, who I love very dearly, is a Mancunian.
And she's very sassy.
And there was a lot of sass in Jamie Tartt.
So I was like, that's quite a good sort of start point.
And I think generally I sort of am okay with picking that up,
but there's a rapper called H.
And it's funny that the difference--
- From steps, yeah, I know.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
No, he's much cooler.
- H from steps is coming on next week.
- Yeah.
(laughs)
- You're not careful.
- But H is really like proper Mank, isn't he?
- Yeah, he's the rapper.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And I think that one of the things was
when we were auditioning for it,
they didn't necessarily want a Mancunian.
They just wanted someone who didn't sound like me.
They just wanted Italian or Spanish or whatever.
And I think that it just felt right for him,
that sort of sense of like,
it'd come from a place that was,
that you had to sort of graft to get out of.
And that's why I say season one, season three,
I'm being totally honest.
It started off as one of the Gallagher brothers.
- Right.
- And it sort of slowly stepped towards
sort of Jesse Lingard,
come sort of a far more sort of contemporary version of that.
It would be like, all right, how you doing?
You all right, mate?
How's it going?
Yeah, I'll tell you a little bit about it.
But it's like, do you know what I mean?
Yeah, it's a lot more like sort of contemporary.
And it feels a lot more like,
he's just got, I feel like he's rapping all the time.
Do you know what I mean?
- Right, right.
- So yeah, and just, yeah.
So anyway, it sort of, it's shifted from
that sort of nineties version of it.
- I've read quite a few things about actors who,
so Austin Butler, who just played Elvis in the biopic,
the Baz Luhrmann biopic.
There's videos of him prior to doing the role
to how he speaks now.
And he's been unable to shift the Elvis voice,
the Elvis role.
So when he received his award
at either the Emmys of the Golden Globe,
he was, well, thank you everybody for this incredible award.
He can't get rid of it.
And he actively talks about it
'cause he's questioned about it.
They're like, you don't talk like this.
And he's like, oh no, I can't get rid of it.
- And so he's trying to lose the Elvis accent.
- That's so random.
- Yeah, well, no, it happens with quite a lot of actors.
That's how I was going to say it.
Did you ever have anything where at home,
suddenly you found yourself not being able to shift
the accent and was it not long enough a gig to each time?
- Oh, I think there was probably a couple of words
I just enjoyed saying, like "pooper."
I just really enjoyed it.
He wrote a pooper.
It just feels right.
A lot of the air words at the end was just quite fun.
But you can track what film Tom Hardy was doing
by interviews at the time.
'Cause I mean, he's got a real sort of chameleon accent thing.
- Remember Steve McLaren when he went to work
in the Netherlands?
And he just started talking with the Dutch accent.
- He was only there for like two.
- So he was a former England football manager.
And he became manager of, I can't remember who it was,
Ajax or something.
There he was in Ajax, but a Dutch team.
And then he would do interviews in England.
And he'd just have this really strong Dutch accent.
- And he'd been there for like only a few months.
And he was like trying to ingratiate himself
for the coaches.
- I think it's subconscious though, isn't it,
when people do that?
'Cause you're talking to people who,
let's say you go to America or Australia or somewhere,
you naturally will,
what all some people do and some people don't.
It's a really interesting thing.
- Well, you do naturally,
you imitate someone's accent, don't you?
Because it makes them like you better.
That's the idea.
But also they've decided that this is a good idea.
And they've got this AI software
where if you phone up, you know,
of what do you call it?
Like a chat, not chat line.
- Call centre.
(laughing)
- Yep, hang on a minute.
Yeah, yeah, one of those call centres, yeah.
- My back card isn't working.
(laughing)
If you phone up a call centre.
And yeah, they've worked out this AI
which can hear your accent and then imitate your accent.
And so they come back in a slightly similar way to you talk.
And it means you trust them more.
- It's so weird.
And it's mostly, basically,
because of where call centres are around the world,
it's mostly to make people in places like the Philippines
sound like they're from Boston or whatever.
And so, but this is the plot of a film.
It's a film called Sorry to Bother You.
And it's about a young black guy
who gets a job in a call centre.
- Oh yeah.
- And then someone tells him,
like an older guy in the centre says,
use your white voice.
And he starts getting lots and lots of business
because he's sounding preppy and whiter.
And so they've literally turned this.
It is a horror film.
- Yeah, they turn it into a technology, it's so weird.
- James, what is this little Bolton quiz?
- Oh, I don't know why.
- Oh, no.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Give it to us, give it to us.
- Give it to us, yeah.
- Pee wet, down.
- Oh, I know what that is.
I read it.
- Pee wet.
- You read it, so you're out of attention here.
I'm afraid.
- Pee wet.
- Two words.
- Pee wet is a type of bird.
- Absolutely.
Is that helpful?
Maybe not.
- Could be.
- 'Cause it goes pee wet, pee wet.
- Would James be trying to help you in this quiz?
Maybe.
- Yeah, is he a friend?
- Maybe not.
- I don't think he's a director.
- Pee wet.
- Pee wet, you've wet yourself with pee?
(laughing)
- I didn't even think of that, yeah.
- Yeah, good if you ever come to Bolton.
- Yeah.
- That's what you have to say.
I go to a chip shop and they say,
"Do you want pee wet?"
I go, "No, of course not."
- I don't mind if I do.
- I don't need your help for it.
Thank you very much.
(laughing)
- James was helping you.
That pee wet is the mushy pee water.
- Yeah, so you can get them to put,
if you have chips with pee wet,
then you don't have to pay for the pee wet.
- They'll get the chips and they'll just pour
a bit of the wet, a bit of the mushy pee.
- Oh, it looks good.
- The water runoff from the mushy pee.
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- I'm sorry.
- No, you didn't.
- Great, that's not what I thought.
I thought it was just mushy pees,
but that's a step towards insanity.
- Why do you want that?
Like, you'd have wet chips.
- It's delicious.
- So you'd have wet chips.
- Chips are too dry.
- So kind of like a vinegar.
- Put vinegar on, don't you?
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- It's very exciting.
- Shakespeare in English, isn't it?
- Yeah, it is.
- I want to try another one of them.
Cracking the flags.
- Bought to flags.
- Cracking flags.
(laughing)
- Is it rude?
She's got a pair of cracking flags.
(laughing)
- No, I don't know.
- Do you know what it is, Phil?
- I don't know what this is, no.
- Really?
What if I tell you that the flags
relate to flagstones as in like pavement?
- Okay.
- Cracking the flags.
- It's like walking as a pedestrian.
- Cobbled streets.
- This is so funny because these are words
that I thought everyone knew.
- And I'd never heard this until.
That's the only reason I mentioned it, yeah.
- It means it's really hot.
It's cracking flags out there.
It's so hot that the pavement's breaking.
- Yeah, yeah, nice.
Wow.
- God, I'm really failing as my pretend Mancunian here.
(laughing)
But the Mancunian accent was,
sorry, just to close this again.
The Mancunian accent was voted,
and I found this in the Daily Mail
and the research was provided by Best Casinos.
(laughing)
- So it's flawless, yeah, come on, on my go.
- I know that you love your watertight fact checking here.
After they asked 2,500 people,
they found that the Manchester accent
was the sexiest accent in the world.
- That's interesting.
- And that's from Best Casinos.
- Is that recent?
- Yeah, yeah, I think it was last year, I think.
- That's interesting.
'Cause like, I reckon that change,
you see those things quite often, don't you?
And they say, oh, the Irish accent's most sexy.
Or the Yorkshire is, never the Birmingham weirdly,
but they do say that.
And I wonder if it's like fashion,
like they've seen people like yourself
doing the Manc accent on TV,
and they associate it with--
- Did the Gallagas have an effect?
- I think they did, yeah.
- On the sexiness of the Mancunian.
- That's what I'm thinking.
- Yeah, 'cause I read a thing that in America,
there was once a vote on what was the most sexy accent
from the UK.
- Oh, the UK, okay.
- Yeah, and Glasgow won it, right?
And I wonder, because Billy Conley is so big in America,
whether or not there was just something kind of like,
I know he's not seen as like a sex symbol,
but he's seen as really charismatic,
really funny, everything that's like likable.
- Silky guy. - Yeah.
- Or whether the person doing the research
was Glaswegian and they felt intimidated.
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
I get, one of my favorite things
about doing this show is, I quite often,
I haven't actually had it in the last sort of 12 months,
but I used to get a bunch of linguists
who would write to me saying,
I take samples of your accent and my accent,
and I play it to other people who are linguists,
and the challenges work out where he's from.
And every time they say, no one can work out,
they say like, Canada or like New Zealand Australia,
like they get elements of it,
but no one needs to collect on tour.
- And we sort of do like signings afterwards,
and people sometimes come up and say,
where are you from, to Dan?
And then you'd ask them to guess,
and I used to keep a list on my phone
of everywhere people had guessed.
- Did you?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And it was, I mean, the whole world.
- 'Cause I think you just have an international accent,
like from, as if you went to international school,
like my wife's got similar.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Kind of slightly North American weird accent.
- Yeah, but I guess if then that becomes the challenge
for the linguists, what are the influences on this accent?
- We were saying before that when people
who are from a certain place go back to that place
or speak to other people from that place,
they start, that accent starts to come out a bit more.
Do you have that with one of your?
- If I go to Australia, I definitely lean into Aussie a bit.
I should have a British accent by now,
'cause I've been here long enough, but I don't.
And the Hong Kong accent was very American,
where I grew up.
- But where do you go to sound more like you are now?
Not just more Aussie, you know?
'Cause you don't really sound very Aussie.
- No.
- When you travel internationally.
It's actually only in departure lounges.
(laughing)
But Dan sounds most like himself.
- Yeah.
- Whenever you're buying a Toblerone, it's like,
"Ah, yeah, I don't know."
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that's my fact.
My fact this week is that of the few people
who have top secret clearance at the White House,
one of them is the person
who writes all of the party invitations.
(laughing)
- Amazing.
- Such a good plot for something, isn't it?
- It is, isn't it?
- You know, the calligrapher.
- And it's the president's party invitation writer.
- It's missing.
- Yes.
- 'Cause you'll know, as the invitation writer,
who's coming to the summits, who's, you know.
- Yeah, it's everyone's address.
He's got Brezhnev's address.
He's got--
- Brezhnev, yeah.
- Do you think of a key global player?
(laughing)
Brezhnev, when did Brezhnev stop running the Soviet Union?
- I was thinking of mine as a Cold War thriller.
(laughing)
- Imagine how beautiful his ransom letters would be.
- Oh.
- From the calligrapher.
That would be perfect.
So this is a thing where this kind of came up in the news
when it was during Trump's administration
that Jared Kushner, his son-in-law,
had been downgraded from top secret clearance
because they sort of just tried
to stop making everyone have it.
And people noted that--
- 'Cause he had too many links to the Saudis, but yeah, sure.
- Yeah, yeah, so--
(laughing)
- It's nice not recording on the BBC, is it?
- So it got downgraded and someone was pointing out
that actually he's now got less clearance
than the calligrapher has on the in-house.
And the reason the calligrapher has it
is because they have to know everything
about the president's appointments,
what's coming up, who they have to,
and they're near dignitaries all the time.
And so they need to be on top of everything
that they need to write
because they write so many invitations.
They have a unit, it's a calligraphy unit.
There's a whole office that does this.
It's not many people, there's only like three or four people.
But-- - That's still a lot.
- It's a lot.
In fact, one of them said that in one December period alone,
they believed that they did 19,000 envelopes.
- Brilliant.
- And those are handwritten.
- So yeah, so, and they're paid very, very handsomely.
And they've been going for a very long time.
Like they're like long-term posts that they can run for.
- But they did ask one of the,
I think he was by this point the former calligrapher
when the story broke.
And Rick Paulus, who had run the office,
he said that it was just 'cause of the schedule
and the proximity to world leaders.
He said he never, ever dealt with intelligence matters,
which you would hope he would not.
(laughing)
As in something's gone wrong if he has to solve a crisis.
- I wonder who's the best RSV peer.
- Oh, like the timeliest.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Of all the world leaders.
- Yes.
- That's interesting.
- I feel like Trudeau's waiting by the post office door.
- Yeah, yeah.
- He'll reply nice and soon.
They did a thing like this with the Royal Wedding.
There was a, I can't remember which Royal Wedding it was,
whether it was William Cate or Harry and Meghan,
but they ran a thing of, so-and-so's replied very quickly.
- Oh, really?
Really?
- Yeah.
- Do you remember the fact that Meghan Markle,
her former job when she was an actor as a side job,
she was a calligrapher for invitations.
So that's what she did.
- She did Robin Thickey.
- Of blurred lines, Robin Thickey.
- Yes.
- Yeah, a blurred lines wave.
He did, his wedding, the invites were written by Meghan Markle.
- You know Robin Thicke?
- Yeah.
- Who's that?
- The blurred lines guy.
Do you know, his dad was really famous.
He wrote the theme tune to Different Strokes, the TV show.
- Ooh, is that also a problematic song?
(laughing)
- Sounds it.
- It's not like a sexy song, it's like a show.
- Sure, it means something very different.
- Wow, that's the best, I mean, no offense by this James.
Trippy effect, I've ever heard.
(laughing)
Like that's good, that's good.
- It's just something that happens to know, that's all.
- That's fabulous.
- Rick Polis, by the way.
So this guy was the head of calligraphy.
Have you seen his website?
rickpoliskalligraphy.com, wonderful.
He's quite annoyed because the kind of digital age
where computers started recording all the examples
of all the invites that they write over the years
and now being archived, he kind of just missed that.
So a lot of his work isn't online for you to see.
So he presents on his website, my favorite invites
and my favorite bits of calligraphy
that I did for the White House.
Yeah, so you can see menu for the president of Ireland.
- That's a cool one, isn't it?
- He did a load of convoluted Celtic style design.
- Oh, that's great.
All of those meals the president pays for, doesn't he?
- Yeah, is that weird?
- Yeah, is that right?
'Cause it's, we, when I went to the White House.
- Clang?
- Yeah, kind of.
(all laughing)
Guys, are we talking about the White House?
- When did you go?
- I went, at the start of this year,
the cast of Ted Lasso were inexplicably invited
for an audience with the president and the first lady.
Insane, yeah.
Six of the cast members sort of spoke to the president
and the first lady about mental health
and the effect that the show has
and sort of impact that is needed over there.
But we also, you know, we were having a tour
and we sort of had, you know, learned some things
about a little thing or two about the White House.
And one is that the president,
because a lot of it is state funded
or sort of funded by taxpayers,
they can't be seen to be handing out big banquets
for everybody that comes.
It is just, like he says, gaff, isn't it?
- Yeah, exactly.
- And you know, hopefully one day we'll be able to say,
huh, gaff, guys, all right, we're all right, guys.
- 2020, '23, did you get an invite and we'll fill them?
- Are you just like a handwritten one?
- No, I did not.
We got an email and obviously we all thought it was fake
that we'd be invited to the White House.
I wonder if the same guy types the emails on.
- He types them incredibly.
He has a little wand he uses to tap each letter.
It's very gay, yeah.
- Did you have lunch with Biden or did you just say hi?
'Cause I saw a photo.
You were in the Oval Office, right?
- We were, we took her to the Oval Office, yeah.
- Oh my God.
- Which is wild.
It was the energy you walk in the room,
you're like, oh, some scandals sort of.
- Yeah, right.
- But no, we were kept in the map room where we ate,
which is where they planned the D-Day landings
in the map room, just to be sitting there eating as odd.
And you're there with like 25 Secret Service
or just sort of knocking them out.
Who were so cool, really nice.
And also like have, you know, you ask them any question
and you can see them go through the Rolodex of
what can I say, what can't I say.
The weird thing was, I don't know if you've had it,
when you call someone by a title,
it suddenly feels very strange
and these people that you've been knocking about
with the cast members I've been with,
hearing them call someone a title,
it feels very contrived the whole thing.
- Do you mean like Mr. President?
- Mr. President.
- Huh, yeah, yeah.
- And so you're just thinking about that the whole time
when you're meeting him.
- What's the term for the first lady?
- Dr. Biden, I think.
- Dr. Biden, sorry, sorry, sorry.
- And obviously the whole time you're thinking,
it's like in Taxi Driver, when you did an eros go,
you're talking to me, you're talking to me.
It was like, before I turned up, I was like,
Mr. President, Mr. President, hello Mr. President.
And of course, it's just, don't say Trump, don't say Trump,
don't say Trump.
(all laughing)
But it was funny when we were saying goodbye,
the guy who plays Isaac McAdoo, Colla Bikini,
I was stood next to him, he was shaking our hands,
the president was shaking our hand,
it's all going around the circle.
And it turns to Colla, he goes,
thank you for coming along, son.
And he goes, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Cheers.
(all laughing)
He turns to me and he says,
I just said, cheers to the president.
(all laughing)
- That's so good.
- I don't know how often people call the president,
dad, by Mr. President.
- You know, like calling the teacher, mum.
- Exactly. - Yeah, yeah.
- It must have happened to him on a sort of daily basis.
- It's such a shame you didn't have lunch with him
because I've heard great stories about his lunchtime.
Well, when he sits with Kamala Harris
and they have their lunch,
he likes to eat with a slideshow going.
So they just eat their meal
while they're watching a slideshow
of all the recent adventures they've had,
just so that they can sort of remember and reflect on.
- What, just the photos of?
- Yeah, yeah, it's just a slideshow.
- That's nice, I think. - Yeah, I think, yeah.
- Is it a slideshow of his stuff or both of their?
- Both of them, I think, it's, yeah.
It's just like, oh, okay, here I am, shaking a hand.
Yeah, so that's Ted Lutter, okay?
He said, cheers.
(all laughing)
But can I tell you one last calligraphy thing?
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Did you hear of Rick Muffler?
- No.
- What a guy.
So Rick Muffler used to be a calligrapher,
maybe the chief one, and he was controversial
'cause he was the only left-handed calligrapher
in the office.
- Oh, that means you're gonna smudge
everyone else's calligraphy.
- Exactly, it was a nightmare.
But just, he's cool, particularly because
it's kind of a family thing for him.
So his grandfather was a chauffeur
for President Warren G. Harding.
And then his dad, John Muffler,
was an electrician who wound the clocks
in the whole White House.
He worked there for 50 years.
He arrived in the late Second World War,
and he was there for Bill Clinton.
That's all that time he was in the White House.
- And so Muffler's the third?
Is that who we're talking about?
- Rick Muffler was the third Muffler.
I don't know if there's a new Muffler.
- I'd like to dream, and I won't be here to see it,
but in like 500 years, there'll be a Muffler president.
And like they'll have muffled the way up to the top.
- That would be good, wouldn't it?
- That'd be great.
(laughing)
- There were some sort of heirs and graces
that the Trump family didn't really follow.
- Oh, really?
- There were traditions that the first lady,
when the president leaves office for the last time,
the first lady would sit for a portrait.
And Melania refused to do that,
or has certainly has yet to have sat for it.
And there's this corridor where all of these paintings
are put, and Michelle Obama is still placed
at the end of the corridor,
which is traditionally where the previous encumbered--
- That's so interesting.
- To be fair, I feel like both Donald and Melania
probably have a painting in the attic somewhere.
(laughing)
- Very good reference.
- Thank you.
(laughing)
- I was reading about top secret clearance,
just 'cause these calligraphy people
have top secret clearance.
- Oh, yeah.
- It's a very weird thing, top secret clearance,
because it appears to, like so many people have,
their numbers are mad.
Okay, so there's like secret confidential,
and then top secret, or something like that.
The top secret's the highest.
But top secret clearance, even back in 2015,
it was 1.3 million Americans.
- Yeah, that's like one in every 300 people in America.
- Well, yeah, and if you broaden it to confidential,
maybe that's the bottom rung.
It's about 1% of all Americans have secret status.
- None of the children will have it.
So that's even, you know--
- God, you're right.
It's really common.
If you're American listening to this
and you don't have top secret clearance,
that's a shame on you.
- Yeah, give you head of wobble.
- So when I said at the top of the few people
who have top secret clearance.
- But I wonder if it's slightly different
than White House top secret compared to,
this is like civil service top secret.
- Yeah, there are--
- And there's CIA and there's--
- There are different donations within top secret where,
like not everyone can look at the plans
of where we're gonna invade next, or whatever.
- Who's coming for dinner?
- Yeah.
- Biden's slideshow.
(all laughing)
- Yeah.
- It is strange.
- It became evident when, during the recent leaks,
during the Ukraine war,
that was one of the things that people were so surprised about
was that there's so many people had this clearance
that was, you know, very delicate.
- A 21 year old.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Very peculiar.
- Yeah.
- I was reading about some other parties,
or some parties at the White House.
- Oh yeah.
- This is a party invitation guy.
- Yeah.
- I found there seems to be quite a common thing
of riots in inauguration parties
when people go to get their coats
at the end of the night.
- Yeah.
- This is really weird.
It happened in President Reagan's ball in 1985.
Like, everyone went to get their coats at the end,
and they got all mixed up.
Because the inauguration takes place in winter, right?
It takes place in January.
So everyone's got loads of coats,
and they're never prepared for it.
In 1989, President Bush had a ball
which got known as the Bastille Day Coat Check Riot.
Because people were yelling and screaming,
and some people never, to the day,
haven't got their coats back.
There was one coat check person for 3,000 coats.
(laughing)
- What a nightmare.
- And people, like, obviously,
these are all, like, really high-up people who think,
well, you know, I'm the most important person in this room.
I should get to the front and get my coat first.
And people are shouting, bushing, and all that kind of stuff.
But it even goes back to 1849
at Zachary Taylor's inauguration ball.
Abraham Lincoln lost his hat.
And for Ulysses S. Grant's inauguration,
all the workers who were working in the close place
were all illiterate, and no one got their coats, them, either.
So it just seems to be a thing.
- That'd be dangerous for Lincoln,
because Lincoln used to keep secret documents
in the top of his hat, didn't he?
- Yeah, exactly.
- Top hat secrets.
- Oh, good.
So just so weird.
- Shame that the beautiful calligraphy
would have been wasted on those people
that couldn't read.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 1999,
The Times newspaper reported that Liverpool FC
were about to buy a footballer called Didier Baptiste.
The Times got the story
from Liverpool's premium line news service.
They got it from the news of the world.
They got it from a sports agency,
and they just found it on a random Arsenal fans website.
In actual fact, Baptiste was a fictional player
in a soap opera.
- What role did best casino play in there?
(laughing)
- Yeah, so this is an amazing thing that happened.
It was in the papers in '99.
Liverpool are gonna buy this guy Didier Baptiste,
but he was actually a character
from the show Dream Team on Skies.
- So funny.
- And yeah, just people hadn't checked it properly.
The Times said he was a promising left-back for Monaco
and a proud member of the French under 21 national side,
surely a steal for 3.5 million pounds.
- Amazing.
- Wow.
- The news of the world said we think Didier Baptiste
will be an ideal addition to Liverpool's back four.
He's a really attractive player.
You'll be seeing a lot more of him
in the news of the world from now on.
- Oh.
- Obviously.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it was just completely made up.
- Lying again.
- Is this like a transfer season rumours thing?
'Cause lots of football stories seem to be about, you know.
- Yeah, of course.
Like clubs gonna buy a new player.
You often have never heard of them,
especially if they're coming from a different country.
And if he's an under 21 player, he's quite young.
It wouldn't be that surprising
that you might not have heard of them,
but you possibly would expect
that newspapers would do a bit more research.
- I mean, you think at today's age,
that would be absolutely absurd, it was absurd then,
but now, obviously, you'd be able to sort of,
you know, they'd be on FIFA
or you could find them somehow.
- That's true.
- Yeah.
- It would be more difficult to do today, for sure.
- When was this?
It was in the '90s.
- It was in '99.
- '99?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Because it was so much harder
to find these foreign players
on databases or whatever.
There was, do you hear about Ali Deer, not Ali Dyer?
In 1996, Graham Sunez,
who was the manager of Southampton at the time,
he got a call from George Weir,
who was a Ballon d'Or winner, you know, player of the year.
- Future president of Liberia.
- Yes, yes.
- Ooh.
- Yeah, there you go.
- And he's interested.
- He's really muffled his way up there.
(laughing)
- He called Graham Sunez,
saying that he should give his cousin, Ali Dyer, a trial,
because he'd been playing at Paris Saint-Germain,
he'd been playing for Liberia,
and he'd been doing pretty well.
And so, Sunez was like, that's amazing.
I mean, you know, playing at Paris Saint-Germain,
that's incredible.
And so, they gave him a sort of trial contract.
They gave him three and a half grand, signing on bonus.
And he turned up to training,
and Matt LaTissier, who was sort of the star player,
he's quite the same.
What's this bloke doing here?
- I honestly thought he won a competition.
(laughing)
But it was the reserve team that Ali Dyer had been put
onto to play for that weekend.
Their match was canceled.
And so, Southampton first team needed a sub.
And so, he went there and subbed on when LaTissier was injured.
He played for 43 minutes before being subbed off again.
He's so bad.
- He was just a made up guy.
Was it even, was the George Wayer thing,
or was it actually George Wayer who called him?
- No.
- So, they don't know to this day who really who it was,
but people believe it might have been his friend,
or it might have been his, you know.
- It was just a bloke.
I love these stories.
- Yeah, I love the Hutzpah.
- Yeah.
- Do you guys hear about Karl Power?
- Karl Power, okay.
- Karl Power was, he wasn't never a sports player,
but he was a serial trickster.
And his thing was tricking his way
into sporting environments that he wasn't meant to be in,
right?
And he started, like, when he was a teenager,
he would tell them about boxing matches
with a towel and a gym bag,
and he would get him for free
'cause they assumed he was part of the fight, right?
- That's a risky one, though, isn't it?
'Cause if they think you're an actual boxer,
you're in trouble.
- He built on it, and he built his career.
And he, so one of his greatest moments
was when he got into a Manchester United team photo
just before they played a big Champions League match.
And you can see a shot.
He's got Ryan Giggs, Andy Cole, Gary Neville,
and Karl, just this guy.
And Neville, Neville, was the only one who rumbled him.
Like, they were all lined up for the photo,
and Neville pointed at him and said,
"Who are you, who are you?"
And he said, "Shut it, Gary, you grass."
(all laughing)
- You can see that video.
You can see Roy Keane right at the end clocks it.
And Roy Keane, he's a pretty feisty footballer.
And you see him look across, and it's daggers.
- That's so funny.
That's really a shut-in grass.
- He spent his whole career doing this.
I said career, he didn't get paid much for it,
but he played on centre court.
He just turned up and played,
he played a match like a little warm-up
with someone like Tim Hemman.
He got onto the podium at the Grand Prix,
the British Grand Prix.
- He came out to bat for England,
and the test match they were playing was.
I mean, it was.
- But he didn't actually hit any balls.
He just walked towards,
and then they realised it was the wrong person.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But I just, I had mine so much.
- But that's performance art.
- That's not.
- Yeah.
- That's pure performance art.
- That's brilliant, 'cause he's still going in car power.
- I don't think he's still trading, as it were,
but I think he's still around, yeah.
- Once you get to an age,
you can't pretend to be a footballer anymore.
- You can't pretend to be a manager, I guess.
- Or like a bowls player, or something like that.
- I found a, this is a real footballer,
but had a fictional element to them.
So it's sort of like mostly real person.
But I was reading about Maradona,
and Maradona, so he used to do a lot of drugs.
I think that's very well known to do.
- I like it.
- Breaking news.
Yeah, Andy, he was big on the old cocaine.
But so he had, he was all real, except he had a fake penis.
- Sorry, Maradona.
- Maradona, he had a real penis,
but he also had a special fake penis made of plastic,
so that when he had to do drug tests,
he would pull the fake penis out,
and he would allow the urine to come through it.
And it's so hard to get to the bottom of this story.
Supposedly, the penis was put on display
in a museum in Buenos Aires, and then went on tour.
I read this in The Guardian,
written on tour, and then someone stole the penis,
somewhere on tour.
So this missing relic of Maradona's
is out in the world somewhere, but yeah.
- Wow.
- That'll be on some billionaire's mantelpiece.
You know, they've paid big, big money to a cabal
or something to source.
- What's called the knob of God.
- Nob of God.
- Yeah, someone's got the knob of God.
- And you have a fake bladder, too, I guess.
- It's called a whizinator, I think.
I've heard of these things before,
and yeah, you use them for, like, drug tests.
- Do you hook it up to a fake bladder?
Or does the penis contain the fake urine
that you're trying to--
- It's not an actual human bladder,
it's just a bit of plastic, but yeah, a bag.
- So you've got the bag and the whizinator,
the fake penis, and everything's in your trousers, right?
- Well, everything's about your person, for sure.
But then there was a person who did that,
and it turned out that they were pregnant,
even though it was a male-spurred person.
Yeah, he'd taken some female urine,
and they were like, "Good news, you didn't take any drugs."
- I heard you used your pregnant.
- And a horse, apparently.
Before you said anything about explaining the drug test thing,
I thought you were gonna say it was
'cause people would try and grope him at clubs,
and then he could kind of make a getaway.
You know, like, a lizard losing its tail.
- Oh, right. - That's a great idea.
- I mean, I don't imagine he played with it, did he?
Did he play?
- I don't think you're asked for urine samples mid-gay.
(all laughing)
- To me, a non-fan, that would liven things up.
- Well, you've seen when Gary Lineker
pooed himself on pitch, haven't you?
- Oh, yeah? - Yeah.
- I haven't seen that clip, yeah, yeah.
- Well, 'cause there's a mystery,
we wrote about this in our book of the year,
the fish book, that Gary Lineker, still to this day,
some 20-odd years after he did that,
gets sent a single piece of toilet paper
that's got a bit of poo on it in the post.
He's just constantly, he doesn't know who's doing it.
- Oh, it's quite easy to find out
surely who's poo that is.
- Well, yeah. - You can just take a look.
- No, but if the person sending it is clean,
they're not on any DNA registers.
- I was thinking with, 'cause Gary Lineker's been
in a bit of problem with the government,
hasn't he? - Oh, yeah.
- This year.
I wonder if Eddie was Czech, so well, a problem.
(all laughing)
- Not saying it's her, but it's just worth checking
everyone, isn't it, really?
All of his enemies.
God bless him.
What were you talking about?
- Football, sort of fake or lie footballers.
- Yeah.
- Looking at you, Phil.
(all laughing)
- Well, I mean, our whole performances on Ted is,
it's so edited that, you know,
it's basically choreography on Ted Lasso,
rather than it being sort of pretending
we're playing football, I see it in one's choreography,
but it's so hard to do.
Because the thing, one of the things I really found,
I really tried to, like, (sighs)
when you see close-up of players,
that was me breathing below.
(all laughing)
But if there was ever shots in the middle of a game,
I wanted it to feel like--
- You're probably panicking.
- Yeah, and I feel like so many sports films you watch
that that doesn't happen and it's really frustrating.
But there were certain things that the production
had to take into their own hands,
which was some of the particularly difficult
choreography that we had to do.
Like, someone shoots, it hits off a post,
it hits someone's face.
It's CGI, the ball is CGI.
So we'd be running around the pitch,
sort of pretending to kick a ball,
which is very--
- That feels like a bit more difficult, right?
- Yeah, it does, it feels hard.
- Because you've got to think of what the weight is
of the ball and how far it's going to go.
- Do they not, like, in some CGI,
they'll just have an orange instead of whatever?
Like, you're fighting a dragon,
but there's an orange or something.
(all laughing)
- It's a guy in green, his head is the ball.
- And the wonderful best actor goes to the ball.
(all laughing)
- Tom Hanks' Wilson Furious never made it to nomination level.
- No, I've got one fact.
It's less about sort of fake football,
but more, there is, do you know about Will Still,
the manager at Reem or Ram FC?
It's a league team.
And every single time the team plays,
they are fined 22,000 euros.
- What are they doing out there?
- Well, it's not so much them, it's the manager himself.
He is the youngest manager in European football.
He's 30 years old.
He's an English Belgian, I think, and it's incredible.
He's like this sort of real hotshot manager,
but because he's so young,
he hasn't really had time to go and get his certifications,
which you need in order to be a manager in Ligue 1.
And so he's just sort of like, he learned off
football manager, and he went to university,
he got a degree, but it was really through that.
But yeah, so--
- So they find because he just hasn't got
the certification yet?
- Yeah, so it's one of the rulings.
- What a fine, how big of that can they forward that?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But he's done so well, and it's incredible.
If you watch a video of him, you hear him speaking
as one normally would in a training session in English,
and then without missing a beat, it goes into perfect French.
And it's incredible, you watch him and it's just, yeah,
he's a really interesting guy, an interesting guy.
- That's a shame, I always thought
that we could just become a football manager.
Whenever Tramir lose that, like Tramir lost,
I'm a Tramir fan, so we lost our manager a few weeks ago,
and I always think, it's worth a try, isn't it?
It's worth a try becoming a football manager,
but now I know I have to get actual qualifications.
- This feels like a French bureaucracy thing, surely.
- Do you think ever since Karl Power turned up
on Paris Saint-Germain and tried to coach the team?
- Do you think it'll be okay?
- I think it'll be fine.
I think you'd be fine, James.
What I don't know about football isn't worth knowing, right?
So I'd say go for it.
- I can friend some park with a new thatched roof.
- I'll be there, I'll be there, all right?
I've got a season ticket.
- Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland, James.
- @JamesHarken.
- Andy. - @AndrewHunterM.
- And Phil. - @PhilDanster.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing,
or you can message us on our email podcast at qi.com.
Otherwise, go to our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
And Phil, do you wanna mention anything coming up?
- Ted Lasso is currently, I think it's just about to air
its final episode, or maybe just aired.
So go and watch that.
And I love you.
(laughing)
- Aw, that's nice.
- That's a great way to end our show.
- Damn, do we have any live shows coming up?
- We certainly do.
James, do you wanna tell everyone about it?
- Oh, fucks sake.
(laughing)
- Yeah, there you go.
- It's happening between the 17th of July
and late August at the Soho Theatre.
We're doing 11 shows, sometimes two a night.
So there are some tickets left, actually.
I think about half the tickets have already gone,
but there are some left.
So hurry now.
- Great, okay.
- Oh, and go to knowsuchsthingasofish.com/soho
to book your tickets.
- There you go, do come.
Tickets are going really fast, so do get in quick.
And we've got a new guest each night.
It's gonna be really, really fun.
So that's it, Phil, we love you too.
Thank you for doing the show.
And we'll be back again next week with another guest.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)