(upbeat music)
- We're basically just a little fact show
where we just tell each other little facts
and then we go home.
That's what you've come to tonight.
They're not shitty facts though.
I think everyone here knows that.
They're kind of like in the,
it's not just like, oh, there's an interesting like,
you know, rising the rates of interest right now.
It's kind of, there's a few people like,
I'd love to hear that show.
No, they're kind of like, we love the juicy facts.
The little facts that like,
give you that little orgasmic shiver
where you're like, oh God.
So, is that literally just me?
- It's just you then.
- Yes.
- Just you.
- Oh wow, okay.
James, you said you had a fact that you were-
- I'll give you a fact.
Prince William is exempt from the Data Protection Act,
the Wildlife and Countryside Act,
and the Nuclear Explosions Act,
which means he is allowed to set off a nuclear bomb,
share your email address with third parties,
and shoot a great crested newt with a machine gun.
(all laughing)
If he wants.
- That's great.
- Living the dream.
- That's amazing.
All right, let's do this.
You guys ready?
(all cheering)
Let's record a show.
Roll the theme tune.
- Do you know what kills most bacteria in the world?
- Metal.
- Nope.
- Is it death hole, like 99.5?
- Death hole, good guess, no.
As in not humans.
- Is it just old age?
- Old age?
No, it's not old age.
- So what do you mean not humans?
- Well, so try thinking of something that's not a human.
- Is it a dragonfly?
- No, it's not dragonflies.
It is viruses.
Viruses called bacteriophages.
Oh, it's viruses, blah, blah, blah.
But here's the really interesting thing about that, right?
They destroy 40% of all bacteria
in the ocean every day.
- 40% of the ocean every day.
- What?
- So if you take all the bacteria in the ocean on a day,
40% of them won't be there the next day
because they've been eaten by viruses.
And of course they keep making more and more bacteria.
Imagine if all the viruses disappeared.
- This is, imagine I'm frustrating the viruses.
This is the real Sisyphian task, isn't it?
We've literally done almost half of, oh God, they're back.
(all laughing)
- We'll get rid of them all this time.
- They're eating them, right?
- They're eating them, aren't they?
When you come back to the fridge and it's full again,
you're like, whoa.
- Yeah, they do phages eat.
- It is, but it's not eating like we're eating, is it?
There's no plates and knives and forks.
- That is a huge number.
- That is insane.
- That's insane.
- Is it totally equilibrium or is there like a clean time
to go each day, like at the end of the day,
the users don't know?
(all laughing)
- And it regenerates at midnight,
like shutting back into a pumpkin.
- I think they do work with the days and nights
and stuff like that to a certain extent.
But on average, a trillion, trillion viruses
will infect bacteria in the ocean every second.
- Wow.
- Whoa.
- We need to teach them to eat plastic.
- That's a good idea.
- Yeah, really good idea.
- I think actually there are,
I think it's bacteria,
the scientists are trying to get to eat plastic
and then you release it and then what could go wrong?
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- I wonder if there's ever been a day where it just,
there was too much eating, you know,
where they just got to like 70% or like something just
ridiculous, one harvest day.
- Or a day when the viruses are like,
oh, it's, you know, virus independence day.
We're not going to do anything today.
- Yes.
- Or Lent, virus Lent.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, exactly.
- So I came across when researching for this fact,
a website called faxcore.com.
No, it's not a fax porn site.
(all laughing)
It basically provides sort of
modern day cloud faxing services,
but it has a page on fax news,
which seems to be really well researched.
There's Sam Minton who's doing a great job.
Just trawling through local newspapers for fax news.
So they reported on a blimpy sandwich shop,
I think it's a sandwich chain in America,
in New Jersey in 2015,
which was being sued by an auto parts repair place
for sending unwanted fax promotions.
So they sent thousands and thousands of promotions.
In, also in 2016, the Milwaukee Bucks,
who were a basketball team,
ran a promotion saying,
if you want to meet Coolio and Glenn Robinson,
who I think was a basketballer in the '90s,
and he, it was like a throwback to the '90s.
So they were like,
if you want to meet these two famous people,
throwback to the '90s,
why don't you fax us to this number?
And they expected to only get about three faxes,
'cause no one has a fax machine.
- Anybody likes Coolio,
it's just gonna fax after fax, right?
- Well, indeed, they had to then put a tweet out saying,
sorry, we're desperately changing the toner in our machine,
'cause there's far too many faxes coming through.
Sorry about this.
And then one, which sounds incredibly annoying,
a woman called Ann Bruce in Phoenix, Arizona, in 2015,
her number, her phone number,
was accidentally printed on a doctor's business card
as his fax number,
'cause doctors still use faxes quite a long way
beyond ordinary people.
And so she was just getting woken up
all hours of the night.
He'd be on call all hours of the night
by fax machines calling her,
just constantly picking up her phone to,
(imitates phone ringing)
(all laughing)
- Have you read the story about the 2015 fake Goya?
- What's that?
- It's just, I actually feel really sorry
for the con artist in this story.
So there were these two men who bought a Goya painting,
I think in 2006, they bought a Goya painting,
which they thought was real
and it came with a certificate of authenticity.
But then, after they paid for some of it,
like the deposit, it turned out that it was a fake
and the court ruled that they could keep it,
but they had to pay the deposit
'cause they lost quite a lot of money on it.
So then they decided they would try
and sell it themselves as a genuine,
they would try and con someone to buy it
to get the money back.
When they successfully got somebody
to say they were gonna pay for it,
and they had a middleman who was a broker
and they gave that middleman 300,000 euros
to kind of do the deal.
So they gave him 300,000 pounds of money that they borrowed.
They then received 1.7 million Swiss francs from the buyer,
but that money turned out to be fake.
So they were there.
- Is this all a weird game of Monopoly?
- It's amazing.
But then they got arrested in the airport
for possessing fake money.
So then they basically sold a fake goya for fake money,
but accidentally used real money as a transaction.
- Yeah, so they lost genuine 300,000.
- So much money, I feel so bad for them, yeah.
- The money was photocopied.
- Yeah, it was so badly forged.
I can't believe that even, I suppose,
you just, when you get a hand at a suitcase of money,
like you just like open and close.
And I always learn from Hustle
that you put real money on the very top.
So that like the top where every money is real.
- Maybe they did that, that's possible.
- I think if you are trying to sell a fake goya,
then check some of the middle notes.
- Hmm, yeah, that's true.
That's a good tip.
- Good tip.
- Good very niche piece of advice.
- Just because we can't leave a fact alone
without mentioning a penis fact in it,
if there is a penis fact to be had in it.
- Oh, okay.
- So I think we should just say
that he had a very close friend goya called Martin Zappete,
who, it's always confusing, I suppose,
when you read exchanges of letters between men,
which are very affectionate in the olden days.
And critics always say,
this relationship has been hugely misinterpreted,
and people have attributed homosexuality to it
when it's not.
- It's just good friends, they're just good friends.
- Exactly, why are we insisting, like, these letters?
So they really loved each other
in whatever way you choose to believe.
And they swapped dick pics, which is a perp,
I'm sure you, James and Dan, do that often.
- Was it?
Yeah, but mine are Saturn devouring Dan's dick.
(all laughing)
- Mine is a dog being drowned by James's dick.
- Oh, that didn't even work.
Okay, so there was this guy,
he was a merchant, Martin Zappete,
and we just have a letter from goya to him saying,
dear, and then in place of his name,
there's just a picture of a penis.
(all laughing)
- That could be a slug.
- So he would draw just a little cock and balls,
kind of thing.
- He drew a little one, but then he went on to say--
- That must have been a burn, a little one.
- I think it was meant to be complimentary,
because then, and it was obviously in response
to a letter that he'd received from Martin,
and in response to the letter he'd received,
he said, Jesus Christ, what an almighty member.
(all laughing)
The Spanish is slightly, like there's no direct translation,
but what an almighty member.
And then he said, you must have drawn that from life,
as in you must have been drawing your own penis.
- You know, like when you're at school
and you draw around your hands to make like hand prints,
do you think that's what he was doing?
- That's what exactly he said.
- He said, I think you've traced around your own penis.
- Really?
- 'Cause otherwise you're an amazing artist.
And then he said, what a pity, otherwise Goya,
you're an amazing artist.
(all laughing)
- I'd love to come around and do a rubbing one.
It's the other, this is Goya writing it.
- I'm Goya writing it.
- The artist, he's like, and then he said,
and he starts referring to the penis picture as a man.
So he says, what a pity he cannot be exhibited
to the public so that he could be tried out
and the lady he fits best can get to keep him.
And--
- This is locker room chat, isn't it?
- Yeah, this is, oh, sorry, Trump.
(all laughing)
- It's lads banter, isn't it?
Although, to be fair, to be fair to the boys, boys, boys,
they also exchange drawings of female genitalia as well.
Equal rights for all genitals.
- How do you trace around that?
(all laughing)
- I'll show you how she was jimmed.
- It's more of a potato print, I think.
(all laughing)
- What did it do to the industry
once people were no longer selling their piss?
- Bad news for the piss industry.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Pissful, pissful, exactly.
- Do you know that in France,
they call Pisoise sometimes Vespasians
because Vespasian, the Roman emperor,
taxed urine because they could use it
in the tanning industry and various other things.
- They use it in everything,
they're obsessed with it.
- Yeah, exactly.
And because he became synonymous with taxing urine,
people called the urinals Vespasians,
and it's still in France,
they're called that sometimes today.
- That's quite cool.
- That's like, like, Boris Bikes, is like--
- Bit like that, yeah.
- He's gonna seem to have the name Boris attached.
- If that still is the name in 2,000 years, yeah.
Do you think separate of Vespasian,
is separate of Vespasian happy
that that's his legacy 2,000 years into the future?
- It's quite grumpy anyway, Vespasian, I think.
- It's not gonna cheer him up, is it?
Well, do you know, your name has remained
in the urinals of Paris.
- Didn't he?
Was he the one who built the Colosseum?
- It's kind of annoying.
- He was the one who started
the building of the Colosseum, yeah.
- That is frustrating,
'cause I think that's a real move
towards your legacy there,
to be like, "Ah, this is what we were running for."
And then there's like--
- Everyone's calling toilets after me.
I'm gonna build this massive Colosseum.
This will do it.
- We'll be in the shape of a massive toilet, then.
(laughing)
- That's cool.
- Yeah, pretty sweet.
- And then there's huge efforts in America
for cyberattacking happens so much more than I realized.
And so say like banks.
Banks have whole, basically, war rooms
in bunkers that are dedicated
in order to stop cyberattacks.
- I mean, like closely under attack as well.
- So per day, this is from a few years ago,
per day they would get 267,000 attacks.
So it's an attack every three seconds
where someone's trying to steal money.
Billions of dollars successfully
would get stolen in the past.
And so this was set up to stop that.
In America, at one point,
they hired up to 2,000 new personnel
to deal with cyberattacks within the government.
And this was under FBI director James Comey
when he was in charge there.
And the biggest problem that he faces
is that the people who were best suited
for fixing cybercrime and monitoring it
were all weed smokers.
And so you can't hire someone into the FBI
if they smoke weed.
It's part of the screening process
to not allow them to do it.
There's a rumor that there's a lot of agencies
that hire a lot of Mormons at a sort of,
they say because they're so easy to screen.
I think that's just a rumor that one.
But this was a real thing.
And so Comey had to say,
we've got to let the weed smokers in
because we need them, they're the best in the world.
So they, yeah, relax the law.
So do apply if you smoke weed.
- Really?
- You will get past the first screening.
We might not make it through in the end, you know.
- So now if you want--
- 'Cause you can't remember anything.
(laughing)
- Steal, just very quickly on sort of steal generally.
I didn't appreciate
what an extraordinary recyclable object it is
and how much we do recycle it around the world.
And that's really impressive.
- Like in buildings and stuff, right?
- In buildings, yeah, exactly.
Particularly buildings that mostly recyclable.
If you take down a building, the metal can be reused.
And in fact, one of the things of, you know,
the Twin Towers when it went down,
a lot of that metal was reused.
In various, yeah, if you go to places like,
I don't know, if you go to India,
you're gonna find a college that has been built
using the steel, yeah, you'll find--
- Did they also make a ship?
- The USS New York?
- The USS New York, it's so interesting.
There is this ship out there
where they have in the ship itself,
there's a steel plate which is on display
above the most used passageway
and they have a firefighters helmet there.
So all the sailors are reminded of the first responders.
Every day the chaplain on that ship
will pick a name of someone who died in the terrorist attack
and they will read them as part of their prayers
so that everyone remembers.
But the bow of the ship itself
is using the steel from the building as well.
So it's a real remembrance ship.
- And it's like the big sort of wires
that you get in reinforced concrete, isn't it?
The steel, I think.
- Right. - Is that right?
I'm pretty sure.
- I think the, I don't know if it is interesting,
but the key reason why concrete,
like steel reinforced concrete works as a thing
is because the heat coefficient of steel and concrete
is the same so that when concrete expands in heat,
concrete and steel expands by the same amount
because they're kind of infused together
so they need to grow and shrink at the same rate.
That is the most interesting
and at the same time, the most dull thing.
- It's the most interesting boring thing
I've ever thought about, yeah.
- I think you've got to be careful
tossing the word "coefficient" into it.
It's so interesting, it's so nice of you, it's brilliant.
- This is suddenly the first stamp
where there's a naked woman on a stamp
and in American, this is 1959, they banned it.
A Time Magazine wrote, "An indecent picture is bad enough,
but a postage stamp whose backside must be licked,
millions of innocent children collect stamps."
And so, yeah, and there were certain places
that kind of allowed it in America
'cause obviously so many different states,
it's not one all-consuming thing,
but eventually they did ban it entirely.
- But it didn't have a picture of her bum
on the back that you could lick, did it?
- No.
- It's just a normal stamp.
- It would be so good if stamps had the back
of the person's head on the other side.
- Yeah.
- Why don't they do that?
- And if like Prince, King Prince Charles,
when they do his stamps, if they haven't already,
then he has a sort of haptic device on the back of his head
that whenever anyone licks a stamp, he feels the lick.
(all laughing)
- Very nice, wouldn't it?
- For whom?
- Nice is not, like, it's many things, it's not nice.
(all laughing)
- Can I give you some metallurgy words
and see if you can guess what they are?
- Yes.
- Bottom running.
- That was when people tried to poo on steel to turn in.
(all laughing)
- You've got to try these things.
- Is that wire that gets fed through the oceans
to connect up internet in terms of the bottom?
- No, 'cause they don't run them
through the ground bottom, they drop them,
they lay them, they lay them, that's always laying.
- So what is it?
- Oh, sorry.
All the answers are gonna be really boring.
It's filling a mould cavity from the bottom
by means of gates from another channel
through which molten metal is passed
from one receptacle to another.
- I did know that, actually.
- Does anyone know what the MF temperature is?
- MF temperature. - Oh, come on.
- The motherfucking temperature!
(all laughing)
- It is the temperature at which
martinsite formation finishes, of course.
Martinsite being a very hard form
of steel crystalline structure.
- I hate this show.
(all laughing)
- Do you know what a slag trap is?
- You're looking at him!
(all laughing)
- Sorry.
- It's so horrible.
(all laughing)
- It's an extrusion in the gating or runner system
in a mould for the purpose of preventing
molten slag particles from entering the mould cavity.
I got a lot more of these, but let's move on.
- Are you sure?
- Yeah, 'cause the joke answers are fun,
but then you actually have to keep
in the responses. - Yeah, absolutely.
I found an interesting thing that a loose bit of wire
is responsible for.
Great innovation in the world.
This is 1962, the year after the Goya is stolen
from the museum, and basically there was a factory
that, it used to be that if you put people on hold
on a phone call, it would just be absolute silence, right?
And so this guy had it as factory.
There happened to be when he put it on hold,
there was just a random loose wire
that was touching a steel girder
that turned it into a transmitter.
And basically it was tuning in a local radio station.
And so anytime someone went on hold,
they found themselves listening to music
from this radio station.
And he thought this was gonna be incredibly annoying,
but every time the people who were left waiting for ages
would come back on, they'd say,
"Oh, that was really nice.
"No, it was pleasant.
"I didn't actually notice time passing by."
So this guy, Albert Levy,
who should never have invented this technology,
patented basically hold music as a signal.
- Just because Andy's not here,
and we all know what he would say at this point.
Oh, all these things that claim
to be accidentally invented, definitely one,
it's just made up on this.
- I'm sorry, miss, through some steel
in the pilot invented wire.
- Also, can Andy smoking 80 cigarettes a day now?
- Just wanna compliment the impression there.
- I think he's spot on.
- I've been really honing it.
Yeah, that's actually, for the listeners,
that's what he talks like when he's not on the podcast.
(all laughing)
- I read about Benjamin Franklin's 40 essay.
- Oh yeah.
- So it was in 1781, he wrote an essay,
which is either known as
to the Royal Academy of Farting,
or Fart Proudly, as it's snappier title.
And it was a submission to the Royal Academy of Brussels,
but he never actually sent it,
but it was kind of like his sort of slamming back
at the sort of, he saw it as like sort of impractical questions
that scientists were looking at.
And he's like, well, he might as well look into
how we stop our fart smelling.
But I was reading what he was saying.
And if I as part of this, he,
so he didn't send in, he just gave it to his friends.
But as part of it, he talks about
how you can change the smell if you're a wee.
So if we've done on QI,
the asparagus makes your wee smell kind of weird.
And Franklin says, if you use turpentine,
it makes your wee smell good.
- What, if you drink turpentine?
- Yes, there are problems with this plan.
(all laughing)
- I don't think you're gonna be around to smell it.
- Well, you're not supposed to,
but apparently it does work.
Don't try this at home, and ever.
But it makes it smell with violets.
Apparently it does.
- Does it?
- Well, does turpentine mean what I think they mean?
So I looked up turpentine to check.
And turpentine, Britannica says,
clear a clear oily liquid that's more flammable
and more toxic than white spirits.
- Yeah, that's what I thought.
- But I think they did use to use it medicinally.
'Cause Britannica also says it has a hot,
disagreeable taste,
which just people have been trying.
- I think they did use it medicinally,
but absolutely don't do that.
- No, and I think I much rather have wee
that smells normal than drink turpentine.
- Yeah, just buy some violets.
Put them in the loo every time you go.
- Get air freshener, you're right.
And much less hazardous.
- That's funny, 'cause I was reading about Franklin
for the last fact on clubs,
'cause he founded an intellectual literary society
which sounded brilliant.
And they met every week.
And the idea was about exploring
moral philosophical questions of natural philosophy,
changing policy, improving the world.
And I wonder if this whole,
that it was a bit of an off day at the reading group,
where they came up with the whole,
should we write to someone about fart-stopping farts?
(laughing)
- Say Shonagun.
- She writes a lot about her affairs in the book.
There were a lot of men in her life.
And I was reading this great article
by a guy called David Greer,
who was saying a lot of people then go to it
thinking the pillow book affairs.
This is gonna be like old school erotica.
And you get to it.
And there's really nothing in there that's erotic in any way.
There's very, very subtle lines.
But the men who she has the affairs with
do appear in the book,
but they largely appear in a list
called things that irritate me.
And it's just knocking them about.
They're snoring, they're stumbling around.
You know, like they're just being idiots generally.
- They're leaving in a rush in the morning.
Take note, modern day men.
She's like a man who leaps out of bed
after you've shagged him,
puts on his clothes and runs out the door.
Not cool guys.
- They get turned into a sex manual.
- Did it?
- Yeah.
And picture books and letter writing manuals,
textbooks, stuff like that.
- At the same time or different months.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so this was basically in the thousand years
subsequently because it was such a famous book.
They would kind of adapt it into various different things.
- Like fan fiction kind of thing.
- Kind of, if you need to write a sex manual
and you're like, okay, well, how am I gonna start?
They're like, well, let's start with this really famous thing
and then take bits of that
and then tell people how to have sex.
- I definitely read something which I wouldn't say
if it had been written in the modern day
'cause it's so gross, but it was written in 1714.
So it feels less gross,
but which takes Seanagan, the character of Seanagan
and is like a fan fiction and puts her in a story
where she's being had sex with from behind
while her brother looks on masturbating.
- Oh, okay.
- Yeah, that's fine.
- It's quite Game of Thrones-y, isn't it?
- Yeah, maybe that's what Game of Thrones is based on.
Does that happen in Game of Thrones?
- There's incest and there's shagging and all that stuff.
- Lots of sex, yeah.
- Is there incest in Game of Thrones?
- Yeah, I think that's one of the main bits.
(laughing)
- I gotta watch it one of these days.
- Yeah, it's kind of episode one, series one,
I think, all those.
(laughing)
- Free titles.
- Just very quickly on the fact
that the book loops in on itself.
I just went down a bit of a loop on that,
just finding other versions of it.
And so one famous version of it
is the Pink Floyd album, The Wall,
which ends on the same wording that the album begins on.
So in theory, you can just play it in one continuous loop.
But the one that seems most exciting to me,
which hasn't happened, but Al Jean,
who is an executive producer and writer for The Simpsons,
he has said that if he has it his way,
that's how The Simpsons will end.
The final scene will loop back
into the very opening scene of The Simpsons
to show that no time has passed.
- That's very cool, but they looked very different
in the first series.
- Exactly, and the voices were very different and so on.
- They go through like a magic mirror and then be like.
- I think there'll be a Doctor Who regeneration episode
weren't there, where it's a really painful
agonizing process and they just turn into these slightly
tweaks, weird versions of themselves.
- I suppose like the first episode will have begun
with him jumping out of the school,
like every episode begins, would it?
Or do you reckon they'll go back to that?
Or do you think they'll go back to?
- Oh, there's a pre-title incest scene.
That is...
(laughing)
- Do you think we should do the final episode of Fish
should be President Garfield's anus or whatever?
No, it was the sun, the get.
- I actually think it should end with you saying to me,
you know there's no such thing as a fish,
what do you mean there's no such thing as a fish?
- Oh, that's a good idea.
- Yeah, that's the loop, 'cause that's the initial.
- Although we could do that, 'cause our first fact was
that someone dropped a baguette in CERN.
And CERN obviously there was a theory
that time travelers would come there.
So we could finish with me saying,
"Oh, Dan, I'm just going off to visit CERN.
"Just bought a nice baguette."
(laughing)
- That's great, what did I do?
- I don't know, guys.
President Garfield ate stuff through his arse.
I think we're disappearing up our own arse.
(laughing)
Let's get out.
- Here's someone who died.
Justin Schmidt.
- Who's that?
- No.
- You might know him by his nickname.
The King of Sting.
- No.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- Is he from the Schmidt Pain Index?
- Yes. - No.
- He's the guy he came up with.
- The bees.
- A thing we spoke about.
I think in the first few episodes of this podcast,
he's an amazing guy.
He was stung over his life by 150 different insects.
He filled his home with them
so that he could feel what it was like
to be stung by each of them.
And then he wrote down how painful it was.
- Yeah.
- And he came up with this incredible,
these beautiful writings.
So a bee, a normal bee is two.
It's called two.
I think it goes up to four.
A bee, quite boring.
A burning match head lands on your skin.
Yeah.
(laughing)
Who cares?
A club-horned wasp, 0.5.
Rather disappointing.
(laughing)
But he collected a lot of quite exotic
and really dangerous insects.
And it's like, okay, here's one.
The warrior wasp.
This scores four.
Torture.
You are chained in the flow of an active volcano.
Why did I start this list?
(laughing)
- And that was four on the pain index?
- No, I think four is the maximum.
I'm not sure why, but like that was really high.
- Yeah, okay, right.
- And he died this year.
- He died this year.
- Such a shame.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- I believe he swallowed a fly, didn't he?
- I've actually just realized,
I thought I'd written down a fact about Berlusconi,
but it was just that he was five foot five,
and it was my way of segwaying into a fact
I thought was very interesting and tangentially related,
which is that this year is the year that we, height-wise,
as humans, caught up with ourselves as hunter-gatherers.
So, the average height of humans
has been gradually going up for a couple of hundred years.
And it, this year, was clarified as five foot 10 for men.
- So, can I just say, after hunter-gatherers,
we shrunk and we're going back up again?
- Yes, indeed.
And we've just reached hunter-gatherer height again.
'Cause what hunter-gatherers, very tall, very healthy,
ate a nice range of berries and bears or whatever.
And then, we (laughing)
started to know, depending where you lived.
And then, we started farming,
and our diets got quite a lot worse,
'cause it was like all monocultures.
- Just eating grain.
- And just eating grain,
exactly, and all hunched over with the labour.
And we started working much harder.
And so, we shrunk.
And I think 4,000 years ago,
the average height was five foot four.
So, Berlusconi, five foot five.
He would have fitted right here.
He would have been tall 4,000 years ago.
But he wasn't today.
And anyway, now we've made it up back to hunter-gatherer height.
- That's nice.
- Isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Can finally reach those high berries.
(laughing)
- Can I just, my favorite promotional story,
Christmas-based, a very specific category,
is, you know, the American dino chain Denny's,
which advertises as always open in America.
So, it's been going around since the 1950s.
So, and it is open 24/7, 365 days a year,
366 in a leap year, always open.
And then, in 1988,
Denny's decided to give its staff Christmas Day off.
And so, they were gonna close for Christmas Day.
The problem with this was that they had never closed before.
So, none of the doors shut.
(laughing)
They suddenly found themselves calling locksmiths.
They had to have 700 Denny's chains,
have locksmiths visit to replace the doors and the locks.
- Whoa, whoa.
(upbeat music)
[MUSIC PLAYING]