Let's go and have a look at the hotel.
Hello, welcome back to Drop As A Line, the Drop As A Line segment of Clubfish where we
talk about the things that you have been sending to us.
So first of all guys, we've had lots more feedback on the name Drop As A Line.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
All good.
Mixed.
Ginger Hilderman says, "I like Drop As A Line as a name, so thank you Ginger."
And all the rest will be negative.
A lot of people coming up with their own suggestions.
Great.
Charlie Tuff.
No, that's a terrible name.
I like it, I like it.
Charlie Tuff suggests Piscine Post.
Okay.
Oh dear.
That's not good.
It looks a bit like Piscine Post.
Yeah.
Just about swimming pools.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
It's a bit confusing.
Jill and Cliff have written, "Given that this is Andy's baby, shouldn't it be Club Moss?"
Because Club Moss is kind of good.
Yeah, that's quite good.
Yeah, that is good.
But it did take two people to think of it.
I don't know who did the heavy lifting Jill or Cliff.
So anyway, I wrote back to them and said, "Thank you for that suggestion."
And they wrote back again, "Could also have Club Foot for Daddy."
Stop encouraging them, Andy.
So, wait, how does that make sense to me?
What, Big Foot?
They could be using Club Foot and Big Foot, they do, please.
Well, no, they say in brackets, "As in Big Foot."
So, Club Foot.
Oh, okay.
I mean, because there is a medical condition called the 12 Foot, which is...
Well, I think that's what they're referring to.
I think that might be...
Okay.
Well, I would argue that's misleading.
There's a single by Cossabian called Club Foot.
Maybe they were thinking you had to call 2000, I suppose it was a great song as well.
It is.
Yeah.
And they come up, "Don't you worry, you guys are great."
And Canadian Club for Anna.
Oh, yeah.
I don't know why.
Type of whiskey.
It's a kind of whiskey, you like it.
I've got James's.
I've sorted it.
Oh, that's good.
That's good, because Jill and Cliff say, "Can't think of one for James."
What?
I mean, how much do I talk about golf on this podcast?
You're kidding.
Are you kidding?
They don't say golf club?
In general, you say, "Can't think of one for James."
Oh, my God.
Sorry, Jill and Cliff.
You've undone all your good work.
Got Club Foot?
But you're kidding me.
Yeah.
I think Club Moss, Club Foot, Canadian Club, and Golf Club.
Jill and Cliff have done most of the work there.
So thank you, guys.
Yeah, lovely work.
Thank you.
The King and Queen of Clubs.
Very nice.
We've had an email from New Zealand on the name.
That's the entire country.
Wow.
Just in the order.
Just in the club.
No, it's from Hayden Freeman.
So thank you, Hayden.
From Hamilton in New Zealand.
I don't know where Hamilton is.
Your new mailbag show.
Oh, yeah.
Thank you.
Should be called "Hook Us Up."
Okay.
"Hook Us Up" with facts, and "Hook Us Up" as fish.
As fish get hooked up.
Sorry, what's the title?
"Hook Us Up."
And that extra bit was just explaining the two versions of what it could be.
Very nice.
The subtitle, maybe.
I could put in quite a mark if you like.
The quiz you did a few weeks ago, James.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
What did we call it at the end?
No, she thinks it's a quiz.
Very nice.
Oh, no.
There's a bit of debate on what we call that, actually.
Someone written in a suggestion.
Well, I lobbied very, yes, they have.
I lobbied very strongly for the Haar quiz, James Haar quiz.
Oh, yeah, that was good.
Yeah, well.
So, you could call James's quiz, "Harkinon."
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
The quiz that tells the story.
That's actually not bad.
That's a genuine suggestion.
It's not bad.
I'm up for it.
You made it worse by the weird "Harkinon" instead of just saying "Harkinon."
Well, isn't the word "harping" on?
He was harping on about that.
Yeah.
Well, there's also...
"Harkins" is his name.
So, that's what he's done.
It'd be weird to call it "Harkinon."
Yeah.
There's a Finnish motor racing driver called Mika Harkinon.
Oh, yeah.
Mika Harkinon.
Put on his name.
Yeah.
Join his song, "Harkinon."
It's Mika Harkinon.
Yeah.
It's a big one.
Okay.
Well, work in progress.
Work in progress, yeah, yeah.
Cool.
What about with "Hark" quiz, if it was an exclamation mark in the middle?
So, it's like "Hark" quiz, like in the Bible.
Well, I think for Christmas, we'll have to do that.
The James Hark quiz.
Yes.
But "Hark" doesn't have to be only Christmas.
"Hark" means the same thing all year round.
It's just less often heard outside of a Christmas class.
It's less often or literally never heard outside the line, "Hark, how an angel sings."
How do you "Hark" at this point?
Oh, my God.
Because I want to say something.
Anna used to work as a town crier, didn't she?
"Oh, really?"
We have an email from Ian Fox, which is good, because Ian Fox is also one of the very rare
people who's posted something physical to the office.
Oh.
Okay.
So Ian sent a fact about Roger Bannister, but that's not the main element, so I'm actually
going to skip past that.
Well, at least you haven't mentioned it.
Left everyone hanging, haunting wall.
It's a related fact.
It's not actually about Roger.
Anyway, look, the point is, Ian Fox then goes on, "Thanks for all the podcasts.
By the way, it took so many years for me to send you my unused penis good, because COVID
meant it took me so long to get back to my parents' house."
And Anna, can you just reach over and grab the thing that's over here?
Can I ask, he says it's an unused penis guard, but actually it's been left unattended in
his parents' house for a number of years.
That's a good point.
During COVID as well.
Who in lockdown has not given that a bash?
What we've got here is something rolled up inside it, and it's a correspondence piece
from him.
Wow.
It's like a Jenga correspondence from Ian.
So a penis guard is a thing that in Papua New Guinea, for instance, they would make out
of a vegetable.
It's shaped a bit like a long carrot that's been bent into the letter J, and you would
tie it around your waist and put your penis in there as an isomer clothing.
Exactly.
J for Johnson.
Johnson pocket.
Yeah.
And so his letter says, "Hi guys, a while ago, I looked this up, it was about four years
ago, you talked about penis goods, and he's just made his first trip home to his parents'
place in New Zealand, weirdly, he said, "I thought you could have my penis good since I am not
using it.
I'm sure you can mount it on the wall and use it as a flower vase or pen holder or something
like that."
You can mount it wherever you like, can't you?
Hello.
That's the sound of Dan opening his mouth dangerously in there at the tip of the penis
good.
It's inside.
I did try it on, Dan.
Did you?
Overclothes.
I would argue that's not properly trying it on.
Okay.
Good point.
That's how superheroes wear penis goods, though, isn't it?
On the outside.
Super Vanuatu, man.
Yeah.
That's where it's from.
Anyway, so I think we put up a picture of ages ago, we should put up another one, but
it's really, really nice.
Thank you.
It's really nice to have evidence of the thing.
Do you want a fact that someone sent in?
Yes, please.
So people sent in amazing facts and we sometimes mention them on the show and it's great, but
actually they sent in so many.
I've now got this huge pile of facts I don't know what to do with.
Here's a fact from a guy called James Milne.
All right?
He's one lesser away from an England footballer.
Yeah.
Which one?
James Milne.
Oh, cool.
Harry Kane.
And I know it, James Milne.
This is just to add into that, as a friend.
Can we hear the fact?
No, no.
Let's build on this friendship of yours.
Right.
James says the most popular wine in the UK is Strongbow Darkfruits.
Okay.
Right.
So that to me sounds like a cider.
Exactly.
Okay.
I think he's a brewer.
He wrote to us because he knows this fact through his work.
Okay.
There's a little explanation, but basically, like you say, Darkfruits is counted in the
cider category by most people because it's a cider.
Because that's what it is.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
So there was a report recently about the best selling alcohol brands of 2021, and Darkfruits
was listed.
Yeah.
It sold 158,000 HL, which is hectolilitres, right, that's 100 litres, so that's a huge
amount.
Okay.
The best selling wine sold 90,009 litre packs, so Darkfruits outsold the top wine almost
by a factor of 20.
And importantly, though, rather than the figures, what we actually are interested in is a justification
for wine.
I'm getting to it.
I'm sorry, but I'm sorry for building the fact in an exciting way.
If you ever go to the strongwell, go to the strongwell factory, they have huge vats full
of dark fruits where everyone stabs on them, don't they?
The UK government definition of a cider, basically, is something slightly technical, but...
Got apples in it, I guess.
Yeah.
It's a liquid that's the colour and flavour of apple or pear.
Okay.
Oh, that's it.
Okay, so that's why...
Right.
So Darkfruits cider falls under the made wine category according to HMRC and is taxed as
made wine, and that is why fruited ciders, like strongbow darkfruits, cost more normally
than apples, just like classic cider.
So strongbow darkfruits is the most popular wine in the UK, because it is technically
a wine.
Legally, it's wine.
So it wasn't that technical, the definition of cider is it's pear or apple fruit.
Guys, bear with me here, I don't have your grasp on this.
We've got to string out the show some more.
I panicked.
It was a slightly longer email.
I couldn't immediately see the explanation, so I said, "That's very technical."
Interesting.
Anyway.
Wow, that's incredible.
James knows this through his work.
It's a bold restaurant, isn't it, that puts it on the wine list.
But when you're scanning, looking for the cheapest wine, it probably is a lot cheaper
than all wine, actually.
So you'd be like, "Yeah, I think that's lovely, bottle of your house, strongbow darkfruits."
If it was served in a wine glass, and you'd already shared a couple of bottles, it's quite
possible no one would notice.
That is true.
What percentage is a cider versus wine?
Is it much lower?
Much lower.
Yeah.
So that's quite nice, you know.
What sort of ease you off after you've done it?
Well, for you say, when the officer says how many glasses of wine you had, you say 12.
He's saying it was cider, but I'm actually, I'm actually...
It's only eight.
So please take that penis cord off in there.
Sorry officer, what?
Could you blow into this, please?
No, not that.
So thank you, James.
That's an amazing...
I just think that's such a cool fact.
It's a very cool fact.
It's a sort of niche, clever...
Yeah, lovely.
Really, lovely.
Thank you.
We've had a complaint from Jam Rain Bird.
Sorry.
That's just three words put together.
Oh, Jam Rain Bird.
What a lot of them.
Jam.
Yeah, jam.
Could be sure for James.
Really cool.
Wait, Jam, sorry.
I thought you said jam.
No, it's jam.
Ian with a J.
Jam Rain Bird.
Are you sure that's not an address?
You know what three words you have addresses when you have three words together.
Jam Rain Bird.
Anyway, jam starts very strong.
I'm so disappointed in all of you.
No.
Especially, Dad.
Unfortunately, no, it's a universal pasting from Jam.
The chocolate is clearly on the bottom of a hobnob.
Oh, yeah.
You just had a hobnob.
I actually just had three.
Yeah.
And I thought we'd already said the chocolate is on the bottom.
We said it was on the bottom.
Yeah.
I think I maybe...
Oh, you argued against it.
I argued that it's on the top.
Right.
Well, does jam justify this?
Well...
Stick to the Dodgers, love.
Oh, my God.
In response to Andy, they obviously wouldn't show the non-chocolate side on the packet
because then they'd be hiding a rather key feature of the product.
Yeah.
When you said this was a pasting for all of us.
Well, I think we all play a role in letting the show go out as it was.
Oh, I see.
Editorially.
Yeah.
Okay.
We're responsible.
No, I don't know why I said that.
It's clearly a bollocking for me.
Because James says, actually, Jam is then speaking up in favour of what you've said.
James is probably out of this telling off.
It's exactly dual with the chocolate digestive where the chocolate is clearly on the bottom.
Point two, the bottom of a plain hobnob is clearly a sort of plain hobnob.
Don't get the penis...
I don't know.
Plain hobnob, anyone?
The bottom of a plain hobnob is clearly distinct from the top.
Three packets of chocolate hobnob have a top, clearly indicated by the red tear line.
When you remove hobnob from the packet the chocolate side is facing down, why would
they put them in the packet?
So vindication for me from Jam, definitely not James, and Rainbird, definitely not just
two random things I saw in the sky and decided to name myself.
Jam Rainbird is a cool name.
It is.
Very cool.
I don't seem to have really good names.
Yeah.
That's the hidden thing here.
Every name you said has been absolutely next level.
Joel Farthing has got in touch.
Beautiful.
From the 18th century.
From Arkansas.
Oh, yeah.
Cool.
Joel.
Fayetteville, Arkansas.
I'm afraid this is a 200 episode old telling off for him.
For James, I'm afraid.
Oh, come off it.
Okay.
Coincidentally.
For a jam over here.
Go on.
I was just listening to episode number 231, during which the panel discussed reginal names
and numbers.
Oh, yeah.
I thought you'd be interested to recall that James predicted in no uncertain terms
that Charles would not take the name Charles III and would instead take the next Edward
Reginald number.
I don't remember that.
I do remember that.
Well, I've been saying that for a while.
In fact, I was saying it to my sister on WhatsApp, literally as the decision was being
made.
Because she said something on, oh, yeah, Charles III, and I was like, oh, don't be stupid.
He's not going to be called Charles III.
Do you know nothing about English history?
What was the reason that?
Well, the other Charleses have had a bit of a rough time.
And so it's like, it's not a cursed name, but it's like, you know, it was, it was thought
that he would go with a name with a 50% of them have been decapitated.
But the other 50%, he wasn't that bad, was he?
The second.
Yeah.
He just sort of like had a vaguely nondescript reign and then he was very, he was very sexist.
Very hot for the time.
Are you counselling Charles II?
I think I, I just read a novel where he's a minor character and like, he's such a disgusting
pervert.
Really?
That is a novel, of course.
Yeah.
No, but it's very well-reserved.
It was Robert Harris.
So it was very well-researched.
Oh.
Good evening.
Supposedly his standard greeting for any woman he didn't know was just to thrust his hand
between her legs.
What were about Harris?
Charles II.
Oh, dear.
So, um, so yeah, that's why he's not, that's why we thought perhaps he wouldn't be called.
What do you think?
You thought it was George?
No, we thought possibly Edward or George, something like that.
But yeah.
Well, I was wrong, but you know, you're going to be when you make so many amazing predictions
like I do.
I went to Nostradamus' house recently.
Did you?
What?
Amazing predictions.
You're kidding.
He was expecting you, wasn't he?
I didn't, I put my hand out to knock.
I put a cup of tea in my hand, closed the door again.
Yeah.
How was it?
It's in the south of France and it's in a village called Saint-Rémy-de-Provence.
That's right.
I just wrote about him in my book and we don't have time for that.
Yeah.
And it's out today.
What's it called?
That's the theory of everything else.
It's presumably only available in a few bookshops or that actually is it's in all online.
Every single book.
That's what I've been told.
If I find a second hand bookshop in the Amazon, only sells you go to Amazon to buy a book.
This is how Amazon goes to Amazon to play a book.
I wonder if that was subconscious.
That was weird.
Yeah.
But there can't be an audiobook.
There absolutely is an audiobook out November 11th.
Anymore Andy or?
There's one more.
This is a...
I can't tell of it.
It's just a bit of an update.
So we did a thing about Saint Hubert or Saint Hubert.
Saint Hubert being...
Yes.
Hubert is...
The patron saint of rotisserie chicken.
That was my fact.
Yeah.
He was basically to do with the Yagermeister, wasn't he?
That's right.
Right.
So his cross is on the Yagermeister bottles and so that's how we got into it.
And Wikipedia says he's a patron saint of rotisseries.
It wasn't of chicken roasts and yes, go on, have we got evidence?
Well, so no, so this is from Alexandre Mackenzie Foucher.
Winner.
The winner.
I mean...
Ba, ba, ba.
We have a winner.
I like the penis good of victory, that's very funny.
That's great.
Okay.
So Alexandre is from Montreal and says, "I found it odd when you mentioned this because
Saint Hubert, Saint Hubert is a massive and beloved restaurant chain in the province of
Quebec, Canada known for its rotisserie chicken and it's not named after the patron saint.
The founder's name is not even Saint Hubert or Hubert.
So the rotisserie got its name because the first restaurant was on Saint Hubert Street.
So it sounds like a joke from someone in Quebec who's put it onto Wikipedia.
Absolutely.
Alexandre says, "I looked up if it was a coincidence that the street which gave its name to a famous
rotisserie chicken happened to be the saint of rotisserie chicken.
The only reference linking the patron saint to chicken I could find in a brief search.
Basically, Alexandre says, "I was wondering if someone would put this as a joke on Wikipedia."
Sounds like it.
Good joke.
Good.
Very niche.
It is.
How long is it going to take for me to be exposed?
For Dan Shriver to finally get there.
Anyway, so that's that.
That's that for this episode of Drop As Alive.
Thank you very much for all your facts, for your amazing names, for your name suggestions.
Please keep all of them coming and we'll see you next time.
Bye.
You're going to have the catchphrase at the end.
Oh my catchphrase.
[music]
(upbeat music)