[MUSIC]
Hi everyone and welcome to this week's Little Fish.
This is the show where you send us some unbelievable facts.
We say whether we believe them or not.
And then we say whether you should believe them or not because we've done some extra research on them.
And then at the end we will do some extra other stuff.
But in the meantime I am joined by Andrew Hunter Murray,
Dan Schreiber, my name is James Harkin,
and who is going to give us the first fact?
All right, this is a fact from Simoneeda Popov.
So thank you Simoneeda for writing in.
Terrific fact is that there is an area in Los Angeles,
which is known as Silver Lake, right?
And it's named after the Silver Lake Reservoir nearby.
And it is named not after the Silver cover of its water,
but after Herman Silver.
[MUSIC]
The LA Water Commissioner at the time the reservoir was built.
That's quite early to get into the things that are named after people.
But you think that it's going to be things that their names are similar to, they're not.
I thought the element of surprise is so important.
The longer I leave it in the episode, the more likely you guys would think,
"I end, he's going to do his blooming book I did now."
But how much of a surprise is it to Little Fish listeners?
Because we talk about it a lot on drop us a line.
I know we do it a lot in Little Fish as well.
Yeah, we do.
We do it in real life as well, Lister.
But the terrible thing is, in the inbox of drop us a line, they're flooding in.
Right.
I'm now being bounced into doing this book by the sheer number.
Well, it sounds like it's more normal than we realize.
So actually, what I might write is the book of things that are named,
not for people who were named after the thing that it sounds like it's named after.
Yeah, yeah, that's a good sequel book.
Yeah.
Well, it's a competitor at the Tills.
Very nice, any more on the lake, or just...
No, it's just called Silver Lake.
Very good, yeah.
Do lakes look silver?
I don't feel like I've seen a silver lake.
Damn.
Yeah, well, give me an example.
Where's Moonlight?
The water is silver, isn't it?
Okay.
Yeah.
I think silver is definitely a word that's often used to describe water.
Okay, I'm just thinking daytime.
That's night time.
It'll be blue, blue to brown.
Blue to brown lake.
It doesn't add quite the romantic, isn't it?
Actually, it's named after Steven Blue and Arthur Brown.
Yeah.
Should I read one here?
Yes.
Okay, this is from Jonas Mortensen of Denmark, who says,
"Long time listener and fellow Factorficianado.
"During a Saturday, low-energy TV watching with my kids,
"watching some random nature documentary,
"I discovered that the hippopotamus has the same body fat percentage
"at Usain Bolt at his absolute peak."
So, basically, sub-ten percent,
less than 10 percent fat.
The hippopotamus is less than 10 percent fat.
They're all muscle, honey.
They're all muscle.
They're incredibly muscle.
You say, "Bolt, I read was about 8 percent body fat."
He probably went a bit lower than that, but that's low.
That's low.
Sorry, I'm not sure.
It's not like you.
No, it wouldn't be high, wouldn't it?
The amazing thing was he did it.
And, you know, yeah.
Well, I suppose they're about 2 to 5 percent fat.
Get out.
That's the data online.
It's interesting.
That's true of quite a lot of animals,
so way less fatty than you think they're going to be.
That's really interesting.
So, they're all muscle.
They're all muscle.
Now, here's the question.
We often get told hippos are faster than you realize,
because they charge at people.
A lot of deaths are a result of hippos.
In 100 meter race, who would win?
A hippo, or Usain Bolt?
For me, a hippo, 100 percent.
Okay.
Is it from a dead start?
Was it when they stopped before?
Because, like I mentioned,
Usain Bolt taking off very fast and winning.
He was actually surprisingly slow starter.
Usain Bolt.
Like he was famous, his start was,
if his start was as fast as some other 100 meter runners,
he would be even faster.
That was really funny.
Sorry, you say he was slow.
He was slow.
He was actually really slow.
He was, honestly,
he was always faster finisher than a starter.
That's very interesting.
How do you do?
I stopped watching after the first two seconds.
So, he's eating.
Yeah.
Oh, that's really...
I mean, it's all comparative, right?
He's better than us.
His slow start is probably quicker than my quick start.
Oh, absolutely.
Yeah.
Yeah, he's better than us.
Arguably, he's better than any human ever.
Not at the start.
Yeah.
That's true.
Okay, so I'm saying, you say Bolt will win over a hippo.
I'm sorry.
You're saying you're saying Bolt will win.
Okay, yeah.
The answer is that you say Bolt
his fastest reached 44.7 kilometers an hour.
And a hippo gets to about 30.
So, actually, you say Bolt
in that 100-meter sprint would win.
But put it over 800 meters.
Maybe we've got ourselves able to go.
Oh, yeah, I mean, who knows?
We've never tested it.
I know Michael Phelps once swam against a shark, apparently.
But a CGI shark.
There's a CGI shark.
We need a CGI hippo against a CGI at his peak.
You say Bolt.
Yeah, okay.
What's interesting is if these speeds
are what they would be running at,
you say Bolt would pass the finishing line
two seconds before a hippo.
And the fact that you did James on the show ages ago
is roughly two seconds is the amount of time
that you say Bolt's feet are touching the ground
over a 100-meter sprint.
Okay.
Not sure quite what that says about the world.
No, I don't know how much.
Oh, but when you sit back and think about it,
well, yeah, that's true.
You say Bolt's fastest speeds
would occur in the 200 meters.
Well, they?
Yeah.
Because he's already going so quickly after the first attempt.
Yeah, yeah, because it gives him a chance to get up to speed.
Because he's so slow off the blocks.
He hangs about, doesn't he?
Anyone who watches athletics,
well, we go, James, you're absolutely right.
He's famously a slow star.
But was it, do we hear the gun go
and then we hear his coach going?
You're sane!
It's got what?
Here is a fact.
This is also about human beings.
And yours was about like fat content and stuff like that.
This is more about height.
And it's from Oscar Matalainen.
And Oscar says, after extensive research,
I have figured out that Eminem
is exactly 138.4 Eminem's tall.
Okay.
That's lovely.
Now, I've done some research of my own.
And I looked on the internet about how tall Eminem is
and how big an Eminem is.
And I don't think Oscar's figures exactly stack up.
Impostive.
But stack up.
Very funny pun.
Thank you.
I'm here all week.
But the truth is that actually the figures that you get online
of like how big an Eminem is,
they vary quite a lot.
Like on Amazon, it says one thing.
If like on newspapers, they say other things and stuff
whenever it's mentioned, which is not often.
On Amazon, because I often, they'll give the dimensions
of like a book that you're buying.
You get individual Eminem dimensions.
I promise you, it does.
It's reading the visual.
It's reading that info before purchasing.
You don't want to order a bag of Eminem,
so that they're all 10 feet across.
We've all done that exactly.
So what I have done is I brought us some Eminem's.
Oh nice.
So we have a little bit of Foley there.
Dan, I've got you some peanut ones.
Andy, I've got you some regular.
Thank you.
And we're going to measure them.
Can I open them?
Yeah, but it's going to be hard to measure them
if you don't open them.
Can I eat one or is it?
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so if you give me one of the peanut ones,
we're looking at diameter, I suppose.
I suppose you were stacking them top to bottom,
like putting them down flat.
Okay, well, we can do it that way as well.
But the one that you've got there is quite spherical.
I don't know if you want to measure it.
So I'm passing Andy a ruler.
It's just over a centimede.
If I'm doing it longest, the longest dimension,
it's about 1.3.
Okay, well, you've got the regular one, Sandy,
so let's go for that.
Okay.
1.3 centimetres.
Yeah.
Okay, so according to the internet,
now this is another problem we have.
The internet is also unsure about how tall I'm in it.
Oh, boy.
But the general consensus is that he's five for eight.
Okay.
He mentions in some of his rap lyrics that he's shorter than that,
but it's not always clear in the lyrics
if he's talking about himself or something else.
Of course.
It's a problem with like going to first hand sauces sometimes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
History, you don't know exactly what they're talking about.
So let's say he's 173 centimetres tall,
which is what the internet thinks.
And do you think that your Eminem is what size?
1.3.
1.3 centimetres.
Then he is 133.
0.07692.
What were we trying to get at?
What was our correspondent say?
He was quite close, actually, 138.
Oh.
But we found that the peanut ones are a little bit bigger than that still.
If I'm stacking mine flat,
this one was about, I'd say,
1.1.
Right, it's about 1.1.
Eminem will shrink as he gets older.
So we could eventually meet the amount we've just had.
So going the stacking method, the AHMSM,
the Andrew Hunter Murray stacking method,
would be 157 Eminem.
Oh, okay, okay, okay.
So it's worse still.
So yeah, Oscar, your extensive research,
I don't know if it was the same as ours as in actually getting the Eminem's,
but until we get the rapper in the room as well,
we can't do a full experiment.
He's on next week, isn't he?
Yeah, he is.
He is, yeah.
And he was very funny in the recording.
Very funny.
If I can't get a full 45 minutes without any swear words,
then we might have a comment.
Oh, okay, that's a shame.
That's a shame.
Okay.
Here's a fact.
From Stuart Dunster, who says,
"In 2024, the British Army was so busy
that 137% of its personnel were committed to operations or exercise."
What does that mean?
This is amazing.
Basically, you can do, if you're in the Army,
you can do a task like readiness training in parallel
with other exercises or commitments or whatever.
So it's over time, basically, right?
Kind of.
You need to be prepared to drop everything if you're called on to deploy,
but also carry on with the current exercise you're doing.
And it causes lots of work and paperwork.
And it's a huge pain.
Basically, it's a fun way of saying the Army is under-resourced,
which is not fun fact.
But there we go.
So when we say that there was, like, let's say,
let's say the Grand old Duke of York had 10,000 men,
it might have only been 8,000,
but some of them are doing two jobs.
He'll only have been able to deploy 2,000 of those men.
100%.
Yeah.
Many of those will be in logistics and supply and all of that stuff here.
Fun fact, who was this fact from?
You just said...
Just do it.
Tunster?
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Brother of?
Oh, Phil.
Really?
Yes.
Very cool.
Yeah.
Well, hi, Stu.
One drift we'll get one from Eminem's brother.
I've got another one here, which is from Julia Fisher.
The subject line of which is,
"Every word of this fact is dubious at best."
Oh, great.
Why did you send this once to Dan Andy?
So I can't remember.
So this is the fact.
The oldest living dog is invisible and 11,000 years old.
Yes.
Now, this is genuinely fascinating.
So this is the email from Julia.
Basically, there is a kind of tumor
that dogs can infect other dogs with already unusual.
This has been discovered to be a tumor which developed on a dog
which was alive 11,000 years ago.
That tumor then jumped from that original dog to a different dog,
but it was still made up of the cells of the original dog.
Those cells have been continuously alive in the bodies
of different dogs ever since.
It's only invisible to the naked eye because it's tiny cells,
not magic or nothing.
I, she wrote nothing, I just said nothing.
I have absolutely zero qualifications in any biology,
so please don't listen to me.
However, I think this is correct.
Just stunning.
So this is called the canine transmissible venereal tumor.
And this is a tumor that is exchanged during mating with dogs,
so it's a genital-based...
Between dogs.
Yeah.
Just used that mating with dogs.
It's just...
It's a very minor difference,
but it just felt a little worth pointing out.
Well, we know we're your red lines, I don't know.
That's an important detail.
That's right.
Dog on dog.
Yeah.
Now, what's interesting is this is one of only three known
transmissible cancers.
I know one.
Yep.
Tasmanian devils.
Yes.
The devil-facial tumor disease.
Yeah.
And then there's the one...
Between Tasmanian devils again.
Got I'm such, yeah.
And then there's the Syrian hamster,
which is the other one that gets it, yeah.
Yeah, so they're infectious agents,
and the tumors that form are not genetically related
to the host dog.
So it is.
It's the original disease cells from this dog 11,000 years ago.
Yeah, now, the thing is, is the question is,
was the dog 11,000 years old?
There's a lot of debate going on.
I think it might be 6,000, then they thought 11,000.
Okay.
And now they're saying maybe between 200 and 2500.
It doesn't matter.
It's a long time ago, and it's the same cells from this one dog.
Yeah.
We've got to remake the dog, haven't we?
We've got to extract some of the cells.
Do a Richard Attenborough on it.
Oh, yeah.
Get that dog.
Jurassic Park it.
Oh, yeah.
Jurassic Park.
Give that man a raise.
That's cute.
Okay.
That's pretty good.
That was a rare example of a joke being so good
that the two people in the room were shocked more than amused.
Instead, in my head, I was just going,
"Oh, God, I can't cap that."
Yeah.
Might as well just retire.
Okay.
We're calling jokes cute.
I think I'm done slightly.
I called it cute because I was angry and insulted.
I just couldn't come up with anything as good,
so I thought I'll try and bring those down.
But it was really good.
I'll see you coming through, right.
I don't think they're the same cells.
Oh, interesting.
Okay.
I mean, they're not, are they?
They're cells that have developed from those cells
as in the original ones are long gone.
Yep.
But they've replicated.
Yes.
I suppose the main thing being it's not genetically connected to that dog,
so I guess that's the cheat.
But yeah, brilliant Julia.
Amazing.
Thank you.
Jurassic World.
We've done it, buddy.
Dog minion.
What?
There was one called minion.
Yeah.
What's that?
Let's come back to it.
Um, let's do another fact.
And this one comes from Stav Burman.
And Stav says space coffee fact.
Coffee on the ISS is made with a machine called the ISS
Spresso.
Lovely.
It is drunk out of a specially designed 0G espresso cup.
Hmm.
Now hang on.
I would assume that a 0G cup is just a cup with a lid.
Am I wrong?
Yes.
Because any cup with athlete is not a 0G cup.
Right.
Okay.
So you've got a cup with a lid.
Yep.
Have you got a little hole that you can get the coffee out?
You have to.
So when you turn it upside down to pour it,
what happens to the liquid?
Good point.
How's it coming out?
Well, you have to suck it out.
Yes.
So you're sucking hot coffee?
You're going to burn your mouth.
Yeah, true.
So this was a problem that was suffered
by astronauts Samantha Kristofferetti,
who was an Italian astronaut who went up to the ISS
in April 2015.
And they came up with this 0G espresso cup
and it uses capillary channel flow.
Oh.
So that is capillary action is that liquid will go
into a tiny tube.
It will move up a tiny tube against the flow of gravity
or in fact if there's no gravity, it gets nothing.
But it will flow inside a tiny tube.
And that's because it kind of sticks to the edges
of the tube a little bit.
And also it sticks to itself.
So once it starts going up,
it starts pulling more liquid out.
Okay.
And this is a well-known sort of physics reaction
of the thing that happens.
And they utilized it to make this coffee cup.
It's a shame it's a coffee cup.
Because if they did tea,
they could just call it gravity.
No, it's not as good as those.
No.
No, nothing's as good as Jurassic Park.
Your career's peaked.
That's it for now on.
Let's go grab a tea.
I loved it.
I liked it.
I thought it was cute.
It was a good joke.
But like it's a curve.
Your career is a curve, isn't it?
Yeah.
You've just reached the very top of it.
So obviously the next show is going to be really, really good.
And which it's not quite as good as that, which it was.
Which it was.
It was still great.
So listen, just listen,
into all of those jokes for future.
Listen to them get slowly and slowly worse than that.
Yeah. So what I should do is just stop talking, right?
And just to allow for your conclusion.
That's not what we are saying.
Yeah, okay.
But if you come to that conclusion,
then we're not going to stop you.
Yeah, okay.
That's a great fact.
Yeah.
Thanks, Saf.
Here's one.
From Evan M. McGildenblatt,
this is about a rather special bridge
between Cincinnati, Ohio, and Covington, Kentucky.
Right?
It's called the Bailey Bridge.
And the interesting thing about it
is that it is named after a man named Clay Wade Bailey.
Yeah, but you would expect that.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
But there is a type of bridge.
If they'd have called it the Clay Bridge,
and it was made out of clay,
but it was named after him.
That would be amazing.
We'd have a ballgame.
But the interesting thing is,
it is not a Bailey type of bridge,
which is an existing very famous kind of bridge.
There's a Bailey bridge.
And the Bailey bridge here is not a Bailey bridge.
Yeah.
It's a cantilever bridge.
OK.
And I just wanted to talk a bit about Bailey Bridges.
Because that's so cool.
Are they?
Bailey was a guy called Donald Bailey.
And he was a civil servant in the British war office
who made model bridges as a hobby.
OK?
Second world war breaks out.
And suddenly lots of bridges are going to be needed across Europe.
When D-Day happens,
the Germans, if they're retreating,
will be blowing up a lot of bridges.
And in Italy, like lots of places you need to get to.
They often made temporary bridges as well,
didn't they, when they were moving tanks around?
These were the bridges that Donald Bailey
proposed and designed.
Cool.
So he literally drew the first model of it
on the back of an envelope.
It was literally on the back of an envelope.
And he said, I think this could work.
And basically, it's like a just huge mechanic.
So it's a lot of slot.
You don't need, you don't need much.
That's cool.
Special equipment.
I think one thing they used to do is they used to have like tanks
that were almost like in the shape of a bridge.
And you would drive your tank into the river.
And it would become the bridge.
And they would drive over that.
That's clever.
There are some devices called, I think,
called Hobart's Funnies,
which was especially weird.
They were the really weird machines
for engineering in the war.
But over 200 miles of Bailey Bridge
were built during the war.
I mean, thousands of, about 5,000.
Are any still eastern?
I think lots are.
Yeah, I think lots are.
And Donald Bailey got knighted for it.
Field Marsha Montgomery said they would not have won the war
nearly as easily or well without Donald Bailey's bridges.
We did win it quite easily in the end, didn't we?
Quite easily.
A bit of a push.
And yeah, if you have enough engineers,
you can build a Bailey Bridge in the 32 minutes.
That is very cool.
That's really cool.
That's very cool.
You guys ever played that app where you have to build a bridge?
No.
You've got to build a bridge using various angles
that you play.
So you don't, you have to work out
how you can create a construction
that allows for a van to cross.
And so it usually collapses
because it's very hard to build a bridge.
No, I have started recently playing a game called Euro Truck Simulator.
But, um, yeah.
Yeah, how far in are you?
Still at Dover, a lot of paperwork.
So it's Brexit, that game has been a nightmare.
Absolutely.
Okay, that is enough of your facts.
What amazing facts they were this week indeed as they are every week.
But now it is time to go through our archive.
The one that Andy has painstakingly typed up over the years
and take those lines from his spreadsheet
and hand them out to you, the listener.
If you are a member of our Patreon
at the top tier, which is Render the Podcast,
you will become a custodian
of a no such thing as a fish fact.
We will send you a digital certificate
and we will mention your name on this show.
So whose name are we going to mention first today?
Dan.
It is Brittany Bentley.
Congratulations.
Your fact is now the world's largest saw
is used to cut through mountains in Kazakhstan.
Terrific.
I wonder if it's still the world's largest saw.
Yeah.
Oh, yes.
Maybe.
Although it can't get much bigger than
a mountain kind of saw.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's very cool.
If you look at pictures of it, it's wicked.
Is it?
Yeah.
How many trips back and forth would it need to make?
Because presumably it's not the size of a mountain.
Or is it a circular saw?
Like, Dan's imagining like, you know,
two people on either side of a saw
sort of pulling it back and forth.
Like a lumberjack.
Yeah, like so.
Tensing and Hillary right at the top
if they just started at the top
and slowly went down with a saw.
I think it might be a circular saw.
I think so.
It rings a bell.
Yes, it's a circular saw.
I've just checked.
I've just found an article which begins
Frodo's journey to Mordor
and all of the rings would have been much easier
if he'd had one of these things.
Yeah, it's good.
It's also much easier if he had a helicopter.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Frodo's journey would have been made
so much easier by modern tech.
I don't know.
I've got effect.
This one goes out to wine cat.
In Victorian speedwalking competitions,
you were allowed to jog as necessary to relieve cramp.
Very good.
Yeah.
You know what I remember most about this episode
is you guys had all research stuff
about speedwalking
and I'd research stuff about cramp.
And so I didn't have anything to say in this whole section.
I don't really.
It's the first moment like that
where I realised that actually we should maybe
co-ordinate what we're researching a little.
And we're about a year into the podcast at this point.
So it's great.
Because now, listen up,
what you don't know probably
is that we send each other our headline facts
and then we usually put a little steers
to which direction we might go in.
Yeah.
We don't tell each other what we've found
but we tell each other which direction we're going.
So we all kind of talking on the same subject.
Yes, exactly.
Yeah.
This one is now under the custodian ship
of Jonathan Mundy
and Jonathan, your fact is that the 2012 law
prohibiting nudity in San Francisco
was proposed by a politician
called Scott Wiener.
Ha, lovely.
How interesting that I'm flashing forward
to another nudist fact that we did.
Flashing, yeah.
That we did years later
which was another one of yours.
So someone one day will be custodian of this
but the nudist in America
who was--
Dick Bacon.
The sort of nominative determinism
of nudists, prominent nudists is quite amazing.
Yeah.
And actually in Germany,
I think a couple of major nudists
in the early days were the Cox.
Yes.
Mr. Mrs. Koch, I can't remember the first names.
But I think it's a real missed opportunity
by San Francisco not to pass this law
and to call it Wiener's Law.
Yeah.
Does that mean they could have gone into your buck, Andy?
Yes.
Yeah, you've missed out San Francisco.
This result no one's ever heard of you, city.
All right, let's do another one now.
This is Phil Wilde.
Phil Wilde's fact is that so he could keep eating,
Charles Darwin's grandfather Erasmus
cut a semicircle out of his dining table.
That was a little crescent
which he'd put his stomach into
so that he could be closer to the table.
You know what that sounds like to me?
It's like he had an extremely
distendable stomach that as he ate
would get bigger and bigger and bigger.
Which does happen to a small extent.
But not enough in my experience
that you would need to cut a hole in your table.
Yes.
Yeah.
I think he was crazy, wasn't he?
He did all sorts of mad stuff.
He was an inventor and he was,
yeah, he was very important scientist and philosopher.
He was part of the Lunar Society
which was the sort of the leading brains
at the time of science.
He would only meet when it was a full moon
so that they could walk home later night
hence the Lunar Society.
That's great, Heather.
Here's one that goes out to Dominique Turin
and this is, this is one of my facts, actually.
It's one I'm very proud of,
is that Volkswagen sells more sausages than cars.
Very good.
I think it's that you've got given a free sausage,
a pack of sausages with every car you bought.
Yes, that is like, it was like eight in a pack.
So it meant that they sold eight times more sausages.
Inevitably, yeah.
There's no way they can get around that.
And no matter how fast the car guys work,
the sausage team are always going to be a step ahead of them.
However, can I say that I have got a Volkswagen in the last
a couple of years, last year, in fact.
And no sausages came my way.
Oh, really?
No, that might be because you went electric James
so there's no exhaust pipe for the sausages to be stuffed up.
Is that how they deliver them?
Yeah, probably, yeah.
All right, yeah.
They're going to put them in the charging pot.
That's amazing.
It's like, hey.
Because you've got that whole grid of charging points.
Yeah, yeah, perfect, perfect.
No, you're right.
I don't know what I meant.
Like six chip elates in there.
You've said that before.
Okay, this next fact is under this custodianship of Chris C.
Chris, your fact is the animal kingdom forgot how to have sex for 40 million years.
What's exciting about this is we did this fact very early on.
Episode 50.
And on our last Australian tour, we met the scientist who published this report.
He came on stage and was put into the hall of fame.
Yeah.
Very cool.
Yeah, he was in either Adelaide of Perth.
And yeah, we got to meet him and he wrote a book about sharks, which is out now.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, a shot guy.
Yeah.
And it's all about the fact that there was internal reproduction, I think,
that happened many millions of years ago.
And then it disappears from the fossil record.
Yes.
Oh, internal, not it within yourself.
No.
Well, it depends who you are, I suppose.
Yeah, it's like dog on dog.
That's brilliant fact.
That's very cool.
Yeah.
I got another one here.
This is to San, this is to Zander Sinji.
And the fact is the son of the man who invented shredded wheat.
Invented round shredded wheat.
Beautiful.
Brilliant.
Perkins are perky.
Perky.
Henry Perky, I think.
Yeah.
And his disappointing son.
Although now, there's sort of a bit round and a bit square, aren't they?
I haven't had a shredded wheat for at least 30 years.
I think of wheat or mix.
disregard whatever I've just said.
I was thinking of wheat or mix, which I'm rounded ends.
Shredded wheat have...
They're all like pillows, aren't they?
They're like pillows.
They've got sharp corners, but also rounded arches.
I'm not doing a pillow fight with you.
[laughter]
Yeah, and the thing is, you can only have two, suppose a day.
Yeah.
Right, and if someone has three shredded wheat in the morning,
that shows that they're forced to be reckoned with.
Really?
Yeah, yeah, that's the old saying.
Isn't that James?
I'm looking at you here.
Again, a little bit thinking wheat or mix.
Like, I'm sure we would like say,
"Oh, you've had an extra wheat or mix today."
How interesting.
Like if someone hits a long shot in the golf course or something.
Oh, man.
I just, I don't know.
The difference is to try to wheat a bit.
I don't know. It might be.
In Australia, it's called wheat bicks.
Oh, yeah.
And I can't tell you when I first move there how distant or...
It's like you're still in jet lag anytime you hear wheat bicks.
Yeah, yeah.
It doesn't make sense.
It's like a glitch in the universe.
I'm so sorry.
I've just checked it.
It's an old advertising slogan from the 1980s shredded wheat.
Bet you can't eat three.
Okay.
And it was when David Cameron, our prime minister,
was saying, "Do you want to go for another term in office?"
He said, "No, it's like shredded wheat.
Two or one to four, three might be too many."
As it was, he led a catastrophic referendum
and was forced to resign halfway through his...
Yeah.
...second shredded wheat.
And now he's got all the time in the world to eat shredded wheat.
Meanwhile, you're stuck at the immigration queue
as you're trying to get your virtual truck into Europe.
Should we do one more?
I've got one more fact.
Here's another one.
Here's one last one that goes out to
Tyler Wittem with him, possibly.
Hi, Tyler.
Your name's definitely Tyler.
In the 1960s, a Canadian psychologist visited cafes across the world
testing how much couples touched each other.
In Puerto Rico, it was 180 times an hour.
In Paris, 110.
And in London, it was zero.
Yeah, very good.
We just don't need to show off about it, all right?
I feel like we've become more
international in the last 10 years since that fact.
So I reckon there's more touching in the UK these days.
Oh, do you think so?
Yeah, probably.
Like, I reckon people give me way more hugs when I meet them
now than they did 10 years ago.
I think you have also dropped your guard a bit.
You used to be a lot more standoffish about being hugged
and you used to make it clear that that's not on the menu.
Whereas now, I think you come across a bit more...
You're wearing a floral shirt today.
People are thinking, "I can hug this guy."
Excuse me.
I wear this knowing that the audience don't know what I'm wearing.
I'm sorry.
Yeah, but you're not wearing anything else.
Yeah, okay.
I never thought about that as part of my personality.
I thought I was still a standoffish now.
I say, "Have I ever used my life?"
You've suffered a lot.
I was living in London, isn't it?
Yeah, it is.
Like if I lived in Puerto Rico.
Okay, that's the end of our facts given to you.
And in fact, your facts given to us.
But we do want to say thank you to Tyler,
Zander, Chris, Dominique, Phil, Jonathan,
Winkat, and Brittany for becoming our latest
friends of the podcast custodians.
If you would like to send us some facts,
then send them to podcast@QI.com,
where Andy will go through them
and pick out the very best ones for this show.
If you would like to become a custodian of a fact,
then go to patreon.com/clubfish
and join us at the very top tier,
which is friend of the podcast.
And it is those special people who get the names
read out on this show.
If you don't want to do any of those things,
then fear not.
We will be back on Friday for another big fish episode.
So it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from Dan Schreiber.
Oh, goodbye.
And it's goodbye from Andrew Hunter Murray.
Jurassic World 2, uh, the bark of the Barking.
I'll just keep workshopping it. Bye.
Bye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]