[phone rings]
[speaking Japanese]
[music]
- Hi.
How was that?
- Lovely.
- James?
- Oh yeah, I'm in 7 out of 10.
- Okay, well.
- But you got a factor at the time.
It's 8.30 in the morning.
That was powerhouse.
That was stadium level.
- Welcome, everybody, to a morning-recorded edition
of Drop as a Line.
Will it be much different to our standard early afternoon record?
Let's find out.
As we go through your inboxes, no we don't.
We go through your outboxes.
- We don't know we don't.
- This is so slick.
- As we go through our inboxes,
covering the messages that have come from your outboxes.
- Should we come back in maybe about three or four hours?
- So, look, let's just get in.
We've got some "um" actuallys.
We've got some "get yourself off the hooks."
Maybe there's some spicy meat lurking in here.
Let's find out.
Message one comes.
This is a bit of an...
It's an "um" actually, but it's a nice one.
This is from Daniel Wilson, who said a few episodes ago,
"We mentioned some facts about the International Owl Center
in Houston."
- "Hoo-hoo-ston."
- "Hoo-ston?"
- Brilliant.
- "It's Houston, right?"
"But it's Houston, M-N."
What's that? Minnesota?
- Minnesota, yeah, that's right.
- Minnesota.
Daniel, there was a point to Daniel's message.
He wasn't just congratulating us on mentioning
the International Owl Center.
He said, "Houston is a small town in M-N,
as we now know, Minnesota.
And the Owl Center is an outgrowth of the relationship
between the founder, Carla Bloom,
and Alice the Great Horned Owl."
- Okay, that's nice.
- I assume it's nice.
Relationships can be nice, can not be.
Might be antagonistic.
Daniel continues, "Since the International Owl Center
is not technically a zoo, and since owls cannot be kept
as pets, all the owls at the International Owl Center
are designated as employees.
They have four owl employees and three humans.
Due to old Asian arthritis, Alice,
that's Alice the Great Horned Owl,
officially retired in 2018.
I went to her retirement party, which was great fun.
She didn't attend physically the retirement party,
but she did attend virtually from her retirement home."
- That's really nice.
I guess if you were an owl employee,
then you would once have the night shift,
and it'd be like, "Oh my god, I'm on day shift today."
- Oh, night there, yeah.
That's really funny.
- What's the law behind that?
It's different to a zoo, I guess, right?
The zoo animals are different.
- Not technically a zoo, I suppose, yeah.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause it would be a good idea at a zoo if all the animals
at a zoo were employees, you would save on staffing,
and you would have some more fun, you know, fun adventures.
- Leaving do's.
(laughing)
- Oh no, the penguins have got together with a fish, no.
Yeah, anyway, thank you, Daniel.
That was lovely bonus info.
- Yeah, brilliant.
- Well, let's move on to an email from jamrainbird,
which is about--
- Sorry, who?
- Jamrainbird?
- Brilliant.
That's not a real name, is it?
- I think so, yeah.
- Who is it?
Jam, first name.
Rainbird, surname.
That's not someone who's having their breakfast
in the conservatory and just pick three random things
to give them a name.
(laughing)
- That's an employee from the birds, actually.
Well, Jam writes, "James confirmed my understanding somewhat
when he said that tortoises have toes."
Do you remember this?
We were talking about tortoises having--
- Yeah, so the idea is that sometimes people put tortoises
in the water to save them, thinking that they're turtles,
and so the best way to tell is that tortoises have toes.
- Yeah, exactly that.
And Jam says, "Tortoise equals land turtle.
Water turtle doesn't need toes.
Makes sense to me.
Tortoises have toes."
Great.
Dan then repeated, "Total, total 101 times."
(laughing)
- Okay, that was Dan's joke, wasn't it?
- Roughly, yeah.
I think it's a proposed mnemonic.
Maybe you said it one or two times, Dan,
but it felt like a lot.
Unfortunately, total sounds more like turtle than tortoise,
so Dan's mnemonic makes me think that it is turtles
that have toes and tortoises that don't,
which is the opposite.
(laughing)
- Oh, no, Dan.
- Yeah, I got a lot of kickback from that attempt
of a new name.
Everyone's saying it should actually
be turtles the other way around.
I was putting it on the wrong side.
- No.
- Neither work, Andy, neither work.
(laughing)
- And then, worryingly, Jam says,
"Even more, unfortunately, I just googled tortoises
and turtles and discovered that both tortoises
and other turtles have toes."
Query needed.
Tortoises certainly have more toes.
- Yeah.
- They'll have the same skeletal structure
because they're all--
- I would say so.
- Because we're all the same, deep down.
- I read this from a conservationist
who was saying that people are doing this
and that it's a problem.
And this was their kind of rule of thumb,
but perhaps it's a rule of toes
that doesn't quite always work.
- I think it's a pretty good--
You can definitely tell more toes on a tortoise than a--
- For sure.
- Yeah, yeah.
I think it works.
And if you're at the water's edge now,
just drop it in.
It'll probably be fine.
- No, I think what we're saying, actually,
is just leave it to the experts.
Like, whether it's a turtle, a tortoise, a terrapin,
or any other animal beginner with tea, just leave it.
Let it be--
- Tiger.
- It's a tiger.
Rub it by the toe.
- Don't return it to the water.
Don't take it.
Oh, here's the most annoying email in the inbox.
This was, do you remember Dan guessing the day of the week
when I said, you know, people can get it.
People, there's math sevens who can get it right.
I said 24 February 1603.
Dan, do you remember what you guessed?
- Monday.
- Yeah.
Well, Heather Morgan writes,
"I'm sure many people have told you this already,
but A, 24 February 1603 was the day Catherine Howard died."
Interesting.
- Oh.
- Yeah, on a Monday.
- And yeah, B, it was a Monday.
You're right.
By sheer chance.
It's so annoying.
- Well, someone pointed out that actually,
I'm probably wrong because the calendars have changed,
haven't they?
- Oh, yes, they have.
- Yeah.
So I think, I can't remember.
I briefly saw the message.
It might have been a Wednesday or something like that.
- So the calendar, there was a point where the calendar
switched over from Gregorian to Julian
or the other way around.
- I think this might have taken it into account
because you don't remember at school.
It's like, "Divorced beheaded died,
divorced, beheaded on a Monday.
Survived."
- So good.
We've got a slightly mystical email from Nathan Galamore Strong.
- Oh.
- Nathan.
- What a Galamore.
- Galamore name.
- Right, let me preface this by saying,
I have no idea why I'm telling you this.
Exciting.
I often listen to the podcast just before bed,
and this was sometimes results in some of my dreams
containing some aspects of the facts or discussions
during that particular episode.
- Right.
- Trippy.
Last night, I had a dream that I was in a pub,
and none other than James Harkin came in.
I freaked out with excitement,
mentioning to my wife about who it was
and if I should go and say hi.
- Yep, do say hi if I ever walk in a pub.
- Well, Nathan goes on.
I built up the courage to walk over and explain
that I'm a huge fan.
James then gave me the most disdainful look.
And when I asked for a photo, he begrudgingly agreed
and posed with the most sour look on his face
before telling me to leave him alone.
- Oh, wow.
- I woke up in a state of utter shock.
That's, yeah, well, that's what I like.
- Checks out.
- Only in dreams.
Like, in real life, I'm actually quite nice
if you ask me for a photo,
but if you do it in a dream, I will be absolutely livid.
- That's exactly right.
That's the way around.
James lives in the other realm where he's grumpy.
Yeah, he says, "I now have an irrational fear
"that if I ever meet James in real life,
"this dream will become a reality."
Could you ask James if this is a weird premonition,
or if he is, as I suspect,
actually a pleasant human being?
Well, he is.
I cannot rest, Nathan says.
- I'd love to know one day,
because there is a possibility that one day,
James, you're having a really terrible day.
You're walking to a pub.
You just don't need it.
This guy's like, "What a dream."
You're like, "Jesus."
Like, you know, that's good deal.
- I'm fucking out of that to leave the game.
- Well, he's even better.
Well, he's got Nathan, something strong.
- Gallimaw strong.
- Nathan Gallimaw strong.
- Yeah.
It's quite a sci-fi name, isn't it?
- Yeah, you're pissed off already.
You walked into a pub.
A bag comes up saying, "I am Nathan Gallimaw strong."
- In that tone of voice.
- Yep.
- Just let me get to the fucking bar.
- Yeah.
I'm so excited for this meeting.
- I know.
He says, "It's worth pointing out,
I love," I assume he means live,
"nowhere near London,
and likely will never run into any of Team Fish,
but this is haunting me."
- Oh, we travel.
- Wow.
- We travel around.
- We do.
- Dancing Liverpool right now
when we're recording this.
- Oh, yeah.
- Exactly.
And I'll be in York.
Well, this is, Windsor's going out.
- You will have been in York.
- Yeah, and Leeds.
- Yeah.
- But you will no longer be in those places.
- Exactly.
- So, like, search your recent memory
if you live in Liverpool, York, or Leeds
for having maybe seen him and thought,
"Is that?"
No, maybe it wasn't.
I don't know.
- Check all your photos and see if there's
a strange, bespectacled man in the background
of any of them.
- Hairy, really hairy.
Look for the hair and the glasses together.
- Was that sort of bigfoot?
Yeah, walking around.
Is anyone, I'm just curious, in the inbox,
going to defeat either Nathan Gallimaw strong
or jam Rain Bird as a name?
- No, I don't think so.
I've got, well, yeah, up to you, really.
- I'm very excited to see what's coming.
- All right.
We've got a few first names, which are,
you know, they're less rounded.
But, so, for example, Courtney, Courtney writes,
"Over the years I have nearly written in a number of times.
However, today I had to.
Please tell Neil Gaiman that our families still say "bygals"
as his mother does, rather than bagels.
We're from Whitechapel, East London,
and all the locals still do.
However, when I talk to anyone outside the postcode,
I have to say it like the Americans do.
So there is still a bygle movement.
- How interesting.
- Yeah.
- And Whitechapel is down the road.
And we got another, we got a second email on this saying,
you're saying it wrong.
I nearly had to stop listening to the episode.
It's bygles, bygles, bygles, bygles.
Don't ever get it wrong again.
- Wow, I didn't realize there was such a...
I mean, I know Neil said that there was a problem with him,
and not a problem with him and his mother.
Just a discussion with him and his mother.
They're not now estranged over the pronunciation of bygle.
But I didn't realize it was such a hot topic.
- It's a hot potato.
- I don't think I've ever heard anyone say it.
- Hot potato, I think.
- Very nice.
- Can't let them, what were you saying?
- No, I just, I don't think, you know, even in East London,
I've ever heard someone say by...
You know, used to go all the time to the bagel shops,
which are on Brick Lane,
which are very famous late night horns
for when you're kicked out of pubs.
- Close to Whitechapel, I would say.
- Exactly.
- But they don't have a...
They might be bygles shops then,
as in they don't have a pronunciation guide
on the front of the shop.
- But I just never heard anyone in the vicinity going,
let's get a bygle.
You know, you know, listening out loud on the streets,
as I do, as you know, Andy.
- All right, so bagels bygles sorted.
We have had a great email from Noah Levine,
and this is a call forward to an episode
that hasn't even been broadcast yet, I think.
- Wow.
- I know.
Adding to the list of weird sports I've discovered lately,
I just learned about walk racing.
- Okay.
- And it's where you ride down a huge,
I think an icy slope on a walk.
- On a walk?
Yeah, nice.
- What's that referring to though?
I don't remember us talking about weird spots.
- We didn't talk about walk racing,
but the fact is this, Nathan Evans,
who recorded the chart-topping sea shanty Wellerman.
- Oh, gosh.
- Represented Scotland in the World Walk Racing Championship 2022.
- How did I not find that in my research?
That's incredible.
- We've just recorded, but haven't yet put out
an episode about sea shanties.
- Yeah, yeah.
Won't go out for a few weeks, actually.
- Right.
- And this episode from 1999.
- We missed this.
- Can we quickly rebook the Soho?
Just get in.
Do this extra bit.
- That's a great fact though, really.
- I know.
- Yeah, that's cool.
- Do we want to reopen the Wicca Satan box?
- Okay.
- Yeah, I like that box.
- I think we've got a...
I'm going to open the box from a different angle now.
- Okay.
- There's a second face in the box to be opened.
And it's interesting because Jamie Lerner Brecher writes,
"Like everyone else who seems to write into this email address,
long-time listener, first-time writer."
Well, people, you know, once they've had a reply from me,
they don't feel the need to...
A lot of them actually put me on a plot list immediately
after getting my reply.
- You just replied back going, "Sorry, did you get my reply?"
- I put read receipts on like the most irritating people
on the planet.
"I'll need a receipt that you've seen this email, please."
Right. "To correct a correction from the recent drop of the line,
brackets, correct-ception, the Satanic Temple is definitely
not just a libertarian organization.
I'm a leftist."
That's Jamie writing, not me.
I obviously vote GB News.
It's a way for people who are either atheists
or don't believe in organized religion
to get the same protections in the USA offered to religious people.
So there was a recent ruling about reproductive justice
and Jamie writes, "I joined the Satanic Temple
because one of its main tenets is bodily autonomy
and the right to an abortion.
As a non-practicing but culturally Jewish atheist,
this was an organized religion I could get behind."
And they're trying to do other cool things.
And he goes on, "It's also extremely different
than the Church of Satan or Wiccans.
And while you guys did say that, it was half a sentence
and I'm sure left people confused."
- Yeah, fair enough.
- They're trying to do other things.
They're trying to end corporal punishment in schools.
Sounds like a good idea.
And they're trying to get a Satanic prayer at the 50-yard line
of a public high school football game
since the Supreme Court recently ruled that legal for Christians.
I don't understand that.
- That's interesting.
Well, I do watch a lot of college football
and American football.
And I assume he doesn't mean during the game.
- I don't.
- He's doing a prayer during the game.
It must be before the game
when they do the National Anthems and stuff, I suppose.
- Could you do it during the game
but at the edge of the line?
As in where, you know, at the edge of the field,
you could pray there.
- You could.
Usually you have, this is quite interesting.
So at the side of the field of American football,
you have a load of referees there
and they're looking out for anything going wrong.
It's not like in soccer where you have like three referee
and two lines when you have loads of referees.
And you also have all of the substitutes,
of which there's lots.
And you also have the managers, the coaches there.
Now the coaches are running up and down
because they need to see everything that's happening.
And American football teams, a lot of them,
employ one person whose job it is
to pull the manager, the coach, out of the way
if he's going to run into a referee.
So he doesn't have to look where he's running.
He can just run up and down the line.
And if he's about to hit a line judge,
they just grab him and pull him out of the way.
- That's incredible.
- So they have to run with him, right?
- Yeah, they run behind him the whole way.
And they're always watching that he doesn't bump into people.
- Oh, I see.
So they're kind of side-running,
sideways running and hauling him out of the way
because he's watching the game.
They're just looking at the pitch.
They're looking to his left and right
to make sure that he doesn't run into anyone.
- That's incredible.
- It feels like with only a minimum more effort,
you could get a sedan chair for the coach.
And they'd be carried up and down the line.
- The thing is, it's a matter of,
if you have to employ two people to do that,
you only have to employ one person to dodge him out of the way.
But sedan chair requires two people.
- It doesn't sound like a game is an efficient hiring.
If the sidelines are thronged with referees and lines,
it sounds like there's a little fat here
to add another employee.
- Yeah, I guess so.
- I think that's worth it.
- But James, has there ever been any sort of attempts
of sabotage where the opposing team will place someone
in the way and take the coach down
so that he's sort of injured and you lose him for a while?
- I see what you mean.
The thing is that your team are all on one side of the,
of the pitch and the other team own the other sidelines.
So you're kind of always on the opposite side to them.
- So you need a mole.
You need someone on the inside.
- Just a little mole, building your little mole, hell.
- That's such an amazing thing.
What's the career progression of that job?
- I don't know actually.
- You move into bodyguarding, I think,
because it's sort of dodging, like taking a bullet for someone.
It's just one or two steps up
from stopping and bumping into an alignment.
- I guess so.
- So good.
What a great job.
That's amazing.
- I've just checked the prayer thing.
It turns out it's a high school football coach
who wanted the right to pray on the 50 yard line after each game.
Any players who wanted to participate
and they were said, they were told, yes, you can.
So that's fine.
So they're just asking for the right to do the...
- I was in Waterstones last night
and I was looking around in Liverpool
and the wicker section is directly
above the witchcraft section.
And I just wonder if that annoys them as well.
Just the proximity towards them.
- Yeah, but it's not above the Satan satanic sex
in the woodlands section.
- Yeah, that's true.
- Which most Waterstones do have.
- Yeah, yeah.
- They do.
Liverpool was missing it for so long, but yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Okay, and now we're closing the box.
- Right.
- We now come onto the...
This is the big...
- Why are we not keeping it in a wicker basket?
Why is it in a box?
- Lack of imagination by me.
That's much...
Oh, for next time.
Don't say next time.
Okay, well, look, I was thinking,
by the way, as I was walking around today,
if we had a fish restaurant,
we could call it in no particular order.
- Very good.
Although orders also are things that you do in restaurants.
- Yeah, it's really right there on the tin, isn't it?
In no particular order.
- Yeah, it is.
- And what it is, is if someone walks in
and they take their table,
they might get their order taken straight away,
or they might have to wait 45 minutes for their order.
- Oh, I thought it was more like,
"Hey, why hasn't the main come before the starter?
What's the dessert coming next?"
- Oh, it's like...
- And bring them out in no particular order.
- It's like, is it Wagamama?
Or they always warn you?
- Oh, yeah.
- Just in case you don't know,
the food comes any order.
- Yeah.
- And it's...
They're always...
They're so worried that you're going to be annoyed about it.
- Well, yeah.
That's because they always bring the ice cream
and then 20 minutes later,
they bring the hot sauce, wings,
or whatever it is that you've ordered.
It's like, "Oh, the ice cream was ready, sorry."
- Just in case you've never been to a Wagamama.
- Anyway, look, we've come...
- It is such a weird restaurant,
when you point out that.
And then they just draw all over your place, man, buddy.
- Yeah, it's true, because I go to restaurants
to deliberately ask for a place mat that I can color in.
I don't want someone else to do it for me.
- So that is a kind of long-winded way
of getting around to me saying,
"We're now reaching the main course."
- Oh, great.
- Sorry, I just thought of hors d'oeuvres,
and I thought, you know, that's where I was going with that.
But we had some fun along the way, yeah.
Right, in the Neil Gaiman episode,
which went out a couple of weeks ago,
Dan brought up a guy who was pushing a peanut-upper
mountain in Colorado with his nose called Pikes Peak.
That's the name of the mountain, not the men.
And I said, "Wow, what do people do in Colorado for fun?
If you're in Colorado, can you write it and tell us?"
There are so many fish listeners in Colorado,
and they've all been in the inbox in the last couple of weeks.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- That's great.
So now, next time we go to Colorado,
we have a full list of things that we can do for fun.
- It's genuinely double-figures,
the number of people who've written in.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- What's the most interesting thing?
- Well, let's get into it.
Beckett writes...
- Long parts.
- So, James...
Main thing to do in Colorado is waiting for Godot.
Brilliant.
Hi, fish.
I've been listening to your podcast for years
and never thought I'd hear a local story on it.
Not only did I already know about the man
who pushed a peanut up Pikes Peak with his nose,
but there were daily play-by-play updates about it at the time.
It was big news/nose.
The irony is that there is plenty to do in Colorado.
We are one of the most active states with a thriving outdoor culture
that encourages skiing, hiking, biking, paddleboarding, you name it.
We also have several beautiful national parks
and a world-renowned film festival.
That being said, we moved recently from Washington, D.C.
to the suburbs of Denver,
and I find it mind-numbingly boring
and commoditonous out here.
- You're sincerely pushing a peanut up a hell.
Beckett.
- I should say that's not a universal opinion
by the people of Colorado who've written in.
A lot of them are very happy about the outdoor activities.
Yeah, it seems like a very outdoorsy place, basically.
- Yeah, I think I said, but maybe cut that it's a big skiing place, isn't it?
- Oh, nice.
Tim writes, Tim lives in Colorado.
I can confirm that, one, there are things to do other than push peanuts up 14ers,
which is mountains over 14,000 feet.
And two, if there is a stupid thing that could be done outdoors,
someone in Colorado will do it.
And there are 53 14ers in Colorado,
and lots of people try and climb them all,
but they also have Frozen Dead Guy Day.
- Oh, Dan's mentioned that before on the podcast.
- Oh, yeah.
- Do you remember that?
- I don't remember it.
- It was, now, I might get it mixed up with an episode of The Simpsons,
but there was a guy who got frozen and died.
- Well, I've got a little detail here.
- Okay, go on.
- There's a guy who frozen his shed,
so you're exactly right, James,
and there are things like a hearse parade and coffin races
where a team has to run up and down hills of snow
while carrying someone in a coffin.
- That's right.
- Wow.
Just a quick little quiz for us here,
because I've just brought it up.
We get analytics of our listeners.
We, you know, it can tell us where people are listening from
if we look into our data.
So I've just brought up America.
So for the last seven days,
what do you think is the most, the number one city?
- New York?
- Number one, no, it's number two.
- Oh, is it Denver?
- Oh, dang.
- No, but Denver does appear on the list.
- Does it?
- It's at six.
- I'm going to say Denver's at six.
- Oh, sorry, it's at six.
- It's at six, yes.
- Because we've had 10 people write in,
so that can't be right.
I'm going to say Houston, but not Houston, Texas.
Houston, Minnesota.
- Is it going to be LA, New Orleans, Chicago?
- So directly below it is New York, Los Angeles, and Chicago.
San Francisco comes further down, but yeah,
it's slightly surprising.
- Boston, Seattle.
- Still a big city.
Seattle is right.
- Oh, well done, Andy.
- Yes, in the last seven days.
- I thought, what are we most like?
- Frasier.
- Exactly.
- The new series.
- Day.
- Who would we all be in Frasier?
Anna is Roz.
- Oh, yeah.
- Sarcastic, wine lover.
That fits.
- Well, Daphne's from Manchester, isn't she?
- Do you want to be Daphne?
- Yeah.
- Although Dan's got a weird accent.
- That's true.
- Yeah.
But I think I'm probably the dog.
- You're Eddie?
- Yeah.
- I think you're the chair.
Still there in the corner.
Good night, everyone.
- I think either of you could be Frasier, actually.
- What?
- You obviously think of yourself as a Niles.
- Yeah.
- I mean, there's nothing.
Guys, good luck knocking me off the Niles perch,
which I've been polishing every day for the last 10 years.
No one's going to step up and be the dad?
- I don't really, I haven't really watched.
- You're the oldest.
- Yeah.
- All right.
- You used to be in the police.
You got shot in the hip actually during a robbery.
Actually, wow, that's weird.
You, yeah.
That's it.
- I like spots.
He likes spots, doesn't he?
- You like sports.
You'll probably, you know the most about beer.
You like beer.
He likes beer.
I think there's a case there.
- I think you like sitting on me?
- Well, we've got it worked out.
Great.
- Nice.
- Okay.
What are we talking about?
- Seattle.
- Oh, we were talking about a dead man.
Was it Seattle?
- Yeah.
- I just brought that up because of Colorado.
We've got a lot of listeners.
- Great.
- Double digits in the inbox.
- Oh, double digits.
Yeah, yeah, you're right.
Okay, great.
Well, Seattle.
We love you.
Okay, here's one.
So we've had an expert write in.
This is someone from the Association of Track and Field Statisticians.
- Oh, lovely.
- Yeah.
His name is Richard Hymans.
Richard writes, in episode 496, Andy described a 2021 Viking attack
on a Scottish town called Kirk-Kudbright.
- Yeah.
- One of the greatest examples of mangling Scottish names I've ever heard.
I'm guessing he meant Kirk-Kubri, spelt Kirk-Kudbright.
Just such a butchering.
I've had so many people write it and say, where?
And I said, Kirk-Kubri is what it's called.
It's very embarrassing.
I'm half Scottish.
- It is.
- It's both.
- Yeah, giving you a Scottish heritage.
- Oh, my deep, deep Scottish accent.
Mortifying.
Yeah.
Oh, I've had a couple of people write to me about that, saying I said it.
So I assumed I said it.
Was that you?
- Yeah, it was me.
- God, I've been fielding, yeah, fielding templates as well.
- Do you get complaints to your email, Dan?
- Not to my email, directly to my Twitter or Instagram or just outside my house.
- Because no one sends messages to me.
Is it because I'm classically a very grumpy person
who'll tell them to fuck off if they come anywhere near me?
- No, I think it more says that you just don't get things wrong.
- People will probably say that.
But it's also a lot of people, when we're in the pub after a show,
they will try and approach you and tell you things.
- I'll have none of it.
- No, you'll have none of it.
No.
- I used to do the QI emails, so for the TV show QI.
And it came up on my, you know, when Facebook tells you things that happened
10 years ago or more.
It came up one of my messages, which was it was the last complaint that I dealt with.
And on QI, we'd compared Klingons and Vulcans to Spartans and Athenians.
And someone had written into us saying,
"Actually, we meant Vulcans and Romulans."
- Oh my gosh.
- Oh, wow.
- That is Wiccan's sensationist all over again.
- That's great.
- Yeah.
- Oh boy, that's brilliant.
Do we have one last one?
This is just a nice little bonus message, actually, from Julia.
And it's a fact that the former Desert Island disc presenter, Kirstie Young,
and her husband, have recently bought a deserted island on Loch Lomond.
- No.
- Yeah.
- Is that true?
It's called, it's called, oh God, Inchkonachan.
Inchkonachan.
- And if Andy has mangled that pronunciation, then write into your podcast at qi.com.
- That's great.
So they're moving in there.
- I don't know.
It's, well, Julia says it's uninhabited, except for it has Scotland's only wild wallabies.
- Oh, wow.
- Unfortunately, since the purchase, there has been talk of eradicating the wallabies,
which many have protested against.
And Julia says, "I recently visited by kayak and camped there and can confirm it's very beautiful.
And as of last weekend, it still has wallabies."
- I assume they must be thinking of moving in there, though.
Otherwise, why would they buy the island?
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So that'll be great.
And she can--
- Bring five records.
- Yeah.
I wonder how many islands are owned by celebrities off the Scottish coast?
- Loads, loads, loads, loads.
- Lamb Island, that's owned by Yuri Geller.
- Right.
- Because he claims that there's a hidden treasure from a lost Egyptian priestess.
- Of course he does.
Of course he does.
And all I'm going to say is, if you have an island on Scotland and you want to sell it
to Yuri Geller, what are you going to say to him to get the price up?
- Yeah, exactly.
It can't just be it's a lovely island and it's got quite a nice bit with a beach.
- No, it has to be--
- Yeah.
- That's the-- actually, I know about that.
Is it called Lamb Island, then?
- Lamb Island, yeah.
- It was completely straight when he bought it.
And then since then, it's now bent into a massive U-shirt.
It's so weird.
Bye.
- That's 9am energy, goodbye.
- Yeah.
- Bye, everybody.
Thanks so much for listening.
We hope you've enjoyed it.
We certainly have.
And if you'd like to cause us further enjoyment, please write to podcast@qi.com.
Maybe you've noticed something.
Maybe you've dreamed of one of us.
Maybe you've got views on the Frasier recasting that we're about to do.
Whatever it is, we're here to read it in your outbox day after day.
So, see you then.
All right, take care.
Bye.
- Really nice.
- I'm going back to bed.
- Yeah.