(Bell)
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast this week coming to you live from Birmingham!
(Cheering)
(Bell)
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with Anish Zinski, Andrew Hunter Murray and James Harkin
and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go starting with fact number one
and that is James
Okay my fact this week is that Hitchbott was a robot invented to see how far human kindness would take a mechanical Hitchhiker
In 2015 he was left on the side of the road in Boston and was found dismembered in a ditch 17 days later
(Laughter)
Yeah and found in Philadelphia which is a city of brotherly love
I read a headline about it which said innocent hitchhiking robot murdered by America
(Laughter)
And there's CCTV footage isn't there, they don't know who the guy is but he was wearing a backwards baseball cap
they saw him starting to beat the robot
he then ripped the arm off the robot and he beats the robot with the arm
I mean it's a proper savaging
So actually there was a few of these robots made, it started in 2014 and it was by a guy called David Harris Smith of McMaster University
And the early ones had gone through Canada, Germany and the Netherlands with no problems at all they'd gone and seen some amazing things
(Laughter)
But yeah this guy they left him off the side of the road in Boston and it did not end well
The Canadian Avengers were amazing
I mean for a start the thing itself was made really cheap, it was made for less than a thousand dollars
So it was not a very good robot
As in the arms that Dan mentioned were swimming pool noodles
And then you could only get about three or four good hits with them
And it had a cake saver over its face
What's a cake saver?
Like one of those plastic lids that you put over a cake to save it
Oh yeah, yeah the little see-through so you can still see the cake
Yeah exactly, yeah see the tea
Yeah it was designed, it was reused as a helmet for a robot
And it had a car seat, it was sitting on a children's car seat so people could put it in their cars
They had some good things though, they had a camera that took regular photos which I think maybe is where we got this CCTV that Dan was talking about
It had a voice box that would explain where it wanted to go and it had solar panels
But it could also be charged by plugging it into the car's cigarette lighter socket
Wow, so good, it was very popular at the time so you could follow it on Twitter and there was a thing where it had GPS in it so people know where it was
And they had to work out how to turn that off because when people collected the hitch-bought and brought it home
Fans would flock to the house of this person and they would be inundated
And the adventures were great, he was picked up by a band called The Wild
Who I've not heard but their members are called Dylan Villain
The kid, booze us and re-slightening
Oh, they sound great
They sound like the guys who chopped into pieces
We've got a strong history of abusing robots, haven't we?
It's going to be awful when they become sentient because we give them a rush of time
There are loads of examples, in 2017 a Silicon Valley, in fact, a drunk man was arrested after knocking over an egg-shaped five-foot-tool security robot called Night Scope
It was really sad, but the Night Scope, it was called Night Scope K-5 actually and it had previously been in the news for running over a toddler's foot
Oh, okay, so there's...
There was some speculation, it was sort of payback
Calm down on both sides
People get very weird around robots because when we were talking about the murder of hitch-bought, every other room felt quite tense
So if people had told to hit a dinosaur robot with a mallet, they got a bit freaked out, they don't like doing it
And roboticists, proper roboticists, are quite annoyed by this
And they say this is just crazy, anthropomorphizing
So there's a guy called Noel Sharky
And he thinks that we need to get over this obsession with treating machines like they've got feelings
And I read this account of him
To prove his point, at one conference he attended recently
He picked up an extremely cute robotic seal designed for elderly care and started banging its head against a table
Oh my god
I think it's just a robot
It is weird though, there was someone I think writing in that article saying it's bizarre that if you're sitting around a table with someone and there's a teddy nearby
And they seize a teddy and tear its head off, you'll think they're a psycho
But if they swat a fly, which is a living creature that's relatively harmless to any of you, then it's perfectly normal behavior
What do I do? In 2018 some German researchers asked 89 students to turn off a cute looking robot called Now
But they asked questions first, but when they tried to turn it off, it was programmed to say no, please don't switch me off
Oh
And every, sorry, a third of the humans took twice as long as normal to turn off the robots and 13 of the group refused to turn it off at all
Wow
It was afraid of the dark
Oh, it's not real
Guys, it's like the end of Blade Runner
I've got a thing about how polite humans are to robots
Okay
So this is in a restaurant setting, people are given the chance to order food from a robot
Researchers from Tufty University, they made a waiter bot and they asked humans in the restaurant to order from the robot
But they also programmed it not to handle indirect speech very well
Okay, so it needed to be ordered from but people are so reluctant to say, you know, they order something
So I just want to try a little kind of roleplay
James, if you play the participants, as James is the human and I'm the robot here
Okay
Can I have one water?
Yes, that is permissible
Great, please tell me your order
Can I have one water?
Yes, that is permissible
Great, I'll take one water
Can I have one water?
Yes, that is permissible
Okay
Can you bring me one water?
Yes, I am able to do that
Please tell me your order
I would like to have one water
Thank you for sharing that interesting fact
Please tell me your order, then there's a 16 second pause
Can you bring me one water?
Yes, I am able to do that
Please tell me your order
May you please bring me one water?
Yes, I am able to do that
So can you do it?
Yes
Please tell me your order
Can you come inside and get the water for me?
Yes, I am able to do that
Please tell me your order
Just people will not say, I order one water
They just won't do it
They just used my entire range of acting ability on this
That's amazing
Move on shortly, unless there's more dialogue
Oh well, just on humanoid robots
They've been around for way longer than I thought
So Japan loves robots now
It's probably the pioneer of robots, but it has done for ages
So in the 17th century
They invented a humanoid robot
And they're called caracurie dolls
And I'd never heard of these guys
Their dolls were basically there to carry tea to you
So they worked with quite a simple mechanism
But basically you got a cup of tea
You had a guest round
You wanted to impress them, you got out your robot
You popped a tea on the tray that the robot's carrying
And this triggered a mechanism that caused it to turn around
And walk over to your guest, offer them the tea
And then stand beside your guest while they drink the tea
And probably quite an intimidating manner
And then when you've finished the tea
You pop it back on the tray
And the robot turned around and walked back again
No, that is amazing
And how long is that from?
That's the 17th century
And they were really popping up on the 17th to the 19th century in Japan
And there were lots of others, there were some that acted out sort of medieval scenes
Japanese scenes, old medical scenes and stuff
That's amazing, I haven't had the robot in Japan actually
It's called RoboV2
And they programmed it to go around the shopping centre
And whenever it bumped into a human
It would be programmed to politely ask the humans to step aside
And if they didn't move out the way
It would kind of go in a different direction, that was all it did
But then what happened was a lot of children worked out what was happening
And started making a circle around it
And then they started shaking it, punching it and kicking it
And the bullying got so bad that the researchers had to put an abuse evading algorithm in the robot
And the robot would scan the area and if it saw anyone that was under 4 foot 6
As in a child, then it would quickly run in the other direction
I do this in shopping centres
Okay, it is time for fact number 2 and that is Chazinsky
My fact this week is that a Hungarian entrepreneur has been fined for not building an underwater treadmill for dogs
Confusing
I haven't done that, Iber
You just expect the police at your door any moment now
I hope we have all done this because this person got in trouble
They got a fine of 140,000 euros this person
And it's because years ago in 2008 this business one said that he needed 140,000 euros of funding
And the EU's Rural Development Fund to develop a hydrotherapy treadmill system for dogs
Now this is a genuinely important thing for animals that have been wounded
Don't laugh, it's crucial for dog recovery
The only thing is he never did any of that
The officers were investigated, they were overrun with weeds
No one was using them six months after the EU payments were made, this investigation opened
And he's finally been investigated and given a suspended prison sentence for never building that treadmill
Which is actually a very lenient fine really
It can't be essential for dog healing, otherwise no dog would ever have survived any injury
Before the invention of the underwater dog treadmill
You got to do it
So hungry at the moment is run by Victor Orban
He has taken money to make a 4,000-seater football stadium in his home village
where he grew up called "Felkshoot"
And the population of that town is about 1,000
So it's 4 times bigger than the number of people who live there
He's also made a vintage railway between his two child hud villages
He took 2 million euros of EU funding for this railway
And they claimed that there would be 2,500 to 7,000 passengers using it every single day
And in the first month there were 30 passengers
That is just him going back and forth
I'm not thinking it might be
He is football obsessed, Orban, isn't he?
So this railway line was connecting the football stadium that he loved to this other little village
But he played semi professional football while he was doing his first in as prime minister
In the fourth division of the league tables but still decent
He said to watch 6 football games a day
Which is a lot for someone who's running a country
And his first trip abroad when he was prime minister was to see the World Cup in Paris
And people say that he has not missed a World Cup or Champions League final since
He's been in the news recently or rather his government has because they have a new campaign about having lots of children
And it's a sort of pro fertility campaign to get the population numbers up
But unfortunately the stock models that they used for this campaign, you may have seen this in the news
Were the two people involved in the distracted boyfriend meme online?
No way
So they were trying to present a couple who were very happily in love with each other
But really we knew the truth
He was a distracted boyfriend and it has no idea what we're talking about
Not on social media, it's not a happy couple
A meme is kind of an image show or video that goes online
Okay
It all goes back to the 1980s
I'll look it up afterwards
So treadmills
Treadmills in terms of animals are always using treadmills
And treadmills were used for animals before they were used for humans even and actually they were really important for horses in farming
They have been for hundreds of years
So in the 19th century especially before things were properly mechanized then farm machinery was basically horse operated
So you had threshing machines which would be these big machines which kind of separated the grain from the corn
And they'd go round and round in one building and the way they'd go round and round is you just have two horses on a treadmill
Trossing along it all day long
They're pushing it
They're operating the mechanism so they're on this treadmill
It's connected to a bunch of pulleys and cogs and stars
And then that's turning the wheels round
It just feels very hard the idea of in a gym pushing a treadmill along with your feet
It is very hard
If the treadmills off for you to push it along
No I was, sorry I was thinking the first proper use for humans of it was in jails obviously back in
Oscar Wilde famously when he was in jail had to do the step treadmill
Which they used to employ to have no purpose other than for hard labor
And Oscar Wilde suffered so much from it he died two years after he got out of jail
Which they think is largely to do with the treadmill
It is quite amazing though isn't it?
It was basically the hardest kind of punishment you could get apart from being killed
For probably about 100 years and now people do it for fun
Yeah
The first, they were massive as well, the Britain treadmills
They started in Brixton, that's what Brixton was famous for 200 years ago
Was having a treadmill which could fit 24 people on it at the same time, so beside
Sorry it was kind of like a game of, did you guys ever play ten green bottles?
No
Did you ever play that?
I know the song, maybe it's not a thing except in my family
Ten green bottles and you all line a bed ten of you
And then one green bottle accidentally falls and you fall out of the bed
Anyway it was kind of like a less fun version of that
We were kind of like ten in the bed and the little one said "Rail over"
Yes, same idea
So this treadmill was like that
These families that you guys just got
Bottles in the bed, I can see where the alcohol is and it's coming from
But the way they would take breaks is the person, nobody would want 12 people on the treadmill or something
And the way you take a break is you'd nudge the guy off who was on the furthest left
And the person to the far right would jump on again and they'd get to walk around the other side of the treadmill
And that would be their sort of a few minutes of break
It would be 60 minutes that you would be and you'd get 12 minutes per 60 minutes of break
Just on horse treadmills quickly
So one of the first ever trains was powered by a horse on a treadmill
What?
Can I just ask why do they have, why are they not horses not just pulling these things
Rather than being on treadmills
So what do you mean the trains?
Yeah, the trains because you don't need a smooth road for the horse
Okay
I mean you do need a rail for the railway
But
Yeah, so
What's that?
Was that an answer?
It's not the best possible answer
I guess your train just can't suddenly just take a left and disappear to someone, some other bit of England
Yeah, that's a really good point
Yeah, exactly, so it's a control thing
Yeah, yeah, good answer now
I never thought I'd say this, but thank God Diane was here for you
So it was called the cyclopad and only two of them were ever built unsurprisingly
And it was at the same time as Stevenson's rocket, which was the train that we did end up using
Was developed, it was in the same set of trials where everyone brought their own train
And they said let's see what works
So I think that Stevenson's rocket went really slow as well
I think though I thought it went at six miles now maybe Stevenson's rocket
So maybe they were really close
But I didn't answer the horses on a treadmill and then what's that powering to make the train move?
It's like your plow thing
But the plow thing stays in one place, which is how that works because the cogs are all attached to it
It's a thrashing machine, so it stays in one place
It's a thrashing machine, so it's in one room
Whereas the train is going to run away from you
And then you're just on a treadmill and the trains at the other end of the field
And it's on the train
Oh my gosh, down to the rescue
That makes perfect sense
Was I doing this exact same thing with boats, didn't they?
With ferries in the 19th century
And these were very popular
They started in 1791 a guy called John Fitch built the first one
And it was basically before ferries were steam-powered
They would look a bit like a catamaran
But with those two shelves on either side
But on those shelves there would be two or three horses on each side
And they would trot along powering this treadmill
Which turned the pedals around
Which turned the paddles round
Which powered the boat
And the only problem with them was that it was a real issue
If the horses on the left side went faster than the horses on the right side
Because your boat just went round and circles
That's amazing
And so there was a study in 2015 that looked at people having treadmills in the office
This is a new thing
So the idea is that sitting down in the office all day is not good for you
So what if you had a treadmill
And it found that people who use a treadmill desk for two hours every day
Had significantly better blood pressure and slept better at night
Which is quite good
Unfortunately they performed worse on almost all aspects of their job
Including the ability to concentrate
And the ability to type
They were substantially slower in all tasks and more error prone
We know someone who does that for their job
They just been fine, haven't they?
Roger Highfield
He was the editor of new scientists for many years
And he used to edit new scientists on a treadmill
And yes, he is no longer there
He works for the science museum now
But yeah, for many years new scientists was edited on a treadmill
You know there's a treadmill for ants?
Is there?
Yeah, scientists have invented a treadmill for ants to test
I don't know, something or other
I don't know
So just a really, really tiny trap
It's a little plastic ball
And you put them on top of the ball
And you have to tether them to a thing above
So they don't wander off
Like mission impossible
They get lowered down
And then they start
And it's the test how they navigate
And where they stop and where they try and find their way
We need to move on in a second
On corruption?
Yeah, quick thing on corruption
In Nepal they have invented some bribe proof trousers
Which they're handing out to all officials
They just don't have any pockets
Okay, it is time for fact number three
And that is my fact, my fact this week is that the late actress
Elizabeth Taylor, who was notorious for always being late
arranged to arrive at her own funeral 15 minutes late
That was in the arrangements that she did with her PA
She said, this is my thing
And I want to make sure that I keep that even in death
Were people pissed off? Did they leave? Were they like when she turned up sort of checking their watches and sying?
Do we know?
I think there was probably everyone knew
This will start 15 minutes late
It's on the sheet
So she was a late one
She was also another thing that she did wrong in her life
Well, she was a shoplifter
Was she?
She was one time shoplifter. She once shoplifted a copy of A.E.H.H.M.A.
a shop she lads from foils
So big time criminal
The reason she did it is because as probably you all know
She's married to Richard Burton twice and Burton boasted her about how good he was at stealing from foils
And so he said, I do this amazing thing, it's so clever
I go into the bookshop and I go up to the till and I buy one book and I get the receipt
And I ostentatiously leave it poking out of the book
And then I pick up six or seven more books on my way out
And because I'm walking out with the receipt poking out with the first, they just assume that I bought them all
And so she thought, I'm gonna fucking try that
And so she stole how I was supposed to drop she had that and Burton was really pissed off with her
And said, why did you bloody well do that?
And then he said that was the last thing she ever stole except husbands
She died in 2011 and when she died the New York Times ran an obituary for her as they would
But it was written by a guy called Mel Gusso who was a theater critic
And he had himself died six years earlier
But it was so good that they ran it anyway
And I think there wasn't many events of her life to update on in those six years late thought
Wait, so he'd written the obituary before she died?
Before she died?
Obviously before he died
Obviously before he died, but...
At the start of the obituary writing process, no one was dead
By the end of publication, everyone involved was dead
I suppose the thing I'm trying to emphasize is that it's interesting people write obituary
Six years before the person whose obituary it is is dead
That's quite common, isn't it?
It does happen, yes
So I was just saying a very obvious fact that we all knew
And that's what's press on
But they didn't...
Well, you had your moment of the son of our ten minutes ago
But he was going to come crashing down
It's always funeral requests
So there are various funeral requests that people have made sort of things they wanted to happen
Heinrich Hein, the writer, he left his estate to his wife
On the condition that she should get married again
And he said, "So there will be at least one man to regret my death"
Ooh, yeah
Slam!
How did he die? Was it with a bread knife in the back?
George Bernard Shaw, he had the best glass request I've ever heard
He left money in his will
And he said, "Right, I'm leaving a parcel of money
And I want it to go towards reforming the English alphabet into one that is phonetic
And has minimum 40 letters, which is the biggest time I imagine to be getting that task from him
He was massively committed to that, wasn't he, his new alphabet, and it did not work
I was reading about Bruce Lee's funeral
Oh yeah, so Bruce Lee obviously he died very young and his funeral, the Paul Barris at his funeral, who carried the coffin
Were Chuck Norris, Steve McQueen, James Coburn, George Laisenby, how cool is that? That is...
Well, I mean, he's the fifth best bond, come on
What?
None of the other four replied to the invitation, hey?
That's embarrassing, quite frankly
He was the best bond
That was very cool
But check this out, so while they were filming, sorry, when Bruce Lee died, they were filming Game of Death
Which eventually became his final movie
But he'd only made about 30 minutes of footage that was usable for the film
And they would largely fight, an iconic fight with Karim Abdul-Jabar, the basketball player, is one of those
He fights a basketball player
Who plays a kung fu guy
Oh I see, he's not just beating up a random basketball player
It seems like plucking low-hanging fruit
I think if you're fighting a basketball player, you mostly go for the low-hanging fruit, don't you?
But so, as a result, they had to scrape around for extra footage to use
And bits of the footage included Bruce Lee's funeral itself
So they used the actual footage to help the plotline go along
How did the help the plotline go along?
I haven't seen the movie yet, there's a suggestion in what I've read that they've actually used
A picture of him passed away in the open casket as well
In the film, yeah, but then for the rest of it, they had a few stunt doubles but they obviously needed his face
So they just had paper cutouts of him, sort of cardboard cutouts that was slightly nudge
So you could see his head moving a bit, and largely the movie is just a cardboard cutout of him
Wow, just on celebrity funerals
Yes
A very famous celebrity funeral back in the day was that of Rudolf Valentino, so the huge silent movie star
He died in 1926 when he was 31, and a hundred thousand people went to his funeral
There were these massive riots outside the funeral parlour, and people were struggling, climbing over each other to get a glimpse of him
It was an open casket, and there were these four guards who looked, there was this claim at the time that Mussolini had sent four fascist guards
And remember, it was 1926, they didn't have the connotations they do now
Four fascist guards to guard
They were widely seen as friendly and good guys, but not nobody
But actually, they'd been hired as actors by the funeral parlour to make it seem more dramatic
And his girlfriend, Valentino's girlfriend, was a woman called Polar Negri, and she really hammed it up
So she fainted on his coffin during the funeral, just fainted on top of it, came round, said the sad thing is he just proposed to me
And therefore I'm actually, he's basically his widow, and then she fainted again
She fainted multiple times, the coffin made this five-day trip from New York to California
And she accompanied it the whole time, just constantly fainting
Dozens of times of five days
Yeah, I read that because there were so many fans going to the casket, they were worried that it might damage the body
And so the people who were in charge of the funeral, there was a company called Campbell's
They put a wax model in its place because they thought that it would get damaged
Wow!
Really?
Wow, something quickly unlateness
So people who are chronically late, according to a new report, have better mental and physical health
They live longer and they're more successful
Hey
Apparently, this is because late people tend to be both optimistic and unrealistic
And having especially an optimistic outlook can give you a better mental health and a better physical health and lower your rate of death
I do find lateness across cultures quite interesting because people get so angry
Because I'm chronically late and I think it's going to shorten my life because it's so anxiety-inducing
But people get so angry about it in our culture
They're like, you're a selfish evil bastard who doesn't care about other people
Guys, guys, yeah
That's why it's in the heat of the moment
But then if you go to Brazil for instance, the culture's completely different
So there was a blog by a writer who lived in Brazil for a few years and she said she was invited to her first party
She turned up about five minutes after the time the party started
And the host was like, she knocked on the door and had to get the host out of the shower
And it was extremely awkward and she sat around for about two hours thinking what's going on
And everyone turned up about three, four hours later
And then she spoke to a professor about it afterwards
And professor said, in Brazil, turning up on time for a party is almost as awkward as turning up to a party
But where you haven't been invited at all, it's a massive faux pas
And they have a thing in Brazil called aura inglesa which means turning up on time
And it means keeping the English hour as any fucking turn up at the aura inglesa
We need to move on to our final fact of the show and that is Andy
My fact is that Mexico has a national championship of double entendres
And it's a big one, so buckle up
And so there was this thing in Mexico called Albert which is a play on words
And it's almost always sexual
And there are lots and lots of different ways that you can make things sound slightly rude
And you combine words to make new meanings or you use words with similar sounds
And they have a competition every year to find the best Albert eros or word playmasters in the country
Can I give you an example of an Alberter?
What is the difference between a chair and an octopus?
The octopus has tentacles and the chair touches backs actually works better in Spanish
No, it doesn't
Because touching backsides or touching bumps is tentaculos
And tentaculos is tent I've really fucked this up
That's great
I don't know if you'd win that championship
It's really intense, so you have...
Someone gives you an Albert and then you have five seconds to come up with another one in return
Playing off what they've said to you or you get knocked out
Like time chest, do you hit like a...
It is like time chest exactly
That's so cool
So for many, many years it was dominated completely by men and then suddenly this one lady, Lordez Ruiz, came along
And she's been the reigning champion for years and years, no one can do anything to outdo her
Yeah, like over 20 years, isn't it?
She's the queen of Albert
Which is amazing because it's a massively male thing, quite misogynistic thing
Women were kind of excluded from it, it's like lots of men making incredibly crude jokes
Like women's expense and yeah, she's penetrated that circle
But yeah, it has quite long history, doesn't it?
This sort of word battles and battles of wits
So there's a thing called "Flighting" which I don't know people know about
But basically this is traditional battles of wits
Which I've been going on since at least the fifth century
And these were basically an exchange of insults
And it was a form of entertainment historically
It was a largely a Scottish thing
And very famous lasted a thousand years from the fifth to the 16th century
So over millennium
And one of the famous "Flighting incidents" that was this event called the "Flighting of Dunbar and Kennedy"
And this is in the 16th century and it was a court-flighting
So it was done for James IV, I think, to entertain him
And it was these two characters insulting each other
And it was the first time anyone ever called someone else a shit
Really?
Surely the first time we have on record
First on record, called a shit without a wit
Oh, that's good
I've got a few more lines from it
So this is one little verse that one person would say
"Gray visaged gallows bird out of your wits gone wild
Loathe some and lousy as wet as a crest
Since you with worship would so feign be styled
Hail Monsignor, your ball of droop below your dress
That's good, isn't it?
There are some other examples of this kind of "Flighting" and "Rap Battle" and kind of stuff like that
So the Iwi people in Ghana, they had a type of poetry called Halo
And again, it's a way of judging disputes
And it's a way of insulting each other
But you said that you had five seconds in this other one
In this one, you have a couple of weeks in between insults
And instead of just kind of coming up with ideas off the top of your head
You actually do actual research into the family history of your enemy
And you look into what their grandparents did and the great grandparents did
And find the best nuggets that you could use against them
Would you go around sort of interviewing their best friends going
Would you say he's a bit of a dick?
I've been looking up in New Endo in general
And so there was a thing about a butcher in Staffordshire
He was asked by this year I think
He was asked by the police to remove signs outside his butcher's shop
Because he said he advertised a big fresh cock
Which is basically a single entendre of this guy's got
And he also offered on a sign the chance to have your rump tenderised before you leave
And the Guardian reported that arguably more offensive was his flagrant use of the green gross as apostrophe
And the police appear unwilling to take action over that
And they had this whole thing about you know in New Endo
So there's a comedian called Stephen Bailey
And it's all about context and who's making the joke
So Stephen Bailey is the stand up who has a lot of explicit material
He's gay himself
And the Guardian reported that Bailey's show contains explicit sexual material
But again it's all about context
The same jokes told by Roy Chubby Brown or the late Bernard Manning
Would sound aggressive
Whereas Bailey's ejaculations are far easier to swallow
Super
So bad
There's a book actually called Away With Words
Which is written by a guy called Joe Birkowitz
And this is basically puns that we're talking about
And he travelled around the world visiting pun contest
And the biggest one is the Oh Henry Panoff in Austin, Texas
Started in 1978 and it's the world championship of punning
And so they have onstage referees during this
And referees can immediately disqualify someone
If they use what they consider subpar wordplay
So I think it has something like that would be you know if you use like
Excellent if you're talking about a normal or something
I imagine that would get boot off stage
What because you're slightly tweaking
No I think it's just like you think that's really shit
That's like not up to the standards
It's like if someone does an on-dram serve or something in tennis
But he said he was going through the best puns he heard in the contest
And sadly for this pun to work you have to know there's a kind of cherry called a Bing cherry
Which I didn't know what kind of cherry a Bing Bing in Chandler Bing
Okay, Bing cherry
He said the best pun he heard was
I went to go shopping for cherries and microphones the other day
But a Bing, but a boom
Yeah
I mean you still did have to explain it before we started
Well the economist did a thing where they said actually some of the best puns
You do have to explain because they're quite complex and layered
And it used the example of the one about Mahatma Gandhi who walked barefoot a lot
And often fasted which led to bad breath
Thus making him a super-calus fragile mystic hex by halitosis
Sometimes it's worth the build up
We're going to have to wrap up very shortly guys
Oh I found a couple of weird fiesters just because this is a Mexican fiester
So they've got incredible fiesters over there
But I did find a British equivalent which I think is one I would like to go to this
There's a Sussex pub called Lewis Arms
And it hosts every year the world P-throwing championships
And the record at the time of recording is 44 metres for throwing a single P
And I think that's amazing
That's incredible, not with your bare arm
Yeah, with your bare arm throwing a P because obviously they're...
There's a lot of air resistances
There's a lot of air resistances, not that they're heavy or hard to throw
But, so the winner, the 2015 winner, Greg Butterworth, he said
"You've got to make sure you pick a P that has few indents because that affects its aerodynamic qualities"
But I think it's really impressive because it's impossible to tell where they land
So that's the real talent in the P-throwing championships
And they have P spotters all the way along the route
Assessing where the P's land
Wow
That's so good
It does not sound like a full-time job
What if the competitors said, "I was the first to throw so I was briefly the world champion"
Although it did not last long but it was nice while it lasted
It's fundamentally failing to understand what being the world champion means
I found a guy who...
Well, I found a competition which is the French PIG squealing championship
And the idea is that you just have to squeal as...
Well, it's kind of on the tin, isn't it? It's a French PIG squealing championship
So you're making the squeal, you're not making a PIG squeal
Yeah, you yourself are making the squeal, so people come up and they start squealing
And there's a guy called Noel Jeanette and he has won it twice
For his excellent PIG squeals, he comes dressed as a PIG as well
It's a sort of really method, very nice
And he's won it twice, he's won twice as well
The international championships for the PIG grunter at the agricultural shows in 2007-2008
And it's a big thing in France, I say it's big, it's not big
There's also the weird festival that I like, championship that I like, is the Naki Sumo Baby Crying Festival in Japan
So I didn't know about this, this is in Tokyo, it takes place in a temple
Although there are other versions around Japan
And the idea is that you bring your baby as a parent, you bring your baby to this festival
And it will get paired up with a Sumo wrestler who tries to make it cry
And the one who makes the baby cry the most is the winner
And the Sumo wrestler, the Sumo wrestler has various tactics, so one thing they might do is they might wear a scary mask
To make the baby cry, although apparently often they just repeatedly shout the word "cry" in its face
Okay, that is it, that is all of our facts, thank you so much for listening
If you would like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast
And we can be found on our Twitter accounts, I'm on @shybeland
Andie
And I do have to wrap
James
@JamesHarkin
And Shazinski
You can email podcast@ky.com
Thank you so much, Birmingham, we'll see you again, goodbye!
[Cheering & Applause]
(upbeat music)