(phone rings)
(speaking foreign language)
(upbeat music)
- Hi, good day, mate.
- Hello, Andy.
- Hi, everybody.
- We've been in this room for, what, three hours now?
- Yeah.
- And you're only just saying hi?
- Yeah, that's right.
(laughing)
- Welcome, everybody, to Drop As Align,
our audience feedback show.
You've been sending in lots of emails,
and we're gonna read out probably 1% of them now,
but the best 1%.
- If you've sent one in that hasn't been read today,
don't lose hope.
- No, but do buck your ideas up.
- Yeah.
- Andy did not like them.
(laughing)
- No, I should say, often we read out emails
and they get onto the show,
but often we read out emails
and we don't have anything funny to say about them.
We just appreciate them, cut them in the edit and move on.
So if you haven't had your email read out on Drop As Align,
it's probable that it's so good, but we failed.
- Are we gonna have a compilation outtake show
of letters that didn't make Jules?
- Because they're a good email
followed by us being not at all funny,
yeah, for like 30 to 40 seconds, and then we, yeah, yeah.
- So it's just you, we're not in it, it's just you.
(laughing)
- Here is an idea for bonus content stuffs,
writes Aaron Michael Reed.
You lot play and commentate on playing board and card games.
He says, "It would be hilarious and very fascinating
"to hear an ongoing live commentary
"on various games being played and reviewed
"through your unique prism of being elves.
"Hope this doesn't qualify me for possibly being dull
"for wanting this."
Regards, Aaron, a board game fan.
- I do very much question the hilarious
and fascinating claims.
(laughing)
- So does Aaron mean a visual?
Like we're on YouTube, we are watching a game
being played out like a game of chess
or a board game like monopoly.
We're playing it and just talking?
- Yeah.
I think it sounds nice.
- Night to D4.
(laughing)
- Is that it?
- Yeah, that's it.
- Okay.
- Maybe we'll play risk or boggle.
- Right.
I think after trying it, I think it could be fun actually.
- Yeah.
- Snakes and ladders.
Something like snakes and ladders
and then just get really into the strategy.
(laughing)
- Okay, thanks.
- Dan's saying thanks.
- I'm saying no thanks.
- There we go.
And Anna's saying but.
- I'll go with the flow.
- Okay, thank you, Aaron.
All right, here's another one.
Indy Carmichael writes,
in your most recent drop as a line,
a listener asked, what were your worst received facts?
I feel you all missed the most obvious ones
through the years.
- Oh, God.
- So here are our worst received facts.
(laughing)
- That's a great idea for you.
- Here we go.
So Anna says Indy.
- Oh, wow.
Thanks for kicking off with me, Indy.
- An underground worker who was blasted through the earth
and meters into the air
by I think compressed gas of some description.
No one believed her despite having a reputable source.
- Yeah.
- Oh, there's still one of the great moments
of the podcast, that story.
- I enjoyed that reception.
I don't take the criticism.
- Okay.
Andy, who could forget the dead frog orgy debacle?
I believe you may have been booed.
I think I have forgotten.
This was in Cardiff at the Glee Club.
I remember strongly because there's a frog
that has sort of necrotic or horrible orgies to breed.
- I remember.
- And it's all--
- And usually you tell the stories
and the audience goes with you, don't they?
- They just didn't.
- They really didn't.
(laughing)
- A conservative crowd, clearly on and off night.
- And they hated it.
They absolutely hated it.
Dan, the airplane loop-de-loop guy who fell out of
and landed back in his plane.
- Didn't you verify that months later?
- Got a great source.
- You got a good source.
- Got a great source for it, yeah.
- Even though it obviously did in the house.
- Go on.
- James, no specific badly received fact springs
to mine for James.
- I like this guy.
- Except, except, says Andy,
I do remember a great deal of tension
over the QWERTY keyboard.
- Oh, that was just me and Anna arguing over
which was better, the Dwarf Jack or the QWERTY.
- Gosh, I don't remember that.
- Sorry, it's--
- I'd like that you have to remind me which side I was on
to make sure that I argue the right side again.
- Actually, I do remember an argument you two had,
James and Anna, over whether the best way to cut tomatoes
was with a normal knife or a bread knife.
- Don't get us started.
- Oh my God.
- I can't remember who was on which side.
- So let me just say, I have adjudicated,
the best way to cut tomatoes is with a bread knife.
I don't know whose side I've taken there.
I've taken Anna's side, there we go.
- And therefore, the logical conclusion
of your argument is that we do not need knives
to have tips because you'd never use them.
James uses the tip to stab his tomato
with a serrated knife.
- I have extremely sharp knives in my house,
so I don't need a bread knife.
- But that means you also don't need the tip to stab it.
- Yeah, that's true.
- What about your bread with just a normal knife?
- I buy pre-sliced bread.
- That's an even better idea.
- Best idea since.
- It does get pretty intense when you three lock horns
in whatever combination.
It never happens with me because I'm like never lump bottom.
I'm just like, I blow myself up
when I'm trying to cast a spell,
but you guys are like Dumbledore and Voldemort.
You've got power.
- I must admit, of all of those arguments,
I hadn't remembered what side I was on for any of that.
- I don't like the reminder me of the tip thing,
which I do remember now.
- Oh yeah, I still got resentment about the knife issue.
- All right, let's go on.
Sam Funk writes.
"My question is potentially some sort of meat."
Or whatever you call the inside baseball questions
that he says.
Do you remember that spicy?
- Spicy meat.
- We should get a little sting made.
That's a good idea.
- Spicy meat, yeah.
- All right, anyway.
- I thought you just used that.
- Yeah, just used that.
- Maybe if you're listening at home,
you can take that little bit of audio
that Andy said, spicy meat,
and then make something amazing.
- Oh yeah, I'll do a clean version now.
Hang on, I didn't get it right the last time.
Spicy meat.
There we go.
- There's someone that's using that to their sex soundtrack.
- No.
- Who is to come now.
- Soundtrack.
- And there's nothing you can do.
- A whole soundtrack, like to a film or something.
- Yeah, you'll see a couple of soundtracks
to get through.
- You just need a single.
You just need one of the old two and a half minute
radio edit single 45s.
- Okay.
It's like all the meat that Sam brings to the table
is actually very vanilla meat, I would say.
- Terrible flavor for meat.
- Do you do the episodes regularly in a weekly schedule?
Yes, we do.
How long do you take to research other people's facts?
- I didn't assign up to this interview.
What's this one?
This is the top 1%.
(laughing)
- I'll be honest.
It was partly just, I love the name Sam Funk.
That is a way of getting a good, you know.
- Yeah, it is.
It's an easy way, isn't it?
It's an easy way.
- About a day for the full four facts.
Do you have a more chaotic approach
where sometimes it's weekly
and sometimes it's several in bulk in quick succession?
- Not usually.
- Touring is bulk.
James will always have pre-researched the entire tour.
I think Andy, you get to like either 100%
or 90% in previous ones.
You and me were on the fly.
- Me and Dan until a minute before we go on stage.
- Yeah, that's true.
Yeah, yeah.
Anyway, hope that helps, Sam.
Lucas Trevino writes,
"As a Michigander," didn't know that was the name.
- No, nice.
- "Your discussion of isolated US highways
reminded me of a Michigan fact.
There is a Michigan State Highway M185
that no cars are allowed on."
- Oh, is it a riddle me this?
- It's a riddle me this.
- Okay.
- Is it technically like a path
that goes through the Lake Michigan?
- Nice, you're thinking creatively.
- Like a fish highway.
- Is it one of those, yeah, animal roads?
- No, that's good, though.
That's very good.
- Is it something that has been called a road
but actually isn't really a road?
- You're getting close.
- Is it, are the vehicles allowed on it?
Is it like a bicycle thing or is it like no vehicles go on it?
It's not that kind of highway.
- Okay, I'm gonna tell you
'cause you've basically got it.
It circles Mackinac Island.
- Oh, yeah.
- Which very few cars are allowed on at all,
except VP Mike Pence a few years back.
Everyone gets around by bike or horse.
So in general, unless you're the Vice President,
no cars are allowed.
- Okay, nice.
- Good riddle.
- Yeah, that was cool.
- Erin Thomas writes,
"I've been listening to old episodes."
- Can I just say this is gonna be a great one
because it's a relatively normal name.
So presumably, I think the Connie may selection.
- You never know.
I might pick a bad email with a normal name.
- This is a little history corner.
Fishery corner.
Old fish is what this new section is called.
- Do this thing.
- Old fish.
Sort of an old timey, you know.
Maybe some lute music on that.
- I think like ♪ Diddle it in ♪
♪ Diddle it in ♪
♪ Did it ♪
♪ Old fish ♪
- That's good.
I've been listening to old episodes of the Fish podcast
and I'm currently at episode 167
when we were all in short trousers.
This is a long time ago.
- James just said,
I'm so sorry, James,
to pick up on this seven years after it went out.
- That's fine.
- That you can no longer get "I can't believe it's not butter"
because they have changed the name.
However, I live in Winnipeg, Canada
and I literally have a container of
"I can't believe it's not butter" in my fridge.
- I can't believe it's "I can't believe that it's not butter".
- How old is it, though?
- Yeah.
- It expired in 1999.
- That's true.
- This is a woman writing in about an episode
from seven years ago.
So we know she craves old things.
- So it could be a very aged container.
- I feel glad to have to know that
because obviously it appears
that it's available in Canada,
although it's certainly not available in the UK.
- That's fair.
- But that's a good bit of knowledge.
I'm happy.
- And it was available here?
- It was, yeah.
- Used to be.
But it's like how in Malta they still have a mother care.
- Yes.
- We just don't have one here.
I think they've got an early learning centre as well.
- I think they've got British home styles as well.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
They've got a lot of old school stuff.
- They do.
- Well, it must be like going back in time.
- It really is.
- That's awesome.
- Yeah.
- Wendy Mabbott writes,
"I have just listened to your latest podcast.
"I am a knitter and know that there are several companies
"available online and I have seen adverts for
"in my knitting magazines that will take your pet hair
"and use it to make yarn."
- Okay.
- That's good.
- The yarn is called, I love this,
Chiangora, which is French for dog.
Chiangora, like Angora.
You can then use the yarn with any knitting pattern
of the same yarn weight.
You don't need to be an artist to do it.
- I think they even, there's an old QI fact,
which is that they bred dogs specifically for
shearing and making stuff out of them.
- I was gonna say, we've got a book behind us somewhere
here in the QI library, which is a book that shows you
how to knit out of your pet's fur.
- Yeah.
- It's like a picture of you with the dog
and then the dog's hair.
- Knitting the dog hair.
- Yeah, knitting which was published by John Metchanson,
formerly QI sort of co-founder.
- Yeah.
- He published that.
- I think that it won the award for weir this title.
- Yes, you're right.
- Amazing.
- You're absolutely right.
Lucy Malcolm.
- Yeah.
- Says, she thinks this is spicy meat,
but she's not certain.
While Anna was on maternity leave,
every episode had Dan, Andy and James with one guest.
Did that mean none of them had any time off
for the whole of Anna's mat leave?
- Yeah.
- She has-
- Largely true.
- I hope this doesn't lead to resentment,
souring relations and eventual breakup.
- Yeah.
- No, we just ended up occasionally did a couple of week,
I think, to make up for that.
- Yeah, we did Soho Theater,
which had this crammed in a couple of weeks.
- But interestingly,
I think we were all three of us were on every episode,
I think.
- I think so.
- You must have been.
- She has a follow-up.
Has there ever been an episode that hasn't had three
of the four main fish on?
- Yes.
- Three?
- Oh, it was two, sorry.
Sorry.
- No, there hasn't been.
So the fewest of the four of us on was an episode
with me, Dan, Greg Jenner and Alex Heddleman.
- Yes.
- Although Anna-
- And there was one with me, Dan, Piz and Justin.
- Yeah.
- Or me and one of you and Piz and Justin.
- I don't remember.
- I think Anna was a fact-checker in that Greg Jenner show.
So you were kind of on the show.
- Interesting.
- Oh my goodness.
James, I think there were times in the very early days,
says Lucy, where there were at least three of you,
but one of you in the fact-checker role,
rather the main fact-deliverer.
- I remember we used to have a fact-checker.
- Yeah.
Whatever happened to them?
Well, we get everything right these days,
at first, don't we?
- She says, I've been mulling this question for a while
and then listened to the recent episode
where Dan was stuck on a train.
Seemed an app time to actually ask it.
- Well, that was the first episode where it was
literally three of you.
- That was crazy.
- Did you get lots of people writing and saying
it was better with three of us?
- Yeah, it doesn't.
It doesn't have people writing.
- I got a lot of DMs about it.
(laughing)
- No, we didn't actually.
We didn't get much.
- Good.
- There was almost no response either way.
- Didn't notice.
- Okay, here's Mick Bremner.
Dan.
- Yeah?
- writes Mick.
"Fishing chips are still wrapped up in newspaper.
It's just that it's never been used or printed on."
- What?
- I know, this is nuts.
I used to work for a company who supplied chip shops
with sundries.
The 12.5 kilo packs of paper are called white news.
- That's great.
- So it's literally the same paper.
- That's fantastic.
- That's really good, 'cause it is actually,
when you get it, it's that exact--
- Crinkly.
- I always thought it was just grease-proof paper.
How is that?
- It's not as crunchy as grease-proof, is it?
It's newspaper.
- That's really interesting.
- Very cool.
- On a no-news day.
(laughing)
- So thank you, Mick.
- That's a really good fact.
- Yeah, it's a really, a very--
- Is it printed by the same company
that prints newspapers then?
Do you think there's a newspaper printing company
that prints a load of news
and then prints loads of blank ones?
- Put it through the printing.
They just put on like a 1000 page word document
with nothing on it and they just print it.
- Oh, no, I've left the header and footer in.
It's got page numbers.
(laughing)
- That's great, thank you, Mick.
- Jill Kendall.
First of all, I just want to say I'm a huge fan
and I listen to the show all the time.
As a fan of the show, I'm sure you will find it
not at all as surprising that I am a bit of a pedant.
I was listening to the June 6th show,
no such thing as the SS Enterprise,
and it came up that Microsoft interviews
would include such questions as,
"Why are manhole covers round?"
This may have been a type of question asked at one time,
but it isn't anymore.
My expertise is that I've worked in tech in Seattle
since 2008.
I've done hundreds of interviews,
both as the interviewer and the interviewee.
I have never worked at Microsoft,
but I have interviewed there twice.
My husband also has worked in tech in Seattle since 2010.
Neither of us have ever been asked a brain teaser question
or asked one.
The reason is that it really doesn't help us determine
if a candidate will be good at software engineering.
(laughing)
- Because you go into Microsoft, of course,
into the coding room and they're all just there
with their manhole covers.
'Cause Jeremy Corbin, of course,
is a big fan of manhole covers.
He knows everything about manhole covers.
- And he's got a big job at Microsoft now, hasn't he?
(laughing)
- He's following Nick Clegg to Facebook,
called me good to Microsoft.
That's great.
So what's being suggested here, that it's all fake?
- Maybe if old mate had got around
to the second round of interviews at Microsoft.
(laughing)
That's one of these questions.
- I feel like it's something that happened
in the very, very early days of Seattle Tech
and probably hasn't happened for 20, 30 years.
- Yeah.
- You've definitely gone out of favor
of that style of question now, I think,
because it's quite, I think it's seen as quite elitist
because maybe I think it favors
your more confident public school.
I feel like I've read something along these lines.
And also it's kind of bollocks that it tells you
anything useful that you need to know
about someone for a job.
- Throw this brick through this window.
You know that one?
- No.
- And then see if they open the window.
- That's right.
The idiot candidate throws the brick through the window.
The coward candidate doesn't.
The successful candidate opens the window
and then throws the brick through it.
- And they get sued by the person who hits.
- Praying a passerby, yeah.
- Has someone told you to get a brick into that room?
- No, no.
For the last question in the interview,
when you've aced it so far,
they whip a cloth off the table beneath it,
a common brick, and they say,
"Throw this brick through that window there, please."
As your final test.
And then they see if you open the window.
- I see.
How many windows do you think had to be repaired?
It's just, I want to get sorry,
the interviewers have been held up.
- I just, we just got to call the.
- Yeah, we've got 20 people to go through
for the end of the day.
- I just threw it through mine directly
at the guy's computer 'cause we were at Microsoft
and when he said, "Throw it at windows."
- There you go.
You got the job.
- Lovely.
- So yeah, I sort of felt like when I said it,
it was like this is a thing that has happened
as opposed to like a current,
I don't even think I thought it was a current day thing.
- No, I don't know.
- There we go.
- It might not have ever happened.
It might be just the kind of thing
that they make up, but I don't know.
- I'm glad if it doesn't happen because all that stuff,
you know that there's you would hear about people saying
they get all the CVs on the table
and they would take the top 20 and chuck them on the floor
and say, "I don't employ unlucky people."
Like that kind of shit.
I'm not into that.
- I actually always liked the idea of the brain teasers
'cause I think really it's one of my strengths
is answering brain teasers.
- Oh yeah.
- And probably my weaknesses is everything else in life.
(laughing)
In a meeting, I think that would be good for me.
- So they're like, "So Mr. Harkin,
"we've got this new code that's coming."
And you're like, "Well, actually, before you get to that."
(laughing)
- A diver is found up a tree.
- Oh, that's great.
We've got a few amazing names.
- Cool.
- Is this another like amazing name, shit emails?
Is this part of that section?
- The other thing, amazing name, shitty email.
- There you go, you have that one, that's great.
Ian Not, quite a good name.
- It's a relatively normal name.
- Right, is that the tone?
- It's with a K and two T's, so like double knotted.
- My old game's teacher was a Mr. Not.
- Maybe some relation.
- Could be, he was brilliant, game's teacher.
- There we go, Ian Not writes.
- Has James kept up his practice?
(laughing)
- It's just a link to someone in New Zealand
who works with penguins.
And she has a double barreled last name.
- He was married to someone from New Zealand, Mr. Not.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
- This is not.
(laughing)
- Ian writes, just stumbled across this
and I'm still blown away.
This woman works with penguins
and her double barreled last name contains not one,
but two birds.
- Yep.
- And she's called Geraldine Gillimott, peacock.
- Whoa.
- That's incredible name.
- She works with penguins.
- That's quite fantastic.
- Gillimott is a very unusual surname.
- I'll say.
- Yeah.
- Also, we've got Laura McCarthy who writes,
I've just found out there's a very talented musician,
the keyboardist and musical director
of Taylor Swift's Eras Tour,
who's called Karina De Piano.
(laughing)
- Good name.
- De Piano.
- That's a real surname.
- Yep.
- Wow.
- De Piano.
And finally, I'm writing to submit myself
for an honorable mention in Andy's list of names
that are sentences.
I say honorable mention because I am not a sentence
but a present perfect continuous tense verb.
- Okay.
- And that is from Ben Cumming.
(laughing)
Childish.
- That's very funny.
- I just read yesterday that the law
that was repealed in the 1950s, I think,
against interracial marriage in America was,
it was the court case,
was loving versus the state of Virginia.
Is that nice?
- That's great.
- 'Cause there was a couple, the loving couple,
Mr. Loving married Mrs. Loving.
- Brilliant.
- And loving couple.
- Loving beat Virginia.
- That's really good.
- That's a great fact.
- Isn't that nice?
- We should write in, Anna.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- That's a really good fact.
- I've seen his filtration system
and it's not making it through.
(laughing)
- We have had a lot of emails from people
who can write, hand write,
because we did handwriting recently.
- Yes, that's right.
- So--
- Yeah, well they say they can hand write
but they've sent you an email.
(laughing)
- That's true.
Leah Denman from Oakland, California
has dear fish team and Andy specifically reading this first.
- Thank you.
- You discuss professions with specific handwriting styles.
In the USA, all architects and civil engineers
typically have a boxy, all caps writing style.
And Leah studied architecture.
And I was in the last class to be required
to learn a standard writing style
for drafting plans using graph paper.
So there is a specific--
- Oh, so because you're writing in graph paper,
'cause you're putting, drawing your houses
or whatever architects do,
you tend to put a letter in each box.
- Exactly that.
- And how interesting.
- And she says I currently work
in the home building industry
and there's a clear divide of handwriting styles
between generations who were taught to draw plans
on paper versus computers.
- Mm.
- They're nuts.
- Yeah.
- Interesting.
- She adds also there's given me a chance
to segue into a thanks but no thanks.
For the fish email inbox,
is there a reason you don't call it the fin box?
No, actually.
- She doesn't come up with anything
that clever at this time.
- Oh, that clever, yeah.
(laughing)
We did that thing ages ago about Meghan Markle
before she was princess.
She was a cursive hand writer for wedding invitations
and she did Robin Thickey's wedding.
(laughing)
- Right, just remember that.
Yeah, that's a really good point.
- You used to write on graph paper
when you remember when you learned to write
and but you weren't good enough
to be left to write freestyle on a line
and you wrote on graph paper.
Do you remember that?
- I don't remember that.
- We never did that.
- Maybe you guys didn't do it.
- But you can surely lined paper does the trick.
As in, what are the vertical lines for that?
- Just to make the size 'cause little squares are smaller.
So technically like the round bit of a B
I think would be in one square.
- One square.
- Yeah, yeah.
- That's clever.
- That was very neat.
And then you get on line paper and it's just chaos.
- Well, while we're on inadequate educational methods,
let's turn to Martha Everett.
(laughing)
She says, "I've just been listening
"to the latest episode in which Anna said,
"we were all taught a script.
"This is not quite true.
"In primary school, my brother and I
"were part of an experiment called emergent writing
"in which children were basically just not taught cursive
"but left to develop our own."
- Okay, so you see the letters printed I suppose
and then you just mimic them however you think is right.
- That's interesting.
- Interesting, yeah.
- She says--
- She's now a literate.
- Well, she says, "I only discovered this as an adult
"when my mum told me and I was furious.
"I only printed for ages
"and I've always had terrible writing.
"And as an adult, I spent a few years laboriously
"teaching myself cursive from the internet."
- Oh, from the internet.
- Yeah.
- Oh my God.
- And now I write and wing big.
(all laughing)
- The email came in in comic sans.
On the one hand, the British education system
has failed me, on the other, such an optimist,
I got to design my own bespoke handwriting.
- Well, in a way, it is, I mean,
obviously it's an experiment on children.
- Yep.
- And it's not done well for them in later life
but we have learned from it.
And no result is still a good result, isn't it?
- Just so, yeah, she says that she finishes
her email, James, exactly like that.
The system was abandoned in the late 80s
as it was discovered after years of testing this method
that not teaching children something
means they don't learn it.
(all laughing)
- That is, like, yeah?
- Children are idiots, conclusion.
- I mean, gosh, yeah.
And then can I tell you one more on this?
- Yeah. - Last one.
- Last one on this.
Eva Hafner, I'm ambidextrous, she says.
- Show off.
- And I've been writing with my left hand
but since childhood I've taught myself
to write with my right hand purely
for the purpose of having a second set of handwriting
to forge my parents' notes for school.
- Right. - That's clever.
- Interesting.
- I used to write left handed as well, actually.
- Did you? - Sometimes, yeah.
I taught myself at uni
just 'cause I used to get a tired hand
so I would swap.
- Get away.
- No, I did and 'cause I taught myself
and I had a lot of time 'cause I was at uni
so it was quite reasonably good
but it would always slant
in exactly the opposite direction.
- Wow. - So can you still, like,
'cause I would be able to begin?
- No, I don't think so. - Really?
- Yeah, it was probably for a couple of years
I could do it relatively well
and then once I stopped practicing I just lost it.
- Gosh. - Wow.
- Could you ever do mirror writing?
- No. - My mum can do mirror writing.
It's very cool. - Yeah, really.
- That's really cool. - Where you write
with one hand and the other at the same time
a reverse image.
- Oh, I didn't know that was what meant.
I thought you just meant writing in,
you know, some kids naturally do mirror writing
when they're learning to write.
They do letters backwards
but she does it at the same time as writing forwards.
Yeah, that's incredible.
- Do you remember when I went to,
did I tell you as this?
When I went to the British Museum
and I saw the notebooks of Leonardo da Vinci.
- Oh, yeah.
- And so I was looking at him for ages
and I was like, oh man, I can't,
I realized why I can't read these.
He wrote in mirror writing.
He always wrote backwards.
No wonder I can't understand.
Failing to remember that it wasn't in English anyway.
(laughing)
But that to me was like, oh yeah,
that's why I'm not getting this covered.
- That's funny.
- There was a president who could write.
- Yeah, James Garfield.
- Garfield in Latin with both hands at the same time.
- Latin with one and Greek with the other.
- That's so impressive.
Eva goes on, she's just a little bit more detail.
So she has completely different
left and right handwriting styles, right?
And she's sent some samples.
She adds, for science, I also deep throated a pen
to send you a sample of my mouth writing.
- Okay.
Okay, so we said that your handwriting,
if you put a pen in your mouth and write it,
it will be similar to your actual handwriting.
So that's why she's referencing here.
- I've forgotten that.
(laughing)
- 'Cause she can write with both hands
at the same time, from right to left.
- That's great.
- Ella Da Vinci, exactly.
And if she repeats this writing a hundred times,
all these handwriting will be distinct and consistent,
except the mouth writing,
I've never tried this before
and I don't want to repeat it either.
- Couldn't she have just used one of those
small election pencils
rather than taking a full pen to the throat?
(laughing)
- I think, yes.
- Was it one of those giant pencils
you get from Blackpool?
(laughing)
- Two more.
Mark Lipsky writes,
"I was listening to episode 527
"where you mentioned someone with the surname POOSE
"and it reminded me of my own experience
"with the surname, with the surname..."
(laughing)
- I had a POOSE on it.
- Here's a photo, you're sincerely Mark.
(laughing)
- Mark says, "I'm a classical musician, brackets.
"It was a struggle to keep my peace during bassoon gate."
(laughing)
- Often, when I'm playing with a particular orchestra
for the first time, I don't know everyone.
There could be 90 people in the ensemble.
Once when we were waiting to go on stage
a few minutes before the concert began,
I was idly reading the playlist
and came across the name Henrietta POOSE.
I found it so funny that I completely coerced
and struggled to stop laughing
as I was going on stage.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Mark continues, "Several years later,
"I was walking in a park
"and noticed that a park bench
"had a little memorial plaque on it
"and it was dedicated to a Mr. Henry Pease."
- That's very good.
- Oh, nice if they married with him.
- "I immediately thought that Mr. Pease
"and Ms. POOSE absolutely need to get married
"and double barrel their surnames,
"except of course that Henry Pease is dead."
(laughing)
- Okay. - Great email.
- Yeah, very good.
- Henry and Henrietta as well, Henrietta POOSE.
- Yeah, I feel like that's part of the nice coincidence.
Wouldn't it be cool, it's such a shame
that you know the room about the brown note
that would always bounce round,
that there's a note you can play
that makes people shit themselves.
- It's such a shame that's not real
'cause if you were in an orchestra with Henrietta POOSE,
you would plot one day before she arrives,
you'd be like, "When she walks in, let's all do it."
(laughing)
And it would be the best moment of your life.
- True, true, true.
- Unfortunately, the thing with the brown note
is it makes everyone poo.
- Yeah. (laughing)
- You can't just direct it straight at Henrietta,
so there would be a bit of a...
- The audience is coming in 10 minutes.
What were you thinking?
(laughing)
- We don't have that many new pairs of black trousers.
Right, everyone's just gonna do the whole gig,
no trousers, all right?
(laughing)
- All right, one last one.
- Yeah. - It's from Matt Duffin.
I saw Andrew wandering through the streets of Soho today
and was, didn't he look handsome?
(laughing)
He was also carrying lots of copies of his book,
which I must say I've read and is a really great read.
- It's okay, James, I told you to stay out of the inbox.
(laughing)
Sorry, fin box.
No, it's just, I saw Andrew wandering
through the streets of Soho today
and was very impressed by the volume of his whistle.
(laughing)
- That's disgusting.
Why were you doing that?
Well, you read so well, I guess.
- I remember walking through Soho whistling jointly.
- What do you whistle?
- At the moment, tequila.
I was whistling tequila the other day.
- Tequila. - By television.
- That's a tough tune. - I know the old one.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Trust me, we're all just fan-sing it.
- Oh, really? - Yeah, yeah.
- It reminded me of a fun fact.
There's a town in South Carolina
where it's illegal to whistle after 11 p.m.
- Is it, though? - Is it?
Maybe.
Maybe. - It'd be.
- Anyway, just, just nice, you know,
let us know if you spot us around.
- Well done, you whistle.
- I'm available for whistling gigs, I'm sorry,
I'm trying to set up. - Are you sure
you didn't see a sexy woman from the 1970s
and that's why you're whistling?
(all laugh)
- You saw Jessica Rabbit walk past.
- Yeah, but just so you know, that's nice, thank you.
- I didn't know you did that, that's--
- What, whistle? - Yeah.
- I whistle a lot.
- I've never heard you whistle.
- I'm the only one on the street normally whistling
and it's a bit annoying to other people around me, I think.
'Cause I do whistle quite loud.
And if you're walking, if you're keeping pace with--
- Not that loud, not like a dinner lady.
Not like he's--
- No, not like summoning a taxi, you know.
I can do that, I bet you can do that, Anna.
I bet you can do the fingers in your mouth.
- Oh, I tried for years.
I just, no, it's too breathy.
But I don't think it's annoying if you walk past it.
I think it's annoying to be in a house with a whistler,
which I--
- Yes, or someone who goes, "Tom Tom Tom Tom Tom Tom Tom."
(all laugh)
- Who was that? - Who was that?
- Or someone you're living with to be.
(all laugh)
- Sometimes, for example, sometimes at a classical concert,
you might end up next to someone who--
- Pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop.
- Really? - Who sort of does a bit
of the music for himself, normally himself, I must say.
- Did I have sheet music to help them?
(all laugh)
- Have you actually sat in the orchestra?
- So rude, this guy next to me had a bassoon
he was playing throughout the concert.
- And no pants.
(all laugh)
- Perfect.
Bye.
(upbeat music)
Please send more emails to podcast@qi.com
and you have a 1% chance, we just get a lot of emails,
you know, I wish we could do more.
I wish we could do these for longer,
but the certain, some people--
- I think we're doing exactly the right amount.
- That's the right amount, I'm sorry.
- Three people, think they go on a bit too long as it is.
(all laugh)
Anyway, but thank you for listening
and please do send us an email, please.
Okay, bye.
- Bye. - Bye.
- Bye.
- All right, nice. - Yeah.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]