[phone rings]
[speaking Japanese]
[music]
Hi!
Hi Andy!
Hello!
Hi everybody!
Hi everyone at home!
Yeah, alright.
Sort of my thing to say.
Yeah, I mean, no, no, no, that's good, yeah.
I just felt like I was excluding
7 billion people
by only saying hi to you.
That's fair.
Well, hi to all of you.
As James said, I don't need to go on
and say that we're hosting...
Can I just say my hi as to everyone at home as well?
I don't want to feel like Anna and I
suddenly were just saying hi to you guys
and you've expressed a hello.
I was.
Okay, Anna has.
That's specifically Andy, yeah.
Okay, well what we're here to do
is to have a session of Drop as a Line,
the audience feedback show
that is now well-established,
and I don't think really needs any
OTOs defining.
You know, screw it.
It's not been cancelled yet, amazingly.
Well, it goes to such a small audience
that really helps.
It's like, it would be like a small newsletter
being cancelled.
You know, it's harder to do.
If no one sees you being
cancelable, then it's hard to know.
But we've had a lot of amazing feedback
since the last time we recorded one of these.
Great.
Some good stuff.
About this show or the main show?
Not about this show.
About the one we're recording now,
they actually say the beginning is awful.
Right, here we go.
Something from...
Well, this is a great thing to start.
This is from someone called Brandy Folk.
A fantastic name.
Very popular over Christmas, I reckon.
Get the Brandy Folk round.
So, I was listening to the episode,
"There is no such thing as a meat cute."
Remember that?
Talked about meat judging.
Okay.
And this actually happened.
My parents met when both of them
were on meat judging teams.
Wow.
My dad at Ohio State,
my mum at Michigan State,
they first met each other
in a meat cooler in Cincinnati, Ohio
for a meat judging competition.
Wow.
They hooked up right after.
Hooked up.
Brilliant.
And have now been married for 33 years.
Isn't that nice?
That's a wonderful story.
That's fantastic.
I know.
And then Brandy adds another fact,
because she's from meat stock.
Yeah.
Another fact is that there is
livestock judging at market shows
where the judge judges the best of the animal
before it is a carcass
and then again after it is a carcass.
Wow.
That was a competition
where you do so well in the first half.
You go to your death thinking,
"I've got this in the back."
Yeah.
Or you do really badly in the first half,
but you go, "It's all right.
I'll make it up in the next round."
A few pittings of wood and corpse.
Yeah.
And now it's time for sudden death.
What?
Oh, my God.
Oh, dear.
So thank you, Brandy.
Very cool.
Great start.
Great anecdote.
Craig Baker writes,
"I was just listening to your recent
episode of Fish One.
I heard you guys discussing pond creation."
Oh, yeah.
"I was surprised."
I love it.
Andy's looking directly at it.
"My parents both met."
Taking a pond.
"I was surprised
not to hear a word about wild boar."
Oh, okay.
"There are 2,600 wild boar living in the UK
and they've been documented by many,
including me."
That's Craig, not me.
Yeah.
"Using their elongated nose bones
to dig out little ponds or wallows."
These wallows are built by the boar
to create places to wash and cool down,
but they also allow habitat and breeding sites
for countless insects and amphibians.
Do you know what?
I didn't know there were so many wild boar in there.
Don't mean either.
I knew they were on the continent,
but I didn't know here.
I'm very skeptical.
I've never seen one.
Except I think I once saw a wild boar carcass.
Again, I don't know what it would have scored
in the context.
Really good though.
But I couldn't tell if it was a badger or a wild boar.
It was either a badger whose hair had all come off
or a boar, and that's the only time.
Those two things are very different sizes.
Actually, when something's been kind of mangled
by various cars running over it,
it's quite hard, I think, to distinguish.
So many of your anecdotes are about,
"I saw these..."
Do you remember?
I saw 50 squashed frogs once.
I saw these moles hanging up dead on a fence, and it's...
Yeah, I remember.
Well, they're quite striking anecdotes, aren't they?
They lead a very sort of primal, earthy life, I think.
Yeah, I come from sort of medieval...
All my stories are about cocktail bars I've been in,
and witnesses of my might have traded.
But they were all when you were living in Stoke Newington,
weren't they?
That's true, yeah.
Okay, here's another one.
This is a new section I've inaugurated,
which is called, "You Said It Wrong."
Oh, no.
Oh, God, pronunciation stuff.
And it's from someone called Don Anthony.
He doesn't specify whether his name is Donald
or whether he's in the mafia.
So...
"Being born raised and still living on the island of..."
Sicily.
Yeah, I was most displeased to hear.
No, Newfoundland, right?
Oh, Newfoundland.
And I don't even know how I'm saying it.
I'm always chuffed to hear reference to my home
or one of my favorite podcasts,
which all happen to be British.
So every time I hear it pronounced,
I respond with the correct pronunciation
as though you could hear me.
The primary issue is that it is pronounced
"Newfoundland" with the emphasis on the land.
Think "Understand" or "Disneyland."
I'm pretty sure that's Newfoundland.
Newfoundland is about you're not stressing the land.
Newfoundland.
I really have to land on the land.
Yeah, but Don says...
Newfoundland.
Don't feel bad about it.
Half of Canada says it wrong.
There's a pleasing thought of Don Anthony
wandering around Newfoundland saying out loud,
"Newfoundland!" as he goes.
The second, possibly more pedantic point, incredible,
is that the province is actually called
Newfoundland and Labrador.
Yeah.
Yes, the two dog breeds.
Yes.
The four.
Yeah, he doesn't specify.
Newfoundland is the island portion of the province
while Labrador is located immediately
to the northwest of the island.
So there you go.
Lovely.
Lovely stuff.
Thank you.
Okay.
Next up is a drop-as-a-line spiral
where it's referring to something
we said on the last drop-as-a-line.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah.
Haven't got a good name for this yet,
but very, very open to suggestions.
Okay.
Think about that.
While you think about that,
think about Kevin Tate's message.
You read a message.
Russian duel,
like a Russian doll.
That's good.
Well done.
But it's duel for drop-as-a-line.
Brilliant.
There we go.
That's it.
I'm going to actually make a little note of that.
You read a message,
Kevin Tate writes,
about roller derby fans
singing the Hot Pockets theme for a player.
She was called --
Yes.
She was called twat rocket.
Twat or twat rocket.
Yeah.
Because we had a long debate
over the pronunciation of twat
and what another hot pocket is.
Well, yeah.
We've been corrected
on one of those two issues.
Okay.
I think a hot pocket
was like a pop tart,
but I think it's slightly different.
James, you prompted
an absolute avalanche
of hot baked goods
into the inbox.
I think it's more like a pizza
that you put between
two slices of paper.
Look, I'm not --
I'm going to read out Kevin's message.
I can't.
I'm not going to steal his thunder.
One correction.
They are not caps lock on.
Pop tarts, caps lock off.
They are microwavable pastries
with fake meat and cheese
that, upon your first bite,
flow out with the searing heat
and destructive force of hot magma.
And then make you regret
having a stomach afterwards.
I wonder what the fake meat is.
Like, why not use meat?
What's a fake meat?
I think --
It is actual meat.
Highly processed.
Just highly processed.
It's a fine word for bad meat.
For multi-meat.
Yeah.
Sounds much better.
What's it called?
Is it called pink slime or something?
Yeah, that's it.
It's the stuff where,
when you're making processed meat,
you scrape it off the sides
of the container.
Okay.
Yeah.
Turn it into meat.
Right.
Which has already been water-blasted
off the body of the --
Yeah.
Anyway, that was the funniest
of the several messages we got
correcting us on the nature of --
I'm sorry.
It's quite all right.
You know what?
I Googled it afterwards
when I was editing,
and I knew I'd got it wrong,
but I thought,
"Surely, even our listeners
will be quibbled off."
I think you got it right.
Oh, interesting.
Well, I mean --
A pop-top has to be sweet in my books.
Yeah, but it's some goo wrapped up
in some carbohydrate.
Like, that's -- and heated.
I mean, that's what we're basically
talking about.
Basic description, yeah.
Would you say a bagel's the same
as a doughnut?
Sorry.
It's the same analogy.
I'm saying a lot of our audiences
in the U.K.
They might not know what a hot
pocket is.
I didn't know what a hot pocket was.
You know, I don't really know
what a pop-top is, to be honest,
but I can clean up a bit closer
to that.
You just go into the shop
and say,
"Do you have any carbohydrates
which are completely surrounding
some kind of goop?"
Yeah.
But I'll let the goop
be made of grouse, please.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Long-time listener,
Thomas Kenney,
writes,
"Wanting to nerd out on a joke
as we're having at the end of
the episode when discussing
cake-o the whale."
Oh, yeah.
Free Willy.
Y'all.
It's funny when you hear cake-o,
because obviously when we were
researching it, it was written
down, and you obviously see it
as K-E-I-K-O, but when you hear
it, I thought we must be doing
a baked goods section, and it
was some cake, you know,
superhero cake-o to the rescue.
How does he or she rescue
people?
By putting, it's people who
are throwing themselves off
buildings, and you always slide
sponge cake underneath.
Lovely.
What, so they can just produce
sponge cake from, like,
Spider-Man's web?
Which RFS does it come from?
So, cake-o's the superhero.
Yeah, cake-o's the superhero.
Oh, sorry, the superhero fan.
Yeah, sponge cake comes out of
all their skin pores.
Oh, okay, so it's a mutation
rather than like a Batman
situation where it's just like
he's rich.
Yeah, he doesn't bring loads
of expensive cake.
Okay.
He's like an X-man,
but also a flower man,
also a butter man.
Yeah.
Jesus.
Do you think cake-o might save
more lives, rather than just
putting bits of cake at the
bottom of buildings where people
have fallen off, then to sort of,
like, I don't know, base himself
in a third-world country and just
feed people with a constant
supply of food.
Oh, with catastrophic sugar
overload.
Just at least just to give them
like...
I mean, yeah, it's kind of...
You can have sugar-free cakes.
We'd actually...
I should have asked.
Sorry for not asking.
Can cake-o produce...
Can he turn up or down the dial
of the nutritious quality of the
cake?
Yeah.
I was thinking he was more on the
bagel side of the donut in its
terms of sugar content.
It's...
Well, the thing about cake-o is
much like the...
Is it the Hulk who doesn't
can't really control when he
turns?
Can't control the kind of cake
that comes out.
So whatever is needed in the
moment, he produces.
I think so.
Produces.
And now it is not to question
how he decides to use it.
So if he's feeding our hungry
people, I'm sure his body would
reduce the sugar content and all
the bad stuff.
Yeah.
I think it's Thomas' email.
That's about whales.
I hear the whale.
Yeah.
I hesitate to pause and
otherwise promising franchises
in his tracks.
Okay.
You all cracked up at Dan for
mentioning cake-o wouldn't be
used to that salted water pool's
altitude, making jokes about the
sea level being the same.
You uno-reversed yourselves.
Amazing.
I learned on your podcast, I'm
pretty sure, because you're the
only fact podcast I listen to,
that sea level isn't the same
everywhere on earth.
K-O.
K-E-I.
Brilliant.
I don't have an answer for that.
I guess that is kind of true.
But the difference isn't enough.
Yeah.
Unless you're very sensitive.
You've got a very sensitive
stomach.
But no, it's a fair point.
Yeah.
Thank you, Thomas.
Thank you.
As you can see, we're all
grappling to come up with a good
answer for it.
We don't.
The real problem is that we can't
think of a good answer for it.
And if we don't answer it
correctly, then we can't use any
of the K-Kos stuff.
Yes.
I think we can answer it
correctly by saying you're
absolutely right, Thomas.
Good point.
And thank you for only listening
to our podcast.
Continue not to listen to any
others.
Yes.
And also, you owe no
proprietary rights to cake-o.
No, absolutely not.
OK.
We come on to the thorny
matter of Chicago.
OK.
BJ Woodstein writes, someone,
Anna, I think, referred to
Chicago being the windy city
because of the weather.
It's true that it's on Lake
Michigan and it can be quite
cold and windy.
Can I just interject now?
No, I don't think.
No, I'm actually doubting you
can.
Can I just?
I'm going to steamroll
forward for a little bit.
Can I just say that the hand
gestures right now around the
table are something.
I'm talking to the hand.
Don't be mad at me.
I need to capture this.
Absolutely.
OK.
We come on to the thorny
matter of Chicago.
OK.
Can you capture this?
As a Chicagoan.
As a Chicagoan, it's not called
the windy city because of the
wind.
It's called it because of the
politicians.
Look, as if QI didn't invent
that fact about series A.
Hand is still up.
Everybody's hand is still up.
But I don't think that's what
you said, though, Anna.
You said it was because of the
wind.
The thing is, it's a
misconception because Chicago
is very windy, famously.
So people think it must be
called the windy city because
of the wind.
OK.
Whereas it's because of the
politicians.
I'd be amazed if I said it was
because of the wind.
I'm pretty sure you did.
Well, call me amazed.
And thank you for the correction.
Well, it's...
Sorry.
Read the email.
They'll explain it more
politely than I have.
B.J. Woodstein has made
exactly those points.
She does also add, actually, in
something that provoked as much
roiling in the inbox as hot
pockets, "Incidentally, as a
woman from Chicago, I don't have
large feet."
Oh, I never said that she did.
I just said that they were famous
in the 19th century for having
big feet.
I know.
Elaine Wiseman, she writes, "I'm
not sure who's reading emails
this week.
It's me, Elaine, as every week.
But please let James know that
in my 28 years of living in and
around Chicago, women with big
feet have never been a thing."
No.
Was she around in the 19th
century?
28 years, can't be.
She's barely around in the
20th century.
So what has happened to the
women of Chicago?
Well, no.
Their feet have shrunk.
Can I add a third email from
Ms. Crisley, who writes, "I'm
sick of these jokes about my
giant feet."
I'm 190 years old.
I grew up near Chicago, and my
whole family has huge feet.
Yes.
I mean, I actually think this is
genuinely interesting, because I
think, like we said on the time,
it's very clear that people in
Chicago won't have above-average
feet, but they did have this
reputation, and if you look in
the newspaper archives, it's all
in there.
But it sounds like they've
migrated to just outside of the
main Chicago area.
Yeah.
Just follow the footprints.
You'll find them.
I was staggered that you didn't
make a Bigfoot joke at the time,
Dan.
Okay.
Are you writing a letter in?
No.
I wouldn't have time to read it.
Dan doesn't joke about Bigfoot.
No.
Sorry.
Just a quick observation about
BJ is that I've only ever heard
people use that as the first two
the way of saying their name in
America.
I can't think of any other -- I
know quite like BJ Novak, the
writer.
Boris Johnson has never been
known as BJ.
No.
It's a good observation.
I'd love to know if there's any
BJs outside of America.
Okay.
Well, if you'd like to --
Dan, Dan, making a call out for
BJs there on the podcast.
You heard it here first.
We're getting closer to that
cancellation line, aren't we?
Mark Tween writes --
That's a fantastic name.
He wrote some young adult novels
about the American South, don't
you?
Yeah.
He's from Cornwall.
He's a big fan of the show.
Club Fish member.
So, hello, Mark, if you're
listening.
I'm writing to you about a point
raised by James in episode 503
in reference to Walk in
Freezers.
I feel like I'm getting a lot
of --
This is positive.
There's no pushback at all.
It's not a criticism, Mark
writes.
It's not spicy meat.
People say that a lot when
they're about to criticize you,
don't they?
That's true.
But it was shit.
No, sorry.
Just some friendly advice that
may help anyone that finds
themselves trapped in a freezer.
Okay.
I am a calibration engineer.
A nerdy job in itself.
And one of the things I
often calibrate is a walk-in
freezer.
As James correctly stated,
these do have a button on the
inside for opening the door.
In the episode, James recalls a
story from a butcher who said a
large black pudding is the best
thing to use as a battering
ram.
Yes.
My boss once got trapped in a
walk-in freezer and the emergency
button failed.
Uh-oh.
He didn't have large pieces of
frozen meat to hand.
What about a large Swiss roll?
I'll give it to him by Keiko.
Where's he produced that from?
No, it's a family-friendly
comment.
Is it?
Okay.
It is, yeah.
Well, I love this.
So instead, my boss wrapped his
hands around the freezer
temperature sensor.
Most industrial freezers have
an alarm that will sound when
the temperature gets too high.
His hands warmed the sensor
enough to raise the alarm and
someone came to the freezer and
opened the door.
That is quite amazing.
That's brilliant, isn't it?
Another tip, because your hands
might get too cold.
It might not work.
Try internal, because your
internal temperature will stay
high longer than your hand
temperature.
Sorry, what do you mean?
Like, sort of climb nude on top
of the temperature sensor?
I haven't worked out all the
details.
But if...
Yeah.
Or if you like fish one of your
organs out and plant it on top
of it.
But that's a great fact.
That is unbelievable.
Really good.
Really like that.
So thank you, Mark.
Dr Alexander Mayer, associate
professor of classical studies
at the University of Western
Ontario.
Does it listen?
It has blocked your
non-listener of the week.
I'm a long-time listener of
the podcast.
I think I've heard all 506
episodes.
Right.
And a professor of classical
studies in Canada.
For 20 years, I've been
involved in excavations and
research at Vindolanda Roman
Fort on Hadrian's Wall.
Oh!
In June of 2022, you mentioned
we had found a stone on the
site that had an enormous
carved phallus.
Oh, yeah.
And the inscription's
secondenous cacor.
Oh, yes.
It was the poor or the shitter
or something.
Anyway, yeah.
Yeah.
In the process, you mentioned
the researchers who published
the press release about it.
Well, as it happens, I am one
of those researchers.
And therefore, you came just
two words from fulfilling a
dream of mine, namely being
mentioned on your show.
Oh.
Turns out, you now have
another chance.
The print version of the full
article that my colleagues,
Alex Mullen and Eunice Van
Halle, and I wrote about it,
just came out in a recent
volume of the Journal of
Britannia.
I thought you might like to
follow up.
Just mentioned my name this
time, eh?
[LAUGHTER]
What was that person?
Actually, never mind.
I've said it before.
[LAUGHTER]
That was an incredible person
to write in.
Very excited.
I feel a bit starstruck.
We get the great and the good
in the inbox.
We do.
I've got one more thing for
you.
Oh, yeah.
Do you remember we had this
story about the cost of beans
in 1996 being minus 2p?
Oh, yes.
Yeah.
So Fraser Johnson writes,
"This isn't really a factor
search, but I wanted to share
a story from a few years back.
I had a part-time job at
Sainsbury's when I was in
college, 2000 and 2001.
I, along with numerous other
colleagues, cottoned on to a
glitch within the checkout
system, where if an item was
part of a multi-buy deal, but
was also reduced due to its
shelf life, the item's full
price would be deducted from
your shopping bill.
So if a $1.99 pizza was on
Buy, 1, Get, 1, Free, and then
reduced to 1.50, you could buy
2 for 99p because the till
would add 2.98 to the bill, but
still deduct 1.99, basically.
So, right.
There's a good loophole there.
Sainsbury were not really
concerned because the offers
were funded by the suppliers
anyway.
I'd be amazed if they could
make a massive loss based on
the quite limited selection of
stuff.
Well, listen on, Anna.
No, I'm not captivated then.
Obviously, this resulted in
some epic bargains, but none
better than when on New Year's
Eve 2000, I discovered that, as
the store was closed the
following day, a large quantity
of avocados had been reduced to
just 10p each, and they were
Buy, 1, Get, 1, Free.
They were originally 69p.
I walked out at the end of my
shift, fully armed for New Year's
Festivities with a bottle of
vodka, some party poppers, 20
Marlborough, some king-size
Risler, and various nibbles, as
well as 104 avocados.
For the princely sum of 9p,
what?
That's so good.
Isn't that great?
Was that on New Year's Eve 2000?
I wonder if that was New Year's
Eve without the Millennium.
That was it.
That was how you spent the
Millennium.
Isn't that great?
Imagine ending the thousand
years of mankind with that.
Incredible.
So thank you, Fraser.
What a great bargain.
You're all skeptical when I said
I've got a good story about a
bargain.
Best story I've ever heard.
Can I quickly, because we were
talking about beans, so that
episode Anne Miller was on, so
Anne messaged me because she's
gotten a few droppers of lines
herself about that episode, and
she said there were three sizes
of Heinz beans containers.
She was a bean expert, and we
went into quite a lot of detail
about the number of sizes of
beans, but apparently she'd
missed a fourth size of bean.
And yeah, she's been getting
messages about that.
Apparently there were four sizes
of Heinz beans containers.
There are two smaller tins around
here in various supermarkets,
plus the big size, plus the
snack pots, says someone to Anne
by text message, which she sent
me.
So she would like to, she's not
here to defend herself, she would
like to apologize to any bean
aficionados out there who were
offended by her lack of bean
knowledge.
Did you talk about flicking beans
on the episode?
Yeah, but I only in the very literal
sense.
We did get an email from a satchel
saying, "Sorry, can I just explain,
oh Dad, you should explain what
happened."
Yeah, I was, and I know what this
is going to be, and I have a
response prepared written for me.
Why is everyone pre-delivering
their responses?
No, I didn't know you were going
to bring this up.
It's someone, someone wrote to me
about it.
So I met Greg Wallace, who's the
master chef guy, he's one of the
guys on there, and he randomly
walked up to me and just said,
"Do you want to hear a bean fact?"
I just didn't know who I was.
I thought he must have known I was
on fish.
Nothing.
And then he said that there's a
laser at the factories where if
they see that there's an abnormal
bean, they'll shoot a laser at it
and flick the bean off.
That is the story.
And so Greg Wallace was like,
"They have a literal bean flicker."
Yeah.
And there's, I believe, a rude
meaning to that phrase.
Yeah.
Sasha writes, "Sitting here, having
just finished the episode, in stunned
amazement, that in a piece where the
phrases 'flick the bean' and 'bean
flicker' were used, nobody commented
on the generally accepted usage of
those phrases.
It feels like there's no such thing
as official equivalent of Ronaldo
not scoring an open goal."
You guys need a new segment and
drop us a line.
Mr. Sitter.
I think perhaps it was more like
Ronaldo got to the goal.
He thought, "You know what?
I've shown that I can do this."
Yeah.
Probably don't.
We're already winning 5-0.
Yeah.
Sometimes when we say something
that's so obviously rude and we're
saying it, a look goes around and
we continue the chat because we
think, "Who's going to go there?
Do we need to go there?
No, let's just keep going on."
Yeah.
You can't see our eyes.
At that point, there was a look
where it was, "No, it's too
smarty.
Let's just carry on."
Fair enough.
Too smarty.
We're flattering ourselves there.
The truth is...
No, just sometimes.
No, it's not that it's too smarty.
We've never ever rejected anything
because it's too smarty.
Be honest with ourselves.
It's because we can't think of the
funny thing to say.
It's like seeing the open goal and
tripping over the ball.
Sometimes something's so obvious.
You're like, "Oh, I can't make it
funnier than that phrase."
This is Anna's internal process.
It doesn't apply to all of us,
we should say.
I thought it was funny enough as it
was.
I didn't need it.
Having listened to it, I agree.
That's what I mean.
It's like you're going to derail the
conversation to make some kind of...
There is a possibility.
Oh, we would never derail a
conversation.
Not always.
We have to hold our bags.
Who's that out of the window?
It's Keiko.
I think we could possibly in the
future invent something where we
get like eyeballs and you can have
them in your room while you're
listening to the podcast, but they're
attached to our own eyeballs.
So the eyeballs in your room move in
the same way that our eyeballs are
actually moving when we're doing the
show.
Interesting.
So it gives you an extra experience.
And you can see us.
You can see just the eyeballs, not the
rest of the face.
They knew.
The thing we've been doing when we
filmed clips of this show, you'd like
us to really focus in on just our
eyes.
Well, I was reading the other day that
John Dalton, who named Daltonism,
which is colourblindness, he gave his
eyes to the Museum of Science and
Industry, and they are there.
You can just see the eyes.
James is offering to donate his own
eyes to one lucky listener who wants
to have nightmares for the rest of
their lives.
Thanks, everybody.
Please keep writing in to
podcast@qi.com with your emails.
You've been hearing other people's
emails, unless you were featured in
this show, but send in your own.
Can I just say something quickly?
So just to talk about the elephant in
the room, if you only ever came to
Club Fish because you didn't like the
adverts, you can now go to BBC Sounds
and get the podcast with no adverts
for free.
You are allowed to do that.
That would be absolutely fine.
But you would miss this absolute
gold dust of bonus material.
Yeah.
You want to miss this outro to a
show?
I don't think so.
Can I do the BBC Sounds version
rather than come here every week?
Yeah.
No, we love it.
No, we love you guys being here.
And thank you so much for subscribing
to Club Fish.
It really means a lot to us to have
this community, but we just want to
say, yeah, that option is open to
you.
Yeah.
But don't take it.
Don't do it.
But you can.
But don't.
We'll see you.
Wherever you are.
Brilliant.
Bye.
[Music]
(upbeat music)