(upbeat music)
- Hey Club Fish members, how you doing?
It's Dan here.
Hope you're well, welcome to your bonus bit of content.
This is a compilation episode that we have for you today,
all the best bits that didn't make it into the main episode
largely 'cause they just didn't fit the narrative.
So hope you enjoy it, but before we get to it,
just a quick reminder, if you happen to be in Sheffield,
we're gonna be there doing Fish Live
at the Crossed Wires Festival.
Alice Levine put together this awesome podcast festival.
There's gonna be multiple shows down there.
So if you're around on the 6th of July,
we're gonna be there from 2 p.m. recording a live show.
Do come along, it's gonna be lots of fun.
Tickets are available at crossedwires.live
or you can go to nosuchthingasaffish.com
and just find all the relevant links there.
Okay, that's it, let's get to the main episode now.
Here we go, the best of the bits that didn't make it.
On with the show.
(funky music)
Hi everybody, Andy here.
Welcome to an audience fact special episode
of no such thing as a fish.
You have all been sending your thanks to podcast@QI.com.
Is that the address?
- That's the address.
- I'm gonna say every week, so I hope so.
- Well, they've been getting through
and they've been coming in second first.
And we've creamed off the ones on the top
and we're gonna be reading them out
and sharing them back with you.
- It's harder than it looks, isn't it Andy?
- It's a very difficult job.
- Damn, this is amazing.
Mother of the year.
- Do you wanna mention who else is here?
- Where are we as well?
And how often does this podcast go out?
- God.
- Can I tell you one last thing about the boss for us?
- Yeah.
I was standing to an opal and how it was defended.
There's one weakness in a naval sense.
There's a waterway which is calm and navigable.
And basically, if you could sail your ships in there.
- Oh, like a harbour.
- Yeah, you could invade.
And it would be incredibly easy to invade.
So how did Constantinople, as it was then,
solve this problem?
- Cannons.
- Great idea.
Arguably better than what they came up with.
- Look at dials.
- Look at those, good call.
- That's good.
- What do you do about the chain of the golden horn?
- Okay.
- They had a massive chain just across the water.
- Yep.
- Like a rope barrier outside of nightclub.
- Oh, you did this work though.
- Even to actually, I'm being unfair.
It worked better than you'd think it would.
It's about half a mile long.
Just this huge chain across the water
and then they can lower it if someone approaches
who's friendly and then what?
- You can get up again.
- There were quite common those things, I think.
- Okay.
- Yeah, I've heard of them before.
- I heard of one, this is in like British history
but there was one of them somewhere where someone was in a boat
and they went in the boat towards this chain
and they're gonna hit it and what happened was everyone
on the boat ran to the back of the boat
so it lifted the front of it, so they went over it
and then everyone ran to the front.
- Exactly.
- So all you know, that's like a hurrieder to story
if I ever heard of one.
- I think it is a story, like Harman were it's from.
- Good.
- That's great.
- There was a report in Scientific American in 1858
about a healthy person called Mr. Groove
but he was born without a sternum or a breastbone
and so you could see completely clearly his heart
and part of his lungs, so it was just a thin layer
of skin around it.
And so he'd be exhibited in theatres around Europe
for a few years in intellectuals
because it really helped doctors know
about the structure of the heart and how it beat
'cause he'd literally stand at the front of a lecture hall
and you'd be sitting at the back
and you could see his heart bum bumming,
bouncing out of his chest.
- 'Cause he didn't grow properly.
He was--
- Wow, good stuff.
- Wow.
- It wasn't grew the name of the guy from this pickable me.
- Yeah.
- So did he have this and then he thought he was so exceptional
that he decided to take over the world with his minions.
- And that's what that's based on.
- Yes.
- There we go.
- Did he have ribs?
- And if so, where did they meet?
- I think maybe the ribs didn't meet, no breastbone.
- It feels like they wouldn't meet.
- Yeah.
- They just sort of stop.
- Big holes.
- He had muscles between your ribs, so he would stay in place.
- Right.
- Yeah.
- It wouldn't be good like my daughter likes to jump on my chest.
That wouldn't be good.
- Oh, yeah.
- I'll start them at that.
- Yeah.
- And if he coughed or sneeze, then there's long,
really bounced out of his chest.
- Oh.
- You really see his lung.
- And if he really fancied someone like Jessica Rabbit
walking past his heart, really.
So I popped out of his chest.
- There was actually a really sad study about which bits
of their lives people would skip.
Like if they could say skip a head five minutes
for about 10 minutes and it found that people would skip
a huge proportion of it.
Obviously, because most of your life is just drudgery.
If we could skip to the end of this, guys, we would, wouldn't we?
- Well, people listening can just fast-forward to the end.
(laughing)
- If only we could.
- Accessory breasts.
That's another thing.
- Accessory.
- Okay, so you know the classic total recall
three-booped lady, three boobs is a thing.
But like Andy's saying, you might not know where to find it.
So it's quite possible that you have three lactating breasts,
but in the image that I saw, which to be fair, was a drawing,
a lady was breastfeeding her child
and then five feeding her other child
because the breast had creased.
- Was this something real?
- Yes.
- This is it from what are your mangoes?
(laughing)
- Herodic mango is unparalleled in this hemisphere.
- Same Jerome was a famous translator.
- Really?
- Not through like audio.
He translated the Bible into the Vulgate.
And what he did was he took the sort of Hebrew Bible
and then he put it into Latin.
But he put it into a way that everyone could understand.
So he changed some of the words that maybe you shouldn't have done.
So there was a, in fact a Greek word, which was maskia,
which meant like Messiah.
And he changed it to Christos, meaning anointed.
But actually the more reasonable way of translating that
would be 'unctus', meaning anointed.
And that is why we call Jesus Christ, Jesus Christ
because of that translation.
- Oh wow, so we should call him 'unctus'.
- Jesus-unct.
- Jesus-unct, yeah.
'Buntiano Ronaldo' should be like anyone called Christian
or anything like that should be 'uncty' under at least.
- He is quite an oily man right now, exactly.
But it's not amazing like one little bit of translation
can change so much in history.
- Yeah, when we get Christopher from as well, isn't it?
- Yeah, Christian, everything.
- So 'unct', 'unct', 'unct', for example. - Oh.
(laughing)
- The untuffer, untuffer. - Yeah.
- The only thing I know about St. Jerome is that he apparently told,
I think this is in the realms of maybe, tree, maybe not, tree.
He told nuns not to eat beans because he thought the flatulence
that they would produce is so close to the...
- Stainerist, dangerous, theorotic.
- That they might induce orgasms accidentally
off the tickling sensation of the fart.
So he said, "Tony beans nuns."
And went back to translating the Bible.
(laughing)
- There's a story told by John Sessions on QI
in one of the early series that you guys might remember,
which I always love.
And I actually don't like, I think his author,
but he's been told by someone else.
He was told by Gandhi himself probably.
That was what I'm assuming, but basically in the scene,
so there are 300,000 extras, as you say,
and Richard Attenborough's the director.
And the person who's organizing all the extras
in the whole scene is this other guy called David Tomlin,
who's overseeing this funeral scene.
So Gandhi's just died, and Attenborough says to Tomlin,
you've got to tell these 300,000 extras how they're gonna behave.
And Gandhi's just died their hero,
like the ultimate icon of their country.
This is the worst news they've ever heard.
They're devastated, their lives have fallen apart
from all the ray eyes.
Can you possibly convey to them how they have to act?
So David Tomlin just turned down to this crowd and said,
"Right, listen up, Gandhi's dead, and you're all fucking sad."
(laughing)
- Wow, that was very good.
- So there are three bridges now, I think,
spanning the boss for us and built it various different times.
But the 1973 one, the first one was the game changer.
In 1960s, you had to wait two and a half hours to cross,
I think by car, but it was just so clogged.
And then for vans and lorries, it was days you had to wait to cross,
on by boat, before the bridge had happened.
- Oh yeah.
- And I listened to this amazing interview with Harvey Binney,
who is one of the architects, British guy.
He's retired now, obviously, because it was a long time ago.
And he was interviewed by the BBC,
and here's a good riddle of me this.
- Oh, okay, come on.
- The distance between the tops of the two towers,
'cause this is a suspension bridge.
It's got two towers spanning a little bit,
is different at the top and at the bottom.
- Riddle me this.
- Sorry, so as a new take the top,
and then you go straight down that pole to the bottom.
- Those towers are not straight.
- Well, they are straight.
- Oh, is it the curvature of the earth?
- The earth is not straight.
- That was right, what I said.
- Yeah, okay.
- Because they had to build both towers absolutely straight,
but it's such a distance apart,
that if you build them both straight,
the curvature of the earth comes in a way.
And it's about 10 centimeters different at the top.
- Who's it?
- We did have to take that into account,
because you don't want to end up with 10 centimeters of cable.
- Can you get to the other one?
- It's long, but it's not that long.
- The earth doesn't feel that curved, does it?
- I know, the earth is more curved than you'd think.
- The earth is a lot more curved than dumb things.
- Oh yeah.
(all laughing)
- Oh, me too, okay, now on the go.
- We're just constantly losing giant containers
off the back of ships.
- Why don't I pick it?
You'd want to fish them out as you was in each one.
- You would, right?
- You could be a container of baked beans,
a container of barbies.
- That is a fun format for a TV show.
- How does it work, sorry?
- They already do this.
- Well, it's a team of celebrities.
- But there is one of these that exists,
but it's on land, right?
Where you go into containers and you open them up.
- That's it, it's an American show.
And you take an all-containing unit
that's not being claimed, or it's run out,
and they haven't paid their rent and so on.
- Yeah, that doesn't, that doesn't,
I don't love this show.
- And a load of experts can look inside,
but they can't, they can't go in,
they can't open anything up.
So you just have to bid an amount for it,
based on what, you know, what is it called?
- Nothing wrong with liking a really good show, you know?
As a storage wall, storage wall.
- Can I just say if the producers of storage was
our listening and they want a celebrity to come on,
then Dan is available.
- I am available.
- It's my house, isn't it?
I'll send you in this little rowing boat
to the middle of the Pacific Ocean to find a container.
- The thing about heartbeats is
some people can hear their own heartbeats better than others.
And this is called empty reception.
And it's the ability to interpret signals
from inside your body.
- I'm so hoping you don't say this means
I'm going to die prematurely,
because I hear my heartbeats so loudly all the time.
- You're more likely to report having anxiety
if you do that, and you're more likely to,
if your heartbeats changes slightly,
to think it's something to be worried about,
whereas actually normally,
people's heartbeats do change quite a lot throughout
the cost of a day.
And actually the best thing is to have a medium,
you want to sometimes hear it a little bit,
but not be obsessed with it, basically.
- So are you concerned about it sometimes, Anna?
- No, I don't get concerned.
It keeps me awake sometimes,
'cause you lie down on your pillow,
you can always hear it in your ear.
- So do you hear it internally,
or can you hear it outwardly?
- Hear it out, what, like,
hear it pretty much gets my shoulder hurt.
- Yeah, can you, no.
That's physically, I mean,
can you hear the noise?
- You're not a cartoon character, aren't you?
Could your husband hear the noise,
or is it through your inner ear?
- I've never asked him,
but I snore so loudly that I think it would cover
your like the, you know, the telltale heart
by a gorilla heart.
- Oh yeah.
- You're like that, your whole life.
- I am.
Hang on, what is the heart tell?
It beats it so much.
- It's he's murdered somewhere.
- He's murdered, he's murdered the old man.
Oh, it happens right away.
It's sort of straight away,
he kills the old man,
'cause he's got this weird eye.
The old man has a weird eye,
the guy hates that this old man has this weird eye,
and he gets obsessed with it,
and he decides, well, I'm not gonna have to kill the old man,
but I mean, I think I just live in the same building
or something, it's always his landlord or something,
but he kills him.
And then he buries one of the floorboards,
and he keeps hearing his heart beat,
and some people come around to investigate.
We've heard there's been an old man murdered.
- Boom, boom.
- And yeah, boom, boom.
He's like, can you not hear that?
- No, I don't know.
- No, I was gonna hear it.
(laughing)
- I was actually looking up,
'cause I was thinking I like eel in Japanese restaurants,
which is the only context I've really had it,
but obviously it used to be a huge thing.
It was mostly in London and Cockney's
and everyone ate jelly deal, right?
You'd have pie, mash, and eel shops, or whatever.
- That's right.
- I was wondering, was it nice?
And honestly, I've been through so many forums
where people were reminiscing about using it
and not a single person has said it wasn't disgusting.
- And that's presumably, if you're posting on those forums,
you're kind of nostalgic or buffer.
- Exactly.
- I would think is the prime territory.
- You're desperate to say,
"Oh, it was better in the good old days."
(laughing)
- It was rank, I thought.
After Brexit, I thought we were gonna get it back.
- Did you?
- Yeah, that was the Sunlit Uplands
that I was looking for.
- That's what you voted for, wasn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Prick that the jelly deal.
- No, actually Brexit has stuffed the eel thing.
- Oh, no.
- I'm so sorry, it has.
- Wasted voters.
- I'm sure you guys are familiar with the Sustainable eel group.
Basically, we used to ship 10 million eels a year to Europe.
Legally, this isn't traffic.
And more than half of that was for rewilding.
'Cause if you get an eel swimming into the Seven Astray,
it's screwed, right?
It's like, it can't get up the Seven Astray
to a spawning ground.
The river is too blocked up.
But there are loads of places in Europe
where you can introduce Neil.
It'll swim up, it'll find a cracking place to spawn, whatever.
And you've done a great job there.
But Brexit has ruined it.
- 'Cause they can't fill in the paperwork and stuff.
- It's good.
- Yeah, they can't fill in the paperwork.
But it basically tried barriers.
- Yeah, it's a bit of a pain.
- Does your heart really go blah, blah, blah?
Does it just go blah, blah?
And you've just heard the blah, blah, blah in movies.
- Or is it an echo?
Is the--
- Oh, oh.
- If you've got a very hollow body.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- The hollow head.
- I'm just testing now.
- It does go blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
- Does it?
- Sometimes I'm only using really hard, I think.
- I can only hear the, at the moment,
I can only hear the boom.
- Yeah.
- Well, you're using your pulse.
- You're not listening to your--
- But it's like, for instance, if you listen--
- But what do you think the, what do you think the heart is?
- Well, I think the heart, I, the boom,
I associate with heart, not with my pulse.
I know that you can feel the pulse,
but you can't say, oh, I can hear my heart
by touching your veins on your wrist.
- Yeah.
- It's like, this is all got a bit stoner,
but go on James.
- Right back, well, I doubt I will, but it's like with a clock, you know,
clock ticks, but it doesn't talk.
It just goes tick, tick, tick, because it's the same mechanism
doing it all the time.
But if you're, if you listen to it, you can almost hear a talk
even though there's not one there because you're expecting it.
- I was playing it cool by agreeing with you,
but I absolutely thought there was a talk.
- Go in every clock.
They'd entered two different tones, just before.
- I thought the pendulum, yeah, I assumed for years and years
when the pendulum goes one way, that makes a tick sound.
And then, I don't know, inside the glass cabinet, there's something
which makes it sound a bit different going the other way.
- It's weird that you still got that pendulum watch.
- There is a different kind of eel,
which does a similar-ish thing.
It's called a snake eel.
And they have a very pointy tip on their tail.
And they use it in a slightly different way.
They use it just to power out of the stomach of the fish,
which has eaten the sideways.
I mean, they just go out of the stomach.
- Oh, like here's it.
- They just pierce it.
They just go through.
- Well, that sounds not very good for the fish.
It's not good for anyone, because they can't get through
the ribcage once they're through the stomach.
So they just end up stuck in there.
- That's like a blooper from the alien movies.
(laughing)
The alien's like, "I'm stuck, we're gonna have to do this again."
- Yeah, and the fish doesn't even notice.
Fish can cope with a lot of stuff.
- Something piercing a big hole in its stomach
and then landing up squirming around at its ribcage.
- Okay, I don't know whether they don't notice,
but they definitely don't take any action.
- They play cool.
- Yeah, good on 'em.
- Oh, if you eat muscles as a human,
you put them in the pot and it's boiling water.
- They often come back out, don't they?
- Oh, okay.
- Pricing onto it.
- But you're not supposed to eat the clothes ones
'cause they might come out.
- Yeah.
- Well, that is actually true if you're a sea an enemy.
If you eat a muscle and it's closed,
then the muscle can just go through your body
and come out the other end and the muscle will still be fine.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
Whereas normally what they'll do
is they'll bring in the muscle and the shell
and then they'll eat the muscle and eject the shell,
but if it's closed, they can't get us
to the muscle.
- Do the enemies and enemies eat the whole thing
and then to sort it out inside?
'Cause that's a more dignified way of eating, I think.
- Yeah.
- Now, if you could do that with a lobster.
- If you could do that with a big mac
and you put in the entire burger and the plastic
that goes round it.
- With a plastic on the trees.
- Oh, if you could, yeah.
(laughing)
- Or if you could do it with a kinder egg
and then you could eat the whole thing
and you could even make the tie inside you.
- I love that.
(laughing)
- There's a little mechanical women on those.
50% of eel consumed on the planet is eaten in Japan.
- It's big.
- And if you go to a Japanese restaurant,
they'll always have, they have eel on the menu.
But the nice news is that 35% of Japanese people
are willing to eat cultured eel.
- What eel that goes to the theatre?
- That's right.
- Yeah, yeah.
It costs more because obviously you've seen the price
of the restaurant these days.
(laughing)
- No, you can't.
It's saturated laden is, it light Hamilton.
It doesn't love it.
It wasn't five stars.
But no, it's like, you can grow really good eel now.
You know, the art of it, like growing meats
which are of different varieties.
The eel you can get now is really, really nice.
- We're at like fake eel.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Oh, really?
- It looks like it, it tastes like it, all of that, you know?
So that might be quite good.
- And how many Japanese people are willing to eat that?
- Over a third.
- That's good figures.
That's much better than like,
proportions of American people who are willing to eat fake meat.
I suspect cultured meat.
- Yeah, but we all say we're willing to eat kangaroo
testicles until we're actually on.
I'm a celebrity, give me out here.
(laughing)
And then, you know what I'm saying?
- You're right.
- Alfred Hitchcock was terrified of eggs had over phobia.
So he said, the white round thing without any holes.
That's how we refer it to eggs.
And when you break it inside, there's that yellow thing
round without any holes.
So I think he likes holes and he doesn't like eggs.
- Did he like ping pong balls?
- Yeah, I don't know.
He's no mention on ping pong balls,
but what's interesting is his favorite breakfast
was quiche Lorraine and he used to make it himself.
- What?
- Yeah, so he would have to deal with his phobia
until the egg no longer resembled an egg.
And then he was fine with it.
- Stick hole in it.
- Stick hole in it, yeah.
- So that says to me, wasn't that serious?
Was it if he's still making his own quiche Lorraine?
- No, 'cause I think it's a sort of,
you face your fears and then it goes quite quickly
once you get the fear.
For him it was the shape and the lack of hole.
- No, no, I know, but if I like,
I don't like a house spider.
And I can't just like go and kill a house spider really fast
and be like, well, it was really quick,
so it doesn't matter.
- I see, yeah.
- 'Cause I can't go near it.
- The other day I met a house spider fell on me
as I was sitting up in bed from the ceiling.
And it was, it was a bit--
- It told me this before I didn't enjoy the story
at the time, I'm not enjoying it now.
- It was a four-incher.
- I don't like it.
- And I was shirtless.
- That's not four-inchers for you.
(all laughing)
- So low-albender, right?
If you haven't already covered this,
I'd like you to know that some US banks
have their own zip code.
- Oh, nice.
- It's cool, isn't it?
- Okay.
- And then they write, I came across this
because for reasons unknown to me, meetup.com
defaulted to that zip code.
But I'm in and then they give their own zip code.
(all laughing)
- Which is?
- Well, I think this might be a call for help, really.
- Yeah.
- What's meetup.com?
- Well, it sounds like a dating site.
- It does, doesn't it?
- And it then sounds like he's trying to give his address
on the podcast, or she, or they.
So I wonder if this is just a trick to try and get some
- Yeah.
- Fistless.
- Three meetups.
- Are we being cat-fished?
- Brilliant.
- Right now.
- Wait, I'm so confused.
So this person went on a dating site
and ended up accidentally booking in a date with a bank.
(all laughing)
Went to meet the date, had put misleading pictures up
of a not bank, and then arrived in it with a bank.
- No, it's better.
- Come over and make a deposit.
I bet the innuendo is going to be,
what's the safe word?
There we go.
- Yep, there we go.
- I'm good, yeah, yeah.
- Put 'em up.
(all laughing)
- This is a stick-up.
- I make the same mistake every week when we do this,
and then I go home, and I get sushi
for the thing next to the station,
you know, which comes with soy sauce and wasabi.
But it's always rammed the train.
So I squeeze in, and then you have to get the chopsticks out
and you have to open the soy sauce,
and you have to open the soy sauce.
And it goes just everywhere.
- And you have to ask someone to hold your fingerball,
and it's, you had to take your shoes off as well.
It's like that.
- But you know when you started,
you're like, people would think I've given up
if I don't keep going.
So I'm always covered in soy sauce and it's stink.
- I don't think people think about you that much.
I don't mean to offend,
but just most people are busy with their own stuff.
They're not gonna think that woman's only,
"I want to stop eating her sushi half."
- What's going on?
- Oh, what?
- She's the top-podcast that I'm at.
- Shinski eating half a sushi.
(all laughing)
- She's quit, isn't she?
She's turned.
That was to finish it.
- Why don't you go and eat the other half?
(all laughing)
- You used to hurt dinner.
- Oh shit, I missed my start.
(all laughing)
- It was worth it.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that after Chernobyl,
nearby children were tweeted.
And they taught, they taught.
We're putting that in there.
- Good.
- Someone sent us a tweet this morning, actually,
Sean Gibson, and it was referring to,
it's just a headline from the Intelligencie Journal
in Pennsylvania from 1913,
Self-Rising Bed exceeds expectations
and throws inventor out of the window.
(all laughing)
No more information given.
- Brilliant, I need it.
- The thing that you have always done back up since I was tiny
is you drink some water upside down.
- Yeah, that all of that stuff is rubbish.
- No, it works.
- No, it doesn't.
- It's just a distraction, Tony.
- It's been proven to be all rubbish.
- It works for me.
- No, it doesn't.
- You're still hiccuping.
(all laughing)
You've been doing it all day.
- No, not.
- My headline thanks this week is from Jeffrey Partica
or Partica or Parti Car.
- Partica, yeah.
- Partica, yeah, it's possible.
- Remember when we went to Dublin,
and we got in a Partica.
- Yeah, that was cool.
- That was cool.
- That was the taxi.
- Unintentionally, we didn't know.
- I don't remember that.
- We got a taxi home from a gig,
and then the guy just pressed a button,
and all the lights start going off,
and there's like a disco ball,
and they started playing music.
- It just went thundersly disco,
like-- - They always do that in taxis for me.
- It's very cool.
- All right, yeah.
- What do you don't remember?
(laughing)
- Electric heels are not a type of heel.
- Are they not?
- No, they don't seem they were.
- They're just an electric fish that's very long.
But I thought I'd read about them anyway.
There's this absolutely hero called Ken Catania,
who's worked out what it feels like to be attacked
by an electric heel,
and he says that being attacked by a large electric heel
is like being tazered by nine tazers at the same time.
- Well, what he did was he stuck his tank arm
into a tank with a small eel.
- I did it 10 times,
and he reckons because he knows how electric heels work.
You could just extrapolate from the small eel
to the size of a normal eel.
So if you get bitten by a small electric heel,
it's about the same as touching a horse fence.
- Okay.
- Do you know what that's like?
- I do, actually, yeah.
- Yeah, 'cause you like to steal horses, don't you?
- I do, I do, I use to raise on the podcast,
but yeah, my horse rusted that.
- You've touched an electrified horse fence.
- Yeah, well, 'cause you know, when you're a kid,
we used to line up,
so one of you touched the fence,
and then everyone holds onto the other one shoulders,
and then you--
- Okay, so it's a bit of a shock, it's not a shock.
- It's quite a shock.
- Hang on, if you're holding it normally,
does it not shock you at all because you're earthed
with your rubber shoes or other?
- No, the earth thing is the problem, right?
'Cause it goes through your body together.
- Oh, sorry.
- So you're not wearing your big wellies at this point?
- No, no, the whole point is to shock you
and your all your friends in a line.
Anyway, electric heels work.
He says, but he hasn't actually had the bulls
to sting himself with a proper big one.
- No, because actually if you're tazered by nine tazers,
you have properly get it die.
- Yeah.
- Oh, good idea, very nice.
(laughing)
- And one interesting thing is that they use their electricity
for electro-location so they can,
a bit like so now, they can kind of fire their electric field
around and then feel where everything is.
So 'cause it's so dark and muddy down there,
and that's how they can see where everything is.
But the sensors that they use, it's not exactly the same,
but it's very, very similar principles
to how your mobile phone works.
So you know how there's sensors in there
that kind of can tell that your fingers there
and it's all about capacitors and blah, blah, blah,
I'm not gonna go into it now,
but it's basically the same technology
as electric heels used to find the way around.
- Do you see?
You've got all your clever computers
and all your internet in the old days,
we got around just with ill tech.
(laughing)
And we jelly him up at the end of the day.
It was absolutely horrible.
(laughing)
I was, isn't it weird that when you have a bisectomy
and then you produce semen?
What would you think that looks like?
'Cause you know when you think about, you picture semen.
- Yeah.
- And you think that that's--
- I can't picture anything in my head,
but I'm not, not even gonna try this one.
- It probably looks absolutely identical.
Yeah, maybe, or just a bit more watery.
- That's what I would have thought it looks more watery.
- It looks like more transparent, maybe.
- Maybe it doesn't have those green bits there.
(laughing)
- It's just...
- We still got the chunky cheesy bits, right?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- It's a different shoe they need to color, James.
- It's not, it's doesn't sparkle.
(laughing)
- Well, in a way, it doesn't sparkle.
- It doesn't sink.
It doesn't make that weird singing sound.
(laughing)
- It's not weird.
- There's some screaming here, so they go.
- Don't do it.
- You're right around.
(laughing)
- I go to Val Halag.
- We'll fight them on the beach.
- So Anna, Anna, come on.
- Tell them more, I wanted to assist his name.
- Where did you want it to go?
- Where?
- 'Cause you want it to go.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, doki.
Hope you enjoyed that compilation.
If you wanna get in contact with any of us
about the things that we said on this episode,
why not write to us at podcast@ky.com
and we will cherry pick some of the best emails
that you've sent in about this
and the main episodes and use them
in a future drop us a line episode.
All right, clubfish members, that is it.
Take care, we will see you soon.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)