(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of No Such Things as a Fish.
It is our summer audience facts special.
So we're gonna be going through all of our mail bag
to find the best facts that you have sent in.
Because right now Dan, we're not in the office, are we?
- No, we are on the road.
We are doing our 10 year anniversary tour Thunder Nerds.
We've already done one in Bristol.
We're on our way to Dublin to do our next one.
And man, what amazing gigs.
- Yeah, it's absolutely incredible.
It's always amazing to do these shows
because there are so many dorky, nerdy, geeky people
out there, we absolutely love it.
We feel like we're in our element.
And the shows themselves have been so much fun.
We've been doing quizzes.
People have been sending in their best facts.
We've met some incredible people, Dan.
- Yeah, so we've set up for this tour,
the Hall of Fame, where we're inducting a new person
who's appeared as one of the facts in our show,
and we get them coming live on stage.
But James, Anna and Andy don't know who they are.
I've been bringing them secretly in.
We have had the descendant of Confucius on stage with us.
We have had the Asparamancer,
the person who predicts all of the future political situations
using Asparagus, aka Mystic Veg.
She was there in Bristol.
We've had the co-writer of Fatberg, The Musical.
I have very exciting ones lined up for Dublin
and for Glasgow, as well as Cardiff, London and Manchester.
I am so excited for these things.
It's an amazing night.
- Have you got anyone for Newcastle?
You didn't mention Newcastle?
- Oh, I do. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Newcastle might be the best.
- Oh, wow. Okay.
Well, if you are in any of those aforementioned towns,
then make sure you come to the show.
There are still tickets available for all of them.
I think there might be a London show that's sold out,
but we did put on a new show.
So the tickets are available and you can get them
by going to know6thingsafish.com/live.
Okay, Dan, we got a flight to get.
- We do. So let's get onto it.
You guys get your tickets.
We'll see you there at the live show.
Come say hi afterwards when we take photos with everyone.
It's a great night.
See you there.
But for now, enjoy the audience fact show.
- Hello and welcome to No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI officers in Hoban.
My name is Andrew Hunter Murray.
I'm here with Dan Shriver, James Arkin and Anna Tajinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with your favorite facts from the last three months.
That's right. It's our summer audience fact special.
You've been emailing your facts in to podcast@QI.com.
We've caught a few of the very best ones
and we're going to be serving them back to you today.
Here we go, starting with James.
- Okay. Well, the first one that I've got
on my big pile of facts is from Glenn Matthews
and Glenn writes to rival the Eiffel Tower.
One suggestion for the Chicago World's Fair
was a 200 person bungee.
- Cool.
On the same but extremely strong bungee rope.
- No, no, all different bungee ropes.
This is from a book called The Devil in the White City
by Eric Larson, which Glenn read.
And he has lots of other amazing things
that you could have instead of an Eiffel Tower
to celebrate your city.
In this case, Chicago.
- Hang on, tourist go every moment of every day
to see the Eiffel Tower.
If you were truly going to rival it,
you would need 200 bungee jumpers
doing that every second of the day.
- What's wrong with that?
- There's nothing wrong with that.
I just want to, I just want to make sure.
- You could do it like not every second,
but you could do it every half an hour, say, right?
- Yeah.
- I remember staying in a hotel in Las Vegas
and there was a bungee jump place on the top of the hotel
and just you would open your window at the morning.
And you'd be like, oh, what a beauty.
And then there'd just be a guy
sort of plummeting past your window.
- If you checked in late at night
and you didn't know that was happening.
Oh my God, someone's, oh no, cancel it.
No, he's going back up.
He must have changed his mind.
Didn't when we stayed in New Zealand
on our first fish tour there was,
the hotel was having a special--
- That big tower in Auckland, whatever it's called.
- Yeah.
- I don't remember.
- Yeah, they do bungee off there as well.
- It's all they do in New Zealand, isn't it?
- It's having been.
People bungee jump all the time, it's everywhere.
- Yeah.
- Quite a lot in Australia, but New Zealand,
it's just New Zealand and Lord of the Rings tourists.
- This is your weirdest stereotype.
I've never heard of that.
- It's not a stereotype.
In New Zealand, there's a different legal thing
and it's to do with the insurance
that you get for extreme sports.
And I think the government might cover some of it,
which means that it's much easier to set up
an extreme sports thing in New Zealand
than it is anywhere else in the world.
- Wow.
- I see, that's why, I thought we're just into it.
So it's not a tax break.
It's not tax deductible.
- It's not tax breaks so much as you don't,
it costs you less to do it.
And it, you're-
- How would that work?
- If you're cost any bungeeing, you don't pay any tax.
- Yeah, you're sitting with your accountant and they say,
"God, you've really gone over the threshold this year,
but good news, Mrs. Saunders.
You can do 76 bungee jumps."
- Your investments can go down and up and down and up.
So yeah, what do you think we could have?
- Let's say for instance, in London,
we wanted a new tower to rival the Eiffel Tower.
They did actually come up with some ideas, didn't they?
But what do you think would be a good thing to have?
- I guess the London Eye was meant to be that, right?
- Kind of.
Well, actually the London Eye was supposed to be temporary,
I think.
- Okay, what about this?
The London Ear.
- Oh yeah.
- Right?
- Oh yes.
- So, keep going.
- Well, it's a huge ear.
Like the London Eye looks like a big eye, sort of.
And you can, if you go in it,
you can hear sounds from all over London.
- Oh, that's nice.
- So it's not an amazing view.
It's an amazing sound.
- And every day, those people from Gladiators
uses one of their massive Pugel Sticks to clean it.
- Exactly, yeah.
- Yeah, okay, that's a good idea.
- Well, you'd want to be able to hear something, right?
So maybe you need another ear set up over in Paris.
So it's like one of the, you know, when you go to--
- Like a telephone.
- Kind of like a telephone.
But in, no, in China, in the summer palace,
I seem to remember that you would go to either end
of the palace and they would have somehow
that you would whisper to the ball
and you could hear--
- Like you have in Playgrounds,
you often have other endpoints of Playgrounds,
those things you talk into that never work.
- There was also one of those at Grand Central Station
in New York, Whispering Gallery.
And also it's--
- It's a good intro, yeah.
- So that's a good idea, thank you.
- Jenga Tower.
- Everyone plays.
Every Londoner gets to play
and you just have to insert a brick each.
And then the person who causes it to come out.
- Oh, no, it's removing the brick.
- That's not how it works.
(laughing)
- Now that's spoiling every game of Jenga.
- She's bringing bricks.
We've been playing this game of Jenga for hours,
but don't understand.
(laughing)
Great, well come on, James.
- Oh, yes. - What did they propose?
- Sorry.
- Was this Chicago?
- This was for the World's Fair in Chicago, yeah.
So J.B. McComber thought you could get a massive tower,
which is much bigger than the Eiffel Tower,
10 times the size of the Eiffel Tower.
And you would put rails from the top,
going all the way to New York, Boston,
and Baltimore, which you can toboggan down to get home.
It's a great idea.
- Hang on, you toboggan all the way from Chicago
to one of these.
That's gonna be a long toboggan commute, isn't it?
- Well, the gradient is gonna be quite unexciting,
I would guess.
- Yeah, it's a green run.
- Oh, but it has to be enough.
It has to be enough that you can toboggan.
- You know, when you go in a water slide
and there's not enough water and there's not enough gradient,
you just have to pull yourself along on your butt.
- Terrifying.
- Like a dog with worms.
You have to do that for 400 miles.
He said in his proposal,
"As the cost of the tower and its slides
"is of secondary importance, I do not mention it here,
"but will furnish figures upon application."
- Beautiful.
- Yeah.
- Should I do another fact?
- Yeah, yeah, let's have one.
- This one is from Suleiman Ilias Charrette,
and he said that he recently learned
that since Biden dropped out of the presidential race,
this will be the first U.S. election since 1976
that doesn't have a Bush, a Clinton,
or a Biden on the ticket.
- Cool.
- Including vice president.
- What?
- And he said, "I even checked it myself
"because I didn't believe it
"and then gave us a Wikipedia link,
"which admittedly I didn't check,
"but I thought it would be bullsy to put that link in there
"if it didn't prove his point."
- Biden's not a great inclusion.
Biden just is a normal president who--
- But he thinks he comes the last three,
'cause he did vice president for two terms.
- Oh, it includes VPs.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So Bush is the running mate of Reagan.
- God, that's weird.
- Do you wanna hear facts about presidential names?
'Cause I thought I'd find one myself
after having read this.
Do you know what Grover Cleveland's nickname was?
- Rover Cleveland.
- Yeah?
- 'Cause he liked to go for a long walk and--
- Oh, yeah, no, it's not that.
- Drover Cleveland, because he would herd
his sheep across America.
(laughing)
- Any more rhymes of Grover you wanna go?
- I'm working on it.
- Should I tell you?
- Yes.
- Well, two, you can have two options.
One is Big Steve.
(laughing)
- Yep.
- Isn't that a great nickname for Grover Cleveland?
- Big Steve, was Steve even a name then?
- Well, believe it or not,
it was Grover Cleveland's first name
because Grover was another nickname that he had.
- Oh, was it?
- He was actually called Stephen.
- Steve Cleveland.
- But as in, I'm surprised that Steve,
of course, Stephen has been a name forever and ever,
but Steve, you don't get a lot of Steve's popping up
in Dickens or in--
- Yeah, but he's American,
and it's a very American name.
- It is now, but again--
- Stephen Fry has this whole thing,
that his American adventure,
he so nearly moved to America when he was a kid,
and he pictures this whole world where he was Steve Fry,
'cause that's the name he would have undoubtedly had.
It's such a, yeah.
- I don't know.
Edith Water and Henry James aren't mentioning many Steve's.
I don't think, but I don't know.
- If you're called Steve and you're 150 years old,
right here.
- Okay, let's do a few more facts.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Mandarin writes in,
and she writes in with some nominative determinism.
- Lovely.
- Arthur Owen Blessit is a traveling Christian preacher
who is known for carrying a cross
through every nation in the world.
- Lovely.
- Every nation.
- That's very impressive.
- There's usually all 193 of them.
- He must have been in Roy when South Sea Darm was founded.
- Yes, whenever there's a new one,
he must be like, oh, for God's sake,
picks up his cross.
- Do we know if he takes a position on places like Taiwan?
- Or Macau.
- Or Micronations, yeah.
- I don't know that.
- Has he visited all those tiresome former oil rigs
off the edge of the British coast?
- Yeah.
- All right, some praters said, oh, this is Steve Land.
All the utopian failed areas.
- I could just imagine other going to him going,
so Arthur, bless it.
Have you been to Germany?
And he's like, fuck.
(all laughing)
- Have you been to Blackadder?
- Yeah.
- And we got one more bit of nominative determinism
from Nathan Dwyer.
He said that Scottish poet, Ivor Cutler,
kept a set of ivory cutlery in his home.
(all laughing)
- No, it's fair enough.
- Probably a lot of people did, didn't they?
- Yeah, he's also a comedy writer.
- Exactly.
- Is he?
- Oh.
- Ivor Cutler, he's a poet, isn't he?
- Yeah.
- Who writes comics.
- I didn't know anything about Ivor Cutler,
but he sounds great.
- He was a friend of the Beatles.
- Oh, okay.
- He was in--
- Sounds like a euphemism there.
- Friend of the Beatles.
- I don't know what for, but.
- He was in the magical mystery tour.
- Oh, okay.
- Where he played a bus conductor called Buster Blood Vessel,
which is where the pop star from Bad Manors gets his name.
- I don't know about that.
- We've gone down a train
that I have not been able to follow.
- We're actually on a bus right now.
(all laughing)
Do you guys remember when I visited the man
with maybe the biggest collection of cutlery
in private hands in the world?
- Yes, not only that, but this just shows
where the hierarchy lay back in those days.
You visited him 'cause you did the original QI research
and you picked up all the cutlery,
and then once we were done with it,
I had to schlep there to take it all back to him.
(all laughing)
- I didn't even know that we'd bothered returning it.
- You wouldn't have, Andy.
You were on to your next project.
(all laughing)
- That was the 11th series of QI
'cause it was the K series.
- Yes.
- What series have we on now, 22 or three?
So you've been carrying around that grudge
for how many years?
- I'm so glad I've got it off my chest.
- The wording, it felt like you've practiced it in the mirror.
It felt like this has been something
you've been ready to get off your chest.
I'm very excited.
So you did that.
You took his cutlery and then you just didn't think
he might want this back?
- No, I probably said something like,
oh, someone sort this out.
- Some fucking idiot.
(all laughing)
- He would never have said that to a colleague
but I'd say, can we get one of the juniors to sort this out?
(all laughing)
James, give us another fact.
- So Lowell Bender writes,
"If you haven't already covered this,
"I'd like you to know that some US banks
"have their own zip code."
- Ah, nice.
- That's cool, isn't it?
Lots of buildings actually have their own zip codes
in America and in fact,
the shoe floor of Sacs on Fifth Avenue
has its own zip code.
- The one floor of a building.
- One floor that sells shoes.
- Ironic because shoes are one item of clothing
that rarely has zips.
(all laughing)
- There speaks a woman unacquainted with high fashion.
- Yep.
(all laughing)
- Auntie and Dad are both wearing their knee-high boots today.
- So many shoes have zips.
- I mean, they're not most.
I think most shoes would have lace.
- Go into a leather shop and you'll see a lot of zips.
- Do leather shoes have zips?
- High heel, female high heel boots.
Beetle-like boots.
- No, you're right.
It's not as ironic as I let everyone to believe
'cause some shoes do have zips.
What's something that never has zips?
Hats, if it was a hat shop, it would be--
- Oh, well, well, contrary to that.
(all laughing)
Lifts off his top hat to show a fully zipped trilby.
Yes, so the zip code of the shoe shop
was created as a one-off partnership
between Sacs and USPS.
- I feel very mucky about that.
- I'm not sure about that.
It's like when, so sometimes the London Underground Stations
will do a humorous collaboration
with a big mega-corp company
and they'll change the name of the station for the day
to Bond James Bond Street.
- Oh, yeah.
- Or something, if there's a James Bond film out to play.
I don't know if they've done that,
but I just think it must be really confusing
for people who are just trying to get around London
if you're a tourist, maybe you're not familiar with it.
- What do you think you turned up to Bond Street Station,
which is on Bond Street?
And you see it's called James Bond Street.
Oh, it must be somewhere else.
- That's a bad example, that's a bad example.
- Yeah, I just got back from Turkey, right?
And I was at the immigration desk, handed my passport in
and the guy behind it, he looked at my passport
and he went out and he looked at me and he went,
"Mr. Bond."
And then he laughed and said,
"I bet you get that all the time."
And I laughed going, "Yeah."
And I was going, "I've never had that in my life."
And then I realized it's because my middle name is Craig.
So I am Daniel Craig on my passports.
- I actually get it quite regularly, I must say.
- You get James Bond.
- James Bond because I'm called James.
Like I've definitely had it at least twice
going through immigration in Russia, for instance.
And I've had it in a few other countries as well.
- Really? - Yeah, yeah.
It's really weird.
- That's so weird, 'cause there are other famous James's.
- Yeah, but I was carrying a revolver and having sex
with a woman and drinking a martini at the time.
- While we're on Russia and also kind of on trains,
I read a thing which I wonder if you know
the Russian word for train, is it like Vox?
How would you spell it?
- Vaxal means Vaxal is train station.
- Yeah, and the story goes a bunch of Russian engineers
came over to the UK that went to Vauxhall Tube
and they were like, "This is so good,
"we'll just go back and name everything after it."
- It was the Vauxhall Overground Station, I think,
which was really ornate at the time.
I don't know if it still has ever been there for four months.
- I wouldn't, if I had to read for one word
to describe Vauxhall, I would not describe it as ornate.
It's very functional.
- Really, 'cause almost all train stations
are quite beautiful, so Vauxhall hasn't managed
to achieve that, but mind you,
it's probably they're probably going
for that Soviet aesthetic, which often isn't ornate.
- Although, in fairness, Russian train stations
are pretty beautiful, generally speaking.
And the underground especially, the undergrounds
tend to be huge bolts with very ornate artwork
and stuff on them.
- Oh, Vauxhall Underground is the eighth wonder of the world.
Oh yeah, it's--
- Can I do one more?
Robbie Garman writes about mushrooms.
He's found a phrase on a website,
"If it smells spermatozoic, eat it.
"If not, you'll probably die."
- All right, wait.
I need a reminder of what that smell is.
- No, no, no, no, I don't think you do.
- What's the deal?
All mushrooms that smell like sperm are safe.
- No, it's a very specific mushroom called the miller.
I don't know if anyone's told our colleague Ann Miller
about this, but it can look very much
like the deadly poisonous fool's funnel.
And apparently the best way to tell
whether your mushroom is a miller
or a poisonous fool's funnel is to sniff it.
And in most polite books, it says it smells like raw dough,
but actually scientific places says it smells spermatozoic.
- Well, if someone's just wanked off
on a fool's funnel-- - Anna.
- It's a great point. - It's a good question.
- It's a good question.
- It's not worth the risk, I think.
- It's not.
- It's possible.
- Wow.
- We're about to be told, like, God,
we've got bad news about your weird fetish.
You thought it was all innocent.
You're out in the fields making all mushrooms.
You've killed 50 people.
- You're under arrest.
- Okay, it's now time for fact number two,
and that is the facts that have been sent to Anna.
- My headline fact this week is from Geoffrey Partaker.
He said, "My fact is that every March,
"the US has a 50% increase in vasectomies
"so that men can spend their recovery time
"watching the men's college basketball tournament."
- Mm, that's superb.
- It is, and it seems to have been a very clever bit of PR
from the vasectomy industry,
because this is known as March Madness in America,
and it's where--
- The basketball.
- The basketball, yes.
And it's where all college basketball teams play each other,
and it's all done very intensively like a knockout tournament,
all happens in the same three-week space.
So ideal for recovery time.
I mean, actually it only takes about six hours
to recover from a vasectomy,
so this is a lot of malingering men on their phones.
- It couldn't be a botched one.
- It could be, but they always ask for the botched ones.
- I was talking to the comedian John Bishop
about vasectomies, and he had one,
and he was telling me that on the day,
'cause you're awake when you have it right,
but they go in, so they sort of cut open the ball sack,
and you've got to go into each testicle with a tube.
So Dr. does the first one, and he's laying there,
and he's sort of like, it's very weird sensation,
he's very aware of it, gets the second testicle,
and the doctor says,
"Do you mind we have a student doctor who's in today
"who would be interested to--
- His big punch run.
(all laughing)
- Can he keep one of your circles, is that all right?
You won't be using it.
- So he says, "Yeah, the student doctor goes in,
"and gives it a cut,
"and then all he hears next is, 'Oh, no.'"
And the doctor says, "What have you done?"
And suddenly there's a bit of a crisis moment
where he sees his testicle being lifted out and so on,
and he's, "Oh, what is going on?"
It was a total botched job, and they managed to fix it,
they sewed him up, so you can get botched,
even when you're famous comedians.
- Especially when, I would have thought,
if you go in as a student doctor,
and it's Judy Dench there who's vasectomy or performing,
which I know is unlikely, but--
- So when they're advertising these vasectomies--
- Yes.
- So you can watch "Basketball,"
do they say it'll give you a free shot?
- Brilliant.
- As in you can have sex without having kids.
- They should, they advertise it as vas-madness.
- When they call it "Vasketball," that's very good.
- I'm sure that's in the press releases.
- Okay, if not, you're welcome.
- Yeah.
- America.
- Why don't they get a key fuzz to do the address?
(all laughing)
- I mean, they might be already doing it.
- I'm sure he is.
- You're welcome.
(all laughing)
- Anyway, this guy sounds great, actually, Jeffrey.
He said, "I wanted to link this fact with information
"regarding frozen pea sales in America,
"because that's a solution often for men
"who don't have an ice pack,
"but there was no public information breakdown
"of monthly sales of frozen peas.
"So I've tended a letter to the U.S. Department of Agriculture
"about this deficiency."
And--
(all laughing)
- Wow.
- He also says, "I feel it should be noted
"that I left the mushy pea jokes to the professionals
"despite the low-hanging fruit."
There we go.
- Yeah, he didn't give us the low-hanging fruit jokes.
(all laughing)
- Jumped in with that one.
- Well, thank you, Jeffrey.
- Lovely.
- This is a great little fact from Robin.
"During World War II,
"the German city of Konstanz actually kept its lights on
"so that pilots flying overhead
"would think they were still over Switzerland."
(all laughing)
- So clever.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Must just be closer to the Swiss border.
- It's very, very--
- In Lake Konstanz, yeah.
- I've been to Lake Konstanz.
- Have you? - Yeah.
- Nice.
Did it have its lights on?
- It was daytime, so they were cleverly--
- So you just bonded anyway.
(all laughing)
- Nice, so yeah.
- Very cool.
- I think I was on the Swiss side of Lake Konstanz.
- Yeah, me too, actually.
- Interesting.
- Funny you didn't bump into each other.
- It was at different times.
- You don't know that.
- I do.
We have not allowed to take holidays at the same time
anymore. - No, that's true.
- In case you're both killed at the same time.
- Yeah.
- No, that is really cool.
And I can't remember why I was looking this up,
but oh, in fact, it was one of my facts.
It was about Royal Albert Hall.
During the Blitz, or maybe it was in the First World War,
but whatever it was, they would put over massive curtains
over the top of it.
And it was the same stuff as they would use to black it out
whenever they showed movies.
But they would put it all the way over the--
- That's so cool.
- Oh, wow. - The top of it
so that no lights would come out and would give it away.
All lights would shine off the glass.
- So they usually use it to black out the inside.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Wow, and they just sort of turned it inside out.
- That's very cool.
- I thought you were gonna say,
wasn't that fact that the roof of the Albert Hall
isn't attached?
- It was mostly that it was built in Manchester
and then taken apart and then rebuilt on the roll-up pole.
- But it's just sitting on top, though.
- Yeah, it's just loose.
It's like an upturned bowl.
- I mean, domes are just mental, aren't they?
Like, what's the one in Florence?
Is it Brunelleschi made the one in Florence
and we still don't know how he did it?
'Cause it's got no structure holding it up.
It basically holds itself up.
- Is that the Duomo?
- Duomo, maybe, yeah, I think it is.
- It's been to the Duomo when I was trying to.
But not all at the same time.
- But yeah, and we don't know how he did it.
What we think is he built, like, the first circle
and then the next level sort of interlocked
with the previous level of bricks.
Next level interlocked with those
and then eventually it sort of holds itself up.
- Like a jigsaw.
- Like a jigsaw, kind of, yeah.
- Interesting.
- Like Lego, almost.
- But we don't fully...
- We still don't know how he did it.
- How do you, do you think when,
if you're one of the builders doing it
and you're like, "This doesn't work."
And he's like, "No, it will, it will."
Like, what's your confidence as a builder
when someone's handed you a blueprint of something
that no other architect can make sense of?
- Yeah, I can only imagine Bruno Lesky was saying,
"Just do it, mate. Just do it."
Yeah, don't ask questions.
Just take this cutlery where I tell you to take it.
(all laughing)
- I think it's amazing anything was built before about 1800.
- Oh, I agree.
- Anything substantial is insane that they did that.
Using what?
- Built better, really, and built to last longer
than plenty of buildings today, am I right?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, Stonehenge.
- Look at that.
It's not that good a house.
You don't even want to live in Stonehenge, would you?
- The pyramids were the tallest building on our planet
until something in America, right?
- To the Eiffel Tower, I think.
- No, no, no.
- It's the Lincoln Center.
- Lincoln Cathedral.
- In Lincoln, UK.
- Right.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Not in the United States, yeah.
And then there was Lincoln Cathedral for 400 years.
- And also the Duomo, I think was the biggest dome
in the world until the Royal Albert Hall,
I think. - Nice.
- Good fact.
- Yeah, good stuff.
- I think this is my favorite fact that came through.
It's from Justice Goldstein Shirley.
And it's this amazing thing that Bookland
is a made-up country.
- Bookland.
- Where all books come from.
- Did that preacher manage to get there to?
(all laughing)
- Arthur, bless it.
- Yeah.
- With his cross.
- I don't know if bless it has been there.
- To me, this is not a good fact.
This is a poor fact, because it's just mediup-y.
- No, no, no, 'cause it's where all books come from.
- Ah, but no.
- I've been to a place where books are printed.
It wasn't in Buckland.
- You went there as well, didn't you, Andy?
Not at the same time as me.
(all laughing)
- Basically, as they say,
I've just learned a fact you all may enjoy.
According to their barcodes,
all published books come from a country called Bookland.
And it's because when barcode numbers
were being standardized in the 1980s,
the first three digits of all barcodes
of like, products, you buy in shops, whatever,
were assigned according to a country of origin.
But books already had ISBN numbers.
And so they didn't wanna completely change the system
for books, so they thought,
we're just gonna add a country onto the front
of the ISBN numbers, a little bit added to the barcode.
But to make things easy, we're just gonna say,
all books are from the same country.
And it's 978, which I never noticed every single book
has the same first three letters at the start.
Numbers at the start.
- We're next to a bookcase now.
- We'd better check.
- 978.
- Yeah, this one's got a label on it.
- How many should we do?
- 978.
- Yeah, 978.
- 978, 978, Katie Hickman's book, 978.
- Dan Shriver's Impossible Things, 978, out now, out now.
- Dan Shriver's Impossible Things, 979.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, all they've got were on 7-8 at the start.
- Amazing.
- All the numbers, it works.
That's great, that's an amazing fact.
- Anyway, and that's Bookland.
- Yeah.
- You're like, this is called Bookland.
- That's like the shoe shop, having its own zip code.
All books have their own country of origin
in an non-existent country.
- Yeah.
- Love that.
- Do you want me to do more?
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- Great, I will.
- I'll cut.
1986 movie, The Manhattan Projects.
Is that anyone seeing it?
- Okay, no.
- It's about a kid who makes, who, nice.
(all laughing)
- It is.
- It was fine, man.
- It was quick, it wasn't funny, but it was quick.
- Was it a fine man?
- Oh, was it?
- Oh, wow, Dan, that was good.
That was high, Brow.
It's about a kid who makes a nuclear bomb
and the prop designer took things a bit too far
and designed a bomb that might actually have worked.
(all laughing)
- Is that based on a real story?
'Cause there was a kid who made a bomb,
wasn't there, do you remember?
- Yeah, there was.
I think that, was that not more recently?
- Was he a boy scout?
- I think it was a boy scout.
- I think it was about then,
and it was in a shed or something.
- Yeah.
- And they had to take a shed
and bury it in the middle of the desert.
- That's right.
- It doesn't claim so,
but maybe they did plagiarize the story.
- How do they know it might have worked?
- Well, this is the thing.
It said it would have worked,
but it was minus the plutonium sphere,
and then I went down such a rabbit hole
about how you make atomic bombs,
and basically the plutonium sphere is the center,
which is quite important.
- It is the main bears.
- Yeah.
So this is the explosives around it,
but I ended up looking up.
- Yeah, but, yeah.
- But still, you know, you've made,
you put all the explosives together.
All you need to do is chuck a plutonium.
- Exactly, yeah.
- If you watch the "Mission Impossible" films,
those things are tenor penny.
They're constantly being traded across that world.
(all laughing)
I love the idea that a prop maker's doing it so well
that the thing of, like, can you imagine
if like Michael J. Fox actually disappeared
when he hit 88 in the DeLorean?
(all laughing)
- Barry!
- Have you guys heard of the demon core?
- No.
- It's kind of cool.
So I looked up plutonium sphere,
and this is the only thing that comes up.
It was the third bomb, so it was meant to be,
the bombs that obliterated Hiroshima and Nakasaki,
the Americans had a third one ready to go
if the Japanese didn't surrender.
They nicknamed it Rufus,
but it was renamed the demon core.
But basically, when Japan surrendered,
they were like, well, we've got this spare
plutonium core now, let's do loads of experiments with it.
And these scientists just went nuts with it,
trying to experiment with how much radiation
it took to kill you and, you know,
where you reach the critical point
where there's a radiation explosion.
But it kept on going wrong, understandably.
So there was a scientist called Henry Daglian
in August, 1945, who went to the lab after dinner,
which sounds a lot like he had a lot to drink,
stumbled back to the lab,
built all these bricks around the plutonium core
made of tungsten carbide,
which apparently makes it more and more radioactive.
And he got to the exact moment where he knew
if he added one more brick,
it would suddenly have this radiation explosion.
- This is your version of "Chengar Game" as well, isn't it?
It's just gonna add one more brick.
- It's the most dangerous "Chengar Game" in the world.
- Wow.
- For bad kids.
- Did he add it?
- No, what he did was he thought, you know,
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna take the bricks away now
'cause I don't wanna kill myself.
But he went to take one brick away
and he dropped it on the core.
And there was a big flash of radiation.
It was only for a split second
and he went and grabbed it and pushed it off.
But that was enough and within 20 days he was dead.
- Whoa!
- Yeah, it's the scariest thing, isn't it?
'Cause you think, oh, that tingled a bit.
It's probably fine.
But it's actually not if it's a plutonium core.
- Good to know.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Public service.
- Anyway, that was just the rabbit hole I went down.
- Wow, that's brilliant.
- Okay, let's have one last one from Sam Bromley
who says, "During a bout of hiccups today,
"I did some Googling and found out
"that some proven remedies for hiccups
"include finger in the rectum or a fist."
- In?
- I'm afraid there's nothing more to that.
- The thing is, like, if a finger in the rectum works,
why go full fist?
(all laughing)
Or did it start off with an arm
and then they felt, actually, just the fist will work.
And then they're like,
"Oh, actually, just a few fingers will work."
- Actually, maybe just give it 10 minutes
and it will go naturally.
(all laughing)
- Certainly it would be a shock.
You know, you're told to shock someone.
- I think, yeah.
- If you start hiccuping
and someone puts the fist up your rectum,
then that will be a shock.
- Yeah.
- And it's worth two in the bush right here,
is the fist in the...
- A fist on the arse is worth it.
(all laughing)
- Tandy.
- Sorry.
- Jesus Christ.
- I bought my wife something called Hickaway.
- What?
- Hickaway.
- Right.
- Anti-hickup thing.
- What shape is it?
(all laughing)
- Mechanical arm that just...
- It's not that.
- What is it?
- It's a thing that you drink from,
but it's like a straw
and it's supposed to be proven to get rid of hiccups
'cause my wife suffers from hiccups.
- James, I'm here to tell you
that you have given your wife the fist,
whether you know it or not.
- Okay.
- That's what the fist is.
So a finger in the rectum study,
and he has cited studies
which actually show a finger up the rectum works,
but the fist is something completely different, F-I-S-S-T,
and it stands for Forced Inspiratory Suction and Swallow Tool,
and it is the Hickaway.
- Oh.
- So you've fisted your wife with that, even knowing it.
- Stop it, Anna, this is the bluest joke.
- It's just facts.
- So what is it?
- It's a straw that's particularly hard to suck,
I think, isn't it?
- Why does the finger work out of curiosity?
- Surprise.
- No, 'cause if I'm doing it to me,
that's not a surprise.
- I think it will still be a surprise.
- I'll be surprised.
(all laughing)
- It's not a surprise to yourself.
It's like trying to tickle yourself.
You can't tickle yourself.
- I believe if you're schizophrenic,
you can shock yourself with a figure up your own penis.
- Right, there we go.
- No, I think, is it, they just nerve stuff, I think.
- I actually didn't read the study.
It's a digital rectum massage that you can give yourself,
but I felt like I'd gone deep enough.
- The only thing I remember about putting a finger
at the bottom is it's the way
to get a dog to stop biting you.
- Oh, the dog's bottom or your own?
- It's the dog's.
- The dog's like, "That's disgusting.
"What a bite of this guy."
- Thank God you clarified, though, Adam.
There will be someone out there
who will remember that little nugget one day.
He died bitten by a dog with his finger up his arse.
We can't quite work out.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for facts number three.
And that is Dan.
- Yep, so we've been sent in a fact here
by John Waldrop from 1934 to 1947.
And then from 1951 till his death in 1954,
the mayor of Fort Wayne, Indiana, was Harry Bowles.
Very good.
Yeah, I sort of, I remember mentioning him years ago
on the show, but I don't think it made it
to an edit in the end.
- It's called Harry.
- He's called Harry Bowles, B-A-A-L-S.
The pronunciation is that because he was once
on a radio show with a guy called Bob Chase
who wasn't quite sure what to say in the moment.
And so he pronounced the mayor's name Bales.
So he said, "Mayor Bales is with us."
And he called him on it and he said,
"Son, this is your mayor.
I pronounced my name Bales."
So he was very into that.
But yeah, he seemed to be a quite an interesting character.
He did a lot of stuff for the city.
He sort of helped to build underground storage systems.
He launched lots of city departments,
lowered the city tax rates, liked Guy by all accounts.
I looked him up on eBay and you can find...
- You can buy him for 12 nights, Guy.
- Yeah, he's available now.
- No, there's a lot of like of the old paraphernalia
that you can buy from his, I guess, election time
and just general stuff.
And I can't tell which ones are genuine or not,
but it's, you know, on the badges it will say stuff like,
"I'm proud of my Harry Bowles."
You know, stuff like that.
So they obviously leaned into it.
And apparently one of the most stolen street signs
that you can get in the States is Harry Bowles Drive.
And that's constantly being...
Yeah, so they had to rename it to HW Bowles Drive,
just to avoid that.
- I kind of feel like the balls bit
is kind of part of the problem.
- Yeah, exactly.
But yeah, so yeah, thank you very much to John Waldrop.
Here's an interesting one that we got sent in.
Someone was saying that, "I love the show."
- Oh, that's great.
- Yep, pretty nice.
- Move on to the next one maybe.
- Yeah, so this is from Jessica Ackerman.
"I love the show."
In episode 538, Anna's fact is that
there are only two colors of cat.
As a cat lover, I love the conversation.
And I have a rad fact about cat allergies to share.
We can use chickens to make cats less allergenic.
Okay, this is how it's done.
The protein, FelD1, is responsible for around 90%
of cat allergies in humans.
The protein is found in cat saliva.
Scientists have found that chickens raised
in the proximity to cats develop an antibody to FelD1
called IgY.
That is passed into the yolk.
If you feed a cat egg yolks
from the cat exposed chickens,
the IgY antibody will cause the cat's body
to produce less of the FelD1 protein,
thereby lessening the allergen that most humans react to.
- So sorry, keep a chicken near your cat,
then feed the cat the eggs that the chicken has laid.
- Yes.
- And the cat will produce less of the stuff that--
- How do I convince my cat to eat this egg?
Do I mix it in with some Evian?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
It's exactly that.
You mix it into the cat food.
There's also companies now.
There's one called Purina that sells a cat food
that I believe has it mixed into it already.
But the DIY solution, as Jessica points out,
is you mix it into the food of your cat.
We can't eat the eggs and sort it out on our side.
It has to be the cats.
- Because then the cat would have to eat you.
- Yes.
(laughing)
That's a great fact.
- Yeah, that's so cool.
- That's very cool.
Well, this is quite similar actually.
This is from Zoe Keen.
She writes that Dr. Anthony Waddle
has created budget frog saunas.
And this could be amazing.
- I hate it 'cause I always spend so much money
on my frog saunas.
That time someone hit the lower end of the market.
(laughing)
- So there are frogs that are being wiped out
by a fungal infection called chitrid or citrid.
- CHY, TRND.
- It's a really big problem, isn't it?
So there are these rare frogs in places like Hawaii
which are just dying by the 1000
because they're just getting these fungal infections.
- Yeah, so it's thought to have caused
90 species to go extinct.
A decline of a further 500 species.
It's a big, big problem.
And the idea is that once this fungus
reaches an environment where the frogs are living,
it's pretty much impossible to save them.
That's what it's been like up until now
until Dr. Anthony Waddle comes in with his frog saunas.
'Cause what he's worked out is that heat treatment
will prevent frogs from croaking as Zoe has written.
So they set up basically,
they set up a bunch of experiments
where they put frogs into a sauna-like condition.
It was very heated.
They made it so that it was fun for them to be in there.
And they noticed that the frog--
- They're sorry, how did they make it fun?
- Well, I guess.
- They said, "You can pour the water on the cold."
- Lovely, fluffy towels so that they make sure
there's a good storage unit for all their gold
and watches and all that.
- Relaxing music.
You don't go to a bunch of saunas, do you?
- Where's the gold locker, sorry.
- Now we have to do, you gotta take off all the jewelry.
- Oh, like your wedding ring or the thing.
- Yeah, it sounded like you were turned up
with a huge chain.
Also, Dan, you shouldn't really take off your wedding ring
when you go into the sauna.
I know.
- Shouldn't you?
I don't know 'cause I don't use saunas,
they're not burned through your fingers.
- It's a message, doesn't it?
So, okay, so basically the idea is that they created
what are effectively saunas for the frogs to be in
and they discovered that the frogs seem to have an immunity
once they are in this heated area
and that the fungus can't handle the heat and dies off.
- Is it if they've caught it, they can be saved?
Or is it sort of, do you know what I mean?
Is it, do they have to have already contracted the fungus?
- Yeah, maybe that builds up an resistance.
- It must be 'cause if you just put a bunch
of uninfected frogs in saunas, they're also not gonna get it
but also you've got a bunch of uninfected frogs stuck
in a sauna forever.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, so hang on.
So in the lab, they allowed infected frogs
the option of spending time in the warm environment.
They sprang up the chance to use the saunas.
The fungus could not handle the heat and the frogs recovered.
A control group without sauna access stayed infected.
- So what they're trying to work out now
is how do we create natural saunas for these frogs
in these-- - Global warming?
- There we go, it's naturally gonna happen.
It's gonna be, we're all gonna die except the frogs.
- Wow, that's fact, but they can have a turn.
- Do you know that fungi are two times more deadly
than they were in 1990?
- Why?
- Because-- - People keeps baffling off
onto them.
(laughing)
- That's so rude.
- It's an epidemic.
- It is.
- Go to a substance that we're putting on them
but it's fungicides, basically.
- James, sorry, I'd never do this
but just a quick request for the edit.
Can you just remove all the earlier mentions
that animated that so it comes absolutely out of nowhere?
(laughing)
- Yeah, we're using more fungicides than ever
and like if you use too many antibiotics,
you get antibiotic resistant bacteria.
You can get more anti-fungal resistant.
So they're much more dangerous than they were
30 years ago.
- I've had a thought about this fact that we got in,
was it, from Zoe, about the frog sauna one.
- Yeah.
- You know, it's nice because now we can update a saying,
can't we?
There's that classic saying, you know,
if you put a frog in warm water and raise the temperature,
how long, how long before it screams or whatever,
or how long before it, you know, panics and dumps out?
- It's like a catchy one.
- It's the same?
- No, but you know-- - It's not the same.
- It's like-- - It's like--
- It's like, count your chickens without I didn't know?
Is this another?
- There's a frog in a bath and you raise the temperature
and you know, how long before it actually realizes
that it's dangerous and tries to jump out?
- It's not a saying.
- No, but it's a-- - It's a thought,
it's a thought experiment. - Use it in like,
I make your house, when would you say that to me?
- So, for instance, Dan, you know what?
These tax rises, they're happening,
but they're happening quite slowly
and so people don't complain about them.
It's like a frog being in a pot of water
and they're getting warmer and warmer and warmer
and they never jump out
because they never realize it's gotten too hot.
- Thank you, exactly like that.
- It's like a political option,
not the one I would have thought.
- That's basically the premise.
So this, but is an update
because you've got a frog in their sauna and it's nice.
It was a more of a slam dunk in my head
when I was clamming this.
- More than that, really.
- Let's move on to Oliver Titcombe,
who says, "My fact this week is that Canadian police
procedural due south was set in Chicago,
but filmed in Toronto.
In one episode, the characters crossed the border
to reach Toronto.
This scene was filmed in Chicago."
- It's very nice.
- Is that a funny joke of the directors?
- I know, I looked into it slightly
and that's kind of one of those IMDB factoids
that you don't get much more on.
Maybe it's out there.
- I never watched you South,
but I always assumed it was Canadian, all of it.
- It was set in Chicago.
- Yeah, which is not in Canada.
- I know, right?
- So how did you assume it was Canadian?
You recognized all the sites of Toronto.
Why did they keep referring to Chicago
when there's the famous--
- Seattle Tower is right there in the middle.
- Hang on, where was it?
It was filmed in Chicago.
- Filmed in Chicago, no, filmed in Toronto.
- Filmed in Toronto, thank you.
- I think, I actually didn't look into this bit,
but I'm gonna assume that it's a Canadian police show
that is based about a Chicago police station.
- How, in what senses is it a Canadian police show
except that it's filmed in Toronto?
- The show follows the adventures
of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.
What are they doing in Chicago?
- What is going on then?
- Wait a minute, wait a minute.
Who first came to Chicago
on the trail of the killers of his father?
- I see.
- I see, so it's a mountain.
It's like a fish out of water
or a frog out of sauna.
- Right.
- It goes to Chicago.
I think this would have been helped
if any of us had seen due south.
- Yes, also Oliver's email was a bit longer
and I cropped it to just that one paragraph.
So he actually did explain a little more,
but I thought, I'm sending it to Dan,
I've just gotta include the first paragraph.
- Yeah, yeah.
- The show's format looked at the stereotypical differences
between Canadian and American culture at the time.
- That sounds quite good.
- Created by Paul Haggis.
- Great name.
- I want to see this show where he goes to Scotland.
- Yeah.
- Okay, another fact from Sarah Ellis.
And I'll do this as a quiz question
'cause I think it's sort of presented like that.
In parts of Australia,
there will be two minutes in a day
that last for a minute and a half each.
Why?
- So I've seen the answer.
- Okay, yeah, of course.
- It came to the inbox.
So I'm gonna rule myself out.
Or I'll try and trick these others actually.
- Okay, go on then.
- I'll say it's 'cause Australia's so big
they have to stretch the minute.
- Oh, that's a good idea, isn't that?
- Yeah, I'm gonna go for that.
(all laughing)
- Can I ask some follow up questions?
- Absolutely, yeah.
- Great.
Is it just on one particular day or is it every day?
- It's every day.
- Could you say it one more time?
- Yeah, so in parts of Australia,
there will be two minutes in a day
and those two minutes last for a minute and a half each.
- Okay, okay.
Do we lose the other minute?
'Cause the number of minutes in a day
presumably is the same as anywhere else.
So we've got an extra half minute from each of those.
Have we lost that minute somewhere else?
- Yes.
- Ah, okay.
So they've decided to do away with one of the minutes
of the day.
- Which minute would you lose?
(all laughing)
- Ooh, what a question.
- I reckon I'd lose the minute
of you talking about people spunking over mushrooms.
Why would you lose a minute?
Well, logically you'd say the first or last minute
would be a good one to lose.
Maybe the confusion of zero, zero, zero.
Like, 'cause in midnight,
is it one day or is it the next day?
- You're bang on.
- Is it really?
- Yeah, yeah, that's absolutely it.
- Wow!
- But where in Australia?
This is a bit too hard to get.
- I should go on Tom Scott's podcast.
- This is too hard to get.
- We can get it.
- It's a bit misleading.
- How many places in Australia rather?
Sydney or Melbourne?
(all laughing)
- Have we heard of this place?
- It's not a place.
It's a, let's say it's a--
- The exact center.
- It's an institution.
Help me out, Andy.
- With the space agency?
Straight on.
- GPS.
- Think, like, they're related to that.
Who invented GPS?
Who owned GPS?
- NASA.
- And the--
- And the Space Force.
- And the American, they've got big guns.
- Army.
- The army!
(laughing)
- Wait a minute.
Is he still tricking us?
- I can't remember.
I think, is it the army?
- It's the Royal Australian Navy.
Oh, sorry.
So the explanation Sarah gives is that
the Royal Australian Navy uses a 24 hour clock
as opposed to 12 hour time.
24 hour time starts at zero, zero, zero.
And it goes until 2359, as we all know, then resets.
Now, some reason they just don't like the zero, zero, zero.
So what they do is they make the minute 2359
last a minute and a half.
And then when it flicks over,
it flicks over to zero, zero, one,
and that lasts for a minute and a half.
And then you move back.
- I love that.
Wouldn't it be amazing if you could lose,
I was just thinking about the minute of the day that I lose.
And getting out of bed is the worst moment of the day, right?
If you could lose the minute between
when you're lying down and when you're standing up.
So you could just be like lying down and be like,
okay, fine, can I skip ahead a minute now?
And then you're standing up.
- That's a great premise for something.
A story or a film or something.
You have a button that you press and it just,
I think that's great.
- Just give it a minute.
Thanks, Andy.
And this is a published novelist here.
Okay.
(laughing)
You're saying that?
- 978.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for the final facts of the show.
And those are my ones.
So get ready guys, 'cause these are the really good ones.
Right, these are the creme de la creme.
So here is a great one.
This is from Derek Dayerman.
And he writes, I'm a train operator
on the New York City subway.
And I noticed the most bizarre Shakespearean coincidence
within the system that I want to share with you.
This is great.
The fact is the Romeo train goes through the Montague Tunnel
and the Juliet comes close but never gets to join it.
Okay, this is insane.
And I'm pretty sure this is a Derek-generated fact.
I think he's the first person to notice this,
which is so cool.
- Okay.
- So there are all these subway tunnels
connecting Manhattan and Brooklyn, right?
One of them is called the Montague Tunnel.
- Presumably not named after the family
in Romeo and Juliet.
- No, it gets its name from the street
that it runs underneath once it reaches Brooklyn,
which is the Montague Street.
So in New York, the subway lines,
they just have a letter or a number.
You know, the A train, the B train.
- Is it like alpha and beta?
- Well, they do the phonetic alphabet.
So train crews on the R train call themselves Romeo's
and train crews on the J train call themselves Juliet's.
And the R train goes through the Montague Tunnel.
There are tracks which would allow the J and Z trains
to also use the Montague Tunnel,
but they aren't used in passenger service.
They both terminate just before the entrance to the tunnel.
So Juliet never gets to join Romeo through the Montague Tunnel.
I just think that's great.
Brilliant.
- So good.
- Brilliant.
- Well done.
- Do you want to hear, this is a great,
this is an Australian one.
We'll go to Australia soon.
- Okay.
- This might be helpful.
From Will Davies, from Emerald Beach, New South Wales.
Familiar to any of them?
- Yeah, it's by the coast, I think.
- Nice.
- I'll do this one as a riddle as well, actually.
The third largest airline in Australia
does not charge its passengers to fly.
Whoa.
- Is it?
- So it's going to be animals that it's...
- Yeah.
- Some sort of freight or military.
- Flying doctors.
- Not freight, it's not...
James has got it.
- Oh.
- Flying doctors.
- Why?
- The third largest by fleet size.
So I suppose that's not total passenger capacity
but number of planes you've got
'cause they're quite small planes.
So yeah, it's flying doctors.
Who I don't think we've ever spoken about.
- No, no, how does, what are they?
- Well, they, they're as it sounds, as it sounds.
- As it sounds, but is it like if you call an ambulance
in the outback or you've been hit by a kangaroo,
then you call and a doctor has to get to you.
- Yeah, or something even less stereotypical than that.
- I don't know, one of the cocks went in my eye from my hat.
- The little roo fell on me.
Yeah, that kind of, yeah.
- I guess 'cause you'd normally have just the paramedic go
and then take them to another place.
- Yeah, but some of these places are so remote
and they're not very low, but small populations.
And so you just need,
if you need a doctor within a couple of hours.
- Yeah.
- The reason I actually knew about it
is probably 10 years before due self came out,
there was a TV show called The Flying Doctors,
which was, I didn't really watch it,
but I knew that it was about this.
- Yeah, I used to watch it back home.
Yeah, it was a sort of staple of, you know,
along with home and away and all that.
- Okay, here's a bonus quiz.
This is something, 'cause I was reading a bit
about The Flying Doctors. - Yeah, yeah.
- So they, if they're landing in the dark,
places they're flying to are not equipped with airports,
most of them. - Right now, I know.
- So what they want is proper sort of flares
or electric lights on the runway to clearly mark out
where they have to land at night.
So if you are landing somewhere
which doesn't have those lights,
what is the best alternative
that The Flying Doctors like to use?
- Pumpkins.
- Fireflies. - Not bad.
Biomanescence. - Biomanescence.
- It's... (laughing)
You have to breed some phosphorescent shrimp to,
and you chuck them out of the tanks,
you just throw the aquariums.
Every community under 20 people in Australia
has millions of shrimps on a sand bike.
If someone takes their leg.
- No, it's... - Phones.
- You are setting-- - Hold your phone up.
- That's a really nice idea.
You are setting light to something.
What does every house have?
- A netflix. - A washing machine.
- Gold. - Safe.
(laughing)
- Evian. (laughing)
- It's a dunny roll.
- Oh, okay. - It's new roll.
What you do is you soak toilet rolls in diesel
and you just line them along your impromptu runway
and set fire to them and they burn for half an hour.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- And the pilots can, and if you can't do that,
if for whatever reason you've got to the end
of your last roll, maybe that's the crisis
that you're calling the fine doctors for,
then you have four cars with their headlights
at the corners of your runway.
- Ah, nice. - Just have to put
on their headlights. - Very cool.
- Flying doctors. - They're awesome.
- Here's one from Henry Biggs.
Until the mid-1920s, Italians drove
on both sides of the road.
- Well, we all drive on both sides of the road
'cause that'd be a complete waste of road.
- Yeah, so you mean one way.
- What? (laughing)
- It's not like you look at a road
and the only half of it's really used.
- Oh, we're in pedantry cul-de-sac now.
They drove on the left and the right.
- Okay. - In the same direction.
- Thank you.
- Why did they do such a thing?
- Well, Italy largely adopted driving
on the right as law in 1912,
but in some cities with tram networks,
drivers would have to switch to driving on the left
as they approach the city centre.
Quite confusing.
- You know what, I once drove the wrong way
round and round about in Italy
and they were very annoyed,
the people who were also on the roundabout.
- But I should have just said,
I thought we were still in 1912.
(laughing)
- That would have calmed it down.
Yeah, but weirdly, they think the Romans drove on the left.
So I looked into this a bit off the back of the road.
- Yeah, I think that's true, isn't it?
They look at the ruts in the road and stuff.
- You've got it.
- Wow.
- Oh, that's gonna be a little quiz.
- Oh, I'm sorry.
- No, that's quite all right.
Just forget.
Okay, Dan and Anna, forget you had that.
(laughing)
- I can't believe James doesn't even eat
the quiz question at this point.
(laughing)
It just comes in with the answer.
- How do we know they weren't just always reversing, though?
- That's true.
- Well, it was 1998, they worked out,
'cause there was a quarry near Swindon.
And archeologists found it,
and they found the ruts on the,
so if I'm looking at the quarry for a distance, right?
The ruts on the right hand side of the road
are deeper than the ones on the left.
So what they think is that carts were arriving lighter
on the left, 'cause they're not weighed down,
and then they're weighed down with stones
as they're leaving, so the ruts are heavier.
So that's how they can tell which side of the road
was driven on.
- Very cool.
- That is amazing.
- It's a great detective work.
One last one.
From Adam Wilson,
"According to the leading piracy historian,
"Marcus Reddica, more people have worked
"on the pirates of the Caribbean franchise
"than there were ever actual pirates of the Caribbean."
(laughing)
And it's partly because the number of pirates
was so small, he reckons, Marcus Reddica,
who is probably a very eminent historian,
that there were 4,000 total ever cumulative pirates.
Yeah.
Imagine that, like 4,000 of them,
and what they have influenced.
Every child pretends to be a pirate.
Honestly, it's incredible, 4,000 people.
- And they are pretending to be golden age pirates.
- Yeah, probably they're pretending
to be 100 of those, right?
Most of them wouldn't have been army hearties.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- That's amazing.
Only 4,000.
- I know, and I presume the number of people
who work on the, I presume even the graphics department
for one pirates of the Caribbean, yeah.
- There have been about 4,000 of the films
that I've seen on the internet.
- Yeah, that's true.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That's all of your facts.
Please keep sending them in to podcast@qi.com.
We love hearing from you, and they all get read,
and some of them may get read out.
So that's an added incentive.
So thanks for everyone who contributed to today's show.
If you would like to get in contact with us
about any of the things that we said,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
Dan, you're on--
- @Sriberland on Instagram.
- James, you're on--
- My Instagram is @NosticsLingersJamesHarkin.
- Lovely, Anna.
- You can get in touch with the podcast as a whole
by going to Instagram @nosticslingersafish,
Twitter @nosticsling, or emailing podcast@qi.com.
- And I'm @andrewhunterm on Twitter.
And if you enjoyed this kind of show,
slightly different format, we actually have a club,
a secret, private, highly publicized members club.
It's called Clubfish.
It's so much fun for a few quid a month.
You get ad-free episodes, and you get bonus content,
including Drop Us Align,
which is already in the feedback bit,
which is very funny.
It's not dissimilar to what you just heard.
- No, audience is funny in the podcast.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, and it's really,
it's, you know, I think a lot of the intellectual life
is happening in Clubfish at the moment.
You know, it's the salon.
- It's the sauna.
So, whip off your wedding ring,
pop your gold in the safe, and step on down.
So that's on Patreon or Apple,
and you can get that at no-such-things-of-fish.com as well.
And if you go to our website,
no-such-things-of-fish.com,
you can listen to previous episodes.
You can get tickets for our tour.
We are going on tour around the UK, Ireland,
and Australia and New Zealand.
We are very excited about it.
It starts soon.
There are still some tickets left for some of the UK dates.
Australia and New Zealand is mostly sold out at this stage.
- Gothenburg, Andy?
- And we're going to Gothenburg.
We're going to Gothenburg for the Book Festival
on the 27th of September.
That's going to be a fantastic fun.
We're going to be doing a show there.
So if you live in continental Europe,
that's your opportunity to see us.
And we will be back again with another episode
of this show next week.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)