(upbeat music)
- Hi.
- Right, let's do some emails.
(laughing)
- No wasting time on it.
- Awesome.
- Let's trim the fat so we can have more emails.
- Great idea.
- But if you are listening to this,
and it's your first time, this is Drop As A Line,
we talk about your facts.
- You're spiling it now.
- You're right.
- Commit.
- Let's start again.
- Hi.
- All right, let's do it.
(laughing)
- What would you like?
First of all, you can have a bonus info,
you can have a bonus fact, or you can have a complaint.
- What happened to the excellent new names for the wall?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
- I've been ditched.
- No, no, no, no, actually of the week,
that's bonus info, but it's bonus info
that's correcting us in a slightly finicky way,
or you can have you get yourself off the hook,
which is the correction one.
- Well, I think we've just finished quite a long recording.
I feel like a nice fact.
- Lovely, okay, here we go.
This is a fact phrased in a QI format of a question, lovely.
In which month in the UK is the longest day?
- July.
- April.
- The day when the clocks go back off.
- Is that actually?
- October.
25 hours, the clocks go back.
You've got 25 hours to play with.
- That's good, that's good.
- That's Chris Boot, I should say.
- That's not an interesting fact, though.
That's just a trick question.
James asked for an interesting fact.
- Okay, some mutant ears broke out.
- I think, cool, I think they weren't
operating within the remit.
- No, fair enough, fair enough, all right.
- That's a good question, though.
- Yeah, I like it.
- I think it's quite a good fact, isn't it?
- I'd like to say this is the longest day of the year.
- No, that's not, 'cause everyone knows
that that happened, that's just a trick question.
- I see.
- You know, you're not like, oh wow, really,
did the clocks go back in October?
- No, but did you ever think of 25 hours?
Is the point of it?
- I don't think you did, Anna.
Otherwise you would have said--
- But it's not an interesting fact.
- Isn't it?
- It's a clever question.
- She's just feeling sad 'cause she didn't get the answer.
- Yeah, exactly.
Anna, maybe, you know, just think more out there, you know.
- Okay, sorry.
- All right, well, let's have a fact
about the old mill in Kennewood.
- Brilliant.
- We spoke about this, which is the ride
where you'd have the plastic bats.
- Yeah, it was like a tunnel of love, wasn't it?
- Bingo.
- And people would make out there and, yeah.
- Also, the paddles to whack the bums.
- Exactly, yes.
- People having sex.
- Yes.
- We really dragged out the explanation of that fact.
We all had a go, we all played.
- And that's it for this week's Bob's Alive.
We'll see you next time.
Chris Messer writes,
- Yeah.
- I live in New York, but grew up in Appalachia,
and Kennewood was a big destination for the area.
The community I grew up in was relatively far away
from Kennewood, enough so that we wouldn't be hip
to any of the CD law, per se.
And still, the old mill was infamous in my community.
People were always making out on it,
and very scandalously, in middle school,
two of my classmates' reputations were absolutely shattered
because of the quite adult behavior
they engaged in on the ride.
Brackets, we call it third base in America.
- Oh, yeah.
- We call it third base in the UK too.
- But do we think we've got that from America?
No, it's rounders.
(all laughing)
- And he goes on, this is the first thing I thought of
when a smutty amusement park ride was mentioned,
and I was delighted to find out it was the same
weird smelly old ride from 1901.
(all laughing)
I had no inkling that anyone besides the horny kids
from my tiny coal mining town near West Virginia
got down like that, but it was a known activity to us.
You go on the old mill to fool around.
And he says, he just adds a bit of clarification.
This is the bonus detail.
There is nothing romantic about the ride.
It is a facsimile of perhaps the least sexy place
you could imagine, a haunted lumber mill.
It is full of ghosts, skeletons, spiders, logs,
and the whole place.
- Do you not think a haunted lumber mill is quite sexy?
- I didn't think it was sexy.
- Like, on our honeymoon, my wife and I went
to a haunted hotel, like, deliberately,
because it was haunted.
- Mmm.
- Oh, yes.
Wasn't that haunted by the guy who was a,
he brought all the chihuahuas across the,
no, the sausage dogs?
No, Andy, you had a dog.
- It was called the drover's inn.
- Yeah, the drover's inn.
It was the ghost of a guy who was at one of the places
where these dogs were just went off on their own
and had bar tabs. - The corgis.
- The corgis.
- Corgis who used to arrive at the pub
a day before their master.
- Without their master.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So anyway, I think haunted things can be sexy.
- Me too, it's dark, there are property candles,
there's a lot of wood, it's a lumber.
- Completely.
I'll just give you Chris's description of it
and see if you still find it as sexy.
- It is full of ghosts, skeletons, spiders, logs,
and the whole place smells like mildew.
- Yummy.
- Mildew.
- I actually don't really know what mildew smells like.
- Yeah, what is mildew?
- It's just that kind of mould.
- Mould, it's a kind of mould.
- Oh, it sounds like your kind of place.
- I like moss not mould.
- Is moss and mould not pretty much similar?
- Dude, are you kidding?
- No.
- Are you joking?
- I thought that was like a subspecies of mould.
- Do you get people growing moss in their walls
when it's a bit damp in winter?
- I just thought it was part of the same family.
- Dude, it's like you haven't paid attention
to multiple space, but I can't see a thing.
- Well, so it has no connection.
Mould and moss are just completely separate.
- The things that grow.
- Yeah.
- Well, there we go.
There's a starting point.
- The parts of different kingdoms.
- Okay, they're very far apart.
- The kingdoms is pretty much the highest up cast we use.
- Yep, yep, yep.
That was a--
- Wow.
- Why didn't I know that?
- There is differences you are to a strawberry.
- Sometimes.
- More so.
- Do you have a moment where you just think,
what's the point of anything I've been doing?
(laughing)
What's the point of even,
if even the people sitting next to me
haven't been listening?
I'm not sure what the people at home have been turning off.
They've just been doing 30 seconds on, on, on, on.
They're still talking about moss?
On, on, on, on.
- To be fair though, you haven't been trying to push
the point that they're separate from each other.
- I didn't think I needed to.
- No, no, I know.
- It's very, you know, Rick explains to me
that moss was different to a puppy.
- Yeah, but I'm saying.
- You emphasized that.
- I'm saying all your hard work hasn't gone amiss.
I'm still taking in the beauty of moss.
I just thought it was connected to another species.
- It was Malt, yeah, yeah, okay.
- Well, no, I didn't think it was Malt.
I thought the same family.
- We still don't know what Mildew is, unfortunately.
- I've got a lot of it in the upstairs of my house right now.
If you want to smell Mildew, come around to my house.
- Sexy.
- Sexy offer.
- Yeah.
- Whoa.
Okay, here's another one.
Thank you, Chris.
(laughing)
You got some feedback on it.
This wasn't an episode that I did,
but it was when you had Reson.
- Oh yeah.
- Talked about moose.
- Yeah.
- Is that the same as moss?
(laughing)
- Same kingdom, definitely.
- Just two Canadians, Andrew and Emma Gilchrist
have written in saying moose are very difficult to spot.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- So, Rhys said that if you're in Canada,
one could be 50 meters in front of you in a plain field
and you wouldn't be able to see it.
- Yeah.
- Well, it sounds quite likely.
- Really?
- So, Emma says, "As a Canadian who lives in the woods,
"I would like to confirm moss is very hard to see."
- Moose.
(laughing)
- Okay, okay.
Moose.
(laughing)
- Very hard to see.
They pop out of wooded areas on the sides of the road
and end up in the middle before the driver even notices.
- Oh yeah.
- And we have signs on the road to one of moose crossing
so the drivers can watch the ditches
'cause they hang out in the ditches.
- Oh, and then jump up like a jack in a box.
- Pretty much.
And then despite their huge antlers,
they are very quiet too.
- I will say that being in a wooded area is very different
and I wouldn't deny that it's probably easy to hide
in a wooded area as a moose,
but Rhys has claimed that he could be on an open meadow
gallivanting towards moss or a moose and not see it.
- I'll refer you to Andrew's email,
who lives in a small town.
So in rural British Columbia,
he says I live in a small town in rural British Columbia
where moose are bound,
but I've only ever seen a handful.
(laughing)
- There we go.
- Well, maybe.
- Do you notice them in photos later?
They're sort of like a dinner party shot
and just there's a moose standing behind the dining table.
- It's like that basketball game
with the gorilla that walks behind it.
(laughing)
You actually never notice it.
But it's all moose.
There's one gorilla at 18 moose.
You can't see any of the moose, you actually see the gorilla.
All right, here's another one.
You talked about goats on this podcast as well with Rhys.
- Yeah, we did, yeah.
At length.
(laughing)
- I know, I listened to it.
Steve Mellon writes, "This is a great email.
"I thought if anyone would appreciate
"an additional bit on goats, it would be you guys.
"I'm on the Ogwin Valley Mountain Rescue Team
"in North Wales."
- Cool.
- "Of our approximately 150 to 200 call-outs a year,
"around five to 10 of these are triggered
"by people hearing shouts for help,
"which is in fact goats calling each other."
(laughing)
- Really?
- Their bleeds sound remarkably like a human shouting,
"Help!"
- Yes, they do actually.
- Help, help!
- Doing their pranking us.
- It says, "We always send a small team to investigate
"and the best way to ascertain if it is goats
"is to shout questions that help is not the answer to."
(laughing)
- What's your favourite sandwich?
- That's amazing.
- "What do you call a place that sells lots of drinks?"
(laughing)
- Anyway, thank you Steve Mellon.
- Great.
- What a great bit of bonus info.
- Yeah, lovely.
- There's been quite,
I'm sort of reluctant to bring this up again.
- Oh no.
- Do we miss a joke?
- No, there's been quite a lot of,
I mean, yeah, with loads.
But there's been quite a lot of urine discourse
in the inbox.
- Yeah.
- Up peeing in the shower.
- Oh, yes, yes, yes.
- I was just listening
to the most recent Clubfish episode.
This is from David.
And you were talking about peeing in the shower
and also the potential use of urine as a skin treatment.
And I have a fact that you didn't mention
that I can't help myself from sharing.
Can't help myself.
- That's always a bad sign, isn't it?
- Isn't it good.
Graham Swan, the early 2000s vintage England off spinner.
- Yeah.
- This is cricket for American listeners.
Used to prepare for cricket matches
by soaking his bowling hand,
or really his bowling fingers in a bucket of urine.
- Okay.
- Oh, I think I've read this.
Is that to make it stick more or something to the ball?
What was that?
- Well, he says it seems to have been for the same reason
that you referenced on the podcast
for new guitar players to tend to the skin
where the ball would be consistently rubbing
against the fingers.
- How interesting.
- Somebody does it before it.
I was suggesting doing it post-guitar playing,
but that makes sense, right?
Get prep, prep the hands.
- Yeah.
- It's about avoidance rather than treatment.
- I didn't Monty Panasar, who was the spinner
before Graham Swan, I think, might be wrong.
But didn't he get arrested for public urination
a few years ago?
- Was it onto his own hands?
- I was wondering if that might have been the reason.
Like he was just.
- Did he really?
- It was into Graham Swan's bucket, that was it.
(all laughing)
- It's a ritual you do to pass on the mantle.
- Yeah.
- I was actually talking with some advice
about urinating in the shower the other day.
Which got anyone off the hook who maybe does it.
But it's more female focus,
but saying that if you've got a sore front bum,
for whatever reason,
might be though that you've just given birth.
Often leaves you a bit sore.
And urinating in the shower, much less painful,
'cause it dilutes it as it comes out, apparently.
This was actively recommended.
So that's when you can get away with it.
And imagine that's why you were doing it.
(all laughing)
- Sovereign bum landing.
- Yeah.
- It's agony.
(all laughing)
- Wow, okay, well, good tip.
- Hot tip, yeah.
- This is becoming a nice lifestyle section,
I would say, to drop us a line.
It's a community.
- If you have any tips for urine or otherwise,
then do let us know.
- Let's keep it urine though.
- Let's be exclusively a urine wellness podcast.
- We've done peeing on your feet.
We've done peeing on your hands.
So now, if there's another part of the body
that you think we should be peeing on,
- Yes.
- Drops a line.
(all laughing)
This is really fascinating.
It's from Sarah Willards.
She says, "I was really interested to hear you
"mention Tintin's lack of aging in the episode,
"saying it could have been due to repeated blows
"to the head causing the problem.
"There is also quite a rare syndrome called Kalman's
"syndrome which causes puberty to be inhibited
"and it can come accompanied by an impaired sense of smell.
"I know this as my son actually has Kalman's syndrome
"and has to have daily testosterone
"to replace the hormone that should be produced.
"It often isn't diagnosed until the late teens
"as it can be really hard to notice the subtle symptoms
"and it only becomes obvious once the male
"has failed to go through puberty."
- That's so interesting.
- So if Tintin has a dodgy olfactory sense,
he probably has Kalman's syndrome.
- That's great.
- Please write in if you know the comics well enough
to know that one plate where he can't smell delicious.
- Well, he hangs out with that sailor.
Doesn't he captain Banacol or whatever he's called?
- No, not Steve.
- Captain Banacol is from Octonauts.
- Octonauts, yeah.
- Kitschers.
- But yeah, Captain Haggard.
So maybe he's like, yeah, he would never hang out with him
if he had a full olfactory system.
- Is the first friend Captain Haggard's ever made?
It's very sad.
- Yeah.
- Well, it's lovely.
It's as lovely as they're meant to be.
He's finally found the person for him.
- Yeah, possibly, yeah.
All right, you guys, you put it off long enough.
I'm afraid we've got to have some get yourself off the hooks.
- Oh, okay.
Just quick one before we finish.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Okay, three people from New Zealand have written to say
that you pronounce the name of the bird wrong.
- Oh, which one?
- Kokako.
- Kokako, yeah, you did say that you didn't know
how to pronounce it, though, in fairness.
- Apologies.
- Yeah, sorry.
- How are they saying that we should have pronounced it?
- I think like I just did.
- Kokako.
- Yeah, yeah, I looked up the pronunciation.
- Hard to put in an email the correct pronunciation,
isn't it?
(laughing)
- That's interesting.
I think I said in the background, Kokako,
because you said the O had a line over.
- Yeah.
- End of Tokyo.
- Someone else wrote in, they said,
"I think reset it quietly and correctly in the background,
"but it didn't get in the airways."
Maybe that was you instead, okay, so here we go.
Anyway, look, that's a brief one.
- Apologies, yeah, no, I should have got that right.
I think generally, this is a horrible thing to say,
but because I can't really speak many words correctly,
I care less about pronunciation.
I understand that it can offend people,
so I apologize for that, but on a personal level,
I just think--
- You're saying things.
- Oh my God, the audiobook that I had to do
for my own book, every three sentences,
I was like, how the hell fuck, how'd you say that?
- Sounds like they put a lot of effort
into that audiobook though, so I imagine it's worth buying.
- Yeah, it was four weeks of audio recording.
(laughing)
- Where can you get this audiobook from?
- Audible's a good place to get it from.
Yeah, it's called the theory of everything else,
it's sort of fantastic.
- And you're dubbed over in the end, aren't you?
(laughing)
- It's by Reese, actually, yeah.
One last thing, just because it's a correction,
but it comes with a little bonus fact, which is lovely.
It's from Oliver Tickham.
He says, "In one of your previous podcasts,
"Anna made some comment about the difference
"between towns and cities being the cathedral."
- Oh, what?
That was a throw away, and we know it's not true.
- In the UK, Oliver continues,
"That is not the difference between towns and cities."
- Oh, Oliver.
- The difference is whether or not it has a royal charter.
(laughing)
- There are so many different definitions,
there are so many different documents you can read
going back all the way, and I'm sorry,
it is, of course, not as simple as the cathedral thing.
- Oliver continues, this is a nice, cool bonus fact.
My fact this week is that Guilford was considered
for city status in time for the new millennium.
The football team prepared for this
by renaming itself Guilford City FC.
It then didn't happen, Guilford is still not a city,
so the football team is now just named Guilford City,
even though it's just in Guilford.
- That's great.
- That's brilliant.
- So there you go, thank you, Oliver, for sending that in.
And don't forget, royal charter is the thing.
Bye!
(laughing)
Thanks so much, everybody,
for all your emails, your corrections,
your bonus bits of information.
We genuinely love hearing it.
If you have listened to the podcast
and you have anything relevant or irrelevant to add,
please do send it to podcast@qi.com.
All emails are read.
- That's it for this time.
- I just said it's so threatening.
(laughing)
- All emails are read.
- Okay, that's it for this time.
Thank you so much.
See you next time on Drop As A Line.
Bye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]