(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Steps to Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoban.
My name is Andrew Hunter Murray.
I'm here with Dan Schreiber, James Harkin,
and Anna Tijinski, and we have gathered
around the table for a quarterly, I think.
- We aim for that, but we only did three last year.
- There we go.
- A...
Triennial...
Show, where we go through the fish inbox,
podcast@qi.com, we find the best facts
that you have sent to us, and we read them back to you.
So we've all learned from each other, and it's all square.
The inbox has had lots and lots of brilliant
fact submissions over the last few months.
- It's overflowing, Andy.
- It's bulging.
We've got a bulging post-bag.
- We have physical things to read.
- Yes, so the guys here have not seen
the facts that we've been sent.
I have brought them in, printed them out on bits of paper,
and chopped the bits of paper up.
We all have a stack of small slips of paper in front of us,
and we're going to see if this works,
which I think it might.
So let's have a fact, if anyone's got one.
- Okay, I'm going to open with a fact from Leander,
from Switzerland.
Inkus, the last Carolina parakeet,
died in the same cage as Martha,
the last passenger pigeon.
- Oh, that's interesting.
- No further info.
- Crazy.
- It's, yeah, mad.
- Are we saying that it's a cursed cage?
- Must be.
- It's got to be, unless they just killed each other,
it's one of those fights of the death where they both.
- So wait, what was it, the last passenger pigeon,
and the last, what, sorry?
- The last Carolina parakeet,
which does seem quite specific, but still cool.
- Still, still, it's two of a kind.
- Oh yeah, actually, when I first read it,
I thought that it was Inkus,
the last Carolina parakeet,
and Martha, and now it would have been even more amazing.
- All the Inkus died.
- This sounds like, I hope Stephen King isn't listening,
'cause that sounds right up his street of a murderous cage.
- The cursed cage, yeah, yeah.
- It could be a sort of like a retirement home of cages,
where it's, you know, it's the last of a species goes there.
- Yeah, it's really, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Maybe.
- They see like little pictures on the cage wall
of the previous tenants, you know.
- Is that what they do in all people's homes and stuff?
They have the pictures of the analysis.
- Have you ever watched the traitors?
Whenever anyone leaves,
they put a big red cross through their face.
They do that in all people's homes as well.
- I didn't know that.
- That's how it works.
- Oh, you know, you gotta face up to the truth, don't you?
- Yeah.
- Gosh.
- Well, that's a great fact.
- It's an excellent fact, very cool.
- Can I do one, honey?
- Yeah.
- This is from Hediver, and it says,
"Dear Anna, you are always my favorite podcast host."
- Yeah, that makes sense.
- I feel like I picked up the wrong pile here.
- That's a good fact.
It's not an interesting fact.
It's a pretty basic fact.
We've had it loads.
- If someone else has taken over the mailbox,
duty please disregard that.
- Yes, thank you.
- Consider it disregarded, Hediver.
I write now to share the most fish fact I have ever learned.
There is one extant species of marsupial,
the water opossum, in which the males have pouches.
These pouches are not used to host joeys,
but serve the exclusive purpose
of storing the male genitalia
to prevent them from getting tangled in weeds while swimming.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- That's so good.
- That's incredible.
- Tangled in weeds.
- Do you wish you had that?
- I don't go while swimming like you do, Anna.
- No, okay, and I don't get stuff tangled in weeds too.
- I'm always getting tangled in weeds.
(laughing)
- I can't picture the genitals of,
can anyone of this particular animal?
- If it's marsupial, then it will be
quite a big bull sack kangaroos, have a leg.
I have a kangaroo bull sack purse at home.
(laughing)
Two dozen.
- To see James tip in a restaurant is quite a sight.
(laughing)
As he gets out his little pantsnay glasses,
and opens the glass on his kangaroo scrotum.
- Yeah.
- I thought you guys knew that, that I had that.
I bought it when we were on tour the first time
in Australia. - Did you?
- Yeah.
- That's, yeah, it's ringing a bell now, yeah.
- So what was it? - Is it roomy?
(laughing)
- No, not, well, you could probably keep
a couple of billiard balls in it.
- Oh, okay, that is roomy.
I don't mean to give away too much.
(laughing)
I am impressed.
- But yeah, kangaroos have got quite large scrotum.
- And what's this called?
There's marsupial.
- This is a water opossum.
But I think generally speaking,
marsupials have similar reproductive systems, don't they?
- Yeah.
- They all tend to have like,
uteruses with three openings.
- Mm.
- Did that specify where the pouch was?
'Cause I'm picturing a kangaroo pouch,
and that feels like quite a long journey to-
- Probably not far off.
(laughing)
- It's probably not far off, though.
- You can't tuck yours in your top pocket, for instance.
(laughing)
Have you forgotten one of those little handkerchiefs?
- But the way evolution works is so mad.
'Cause it must have started out as a little skin flap
or something.
- Yeah.
- And presumably fewer male water opossums drowned
because they had this little evolutionary skin flap.
- Well, all had their testicles torn off
and couldn't reproduce.
- Right, exactly.
But there must have been a way in which like,
have you heard the latest thing in the water opossum world
is this little flap of skin, which protects your knackers?
I just think that's, it's unbelievable.
And then those are the fit ones that survived.
- It's crazy.
And of course, with this entire format,
we are relying on the people who wrote to us
telling us the truth.
- Oh yeah.
I've done no quality control on these whatsoever.
- Do your own research, guys.
We do it every week, you know?
Still haven't taken some responsibility.
- But ahead of that, I believe you.
- Very cool.
- Brilliant.
- Shall I do one?
- Yeah.
- This is from Dr. Kevin W. Jennings,
Department of Social Sciences, Lincoln Memorial University.
Astronaut Steve Hawley's space shuttle launches
kept getting scrubbed.
He had 15 or 16 launches scrubbed in his career.
A record, question mark.
After one scrub, I think scrub means didn't happen.
- Capsled.
- Yeah.
- You know, that's some no scrubs.
It's written by an astronaut
who really wanted to go into space.
- After one scrub prior to his fourth mission,
he remarked that the space shuttle
obviously knew he was aboard.
So it was refusing to launch.
His crewmates agreed.
So they made him wear a disguise
during the next launch attempt.
- No.
- They're all in spacesuits.
How much better disguise can you get?
- Yeah, so they made him wear a disguise
during the next launch attempt.
So the shuttle wouldn't recognize him.
It worked.
And the shuttle launched on that attempt.
The crew of his fifth mission forced him to do it again.
And it was successful again.
Apparently the space shuttle just didn't like him.
Pictures for a proof.
And then Andy's not included the pictures.
- Oh, no.
- But wow.
- The pictures seem essential.
This disguise, was it a kangaroo disguise?
Was it, what could it have been?
- Testicles were popping out of the book.
It's called Harley this guy.
- Steve Hawley.
- That's amazing.
- Very cool.
- God, and that's the scientists who believed that.
These are the people who were trusting to build rockets.
People who think space shuttles decide against people.
- The astronauts, they'll build the rockets.
- Oh, do they know?
I thought you had to do it all the way through.
- Dan, was that from an eminent scientist?
Did you say?
- That was from a doctor.
- Okay.
- It's not eminent, is it?
That'd be professor.
- You get away with nothing in this game.
- I'm a moderately achieving scientist.
- Okay.
Well, this, geez.
Here's an email from Colin McIntyre,
who says, "I'm the educator and resident historian
"of the New England Aquarium in Boston."
- Cool.
- "It entertains me and my colleagues no end
"when our beloved aquarium is mentioned on your podcast,
"e.g. Andre the seal, Animal Bartering,
"but we've never heard you refer to it by its actual name.
"As a friend of the podcast,
"I believe we've earned the right to be called
"the New England Aquarium
"rather than just an aquarium in Boston."
So fair enough.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And he's included some facts and here's one of them.
There is a mummified cod buried in the foundation
of the New England Aquarium,
but that's not the weird thing about it, I think.
What he says is it's called Ichabod.
The fish started the construction of the entire aquarium.
This is mad.
So the fish was the star
of the aquarium's groundbreaking ceremony in 1965,
when a scuba diver holding him
emerged from nearby Boston Harbor
and dropped him into a tank of water.
So at this point, it's a live fish.
This electronically triggered the construction equipment
on the future site of the aquarium,
thanks to a system designed by Harold Doc Egerton.
So the New England Aquarium was,
the construction was kick-started by a fish
being dropped into a tank of water.
- It was intentional.
- That was what it was always going to be, right?
- Yes.
- They planned.
- This was meant to be a library,
but we were going to drop in a book,
but then we dropped in a fish by mistake.
It's hard to tell if rockets know
which astronauts are going to go.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So they decided to build as a aquarium,
starting with a fish.
- Yeah, yeah.
A scuba diver comes out of the water holding a live fish,
drops it into a tank,
and that electronically senses a fish has been dropped in
and triggers the construction equipment.
That is a very cool opening ceremony.
- You know, like if you watch the Olympics,
they have the word they set off the fire, the flame.
They always do something really exciting,
but actually it's just a guy with a button
who's sat next to it, right?
- Right.
- I feel like I would do it in this situation as well.
I'm sorry to say.
- Do you mean like there was that famous one
where an archer shot the flame
and we all thought it landed?
Yeah, but it was, I see, yes.
- And who was it?
Which president?
There was a president who had to tell
on the Christmas lights once remotely.
And he thought, I think it was in the '50s,
it was maybe it was Lyndon Johnson,
and he thought he was doing it remotely
'cause of this amazing remote light turning on technology.
And actually, I think there was just someone
that lights in the White House who just looked to switch.
- Yeah, right.
- Maybe that's how it's happening all over the world.
- So you're casting doubt on this, James, I think.
- I'm just saying that if I was in charge,
I wouldn't rely on the fish.
- Yeah, that's fair.
When the Queen, the true Queen, sent her first tweet
or whatever, she pressed a button,
and then I think it just like prodded a nearby intern
to a friend and sent tweet.
I seem to remember.
- Wow, a fister of a Jack in a book.
Here's one from Ralph Linsangan.
He says he's a big fan.
Thanks, Ralph.
And-
- Of yours or of all of us?
- I've got a scene of mine.
- What's your doctorate in?
Ralph?
- America's just 71 miles long,
measured from its easternmost point
to its westernmost point.
And he's talking about that trick fact,
which is the Aleutian Islands,
which cross the 180th Meridian.
So they constitute the easternmost
and the westernmost point,
but the other way around to which you'd think.
- Interesting.
- Because the easternmost point is the furthest
sort of west from where we are.
So there you go.
- That's a great fact.
- Yeah, that's awesome.
- It is.
And I remember, we were actually just talking
about the Aleutian Islands in a podcast we recorded,
which may have gone out by the time this goes out,
or it may not have.
It's about Alaska.
But we were talking about something
that I don't think as well-
- It was last week's show.
There you go.
We were talking about something,
I don't think it's well known enough,
that the only land war fought in America
in the Second World War was in the Aleutian Islands,
with the Japanese just-
- That was Japan, USA.
I didn't think any bit of America
had ever been occupied in the Second World War.
- Everyone forgets, Fuehler Islands.
- Yeah.
- That's the bit where humans walked across, isn't it?
You know, there was a land bridge there.
- Oh really?
- From which side?
- Well, Andy nodded, so you get a klaxon,
because it's not true.
And this is recent.
They've kind of looked at what it would have been like
around the time when humans came over,
and that would have been pretty much impossible
to walk over, because it was so muddy
and swampy and stuff like that.
So they must have gone across in either boats,
or you know, like putting huge tennis rackets on your shoes.
- Like Pogo Sticks, isn't it?
- Oh, Pogo Sticks could have done it, yeah,
but there's no way you could have walked across.
It wasn't a bridge in the modern sense of the word.
- Really? - Yeah, right.
So here's the fact that I think could have been for you, Dan,
because they referenced two of your facts from history.
- Okay.
- It's from Vic Olds.
And they say, "I've been meaning to send in this fact
"for a long time and have been,
"after hearing your recent facts
"about Harry Balls and Willie Hull,
"I believe I have a female name to rival them.
"About time we had some representation on this show, Dan."
- Back away. - Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
- "In 1943, a horse called Count Fleet
"achieved the US Triple Crown in horse racing.
"His owner/trainer was called Fanny Hertz.
"And I believe it does sometimes when you ride horses."
(laughing)
- Very strong. - Lovely.
- Very strong, Fanny Hertz. - The famous hymen breaker,
you're always told as a kid.
- Is that right?
- Always told as a girl, don't worry.
Your hymen doesn't always break when you lose your virginity
because you might have been a horse rider.
- Yeah.
- And that probably would have broken it.
Gross for the horses.
(laughing)
- You're not doing it naked, are you?
- Well, it depends which riding school you attend.
- Yeah.
Shall I do my next one?
- Yeah, we probably had enough hymen chat.
(farting)
- I was curious about the name Sherlock
and how common it was in general use in the UK.
Turns out very not.
- According to...
(laughing)
- Did you write the same old time?
- Very not.
- Did I say very not?
- He said it. - Yeah.
- Who wrote the same old?
- I'll come to that a bit.
Turns out not very.
(laughing)
- Oh.
- According to free BMD, births and marriages and deaths,
there were seven children registered with the name Sherlock
between 1837 and 1887 when Conan Doyle
first published the fictional detective.
Between 1890 and 1920, there were 16 Sherlocks born,
half of whom also had the surname Holmes.
So families called Holmes seemed to like
having a son called Sherlock.
One family in Pontefract had both a Sherlock and a Mycroft.
- Oh.
- The sons of Richard Holmes and Martha, Ney Belch.
So fan worship isn't anything new.
It goes on, but the last Sherlock Holmes
was born in 1942 in Stoke.
I believe he is still alive.
And if so, would be the last of the gentlemen still standing.
And that's from Guy Holmes.
- Ah, lovely. - Oh, nice.
- That's very cool.
- Yeah, really cool research.
- Right, here's one.
Evan Friedman, American actor, Jerry Hallever,
has appeared as Saddam Hussein in six separate films.
In fact, Saddam Hussein is the only character
he's ever played.
- Right.
- That's very good.
- Typecasting.
- I have a typecasting fact that I was gonna suggest
for a future show.
Well, maybe I'll say it now.
- Yeah.
- So the woman who won Best Spotting Actress
before Gone With The Wind in 1939 was Hattie McDaniel.
And she played the same role
in I think it's about 130 other movies.
- Basically.
- Not the same character, but the same style of character.
'Cause she was typecast as like this sort of matriarchal,
African-American mother.
- Okay.
- And you know that in the Tom and Jerry cartoons,
when there's a lady stud that she's going,
"Tomas, Thomas!"
That's based on her as well.
- Is it really?
- Yeah, but she won this award.
And actually, I think she couldn't go to a lot of parties
'cause they were still segregated at the time.
But when she won that award, yeah, basically they put her
as exactly the same character in everything.
- What a shame it's not literally the same character,
like combining all these universes of film together.
It's one person.
- That's amazing.
- That's incredible, yeah.
- Japan's crown jewels probably don't exist.
- Oh. - According to Steve McCabe.
(laughing)
- And he would know.
He says that Japan has three Imperial sacred treasures.
And then he lists those.
And apparently they're handed over
to each new emperor, his coronation,
but they've not been seen by anyone
outside the Imperial household in centuries.
Wikipedia notes that the actual historical status
of these legendary treasures is unknown.
And they're intentionally kept from public view.
So Japan's telling us they're real.
We're not allowed to see them.
It's not certain where they're kept.
And the three treasures are a sword, a mirror,
and a jewel with special names.
What do we think?
- I think that's, there must be lots of things
in this country that we don't know where they are.
- Yeah, we've never seen. - That we've never seen.
- Yeah, they must be right.
I don't know what they are.
- Head of MI5.
- Oh yeah, do they exist?
- Oh, you think we have a prop head
and there's a secret actual head?
- Yeah, I didn't think until you said that,
but that's so convincing.
- It is when you say it, yeah.
- What's the point, 'cause crown jewels are something
that's to show off, isn't it?
What's the point in having that if no one's allowed to see it?
- I wonder if in the olden days,
you could leverage against it,
borrow stuff from your barons.
- I bet you could.
- Because I got this really old spoon here.
- Isn't that the last bit of the old crown jewels
that still survives as a spoon?
It's the only one and everything else has been--
- It all got lost in the wash, didn't it?
- There was the wash and then there was the Civil War.
- Not the wash, I'm sorry,
which is better if I not in a washing machine.
(laughing)
- Sorry.
- We've totally done two high eight.
- Where's the wash again?
Is it Lincolnshire?
- Off the coast of Norfolk, isn't it?
- Oh, it's off the coast.
It does a bit--
- I don't know, maybe it's Anning Street.
- It does a very marshy bit
and King John supposedly lost the crown jewels in the wash.
Do people still look for it then?
- No.
- Why not?
- I feel like they're not.
- If we know a specific location,
I think it's probably a bit bigger than is easily searchable.
- You're right, there should be detectorists
that are really--
- I actually thought detectorists,
I kind of assumed that was a place where if you went,
then you would see lots of detectorists desperately hoping.
- Maybe all the detectorists are just assuming
that all the other detectorists are going for it
and they're like, oh, that's too obvious,
I'm gonna look in this field and search.
- They're actually poking out of the ground there.
(laughing)
That could not be easy on a phone.
(upbeat music)
- Here's one, this is from Eddie Edwards.
I was, Edward Edwards.
- Fake name, clearly fake, John.
- I was listening to your audience fact special
and you were talking about that prop nuclear bomb
that was too accurate.
Well, the fake money used in rush hour two,
the second rush hour movie.
Thank you, Eddie.
(laughing)
Was so good that a bunch of people working on the movie
spent some on the Vegas strip
and the secret service ended up getting involved.
It led to a bunch of rules being put in place
about prop money going forward.
- I remember this 'cause they are incredibly strict now.
- Yeah, great scene in the film as well.
It's a good film rush hour two.
Absolutely decent movie.
- Absolutely.
- And it ends with this money showering all over the place,
you know, the suitcase full of money explodes or whatever.
And it's this huge, great room they're in
and the money is going absolutely over.
So I'm sure a load of people could have just pocketed some.
- It's a big thing in films that they worry about on set
when they're using a lot of money.
And actually, if you look at the money
that you have to use in films,
it looks absolutely nothing like real money.
It's got to be about 1.5 times the size and have,
you know, 'cause they've even done ones like British money
with kind of a dog instead of the queen on it
or weird stuff like that, I think.
And they've still said that's too similar
that could be passed off as real money.
- Very, very rich.
- Has to be so different.
- Can I cheekily pull off a double now?
I just have two thematically very linked ones.
- Sure, please.
- I thought it might be fun.
So Lake Berg writes,
"I've come across the following.
"Apollonia was a Christian martyr
"who had her teeth pulled out as torture in 249 CE.
"She later became the patron saint of dentistry.
"Unsure how deep-cut this is,
"and you've probably looked into saints plenty before,
"but I find it funny that she got qualifications
"in the technical field of dentistry
"by just having her teeth pulled out."
I think that's fair, that's a good point.
And then, David and Katie write,
"Hi, just writing in with a fact in dedication
"to our friends Scott and Doris, who've just had a baby."
So quite a lot of names flying around,
but congratulations, Scott and Doris.
And hello, David and Katie, who write,
"The phenomenon of babies being born
"with teeth already erupted, brackets natal teeth,
"has an occurrence of around 0.05%.
"In other words, there is approximately one case
"every 2,000 births."
- Last piece, duh.
(all laughing)
- How good is that?
- NB, yes, it's a bit of a stretch
because the prevalence varies between studies,
but roughly, roughly,
what every 2,000, that's stunning.
- That's really good stuff.
- Lovely, thank you, David.
- You know what I tried to find the other day,
and I couldn't, is a picture of a baby skull.
You know how babies are born with all their teeth,
and then you get photos of baby skulls,
which do the rounds where you can see all their adult teeth
up in their gums that haven't come down yet.
But actually, I'm not convinced that those pictures are real.
There's only about two of them floating around,
and they don't seem to be very well verified.
You know, there was one science writer who tweeted one.
So I really want to know if anyone's ever seen
an x-ray of a baby's skull.
- Yeah, I have a feeling that's not true, that.
'Cause I wonder if they're smaller at the time,
and then they grow in your head.
- We're not saying you're not born with all your teeth.
- No, I think you definitely are born
with all your teeth, aren't you, and they descend,
but maybe they're tiny.
- They can't, well, they're not full-size, are they?
'Cause you've seen a baby, they're small.
The head would be all teeth if they had 32 adult teeth.
- In the pictures that they show, the head is all teeth.
Like, it's full-size adult teeth,
up in the baby's cheek, it's scary shit.
And I've believed it for years.
So yeah, please if you've seen an x-ray.
Yeah, I'm interested that James also thinks maybe it's small.
- I think it's not, I think some of those are fake pictures.
I believe, I feel like I've heard that, maybe I have.
- But how do the teeth get in then?
- They sneak in, and the tooth fairy brings them.
- I think when you eat more calcium as a baby,
for the first seven years of your life,
you take in the calcium, and that helps them to grow.
The same way that you don't have kneecaps and stuff like that.
- Right, and then all the milk gives you all the calcium?
- Yeah.
- There we go.
- I think, I can't really.
- Wow, that would be blowing a shit wide open,
'cause I've seen that image of a side profile of a baby's girl.
- Indeed.
- God, that's incredible, it's all tooth.
- Yeah, disgusting.
- The whole tooth, nothing but the tooth.
- It was when I showed that.
(laughing)
- Jesus.
- So anyway, if you know about that stuff,
'cause we are speculating a little bit here.
- Absolutely, please tell us.
- To podcast.qa.com.
- This is a fact from Andrew Kirkland,
and Tee just says that his favorite fact this week
is that according to Wikipedia,
the Irish invented whiskey in the 14th century,
and then they didn't invent anything else
for another 300 years, and.
- That's understandable.
- He's got a point.
- Well, exactly, you've reached your peak, haven't you?
And it's true, the Wikipedia page on Irish inventions
does have a 14th century section,
where they have three inventions.
They have the Precursor to Modern Gaelic Football.
They have the Northern Reginians Anthem,
a huge invention, I think we can all agree,
and whiskey, and the next invention is 17th century.
- And what was that?
- Good point you asked.
(all laughing)
- You don't know it's the whiskey that did it,
it might be the Northern Reginians Anthem, it's so catchy.
Everyone was seeing it for the next 300 years.
(all laughing)
- I have a whiskey related one.
- There you are.
- Okay, so this is from Chris Patterson,
and he thinks that he might be the first outside voice
to be ever heard on noses and things of fish.
- Chris Patterson, the former governor of Hong Kong.
- Sorry, that's Chris.
- Chris Patterson.
- Yeah, okay.
- Carry on.
- Maybe his son.
- Yes.
(all laughing)
- Can you remember?
So this was someone,
we did a live show and this person shouted out.
- Okay.
- We were in Scandinavia somewhere.
Can you remember anyone who shouted out in Scandinavia?
- Where did we go?
We went Gothenburg, and we went Stockholm.
- I think it was in Gothenburg.
- Gothenburg.
- Oh no, in Stockholm, he says it in the email.
- I can't remember.
- Did they shout out something other than--
- Yeah, so we were discussing cyborgs
and asked in the audience if there were any cyborgs
in the crowd, and he got to shout out I'm a cyborg.
And this is 'cause he had an RFID chip
put into his body.
You know, like you could get a little chip in your body
so you could use it as a credit card or something.
Anyway, he never got to tell us the whole story that time,
but I've got the whole story here.
He went to an event called Chips and Whiskey,
thinking that it was potato crisps and alcohol
that he was gonna get.
But in fact, it was someone giving you these implants,
and he said after a few whiskies,
it seemed like a good idea,
and I got the largest needle I have ever seen
injecting a chip into my hand.
I've used this as a gym card and not much more.
- That's so great.
- Do you know what was that guy called?
- Chris Patton's son.
- Of course.
I've always thought those people all got chips
and started to kind of card douchebags, to be honest,
but that is the best excuse for doing it, I've ever heard.
- I almost got one.
- Exactly, exactly my point.
- Moving on.
- Well, I did, years ago,
I did this little taster tape that was filmed,
whereby it was looking into all of this world of cyborgs,
and as part of it, they wanted to put a chip into me,
and then right at the last minute,
they had someone come in with the device,
and the health and safety didn't allow
for the chip itself to go in,
but they still injected me with the thing to put it in.
It's so painful.
So I was filmed as the process as if I had the chip in me,
and then I had to--
- What did they put in there?
- Nothing, it was just empty.
- So they say.
- Yeah, but yeah, they still,
and then I had to sit there and pretend
that I was turning a lamp on with my hand,
and they, like we're talking about with the queen
having someone press the button,
there was someone on the floor, out of shot,
pressing the button of the lamp flickering,
as I was going, "Look at me, I'm a cyborg."
- Wow, TV is full of lies, isn't it?
You and David Attenborough.
I just, I can't believe with you, Dan,
that however many years I know you,
there's always a new anecdote that I've never heard.
- I'll do one now.
Derek Bailey writes,
"I heard the weirdest fact about albatross
"that may be fish worthy.
"They knew from finding remains of birds
"that the main thing that they eat are squid,
"but they've never been observed catching them.
"They can't dive, so they decided to tag some birds
"to see what was going on.
"The signatures of these tags show they swam for a bit
"and then the line went into crazy squiggles.
"A young scientist showed his professor
"and he said he thought the tags were broken.
"The prof decided they needed to go
"and watch what was happening.
"They went out to see at night to observe.
"They found these huge birds swimming around
"in tight circles, pulling and pushing
"with their large webbed feet.
"They were creating phosphorescence,
"which was drawing the squid to the surface
"and there was their buffet."
- Cool. - Lovely.
- Like monster flames. - Very cool, Derek Bailey.
- How are they creating phosphorescence
with their feet, Derek Bailey?
- Well, you get those little sort of bacteria and stuff
and algae that live in the water
and when you move your hands and make waves,
they light up. - I see.
- You get them in Mexico.
- Do you remember that more thing?
- The trails of ships can sometimes glow.
- Yes, I know, I know, but I didn't realise
that another animal who didn't have it
could deliberately would swish it up.
- Oh, it's just water churning, isn't it?
- Yeah, isn't it? - Yeah, very cool.
- Actually, 'cause I was walking on a beach in Hobart
in Tasmania a couple of years ago,
I've never seen anything like it.
It was at night time and as you put your foot down
on the sand, it glowed fluorescent blue all around you.
It was absolutely extraordinary.
- Wow, it's like avatar.
That's very cool.
- Is that what happens in avatar?
- I actually can't remember, Andy.
- Yeah. - There we go.
- It actually reminded me more of those disco pads
where if you step on a glowing bit,
a bit glows and you step on it.
- Those dance machines, I used to love those things.
Oh my God, I used to love them so much.
- Oh, they're good.
I still do the occasional dance.
- Yeah, if I'm passing an arcade.
- God, is that right?
'Cause I find them very exhausting.
- Oh, the tiring, yeah.
- I guess probably you're a bit younger than me, but yeah.
- Well, no, it's tiring.
- How do you, was it, you both still do dance?
- No, I haven't done it for years, no.
But like, would you hold onto the bars when you did it
or were you like hardcore?
- No, I don't think I do.
- Is that like having the walls up in Berlin?
(all laughing)
- Exactly.
- When's the last time you did it, Andy?
- I would say within the last year.
- On your own, walking past an arcade.
- With my wife.
We went to a video game arcade.
- Okay, that's different.
- Did you do it where you were like on the same team?
- She didn't participate.
(all laughing)
She didn't want to.
She said, "I'll just watch you, darling."
- I want you to take on that nine-year-old.
(all laughing)
- Yeah.
- No, it was really fun.
It was really fun.
It was a video game bar.
A video game sort of bar slash arcade thing.
I wasn't drinking obviously, but.
- No, your wife ordered three large vodkas at the bar.
- Do you guys remember that great story
about Jim Lovell from Apollo 13?
So obviously the story of Apollo 13 is insane.
They break down in space on the way to the moon.
They need to get back.
But he had a situation back on Earth
when he was a fighter pilot that was equally as dangerous.
He was on his plane over the sea, got lost
and managed last minute to find his way back
to the ship to land on
because he followed the trail of phosphorescence
that was being left in the wake of the ship.
- I thought that was what you were referencing.
Yeah, it was when he was landing on aircraft carrier,
wasn't he?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Astonishing, very cool.
So where did the dance mat fit into that?
(all laughing)
Once he got out.
All right, here's one.
Alexis Beckett from British Columbia.
I'm a long time listener.
I've never written him before,
but for some reason,
Andy Demarney we do persuaded me this Saturday afternoon.
Hmm, I think.
I had nothing good to say.
(all laughing)
- Welcome to the podcast recording mate.
So I reached for a weird fact.
I remember being told in high school,
in the Yukon, it's illegal to push a moose
from an airplane in flight.
It's also illegal to watch a moose
be pushed from an airplane in flight.
I'm not certain whether this is accurate,
but I've always found it entertaining
and we shouldn't let the truth
get in the way of a good story.
Thank you, Alexis.
- That feels a bit cheat, right?
- Yeah, I don't know, Andy.
That doesn't sound true.
- It would be hard to prosecute people who've watched it.
Now the prosecution is gonna bring in some witnesses.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, okay.
No, it's almost certainly nonsense, isn't it?
Thank you Alexis, regardless.
- Yeah, it doesn't feel like it.
- Nice try.
From James Milne, everyone knows he says,
and I think he's correct,
that Oslo gifts a tree to London for Christmas every year,
which it does, has done since World War II.
But James Milne says,
it's not the only tree gifted to a British city
from a Norwegian city.
And I didn't know this.
The city of Bergen gifts a tree to Newcastle every year as well.
Also in recognition of World War II.
And it's because Oslo started gifting London this tree,
and other parts of Norway wanted to recognise
it wasn't just London.
It was the whole of the UK that contributed to World War II.
And so actually there were quite a lot of cities in the UK
that get free trees from Norway.
There's Grimsbury, Edinburgh, Orkney, Shetland.
- Grimsby.
- What did I say?
- Grimsbury.
- That's a local cheese limit.
(laughing)
- That is a really good fact.
- Yeah, I can know that.
- It also is, people always complain
about the Trafalgar Square Tree,
because it's this particular kind of coniferous tree
that the Norwegians send over.
And it doesn't look as glossy
as some of the really thick branched trees.
People say, "Oh, it looks so scraggy."
And you just think, "Learn some history."
You know, it's the--
- But I also think they put some not very good lights on it.
You know, like when you do your tree,
you put like baubles in really nice places.
You've got tinsel all the way around.
They just kind of hang it from the top,
these sort of lights coming down.
- They just do some strings down, don't they?
- Yes, I think it looks crap.
- That's probably us, though.
I'm sure we do the lights.
- Oh yeah, I'm not playing in the Norwegians for that.
But I just think they don't help themselves.
- Yeah, I've always thought that.
You've got to embed the lights.
They're not for draping.
- Yeah.
- It's mad.
- Probably a health and safety thing.
Just on war thanks things,
when we were on tour in Australia,
not so long ago,
we went to Melbourne,
and I had a day of sightseeing before the show,
and Melbourne has a present that the British provided
in thanks for years of support during total war.
Britain gave Australia a small model village.
- Really?
- Yeah, and you can walk around it now.
- That's fantastic.
Of what village?
- Which village, yeah.
- It's a generic village.
So there's, you know, the Shakespeare Arms Pub,
and there's a little post office.
But honestly, you go there and you think,
this is not a good thank you present
after quite a lot of sacrifice.
- Well, everyone loves a model village.
- Yeah.
What's an appropriate thank you for you.
After six years of support during total war,
I'm trying to dance that.
That's a good point.
Maybe Melbourne really wanted a model village.
But it's very sweet.
It's really sweet.
If you're anywhere near Melbourne,
you've got to check it out.
- That is quite strange.
What was it?
Do you remember that thing where there was a gift exchange
between Gordon Brown and Barack Obama?
And Barack Obama like?
- Gordon Brown gave Barack Obama an incredibly beautiful,
I think it was a pen holder carved from the wood
of an anti-slaving ship after Britain outlawed slavery
and was cracking down on the illegal slave trade.
So it's very symbolic.
And Obama gave Gordon Brown a bag of DVD.
- A shower too, I think.
- Which were in the wrong zone
to be played on British DVD players.
A golden age of translates.
Obama's one misstep, I'd say.
- Yeah, absolutely.
Just actually, can I say it on war related gifts?
- Gernica, the battle started by Pablo Picasso.
- Just so that he had something to paint.
- Exactly, you know.
You've got to create your material sometimes.
No, Gernica was a battle in the Spanish Civil War.
The Spanish right wing side had a lot of help
from fellow fascists from Italy and Germany.
And the reason the Nazis got involved
was because it was a birthday present to Hitler
from the head of the Luftwaffe
who I think was it going?
It was going, had a Luftwaffe.
Yeah, so it was a happy birthday.
And actually it really fucked up
because the weather screwed it up.
So it had to be delayed by about five days.
So if you look at the dates of Hitler's birthday
and the dates of Gernica,
they were five days late,
but apparently Hitler was very understanding about that.
- Yeah, I mean, sometimes you can't have your birthday party
on the day of your birthday, can you?
- Exactly, you've got to wait till the weekend.
- It's on a Tuesday.
That's a callback to last week's show.
- The Luftwaffe's involvement in a battle
was a birthday present.
- Yeah, because I think Gary knew
that Hitler would be really pleased.
And it was like a surprise.
You know, I decided to get it built.
- Did they arrive in a giant cake?
- They came out of a cake.
- Yeah, flew out of a cake, yeah.
- Here's a fact from Mark Weiberd,
after whom the play bus stop is named.
That's a bit of a niche one.
People of a certain age.
There was a kid's show called Play Bus
and they had the Weiberd stop.
Anyway, Mark Weiberd says,
"There is a recently completed Australian legal case
"establishing an important legal principle
"that is called Tickle versus Giggle."
- Come on.
- He says, "It is important and serious
"for reasons of establishing trans rights,
"but it is purely the name that makes me smile."
- Do we get any more details?
Or is it like, details too dry and serious?
Name, very funny.
- I don't have any more details.
It feels like it would be dry and serious.
But Tickle versus Giggle.
- Tickle versus Giggle, lovely.
- I wonder who's the good guy there, Tickle or Giggle?
- Tickle.
- Gotta be Giggle, Tickle is a bad guy always, right?
- Mr. Tickle.
- Yeah, no one likes being tickled.
- He's a good guy.
He's misunderstood.
- What about John Tickle,
the ex-big brother housemate who then went on
to do gadget shows?
- Yes.
- There's quite a lot of amazing niche references
coming in one.
- I reckon AI could just listen to me
in the last 10 minutes and work out exactly
when I was born, but John Tickle.
- John Tickle, I always remember what I liked.
I think this was his first so-called invention
after big brother was the toaster.
Do you remember the toaster that delays
the second bit of toast?
So you put it down, but it doesn't start cooking
the second bit of toast until your first one's ready.
Very sensible.
I don't know, 'cause you're always gonna deal
with the second cold bit of toast.
- Yes.
- Where is he now?
- Where is he?
- John Tickle.
- Well, you can retire after that toast moment, can't you?
- Really?
- 'Cause we've all got one now.
We've really shaken off any international listeners,
I think.
- I've got one here from Nina de Villiers.
Long time listener of the podcast.
I used to work on seahorses.
- On seahorses.
- Very, very small wet grad national.
- That's how I broke my hymen.
- In South Africa, actually, I should say,
how would you pronounce that?
- Ooh.
- South Africa.
- I wouldn't, I'd guess canizna, I think.
- Okay, canizna.
So I used to work on seahorses and canizna,
and a while back, I learned from a colleague
that seahorses make vocalizations.
They make clicking noises during courtship and feeding,
but they also growl to startle predators.
This is followed by quivering their bodies.
At one point, there was research investigating seahorses
to determine where the sound were produced.
I briefly got involved by taking a dried seahorse
to be scanned at our local hospital
in the X-ray and CT machine.
Other than a very cool looking scan,
where you could see all of its baby teeth.
(all laughing)
I'm not actually sure it helped the researcher.
But she took it, yeah.
- But it did help the hospital waiting list,
the queue of ambulances outside,
waiting for you to scan your seahorse.
- This is a very recondite one, I love it.
It's from Isabelle Starling, in relation to Mark Weibert.
Something fun I heard the other day.
William Jones, the man generally credited
with the use of the Greek letter pi
for the ratio of a circle's circumference to its diameter,
was the father of William Jones, another William Jones,
one of the first to suggest the existence
of the Proto-Indo-European language known as pi.
- Oh, very good. - In no way!
- How good is that?
- Hang on, is that a coincidence?
What, is it one of the names after the other?
- No, it looks like a--
- 'Cause why do we call pi pi?
- Because after the letter.
- Just the letter, that's just how far we've got.
'Cause you don't hear all the alpha to--
- No, there is a reason, there is a reason.
I can't remember what it is.
- Yeah. - Wow, that's amazing.
- I think that's a cracking fact, thank you, Isabelle.
She finishes her email.
I also discovered that Shirley Ballas'
ex-father-in-law invented the strimmer.
Although I suspect that one is only interesting to me.
- Yeah, I like it.
- Yeah, and for international listeners,
Shirley, I can't explain Shirley Ballas.
- There's no one left, there is no international listener left.
- I don't know who that is, so please.
- She's on strictly.
- Former dancer.
- Got it, asking if Shirley Bassie, got it.
All right.
This is from a guy called Matt Lowry.
A new pre-print by some folks at the University of Pennsylvania
claims we can use resus macaques
to predict the winner of elections.
And it's a pretty interesting discussion
about behavioral neuro-economics, is it now?
But it's basically judging on how long
they look at each candidate.
He also says that the area of behavioral neuro-economics
is a field in a bit of crisis at the moment.
So I think actually, 'cause he works in that field,
he's just angling for some funding.
But there you go, how long a resus macaque
looks at a candidate?
I guess it must mean they're more likely to win,
although he doesn't specify.
- So do you reckon if you want to be president,
if you sell a table load of bananas to your face,
(all laughing)
that gives you more of a chance?
- That'll do it.
(all laughing)
- I can think of a conch, he's all right with mine, yeah.
- We've seen worse candidates, that's all I'm saying.
- Meanwhile, the Swedish minister of equality's going,
"No!"
(all laughing)
- Two week call, like, lovely.
- He, oh well, here we go.
He says, so the paper's filled with a number of amusing quotes,
such as, "Here we show that resus macaques
"who have no knowledge about political candidates,
"all their policies implicitly predict the outcome."
Why would they predict the outcome?
- So is it different though,
when they do understand their policies?
- If they've read the manifesto,
then yeah, it does change their responses.
"Implicitly predict the outcomes of U.S.
"a gubernatorial and senatorial elections
"based solely on visual features,
"and our findings have implications for political campaigns,
"which should strategically use photos emphasizing
"or de-emphasizing jaw width and cheekbone width."
I don't know which they prefer,
he doesn't say which they prefer.
- Oh, wide or narrow, draw bones.
Oh, probably wide, nice wide cheekbones, you know.
- Wide jaw, gotta be, yeah.
Well done macaques, let's just get them to vote.
- Isabella Remet writes,
"At the Gothenburg Universium,
"we support mantle of universe and museum,
"and which I went to when we were in Gothenburg,
"text messages are sent to the sharks
"so they don't get scared
"when the nearby train tunnel under construction
"blasts in the rock."
- Aw.
- So they've got a warning text,
like when someone comes around the cafe saying,
"We're doing a fire alarm, it's just an alarm."
- Like when the government sends you a message saying,
"This is a test alert."
Honestly, it's fine, there's no nuclear weapons on the way.
It's just a test.
- I mean, we've obviously got no more to go on here,
but I wonder what the text says.
(all laughing)
Probably in Swedish, who says da-da.
And also would you not get, if I was a shark,
I would think a text message would scare me quite a bit.
- That would be very scary, yeah, yeah.
- I just don't work on the water phones, do they?
- You get these really cool packets
so you can put them in now with a pouch.
- Yeah.
- I mean, I keep my genitals in mind,
but that's for a time as well.
(all laughing)
- Whose turn is it?
- Oh, it's my turn.
So thank you, that was a good one.
- Antonio Mantica says,
"Just finished listening to episode 559
where you mentioned that the Catholic diocese
of Orlando claims jurisdiction over the moon
since that's where Apollo 11 launched from.
I'm surprised nobody, brackets Dan,
didn't mention that Buzz Aldrin,
a Texas freemason established a Masonic lodge
on the moon called Tranquility Lodge,
a number 2000 under the Grand Lodge of Texas
who now claim Masonic jurisdiction to the moon.
According to their official website,
meetings are held quarterly in various cities around Texas
until such time as the lodge may hold
its meetings on the moon itself.
Can I just say, I did randomly select these things
out of the pile.
I've never heard of that.
- I didn't think he was a Mason.
- I mean, you can be a Catholic in a Mason.
- Of course, what a surprise.
- Yeah, that rings a tiny bell.
I don't remember.
- We did quite extensive research on him
when he came on our radio show.
- Yeah.
- I didn't, that never came up.
- Well, it wouldn't do.
- Oh, did it.
- It feels like the 20th century was big for the Masons.
- Oh, yeah.
- It's now not quite as big a thing.
- Yeah, I think on downhill a bit, do you think?
- I think a little bit.
- That's a shame, isn't it?
I think that all the forces are at large now.
- Internet.
- The Masons of the modern day, the Internets.
Well, it's just a shame to lose
those exciting handshakes.
- Yeah, that's true.
That's true.
I agree with that.
Here's one.
- I don't know them.
How do you know they're exciting?
- Yeah, you are not allowed in.
What's going on?
- Any handshake is exciting.
There's not a conventional handshake, right?
If you shake someone's hand and anything happens,
that's not just them grasping your hand and shaking it,
you're excited.
- I don't know.
That one with the finger goes and gives you a little tickle.
- You'd be excited.
- I'd rather giggle than tickle in my case.
(laughing)
- Here's a great one from Andre Ryback.
Regarding pink noise and the human ear bracing
for impact of a louder noise.
- Yes, I mentioned that where cars have a pink noise
that they release just before impact
so that your eardrums don't shatter.
- Brilliant.
I was very surprised that none of the hosts mentioned
the tense or timpani muscle.
It's one of the most, no such thing as a fish muscles
in the human body because a portion of the population
has voluntary control of it.
The other portion who only have the automatic reflex
that was mentioned on fish
can never fully know what it's like.
So this is what Andre says and it turns out I can do this.
Tensing the tense or timpani muscle allows you
to make a rumbling noise in the ear on demand,
a noise that only you can hear.
So you just sort of tense your inner ear.
You can hear that rumbling.
- Oh my God. - Change of nodding,
you can do that.
- Hold on, so I tense my inner ear.
- Just make the rumbling noise in your ear.
- Oh yeah, just did it.
- Yeah.
- No, I can make a high ringing noise, but not a rumbling.
- You can't join the secret club then.
(laughing)
Oh, we had such an amazing hand shake plant.
- I love that thing that they said of the most
no such thing as a fish muscle, they say.
- Yeah, he said most no such thing as fish
class QI muscles, but I edited it down.
- Oh okay, but still it's quite a cool thing
that we've built off the back of finding
these interesting facts and that's another book idea.
You know, the most no such thing as a fish thing.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I love that.
- Can I give an alternate muscle just while we're
in the ear area?
And that is recently, you know, like some animals
can move their ears and humans can move their ears,
but really they're just moving the jaw
and the ears kind of go, but we have the muscles
that can move your ears in the same way
that a dog or a cat can move their ears,
but the muscles are not strong enough.
They did an experiment where they played some sound
in an area and they looked at what like muscles
were tensing and they could see that these muscles
were moving, but they weren't moving their ears.
- Wow.
- So yeah, like if you hear a sound,
if you hear someone you say your name
behind you to the left, your body is trying
to move your ear around towards it,
but the muscles aren't strong enough.
- Is there something we could, like if we snipped
a bit of the top and bottom of your ear,
do you think it could swivel?
- Oh yeah, like a tongue tie, we've got a near tie.
- What if you just spent your life training
and then you spent your life training your children
to try and move their ears
and they spent their life training their children.
How long would it take before we could get this back?
- We will probably have to find--
- That's not how evolution works, I don't think.
- Oh, you have to get a flamarcosis.
- Yes, you are.
- Has a flamarcosis been overtaken, sorry?
- What would be better is if some people
genetically modified so that they could move their ears
and then they found each other really sexy.
- Will they hear more people saying, "Do you want to have sex?"
And then they are more fertile as a result.
- Exactly, yeah.
- That's all you think's been holding you back.
- I'm on the dance mat, I can't hear a thing.
- Well, shall we wrap up?
- Yeah.
- Thank you so much to everyone for sending in your effects
and for listening and please keep sending them in.
We are podcast@qi.com.
We love getting facts, we get a load of great ones.
These are the absolute creme de la creme.
This is the standard, really.
You should be matching.
- Variable.
(all laughing)
- Just like us, it's the nicest tribute anyone could pay.
So thank you again, we will be back in a week
with a regular broadcast between now and then,
I guess it's just time to sing the song.
- As we always do, Andy, we'll get out of here.
- Yeah, just go to, just, I mean, just, you know.
- Darn, you want to wrap us up?
(all laughing)
- Okay, that's it, that's all of your facts.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact, Andy, take over.
- You can get in touch with us on the internet.
I'm on--
- I'm back in.
You can get us on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @shrivaland, James.
- My Instagram is the nicest thing is James Hacken.
- Andy, I'm on Blue Sky, @andrewhunterm.
- Yeah, and @andrewhunterm,
where can they get to us as a group?
- Instagram are no such thing as a fish.
Twitter are no such thing.
Or email podcast.qi.com.
- We can do it.
- We also have a website, don't we, Andy?
- Yes, it's no such thing as a fish.com, is it?
- Yeah, it is.
- Okay, yeah.
- And if you go to those such things as a fish.com,
there's all sorts of stuff there.
Lots of previous episodes, some merch.
There's the Portal to Club Fish,
which is our member's club,
where you can get all sorts of bonus content,
really fun, ad-free episodes.
Oh.
- Do that.
- Get back in, Dan.
(both laughing)
- Tag me, tag me.
We're also playing a live show in Sheffield in July.
You should come to it.
It's called The Crossed Wires Festival.
It's a podcast festival, very exciting.
But otherwise, just come back next week,
where we'll have someone who actually knows
how to helm this show.
We'll see you then, Andy.
- Bye.
- Goodbye.
- What, did I get that wrong?
(both laughing)
(upbeat music)