(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of "No Sex Things as a Fish,"
which was recorded at the Nerdland Festival in Belgium.
This is the thing we do every year
we have done for the last few years.
It's a brilliant festival.
It's definitely worth checking out for future years.
It's basically, imagine Disneyland had nerds instead of mice.
It is, that's what it is really.
It's loads of talks, it's loads of exhibitions,
it's science, it's nerd culture,
it's everything you can want if that is your bag.
And we always have an amazing time there
with a great audience.
And as usual, we were joined by Leven Skela.
Anna did not make the journey this time,
so it is the boys and Leven who did this show.
And Leven, you will know if you are a regular listener
to fish, he may well have the record
as most appearances of a non-elf on fish.
I'd have to look that up,
but he's been on quite a few times.
He is an expert on all things nerdy, all things science,
but at the moment he's really into AI as many nerds are.
And why that's important is because he has a book
about AI, the title is AI.
It can be found on Amazon and I'm sure in other places.
But if you search for his name, L-I-E-V-E-N-S-C-H-E-I-R-E,
Leven Skela, then you will be able
to find his book on AI.
And actually, if you go to levenskela.com,
then you can see all of his recent AI talks,
which are very informative and very funny.
If you struggle with Leven Skela's name,
then you can also go to www.levingshire.com,
as in what hobbits do I presume,
which apparently also works.
So go to either of those places
and you can find out more about Leven and his works on AI.
Anyway, enjoy the show.
Like I say, it was really fun, like always.
And of course, we are doing lots of live shows,
which will include Anna towards the end of the year.
So go to www.nosesthingsoffice.com/live
to find out more about what remaining tickets there are
and there are not many, so get in there fast.
On with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing as a Fish,"
a weekly podcast this week coming to you live
from Nerdland in Belgium.
(audience cheering)
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin,
Andrew Hunter Murray and Leven Skyra.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Leven.
- My fact is that in 2017,
the AI computer AlphaZero was given the rules of chess.
And four hours later,
it was better than the human world champion in chess.
- Wow.
- So it was given just the rules, no strategies,
no examples of chess games ever played between humans,
and it started practicing against itself.
- Did it try any really weird things?
- It plays chess in a different way than humans.
One chess player said, "I've always wondered
"if the same game was invented on Mars
"and without any interaction between the cultures,
"we would have developed our own strategies
"because everybody learns from the people before them."
And he says, "Now I know."
Because it takes more risks, for example.
It will offer its queen sometimes,
without anyone knowing why, and then it wins in the end.
So, really. - Wow, yeah.
Can I just say, Leven, I think part of,
if one of the main parts of playing chess
is being able to pick up the pieces
and move them from one place to the other,
and until it can do that, I think I can beat it.
- Yeah, well, then you need robotics,
and some people are afraid of robots,
and I always tell them, "If at this phase of technology,
"you're afraid of robots,
"the only thing you need to carry with you at all times
"is a bucket of water, and you're safe."
- Well, actually, we were in the green room just now,
and there was a robotic dog in there.
- Spot robot from Boston Dynamics, yeah.
- Yeah, and also, yeah, there was, and also a real dog.
And I can tell you that real dogs
do not like robotic dogs either.
- Really? - Yeah.
- I'm just wondering.
James, I know you like chess, Leven.
I'm sure you like chess. - A bit.
- And I know you know a lot about AI.
Have you ever played against a man called Martin?
(laughing)
- Probably. - Okay.
- Who is he?
- Martin is a middle-aged Bulgarian man
who wears a turtleneck jumper,
and he is the worst possible opponent on chess.com, right?
So he's an AI, he's a computer chess player,
but he has been programmed to be deliberately,
unbelievably bad. - That's amazing.
- He plays 10 million games every week,
and still he sucks at chess.
- Really?
Does he like call the pawns prongs?
- Yeah, it does. (laughing)
His catchphrase is, "My four-year-old son just beat me.
"Ouch." (laughing)
And he's really, really bad at chess.
He's done experiments with him to test how bad he is,
'cause he's programmed to be a weak chess player.
He has been given 31 queens on one board,
and the opponent only has pawns,
and he has still managed to lose that game.
- Really? - Wonderful.
- See, that feels more in check with where I thought
we were at.
The creator of QI, John Lloyd, he always has this line
where he says, "Not only have we not invented
"artificial intelligence yet, but we haven't even invented
"artificial stupidity."
Like, that's how far away we are from taking over.
- I know we have Martin.
- So that's Martin. - Yeah, yeah.
- So this robot that we're talking about
that beat the record in chess,
the way that they trained it was they gave it
a bunch of games to play, and it had to learn strategy
from that, and whoever was the best at learning a game
would advance to the next level
and train the next AIs together.
So it didn't just beat chess,
but it beat multiple Atari games.
So as part of this program, the AI set a score on Pong.
The highest score a human has ever set is 56,851.
It scored 407,864 as part of this programming.
- Important thing there is that the only input it gets
is what is on the screen.
So of course it's easy to program and use the software
of all the positions to have an optimal software running it.
But this was only fed what a human can see on the screen,
and then adapted its own neural network
until it could play very well.
They thought it all the Atari games.
It was at DeepMind, Google DeepMind in London,
that's how they did it, all the Atari games,
and then go the Chinese-Japanese game, Shoki, and chess.
And so in fact now they can just give it rules of any game,
and then it will practice against itself
and improve until it can beat it.
- Is there anything that we can win at?
- Well, especially when it comes to boxing.
There's one game that we still win,
but I don't know how long it will take us.
It's the game diplomacy.
- Oh, okay.
- It's a bit like risk.
So you have to move around the world and capture areas.
But there's more tactics.
You have different kinds of troops.
But between every round, there's a round of diplomacy
where the players can go one-on-one
and talk strategies with each other.
Like if you move like this, then we can attack Italy there.
Kissinger loved it, apparently.
Kennedy played the game.
And so now they have taught an AI to play it.
It's a bit scary.
You can see these large language models
talking to other players.
Like if you do that move there,
then I will come from that way.
So it figured all of this out.
It can't win from the world top yet,
but it ends in top 10 at this moment
in the game of diplomacy.
- I have a feeling that I would be able to beat any AI
because I'm so dumb,
it wouldn't be able to guess the strategy that I was playing.
It would be like, why has he done that?
That's probably where it learned to give the Queen away first.
I'd be like, yep, you can have that.
Like, I feel like stupidity of human error
would be what confuses AI in a game.
- Cup two, the year 2030.
The war against the machines has gone terribly badly wrong.
Step up, Dan.
- But one man survived it and repopulated the Earth.
- The one AI that's been built this year,
this is very exciting, this is a new development this year,
researchers have built an AI sarcasm detector.
- Oh yeah, sure they have.
- It was in Holland, it was in Groningen.
- Yeah, it was in Holland, and they trained it
with pieces from the Big Bang Theory and Friends.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, so it's sitcom sarcasm.
- Oh, okay.
- It's if they be any more predictable.
(laughing)
- But I read about it, and there was, you know.
- What does it do?
- Mostly, it can just detect sarcasm.
It can detect if you're being sarcastic, which is useful.
But there is a risk that it might start using sarcasm
for its own--
- Against us?
- Evil purposes, yes.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- That's amazing.
Do you think even there's anything that AI won't be able
to do in the future?
- Well, that's a difficult question.
Basically, you could say AI is a new kind of software
that is good at pattern recognition
and recognizing patterns and generating patterns,
like generating images and language.
But it does it so amazingly well at this point.
The fact that it can win a game of diplomacy,
it kind of makes you think with these large language models,
it's not unthinkable that I ask an AI
to buy a new car for me.
It can do the negotiations much better.
It's not unthinkable that an AI will sell your house
at a better price because it knows what language to use.
It could be coming.
And especially when they start combining it with robotics,
which is what they're doing now,
then you give the system sensors and a sense of the world.
And that's what probably the next revolution will be.
- How interesting.
In February, 2023, so just over a year ago,
we asked ChatGBT to give us an episode of Fish.
- Oh yeah, yeah.
- Let's see if they could do our job.
And they were pretty terrible, let's be honest.
Anyway, I asked them to do it again this week
with one more year of ability with the ChatBots.
And they did a pretty good job.
So it begins with Dan Schreiber says,
"Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Things as a Fish, blah, blah, blah,
weekly podcast, all that stuff."
And then in no particular order, here we go.
James, what have you got for us?
And then James Harkins says,
"My fact this week is that AlphaGo,
the AI developed by DeepMind,
learned to play the game Go at a super human level
by playing against itself millions of times."
- Oh my God, you're doing the AI's fact,
is it your main fact here?
- No, but Leven's doing it.
- So Leven didn't know about it.
It predicted what our fact was going to be.
- Are you kidding?
- Honestly, and literally all I put in was,
"Give me a transcript of No Such Things as a Fish."
- It's over, let's just go home.
We just, okay, but some fields, like creative ones,
surely they're immune.
- Yeah, surely Andy.
- Surely.
- Well, hang on, I'm sorry.
Are we just gonna let that fly by?
Are the exact same fact was predicted by the machine?
We're all cool with that?
- Dan, I guess, I'm sorry.
- No.
- That's the end of the world shit.
- Dan, it gets worse.
- It gets worse.
- There's a new podcast, it's out this year.
It's hosted by a guy called Jake,
and it's created by a man called Jacob Redstrom,
but Jake is AI.
It's a podcast hosted by an AI.
- Okay, right?
- Yeah.
- Surely Andy, I mean, things like beauty,
that will never go to AI, will it?
- Beauty?
- Yeah, yeah, that'll always be a human trait.
- Yeah, of course.
- Well.
- Oh no.
- There has been this year a Miss AI competition.
- Oh, cool.
- Where a lot of chat bots/attractive creations online
went up against each other to see who was the most attractive.
And not only did that happen,
two of the judging panel were also AI-generated models.
- Wow.
So the worrying moment will be in that competition
when they say, what do you hope for?
And they say, I would love world peace
if the judge goes sarcasm detective.
(all laughing)
- That's when we're dead.
- Have you ever asked GPT-4 to write a sonnet?
- No.
- This is, okay, write a sonnet.
I'm gonna do it live now.
An animal, what's your favorite animal?
- A chinchilla.
- Yeah, chinchilla.
- A chinchilla, okay, write a sonnet about a chinchilla,
okay, a chinchilla who really wants to fly like an eagle.
Okay, there we go.
So a chinchilla is kind of rodent, cute.
- I'm not totally clear what it is.
I just said it 'cause James said it, but.
- Yeah, kind of, I'm gonna press start now.
So I asked it to write a sonnet about a chinchilla
who really wants to fly like an eagle.
This is just, this is coming out as we speak.
It's finished now, there we go.
In twilight's hush, a chinchilla dreams bright.
With fur as soft as whispers of the breeze.
He gazes high where eagles take their flight
and longs to soar above the tallest trees.
His heart so bold defies the earthly bind,
for in his tiny chest a spirit burns.
With wings of faith, though not by nature's kind,
he yearns for heights for skies his soul discerns.
He climbs the peaks where shadows kiss the light
and calls to eagles with a hopeful plea.
Their feathers brush the heavens free in flight
while he on ground remains but longs to be.
Yet in his quest, a truth begins to rise.
The flight resides in dreams, not just in skies.
- That's very good, that's right.
- I thought it was, it was quite long, was it?
But that's sonnets.
- That's sonnets, the 14 lines.
- Can we ask for a limerick next time?
- A limerick, I'll try.
- I'm looking for high coups if we do any more.
Here's the thing, AI has been very big in the news
in the movie industry, I would say.
Well, you know, a lot of the strike that happened in America
was off the back of how artists were having to be asked
to sign their voices over as well as the writing to AI.
And a lot of things are coming into place
where they're trying to protect the artist's integrity
and livelihood and in Tennessee, a law has been passed
where they are protecting musicians from AI.
So the act is called the ensuring likeness voice
and imagery security act or the Elvis act
because Elvis is from Tennessee
and that's happening in places now where they're gonna say
you can't use the likeness of the voice anymore
'cause it is happening.
- It happened with the new GPT system that talks
and Sam Altman who runs Open AI really wanted
the voice of Scarlett Johansson
because she was in the movie "Her"
and he contacted her a few times and asked for it.
She thought about it and she said, no, I cannot do it.
I don't want to relate myself with AI
because there's so much criticism of it.
And then the voice came out
and it was almost exactly like Scarlett Johansson.
They had probably, they say they had found a voice actor
who sounded really like her and adjusted it a bit.
But well, she filed a lawsuit and it's all taken down now.
But so they're trying to copy the voices of...
- Well, James Earl Jones has given over the voice
of Darth Vader now to AI based on his voice,
which is so interesting 'cause that kind of is like
the final step in Darth Vader's journey anyway
from going human to Android, isn't it?
- Yes.
- Like a real world.
- He's more machine now, isn't he?
- Exactly.
We need to move on guys.
- Well, what's Belgium best at, Leven?
- What is Belgium best at?
- It's one of the most proud things that Belgium produces.
- What I just learned at the theme park science show
that we just had, we are world-class
in the wheels of roller coasters.
I didn't know.
- Okay, that's very cool.
- And beer and fries.
- No, no, no, let's hear you roll the coaster fact, Andy.
- Okay.
No, an AI has just beaten humans at beer.
- Drinking or making?
- Belgian beer.
- Not drinking.
- Making.
Coming up with new recipes of Belgian beer.
They had 250 Belgian beers,
a panel of the best beer experts on the planet,
rated them on all sorts of metrics,
rated them on 50 different kinds of flavor
and lab analysis,
and then an AI algorithm suggested,
why didn't you add a bit of this and a bit of that?
And it came out tasting better according to the experts.
- Wow.
- So this is trouble.
Today beer, tomorrow.
- I didn't speak up because I wasn't beer.
- Tomorrow the roller coaster wheels will be a new shape.
(audience laughing)
(upbeat music)
- It is time for fact number two and that is Andy.
- My fact is that crocodiles can cough up hairballs.
- Ah.
- This was sent in by Colin Croakshank, thank you Colin.
This is about, basically, I didn't know this.
I knew cats produce hairballs and owls and things,
but crocodiles, they have the most amazing jaws,
they have the most amazing stomachs,
they produce amazing acid to digest things.
They cannot deal with hair.
And normally it's not a problem,
they don't eat a lot of hair,
but occasionally they'll eat a pig,
and they end up with a hairball
'cause they cannot deal with the pig's hair,
or the hooves,
and they will just see a crocodile
on the banks of the river going (hissing)
(audience laughing)
- Where are these hairy pigs coming from?
They're bristly, I guess.
- They're bristly sort of wild ones.
- Well, that's amazing.
- I know, they're big.
They're collectors in Queensland.
The biggest one is the size of a football.
Well, that's what's amazing about it as well,
'cause it's not like it's just they've had a meal
and they want to cough it back up.
They can store that hairball for like 40 years,
so when they cough it up,
it can give you an idea of the diet over decades
of while they have eaten,
so it'll be like hairy pigs, you know,
all the other things.
- That's so cool.
- Human in some cases, an Australian.
- Yeah, it is the best option
if you see a crocodile coming towards you
with its jaws open, that it coughs up a hairball, isn't it?
Like, that's what you're hoping for most of the time.
(laughing)
- That's amazing, hairballs.
- Hairballs, hairballs are good.
- They used to be thought that they cured poison hairballs.
- Really?
- Yeah, these are bazoas, which are, you know,
hairballs that would come from animals mostly,
but there was a guy called Amboise Pare,
friend of the podcast actually,
you've mentioned him a few times,
and he decided to see if this was true,
so he took a cook at the King's Court
who had been caught stealing fine cutlery,
so he'd been sentenced to death for stealing these spoons,
and he said, well, what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna let you off,
but I'm gonna give you some poison,
and then I'll give you this hairball,
which we all know this works, so it'll be fine,
and then we'll see what happens,
and it turned out it didn't work at all,
and he died anyway.
- Oh, wow.
- But that was the first evidence we had
that these hairballs don't cure poisoning.
- They do, they sound so weird and cool.
- They're incredible.
- Like the bazoas, or bazoas, or whatever,
don't know how you say them,
but they were for the rich, you know,
'cause real bees are really rare,
and if you couldn't afford one,
you could maybe buy a sliver of one,
or you could rent one for the day.
If--
- I don't know what--
- What for?
- I think they were also thought to be useful
in times of plague, so maybe if you were visiting--
- Magic spells as well.
- Magic spells. - Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And if you were very wealthy,
you might have one for yourself,
but one for your friends,
you know, if any friends are visiting,
so that's nice.
- Have a hairball.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
No, they're very cool.
- Lions can get hairballs?
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, there was one found in an African lion
at the Colorado State Zoo,
and it was, how big do you think a lion's hairball would be?
- The size of a cricket ball.
- Bigger.
- Okay, two cricket balls.
(laughing)
- Let's go in sizes of animals rather than balls.
- Melon.
- Sizes of animals.
(audience laughing)
- The famous animal, the melon.
- The melon, well, there's a kiwi, so who knows?
(laughing)
- Lee and Will have come here with the latest research,
proving that melons are actually technically.
- I think it was like, I didn't know what a chila was,
and now I'm not sure I know what a melon is.
(laughing)
It was about the same size as a chihuahua dog.
- Oh, wow.
- So I like the size of a small dog, yeah.
- Wow.
- Do you know why chihuahuas were bred in Central America?
- Mexico, right?
- Yeah.
They were religious animals,
and they were sacrificed to the gods.
- No.
- It's not much of a sacrifice.
I've got to say, if I was one of the gods,
looking down, and they're bringing me this tiny--
- And you were hungry?
- I'm hungry.
They're bringing me this tiny--
- You wouldn't want a dain.
- Yeah, I would.
- A big dog.
- Yeah.
- What was the sacrifice like?
'Cause if it's burned at the stake, very easy to light.
That's a--
- What?
- Well, they're gonna just go right up, aren't they?
That's a--
- Yeah, that's when they say, "Woof."
(laughing)
(audience applauding)
- So they were sacrificed to the gods,
and I love it when I walk in the street,
and I see people with a shiwawa to go in,
"Oh, sweet dog, what are you gonna ask
"from the gods if you sacrifice it?"
(laughing)
- Well, do you know, this is a tangential story,
but there was a thing in the UK,
I don't know if you guys in Belgium heard about it here,
but there was a, what looked like a giant hairball,
was found by a lady.
But she went, "Oh, it's a hedgehog."
And so she brought it home, and she put it into a box,
and she gave it a hot water bottle,
and some food, then it didn't recover,
took it to hospital, and it turned out it was the bubble
on the top of a hat that people wear,
those beanie bubbles.
- And apparently this happens a lot.
Zoologists and also vets are saying,
"We gotta start understanding what animals look like again,
"because we're losing a lot of time
"when you're calling us out to help a drowning swan,
"and it's a chair leg upside down, we can't do that."
Someone brought vets to their house to help them revive
what they thought was a hedgehog,
but turned out to be a fruit loaf.
Now, a fruit loaf doesn't look like a hedgehog,
but apparently it had been pecked at by a lot of birds
so that it looked very spiky.
And even then they were like, "Oh my God, it's dying!"
And they pulled out people to come.
So this is a big thing at the moment.
- That is amazing.
- Sounds like cheap tamagochis in a way.
- Yeah.
- Just take cotton balls home and care for them.
- Or like chia pets, remember those?
- No.
- Chia pet.
- The pottery that grows.
- No one?
(laughing)
- No one's seen Wayne's World?
- Imagine the size of a room like this
and you're the only one who gets that reference.
- Yeah, that was a pretty special moment.
- That's like me playing a move to AI.
And then it's like, "What was that?"
- Do you want to know the record
for the largest ball of hair ever created?
- Okay, so this is not an accidental in your stomach thing.
- This is not an animal product.
- This is someone with a weird fetish.
- I would not, I would not disagree.
(laughing)
- But for legal reasons.
- It's, well, it was created by a hairstylist
from the USA called Steve.
And he said, "I got more spiritual as I've aged
"and I wanted to leave some kind of legacy when I'm gone.
"And it hit me, I'm going to build a giant hairball."
And he made a hole in the wall in his hair salon
like a, and he put a slide down
to the basement of the building.
- Oh my God.
- And every time he had hair,
he'd just shove it down the slide.
And then he glued it all together.
So how big was it?
- Oh, so it's the biggest ever, so it must be quite big.
- It's quite big.
- Shall I go by the size of an animal?
- Yes, please.
- Okay, large horse.
- Oh, not far off, actually.
- A bison.
- Smaller than a bison.
- Wow, what is that difference?
I can't even, what's an in-between animal to that?
- Look, I don't know what animals are, it turns out.
I don't know what animals are or look like.
- I actually saw this and I thought it looked
like a really, really big hedgehog.
- Yeah, it was that, it was a bit, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It was actually a fruitcake.
(laughing)
- It weighed 102 kilos, 225 pounds.
It is disgusting, it is so, is horrible.
- How big is that, Andy?
I can't actually picture that.
Genuinely, can't.
- It was, I mean, it was on a wagon when I saw it, so.
- Like a large-ish man would be about 100 kilos.
- Okay.
- Yeah, and it's maybe eight feet high,
'cause it's made of hair, it's not very dense,
and it's half-glued.
Anyway, you can go and visit it now
and add your own hair, if you too have got more spiritual
and you want to leave a legacy behind, yeah.
- All right, do you know a cat coughing up hairballs
is responsible for one of the great voices
of nerd culture?
(dog barking)
- That one.
- That's a duck.
- Yep.
(dog barking)
- Duffy duck, yeah, Jen does a better duck duck.
- Still a duck, yeah.
- But that's a nerdy--
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Is it like the dinosaurs in Jurassic Park?
- No, so it inspired the voice of something
that's very big in the dork-nerd world.
- So what does it sound like a good cat coughing up hair?
- Oh.
- Gollum.
- Really?
- Andy Serkis, when he was going to the audition
of Lord of the Rings, was going,
"How am I going to portray Gollum in my audition?"
And his cat was next, so I'm going,
(dog barking)
- What a disgusting hairball Gollum would produce.
That would be awful.
- That's the whole time, that's all it is.
It's just got that in its throat.
Interestingly though, cats,
when we think of them coughing up a hairball,
according to vets, they get pissed off
when you say coughed up a hairball.
They don't cough up a hairball.
They vomit up a hairball.
- Oh.
- Or they're really kind of just trying to thrust it out,
but they're not coughing.
It's not a--
- It doesn't matter, whatever it is,
Steve will take it and he will glue it onto his big ball.
Do you know we've just missed
National Hairball Awareness Day?
- Oh, God.
- Yeah.
- By how long?
- Anyone else observe it?
- That's terrible.
It is bad when you're the only one, yeah.
(audience laughing)
- How long Andy, since it was--
- It was, it's the last Friday in April.
So it's an annual thing.
- Do you know the date, the specific date?
- Well, it's the last Friday in April.
So like Easter, it moves.
- I don't know.
- Which is convenient,
'cause what if it's at the weekend
and not enough people come and celebrate?
- Yeah, good.
And what did you do to celebrate?
- Well, you know, just pop 'em visit Steve
at this great big ball.
(audience laughing)
- You know, it was founded by a vet
who wanted to raise awareness of--
- And what's--
- Of hairballs.
- Oh, okay.
- I mean, I guess they can be bad for a cat's health, maybe?
- Yeah, yeah, it makes them sick.
If your cat is coughing up a hairball,
it is a sign of bigger issues,
gutturally, that is going on.
- Really, really?
'Cause theoretically it should be able to process
the bit of hair that it eats.
- Yeah, so that's been building up inside of them in ways.
We're gonna have to move on,
so I can do this.
- Oh, should we do a bit on crocodiles or not?
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- If you give someone a crocodile to hold
when they're in the casino, they'll make bigger bets.
(audience laughing)
- What size of crocodile?
I mean, like, as big as a chinchilla
or as big as a melon?
- I think it's the bigger the crocodile,
the bigger the bets.
So it's like, apparently, it's a sense of height
and the rousal makes you want to gamble more.
- Oh.
And if you think the crocodile might eat you,
that puts you in that state.
- You're aroused, but not in the way you're thinking.
- No, no, no.
I'm not thinking anything at all.
I'm just thinking, how do I get rid of this crocodile?
If I win another $50,000,
maybe I'll get someone to hold the crocodile
and take it away from me.
Yeah, that's my plan.
- Do you know that sometimes in the States,
you have frozen lakes with crocodile snouts
peeping out of the ice.
- Oh, really?
- It's when crocodiles hibernate
and there's an ice layer on the lake.
They just pop out their nose.
So it looks like little green pebbles on the ice.
And it's actually, when you pull the pebble,
it's attached to a crocodile.
And they're completely hibernating.
So they're in standby mode as they don't react
if you wiggle with the snout.
- That's a good prank, though.
- Yeah.
- So let's see who can pick up that pebble first.
(all laughing)
- Actually, the word crocodile means pebble worm.
- Really?
- Yeah, the croco is the pebble
and dailos is the worm.
But in Greek, delios also means circumcised man.
- Right.
- It could be that crocodile means pebble circumcised man.
- Okay.
- Not sure.
- Either way, how misleading if someone says,
can you go and collect the pebble circumcised man
over there and you come to a crocodile?
That is, yeah, that's bad naming, I would say.
(upbeat music)
All right, it is time for fact number three.
And that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in the 14th century,
there was a rumour among Europeans
that all Englishmen had tails.
(audience laughing)
- Now is the time to prove otherwise.
(all laughing)
- And I've basically come here to see if it's still a rumour.
- Oh, yeah.
- Is this still a thing that people in Belgium think
that English people have tails?
(audience laughing)
Wow.
- Oh, there we go.
- So this idea basically comes from the idea
that St. Augustine had visited the people of Kent
and he was mocked by the locals
and they pinned tails of fish to his robes
to kind of kick him out of the town.
And he turned round and he cursed them with their own tails.
And this became a thing in Europe.
So it's the extent that when there was a siege in 1436
in Paris and the English were kicked out,
they were taunted by the locals saying,
were your tails, were your tails?
And the Scottish, before a battle in 1332,
said they would make ropes from the tails of the English
to tie them with.
- Oh.
- They thought we were basically more close to Beast Hut,
more close to the devil.
It was said the English were.
And there is a thing in French where the word for tail,
which is coup, and the word for hatch,
which is coup apparently, I don't speak French,
but they're so close together,
they had a theory that English people sat on eggs
to hatch them.
- Oh.
- So yeah, that was how we got our eggs.
We all sat on them.
- I think we're getting off quite lightly now
with just you've all got bad teeth as a reputation.
That is quite, you know, that's better.
And by the way, we don't all have bad teeth, just to say,
almost all of us have some teeth.
So I just want to say.
- We have the best teeth ever, ever seen.
- So do you, do you have in Belgium then,
are there any things that if you were talking
about an English person, you would say a certain thing?
Like I was just suddenly remembered that Michael Palin,
when he went out to the Amazon,
they were describing to him how many trees
are chopped down per day.
They would say a Belgium, and it was the size of Belgium.
So that would be a unit of measurement out in the Amazon
for saying how much was chopped down.
- One Belgium of trees was chopped down again.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Yeah.
- Do you have anything here where it's like,
oh, you English people.
- We chopped down one England of trees.
- No, no, no, no, no.
- Just like we smell or we suck or you know,
that kind of thing.
- No, no, no, not really.
- By the way, Dan's just saying this
'cause he's not English.
(laughing)
- Dan is Australian and he wants to get in on this bullying.
- Well, you know, when you're a child,
you read comic books and like Asterix going to England
and then you have all these, oh really, oh dear.
And they're all very, ooh, polite.
- What, polite?
- Cutting the grass, really upperclass.
- You're describing Andy, you're just, yeah.
- But you get this upperclass image of what England is.
And then you go there as a tourist.
(laughing)
And you spend a Saturday evening.
- Okay.
- You spend a Saturday evening in a city centre
and you go, oh my God, I had no idea.
- Can I just, yeah.
- Well, okay, there is research on this,
which is people around the world were asked
what the worst habit of the British is.
So people in Brazil, China, Germany, India,
and the USA, they were asked what's the worst habit
of the British, 27% of young adults said
is that they drink so much.
But not all of those people--
- We would never say that in Belgium, we wouldn't know.
- Not all of those people had visited the UK, actually.
So this was a preconception.
And of the people who had visited the UK,
34% of them said--
(laughing)
- Well, it's amazing.
I was looking at some other stereotypes of the English
from the 14th century, and sure enough,
drinking was one of the things that Britain
was most famous for all the way back then.
There was also the stereotype that British people
took excessive faith in the dreams of old women.
- That is so me.
(laughing)
- I was thinking it was maybe Theresa May and Brexit.
And also the Italians and Germans thought
that the British were great lovers of themselves.
(laughing)
- Very nice.
- Leven, do you think British people are emotionless?
Like, reserved, calm?
- That's what the cliche--
- How dare you!
(laughing)
- Well, apparently British people
are not the most emotionless in the world.
So again, that people have been asked around the world,
how many emotions did you experience today?
Or did you feel anything today at all?
And Britain was sort of in the middle of nations.
It was not especially interesting.
So the most emotionless country in the world,
according to this survey from Gallup,
which is asking people from these countries,
is Singapore, right?
The number of people who reported on any given day
feeling any positive or negative emotions was 36%.
- Oh, they were literally neutral.
- And the rest of people said,
"No, nothing occurred today in my mood."
I didn't have any feelings today.
It sounds rather Swiss to be so neutral, doesn't it?
- Yeah, it sounds very Swiss.
- Could that be that their sort of normal level of emotion
could be, they could be always really happy,
but they're not getting the highs and the lows?
- Yeah, possibly.
Yeah, yeah, that might be it.
I mean, it's a really strange finding.
- That's amazing.
- Yeah.
- Are we close to where the Flemish live around here?
- We are in Flanders, yes.
- Sounds like you're pretty close, James.
- Yes, yes.
- Not a preconception.
British people know where everything in Europe is.
- Here's a question for you with that in mind.
16th century French scholar Jean Baptiste Le Bleur-Champier
wrote that whenever you go to see the Flemish,
you should always carry a knife.
- Yes, it's to join us for dinner.
That's why you will always be welcomed.
- Any thoughts, Dan or Andy?
Like, you might need, now you've been here for a day.
- Why you might need a knife?
- Yeah, among the Flemish.
They only have the plastic disposable ones.
And it's very actually hard to cut through your food.
- In the 16th century, you're right, yeah.
- Well, 'cause we're staying at Leaven's house
and his kitchen table.
There were like 16 different peanut butters on it.
And I feel like you need multiple knives.
- You're pretty much there, Dan, actually.
They had a reputation of consuming the most butter
in Europe. - Oh, oh.
- And so you should always carry a knife with you
so you can spread the butter wherever you want.
- That's not a knife, this is a knife,
but it is a butter knife, so.
- This guy said that a day not a meal has gone by
without me eating butter.
I'm surprised they have not yet put it in their drink.
- Working on it.
But we also use kind of a knife-shaped thing
to clear the head of a beer.
So we always have, we always want a bit of foam
on our beer.
And so the foam is a bit over the glass.
And then we have this knife-like thing to scrape it off.
For us, it's very normal.
The first time I went to a bar with an Australian
in Belgium, we went to order a beer
and then there's no way, preparations are going,
and this guy pulls out the knife.
He was really startled, I tell you what.
- What's it called?
- I don't know, does it have a name?
- No, nobody knows the name.
- We don't bother with names, we want the beer.
- Interesting fact, that is actually
how the French Revolution started.
It was a simple misunderstanding in a bar,
which then just escalated.
Just please remove the head from this one.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- The kitchen knife was, I think,
invented or put in as a law that you had to use it.
I think it was by Richelieu.
And the number of deaths at the dinner table
dropped down to one-tenth.
Because people use daggers.
You would eat with a dagger and cut your meat with it
and everything.
And of course, it's a dinner table,
it's where you have discussions and there's drinking.
And so, quite often there was a knife fight at the dinner table.
And so, by simply inventing this kitchen knife,
this simple knife that is not sharp,
he cut down the lethal fights over dinners.
- That's incredible.
- He did ten or something, yeah.
- 200,000 people forked to death.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, I'm gonna move us on to our final fact of the show.
It is time for the final fact.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that toilet paper testers
have to train for six months before they are allowed
to apply for the actual job.
(laughing)
- That is, wow.
- This is not, 'cause obviously there's multiple
different companies that hire people
to test out toilet paper for them.
This is very specifically an article I read to do
with Proctor and Gamble, who do make toilet paper.
And basically the idea is that you need,
in order to understand what a perfect bit
of toilet paper is, as a tester,
you need to do, you need all your senses.
And the article that says outside of literally tasting it,
you need to know how does it feel in the hand?
What is it like to wipe, you know,
if you've had, you know, a couple of Belgian beers
the night before, or what is it like
if you've had a lot of peanut butter at Leven's house?
Like, it's gonna be different viscosity of poos each day.
- Yeah, okay.
So basically you spend six months doing that,
and then when you get to the moment where they're saying,
okay, now let's give you the actual test
to see if you can get the job, you can fail it.
You can fail it if you haven't prepared for those.
- But how do you fail it?
Do they, do they, I'm imagining they give you-
- I'm imagining that your finger goes through.
- No.
- Yeah.
- But I'm imagining that they give you a single sheet
of toilet paper, and you have to,
you have to know where it's from.
This is a single origin.
- How many ply?
- Yeah.
- It might be a combination of that stuff.
They're quite secretive in the toilet testing world.
So it's a bit hard to get into the clandestine world
of what's going on in those factories.
But they do say that in that particular moment
after six months, only half of the people
will make it through to the job itself.
Can you become a toilet paper sommelier?
(laughing)
Like you're like, sorry, last night I had steak and red wine.
Oh, then I recommend this one for you.
- Oh, yes.
Yeah, there has to be, right?
- There must be.
- That doesn't have to be done.
(laughing)
This is just a little bit of whimsy.
- It feels very, I think if you spent six months
of your life and then you fail the audition,
the least you can do is have at least
three different toilet papers in your house.
- No, I don't like it.
You hear the boots approaching your stall
and someone's standing outside with the silver dough.
No, it's not.
- I hear the sound of soft ply going in there.
- They do have a lot of robots as well.
I mean, I don't know if this is an AI thing too.
Or maybe it will be soon, but they have a lot of robots
because they need to test the qualities of the paper.
They need to test how easily it tears,
the angle that it hangs at if it's on a roll, you know?
Or, and they have a range of finger probe robots
to test how sheets break.
- Really?
- If they're mishandled or they're sort of tore or, yeah.
- Well, then AI robots have eight fingers.
So that's easy.
(laughing)
- Actually, do you know if you are in one
of these facilities how you test a toilet paper
against a butt, a bottom?
- So do they have like an AI bum as well?
- No, it's to do with you.
You're the person who's doing it.
- Me? - Yeah.
So you're in there.
You're given a fake bit of poo
that they have created with NASA.
So it's 'cause they, today's poo.
Because they don't want to have to.
- Why haven't we been back to the moon?
Wow.
- To boldly go.
- So here's the thing.
If you're working in a factory that's testing toilets
and testing toilet paper,
you don't want to have real feces in there
because it can cause lots of disease and so on.
So they, for years, it used to be dog food
that they would use to flush down toilets.
Then they created like bean curd and a lot.
And then there was like a,
like how KFC and Coke have a secret ingredient.
There was a secret ingredient poo that they would use
that they didn't tell anyone about.
And then they created this thing with NASA.
And so what you would do is you would put your arm tight
so that your elbow would have a little bum bum
basically in the corner.
And you would put the poo in there
and you'd squeeze it out.
And then you would wipe your bum elbow.
- That is very terrible.
- That is the most disgusting thing I've heard all year.
I don't know why.
- I think it was like he said bum bum.
- That was it.
It was bum bum.
I know it's fake poo.
I know it's your elbow.
There's no actual poo involved here.
I'm still revolting.
I feel worse about this than I do about
Steve and his big old balls there.
- How many listeners are going to try this at home?
- Oh no.
- Send your photos to Andrew Hunter Murray.
- Maybe not.
- Podcast@QI.com
- No.
- Not to give you any ideas,
but I have 12 kinds of peanut butter at my house.
(all laughing)
- You know, like it's very trendy to get bamboo toilet paper
these days, very environmentally friendly.
Well, they did a lot of tests recently
and they found that some products
contain as little as 3% bamboo.
So you think on the packet it says
this is bamboo toilet paper,
but actually it's mostly just old paper
and they just put a tiny bit of bamboo in.
This has been a big deal in the toilet paper world recently.
- Yeah.
- I worked out that if you were a panda
and you wanted to live entirely on these toilet rolls,
you would have to eat 7,200 toilet rolls every day
to get enough bamboo
and that's how many I would use in 50 years.
That's almost a Belgium.
(all laughing)
During lockdown,
somebody figured out how to make moonshine alcohol
from toilet paper.
- No. - Why?
- Yeah, because there's cellulose in it
and of course we cannot digest cellulose
and I think the yeasts that make the alcohol need sugars.
- That does feel like you're solving one problem
but creating another one.
- Probably, yeah.
But you can use certain enzymes
that can dissolve the cellulose into sugars
and so he actually did it.
It's on YouTube.
He documented how he did it.
So this might be the reason
why everybody was hurting toilet paper.
(all laughing)
- Don't take my booze away.
- That's so funny.
- We actually looked into the kind of lockdown hoarding
and we thought that actually a lot of it
did kind of make logical sense that you would hoard it
and that's because everyone was suddenly at home
and you weren't in the office anymore
and the factories that make office toilet paper
are different from the ones that make home toilet paper
because the office ones are often
those really big sort of rolls.
So there was actually gonna be a massive shortage
of home toilet paper because no one was in the office anymore
and everyone was going to the toilet at home.
Obviously there were crazy people
just buying loads of them as well.
- Yeah, yeah, that makes sense.
Do you know if you go into a toilet paper factory,
where do we get individual rolls of toilet paper from?
- From the packet?
- No, before then.
- Is it a long one?
- It's a long one that is cut.
- No.
- From the mother reel.
- Oh.
- It's called the mother reel.
It is a ginormous toilet roll.
- That's amazing.
- Wait, is it long?
- Yeah.
- Or is it?
'Cause you're gesturing, you're saying it's tall.
- I know, I sort of thought,
'cause this is audio for the listener at home,
it didn't matter what I did with my hand.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
(audience laughing)
- I'll tell you what, you've had a bad day
if the sommelier comes with that, haven't you?
(audience laughing)
- So each mother reel, as they call it,
contains, when chopped up into individual rolls,
25,000 individual rolls.
- What?
- Right, yeah.
So there's a guy called Greg Wallace.
We've mentioned him on the show before.
He makes a show where he goes around
looking at how they make things in the UK.
It's a documentary series.
Each show, different factory to show you how it's done.
So he was in a big warehouse
where they had 2,000 mother rolls in there.
And they worked out that if you were an average family,
you would have four toilet rolls a week
in an average family.
That's how much is used, right?
So the amount of toilet rolls in that room
would mean that your family could be wiping your bum
for 96,000 years.
Just from that collection of 2,000 mother rolls
that they had sitting in the warehouse.
- Do you know these toilets that squirt water on your bum?
- B-day. - A B-day?
- No, the toilets as in inside the toilet.
- The Japanese.
- Well, I was going to ask you.
Do you know where they were invented?
- Japan.
- No, they weren't.
- No, no, no.
- They were invented in America.
- Really? - Yeah, yeah.
They were invented in America
and they were supposed to be for like care homes and stuff.
- Okay.
- And then they sent a few over to Japan
and this company who got them thought,
everyone's going to want these.
Let's start making them for everyone.
And so they did.
But the problem was that the ones in America
were kind of prototypy
and they were very good at measuring the temperature
and they were very good at measuring the angle of squirt.
And so they quite often fired boiling water
straight into people's anuses.
- And there was a market for that too.
- Yeah.
- So we were talking about...
- Are you too busy to drink tea the normal way?
Well...
- That's a couple of English stereotypes together, isn't it?
But then, yeah, so then this company called Toto
decided to start making these.
But we were talking about testing toilet paper and stuff.
They needed to get the angle right.
And so they asked all of their staff members
to test these toilets.
- Okay.
- And to be honest, it took quite a lot
to get people to cooperate, but eventually they did.
- Okay.
- And all the members of staff would take it in turns
to sit on these toilets
and have water fired up at different angles.
And they found that the golden angle is 43 degrees.
- Right.
- So it just cleans you the right amount.
And for women at the front, it's 53 degrees.
So that's a bit of information you never wanted to know.
- Yeah, wow.
I've read about the founder of Toto.
I didn't read any of that,
but he was an amazing guy called Kazuchika Okura.
And he sort of had been to the West, I guess.
And he also helped introduce the car to Japan.
- This guy was a big deal.
- Right.
- And he also created his own new musical instrument,
the Okuro Ulo, a kind of vertical flute.
- What?
- A vertical flute.
- A recorder.
- He invented the recorder.
And he was president of, linking it back to AI,
the Japanese Go Association.
- Wow.
- Yes.
- That's very cool.
- This guy was a big deal.
- Well, while we're on inventions,
there's a British word, I don't know if you know it here,
but we often call the toilet the throne.
So the throne, the toilet,
it's attributed as an invention
to a guy called Sir John Harrington.
And he built it.
He was the godson of Queen Elizabeth III.
And supposedly--
- Okay, we've only had two Queen Elizabeths,
so I'm gonna stop you right there.
- What did I say?
- Queen Elizabeth III.
- Yeah, so John Harrington invented it in the year 3000.
(laughing)
No, so sorry.
Queen Elizabeth I, yeah.
So he invented it for her.
And it basically, what I'm talking about
is a toilet whereby it had valves,
it had a flush, and she tried it,
and she was like, this is fantastic, I'll take one.
So it was a big deal.
So he invented the throne,
and a descendant of his is Kit Harrington,
John Snow, from A Game of Thrones.
- Wow.
- So this is a series about everyone wanting
to get on the loo.
(laughing)
- Yeah, one more thing on poo.
There's a famous biologist in the Netherlands,
who's called Midas Dekkers,
who writes great books about science.
And one of his latest books is The Story of Shit.
So he's a biologist, and he just explains
the entire god system, how it's produced,
what is happening there biologically.
And they asked him in a talk show,
they asked him like, why did you want to write
a book about poo?
And he said, well, I was walking around
in these bookstores.
You see all these cookbooks.
Nobody ever tells you how it ends.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Luke, we need to wrap this up.
Thank you so much everyone for coming
to this live recording, we really appreciate it.
(audience applauding)
That is it, that is all of our facts.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland, James.
- My Twitter is @JamesHarkin.
- Andy. - @AndrewHunterM.
- And Leven. - @LevenSkader.
- Good luck with that.
(laughing)
- It's the one country you can say that to, it's fine.
If you want to get into us as a group,
you can go to @NoSuchThing
or @NoSuchThingAsAfish on Instagram
or you can go to our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
You can also get tickets to our live tour,
we're about to go on tour around the world.
So please check that out.
For everyone here, thank you so much for coming.
We're gonna be back again next week
and we hope we're gonna be back here again
next year for another awesome Nerdland adventure.
We'll see you again next week, everyone else.
Goodbye!
(audience cheering)
(upbeat music)