[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome to another episode.
A nice such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covern Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Anichezinski, Andy Murray, and James
Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
[MUSIC]
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
>> Okay, my fact this week is that according to a 2011
Yugov survey, 27% of Britons neither love nor hate Marmite.
>> I love that.
>> That makes a lot of sense.
>> It is a great fact.
>> I really love it.
>> I think that's 27% I think.
>> I think I am too.
>> I love it, I love it.
>> Yeah.
>> But here's a weird one.
I love Vegemite, but I hate Marmite when you take the comparison higher.
>> So you would obviously love Vegemite, because you're Australian.
But I actually prefer Vegemites of Marmite.
And I think I'm probably the only British person who would admit to that.
It's just better, guys.
>> Well, I read an extraordinary story that IBM did a global survey of the most
talked about brands online.
And they went through the internet scouring it for the most brands that were spoken about.
And the top brand, higher than Coke, higher than Nike, was Vegemite.
>> Really?
>> More spoken about than any other brand.
You don't need to speak about Coke because it's always going to be like that.
>> Yeah, it could be that.
And the weird thing is that they tracked it down that 98% of Vegemite eaters are all Australian.
>> How many, what percent, are you?
>> 98%.
>> Well, that sounds right.
>> Well, I don't think you can buy it anywhere else.
>> You can get it overseas now.
You can get it in the supermarkets here.
But so what's even more interesting is that it wasn't like they were tracking it to Australia.
They were tracking it globally.
So they know where all the Australians are around the world.
>> Wow.
>> Through Vegemite consumption.
>> Yeah, that's really great.
>> I mean, that's not obviously all the Australians.
But it's like, it's just, it gives you a great map of how spread out Aussies are around the world.
>> You could probably do the same with British and baked beans.
>> Yes, yeah.
>> Although Vegemite is now really popular in certain Asian countries, like in Hong Kong,
it's all sold out in Hong Kong from all supermarkets suddenly.
And that was when it was connected to umami flavor.
So there was like a little press around it at some point, which said that is the umami flavor.
Because that's, you know, hailed as a brilliant flavor in particularly in Japan and Hong Kong.
Suddenly it's incredibly popular.
>> Wow.
>> Right. Hey guys, are we talking about Vegemite on this podcast?
Or are we talking about James' fact about mami?
>> My fact is about mami, so don't bring your Australian waves up in here.
>> I didn't know it's got celery in it.
>> That's it?
>> Yeah.
>> Mami is made with celery.
>> Wow, that must have been so good for you.
>> Yes.
>> Excellent.
>> It also has like the remnants of beer in it, doesn't it?
That's what it's made of, it's like the extract from the beer making.
>> Is it still, well, probably not anymore, but that's where it originally came from.
>> If you've got yeast left over, you may as well use it for a little while.
>> Yeah, I want to know, it's not drunk after breakfast.
>> That's because you have a serious problem in it.
It's because you're always drinking a breakfast.
I don't think it's the mami.
It gives the pine pine to wine if you're having good.
>> I don't blame the mami.
>> I think I must have had a bad slice of mami.
>> There was speaking of drinking, they released on Valentine's Day.
In 2008, they released champagne flavored mami.
>> I don't remember that, and it had 3% champagne in it.
Now, I would have thought that the mami would overpower the 3% of champagne.
>> Mami's a famously mild flavor.
>> Mami, do you know what it means?
It means our mami is an old French cooking pot.
So, you know the front of a mami jar, there is the little picture of a red and yellow.
>> Yeah, of a casserole dish.
>> Of a casserole dish, that is a mami.
>> Yeah, it's because it was originally made to add a little bit of extra to casseroles.
That was the point of mami in the first place.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yeah, flavor.
>> Yeah, it's like a stock cube or something like that.
Because it was invented by the same guy who invented oxo cubes who was called Justus von Liebig.
And he was the first person who realized that you could take the yeast extracts and turn it into something you could eat.
But he is also known as the father of the fertilizer industry.
Because he discovered that nitrogen is essential for plants.
And he also developed a breast milk substitute for babies.
>> Wow, wow.
>> So, he taught this guy, yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> So, hang on, archetype of the British mami was invented by, was he German?
>> Justus von Liebig sounds German.
>> Yeah, I think he was actually.
I think his main manufacturing place was in Freybentos, which is in Uruguay as well.
>> Yeah, why do you call it mami?
He should call it justice, so he could say justice will be served and breakfast.
>> Why do you want this mami thing to even?
>> So, was his breast milk substitute mami?
>> That's what it was.
>> You just claim to have invented it.
>> I mean, invented a delicious ability.
>> It's a mami shot.
>> And a fantastic new hemorrhoid crepe.
>> Right.
>> There are a lot of articles I'd like about mami, because it's something that people like talking about.
And I read this phrase, mami, one, two world wars.
Okay, that's not strictly true.
It's the fastest climb down from the assertion of a fact I've ever read.
And that was on a BBC article about it.
>> But what they mean was it was in Soldiers Rations in the First World War.
>> Yeah.
>> Because you would get spammed condensed milk and mami basically didn't you?
>> That's not me.
>> They had this kind of con beef stuff that no one liked.
And so a few people wanted to eat it that they ended up just using it to prop up things in the trenches.
And they'll crates and crates of this stuff that normally eat.
>> I think they would over indulge in the trenches if they were just using their food as opposed to.
>> Not genuinely they did, because they liked something.
>> It's not bad, was it?
>> You think they were over indulged in the trenches?
>> [LAUGH] >> Just replay that.
>> How have I much?
>> I have much.
>> You think that the rancid meat they were served, which they could only walk on.
>> [LAUGH] >> Wow.
>> They were a little bit spoiled.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So the thing about the actual slogan itself was that it was just a genius slogan in that it just created a whole lot of things.
>> Yeah, it was just fantastic and I was looking into a few slogans and I read the most popular slogan.
We've mentioned it slightly by saying if British people were around the world.
>> Heinz makes beans or whatever.
>> Beans means Heinz.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, supposedly the most successful of all the slogans.
>> Do they know on what metric that's the most successful in terms of the most people who remember it or.
>> Yeah, I don't know, I actually know it was just a poll to say which was your favorite and.
>> But it's very good.
>> Beans means Heinz.
>> This led me to a kind of little snoop into the world of slogans, which I just.
I ended up looking at basically the last Brazil world cup.
>> They all came in with country slogans, did you see the slogans?
>> I don't remember.
>> Each country had a brand new slogan that they brought with their country.
>> Okay, so give us a country and we'll see if we can work out like that.
>> Okay, origin Tina.
Give us the Falcons back, you bastard.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Is that it?
>> Catchy.
>> No, it's a rather boring word for that.
It's not just a team, we are a country.
France, this is my favorite one actually, the French one.
>> Total France.
>> No, so it's impossible is not a French word, which I love, because it literally is.
>> [LAUGH]
>> That's amazing.
>> Yeah.
>> I think that that French line, impossible is not a French word, is it was originally an
appolian quotation.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Just in case we get to that if I could.
>> Yeah.
>> He was also wrong.
>> Yeah, this, I really like this story is from an article, again, sort of interesting
fact about Marmite, I'm quoting directly, in 2009, a Marmite obsessed thief targeted a
petrol station and stole 18 jars over a month.
Ultimately, the owners stopped stocking it to prevent him striking again.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I love that, you go into like Tesco's and there's nothing there, it's like, well, we've
had no robberies for the last three years.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But that's what they said, I read that article and they were like, well, what's the point
of us putting it on ourselves?
If this guy's just going to nick them, there's no point.
>> No, but it's such a capitulation.
>> Yeah.
>> To theft.
>> It does feel like that guy's one.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Should we move on?
>> Yeah, let's move on.
>> A bit of joint matters.
>> Yeah.
>> One more thing I read.
Former Chelsea Footballer Nicholas Anelka is said to be scared by Marmite.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Why?
>> I don't know, but he always goes to that petrol station these days.
>> Yeah.
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, time for fact number two.
My fact this week is that the Knights of the Round Table included Lancelot,
Gawain, Galahad, and Gareth.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Gareth, the Knight.
>> What was his job?
>> He was just like a classic Knight.
>> The weird thing though, I was looking.
>> He's not one of the famous ones, isn't he?
>> He's not, then I was looking into him.
He's actually Arthur's nephew, which seems like autism in the workplace.
Here we go.
>> I can't believe there's a new seat at the table.
>> Yeah.
>> I think he was going to be one of the great knights who's finally made his way.
>> [LAUGH] >> Because you know there were lesser tables?
>> No.
>> Really? >> Yeah, are there other shapes as well?
>> I'm not sure, I thought there are oval tables, and then.
>> It was kind of like a main hall where they had, I mean, it obviously never happened.
But like, there's a novel that's come out talking about the lesser knights.
And I didn't realize that the novel actually has a basis in what is closer to the actual mythology.
There were lots of other tables where there were like older knights who were retired, and there were.
>> So it's like at a wedding where you've got the head table, and then you've got a really
crap one in the corner with tedious people.
>> Was there a trapezium table, with the knights of the trapezium table, or the rhombus?
>> [LAUGH] >> Just some of my favorite shapes, I thought I mentioned.
>> So they have round tables at Starbucks, apparently.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And the reason for that is that people look less alone when seated alone at a round table.
>> Really? >> Yeah.
>> Yeah, that makes sense, because there's no obvious place for
other people to go, or as a square table I suppose, you want other people on the extra edges.
>> Yeah. >> So Gareth?
>> Yeah, so he was the nephew.
>> We don't know anything else about him.
>> No, there's quite a lot.
I mean, he's a big part of the story.
Actually, it's a bit unfair to say that he's the nephew and make that sound as a bad thing,
because actually quite a number of the other knights were nephews of Arthur as well.
>> Just because everyone got in on special favors, doesn't mean it's any better than the Gareth.
>> [LAUGH]
>> The only thing I know about him is that his nickname was Beaumont, which is Beaumont as a French word.
It's beautiful hands, which people teased him, saying, hey, pretty hands.
>> Teased, Gareth.
>> Yeah.
>> But that does imply that he's not getting his hands dirty by killing dragons and stuff.
>> Yeah, it does, yeah, yeah.
>> I think he was a kitchen assistant or something like that.
>> He was, yeah.
>> Is that right?
>> Yeah.
>> For a while when he was sort of undercover.
That sort of period where a really rich famous person goes into the slums and sees what it's
like to be a normal person.
>> Well, he was undercover with his massive shield and massive sword, which I mean.
>> Yes, exactly.
>> Peter the Great went undercover all the time.
>> Yeah.
>> He loved doing it, yeah.
>> He was about seven feet tall and clearly the Tsar of Russia, so it was very hard for
him to do it.
>> And he had a big group of people with him that didn't he, like, 30 people walking along
with him and he's going, nope.
I like not him.
>> Right, yeah.
>> But he went, he got a job in a shipbuilding yard and he would only answer to the name Peter
the Shipbuilder.
And he would bring him matters of state in the evenings after he finished building ships
for the day.
>> Wow.
>> And then he would say, he would sign a few documents and things and then he'd, yeah,
he's kind of got it wrong if he calls himself Peter, what ever he does.
>> Yeah.
>> Old habits die hard, basically.
Yeah, you can help it.
>> But I think people like pretended to not recognise him, didn't they?
>> Yeah.
>> You make him feel like he was.
Things are successful.
>> Yeah.
>> I guess it was easy to go undercover in the olden days, you know, pre-photography days.
There was a rumor in down at the time, wasn't there, that the way Marie Antoinette was captured
was because some recognised her from the coins.
>> Really?
>> And that's then reported to her to the authorities, and that's why her.
>> Yeah.
>> That's pretty funny idea.
Someone looking at the coin and then looking back at the coin, going, wait, excuse me Madame,
could you stand sideways for a minute?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Back two nights, what would you guys say at night tournaments in the Middle Ages?
What was the main sport?
>> Jasting.
>> No, it wasn't.
Jasting was always a side sport.
The main sport was always the Malay, which was the big group fight where all the nights
like galted towards each other had a group fight.
>> Like a melee, like her.
>> Yeah, so we get Malay from.
>> That's how it's supposed to be.
>> Jasting was always just a side of it.
>> So like a lot of rulers and people campaigned to get jousting band because they thought
it was distracted from the main Malay, and they thought it wasn't a necessary part.
And Count Philip of Flanders actually used to turn up with a whole retinue and decline
to join the Malay, and so make sure everyone else got in the Malay.
And then when he was jousting, he'd be able to win the joust because everyone was tired
from the Malay, and so people wanted to ban the jousting.
>> I think it's true that the only reason more people didn't get killed in the Malay was
because the main aim was to capture other people.
>> Oh, really?
>> And then you would sell them their armour back to them because it's very embarrassing.
They basically rent some of your armour from you.
>> Yeah.
>> Would they go in with a lance?
>> I don't know.
>> Lance a lot would.
>> Okay.
A lance a lot.
There's a guy called George Lancelot, he's in the news quite recently.
He's had 176 convictions for repeated swery outbursts.
>> Swery outbursts.
>> He's been arrested for abuse a few times, and he claims to suffer from personality disorder,
which makes him swear and run whenever he is out in public and he's been drinking.
And recently he was sent to prison for a short amount of time.
Because he was led from the dock in extra crown carts, he shouted, "I get less for burglary,
fuck off."
>> In his defence?
>> Yeah.
I've been drinking.
>> Have you guys heard of the game, King Arthur, or played, in fact?
>> No.
>> This was a game that sailors played in the 16th and 17th centuries.
So you'd let one crew member to play King Arthur, and he'd be dressed up in ridiculous robes
and apparently wear a wig made of rope, and then everyone else of the crew would have to
be formally introduced to this King Arthur, and they'd have to tip a bucket of freezing
cold water over his head.
>> So it's like the ice bucket challenge.
>> It's a bit like that.
But if you, when you tipped it over his head, and obviously I guess his reaction was quite
amusing, if you cracked a smile or a laugh, you had to swap places with him, and you had
to pick up the King Arthur character.
>> Wow.
That's great.
>> You only shouted.
He said, "Hail King Arthur."
Tipped a bucket over his head.
Have to keep a straight face.
I nominate Long John Silver.
>> So just back to the nights, very quickly, because I'm not of your country.
I didn't really get enough bringing totally with it.
Obviously you guys might have them guessing in school.
Was it a big part?
>> Bitnighted.
>> No, no, no.
Just King Arthur the whole mythology.
>> Not really.
>> It's not true.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> I've seen the sword in the Stone Disney film.
>> Yes.
>> I haven't.
>> Oh, well, it's the best Disney film.
It's a really hot squirrel, isn't it?
>> That is true.
>> True, right?
>> It's pretty fit.
>> She is sexy.
>> Like the fox in Robin Hood, for example.
That was Robin Hood.
>> What?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
I'm sorry.
>> He's a handsome fox.
>> Yeah.
But so there's no basis of truth in it whatsoever, right?
>> There are certainly claims.
There's a claim that a huge round table that hangs in Winchester Hall is the real round
table.
So what happens is there's this mythology which most people think isn't true, but there
might be some kind of historical basis to it, probably not.
And so when you have anything like that, it means that everyone can claim part of it.
So --
>> Okay.
>> I think the latest theory is that -- so it's a bit like Robin Hood, I think, is that
people often come up with theories of where the Arthurian Legend might have come from.
And the latest is that he was Kazekstani.
>> Oh.
>> Really?
>> His mom interpretation.
Kazekstani King.
>> But he was a mythical Kazekstani King, as opposed to a mythical English King, is that
right?
>> I think so, yeah.
The theory that he's Croatian, because his wife was called Igrain, and there is a town
called Igrain in Croatia, and they've decided, well, it sounds the same so she must have been
from here.
>> Fair enough.
>> So just with the round table and Gareth specifically, it turns out that Gareth's death
is what led to the sort of breaking up of the round table of the night being their
oldest vine.
Yeah.
>> So they really did care about the little kitchen.
>> They loved Gareth.
Yeah.
>> He wasn't just the nepotistic nephew coming in, he was very much loved.
So Gareth, that was actually the first use of the name Gareth in recorded.
>> Yeah, I read one theory that it was a mistake by Mallory.
>> Oh.
>> Okay, he was supposed to be called Gahariat, but he'd misheard Gahariat and said Gareth-
>> I mean, it's not that much as Gareth and having the female name Hariat as the main
part of your male name to be there.
>> So do you think we could say that Gareth, in the same way that like Joe Anna is the female
version of Joseph or whatever, Josephine, probably, do you think we could say that Gareth
is the male version of Hariat?
>> I could think of a better male equivalent of Hariat than Gareth.
It's taken me a while.
I don't know.
[LAUGHTER]
>> I don't know what you're talking about.
It must be really obscure name.
>> Let's move on to fact number three, and that is Andrew Hunter Murray.
My fact is that the Ministry of Defence owns 15 gold courses, this is the British Ministry
of Defence.
>> Right.
>> Yeah.
>> Why do we know why?
>> Why not?
It's hard work killing the enemies of the crown as you can't relax and have a quick
nine.
>> I think it's because you know when you watch a James Bond movie, and I know Ministry
of Defence is different MI6s, but they must have their spies as well, right, Ministry
of Defence.
Whenever you see James Bond movie, Bond is brilliant at everything.
You don't become brilliant at everything without training like crazy.
>> Good at golf.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, golf would be one of the things.
There will be a Bond movie when he plays golf, and he just --
>> He plays against a golf finger.
>> Well, there you go.
>> You assume down at the Ministry of Defence also owns loads of tennis courts and bowling
alleys.
>> I think I read that they do have like polo, poke tables, ski resorts, they've got a
dart board, they've got a dart board, they've got one spy waiting for the evil villain who
plays shoved hate me.
>> I want to see the inventory of everything that's red foot green.
>> He's saying red foot green, red foot, red foot, red foot, red foot, red foot.
>> Another thing the Ministry of Defence has is, this is in their list of achievements
for 2014, completed a rollout of Internet Explorer 8 as its default browser.
>> Not bad, that is.
>> Still on Internet Explorer, not only that Internet Explorer 8 came out in 2009.
>> Wow.
>> Have you heard of Kabul Golf Club?
>> No.
>> This is the only golf club in the whole of Afghanistan.
>> Right.
>> And the course rules specifically call the Greens Browns, because it's very, very dry
and there's no grass.
>> Oh, really?
>> It's all, basically, it's all sand, but they make the Greens more compact, don't they?
>> Yeah.
I think.
>> It used to be an area for training in the removal of mines.
And you have to carry artificial turf with you sometimes, put that on the ground where
your ball is, and play off that to the next bit, and then carry your artificial turf with
you.
>> That happens under the ball.
>> That happens in actual, not like professional golf, but if you remember of a golf course,
some golf courses in the UK, you'll carry some artificial turf really in the winter,
because they don't want you hacking up the margin, you're on a bit of artificial stuff,
put it down, put the ball on, and play it off that.
>> That's fantastic.
>> Yeah.
>> I think that's really cool.
>> So what the first crazy golf course was?
>> No.
>> It was, it's still around, it's St Andrews, and it's a putting green, and it's got loads
of real big hills on it, so the ball goes in all sorts of directions.
And it was invented because ladies weren't allowed to play on the golf course, so they gave
them this little fake golf course to play.
And then it became so popular, because actually it's a lot more fun than proper golf.
>> Yeah.
>> If you're not good at golf, and that everyone starts to play in it.
>> And then they kick the women off that one as well.
>> No, no, no, no, you can play this tiny golf, you've just invented.
>> For your fingers.
>> A little cocktail stick for a golf club.
>> That's so funny.
>> It's true Mary Queen of Scots, first female golfer in records.
>> Yeah, that is true.
>> Wow.
>> Records, though, tricky things.
But yeah, I think it is.
And I think James IV of Scotland was the first recorded golf player.
Again, he definitely wasn't the first ever golf player.
But yeah.
>> He played in 1502.
He lifted the band that had previously been in place on playing golf because it was encouraged
to encourage archery practice.
Golf was not allowed, because you know, if you can't play golf, James, as you know.
>> Yeah, his grandfather banned it, didn't he?
>> Yeah.
>> So.
>> Probably part of the reason that he lifted the band was he realized that Cannon would
probably replace archers in time, so it wasn't as important for everyone to be doing
archery practice.
It was a long-sighted, yeah.
>> Quite a lot of famous people in history have been known for playing golf, haven't they?
Like I think Rugged Kipling was a big golf fan, and it's claimed that Rugged Kipling, I mean,
it's true that Rugged Kipling invented snow golf, but it's often claimed like this is a
sport that now we're all playing.
And did you know that the Rugged Kipling invented it?
>> I'm almost constant.
He's getting a bit out of hand actually.
I don't know how to snow golf, I play.
>> Snow golf didn't do any archery anymore.
>> Okay, so there was a golfer in Benine called Matthew Boyer.
>> Okay, this might be a made-up story, but it's all obvious on it.
One day he played a shot, described as a glorious slice.
The ball hit a bird, which in turn dropped onto the windshield of a trainer jet.
That trainer jet pilot then swerved out of the way and took out four new Mirage jets.
And in one goal, totally demolished the entire air force of Benine through one golf shot.
That's what happened.
>> That is impressive.
They worked out it would take him 145,000 years to pay off his debt.
>> Did he yell out in the court?
I would have got less of a bergerory?
>> Fuck off.
>> I could be a cool catcher, it's relieving court every time.
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, time for our final fact, and that is Chazinski.
>> My effect is that the rise in the use of female contraceptive pills is causing fish
to become too effeminate.
This is a genuine problem.
This is about how the lot of women use a female contraceptive pill, understandably, it's a great thing.
But that does mean that we end up flushing out of our system, a lot of female hormones.
That go into the drains and get into rivers, and the fish take them in.
And it causes this thing called intersex, which means that like a male fish will stop producing sperm.
It'll start producing eggs, and then it damages fish populations because it's thought they can't really breed as well when they stop doing that.
So, yeah, bit of an issue, stuff being flushed down the drain.
>> Huge issue, yeah.
>> How can there be that much that's going into the fish hanging out by the source of the sewer?
>> It's a good point, so yeah, it does take the tiniest amount to have an effect on them.
So they added its EE2, which is ethanol estradiol, which is the main active ingredient of contraceptive pills, which triggers the condition in fish.
And so they added five parts of that per trillion to water to test it out, and it still had an effect on the fish.
>> Wow, that's extraordinary.
>> That's right on out.
>> So I was just other things that go through the drain systems and out in the ocean.
I was talking to this lady from the Natural History Museum, Sandy Napp, and she's actually, it's not relevant.
She's a curator of potatoes and tomatoes, but what I'm talking about is facial products.
She was telling me, she gave me this little vial of these little blue beads.
And she was saying these beads are from, when you wash your face, with face washes.
Those microbeads that they say they're inside the thing.
And she was saying, what do you think these are made of?
And I assumed it's a natural product, and she said no, it's a little bit of plastic.
And the plastic is now apparently when it goes through the drains, that gets forced down to the ocean.
It makes it through the system, fish are eating it, becoming toxic.
It's actually poisoning the fish.
And then when you eat the fish, it's actually harming us now.
It's apparently it knocks up radiation levels or something.
I don't, yeah.
I've probably gone all pseudoe there at the end.
>> And that's in moisturizer?
>> It's in like a face wash.
>> You know, if you buy, if you buy face wash, and it's kind of a bit rough.
>> You know, and when you buy face wash, you know, when you wash your face.
>> Never done that.
Humans are paying for their vanity now, aren't they?
>> You said that, like you weren't a human.
>> New people will suffer puny morpals.
>> So industrial pollutants are shrinking the genitals of polar bears in Greenland.
>> That's their excuse.
>> They should just inflate down the cold, shouldn't they?
>> But apparently weakening their penis bones and industrial pollutants.
>> Yeah, and also there's a chemical used to paint boats on the western coast of Australia
called TBT.
And that causes female sea snails to grow male sex organs on the heads.
>> Wow.
>> That is pretty comfortable.
>> That's an on mutation, yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> It's a funny one.
>> The good news is that the percentage of snails with the penis on the foreheads is
going down, and the size of the penis is shrinking thanks to a decreasing proportion of chemical
in the water.
>> That is good news.
>> I think we all know what the most common insult is in the snail population there, isn't
me?
>> It's a pretty straightforward one.
>> So another fish that would change sex is Nemo from the film Finding Nemo.
>> Okay.
>> Did you know about this clown fish?
>> I mean, if the story went as a proper clown fish life cycle does, Nemo would hatch as
a hermaphrodite, because all clown fish are born in heraphrodites.
And when the female mate dies, Nemo's father would have turned into a female.
Now, because Nemo is the only other clown fish around in this setting of the film, he would
then become a male and mate with his now female father, unless his father dies, in which
case he changes into a female and goes off with another male.
>> I haven't seen this movie, is that not what happens?
>> That's pretty much it.
>> He's an extended director, isn't he?
>> I did read that the mother of Nemo dies after four minutes and three seconds of finding
Nemo, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Eat and buy a baracuda, apparently?
>> Yep.
>> But this was in a story.
>> Boy, don't relax.
Boy, don't relax.
>> Those who've only made it two minutes in.
>> So this was in an article that says that two thirds of children's animated films contain
an on-screen death of an important character, compared with only half of comparison films.
So there are more deaths in children's films than there are in the other films.
So basically it's either a dead parent, a single parent, or a mother who turns into a father
who turns into a mother who has sex with a child.
It's usually one of those plot lives on the three classic.
>> That is a fully functioning fish family, that you just described.
So on finding Nemo, there's a book that's just come out I think, which is called Water,
the Past, Present, and Future, which is quite interesting.
And that states that one of the reasons that finding Nemo is set in Sydney is that Sydney
is one of the only places in the world.
So one of only three English-speaking places in the world where you could flush a fish down
a drain, and it would make it to the sea without dying because the others are going to get
ground up and crush the death in various sewage treatment bars.
Yeah, in fact, there was panic when finding Nemo was released that kids were going to start
doing this to their fish to free them.
And so they released a statement saying actually a better title for this film would have been
grinding Nemo because actually if you do this to a fish, it will end up crushed.
>> Wait, who released that statement?
>> It was the national pun or a trait for you to move them.
>> It was set.
>> It wasn't at all right, it's group.
>> No, it was someone involved with the film.
>> Oh, okay.
>> It was helpful though, because children don't normally read a lot of statements.
Well, I appreciate a good pun in the title of them.
So apparently there was a rise in parents calling plumbers going, how do I get my fish out?
We've flushed it down, is it going to be saved?
>> Really?
>> Yeah, yeah.
Because children were just doing it.
>> And there was, and also a lot of children, even though it doesn't exactly like hold up
the virtues of owning a clownfish because he does just escape, there was a problem with
kids suddenly wanting clownfish, and I think there was a certain sea that they were
just taken from where it was empty to build clownfish.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> The damn selfish.
>> I don't know.
>> No, that's actually the group of fish that clownfish are called damn selfish.
It's not a cool name.
>> The damn selfish.
>> Wait, damn.
>> D-A-M selfish.
>> One word.
>> Oh, damn selfish.
>> I say it.
>> [LAUGH]
[LAUGH]
>> That's good.
>> Yeah, well done.
>> Quick question, why do people flush old fish down the toilet and not eat them?
>> [LAUGH]
>> That's the only two options.
>> What, I just care for some reason that people bury their dogs and don't eat them?
>> Yeah, but we eat fish.
We don't eat dogs.
>> Okay, good point.
>> There's fresh fish in the house now.
>> There are so many reasons for James.
>> Right, here's one good reason.
>> Yeah.
>> If your fish has just died, you don't know what it died of.
It could have died of a disease or something.
>> Okay.
>> So you won't want to eat it in that way.
>> Yeah, but that's one extreme.
>> That's not the reason I didn't eat my hamster, for example.
>> Right.
>> Also, I don't ask for a certificate of death when I'm in a restaurant.
>> Well, it's a habit.
>> Okay, you don't understand, don't you, that the restaurants have asked for that?
At some point, the restaurants have to go through a process where they make sure their fish are healthy to eat.
>> It was kind of dead animals.
>> [LAUGH]
>> You've seen those big ads in the newspapers.
We buy dead fish.
[LAUGH]
>> Cash for dead fish.
>> Cash for the old fish.
[LAUGH]
>> It just seems you're throwing away food.
>> One story I like about finding Nemo is that when Andrew Stanton who had the big star had the idea and pitched it to the head of Pixar, John Lasseter.
He did it in a session that lasted over an hour and he had lots of visual aids and character voices and it really tied him out.
He says, and at the end of it was like, oh, Lasseter, what do you think?
And Lasseter just went, you had me at fish.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Okay, so some stuff on contraceptives.
Maybe sponges were used as contraceptives in the 1800s and 1900s.
They would use them with spermicides.
>> Okay, what I'm putting them into.
>> Yeah, so they would be used with things like quinine and olive oil and that would possibly be a contraceptive, yeah.
And some even doubled as household cleaners.
And one was advertised as a dual treatment for successful womanhood, which means contraception, and athletes foot.
>> [LAUGH] >> Two for one.
>> I don't know which order you'd want to do that.
>> I do, I say, now my athletes foot is clear up.
>> [LAUGH] >> But I have 20 children.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Okay, that's it, that's all of our facts, thanks so much for listening.
>> If you want to get in contact with any of us about the things we've said of the course of this podcast,
you can find us all on Twitter.
I'm on @Sriberland, James, @Xshaped, Andy, @EngruConto, and Shazinski.
>> And you can email podcast@QI.com.
>> And you can also go to nosuchthingasafish.com where we have all of our previous episodes.
Have a listen, and we're going to be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]