(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of "Notice Things of Fish"
where we are joined by the wonderful Ella Al-Shemahi.
You might remember Ella from episode 373
of "Notice Things of Fish" when she last appeared,
but if you don't remember that,
then she is a paleoanthropologist.
She's an expert in Neanderthals.
She is a National Geographic Explorer.
She's just an all-round badass.
Ella has written a book called "The Handshake
"A Gripping History,"
which we talked about last time she was on,
but she's also been on loads of TV shows,
loads of documentaries.
The last one I think was called "Our Changing Planet,"
all about the world's most threatened ecosystems,
and you can actually still watch that
if you go to BBC iPlayer or PBS Video app.
Anyway, really hope you enjoyed this week's show.
Don't forget, "Club Fish" exists,
a place where you can get loads of extra content
and ad-free episodes.
Don't forget, there are still one or two tickets,
I think, possibly left for our live shows
coming up in the Soho Theatre in London,
and you can get those by going to
noticethingsofish.com/soho.
Anyway, that's enough of that.
Really hope you enjoy this week's show with Ella,
and it's on with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here
with Andrew Hunter Murray, James Harkin,
and Ella Alshamahi, and once again,
we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Ella.
- American beer was so bad in the early 1900s
that the US government sent Alexander Graham Bell's son-in-law
on a secret mission to Bavaria to steal German hops.
- Wow, God, so much to unpack.
- Yeah, okay, so Alexander Graham Bell's son-in-law,
was that an important part of,
was that what the American government
were looking for, was that the brief?
- The really sad thing is, David Fairchild
is like a hugely celebrated botanist,
and is described as the food explorer,
and yet for our purposes,
he's just Alexander Graham Bell's son-in-law.
'Cause to be fair, if he was your father-in-law,
that's the end of your identity, right?
- But was it, maybe this was at the point
when there was only two telephones in the country,
and so the government would just call him up
and say, "You got anyone we could use?"
- Yeah.
- So you think when he invented two telephones,
Alexander Graham Bell, he gave one to the government,
and kept one himself, and no one else needs one, it's fine.
- And it became like the bat phone,
was any time they were needed for anything.
- The bell phone.
- Yeah, the bell phone.
- I'm loving the facts today, guys.
- So yeah, what's this guy, Fairchild?
- So, all right, so David Fairchild,
so he's a food explorer, and I think he's absolutely
fascinating, 'cause explorers usually go around the planet,
let's be honest, discovering stuff,
but also pillaging a lot, and what have you,
and like stealing artifacts, and whatever takes your fancy.
But this guy did it with plants, with botany,
which is, in my mind, is just like the loveliest thing
to go around the planet stealing.
(laughing)
'Cause all he's doing is, he's basically turned around
at the beginning of the 1900s going,
and the end of the 1800s going,
America is a country clearly on the rise,
but our agriculture's bad, our food is bad,
but our industries as related to plants are just bad,
so I'm gonna go off to 50-odd countries,
and just collect samples, send seeds back,
send saplings back, that kind of thing.
And because it's plants, I just can't get mad at him,
because I'm just like, you were just helping
to feed your people, and build industry.
- Could we get him canceled because he was like,
stealing from the farms in other countries?
- Are you trying to get him canceled?
- I'm doing my best.
I do this on this podcast, you know, and we have that.
- Don't ever mention anyone you like on this show.
James will find a way to destroy it.
- Do not do this to me, 'cause I actually,
I've decided that he's like the one explorer
that I really have nothing bad to say about.
I'm like, I'm not fair enough,
you're trying to feed your people.
He did give the Americans broccoli and kale, so.
- Oh yeah, yeah, I love those two things.
- It's interesting how limited American food was.
I didn't really appreciate that before the 1890s,
when he really got crack.
They had occasional introductions,
like in the World's Fair in 1876,
which was effectively America's 100th birthday,
they got the banana, that was good.
That was a big advance.
- Also, can we just take a second to talk about world fairs?
Aren't they just the best thing ever?
- Yeah.
- Just this world where you were like,
oh, let's just do a World Fair.
And it actually was like everyone was like,
oh crap, that's actually, that's new.
That's, what is that?
It's yellow and it's bendy.
That's amazing.
- When did we last have one?
It's been a long time.
- Well, I went to one in Dubai this year.
- Oh yes, okay, so this year.
- Oh yeah, they did that, hold on.
- Well, they did one during COVID,
and obviously no one could go.
And then when I went, everything was closed.
So you couldn't even get an Uber, everyone had gone home.
- Oh, right.
- 'Cause that's what it is.
They build them these sort of huge things, don't they?
And all the different countries have their different stalls
where they're saying, in Uzbekistan,
we make amazing bananas or whatever.
And then two years later, they all go home and that's it.
- They only do with countries that are on the rise, right?
- Yeah.
- Like, we wouldn't do a world,
America wouldn't do a World Fair anymore.
We are the world, why would we do a World Fair?
- There was the big one in America.
Carl Sagan went to as a kid.
So Sagan would be in his 80s if he was still alive
in the 1990s, so, you know, within that world.
- The one in Dubai, just to say this is quite interesting
'cause each country made their own sort of building
and they were all kind of shaped
with Uzbekistani design or Azerbaijani design or whatever.
And now they're changing it
and they're turning it into flats the whole place.
- Oh wow.
- And they're gonna make it so you can live in this area.
But it means that all these buildings
are just these incredible designs
that have made from the best architects in the world.
- It sounds like you're selling Dubai
instead of cancelling Dubai,
which I thought you were the cancelling Dubai.
- Is it Dubai?
- There's no, you can't get an Uber there.
You can't, there's no shops there already for you.
So I'm gonna live here.
- Oh, that's the bad side of Dubai, guys.
I'm all the bad crap.
- Famously, there are no shops in Dubai.
Someone emailed in and I've got a bunch of their fact now
and also not credit them
'cause I don't think we're gonna end up
talking about World Fairs.
It was a few years ago, the Brazilian delegation
turned their entire thing into a trampoline.
- What?
- It was something like a 4,000 square foot trampoline,
the Brazilian bit of the world.
- Was it to sell rubber?
- I don't think it was.
I don't even think it was.
I think it was just saying,
look, everyone else has got good stuff here.
Well, you've got a big old trampoline.
So just come along, have a bounce, enjoy yourself.
- They had a big project that at the last minute
got taken away.
They went, what have we got?
- Why are we talking about the World Fair?
- I'm sorry, I got distracted.
- Yeah, this is what happens when Ella is around.
- Because during the World Fair,
the banana was introduced to America.
- Yeah.
- And it's not food introduction.
- By Fairchild or someone else.
- By someone else, that was like a sporadic thing.
But then when he really got going,
he was privately funded as well.
- Yes.
- By Barbaul Lathrop.
- Yes, yes, yes.
A wonderfully gay, fabulous figure, basically,
who was just this incredible philanthropist.
- Squillionaire, just looking for something to fund.
- And they bumped into each other on a boat, didn't they?
And he just went, I'll fund this trip.
Are you trying to steal avocados?
- Yeah, why not?
This sounds great.
- Can I just say, as an explorer with National Geographic,
that is our dream, that we're like, no, no, no.
If you think I am kidding, you do not know,
like my friend group, in the sense that we are like,
we literally just sit there, constantly going,
all right, how do we get this kind of thing
from philanthropy?
And every so often it works out.
So I've got friends that like,
they're like this smart friend of the philanthropist,
who is like some billionaire or millionaire.
- They're like their sugar mama, dadda, whatever.
- Have I ever told you the story of Nat Geo?
Somebody walks up to me.
It's really old guy, bless him.
That's the first time I've ever been at National Geographic.
And he looks at me and goes, I'm from Austin, Texas.
I'm not an oil man, but I've got money
and I want to give you some.
(laughing)
- What the hell?
- I saw that money in my account.
An expedition was part funded by it.
- Wow, so as simple as that.
Okay, so it does happen.
Yeah, that's amazing.
So Fairchild, I agree.
I think reading about him,
he seems like an extraordinary guy.
I'm surprised I'd never heard of him, for example.
But if you're in America and you're eating,
say like peaches or nectarines or avocados or mangoes,
most likely the one that you're eating right now,
someone's bound to be eating one right now as they listen,
shares genes from the ones that Fairchild
introduced to the country all those years ago.
What a sort of footprint he's left in the country.
- It's incredible.
- Send us your photos.
If you're eating a mango now in America specifically,
or an avocado, some quinoa.
- Yeah, did he bring in quinoa?
- Yep, podcast at qi.com.
- Mangosteens?
- The mangosteen, oh great, let's talk about this.
This is great.
- Go on, what about the mangosteen?
- It's a fruit that he introduced and that never took off.
'Cause he introduced thousands.
And they didn't all take off.
- Yeah, you can still buy mangosteens though, can't you?
- Think so.
They just never explained it.
- I had never heard of the mangosteen before.
- I had never. - Really?
- Yeah.
- The guy who wrote the book on David Fairchild
is Dan Stone, who's a friend of mine.
And apparently while he was writing this book,
everybody would just send him really exotic fruit
like for the whole time he was writing the book.
'Cause they were like, this is good for you, no?
- Yeah. - He's not sure.
- Yeah, the book's called The Food Explorer, by the way.
I think it's fair to say that every bit of research I have
is from Dan Stone, so yeah, well done.
- So Dan, tell us about mangosteen, Sandy.
- Well, as far as I can tell,
again, Dan and I have never heard of them before
and you two are having them for breakfast every day.
So correct me if I'm wrong.
But the size of a fist, roughly, and they're like a lychee.
- Brilliant.
- But the problem is, they're not great for farming.
And what he was doing, Fairchild,
you have to persuade the farmers to grow the things
and the public to buy them.
So it's got two jobs to carry out, basically.
And he couldn't persuade either, apparently,
either side of the equation.
'Cause they're really hard, they bruise worse than peaches
and they're just a nightmare to transport
and they go off really quickly.
But he said they were the queen of fruits.
- They were his favorites. - Oh, really?
- I know. - And he kept trying
to make them happen, like fetch in Mean Girls.
(laughing)
He kept trying to make it happen
and no one was picking up on it.
And so all these things he brought into the country,
but the one of which you headlined your fact with
is very interesting because it was the beer hops.
And you'd think you'd just go into a country,
grab some fruit and leave the country,
but no, people were so protective.
They would have boys sleeping with the hops at night
to make sure no one would steal.
- Yeah, they would pay to security, that's the thing.
- So he'd come in and integrate himself with the communities.
He would sort of become friends.
- And so this particular hop,
so this is, I think, the Sems hop,
he basically started talking about Sems,
the guy that came up with it, who was dead at this point.
And he offered the son of Sems, basically he said,
"Look, I'm really scared that in a few generations,
"people aren't gonna know about your dad, blah, blah, blah."
So he was like, "Why don't you build a plaque?
"I will pay for it."
So he basically put money down.
Impressive US diplomacy here.
And they made such a song and dance about it.
Everybody was really happy.
The whole, like, everybody in the town was happy about it.
And then apparently somebody at night knocks on his door
when it's raining and goes, "Do you want some?
"Do you want some cuttings?"
And apparently he has to really restrain himself
to not be like, "Yes, this is exactly why I did all this
"and I've been manipulating you guys for weeks."
And he was like, "Yeah, okay."
And he goes, "Okay, I can't do this publicly.
"I have to do it quietly, but I'll send 100 cuttings
"to the next station down the line."
- Oh, not even handing them over now.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
It was proper espionage.
- That's amazing.
- It's hilarious, but also to think of all the espionage
that the US government has ever done.
- I just can't object to this one.
- Yeah, that's why American beer now is so delicious.
(laughing)
I mean, how bad must it have been?
- So, here's the crazy thing.
Apparently during Prohibition,
all his hops were uprooted.
So all the same hops that Fertile Halled.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, they were all uprooted during the--
- I read that.
Basically when Prohibition came in,
all the breweries closed down.
And then when they reopened,
there was a few more big ones
and they decided to sell what they knew would sell
'cause they weren't sure anyone would buy any beer anymore.
And so they went with the really safe stuff,
which was the light beers and the mass produced stuff.
- Okay, now can you explain Hershey's?
- Hershey's.
- Tastes like sick.
- Tastes like sick to British people.
- Well, you know, it contains some chemicals
which happen to also taste like sick.
- I don't know how people have gone around tasting sick.
They haven't, they haven't.
They really haven't.
That's not how it is.
- Well, if you're eating a Hershey's bar right now,
please send a photo.
If you're being sick, if you're, you know.
- Oh, yes, that one.
- Podcast at qr.com.
- Do they have your address?
'Cause I feel like if they have your address,
they could send the Mangosteans and the sick,
et cetera, et cetera, to the address.
- We've just moved offices.
And the reason being that the old office
was just full of sick and Mangosteans.
- Soon undated, yeah.
But everyone's tasted sick if they've ever been sick.
- True.
- You know.
- Oh, wow.
- You just taste it in reverse, don't you?
Sorry to, I mean to, you know, to lower the tone.
- That's nasty.
- That's how we know what American chocolate tastes like.
- Yeah.
- Great.
- Thank you.
- Could you guys hear about the cherry blossom trees in DC
and how he's responsible for all of them, basically?
So, I mean, we have them now in London quite a lot.
They're very kind of ornamental and very beautiful.
But he introduced them from Japan.
And then it became all the rage and people were like queuing
up to see him and Alexander Graham Bell's daughters.
- Is that their house, wasn't it?
He put it to his, yeah.
- Exactly, exactly.
And then basically Washington DC was not the beautiful
metropolis it now is.
Back then it was kind of ugly.
And he started saying, well, maybe we should just plant
some cherry blossom trees around here.
And that would be kind of beautiful.
And then the first lady heard of this.
And before you know it, the Japanese who at this point
they're not particularly like chummy with.
They're like, okay, this could be a symbol of friendship.
If you give us 300 cherry blossom trees,
we can plant them in DC.
And the Japanese got carried away, ended up shipping 2000.
But they opened the crate.
So I think it was in Seattle and went, oh crap,
they were diseased.
They were absolutely infested with invasive species.
So then they had to publicly burn the symbol of friendship
between Japan and the US.
And it was like on the front page of the New York Times.
- And the thing I read was it was from orders
of the president, which feels like he should have been busier
than having to make executive decisions
of agricultural imports.
- Although it was his decision, wasn't it?
Because it was him and the first lady who kind of made
the decision to bring it over, wasn't it?
- Wow.
- But the Japanese were like, are bad.
And so it was all fine.
They sent more over and then they are now.
- And as a result, US-Japanese relations
stayed very harmonious, didn't they?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, good.
- It was interesting 'cause the ones
that they sent over the second time,
they had to make sure that they were really not infested.
So they raised the trees in virgin soil.
So the soil was brand new
and they'd never been anywhere else.
They wrapped the roots in damp moss to stop any--
- It's a long work for a friendship man.
- Yeah.
- That's great.
And they fumigated it twice, once to asphyxiate the insects
and then once just in case.
(laughing)
But yeah, and the reason that they did this
is because this guy, a fair child,
had a nemesis called Charles Marlatt, didn't he?
- Yep.
- This is an amazing story.
So Charles Marlatt was in charge of the FDA
sort of anti-insect part of the FDA,
but they were boyhood friends.
And actually Marlatt was Fairchild's best man at his wedding.
But then they fell out because Fairchild basically got
a load of easy jobs through his friends and family,
he'll have a bit of nepotism and stuff.
And Marlatt had to work hard for his job.
And so they really fell out.
And Marlatt basically, whenever Fairchild brought in
any new species, he would be like,
"Does insects on that get rid of it?
"Burn it, do it now."
And so they really, really fell out.
- I have to defend the entomologist,
even though I love doing Fairchild.
So it's worth saying that like Fairchild,
he did get a lot of fame,
but a lot of that was off his own back.
But then, yeah, sure, he married into like
this really prominent family
and became really big with National Geographic.
But today, we would actually side with the entomologist.
Like, scientifically, he's the sound one.
Not the botanist just being like,
"Well, let's just hope it's gonna be fine
"when we bring all these parts from all over the world."
- Yeah, definitely.
- It was dangerous, yeah.
- I read this amazing story that he wanted to send
a thousand mangoes back to America,
but he put them on a boat and they were too heavy.
And so he solved it by getting a load of local children
to eat them all.
- What?
- Because all he needed were the stones.
He didn't need the mangoes themselves.
So he just got all the kids and said,
"Free mangoes as many as you can eat."
They all went, "Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no."
- U.S. diplomacy, there we go.
That's another...
- I thought you were gonna say something really clever,
like, "He only needed to ship the children there."
- And then they poo the mouse.
- Exactly, exactly.
And I was thinking, "Oh, those children are brave,
"like pooing at a mango stone.
"That's not funny."
No, children famously a bit more heavy than a mango as well.
So, wait was your issue.
- Oh, no.
I'm sorry.
- Okay, it's time for fact number two, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that up one stage
of the 17th century, every woman living on the Yemeni island
of Sokotra was called Maria.
- Was it?
Okay, okay.
- How many women were on the island?
- Well, I don't know, but it wasn't completely insignificant.
It's a big island, right?
It's about the size of what you've been there.
- Long Island.
- It's big, haven't you?
- Long Island, yeah, yeah.
- Is it that they were hosting a sound of music reality show?
- In the 17th century.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- I feel like it's a real Yemeni vibe.
It's like the tribesmen and the sound of music.
- Well, I don't know exactly how many people live there.
How many people do you say live there now?
It's in the 10, 10,000.
- I think it's about 40,000.
- 40,000, yeah.
It would have been less then,
but basically it was a Christian island.
By tradition, it was St. Thomas who was shipwrecked there
in the year 52 AD.
And he supposedly brought in Christianity,
but definitely the Greeks brought in the 4th century
that definitely happened.
And Marco Polo wrote about it in the 13th century
that there were Christians there.
And in the 17th century, there was a guy called Padre Vincenzo
and he visited Socatra.
And he found that they were still Christian ostensibly,
but they'd kind of moved to other beliefs
because Socatra is a place it's very difficult to get to,
especially at certain times of year,
you can't really get there at all.
- The monsoon is, yeah, good luck.
- And so because they were isolated
from the rest of the world,
they kind of had this new version of Christianity.
So a lot of them were called Maria.
There were still a lot of churches,
but for instance, they used to do sacrifices to the moon
and a few different things.
- Why not keep some of your old beliefs in?
Just spice it all up a bit.
What year was that again?
- It was in the mid 17th century.
- Why were they called Maria?
- Because Mary, the mother of Jesus.
- Oh, that must have been confusing.
- Oh, yeah. - No, 'cause they'd...
- Have you been there?
- Yeah, so I've been to Socatra.
It is, I can verify that it's very difficult to get there.
- Have you met a Maria?
- I have not met a Maria
'cause weirdly there's no Christians left on the island.
- Oh, what's that?
- Someone's had Maria, come on.
(all laughing)
- They're all Muslims now.
- So I went there kind of 2018, I think, or 2019.
And we had three options to get there.
Either we fly in via mainland Yemen,
but the airport we were flying into
was on Al Qaeda stronghold.
So decided maybe that's not the best way of getting in.
And then the other route was via,
kind of almost like a private jet via the Emirates,
the place that you like.
But they were only giving us verbal permission,
not written permission.
And then the third option was to get on a cement cargo ship
from Oman and sail through pirate waters.
And the ship was like infested with cockroaches,
like completely infested.
And it had like a, the toilet was like a basket
on the side of the ship, like attached with rope.
- Is this the route you went?
- Yeah. - Whoa.
- Yeah, it was hilarious.
- No pirates?
- Yeah, we luckily didn't have, you know.
The Swede in the group had his wits about him,
let me tell you that every time,
every time a ship went past you like just very nervous.
- But yeah, so it's really hard to get to
and that's the thing, right?
But then that's good news for other things.
So it means that they have amazing biodiversity there.
- Yeah, you've seen the trees there, there.
- They look incredible.
I mean, the dragonblood tree,
I know that's the most famous really,
that's the sort of like the headline tree out there,
but they do look beautiful.
- They're beautiful.
- They look, they're described,
if you'd want to picture it,
they're described as sort of looking like umbrellas.
But a lot of them look like umbrellas with a high wind
where you know when your umbrella flips on side out
'cause you see the stems coming up
and they're known for the fact that if the sap comes out,
it's red sap, hence the kind of dragonblood thing.
And they've been exporting that for years
and it's been used for all sorts of like nail polish
and medicines and so on.
- Smirring gladiators?
- Really? - Really?
- I think gladiators supposedly had a bit of it
to smear them as decoration and a bit as disinfectant.
But the thing is that the tree,
I think it only exists there now,
but pollen has been found all around the Mediterranean
as in fossilized or archeologists
have found pollen of it around the Med.
So this is what the Med used to look like.
There used to be these trees much more commonly.
- So the dragon's blood tree,
there's different species of dragon's blood.
And there are still what we call
in biology relic populations.
So kind of populations that are on their last leg in Socotra,
but there's different species of dragon's blood
in the Canary Islands.
There's another species in Ouan
and kind of a remote part of Oman.
And it looks like the dragon's blood tree
was like a really dominant tree
in the whole of kind of that old world.
It's kind of old school.
It should kind of really be on its out and it is.
- But it is right.
They're saying possibly in the next 80 years,
if we're not careful,
it's gonna be an extinct species of tree.
And it's so interesting how it survives
'cause most trees obviously get their water
through the roots under the ground.
But this tree has worked out a way.
I don't know if that's a language you use about trees,
but it's got the ability to take in the moisture
of the clouds that are going above it.
So it can pull from above as well as below,
which is pretty amazing.
- It injects much more water into the soil
from the air than it gets in rainfall.
'Cause sometimes it's foggy and cloudy
and it sort of sucks all that.
It's called horizontal precipitation capture,
which is as it sounds.
But they've got I think 92 different plant species
which live in the undergrowth.
The few surveys have found that.
And seven of them are only found
living in the undergrowth of the dragon's blood tree.
That's mad.
- That's so cool.
- I suppose that would make it an umbrella species.
It looks like an umbrella.
- Oh!
- I'll tell you what, at National Geographic,
they go wild for that long.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I mean, when you turn up there,
I'm not gonna lie, you're like, what is this place?
It looks, there's so few places on Earth
where you look at them and you go,
"Oh, that looks really alien."
Like that's a really unusual landscape.
And cicotra is definitely that, like these canyons,
like Grand Canyon or more obviously not that scale,
but with these dragon blood trees.
And other trees as well, you know,
and giant snails and a bunch of stuff
that you're just like, "What is this?"
- Well, Ella, I can ask you,
as the only one who's been there,
did it seem to you at all like the atmosphere
of the planet Pandora in the global mega hit avatar films?
- Okay, okay, actually this is a good crowd
to ask this because I've heard that as well,
but that was an inspiration.
And I wondered if we knew what the source of that was
because I could, here's the thing,
the thing with cicotra is,
if you speak to people that are really in the know,
so people, the kind of off the beat travelers,
people that are very interested in kind of biology,
that kind of thing, they all know cicotra.
It's like this hidden secret
that actually everybody in a certain industry knows about.
Like, you know, and it's on people's dreams.
I've met very rich people
that are desperate for me to take them to cicotra.
And I'm like, sure, once I've dealt with the pirate situation,
I will get you, and you're very rich.
- Cue of wizards Texans just waiting to be.
- But yeah, I wondered about that
because I was like, I can see that,
but I just wonder what the source is.
'Cause I just, being that we care about fact here, guys,
right? - Yeah.
- Right? - Yeah.
- Right? - Sure.
- I need more.
- Well, there's one thing we care about more than facts,
and that's the continued success
of the way of water franchise.
(laughing)
Nevermind, nevermind, nevermind.
- Just on the Christianity in Yemen in the 17th century,
this was what Padre Vincenza was talking about.
A few weird things that they did.
They had a priest called Adambo,
who was elected by the people
and changed every single year.
Just like almost like an archbishop of the island.
- But democratic. - But democratic.
That's quite cool, isn't it?
- Yeah, very cool.
- Let me tell you about modern day Yemen.
(laughing)
- The other thing is, in the churches,
they had like a, what would you call it, like an altar,
and every day they would smear it with butter.
- Oh, lovely.
- That does sound kind of--
- What for what reason?
- Yeah, do they slide along it?
(laughing)
'Cause that would be a great way
of starting a service, wouldn't it?
- You know, whoosh, I'm here.
- Was it sort of like, you're going up for your body of Christ?
Would you like some butter?
(laughing)
- I don't know how this is just the fantasies
of these two heathens.
That's what would take those two heathens back to church.
- I've got a general Yemen fact.
- Oh, yeah. - Yeah.
- During, so Yemen, I think,
used to be a British colony protectorate.
- Protectorate the south of it.
- That's safe to say about anywhere in the world.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- The British were involved in something.
- Well, you know, yeah.
- So during that era, the port of Aden, which was,
and I think even after the rest of Yemen might have gained it,
it depends, Aden maintained a kind of special status.
Basically, Aden was in a pretty constant state of emergency.
Things were so dicey there
that British citizens living there were issued
pretty much as standard with revolvers
in case of assassination attempts on them.
Imagine that, imagine just moving to somewhere
and being fitted with a revolver.
- Yeah, Yemen's an interesting place.
Like, during, so there was a revolution
and obviously now there's a war.
And there was like a protest and outside the protest,
it says, "No bazookas."
(laughing)
- So you were allowed to...
- Wow.
(laughing)
- Other way, but just no bazookas.
We're drawing the line of, oh, and land mines.
They were like, "No bazookas and no hand grenades."
- Oh my God.
- That's so funny.
'Cause like, we just had protests here.
And if you brought like a...
- A whistle.
- A whistle or a luggage tag,
they'd kind of ship your way to prison.
- Yeah, no, no, no, no.
But in defense of my parents' home land,
I will say it is a,
have you seen pictures of mainland Yemen
and the island of Scotland?
It's the most stunning place.
And I know, like, I'm biased,
but it is absolutely absolutely beautiful.
- I saw a photo of a place.
I wonder if you've seen it in person.
You've been there quite a few times, right?
It's described as the Manhattan of the desert.
- Yes.
- I mean, it sounds incredible.
That was Freya Stark, explorer who called it that
in the 1930s.
But this is a 16th century walled city
that was the first ever city of skyscrapers.
They went seven floors high
and the buildings were made of mud.
It was just a mud trouble.
- And higher actually.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And there's still, obviously,
there's been renovations and so on,
but is there anything original?
- Oh, it's all there.
Yeah, so it's a UNESCO World Heritage Site.
Again, so it's,
so Sokotra is also a UNESCO World Heritage Site.
And it's basically buildings,
10, 11, whatever, stories high.
The really cute thing is that
some of those houses have bridges
on the top of the houses
because people can't be bothered
to go all the way downstairs.
'Cause I have elevators.
They're like, right, historic buildings, right?
So they, instead of going all the way
downstairs to go visit the neighbors,
they just go to the top,
which they call the drill band.
They just leg it along these little bridges.
- But the thing is, it's so old
and it's still inhabited.
That's the amazing.
- Oh, no, no, it's inhabited.
It's completely inhabited.
It's a lived in and World Heritage Site.
It's great.
I mean, when you turn up there,
you're like, are you kidding?
So bazookas and pistols, yes,
but also heritage.
- It was the...
- Go visit, guys.
- It was the only place you could get coffee from
for 200 years until one of these people
who stole plants went in.
(laughing)
- You're hero, Zala.
- Suddenly, I don't like them.
Went in, nicked all the coffee.
And if Mocha, which is the place
where the coffee was exported from,
if they still had the monopoly on coffee,
there would be enough money for everyone in Yemen
to get a payment of $16,000 per year
on top of anything else they earned.
- Are you kidding me?
- And that would be eight times higher
than the actual average salary of a person from Yemen.
- Wow.
- So yeah.
Just one more thing on Marys.
- Oh yeah.
- At the end of the 18th century,
24% of women in England were called Mary.
- The secotra of the North, so called it.
(laughing)
- And in Vexan, which is in France,
just Northwest of Paris,
in 1740, 68.4% of women were called Mary.
- What?
- Or Marie, it would be.
- Do any of you have Marys in your family?
- I have a cousin.
- Yeah, my, Rosemary is my auntie.
So there's, yeah, I wonder if it's that,
if it's the double barrel first.
- Well, in France, that's what happens.
So around that time, around the 18th century,
they started doing the double names,
so you could have Marie Claire or Marie, whatever.
And yeah, so they started almost,
everyone was called Marie something.
- Oh.
- In 1379, 33% of the male population of Sheffield
were called John, and 22% of the women were called Alice.
- John and Alice have invited us round.
- Be more specific!
(laughing)
- That's us!
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that during the Second World War,
the making of Spitfires was so secret
that one married couple didn't know
they were both working on it.
- Was that John and Alice?
- It was John and Alice.
- That's cool.
- It's so weird.
- I wonder if they both thought
that the other was having enough.
- I know, imagine them going to work in the morning,
playing off to work.
- Yeah, me too.
- Okay. - See you later.
- I'm going in this direction.
- Oh.
(laughing)
- I'll just pop back to the house for a minute.
- Who's there somewhere at work,
whose job it was to keep them apart as well?
A nightmare life of the coming to the canteen
at the same time.
Oh, hey, what are you coming for?
- It's such a weird fact.
- How did they find out?
So many questions.
- They found out decades later.
That's the crazy thing.
So this is a slight--
- Was that the only secret thing they were working?
I have so many questions.
Was that the only secret thing they were working on?
- I think they were both working
in this specific factory.
- The same factory even?
- Yeah, it was the same factory, yeah, yeah.
But so this is--
- I mean, they might be idiots, guys.
(laughing)
- Basically, for anyone who doesn't know,
we're talking about the Spitfire,
the Super Marine Spitfires legendary plane
of the Second World War and big thing in Britain,
a kind of national myth item in Britain, the Spitfire.
And there was a factory in Southampton,
which made, I think, most of the Spitfires,
and it was bombed in 1940 by the Luftwaffe,
and it was not just bombed, it was flattened,
and this was a disaster.
And they needed to work out how to, you know,
keep Spitfire production going,
but keep it safe from bombing raids.
And what they did was they said,
well, we'll make it in secret.
And not only that, we'll divide all the factories
into, you know, lots of different tiny micro factories
around the place, which are all hidden.
So they used all sorts of little offices or garages,
a laundry, an old glove factory, they just divide,
it was amazing, they just divided it up.
And lots of them were in Salisbury and Reading
and Trowbridge and just like all over the place, basically.
And this came out decades after the war,
that this is how it had been done, basically.
And there was an engineer who worked on them
called Norman Parker, and he said in 2021,
he was interviewed about it.
He was about 95 at the time that he was talking about this.
He said, "We had one case, there was a couple
at a dinner party in the 1970s,
and over the dinner table, the wife said,
"Oh, I was building Spitfires in Salisbury during the war."
And the husband said, "No, you weren't, I was."
And they had both been working in the same factory
and they didn't know it.
- It could be a false memory, I guess.
- I think this is a really bad marriage, guys.
- Yeah.
- I've got-
- Well, there are a number of things
it could have been, but basically.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- I reckon I have things with my siblings
that we talk about when we were really, really young.
And we all think that we were the one
who did a certain thing.
- Oh, right.
- Do you know what I mean?
- Yeah, I see, you're throwing shade on the-
- I'm not saying that's true, but I'm just saying,
I remember I was, my brother was locked in a toilet
in France when we went to a restaurant once
and we had to get him out.
And then he thinks it was my sister who was that.
Do you know what I mean?
So it's like, weirdo.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Or it could be that they're telling the truth
and it's a real thing.
(laughing)
- Do we know what they worked on specifically?
- Well, that's the other thing,
production was divvied up in lots of ways.
So it might have been by same factory.
It was a factory, it was at different sites
or it was a, you know, they probably weren't in the same room.
- He could have been making the leather chairs
for what could be used for a car, but it was for a plane.
And as in like-
- Sure, yeah, yeah.
- That's what I mean, to the level
of what were they making.
- Exactly, yeah.
- The spitfire.
- It's plausible, for sure.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I mean, it's-
- I think they sort of dug into it.
- And everyone was very secretive.
- And people were very secretive.
Or you might know in a couple,
I'm working on something that's secret
and I can't really tell you what it's about.
And they're both in war work.
And the thing is about aviation, during the Second World War,
65% of the aviation workforce were women
because most of the men were in the arm.
- So statistically, she's more likely to be correct.
- Absolutely, yeah.
Like I say, I think they're both correct.
- So she's told this guy at the dinner table,
he's gone, wow, what an amazing life.
What did you do?
Yeah, yes, spitfires as well.
(laughing)
- So anyway, the spitfire.
- Spitfire is amazing.
- So are you into the spitfire?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause I feel like I don't,
I feel, how do I put this politely?
- The people that talk about spitfires a lot
tend to be a few years older than you.
- Thank you.
That's actually a compliment guys.
I don't know if you heard that was,
(laughing)
I'm young seeming for a guy as interested in spitfires.
- Shit, my teacher at school when I was a kid,
was an older guy, was really into spitfires.
- I think actually, Ella, you'll find,
the more that you meet Andy and talk to him.
- He's an old man.
- Well, a lot of the things he's interested in,
you would expect older men to be interested in.
- Is that fair to say?
- I think it's not, I'm fair.
(laughing)
I'm not really, I'm not deeply into them,
but I am interested in logistics.
(laughing)
- So for those who can't see this,
he might be shaking a little bit.
(laughing)
I'm not really, really into it.
- I'm trembling with joy.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I had a look at, just, you know,
we check what we've talked about before in this podcast.
I had a look, I can't believe you guys have stopped me
for nine years from ever mentioning the spitfire
on this show.
We've never mentioned that.
- Well done guys, high five for the rest of the day.
(laughing)
- Great place.
- Yeah, incredible plane and also,
what a group effort of the UK during wartime
to make this plane built to the numbers
that it was built at.
Basically, there was, I was reading an article saying
that it was effectively like one of the early kick starters
where people funded,
coal communities would go around funding single planes
and they, as a result, got to name the plane.
So lots of the planes flying that were in the war
had names like Dorothy of Great Britain and Empire
and that was funded entirely by women called Dorothy.
So, it's so, yes, it's so funny.
- Maria plane.
- Yeah, by the fact that 70% of women
were called Dorothy.
(laughing)
- There was the dog fighter as well.
There was, and that was the Kennel Club
who had funded that. - All right,
it wasn't people who did dog fighting.
(laughing)
Think for the back of the pub.
- But check this out, this is the most incredible one.
There was one that was POWs of Oflag.
This is a prison camp in Germany
with captured officers who donated their month's pay
through the Red Cross.
Then that went into the building of a plane.
So they were in prison and they were funding the plane.
- That was war actually.
- I read about that and they had to send letters back
saying I want to give my money to this crowdfunding, right?
But they had to do it in code.
So, because you couldn't send a message
that the Germans will be able to read saying,
please put all my money into spitfires.
Otherwise they're just gonna accidentally lose it, aren't they?
- Yeah, exactly. - It's amazing.
- It was, that was a really nice thing,
this crowdfunding effort, which I had not heard of.
- What would they have called it back then, though?
It wouldn't have been crowdfunding.
- They were called Spitfire Funds.
And the planes were kind of arbitrarily priced.
They said 5,000 pounds will buy a Spitfire,
which was not actually a true figure,
but it sort of was a peg for people too.
- But also that thing of charities,
these days they would say,
two pounds will buy a meal for one person.
- Yeah, it was like six pounds will buy a rivet.
- Exactly. - And 2,000 pounds
will get you a wing.
- No.
- So you can see what you were buying.
- They raised a lot of money.
It was nearly given a much less sexy name
than the Spitfire.
Spitfire's quite a swashbuckling name.
Other contenders included Scarab, Shrike,
which is quite good, 'cause that's a bird
that impales its prey, and it's quite sort of...
But I looked up the complete list of Super Marine aircraft,
and there were some many bad options
that the Spitfire could have been called.
There was the Super Marine Commercial Amphibian,
the Super Marine Sea Urchin,
Super Marine Spiteful, quite good,
the Super Marine Seagull, Super Marine Sea Otter.
- No, no, no, they're taking the...
- No, they're a rip, and the Super Marine Baby.
- Oh, yeah. - Oh, yeah.
- I know. - In a brainstorm,
sometimes there are bad ideas.
- Unleash the babies, yeah, yeah.
But they mostly began with this,
and they were mostly sea planes.
That's what they started out as,
the firm started out making sea planes and so, yeah.
- I love sea planes. - Yeah, they're cool.
- Imagine they're a plane where you can just land anywhere.
As long as there's a body of water, you just land.
- So not on land.
- Yeah, well, yeah.
- No, no, no, no, sorry.
- I'm sorry.
- Dan suddenly brings the facts.
- You get special life jackets in case you land on land.
- Yeah, yeah, exactly.
- These Super Marine Spitfires,
when they were taxiing,
so just kind of driving around the airport,
they were quite often sort of,
not overturned, but get really wobbly.
And so what would happen is someone would often sit
on the tail of the plane to keep them steady,
and it was often a woman who did this,
and there was a particular woman called Margaret Horton
who did this in 1943 at RAF, Heibaldstow,
and she was sat on the back
and the guy was a little bit anxious to get in the air
and forgot to get her off the tail.
- No, no, no.
- So started taking off
while she was sitting on the tail of the Spitfire.
And he radioed down to traffic controls saying,
there's something wrong with this plane.
It's kind of really heavy.
- And so they talked him down,
but they never told him that there was a woman on the back.
- Oh, no way.
- Well, because as soon as they tell him,
he's gonna be--
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So true.
- So they're like, oh yeah, there's obviously a problem
with the wing, we'll just talk you down on how to get down.
And so he never knew until he landed that this woman was--
- Bloody hell.
- And she survived.
- She survived, yeah, yeah.
- She survived.
There's a museum called Tagmeer Military Aviation Museum.
And when you go to it,
there's a model that they've made.
So you can see a model of a Spitfire taking off
with this woman.
- A little plasticine woman
or whatever the material is holding on the tail wing.
- It's so funny.
- It's so brilliant.
- Should we say why it was so good?
- I'm intrigued, yeah.
So apparently all the pilots loved it,
but I'm like, why, why did they all love it?
- Well, it was really nimble.
It turned very, very fast.
And also the other thing about it was,
it was, you know, it's like,
if you guys want to tease me when I say this bit,
I don't mind, right?
But basically they had flush riveting, which is a good--
(laughing)
Okay, talk amongst yourselves.
Dear listener.
No, so metal skin, very, very cool.
But if you had lumpy rivets all over it,
which most planes did before that,
it drags the plane back a bit.
Whereas if you sink, you use the little countersunk rivets,
so you can see where it's going to go.
So it's like, what's going on?
If you sink, you use the little countersunk rivets,
so you sort of, it's exactly level
with the surface of the plane,
then the airflow is very efficient
and you get a much faster plane.
And they did some experiments on early spitfires.
They replicated what it would be like
if it had external rivets by gluing split peas
onto the spots where the rivets were all over the plane
and then flying it, doing a speed test, basically.
And it was about 20, 22 miles an hour slower.
It was a fair chunk slower,
which would have had a serious effect
if you were in a combat situation, you know.
So yeah.
- Couldn't you have stopped the enemy
by going in and putting peas on his plane?
- Definitely.
That was a big part of the early SIS job was, yeah.
- I used to do that and so did my wife.
(laughing)
- So that fact would be even more impressive
if I knew what a rivet was.
(hissing)
- Yeah.
Well, you've got to retain some mystery, I'm afraid.
- That's still under the secrets act, actually.
- What the hell's a rivet?
- A kind of screw, kind of screw.
- Like a big old screw.
- It joins the bits of the plane
to the other bits of the plane.
- I'm googling rivet.
- That's so funny.
- You know the word riveting?
It's got nothing to do with what a rivet is.
(laughing)
- Hold on, rivet.
Just googling.
- 'Cause it holds you together, it holds you in place.
Yeah, you're right.
- This is, yeah, they're just, it's a kind of screw.
- Yeah, yeah, basically, yeah.
- Message in if you didn't know what a rivet was.
- And if you like, I can repeat that fact for you now.
And it'll be even more exciting this time round.
- Shouldn't be that, though.
- Yeah, I'll just quickly mention.
- What?
(laughing)
- I feel like we've got it now.
I've read a tenth of my stuff out.
I haven't told you about the Super Marine Walrus.
- So it's just not of interest.
Like, what are your subjects that they won't let you
normally talk about?
I just need to know, like, how valid.
- It's mostly second-world war logistic.
- Yeah, we end up letting him do it
because he does crowbar it in somehow into any old fact.
- So it is a question for you.
Do you follow current war strategy and logistics?
Like, I've got a whole bunch of male friends
who are so into the logistics of the Ukrainian war
that it's gone beyond anything that I think is normal.
- You'd have to ask my wife what's normal
in terms of what--
- It's past and present.
- I think logistics is interesting.
(laughing)
And I'm not, I'm blushing now, but actually,
I'm not ashamed.
- Logistics is interesting, needs to go on your tombstone.
- We can't all be, we can't all be bloody explorers, you know,
on cool cement ships.
I'm gonna stay on the cement ship.
Thank you, I don't wanna see Sokotra.
- Look at the rivets on Andy's tombstone.
(laughing)
- Oh, dear.
- We've been so mean.
- No, no.
- Look, some people need to be in logistics.
Just--
- Well, actually, James is right.
We're not actually out of time, but we should move on.
- Oh, can I tell you, can I tell you one more?
Like, sort of, Spitfire here,
he actually wrote a book partly about the Spitfire.
Douglas Bader?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- He was a really famous pilot,
partly because I think it was in,
I don't know if it was an accident.
- But he famously had no legs.
- He had no legs.
But he nonetheless--
- He almost lost his legs during mission flight.
- Yeah, flying accident, yeah, yeah, flying incidents.
And he became a Spitfire ace nonetheless.
In the Second World War, he was shot down over France,
and he ejected, so he survived,
but he lost one of his prosthetic legs
in the course of being shot down.
Well, no, he was treated with a lot of respect
by the Germans who captured him,
because there were rules about that.
And he was in a prisoner of war camp.
And Gring, who was the head of the Luftwaffe,
gave special permission for an artificial leg,
a spare leg to be parachuted into his prisoner of war camp.
- Amazing.
- Yeah.
- I think what happened was, though,
he kept trying to escape,
and so they confiscated his prosthetic in the end.
- Yes, they did, yeah, yeah, yeah.
That was before the relationship started, I guess.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And that was called Operation Leg.
- Nice.
- Where do they come up with their legs?
(all laughing)
- There's one other hero we should mention,
which is Lady Houston.
Lady Houston's sort of the reason
that the Spitfire became the Spitfire during the war.
She was a suffrager, political activist.
She also was one of the richest women in the UK,
if not the richest at one point.
And she was someone who kept helping out with war efforts.
She was always donating things.
- I think the war people didn't like her very much, right?
- That's right.
- Because she kept saying that they weren't giving
enough money to the war effort.
They weren't giving enough equipment,
all that kind of stuff.
And she would go around with placards saying,
"Give them more guns," kind of thing.
And they got really annoyed.
But she did get a lot of money together.
And I think, are you gonna say that she helped
to pay for the design of the Spitfire?
- Yeah, basically what it was,
was there was a thing called the Snyder Trophy,
which was a biannual international airspeed race.
And Britain won it twice.
And the idea was if they won the third one,
they would get to keep the trophy for good.
But at this point, the government said,
"We're not gonna fund this stuff.
"We need all the money."
And she thought that was a huge mistake.
- It was seen as a bit of a like,
"This is a crazy wonder weapon idea.
"It's not gonna, like this is a mad waste of money."
- It was in a depression.
It was, yeah.
- This was in like late 20s, early 30s.
This was before.
- Exactly.
And so she said, "Well, no, that shouldn't be the case."
So she funded it.
She funded it for it to go ahead.
And as a result, Rolls-Royce developed a new engine
that became Spitfire's engine and so on.
So it was down to her and making that happen.
She was the wizened old Texan of her day.
- Yeah, she was.
- Exactly.
- They're wonderful.
Let me tell you, if you've got some money,
lose some of it with me.
It's fine.
- We also have a Patreon just to say.
- Dammit.
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that one of the original names proposed
for what we now know as Neanderthals was Homo Stupidus.
- Brilliant.
- Yeah, so this was in the early days
when we were finding skulls of what was then thought like,
is this a bear?
Is this a sort of just like, no one knew what it's a plane.
There was a point where we were finding lots of skulls
and we didn't quite know what this thing was.
It would later turn out to be Neanderthals.
And when they got to a point where they were thinking,
"Okay, actually we do have a new different species
of Homo here, we need to give it a name."
But by the look of it and by the skeletons that have been
found, it looked like a very clumsy, bulky idiot.
And so a very famous scientist at the time, Ernest Haeckel,
suggested, why not call it Homo Stupidus,
to really dig home that this is why this moron
is no longer existing on our planet.
Now we now know that this is completely wrong,
that Neanderthals were actually very intelligent.
They did art, they could sing, perhaps.
There's lots of things that we're discovering
more and more about them.
They used penicillin even, like a whole version of penicillin.
- I mean, prehistoric version.
- Prehistoric, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Not over the counter stuff.
- Sure.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But you're a Neanderthal expert, Ella.
- So I have a number of questions.
One is...
- I feel we're doing this the wrong way around.
(all laughing)
- No, this is definitely targeted at you three.
So when you have the guest on,
are the topics always consistently the topics
that they are specialists in?
And if so, why did I get a spitfire?
(all laughing)
- I think we try, we try a bit of inside baseball.
We try to do things that our guests
are going to know a lot about.
- Yeah, on your Wikipedia page,
it says you're an expert in rivets.
(all laughing)
- Please nobody edit it.
There's already a whole bunch of untruths on that page.
- But sometimes a little fact about maybe logistics
or military strategy will just slip through that.
- I wish this was being filmed 'cause you're Facebook.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, no, the thing with...
So taxonomy is the system of naming things in biology.
And there's this rule called, it's an a priori thing.
And what it means is that if we find a fossil today
and we call it something,
that is the name it is given if it becomes a species.
So if I find a fossil today and I go,
oh, it might be homo sapien,
or it might be homo shriver.
- Okay, we already had a hop of stupidness.
(all laughing)
- Then let's say there's this, but I publish it.
So if I publish it in any journal,
then later on, if people are still like,
no, no, no, we don't think that's a separate species.
If suddenly two more of them are found
that really do look similar.
And somebody goes, no, actually,
we really do think that now needs to be a species.
They can't go, well, we want to call it homo, whatever.
No, no, the a priori rule is very clear.
It has to be called that.
So luckily, homo neanderthalensis must have got in there earlier
'cause otherwise we would be stuck with that bloody name.
- Yeah, it was proposed.
It was never seriously taken to a board.
It was a guy called Dr. William King,
who was an Irish geologist who eventually was the one
who said, let's call it neanderthal
because it was found, the particular one they were looking at,
found in 1856 at the Neander River Valley.
So it was named after the area.
- And Thal is a valley, isn't it?
I don't know that.
- Oh, I don't know that.
- It was in the Neander Valley.
It was in the Neander Valley.
- Wow. - Yeah, that's all.
- So the homo neanderthalensis is what we call it now.
But some people call it homo sapiens neanderthalensis
because it might be a subspecies of homo sapien.
If it was called homo sapien stupidas,
then that would literally be stupid wise man.
- Oh yeah.
- Because sapiens means wise and that would have been quieter.
- Yeah, I don't actually know how sapiens was picked
'cause it does feel like we've given ourselves
the nice end of the violence, you know.
- Yeah, we're great, but I'm just saying it's a bit--
- With the naming committee, of course we're gonna.
- Some people said once that the brain is the only thing
that named itself, which I think is nice.
So brain must be a really good word for it.
- Yeah, it's actually a rubbish word, isn't it?
- Yeah, I think your brain would have come up
with something better than that.
- Yeah. - Idiot.
- One of the names that the neanderthal could have had
was Gibraltar man, homo gibraltaris or whatever,
because the first, I think the first skulls
were found in Gibraltar, but they were found too early.
And they were found by I think a soldier
and he was a soldier and geologist and he said,
I think this might be something new,
but he didn't really get anywhere, you know.
- Yeah, I think there was a few
that were found technically before,
but they just didn't identify that.
I think there was one in, I think the spi one as well,
which is Belgium, I think that's also an early one,
where they just didn't--
- Oh, Flint, sorry, Flint was his name, Edmund Flint,
which is a nice sort of prehistoric sounding name,
or you know, like that.
- He sounds like he's from Flintstones.
- Yeah, he does, and he found it,
but again, he didn't get anywhere.
And actually, I think the last neanderthals
also lived in Gibraltar.
- Well, that's, I disagree with that.
- Ooh, go on.
- No, I think the team out there really believed that,
but I don't think most of the rest of us believe that.
I think we think it's a tosser.
They might have been the Iberian Peninsula, but I just, yeah.
- Was it somewhere islandy,
where things kind of cling on a bit?
- It was probably just the south,
but also we just don't know, actually.
The dates are consciously shifting.
When I say that, I mean that
when the scientists are dating them,
they're realizing that all the dates we thought we had
are kind of not as great, shall we say?
There's many question marks about these dates.
- I was reading about a neanderthal site in Croatia
called Krapina Cave.
- Yeah.
- And what I found is that they found copper lights in there.
So that suggests that the neanderthals
might have actually crept in a cave.
- Do you know what?
It would take you lot for me to realize that Krapina,
which is an integral part of my research,
(laughing)
is actually crabby.
I had never in all my years realized that before.
- That's so good.
- Thank you.
- You're very welcome.
- Don't really appreciate it.
No, I'm not gonna high five you.
- Sometimes it takes a fool to teach a wise woman.
- That's stupid.
(laughing)
- Ella, do you know whether or not
you're a bit neanderthal?
- Yeah, yeah, I got tested.
- Yeah.
- What's your, what's your number?
- I don't know.
I can't remember.
- You can't remember?
- I can't remember.
- You study neanderthals and you can even be--
Retaining it.
It was average-ish as far as I can remember.
- Is that what I want?
- 2% is average, yeah.
- 2%, and you can do that.
So the National Geographic Society,
they have a geographic project
where you do a swab in your mouth and you send it in
and then they can give you the results
and tell you whether you're not.
And then I think we've, you know,
we know Ozzy Osbourne is a bit neanderthal.
- I mean, we mostly are.
- Is it, everyone outside Africa is a couple of percent
and that because early humans left Africa,
bred with neanderthals,
those populations spread to like Europe, Asia.
But then, so is it called ghost DNA?
I love this.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Even people in Africa these days have kind of
a small fraction of a percent of neanderthal DNA.
- Well, so there's a few things going on there.
One is that, yes, it's,
so everybody outside of sub-Saharan Africa.
So like the Tennesseans have got some,
you know, the Egyptians have got some.
And what it is is neanderthals were more European,
Asian species and never went into Africa.
So it was, that's why sub-Saharan don't really have it.
The ghost DNA, so this is really cool.
So now ancient DNA is so fascinating
that they have been able to identify
that there are other species out there
called Homo God knows what,
but they just don't have a single fossil for it.
They don't know anything about this,
but they know based on looking at all of our DNA globally,
there were other species that we interbred with.
And we just don't know.
So we know that we interbred with neanderthals.
We know that we interbred with a species called Denisiva.
And then yeah, in the process of doing all this,
they've also come across a few ghost lineages.
And they're like, how do you marry it up
with the fossils that are out there?
'Cause you're like, I don't know what it looks like.
- So can we, do we not name it until we find a fossil?
- So in genetics, if it's a ghost lineage,
they tend to like give it like population Y
or population X or that kind of thing.
They don't give it a name because they really don't know.
- You've got to give it a cooler name than that, you know?
- With that, yeah, that's the whole point.
It's a standby name, isn't it?
- Oh yeah, I see.
And then they'll come up with a really cool name first.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, you're right.
- But like imagine if like, so you've got Homo naledi,
which is a new species that they discovered in South Africa.
And that might be the ghost lineage,
but that might be one of them.
But we just, we don't know.
'Cause until we've got DNA, we can't compare the two.
- A DNA from a fossil.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You need the DNA.
You need DNA from the fossils you've got
to be able to compare it to this ghost lineage.
- So it might be from Homo naledi.
- It might be naledi, it might be naledi.
We just don't know.
It's so cool.
- It's cool.
- So the guy that found naledi, Lee Berger,
is like, I reckon it is.
But we were like, maybe.
We don't know though.
- Yeah.
- Sorry, I got very excited.
- No, it is exciting.
It's incredible.
- Do you know, is his name Svante Pabo?
- Svante Pabo, yeah.
- So he's a Swedish DNA expert.
And I think, did he start the field of extracting DNA
from ancient bones?
- He got a Nobel Prize for it.
- Oh, nice.
Well, congratulations, Professor Pabo.
- And it was really funny because he won it for medicine.
And everybody went, we just had COVID.
What?
We just had COVID.
And you've given it to this guy.
He's found a DNA for slow clap.
- He published this study.
And you know, he'd realized that you could extract DNA
from old bones.
And that's a huge realization.
He worked out how to do it as well.
And he got letters, lots of letters from men saying,
"I'm Neanderthal actually."
And he said, "Fully or partly, Neanderthal."
And offering him samples to analyze for his work.
- What kind of samples?
- I think spit samples.
I think, but there's a really interesting,
there's definitely a gender divide here
because 12 women wrote into him to say,
"My husband is definitely, he's a Neanderthal."
You can study him if you like.
Only two men wrote saying the same of their wives.
And I don't know if any women wrote in saying,
"I think I'm pretty sure I'm a Neanderthal."
So there's an interesting thing
about how we think of Neanderthals today.
That's what it tells us about, really.
- Fair enough.
- That's actually so true because,
sorry, I pointed at you very aggressively then, but.
- Andy just for the listeners.
- Yes.
So I made a show called Neanderthals for the BBC and PBS.
And.
- Oh, with Andy Serkis.
- Andy Serkis who is Gollum in Lord of the Rings.
- Yeah, and a million other things.
Like the guy's got a very impressive resume.
And there was this really big discussion
because we were like, "Blatingly, you're gonna make,
"the reconstruction is gonna be a male."
But actually, why are the reconstructions of cave men
always men?
Like, it doesn't make,
like think about the descent of man image
where it's like, you know, from ape to human.
It's always just men.
And it's like, well, they definitely
didn't do that on their own, right?
So it's like, where are the women in this?
And we had a really big discussion.
And in the end, we did make a man and we called it Ned.
But we did make a Nelly.
But the Nelly was not of the same quality.
The animation wasn't, it wasn't Andy Serkis' work.
Let's just put it like that.
- Was Andy Serkis playing the motion capture Neanderthal?
- He brought the Neanderthal to life, basically.
- Did he co-host as that?
- No, no, no, he was, there's this scene where he,
actually, I love this scene.
It kind of gives me goosebumps when I see it,
where he wakes the Neanderthal up from his slumber.
So it's an Iraqi Neanderthal and he wakes it up from its slumber.
So he's used it.
He's like Andy's freaking Serkis.
- Was he both of the male and the female?
- No, no, no.
They literally, then he was forgotten about.
Not in your Nelly.
- No, no, no, no, no.
- But he was.
- I do wish he co-hosted it as the end of the film.
- Yeah, that would have been.
- What could she have been?
- Al-Shamahi.
(laughing)
- So do you guys know why Neanderthals
have got such a bad rep?
- Oh, oh, was it, oh.
- Did they find what were effectively, unfortunately,
deformed skeletons and so on?
And yeah, and so we just thought,
ah, that must be what they all looked like.
- Yeah, so basically it was an individual,
L'Achabalocin, don't query my French.
And it was a highly arthritic individual.
It was an old man, although I'm pretty sure
it was only like 40, but, you know, old for the time,
but very young for today.
(laughing)
And they basically, he was--
- I don't like the way you looked at me
when you said that, I like that.
(laughing)
- He was highly arthritic.
And there's a number of things going on here,
but the guy who did the reconstruction of this fossil
basically portrayed it as being like,
essentially knuckle-dragging,
well, kind of its heads jutting forward.
It's, you know, its knees are bent, blah, blah, blah.
And then they obviously realized later on
that that was completely incorrect,
but it was too late.
It was like it got out there that this is,
and because we were looking for a missing link
in inverted commas, right?
So it kind of fit the narrative.
And it was a new field, right?
Reconstructing what somebody looked like from a fossil
was such a new field that, you know,
and so essentially, it's everybody's speculating since
as to why he did such a bad job,
which is really embarrassing because he's a legacy
amongst other things, 'cause he's quite a renowned person,
is that he basically did an awful PR job on the underfills.
- Oh, this is amazing, like if just like, for instance,
in a million years time, they find humans
and they only find my body,
I have very bad sinuses, right?
They're just gonna think all humans had a cold all the time.
- That's it.
- Yeah, that's it.
- You know, and that's basically what happened.
- That's completely--
- They're gonna find Dan's body and think
all humans were unbelievably hairy.
- So they'll think, oh, wait, they--
- I love how you guys don't know how bodies
and decomposition work, so we're sure, yeah,
hair is gonna be found on--
- They'll find Andy and they'll be like,
well, all humans used to make model hair replacements.
- That's 'cause they'll have found me in my tomb
where I've been buried with all my air fixes.
- And all your rivet pivots, rivets, rivets.
- Oh, my riveting.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland, Andy.
- @Spitfire, Spitfire, Spitfire.
- Jesus.
(laughing)
- James.
- @JamesHarken and Ella.
- @ella_alshamahi.
- Yep, where you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing, or you can go to our website,
NoSuchThing, as a fish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there,
so do check them out.
And Ella does wanna give another shout out quickly
to Daniel Stone's book, The Food Explorer.
It is an amazing book, so do try and track that down.
But otherwise, come back next week,
'cause we'll be back with another episode,
and we'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)