(upbeat music)
Hi everyone, James here.
Now, before we start this week's show,
Merry Christmas.
I hope you've had a great Christmas.
When I edit every single week,
there's sometimes bits that are just
don't quite fit in with the rest of the show.
But maybe they're just really interesting.
Maybe they're really funny and they don't fit in.
Maybe it's just one incredible joke about hedgehogs
that was just so good.
I thought it would detract from the entire rest of the show
if I left it in and so I took it out.
I take all those bits, I snuffle them away
like a hedgehog does with nuts or whatever it is
that hedgehog's eat.
And then at the end of the year,
I put them all together for the best off show.
And this one is a real bumper special.
It's over an hour.
I really hope you enjoy it.
It's us just messing around
and we'll see you in the new year
with one of our normal shows.
But in the meantime, enjoy this one and happy new year.
(dance music)
Hello and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast.
- Can't be what I do.
(laughing)
- I don't know if I'm doing it too.
Is that okay?
- I just try to put you up.
- Oh, okay, cool.
- That's because I think you're like,
it's the volume thing.
So I'm like, oh shit, shall I just start again?
- No, no, it's just being a dick.
- Cool, all right.
- What?
- Chang and Eng, the original Siamese twins,
as in the first Siamese twins to be written about
in the West, they were really interesting.
So they had a system where they were both married
and they would spend three nights each with each wife.
And their great, great granddaughter
was the first, was the youngest ever recipient
of a Pulitzer Prize for music.
- But yeah, how weird is that?
2013, and yeah.
- Do you know her name?
- Yeah, she's called Caroline Shaw.
Do you know her?
- Never heard of it.
- Oh, okay.
She's done work with Kanye West.
- How's she?
- Do you know him?
- Never heard of him.
(laughing)
But the thing that toured Chang and Eng apart
is that Chang developed a drinking problem,
quite late in life.
- Suddenly.
- Suddenly, hang on a few developer drinking problem.
Surely your Siamese twin also developed
a drinking problem.
- They were only, they were joined at the chest.
So I think they had different livers.
- Okay.
- But it's not quite annoying
if you're constantly attached to a drunk.
(laughing)
- Yeah, to be about it.
- Oh, I've been touring for a while, yeah.
(laughing)
- There's one thing that Sonny Day is good for.
Well, actually, there's loads of stuff.
(laughing)
Okay, well, nice swim, a sunbathe,
but mostly asking someone out.
So it's good to ask someone out on a date,
and this is a French study, obviously,
and this French study found one attractive man,
and they sent him round to ask out strangers.
- How did they find one of those in France?
(laughing)
- They had to recruit one from Scotland.
Sorry, Scotland.
- We're looking forward to have a date next week.
(laughing)
- I don't mean that.
- So yeah, they recruited this attractive French man,
and made him ask out lots of strangers on the street,
and they found a huge difference.
So when it was Sonny, 22.4% gave him a positive response,
and when it was cloudy, so not rainy, just cloudy,
then 13.9% did.
- That is quite a big difference.
- But they did warn that it's not necessarily
that we feel more prone to say yes on sunny days,
it might be that your flirting skills improve in the sunshine.
- It could be also that he was very bad her die,
and when it rains, it kind of washes down his face.
And everyone's like, "No, I'm not gonna come out with you,
"you just got ink all over your face."
- It's not raining.
- Maybe when it's cloudy.
- It's cloudy.
- We don't know about this guy,
'cause maybe when it's cloudy,
he insists on wearing his Donald Duck shaped raincoat.
(laughing)
- That's his one with his white coat.
- Donald Duck actually is a very sexy character.
(laughing)
- Are you sure he's the right guy for this study?
I don't see him making a difference.
- Trance is off, he's ready to go.
(laughing)
- In France, there's been robots that have been designed
to help out with any kind of fights
that might happen between, let's say, football teams
who happen to be watching the match in the same area.
So in this case, there was a match going on
between Russia and England.
And there was a robot put in place called Alentom,
or a Lantom, and the robot's job was to basically stop the fight,
but not only that, they can see by using data
whether or not it thinks a fight is about to break out.
So it can alert the police if it thinks
that something is gonna go wrong.
Unfortunately, before it could do any of that stuff
at this match, someone beat it with a baseball bat.
(laughing)
Yeah, and they couldn't revive it.
So that was Alentom's career.
- Is that because Alentom has had a rough time?
Is that the same instant that there's a video of on YouTube,
which is where people are in Russia and in Moscow, in fact.
And there's a home video of people who are driving
in their car, nor people got a video.
And they see someone drive out in front of them
in a side car, with a side car.
So on a bike with a side car, and in the side car is a robot.
So there's some chuckling in the car that we're in,
as the viewer, 'cause they're like, "What the fuck is that robot doing?"
And then they see that robot get cut up by another car,
and then both disappear around a corner,
and then you as the viewer, so these guys in the car
with their home video, follow it around that corner.
And at that point, the bike with the side car has disappeared,
and Alentom, slash Alentom, we'll never know, he's dead now.
Spoiler, it's just standing by the side of the road,
and the guy who's caught him up gets out of his car,
pulls the baseball bat from his passenger seat,
goes up to him and knocks his head off.
- Oh, I've not seen the footage, yeah.
- So is this, like, like, yeah.
- It could be, it wasn't a football match.
- No, I should quickly say, this was in Moscow,
I said it was in France, this was in Moscow,
and it was during the 2016 matches of the World Cup.
But what happened to Alentom is they set up the first ever
robot symmetry to bury him in.
Yeah, it was seen as like, "Don't do this to robots."
- Have you seen it?
- No, I've not seen anything apparently.
(laughing)
- If this robot's symmetry, I look at these pages.
- I said, "I click on it, I don't just close my eyes
"and hope for the best."
Right, this symmetry.
(laughing)
No, this symmetry is a piece of shit.
If it's made to give robots a proper burial,
it says it was spied by the murder of Alentom.
And it's called a symmetry.
If you look it up, it's a cardboard box
full of parts of robot.
It's in the lobby area of some kind of random conference building.
And she said, the person who said it, I've said,
"It's great, the symmetry's been really popular,
"we're already getting lots of requests from people
"to bring in their own dead tech,
"like a red toy car and some batteries."
- Wow.
- It's a plastic bag.
- If you're a hedgehog who's running a circus,
don't say roll up, roll up.
(laughing)
- No one's gonna come, we're just gonna stop that.
- Really boring circus.
- Yeah.
- There was another Elizabeth Taylor,
as well as the famous one who Kingsley Amos said
was one of the best English novelists
born in this century, in the 20th century.
And she was, the problem with her obviously,
she had the same name as this extremely famous Elizabeth Taylor.
And when her book Mrs. Lippincote came out in 1945,
it was almost the same time as National Velvet came out
for Elizabeth Taylor, the actress.
And then they interviewed her towards the end of her life.
And she said, I've had a rather uneventful life, thank God.
But sometimes the more eventful world intrudes into my life,
I get fan letters to the other Elizabeth Taylor.
Men write to me and ask for a picture of me in my bikini.
My husband thinks they should send one to shake them,
(laughing)
but I have not got a bikini.
- So actually it's like insulting from your husband
saying how you could really repel these people,
is actually send that photo love.
- I've got a fact about people who are interested
in Nazi memorabilia.
- So there is one guy who, he does just seem to be an obsessive collector,
but the Guardian profiled him a few years ago.
He's called Kevin Weakroft.
And he grew up a multi-millionaire.
He's the editor of a huge fortune.
And he has the world's largest collection of Nazi memorabilia.
He sleeps in Hitler's old bed,
which he says he has changed the mattress.
(laughing)
- But he used a Lisa mattress.
- No, no, no.
- But he has the last time they asked us.
(laughing)
- He owns 88 tanks,
which is more than the Danish and Belgian armies combined.
- Wow. - Yeah.
- Jesus, so they're quaking in their boots.
The idea he might invade?
- Yeah, I mean it's more the historical pieces, obviously,
and they wouldn't be much good today
for invading anywhere.
- Okay.
It is weird, isn't it, collecting Nazi memorabilia?
You've got to ask some questions, I think.
- They did ask him a lot of questions.
(laughing)
- Well, they're doing the right thing.
- But they concluded he was just,
you know, he was a collector rather than a Nazi, you know?
- If you ask some questions and people answer them,
that's absolutely fine.
I'm just saying you've got to ask the questions.
- There are lots of things he could collect though.
Why did he choose that?
Did they ask that question?
- I can't remember what his answer was,
but I'm sure it was a good one.
(laughing)
- I'm sorry, really like the nonsense.
- And wish they were back.
(laughing)
- I was reading that, so I was looking into
just general shrimp, like eating shrimp particularly,
'cause they're eating it on the space station.
Did you know that there are shrimp recipes available
from the rapper Kulio?
(laughing)
I did not know that.
- Yeah.
He released a cookbook a few years back,
called How to Become a Kitchen Pimp.
And it's got, I mean, there's great chapters.
Appetizers for that ass, Saladied in Bitches,
Vegetarians, Question Mark, okay, whatever.
That's it.
(laughing)
And then he has a whole chapter for shrimps,
which is called It's Hard Out Here for a Shrimp,
which is, some will know, is a famous song,
It's Hard Out Here for a Pimp.
Yeah, so, and there's videos of people trying out
his recipes and he doesn't come across great
with his choices of what to do.
But yeah, but if anyone needs a Kulio Shrimp recipe,
yeah, it's there.
(laughing)
- It's what a lot of people here came for to buy that thing.
- So Hedgehogs, there's a Hedgehog Olympic Games,
which is from, I found this out of a book
called A Prickly Affair, which is by a guy
who's really into Hedgehogs.
But he was talking, I think they're in America somewhere
and he was saying one of the competitors
is a guy called Zug Standing Bear,
who was one of Gerald Ford's bodyguards.
And he's now a champion,
and he now has a champion hog called Buttercup,
which he can piece at the Olympic Games.
And he reported of another one,
who's a woman called Dawn Robelle,
who says that she communicates telepathically
with her Hedgehogs.
- This has got to be a cheat too, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- You can't do that.
- Is it in the human Olympic rules
that you can't communicate telepathically?
- No, telepathically, yes, yeah.
Because what would you say as well?
Try the traveling really far, you know?
- Yeah, faster, you're saying faster.
- You can't cheat in the Olympics.
Well, actually, we have learned over the years,
definitely not.
(laughing)
You can't cheat by whispering in someone's ear
with the Olympics.
But she does say that her Hedgehogs
call themselves star children.
- They call themselves that.
- Yeah, they refer to themselves.
- Oh, I see, telepathically, yeah, yeah.
Sorry, what are the events at the Hedgehog Olympic Games?
- I think sort of racing and chopping and jumping.
I actually don't, so I didn't read in this article,
he didn't detail what the events were.
- Okay.
- Why the Hedgehog races?
Because they run quite fast.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Surprisingly, yeah, not as fast as humans.
- No, you could beat a Hedgehog, yeah.
- That's why the inter-human and Hedgehog Olympics
have never taken up.
- But actually, what people don't know is
that Hedgehogs are allowed to take part
in the human Olympics, but they just never qualified.
- That is slow.
- Yeah, yeah.
- You never reached a qualified type.
(laughing)
- I found just a couple of animal smells.
So male silkworm moths, they can sense a single molecule
of female sex hormone from a mile away.
- I'd never understand what they mean.
- I know, I don't know.
I'll say that because presumably you need the molecule
to get into your nose before you sense it.
And so how can it be a mile away?
I've just never understood that.
It's the same with sharks and blood.
- Yeah, just don't get it.
- Yeah, I know.
That's the thing.
All the things I read about animals smelling it,
like, albatross can smell fish from the air.
- That makes a lot of sense.
Because that's the scent molecules that are the problem.
So the scent molecules are coming off the fish.
That's fine.
Then it goes through the air
and then up to the albatrosses knows.
But if you're smelling a molecule,
that's the thing that causes you to smell, if it's a mile away.
- I think it's a distance, though,
with the albatrosses, what is amazing scientists,
because the molecules break up with whatever direction,
the wind is blowing in.
- It is incredible.
But at least we understand how it's possible.
- I guess it must be that the molecule is entering
that was it a moth, did you say?
- Yeah.
- It must be that they can,
when a molecule released by a female,
a mile away gets in their nose,
they can tell the direction has come from
or it retains its potency or they can still detect it,
even though it's traveled a mile.
- Yeah.
- It must be something like that.
- You can't smell a molecule from them.
A mile away from the molecule.
- But that's the thing, it's like when you're in the sea
and you cut your finger, right?
And there's a tiny little blood goes in the sea,
then supposedly, Jaws is able to tell it's there
from like 10 miles away, right?
That's the whole point of it.
- Yeah.
- But Sholly has to wait for the blood to get to him.
- Which will take ages, right?
If it's traveling through water.
- Well, current, though, current's happened.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It's like me looking at that wall
on the other side of the room and saying,
"I can feel that from here."
And it just doesn't, in order to feel it,
it has to come to you.
- You don't necessarily have to go to it.
- Exactly.
We have to meet.
(laughing)
- I mean, Anna, that was a stunningly vivid example
of that wall on the other side of the room.
(laughing)
Where do you get these ideas from?
- I don't know.
- I'm a creative kind of guy.
(laughing)
- Did you know the ISS is battery powered?
- I didn't know that.
- Is it AA or triple A?
(laughing)
- There are actually no A's at all.
They are the size of fridges, the batteries on the ISS,
but sometimes they have to change the batteries.
- How do you do that?
- So you take these fridges out,
you rub them a few times, and then you put them back in again.
- So there are 48 batteries,
and it's for when the stations are in shadow,
'cause there are big solar cells for when it's in sunlight.
But these are nickel hydrogen batteries,
and they are slowly being swapped over
for new kinds of batteries, which are run on lithium.
So they all have to be changed.
And you get two astronauts out there
who have to take a fridge out of position,
carry it back to the right place,
and then put the new one in, which is--
- Yeah, it really is.
And they have to strap them to a pallet.
They weigh about 200 kilos, but obviously in space,
you don't feel that.
However, that is stressful.
And also, if you slightly dent the back of it,
the connection bit, it won't fit in,
and then you're absolutely stuffed,
and they're trained, obviously, and taught about it,
but a lot of them change the batteries
without having practiced it.
- Yeah, practice that kind of thing.
- Yeah.
- Gone work in MFI for a week and a half,
maybe in French is around.
I remember reading earlier this year
that there are massive batteries
all around the British countryside,
which we use whenever our electricity goes off.
Do you remember there was a massive power cut?
Two things got hit at the same time,
and loads of people went off.
Apparently, what happens then is these batteries kicking,
and they're just kind of hanging around.
There's like about 50 of them, absolutely massive batteries.
That's so cool.
- Isn't it cool?
- I didn't really read any more about them,
so I don't know how to tell you anything.
- It's the way you're painting it.
I'm now sort of imagining a real walking,
finding a giant gyro cell,
and a funny battery just standing up in a field.
- That's what I imagine it is.
Let's assume it's that.
- I was, this is not a fact.
It was just a thought I had today,
which is what happens to rain when it rains on a cloud?
- Oh.
- So you get higher clouds and lower clouds.
Does it get collected by the lower cloud,
like a sponge, or does it go through the clouds?
Like it darts through and just passes through the...
- Some of it might become the cloud,
or some of it might go down through the cloud.
- It's such a good question.
- It's a good question.
- Clouds are not like sponges, I should say.
- No, but I guess 'cause it's water,
I just didn't know if it just sort of collected
like a, like a sky puddle, basically.
- It probably depends, yeah.
- It probably depends how big the droplets are.
- Clouds are very small droplets.
By the time it's big enough to fall as a raindrop,
that's really big, isn't it?
- It's gotten quite heavy.
So actually, yeah, that's right.
So it will be too big.
If it's big enough to be falling,
it'll be too big to be staying as a cloud.
- And it also, yeah.
And it would never rain on a cloud.
Anyway, would it, would any of us snow on a cloud?
- No, it isn't.
- Basically, rain on it.
- Does it all rain start out with snow?
- Yep.
- No.
- It's always, if it's raining outside,
it's all snow, which happens to have melted on the way down.
- You're kidding.
- It's always snowing.
- Look at it that way.
- Yeah, that's very cool, didn't know that.
- Yeah.
- Just one more actual effect of climate change,
as it's happening, is that some clouds may go extinct.
- What?
- Yeah, this is how big the effect we're having.
So, Stratocumulus cloud decks,
they're the very low clouds which reflect
a lot of solar radiation back into space.
And if there are, if levels of carbon dioxide
go up much more, this might suppress
the actual formation of these clouds.
So you won't get them anymore.
- Oh no.
- We can no longer make hilarious animal shapes
in our imaginations out of clouds in the sky.
- Oh, we all still have clouds.
It's just this one particular.
It's not gonna be a sunny day after a single day.
- But what if this one particular cloud
is the only one that ever made those shapes?
- Oh, absolutely, right.
- Wow.
- It could be the animal shape cloud.
- Anna Toshinsky, really bringing home
the eco crisis that we're in at the moment.
- Yeah.
You're welcome extinction rebellion.
Say it loud and say it cloud.
That's all right.
(laughing)
- I went on to the website CNN's most secretive jobs.
And they had the usual things like spies
and restaurant reviewers.
Another one is a ward show auditor.
- Oh.
- Apparently you have to be very secretive with that.
- What's that?
- It's for results.
So you don't tell, you know, you don't screw up
and give, well, I'll land the right food.
(laughing)
Envelope.
So what you need is a bachelor's degree
in an accounting or related field
and experience in accounting or auditing.
That's all it says you need.
And I've got both those things.
- Need us to hold us.
- Yeah.
- Oh.
(laughing)
Apart from that, you're doing so well.
- Damn it.
- That's awesome.
Hey, how about a made up language?
- Yes.
- It's called dothraki.
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah.
- So all languages are made up.
(laughing)
Oh, here he goes again.
- Oh, conspiracy theorists.
(laughing)
- No, it's on point.
- That's very enough.
- Sorry, okay, a recently made up language.
- Made up language, yeah.
So obviously so many people have heard it being spoken
'cause it became the trans, you know, being big this year.
So 10 to millions of people have been hearing it.
It's more than Welsh, Irish, Gaelic, and Scotscale combined.
But I did not know the language is full of little Easter eggs.
So normally people speak it, actually speak it.
One of them is the inventor, David Peterson,
who's really, he sort of makes languages for Hollywood
as his job.
- Oh wow.
- And obviously there are not many jobs in the world,
but there are not many jobs in that industry
because it's such a rare thing to be commissioned
to make a full language.
So he has a little fun with it.
So the Dothraki word for eagle is culvert
and that is based on Stephen Colbert.
For reasons I didn't get to the bottom of, yeah.
And there was, based on his wife,
not Colbert's wife, David Peterson, the inventor.
- The word for periatracting.
(laughing)
- So David Peterson's wife is called Erin.
So in Dothraki, Erin means kind,
or Erin act means kind one.
- Cool.
- Lucky it's not fucking bitter.
(laughing)
- Yes, he's really venting through these languages.
- I think I read and I, so, I hope this is right,
but I believe as well that he's a Monty Python fan.
And so there's points when there's armies coming towards
some like a scene in Game of Thrones
where they're yelling at people coming towards them.
He takes the words that were used in Monty Python
and the Holy Grail when they're yelling,
"You are French, Cal, you're whatever,
"whatever those words I comment what they are."
But yeah, it's Monty Python dialogue
translated into Dothraki used, yeah.
- So I've got a fact about modern trains,
which is about the queen who, as we know, has the royal train.
So when she's traveling on the royal train
and when she's been traveling overnight,
there's a special instruction that gets given out.
And that is that the queen has a bath at 7.30 in the morning.
So if the train is going then, the driver is ordered
to, the driver is ordered to avoid any bumpy bits of track
so that her bath doesn't slosh around too much.
- Okay.
- Bumpy tracks, first of all, do we have bumpy tracks?
Or are they all full?
- You get bumpy bits, don't you?
- Yeah, it's trap corners.
- And certainly, you don't get corners.
- Well, like you do, not corner like round bits.
- But secondly, how do you avoid the bumpy bits?
You can't swerve in a train.
- You can get lifted off onto a boat.
- Then you gauge, then it comes back down there.
- Yeah, I think the queen's freedom of movement
is just severely limited as to where she can go.
- She can only go to the flat bits.
- She can only get to the flat bits.
- The queen's going all directions.
- It's a good point, yeah.
- That's weird knowing when the queen has a bath.
I think you'd be freaked out as the train driver.
Every morning at 7.30 you'd think,
"Oh, she's passing now."
- Don't make any mistakes.
- She's naked, and he adds for me.
It's a weird thought.
- It's a big train.
- I don't think it's only 10 metres long.
- She's like in the cab, in the tub.
(laughing)
- He puts the bath next to the driver's seat.
- More coal.
(laughing)
- It's much bigger than the vehicle van.
- One more thing about Luroll,
which is more just a rant than in fact,
coloured Luroll,
disappeared off the face of the earth, right?
- Uh-huh.
- So, I think you can still buy it, can you?
- You can still buy it.
In 2004, it was 30% of Luroll that was sold.
- Wow.
- Now it's under 10%.
And this, I was reading an article in the telegraph
about why this has happened,
about how angry people are about it,
'cause people used to buy their Luroll
to match their decor, right?
And now, they did, that was a thing.
There was someone who wrote into the telegraph saying,
"Why is it impossible now to buy blue lavatory rolls?
"Unless we find some soon,
"I'll be forced to redecorate my bathroom."
(laughing)
- There was another one,
corresponded in bletchingly,
who described a priest friend
who used to change the hue of his Lurolls
to match the liturgical seasons.
(laughing)
- Green for Trinity, purple for Lent and Advent,
and pink for Saint Stays.
- Well, there's a lot of Saint Stays, isn't there?
- Yeah, he was doing a lot of Luroll changing.
- That is amazing.
I suppose the other thing is,
like you don't really get colored sinks
and stuff like that, do you?
Like in the '70s and stuff,
you get avocado, sink, stuff.
If that was the first time I knew the word avocado,
'cause I didn't have avocados when I was growing up,
you didn't really get them in the '70s and '80s.
- Yeah.
- But we used the word to describe the color
of people's toilets.
- Yes.
- So when people started eating them.
- I was so confused.
(laughing)
- You break your teeth.
- I have one more drink
that William of Orange drank.
So I'm talking to William of Orange,
who was married to Mary.
So he was a King of England, there's a few other ones,
but this is that one.
He drank Benedictine Posit,
which was a mixture of warm milk,
eggs, cream, and ale,
with nutmeg and custard on top.
(laughing)
And he drank this on his wedding day,
'cause it was what?
Everyone who was rich and posh used to drink
on their wedding day.
And the priest would come along, he would bless them,
and then they would give them this benediction Posit,
and people wouldn't leave until they drank it.
Charles II waited until the bride and bridegroom
had finished off their bowl of Posit
and then drew the bed curtains himself
on the day of their wedding.
- Oh really?
- So I read that he stayed in the room,
shouting encouragement during the,
there are lots of stories saying he was shouting
during the consummation,
but we've asked the team before that consummation
doesn't mean they're actually having sex.
I mean, the bride was only 15 at the time,
but yeah, that's the story.
- So Charles, we think Charles might have been there,
'cause if he'd drawn the curtain,
he could still have stayed on the outside shouting encouragement,
couldn't he? - Yeah.
- That's true.
- You know when you were younger and just...
- That's not what the story could have been.
- Here we go.
- You know when you're 15,
I read a kid going good. (laughing)
- Someone draws the curtain,
but they still give you instructions.
You know when you go to the Lou when you are kidding,
you're just learning to go to the Lou on your own,
and your mum stands on the other side of the door
and she's like, you know, have you wiped your bottom?
Maybe, so it was sort of like that,
you pulled the curtain, but you're still outside saying,
you know, put it there. - Put it there.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, that's the nostril. (laughing)
- Splendid difference. (laughing)
- There's another old Scottish one, which is,
if you're fishing and you catch a boot,
that can go either way for you.
If it's a left boot, that's bad luck.
You're in serious trouble.
Fish are not gonna come to you.
If you get a right boot, you're in much luck,
and you have to nail it to your mass to say,
"Look at my right boot, come fish."
And that's, in both instances, you're in a cartoon.
(laughing)
- And in neither instance have you caught a fish,
which presumably is the aim.
(laughing)
- Yes, but your boot business back home is going,
you've caught a soul.
(cheering)
- Yeah.
- I was quickly just on "Rudeness."
I was reading Danny Wallace's book about "Rudeness,"
which is called "Fuck you very much."
The surprising truth about why people are so rude.
And he did some of his own research,
and he asked what people had done,
'cause like I was saying, if people are rude to you,
you automatically are rude back to them.
It's the weird kind of contagion thing.
He was asking people what they had done
when someone had been rude to them.
And answers included, "I rubbed fries on the windshield.
I turned all their possessions upside down.
I let a dog lick a sausage.
I was serving them, (laughing)
and I slept with their partner."
(laughing)
That's rude.
- And was that all the same person?
- Just kind of a very bad day.
(laughing)
- I was looking at flaws, some flaws.
So the world's flattest flaw is owned by NASA.
It's in Huntsville, Alabama,
and it's made of this kind of resin.
And it's a bit like, do you know these hockey tables?
- Yeah.
- So there's a cushion of air on it,
and whatever what they do is they kind of get like a sofa on it,
or anything, they'll can do it with anything,
but the funnest one is a sofa.
And they have little air coming out of the sofa,
and then they push it along this extremely flat floor,
and it just kind of glides along.
- Ooh.
- It's really, really awesome.
And the way that, and what it's for is to see
what it's like in space.
So, (laughing)
because it's like, there's no friction,
so things just keep moving.
And if you push them in one direction,
they just keep moving.
And I think we might have said before
that NASA around there also has the world's biggest door,
and they also have the world's most perfect balls,
which is a pair of mathematically perfect spherical balls.
If they are one point, they're really, really small.
They're just 3.81 centimeters across.
And if you scale them up to the size of the earth,
then the highest hill on there will be 1.5 meters high.
- Wow.
- That's how perfect these balls are.
And is that because they're such perfect spheres in space,
they're imitating the sun?
- Or just, they're using them for possible, future,
joy or scopic motors.
- They don't know what they're for, do they?
(laughing)
- Someone thought of the phrase
the most perfect balls in the world,
and they thought, better make those.
(laughing)
- You know the saying, beer before wine, you'll feel fine.
- Oh, I thought it was.
- Wine before beer feeling queer.
- I always get mixed up.
- Well, it turns out that neither of them works.
And this is thanks to scientists who got 90 students drunk
and found that none of them felt fine.
(laughing)
- No matter what, he was struck off.
- No matter what, he, combination.
He got 90 volunteers, and they have.
- I bet he did.
(laughing)
- They're only 70 people in his class.
- They all had two and a half points,
there was a first group,
we had two and a half points of logger
and then four big glasses of white wine.
And then the second group had the same drinks in reverse.
So you've got beer, then wine, and wine, then beer.
And then there was another group who had only beer or wine
up to the same level.
And they all felt terrible the next day.
One and tell of them through up.
And they--
- A bunch of lightweights.
(laughing)
- I knew you guys would say that.
- Can I just say, while we're on trains,
this is so outproposing, nothing.
But when I was in Japan, I noticed that the train drivers,
they always point and shout stuff at themselves
while they're driving the train, wherever they go.
So if you're near the front, you'll always see this
'cause you can see the driver.
And just every like three or four minutes,
they'll just point at something
that doesn't appear to be anything at all.
And they'll just yell something that I don't understand, right?
- Another yelling to the passengers or to--
- No, they're yelling to themselves.
And I read this today of what they were doing
'cause I looked it up.
They have a thing where every certain amount of time
they point at like just a thing around the tracks.
Doesn't matter what it is.
And they shout where they are and what they're doing.
And the reason they do it is so they can concentrate
the whole way because if you're not doing that all the time,
you're just kind of my daydream or something like that.
But if every five minutes or so,
you have to point and shout something.
You're never gonna kind of not think about that.
- That's wonderful.
- Isn't that great? - That's great, yeah.
- I think it's stupid.
Does anyone have a read the story of Cry Wolf?
What happens when there's actually, you know,
a huge bomb in the middle of the track?
And they're pointing and shouting,
there's a bomb, everyone get off the train,
everyone get off the train.
And everyone's like, oh, it's just the standard
five-minute-ly shouting fest, he does.
Maybe he's shouting something, maybe he doesn't always shout
bomb on the track.
(laughing)
Maybe he's normally shouting, I am concentrating now.
But what I was thinking is, if you're driving
on the motorway, then every time you go past a junction,
if you were to point at it and shout the names of the places
that junction goes to, then it would help you concentrate
and you get less sleep at the wheel, I think,
is a really good tip.
- Okay, okay.
- Also, your geography of the UK would probably improve.
He's keep noticing all these irrelevant places.
- Yeah, that's true.
- Have you guys had a hook swinging?
- No. - No.
- This is another Indian ritual practiced in the 1890s,
not very much in the 20th century,
but basically, in order to make it rain, if there's a drought,
farmers would find a willing volunteer
and then they would sew large hooks into his back
and they would lift him 50 feet into the air.
- Sorry. - What?
- You would be lifted up into the air on massive hooks.
It's very, very, very painful.
- To make it rain. - To make it rain.
And it causes you lasting damage, obviously.
It's extremely painful.
However, you were allowed to keep the hooks afterwards.
- By us.
- But only for three months.
- What?
- You were allowed-- - Why would you keep them?
- Well, you were allowed to keep the hooks
and the cord and the knife for three months afterwards
and beg with them and show people, look,
I went through this for the community
to show your bravery, but only for three months.
- So when you said you had to find a willing volunteer,
that actually does feel like the hardest part of it.
- Where were they?
Where were they finding these enthusiastic people?
- It's a good point.
Also, I would probably just trust that that was the guy
who was held 50 feet in the air with hooks,
even if he didn't have the amount of his back.
I imagine he's a local celebrity.
I imagine no one's like, oh, did that happen?
Oh, okay, and I didn't read about that.
- Actually, a lot of people thought that chess wasn't,
well, a lot of people who thought that chess wasn't
a particularly intellectual game,
compared to something like West, for instance.
And that was because the argument was
that chess has a finite number of moves.
There's only a certain number of moves you can make.
It's quite a high number, but it's finite.
And in West, you're playing with your wits
and stuff like that.
And it was kind of like, if you're doing something
which is really regimented,
maybe that doesn't help the creative part of your brain.
That's what they used to say.
Like, for instance, there was an argument
in Scientific American in 1859
that Napoleon the Great loved playing chess,
but he was often beaten by a rough grocer in St. Helena.
- What went rough in what way?
- They didn't specify.
(laughing)
- It wasn't an asterisk.
- It didn't shave much.
- Right, okay.
- I don't really know what rough meant in those days.
It says, now the Shakespeare Milton Newton
or any of the great ones of Earth,
acquired proficiency in chess playing,
it seems to help people with an intuitive faculty
for making the right moves.
But at the same time,
these people have often possess very ordinary faculties
for other purposes.
So they thought it was only a very specific kind of person
who'd be good at chess and...
- They wouldn't necessarily be good at other stuff.
- Whereas Whist players.
- Oh, yeah.
- All of those people you mentioned were keen Whist times.
(laughing)
- I mean, if that's what they thought of chess,
imagine their response to angry birds.
(laughing)
- Well, you do know pop culture.
- No, pop culture.
I've read about it.
- There was another old rule that used to be in place,
which is that you could use a baseball bat
which had a flat side to it like a cricket bat.
- Oh, yeah.
- It was just to help with accuracy, I think.
But yeah, that was kicked out.
So that was between 1885 and 1893.
- I think that was for power, wasn't it?
- Wasn't it?
- Like you can get a bigger hit on it
if you've got that big flat surface area
and they ditched it straight away, I can't remember why.
- Yeah, I can't.
- Maybe it just made the game too easy.
- I think it was that.
- 'Cause in cricket, for instance,
full toss is a very easy ball to hit.
- Yeah.
- Why then in cricket do they have the other side of the bat
in a triangle formation?
- Well, good question.
And I don't know the answer, but I would guess
that it's so that your sweet spot
is a thicker part of the bat.
So you want your edge to be very small
because you don't want to edge the ball
so they can catch it, but you do need it to be thick
so that if it hits it right in the middle,
it goes miles.
So you want it to be thick in the middle
and thin on the outside.
I don't know, for sure.
- I think it's because if you flip around the bat
the last minute, then you get a mental angle
on your bat, and that's exactly what they used to use,
but they've never used it, so that's right.
- I don't know why they don't use it anymore.
- Just this is just a brand in fact,
nothing to do what we're saying,
but just hedges.
We were doing a live gig the other day
and someone told us in the audience
that if you go to Liverpool,
there's a hedge of all the Beatles there
sitting outside the station,
but Ringo is really hated there.
So people keep trimming his head off,
and they have to weigh ages for Ringo's head to regrow
and that's someone immediately choss up again.
- So sad.
- On mud, so there's the disorder
where you eat soil or dirt, it's called peaker, I think,
where some people eat mud,
but in southern parts of the US,
eating mud is a traditional thing
that some people really enjoy,
and I didn't know this still happened,
but it does, so it's in southern states
like kind of Mississippi and Georgia,
real deep south-state,
and people eat kind of clay,
and it's a very specific thing called like white mud
or white clay in its clay-rich dirt,
and they love it,
and it's part of the diet,
it's often poorer families,
it's black and white families,
and there are various theories about where it came from,
but I was reading an article in the New York Times
from 1984 saying this is so tragic,
the tradition of mud eating will disappear
in the next generation,
and then an article from a couple of years ago,
it hasn't disappeared, guys.
It's still there.
- It's because it's like higher minerals and stuff.
- We don't really know.
I think it's, maybe it's just a traditional thing,
but they like the taste.
- Are there recipes?
- There are some recipes.
Well, sort of recipes,
if you count the fact that, for instance,
people who like it will keep it in jars
and sprinkle it with salt and vinegar.
- That's a recipe.
- Okay, yeah.
- Well, I thought you said they like the taste of it,
why are they putting salt and vinegar on it?
- James, I like the taste of chips,
but that doesn't mean I don't enhance it.
- You're so right.
(all laughing)
Sometimes they substitute it for baking soda or for starch,
because they can't get to the right kind of soil,
the right kind of mud,
but apparently it's not quite the same.
And there was an interview with someone called Mrs. Glass,
who said she's been off the dirt for a full year,
even though she still gets really strong cravings,
but she's been off the dirt
'cause her husband said it makes her mouth taste like mud.
(all laughing)
Which does make sense.
- It is one of those pregnancy cravings
that you hear about.
- It is, yeah, yeah.
My mum had that.
- Could she?
- Yeah, mud and coal, I think, yeah.
- She didn't eat coal.
People, women do.
- But she just had the craving.
- But it was usually would be charcoal.
Like husband, you'd get bits of charcoal
and you could chew on it.
- Ah, but not a large lump of coal.
- No, you wouldn't go down to mine.
(all laughing)
- No, my daughter got home from work every day
and she was a black face full of the coal basket.
- That would be so good.
- Hopefully, if you're having cravings for, you know,
gurgons, you don't eat a billion, the gurgons.
You just need a small amount to get your cravings started.
- Yeah, it's true.
It's just this funny idea of like replacing miners
with pregnant women who, they know where the coal is
'cause they have the desperate cravings
and they're just chewing through the rock face.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, and none comes back up.
(all laughing)
- Just on big shoes.
- Yeah.
- On shoes.
Used to be a big thing and they're called crack-offs.
So crack-offs were shoes that were really popular
from about the 13th century to the 15th, 16th centuries
and they're called that after the assume place
of origin crack-off in Poland.
And they were also called Poulin,
which is Polish shoes, Polishings.
And they, so it was just fashionable
to have these incredibly long shoes
and they were gone for sort of eight, nine inches.
And then eventually there were various edicts passed
that said you had to limit your toe length to two inches.
It was still quite long.
And it was partly because it was seen as showy,
like we've talked about the summary laws before
and partly because it was quite difficult to pray, apparently,
'cause it's quite hard to kneel down
when you've got a 10-inch toe poking out.
- But you can always see if somebody's in a toilet stall.
- It's nice.
- Yeah.
- You can usually tell that just from the engaged side,
but it's poking your head under that little gap
between the guys.
- Sorry.
- Also, you know, you might be using to wipe as well
if you do.
(all laughing)
- Oh, you've got to be flexible for that, too.
- Long enough.
(all laughing)
You know, they're using bacteria to solve crimes now.
- That's a cup show I want to see.
(all laughing)
- No, they are using it to solve crimes
because we all have this fingerprint,
which is our huge cloud of bacteria
that we're walking around with and they're all individual.
And so, police have started thinking maybe we can take
the bacteria that's left in a room that's been burgled
and then match it to a database of other people's bacteria.
And if there's a match, they did the robbery.
But it's quite cool, 'cause it's a very good plan.
And they've experimented with it by staging
a load of mock burglaries, which just sounded like
the funnest science experiment to be part of.
So there were 400 study participants,
some home owners, and some who had to pretend
to burgle their homes.
And they had to properly act it out.
So they did stuff like they rifled through all their drawers
and they carried away their TV.
They all had to open the fridge
and kind of have a sip of the Coke and the fridge,
'cause that's something that burglar's doing apparently,
sometimes.
- A sip of the Coke and the fridge.
- Yeah, burglar's always do that, you know?
- It's a signature move.
- The one thing the burglar's do do a lot
is poo in houses, don't they?
Sorry to bring it back to poo.
- I think they might have asked them to do that as well.
Maybe it didn't make it into the study right up, but.
- Apparently that does happen because you're so stressed,
your body just wants to defecate.
- If someone's left a poo in a house,
you probably don't need to swab for the microbiology.
(laughing)
- But so do all of them.
- We're looking for a corn cob who can make a dick robbery.
(laughing)
- I've done what you've done.
You can ask your question anyway, though.
- Well, it's just going out so,
if the four of us are in this room,
we all have our bacteria, what did you call it,
the cloud, the biome, will all be so different,
so noticeably different?
- Well, the thing is, the more you hang out with people,
the more your biome is similar to theirs,
'cause you end up sharing bacteria.
- Yeah, and the same thing.
- There is a thing, yeah, we're basically
all the same microbiome, no, probably.
Well, I'm not really the same.
- But they are still really individual.
- Yeah, yeah, okay.
- So people develop really differently,
and develop it in the first three or four years
of your life, I think, specifically the stuff
that you're at the bacteria you're going to want.
- But the other thing is, you can get a hotel room,
and I think it's within something like two or three hours,
that room will be indistinguishable
from your actual house, from the microbes in there.
- Oh, okay, yeah.
- And also, 'cause I always take all my furniture
to the hotel rooms.
(laughing)
- I always do a poo with a corn.
- Just make it feel like home, isn't it?
- Oh, good.
- That's crazy, though, using that for crime.
- That is crazy.
- That would be really weird if you could see,
if you spent all your time, for example,
with a dancing partner, like on Strictly,
if your microbiome came closer to your dancing partners
than it was to your real life partner at home.
- I'd like to see that headline in the daily express.
(laughing)
- Sean Walsh is microbiome.
(upbeat music)
- We're gonna have to move on to our next fact in a second.
I got one last thing that I like, which is in 1956,
there was an English composer who was quite well known
at the time, called Malcolm Arnold,
and he actually wrote a overture for vacuums.
So, when you saw it, it was vacuums on stage,
it was three vacuums, it was one floor polisher,
four rifles, bizarrely, and then an actual orchestra,
and it was a piece that he put on called a grand-grand,
and it was dedicated to U.S. president Herbert Hoover.
So that was quite a nice thing.
- Very good.
(audience applauding)
- Just on the losers, is you were just saying
Anna in the campaign.
- Okay, Dan, you know, let's do this backstage, all right?
(laughing)
- Just some other rain-making ceremonies.
- Oh, yeah.
- Because they've always existed in hot countries,
I guess, 'cause people need rain,
and they are quite a big thing in various parts of Africa.
So in South Africa, the Lovedu people have a rain queen,
and the rain queen is basically their ruler.
They always have had traditionally.
- Long may she rain?
- Long may she rain, indeed.
And she, that sort of implies that she's urinating
on her people as a replacement for rain,
which she doesn't do.
- That's spile by little pod, sorry.
You've got disgusting images.
So this is this woman who isn't allowed to marry herself,
but she can have female wives, inverted commons.
And so she also has to bear at least one child,
at least one daughter, because you inherit it from your mother.
So she has to bear one daughter by a royal relative,
interesting rule, and then age 60, when she hits 60,
it's assumed that her powers of making the rain come,
or sometimes stopping the rain.
Her powers are perceived to have waned,
and she's expected to commit suicide by poison.
- Oh.
- And so she has to do this.
And those is really controversial scandal in 1959,
when the raining rain queen refused to bloody commit suicide.
She was 80, and people kept going,
'Come on, you've lost your power, and I'll do the thing.'
So your daughter can take over, and she understandably was like,
'I don't want to.'
And so this sort of ruined the tradition for a while,
but it's being brought back.
So the next rain queen, when she comes of age,
when she turns 18 in a couple of years,
is coming back into the form.
- Have they fixed the succession procedure?
- I think they might have tinkered with it a little bit
about the edges.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, it's more optional these days.
- Rain dance is quite big in North America as well.
Historically, they're probably the ones we know of most,
or we hear of most.
The hoppy snake in Antelope's ceremony is quite a common one.
And people wrote about this a whole lot,
because it was performed in August,
it was to ensure abundant rainfall,
but it used live snakes.
And they did loads of different ceremonies,
all the time for loads of different things,
but this was the only one that used live snakes.
And so this was the one that became really famous,
and that's why the North American rain dance
became one of the more famous kind of ceremonies
that they all had, and it's because it had snakes in it,
and these snakes are exciting.
- Yeah, that's very cool.
- Do we know what they did?
- And you would dance around in a circle.
Me saying that makes it sad,
like I'm just doing a throw away comment of what you did.
It was very important, but yeah, basically,
it was danced around in a circle with live snakes.
- Was the snake in the middle of the circle?
Or were you holding a snake?
- I think you were handling the snake.
If I could tell, no, you were handling the snake, yeah.
- Otherwise, the snake might leave the circle,
get a bit bored.
Probably doesn't believe in this city.
It might have been ahead of us scientifically.
(laughing)
- There was a Cypriot rain ritual in ancient times,
where you had to do a rain dance,
and then after the dance, you had to spit
on the back of a turtle.
- Okay.
- And the book I was reading, it said that henceforth,
it became popular as a spit turtle.
(laughing)
- That's such a rubbish joke.
- That's awful.
That's like at school, if someone spits on you once,
you get known as spits having the answer.
(laughing)
- Was it allowed to keep the saliva on it,
so I was three months away from there?
(laughing)
- It's a museum in Kansas.
It's a very small museum, but it pays homage
to all the losers of presidential campaigns.
So it's got a picture of them, a bit of a biography.
And it's run by this lady who, when I was reading the article,
she was very excited about the last election
that you guys had, because she really wanted Hillary Clinton
to lose, and I don't know if it's because she didn't
want her as president.
It was more that she was excited to have the first woman
ever in her museum of losers.
(laughing)
I should really be proud of that.
Finally, your woman will be in the losing museum.
(laughing)
We have to find the silver linings where we can.
- Do you know how you can weigh a whale?
- No, oh well, I don't always take it.
(laughing)
- Well, no.
So it used to be that to weigh a whale,
you would have to get one that's been beached
or one that's dead, something like that,
but it's really hard to weigh them in the wild,
but they've got this new system of drones.
- Wow.
- Which you're able to estimate the weight of whales
from the sky.
- Cool.
- So they no longer have to shove a set of weighing scales
underneath the beach whale.
- Well, mostly it's just that joke doesn't work anymore.
(laughing)
- Another joke ruined by the scientists of the world.
- You busted.
- I actually also have a French,
this is very tangential though,
but it is a French and fast food fact,
which is about in 2016, there was a McDonald's in France,
which was subject to an armed robbery,
and two guys burst in with guns.
They were armed, it was obviously very terrifying
for all the customers and they wanted all the money
in the till, which is about 1500 quay, I think.
But unfortunately for the two robbers,
also dining in the restaurant were 11 off duty members
of the French SAS.
(laughing)
- SAS.
- Well, the French paramilitary special forces,
and they're really, really good.
And they kept the cool, they didn't do anything
during the holdup, and then when one of the robbers
was leaving, he tripped a bit,
and immediately they bounced on him,
and then they shot the other one in the abdomen.
- But still.
- Oh, it's what?
- Well, they took him to hospital.
I don't think he died.
I mean, he was, but then sent to prison for armed robbery.
- Okay.
- So it's a funny story with one quite bad sounding injury
at part of it.
(laughing)
- Why did they wait for him to trip?
- Well, if they didn't trip,
they didn't immediately want to start firing their guns
in the restaurant, because they thought,
well, they're customers here, and we want to, you know.
- Yes, customers here enjoying their meals,
enjoying to blank out the armed robbery.
(laughing)
I imagine that Ronald McDonald is stood there
with his massive clown shoes,
and he kind of trips that night.
(laughing)
- I don't know what would have happened
if the guy hadn't tripped.
I'm sure they would have thought of some other way
of resolving the situation.
- I know, yeah, yeah.
I'm sure that's not the strategy
of all of the French ass, I ask.
Do not make a move till one of them trips.
- Do you guys know that chess pieces, the pawns,
they used to have jobs?
- Each of them?
- Well, did they work out?
- So in the middle ages, monks tried to represent them
as citizens, that was the idea.
And so you had an agricultural worker, you had a farrier,
you had a weaver, the fourth was a businessman,
it was a doctor, an inkeeper, a policeman,
and the last one was a gambler.
- Wow.
- A policeman.
- Yeah, but policeman.
- So that's no longer used.
- That would have made blindfold chess a lot harder,
wouldn't it?
If you had to remember all every individual pawns.
- Farrier to E4.
- Yeah.
- Also, you would think they would have
pawnbroker and pawnstar.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- I was sure it had been invented in the middle ages.
- What, pawnbrokery?
- pawnbrokery had been, I think.
- Well, the queen didn't use to be a piece, either.
So the queen wasn't a piece for about a 600 AD,
and then she was really rubbish for ages,
'cause, you know, queens were quite, sort of,
was quite inferior, you know, a male should be the leader.
And this only changed in the 15th century
when the queen came along, who was actually decent,
and people started to say, "Hey, queens can be powerful."
And this was queen Isabella of Castile,
so it was Isabella and Ferdinand.
And basically, their relationship mirrors
the one of the king and the queen on the board, where she-
- You could only walk one step in any direction,
and she was legging at everyone.
(laughing)
- He was always running and hiding behind the book
of the baker and the candlestick maker or whatever.
- Was it, but no, behind the Castile.
(gasping)
- Castile, yeah. - Castile, yeah.
- No, she, so when they got married,
she forced them into this really humiliating marriage,
where she got much more authority than him.
She used to ride out to command troops on her own,
leaving him behind.
She was made queen of a particular country or state,
and she didn't even bother to tell him about it.
But yeah, then they changed the queen and made it more powerful.
And one argument to say this is why that happened,
is that in Russia, the queen remained impotent
until the 18th century, when Catherine the Great came in,
and then she got a lot of power there.
- Oh.
- Just, this is not to go out really,
but I just found out that I found a paper called,
Reservoir Dogs and the Implications for Disease Control,
'cause obviously Reservoir is the animal
that the disease lives in.
- Oh. - And this is from the early '80s,
which is before Reservoir Dogs came out.
And no one knows where the name Reservoir Dogs came out.
- You're kidding.
- Yeah, so my theory is that Tarantino was reading
a very obscure medical paper about rabies in Zimbabwe,
and that's where he got the name from.
- Nobody knows where the film's name comes from.
- No, when he was selling it, he claimed that it was a gangster term
for a rat, but actually that's not true.
And some people think he might have misheard
the name of the title of the movie,
'Aruvoire Les Enfonds', which is a French movie.
- Yeah, it is.
It's not very similar to Reservoir Dogs, is it?
- Oh.
- Yeah.
And also it doesn't sound very much like Reservoir Dogs.
- Nope.
- I believe you're theory.
(laughing)
- I'd just one thing about someone who dealt with syphilis,
and this is in the early 18th century,
it was a guy called Daniel Turner,
and he was the first person ever to use the term syphilis
to refer to the illness.
So it came from actually an epic poem
written about a hundred years earlier
about a guy who got it in short.
And so he--
- He was called, the guy in the poem was called syphilis.
He was a shepherd.
- Yes, exactly.
He was a poem about a shepherd called syphilis.
And so then this doctor said,
"Okay, well, let's call this syphilis."
- He was just like a boy named Sue, but worse.
(laughing)
- Sue's poor sister.
And so he also wrote about the use of another new word
that he'd coined, the condom.
So it's about UM, but I think they're the same thing.
And he said that's the most effective thing
to prevent its transmission.
This was 1770.
- Wow.
- But I was reading the report he wrote on it.
And he said the condom is the best,
if not the only, preservative that we have from syphilis.
But by reason of its blunting sensation,
I have heard people say they've chosen to risk the clap
rather than engage, "Kum has to sick cli-piatus."
Which--
- Well, the one person got that.
(laughing)
- And we're so sorry that you've got that.
- I actually really wanna know if you did get that.
- Did anyone get the Latin for that?
- No.
- Well, I really enjoy the idea of putting really rude stuff
in Latin to make it more appropriate.
But it means with spears, thus sheathed.
- Would you have a sheath for a spear?
- To have a sheath for a sword?
- Sure.
- That's a really good point.
- That's a long sheath.
Or it's a tiny sheath just for the head of the spear.
(laughing)
But both of them feel impractical in the battle situation.
I mean, just get my sheath out of there, there, there, there.
- He added the thought of it through.
You're completely right.
I was feeling so smug about the Latin translation.
Because I heard about James Harrison.
James Harrison, he's an 81 year old, sorry,
this is four years ago now, but he, at the time,
he retired from being a donor, a blood donor,
81 years old, and he'd been donating blood
for every week, virtually every week,
for 60 years of his life.
And he was known as the man with the golden arm.
And in Australia, he had a very rare type of blood,
which they reckoned there was only sort of like 50 people
or so that had it.
And it was very important because mothers who were pregnant,
they would have recess positive blood.
But if the baby had recess negative blood,
which would be inherited from the father,
that would go against the baby
and it would start killing the baby inside the womb.
So they used his blood specifically to save all these babies.
And the Australian Red Cross believed that over the years,
he saved the lives of 2.4 million Australian babies
from the 60 years of giving blood 17% of women
are at risk of this in Australia.
And every single batch of anti-D, as it's called,
is from this guy.
- Wow. - Yeah.
So he's an absolute hero and he's just retired.
- Kind of mean to retire, to be honest.
(laughing)
- Come on, mate.
- Yeah, stick on it.
- No, I've done a good long time saving children
and now I'm gonna stop.
(laughing)
- Wow, how easy that, right?
- I was reading a tiny bit about dog research.
'Cause dogs have been researched on it
in historic medicine for so long,
'cause they were just a useful thing
that was always around, quite tame.
And so you know Pavlov of dog fame.
- Yeah.
- He had some breakthrough dog research,
although his most of his breakthroughs weren't
what we now think of him as doing.
So obviously we think of the Pavlovian dog responses,
a behavioral thing.
But really, he was interested in dog digestion.
I think it's that kind of thing
that he got his Nobel Prize for in 1904
and not the experiment that people know.
But one of the things that he did was he looked at,
it was really interesting in dogs livers
and how dogs when dogs generated saliva.
And he did this thing where he created fistulas
in the esophagus of dogs.
And so a little hole with a tube attached,
which meant that when dogs ate,
it would just come straight out again if it's neck
and not go into it stomach to find out what would happen
if they weren't getting the, you know,
if they weren't filling up their stomach as they ate.
And so he had all these dogs with food just,
how frustrating would that be?
Yeah.
Eat your food and it's full straight out of you.
Just going, yeah.
That's like a torture in,
but you'd be given by the gods in the afterlife.
It is, isn't it?
Yeah.
Forever hungry.
He also used to sell quite a lot of dogs' saliva, I think.
What for?
He made quite a lot of money out of it.
Yeah, he had a dog gastric juice factory.
[LAUGHTER]
That's just a dog.
That does make him sound very evil.
I think he wasn't a nice guy anyway.
A lot of people say, but this one, particularly,
he just had these dogs working to produce loads of saliva,
but he bottled up and said, oh, that's--
What was the purpose of selling it?
The idea was that it helped out with things like dyspeptia
and stamenolins.
Sorry, you would drink it.
Yeah, yeah, you'd find dogs.
Oh, the number really.
Before you were saying that you would kiss a dog,
I know you're like, no, I said, the number really.
Oh, yeah, I'm sorry, it's a word I'm not for the number.
[LAUGHTER]
I just have a couple of things about saliva, right?
Humans, obviously, when the plague was around,
so the 1,400s and the 1,500s, that was a massive thing
where kissing almost became taboo because they thought
that that's what was spreading it, so they stopped.
But what I didn't realize was the alternatives to not kissing
to make sure you still had great sort of sexual contact
with your partner in the face.
And alternatively, we're licking, sniffing,
and nibbling of eyebrows.
Sorry, wait a minute.
So you couldn't kiss because you didn't want to get any bacteria
going over, but you could just lick someone's face.
I think you'd lick their forehead or their ear
or go for just general away from the mouth legs.
But nibbling of eyebrows was a safe alternative, supposedly,
at the time.
Wow.
So would you lick someone on the cheek if you didn't really
know them and lick them up the middle of the face
if they were your partner?
I don't think you're in France.
You'd have to lick them on both cheeks.
That's so true.
Can I just tell you about a new story from 2012, which
was quite good.
So this was about a leak in a statue of Jesus.
And it was in a Catholic church in Mumbai.
And the toe of Jesus started leaking.
And so a miracle was immediately declared.
It was obviously holy water, because this toe was crying.
And so lots of people came and visited--
That's way more emo.
Lots of people came and visited this sobbing toe.
And the church promoted it as a site of pilgrimage.
And it was quite good for tourism
in this relatively backwater of Mumbai.
And then this guy called Sanal Edamiruku,
who is a rationalist, a buzzkill someday,
went to investigate.
And he found that it was moisture from an overflowing drain
that was being fed by a pipe issued from a nearby toilet.
And he was investigative of a blasphemy
by various police stations, then has fled to Finland
where he's been in exile for the last seven years.
Yeah.
So when Jesus cries, don't say it's a toilet leaking.
Come on, right.
It's weird, though, isn't it?
If you have water coming from your--
if I had water coming from one of my toes,
I would say it was probably sweat.
Yes, not like holy water or tears, or anything like that.
I mean, I've embellished with the tears.
It was holy water.
It was holy toe water, yeah.
Holy water.
Holy water, very good.
Can I just do one more quick thing about leaks?
So here's a family thing, which isn't really--
it's not a legal thing.
But I read it the other day, and I think it's kind of cool.
In medieval Scandinavia, they would have civil wars,
and families would often put brothers
on opposite sides of the battles, so to hedge their bets,
so that one of them would survive the war.
Wow.
That's cool, isn't it?
It's quite clever.
It's dark.
It's dark, but it makes sense.
It does.
So you want to continue your genetic line,
and say, exactly, you want to make sure that someone--
oh, someone to look after you in old age,
or to look after the farmer, whatever,
so you would put one brother on each side.
But the thing is, with war, it's not like the winning side
in a war every single person survived,
and the losing side everyone died.
You could very easily put them on either side
and they're both killed, and then you
look like an idiot and a twat.
What would happen?
But what would often happen afterwards
is the losing group would be punished.
Yeah, OK.
But if you put two on the same side,
it gives that side a tiny extra advantage.
It does, but then if the neighbors have got three kids,
and they put them on the other side--
Oh, yeah.
It's always a problem, isn't it?
The answer is not to have a war.
Or any kids?
Yeah.
So there are enclave countries as well, aren't there,
which are countries wholly inside other countries.
Oh, yeah.
So Lesotho in South Africa--
literally, inside Africa, actually, is one of them.
And one of them is San Marino.
It's a tiny country inside Italy.
So Italy has two smaller entities
within it, the Vatican and San Marino.
And this is kind of off the beaten track a bit.
But in 1999, San Marino was really worried about its male
citizens being ensnared by sexy foreign women.
And it banned them.
Banned all women.
It legally legislated.
It banned any female domestic servants younger than 50.
So--
When was this used to you say?
1999.
Come on.
I'm serious.
Do you like joking?
No, no.
Because there was this sort of panic in San Marino
about foreign women coming as carers and domestic servants
and marrying the elderly men they were looking after.
And maybe not with their best interest at heart.
Maybe there was some financial motive or something.
So it literally just banned any female domestic servants
under the age of 50.
Assuming that if once you get to the age of 50,
you're probably fine.
1999.
I know.
I don't know if there's ever been repealed as well, actually.
Well, anyone might have found out if there's anyone
under the age of 50 who vans is a trip to San Marino.
And then prison.
Yeah.
I found someone who was the arch enemy of gravity.
So he was a man called Roger Babson.
And he was an American businessman.
He was a Newton fanatic.
He made a lot of his money using Newton's principles
in business for every action.
There's an equal and opposite reaction.
And he had a satellite.
He lost a couple of close relatives to drowning.
And he, instead of blaming the water conditions,
he decided gravity was the culprit.
Because it pulled them down.
So he described old man gravity as our enemy number one.
He wrote this essay.
He said broken hips and other broken bones,
as well as numerous circulatory intestinal
and other internal troubles, are directly due to the people's
inability to counteract gravity at a critical moment.
And he founded a gravity research foundation
to basically destroy gravity, if he could.
And how is that going?
It's ongoing.
It's-- they now have slightly pivoted away from that.
And they just sort of research it.
I did read about that guy.
He's pretty amazing.
He believed that there was a metal alloy
which had anti-gravity properties.
And if they would be able to find it,
they'd be able to-- he said they'd
be able to co-terror planes in it
to make impossible for them to crash.
But he didn't say how they'd be able to land.
But he actually-- this institute that he put a load of money
and it was both him and Captain Bird's Eye.
He put the money in-- I don't know if you have that in America,
actually, Captain Bird's Eye.
But he's like a frozen food guy.
But he was real.
And he made a load of money from--
Wait a second.
But that feels to me like the bigger headline.
It's the Captain Bird's Eye.
Well, not here.
But just so you guys know, anyone who's now listening
to this podcast back in England has just gone,
what the fuck?
Do you guys not have Captain Bird's Eye?
Guys, you don't know what you're missing.
He's great, fun. He sells you fish fingers.
And he sort of powers around on boats with children.
They got Captain Crunch.
Captain Crunch is different.
So you can see, there's no qualification for this.
There is probably a secret club where Captain Crunch and Captain
Bird's Eye hang out together.
Yeah, bitching about gravity.
So he was an anti-gravity?
Yeah, he was.
And when he first put the money into this,
him and Captain Bird's Eye, they
paid for three people to sit in the US Payton's office,
just looking for any patents that were anti-gravity inventions.
And then as soon as one came in, they would go and find
that person and go, have you found it?
Have you found it?
And they never did.
Oh, there's a grant that his company
give to lots of universities.
And one of the rules of receiving the grant
is that they have to get this monument where he has words
about his personal.
But it's quite coded.
But it sort of says, I don't think gravity is a thing.
Or conquer it.
So they have that sort of planted at these universities.
But a few of the universities from what I've read,
the students like to push it over.
I tried to find a site called--
I tried to find if there was a YouTuber,
like with an A at the end of their website for Tuber People.
Oh, yeah.
There isn't, sadly.
Well, there's a niche.
There's a niche.
And then I tried to find you Tuber, like for potatoes.
Oh, yeah.
Is that--
No, well, there might be.
But to be honest, it's so hard to search
a YouTuber with an E.R. with potatoes in mind.
And I--
You have to put minus quite a lot of things.
You have to put minus, PewDiePie, minus.
Exactly.
Zawella and all of this.
I did find a guy who made a self-driving potato two years ago.
Did you hear about this?
There's hardly no.
Yeah, of course I saw that.
I'll YouTuber.
I've been looking at the chess records.
Sorry, not chess records, the record company.
The Wikipedia-- you know, chess was a record label.
Was it?
Yeah, we did.
Hang on.
No.
It was a music record label.
I think it was a record label called chess.
That was an extremely esoteric joke, I think.
Yeah.
It was-- you meant to unconfuse us.
And you've actually confused us a lot more.
What I mean to say was, I've been looking at the Wikipedia
page for the records in competitive chess.
It was a musical called chess.
Yes.
I think there was a record label called--
Of sure there was.
It didn't make sense.
There were so many record labels, aren't there?
Anyway.
These chess records.
I was eating an apple, and I don't mean the record label.
[LAUGHTER]
There's a company called Love Honey
that makes sex ties and stuff like that.
And they recently revealed the weirdest search terms
they've ever had.
That included pepperami loop.
A few others.
Pies for women to get horny pickled onion condoms.
Wow.
No?
No.
Probably not this time.
[LAUGHTER]
Pope Gregory issued a special decree saying
that Satan was half cat.
Wow.
So not all popes have been fans of cats.
Yeah.
Wow.
Because there was Pope Paul II, and he
was a 15th century Pope, who had his cat treated
by his own personal doctor.
And then Pope Paul VI had his cat dressed up in mini cardinals
robes, apparently, although I've never seen a drawing.
I don't know if we have evidence of these tiny cat cardinal
robes.
But it's called the Vatican, not the Catechon.
Yeah.
Oh, now come on.
That was good.
I was reading about, so Spartacus,
the movie Spartacus, starring Kurt Douglas.
So Kurt Douglas has Michael Douglas as a son.
But then he also has Eric Douglas.
And Eric Douglas is a lesser known--
he hadn't really heard of him, right?
So he was in the industry as well.
And there's a very famous story of him
going to London to do stand-up comedy.
And he did it in a London club.
And he started telling jokes.
And he was getting nothing from anyone.
And he got really angry on stage for the fact
that he was getting nothing.
So he suddenly turned on the crowd.
And he was furious with them.
And he was saying to them, do you know who I am?
I'm Kurt Douglas's son.
And someone in the audience stood up and went, no, I'm
Kurt Douglas's son.
That's fantastic.
I was looking at very, very loud things.
We mentioned Cracator a while ago.
We said it was the loudest noise ever.
I looked into it a bit more how loud it is.
So that was the volcano that went off in the--
Yes, in 1816, I think.
Was that Tambora?
Oh, it was 1883.
Yeah, yeah, 1883 happened.
But the Cracator was the equivalent of hearing a noise
in New York that happened in Ireland.
And it would take four hours to get to you.
So there was a ship 40 miles away from Cracator
when it went off.
40 miles away, the ship was blasted so much
that half the crew's eardrums were shattered.
And the captain had no idea what was going on.
He wrote in his diary, "I am convinced the day of judgment has
come, just because this noise was so loud."
Imagine, I mean, the wire with all to write, update your journal.
What the day of judgment?
[LAUGHTER]
You've got, like, 10 minutes left to live.
Max, what are you going to do?
Well, I better report this.
[LAUGHTER]
It used to be a thing where the vacuum cleaner
was only in one place in your home.
And you would attach huge tubes to it.
So the vacuum cleaner had its own spot in the house.
I mean, it stays in one place in my home, certainly.
So you didn't move it around.
You didn't move it around.
You just have a great long tube to the bit
you needed to suck that or cleaned.
But then, the Hubert Cecil Booth, who
was a huge figure in the vacuum cleaner invention process,
he created a giant vacuum cleaner for cinemas, which
was hidden basically inside the walls of the cinema.
So it's in the building.
And there are pipes going through the walls
to all sorts of different, like, power points, vacuum
sockets in the cinema.
And when you want to clean, you find the vacuum
point in the floor, and you open that up,
and it's just constantly sucking away at that point.
And you just attach the hose to that and get hovering.
So were there ever accidents where it was opened at the wrong
moment, and a whole audience got stuck into it?
Thousands.
That's why they stopped it, too many deaths.
Yeah.
Can see that.
You know, hedgehogs can get balloon syndrome.
Why have you said that, like, it's something where you all know?
Oh, well, I've seen one with it.
It's amazing.
I've heard of it.
It's just as many as referring to balloon syndrome
as, like, they get flew.
You know, they can get balloon syndrome.
I think we all know that.
So, sorry, balloon syndrome is a condition
that hedgehogs can get there.
And basically, it's because they have lots of space
under their skin.
And this is to allow them to roll up.
It helps them roll up.
But if air gets trapped under their skin
and it keeps getting in, they can just blow up and up and up
and up.
And then they can be the size of a beach ball.
And then the best thing to do is genuinely
to pop a needle into it and drain the air.
You're kidding.
Can you take one of their own needles?
I don't know.
Probably, yeah.
God, that's the ultimate irony, isn't it?
It's like being a balloon made of needles.
Yeah.
Oh, so sad, but if they learn to cooperate,
then they'd be able to puncture each other's balloon syndrome.
So, that's the lesson we've learned, right?
If they join forces, they plug a needle out of each other.
Yeah.
That's a good point.
You know, they've got drawstrings around them.
What hedgehogs?
No, they don't.
They have to get money passes.
Oh, sorry, I'm thinking of money passes again.
No, they have this muscle called an orbicularis.
And it's a ridge of muscle, which goes all the way around.
It's like a skirt, basically.
And it's what allows them to roll up.
So, they just tighten the orbicularis
and the drawstring just closes.
And they can still look out for hours.
But, but when they run, they hitch up their skirt, basically.
And they have these weird long legs.
So, if you look up footage of a hedgehog running,
it's got much longer legs than you're used to.
They still have lifted up their skirt or rubbed it.
No way.
It's bizarre.
Guys, heard of the game campaign for North Africa?
Yes.
That's incredible.
I don't know if we--
I don't think we've spoken about it before.
Campaign for North Africa, the desert war, 1940 to 1943,
it takes, roughly, they've worked out 50 days
without breaks to complete the game.
And you need 10 players.
It comes with 1,600 cardboard tokens.
Yeah, wow.
And it's so detailed.
It's the map that you play on.
It stretches out 10 feet.
Yeah, that's how big it is.
Big table, basically.
Yeah.
So, it's mostly sums the game, the campaign for North Africa.
It's made by a guy called Richard Berg, who, you know,
just wanted to develop the most complicated and realistic
game.
But if it's 10 feet long and it's the campaign for North Africa,
is that not just old desert?
Yeah.
It's not a great game.
So, what are you saying?
I just think you can make it smaller.
Yeah.
Oh, you mean cut out the desert?
Yeah, cut out the desert.
What if you cut out the desert?
You haven't got a game, have you?
But so, for example, there is a thing in the game
which you have to do.
You just get a sheet of paper and it's mostly sums.
So, every game turn, 3% of your fuel evaporates.
Unless you're the British before a certain date,
because they use rather inefficient means of storing
their fuel, they use drums instead of Jerry cans.
So, if you're British before a certain date,
7% evaporates every turn.
Amazing.
If you're Italian, you have to distribute an extra water
ration to your troops so that they can boil their pasta.
Otherwise, otherwise, there is a greater risk
that they all become disorganized and desert.
Like, it's incredible.
They worked out that if you played this game as a hobby,
so the game, which is the desert war in 1940 and in 1943,
if it was done as a hobby, you could make it last
longer than the war itself for playing it.
And it was more traumatic.
Shall we finish?
Sure.
You know how you were saying about how you would give
Lam's blood to someone to make them more Lam-like?
Yes, yeah.
Another thing they kind of thought was a good idea was,
if you had fallen out with your husband or wife,
your discard might be settled by giving each other your blood.
So, I might swap blood with my wife,
and then it would kind of bring her to my point of view
all the other way around.
Wow.
And would you maybe sneakily inject the other person
with your wife?
I think you'll find out right now, I'll make sure.
Wow, I do believe you're right, that's weird.
No, it would be like, if you've had problems in your marriage
for a long period of time, then it might kind of solve things.
What are you saying?
It's a last resort.
It's a last resort before getting divorced.
This is one thing you'd try.
And did you have to swap?
When you say swap, do you mean I can just give you
a little cup of blood and you can give me one?
Or do you have to put it properly in?
It was a proper transfusion.
Well, I did the blood brothers thing with my best friend
when I was younger, which is basically
had many transfusions, isn't it?
It is.
It is a very, very small transfusion.
What's quite small, yeah?
And the idea behind this of the blood
giving you whatever it came from, that
began with Samuel Peep's, who at the raw society was telling
about a guy who only lived on women's milk as in breast milk.
And apparently, he used to be angry and fretful.
But by taking this women's milk, he became a good-natured patient
and found himself so well.
And they thought he'd somehow got the characteristics
of a woman.
Like a drinking breast milk.
But if that was the case, then every baby would--
Right.
You're right.
Well, you don't see many babies with moustaches, do you?
It's a very good point.
Like all men have.
Just one more thing.
There was a guy who called Petra de Tabano in the 13th century.
And he said that he who drinks menstrual blood,
or that of a leper, will be seen to be distracted
and lunatic, evil-minded and forgetful.
And his cure is to drink of Daisy's powder
and mix with water of honey and to bathe in tepid water
and to copulate with girls.
[LAUGHTER]
Sound like you was building up to an excuse.
It was a weirdest day off ever.
But menstrual blood was thought to be quite a negative thing.
Quite a lot, wasn't it?
Although, Pliny, I thought a lot of fun stuff,
but thought that one of the things you could do
was collect the menstrual blood of someone.
And I don't know how you go about doing that.
And then you sprinkle it over your crops
because it kills all the bugs, because everything around.
But not the crops.
Doesn't kill the crops, crops love it.
Bugs hate it.
Wow.
And also, in Papua New Guinea, there's--
so in an island called Wogeo, which
is a tiny island off Papua New Guinea,
then menstrual blood is thought to be cleansing.
And it's thought to be kind of a good thing to menstruate.
And men want to do it.
I mean, this is really disgusting, sorry guys.
But they will sever their willies in order
to mimic the menstruation of women.
I heard they just sort of cut them
a bit without severing with crab claws.
Oh, they don't come off.
Sorry, they--
I'm sorry, it's just the word sever.
You're right.
It's just the word sever.
When someone says his head's been severed,
you don't think, oh, we all need a plaster for that.
Sorry, you are right.
They didn't chop them all the way off.
Because you can only do that once, really.
You need a very willing and patient crab, too, don't you?
Yeah.
Do you think what you think was attached?
Well, yeah, I imagine so.
Yeah, OK.
It's cool if you cut off the crab's claw
to cut your own penis.
I know, but you can at least control the claw at that point, I think.
Maybe the crab wants to emulate menstruation, as well.
So it's actually quite grateful.
Probably not.
OK.
OK, we'll get something out of that.
So you're right.
He did kind of move his face a lot, didn't he,
correct?
That was one of his main things that he did when acting.
There was a guy in 1756 who said that his realistic style
went too far.
His overfundness for extravagant attitudes
frequently affected starts convulsive twitchings,
jerks of the body, sprawling of the fingers,
and slapping of the breast, were no good.
And he was a really good friends with Hogarth, the artist.
And so he was probably the most painted man in England
at the time, because Hogarth used to paint him all the time.
But Hogarth used to complain because he
moved his face so much all the time.
They couldn't paint him properly.
Oh, really?
There's one portrait of him, which is in the British Museum,
I think, it's called a mechanical portrait.
And it's a picture of him being painted by Hogarth.
But in the space where his face is,
there's one of those spinning wheels behind the picture.
And you can have 30 different facial expressions
as you wheel around.
He is very interesting.
He ran Drury Lane, which was one of the theaters that he had
for 30 years.
And no plays that were new plays at the time have survived.
It's a very odd thing, because there are a lot of plays
in that time.
And he was someone who he was doing a lot of the scheduling.
And despite his absolute love for Shakespeare,
he also had to do things that he absolutely
detested pantomime.
He absolutely detested.
He hated clowns.
But--
Oh, no, he didn't, yeah.
He didn't?
Nice.
Oh, no, he didn't.
[LAUGHTER]
Oh, my goodness.
Get everybody-- he's behind you.
[LAUGHTER]
This is what we have to deal with.
[APPLAUSE]
God, that's just the proper insight
into how bad I feel about facts all the time, I just say.
Oh, he didn't-- random guy?
OK, you're right.
Must have checked my facts, you're definitely right.
Yeah, so he made the start of an evening
be the thing that would be the clown.
And he-- so like the pantomime clown stuff would be--
That's what we do, too, Dan.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah.
Slav Doug, OK.
So what I was saying is, I will get to the--
You will.
So what's probably a wrong fact?
But so before a play started an evening,
they would have an appetizer, which
would be a hard-lequin style clown, a gremaldi,
who would come on and do a bit.
He absolutely hated that.
He, at one time, he was at a puppet show,
and he had to leave because he thought the applause
for Mr. Punch was so repulsive.
He was like, I've got to get out of here.
But he had to keep it in because people loved it,
particularly King George III loved it.
He'd never laughed so hard apparently
than when he was seeing a clown swallow a whole carrot on stage.
And that was the reason for keeping it.
Everyone in this audience is thinking,
God, I wish that was what was on tonight.
Are you apparently swallowed a lot of carrots?
It wasn't just the one as well.
Amazing.
But--
[LAUGHTER]
That's it.
We've all been there.
[LAUGHTER]
We--
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
Before you find your prints, you
have to swallow a lot of carrots.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
What are you uploading?
[LAUGHTER]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)