[MUSIC]
>> Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast this week coming to you live from Edinburgh.
[APPLAUSE] My name is Dan Shriver, I'm sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered round the microphones with our four
favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
>> Okay, my fact this week is that when Dick Loss,
the president of the Montana Cowboy Association,
drove a car for the first time, he crashed it into a fence.
Because instead of using the brake pedal,
he pulled back on the steering wheel and yelled, whoa!
>> [LAUGH]
>> Incredible.
>> Lot to unpack.
>> So who was Dick Loss?
>> He was the president of the Montana Cowboy Association.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Cool.
>> A cowboy.
>> Who's a cowboy?
And I found this because he's just been inducted into the Cowboy Hall of Fame in
Montana.
>> Cool.
>> He was a male carrier.
>> Do you keep tabs on the Cowboy Hall of Fame in Montana?
Every new person who's inducted, you know about it.
>> I do. >> He's got one of his phone,
he's got one of those notifications.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Do you want some other people who are in the Cowboy Hall of Fame in Montana?
>> Yeah, yes, so.
>> Bob Fudge.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Oh no, the Fudge Gang are in town.
>> It's just a funny cowboy name.
>> Bob Fudge, Fanny Steel.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Fanny Steel, yeah.
>> Johnny Flowers, Carl Moss, Spud Creamer.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Spud Creamer, Chief Sitting Bull, and
the 1904 Fort Shore Indian School Girls Basketball Team.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Wow.
>> Did you say Spud Creamer?
>> Spud Creamer.
>> [LAUGH]
>> These are incredible.
>> It's a great name, he was incredibly dull, I have to say.
>> Really?
>> I read all of the,
because they have the biographies of all these people, and
that's how I read this about Dick Loss.
Basically, I found this Hall of Fame, and they had all the names.
I don't know what drew me to Dick Loss, first of all, but I read his biography,
and it had this amazing thing.
But he was a male carrier, he was a cowboy.
He lived in a place called Square Butte, and it's pronounced Square Butte.
And every time we say the word But, it's spelled B-U-T-E.
We get loads of people writing in from Montana or Wyoming saying,
it's pronounced Butte, and I'm like, well, don't spell it like Butte then.
>> Yeah, yeah, good point.
I was looking up the meaning of whoa, whoa.
So there's some, I wouldn't go so far as to call it controversy.
But a little bit of debate, I was reading horsejournals.com.
Which is a great site, if you're into horses.
And Jack Ballew, who is, she's a horse trainer of many years experience.
She wrote a piece about the meaning of whoa.
And her contention is that by and large, it means nothing.
It means nothing at all.
It's something for humans to say while they try and sort out the horse situation.
Horse doesn't care.
>> But it does have a meaning, doesn't it?
>> It has a meaning, yeah, yeah.
>> If you're running towards me and I say, whoa, you know what I mean.
>> Yeah, but I'm not a horse and neither are you.
>> So it's, she says, the word whoa is used with zero purpose.
This is in general, other than to fill silent air and
give our busy human minds something to work over and repeat incessantly.
>> No. >> What is this person talking about?
We all know that whoa means slow down or stop.
This is person illiterate.
>> She's a very experienced professional horse trainer.
She said on some occasions it can really work if you say it just right.
>> Well, then it fucking works.
What is that?
>> It's like, but in general, I can't believe I'm having to, in general,
it means nothing. >> Ghost don't exist,
except that one time when there was a genuine ghost.
>> Jeez, most of the time when horse people say, whoa,
they're just saying something to say, right?
>> Let's not talk about this now.
We'll take this backstage.
>> Okay, anyway, anyway, that's a distraction.
>> I did a bit of looking into cowboys and some of the cowboys that I love most
are movie cowboys, the sort of John Wayne and the Clint Eastwoods and so on.
And some of the cowboys were genuine cowboys that then
became movie stars.
So they just found their way into Hollywood in the early days.
So there's a guy called Louis Burton Lindley Jr.
And he was a cowboy who got conscripted into the war.
And the only reason he really got into the world of Hollywood was when he
enlisted into the war, they said, what is your occupation?
He said, rodeo.
And the person went, radio, okay, and then they put him down and
he did radio throughout the war.
And he was like, this is pretty good. >> Well, after he'd done rodeo,
rodeo is a very easy to sit on.
>> So after the war, he was like, I really enjoyed that radio stuff.
And then he went into movies like Blazing Saddles and stuff like that.
>> Wow.
>> And then there was another guy who was, he wasn't a real cowboy in real life.
But James Arnes, and he was a famous actor in a TV show called Gunsmoke.
And Gunsmoke was really big.
During the war, his thing was, he was a really tall guy.
And so as a result, as the tallest man in the outfit of his platoon,
he was always sent down the ramp of a boat first to see how deep the water was.
>> [LAUGH]
>> He was the measuring stick, the human measuring stick.
>> Yeah, you mentioned John Wayne.
Middle name Marion, if you didn't know, anyone out there.
>> Didn't know.
>> And didn't like it, didn't like the fact his middle name was Marion,
because he liked to get a bit of a macho image.
And he said he actually got bullied loads for it at school.
His full name was John Marion Robert Morrison, I think.
Sorry, his real first name was Marion, even worse.
>> Yeah, this is a Johnny Cash song, basically.
This is a boy named Sue.
>> This is the boy named Marion, yeah.
>> Is that where Johnny Cash got it from?
Or is it?
>> No. >> Okay.
>> But he changed his name, and he's actually credited in some films as Duke.
And he's often called Duke as a nickname.
And that was after his family dog.
And it was because he had this giant dog, this Airdale, who used to walk him to
school every day when he was a boy, and they'd stop at the local fire station.
And the fireman called him Little Duke, and his dog Big Duke.
And so he had the name stuck.
>> That's very cool.
>> Yeah.
>> Can I give you some more, Montanon cow people?
>> Yeah, definitely.
>> Hilda Redwing is recently in the Hall of Fame in Montana.
She took part in a rodeo at the age of 90.
And during the rodeo, one of her friends who was running it,
his horse ran into her and broke her leg.
And she carried on doing the rodeo with a broken leg at the age of 90.
>> What?
>> Isn't that amazing?
>> Was she riding a bull or anything?
>> No, it was like a relatively calm horse.
>> Okay, okay.
>> Still amazing.
>> And I mentioned the 1904 Fort Shore Indian School Girls basketball team.
>> Yeah.
>> And they went to the St. Louis World's Fair, and they spent five months there
as part of the anthropological exhibit that they did at that same time,
where they brought lots of Native Americans in to do stuff.
And during that, they started playing basketball against all comers.
And they beat anyone who came.
And so they were named champions of the world.
>> Wow.
>> That's great.
>> It's like a world.
>> And why does that get you into the Cowboy Hall of Fame?
>> I think really they were short of people.
>> Yeah.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Tough year.
>> They didn't, you know, they weren't in a shoot up, they didn't win a duel.
>> Have you guys heard, in Alaska, there are cowboys who ride helicopters instead of horses?
>> Yeah, that's cool.
>> When you say ride.
>> Well, they don't.
Obviously, yeah.
>> They're not spinning around on the-
>> It's like- >> Definitely looking at some tick loss there, aren't you?
>> [LAUGH]
>> No, they round their cows up with helicopters.
But I didn't even know there were Alaskan cowboys.
>> No. >> And Hawaiian cowboys as well.
Which is a very famous thing in America.
>> Yeah, they're bloody everywhere, aren't they?
>> Yeah. >> And in fact, American US cowboys really
nicked all of their gear, all of their cliches, all of their hats, their coats,
their everything from Mexico.
So they're based on Mexican vaqueros.
And in fact, the word buckaroo, I didn't know, comes from vaquero.
>> Wow, really?
>> Yeah. >> And we get so many words all come from
those Mexican cowboys.
So lasso, bronco, chaps, as in you're wearing chaps, not high chaps.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Yeah, and gouchos as well, the Argentinian version,
which I always think of the coolest.
The thing I like about gouchos, so Argentinian and Uruguayan cowboys,
is that they, again, they're just really cool cattle herders.
It seems like if you're in the Americas and you're herding cattle,
you become really cool.
And they were really fussy about the color of their horses.
And if you're a proper goucho, all of your horses have to be perfectly color
matched.
And so you get pibled horses, like white with black splodges.
But you want the black splodges as perfectly matched as possible to each other.
>> Really?
>> Yeah, it's cool.
Apparently it was so that if your herds got mixed up,
you could tell which ones were yours.
>> Wazers.
>> Yeah. >> That's very cool.
>> I think like a quarter of the cowboys,
what we would call them now were not whites, right?
>> Yeah. >> In the time of the cowboy,
basically, in the post-Civil War time.
And actually the word cowboy would be mostly used for
African-American cowhands.
Like the white people would be called cowhands, and
it was kind of a bit of a slur to say boy, do you know what I mean?
>> It was kind of diminutive. >> Yeah, exactly, yeah.
>> Wow, interesting.
>> I didn't realize how short the Wild West was after the Civil War,
before about 1900.
That was it.
>> Yeah. >> It was a really brief period.
>> Right. >> Here's a mind blowing thing.
Cowboys basically invented dust in America.
The reason that America is dusty is because of cowboys.
>> Really? >> Yeah.
So there's been this guy, Jason Neff, he's a geochemist.
I hadn't heard of that.
He studied the sediments laid down in various mountains in Colorado.
And he looked at the sediments that had been laid down in the lakes and
things like that.
And he found there was basically no dust in America for 5000 years.
And the soil had this, it was vegetation, it had this crust,
this nice thick crust on it, right?
>> Yeah. >> No dust blowing around.
1860, the rates suddenly shoot up of dust in the atmosphere.
And it's because the cows had arrived, they stripped the grass.
And then their feet, their big clumping hooves broke through this gorgeous crust.
And as a result.
>> It must have been nice, when you first go through that crust.
Like breaking into a crème brûlée.
>> That's the least cowboy thing you've ever said.
>> [LAUGH]
>> That bloody hell.
>> But we have dust, I get dust in my house, right?
>> That's nothing to do with the cowboys, you're right.
That's pre-existing dust, that's, yeah, yeah.
I just mean that the reason America is-
>> So basically apart from that one example, this is true.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Just on names, Dick Loss, a friend of mine who's actually in
the crowd tonight, Shona, sent this ridiculous fact.
I can't believe that it's true.
>> Any fact that comes from a friend of yours.
No, I meant Shona.
But there's some skepticism in the room.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So Wild Bill Hickok, right?
So the name Wild Bill, this really kick-ass name, scared people.
He was just like this beautiful, amazing cowboy.
Supposedly, the reason he got it is not because he was this incredible cowboy who
could do dangerous things, is because his face, his nose and
mouth look slightly like a duck.
And- >> No.
>> And Wild Bill is the bill of a duck.
But, and so he was sort of bullied, this is Shona's fact.
He was sort of bullied by his buddies, and then he changed it to be like,
no, I'm really cool and wild.
>> His brother was called Tame Bill Hickok, wasn't he?
>> Yes.
>> So did he have a face that looked like a normal duck's beak?
>> [LAUGH]
>> I will bet a decent number of doubloons that that is not true.
>> Okay, using a pirate currency, apparently, now?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Pirate's Cowboys.
Sorry, what's it called, cowboy currency?
>> Like gold nuggets.
There you go, that's what I'll bet, I'm sorry.
>> You'd wager your parrot on it, wouldn't you, Anna?
>> [LAUGH]
>> I'm gonna have to move us on in a sec, guys, we gotta move on.
>> The Cowboys all went on strike in 1883, which I think is a very funny-
>> [LAUGH]
>> Okay, there was a cowboy strike in 1883.
>> Well, they had very good unions, the Cowboys.
>> Right.
>> And, guys- >> [LAUGH]
>> Peter, how to let Jeremy carbon in?
>> Yeah.
>> If you're equating the striking bin men with these Cowboys,
that's very fluttering to them, but we're all about the Cowboys here, and
their unions- >> And pirates, don't forget the pirates.
>> And pirates, also very strong unions.
They were called the Turtles, they were the original Turtles, Cowboy unions.
>> The original Turtles.
>> Yeah.
>> [LAUGH]
>> What were they called, Turtles, do we know?
>> They were called Turtles, it was the Rodeo's Union, and so it was in response
to bad-paying stuff, and they were called Turtles, because the idea is they're,
I don't know why they're proud of this, but they're slow to organise,
but once they do, they're unafraid to stick their neck out.
>> [LAUGH]
>> It's good.
>> I don't know if that's what you want.
>> Kind of good.
>> Yeah. >> I thought that when Turtles were afraid,
they didn't stick their neck out.
>> I think that might be true as well.
I don't know how much they knew about naturalism, the Cowboys.
[MUSIC]
>> It is time for fact number two, and that is Anna.
>> My fact this week is that until the 19th century, if someone shouted,
stop thief, you had no choice but to try and stop the thief.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Cool.
>> You were legally obliged on pain of being arrested and
facing a penalty to chase the thief.
>> But with the crowd who were trying to stop the thief,
if you didn't join in, does some of the crowd then start chasing you?
>> Yeah, good point.
Stop non-thief stopper.
>> Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
>> Well, there was a time in, this was in 1760,
there was a Jewish second hand clothes dealer, and he followed this,
what was known as hue and cry.
And he was faster than everyone else, so he got at the front of the group, and
then they thought that he was the one who was- >> No.
>> And so they grabbed him and arrested him.
>> My God.
>> That's like a scene out of life of Brian.
>> Yes, but that's a really good point.
What was the policing of that situation?
Because you've suddenly got potentially one criminal and then 30 criminals.
>> Yes, so I do think the crime of not stopping the thief wasn't as large as
the crime of being the thief.
So your priority is still to chase the thief, but I think after you'd given chase
and you'd caught the thief, you can mention to the constable, by the way,
the old Angela who lives next door didn't even give chase, so.
>> Well, one reason was if you didn't chase them and they got away,
you became liable for the robberies, so you might have to pay money for
the person who got the robberies.
>> Wait, if I just don't chase, because I'm halfway through doing something,
I'm liable for the stuff- >> Like a Sudoku or something.
>> Yeah, I'll have to do my Sudoku, and then I don't join the hue and cry.
I'm then on the hook for the theft.
>> You wouldn't go to prison for the theft, but you might have to pay some
recompense to the person- >> Well, I refuse to pay, that's outrageous.
>> Well, then you are going to prison.
>> Yeah, prison.
>> Then I'll maybe have a bit of peace and
bloody quiet to do my Sudoku.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Everyone's won.
>> Wow. >> You're going shopping must have been so
stressful back in the day.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Yeah, well, this is what if it makes you guys feel better,
Dan and Andy, because I can see you're having trouble with this.
There were also penalties for raising a false hue and cry for exactly this reason,
because it was acknowledged that people would be busy working in the farms or
doing Sudoku, and so it could interrupt the village economy.
Every time you shouted, stop thief.
So you did get in trouble for doing it falsely.
As some people did, I think there was one person who raised a hue and
cry on his dog, I believe.
I think this is in the 15th century, and it was found his dog was chasing some sheep.
And so he did the stop thief, or the stop done my dog's chasing sheep hue and cry.
>> Right. >> And he was fine for that.
>> You know the descendants of Sigmund Freud,
Lucian Freud, Clement Freud, a big broadcaster and an artist.
When they were younger, they were going through a park, and
they decided to challenge each other who could run faster to the destination they
were getting to, and they both convinced that they were gonna be the person that
could do it.
So they started running, and as they were going, Clement took over,
was going much faster, and so Lucian went, stop thief, he's taken my money.
And he was grabbed by Pastor Byes, who stopped him.
And Clement was so pissed off with him that the two of them barely spoke for
the rest of their life.
That was the incident.
>> I knew they hated each other.
>> Lucian didn't even go to his funeral.
>> No way.
>> They hated each other.
>> Because of that, what?
>> That was the biggie.
That's what everyone says, well, it all comes back down to the stop thief moment.
When he did that, he said- >> You should have made his tombstone,
boy, you've stopped now, haven't you?
>> Nice.
>> That would be good.
>> You didn't always have to shout stop thief, there are a few other things you
might shout.
In Scotland, sometimes you would shout, oh, yay.
In Wales, you might shout, hubbub, and in Gloucestershire,
you might shout, utestes.
>> Isn't it like, you parabolics, you've nick my purse.
>> It's U-T-E-S-T-E-S, utestes.
>> Right, utestes.
>> Okay.
>> Sounds like a Greek philosopher, doesn't it?
Utestes.
>> Yes.
>> He's just bouncing out a lot of bollocks all the time, yeah.
>> It's really interesting.
I think, so there was this thing.
There was a magazine, the magazine is putting it a bit strong.
It was a kind of a one sheet thing in the 1770s that was run by the Bow Street Magistrate
in London, and it was full of unsolved crimes and details of criminals, and it was called
general hue and cry, and it was distributed across the country, and it was a way of catching
criminals, it was basically like an extremely long distance hue and cry.
You'd say this person has stolen this, and they look like this, so if you see them, please
pick them up, and it worked.
Even in the 1770s, people were being picked up hundreds of miles away for crimes they
committed.
>> It just feels like being a civilian was a full-time job in those days.
You have to constantly, because again, it wasn't just that you had to give chase when
people cried.
You had to if you read it in the magazine, and also by the 17th century.
>> Sorry, what do you mean if you read it in the magazine?
>> No, you didn't have to chase when you read it in the magazine.
People desperately tried not to look at magazines, because then they're legally obliged.
>> It made it very hard to do the Sudoku, didn't it?
>> But warrants would be passed from parish to parish, so let's say you're looking for
a thief, then you go to the next parish, and you give them a picture, a drawing of the
criminal and a description of them, and you say, "Can you spread this around your parish?"
And then everyone in that parish is obliged to keep an eye out for them.
So I don't know how anyone held down a job.
>> They had delayed hue and cry in the Scottish borders as well.
The reason being that you would have a lot of people from England coming over and trying
to steal people's sheep and belongings and stuff like that.
And often what you would do is because they were armed, these people, it's a bit the Wild
West really, and so you might kind of hide in your hedge or kind of just try and get
all of your really expensive belongings and go there.
>> In the hedge.
>> In the hedge, yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Anywhere really.
>> All your sheep in the hedge.
Entire block of sheep, one hedge.
>> And then someone comes out with a hedge trimmer and you go, "Oh, no!"
So you would hide often because they were armed.
And so there's a special border law where you're allowed to do a counter raid as long
as it was within the six days.
You still had to shout hue and cry as you went.
And you had to carry a lighted torch so that everyone knew you were on a legitimate return
mission.
>> That's amazing.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> And then they had to join you on that.
>> No, that was just you getting your own back from the Cumbrians.
>> Got it.
Fair enough.
>> And these days, if you shout stop thief, you can get in trouble.
There's quite a few people who have sued, like, shop security because they've shouted
stop thief.
And they're like, "Well, I'm not a thief," and everyone's heard that, and everyone's
going to think that now.
>> Yeah.
>> There was a guy in Dublin, he was 28 years old, and he claimed that he'd been wrongly
accused of shoplifting a toy duck from a toy store.
He basically said he was deeply embarrassed and ashamed when a security guard approached
me and said, "Where is the duck?
I know you have it."
>> And the best part about it was they went to court, and they brought out the duck as
evidence, and it was a talking duck, and they couldn't turn it off.
All the way through the court case, this duck was just talking all the way through.
>> Are you sure it was a talking duck and not Wild Bill Hickok sitting in the court?
I've heard they're identical.
Do you guys know the bloody code?
>> No.
>> The bloody code.
>> Is that like a penal code, and you could be effectively executed for lots and lots
and lots of crimes?
>> It's pretty much, yeah, dropping a handkerchief.
Yeah.
This is in England, so Scotland tended to have a bit of a more, we might say better,
we might say more lenient legal system in sort of later medieval time where you didn't
get the death penalty for everything, but in England there was the bloody code, which
was the English legal system from the 17th to the early 19th century, and I hadn't realised
how many crimes you could be killed for, so there were over 200 crimes that were added
to this code.
Crimes you could be executed for included damaging orchards or gardens, cutting down trees on
an avenue, destroying a turnpike road, wrecking a fish pond.
>> I've got to say, Anna, I'm agreeing with all of this at the moment.
If I owned a fish pond, I would...
>> You're very so proprietary about your garden, aren't you?
>> Wow.
But there was this thing where if you were done for a crime and the jury thought, oh,
we don't really want this person to be literally hanged to death, they would return at what
was called a partial verdict, and they'd say he's guilty, but not as guilty as the judge
is trying to make out.
So there was this thing called grand larceny, if you stole something worth more than a shilling,
that was the death penalty for you.
So a shilling is not a huge amount of money even then, but what juries would sometimes
do is they would return a verdict of not grand larceny, but petty larceny.
So in 1751, for example, there was a crime where the accused had stolen a pound and seven
shillings and sixpence, definitely way above the barrier for being hanged, but the jury
said, we think those coins were actually only worth seven pence, so as a result, you get
off.
So that meant fewer executions.
>> Well, you say Anna about them being a bit more lenient in Scotland is mostly true,
but then after the reformation, the law was sort of done by the Kirk, by the church, and
they started bringing in laws for quite a lot of things that we would be surprised about
today.
So there were statues of 1661 in Scotland that said that if a child beat or cursed, either
their father or mother, they should be put to death without mercy.
>> Oh.
>> Yeah.
>> My numbers first.
>> If you were found guilty of the vice of, this is the exact words, filthy fornication,
you would get a fine of 40 pounds, 40 Scottish pounds, which in those days was absolutely
enormous.
And in 1697, as late as then, there was a guy in Edinburgh called Thomas Aikenhead.
He was hanged for declaring that theology was a rhapsody of ill-invented nonsense.
>> Oh.
>> He was hanged for that.
>> Yeah.
It wasn't, you know, the Norwegian today, it was slightly more lenient.
>> I was reading about, there's a classic book that was written by a guy called Havlock
Ellis, and it's all about the study of what a criminal, the makeup of a criminal, and
this was during Victorian times.
>> Like the face was supposed to look different if you were a criminal.
>> Exactly.
So there was a guy called Salsotto who was someone who paid particular attention to
different bits of the body to see if that, and he found, he believes that you're more
likely to be a criminal as a woman if you have a hairy anus.
>> All right, so from a show of hands, ladies.
>> She said hands.
>> That is a terrible episode of "Cry Watch," isn't it?
We've done a recreation of the cry.
>> Is that part of the search?
Like who's the criminal?
That's, yeah.
Has everyone shaved their anus before we commit this crime?
We don't want anyone caught.
But so he found it basically in seven out of 40 women that he studied.
>> Seven out of 40.
>> Who were criminals.
>> Right.
>> Had a hairy anus.
>> It's not a huge proportion.
>> It's enough that it made him write it down.
>> Did he study 40 non-criminals as well?
Was there any control group in this experiment?
>> Yeah.
All right.
Okay.
>> Do we know the proportion of women that have under normal circumstances according
to him hairy anuses?
>> That's what I'm saying.
>> Do we know what counts as a hairy anus?
>> Yeah.
Where's the anusometer of, you know.
>> How rigorous was this study?
Was it peer reviewed?
>> It sounds like he wasn't a proper scientist at all.
>> This is in Victorian London.
>> Oh, Victorian London.
>> Yeah.
>> Fine.
>> Okay.
>> There was no science.
And I kept reading it because it's a lot about hair.
Like does hair mean you're a criminal?
I'm a really hairy guy.
You can probably see from the audience.
>> We can't see all of you.
>> But I am a really hairy guy.
And so I was reading on.
And it said it's worthwhile pointing out that there are frequent anomalies in the development
of hair among idiots.
>> It's the hair.
That's what it is.
>> But yeah.
So any hairy anus women out there?
>> Stop.
>> We're watching it.
>> Oh, my God.
>> Good grief.
>> It is time for fact number three.
And that is Andy.
>> My fact is that in 2016, scientists found a pocket of helium so big that it could make
everyone on the planet sound squeaky for 20 minutes.
>> I mean, what great use of that helium.
>> Incredible.
We would have had such a good time.
And then actually later on, they upgraded the estimate they thought and it would have
been 40 minutes.
We could all have been squeaky for 40 minutes, everyone.
I'm sure that would have had quite serious health consequences for everybody, breathing
non-oxygen for 40 minutes.
But nonetheless, this massive, massive amount, and this is the thing of helium is we're always
running out of it and then suddenly always discovering more.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's just this constant sea salt.
>> Where is this pocket?
>> This was in Tanzania.
>> Okay.
>> Under the ground, presumably.
>> It's in an area called Rukwa in Tanzania.
And Rukwa is also the place which has the largest number of crocodiles in the whole
of Tanzania.
And the interesting thing about that is if you give a crocodile helium, its voice doesn't
go higher, it goes lower.
>> Yeah.
>> Really?
>> I remember we did it on QI and it's weird because the same thing is happening to, I think,
is it the timbre of your voice that helium changes rather than the pitch?
>> Exactly.
>> I think it is.
>> Yeah.
>> So you'd think that a crocodile sounded like us, like it's going higher, but when
the timbre of a crocodile's voice gets higher, it sounds to us deeper, so they sound more
sexy.
>> I don't think I've ever heard --
[ Laughter ]
>> Even more sexy.
>> I feel that.
>> Even more.
>> I can feel that.
>> Hard to believe.
>> Yeah.
A crocodile hunter was a very sexy show, wasn't it?
Steve Irwin was --
>> Is that what he was doing to those crocodiles?
>> Well, I've never heard a crocodile make any kind of noise.
>> They kind of growl.
They grunt.
Yeah.
Well, that --
[ Laughter ]
>> Okay.
Okay.
That was hot.
[ Laughter ]
>> Okay.
So they growl.
Okay.
Cool.
>> And the other interesting thing, I suppose, is that on this whole thing is that we were
running out of helium, and it was a big problem because we use it for MRI machines, we use
it for all sorts of important stuff, not just balloons, and we were running out of it, and
the price was getting higher and higher and higher, and this was the first time we'd ever
really looked for it, and they started looking and they found shitloads of it, and so they
think that maybe if we keep looking, we might find a lot more, and in fact, in 2017, some
scientists at the University of Edinburgh found a huge amount of helium in the middle
of Scotland as well.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, thank God.
The parties are saved.
[ Laughter ]
>> No, it isn't.
The parties are saved.
>> It's really -- it's weird.
It's the second most abundant element in the entire universe, but it's incredibly hard
to keep here.
>> That's crazy.
>> If you look at the deposits of it, they're mostly deposits of rock that are capped with
some impermeable rock, so it's basically in a cave that you're looking for it.
>> Yeah.
Do you know the biggest amount of helium you can currently buy?
This is quite exciting.
>> Oh, okay.
>> This week.
This is really thrilling.
>> This week?
Well, you would say they would come in those kind of canisters, right?
>> Yep.
Yep.
>> A big one of those --
>> It's even bigger than that.
>> By weight?
Because --
>> Well, it's -- I'm going to tell you by volume and by length.
So --
>> Okay.
>> So we could work out the width of the depths from that.
>> This is GCSE math.
>> And you've just got a GCSE math.
Yeah.
No, the USA have just announced -- this is really thrilling stuff.
They are just announcing they are selling off the entire federal helium system because
they nationalized it really early on, like in the 1920 or so, because they needed airships.
So they said we have to -- the government has to control the global supply, but we can
now get in on it.
That's great news.
So if they decided we don't really need airships anymore, so we might as well come in.
>> I don't know.
>> That was -- the Hindenburg wasn't able to use helium because of that global monopoly
was --
>> Exactly.
Yeah.
>> Exactly that.
>> Did you -- sorry, Andy, did you tell us the size of this?
>> Actually, I didn't.
Thank you very much, James.
So --
>> I could just tell that everyone in the room was like, "But, Andy, what is the length
and the volume?"
>> It includes -- thank you, James -- 700 kilometers of helium pipelines which are spread across
Texas, Oklahoma and Kansas, but I'm sure they can move them for an extra fee.
There's the Bush Dome Helium Storage Reservoir, a 4,000-hectare rock formation, capped -- you'll
be glad to know -- by two layers of non-porous calcium and hydrite, and it is likely to contain
65 million cubic meters of federally-owned crude helium.
>> And are they going to deliver this in convenient packages, or do they just say it's there,
get it yourself?
>> Because you can't come, and you know, like if you go to a supermarket and they say
you do want a bag, and you're like, "Well, I think I can fit it in these pockets."
You can't do that with that much helium, can you?
>> No, no, no.
I'm not sure who's going to buy it or what for.
>> Well, we might for helium airships, because, bizarrely, the UK has just decided to start
investing in them again.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
After a bit of a hiatus, and it's air nostrum, the -- it's a sister airline of BA, and it's
just put in a massive order for some helium airships, and, in fact, this venture is backed
by Iron Maiden frontman Bruce Dickinson, who I think he's pretty into flying, isn't
he?
>> He's a pilot, yeah.
>> There you go.
That's why he's into flying.
So, he's into this idea, and the idea is that it slashes a lot of carbon use, because we
could use them instead of aeroplanes, it'll slash carbon use by 90%.
I liked the fact that quasi-quarting, the business secretary said, "This is proof of
how the UK's businesses are embracing new technology."
Anyway, a prototype crash landed in 2016 on its second test, but it is going to be great,
we're told.
>> Oh, boy.
Wow, that's so good.
>> Who would win, this is an open question, in a conflict between an airship and a submarine?
>> Well, it depends where the conflict takes place.
>> Fair play.
>> Let's make it a neutral territory, let's make it above water.
You've got all the environments there apart from land, it's not on land.
>> Because this has happened.
>> Oh, has it?
>> Yeah.
>> Specifically, though, as in they were pitted against each other.
>> No, it was during the Second World War, there wasn't time to set up like fun...
>> It wasn't like Robot Wars.
>> It wasn't pay-per-view, airship versus submarine, okay.
>> So there were loads of US ships near the coast, which were sunk by German submarines
during the war, and there were ships which went in convoys that were protected by airships.
You've got a ship on the sea, then an airship above it protecting because they can see when
a submarine is approaching, they can detect it, and then drop depth charges.
You ordinarily wouldn't hit one, but it would just force the submarine to go lower and not
use its torpedoes, and of the 90,000 ships that were in convoys escorted by airships,
only one of them was ever sunk, but in 1943, a submarine fought a U-boat and the submarine
won.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> And what did it do?
>> Sorry, a submarine fought a U-boat, do you say?
>> Yep, I got that wrong.
That would have been a completely ordinary thing to happen in 1943.
>> It's not the best fact you've ever had.
>> I did a submarine fight against an airship, how did they shoot it, like torpedoes wouldn't
go in the air, right?
>> The account is quite vague on the method used.
I'm sure it wasn't a torpedo, but I think I might have been firing from the surface,
because I think I might have had surface guns.
>> I can't believe you don't know the answer.
>> I know, I'm sorry, I don't know who won, I just don't have a fucking match report,
you know, I'm sorry not to know.
>> If you take some helium and freeze it down to pretty much absolute zero just above it,
and you put it in a teacup, and you start stirring it, and you go away, and you come
back a million years later, it will still be stirring.
>> What?
>> That's so spooky.
>> I know.
>> It has no friction, doesn't it?
>> Exactly.
>> It's like this amazing capacity, but only when it's right and you're absolute zero.
>> It's because it doesn't go, like most things as they get colder, if you remember, from
your GCSE chemistry, they turn into solids, helium doesn't turn into a solid no matter
how cold it gets, unless you put it under loads and loads of pressure, and so it just
has these amazing properties, like a superconductor would.
>> It also, if you leave it in a glass and you bring it right down, A, it'll fall through
the glass, so like because, because it doesn't undergo friction at all, every tiny molecule
sized hole in your glass, like I'm holding a glass now, there are molecule sized holes
in it, most liquids stay in that because friction is holding them in, helium, when it's liquid,
will just slip through, and it will climb up the sides of the glass, because gravity
doesn't work the same way, gravity's not strong enough to hold it down, it's magic.
Can I quickly tell you my favourite helium story I've ever read?
1999, headline was, helium blew women up like a balloon, she was fine, by the way, I just
said the solid lips, she wasn't fine, she had a bad day, she was called, she was called
Samantha Munn, she owned a toy shop, she was standing on a stepladder in her toy shop,
she slipped off, and she was speared by the metal spike, which was in a helium tank, in
her left thigh, thank God for that, and she looked down and she saw her left thigh and
her stomach inflate like a balloon, they managed to get her to a hospital, where they extracted
her from the helium tank, did she just kind of go, around the room, we don't have any
beds for this patient, we'll just rubber it against your head and stick it to the wall.
Wouldn't it be great as well, because this was in a toy shop where they sell balloons
to the brand of kid, can I get this mum, for an hour she's been walking around the shopping
mall.
This is just the kind of joke she dreaded happening after this story.
She's fine now, right?
She's fine, they said a doctor x-rayed her left thigh, which showed that it was about
twice the size of her right, which I would argue you could tell without an x-ray.
Time for our final fact for the show, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is if you look up humour on Wikipedia, the first thing you'll see
is a picture of my face, and this is something that as of the 21st of August, someone changed
the photo on the article for humour, and very randomly they don't know who I am, they've
made that very clear in their comment, going, I have no idea who this person is, if anyone's
got a better picture, please replace it, but it hasn't been replaced, and I now find myself
the global face of humour.
And in the photo, it's not just me, there's someone else, so the wording, the caption
underneath is a viewer brackets Jimmy Wales left laughing at a comedian, Dan Schreiber
right performing stand-up comedian, if you don't know who Jimmy Wales is, Jimmy Wales
is the creator of Wikipedia, which is basically like making God laugh, right?
So this is a very exciting development.
I imagine God's laughing a lot when he's looking over at you.
Now that is really cool.
I don't know, if you ever needed evidence that Wikipedia's an unreliable source, I think
you're looking at it.
I wasn't there on this day, Dan.
You weren't?
So why are you not in the picture, Andy?
I don't know, but I did look up the Wikipedia for Wanker recently, and very upsettingly,
no, no, no, but this was a thing called Wikimania, where they sort of have an annual conference
all about Wikipedia and Wikipedians, and they have seminars, and they have fun quizzes,
and yeah, Andy and I were actually at the Edinburgh Fringe when it was on, it was down
in London, and I had this idea called Wikipedia the missing bits, and the idea was to do a
stand-up show where a comedian would come up and present a set on a missing page on Wikipedia
and their pitch for what should be involved in it, and Jimmy Wales came up, and actually
Jimmy came on stage with you, Andy, and did a quiz.
Yeah, yeah, no one apparently took a fucking photo.
Didn't you try to edit Wikipedia on the way down to say something about yourself?
No, there was a comedian who was on the show that day called Steve Cross, who was complaining
that he doesn't have a Wikipedia page, so I created a page where I could put his name
on, which was People Who Don't Have Wikipedia Pages, and he was the first on the list, but
it got taken down immediately.
It was within a minute or something, it was amazingly fast editing by the people at Wikipedia.
All the four of us have Wikipedia pages, right, and I had a quick look at the editing online,
because there's been a few times where comments that have been made on this show have made
their way onto my Wikipedia, and I've had to go in, and I've complained about it, and
no one changes it, so I've had to physically edit my change into it, and I'm now banned
from Wikipedia, yeah, before editing my own page for factual accuracy.
So one of the things was, someone changed my name on it to Daniel Indiana, Craig Schreiber,
because I once said that I almost changed my name to Daniel Indiana, to Indiana is my
middle name, so for a while on Wikipedia it was Daniel Indiana Craig Schreiber, Brackets,
Dix, which is what James said on the podcast, is what's made it on, then a few years later,
I had to change that, a few years later, Andy makes a joke, and it's a joke that I have
an interest in, sort of, we were talking about Nazism, and stuff like that, you're an avid
collector.
Daniel Indiana Craig Schreiber, aka Dix, is a radio producer living in the United Kingdom,
others have claimed him to have an extreme fascination and an expertise in Nazism and
Nazi sacred myths.
I hate to think what it's going to say about Heria-nesses after tonight's show.
And then some other dick put this on, I found this because this was in an edit, it said,
"Remove incorrect statement, Schreiber is not particularly noted for this catchphrase,"
and then what originally was put into my account was, "Schreiber is famous for his hilarious
catchphrase," yep, which he uses after Twitter handles are announced on no such thing as
a fish.
It's such a good catchphrase, though, because you've called it like, "That's a biggie,"
that's a huge word, oh my God, that's so good.
On Wikipedia pages, often it says, "Notable people," so if you had Bolton, for instance,
it might be notable people from Bolton, I thought I'd check where we are, if any of
those things, so this is all that I could find.
I am mentioned in "Notable people" with Afantasia, because I don't have like a mind's eye, so
I'm in that.
So James can't picture your face if you leave, he can't remember your face, that's all.
Uranus on the other hand?
Photographic, absolutely.
Dan is mentioned as a notable Australian in the United Kingdom, and Anna is a notable
person in the Poles in the United Kingdom, as in people from Poland.
Andy Murray is a notable tennis player.
Wow.
I'm not joking, I genuinely searched, and I didn't find that phrase.
Thank you for looking.
There was a thing, so the editing can be used for good and for ill, as we've clearly seen
from Dan's extensive list of grievances that he just read out, but a couple of years ago
there was a bloke in Australia who was a really big fan of a band called Peaking Duck.
He was a bloke called David Spargo, and he was going to see them at a gig, and he really
wanted to get backstage to see them, and so he changed the Wikipedia page of the band
Peaking Duck, creating an entry for family and listing himself as a family member.
And then when he got to the backstage bit of the gig, he said to the guys, "No, no,
I'm their step-brother or cousin or whatever, show that to the security guys who let him
in."
Genius.
And the band just gave him a beer and said, "Fair play, that's a very funny thing you've
done."
They said, "I love this so much," they said, "He wasn't creepy at all, and was actually
much more relaxed and cool than we would have expected from someone who went to those lengths."
That's so good.
The band hasn't been seen since then, has it?
You know on Wikipedia how there are multiple language Wikipedia's, and so there may be
a translation of no such thing as a fish into, I don't know, Mandarin, for example, or whatever
languages there are.
So there's a list of the articles where people and things have been the most translated,
so it's the leaderboard of that.
So in terms of humans that are on that leaderboard, the top people are, the most translations
is for Jesus.
Third is for Michael Jackson.
Third is for Barack Obama.
Fourth is for Donald Trump.
Fifth is for Adolf Hitler.
Sixth is for Albert Einstein.
Who do you think is seventh?
Is that Andy?
Please.
I need this, Dan.
I would have liked someone like Harry Potter, perhaps, or...
It's got to be a real person.
Mr Bean?
Oh, Rowan Atkinson.
Rowan Atkinson.
Same answer, yeah.
Yeah.
Is it another world leader?
No.
And I called Corbin Blue, BLEU, who was initially at the time a supporting actor from the movie
High School Musical, who, one enthusiastic fan, translated his account into every single
language that he could, as using Google Translate and stuff like that, giving him over 200 different
languages of translation.
So, he's just behind Albert Einstein, Julius Caesar's behind him, but it's, yeah, and it's
the theory that it's one person who's been doing that.
That's amazing.
So, we just think...
Because it sounds like that person is in tonight, if we do want to ask.
God people have a lot of time.
Like, so, on languages on Wikipedia, actually, there is a Scots language Wikipedia section.
It's got 41,000 articles, as in Scots, the sort of language Robbie Burns, kind of, some
people will say it's a dialect of English, some people say it's its own language, but
you know the one.
Anyway, people started to notice that some of the Scots language articles were not entirely
correct in terms of not really being written in the Scots language, they were really written
in a parody version of it, or what someone who didn't actually speak the language might
guess that it sounded like, and it turned out, it's because almost half of the articles
had been written by a teenager in North Carolina who did not speak a word of Scots.
It's the most odd story, and he started off doing it, he was 12, I think, when he started
doing it.
What a strange kid.
And they started at the top, all with the warning, "The Scots that was oozed in this
article was written be a body that's Mithra-Tung, is now Scots.
Please improve this article, Guinea Can, which I think is translated as, this is all bollocks,
please improve it."
But then he took that away, and it was only a couple of years ago, it was revealed that
it was just this boy in North Carolina who, I know, because then he felt so bad about
it.
He felt so bad about it.
He hasn't been named, I think, which is good.
Now, we know his Wikipedia name, which is Amaryllis Gardiner, but I don't know if you
can track him down with that.
And very sweetly, because a lot of people said we should scrap the whole Scots language
page, the Michael Dempster, who's director of the Scots Language Center, said, "Look,
this kid's put in an incredible amount of work.
It's a great resource, but it does need people who are literate in Scots to edit it now."
So get on it.
The editing of Wikipedia is such a hotly contested area, the behind-the-scenes of it is just
constant fights going on.
One of the famous ones, which probably a lot of people here know about, is there is a page
for a guy who's called Guy Standing, and in the photo, Guy Standing is sitting.
So the caption reads, "Guy Standing, sitting."
Beautiful.
That's great.
It's great, except it's a very contentious photo, which has now been edited away, brought
back because people are saying you're making fun.
This is an obvious joke, and we're not about jokes here, we're about information.
So if you want jokes, head over to Dan Schreiber on the human point.
I just have one or two things about stock photos, because this is a stock photo, this
is a public use photo, but the stock photo libraries that exist, they lead to all sorts
of weird quirks and tangents.
So for example, in 2019, the New Zealand budget featured stock photos, a stock photo model
on the front of it, and it turned out to be a woman called Vicky Freeman, who just had
the picture taken and just sold the rights to it.
Anyway, she had moved to Australia because she could no longer afford to live in New
Zealand, and was on the front page of the New Zealand budget document, all about making
life affordable.
And you don't really have many options, normally.
You can sometimes say, "I don't want to be used to advertise an extreme political
view," or whatever, but you often just have no rights at all.
So in 2014, a woman called Samantha Ovens had years before done a photo shoot for colds
and illnesses.
You know, those sort of cold remedy photos, where you just have to pinch your brow and
look a bit pained, or look a bit...
Yeah.
...like you're having a slightly, "Oh, I've got a bit of a cold or a headache," or whatever.
Anyway, that then got used as the lead on a Guardian article, a confessional article
blind, "I fantasise about group sex with old obese men," and she just found people started
contacting her, saying, "You're right, Samantha."
A lot of old men getting in touch.
Honestly, Sam, see you dance, mate.
I'm going to have to wrap this up very shortly, guys.
I know.
We're nearing the end.
Could I tell you one funny thing?
Yeah.
I saw...
Which is that, following one of the Football World Cups, Seth Blatter, who was the FIFA
president, he was awarded this beautiful award, the Order of Companions of OR Tambo, for his
contribution to the World Cup, and to announce it, the South African government put it on
their webpage, but unfortunately, they took his name and details from his Wikipedia page,
which had just been vandalised.
And so, what they announced on their website was an award for Joseph Sepp Bellend Blatter.
That is it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we've said about
this podcast, you can get us on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sribeland, Andy, @AndrewHonderem, James, @JamesHarkin, and Anna.
You can email our podcast at qi.com.
Yeah, or you can go to our group account, which is @NoSuchThing, or our website, NoSuchThing
isafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
Do check them out.
Also, check out the option of going Club Fish, Club Fish, very sexy place where there's
no adverts.
Check it out.
Very quickly.
Thank you so much, Edinburgh.
That was awesome.
It's always so much fun being here.
We love being here.
We will be back again, and we'll also be back again next week for another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye!
Bye!
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)