- They don't look at it, but who don't look at it?
(techno music)
- Hi, welcome to Drop us a Line.
The mailbag special.
The post-ease sack is bulging.
Let's empty it.
All over the desk.
Was that good?
Was it why you were fired for the Royal Mail or something?
(laughing)
- It was the annual review that you had to give
to all the shareholders.
And it was just followed this bill.
(laughing)
- I was running the Royal Mail for a while.
- I love these jokes more.
Welcome to Drop us a Line.
Okay, let's start with some brutal takedowns
from our audience.
- All right.
- These are good.
So Jim Robertson dives in.
This is something based on our London podcast festival shows.
Watching the livestream tonight, I noticed a wrong fact
by James Harkin.
- Okay.
- Outfall.
(laughing)
- He stated that facts in Chinawattlitty Chairman who died,
when in fact, he was Manchester City Chairman
who was disgraced, the Leicester City Chairman
was Vichai's riddener Praba.
- Yes, in the helicopter.
- Accident.
- But you know what, that is so useful
because that show hasn't come out yet,
and I can edit the actual podcast.
- That's a great time travel.
- That's good.
We should do all of our shows live,
so the audience to fact check.
The audience to fact check it.
And then that would,
but we'll still get nice emails for Drop us a Line.
But then the actual show that goes out will be accurate.
Yes.
- Was it the Osman one that we said that
or was it the Jamie Maltemann?
- I'm a friend, I don't know.
- I'll remember.
It was about Mrs. Golf.
- No, it was Jamie.
- It was Jamie.
It doesn't go out for weeks.
- So you've got ages to fix it.
- Oh, what a treat.
- Or change history.
So we've opened up some, so all I have to do
is get disgraced Manchester City,
former chairman,
Thex and Shinnowatra to take over Leicester
and have a terrible accident.
- And you've got three weeks to do it.
- That's a movie.
So we've really opened up a lot of timelines there, haven't we?
I'm really don't know what's going on anymore,
but I'm glad for Jim Robertson's email.
- Thank you, Jim.
- Yeah.
Robin, I'm actually me, which should not be.
- Is there a surname there?
I'm thinking Fickie.
- Do you know what?
- Robin doesn't give a surname, I believe.
Technically, Louis doesn't come from Clovis,
but is a doublet of it,
meaning they both trace back to the same word Ludoig,
meaning famous in battle.
- Okay, that's good.
- That's because Andy said that the word Louis,
at the name Louis, the French king name,
came from Clovis.
You knock off the sea, you get Louis.
- Yeah, Louis, Louis.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- Which I stand by.
- I don't think that's quite right.
Is it like saying that you're descended from monkeys
when actually you and monkeys are descended
from the same ancestor?
- Well, Cludoig, does that really sound like Louis?
I don't think it does.
So, sorry, Robin, and thank you.
- Interesting thing.
How many different names do you think come from Cludoig?
'Cause I reckon Ludoig does, and I reckon Louis does,
and I reckon Clovis does.
Clive.
- Three.
- Definitely.
- Yeah.
- Ludo.
- David.
- Yeah, probably.
- David, yeah.
- Hugh.
- Cludoig.
- Yeah, just knock out the elf.
- Yeah.
- Basically, we all have the same name
if you go back long enough.
- That's a minute, and it's all this.
- It's all Cludoig, we're all famous in battle.
- Cludo-dan-wig.
- Yeah.
- Dog.
- Not really a name, but more of a title.
- Yeah.
- My dog.
- All right.
Dana Johnson writes.
- Oh, this is...
- We're getting one each.
This is very egalitarian.
- Yeah.
- This is really nice.
Like one chewing each.
- I mean, you do select the emails.
It's not as if some bigger force
has accidentally put one each.
- Well, no, but I don't, I'm not planning it at that level.
- Okay.
- It's a miracle if I get them in the same categories.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's a miracle all the corrections are in the same page.
- Yeah.
- That's rare.
I'm a huge fan, right?
It's Dana Johnson.
Dana?
Comes from Cludoig.
Of course.
(laughing)
- And got livestream tickets for both the live shows
from the London podcast festival this weekend.
It was my first time watching a live show of yours,
and I thoroughly enjoyed it.
This probably isn't so important,
but I'm a professional violinist
based in Northern Norway,
and I just thought I'd mention
that the Rachmaninov piece that was quoted in all by myself,
to your face, was his second piano concerto,
not his second symphony.
- Okay, that's gonna be a more difficult edit,
'cause I'm pretty sure I never said the word concerto.
I think it was me who said that.
- I was a U, I'm sorry, I thought it was that,
'cause it was down the fact.
So anyways, it's a small detail, but thought I'd share.
So thank you, Dana.
- That's good.
- Lovely.
- It's a good book,
and it's all about how to tell the difference between things.
So it's like it's an encyclopedia of small differences,
and one of them is concerto and symphony.
- So concerto is where you have a main instrument
who plays the main bit,
and then you have the orchestra playing the background,
and you're saying that all by myself was not that?
- It was Rachmaninov's second piano concerto,
so that is that. - But Rachmaninov
does have a second symphony,
and a symphony is all the orchestra playing together.
There's no king instrument popping over the others.
- So there you go.
- Yeah.
- That's interesting.
- Sorry James, you were able to go back in time.
- It feels like I can't fix that one,
unless I book out the King's Place Theatre,
and get find 300 people who will sit there
to give the same sound effects.
And I've got three weeks to do it.
- I actually got it.
- Yeah.
- And you're busy with the football thing already.
It's quite stressful.
- Oh, dear, interesting.
- Yeah, we didn't mention on the night, but that song,
Eric Carmen wrote that song.
He started, have you listened to the original version?
- To the rap map enough.
- No, to the Eric Carmen all by myself.
Halfway through it, there's this like five minute long solo piece
that he does on the piano and with guitars and stuff.
And that's what he started with.
So he finished the solo to the song,
and then he was like, okay, now I need to book
and it with an actual song around it.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, he spent months doing that.
- I think we also didn't mention is that he rips off
the rap man enough for the...
- The melody of the main.
- The melody of the verse, I think.
And then he rips off his own old song for the chorus.
- Yes, that's right.
- So chorus is identical to a song that he did with his band
before he became a solo artist.
- Yes, that's right.
- Eric and the song.
- We also didn't mention that Carmen is the name
of an opera by Beese.
- Yeah.
- And that's extra plagiarism by George Carmen
of another composer.
- Yeah, right.
- Yeah.
- That's good.
- This one, I'm sorry.
- With Eric Cartman from South Park gets his name
from Eric Carmen from all by myself or not.
And I couldn't find non-line whether that's true or not.
- That's such a good call.
- They both get their names from Fludeauwig
reading "Favorite Battle" eventually.
So it doesn't sort of, so yes.
- I wonder who's had more number one hits.
'Cause South Park have had quite a few.
- I've never known what to do.
- Chocolate salty balls.
It's the biggest I don't think that got to number one.
- That's technically chef as well, I guess.
- That's true.
- You guys have good knowledge of that.
- Nice, okay.
- Amazing.
- Oh, here's, okay, here's a good question, question corner.
- Okay.
- Sammy from Vancouver, right?
- Like most of the people emailing you,
I'm a huge fan of the podcast.
That's actually not true, Sammy.
(laughing)
It's about 50 spam and indifference corrections.
But you often bring up weird or cool museums
that you visited usually on travels.
I'll be visiting London in December
and I wonder if you have any fish favorites
that you'd recommend.
I've been to the British Museum
and the National Library.
I guess Sammy must be British Library.
But that's it so far.
- Good question.
Maybe you've got one and the one
that you went to near the Thames,
near the Old Office, do you remember?
- There's it.
- Glass Spectacles Library.
- That one is amazing.
The British Optical Association Museum,
but it is appointment only.
- Well, he's got time.
- That's true, you've got time to book in.
It's really cool.
It's sort of collections of old optical instruments
and history of glasses and history of contact lenses and all that.
It's a, yeah.
So that's a very niche museum.
- Yeah, so it's good.
- Gosh, I mean, they're all brilliant as a truth.
I really love the Museum of Childhood.
I really love that stuff.
- Why have you been there?
- Yeah, I've not been to the National Green, is that?
- Right, if you've got kids going down the London Museum.
You've been to dozens of them.
- I have, yeah.
I tell you what, this is not a museum
but it is as such a sort of museum in the wild.
I used to love going to Crystal Palace
because there are the oldest examples
of what dinosaurs would have looked like
as part of the park.
- What they wouldn't have looked like.
- Well, the idea is what they would have looked like
and they've got a horribly wrong
and they look like these goofy creations.
It'll take you two minutes to see them
but it was part of the Crystal Palace exhibition
back in the day.
It was based off the designs of Richard Owen
who's the person who coined the word dinosaur.
So you're seeing the original Jurassic Park effectively.
- It's very cool.
It's very cool.
I'd say that.
- That is amazing.
- It'll take a long, old time to get to Crystal Palace,
doesn't it?
- Absolutely.
So it'll be empty.
(laughing)
- That's not how time works.
It's not like the time takin' to get them.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Handy yourself?
- Have you done one?
- I've done a museum of chartered.
- I will say, do you know what?
It's in it's own Hoban, the John's Zone Museum.
- Oh yeah.
- Which is a collection of John's Zone
who was just this mad collector of everything.
- And I think his collection form
the basis of the British Museum, but also his house,
which is now three houses, not into one.
It's just an amazing, weird collection of stuff.
- Can I say a fact about that,
which might not be true 'cause I'm going off memory.
But I think he might have been friends with Frederick Chopin
or I think might not be Chopin, but he's someone like that.
- Okay.
- Came over to London, visited him and then put his cup
on a place where he shouldn't have put his cup.
And so John's Zone thought, you know what?
I can't have all this stuff in my house anymore.
I need to find some words and put it.
And so he put it all in the museum instead.
- Oh wow.
- That was really good.
- I might have got everything wrong about that anecdote.
- No, I think there's, I can't remember it either,
but I think, yeah, I've heard that story
or something like it, yeah.
That's great.
- So are you good, Sammy?
- Happy travels.
- Can we do this as a new thing?
If anyone's coming to London and they need some tips,
maybe next time it'll be a restaurant.
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah.
- Or a brothel.
(laughing)
- Who did he point out?
I wasn't like it.
- I don't know, it was a warm gesture.
(laughing)
- For a bookshop.
- There's great bookshops.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Jamie Lerna Brecher, right?
- Dan's show, "Big Hands."
- Oh yeah. - Yeah.
- Okay, this was your show you pitched.
- Yes. - "Big Hands."
- Well, "Packanini", the violinist, apparently,
also had enormous hands.
- Yes, that's right.
- And this often comes up in music classes
because when you talk about Rachmaninov,
because both Rachmaninov and Paganini stuff
is extremely difficult to play.
- He also sold his soul to the devil Paganini.
- That's right. - That's right.
- Yeah.
- His mum had to release a letter
like in a newspaper to say,
"I can tell you that he's definitely my son
and that his father is his father
and the devil was not part of our courtship."
And he was like the original rock star, wasn't he,
of the-- - Oh, one of them, yeah.
- It's a few that I'll name like that.
- Yeah, but he had like merged people with girls
who go nuts for him and he had these giant fingers.
- Well, I wonder why the girls might not serve.
(laughing)
- No, I mean, I love a bit Paganini, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I don't really know Paganini's stuff,
but apparently historians believe Paganini
likely had "Marfan's Syndrome,"
or possibly Earl's "Danlos Syndrome,"
which often causes double joy to this.
Other notable people with "Marfan's Syndrome,"
and that's definitely "Big Hands," include.
(humming)
- Okay, Abraham Lincoln. - Mm-hmm.
- Chewbacker. - Peter Mayhew.
- Who played you right here? - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Jonathan Larson.
- Who's Jonathan Larson? - Reator of Rent.
- The musical. - The musical.
- Okay. - And it's no.
Vincent Sheavelli.
I mean, there's a big drop off in the fame after Chewbacker.
I wonder who's this?
From Ghost, tomorrow I never dies,
and first times at Ridgemont High.
Other people who may have had "Marfan's,"
include Shalda Gaulle, Caesar, Jamie.
You've got to get the order right in terms of fame.
There's no universe in which Caesar is less famous
than Jonathan Larson.
- No, no, but this is now into the may of her.
- May of her. - That's the top of the may have.
- That's true, that's true.
And King Tutan coming.
- Really? - Yep.
- Really? - So they got may have, may have.
So they just, they had big fingers, but we don't know.
Or long fingers, rather than big fingers.
- I believe so. - Interesting, I believe so.
- I've never heard that about Tut.
- No. - No. - All Caesar.
- No. - Are any of those people, I'll be honest.
The only ones I really believe are the ones
I'd never heard of.
- Yeah, right, yeah, yeah.
- Now, Danny Sugar writes.
- Great name.
- Coming back to the episode about Jimmy Hendrix,
opening for the monkeys, fun fact about the monkeys,
is that monkey, Michael, is he called Nesmith?
- Nesmith, yeah. - Nesmiths.
- His mum invented Tipex, is that the facts?
- Have you been in the inbox?
- It's quite a common factoid about it.
I wasn't on that episode, it was with Nesmith, wasn't it?
- It was. - Yes, that's right.
- Oh, Danny, Danny, Danny, you've been harkened.
Sorry. - What's this?
- I think we could do this as a section as well
when people give the facts, you read the first half
and I tell you what the second half is.
Having done this job for 20 years.
- Anyway, Michael Nesmith's mum invented
a correction fluid and founded liquid paper,
which later became a large company
and was sold to Gillette.
But that's the, that's just dotting the eyes
and crossing the teeth on that one.
- It's a good fact, we always like it, yeah.
- And Danny Sugar adds in,
the paper product company, Torque,
seems to have nothing at all to do with Monkey Peter Torque.
So it's good to, good that Mr. Bed.
I'm sick of it in the inbox every week.
Does he know?
- That was great. - Yeah.
There we go.
- I'm so funny.
I'd never even heard of that member of the monkeys.
- No, no. - Torque.
- All Torque, would be his podcast.
- Yes. - Torque with Torque.
- Oh, yes.
- That would be good.
- Is he living?
We don't know.
- I'd never heard of him until 10 seconds ago.
I used to watch the monkeys when I was a kid.
One of my earliest memories is being in hospital
'cause I had some adnodes removed
and watching the monkeys on Saturday.
- Wow. - Yeah.
- Good.
Now let's get into,
what is it called?
Is it called the Big Meat?
There's one episode each.
- Spicy Meat?
- No, no, no, spicy meat is controversy
in the right environment.
- You make them up every week, I think.
- I've got to rigorously maintain
spreadsheet of these things.
I've never bring you with me.
There's often one subject with which dominates the inbox.
- Okay. - The rodeo clown section.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Would you use meat twice for your sections?
That doesn't feel very-- - Oh, yeah.
- Spicy meat.
You wouldn't have then-- - Yeah, you're right.
- Maybe you should just call it the rodeo clown section.
- That's it. - Yeah.
- I'm writing it down.
This week's rodeo clown.
- Yeah.
- It's a small rodeo clown this week,
but it's the donut hole.
- Oh, yeah.
- So we've just broadcasted an episode
all about donuts and their holes.
- Yeah.
- Is it about the invention or the size or--
- It's gonna be, my guess is the pirate ship moment
of where it's supposedly put on the wheel of pirate ship.
- We've had a few correspondence.
I've only copied out one of their emails
'cause it was kind of indicative or representative.
John G. Erickson said, "I heard James say
that the nut in donut referred to a small cake."
- Yeah.
- I knew that was wrong because I knew, in quotes,
the correct origin of the word, or so I thought.
I asked my wife and she knew the same origin that I did.
Problem is I can't find our version
anywhere on the internet, so there you go.
So that's John, giving himself a show and that.
- But what's his version?
- His version. - What are people saying
they're saying that that's not true?
- A couple of people have written in saying
that we don't have to shape like a zero for which
- Nought is a synonym.
- Oh yeah, what sounds most likely?
Me that it's an old word for a cake-like product
that's like hundreds of years old.
Or that someone would call it a doughnut.
- A doughnut, isn't that more satisfying?
- It's a great coincidence. - It's so John.
- I mean, to be honest, mine just came from memory,
so it might not be true either.
- I'm sure you'll do it. - I can check it.
- John can't find this on the internet,
the whole internet, so I think you'll save James.
Yeah, anyway.
So that's interesting.
Paul Hoffman, greetings again, says Paul.
- I have no idea how fish,
I love it when people start with that.
Could have a whole question.
- I shouldn't have already questioned, as well.
On doughnuts, I'm not mentioning the banned fish
with a pH, but I haven't heard of.
- They like blur, or?
- They're less famous than blur, I would say,
but they're not not famous.
- Okay, 'cause I'm a rowbacked Paul,
saying thank you for your email.
I'd actually never heard of fish,
and he wrote back saying, well, they're actually incredibly famous.
- Yeah. - So they're famous, yeah.
- Then just they're not a racist and blurred.
- Right, so they famously did a set of 13 shows,
a Baker's dozen.
At each of these shows, fish handed out thousands
of one particular type of doughnut,
and at least one song they played that night
was a riff on the type of doughnut.
- Oh. - Have a go?
- So go on.
- Do they have to be songs by the banned fish?
- No, no, no, no, they played songs from everyone.
- I don't know. - So, they play
"Hole Again" by Atomic Kitten.
- Got it in one?
- They play "Hole Again" by Atomic Kitten.
(laughing)
- They played "Rigger and Garoses" by "Children."
- By "Trad."
So it is strawberry, strawberry doughnuts,
for strawberry fields. - Oh, that's good.
Cinnamon doughnuts for cinnamon girl,
by someone called Neil Young.
Night 12, they handed out Boston cream doughnuts,
which was a matter of more than a feeling by Boston
and sunshine of your love by cream.
- Wow. - Night 12.
- So they really committed to the bit.
- Well, they did 13 nights?
- I think they possibly could have done more
than 13 nights at Madison Square Garden,
if they'd have thought of more puns about doughnuts.
- Yeah, for sure, that's the reason they only did 13
as that's the most they could think of.
- That's probably it.
- If they'd have thought of "Hole Again"
right into the kitchen, they might have done 14 nights.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Is it, is it, is it, is it sounds that some?
- Oh, the gun, no, no.
- It was "Hole with the Night" or "W", is it?
- "Hole Again", yeah, with "W".
- All right, is it your gulfing,
like pump you up song before gulfing?
- But it was number one.
And he was written by what's the name for the bangles, I think.
And also it's, they did a cover version
for the World Cup when "Garret the Southgate",
they do a "Garret the Southgate" version of it.
- Mmm, interesting.
- Gulf, hole?
- Yeah, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
- This is, there's a lot of pop trivia in this.
- Yeah, we should do a mashup episode
but then no such thing as a fish.
- Brilliant.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Ben Gill says, "My partner's birthday is coming up
and I'd like to find her an unusual book.
She's a quantum physicist, a huge reader,
and of course a big fish fan."
And we've already made a dent into the fish's books
and we love the book of the years,
but I would like to ask for your most loved off-piece
book recommendations,
prompted by episode 600 "Donut" book,
"What are the still readable books you could recommend?"
- Oh.
- That is so...
- 'Cause I had one in my head,
but I've got a brilliant history of "Darts",
which is...
- There we go.
- Like "Borderline Readable", but it's really good.
For me, if we're doing non-fiction,
then "Band Vads" Foley is always my favorite.
It's a really old book, I can't remember who wrote it now,
but it's people from history
who should be more famous than they are.
- I'm not quite famous at the time,
but aren't famous anymore.
- So that was a book that we mentioned very early
on the podcast, and the earliest of emails would be
what was that book?
- The original "Dropper's Align"
would have just been full of that.
There's a great book called "Tolstoy's Bicycle",
which is a sort of QI classic as well.
It's basically, it's broken up by ages
and what people had achieved by certain ages.
It starts like one or two, it's a bit thin.
But then the early chapter is quite nice.
- So then you've got Mozart wrote his first
little piano piece or whatever.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's really fun.
It's just a really good encyclopaedic way of breaking up.
- That's really good.
- What people have done.
- I am looking, I'm sorry to be disfigured.
I'm looking for my favorite one,
which is not on this bookshelf, which is really annoying.
No, it's not here.
I'm looking for Wales' bones of the British Isles.
- Oh, yeah.
- Which is...
- That's a bit big to take on holiday, isn't it?
- You look pretty daft at the beach with the 800-page
giant whale bone in psychopaedia, but it's bloody good.
- So anyway, so we can come back to that.
- Yeah, but those are three.
- Ben Vars-Folly, Tolstoy's Bicycle,
- And Wales' bones of the British Isles.
- There we go.
- Yeah.
- Great.
Oliver Kassel has a suggestion for a section.
- Ah, thanks with no thanks.
- Yes.
- How have you not all come up with a segment
for a clubfish bonus episode called Go Fish?
- Well, we play Cards.
- And then he says, what would it be?
(laughing)
- I don't know, Oliver.
- We could play Go.
- Yeah, the game of Go.
- Yeah.
- What was the question that for the three of us to play?
- Yeah, so it would tie into our knowledge.
Do you remember we played a game a long time ago?
It was so fun.
And I think we literally only played it once,
where we used to have, in the office, a big...
You know, those big reams of paper and you'd...
- A no flip chart.
And we used to, so what it was is you would draw the fact,
and whoever was guess what the fact was as you were drawing.
It was so much fun.
That was great.
- I remember amateuring President Garfield's anus.
(laughing)
- You're like, "I saw wrong."
What have you drawn here?
- Yeah.
- God, that's good.
- That could be a section of the drop us a line,
you know.
- That's a really good idea.
- And this is gonna be Cold Go Fish.
- Yeah, that was what the, basically this guy's rotten in,
and then with the idea of a title and nothing else.
- All right.
- I don't think you get any credit for all of it.
If we 50/50 on the royalties, coming your way, buddy.
All right.
He has a question though.
- Yeah.
- And this is a little spicy meat.
It's slightly spicy meat.
It's like a pepper army.
Tell me in secret, I promise I'll keep the secret,
or maybe just mention it to all fishers,
or do nothing.
I don't care.
Oliver, you're really giving us options here.
What does the organizational chart at no such thing
as a fish look like?
- What do you mean?
- Why is it just you for Illuminati?
- Freemasons.
(laughing)
- Shut it down.
And the episode now, that's the four of us,
'cause that's how we started out and went on.
We only brought people in if they missed an episode, right?
- Yeah.
- That was the idea behind it.
- But we are also in the Illuminati.
Sorry, just to like get below that wide open,
but we are Freemasons.
- Yeah, is it?
- Why have we got this desk here?
'Cause our trouser legs are rolled up.
- Is that Illuminati thing?
- That's Mason's, isn't it?
- You roll your trouser legs up.
- Oh no.
- You roll one trouser leg up.
- You two in the first meeting.
(laughing)
- It's gonna be so embarrassing
when I bring you to my Illuminati meeting.
- I've come with shorts.
They're both Freemasons rolled up.
(laughing)
- What's up, I've never heard that before.
- Dan, you've written a book
about weird things people believe,
but I don't do Freemasons.
- Oh, no, actually we do get emails
from Agrived Mason sometimes.
- Yeah.
- You mention the Masons.
- They will email it.
- Yes, they will.
- And they say we don't do this
in that weird utray thing.
- They emailed in because I said
that they all have Harry Potter like wizard ones
in their briefcases.
- I don't know, it was like,
it's not a wand, it's a staff
which we use for our spells.
(laughing)
- Come at me Gandalf, right?
- Okay, Claire Matthews from Esquimalt,
which I'm assuming I'm saying correctly.
(laughing)
- On Vancouver Island.
- It sounds like how you might spell Eskimo.
- Yeah, it does, doesn't it?
And maybe it's pronounced like that.
I just don't know.
I absolutely loved Dan's comment
about how King Dagobair was docked by controversy.
- Oh.
- We're back into conspiracy territory.
- Well, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Is this just the dag and dog?
Is that what she likes?
- No, no, but because in the French translation
of Enoch Blighten's famous five series,
Le Club des Sank, the dog Timmy is called Dagobair.
- No.
- So you were scoring a hoop you didn't even see.
- Very good.
- Yep, that's a lovely fact.
- I know.
- Great fact.
Jetta Doran writes,
I grew up in France, Le Bonne Rat Dagobair,
the song is familiar to me,
but only through the nursery rhyme.
I'm an interior podcast.
I didn't know he was a real historical figure.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, yeah.
That is proof that the nursery rhyme exists.
And she points out that it does not recover his reputation.
It's making a lot of fun of him and all of that.
- Right.
- But he puts his chasers on back to front
and he gets chased by a rabbit.
Another amusing thing's happened.
Dom Paddon writes,
in the 1990s German extortionist Arne Funk,
Arne Funker modeled himself on Scrooge McDuck,
which is Dagobair in German.
- What, so jacket, no trousers?
- No, just, what, sorry, I didn't actually understand
that sentence.
So it doesn't need a bit of passing, doesn't it?
- So Dagobair is the German version of Scrooge McDuck?
- Yeah, in Germany,
Scrooge McDuck is called Dagobair.
- Is he?
Wow.
- And in the 1990s,
there was a famous extortionist called Arne Funker,
Arne Funk, who modeled himself on Dagobair,
and successfully evaded the police for years.
- What did he do, like, swim in gold coins or something, maybe?
I'm trying to think of how you can model yourself
on Scrooge McDuck.
- On Scrooge McDuck.
- 'Cause he doesn't have that very, very clear characteristic.
- And you're absolutely right.
But apparently the police resorted to studying
Donald Duckhart's to see what he would do next.
And there were people wearing,
I am Dagobair T-shirts,
and he was mentioned in rap songs.
At one point, he evaded capture
as the policeman chasing him,
slipped on a dog poo.
- Interesting.
You know what?
I always thought that dog poo's would be a better
comedic thing than banana skins.
'Cause I have stood on banana skins
and don't think they're very slippy,
but dog poo is really slippy.
- Oh yeah.
- If you stand on a dog poo,
like I've seen people properly skidding on dog poo.
- You see?
- Yeah.
- But yeah.
- Can we just go back to you standing on a banana skin,
saying, see, I'm not slipping on it.
- I stood on one, like, literally this week.
I stood on a banana skin.
- You, you.
- I was walking down and I had something squelched
in the microphone.
- You were carrying a paint of glass
across the street when you were at this time.
- I'm not that slippy.
- It's quite, I have a faint memory.
The bell is tinkling
that banana skins are sort of an accepted code for dog poo.
But you couldn't show dog poo on film.
'Cause it was too sort of a bit rude or a bit gross.
- Right.
- So you'd sort of every, you know,
well, because you don't get banana skins
just all over the place.
- You didn't America.
I think we spoke about this on the podcast.
In New York, there was a big period
where rubbish wasn't being collected.
- I was okay. - And those guys were everywhere.
And so it became, and then there were variety acts
that would go on stage, specifically slipping on bananas.
- Was a guy who literally, he would put a banana on the stage
and he would walk and then skid all the way across
the stage, go off stage, laugh.
- Brilliant.
- I remember his name, but yeah.
- Oh my God, the comedy ice skating awards
would be amazing.
What tricks you could pull on two bananas.
- Me, YOB, that's where that comes from.
- So is that two major characters that are called
Dagobair in different countries?
- Yeah.
- Timmy The Dog.
- Timmy The Dog and Scrooge McDog.
- Wow.
- Interesting.
- Dogobair, more like?
- More like Duckobair.
- There we go.
End it.
- Right, you've had your fill.
- Randall Cleaver writes,
"Mine and Laws live in Lexington, Virginia,
where the Virginia military institute is located
in the local town cemetery is Stonewall Jackson's grave."
- Oh, cool.
- Which grave, the...
- I presume the full, the three quarter ones.
- Yeah.
- One day, one visiting them, I went over to see his grave
and I saw what's on the ground surrounding his grave.
- Like a zombie putting his hand out of the grave,
it was his big hand.
- Brilliant.
- Not that.
- Oh, and all that.
- Was it the Stonewall magazine, the pro LGBT?
- It wasn't Stonewall magazine.
- Was it a literal Stonewall?
- No, very nice.
- I don't know, I think we said that people believed about him
that was not true.
- Oh, okay.
- Oh, he always ate lemons.
- Yes, that's right.
- Dozens of lemons on the ground surrounding his grave.
Many of them had writing on them.
I went over to the museum.
- Ah, deliberate.
- And I went to the museum and I talked to the docent there.
I don't know the word, about the lemons.
She said that someone saw him eating lemon
and it became law.
And the museum gift shop sells lemon shaped stress balls.
- Brilliant.
(laughing)
- All right, last one.
Should we have, I think we've--
- Yeah. - Yeah, yeah.
- We squeezed this lemon.
(laughing)
- And the pips are squeaking.
Now this is a great one.
Martha King writes, "Long time emailer, first time listener."
(laughing)
- I'm sorry, I've just got that.
I'm showing you.
(laughing)
- That's a good joke.
- That's the first time we've ever--
(laughing)
- That's for you, Martha.
That's the first time we've ever had that.
And I've been in the box for about four years,
and I've been in the box for about four years.
- Yeah, that's great.
- Oh, I'm going to say something potentially controversial.
- Yeah.
- Are we entering spicy meat alley?
I don't think of Dan Treiber as a wife guy.
- Oh.
- She's flirty, what do you hear?
- I see.
(laughing)
- My understanding of the phrase wife guy
is as a pejorative for overly performative behavior,
specifically straight men who cultivate and profit
from a family man image until a cheating scandal
inevitably breaks.
- I think Adam Levine or Ned Fulmer.
- Who's Ned Fulmer?
(laughing)
- And if you're Mrs. Fulmer, I'm so sorry.
- Ned Fulmer.
- Who's Ned Fulmer?
(laughing)
- Adam Levine was here in Maroon 5, possibly.
- I'm sorry, I don't believe that.
- Yeah, just while we're on our pop culture references,
but yeah, Ned Fulmer.
- Ned Fulmer, that was very much the, you know,
like Chewbacca and then Abraham Lincoln
and then Jonathan Larson.
(laughing)
- Ned Fulmer.
- He's from a thing called the Try Guys.
- A YouTube channel.
- Okay.
- I think they're relatively famous.
- I think, yeah.
- Well, sorry Ned.
Sorry to back Dan, right, Martha,
but I will not let him continue to give wife guys
a good name.
(laughing)
I do agree that Dan is the textbook example
of whatever the wholesome version of this is called.
Maybe just a good husband.
And I'm obviously delighted that he and Ben found each other.
- Yeah, just a nice email, isn't it?
- A nice email?
- Yeah.
So I think, I take that point.
When we say, a wife guy is often someone who's saying,
oh look, I love my wife so much.
I'm great, rather than actually saying,
I just think my wife's brilliant, she's great.
- Oh, you know what I mean, right.
- 'Cause I think you do mention a thing a lot,
but that's because I think it comes from a genuine place of,
- What was anecdotes to tell?
- Yeah.
- So anecdotes.
(laughing)
- So Jenny complies some trying to fill out.
- She is.
- She's anecdotes central.
- She's anecdotes city.
- Yeah, you're right.
- She fucks up as much as she does.
- Of course she's going to get mentioned.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- That is Drop us Alone for another fortnight.
Thank you so much for listening.
And if you've enjoyed this,
there's nothing more for you to do.
- If you haven't enjoyed it,
why not write an email to Andy explaining why not?
- Anyway, thanks very much.
Yes, podcast@coy.com.
Keep those emails are coming.
Keep 'em rolling in.
- Keep 'em drumming in.
- Keep 'em drifting in.
- Cheers, bye.
(upbeat music)