[Music]
Hi everyone and welcome to the last episode of Gnosis Like This Fish before Christmas.
We're getting really close to Christmas now so obviously very very much in the last minute
stocking filler area but if you have very odd shaped stockings then maybe you would like to
buy some of our books because probably from some online retailers you'll be able to get them just
in time if you're listening to this on Friday or Saturday so let me remind you what we have.
Andrew Hunter Murray has written a number of novels but his latest one is A Beginner's
Guides to Breaking and Entering. It is a book that shows off everything you love about Andy,
it's very funny, very witty and at the same time has his classic thriller structure as they all do,
all of his books. Dan Schreiber has a book called Impossible Things, it is a children's book and
it is a way to get your children to think like Dan Schreiber. Is that the kind of thing you
want? Well let's be honest it is, he has a unique brain and his books are absolutely amazing and
it really gets kids interested in everything that's going on around them and if you're an
adult which you probably are if you're listening to this then you can get the theory of everything
else which is his adult's version of that book. When I say adult I mean it's for adults not that
it has anything naughty in it, it is complete family friendly fun. Of course Anna and I also
have a book it's called A Load of All Balls, doesn't sound very family friendly does it but it is our
look at the world of sports. If you've got any difficulty buying for relatives but you know
that they like any kind of sport then this is one to get for them because it is a classic
QI thing of all the kind of weird facts that even the biggest sports fan in your family will not know
and actually even if you don't like sports we know that you will like this because there's a
book full of facts and it really gives you an idea of why humans like this thing that a lot of us
really find quite impenetrable. Anyway so that's the books from the three of us get them now they're
the perfect present for any fish fan in your life but don't worry if you can't or don't want to get
those it's absolutely no problem all we really want is that you listen to and enjoy the podcast
which is free and which will always be free so there's nothing more to say I suppose then Merry
Christmas hope you have a great time over the next couple of weeks and on with the podcast
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish a weekly podcast
this week coming to you live from Melbourne
My name is Dan Schreiber I am sitting here with Anna Tyshensky, Andrew Hunter Murray and James
Harkin and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts
from the last seven days and in no particular order here we go starting with fact number one
and that is Anna. My fact this week is that to get a good close-up photo in the early 1900s
your camera had to be 20 feet long which was tough to take in hand luggage we've got a photo of it
up on the screen a black and white photo we do so there's a picture here of the two people who had
to operate this camera who were David and Marion Fairchild I think we mentioned them briefly on
the show before she was Alexander Graham Bell's daughter and this is around 1913 and David really
wanted to take some close-ups of insects he thought they were very very beautiful uh creepy
crawlies and he was annoyed that the only way you could look at them close-up was by killing
them squashing them drying them out and putting them in a book so he was like let's try take some
pictures but in order to get the magnification you need this incredibly long extension tube
or you did when the tech was a little bit simpler and so you've got the lens at one end
which person number one is having to hold and then at the very other end of the camera you
have the person who takes the photo and eventually you get an insect in very high definition well
these insects living can I ask Anna they were not it was actually quite amazing what they did so
yeah so it wasn't I thought at first how lovely he wanted to keep them alive to photograph them
no he just didn't want them dried out so Marianne actually came up because I've already needed an
exposure of 80 seconds yeah which are no insects no matter how well trained is going to sit there
I can't sit there they might be asleep right they might be asleep they might be asleep sorry I've
seen insects stay still for long periods of time but these ones were deceased and the way they did
it was Marianne would cover a block of wood with a layer of candle wax and then she'd put a leaf
on top so it looks like it's in a realistic position because insects hang out on leaves
and then with a little pin made a few holes for each foot of the insect in the leaf
and the feet would stick to the wax underneath and so then it would look like they were naturally
just standing on this leaf right okay there are some other ways of doing it these days if you
have forums of how to photograph insects they come up with ideas one idea is to put them in the
freezer for 20 minutes and that will keep them still but it won't kill them right which is good
another one is if you let's say it's one that doesn't fly if you put it on a table and then put
vapor rub fix vapor rub around it then it won't be able to get out of there and so it'll just stay
in that little I thought you were going to say they're superstitious and they won't step over
it's like summoning a demon that's okay they just slip around and one of the earliest this wasn't
photography but one of the earliest close-up books was Robert Huck's micrographia so that
will have been what 17th century I guess and he drew lots of pictures of tiny insects that he could
see through these new lenses that have been invented and the way that he did it was that he
would give a fly a quarter of a pint of brandy oh no sorry what do you mean give a fly a quarter of
all right lightweight if even Anna is quibbling over the you know I'm not sure I can wouldn't he
would he drop them in it yeah he would put them in it oh no he probably could have gone for a bit
less brandy but maybe yeah the photos by the way that they took so it published in the book called
the book of monsters and they are terrifying and what it really gives you for the first time
anyone really had it was the sort of point of view of say like an ant coming up against a giant
cockroach or a worm and it's terrifying the insect world is it's scary in black and white when it's
big it is they named the camera which is quite nice oh they call it long tom did you guys come
across Frank Percy Smith no okay I was looking up pioneers of insect photography um a crowded field
I think Frank Percy Smith is the other one 1880 to 1945 was his lifespan and he got okay
I'm just going to read out a quote I found Frank Percy Smith got his big break after he was so bored
at his day job that he adopted a pet blue bottle keeping it on a tiny lead and feeding it milk
that's so amazing now do we mean feeding it or submerging it in milk I was just thinking
we were chatting today Anna because I've been playing golf and there's loads of flies everywhere
and you said that a single fly followed you for about 45 minutes when you're walking to the
I didn't know the information about my private life was going to be brought to the table today
yes it was trying to domesticate itself I think it was and you were rejecting its overtures that's
very sad all the way down St Kilda road it's very annoying but he genuinely he had a pet fly
yeah he just had a pet blue bottle on his deck I mean that's I feel like people should be more
staggered about this yeah I mean he had it on a lead and he had a lead anyway how long did it live
sauce does not relate um but he he took close-up photos of the fly drinking its milk in the morning
okay um and he showed it to a film distributor who specialized in insects a guy called Charles Urban
and um this was in the 1900s he was so he was a young man at the time and he he's he would film
amazing footage of a fly juggling uh like a ball or a piece of corn or some twine really big bigger
than it was like much bigger than it was and it turned out the way he had done this okay it's
not great but what he had done was he had glued it upside down to something so his legs were all
sticking in the air and then put a little piece of fluff or whatever on it and it just bats it around
with his legs and it looks very very amusingly like it's juggling um the fly would be dead by now
anyway I think it's important to say that and um wait how was it bashing something around with
his legs if it's dead no no no it was alive at the time yeah he glued it upside down to the thing so
it would at least just saying that it's not offensive because the fly's dead but he will have
hundreds and hundreds of thousands of relatives exactly yeah many of them in tonight but he's
saying they're all waiting for you at the stage door right um but he's this was the little thing
but he said about his work he said I've always endeavored to administer the powder of instruction
in the jam of entertainment what a good motto for is it like the powder is the medicine like giving
your dog some some medicine or whatever I see yeah when he was a child Frank Percy Smith he was so
into nature uh that he lay down on a frozen lake with his head in a hole looking at the things that
were happening underneath the water and his friend found him like that and he'd become frozen to the
ice and had to be freed no really my goodness that's amazing um I've got a thing on early
photography here and I have a little riddle for you and I guess only you as well um which is 1837
the first ever photo is taken it's called boulevard de temple and in it you see the photographer is
looking down over a sort of promenade there's a big road and there's just one human there okay
so that's all you see it's the first photo so far as we know of a human in a photo
however the photo was basically taken during rush hour so there should have been horses there
should have been lots of people why is it just one man vampire's I guess yeah I've got it I've
got it now hang on please guys please let's see if the guy with the microphone can get it first
right the man the man who what did appear in the photo was a scuba diver who was stuck in a tree
and yes so it's because of the exposure exactly took seven minutes to get the exposure done right
he's still living statue he wasn't living statue he was having his shoe polished so he's standing
with one leg up which is clearly having the shoe polished and everyone else all the horses all the
everything that was going the people they just didn't connect with the photo because they weren't
in one spot for so long can I ask the guy who was polishing his shoes was he sort of doing this
you get you get a bit of him he's slightly there so he almost makes it into the first ever photo
of a human but that's it it looks like a desolate area with just one person and it's wow yeah you see
the jam of entertainment was the quiz and the powder of instruction was the information I think
that's what we do it's what we do it's what the largest camera on the planet yeah we're doing a
very long camera here long tom the largest camera on the planet was built in 1900 specifically to
take a photo the largest photo in the world large camera large photo what was it to photograph
oh okay was it a large building it was a large object the galaxy a moving object smaller than
the galaxy okay what was new and sexy and cool in 1900 more or less motor cars a bit older
but moving but moving I think yeah it was the handsomest train on the planet oh was that its
name or a train yeah it was it was blurbed as like this was the the pr around it was this is the
coolest most gorgeous train you'll ever see and it was it was called the Alton Limited built in
Illinois and the big deal was it was symmetrical that apparently I have no idea what previous
trains look like apparently completely like bulging on one side and they fell off the tracks a lot
yeah basically everything was the same length and height in it and that was amazing and they
had to make a single photo plate you know those plates that old photographers have dipped in it
was eight feet wide and four and a half feet tall it was like there was a giant needed to drop it
into the camera and the camera was 20 feet long as well and they got the shot that's very cool that's
awesome yeah love that good shot it's fine that doesn't say much for the handsomest train
here's a little quiz for you there is a thing called the Nikon Small World Photo Micrography
competition and it's a competition where you take photos of very very small things
and whichever is the most beautiful wint okay okay so in 1975 the winner was a photo of oxalic acid
crystals that were magnified 100 times okay so that's 1975 100 times in 2024 how many times
magnified was the winner so it's 100 times in 1975 okay it's either going to be 50 quadrillion or it's
going to be like twice as magnified yeah that's it 102 no um 100 times magnified 1975 yeah i'll say 100
uh i'll say half a million 500 000 times it's in between of the two extremities that you were
going for because it's actually still 100 so it was 100 in 1975 and it was 100 in 2024 and they
haven't been able to improve it since then really and the reason is physics it's just physics these
are not like electron microscopes or scanning tunneling microscopes or these special things that
physicists have these have got to be light photographs and once you get smaller than 100
times magnified the very light itself starts to diffract into each other and you can't see things
really right and even if you push your fingers out was an out was on the screen of your iphone
eventually believe it or not you will reach a limit wow that's so funny that's so it's an
annoying quiz which is why he said it i understand okay here's another early uh former photography
that was experimented with have you guys heard of thoughtography thought yeah thought photography
picturing parts of your brain and working out what people are thinking about from the neural
activity no it's uh it's basically psychic photography you have to stare at what you want
to be appearing on the photo and then gradually it comes onto the photo except it doesn't well tell
that to urie geller who is able to photograph himself with the lens cap on the camera although
for some reason he only takes photos of his forehead i can't work out why that is but um
but that's urie geller's our source is he uh yep oh no switch source cool well how about how about
this one optography octography yeah octo octography okay octo okay um so eight sided photographs
this is no i didn't actually look up the etymology um it's this was something that was actually
practiced in the late 1800s that they thought might be a thing it was when someone if they'd been
murdered you would take a photo of their eyes because they believed that the eyes captured
the final image it ever saw and they would see the murderer sort of like in the in the eye going
or whatever and they would then go that's martin and and fuss it's optography i think with a p right
that would make more sense wouldn't it unless people had eight eyes back then only spy does it
work yeah and it's always either an old woman or a bird that's the culprit i i remember reading
about this and i think so many people believed it that there were murders where they removed the
eyes because they thought the eyes would give them a yeah that's dark murderers dark murderers
it is time for fact number two and that is my fact my fact this week is that
in america there is a secret society called the order of the occult hand whose sole mission
is to sneak a very specific phrase into newspapers and we have no idea what that phrase is
so this is this started back in 1965 an american journalist called joseph flanders put into a
report that he was writing about where there was a murder and these words came up and said
it was as if some occult hand had moved pawn after pawn until they were in the right with
a w i think yeah how does it make sense when it's the other one it doesn't you could have
could have murdered in a newsagents which has moved palm after palm
how did they get the corpse onto the top shelf man found dead in penthouse the other kind of penthouse
so it was as if some occult hand had moved pawn after pawn until they were in the right place
and then tragedy and so that phrase made it in there that uh that little phrase about the occult
hand and he went to the pub and his buddies were giving him crap about this saying what that was
such a funny ridiculous thing and they decided we're going to start a secret society whereas
many journalists are going to try and slip that exact phrasing it was as if some occult hand had
dot dot dot into it and that was good because it was so pretentious yeah exactly it was just
such a ridiculous thing to write and so for 40 odd years it kept appearing in newspapers
and it started to be a thing where editors would find out that people were doing that
and so when it came to a final proofread of the articles that were going out they had to do
an occult hand check to make sure that the phrase hadn't been slipped into it and we only know what
the phrase is because in 2006 it got properly outed so instead of it dismantling they have
a new phrase now and we don't know what that is right so in the newspapers globally there is one
particular phrase that will still be appearing and until we know what that is it's going to be
their secret it's not trump has won the election is it imagine um yeah it is fantastic and newspaper
language is very you know specific about this kind of stuff so obviously the headlines you miss out a
lot of conjunctions and prepositions you miss out anything which slows down the phrase yeah
ideally dog bites man not a dog has bitten a man exactly exactly that and so it's obviously it makes
it spicier and more exciting and draws the reader in which is the whole point but sometimes you get
headlines which don't quite work as a result so there was a headline from 2014 Patrick Stewart
surprises fan with life-threatening illness which what a bastard
i'm afraid you won't live long in prosper
i like there are lots of things that are sort of concealed in newspapers aren't there lots of
kind of within fleet street jokes um often they happen when there's a bit of a disagreement between
the journalists who are writing this stuff and the owners of a newspaper and often those journalists
don't like those owners so in 2001 for instance Stephen Pollard was sacked from the express and
the express had recently been taken over by a guy called Richard Desmond and Pollard's last article
was just a very innocuous commentary on organic farming but the first letters of each sentence
spelled out fuck you Desmond she's very good and i also james may you got do you guys have top gear
james yeah james may of top gear fame in 1992 he was fired from auto car magazine because he
been asked to write 42 pages of like a roundup of the cars of the year and he had to do a little
review of each car and i think he thought this is a very tedious task but it's 42 pages of reviews
so he had to come up with a very long kind of a cross stick so the first letter of each review
spelled out so you think it's really good yeah you should try making the bloody thing up it's a real
pain in the arse wow that's really good we had to read quite a lot of old articles for this and
one of the ones that i get this is a bit non-sequitur but i read this amazing article in the new york
times about the grunge movement in seattle okay this is in 1992 and it had a list of grunge terms
and i just thought i could do a little quiz all right and see if you could say where they are
so in seattle in the 90s early 90s what was a cob nobler cob nobler oh uh shoe shiner shoe shiner
no i didn't really have so many shoe shines in seattle in the early night not for a dime sir
is it what you um is it what you call the little um thing that you stick into the
corner of the cob like it's a little knob oh i see no it's just a word for a loser um okay uh lame
stain lame lame stain sounds like another word for a loser it's another word for a loser uh wax
slacks uh all right james we get it you don't like hanging out with this um the trousers some kind
of yeah all drip jeans and swinging on the flippity flop oh that's just being a cool guy hanging out
it is is it hanging out that is honestly that's that's amazing andy you could have been in early
90s seattle in the grunge scene apart from the fact that they were all made up oh they were made up
by uh people who didn't like the fact that their scene was getting into the national press and so
they did a fake interview where they made up all of these words and it got into the times
and it was years later when they found out that it was that these were all fake and the new york
times dismissed the prank as irritating oh they really care about the this sort of accuracy of
everything they sort of check everything so many times i do think this phrase like what this phrase
might be is interesting yeah because they'll have been smuggling it in they will have been
concealing the powder of instruction in the jam of entertainment yes we might
the way i feel about it yeah yeah this is food for thought isn't it that's what's called purple
pros that's what journalists often refer to so this was a thing it's a style off the back of a
quote of a roman poet hoarse someone would basically patch purple onto their clothing
in order to make them look more rich but it was so badly done it was so obvious and so trying to be
pretentious that you would notice it immediately and for journalists uses purple pros yeah yeah
that's where i was from yeah um we should talk about australian hackery as well okay as australia
is home to you know great newspapers and and a great newspaper family
i'm so glad he's like that no sorry um who was that was that your elizabeth murdoch
um great australian headlines uh the northern territory news i i imagine it's
oh yeah mostly read in the northern territory but you know if you if you if you do subscribe
you will have doubtless been delighted by the 2013 headline why i stuck a cracker up my clacker
which was a first person account by a man who put a firework up his bottom
and it won its writer awokely which i gather is the highest award in australian journalism
is the Aussie Pulitzer as far as i can tell what is i haven't heard of that awokely oh well
so this before was about putting things into newspapers or tricking a newspaper of course
newspapers can trick their readers as well and it often happens on april the first usually quite
irritating i think actually there's someone who fell for the old spaghetti tree
but some of the like some of the worst april fools tricks in 1998 on the first of april in
iraq the newspaper that was owned by saddam hussein's son uday said that president clinton had decided
to lift all sanctions against iraq it was funny if you were there it is mental and then the next
day they had to admit they were joking ah gotcha no good um in 1927 uh princeton their internal
newspaper the daily prinstonian uh they revealed that the university was going to begin admitting
women oh can't believe anyone fell for that one and then in 1864 there was the evening star of
hislington they announced there was going to be a grand exhibition of donkeys at the agricultural
hall yeah and so the next day everyone went to see the donkeys and of course they were the donkeys
themselves oh i thought that's quite a good one that's very good i thought it was going to be that
people all brought their donkeys the next day like a load of donkey keepers would fell for it as well
but it doesn't sound like that happened no if you've got a donkey you probably can't do things
at one day's notice you probably have a plan if someone announces as an exhibition of something
you can't bring your own version if you see there's an art exhibition on make to disagree
make to disagree i frequently frequently take my sketches to the gallery i'd be turned up at cold
play with his guitar the other day no one could tell the difference um uh
it is time for fact number three that is james okay my fact this week is that 18th century king
of sweden gustav the third was into larping mm now so larping um live action roleplay for the
uninitiated but that is where you pretend to be someone from history so what's his excuse because
he's from history yeah but interestingly at the time he was from the present yeah right right it's
like so who was he dressing was he dressing up as someone further back from history can't can't
that's how time works yeah i mean that's like something i should have asked i don't know what
happened there how's a weird glitch uh so this is something i read at the museum of world culture
in gothenberg when we played gothenberg quite recently and he was a king who was really into
the arts and he knew that it would be good for promoting the monarchy and so he started these
festivals where there was loads of jousting tournaments and masquerades and stuff like that
that wasn't new but what was new is that he and his other royals would take part and they would act
out um battles from the past and show how great the monarchy was right and it's not that i made
up but i didn't sex it up by saying larping yeah no how could you um it was that is specifically
what it said in the gothenberg museum that it was larping okay but he didn't call it larping no no
because the initials would be different in swedish wouldn't they yeah that's what he said do we know
who he dressed up as specifically or uh it will have been his former relatives relatives yeah
ancestors his ancestors yeah okay right and this is the really so he was such a thespy king
basically i mean you know royalty is already full of pageantry and flummary and you know we
know you guys love that but um but his love of larp killed him he was uh i mean it really genuinely
did he was he he was at a look out nerds is what are you saying sorry go on he was at a masquerade
ball uh which he was excited about throwing you know everyone was in masks and dressed up and all
that he was in costume he was clearly identifiable as the king because he had a very notable star
medallion on his breast so he was clear who he was uh he had received multiple warnings not to go by
letter saying someone's going to kill you slash we're going to kill you slash don't go oh really
yeah he's at loads he got at the very end of supper just before the ball started he got one
final letter saying someone's going to try and kill you disregarded it went along anyway uh and was
and was was attacked who's delivering the letter like like as in i think it was a spies warning
that i've uncovered some kind of plot everyone's in masks though aren't they so it could have been
anyone yeah that's true except that we know who it was yeah we did well yeah we know who was um killed
for it don't we point a it was Jacob Johan and castrom whoa um we can't it's always the one you
least suspect csi Stockholm 1792 we can't keep making encouraging noises after every fact that
we say yeah that's my thing back off no b the assassination itself was extraordinary i i'm
actually kind of obsessed with Gustav III and i think he's an amazing person if a bit of a weirdo
and one of the things i love is how the assassination went down so it's 1792
and this guy Jacob comes with a cavalry pistol a big pistol and it's loaded with two balls or
bullets uh a bunch of nails 14 assorted scraps of lead and iron and he put the muzzle straight
into Gustav's back it was you know it was point blank pulled the trigger Gustav staggered but
didn't even fall over and the the assassin was so shocked he dropped all of his weapons he had
two guns on him and a knife and he dropped them all and uh Gustav had a hole so big in his back
you could put your whole fist in up to your wrist wow he still lived for two more weeks he did and
he's cool about it he tried to walk to hospital to start with as well and then he was like fuck
and and they got him a chair and he was in Australia, he was in Australia, fuck mate,
put a fist in that
he wasn't to role play but not that much into role play
and then he and then he sat back down on his chair and they carried the chair to where he was
getting medical attention that's one of those things where because it was such a documented
moment you can go visit the masquerade clothes that he's wearing that he was wearing in a museum
and they've still got supposedly the chair which is bloodstained and so on that you can visit as
well as like relics of Gustav and have you heard what he said when he was told who did it oh shit
mate it was in yeah it was that bonza what did he say he he was told who the culprit was because
they caught the assassin and he just said and he's got a fist-sized wrist deep hole in his back at
this point and he just says i don't want to know the names it's only their political plan i should
like to know about some time or other because i'm curious to see whether there was anything sensible
in it wow what a guy well and castrum was publicly flogged his right hand was cut off his head was
removed and his corpse was cut into quarters wow until he apologized and he had two accomplices
who were stripped of their titles and expelled from the country and they were called ribbing and
horn what ribbing ribbing ribbing and horn good no no further questions one more thing on masquerade
bowls really quickly just because we're on the topic there was a moral panic in the uk even about
masquerade bowls in the 18th century because they become really really popular in the upper class
and the bishop of london said that it was a plot devised by the french to neutralize the beauty
of english women okay so it's not the only way those disgusting french people can get any sex in
the uk is by everyone wearing masks yeah it makes sense what are you saying what what what is the
tone of sarcasm that i sense here i think it's an interesting point because i in my single days if
you go to a halloween party right everyone looks so hot but they would be not who they were right
it'd be like wow look at that skeleton she's awesome and and then she took up her outfit you put on a
lot of weight but there was a study that showed that uh people found during the covid pandemic
times that wearing a mask enhanced the hotness of the face people mistake oh really glamour yeah
exactly misty mystery hygiene sanitizer but i genuinely i i scored a date on her at a halloween
party and then we went on the actual date and like unfortunately ironically she was frightened
more on the date yeah when you turned up and i preferred her as a tetris block it was uh which
one the square no she was the l nice yeah um just a little bit more just have the third please
sorry to go sorry i know we're doing dan's dating history but he was incredibly interesting he was
the third swedish monarch to die of being shot in 160 years right apart from his father who
died after eating 14 helpings of sembler buns um just loved loved buns but he he did so many
different i mean he was a despot he he took over and he he rolled government back he was he was
anti-democratic but he banned torture and contributed to culture so he did a lot of self-promotion
and one of the most interesting things he did was he he was engaged at the age of five uh too young
to be married to be sorry here to be married to another five-year-old right oh that's not too
that princess from Denmark yes princess Sophia Magdalena of Denmark and then when they were 20
they got married but he wasn't there so you could do this thing of getting married by proxy yeah in
the old days if you were marrying another ruler then they were busy because they were on a campaign
or something yeah you would just have someone else step in so the bride's half-brother Frederick
played the role of the groom just at the ceremony just sort of in a purely ceremonial function
and only half brother exactly and then she came to Sweden and they properly got married um but they
did have to have a kind of um love tutor as in they they needed to be slightly taught the facts of
life uh because for 10 years they did not consummate the marriage and um they had to have a coach
who was Count Adolf Frederick Munch Alfvölkula who was the that's that sounds like a sexy Dracula
Count Fulkula
I want to suck you up nevermind
but there were rumors that Count Adolf was the father but when they eventually did have a child
and spread by his mom so Perot Gustav's mom Gustav's mom thought he was impotent was like he can't
perform sexually no way did he father that child and spread the rumor where even even in his own
diary Count Adolf unfortunate name said that he was obliged to physically touch and guide them
to the right positions because somewhat mysteriously he said they had both had anatomical problems
which caused some trouble what were they I must know um but yeah the mum was like my son is
bad in bed there's no way he's rather that child I bet it belongs to the count
Gustav the third he gave us the sweet you know the vegetable the sweet
it came from him because he's Swedish what what do you mean when you say gave us
well I'm going to explain but it's literal um so there was a guy called Patrick Miller who
invented a new kind of paddle steamer and he tried to sell it this feels like a start of a very long
story now we have to go back to Patrick Miller
you'll see why he's imported much later
so Patrick Miller I'm on tanto experience even if that one else is he tries to sell
his paddle steamer to Denmark and Denmark said we don't need your paddle steamer
but Denmark was at war with sweden at the time and so Miller went to sweden and said do you want
our paddle steamer and they said yes great we love paddle steamers so he sent the paddle
steamer over to sweden and by the time it got there the war had already finished this is like
grandpa simpson's story does he go to shelbyville with an onion in his pocket it was the fashion
at the time Andy okay so they got this pointless paddle steamer but he was really happy Gustav
and so he sent Patrick Miller a gold snuff box and a painting of the paddle steamer
and a swedish flag and a swede and the swede came with finally
and the um the swede came with some seeds that said plant me and he planted them and from then on
the uk could grow its own swedes right and because they came from sweden we called them swedes
and is anyone still here because i'm not sure
it is our it's time for our final fact and that is
Andy my fact is that some people have tattoos on the inside of their bottoms
um this is really interesting yeah so fashion not fashion the reverse necessity um
is that the reverse of controversial controversial yeah okay this is really interesting there is a
thing called endoscopic tattooing uh and it's colon tattooing so it's tattooing you know right
inside your bottom and the reason is that some people have lesions they have areas of unusual
tissue inside their bottoms and they might become dangerous in future years they're not now but they
need to be monitored you know if they if they change it's like having you know a mole that you're
keeping an eye on just in case it changes or anything yeah so they need to be kept an eye on
and for that they need to be marked and so this this in 2022 the american chemical society launched
a new ink that was going to be used for endoscopic tattooing so that's how i found this fact um
and basically it marks just sort of next to it because you can't mark the area itself but you
mark look here's the size here's the shape here's and there's a kind of whole code language of
what you are showing with this tattoo so that any future doctor can have a look at it and say
ah that's okay it hasn't changed or oh it has we need to might need to do something here so it's
just a brilliant area of do you know how do they get the pen up there like is it how do they do it
it's very hard to draw the dolphin with um i actually don't know i think i think it's like
endoscopes it's not the endoscope yeah it's endoscopes and it's very common and it's and it
serves a few purposes it's you know it's it's sometimes marks a site for surgical removal if
there's something that's been decided has to come out anyway um sometimes it says like here's a place
for follow-up to just check this out we've done some surgery just check it out but it is um it is
very cool i was very surprised to find a reddit thread about it from a surgeon who i guess operates
on areas that might have been previously tattooed to take away certain things and a big thing in this
industry is not tattooing the rectum so you you tattoo further up the colon but rectum don't
need to do it and the reddit thread the headline was please don't tattoo the rectum don't worry
we will find a tumor if it's there the tattoo gets in the way and makes everything hard to see
and dissect please which i was just very surprised that surgeons are using reddit as a way to say to
other surgeons please stop tattooing people's rectum that's so interesting there is i mean
there are people who will have tattoos down there for fashion reasons yeah uh there's a guy called
randy candy uh who will ink you anywhere you want and he'll give you a discount if you choose to do
it on your bum hole uh he's i don't want it yeah but sometimes if you don't have quite so much money
beggars can't be choosers can they andy you want to have i love mum somewhere um he's had he's done
like an enormous spider exiting someone's body oh cool that was extremely cheap he says basically
the weirder it gets the cheaper it becomes did you guys hear uh of the project whole glory in
2016 now whole glory this was it's not as bad as it sounds um there's a tattoo artist called scott
campbell who said anyone who puts their arm through this hole will get a tattoo all right you can't
decide what it's of which oh i see thank god you get no communication you just put and it was in
an art gallery that it happened so you would put your arm through and he was a sort of very famous
and decorated tattoo artist and did he do it like sometimes it was good and sometimes it was bad
that's right some of them were spelt well some of them were just one in five was like swastikas
i don't think i don't think he did that on swastikas um oh yes it's always good to drop them in um
if you were given the chance of having a swastika face tattoo yeah or losing your dominant hand
having it amputated which would you choose um i'm allowed to put a big eye patch on over the
tattoo for example what is it over your eye your whole face your whole face i'm sorry it's the
whole thing i think balaclava i think yeah the mystery that the mystery that dan was talking
about you know who's that guy why why do you think most people would say what did you i don't
even think i've read a study yeah 70 of people would rather have their dominant hand amputated
than have a swastika face tattoo that's fascinating yeah wow and it makes sense and
what a weird thing to cheer but yes yeah yeah it does make sense yeah okay well how about a wrong
tattoo i really like these so there's a this year uh an england football supporter was so
confident about england's chances in the euro's football that he got england euro 2024 winners
and the picture of the cup tattooed on his leg he's called dan thomas he's a data consultant
ironically and he he predicted a win for england in the final he said they're gonna win two one
and he one might remember england lost two one and he said he will get it altered after they
win in 2028 that's good so confident you can always get the word not tattooed above that
i like the person i've read about is probably a mate of this guy but um this is a guy called
tom washington he's from grinsby he got a lifetime ban from the airline jet two as a result of
exposing his pinocchio penis tattoo on the plane and i've seen a photo of it it's actually really
funny so i i don't see what the because he showed he just showed like the top so he didn't he didn't
take out his member what's his name uh what you want me to doubly name him tom washington
yeah yeah i think that's very funny are you lying tom they call him but yeah it's happened
there's an amazing thing so we're talking about medical tattoos basically medical tattoos have
been happening for basically since we've found a properly preserved human so uzi we've mentioned
this before so he was the iceman that was found in the alps yeah exactly and we found tattoos
all over his body and they think that it was almost like acupuncture spots like it was so that
they could spot where he needed to have things done but um all over the world tattoos are used
for similar reasons so there's a tribe in berma called the pakoku and they do a thing where
they're a snake society they play with snakes and they use them for rituals and so on all the time
but they're poisonous snakes and so what they do is they tattoo themselves once a week where they
mix the ink with the venom of the snake and it inoculates them to make sure that if they do get
bitten their body already has it inside so that they're okay and they have to do it as a weekly
ritual to do that so they get tattooed every week because it is mad that our bodies don't destroy
tattoos even you know a tattoo is any foreign object that you inject into your body is bad as
far as your body's concerned and it was quite confusing for a long time that our bodies don't
just get rid of the ink and the reason is much like a lactose intolerant person who loves pizza
the microfages the white blood cells love the taste of tattoo ink but can't digest it so it's so
interesting so if they could digest it well they would literally just eat the ink up you know they'd
be like foreign body inserted into you eat the ink up digest it get rid of it the tattoo would
disappear but they eat the ink and their bodies can't digest it and so it just sits there so when
you're seeing a tattoo you're seeing the stomachs of millions and millions of bacteria with ink inside
them the bacteria with terrible indigestion going how do i get rid of this and then they die and
another bacteria quickly eats the thing that they found in their stomach and it keeps on happening
that amazing that's so cool and makes them even more sexy if anything
the word tattoo comes from Tahitian and we've got it from Captain Cog's first flight so we got it
in English around 1760 1770 and according to the OED the word is onomatopoeic so it comes from the
sound so the tat comes from the tapping of a tattooing instrument into the skin and the ooo comes
from the cry of pain from the person being tattooed brilliant that's amazing that's so good um have
you heard of 3d tattoos no these are brilliant okay these are another medical innovation they're
so good um so i was reading about a woman from the isle of wight who she had to have a hernia
operation and she lost her belly button okay so she felt a bit self-conscious and she decided to
get a 3d tattoo the photos of it are unbelievable i wish i could show you all now i wish i brought a
bit of paper with it printed out because it looks so so realistic isn't there a model with a fake
belly button or not maybe i thought there was a model with no belly button or there's a model
with three belly button no there can't be a model with three belly buttons there's something um but
the recipient said it was so good that her son wanted to sort of put his finger in it because
he couldn't believe it wasn't real it does and it looks unbelievably good i think the thing is
about belly buttons as well is depending on how high or how low they are it can be like a visual
illusion of how long your legs are or how high your torso is so you could deliberately get your
belly button a little bit higher or a little bit maybe not right up there because legs go all the
way up to his nipples so hard because there was that claimed trend wasn't there in somewhere like
china people having belly buttons put on their stomachs higher up yeah that's what we're talking
about yeah unless you have any regrets andy i think you could brought an a4 print out of this belly
button here tonight it wouldn't have made a difference to anyone's lives right good point
another another weird interesting new tattoo that i've never seen before but someone showed us the
other night we went out drinking with one of the old wiggles a couple nights ago sam the former yellow
wiggle and um he's got amazing tattoos he's got a tattoo on one arm which is every country he goes
to whatever is stamped into his passport he gets tattooed onto his arm while he's in the country
so his arm is covered in passport stamps but on his right arm you can't see it it's in uv you get
uv tattoos now which i hadn't heard of but that might be very obvious to a lot of people but yeah
so yeah so you have to go under uv light in order to see it and it comes through um but it's invisible
during the day really awesome so you have to keep going clubbing yeah well he showed me as we were
shooting up heroin in a public toilet and it really pops when you see it but that is it for now
that is all of our facts thank you so much for listening melbourne you've been amazing we will
be back thank you very much for the rest of you we'll see you next week