[Music]
Hi everybody, just a quick announcement before we start this week's show and that is that
we have a special guest on. He's been on once before and he was so good that we decided
we absolutely had to have him back. It's Jamie Morton from My Dad Wrote a Porno. He is the
star. He is the one whose dad actually wrote a porno and we're having him on partly because
he's a brilliant guest and also because it's a very sad time in podcast land because the
final episodes of My Dad Wrote a Porno have just gone out all apart from the very, very
last one which is coming out on the 12th of December and it features an exclusive interview
with for the first time ever Rocky Flintstone himself, the Banksy of Erotica as they call
him. Missed opportunity to call him the Wanksy of Erotica but never mind. Jamie was absolutely
brilliant. This was such a fun episode to record. He is so funny. We think you're going
to love it and so do check out the final My Dad Wrote a Porno episodes and all the other
ones too. All right, on with the show.
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming
to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden. My name is Dan Schreiber. I am sitting here
with Andrew Hunter Murray, James Harkin and special guest is Jamie Morton. And once again,
we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven
days and in a particular order here we go. Starting with fact number one, that is Jamie.
Okay, so my fact this week is this week. I'm not on the show. My fact is Barry Fitzgerald
is the only actor in Oscar history to be nominated twice for the same role in the same film.
Oh, was the film an early version of Mrs. Doubtfire? Best actor and best actress. Yeah,
exactly. No, no. He had one role. It was Father Fitzgibbon in 1944's Going My Way, which did
win Best Picture, actually. Yeah, he was he was nominated for both Best Leading Actor
and Best Supporting Actor. Yeah, yeah, which is insane. It doesn't say much for the rest
of the cast, does it? Exactly. But he won for Best Supporting Actor. So he could have
conceived of the one for both. Yes, but it went to Bing Crosby, who was the lead in the
film in it. Or Co-lead. Hang on to it. One best film, it won Best Actor for Bing Crosby.
Yes. But then Fitzgerald lost Best Actor, but he won Best Supporting Actor. Yes, correct.
That is amazing. I know. What a sweep. Yeah. Do you have to pay entry fees for the Oscar
Oscars? That is a great question, James. Andy. Yeah. Yeah, you do. I imagine you do. You
have to nominate yourself. Yeah, yeah. You have probably an administration fee, like
20 quid or something. 20 quid. Probably. But this movie sort of set a lot of records.
For example, it's the first film to ever have two actors win the Academy Award for Best
Actor and Best Supporting Actor. It was the first movie to get the Academy Award for Directing
and Writing, which was by a guy called Leo McKerry, who wrote and directed it. Oh, so
he won two. He won two at that one. It was the first film to win Beck's picture at the
Academy Awards and the Golden Globes. It was the first picture to win Best Picture and
Best Song. It has all these records as the first movie. No one's seen it. I never heard
of it. Exactly. It seems such a waste. I suppose 1944 we had other things to worry about. Didn't
they hit Europe? Well, it's interesting you should say that because during the war, all
Oscar statues were made of plaster instead of gold or gold plated bronze, which is what
they're actually made of. So he got a a plaster Oscar and he was a massive golf fan was old
Barry Fitzgerald. And he was practicing his golf swing one day and he decapitated his
Oscar. That's a great picture of him with like the head and the body. I was reading a bit
more about this guy, Barry Fitzgerald. Yeah, yeah. Oh, interesting man. Yeah. He was childhood
playmates with the siblings of okay, fine. James Joyce. Okay, not James. No, they thought
he was weird. He was older and they said that he had a beard and glasses and was always
reading books and so didn't play with him. His name Barry Fitzgerald. It's not his real
name is it? And usually you do that because you arrive into the world of the arts and
someone has your name and so you have to register your name right and you change it. But for
him it was because he was trying to hide from the fact that he was sort of doubling on his
work when he was meant to be working in the civil service. So they wouldn't, his name
would be on the bill and they wouldn't know it was him. The worst thing was he worked
in the unemployment department. So they had all of that. Yeah, they had all of the lists
of who was supposed to be working and who wasn't supposed to be working. So all of his mates
would have known that he was. He's a movie star. Oh, this is hard to hide because when
he started, he was doing plays. He worked in the Abbey Theatre with Sharon Yates as
well. So more. Oh, what a milieu. I know. He was once almost kidnapped before the opening
night of a play he was in. By his boss who said you should be working. It was quite a controversial
play and Ireland was very recently out of a civil war. You know, it was a febrile time
and the play had a lot of controversial stuff in it and the Irish Times reported this. It
was in 1926. Several gun boys turned up at Fitzgerald's mum's house. I don't want a
gun boy. A young gunman. I mean, we've got a gun man. That's the thing. Yeah. I think
people who carry guns around between places, maybe like gun runners or young people, maybe
might be. Well, anyway, the gun boys were there at the door and they met his mum and
they said, right, we're here to take him. Just keep him safe until the opening night
is gone. So he won't be able to appear on stage in this play. Right. And she said, well,
he doesn't live here. This is his mum. And I'm not telling you where he is. And so they
had to go away and then he did the play. Wow. Yeah. What polite gun boys. Just because
the gun boys still live at home doesn't mean that everybody's sleeping. They were 12. They're
almost like knocking his barry. Okay, to come out and play, please. Have any of you ever
held an Oscar in real life? Oh my God. I reckon there's an addict out coming out. You haven't
lived boys. And I'll tell you something. I've held two. Same time. Same time. Oh my God.
I went, I was name drop hideous, name drop, but I was at Emma Thompson's house for doing
that. She's not that hideous. No, the name drop. She's lovely. She fed me and everything.
No, but in her downstairs loo, her two Oscars right there. An interesting fact about Emma
Thompson, you might know this, that she's the only person in history to have won Oscars
for writing and acting. Still to this day. What? Yeah. Were they both for, I mean, was
the writing one censored sensibility? Correct. And the acting one. I thought Jane Austen wrote
that. Well, agreed. It was a controversial year. It's like when Kenneth Branagh won the
Oscar for Macbeth or whatever he thought. Best adapted screenplay literally just used
the words. He didn't actually win for that. I was going to come onto that. You mentioned
Kenneth Branagh. You know, they used to be married. What? I did not know that. They
used to be married and he just won an Oscar for writing Belfast at the last Oscars. And
if he were to win an acting Oscar, him and Emma Thompson would be the only people in
history to have acting and writing. And he's been nominated for two acting Oscars. So it's
not beyond the realms of possibility. We sort of parent trap them back together, right?
Well, maybe not. I think she's very happily married to Greg Wise, but you know.
Jeremy, did you take a selfie of yourself in Emma Thompson's toilet? And what he was
holding to Oscars? I mean, what were you taking a selfie with? Well, I didn't, but my friend
did. And then weirdly later on in the evening, somehow, I think we were taking pictures and
like we were like saying, oh, that had dropped me the more ever. And Gaia, Am's daughter,
took his phone and found, honestly, about 50 selfies. She was like, oh, my God, that's
so embarrassing. But I didn't because, you know, too classy. Yeah, wait till you get
your own. Well, I'll be waiting a while. But I'm not sure that Barry Fitzgerald should
have got the Oscar for Best Supporting Actor. Well, for example, there's a little a little
goof in this, which is that so he plays a Catholic priest in this film, but Barry himself
was Protestant. So he wasn't kind of fully aware of how priests act. And in the film,
I haven't seen the film myself, but I didn't deserve the award. They want you. Well, apparently
when he does the crossing of himself, you know, he does it the wrong way, which feels
like as an actor, you would look into the basics and post. Oh, my God, that's possible.
He doesn't do it the wrong way upside down, though. He does it right to left away. He
should be doing it left to right. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I think you meant to do the left to
right. You do top to bottom. I go top to bottom, left to right. That's correct. Yeah. So yeah,
take it back. Take it back. Curiously isn't everything in the arts, Dan. It's an interpretation.
Do you think maybe he was making a comment on Catholicism as in, you know, like the devil
probably would do it that way. Yes, yes, really good call. Oh my God, it's even deeper than
I realized it was. Do you know that it's, this is a bit of a reach, guys, but I found
this and I thought I'd share it. Male actors who have won or been nominated for an Oscar
are statistically more likely to get divorced than their osculous acting peers. Interesting
because because they've just got women throwing themselves at them. Well, because there's
a thing called the negative consequences of positive status shifts. So basically when
you get a bit arrogant because you've just been nominated or won an Oscar, men tend to
leave their wives. Interesting. I could do so much better. And then there was, I remember
years ago reading a book where Dustin Hoffman, struggling actor for years and getting bit
rolls and stuff suddenly gets cast in the graduates. Yeah. And this line being that
when he got the call, he tells his wife and they just stared at each other and there's
an unspoken thing that's happening there, which is this is the end of our marriage.
Bloody hell. Yeah, because he's now going to be, he's going to be globally famous and
obviously he's going to go off and obviously that's obviously in the room to them too. It
was obvious to them too in that moment that that was the end of their marriage.
Gosh. To be fair, this does remind me a little bit of the time. I don't know if you, Dan
and James, remember the time we won our first, uh, Chortle Awards. Yeah, I do remember that.
We all split up when our partners didn't leave immediately. Speaking of Oscars. I keep my
charsal wad in the bathroom, actually, um, which has led to a lot of weird stains on
it, but. I keep one of my wards in the bathroom as well. We won a Webby Award. One of my wards?
One of many. They don't all fit in the cabinet. That's the problem. So mine is next to a,
um, a review that I got in the Sunday times, which called my dad wrote in porno the quote
worst cultural event of the decade. So it's ying and yang in my bathroom. It was in the
Christmas edition of the Sunday times, 2019. It was like a roundup of the decade and some
absolutely poisonous little, little, little, little toad of a journalist. I won't name
him. He knows who he is. Um, he finds a way to worm us into any bad review he ever gives.
This was terrible, but not as bad as my dad wrote in a porno. So he'll be thrilled that
we're ending. Um, yes, I thought it's important to kind of have them both to realize that
neither really matter, do they? Oh, that's very good. That's like, um, Reddy Kipling,
isn't it? If the tribe from the disaster, and you know, you treat them both the same.
It's exactly like that. I'm often called. Um, if you go on IMDB, they have lots of sort
of tagging that you can do and people just go and do it. It's not like an official thing,
but, um, there's loads of different tags and each movie might have 20 different tags. Uh,
someone went through them to see if there's any correlation between these tags and whether
you can win an Oscar or not. Uh, and the apparently there are some keywords that have never been
even nominated for an Oscar. So zombie food fight and breast implant. There has never
been a movie with any of those three things that has ever been nominated for an Oscar.
I don't think that's true. It's the tagging. So it could be that's because I'm pretty sure
that hook has a fantastic food fight. Absolutely not. But it must be something like production
design or song or something. You're saying that my screenplay, my double D undead custard
brawl is not probably not Oscar worthy. Just quickly ask in my double D undead custard
brawl brawl. Sorry. Um, is it the simply the breasts that are undead? It is. It's about
a woman who goes in for a routine operation, a breast enlargement and she gets given the
breasts of a dead person. Ah, yes. Yeah. And it's, and they come to life and they can put
still attached to her and she's alive. Wow. That's weird. You rarely have a zombie attached
to a human who's alive. We don't have a woman on this podcast where we normally do. But
um, is that how breasts implants work? They just take the breasts off another person and
stick them onto you. Is that right? I believe, I believe so. I did need to do the screenplay
is still in the research phase. Russell Crowe has an Oscar. Doesn't he? Russell Crowe has
one for gladiator. Yeah, he's got a few. He's got a best actor. No, he's the only one
wants. But you know where he keeps his, um, Oscar, he doesn't keep them in his bathroom
like, Oh, okay. I haven't been to his house and taken self. Oscar. Okay. Um, what's the
most Russell Crowe place to keep an Oscar? Like his barn or something. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So close. In his chariot, I bet he has the chariot from gladiator. He's got, um, in a
haystack. He's like, it's a needle in a haystack and he keeps it in his haystack. It's like
it's a sort of metaphor. It's like your thing. Yeah. Has he got colosseum? Did he take that
home as a prop? He has a chicken coop and he keeps it in his chicken coop at his ranch
and he claims that it helps his hens to lay bigger eggs. Wow. All the cock crows sadly
leave the chickens. That's the problem. Yeah. Yeah. Rosamund Pike buries her rewards in
the garden. What? Yeah. So weird. She's so bloody goth, Rosamund Pike. She's all classy
and la, la, la. Actually, there's a heart of darkness. She like leaves a little bit
of the top of them to kind of glint in the sun. That's nice. Yeah. I know. It's, it's
kind of interesting, isn't it? And what awards her she won? She's won like a Golden Globe.
She hasn't got a chortle. She hasn't got a chortle. Well, you can't sacrilege to bury
a chortle in the garden. They'll come and dig it up and take it off you. Okay, it is
time for fact number two and that is my fact. My fact this week is that one of the attractions
at Disneyland in 1956 was the bathroom of tomorrow, which included amongst other exciting
exhibits an array of interactive faucets and a dramatic story of valves. Not valves. Yeah.
What a narrative. What a narrative. Ripping. Any Oscars in this bathroom? Oh, God, this
should be right. Except the, well, there's not, but the whole thing is kind of one big
Oscar because it's gold the entire thing. Yeah. The idea was in the fifties, they thought
in the future, everyone will have a gold bathroom. I think so. Basically. Exactly. Only Donald
Trump has managed to make that dream a reality. Yeah. So this was part of an area of Disneyland
that was opened along with the original Disneyland in America called Tomorrowland and Tomorrowland
was going to have lots of exhibits where they could showcase how the world was going to
look in the futuristic future of 1986. And it included things like this bathroom of tomorrow,
whereby air conditioning was going to be in there. There were dumbbells so that you could
do exercise while you're having a bath that were on the side of the bath, you know, all
these sorts of like little innovations, but the whole premise of it, it was done by a
company called the crane company. They were selling it now. So the bathroom of tomorrow
was actually today. And yeah. And so this was one of many of these little exhibitions
that were put on that were slightly sponsored by corporations who wanted to showcase their
related stuff within this area of Disney. Yeah. Very cool. It was designed by Henry
Dreyfuss, who was a designer. Dreyfuss also designed the classic black telephone, you
know, this one that you basically see everywhere. He also invented most of the Hoover models
of vacuum cleaners, the upright ones. And he was also the chair of the meeting of the
International Organization of Standards Committee in Berlin when they kind of came up with
all the different signs that there would be around the world. You know, like if you got
to an airport, the sign for a taxi rank is the same everywhere. Yeah, I love that kind
of stuff. I love those shadowy organizations that, you know, secretly, secretly dealing
with signs. And I did, I went on a mad research bender last year for QI about plug, plug sockets
and standardization of plug sockets. Yeah. Yeah. And are we going to hear fear about
it now? I think for everyone's benefit. That would be the worst cultural events of the
2020s if we did that. I had such an amazing time doing the research. I looked back and
I've written about 20 paragraphs of just dross. So, yeah. This bathroom does have some good
things in it. It had a sink, which you can adjust the height of. You just sort of pull
it up or down. That's clever. Yeah. Accessible. Accessible. And, and if, you know, for kids,
they can pull it right down and, you know, it's there. And it was hydraulic powered.
And I think that's, that's cool. It's a good idea. Yeah. I mean, it totally a huge pain
in the bum to install. But, you know, once it's in, it's in. Exactly. You know, yeah.
Never think about it again. Yeah. And is it still there? No, it shut down after a couple
of years. Yeah. It surprisingly was not as exciting for kids as they, as they probably
thought it was. Well, this isn't just for kids, Dan. It's also for adults. Absolutely true.
Yeah. I have worked for Disney parks and resorts for, have you? Like more than 15 years. I direct
a lot of stuff. Are you in the mouse suit? No, you're not. There is no mouse suit, James.
Oh, sorry. Mickey. Yeah. So I have been to the parks a lot. Wait, wait, wait, but there
is a suit, right? No, he's saying it's just Mickey. It's just new. It's just a new rodent
man running around, genetically modified mouse man. Mickey mouse. That's cool. Yeah, it's
cool. So I have been there a lot, actually. And have you then got access? We've spoken
in the past on the podcast about all these like crazy corridors that you can go. Yeah.
The tunnels underneath what Disney has done all that. I've been in those tunnels. They
are called, what are they called? They're called the Utilidores. All of these tunnels.
And you know, they're actually not a basement. People think they're the basement, but because
it's built in Florida, and it's essentially on a swamp, you can't have basements in Florida.
Okay. So it's all. So everything else is on the first floor? Exactly. Magic Kingdoms
on the first floor. What? Yeah. That's so funny. And if you walk up to Magic Kingdom,
it's on a very, very subtle slope. So you're actually climbing up a full flight of stairs
as you approach Magic Kingdom. That's incredible. That's incredible. Yeah. Wow. But those tunnels
are mad. And there's everything in there. There's like coffee shops. There's like dry cleaners.
Yeah, it's amazing for the staff, exclusive staff. Yeah. And it's good to kind of get
people through the park so that like no character or cast member from one part of the park will
ever be seen in a different part of the park. They'll just go through the tunnels. I imagine
like a race of troglodytes who live under there and have never come to the first floor.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's that. I don't think it would be a great movie. Yeah. Disney
will never make now. From the maker of Double D undead custom brawl comes. This does quickly
on Tomorrowland before he goes to Broad Disney. It does sound absolutely bananas because
all of it was sponsored by one company or another. And there were so the house of the future
itself was actually sponsored by Monsanto, who later became extremely controversial as
one of the makers of Agent Orange. Oh, really? Yeah. So Disney kind of dropped that sponsorship
once. Yeah. Sort of, you know, came out. But all of these different firms. So American
Dairy Association, American Motors, National Lead Paint, who sound great. Wow. Very much
of an era, aren't they? Very mid 20th century. The Dutch Boy Color Gallery was sponsored
by Dutch Boy Paint. Wow. Wow. Can't find much more information about it. Friends with
the gun buys. Yeah. Amazing. And when they opened it, they didn't cut a ribbon, did they?
They just turned some taps on instead of yeah. Yeah. Because it was the house of the future.
Just to show that it's the future. Yeah. What's more of the past than cutting a ribbon? Yeah.
I was told by someone that I worked with over there that this is an it is insane, this fact.
Okay. And I'm not sure if I believe it, but he told me and I and he's very any work. So
yeah, quite senior where though, is he one of the trouble adults? Has he gone nuts? He's
not seen sun in 10 years. Let's just call him Mr Mickey M. No, the boss. No, 4% of all
the photographs taken in the United States are taken at either Disneyland or Disney World.
4%. 4%. It's not insane. It's quite a big country, isn't it? Yeah. States of America.
4% is that's amazing. Mad, right? Yeah. It doesn't. You're right to be skeptical. Yeah.
I was like, is that true? But wow, amazing. And you know, they also isn't just theme parks.
They have cruise ships. Right. Have you been on a Disney cruise? I have. Oh my God. Okay.
I've got so many questions to ask you. Right. Okay. This is amazing. Wow. I've never seen
you so animated. Yeah. Not since we started talking about plugs that time. Okay. I was
reading an article called Disney cruise secrets. Right. And I have to say it was the most disappointing
article I've ever read. Okay. Let me just, I'm just going to tell you a few of the secrets,
right? The Disney cruise secrets. Okay. Okay. Secret number one, Disney cruise state rooms
are not ready until one 30 p.m. Secret. Secret. How's that a secret? I know it's only a secret
when someone rocks up at 1230 and they say, yes, it's ready. Secret number five, you
can bring bottled water on board. Secret number 14, Disney will provide you with soap. Oh,
the soap's so good on the cruises. It's some of the best soap you've ever had in your entire
life. I may have taken it with me. It's really good. Okay. So that is a secret. Yeah. Yeah.
So can you confirm about the rooms are not being ready until one 30 p.m. I actually can't
confirm that because here's the thing with those ships is that you have to get off them
really early because they have a, they're, they're changed over the same day. So everyone's
going to be off the ship by like nine or something. So how long are you on it for? Is it a few
days? You can do two nights. You can do four nights. Dan, you can do a week. I'm now a
travel agent. But so yeah, I guess the turnaround is that they, yeah, so until one 30, that
gives them time to clean all the, all the stator rooms. That must be a chaotic four and a half
hours on board. Just finding out what's left in all the rooms. I mean, that happens in
every hotel in the world. It must be absolutely. But what's fascinating about the Disney cruise
line is that they're the only cruise line on the planet that has fireworks at sea. Okay.
So, yeah. So they have a big deck party normally on the penultimate night and they have fireworks
that set off from the ship. And what's fascinating about these fireworks is that they are made
from a biodegradable material so that when they hit the water, they become fish food.
Oh, that's cool. Isn't that cool? That is really cool. Is it, do you need special dispensation
for fireworks at sea? I think they would be able to. Yeah. Because it might be seen as
a signal. It might look like flares, right? An SOS. Yeah. Wow. They're going very whimsical
with that. They're very extravagant flares. Wow. They're sinking, but they also want to
let them goofy is having a great time. I was once on one of these ships and they have these
rides on board the ship. It's like a slide that goes off the edge. Oh, you know, this
one is like kind of you stand on like a trap door and it opens and you go down a shoot
and stuff. I got all the way up to the top, stood on the trap door and I was too heavy.
But instead of saying, I'm sorry, sir, you're too heavy, they said, I'm so sorry, buddy.
You're just too full of magic today. Too full of magic. I mean, I could see what they were
going for, but it was even more annoying. I was like, just call me a fat bastard to be
honest. That's so funny. So I had to walk all the way down in front of all the children
and their parents. You said to each one, too full of magic. I was like, I forgot something
in my room. Sorry, couldn't get into 130. It was a low point on what was otherwise a
beautiful trip. Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is Andy. My fact is that 5%
of the world's electricity is spent turning big rocks into small rocks. Mad. That is mad.
5%. That is crazy for something that sounds unbelievably dull. I know, but this is this
is big. This is a big business. So what exactly is it? Because I'm I mean, I tried to research
this topic. I failed. I'm not going to lie. I will be a passenger for this podcast. Andy
educate me. I found this in an interview. I was reading an interview with a guy called
John Stanton who specializes in crushing big rocks into small rocks. That's his line of
work. He's a big rock crusher. And basically, when you're mining, you might get some big
rocks out of the ground. But the ore is inside those and you can't just you can't just deal
with the big rock you've got. You need to turn it into a small rock. Yeah, you need a
rock crushing machine. And there are lots of great lots of great models available on the
market. Yeah, can I ask when you say he's a big rock crusher? Is he a big as in like
big in the industry rock crusher? Or is it specifically he's a big rock? I think it's
all for those works on the two levels. I don't know how big he is as a man as well. It could
work on three levels. I don't know. I don't know much magic. It doesn't. I saw that piece
in the times. He's got as much magic as me. Wow. It's called comminution, isn't it? Turning
big rocks into little rocks. Oh man. And then you screen them and then you might grind them
smaller again. Yeah, crushing grinding. Do you know what's better wet grinding or dry grinding?
Oh my God. Because they're both done. I do know. I've got an Instagram. No. I would feel
like, what do you say better? Yeah. Grinding mills can be operated both dry and wet according
to the encyclopedia Britannica. Let's go wet. Yeah. And wet grinding is predominant. Yeah.
Wow. So what is wet grinding you just add? Give me a break. Literally read it directly
from the encyclopedia Britannica. You add water to the crushing. Yeah. I just wonder why it
helps. I guess it's lubricates. Yeah, lubrication. And it helps with like the dust probably. Absolutely.
But when you cut into flagstones and things, it helps have a bit of water to kind of. That's
true. How do you come from? I'm sorry guys have arrived. What can I say? Yeah. But most
of them are like massive nutcrackers basically. They're all top loaded because then the pressure
from the rocks above acts on the rocks that you're trying to crush down and so they're
being forced into two different directions. Right. And you just feed the rock in and the
rock cracks and because the metal surfaces are harder than the rock, that's, you know,
that's the process. And then eventually when it's small enough, it's a dust and you can
get the lithium out or the gold. So hang on. So you're using big rocks as your tool to
crush the former big rock into smaller rock. It's helping. It's a partner. It's actually
a thing called auto genus milling. It's literally just the rocks that you're crushing are all
crushing each other. That's so cool. That's incredible. I love that. I was reading about
the history of crushing rocks. Think too small. And one of us had to. I just want to give
a shout out to the website machinerypartner.com. Okay. Because I'm quoting directly here. It
was event in 1881 when Phyllitus W Gates got a US patent for his device, which was that
was the sort of rock crusher. That was the basic model. Phyllitus. Not a name you hear
often these days, is it? Yeah, Phil Gates. In 1883, Mr Blake challenged Mr Gates to crush
nine cubic yards of stone in a contest to see which crusher would finish the job faster.
The Gates crusher completed the task 40 minutes sooner. I was looking into humans who can
crush rocks. Oh, that's good thing. Because I thought before we had machines, we must have
needed humans. Yeah. Yeah. And then I thought, you know, can anyone do it with their bare
hands? And I actually found the first non-Roman emperor, Maximus Thrax, who was supposedly
a rock crusher. The first non-Roman emperor? Yeah. As in he wasn't born in the Roman Empire.
Yeah, but he was. Sorry, but he was Emperor of Rome. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. And he's a person
who was very tall, but because he was quite a lot taller than most people, the exaggerations
have been written down and it's hard to know where he was. So supposedly, and this was a
Roman emperor, he was eight feet, six inches tall. No. Yeah. Apparently, his, his thumb
was so large that he wore his wife's bracelet as a ring on it. That's how he's gonna hitch
hike in that guy. And so during public events, he used to impress people by picking up rocks
and crushing them with his bare hands and pulling wagons on his own. Yeah. Feels a bit
demeaning for the Emperor of Rome to be having to do like, "Hey!" He had a very short tenure.
It was three years as Emperor because he was overthrown because of his disastrous idea
on war, just by some people, some other people. Yeah, just that's very impressive that they
managed to overthrow. I mean, it's not just him fighting against everyone. He's not like,
"Let's do a thumb war. Anyone can beat me in a thumb war. I will hand over." Oh God, yeah.
But he's telling the gladiators whether or not they've survived or not. There's no mistake
in doing that. It's like a foam hand in a basketball match. So this was a really interesting
topic for me. Yeah. So I have decided to go a little off-piste and discuss The Rock. Did
you know that The Rock's nickname as a kid was Jewy? I bet you didn't. No. Jewy. Jewy.
Was it covered in dew? Yes, exactly. And that's the reason why. Do you know that he has a
degree in criminology? I bet none of you knew that. He's an ordinary minister, guys. He's
an ordinary... Okay, that's more understandable. That makes sense. On Jewy, is it like Huey,
Jewy and Louis kind of thing? Do we know why? Or is it the Jewy decibel system? He's spent
all his time in the library as a kid. I'm going to be honest, these are bullet points.
I haven't really delve deep into it. Do you guys know what the smallest rock is? Here
we go. Back to business. Back to proper rocks, boys. Well, okay. Well, what is a rock? You
know, is a speck of dust a rock? No. Oh, it's not. Is a pebble a rock? Yes, I think it is.
Okay. Is it grit? Is it smaller than grit? You guys are never going to get it. Talc seems
pretty small. Yeah. Yeah. It's clay. Clay. Clay. Oh my God. Clay. Clay. Clay. I'm so
excited. I'm going to have to really sell this coffee. Okay. No, this is really interesting.
Genuinely, this sounds so boring. I appreciate that. You don't need to keep saying that.
Everything in this segment follows that trend. So, which is smaller, sand or clay? We now
know it's clay. It's clay. But you might not have thought that, right? No, no, clay. Like
sand feels so fine. Like, you know, the very fine Caribbean sand, it feels so fine. Okay.
So clay particles are unbelievably tiny. What is clay? Small rocks. It's a sort of little
silica. I think it's a silicate. Okay. But yeah, you never feel it as like sand. It doesn't
fall through your fingers. Yeah. Exactly. Right. But I think you've got clay soils and
stuff like that and there it is in granular form. So particles of clay can be less than
0.002 millimeters across. I think that's two microns possibly. It's unbelievably small.
So the largest particle of clay you can get is not even a thousandth as big as the smallest
particle of sand in the world. That's incredible. That's the scale of difference we're talking
about. I take it all back. And this is the really weird thing. Clay particles can be
so small. I'm quoting directly from a site I read here. Clay particles can be so small
that it could take hundreds of years for them to settle from the top to the bottom of a
bottle of water. What? Because it just takes everything gets in their way. Everything, you
know, the tiny molecule of anything just disrupts the clay from its path. And this is why clay
soil is so sticky is because there are so many spaces in between these tiny, tiny particles.
The water fits in between the particles. So it just holds huge amounts of water. That's
why clay soil is so heavy. Has someone actually done that experiment? No. We've had a plastic
a hundred years ago. Yeah. Well, that's if they started then they would have, they would
have watched it hit the bottom. I'm afraid I don't think anyone's done that experiment
properly, but it just needs sort of. Yeah. And also we're actually banning plastic. Yeah.
We don't want to encourage that. Do we? Sorry. I found a mystery rock. Oh, it's a mystery
rock that grows baby rocks. And it it's very bizarre. So and it's only found so far as
we know in one place in the world, or at least so far as the article claims. And this is
in Romania. And it's in a town called Costesti. And these are called trovant rocks. T R O
V A N T. If you saw the rock one day, and it's raining overnight or whatever, and you come
back the next day, suddenly the rock has grown. It's got like a bulbous new bit of rock that's
on top of it. And they basically secret cement and hardened. So what happens is during rain,
during a heavy shower, they absorb the rain minerals, and then they come into contact
with chemicals that are inside the rock, which then create a pressure reaction, which pushes
out this kind of concrete. And sometimes they become so bulbous that they loosen and they
fall off. And that's the baby rock that's created next to the rock. Other times they
just stick like giant pimples coming out of them. We could utilize it to build things
like build a bridge. You put one of these rocks and then you fire a hose at it and then
shake it. Yes, exactly. Yeah, I think it's true. And some are some are tiny. They can
be really, really tiny or 15 feet high, these rocks. So when the bulbous bits are secreted,
they're like giant rocks. Yeah, two Roman emperors. Yeah, like what? And you just get
it in this one spot in the world so far as we know. Wow. So interesting. Yeah. But did
you know that the rock has a tattoo that took 60 hours to do? So what is it off? Yes.
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show. And that is James. Okay, my fact this
week is that one of the biggest TV events of 1966 involved someone reading extracts from
a book written by a relative known as Rocky Flintstone. What? This is an outrage. This
is insane, James. This is an accusation of plagiarism. Isn't it? Against my father. This
is astonishing. I have never heard this. So I was just reading the old newspaper archives
and I searched for Rocky Flintstone because I thought maybe there was someone with that
actual name who lived in the past. And I couldn't find anyone like that. But there was a big
spike of mentions in 1966. And that was then the final episode of the Flintstones Ed. And
you can still watch this today online. It's an episode where Fred finds an old diary of
his grandfather, Rocky Flintstone. His name was Rock Bottom Flintstone, but he was nicknamed
Rocky. That's an even better name for my dad. And it was about a running with some Stone
Age Nazis and a romantic escape with a character called Mataharok, like who's based on Matahari
this man. So there's a little bit of romance in there as well. Do you know what? That makes
some sort of sense because my dad, my dad recently tried to trademark Rocky Flintstone
because he's an idiot. And he thinks that's going to be able to be done. And he got a letter
back from Warner Brothers basically saying, absolutely not. No circumstances. And actually
you're lucky that we're not suing you for using it up until this point. But you know what?
The parallels here go a bit further than just the name being the same. So my dad wrote a
porno is ending now after six seasons because we're being sued by the Flintstone. And the
final episode of my dad wrote a porno is going to feature for the first time, Rocky
Flintstone himself. That is the first ever appearance of Rocky Flintstone. Someone's
read the press release. So Flintstones, this episode where Rocky Flintstone appears for
the first time is the final episode of season six. Yeah, so it's the exact same scenario
as you. That's so what this is. So did you have any idea that your dad, I mean, has your
dad seen the episode of the Flintstones? No. Did you sort of see it and then forget all
about it and then years later? No, because he would have been, I think it's just an
awesome name and the coincidence. Yeah, well, he was he named himself the Rocky after a
dog in Brazil, which we don't need to go to. But the Flintstone bit was because he really
relates to, you know, in the title sequence, yeah, when he gets locked out the house, he
gets like back to the talk. Yes. Yeah, that's very much like my parents. So I think that
that's where he was inspired from. But that is mad that is actually a character and the
grandfather of Fred, you said. Yeah, that's right. Yeah. So one generation difference,
but closer. And I watched a bit of the episode in it. It's going from Fred reading out loud
to his wife and Barney, his friends. So it's a similar thing. Extracts of the diary out
loud while they then cut to the scenes itself. I think there's something of Alice in Wilma
as well. Is it there? What do you not say? Yeah. Redhead. Yeah. I mean, I'm not sure
how I feel about this. That makes me think my whole career has been a lie. But obviously
the Flintstones was massive and the 60s was absolutely enormous. And so the end of the
Flintstones was watched by, I don't know how many people I couldn't, they didn't have the
actual figures, but it was like 30% of the TV watching. Wow. Yeah. And it was the end
of the original series because obviously it's gone on and on and so on. But we're going
to talk about the Flintstones movies later on. Don't you worry. I bloody hope so. Iconic
bits of cinema. But the Flintstones, the cartoon, I didn't realise, was also originally aimed
at adults just as much as children. Yeah. All cast late in late evening. Primetime show,
8.30pm. Yeah. And I really liked the fact it was originally called the Flagstones. And
then the Gladstones. Yeah. And then the Flintstones, they finally hit on that as a, because those
two both sounds so weird. Yeah. A comedy called the Flagstones. Have you seen the pilot of
the Flagstones? No. No. I actually watched it. All 90 seconds of it. 90 seconds. And
it was, it was good. It's amazing that it got picked up. Are you saying it is good or
is it? It is good. It is good. But it doesn't have the magic of the Flintstones. Was it the
same characters as well? Yeah. Okay. Right. Yeah. But it was made in 1959 but never aired
until 1994 when it was discovered. Okay. Right. We should watch it. It's interesting
to see. 1994 is the year that the Flintstones movie came out. No. Yeah. So anyway, in the
original series, one of the things that to appeal to adults as well that they did, I'm
pushing on, is they would have celebrity guests that would come on or they would parody celebrities
of the day in order to give some comic, as you would say, for the adult sort of recognition.
So quick quiz, because they loved a pun. They absolutely loved a pun. Okay. Cary Grant is
a character. What has he been renamed? Clay Grant. Oh, that's good. Cary Granite. Yes.
1-0. Tony Curtis, who voiced himself is on. What is he called? Boney Curtis because they
were in there. That's good. Yeah. No. Close. You're in the right area of the name. Stony
Curtis. Yeah. Keep going. They're one of these. Yeah. There's Rock Hudson. Amazingly. Yeah.
It's Rock Hudson stone. Oh my God. And Halle Berry in the movie, the Flintstones. I don't
know if you're keen to talk about that. She was actually directly named after a famous
female celebrity. Halle Beryl. No. So, no. So you've got to step away from Halle's name
all together. Shelly Berry. No. No. What? Hallite Berry. No. Her name is nothing to do with
it. Right. It's another famous actress. The character's name. Yeah. The character's name
is actress. Yeah. Named after another famous actress. Shelly's The Rock. No. So there's
no pun. It's just outright her name. Sharon Stone. Yeah. There we go. And she's called
Sharon Stone in the movie. Halle Berry is called Sharon Stone in the movie. But that's enough
on the movie. Let's get back to the TV series. Well, just lots of, I really find it interesting
that the sort of adult elements of it, because I did not, I never watched the Flintstones
really. Really? Yeah. Just not referring to me with it. I guess so. But it's, they, they,
they were sponsored by cigarettes in the original days, which Winston Andy, how many times did
I have to tell you? Jesus. Anyway, they were sponsored by this film, Winston Cigarettes.
Was that when it was going out to children? It feels like that was when it was being shot.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Even then it was good. Well, yeah, because advertising was just different
back then. They were advertising to adults. They weren't, they weren't kids smoking. Have
you seen that as well? I actually watched that. Yeah. It isn't the smoking that got me. It's
the outrageous misogyny of those two men. Oh, really? It is insane. Like Barley and Fred
are just like watching their wives do loads of chores and housework. And then they're
like, let's go around the back and they sneak off and they just like, oh, like reclining and
just smoking and just chatting and watching their wives work. Right. They are cavemen,
but it is literally. There's a theory that the Flintstones are from the future, which
I quite like. That's the Jetsons. Well, they do meet the Jetsons at one stage, don't they?
So that's part of the theory. Okay. One theory is because they have four fingers. Obviously,
we have five fingers in this time. So perhaps the little finger has sort of vestigially disappeared
because you don't need it anymore because, you know, what do you use your little finger
for? You're right. And we never had four fingers. So that has to be an evolution. Yeah. They,
the animals in the Flintstones can speak. Obviously, these days, animals can't speak
and never in the past, as far as we know, have animals been able to speak. Yes. So perhaps
in the future, they will be able to speak. Humans coexisting with dinosaurs never happened
in the past. So Jurassic Park. Is it a sequel to Jurassic Park? The theory is that it's
a post-apocalyptic future where all current technology has collapsed. They're trying
to replicate it using the mutant dinosaurs. My theory is that they listened to this podcast
and rocks became so popular because of the last section that we just did away with all
of the technology and people lived in a rock-based society. Yeah, I'd live there. I'd move. Wow.
Did you guys see the Flintstones kids just say no holiday special? I missed that one.
This was something that went out in 1988 and it was a public service say no to drugs Flintstones
episode. Brilliant. Oh man. Can I tell you the plot? Yes, please. So the Flintstones kids,
it's like young Flintstones. It's just bam, bam and pebbles. No, it's not. It's actually
the main generation we know, but they're trying to win tickets to a Michael Jackson
concert who in this is called Michael Jackstone. Thank you. Exactly. And Wilma is tempted to
join up with a gang of older kids whose leader, Stony, smokes, crack marijuana. Unfortunately.
You're right. They should have gone with it. And then we'll talk to her parents and they
tell her that a real friend wouldn't offer you drugs. And Stony is arrested for drug usage
and ends with a version of Michael Jackstone's song beat it. And the episode also features
Nancy Reagan as herself. Does she have a funny name? I think she might have been doing a
kind of extra like hi everybody, you know, rather than Nancy Reagan. Yeah, that is a
really hot. That's probably why she never made it onto the Flintstones. Can we talk a little
bit about the movie? Oh, go on. Okay. Well, this is kind of tangential. It's not really
about the movies, even though it is the B 52s. Oh, yes, the band. Yes. Love Jack of
love Jack Fane. Yeah. What a tune. They recorded versions of meet the Flintstones and the bedrock
twitch, which I'm sure you've got that record. Did you? The B 52s are they did change their
name? They changed their name to the BC 52. And they even appeared on the top 40 chart
as the BC 52. That's great. Everyone got on board. I really want to see both the Flintstones
film and the Flintstones film sequel, Viva Rock Vegas. Yeah. So you've seen both. Of course.
Yeah. I just mentioned to my wife that we were recording this. I've seen that. How they
buried tries to have sex with John Goodman in the film. And it's quite, it's quite a
sort of saucy plot where John Goodman is Fred Flintstone because he's incredibly eminent
as an actor now and seeing him in 1994 playing Fred Flintstone is very funny. But he looked
so like Fred Flintstone. It's amazing to have to say yes. Is it not a good film? It's, it's
quite like his cult film. It was commercially successful. But afterwards, the entire cast
refused to return for the sequel, which is why prequel Viva Rock Vegas was recast entirely.
Nobody the same. Yeah. Because the first of its own movie is Elizabeth Taylor's last
ever film, which is really terrible. The casting is amazing. What a way to go out. It's got
Rick Moranis. It's got Elizabeth Taylor. They clearly thought they had something. One thing
I read was that Rick Moranis basically quit acting after this movie because they realized
that they were using him. He peaked. I personally, I think I'd read that he had, he had family
issues, which meant he had to step back from acting. But the thing claims that he was just
like, I can't be put in any more movies like this. Rick Moranis, like a Moranis, like a,
it's like Scree that you get on top of a mountain. Very nice. Because Rock Moranis was
right there. He needs the puns you need explaining for. That's his puns. Glass was banished from
the entire set of the Flintstones. What was it? He guesses why. No glass in the future.
In the future, there's no glass. That's correct. Was it that though? Because I know that in,
is it in Downton Abbey, you're not allowed to wear Calvin Klein underwear. Because even
though it's not on show, they think maybe your sackcloth or whatever it is they wear
in it might ride up and they might see it. So your sackcloth? Do you think it's set like
in the 14th century with peasants and things? It's not, it's not. But you can see, you can
see there are lots of, it's an Abbey. I thought it was about monks. There are lots of probably
quite sheer and slinky gowns and outfits and maybe if you're wearing modern. You can't
wear modern underwear basically, even though it's not going to be on show. Is it similar?
It's not that. No. Glass ban from set. I think Jamie, you're the only one who hasn't
slung it again. James has got quite a good one. Darren's no glass in the future. There's
a wide range of plausibility. I forgot again that we talk about the Flintstones. The Flintstones
movie. They're worried that, because there was so much rock on set. No shoes. No one's
wearing shoes. Oh, no one's wearing shoes. The entire cast are filming barefoot. That's
clever. And so, really, kind of any glass on set. Yeah. Well done, Daphne. That is good.
There was the actor in the original series, Miss Jean Vanda Ply, or PIL, PYL is her surname,
and she was the voice of Wilma. And she gave an interview in 1995 where she explained that
they were basically for the amazing amount of money that this made, because it was syndicated
around the world. I mean, there was just so much money being made. She only received $250
an episode. And then she did a contract that said the residual payments from syndication.
She did a one-off payment of $15,000. And that was it that she got. And she was a great
voice. She did a lot of voices in the Jetsons as well. And she did, I think, as well as
doing Wilma. She did pebbles in that show. She was Rosie in the Jetsons. Rosie. She was
the maid. Yeah, Rosie. Yeah, it's so incredible. Oh, that's awful. Yeah. And so, yeah, she said,
"If I got residuals, I wouldn't be living in Sam Clement. I'd own Sam Clement." Yeah.
So, well, she should have a better agent, frankly. Exactly. Don't be glad yourself.
Okay, that's it. That's all of our facts. Thank you so much for listening. If you'd
like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said on this podcast,
you can find us all on our Twitter accounts. I'm on @SribelandAndy. @AndyHunterM. James.
Hi, James Harkin. And Jamie. @UncleEagle. Don't ask. Okay. That's the whole thing. Yeah,
or you can get us on our group account, which is @NoSuchThing or our website, NoSuchThing,
as a fish.com. Check out all of our previous episodes. They are up there now. You can also
buy the new merch that we've released. It's a bunch of t-shirts and pin badges and so on.
And also, you can get access to Club Fish, the private member club. Jamie, you can listen
to the final episodes of My Dad Wrote a Porno, which are going out in December. These are
the final episodes, one including Jamie's dad, Rocky Flintstone, for the first time ever.
No one's ever heard his voice before. Well, you have to. I know your dad, but yeah. And
it's a good voice, so I'm very excited to hear it. But on behalf of the podcasting world,
we're very sad to see you guys go. So we're now... We're delighted. Well, I mean, financially...
About lifters, all right. Fine. Fish live on forever, don't we? Anyway, we're gonna miss
you guys. But we hope to see you coming back for reunions. Anyway, that's it. That's all of our
facts. We'll be back again next week with another episode. We'll see you then. Goodbye.
Oh, my God, I just broke it.
What's that?
I didn't see there was one behind it. Oh, my God.
Oh, no. You know when, like, people win awards, and I wish I could break it in a hair and give
it to the other nominees. I'm really sorry. I was practicing my golf swing earlier.
You.
[BLANK_AUDIO]