Hi everybody, Andy here. Just wanted to let you know there are some exciting times going on here at Club Fish.
We have launched two new tears. So for everyone who is already a member, you will keep getting droppers of line except now you're going to get it every fortnight and if you join at the top two tears, plenty more fish or friend of the podcast, you are going to get the thing you're about to see a filmed version of droppers of line, you can see us crying with laughter as we respond to your emails. It's so much fun.
So we're going to show you one that we recorded a couple of weeks ago. We hope you really like it. If you would like to check out the other things available, there are so many from the ad free to the quarterly quizzes to the shoutout on the show. There is so much stuff happening.
So check out what you can get at every single tear. It's so much fun and in the meantime we hope you enjoy this filmed droppers of line. On with the show.
Hello Andy, welcome to droppers of line. This is already in feedback and let's not pretend we're not filming hello to you at home or wherever you are.
The people who are listening might be at home as well. And if you're listening at home, but not able to see the film version of this, let's paint a picture.
There are three of us here. Yep, because someone is now missing. The last droppers of line had one extra fish. Yeah, she's gone. She's gone only for nine months. She'll be back. Yeah, yeah. Hope so. She might look very different.
She might look like a white middle middle age man. Another different name. But she'll be back in spirit. She will be back. Yeah, she's having a great time. She. Yeah. I haven't kept in touch.
That's it. I've been trying to observe the rules about employment law. I don't think you're allowed to contact people when they're on maternity leave. Well, I messaged her as a friend. Yeah. That's where I went.
And if you're listening with us, which I know you're not. It's crazy. All right, welcome to droppers. This is an audience feedback segment. The inbox.
It's been absolutely bursting. Bulging. Oh, come on. Bulging. Overflowing. Really? Yeah, it's been big. It's been a big month. We've got a lot to get through. Let's stop fanning about and let's go on with it. Let's go on. All right.
Number one fact of the week. New segment that I've introduced. Great. From Andrew C long time fan and recent clubfish member. So hello, Andrew. I have my first fish fact in South Carolina. North is 90 miles southeast of due west.
So north is the name of the town. Yep. And due west is another town. And I suppose that that means that due west is 90 miles north west of north. Right.
Do we have any details about these places? Nothing. Because north might just be named after Lord North. The Prime Minister. He doesn't specify, but I can't imagine it isn't.
Yeah, no, that's just that's just a terrific fact. We don't know anything else about it. I'm afraid not the context is pretty slim here. These places don't sound like they're massive. I will say that. Yeah.
I always love going on the Wikipedia pages of these places because the notable people there's always just one person who is like the biggest basketball player, you know, in the world or it's it's always really fun. Unincorporated. I'm guessing these towns.
Again, Michael Jordan. It's from all those places. Well, Michael Jordan played for North Carolina. Where are we talking South Carolina? So close. So close. One long throw away.
Anyway, Andrew, thank you. That's just a great fact. Yeah, it's a really good fact. I feel like we're off the blocks. But now we're also on the hook section two is get yourself off the hook. I'm numbering the sections this month. Okay.
Which of us is on the hook? Well, great news. It's Anna.
Dear Anna, I heard you say on the podcast that Singapore is the only country that sells other flavors of yakult. Oh, no. I've got terrible news for one member of the team. I was me who said that.
Oh, really? That's very honest. I know some people watching this. I'll listen to this word of no. And if I'd have kept some, it would have put me in a bad light. So it's tactical honesty in a way. Yeah, fair enough. You've been thought your hands been forced.
Well, James apparently supermarkets across the channel do do to and then Bart has sent an image of some yakult plus pair zik smak from the. I can only assume the Netherlands.
Okay. Yeah. It's just a new N E U W which suggests that it hasn't always been there. That's a good point. I think you're off the hook.
Easy. What a great detective. You just got given one bit of evidence. So you're you columbod it. That's one more question. That was great. Vince writes fun fact. The only advert not to offer a discount on no such thing.
So we're an ad land now. I'm afraid. Okay. Has been the BBC TV license advert. Is that true? Why? Where is the fish discount? No, that's not that's not true. It's not true. Airbnb. We don't do a discount for it.
We've done some charity ones which are sort of, you know, horrible disease or something and then like you can't give a discount on that. So quite rightly. Quite rightly.
You can get discount of course on your TV license if you go black and white. Can you still believe there is still one or two holdouts? Can you still get a half price?
I believe there is still one or two people in the country that have every now and then you get a news article don't you that says there are still 37 people with black and white TV licenses.
That's brilliant as half price isn't it? Whenever the TV licensing guy comes round they turn down the color on my TV.
I saw a I saw a fact just yesterday which was you know the scene in the Wizard of Oz where it goes from black and white and then she opens the door in its color.
So there is this little video that suggests I want to say it's total fact by just saw this the other day that the black and white they painted the inside of the room seepia as it were.
And they did that to Dorothy as well. So they put her in clothing which was matching the color and they did up her face to match the color.
So the idea is that they filmed it in color but they made it seem as if it was in. So when she opens the door they use a stunt double as the door opens of the background of her and then Dorothy who's in her normal clothing walks into the color.
So it's not it's not a jump between black and white and color the whole thing is in color.
That's really that's a really if you go back and watch the clip again it's pretty remarkable if that's the case yeah if that's the case.
Did you say yeah as I said I saw a video on it yesterday but I didn't think this would come up I haven't checked it to verify it I believe it.
Kicking for me oh yeah Kyla Jemisin writes about I don't know if you remember we mentioned a lake in Canada called like mini wanker.
Oh yeah we did and you said that it would be where Tom Cruise went or something something like something really unkind like that and I'm sorry Tom if you're watching.
And he probably is watching watches yeah he gets this footage even though even if we don't release it he'll get it.
Do you know what I mean it's being live stream like he's got full he's got power yeah anyway it's pronounced mini wanker.
Oh I will you won't go yeah mini wanker is chopped up factory.
There you go very nice yep source I used to live near it it's lovely says Kyla so thank you for that.
Yeah I'm just going to say that this podcast does have a history of mispronouncing things to come if it's correct and if you don't like that listen to it.
Yeah we used to apologize didn't we not anymore.
When I do yeah she gets about a night about it but if she's not here then yeah yeah.
So for the next nine months we're off the blocks.
This is just a thing we said slightly wrong but it's from Josh McDonald from Atlanta judge.
Anyway we this is a very recent episode we talked about quantum baseball.
That was the reason the episode no such thing as quantum baseball.
So what happened was there was a question about how did one player play for two teams in the same match.
And you suggested it might have been a quantum effect and actually the game was postponed halfway through and the guy was transferred.
That's right exactly right well in the course of that episode we also did a large bit about Sumo wrestling.
Oh yeah is that it?
So there's no reason for me to go into that.
But you were so fluent when you said it I thought well I can't I don't want to.
So the thing about Sumo wrestling I could go through the whole thing but it was about them being on bicycles I think.
Yes but Josh says during the episode you're referred to the wrestlers as Sumo's multiple times.
But actually that would be like calling a dance player a dart or a football at a football.
Yeah they're your casinos are they?
He says Rikishi Rikishi there we go.
Rikishi and you know it was something to do with wrestling.
Yes there was a wrestler that went under that name in the 90s dance eyes light up the bloodline.
Well it's interesting because Rikishi is related to Yokozuna who you just mentioned is another thing.
And the current crop of the biggest stars in WWE are the son of Rikishi.
So they're the son of what?
Jay Uso is the son of the wrestler Rikishi who's one of the biggest wrestlers Jimmy Uso is one of the biggest wrestlers.
It's not that every single wrestler in WWE are all sons of this one.
No it'd be crazy but there's a compelling storyline dominant bloodline.
We like succession but with being thrown through tables.
Yeah it kind of is.
Well Josh has a fun fact because of all the breathing exercises that the Sumo wrestlers do for training.
Quite a few of them are excellent singers and he attaches a video of the now retired Kokozuna Kakuru singing Frank Sinatra's My Way.
Lovely.
He's got the chops.
It feels like My Way might be the name of a person in Japan or China.
My Way, My Way, My Way Way would have been a good show.
Yes that's a good show.
That's a good end if he's looking for a fringe.
A number of fringe show.
Absolutely.
I think he is.
Yeah.
All right we now come to the arm actualies.
Okay, section three I think.
Yes we're in section three.
And the previous one was get yourself off the hook.
So that was like you're in trouble and this is just his extra stuff.
Can I just say this is terrible for the edit that you're putting everything in an order and you keep referencing the order of things.
We can't move anything around.
I want, I want you not to.
I want to ruin things.
I'm in tricks to mode.
This is dark Andy you're seeing now.
Yeah.
Actually also my bottle of water that's on the table considering we're filming.
That would jump up and down as well wouldn't it?
It would do.
If I drink too much and then we go back in time.
Yes.
We're in continuity towers.
The sun's going to go down at some point and that will present a problem.
So.
Well we'll get through it.
Andrea Gilby.
Oh yeah.
No we really missed it.
We dropped a great opportunity.
We missed it rather.
In one of the Edinburgh shows there was Nish Kumar talking about Jimmy Hendrix.
I just listened to the latest episode and re-nicious story about Jimmy Hendrix and the monkeys.
They toured together.
Jimmy Hendrix opened for the monkeys.
Yeah.
I don't know why.
There's a coronation street connection between them too.
Oh really.
So Jimmy Hendrix loves coronation street.
Yeah.
David Jones played the grandson of Ena Sharples in Coronation Street.
Wow.
So Jimmy Hendrix sort of seen Davey from the monkeys on TV.
And then potentially if it was in the right.
Oh yeah.
He actually didn't miss that day's episode or anything.
He played the who?
The grandson of Ena Sharples.
Okay.
When he was really young.
It sounds like he was young because it was before he moved to the USA to play the artful Dodger in Oliver.
So he can't have been like unless he was watching reruns.
Unless he was playing an old Dodger.
We've decided to re-imagine the role of Dodger.
A cast of a 45 year old man.
No, it sounds like, no, maybe Hendrix wasn't into Coronation Street at that point.
Anyway.
We've had a fun audience message from Luke Delaney who was in Kev Lovic International Airport in Iceland.
Okay.
And as Anna mentioned, Jimmy Hendrix is phallic cast where he got his thing cast in plaster.
And it's in the phallological museum in Reykjavik.
And an advert came up for the Iceland penis museum on the screen above the carousel,
the baggage carousel, while Luke was waiting to get his bags.
And then he went fishing while listening to no such thing as a fish.
That's good.
Did he go to the museum?
He didn't because he was too busy fishing.
But he said...
It's a small museum.
What was he called?
Andrew.
Luke.
Honestly, you could do it in half an hour, Luke.
But Luke was too busy catching this salmon.
Very cool.
A biggie, which he then did release and it went on its way, while listening to fish.
Right.
So if you've got photos of you doing something extreme while listening to a podcast, like...
Yeah.
...fishing...
...and the...
...drops the line.
I wonder how the owners of a phallic museum feel when someone calls it small.
You'll hear in the winter.
There is because we're sometimes called QILs.
If you go to the phallological museum,
you also have displays of fictional characters on what their penises are like.
What?
And it has elf, and then it says penis-sized, presumably small.
Wow.
And they have a golf putter in the shape of a penis, which I used.
So you get to take it down and hit a ball?
Yeah.
It was just on...
You could just pick it up and knock a golf ball.
There's no one of the precious display.
It's sort of what...
Sometimes museums are like, you know, they have interactive stuff.
Exactly.
Does the ball look like a testicle?
No, it's just like a golf ball.
Actually, don't know what a testicle would look like.
Mine look like golf balls.
We do that.
Golf balls is a condition like tennis elbow, isn't it?
Let's have some spicy meat.
All right.
Let's do it.
Steve McCabe.
How many of these have we done, Andy?
Would you say, drop us a line?
36.
I'm still not sure what spicy meat is.
It's like...
I don't need to explain it.
Steve says...
What section are we in now?
I don't know what number it's section four.
Okay.
For the edit.
Not sure how, or indeed, if you could use this one,
but it feels too good to not share.
Apparently, as your spicy meat, it's sort of gossip.
You know, all behind the curtain stuff with the three of...
four of us.
Apparently, in the folklore of the Latter-day Saints,
brackets, Mormons, Bigfoot,
is identified as Cain, the son of Adam and Eve in the Bible.
Just Google Cain Bigfoot and Mormons.
It's a great rabbit warring to go down.
And that was just because it's down-relevant.
I thought...
It's not very spicy that meat, to be honest,
but I thought you might know about that already.
It's ringing a very, very, very distant bell.
Cool.
Cool, anyway.
Question about Bigfoot?
Yeah.
Are they an individual?
Or are they a species?
Species.
In that case, if Cain is a Bigfoot, presumably able,
his brother is also a Bigfoot.
Yeah.
Which makes Adam and Eve Bigfoot.
Wow, this is actually...
Like, we're all...
So we're all Bigfoot, is what I'm saying.
We're all Bigfoot.
Oh, that's a nice theory.
Mystery solved.
This detective work that James is doing in the show is wild.
Liz May, this is stunning.
This is a dance-centric, potential identity theft.
He may need to consult a lawyer.
God.
All right.
No, no, no.
You've been ripped off.
Have I?
Is there a headline?
You could morph seed.
No.
Dan, you could get potentially hundreds of thousands
in compensation.
Okay.
There's a Japanese anime where one of the main characters
has wavy dark hair.
Okay.
I'm sorry, but in Japanese anime, I imagine a lot of the characters
have wavy dark hair.
It's common.
Glasses.
And an obsession with all things cryptid.
In the second season, he fights a Mongolian death worm.
Oh.
Okay.
Here comes the coup de grace.
The show is called Dan, Dad, Dan.
Oh, Dan, the Dan.
I've seen that shit.
Yeah.
I've not watched it all the way through by seen clips of it.
Oh, okay.
Is that a fair?
Like, is it?
I guess so.
I didn't see it before, but yeah, I see that now.
Who stole it from home?
Do you think I modeled myself of a Japanese anime?
It's possible.
We've always had questions.
Whenever my son is in a touristy area, my youngest kid,
if there is a group that are from Japan,
they all respond to his look, because he has very curly wild hair,
as if they point.
They don't point to any of our other kids,
and they don't see them.
And they kind of go, oh, and it suggests that he looks exactly
like an anime that's over there.
And I haven't been able to find.
Ooh.
So maybe my whole family.
Yeah, I don't know.
I don't know.
For instance, my daughter got a similar thing when we were in Sicily,
but I think it's because she's very blonde and very fair-skinned,
and it's kind of different to the people in Sicily.
And so they really like blonde kids.
Right.
Do you know what I mean?
Yeah.
Because it's an unusual.
I think so.
Or maybe she's part of a Sicilian anime.
Yeah.
Maybe she looks exactly like one of the heads of the Camaro crime family.
That's it.
They all fled in fear.
Yeah.
But ever she walked out the street.
Little Bella was here.
Little Bella.
She, she looked like Molly Brando.
Yeah.
She talks like him.
Ooh.
Hit.
Now this is pretty spicy meat.
Cam Tocos.
Right.
Hello from Kansas City, Missouri.
Oh.
Hello.
So global to show with a very heavy accentuation towards the USA.
My name is Cam and I have a very fun fact to share about Dan's book,
The Theory of Everything Else.
Okay.
Dan, a copy of your book is currently doing a submarine tour at brackets,
classified location, many, many miles underwater.
What?
My younger brother is currently working on a submarine
where he is heavily restricted on what he can carry on.
About an hour ago, my mom informed me that she sent him your book
in his latest care package.
Like, it's a bit lightweight, isn't it?
I can't really put any of under the adjacent,
because there's such effey tones.
That's thick.
What you need to write is a 30-page.
Oh, that's amazing.
That's incredible.
And it's got a good review.
My brother wrote to her from underwater saying he enjoyed the read.
Oh, cool.
That's incredible.
Thank you for sending that in.
Now, this was a bit I wasn't in,
but it was in one of the Edinburgh episodes.
Gonzalo writes, we don't know where from.
In fact, number two, about pigs on trial.
Dan mentioned how in China, some farms created pig toilets.
Now, can you just remind the listener?
My memory of it is that the idea is that you would make an outdoor toilet.
And when you flush it, the flush takes it directly into a trough,
which becomes part of the food.
It's not so much a flush as a long drop.
As a long drop.
OK, if you're of a sensitive disposition, you might want to just click forward by 90 seconds.
OK.
This made me remember a story that the father of one of my exes told me.
He was temporarily moving to a province in the Andes in Peru and got invited to a farmhouse for dining.
After dining, he did ask for the bathroom and got pointed to its location, far from the house.
The toilet itself was just a block of wood with a hole in the middle.
He didn't think much of it, since it was something common in the area.
But as he was finishing, he felt something moist from below.
He stood up in a hurry and saw a pig looking back at him from the hole in the wood.
He then noticed a kind of bowl below in the dirt.
It came to the realization of the pig and legged him in the ass as if searching for more.
So in that case, you don't even need toilet paper in those toilets.
It's like you know those Japanese toilets where you press a button that washes your butt.
Oh my god.
Yeah.
So there you go.
Peter on this?
Sorry?
Peter.
Oh, Peter.
Peter?
Peter Andre.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, I don't know, they've got, I mean, they get a lot of animal welfare, but no, I don't know.
I would have thought that a pig would have quite a rough tongue.
Yeah.
Sure.
Your hemorrhoids are coming right off.
Oh, Dennis.
Oh my god.
Anyway, 90 seconds, because I worry that 90 seconds was when you just said that.
Yeah.
Anyway, there you go.
Wow, that's great.
Thanks, Gonzalo.
Yeah.
Brilliant.
Quite something.
We've had a query from Nathan Powell.
This is an old fish.
This action is called old fish.
You made a comment many episodes ago about fish not being able to swim up a urine stream and into
a penis.
Okay.
Yeah.
For years, I have been very nervous about this.
And I've been very --
One day I went to the toilet in the Andes and the whole pig swam.
I've been very selective over my Riverside urination areas as I believe that fish could swim
up a urination stream and into my penis.
Please, can you confirm that fish are unable to do this so I can urinate freely?
They can't.
Because urine stream -- one reason is because a urine stream, if you look at it, it's not usually
a full stream when it goes all the way down to a river.
Right.
Or break off very slightly.
And you can especially see that if you kind of do a slow-mo camera shot on it.
Right.
So you couldn't get a salmon jump because salmon's do jump up streams, don't you?
Not the one that we just saw that guy call, which is about his entire height.
But no, I believe that that's at least one of the reasons why.
But there's a few reasons why that wouldn't happen.
Do we know the origins of that myth?
I think it's 19th century.
So I looked up in the archive, episode one, two, one, it was, James, you said, idea that
candy-rew fish will swim up your penis.
There have been only one or two stories of it happening in medical literature.
That's right.
But that must be people who are already in the water.
I believe, yeah, that's the idea.
And that they are in the water and their fish sort of follows the stream.
Yeah, they can take times to do it or whatever.
But yeah, I think them jumping up the stream is not possible.
And also, I think that the case in medical literature are not certain.
Bit dubious, yeah.
Well, after you said that in that episode, the Anna added, according to one bit of 19th century literature,
the only means of preventing the candy-rew fish, swimming up your stream of urine into your bladder,
is immediate penis amputation.
Right, let's carry on.
Yep.
We're back on Quantum Baseball, actually.
So this is in the nap.
CF earlier, or later, depending on the edit.
Jacob Morris writes, "Not only did Danny Yance and play for two teams in the same game,
but the rules allow for time travel.
So when a game is suspended due to inclement weather, it is frozen in time, effectively.
And when it's resumed, the game is considered for record keeping purposes
to have taken place on the same day that it was suspended.
So you just cut them together.
This means that it's possible for a player to reach a major milestone,
quote, "before they did it," because the stats from that game are retroactively uncertain.
Notably, superstar Juan Soto made his majorly debut May 2018
and hit his home run.
First home run, May 21st, so the next day.
Thanks to the quantum science of resumed game time travel, he hit his actual first career home run
in a game on June 18th, that was resumed from May 15th, five days before he made his debut.
Amazing.
That's incredible.
Isn't that good?
It was confusing, but I love it.
Yeah, thanks, Jacob.
I feel like when you do the second half of that game, resuming it,
there should be a thing of continuity, where if you were in the stands,
you had to come dressed exactly as you were.
Everyone has to, so you can smash the two bits of footage together.
That's a really fun idea.
I'll mention that to Jacob next time.
Derek Elliott Jones writes, "I was a good little listener this week,
and followed James' instructions to connect on LinkedIn."
Oh, yeah.
Was that your end of show on LinkedIn?
Yeah, I did, and I've been absolutely inundated.
I've been LinkedIn links, yeah.
Wow.
I've got loads.
They're still coming through.
Great.
People who want to connect.
Your professional network must be absolutely bulging.
It is.
I've never going to do anything with it, because I don't really use LinkedIn.
But if anyone wants to offer me a job.
You're looking.
Yeah.
I did years ago, when we did LinkedIn ads, I made a joke in the show
that I ran a banana company, something like that.
That's all bananas.
And was it called "denana"?
It should have been.
It's absolutely should have been.
But I just put it as my description.
I did it on the day.
Oh, nice.
And I went back not too long ago, and I forgot that I'd left it there.
And so it's my professional page, you know.
Oh, I thought you were going to say that big banana have been in touch.
And they wanted to say nothing didn't get anything.
Really?
Just a banana salesman on it.
And door-to-door, or...
It's in specify.
Maybe I should have been more specific.
And door-to-door is a good offer.
I would be compelled to buy a banana at the door from someone who turned up as one.
That was just one.
Someone just came to your door and said, "I have one banana."
He's tempting heavily. He's been running.
We don't know where from.
But he needs to get rid of this banana.
I'd be tempted.
I have had two bits of work from LinkedIn over the years.
A few.
Yeah, when people have just messaged me saying, "Well, I do this."
I must have met at least one of them was unpaid.
But...
It must still.
That's great.
When we did our tour and I had to find people for the end of the show,
LinkedIn saved me about four times.
This sounds like we're doing an ad for LinkedIn now.
But it genuinely did save me.
That's how I got the Asparamancer.
It's LinkedIn.
Confined asparagus fortune teller is on LinkedIn.
Yeah, but it's only if you're banana salesman,
you're going to be connected to her, aren't you?
Yeah.
She did get confused when it turned out I was on a podcast about facts.
Well, Derek writes, because you know when you connect with someone,
there are more profiles for you.
Or if you search for someone that'll suggest links.
So basically, the algorithm tried to find other QI people for him to connect to.
So there's Andrew Murray, but just a random director at Hunter Mason.
I don't know what that is.
Yeah.
There's Anna Tajinska, a content producer.
There's Anna Tajinska-Biali.
And there's Laura Coonsburg.
I get all those as well.
I do.
Yeah.
I just assumed it was you guys, because you didn't want to have your real name on LinkedIn.
I'm Laura Coonsburg on LinkedIn with me.
Yeah.
I like the Andrew Murray who's at Hunter.
Which one was that?
Oh, yeah.
Did you not connect the Hunter bit?
Nope.
Okay.
Wow.
It's a very difficult job hosting this show, Dan.
You're doing a great job.
I don't have time to spot my own name in the middle of a sentence.
Okay.
Yeah.
If anyone's listened to this and hasn't added me on LinkedIn, then why not?
Why not?
I mean, I don't see what said it for you.
Definitely not.
I mean, but do it anyway.
And Caleb Patrunch writes, "I was wondering if you've noticed," writes Caitlin, "that the name Everard Digby scans perfectly with Ellen Erickby."
I have noticed.
Aha.
Because do you remember?
Did I actually do this or did I just write it?
I wrote a song.
Yeah, I heard it.
I did do it, didn't I?
I did it on stage.
And it was, Ellen Erickby was a tune.
And Everard Digby was one of the verses.
And Anna Toshinsky was another one.
And it was like...
I remember this.
I don't think you ever...
I think maybe you played it once at a work in progress.
But I remember you sending us a video of you playing it.
On piano?
I think you played it on piano?
I don't know.
I don't remember that.
Everard Digby.
Yeah.
Wow.
And it was like...
I don't know.
I can't remember what it was about now, but it was just something about the podcast.
Yeah.
And they all led up to the final song, which was Ellen Erickby.
Love it.
But I suppose you wouldn't be able to do that anyway, because the Beatles are...
I don't know.
We adopted it.
It must be parody laws.
I think there are parody laws.
Yeah, yeah.
So thank you, Caitlin.
We've got a wedding coming up.
Ah.
This is nice.
Jodie has written some information about golf, which I'll tell you later, James.
I think everyone would like to hear that.
All right.
It's about a cup price golf.
It's about railway tickets, as well, so I am interested.
In the 20s, there was a...
There was a cup price golfers permit between Liverpool Street in London and Oldborough in Suffolk.
So a couple of hours away on the train.
Wow.
And there was a golfers certificate in the 20s where you had reduced fares to 130 golf adjacent stations
if you got it signed by a golf club secretary and you were going to play golf.
That sounds right.
Get money off.
Isn't that crazy?
That is really cool.
A tick tocker who goes around all the golf courses in London and plays them and says how good they are.
And also how far they are from the tube stations.
That's very useful.
Right.
It is, yeah.
I stayed in a caravan park the other day and we'd go there.
Yeah.
Officially.
Oh, as in we were allowed to be there.
You booked.
Yeah.
I stayed in it.
How did you see that?
It just...
You made it sound a bit like you just like...
I stayed in a caravan park the other day.
I wasn't...
Like I just passed out, you know.
That's Anna, I'm thinking.
Oh, that's Anna.
Sorry.
It's my head went straight to that you've been kicked out of home.
Well, let's not reveal all of her personal stuff here.
Is it a summer holiday?
Is it a marital breakdown?
It doesn't matter.
The point is I'm away and I'm getting the fresh air.
And it's really nice.
And actually I prefer it without a caravan.
You know what I mean?
Yeah, because you didn't say I was in a caravan.
You said I was in a caravan park.
Yeah.
Because the anecdote hasn't got me in the caravan park.
I'm so sorry.
We jumped right and we jumped all over.
No, please.
I just know that your anecdotes need help sometimes.
Let's...
Let's let this one struggle for me.
That's Andy's anecdotes.
My anecdotes need ending.
That is a difference.
There is a crazy golf course there.
And there was a board inside the restaurant that they have there
where it showed a giant circuit of crazy golf that goes on
where it was a leaderboard
and it printed out the monthly list of who was leading
around the fanat area.
And I wonder if you've ever been part of a crazy golf.
To be honest, I'm more of a maxi golf guy.
What's maxi?
As in large golf.
I'm not really a mini golf person.
So no, here's the answer.
Also, I've never been to Thamets.
Well, I've been inviting you for a long time.
It's a lovely caravan for you to stay in what you are.
No, I haven't put that big right.
To a few like small golf courses where they put the best scores
of the month.
I think that's nice.
What about this wedding?
Yes.
Jodie writes.
She sent the information about the golf.
And then she says, I'm getting married to my own James
at the end of September.
Sadly, I can't say we met through the podcast.
But I was already a fan and introduced him to it.
But as we were both obsessed with Heritage Railways,
there is a steam train theme to the wedding.
Yes.
We will be travelling and having the meal on a steam train.
And I'm also planning to make candy coal for the favours,
which has made me think of you guys.
Is there somewhere I can send some to you guys?
So she's going to send some candy coal for us.
Great.
Nice.
How far will that be?
We'll eat it on our next duel.
Absolutely.
Very cool.
There you go.
Kathleen Keast.
I've just listened to episode 5 and 4 about a pig being tried
for murder in France.
You might want to check out a 1993 movie, The Advocate,
which starred Colin Firth as the lawyer who defended
that murderer's pig.
Wow.
Really?
How good is that?
Yeah.
He's not afraid to take a risk, Firth.
Yeah?
And Daniel Day Lewis played the pig?
Yes.
I had to live under a ty-related Peru for three months beforehand.
Oh, God.
Oh, there you go.
Thanks for that.
Buff Fins.
I can't even remember what that stands for.
It's big.
It's like...
Big old fish fan.
His experts.
Pete Day has just written.
High ladies and gents.
Just listen to your piece on Jixels.
I wanted to thank you for the publicity.
Because Pete is the chair of the benevolent confraternity
of dysectologist.
Oh, cool.
The Jixels group.
Yeah.
And it's included a link to some of his collection of old
and new wooden puzzles.
The young wife is a member of.
She...
I'm afraid it's a former member.
She never made it along to the meetings.
And she wasn't kicked out or anything.
I just think she renewed herself.
Membership laughs.
Right.
I bought it for her as a one-year thing.
And I said, unless you're using your styling, I'm going to be quite serious.
And come off it.
I think it's about £12 for the years.
Membership.
You're the same with electricity.
You're not using it.
You're not using the light.
of his collection of Jixels.
So is the informational gift not a--
- Well, that went into your personal folder.
- Yeah, exactly.
Did your wife have the card, you know,
the duos in this and the absence card?
- Yeah, no, I can't remember now.
- I can't remember either.
- Is this where we got to last time?
- It was a bit of an ampass.
I think I politely said, yes,
she did have the card, but I can't remember.
She probably did.
- Yeah, imagine if you joined, you get the card.
- All right.
- We've had a bit of fan art.
- Great.
- Some Gremlin arts, but I'm afraid it's just of me.
- Okay.
- Um, very nice.
- Well, I mean, that's just a nice picture of you.
- Yeah.
- That's no fun, is it?
- It's got a whole point of fan art,
is that it looks nothing like us.
- I know, this does look quite like me.
- And do they only do artwork of Gremlin,
so do they.
(laughing)
- Oh no, that's why.
That's why.
- That's the weird little goblin one.
- No, it's just very nice picture, thanks for that.
- Very nice picture.
- It's quite a lot of fan art,
and it's really tailed off these days, isn't it?
- Well, now we're filming this.
- Maybe they'll come in the spades.
- Yeah, we can show it.
- We can show the art.
- Yeah, yeah.
And just to finish us off.
(laughing)
- So, do you fall that point?
- That's definitely gonna have to go
at the end for continuity reasons.
(laughing)
- Honestly, Adam's been away for two weeks.
- He's talking about introducing this.
- Age.
(laughing)
- A new tier on Patreon.
- Okay, sorry.
- I can't actually see anyone coming in, too.
- Oh, dear.
All right, well, the continuity of me crying with laughter,
will that be a problem?
- Yeah, just a little bit of nom to term.
- Go on.
- There's a guy called Dr. William Wood,
who's on a mission to ban wood stoves in Tasmania.
- Very good.
- Yeah.
- I saw a book about the history of bread
by a guy called Dr. Butterie.
(laughing)
- No.
- That's the name, yeah.
- That's brilliant.
That's really good.
That's from Sam Leicester, I had to say, sorry.
Also, Tracy Gunn writes,
"Her and Gate Council's noise and nuisance officer
"is Craig Belringer."
(laughing)
- Very good.
- Pretty good.
- And that's it.
- Ah, nice.
- That was a happy ending.
- That was a...
(laughing)
- So thanks so much for listening to Dr. Zaline.
This month, it's wonderful.
It's just a joy to read your emails, keep them coming.
- We should do this more often.
- Yeah.
- What a good idea.
- Okay, finish us off.
(laughing)
Bye.
(upbeat music)
Thanks for listening.
And if you'd like to comment on anything we've said
in the course of this episode or any other episodes,
then write an email to podcast@QI.com.
We'll be back, we'll be back before long
with another Dr. Zaline.
We'll see you then.
Bye.
(upbeat music)