(upbeat music)
- Hey everyone, welcome to this week's episode of Fish.
Before we get going, we've got a quick, exciting announcement
which is that two of our colleagues, Jack and Manu,
along with their chef friend, Rosie McKean,
have just launched a brand new podcast
called Lunchbox Envy.
- Yes, it's all the most interesting, weird,
incredible facts about specific foods.
Every episode is based around a food stuff,
so bananas or garlic or sausages.
There are a couple of episodes already out now.
More will be released very soon.
They really are fantastic.
You might have heard Jack and Manu,
the elves on our spin-off show, Meet the Elves.
They obviously have the bona fide research credentials
of QILs, and then Rosie really knows
what she's talking about in the kitchen.
- I've learned so many amazing things
off the back of listening to these episodes.
All the things that they pull out of their Lunchboxes
make you just go, what the hell is that?
Jack, for example, pulls out a chocolate garlic bar
which was used by the British Secret Services in the war.
I'd never heard of it before.
You get these amazing, untold histories,
but also good advice on food.
- Yes, in fact, as a result,
I have started slow cooking sausages.
Find out why.
The good thing about the good advice is
they don't just tell you what to do.
They tell you why certain things work.
It is jam-packed.
Jam-packed, yeah, very good.
Jam-packed with interesting facts
from why food tastes better if you eat it with your hands.
There you go, toddlers, you've got it right.
As to how you can turn peanut butter into diamonds
and make your fortune, go and listen to it right now.
Go to qi.com/lunchbox
or wherever podcasts are available.
- That's right, so do check it out.
Lunchbox envy, out now.
Okay, on with the show.
(dramatic music)
(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
Anna Tyshinski, and James Harkin.
Once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that every time your heart beats,
your memory gets worse,
but you become better at firing a gun.
- Better at firing a what?
Sorry, better at firing a gun.
Better at firing a what?
- I see, I see what's happening.
- You see what I'm doing there?
- Yeah, you expose some obvious flaws in the system.
- Your heart beats a lot,
and I don't feel like I lose my memory
every second in a bit.
- You are, I think this is useful information to know.
So if you're ever doing certain things,
always do it on the offbeat.
Other things, do it on the onbeat.
And I found this a really interesting study I came across
about the cardiac cycle, basically,
which is the cycle of how your heart beats,
which says that in cisterly, which is when it's beating,
basically it triggers these barrier receptors,
which are nerves in your blood vessels,
which clock that the blood vessel is stretching,
'cause the heart's just beat, the blood vessel stretches,
the barrier receptors send a message to the brain going,
"Right, the blood vessels have stretched.
"This is how much, this is what's going on."
And it sets off all this activity in your brain
every time your heart beats.
And all that activity in your brain,
which is giving your brain all the information
about exactly how much your heart's beat,
how hard, how fast, how much the vessel's expanded,
that drowns out loads of other stuff
that's happening in your brain.
So you get worse at lots of stuff,
like your memory gets worse.
- How do they test this, Anna?
- That's a very good question.
They rig people up to ECGs
and they do things like really scare them or they--
- So they have more heartbeats.
Is that what you mean?
- No, so they test exactly whether they're on cisterly
or diastole, if their heart's beating or not beating,
and then they scare them with something,
and if their heart's on an on beat,
then their reaction will be slightly slower
than their heartbeats. - Like reaction times.
- Yeah, and they had people in a rifle range
and they logged them up to ECGs and they did the same thing.
- I've got two questions.
One, memory, is this long-term memory
or is it memory in the moment that it's making worse?
- It's memory in the moment.
So I think they'd say, what's Ernzo's name?
What's the name of the person who was that next to you
yesterday, Dan, and then on the on beat,
you'd be a bit less--
- Dan is not gonna remember that.
- Any circle step is.
- Question two was to do with the gun.
So I'd read a study a while ago,
which is that apparently snipers
like to take their shot in between heartbeats.
- How interesting.
- Yeah, so they've been doing it wrong.
- Yeah, that's why they keep missing.
- Yes, that's why they keep missing.
- Yeah, well, it's a technique that they do,
which is it's a bit of meditation prior to it.
Slow breathing, they time the shot.
Apparently if your heartbeat is raised
and it's much higher than the blood pressure
on your trigger finger, like pulses will come in there,
it might make you pull a shot slightly differently.
- If you ever watch Biaflon,
which is cross country skiing and then shooting.
- Not at the same time.
And that is the critical point
because your heart rate gets really, really high
because you're doing this really big exercise
and then you have to shoot.
And the best players, the best people
like Johannes Tingersboro, people like that,
he would like really lower, lower, lower his heart rate.
And you can see it, they often have it on the screen.
It'll say what their heart rate is
and you can see it going down, down, down,
and they won't shoot immediately.
They'll let the heartbeat go down and then they'll shoot.
- That's really cool.
So they do, okay, yeah.
- And that makes sense to make the heartbeat go down, I guess,
'cause you're more focused, you're more relaxed.
I've watched my own heartbeat during surgery.
- What?
As in the actual heart itself?
- No, I haven't seen my physical heart pumping away.
I mean, on a screen, I was having a minor operation
which I was allowed to stay awake for.
And you can see it.
And they sort of accidentally left the screen
like pointing a bit at my face.
So I was trying to muck around and speed it up
and slow it down.
It's great fun.
- Were they inside,
they have something inside your body?
You said that actually.
- Oh yeah, oh yeah.
- But you didn't have an open heart surgery, did you?
- No, I said a minor operation.
I like to play it cool,
but even I would probably say
that's a medium-sized operation.
- And when they actually put the extension in your penis,
did your heart rate go up or it made that noise
like a slide or something.
- Can I just say the potential reason for this,
evolutionarily, which I also think is really cool.
And just to let you know,
is that when your heart doesn't beat,
your sensitivity to pain goes down.
You have a worse memory for words,
your concentration is less good,
you've got higher fear response,
so you're more afraid, more intense reaction,
but your reactions are slower.
And then on the offbeat,
you have a stronger grip,
so you're stronger,
you're more accurate at firing a gun,
and your eyes flicker around more.
And weirdly, I didn't know what happens is
when you're under threat,
what do you think happens to your heart rate?
- Speeds up, speeds up.
- Incorrect.
- What?
- Isn't this incredible?
Immediately after you're under threat,
usually your heartbeat for a second slows down.
Apparently, in an evolutionary sense,
and that's because for a second,
it needs to be on the offbeat more often.
So when your heartbeat goes slower,
it's more often on the offbeat,
so that you can have fast reactions
and process information more.
So you process everything around you,
and then it speeds up a lot,
because as soon as you've done that,
then it's on the onbeat,
and then you're really good at firing a gun,
or punching someone, or gripping something.
- I would've thought it would be a part of
just trying to be quiet, like more quiet,
so they don't find you.
Not having that pumping heartbeat.
- Just as psychologically, you'd be like,
you can hear, you know, you'd be like,
- Can I just ask for clarification?
If your heartbeat slows down,
and you go from 100 beats to 50 beats,
that means you also have 50 offbeats in a minute.
So does that not mean you have fewer offbeats
as opposed to more?
- I think it's more time is spent on an off,
so you've got a longer offbeat,
'cause like an onbeat is always going to be
the same amount of time your heart takes to go,
but to pump the blood out, right?
But then between them, there's a longer gap.
- So the offbeat is actually the gap
between your heart pumping and not pumping.
- Exactly.
And this was only in one study that it said,
usually the fear response causes your heart
to immediately slow down and speed up,
and I couldn't find it many other places,
but I thought that was fascinating.
- That was very cool.
Heartbeats are something that I didn't realize
play quite a feature role in the world of music.
- Heartbeats is a single by steps.
But there you go.
- Is that what you're thinking?
- That's not what I'm thinking.
I mean, artists recording their heartbeats
or their of their children and putting them into songs
have been used multiple times.
You've get them in print songs in John Lennon,
very sadly released it as part of an ultrasound heartbeat
to a child that unfortunately didn't make it full term,
but so many bands.
Max Cavallera from Sepultura, he did it.
Interestingly, Taylor Swift did it for one of her songs, right?
And it was a song that was re-recorded as you might remember,
Taylor Swift had this huge moment
whereby she had her manager claim all of her music.
So she went and re-recorded every single album.
- I do remember.
- So one of these songs contains her heartbeat.
So she had to replicate the sound recording of her heartbeat.
So she's got twice recorded heartbeats into tracks,
but they all get listed in the song credits
on heartbeat, Taylor Swift.
- Very nice.
- So it means you get more money.
- Yeah, exactly.
- That's like Phil Collins.
Do you remember Phil Collins, didn't he do an album
where it was all Phil Collins?
And I think he put himself in the credits as everything.
- So he played like the kazoo when he played it.
(all laughing)
- Huge kazoo guy, Collins, yeah, yeah.
- You can't just add more on,
you can't just add a triangle
and get paid a whole extra bit, can't you?
- Well, you can, that's the whole idea.
So Simon Cowell, that was a story
that he would play a minor instrument,
like one cowbell noise,
and that would be writer's credits on the songs
to all his audits that he would get.
- And that's why we renamed it the cowbell.
But no one knows.
- It's so beautiful.
- Very good.
- When your heart rate synchronizes,
we've briefly mentioned before, I think,
that it's choirs, their heartbeats all synchronized.
It's pretty cool.
- That is cool.
- When you go to the theater,
your heart also synchronizes with the people around you.
And it lasts into the interval.
Everyone goes out into the interval,
with their hearts speeding up,
sort of going at the same rate.
- I wonder why we all go to the toilet
at exactly the same moment
when there's like five minutes left before the second half.
'Cause our hearts is the problem, isn't it?
- It's the problem.
- But so that's saying that a movie has a heart rate.
- Yes, it does.
- So you could actually probably,
you know we talked before about how you could do CPR,
singing a certain type of song,
because it's the right BPM in order to do it.
There probably is, like, if you want to go to a movie
that puts you on this heart rate.
- No, 'cause it'll go up and down.
So you'd be caught if it was Titanic, you know,
as the ship cracks in half,
you suddenly have to double the rate of CPR.
- Oh yeah, but I'm sure there's some like,
how long are you going to do? - How long are you going to do?
- Movies where you can just sit for...
- If you're like, if it's something really tedious,
like June two, you can just sit all the way through it.
- That's too slow, the person would die.
- But if it's something really exciting, yeah, then...
I mean, you don't need to do it for long.
How long do you need to do CPR for normally?
If you...
- It's all the way through.
- Okay, yeah, I've done 45 seconds now.
I'm afraid we've watched the whole
of the climactic fight scene in Gladiator,
so I am going to be clocking off, yeah.
Pig hearts, you know how we were all going to get
pig hearts a while ago? - Oh yeah.
- That was going to be the big thing.
- I know, I was so excited.
- It's so complicated, the process.
'Cause basically pigs are very similar to people
in lots of ways physiologically.
And there was an idea that we were going to be able
to transplant pig hearts into people.
And that was going to be, 'cause there are loads of pigs,
I mean, there are hundreds of millions of pigs
around the world. - Sure, just sitting there
with their hearts beating away and around, oink oink.
- We're not using them for anything, right?
- Exactly.
- So let's steal their hearts for us.
It's pretty sinister as a species.
Anyway, but it turns out you have to do so much stuff,
you have to make the pig more human before you do this.
- How do you do that?
Dress it up.
- Give it a newspaper.
- Sprig it to the movies.
- Like grandma, what big trotters you have?
Yeah, it's so, no, you can't just take a,
like take a heart out of a pig and shove it in the person.
You have to take a pig, right?
Remove three of its genes, knock out some growth hormones.
- So you have to dress it up.
- Knock out some growth hormones.
Add a couple of other genes.
Then you have to keep the pig nice and clean,
so it doesn't get any pig bacteria.
Then you breed from that pig and you make these GM embryos,
you put them in surrogate cells,
and then you have to give the mummy pig a C-section
so that it doesn't get contaminated at all.
And then those piglets have to be bred up
until they're big enough.
- Wow.
- And those are then the sort of a bit more human pigs.
They've had no contact with the outside world,
no external viruses.
Those are the ones that--
- And has anyone ever had this?
- I think two people have, and they both didn't survive.
- Well, one of them built a house out of straw,
the other one built a house out of sticks,
and they never made it.
- No wonder we don't use it.
You got to, it's like, we found a match,
we now just have to get it pregnant.
- By it didn't first.
- Let it birth some, and then take their hearts.
- Anna's right, a couple of people have had it,
but I think it didn't, it didn't--
- I think the reason is like hearts in all mammals
are kind of the same, aren't they really?
- Right.
- They all work the same way with electrical impulses,
and they have sodium and potassium
that make the electricity happen,
and they're all kind of the same, so that's the idea.
- Is it right that we have a billion beats, all mammals?
- Three billion.
- We've got roughly the same number, yeah.
- Humans get about three billion.
Humans get a bit more, basically,
'cause our life is longer because we have invented indoors.
And indoors is a more relaxing environment, and--
- But like we're similar enough
that we have roughly the same--
- You do, but it's not like you have that number.
Like Donald Trump thinks that you have a certain number,
and if you use them up, then that's when you die.
And that's why he doesn't like to do any exercise
apart from play golf.
And I think a few other famous people have thought that.
Maybe Neil Armstrong thought that.
- I think, I think, yeah, yeah, no, there's a quote.
I think they've looked into it.
- Maybe as a joke, he said, "You only get a certain amount,
"and I'm down if I'm gonna use all mine
"running up and down the street."
- Oh, well, that's a funny line.
- That's interesting, when you're playing golf,
because it is reduced, is it better to play in the gaps?
- Well, you know what, I'd never thought that before,
but I'm gonna try that next time on the course.
- Yeah, I think that's why small animals
don't live as long, isn't it?
'Cause as a small animal, you have to,
your heart beats faster and so use them up.
- I got one last thing before we move on.
Have you guys heard of the Intimacy 2.0 dress?
- No.
- No, okay, let me guess.
It's a dress you wear.
- Correct.
- And two people wear it, and it syncs your heartbeats,
and it changes color with the heartbeats
so you can see that each is flashing at the same time
and that you're in sync.
- Is it like a dress version of paddles, basically?
(all laugh)
- Aggressively stops your heart and restarts in that,
tell you what I'm saying.
- No, no.
- Does it change color?
Does it go transparent if your heart rate rises?
- There we go.
- Is that what Kanye West's partner was wearing?
She was just so excited to be at the Grammys.
Her heart was going 10 a second.
- But it's basically that.
So it's a dress that you would wear.
Obviously no one is wearing this, as far as I can tell.
And it's got a neckline that plunges to the midriff,
which if your heart rate rises and you're out on a date,
it slowly makes the dress more transparent around these,
yeah, sort of like the cleavage area and so on,
in order to, yeah.
So it's just enhancing.
- In the woods, you're wearing it
and you're threatened by a lion.
Now the lion's seen your naked flesh exposed.
That makes the duration even worse.
- Well, fortunately, when you're panicked,
your heart rate goes down.
So you should be fine.
- Good point.
- Have you learned nothing from this section?
- Where'd she go?
(all laugh)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 2023,
a team mapping the ocean floor
announced they may have found Amelia Earhart's plane.
In 2024, they announced it was actually
a plane-shaped pile of rocks.
(all laugh)
- Could they not have looked a bit closer
the first time round?
Got a second opinion.
- It's at the bottom of the sea, Anna.
- Ah, it's very hot.
It's amazing they found such a plane-shaped pile of rocks.
It would have been cool if they had just announced
we found a wicked pile of rocks shaped like a plane down there.
- Yeah.
- But they had to go a bit further
and say it's one of the most famous lost planes ever.
- Yeah, so this is Amelia Earhart.
We've mentioned her once or twice before.
She was flying around the world in 1937
and she was about 100 miles from a place
called Howland Island, which is in Kiribati.
And she started running out of fuel
and we never heard from her again, basically.
She gave one last radio call and then disappeared
and for the subsequent 90 years,
people have been wondering what's happened to her.
- Yeah.
And she was really, she was well-famous wasn't she?
- Oh yeah, yeah.
- Incredibly celebrated aviate tricks.
- Yeah, prior to the disappearance as well, which is-
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Often sometimes these things make you.
- She broke in so many records and things like that
and she'd done a lot of trips,
which was the first time a woman might have made those flights
and things like that.
She was amazing.
- And this is a group called Deepsea Vision,
the CEO, Tony Romeo,
who's a former U.S. Air Force intelligence officer,
said that they'd found these.
(laughs)
Rocks said that they found this plane
or what they thought was a plane
and then they've done a bit more work
and they realized that it is some rocks.
And Tony said, "Talk about the cruelest formation
"ever created by nature."
- Yeah.
- And I can only agree.
- 'Cause it was, yeah,
it's a hundred miles from Holland Island, right?
So if you see a plane shape.
- I don't mean to be morbid,
but when a plane hits the water,
it often, especially a 1930s plane,
it might not stay looking like a pristine plane
all the way to the ocean bottom, you know?
- Absolutely.
And what were they using to see it?
Was it like a sonar thing that sent back a vague shape?
- The image does look pretty good.
- Is it very plain?
- Oh yeah, it's even got a little tail fin on it.
- Yeah, it looks very plain like.
- Does it?
- It was a huge search for her at the time.
As in, the U.S. Navy did a lot of searching.
They even sent, I think, an aircraft carrier
to the region, which had 63 aircraft on it.
So, you know, all those planes can go out making trips.
- I thought you meant like an empty one,
optimistically hoping to carry her aircraft back.
(laughs)
- Yeah, and it cost them about four million U.S. dollars
at the time, it was about 90 million U.S. dollars today.
This, and of course they didn't find her.
And actually that became kind of the end
of celebrity aviation because at that time,
the loads of celebrity flyers who were doing loads
of crazy stunts and everyone that they're on the front page
of all the newspapers, but when Emilia Earhart disappeared,
Congress decided to make it illegal for the Navy
to spend any money on search and rescue.
And when they did that, everyone just stopped
carrying a little bit.
- Wow.
- Yeah, there were all these psychics who were claiming
that they were in touch with her.
And the family were looking for anything.
So, they were going to see psychics
and hoping to follow up on things.
There was this story that we mentioned briefly,
which was the Tokyo Rose story.
It's the idea that the Japanese had got hold
of Emilia Earhart, she was captured,
and she was putting out propaganda radio news
about what was going on in the war.
- So, Tokyo Rose was real, right?
- Yeah.
- That was actually, but they were saying that that was her.
- That was, they were saying it was her,
but what's interesting is her husband,
'cause she was married, Emilia Earhart,
to a guy called George Putnam.
He actually made a three-day trek
through a Japanese-held territory
so that he could get to a US Marine radio station
to confirm whether or not it was her voice.
So, it was taken really seriously,
even by the immediate family, some of these,
some of these theories.
- I think that was one of the ones
that vaguely sane people believe.
- Yeah.
- The person who was in charge of the island.
I have to say, I find that Emilia Earhart searches,
I have a real blank like with Jack the Ripper on them.
I'm like, "God, get a life, guys."
A lot of them, no offence.
- Interesting.
- Also, welcome to the podcast.
We appreciate you listening.
- It's interesting you've made these people your bet noir.
- I don't know why.
- The people, relatively blind-minded people,
trying to solve a classic mystery.
- New enemies of the podcast.
- Yeah.
- I'm so sorry, I'm so sorry.
You can buy stuff from their website.
Look, I'll advertise for them.
They sell little, they sell t-shirts, they sell badges.
If you wanna help fund their expeditions,
each trip costs up to $500,000 to go and uncover
another rusty jackknife or compact mirror in the ocean
that you say belong to Emilia Earhart.
- Sounds good.
- Okay.
- So just on sort of the ocean
and the mysteries of the ocean.
Something that I read about, which is a big problem
for a lot of boats out in the open sea now, is UFOs.
- Oh, no.
- Unidentified floating objects.
So this is to do with container ships.
And container ships, when they're in rough seas,
they can lose, so many containers have gone missing.
There was an estimate between 1985 and 2007,
five to six million container units
would be floating--
- Wow, it's mental.
- Yeah, and--
- Do they all float?
- They do for a while, so they can for a few weeks.
If a container is up to 80% full,
then you've got enough air in there for it to,
but they're not airtight,
so they will eventually seep water and go down.
So a lot of ships just say that if they're out,
these come out of nowhere, 'cause they're not mapped right.
So you're dodging UFOs all the way through the ocean.
- Wow.
- Yeah, we're just constantly losing giant containers
off the back of ships.
- Other mysterious things in the ocean.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Well, one big ocean mystery is,
you know all the plastic in the ocean?
- Yes, yeah.
- Well, where is it?
- In the ocean.
- It's not nearly enough there.
- It's in the garbage patch, isn't it?
- Well, not nearly enough, James.
- What do you mean?
- Let's get more in there, guys.
- Yeah, what is the problem you're trying to solve here?
- This plastic.
- It's in animals.
- No, we don't know, so you,
well, we're starting to find out,
but basically 99% of the plastic
that should be in the ocean is not in the ocean.
We keep on looking,
and most of what is there is in the garbage patch,
but a lot of that is kind of old plastic,
and we don't know where the newer plastic's gone,
whereas you'd think the older plastic
would be the stuff that degrades, if anything,
and is getting smaller and disappearing.
- So when you say it's not there, sorry, what do you mean?
- So in the surveys that we've done of the ocean,
looking at how much ocean plastic there is,
we haven't found nearly enough to equate
with how much we estimate we've been flushing into the ocean,
and it's called dark plastic,
and they equate it with dark matter.
- I knew, I knew.
The climate change was a hoax
in this whole environmental push.
I knew it.
- It's actually not,
it's only quite for the climate change,
but it's not quite the same.
- Yeah, but that's crazy.
- So is this scary, Anna?
'Cause presumably it's somewhere bad.
- No, it's actually somewhere good.
I think the latest research shows,
and this is great news.
- Anna, this is a roller coaster of the fair.
- I like to keep your heart beats fluctuating.
The latest research is a guy called Lauren Lebriton,
who's an oceanographer who ran this big computer model,
looking at how the plastic that we know about
gets distributed, where it lands in the ocean,
where it floats to and stuff.
He's concluded that the vast majority
of macro plastics and micro plastics,
so big and small bits,
rather than being lost in the middle of the ocean
or deep down where we don't know,
they actually all wash up on beaches
on a buried in shorelines or a right on the coastline.
- Interesting.
- Which to me says, great,
I always thought we can't get that plastic back.
I can't row out to sea and get it back.
But if all you need to do is go to a beach.
- That's great, we just need to pick up
the baby turtles it's choked to death on the beach.
- Well, it's amazing.
- Under the beach is the lug worms who are getting it back.
- Oh no.
- I know the lug, the poor lugs.
No one talks about them.
- And it's gonna turn out the lug worms
with a keystone species keeping this whole thing going,
and we'll be sorry.
That's really interesting though.
- It just seems more accessible, doesn't it?
- Does it make it easier for us to deal with
if we can work out technologies to do that?
I understand animals will die, obviously, but like.
- I think really the problem is stopping it
from entering the oceans in the first place.
- Yeah.
- But I mean, I think once it gets to the coast,
to me, I mean, this is new research,
but it seems like it would be easier to access
once it's not in the middle of nowhere.
It looks like it.
So get to your beach, people, with a bucket and spade.
- Yeah, nice.
- Have you guys heard of dark oxygen?
(laughing)
- Dark oxygen.
- So by extension, it's, there's not as much oxygen
as we thought there should be.
- Yeah.
- And some of it's missing.
- This is stuff that's found on the ocean floor.
- Yeah.
- And it's produced this dark oxygen by battery rocks.
- Okay.
- These are the nodules, metallic nodules
that are all over huge chunks of the ocean floor
around the world, and they make oxygen without light.
They do it chemically.
So they split the water molecules around them
into hydrogen and oxygen.
So that's insane.
I mean, that's the source of oxygen.
- Yeah, it's like putting an electric,
like we would make on a chemistry lesson.
- Electrolysis.
- It's crackers.
Yeah, yeah.
- Are these connected to ocean farts?
- No.
(laughing)
- Walk in one of those in a minute.
- I just love the idea of having me doing a lecture
and dancing on the front row with questions like,
if you could put your hand down until we end up.
(laughing)
- We will have a question and answer session by in writing.
- Go on, please go on.
- How can I possibly continue talking about something
really interesting when you say, about ocean farts?
And that's how the disruptive kids do it.
- Yeah.
This is why no one learns anything.
No, it's just interesting
'cause there's a huge debate at the moment.
I'm sure you're all keeping up with it
in the International Seabed Authority
about ocean mining the ocean floor.
Are we going to do it?
Should we definitely not do it?
And...
- Well, the problem is,
one of the big problems is,
obviously logically you say we shouldn't do it,
but it contains so much stuff like lithium
that you need.
If everyone's gonna have an electric car,
you need these minerals and where you're gonna get them from.
So it's like this weird sort of balance.
- Do you get them from land,
which we know causes some damage,
do we get them from the ocean,
where we really have no idea what effect it would have.
- It might be none.
- Might be absolutely fine.
Why not just do it, assuming it'll be none.
- That's really big, the ocean, isn't it?
- Oh, it's huge, yeah.
So, but it is a really big debate at the moment.
- So, wait, these batteries,
how are they, are we mining these big ocean floor batteries?
- These are the nodules that people want to mine
because they contain these metals.
And so it's being debated at the moment.
And it was found in a study,
which was funded by a mining firm,
which is desperate to mine the ocean.
And then it turned out,
oh, these might be a really important source of oxygen
for all kinds of life.
And so they were furious
that they'd accidentally funded this study.
- One of the problem is that they are mostly found
in something that's called silicious ooze.
Silicious ooze is this kind of really low sediment
at the bottom of the ocean,
but it accumulates about one to three millimeters
every thousand years.
So once you dig it up, it's going to take a while to get back.
- Oh, 'cause we're probably going to dig faster than that.
'Cause we dig faster than one to three millimeters, don't we?
- My company is suggesting that we will do faster than that.
- And I've invested, so.
- Interesting.
- Well, there is one kind of ocean drilling, which is good.
And that's the scientific research kind.
And the first mission was really cool.
It was in 1957, and it was organized
by this group called the American Miscellaneous Society.
- I love them already.
- They are so cool.
They're like the ignobles of their time.
They were a bunch of geologists and oceanographers
who just wanted to get together and have weird ideas.
Anyway, there was this thing called Project Moho,
which they started,
which was to investigate the Mohorovich discontinuity.
- It sounds sci-fi, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- The Mohorovich discontinuity
has been producing dark oxygen.
- It does sound like someone who thought,
I'm going to write it as a Russian name.
And they go, no, no, that's not Russian enough.
Let's put another it to the end.
There are too many O's and too many itches in it,
for me, to be honest.
But that's this bit between the crust of the Earth
and the mantle,
where suddenly seismic waves start moving much faster.
And it was the only reason we knew back then
that there was an Earth's crust.
So these guys, the Miscellaneous Society,
were like, well, let's go and dig into the ocean
and find out what's happening.
It ended up being a failure,
but it started off this thing that happens today,
a lot where we dig into the ocean floor
and pull up all these cores
and find out loads of cool stuff.
And the person who came along with them to write about it,
and to report about it,
was oceanography fan and big lover of the sea,
taking a guess.
- James Cameron.
- Ah, he, I think in a former life,
maybe this is who he was.
- Jack Cousteau.
- In '57.
- Ooh, Jack Cousteau.
- Yeah, no.
Oh, I can give you a clue by saying,
one of the lesser books he wrote
was called Steinbeck and Ricketts Sea of Cortez.
- So John Steinbeck.
- So it was John Steinbeck.
(all laughing)
- He absolutely loved the sea and oceanography.
- Really?
- So he hopped on board this research boat
and recourse for it.
- That's so good.
Mentioning Jack Cousteau,
the Calypso and his efforts of ocean mapping
are some of the greatest that we've ever had.
On his ship.
- With the Calypso, his ship.
- The Calypso was the ship,
it was a very famous ship.
And he had three tanks
that would be there to take out to sea.
So you had the diesel to run the ship,
you had the water to drink.
What do you think his third tank was?
- Probably ocean farts.
- Which he's bottled with, yes.
- Along the way?
- Thank you for reminding me.
We didn't pick up on my question.
- It's just like bilge water to keep him.
- Wastewater?
- Yeah, wastewater.
- So it did not pollute the sea?
- No.
- Is it just whiskey or something?
- It's wine.
He had a giant wine tank attached to the ship
in order to.
- For drinking?
- Of course for drinking.
- Right, not for some kind of fuel purpose.
- It's Jack Cousteau.
He's gonna be, and his French buddies,
drinking as they're...
- Amazing.
- Have you guys heard of,
while we're talking about weird rock formations?
Do you guys know about the Ararat Anomaly?
- So Mount Ararat?
- Mount Ararat, yes.
- Above land?
- It's above land.
- Oh, is it that there are loads of fossils
that should be ocean things on Mount Ararat?
- There are those, but that's not what this is.
This is if people have taken photos
of the snow near the summit of Mount Ararat,
there's something that looks very much like Noah's Ark.
- Brilliant.
- And if you see the pictures,
you can kind of see where they're coming from.
I mean, they're very fuzzy.
But the interesting thing is,
this was classified as secret for the U.S. Air Force
from 1949 until the '90s.
- Wow.
- And it's in snow, it's like a snow arc.
- It's kind of, it's basically just a jagged bit of rock.
- A snow, it's an arc shaped pile of rocks.
- Precisely, okay.
Yeah, why do you think it was classified as secret
for so long?
- Because it might provoke religious conflict.
- Interesting, because obviously,
a lot of believers think that this is evidence,
that the Bible is true, but no, that wasn't it.
- Okay.
- It's much more Cotidian, much more boring than that.
- People might visit if they didn't want to visit.
- Basically, it's on the border of the Soviet Union.
And so there was lots of things happening around there
between America and the Soviet Union,
so they didn't want any photos coming out.
But obviously the conspiracy theorists were like,
oh, what are you hiding?
What are you hiding?
- Yeah, Noah's Ark.
- Noah's in there, you're keeping him prisoner.
- I've got one last thing, it's very silly,
but I was looking into people
and how they managed to survive the ocean
once they'd been lost and people are out looking for them.
So there was a group of people, eight men and seven women,
and they were stuck out on a sort of life raft situation.
No one there to save them.
They have no water, how do they survive?
And they managed 12 days.
- Huge barrel of wide floats up.
How long did they manage?
- I think they were out there for 12 days.
- Like drinking turtle blood, that is not okay.
- So we're in that territory,
they've got to find a source of food.
- Drinking the little bit of liquid you get
in a fish's eye, we've said that before.
- We covered turtle blood enemas in the past.
- Yeah, turtle blood enemas.
- They were on a journey to Puerto Rico.
So one of the people on the boat was Faustina Mercedes.
She had back at home a one-year-old daughter,
which meant she was still lactating.
She was lactating.
And so she offered up her breasts to everyone on the boat.
And every day.
- How many people were on the boat?
- There were a lot, there were eight men.
- It was a cruise ship.
(all laughing)
- 2,000 people.
- Oh, Lord.
- Killing up every day.
(all laughing)
- Eight men, seven women.
Every day they would take a quick couple of sips,
and then that was just keeping them at bay.
And in order to feed herself,
her sister would go on the breast
and then pass the milk back to her.
- Oh, clever.
- Yeah.
- Wait, does that keep her going?
Does that, it feels like that doesn't make any sense.
It doesn't make any sense.
I know many people have pointed this out,
but it's-
- We're not producing milk out of nowhere.
- But it deals with your dry mouth, you know?
- It's basically,
they're very, very slowly cannibalizing this woman.
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- And our motherhood-
- She must have been quite saggy by the end,
was she?
- When she got back,
she said she was unable to feed her own child
because of the, it was pretty traumatic.
It was pretty weird.
- It was highly unsurprising.
- She said it was weird, yeah.
- Well.
- That's, that is weird.
- It is weird.
- I'm with her on that one.
- It's also, it's also the ending of,
loop it right around,
"The Grapes of Roth".
(all laughing)
- It is, "The Grapes of Roth" ends with a lady-
- Yeah, we're suckling on it.
- It ends with a young lady suckling an old man
who's starving to death.
It's the Dust Bowl America.
It's, that is the final seat.
- That's not right.
- That's the final seat.
- That's an incredible full circle.
I am only a hundred pages into "The Grapes of Roth",
10 years ago, fine, I never got any.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that when the Forbidden City in China
had its first telephone installed,
it was first used by the emperor to make prank phone calls.
This was the last emperor of China known as Puyi.
And after having the phone installed,
he went through a phone book.
He found one of his favorite opera singers,
a guy called Yang Xiaolu.
And he called him up and he said,
"Is this the great operatic singer?"
And he said, "Yes."
And then he just giggled and hung up.
- He hadn't developed the pranks by that point.
- No, that's not Bart Simpson level.
- No, the second one is closer to sort of teenage pranking.
He would call up local restaurants
and he would order a bunch of food to an address
that wasn't brilliant, the Forbidden City.
- And so here's a question.
It sounds like everyone in the country
had telephones apart from him.
- Yeah, possibly.
I mean, well, they, you know,
the emperor was kind of isolated from the rest of the world.
They were sort of, no one was really allowed
into the Forbidden City who weren't part of the system.
- Okay, you should probably explain who he was then.
- Well, yes.
So he was the, he was no longer really the emperor
by the time we were talking about when he was a teenager.
So he was born in 1906.
He became the emperor in 1908.
And he was deposed in 1911
because he, you know, he did such a terrible job.
- Yeah, they screwed him up.
- He thrown his ties out of the pram or something.
- It was like having Boris Johnson in charge over there.
- Yeah, so he, but he was allowed to stay in a palace
and keep living as though he were the supreme authority,
even though he wasn't.
So it's really strange.
- Well, he's a figurehead, wasn't he?
- That is a bit like Boris Johnson and Dominic Cummings,
isn't it?
- Yeah, exactly.
- It's exactly that.
- I'll let you stay.
- But when he asked for his phone in the first place,
he was told there is nothing in the ancestral regulations
to provide for this.
Because obviously his ancestors had been saying,
"Oh, I gotta have a phone."
- He wouldn't predict these things.
- It was a really weird, the old fashion,
and his father said it would upset imperial dignity
if outside voices could ring into the palace.
So there was controversy about it at the time.
- There were, absolutely.
And this was, he only really knew about the phones
because he had a British tutor,
who was a guy called Sir Reginald Fleming Johnston.
Not a sir at the time, I don't think,
but he became the English tutor to Puyi.
And he was the one who mentioned it.
He was, "Oh, you've got these things called phones."
And he said, "I love one."
- Johnson got pranked all the time by Puyi.
Puyi was constantly bringing up the man who'd got in the phone.
- That's a, 'cause kind of he was his only friend,
I got the impression.
So that's kind of sad.
And I'm sure Johnston pretends to be really upset
or amused every time.
- I think what we're gonna find
is that this is a pretty tragic story, isn't it?
This guy, very young, made an emperor,
turned out to be a utter, utter asshole,
but probably a victim of circumstance
because he was left on his own the whole time.
- That's the thing, the whole thing feeds on itself.
It's like no one comes out good in this story.
I just want to stick up for Puyi.
- Oh yeah.
- Because I've got this book out of the library.
- Yep.
- It's from Emperor to Citizen.
- Oh yes.
- And it's his memoir.
- Oh yeah.
- And I've been reading it.
And he, you know, it's actually a lot funnier
than we're all giving it credit for.
- Does he mention all the stuff
about constantly whipping eunuchs
just for the sake of having fun of watching that?
- He does.
- He beats them to death.
Did he do that?
- Does he mention it when his wife
had a child with another man
and then he had that baby stolen and killed?
Is that in there?
Is that part of the funny stuff?
- Okay, I haven't read the whole thing.
- Yeah.
He's a bad dude.
- No, he does mention the eunuch stuff though
because that was his whole big repentance thing.
His memoirs at the end of his life
was when he said, "I'm sorry for all this."
- There's an entire chapter called the eunuchs
because he lived surrounded by eunuchs.
- Yeah.
- There were a few hundred
and even that was a substantial cut down
from the glory days when there were--
- Substantial cut down to make those eunuchs.
- In the good old days,
there were thousands and thousands of you.
Look, just look, eunuchs, page 61,
just a great section on, you know,
the eunuchy life he lived.
- That's pretty funny.
- Until he was 10 years old,
he only played hide and seek with his own eunuchs.
He was very isolated growing up.
I mean, he had siblings,
but he didn't see his own mother for years and years and years
'cause he was taken away to live in the--
- He wasn't the child of the previous emperor.
The previous emperor was his uncle.
- That's right.
So there was the emperor Stowager,
who's a very famous character in ancient Chinese--
- Yeah, Sushi, who's this amazing person.
- And she, when the emperor had passed away,
there was no child in order to take over.
So this was the nephew.
- But there were moments of levity in his childhood.
I just think there were a few.
So just get this, if you ever went to the park,
this is the process of how it would happen.
He would have a eunuch walking ahead of him,
basically honking with his mouth to say,
"Everyone keep away."
He was like a sort of one-man beep, beep, beep system.
- Well, they hadn't invented the klaxon horn,
had they ever done yet? - No, yeah, no.
- So you needed the eunuch.
- A rare example of China not inventing something first,
just 'cause the eunuch system works so well.
Then there would be two chief eunuchs
going kind of crab-wise sideways,
just keeping an eye on everything.
Then there would be junior eunuchs with him.
There would be a eunuch with a canopy,
then more eunuchs holding a chair, a change of clothes,
some umbrellas, some cakes,
some hot water.
Then there were the medical eunuchs who came behind them.
- We've all been to the beach with our kids.
We know how much you have to take,
how many eunuchs you need.
- And then at the end is the eunuch with the Lou,
or the eunuchs, several eunuchs
with commodes and chamber pots and things.
And when he was a kid, he would just run around.
And it's called absolute mayhem
because the whole procession was trying to keep up
with a five-year-old boy
who was just running around in a park.
- Can I do it an incredibly quick?
This is his life.
So on the throne at two, kicked off the throne at six,
but got to be pretend emperor until like early mid 1920s,
at which point he was booted out by a warlord,
hung up being a playboy who used to be the emperor,
shagging around a bit.
Until 1931, Japan invaded Manchuria,
thought we'll pluck this former emperor,
put him in charge apparently, but he's our puppet.
He had no power,
but he got to keep living this weird fake royal life.
So continued being pampered and petted,
having people wait on him.
No power.
Then Japanese surrender 1945, he's fucked
because the Soviets come,
they put him in prison for five years.
Then they hand him over to the Chinese who reeducate him.
- The communists at this point.
- Who are communists, reeducate him.
He comes out, bona fide communists
and ends his life for Gardner.
Mad life.
- It is a mad life.
And reeducation is like being in a jail cell, right?
Like it's your-
- It's like going out to school, Dan.
- You're being conditioned.
Yeah, it's like a British boarding school.
Maybe that's why I think all this sounds absolutely
part of the course.
(all laughing)
We were constantly firing air guns at the Unix
at my school.
(all laughing)
- And the final bit of life where he became a Gardner,
he's fascinating just reading how useless he was
in day-to-day activities,
where he would sort of forget to flush a toilet
or know any directions or all these basic things
that you would-
- Shoelaces.
- Yeah, shoelaces.
- Just done his shoes for his whole life.
- I found it, I really question this,
but I mean, all the historians say it,
that when he was being reeducated by China,
it was partly to say be a communist
and apologize for uniting with the Japanese.
And it was partly to say,
"Here's how to look after yourself."
And they taught him to tie his shoelaces
and brush his teeth.
- He was breastfed until the age of eight.
- Yep.
- And at that point, the Dowager,
the powerful Dowager said,
"I think it's probably time we've removed your wet nurse
from you."
Which made him very sad,
'cause he would just believe we're still enjoying it.
- But he was stranded out in the Pacific at the time,
wasn't he?
(all laughing)
He had no other sustenance.
- If you were the Empress Dowager
in this weird fake palace situation,
was it real palace?
- First of all, what is an Empress Dowager?
- So she's the widow of the emperor,
who is now in a senior position,
kind of like a regent.
She's got a lot of authority,
but she's not technically--
- So she basically runs everything.
- Exactly.
- But she's putting in little puppets to do her work for her.
'Cause arguably this guy,
even though he was emperor three times,
he was never really in charge at any stage.
- Absolutely, absolutely.
He just wasn't in charge.
So yeah, the Dowager would have been the one
really controlling things,
saying, "I think maybe we should stop breastfeeding you now,"
that kind of thing.
- Or more like, "I think maybe we should invade Mongolia now."
- Yeah, exactly.
(all laughing)
They had this thing in the palace,
and again, this is after the First Revolution.
So they're not really in charge anymore,
but they're still treated with a lot of respect.
There was an as you wish lodge,
which was one of the 48 offices
that the staff were working in.
And if the Empress Dowager decided to do some painting,
the staff at the lodge would make her the painting already.
They basically made her a paint by numbers,
and she just had to fill in the colors
and put the title on it.
- That's great.
- What a great service.
- How cool is that?
- Wow, I want that.
He married five times,
which was easier to fit in
when you're allowed multiple marriages at once,
as you were.
But again, this seemed like an unfair trick.
This is in 1921.
So when he was being like pretend emperor with no power,
he was shown five photos of women.
It used to be that the emperor had women paraded
in front of him and got to choose,
but because he's been downgraded, he just got photos.
And he was asked, "Choose who you like best."
He picked one.
And then they chatted amongst themselves.
The other people at court went,
"No, she's not fit enough."
- No.
- And they made him marry the other one.
- So he did get a second wife from a different photo,
but on the day of marriage,
he then also married this first choice.
- Yes.
- He had two marriages on the same day.
- On the same day.
- That's a sitcom, ready to be written, isn't it?
(laughing)
- You know what, it sounds so unfunny their lives.
I want you to inject some gags in there, please.
- If anyone has any objection
and you're hoping the concubine hasn't turned up
to your wedding, or your wife hasn't turned up
for the concubine marriage, I think this is good.
- They were really young weren't they?
These young women who were brought in.
The last one who was called Li Yuqin.
She was, I think she was 14 or something
when she became the last imperial consort
and the emperor was comparatively old at this stage.
But she said, and in his view she said
she didn't even know how children were made at that stage.
She believed what she was told by her mother
that we were picked up from the rubbish bins.
I just think that's an unusual way of telling kids
that that's where babies come from.
- It's good parenting, and it's a story I've maintained.
- Well, I just think, 'cause we have like the stock
comes and drops the baby at the front door.
- That's very nice.
Cabbage patch is nice, fertility and growth.
- But rubbish bins?
- Yeah, to be fair,
this is an almost entirely unique based society.
It's very hard to actually get a handle
on where children come from in this world.
But he doesn't seem to have been
especially actually interested in women now.
- Well, he used to have blazing rounds with his wife,
both wives and all five wives about,
they would sometimes refer to him as a eunuch
because of his lack of prowess.
In the bedroom on the honeymoon night,
he had both of his first wives,
so the wife and the consort in the same bed,
waiting for him.
And when he went in, the story goes,
he ran out of the room and they don't know
if there was much, with any consummation happening.
- I'm hearing sitcom, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
- They're running in and running out,
certainly out of the element of farce.
His last wife seemed like quite a sweet story.
So this was in the 1960s.
He started off working as a street sweeper.
So the Chinese reeducated him, then pardoned him.
He became a street sweeper and there's a very sad story
of him getting lost and he has to approach his former subjects
and say, "Hello, I used to be the emperor.
I don't know how to get home.
I'm staying with family."
- He should just follow the clean streets.
If he goes back in the direction
that all the clean streets are,
he knows that's where he came from.
- The thing is James, he was so bad at all these tasks.
He hadn't actually effectively cleaned the streets.
- I think it's like the reverse of following the breadcrumbs.
- Yeah. - That's beautiful.
- Follow the lack of breadcrumbs.
But then he married this woman who was a nurse
and they stayed together forever.
And I think she didn't die until 1997.
And she said he was just desperate for someone to love him.
Which after that life?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Yeah, it's wild.
- So you find the story very depressing Dan,
which is fair. - Yeah.
- But actually, when he did write his memoirs at the end,
which were heavily influenced
by the Chinese Communist Party and its free education,
he did say he was-
- They come in for some very good press
at the end of this one, I've gotta say.
- Exactly.
He was at least contented with his current status
as a repentant and devoted communist who loved the party.
- I didn't notice, Addy, that it is a little red book.
(all laughing)
- Yes it is.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that the film "Spider-Man"
once cast two crowds of identical twin extras,
so they could film the same scene at the same time
in different places.
- Amazing. - That's amazing.
- Why?
You know, the first thing that comes into my head
is that meme of all the Spider-Man points at each other.
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- This is a really weird thing that just happened to happen
once in the annals of filming history.
And I got this because I was looking in the mirror
in history and I got this because I was looking
into casting and how people are cast
and how extras get cast in films.
And there was a woman called Jennifer Bender
who was the vice president of an extras film
about 10 years ago and she was being in due
to develop a business.
And she said that this film, they had two units shooting.
You know, you have-- - Sorry, two eunuchs.
(all laughing)
- There's a main unit and a second unit.
And they needed, yeah, due to just the nature of film.
It's so weird when you ask anyone about the world of film,
why their stuff is so weird.
They just say, "Well, that's just filming, isn't it?"
And it's basically, they had to shoot this scene
in two places at the same time
because of the schedule they were on to get this filmed.
So they said, "Well, let's just cast twins."
So they got 25 sets of twins, so one lot to one set,
so one lot to the other set, dressed them the same.
- That's really good.
- That's really cool.
- And one of the thing is that the twins,
they can telepathically communicate to each other, right?
So they can tell them what's happening in the other place.
- So when he said this fact, so we were like,
"Wow, why?" and you said, "You'll have to wait and see."
But what the answer is just,
'cause they're really shit at making film schedules.
- Schedules, it's just, you know.
- I'm sure it's easier to repack the schedule.
- I've got to say, Andy's sort of amazing mystery
is always going to end up, it was a matter of scheduling.
(laughing)
- Anna, you don't understand the nature of film.
Like, there are producers on your ass all the time saying,
"We've got to get this ready
"for the Hong Kong market in two weeks," you know?
- Can't have that many identical twins in the world.
- We've got to do the re-shoots.
Get Chalamet now.
I want five Chalamets on my desk tomorrow morning.
You know, it's hard, that's film.
- Incredible, so good.
- That's really cool.
- It's hard to be an extra.
- Oh, it sounds it.
I've done extra work a couple of times.
- Have you?
- Yeah.
- Well, in this podcast.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- What did you do?
- I can't remember.
It was a film with James McAvoy, which was quite exciting.
'Cause you often don't know before you turn up
what it's going to be.
- Yeah, right.
- Are they looking specifically for people
with quite normal-looking faces?
- Planned, ideally, they want balloons on sticks.
- Well, that is a thing, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Like, you can buy it.
- Is it like inflatable crowds for movies?
- No.
- Yeah.
- I think Seabiscuit famously, like, that's where it started.
- I think that was the first one.
Yeah, this guy called Joe Biggins,
who suddenly realized rather than organize loads
of extras and have to pay them,
you can just make inflatable people.
- Really?
- And you can do,
I think he got 10,000 in the back of a lorry,
which you can't do with extras.
(laughing)
- That's against union rules, yeah, yeah.
- Oh, they're very annoying about that.
- I really hope, like, in the background of, like,
a movie, like, Gladiator, if you look carefully,
there's just a slowly floppy, deflating.
- They're floating away, unfortunately.
- He is helium.
(laughing)
- Weirdly, appendages cost extra,
so he charges $50 for the Bod the torso.
- So is this from a big distance that you're shooting?
Of course, 'cause it couldn't be--
- Yeah, it is.
It's like crowd scenes, really.
So Seabiscuit, they're running around a horse track,
and they-- - So that's kind of perfect.
- And what you do is you get loads of them,
and then you get some humans in between them,
and your eyes are naturally drawn to the humans,
so the rest of it is just background.
- That's brilliant.
- It's amazing what we don't notice.
- I read about a movie that was made
by actually an old buddy of mine called Anthony Ng,
where he tracked down the lady who has the Guinness World
record for the most extras appearances in movies.
So her record was 1,951.
And they're everything from,
she said she was on 80% of the carry-on films.
She was in the very first episode of EastEnders.
She remembers being on a set one day with a guy,
having a great chat at the lunch hall,
and then he's the lead in a movie years later.
It's David Bowie, who says,
"Hey, we had a great chat,"
and they reconnected through that.
So she sees people go up.
So her name's Jill Goldston,
and we know that she has appeared in the 1,951 movies.
Certainly, she had at that point for the record,
because her husband is an accountant,
and he marked down every time.
He just got obsessed with making sure
that he had lists of what was going on.
Yeah, so there's a whole documentary about her,
and all her little things that she learned along the way.
Don't look at Tom Cruise when he's on set, you know?
- Are we saying because her husband's an accountant,
therefore sort of a really boring guy
who loves tallying up on hate information?
- He just happened to do it.
Yeah, he liked making Excel spreadsheets.
- Fair. - For respect.
- Yeah.
- Don't point at me when he's talking about a boring guy.
It's offensive.
- When we say someone comes from central casting.
- Oh, yeah.
- That's a phrase, right?
It's a sort of, oh, he's straight out of central casting.
I mean, someone's a bit of like a stock carrier,
or like if someone turns up and they're an accountant
and they're wearing a gray suit
and they're carrying a gray briefcase
and they've got to roll up a breller.
Central casting is an actual company,
which I didn't know until I was researching this,
and it's 100 years old this year,
'cause it started in 100 years ago, 1925.
- You could do the math as well.
- Wow, are you an accountant?
- Yeah, and just, that was the firm that Jennifer Bender
was the vice president of.
They place hundreds of, even now, these days,
they place hundreds of thousands of people a year.
- American based or here?
- Certainly in America, and I think all over,
and lots of people started out there.
David Niven started out there, he's a famous actor.
He was registered as Anglo-Saxon type number 2008,
and in the 1920s, extras were categorized into groups
because you just needed like a job lot of people
who looked a particular way,
and the groups included blonde, beautiful,
Latin, nurses, swimmers, and toothless.
(all laughing)
- Sometimes you could take a few boxes,
didn't you?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Beautiful, but toothless, you know, I'm not too gigs.
- The Log of the Rings films have got a lot of extras in,
haven't they, famously?
In fact, they pretty much cast everyone in New Zealand,
in those movies, I think.
In Return of the King,
they brought in some members of the New Zealand army,
and apparently they were way too enthusiastic
and kept breaking all the wooden swords and stuff.
(all laughing)
But in the two towers, they had a group of,
apologies to people who like Log of the Rings,
'cause I've never read any of them,
but there's a group called the Uruk High,
which is the orcs.
- Floorless.
- And they needed to get people to play them,
so they put a casting call out for everyone
over six foot tall in New Zealand
to come and play the Uruk High,
and they couldn't find enough people,
so they said, okay, everyone who's over five foot
can come in, and they brought in all these
like slightly shorter men,
and they were no one on set as the Uruk Low.
- Brilliant.
(all laughing)
- Having a fun day out as an extra on a movie.
Can we get the Uruk Low in?
- We would.
- Do you know how many extras were used on those movies?
It'd be in like the tens of thousands, right?
- Tens of thousands for sure.
- Yeah, so the one that gets cited as the movie
that possibly will never get broken for most extras
is Gandhi, which had 300,000 extras,
which is pretty extraordinary,
and that was for Gandhi's funeral scene.
- They weren't all paid, though.
- No.
- Most extras, like 200,000 of them
were just people who were milling around.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, that's true.
And that's often sometimes the case,
it's just actual people in the background.
There is a big list of movies of the most extras ever used,
Lord of the Rings is in there as well,
and another one is The Last Emperor movie,
which was filmed--
- Oh, about Puyi.
- Based on Puyi, it was filmed in the Forbidden City.
It was an extraordinary achievement of British filmmaking
because they managed to get access
to the Forbidden City itself to film inside.
So even when the queen was over there,
she couldn't visit it because they had priority access
over filming in there.
It was a big deal, it was a big collaboration.
- Well, she could have, if she applied to be an extra.
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- Is it a comedy?
- Yes, it's hilarious.
- It's a raucous unit-based comedy.
Have you guys heard of Waller groups?
- Waller.
- Waller, W-A-W-L-L-A.
- Yeah.
- No.
- Rick Waller was a singer from the early days of pop idol.
- Fats Waller was a blues, blues, you know?
I mean, we're talking extras in movies here.
Phoebe Waller Bridge, there's a bit of lots of movies.
- Oh, the prequel to Wall-E.
- Wall-A.
- Yeah, yes.
- I'm in the film area at least.
- You are, that's very good.
- No, this is to do with the fact that
if you were filming extras in the background,
you're miking up your main characters who you're recording.
You haven't necessarily miked up the extras,
but you need that background noise.
So they often hire people to come in
and make the sounds of the extras.
So they're sort of actors who are acting as the extras.
- Oh my God.
- And so they stand in and there'll be a group of them
who will stand in a studio
and they just have to make murmur sounds.
They're called Wallers because Wall-A, Wall-A, Wall-A, Wall-A.
- Like group-up, group-up, group-up.
- Exactly, yeah.
And so they're called Waller, but it's obviously changed.
But so that often happens where you just have a group of people
having to make the sounds of the people in the background.
- Who mentioned short extras?
Oh, the Uruk Hai, being the Merrick Lowe.
So there's another film which had short extras
for a very specific reason.
So can you guess?
It's one of the most famous films of all time.
- Chocolate Factory.
- Yeah, that was my first thought.
- Not Chocolate Factory, not Wizard of Oz.
Those probably both did do exactly that,
but please let's just move on.
- Yep.
- Okay, it's something with lots of children in it.
- It's not.
It's something where you need to make something else
look a different size.
- Oh, okay, a film about a giant.
- Dullover's Travels.
- Very good.
- Very nice.
- No one's so short they can be a little appugian.
(all laughing)
- We've been in a bunch of three entire people.
- Honey, I shrunk the kids.
- I think we've still got the same problem here.
- You've built a prop, but you need the prop to,
but the prop is only like three quarters
of the actual size of the actual thing it's representing.
So you need to make it look bigger.
- That, what's the one where the monkey's coming?
It's Earth all along and they planted the apes.
So there's the Statue of Liberty,
but they couldn't get a full size one.
So they had to get small apes.
- That's right.
This is not, I mean, it's not right, but it's brilliant.
- Oh, damn it.
- But it's right in that it's good.
Yeah, it's exactly that kind of thing.
- But it's something else like Stonehenge or the Eiffel.
- Titanic.
Leonardo DiCaprio is actually four foot two.
- That was a Titanic.
- James Cameron only used people under five foot eight
on the actual ship.
- Okay.
- To make it look, to make the ship look bigger.
- Wow.
- 'Cause it's a pretty big ship already.
- It is pretty big, but the ship was a bit smaller
than the real life Titanic.
It was 15% smaller.
So if you cast a load of like six foot nine people,
it was like a bit. - It's gonna look tiny.
You're right.
(all laughing)
- Why have they started the movie in the lifeboat?
What's going on?
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @Shrieberland.
Andy.
- I am on Blue Sky at @andrewhunterab.
James.
- I am on TikTok.
(all laughing)
- No, I just think it's James Harkin.
- And Anna, if they wanna get to us as a group.
- We are on @NoSuchThing on Twitter
or @NoSuchThingAsAfish on Instagram
or you can email our podcast at qi.com.
That's right.
What enthusiasm.
(all laughing)
- I always forget.
- Please do email podcast at qi.com
'cause we love hearing from you.
We love hearing from you.
Have you ever been an extra?
Are you Ridley Scott, you know, like right in?
- Yes.
- You're a eunuch.
(all laughing)
- But I actually do write it
because we use that material for our bonus episodes.
- We do, you can get a mention.
You can be an extra on our show.
- You can, you'll get a mention on Drop Us Align,
which is part of Club Fish,
which is our very secretive community of bonus episodes
and stuff.
It's great.
It's check it out.
And you can find out more about that
by going to NoSuchThingAsAfish.com
and you'll find all of our previous episodes
up there as well.
Or you can just come back next week.
We'll be back again with another episode.
We will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)