"Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern."
This episode's Annotishinsky's last episode for a while, as she heads off onto maternity
leave. We'll be seeing her in nine months, but we've got one more episode. Once again,
we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven
days, and in a particular order, here we go. Starting with fact number one, and that
is my fact. My fact this week is that Harriet Beatrice Stowe, author of Uncle Tom's Cabin,
wrote the novel for the first time twice. This is a story I found it on a website
that is Uncle Tom's Cabin, an American culture. It's a dedicated page to all historical articles
about Harriet Beatrice Stowe. In it, it points out that near the end of her life, she was suffering
from a disease of the brain. She might have dementia, she might have Alzheimer's, we're
not quite sure. But in that period, she found herself rewriting as if it were a new story
Uncle Tom's Cabin, and telling everyone, "I've got this amazing book that I'm writing.
I think it's going to be big." Apparently, when people were looking at the writing, it
was almost word for word what the original book was. The Washington Post said, "If the
manuscript could be compared with the corresponding portions of the original copy, it is not likely
that much difference of appearance would be discovered."
So it wasn't a big prose-lavery tract suddenly that she found herself producing in the
'80s.
We should explain those two things, Harriet Beatrice Stowe, and Uncle Tom's Cabin, I guess.
It's a property book, isn't it? How to make a desirable residence on a budget.
This is a game-changing book in America.
Harriet Beatrice Stowe, she was very much against the world of slavery in America, came from
a family that was very, very much fighting that cause. So she wrote a series of stories
that were published, like how Dickens used to do it. It's serialized in a magazine.
When the book came out, it just really hit a note. It suddenly made sense to a lot of
white America about what was going on. There was this new thing that was put in place in
this period whereby if you were caught housing a runaway slave, you were now going to jail,
or you were going to be fined, which meant that no one was looking after these people. And
then there was very much parallels of what's going on right now in America. People were
being taken away. Black Americans would know due process, and they were being jailed, and
it was a hectic time. So this book was saying this is not acceptable.
It arguably led to the civil war. I think, right?
Yeah, Lincoln jokes about that, didn't they? The little woman who started the civil war.
I love that. So they met. Harriet Beatrice Stowe, Met Lincoln, and I think about 1862, and
he supposedly said that to her on the little woman who wrote the book that started this
great war. I think it might be a later. Her family said it would have been said later.
They were allowed to do that. They achieved a lot of the family.
But for sure, it did change a lot of minds in America. It was so, sorry to go into book
sales mode, but it was so successful. I think it sold 300,000 copies in the USA in its first
year. And it I think might have been the biggest seller of any book in that century, the
19th century, barring the Bible. I think it was. It was big. The time said that the amount
of royalties that she got is the largest sum of money ever received by any author, either
American or European, from the sales of a single work in such an amount of time.
Wow. Do you know what the second best selling book of the 1850s was?
Oh, good question. 1850s. Is this guessable? Dickens? No, no, it's not guessable. I'd be astonished
if you don't have it. Right. It hasn't had the same kind of longevity as Uncle Tom's
cabin. So Uncle Tom's cabin was the top. And then the second was called Ten Nights in
a Bar, and what I saw there. Absolutely. That sounds awesome. It does sound like more fun
reading. Unless it's like, because I've been to bars regularly, and actually you tend
to see the same things again and again. It's like, oh, that group of people watching
the horse racing. Yeah, same like crying in the corner. There's Andy telling the same
anecdote over and over again. I empathise with Harriet and be just, I don't mean to trivialise
whatever condition she had, but like I frequently will get to the end of an anecdote and people
around me are going, yeah, yes, Andy, yes, that was, yeah, that was, that was an anecdote. I told
you. Half an hour ago. In that article, by the way, because I found it in the newspaper
archives, they also said that she had confusedly given permission to two publishers to write
her official biography thinking that they were the same person. And there's a big sort of financial
problem between those two companies. I can really imagine doing that now. Actually, like
you see that same, not very good with family. You've got face blindness. You've probably promised
your biography to ten of them. Yeah, I'm quite disappointed. It hasn't been written yet.
What's really interesting is the reaction to the book. Because obviously, as we've also had
a huge reaction, there was a real life inspiration, a man called Josiah Henson, who was himself
enslaved and in real life escaped to Canada and founded a settlement and a school for former
slaves. But what's amazing is after the book came out and had this huge social reaction
and effect, there was a ferocious pro-slavery pushback even in the novel sphere. So at least
15 novels were published in response, very much in favor of slavery, saying slaves in the
south are better off and then free men and women in the north. So one of them was called
Uncle Robin in his cabin in Virginia and Tom, without one, in Boston. Not a good title.
Like we can all agree. A shit title for a book. And the argument inside, obviously. Yeah.
Yeah, and you were saying that it was kind of in magazines to start off with, it was serialized.
They also had pro-slavery magazines. Right. Basically doing the opposite. So if you went
to WHO Smiths in mid-19th century America, on the shelves, you would have half of them
would be pro-slavery magazines and half would be anti-slavery magazines. Well, it was like
the BBC today. You've got to have balance, haven't you? If you get on then. Get on the
anti-fascist, you've got to get on the fascist. But she wrote another book off the back of Uncle
Tom's cabin, the key to Uncle Tom's cabin, which was basically a bibliography describing
everything that had gone into Uncle Tom's cabin. She named Josiah Henson as the inspiration
for the Uncle Tom character. Because they were like, oh, you just made it up. You'd never
even been here. You don't know any enslaved people. You just like, and she needed to prove
that it wasn't like that. Yeah. But good. I mean, great. When the publisher says, what's
next? Harriet? Well, it's more Uncle Tom's cabin in a good way. That's a good idea. Like,
you know, like the QI fat books that we used to write. We could write another one saying,
no, no, this is true. Well, that's the thing. Well, then I'm keeping our sources. Because
I have a panic attack every time James sent me an email going, and what is your source
for this? Like, I don't know. I do need it immediately. Which James, you want to publish
a book of just pure URLs. It's the key to QI. I got another one of her writings. Lady Byron
vindicated. Oh, yeah. This is where she gets spicy. Yeah. She was defending Byron's widow
by revealing that Byron had an affair with his own sister half sister. Okay. Not that that
changes matters. Sorry. Half sister. Oh, well, that's not even a fact then. Is that not interesting?
No, it was incredibly. This was a second most controversial book. I'd say when she published
this piece in the Atlantic, American magazine still going today, it lost them 15,000 subscribers
who said, I don't mind reading about various other things, but I draw the line at Law Byron
having an affair with his half sister. I think it was a third of a subscriber's cloud. I mean,
that's a big hit, isn't it? That's one article you feel so. You know what? She wrote another
book in 1873 called Women in Sacred History, where she said that one of the apostles was
a woman, Lydia. So she was just an edgelard. Yeah. It's just keeping coming. That's stunning.
Yeah. And the clue is in the name, isn't it? Lydia the Apostle? Oh, there's no one else
in that. Did you say which of the apostles was? Yeah, Lydia. No, but which was that Thomas?
No, I think like the Bible, just there are actually 13 apostles, but the Bible never mentioned
it. See, it must have been one of the judices. Well, there were two judices. That's right.
Two James's. One of them must have been the Lydia. I reckon. You just like panicked and
gave the name of the person she was looking at. That's what you do, isn't it? It's a Mrs.
outfire moment. Just quickly on the on the Byron thing, because she was great mates with Lady Byron,
because after Uncle Tom's cabin, she met everyone. I mean, she was friends with so many
eminent people. George Elliott, wouldn't she? Great mates. But this wrecked her reputation,
the Byron book. There was so much criticism. She had to hire a secretary to deal with the
correspondence and hire a lawyer. And the person who stood up for her, I'm afraid enemy
of the podcast, Mark Twain, he stood up for her and he was really good about it. And I just
think that's inviscated a bit. They were mates. They were mates. They were mates, but have
you seen what he was running about her in their later life? Because they were neighbours,
not just mates. Oh, what did he say about her? I mean, it's not very nice.
She trimmed the head wrong. Yeah. That's not getting the garden. Dogwood shit in his garden.
No, he said her mind had decayed and she was a pathetic figure. But I think he means
pathetic, not as in we mean pathetic. Yeah, that's not criticism. I read that wrong then.
Yeah, that no pathetic back then would have meant someone that you feel really sorry for
because she's got really unwell. And then he wrote, people in the area where they both
of them lived would leave their doors open and then Harriet Beecher Stowe would go into
their houses and then push them over and go, "Whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop,
whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop. She wrote that as well."
But then also that she would play her piano and you'd hear her singing melancholic songs to
great effect. Right. Yeah, no, they were mates. They were mates. Okay, cool. Can we finally
talk about her husband? Because we talk about these women all the time on this podcast,
don't we? Agreed. She wrote a lot of stuff, but he did write a pamphlet.
And the pamphlet that he wrote described the frequent visitations from tiny fairies that
danced on his windowsill. Really? Yeah. And I bet he talked about his pamphlet much more
than she talked about her, like 50 seminal books and crucial impact on 19th century literature.
Well, I can tell you that his fairies that he saw were ruled over by King and Queen, who
were slightly larger than the other fairies, but they had a sinister and selfish expression
on their faces that stopped him from trusting them. Even though they always smiled, there
is something sinister about them, so he didn't trust these fairies. Sorry, is this a vision
he had, and then he wrote into a pamphlet? Or is this a metaphor for something? It's a metaphor.
Yeah, it's what he thought, yeah. That's kind of sad, because I know he was very encouraging
of her, this very career, and she probably felt like she should do the same for him, but...
I just need a quick quote for the cover, darling, if that's all right. Just like something
about the fairies and how they're really well described or something. Yeah, yeah, well,
yeah. Sorry, I've got to go meet Queen Victoria now.
Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Andy. My fact is, some tortoises have hinges.
So these are imaginatively named animals called hingeback tortoises, and there are loads of species,
and they have a hinge at the back. It's like a hatchback car. Yeah. And it means their back can
just go boom, and close up when they're trying to retreat into their shell. There are loads of
different species. There's the forest, there's bells, there's the homes, there's the western.
I saw some of them two weeks ago, which is why I submitted this fact, yeah. That's so cool.
Could you see the hinge? I couldn't get my arm quite far off into the enclosure to...
It was a shame, but I read all about them. This was in a little rainforest experience near
Reading. It's the home of rainforest experiences. It's a fantastic place, like it's amazing,
the stuff they had there. Anyway, and they have these. Sorry, when you say retreat into their shell,
I would have thought that that would be on the front, then you'd put their head, retract
their heads in, and then they'd drop a hinge down. But what they're retreating their bottom into
their shell, and then they're... I think they're legs on their legs and their tail, basically.
Their legs and their tail just go back in. I don't think any species has yet evolved a front hinge,
but that's something evolution is probably working on. So if the predates are comes from the front,
they're buggered. Well, I don't know. I mean, because you're always going to be running away from
a predator, aren't you? So it does make sense that you're closing the back. Yeah. They can retreat
a fair bit inside. I think they can pull, obviously, they can pull their heads in. I just don't know
how far in. There are some which have a really awkward thing where they put their head in and to the
side, and they just sort of scooch in there like that. I'm doing it now for the benefit of listeners.
You've done a lot of physical stuff so far in this fact for the benefit of listeners,
that they're enjoying. That's more to come. I believe also the hinge helps them to open their shell
a bit further and lay their eggs. And they have eggs that are bigger than average for a turtle,
which means that the hinge is useful. Brilliant. They're mutant turtles. They do live into their
teens, I believe. Yeah. And we should say just because you've chucked in the word turtle now,
and I didn't look into them, but they are tortoises, right? Yeah, they are. Although they're
often used interchangeably, and we've talked about the difference. Well, tortoises are turtle,
but a turtle's not a tortoise. Yeah. Okay, I get it. Yeah. I don't. And they also, their shell,
is slightly different than normal shells. It's got a little channel that when it rains,
the water goes down the channel and goes straight to their mouth. What no it doesn't.
They've got guttering. What do you mean? Like one of those American sports hats that has a straw
that comes right in. Exactly like that. They shouldn't be the hinge back tortoise. They should be
the beer can. That's tartar. That's unbelievable. Yeah. That's incredible. That's incredible.
Evolution, man. I know we say it week in, week out on this show, but it's thrown up some cracking
stuff. It does well. Yeah. There are box turtles, and they are slightly different. I think they might
also be a kind of tortoise, but they're definitely called the box turtle, and they have a hinge on
their belly, which helps them to close the front and back half up like a box when they flex it.
So they become, like all your innards are going to drop out every time you open it. I believe it goes
the opposite way to that. Yes. Right. I think it's closing up, not opening out. I'm splitting open.
I've got to pick that up. Yeah. I find that hard to visualise without anything. I'm not getting on
the floor, but I'm sorry. But the eastern box turtle was going to be made the official state emblem,
or one of the official state emblems of Virginia. You know, every American state has like this is the
official state fern and the official state ice cream flavour. Yeah. Exactly. And so Virginia,
they suggested a couple of times in different years, bills to honour the eastern box turtle.
And I just really like this. I think this is from the Wikipedia about them. In 2009,
delegate Frank Hargrove of Hannover asked why Virginia would make an official emblem of an animal
that retreats into its shell when frightened and dies by the thousands crawling across roads.
I just think that's such a mean thing. Yeah. Yeah, it's got other assets. It's not it's fault
that we've created the car. No, exactly. On turtles being able to do entertaining things.
In the olden days, I found this out in a study which was called tortoise rides and alligator slides.
In zoos that had tortoises, tortoise rides were the thing. It was like the donkey ride,
but it was a tortoise ride. I've seen a photo of Rothschild on the back of a tortoise.
Rothschild loved riding his tortoises. Yes, but if you went to the zoo, sorry.
You wanted to just Walter Rothschild, who was a big old collector. Is that one knows who Rothschild is?
Or it might be that I couldn't remember his first name, so I just said his surname.
But this is what you would do if you went to any zoo which had giant tortoises,
then they would offer rides and it would either be just lots of children would climb on top.
Or they had little tortoise carriages and the tortoise would pull it.
Okay, that is cute. I don't know why we stopped doing that.
No, let's bring it back.
What's an alligator slide, sorry.
The alligator slide. No, it was said in this study that this was the most outrageous thing
that they made animals do, but basically it was making an alligator go up before me to high-ish ramp.
And then sliding down a steep slide, which sounds to me incredibly fun.
You wouldn't have to make me do that. You're not an alligator though, are you?
I'm not an alligator. Also, alligator rides were commonly offered.
There were lots of pictures of children. Children sitting on the backs of alligators.
It's not your most loved child though.
I think it would be the least favourite. Yeah, number three.
I guess if you lock the mouth shut, you're okay if you're not in water.
You can hold the mouth shut with no force or with elastic band, you can hold it.
And that's what you'll say to child number three as you said in English.
Come on, little Johnny, you're stronger than the elastic band, aren't you?
What kind of pair of you? You see an elastic band over their mouth?
You go, "Yeah, it's all good, man. It's all good."
I can't say. In the pictures I saw in the mouth, it was hanging open.
As it crumbled along with the child, but I'm sure that they're very well-trained.
Just to say, the jaws of these animals like crocodiles and alligators and camons,
they're really strong for closing, they're really weak for opening.
No, absolutely. That's the kind of ki-fact that, in real life, I'm not sure.
I'm willing to put my reputation on the line and my genitals.
No, you have further alligator, a very good breakfast already, right? I think so.
It was either today or last week that he had breakfast. I'm sure he's still full.
Have you guys heard other unusual tortoises and turtles and things?
The African pancake tortoise.
No, this is a great one. I'm going to say flat.
It's flat. It's got a flat shell, but the cool thing about it is not only that,
but it's that it can flip over very quickly when it lands on its back because it's so light.
It's a bit like in robot wars, there's always one that can write itself.
Yeah.
And those are always the most dangerous robots of all.
But you're saying this can flip onto its back very quickly?
I can say it flips off its back.
It can write itself.
So like the fingers with tortoises is at least in cartoons,
they end up on their back and they can't get back onto their feet, right?
I think that is real.
I think it takes twice or three times as much energy for most of them to do that as it would to walk.
So that's great.
Well, the African pancake one, though, it has a very light shell which means it can run
much faster than your average tortoise.
But it's not got a big defense because it's got a very light shell.
So when it's threatened, it just runs for cover and it runs under a rocky crevice
and then breathes in like a puff of fish.
And it's impossible to pull it out because it's just wedged in there.
Oh, so cool.
The rock becomes the shell.
Yeah, wow.
You've really got to find the perfect shape, rock.
I can imagine running to a huge pile of rocks is staring panic.
So all of them, I can't get under that one.
That one's too big.
That one's, ah, where's the rock that's made for me, but cool.
That's a really good point.
Do they sus out the local rocks ahead of them?
I don't have data.
We found the new books of tortoises with all the rock locations.
Well, because they do an interesting thing whereby they'll often sleep
in a bit where they know the sun is going to get to them in the morning.
So this is not all species of tortoises, but a lot.
They can't dissipate the part of the sun.
Yeah, quite clever.
So that's where they will sleep.
So they know that when the sun hits in the morning, it warms them up and it gets them going.
They only have to have been there for the previous morning.
They've got good memories.
Yeah, okay.
It's not so, okay.
Unless they go to a new place on holiday and they just work out which way is east and west.
That's quite cool.
Because I've failed to do that on holiday when parking the car, for example.
You park the higher car under the shade of the one tree.
And you think, oh, that'll be right for four hours.
Then you come back, same getting on a train.
And you sit on one side of the train and you're like, oh, this will be beautiful.
And then suddenly you're in there.
You're in an oven.
Well, that's because you're both warm-blooded creatures.
So you don't understand the necessity.
If you were a tortoise, you would have died on that train.
And you would have died on that path.
So it's more important.
Well, when the ticket collects, okay, my ran and hid between some perfectly sized suitcases.
The Galapagos silence tortoises.
Very famous because of Darwin going there, finding them.
And they were also really endangered.
Partly because we ate them all.
So Darwin came across them.
They had delicious meat.
Who rode them, too, didn't he?
I think he did he ride them.
Yeah, picture of him having a cheeky ride.
Yeah, he was good.
If you're the one who's discovered them.
Yeah.
And also, I think if you discover any species, you should be allowed to ride it.
Yes, that's a good rule.
I mean, incredibly fragile bats.
No, I'm getting on that.
Settle it up.
I think if you discover a new species, you get a little card.
And you can go to any zoo in the world.
And you just pull it out and you go, "I'm allowed to ride this."
The Lama is recovering from a serious lumbar region surgery, it doesn't matter.
So yeah, they were big and delicious.
And they were endangered.
And actually, on the island of Espanola,
there's a specific kind of giant tortoise,
which was down to 14 in number in the 1970s.
Wow.
But now, their numbers have really recovered.
And there are over 3,000 because of breeding programs.
And the reason this is really important to conserve them.
One of the reasons is that they're extremely important for albatrosses.
Because they facilitate something about albatross lives.
What do you think of when you think albatrosses?
I think of them at sea, bad luck.
- Yeah. - In Japan. - Oh, no.
- In Japan. - In Japan.
- Crossbow. - Yes, yeah.
- And they fly for extremely long periods.
- That's good. - Oh, big wingspanes.
- Big, there we go.
You can have your guest down, but we've got the rounds.
- I think, I think.
- It was a phrase in car games, a dead rubber.
- Well, there's absolutely no consequence whatsoever.
- I wouldn't see that on university challenge
where someone buzzes in, "Bzzz."
Lord Byron, that's correct.
- That goes, "No, no, I can have another guest."
Sorry, Jeremy, just quickly.
- I think. - Yes.
- That, quite often they need to crack things open.
And there's nothing that's really hard around.
So, an albatross will fly over a giant tortoise,
drop the item, be it an egg or whatever.
It cracks open on their tortoise shell.
- Like a reverse escalus.
- Yes, exactly. - Oh.
- Exactly. - That is correct.
That's actually how albatross has hatched their eggs
is they dropped more bags of tortoises.
- So escalus supposedly died when an eagle was carrying a tortoise
and dropped it on his head,
'cause thinking it was a rock.
- Exactly, yeah, this is the opposite of that.
- Is he right, Anna?
- It's really more about Andy's answer
that they're very big windspans.
Mean that, and the fact that they're very large anyway,
they need a long runway to take off
'cause they keep running and flapping, but like this one.
And they need to be very wide.
And as soon as the tortoises went,
what they do is they tramp up and down the mountains all day
and they tramp down the vegetation straight lines
and they make these flawless, huge runways.
And without them, the albatrosses can't take off.
So the albatrosses were all dying out as well.
- I don't think Andy got that right.
I think he just said wings and you filled in the rest.
- It's a very big, and I was about to go on to say,
exactly that about what they're creating.
- Yeah, sorry.
If you're a cuckold in Northern China.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Big shout out to the cuckolds in Northern China.
- I know, I know you guys are listening.
You've got time on your hands, now she's gone.
Your known as a tortoise, that term survives.
It's hundreds of years old term.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Why is it?
- Is it about being too slow and so someone's whips
someone out from under your nose?
- Oh, very good, but it's not right.
- I think it was getting going into your shell.
Something like that.
- Yeah, that's it.
So they're associated.
- I'm not a psycho.
- I think I know.
Basically, they're, I think they're associated with,
I'm sorry to say a D2 messing penis.
And so it's all sort of shrinking down and going
soft and you're shirking danger as well.
So that's why.
- Thank god he didn't act that one out.
(laughing)
- I am, Dan, I am.
You just can't see under the table.
- Can I say one thing about hinges?
- Oh, okay, yeah.
- So there's a door in this room.
- Yeah.
- It leads to the next room.
And there are three hinges on it.
What can you tell me about the spacing
of the top and bottom hinges?
- The, the equidistant?
- Yeah, they seem, they seem--
- They seem it, don't they?
- Yeah, they seem the same as in the top of the bottom.
- Is the bottom one actually a bit closer
to the middle one compared to the top one?
- Yeah, but the bottom one is further from the floor
than the top one is from the top.
- Oh!
- And there's a few reasons for that.
One of them is, it's an illusion.
- Yeah.
- So to you, it looks about the same,
but actually it's not the same.
And that's because of the foreshortening effects.
So when things are slightly further away,
distance looks different.
And the other thing is, the top of your door,
the hinge is holding more of the weight.
So the top one needs to be closer to the top.
- Close to the pivot.
- Closer to the pivot.
- Closer to the pivot weight.
- Exactly, yeah.
- We can all agree the middle one
is not pulling its weight there, right?
(laughing)
- What's it he been doing?
- What's middle hinge doing?
- The middle one is there just because
three is a good number for the size of a door.
- I guess it helps with the illusion as well.
- Yeah, it does.
- But the middle one is usually exactly in the middle.
- That's very good to know this.
So if you ever climb a step ladder
and suddenly look at your door and think,
hang on, the hinges are all off.
And then you get down and think they're not again.
That's just the illusion.
- It might not just be the illusion
if you're doing DIY, and it might be like,
and with this particular door, James.
- Yeah.
- The frame that's around this door
is not on the bottom, but is on the top.
- Oh yeah.
- It's creating anything towards that illusion as well
that I'm adding in the frame.
- Can't hurt.
(laughing)
- If the frame is--
- It's a little question of the night,
because this is, he wants to get home.
(laughing)
- And all questions don't go.
Bye.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, and it's time for fact number three.
And that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that after Frida Kahlo died,
all her clothes and possessions spent 50 years
in a bathroom.
- Wow.
- Functioning bathroom?
- People weren't going in and out using it, no.
With no number ones, no number twos.
- Big bathroom, 'cause presumably she had a lot of possessions.
- She did have a hell of a lot of stuff in there,
so because it must have been.
So just to tell you how this happened,
it wasn't necessarily the plan,
but Frida Kahlo died in 1954.
- She was a Mexican artist.
- And yes, to go back one step further,
she was a Mexican artist.
- Famously Mono Browd.
- Famously Mono Browd, yes.
- Imagine Oasis, but they're Mexican,
and instead of singing songs, they paint stuff.
- Yes.
- And she did, she modeled herself on Oasis, actually.
So I think you've got the picture.
She dies 1954, her husband, Diego Rivera,
shot all of her belongings in a bathroom in her house,
which is called the Blue House in Mexico City.
And it was a house where she'd been born,
where she'd grown up, and where she and Diego Rivera lived,
and where she'd died.
And he said, "I want all of her possessions
"to be locked in here until 15 years after I die."
- 15.
I know a bit of a twist coming.
And we don't really know why.
We think like out of sensitivity for her,
things that might be revealed,
and thought, you know, give it a bit of time,
'cause there's all her letters and stuff.
But basically, he entrusted this task
to a woman called Dolores Olmedo,
who was a huge fan of Diego Rivera,
as all women sort of were.
He was obviously a compelling man.
So I think she probably fancied him
and definitely adored him, didn't really like Frida.
And so she just never took him out.
She just locked them in the bathroom,
waited, Diego Rivera died a few years later,
and she just kept them in there.
- Of constipation.
(laughing)
'Cause the bathroom door was locked.
- Indeed, no, but the rest of the house was full of shit,
but the time you got there.
(laughing)
And yeah, it was only in 2004,
after she died that someone said,
"Should we open that bathroom for the Frida color shit,
"see what's in there?"
And it's all her stuff, 22,000 documents,
300 items of clothing, 6,000 photos,
her prosthetic leg, her back brace.
- Oh, wow.
- All of her makeup textiles.
- So why did she need the prosthetic leg
and her back brace?
- Oh, yes.
Well, this is all part of her great stories,
isn't it, of pain and injury?
- Well, she had a terrible, nearly fatal bus crash
when she was 18.
She was involved in that.
She had already got polio as a girl.
She already had to wear a prosthesis
on her right leg due to the polio.
And then this bus crash completely wrecked her life.
She broke her pelvis, her collarbone, her ribs, her back.
Most of her life, she had to wear plaster corsets
to support her.
And so much of this, as Anna says, made its way in her art.
- Frequently about pain.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I mean, it's frequently just this,
she's got this really badly broken body
for the back bone.
- She also painted her casts quite a lot, didn't she?
- Yeah.
- Kind of some of the first paintings she did was on her casts.
And she even painted the bus that hit her on her cast,
which I think is pretty badass.
- We should talk a bit about this crash
'cause it was an extreme crash.
She was with her boyfriend.
She was about 18, it was 1925.
And basically a tram plowed very slowly into their bus.
And the boyfriend remembers his knees
were suddenly touching the knees
of the people sitting on the bench opposite as it bent.
And then the whole vehicle splintered
into a million pieces.
And as well as all those horrendous breakages
were the worst thing that happened
was she got impaled on a steel handrail
that went straight through her abdomen.
And she didn't realize at the time
the extent of her injuries.
It's like, I guess you don't in the shock of the moment.
She said, "The first thing I thought of
was this Mexican toy that I just got."
And I thought, "Oh, no, where is it?"
I've lost it in the wreckage.
- Yeah, right.
- And her boyfriend looked at him and was like,
"Yeah, you're also impaled on a large metal spike."
And they had to pull it out.
- Oh, God, and also there are the mad details
that she's covered in blood, obviously.
But then someone, who they speculated
was probably a house painter,
was carrying a big box of gold paint, sparkly gold paint.
And that sort of flew through the air
and landed all over her as well.
- Oh my God.
- So she was covered in blood
with all these gold sprinkles all over her.
- And then a piano that was being lifted
into a building dropped on top of her.
- Yeah, so every laurel in heart.
- It is absolutely extraordinary.
It's just really, really kind of broccoli awful.
So she started painting partly in recovery
from this.
And she's an amazing artist.
I didn't really know much of her work before this.
And like frequently self-portraits
and self-portraits throughout her life, you know?
And then she met Diego Rivera,
who was a mural painter.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
Incredibly famous.
- Incredibly famous.
- Much older than her, like 20 years of senior.
- Yeah. - Twice her age.
- Twice her age.
She'd been married twice before.
His doctor had told him he was unfit for monogamy
as a diagnosis.
- Is he?
(laughing)
- Oh, you look like you're out with the doctor
when you book that GP appointment.
- I just know that when you book a doctor's appointment
in the UK, I don't know if it's for everyone,
but I have to go on a website
and I have to click all the things that are wrong with me.
- Me too.
- And monogamy has never been one of the checkmasters.
- Did he have that as like, you know, if he got caught,
he would show that note to his partner.
And just saying, I think he did get caught a lot.
I mean, he had so many affairs.
- Yeah, so did she.
- Yeah.
- Well, she made a tortoise out of him.
I'll tell you that much.
But he also made a tortoise out of her a lot.
- So what's the making the tortoise?
- We're in Northern China, I know.
- Sorry, I forgot that bit.
- Her sister he hadn't affair with?
- Yeah.
- God's sake, Diego.
- Well, they had a very interesting setup though.
When they moved into their marital house,
weirdly, it was two houses connected by a rooftop bridge.
And so he had his studio in one of them.
She had her studio in the other,
but they just had their own pads
for sleeping with him models and assistants
and her with just men and women that she fancied.
- And Leon Trotsky.
- Right, the twist.
- What a cameo.
- Extraordinary.
- I can't get over the Trotsky thing.
I can't get over the fact that she hadn't affair
with Leon Trotsky.
When he was, you know, he'd fled.
He'd been kicked out of Russia, hadn't he,
after the revolution.
- So he was like a revolutionary
who fell out with Stalin, basically.
- That was not the thing to do in the thirties.
- Oh no.
- No, no, no, no.
- All the people in the world to fall out with,
he was one of the worst.
- Absolutely, absolutely.
- And he needed someone to go, didn't he,
that we're safe.
And actually it was Diego.
- I'd done it.
- Spoiler, he was assassinated a few years later
by one of Stalin's henchmen.
- Sure.
- So he didn't find that place in the end.
- No.
- But he did meet Diego and Frieda
and they banged the Mexican president
to let him into the country and his house him.
So the president said, okay, we'll house him
and then they kept him in that house for two years
and their affair was very short.
It was just at the start in 1937.
- He was also very done.
- Yes, and he was very--
- He was married, Mrs. Trotsky was around.
Mrs. Trotsky is a funny name.
I just think that's a funny, you don't think of,
and is there a Mrs. Trotsky, you know?
- It sounds like a little piglet.
- A pig mind a character.
(all laughing)
But some of their meetings,
Frieda's and Leon Trotsky's, they took place
at the house of the very sister
who had slept with Frieda's husband, Diego.
- Right.
- Oh, it's messy.
- His death was wild as well, Trotsky's.
- Trotsky's?
- Because he was killed with a nice pig,
and the guy was a mountaineer who did it,
so he knew how to swing one,
and he thought I could probably get it in two goes.
He didn't want to fire a gun,
because he didn't want to raise noise.
He needed to escape from this compound
that Trotsky was staying in.
So, but he did it, it went into his skull,
but not deep enough to kill him.
So Trotsky was running around,
going, there's a nice pig in my head.
Can we talk about the brows?
- A famous brow.
- The bruise.
- Oh, okay, her brows, her brow.
She emphasized that, didn't she?
- Yeah.
- She painted it on, she made it up.
She emphasized her moustache as well.
She had a tiny little bit of moustache-ness,
but she really emphasized it to make herself seem
strong, basically, at masculine.
- Yeah, yeah.
- She did really like that sort of,
she really did push her brands, didn't she?
Like, she claimed that she was born on a day
that she wasn't born at,
'cause it was the same year as the Mexican Revolution.
- Oh really?
- Yeah, I mean, three years apart.
It wasn't like she claimed she was born the next week.
She killed her three years later.
- Wow.
- Coincidence, it makes her three years younger.
- But then, of course, like, it's still the case now.
We're like, Frida Kahlo.
If you look at all the kind of art books
that my daughter's got three years old
of all got Frida Kahlo in.
'Cause she's just such a brand, isn't she?
- She invented an aesthetic that genuinely
think my three year old
would be able to recognize Frida Kahlo.
- Yeah, right.
- For sure.
- Well, they did a Barbie of her as well.
- Yeah.
- And the Barbie got banned in Mexico
because weirdly, they took away the monobrow
as part of the look, this iconic look.
They made her incredibly slim.
So the family, basically.
- Yeah, it wasn't the government banned there.
- Yeah.
- There was a lawsuit because they didn't want this
to be sold in Mexico and they pulled off the shelves.
- Yeah.
- But it wasn't.
- You wouldn't not have a monobrow out of the Barbie.
- Yeah.
- The most famous thing about her.
It's extraordinary, isn't it?
- And so Andy, as you said, she did paint herself a lot.
So apparently, in total, it's 143 paintings.
55 of which were self portraits.
And they're very surrealistic.
I didn't realize she was as surreal as she was.
There's one, which is called my birth,
where she's giving birth to herself.
So you see her head coming out of her own vagina.
You don't see that it's her because there's a sheet
over the head of the person giving birth.
But through notes that she left in her diary and so on,
we know that that was her being represented underneath the sheet.
Now that is owned by Madonna.
We know that Madonna owns roughly five self portraits
by Frida Kahlo, two of which we know the names of that one.
And then there's another one where there's a monkey
on the side of her arm.
- And Madonna got that one.
- Yeah, Madonna's got that.
Yeah.
And Madonna has been quoted in Vanity Fair
saying when she brings people over who are new people in her life,
she'll show them the my birth one.
And if they don't like it, she'll know
that they're not going to be a long-term friend.
- I feel really sad about that.
- About what?
- That I'm never going to be friends with Madonna.
(laughing)
- Do you know why?
- I do like lots of Frida Kahlo stuff, but that, honestly,
it's a bit much for me.
- For me, right.
- But my question is, would you really be honest about that?
- If Madonna asks, I think no one's saying to Madonna to her face.
I don't like your painting.
- Yeah.
- I think she's like, well, everyone's my friend.
James is actually the only person I know who might just say,
I really hate that.
- You know what?
- You should take it down.
- Actually, I didn't really care for like a virgin.
(laughing)
- Ouch, okay, well, we can't be friends now.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for a final factor of the show.
And that is James.
- My fact this week is that actor Noel Gubiemi
played Hector in the Fast and the Furious.
Since then, he has played a character called Hector
in 30 other projects.
And now, if he's in a movie where he's not called Hector,
he'll try to change the character's name to Hector.
- Yeah.
- What?
- He's, is he confused about acting?
What, acting?
- He's found his niche.
- Yeah, he's a Hector.
- So basically, this is something I saw in an interview
with Los Angeles Radio Station.
And apparently, started as a coincidence.
So the writers just were looking for a Hispanic name.
And they would often just come up with Hector or Carlos
because it's like not the most obvious,
but it's like one of the most obvious.
- Interesting.
I didn't, so it's like not calling your English character John,
it's calling him Michael.
Do you know what I mean?
- Yeah, 'cause I used to just get Hector
just with the Trojan War.
- Yeah.
- And I can think of it in a Hispanic sense.
- Well, it is kind of a popular Hispanic name.
- So in Puerto Rico right now, Hector is the 18th most
popular name, which is beaten by Michael Kevin and Brian.
But in the '80s and '90s and early 2000s,
it was very popular.
So these characters, this guy is in his 30s.
So his character, people of that age were called Hector
quite a lot in the Hispanic speaking world.
And so yeah, it started as a coincidence.
And then it was noted in an Instagram post
and it went a bit viral and he sort of ran with it.
And now sometimes in a movie, he'll get a choice
to chase a name or keep it.
And if he has the chance, he'll always say,
"Now I want to be Hector."
- Well, he's got a hell of a list of movies he's done.
He's been in so many movies.
So Hector's not even the only recurring name
that has come up in his movies.
So he's played Jose four times.
He's played Cruz twice.
- So I would say Jose is the straight up
first Hispanic name you would go to, right?
- Yeah, okay.
- No way.
(laughing)
- Just put it in anywhere.
- Well, how about this one then?
Twice, he's played someone called Gang Banger One.
(laughing)
Again, that's the 19th most popular name in Florida right now.
- This is not an unrelated film.
(laughing)
- He completely is.
- No.
- So when he did it, Gang Banger One,
he's listed in the X-Files.
- And that's just a gang member, we should say.
It's just someone who's in gang fights a lot.
- Oh, is it?
- Oh, grow up guys.
- What?
- I've never heard of that.
- He's a Gang Banger, is very common.
Come to South London, you'll hear it said.
It's someone who's in a gang.
It's someone who gets him gang fights.
- Are you sure?
- Who plays the drum in the gang?
- No, just anyone.
- Any gang, yeah.
- Are you sure?
- I'm positive.
I remember from my time in the Peckham crew, all right?
(laughing)
- I remember from my time in the Orgy.
We all had a different understanding.
- So yeah, it's an old fashioned term.
It's not as much used these days out.
- That's right.
- Because I would say probably, my memory of the X-Files
is there would be more likely to be gangs than...
- The bags.
- Yeah.
Well, the other time was in a movie called Out of Sight,
which is listed on his Wikipedia,
but not listed on IMDB,
and I didn't have time to watch the movie.
- Wait, not out of sight with George Clooney and...
- And Jennifer Lopez.
- And I'm amazingly bad film.
- Well, yeah, he's had so many roles.
He's been called Snuffy, Chicken,
Lord of the Garbage, Subway Guy,
Sam the Man, Random,
why didn't he demand to always be called Lord of the Garbage?
(laughing)
- That's a Michael flatly dance that I didn't really want to see.
- Latin Guy on a bicycle,
and that was in the video clip
for Pretty Fly For A White Guy.
The offspring is in that.
- It's in that.
- He's in that.
- Yeah, very good.
- Character names are funny, are they?
- Kambi.
- Often, they express something about the character.
- Yeah, like some writers will,
as soon as you see a character's name,
you'll know exactly what they do.
Like Dickens, for instance, called JK Rowling.
- Exactly.
- But then other ones,
they would just call themselves Jack Reacher,
and you don't know what that is.
It's just a person called Jack.
- Exactly.
And so the Dickens character's,
and they're called Crathillic Names,
which I didn't know.
They dates back to Platonic Dialogue.
So there's a Platonic Dialogue,
which is all about,
is your name relevant to your character.
And so when Dickens has Mr. Bumble,
or Mr. Murd Stone,
who's a tough, hard character,
that just...
- Who's the Mr. Chokam,
something in... - Chokam Child.
- Chokam Child.
- Yeah.
- That's a really rubbish one.
But so there's this story about Dickens
that Tiny Tim was allegedly going to be called
Puny Pete at one point.
And it's, I have been trying to nail this
because I don't think it's actually true.
Like there's this piece from Dickens Quarterly in 1995,
which says actually this might be from an advert,
'cause there was an advert which said,
little Larry, small Sam, Puny Pete,
they were all crossed out,
and then below it it says Tiny Tim.
- Not crossed out.
And it's saying like, sometimes you have to iterate
and go through a few versions
before you get the final thing.
So that might be,
that's a common internet factoid
that actually might not be.
- It's one of my favourite things we do
is explode misconceptions
that only two people had.
Those two people will be listeners.
So it's good.
- This guy, Hector, arguably is Typecast.
He's doing quite similar characters in all these things.
IMDB has a category of the most Typecast actors in the world
and it explains the kind of character that they do.
So I want to do a quiz where I'll give you the explanation
of the character and you have to say the name of the actor
that they're describing.
So easy one to start off with.
Neurotic, sex-obsessed, intellectual.
- Woody Allen.
- Straight in there.
If at home you got that quicker than Dan and Andy Weldon.
Greasy, weasily, slightly mental creep.
- That's Dan, isn't it?
That's, he didn't do much acting.
- I've got that one credit.
Gang banger too.
- Alan Whitman?
- No, Greasy Weasily, slightly mental creep.
- And when I tell you, you'll go, oh yeah.
- Okay, hang on a sec.
- Oh, no, I can picture him on my head, stupid Chevy.
- Correct, that's who I was going for as well.
- Yes, okay, well done, Andy and me.
- Offbeat quirky hipster who's a little stuck
in Dreamland.
- Michael Sarah?
- No, it's.
- Ah, that annoying woman.
- Yeah.
God.
- I need to pick the mom in Paddington.
- I mean Sally Hawkins.
- Sally Hawkins.
- Oh, no, it's not her.
- Is it a woman?
- It's a woman.
- Offbeat, say it again.
- Offbeat quirky hipster who's a little stuck in Dreamland.
I'll tell you this one.
- Is it Woody Deschanel?
- It's correct.
- Yes.
- I don't know what that is.
- A tough woman who eventually shows vulnerability
by breaking down in a crying scene.
- Sigourney Weaver?
- She doesn't break down in crying scenes.
- She breaks others.
- Mell Street.
- Who's he saying?
- No, we're kind of getting there.
- Julia Roberts.
- Correct.
- Oh.
- He's back in the game.
- Is she a tough woman?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- Finally in this quiz, immature man child.
- Adam Sandler.
- Correct.
(all laughing)
- It's good.
- Oh, sorry guys.
- That's quite striking.
- No, it's very good.
- Oh, clearly they come across.
- So the tight casting is so dangerous for actors.
- There's an ed O'Neill.
There used to be a sitcom married with children.
If you can't picture him from that,
he was in that, he's in modern family as well
as one of the husbands in it.
- It was like a long suffering husband.
- Yeah, incredibly funny to the point
where he almost just had to shrug and people would laugh.
And so he was in a movie called Flight of the Intruder,
Drama Movie, 1991 it came out.
Test audiences kept on laughing.
Anytime he came on screen or did any movement
that he was just cut from the film.
- Wow.
- They were like, you're ruining the film.
You're too funny.
You're too funny at the moment.
- That's tough.
- That's the tight casting.
It isn't real thing, isn't it?
So there's an actor called Mikael Gillavani
who played Stalin in 12 different films
made during Stalin's lifetime.
And then the work did dry up.
(all laughing)
- Why are we gonna get a job now at Leaves
in the right country?
- Yeah, I read about him.
He basically played Stalin in one movie
and Stalin really, really liked him
because he was by far the most handsome and tallest
member of the cast and he was playing Stalin.
And Stalin was like, that's exactly who should be playing me.
And then from then on, yeah,
he was like, this guy is gonna play me all the time.
And obviously there were quite a few movies
about Stalin made.
- Yes.
- And when the casting call comes in,
it must be a tricky, like, do you wanna take this job?
- It is time casting me.
- But I'll be killed if I don't do it.
- But yeah, then after Chris Chev did that speech
that said to Stalin was a wanker, then no more.
- No, James Doohan had a horrible one.
James Doohan was scotty in Star Trek.
So he was the guy who would fix things.
He had a Scottish accent.
He kept not getting films off the back of it
because they kept saying, we don't need a Scottish guy
in this movie.
He was Canadian, that was just an accent.
But he was so tight cast to that character
that yeah, he lost roles.
- I was told, did you guys read about Jagdish Raj Kuranah,
who's a, he's got Guinness World Record,
he's a body with actor, he was, he died in 2013.
He's got a Guinness World Record
for being the most tight cast actor.
And he played the role of a police inspector in 144 films.
- Wow.
- Which is just, and I looked at his whole Wikipedia list of films.
And God, he worked hard.
Small bit parters were bloody hard.
They do about 10 films a year.
So he also played a doctor 10 times.
And he had various ones where you'd think maybe
he wasn't gonna be a policeman,
like a film called 'Soo Hog' and he's visiting a brothel
and he's a bit of an underworld character.
- Bicking up a gang wanger.
- Exactly.
- He's doing some gang banging undercover cop.
There we go.
- That's good.
- But if you know the actor, you will know
he will turn out to be a cop, right?
- Yeah, you're so right, that ruins it.
- Yeah, I read that he had his own police uniform
that he used to keep up, 'cause he was gonna be a policeman
so often in his movies.
And he has his son called Bobby.
- Oh, no.
- Nice.
- Lovely stuff.
- You know how Jack Reacher, the character, got his name?
'Cause Lee Child chose his pen name
because it would be between Raymond Chanber
and Agatha Christie is the story, okay?
But Jack Reacher, the character, is named
because he's good at reaching things.
So Lee Child is very tall, right?
That is true.
And he started writing these books
during a period of unemployment.
He used to be like a 90 feet floor manager, I think.
And he was sacked from that job and started writing.
But during that period where he was unemployed,
when he was in the supermarket,
or little odd ladies would sometimes say,
"Can you reach that thing for me down?"
And his wife used to tease him,
saying, "Maybe you could get a job as being a Reacher."
And he's since turned that into a globe straddling
like the cultural empire of--
- So funny.
- And I haven't read or seen the films,
but is Jack Reacher someone who's always fitting like bulbs?
Is he a handyman?
- He's basically like a human Mr. Tickle.
- Right, okay, there's so much more fun than they hear.
- Yeah, he is very, the character is very tall.
- Which was the huge controversy when Tom Cruise was cast,
because he was--
- Oh my god.
- Yeah, honestly, what everyone--
- There's someone who doesn't get type cast as a shartass.
- Does he?
- Jack Reacher's six, five, I believe.
- Is he?
- Yeah, and he's a tough guy.
I think there's one book where he stops a bullet
with his chest, and that's right.
- That's not easy to do, can I just say?
But it's not that easy to survive it.
- Sorry.
(laughing)
- Yes.
- I'm sort of a, I know I'm not used to this part,
but I'm astonished that he, specifically a 6.5
and he's played by Tom Cruise.
Was that a funny joke?
- No, the first Jack Reacher film with Tom Cruise is brilliant.
It's really good.
The second one is also decent.
- Yeah, go back.
- Do they have very small actors around him
to make him look tall?
- They cast only bunch of kids.
Yeah, and he beats up a hell of a lot of bunch of kids
in that film.
- No, you're right.
I think they just show him like he's short,
but he's accelerating up towards your face with his fists.
- I see.
- Right.
- Oh, it's good.
- It's not mentioned in the movie, his height.
It's how they go around it.
They don't go, "Oh my God, he's huge."
- They don't call him Jack Cart Reacher.
(laughing)
- Dan, I have a fact that I wonder if you know,
or anyone, in absolutely fabulous,
internationalist as great British comedy,
Jennifer Saunders' character is Eddie, Adina Monsoon.
Do you know why she's called that?
- Hmm.
- Can you work it out if you know stuff about her life,
which I reckon you do?
Eddie Monsoon is her name.
- Eddie Monsoon.
- Eddie Monsoon, do you know any about her personal life?
- Yeah, she's married to Adrian Edmondson,
and he's Eddie in bottom.
- Ed Monsoon.
- There you go.
- Wow.
- That's an incredible fact.
- Isn't that nice?
- Ed Monsoon.
- Very good.
- There you go.
It's a shame that Andy had to get that for you,
but you helped him.
- Made it all the more exciting.
- You two are working as a great team today.
(laughing)
- So sometimes character names can get you in trouble.
- Oh yeah.
- There is a writer called Jake Arnett, author of books.
And in 2006 he was writing a book,
and he had a character in it who was a real villain.
It was a 1960s cabaret singer,
and he named him Tony Rocco, right?
And the character was a real sleaze bag
who preyed on teenage boys.
Now unfortunately for Jake Arnett,
there was a real 1960s London cabaret singer
called Tony Rocco, who was not a pervert
who preyed on teenage boys.
And he was still trading,
having had a very successful hit single
and was still performing with a loyal fan base.
- Wow.
- Obviously he was not happy when this book came out.
- Was it a complete coincidence?
- It was a complete coincidence.
He just, I don't know, he hadn't Googled it.
- So did he get sued?
- There was a legal process, which played out,
and led to some compensation being paid, I think.
And Tony Rocco, the real Tony Rocco said,
"I'm very glad we can just work this out and move on."
- There was a famous thing with Peter Kay in Phoenix night.
Was it in Phoenix night?
So the one that he did before that.
But it was one of his sitcoms
and there was a character called Keith Ladd
who was like a health and safety officer
who had sex with dogs.
And it turned out that Peter Kayd had previously worked
with the health and safety officer called Keith Ladd.
- Oh.
- And it was a complete coincidence.
- Was it really?
- It was, says Mr. Kayd.
And there was some legal process.
And again, I think some, some--
- A compensation was distributed.
- I believe it was.
- It might have been the compensation went to,
you know, fire safety thing.
- Well, dog trust.
(laughing)
- Well, then there were things within books
where people would add the detail of a small penis
if they were describing someone so that they would never sue
'cause they wouldn't want to admit that the character was them.
- Yes, it's not one prime prejudice.
It cut out chapter four, isn't it?
(laughing)
- But if I write a character called, like,
Den Tribeur, who's, I write as a really, a real bastard
and I say, and he's got a small penis,
is that gonna stop me sewing, Den?
- What the small penis bit?
- Yeah.
'Cause it's so obvious I'm making fun of you in the book.
- And in fact, this is gonna be a great idea
for my next novel.
(laughing)
- This is small penis coming to it.
- Well, it's part of the reason he's cuckled it
by his Northern Chinese wife.
(laughing)
Well, I'd be angry, but this sounds so damn good.
I'm in.
(laughing)
- Well, you're not quite in.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course
of this podcast, we can all be found
on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @tribaland on Instagram, Andy.
- I'm on Instagram @AndyHunterM, James.
- I'm still on Twitter.
- Oh yeah.
- Don't really use it very much,
but if you wanna message me @JamesHarkin,
then there's a decent chance I'll see it one day.
- Yep, and if you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- I think there's an email address,
probably pullcars.cui.com.
There's an Instagram @noseutshingasafish,
or you can do the Twitter thing @noseutshing.
- Yep, okay.
Or you can go to our website,
noseutshingasafish.com, do check it out.
You can also find merchandise.
You can find clubfish, which is our special place
where we put up lots of bonus episodes.
Drop us a line, which is the mail bag episode.
There's compilation episodes of all of our outtakes.
Do check it out.
Otherwise, come back next week,
'cause we will be back.
Well, three of us will.
And Anna will be back in roughly nine months' time
with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)