Hey everyone, Dan here. Welcome to this week's episode of No Such Thing as a Fish. Before we get
going I just have a quick personal announcement that I want to make, which is to tell you that my
first ever non-fiction kids book is out today. You can get it in shots now, it's called "Impossible
Things, Unbelievable Answers to the World's Weirdest Questions" and in it I have gone on 10
adventures to try and answer some of the big questions that kids often ask us about the mysteries
of the universe. Oh my god, get out of here James. Is time travel possible? Will we ever talk
to animals? Do ghosts exist? Can imaginary friends come to life? Are we all actually living in a
giant video game simulation? Using these questions as starting points, I've written something that
combines really interesting facts with great spooky tales and along the way I managed to get a 2500
year old Babylonian ghost at Guinness World Record and also sit down with a psychic spy. It's the
perfect summary for your kid. For any of those questions, if they've ever wanted to know why we
haven't been taken over by zombies, why in 1991 there were over 60,000 jellyfish in space, and how
to throw their own time traveler party, well then this is the book for them. So guys, I'd really
appreciate it if you could buy it. So hard for authors these days to sell their books, but we
rely on people like you, our fish club, to help us do that and I'd really appreciate the support.
So if you can do it, it's out there now. Impossible things in all good bookshops.
Thank you so much and on with the show. Also buy my book. No, next week. Buy his next week. On with the show.
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn. My name is Dan Schreiber. I'm sitting here with James Harkin,
Anna Tyshinski and Andrew Hunter Murray. And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days. And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is James. Okay, my fact this week is that Yves Saint Laurent's
gardener used hair clippers to keep his cactuses perfectly trimmed. That is, that is care.
And hair clippers are those ones that men use to keep their hair really short, right? Yeah.
So you set them to a setting and you go... Or you may use it for your beard. Right. So yes,
that's what hair clippers are. Cactuses are succulent plants and Yves Saint Laurent was a
fashion designer. Any more announcements in this one, maybe explain it. I didn't think that cactuses,
I've never seen a shaggy cactus. Do you know what I mean? Well, the thing is, there's lots of
different types of cactus. And Yves Saint Laurent loved cactuses. He had a garden in Marrakesh called
the Jardin Marjorelle. Actually, it was started by another artist called Jacques Marjorelle.
But Yves Saint Laurent bought it when it was going into disrepair and he looked after these
cactuses. And it's a really beautiful garden. It's a place that I've been quite recently,
where I saw this fact. There was a video of his gardener who was going around with these hair
clippers making them all perfect. The only thing I can imagine you could do with hair clippers
on a cactus is to trim the spines. Is that what he's doing? Is he blunting them so they don't
prick anyone? No, it wasn't. It was just to make them all look perfect because I don't think it's
controversial to say that Yves Saint Laurent was something of an Yves Thiet. Yeah. I don't
understand when, because I don't know much about fashion, but when I read about Yves Saint Laurent
and his achievements, his concrete accomplishments, they're all quite, you know, he took risks by
turning a trench coat into haute couture. Yeah. What does that mean? I don't understand. This is
the character of Dior. He is taken on the mantle of one of the biggest fashion houses ever. And
he's looking at trends that are going on out in bits of America and bits of France. And he's saying
this is seen as low rent. I'm putting it back into there. That's a risk. It's basically me not
understanding the plot of the film The Devil Ways Prada. It's basically what I came to understand.
Oh, right. That's right. But yeah. The thing I guess that I found interesting was his personality,
because I agree. It's hard to get a grip on fashion if you don't know fashion, but it is striking
that he was so young when he took over at Christian Dior, right? He was 21. And he was, for someone who
was kind of famous for being a strong character, maybe not that likable a character later on,
he was probably incredibly shy and like couldn't even look anyone in the eye. He was just new at
Christian Dior and Christian Dior died suddenly. And I think there were these four women who worked
there and the company was left to him to basically take charge this weird shy boy who couldn't look
anyone in the eye. It's an amazing story because he moved to Paris when he was 1718 and he entered
a competition where he just did some designs. He then took it to Dior. Dior saw it. It really was
so similar to what he was working on at that point that he just on the spot said, you're now my second
in command. You're my assistant. What's nice is this little competition, you know, sometimes you
hear about a school where it's like seven comic book writers were there at the same time. Carl
Largefeld came second in that competition. That he won. That eventually got him his job at Dior.
Dan, was this the competition of the international wool secretariat?
Yes. Yeah, I think we'll say that. Yeah. Did you have to make everything out of wool?
Yeah, they gave you a big pile of wool and 20 minutes. 20 minutes. I'm joking. I'm joking.
I think it was just the design. Do you know this is off topic now, but I was reading about wool
this morning and in, let's say, when was it? Probably about the 15th century, there was a wool
guild and a knitter's guild. And if you wanted to be a knitter and sell your knitting, you had to
be part of this guild. And in order to be part of it, you had to study for six years and then do a
knitting exam at the end of it. And the knitting exam would take like a day where you showed off
everything you've learned over the six years. And if you didn't pass that exam, you couldn't be
like a professional knitter. Could you take the exam again? Good question. It's an all or nothing.
You know what? I didn't go into all the admin yet. But you will because you're applying, aren't you?
Dior. Yeah. So he obviously became very famous colossus of the industry, all of this. He was
responsible for, I think, the most French thing that has ever happened, right? Okay. It's a 1998.
Yeah. We're in Paris. Yeah. What's going on? 1998, Diana died the year before. That's right. It was
the one year anniversary. Was it the World Cup? It was the World Cup. Yeah. So France was hosting.
Yeah. And they won it. And they won it, as in Zidane and all that. Bloody hell, Andy. I do contain
multitudes. It's on the paper in front of them. Before the final of the World Cup on the pitch
in the big stadium was an Yves Saint Laurent retrospective show with 300 models celebrating
40 years of Yves Saint Laurent. I just think that's so French. Like, we will have the football,
but first fashion. They do take it seriously. The way that Yves Saint Laurent's career is reported
on sometimes when it talks about the absolute scandal. What was the scandal? The scandal,
so it was 1971 and it was this show called Carrant, which was a reference to the fact that it was
an imitation of 1940s fashion and it was put on in Paris this show. Of course, it was early 1940s
fashion. Now, as you may or may not know listening at home, the early 1940s was a difficult time for
the people of France. And the fashion was meant to imitate kind of occupied France and sort of
not only that, but the costumes that he recreated sort of imitate people who were doing quite well
in occupied Paris. We're talking collaborationists. Are we talking like René Artois from Allo Allo?
It was one for the younger listeners.
Good morning to you. You're listening. Yves Saint Laurent's cameo in Allo Allo was so weird,
wasn't it? Yes, it was all Allo Allo and, you know, Dad's army based fashion.
No, but it's Vichy France, right? It was Vichy, it had a lot of nods to Vichy France and it was
quite extreme. The press were very offended saying, you know, it's in a very sensitive reminder of
the Nazi days. It's an insult to fashion. But this was obviously good for him because any
publicity is good publicity. So it was things like it. I think people had to wear practical clothes
because they didn't have many materials. So it was lots of tiny mini skirts and platform shoes.
Actually, this is like Allo Allo. When was this? '71.
Okay. Wow. So that was when he was an Yves Saint Laurent designer, not a Dior designer, right?
Yeah, he was himself. Because he was Dior and he did all this stuff where he was taking stuff off
the streets, like Dan said, but then they basically kicked him out, didn't they? Or rather, he got
conscripted to the army and the fashion house could have said, well, no, he's so important to us
that he can't go to the army, but they didn't say it, they just let him go. Yeah, interesting.
And he's so stuck with a nervous breakdown, didn't he? Yeah, well, he didn't go to war
because he had a breakdown in the incident. Did he even make, because he was going to be sent to,
it was Algeria, wasn't it, the Algerian front? He didn't even make it to Algeria.
He didn't even make it to Algeria. But the thing is that while he was doing his induction before
he collapsed, they replaced him with someone else. And they really shouldn't have done that.
Like they should have kept his job open for when he came back. And so they sued Dior and
they got some money from Dior and that's when they set up their own fashion house Yves Saint Laurent.
Right. And when you say they, you mean him and his partner, lover, best friend in the world,
soulmate guy, right? With whom actually he bought this cactus garden in Marrakesh.
Just to bring it back to that. And of course, while we're in North Africa, Zinedine Zidane
himself of Algerian stock. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So if Yves Saint Laurent had made it to the war,
he might have met Zidane's family, you know. What have you done with Andrew Hunter Murray?
I feel like you've just recently read the encyclopedia entry on Zed and you're not
desperate to smuggle in. It's the last football I paid any attention to because I was 11 at the time.
I'm so impressed. Yeah, Berger was an interesting guy and seemed to run Yves Saint Laurent's life
because Yves Saint Laurent was a very vulnerable person, wasn't he? And Pierre Berger just was
the organiser. So he was his lover from 58 to 76 and then they were very good friends. And
he had a weird introduction to Paris as well. So he moved to Paris from an island and he was 18
years old, moved there on his own. And on the day he moved, he was walking down the Champs-Élysées
and a famous poet called Jacques Prévert fell from the sky above him and landed at his feet.
Wow, but not on him, like right in front of him. No, he says, I always remember my first day in
Paris as a day a famous poet landed on my head, but he didn't. In his actual description, he
fell out of a French window a few stories on. Oh, right. They're all French windows, if we're embarrassed.
All these people are so young at the time when they sort of move their formative experiences. So
when Saint Laurent was, when he got the job, when Dior died, did we say he was 21? 21. And at that
point he went home and again, this is the story, he drew a thousand designs in a fortnight.
I can't imagine, once you've drawn like five different pairs of trousers.
Oh my god. There are only five. I know that this is ridiculous. How many pairs of trousers could
there possibly be out there? There's skinny, there's straight and there's fles. I think all of that
football knowledge has pushed out all of the fashion knowledge. Do you remember only having
any fashion knowledge if you've passed your mind back over the last 10 years? And then they moved
to Marrakech, didn't they? Because it was the cool place to be in those days. It was where all the
hippies went. And there had actually been an international zone in Tangier, which was like
not owned by anyone really. It was just like a trading port and it was very, very low tax. And
there weren't many rules compared to other places in North Africa and loads and loads of hippies went
there. But eventually Morocco took over it and then they decided actually Marrakech is a better
place to go. And it was set up this kind of hippie group in Marrakech by Talifa Getty, who was a wife
of John Paul Getty, of the Getty millionaires. And he was like a playboy and he had this partner
who was just absolutely crazy. And she had all the best parties and Keith Richards said she had the
best friends and the best opium. And she and John Paul Getty named the son Tara Gabriel Galaxy
Gramophone Getty. Which is a name. Gramophone. We've got options when you grow up. If you want
to be a bit kooky, you can take on gramophones. True. I actually think they took the other option
of removing their middle names as they all did. Have a gramophone related fact. Brilliant. Which
brings it in a big circle because cactuses are incredibly useful in the world of gramophones.
The needles. The needles. No. Yeah. It's so cool. I did not know about this. But in the 1920s when
people had wind-up gramophones, 1920s and 1930s, cactus spines or prickly pears were really,
really popular and they were thought to produce a much higher quality sound than the actual steel
needles. It's amazing. Yeah. And you could sculpt them because they're a bit softer than the steel.
So you could sculpt them so they don't miss. And it wouldn't break the record.
Wouldn't break the record. Yeah. And just this one company found the niche in the market. Some
cactus names. Yeah. Big nipple cactus. Lovely. Woolly nipple cactus. Bonker hedgehog cactus.
Sorry, is that bonk a hedgehog? It bonks a hedgehog? No, it's bonker hedgehog and it's named
after Frances Bonker. She was a cactus expert and she also wrote a book called The Mad Dictator,
which was a novel about Hitler's life. The prohibition cactus because it likes its home
place dry, likes a dry area. Clever. Applies to a lot of them, doesn't it? It does actually,
doesn't it? And there's a lot named after nipples. But I think that's because the part of a cactus
where the spines come out of is called the areola. It is. Yeah. Because they are kind of a little
bump, aren't they? This is so weird. I have a related nipple cactus nipple fact. Perfect.
Yeah. Which is that scientists, this is a very recent discovery, there are 100 species of cactus
which act as breasts for ants. Okay. In other words, so they have these tiny nipples in their
flesh, not I think where the spines are, but they produce this tiny supply of sweet nectar
and the ants go crazy for the nectar and then the ants protect the mother udder against insects
and they clean bacteria and they fertilize the soil, they spread the seeds to new sites.
So that is... That's not what babies do though, when they're drinking from breasts. I mean,
they do a lot of fertilizing, but not necessarily... They do very little protective work. You're
all right. I didn't realize the threat to cactus, so the climate is one thing because it is obviously
they're living in an extreme environment already, you know, and if it gets much off for a dryer
then they're in trouble. But the other risk to them is cactus smuggling. Good. It's one of the,
it's one of the... I had 10 cactuses down my underpants when I went abroad last time.
Can I go take the cocaine next time, please? I can't fit another one up there. There is a cactus
called the dildo cactus. It doesn't look very usable, does it? No, I'm not actually sure why
it's got that. I try to find out why it's called the dildo cactus. I think because it's slightly
felicin-shaped, but obviously... Right, but so many of them are. And in fact, if any of the cacti
that I have seen, that one could do with pruning. It's a very furry and spiky-ish.
Well, people like different things. Yeah. Do you guys know about... So we're recording this
on the 4th of July, big election day, and I found a nice little political connection to cactus,
which is Nick Clegg, the former head of the Liberal Democrats. Do you know that he was
arrested in Germany or certainly was taken... Got in trouble in Germany because of arson,
because he was lighting cactus up. Do you remember that? Was he smoking them for a drug?
No, he was just drunk, and he was just setting fire to cacti, you know. And he admitted this.
You're a prick. You're a prick. Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Anna.
My fact this week is that in the early 1400s, China had ships four times larger than anything else
in Europe. By the 1500s, it had deliberately destroyed them.
European ships tiny, Chinese ships massive, basically. European ships perfectly acceptable.
Chinese ships unbelievable. I just think more people should just know about this fleet,
because it is an amazing period in Chinese history. It was called the treasure fleet,
and they seem to have now proven how big they were, because the claims were that these ships were
up to 140 meters long. And I think no one really believed it. And no one believed it. No, it was
like, come on, that's not possible, genuinely. I mean, the ship that Columbus sailed on was 20 meters,
and that was what was huge. That's almost the same size as the world's largest
foosball table. It's not credible. It's not possible. It doesn't make any sense.
Unbelievable. Yeah. Thank you, James. So yes, ships as long as a particularly large football table,
and there were tons of them as well. There were 3,500 of them. So for comparison,
you know, our pathetic Navy today is 66 ships. And even. There have been some cuts lately,
but we had a lot more in 1945. Because it's not necessarily something we need.
Russia and China, though, they have the largest navies in the world, and they're in the 700.
So this is, you know, much bigger than any of those. Almost 30,000 sailors went on just one of the
voyages. So the whole scale of it is mad. Over 300 ships would sail out at once. And they went an
incredibly long way. And they're mostly to just show off, weren't they? Well, it's kind of was.
Yes, basically, yes. Yeah, it was a cultural sort of just say, hey, have you heard of China?
It's like kimchi. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's about last week. Exactly. It wasn't really plundering.
They did bring back some treasure, but it wasn't when I read about it, I thought, oh, well,
they'll be going off finding treasure, bringing it back. And that wasn't really. No, no, not really.
It was more showing off their treasure. There was it was destroying pirate fleets,
occasionally, for a bit of fun. But imagine if you're a pirate. I mean, it's not a pair, is it?
Like just doing your thing, getting a little bit of plunder here and there,
and then suddenly 300 foosball table sized. You've gotten to stop using that comparison.
But so the Wikipedia on the treasure fleets is great because it does acknowledge there are a
couple of gaps, right? So listen to this, there is still much debate regarding issues such as the
purpose of the voyages, the size of the ships, the magnitude of the fleet, the routes taken,
the charts employed, the countries visited, and the cargo carried. Basically, we don't know who
was going or where or why or what they were on or who they were with or how. Well, I think what we
have is that's very good in our time on it, actually. What we have is very detailed records
from China. So we do know a lot about it. It's just we don't necessarily know the negative things
that might have been how many ships sunk. I mean, we have no evidence that any of them sunk, but it's
implausible, surely. And we genuinely thought it was impossible to make ships out of wood this big.
They're the biggest wooden ships that have ever existed by a long way. And one thing was discovered
not too long ago, which was an 11 meter long rudder. And that's one of the most concrete bits
of evidence we have for the size of these ships. If I was a 15th century Chinese emperor, I would
just make a massive rudder to mess with future historians. I think you almost understand their
ambitions. They're not trying to impress us. The thing I find most amazing about this whole saga,
this whole sort of journey that these fleets went on, is the leader of it. So this was a guy
called Zhang He, who was basically he was he was a young kid whose father was killed in a war.
He got taken as prisoner, brought to the emperor's palace in China, made into a eunuch,
and just showed amazing skills in the world of warfare. Britannica says he was six foot five,
others say he was seven feet tall. And this is a guy, imagine a ship's come in and this seven foot
giant... So the ships look like small. They were hitting his head. They said his voice was as loud
as a bell. He was by all accounts an extraordinary character. He's got a tiny dinner bell in our
house. It's just going ding, ding, ding, ding, ding. I'm sorry. He paused the show. Oh, I knew
this had to come out eventually. Is that because your gong is at the repair shop or is it?
That's a good point because I have been thinking he's going to have this deep booming voice,
but I've completely forgot he was a eunuch. One of the reasons they think that he was chosen
is because he was also a Muslim. And they were going, yeah, and they were sailing part of where
they got to was the Gulf. And so he was going to be in lots of Islamic territory. And so the
idea is it's a diplomatic mission to go and make contact with these places and basically say,
will you acknowledge that China is the best country in the world? And if you do that,
we sort of won't take over you. And it was lots of Muslim countries. So, you know,
he would have been able to go and be like, hey, I get you and my dad went to Mecca.
Is China the best? Yes, great. Right. He sounds amazingly impressive,
Chang He. And I'm interested also in why their voyages ended, because there's lots of debate
about what brought them to an end. One theory is that they're worried about Mongolian invasions,
and obviously, Mongolians have paid over land. But another reason they were discontinued,
potentially, is that there was a conflict between the Confucians and the eunuchs.
Yeah. There's this big eunuch power base in the court. And there was a eunuch establishment,
partly because it was thought, oh, well, if eunuchs can't have children,
then they're not going to be seizing power and starting a dynasty.
That's why they were chosen. That's why they were the court assistants, really, wasn't it?
That's what I mean. Yeah, yeah. But for some reason, obviously, that builds up into a powerful
bureaucracy. It feels like the movie franchise we're all waiting for, the bureaucrats versus the
eunuchs. I mean, it's weird, isn't it? There being this court of eunuchs and then this court of
Confucian bureaucrats, and there's war between them. I'm joking for position.
When Zhong He died, basically, he was the main eunuch. When he died, there was kind of a vacuum
in the eunuch world, and it meant that the Confucianists could jump him.
In addition to the obvious vacuum in the eunuch world, of course.
And it was a new emperor as well. So Zhong He's emperor, who took him on, had died. A new emperor
came on. He became part of the expansion of the Great Wall of China. There were lots of different
projects going on. He talked him into one final adventure going out, and Zhong He died on the
way back. So then that was kind of it. I think that's it. Kind of like you can't spend all your
money making a massive wall to stop the Mongolians coming in, and you can't spend the same money
making massive ships to go to the Muslim lands. You have to choose one or the other.
We'll tell that to the Labour Party, who apparently aren't even going to raise taxes, James. No, I
guess. Wow. I can see why you've got a denabel and not a satire bell in your home.
So yeah, I think the main thing was you say the Confucian bureaucrats, and mostly the bureaucrats
complained whether it was thick and expensive. And there was one claim that it cost half of the
tax revenue of a whole year to send them out, which is mad, and probably an exaggeration.
But also, there's one other theory that they just done what they wanted to do.
I mean, they got, as far as the East African coast, they got to Somalia. They've shown everyone
how good they are. Everyone has said, "Yeah, you're the best." Yeah, they've gone, "Cool. Job done."
Zhong He supposedly named the durian fruit. Yeah. Supposedly, he ate it when he was on one of
his journeys, and he was so delicious, he forgot where he was, and he stayed there for three days,
and then realized, "Oh, wait a minute. I'm supposed to be doing this three days."
And so he went back again, and the name durian means to linger and forget to return.
Supposedly named by him. And also, he supposedly invented the queenfish.
So the queenfish is like a fish which has got like five spots on it. And the theory goes that
there was a big storm. There's a hole in his boat. He prays to God, and the storm dissipates,
and they realize that they haven't sunk because there's a fish in the hole in the boat.
Brilliant. Okay. And it's this queenfish. He takes it out. His five fingerprints go onto the fish
and forever are on this fish. And for that reason, Chinese people in Malaysia don't eat queenfish,
although some skeptics point out the fact that it is quite poisonous.
Just the second best reason not to eat it. Obviously, the Shanghai thing is the main reason
we don't eat it. There's another thing about these giant ships. They had rigging that was
decorated with yellow flags. The sails were dyed red with henna. The hulls were painted with huge
elaborate birds, and on the front were large eyes painted onto the bow. So as it was coming towards
you, just the sense of a big face heading towards you. I mean, that's what an image. What a striking
thing. And a seven foot giant walks off the ship, be like, "Avatar, have we been invaded? Is it aliens?"
Here's a last legacy of the treasure fleets. This is a New York Times report from 1999, right?
What? One year after the most French thing that has ever happened.
Two years after the death of Diana. They had a reporter called Nicholas Kristof, right? And he
went to this tiny island off the coast of Kenya, which was called, I think it's called Pate, P-A-T-E.
It might be Pate, it might be Pate. I think it's Pate. It's called Pate. It's pretty squishy ground.
And he found there a number of elderly men, and they claimed to be Chinese, right? Now they looked
like they might have Asian ancestry, East Asian ancestry, and they claimed they'd been there for
600 years. Well, they claimed that their ancestors had got there 600 years ago. They claimed that
they were descended from the sailors of the treasure fleet who'd been shipwrecked on Pate
600 years ago. And supposedly they had some very ancient porcelain in their home, some
which is incredible. It's true, that is unbelievable. I mean, you know, big tongs on that one, but it
does sound. But you would have thought you could tell when you go somewhere if someone's, because
they can't have shacked much outside if they've only been there. Can't we take a swab or something?
Like, we've got technology now. It might have been pre-swab. I don't know. If anyone listening is
in Pate, can you write it and tell us? In return, we'll send you some very small bits of toast.
Vikings had big ships. Oh, yeah. Famously. I mean, not by comparison.
But they were also quite decorated, like the ones we were talking about. Yeah, yeah.
You should always realize. But it turns out they had woolen sails. I was just saying that I was
reading about wool today. That's why I bring this up. And there's a traditional handicraft expert
called Amy Lightfoot who decided to try and make a sail like a Viking woolen sail. And she and her
colleagues had to spin 188,000 meters of yarn to make the sail. It took them three years to complete
and it used the equivalent of a year's production of wool from 2000 sheep.
Wow. To make a single sail. That's insane.
So how did the Vikings manage to make all these sails? Is there an answer that you can tell us?
Okay, okay, okay. We can get this. Did they tie together their clothes and make a sort of amusing
like... Like they're trying to escape from a building. How would they do it?
They had 2000 sheep. They had lots of sheep. They had lots of sheep as half of the answer.
Okay. And lots of people and lots of time. No telling. Yeah, that's basically all of it. The only
missing bit is that obviously there were lots of them going on sailing missions. So they didn't
really have time to make the sails. Did they knit as the... So who made the sails? Did they knit as
they sailed? Let you row and then you knit a little bit. I guess the winds that could make them,
they settled. Precisely. It was all the women, basically. All the women would live near the coast
and they would make all of their sails for the ships. I feel like we were really working our way
towards a good wrong answer there. I know. I was so more ruined by like... So sorry. Reminding you,
women were also existing in times. Actually, just on what you were saying and on women,
I was reading about wool earlier today. Oh, gosh. And you know the herring girls, do you remember
them? Yeah. They were like gut herring and they would start in the north of Scotland because
the herring shoals would come down the coast of England and they would follow the coast because
they would follow the herring. So as the year went on, they would just like get further and
further down the coast until they ended up in Great Yarmouth and they would stop off at the
gutting centres. But as they went, because they were walking this whole way, they would knit as
they went and then they would sell their goods as they were walking down. So they would do walking
and knitting, walking and knitting, sell their stuff and then do your gutting and then do walking,
knitting, walking, knitting. Do you think it was right? You know when you see someone on their
phone walking down the street and you're like, "Oh, for God's sake, just put it away." Do you think
people thought that when they saw them? Yeah. Just admire the scenery for a minute. Do you remember
we talked about the drovers? Yeah, yeah. Similar. With their magic dogs. Do you remember they walked
long knitting as well, didn't they? Well, they had woolen socks for their pigs, didn't they?
Yeah, it's quite romantic. The idea of, you know, a drover and a herring girl meeting.
Yeah, they wouldn't ever meet as close. That's quite a long distance between shoreline
and... Yeah, but if you're drovering in from the coast, maybe, I don't know. Maybe you do, yeah.
Romantic like they accidentally swap balls of yarn and then, "Oh, no." And then they got to get
back to each other. I just think it's like... I don't know, it's the same ball of yarn and it's
like in Lady and the Tramp. It's reverse Lady and the Tramp. They're getting further apart,
but connected by the same yarn. James, you're shaking your head. It's the default. It's a break-up
story. There's a screenplay in this somewhere. He was a drover. She gutted herring for a living.
Can I make it any more obvious? Let's not imply any historical consultants
when they get this far. No, no, no. Or geographical ones.
Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is Andy. My fact is that the largest
kettle in Hamburg is called Caroline. This is about a very large kettle called Caroline. Caroline
with a K. Does she get offended if you misspell it? You were quite specific about that.
So this is because there's a lot of renewable energy being built in Europe at the moment,
mostly wind and solar. And it's pretty cheap, especially during sunny or windy hours, basically.
Prices drop massively. It just gets really, really cheap because there's so much access
being produced. And in some cases, the prices get negative because the power has to go
somewhere. And so it's kind of not totally ideal because you want to put power to good use,
basically, when you're generating it. You just see what I mean. This is all from an article
in The Economist. And you need to use the power a bit better. You need to link to other countries
which don't have a surplus at that moment, maybe, or you shift demand. So like everyone charges
out their cars in hours where there's lots of power on the grid, whatever. And another option
is to boil up the largest kettle in Hamburg, Caroline. Just tease all around. Just tease
everyone in Hamburg whether they want one or not is getting a cup of tea. This is a giant
electric kettle, basically. And it turns surplus wind energy into heat. It heats up water using
the electricity. And it gets used in, I think, a district heating network, which is like where
everyone's hot water comes from Caroline. And sort of 20,000 houses, I think, are on this system.
So yeah, and that's Caroline. Good honor. I know. And she doesn't look like, you know,
she doesn't whistle and she doesn't have a spout and a handle, right? She looks like a big tank,
presumably. Basically, a big container of hot water is what I have chosen a kettle is.
Yeah, fair enough. That's fine. I think that's fine. It heats up to very, very hot. And yeah, nice.
Renewable energy. Well, I think it's amazing because we're at a point now in history where
we're literally looking at everything around us going, how do we turn this renewable? How can
we do using this to be? I was reading the other day that there's, in toilets now, there's a thing
that they're trialing whereby, how do you create renewable energy off the back of toilets? Oh,
what if you put in the equivalent of a wind turbine into the pipe for your farts?
You lean over a fart at the little windmill. Yeah, yeah. That's good. No, it's using the
idea of the water. It's using the water. Do you mean a watermill? More like a watermill.
Sorry, I forgot about that. I'm trying to talk to the kids. Sorry,
I haven't got allo-lo references to this, but it's basically your flush and it spins and it creates
energy. Do you have a great idea? I actually came up with this idea quite a few years ago of putting
many sort of water wheels in everyone's gutters. That's why I thought, I thought it was a brilliant
idea that no one had thought of. Right, yeah. And then I never pursued it. And it seems like
it's actually going to become reality. It's not none of these. We should go back over all the
things quirky renewable energy ideas we've mentioned over the years and look at how many of
them have come to giant fruition. Big aisle. Sorry, I must clarify here. I am incredibly pro
investing huge amounts of money in the big scale ones, but quite a lot of these little
ideas are so nice, aren't they? But they can't scale up and you can't like fix them into the
end. But I reckon they're like a good science fiction idea. They're worth saying out loud
as much as possible because someone listening out there somewhere will go, that's a great idea.
Actually, I could do this with that and turn that into I just think as much as it pumped out.
What happens when a poo gets stuck in the water wheel again? Again, every day, every day.
Millions of engineers are going to be called out. Yeah. Unaccountably, there's a poo in the water
wheel again. Here's the thing about kettles. This is crazy. It comes from a book I read recently.
I think I may have mentioned it before. It's called Power Up. It's a great book.
This is about the world's first ever coal powered public power station, right? Right.
So it was called the Edison Electric Light Station. It was built in London in 1882
and it generated enough electricity power 30 modern kettles. Wow. That is partly it was a
small power station. It's also partly British kettles are world leading. They're just so powerful.
Sounds actually like the dream would be that your kettle didn't use that much power in order to do
the same thing. Yes. No, no, no, no. You want tea now. That's the point. Did they call this power place
Electric Eels? No, they didn't. It was the Edison Electric Light Station. They should have done.
They should have done, but they didn't. And it generated 93 kilowatts of electricity at one time,
which was for lights in the local area. Yeah. But basically it's partly a function of just
British kettles being absolutely punishingly powerful. That's the thing we should say to foreign
listeners, especially Americans, what a kettle is, right? Yeah. Americans don't have kettles.
It's like a saucepan with a lid. Yeah. If you want to make tea with water that's
more than 40 degrees in temperature and that's Celsius, not your Fahrenheit system.
You know what? I think if we start a battle with the Americans over tea, then we're only going to lose.
What do you think? Oh, I see. It's a funny reference. It's a reference to the Boston Tea
Party. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Very nice. Very lovely. Don't rig that satire bell again.
Another China fact for this section, the world's largest hydroelectric plant is in China,
unsurprisingly. Yeah. Like the world's largest, most things. And it's the Three Gorgeous Dam,
which you've probably heard of, and it's obviously massive and... Gorgeous, sorry.
Sorry? I heard gorgeous. The Three Gorgeous Dam. Well, it is gorgeous. I think it is gorgeous. Yeah, yeah.
Do you think it's gorgeous, the displacement of over a million people? I don't know.
They would say what about the people living downstream of the Three Gorgeous Dam?
Andy, oh, I dropped you in that one, mate. Do you think it's gorgeous, the submerged villages?
Do you think it's complicated and they have to be trade-offs, Anna?
Yeah, I look at them with you, and obviously produces a huge amount of power. But it does
slow the earth down. What? Oh, yeah. Really? I think it was NASA who verified this in the end,
because there are rumors that it slowed down the rotation of the earth and lengthened our day a
little bit. So, if it's 459 and you're at work looking at your watch right now,
you can blame the Three Gorgeous Dam. Yeah. Yeah, it's the dam's fault. Dam it.
Anyway, it's quite... In fact, kind of everything does that when you move mass around,
but it does it to a measurable extent. And so, it's because it's... This huge amount of water
is being held. It's 39 trillion kilograms of water is held 175 meters high above sea level
in this dam. So, that's a huge amount of water that's being held quite a big distance from the
centre of the earth. Imagine you're spinning round on a chair, right? You're spinning round at a steady
speed, and then you get a huge water balloon, and you hold it in your right hand at arm's length.
It's going to slow you down a little bit. And it actually... That is crazy.
Has slowed us down by 0.06 microseconds, a microsecond being a millionth of a second.
So, where does that matter most? Like, what business? The Olympics, you know? So,
Usain Bolt has always just missed out smashing the 100 meters.
That would be good, wouldn't it, if you could just let the water out at the same time.
You are all running in the same direction in the 100 meters, I suppose.
Yes, it's true. There will be a use, I'm sure.
The next Chinese Olympics, they're taking notes. I can imagine them doing that sort of thing.
But you know that got proposed in 1919.
Well, they drain the dam just to help someone win 100 meters of sprint.
The building of the dam was proposed by Sun Yat-sen, first president of China.
Really? Yeah. And it took... It was partly because they got insane floods about once every decade,
that were just totally destructive. So, it was partly that and partly for electricity.
And the water that they store up there gets dropped through tubes and turned a turbine,
much like Dan's toilet idea. But it drops 185 meters, which is two statues of liberty in height.
Like, it really is... And it generates so much power. It's just extraordinary. I think it's 20%
of China's electricity. It's a lot. It comes from hydro power.
And China's big. And China's big.
And they had... Also, the construction of it, they had to divert the entire Yangtze River
while they built the dam. Imagine. It's just... It's stunning.
Yeah, it's good. I can see who the propaganda is working on, Andy.
Is China the best country?
For this? Yes. So, there's another heating plan operating at the moment, because waste heat is
like massive. Like, waste heat, if it can be used, would be an enormous resource.
So, there is currently a project going on. You know, when you're somewhere cold and you get those
little hand warmers where you snap a coin. Yes, I do know those.
And it heats up. So, yeah, it's like this jelly...
Use them on the golf course.
Yeah, it's got like stored heat and you snap the coin, this little metal thing in it.
I always thought it's like two little chemicals sort of mixed together.
And then that heats, it's an exothermic reaction.
That's exactly it. And then you can put the heat back in. Like, you can reheat it.
And it's sort of...
Oh, that's amazing.
Those things only last about, like, 40 times, right, those little hand warmers.
But there is a system currently being worked on to charge thermal batteries from...
Like, places where they burn rubbish, for example.
And then transport the heat back into the centre of London
and use the heat there where it's needed.
Right.
Like, really creative things that are being proposed to deal with energy loss.
Using burning rubbish, basically.
Well, that's already used. For example, maybe you'd only generate a bit of electricity from that.
But it gives off a lot of waste heat in the process.
That's amazing.
Catch that. Well, similarly, if you swim in redditch in the Abbey Stadium Leisure Centre,
anyone who's ever done that, you are being heated by dead bodies from the crematorium.
And they came up with the idea in...
I think it was 2012 that they started implementing it.
And it saves 40% on the Leisure Centre's energy bills.
Because it's so much cheaper.
And, you know, what a useful thing to contribute in your last moments on this earth.
They're doing this system in Sweden, by the way, as well.
But it's actually crematoriums that are using it to heat their own crematoriums.
So if you're waiting in a crematorium, yeah, yeah.
You don't need that. I mean, having been into a crematorium,
it's like a room. How much heat do you need?
Oh, there's a waiting room. There's the front desk.
You've got a person gone off this.
You've got a whole system there.
What country is this in?
Sweden. Sweden gets very cold then.
Does get colder there, yeah, fair enough.
Yeah.
So they're using that.
I love, just by the way, Andy, that thing you said with the coin that you snapped.
That technology is going wild at the moment.
I was at an arcade down the road from where I live.
And my son had enough tickets to win a prize.
And he got an inflatable hammer.
And instead of having to blow it up,
you just snap a thing inside it now and inflate.
Yeah, okay.
I was not on board with this anecdote until I heard the end of it.
And I'm so on board with it.
And somebody's had to blow up lots of inflates in the last year or so.
Yeah, this giant hammer that you don't do anything to,
other than snapping a thing in the middle.
I asked the guy behind the counter and he was like, I don't know, mate.
I didn't actually construct everything you see.
I'm not Wallace for Wallace and Gromit.
That's the first thing I do.
I'd be like, hello, how do these hammers inflate?
I really do just operate the till and I open up and close the shop at night.
Can I do a quick facts on Caroline before we move on?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Because that was the name of this so-called kettle.
Do you remember a few days ago when England won the Euros?
And we all sang sweet Caroline.
Yeah, my Prime Minister Farage came out to shake the hands of the boys.
We're both recording in the past and in a parallel universe.
So we recorded this before the Euros.
But at the time of recording, we had just absolutely battered Slovakia
to one after extra time.
And we did sing sweet Caroline, or the England fans did.
And sweet Caroline is written by Neil Diamond about his wife, Marsha.
And he called it Caroline because Marsha doesn't scan the tune.
But what's interesting is that the reason England sings sweet Caroline is there was
a DJ at Wembley Stadium called Tony Perry, who was supposed to play something else.
And he played sweet Caroline before the game and it had gone really well.
And so after England won, this was against Germany.
He thought, well, I'm going to play it again.
And he played it again and it really kind of took off.
And when the women's football team won the Euros, whenever that was a few years ago,
it was the big sort of song for them.
And it is the big song for England teams now.
And this guy, Tony Perry, he's said something really interesting in an interview,
which is like he's quite important for the team.
Because if you imagine like England played Denmark a few years ago and there were 15 minutes left,
England are winning.
They have the halftime of extra time.
The fans again, really nervous.
The nerves of the fans can kind of go to the nerves of the players and it can kind of affect the game.
But what he can do is he can get the fans going
and he would play Freeford Desire by whoever that's by.
It's like a real proper dance anthem.
The crowd go absolutely mad.
The crowd are suddenly really, really infused and that helps the team to do the job.
So actually the DJ who's at the football stadium can affect the game.
Can alter the game, that's amazing.
I didn't know they had DJs in football stadiums.
Yeah, they do.
But where do they set up?
They're going to annoy the people on either side of them, aren't they?
They're not in decks in the middle of the pitch, they're just in a little booth in there.
So if England does lose and you want to take out some steam of your own sort of anger.
You mean in the next world?
Obviously we won't be able to.
In the next World Cup, yeah, find the DJ and kick the shit out of them.
Didn't do his job.
I thought it was all chanting the referees of anchor and stuff like that.
Is that gone out these days?
Well, during halftime, you don't just sit there shouting the referee.
I mean, the referee's having a cup of tea.
You can't hear anything, there's no point.
Okay, that's interesting.
But then they'll play music.
They'll play loads of music.
And there's specific DJs whose job it is to do all these big events.
And they'll do the Super Bowl and do the World Cup and all that kind of stuff.
And they make their living by knowing what will get the crowd going.
That's interesting.
Do they take requests?
Can I pop to the booth and say, could you please be a bit quiet?
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the classic textbook,
The Art of Editing, was co-written by Jack Scissors.
Very good.
Yeah, that's great.
It's 432 pages.
It was 434, though, before Jack got involved.
Do you know that in the old newspapers, when they were editing,
is they used to use scissors because big part of making your newspaper
was you would take all the stories from all the other newspapers
and you would cut them up and then you would put them on a sheet of paper
to make sure that they all fit it in the right place.
And then you would send them to your printer who would then print them.
Hang on, that implies that to do your newspaper,
you're just taking other stories from other newspapers.
What are the first newspapers?
Well, they borrowed from your edition yesterday.
That's basically kind of how it works.
So if you're a national newspaper,
you would take it from the towns and stuff like that.
In the really early days, there were things called avici,
which were like newsletters that were sent round people
and then they would be all sent to the newspaper
and they would cut those up.
But actually, all the newspapers would just copy off each other a lot of the time.
And obviously, you had to have someone who wrote it originally,
but there were so many newspapers and so many pages to fill,
you wouldn't have enough reporters to do all that.
So you did have to do that.
And you would usually credit wherever you got it from.
In the same way that today, it would say this is an associated press report
that is in the BBC or whatever.
And that was really, really common.
That's amazing because if you got something just completely wrong,
usually you'd think as a local newspaper,
you go, "Well, at least only a couple of thousand people saw that."
Suddenly, it's global news, literally by the name of it.
There was the Charlotte News, this was in 1902.
So towards the end of when they were doing this,
but they set up a trap saying that there was a gang of anarchists
in the Vladivostok who were going to kill all of the prominent rulers on the globe.
And the leader was Count Robgian Ruomoth Lyetsu.
And if you read that backwards, it says, "We steal from our neighbour."
Oh, very good.
That method of cutting out and arranging on the page,
that survived Private Eye Magazine, where I work, also.
I took quite recently.
Yeah?
Oh, is that done now?
No longer. It has gone out now.
But it's during my time working there.
I think that it stopped.
I one day popped into the office while you were there
and you showed me how it was laid out.
It was fascinating.
And sometimes, if someone picks up one of the finished pages,
carries it across the room, there is a bow or everyone goes,
"Oh, just no one coughed to that like it really."
Yeah.
So scissors.
Scissors.
I was looking into a few words around the world
for what scissors are in different languages.
Oh, yeah, that's a good idea.
It's quite fun.
So the Māori for scissors is kāti kāti or kūti kūti.
German, Andy, you speak German.
Do you know what scissors are?
Is something, isn't it shais?
It's like shia.
Yeah, shia, yeah.
So like shearing has a…
Say it in English, I guess.
Shias.
This is the most interesting one.
Hungarian word for it is olo.
Olo.
Yeah.
Now, why is that interesting?
Is it because it looks like a pair of scissors?
It looks like a pair of scissors.
Yeah, is that why it's called that or not?
Well, that's what that's…
Actually, what you've drawn looks like a penis.
That's a pair of cheeky testicles on the other side.
Is that great?
Yeah, good on them.
That isn't presumably why it's called that.
No, I don't think so.
I think it might.
I mean, but it's hard to think that that's not why it's called that.
They're still made in the UK.
Scissors.
Scissors aren't.
Yeah, but lots of manufacturing's gone elsewhere.
In Sheffield, bingo, there used to be, in Sheffield,
40,000 workers in the scissors and cutlery trade.
Mostly cutlery.
But some scissors too.
And obviously, a lot of them aren't in business anymore,
but I think there might still be two.
There's Whiteley, who've been going since 1760, at least,
and there's also Ernest Wright and Son.
They have two, what they're called, master putter-togetherers.
Is their job literally…
That's the title.
That is what the title is for anyone who does the job of putting scissors together.
They'll put her together.
And they're proper, you know, they're metal,
all the way, handle, blade, everything.
They're sort of proper…
Stay in the steel, I guess.
Yeah.
And there was a brilliant video in 2014 showing the trade
and how it still operated.
So I don't know if this guy is still working there anymore,
because he'd been there about 50 years when this was made.
So he probably isn't still there now.
But he, one of the two master putter-togetherers,
was called Eric Stones.
Now, you would have wet stones in there.
Yeah, just show them.
Oh, I was thinking…
Grind stones.
I was thinking like, rock, paper, scissors.
What's another word for rock?
Oh, I see.
A stone.
Do you, does anyone ever say stone, paper, scissors?
Yeah, and in other countries.
There we go.
I did see a story of someone trying to rob a shoe shop
with a stone.
But the person behind the counter…
That's some paper.
No, had some scissors.
Oh, sorry.
But the story made it into the papers.
So you've got all three there.
Anyway, Sheffield, yes, did used to make even more exciting scissors.
They made the smallest pair of scissors in the world
in the 19th century.
Did they?
Yeah, they did.
So they claimed…
Was it for cutting something very small, or was it just for fun?
I think it was just for fun.
And to entertain the royal family, they went to show them all.
Britain's chief industry until the mid-20th century
was just doing things to impress the Queen.
It was actually the 1820s.
So it was King George IV.
And the manufacturer was Joseph Rogers and Sons.
And they took some tiny scissors to show George IV.
And according to Sheffield museums,
they dropped them on its carpet,
and they were so small that they were never found.
No, get out.
They're still there on the floor of Focke and Palace.
That's a risk, isn't it?
You know, you don't want to walk around barefoot, do you?
No.
You want to be in a carpet where you know there's a pair of scissors here somewhere.
That's why the royals are always wearing shoes.
From small scissors to large scissors.
I didn't know this.
But often, you know those large scissors that you get
when someone's unvaving something?
Oh, yeah, the novelty of cutting a ribbon.
Ribbon cuts it.
They don't look very sharp, though.
I don't think they are.
No.
I think… I don't know.
Oh, they're sharp enough for a ribbon.
Oh, yeah.
Ribbons really aren't that hard to cut.
They can't do micro-surgery or anything like that.
But why would you want them to?
But normally, they're…
Your doctor brought those out during micro-surgery.
The last thing you see is you're doing the couch for the anesthesia.
Five, six, what the fuck?
But normally, you hire them.
I guess because why on earth would you want to keep a two-foot-long pair of scissors?
It's just…
There can't be many in the country.
There aren't many in the country, James.
I'm so glad.
So, in the UK, there's unveiling curtains.co.uk.
Oh, yeah.
And they say no unveiling ceremony is complete without a pair of our giant ceremony ribbon
scissors.
But in America, there's goldenopenings.com.
Oh, I saw their website, really great.
Yeah, and Goldenert, what were you googling when you found that?
But they are 40 inches long.
They advertise themselves as the largest working scissors in the world.
Someone who apparently keeps scissors on them at all times is…
A hairdresser.
A hairdresser, yes, in this very specific case, Richard Branson.
Oh.
This is such an odd thing that he does.
He hates when people are a bit too formal.
He thinks that businesses should be relaxed.
He's often asked by CEOs, "How can I make my business more relaxed?"
If he sees anyone around the table with a tie on, he gets his scissors out.
He goes over and he cuts their tie off.
And he says, "Everyone laughs.
Everyone has a great old time."
But that's his thing.
I'm sure they'll continue laughing when he's left the room.
Yeah, exactly.
I don't just call him a wanker.
Yeah.
I must have said this tie was given to me by my grandfather.
Does he have special…
They must be quite sharp scissors.
I'm sure they are.
But…
You know, how strong are you?
Do you have ties made of wood?
No, to cut through a tie in a single amusing chief executive gesture.
It's quite…
He must have killed thousands of underlings.
I do have a tie made of wood, like a bow tie made of wood out of cork.
Of course you do.
But I think if I ever meet Richard Branson, I'm going to wear it
and see how strong a scissors really is.
Exactly.
There's a pair of scissors that I've only ever used three times.
What are they?
I know what they are.
Oh, yeah.
Unfilical cord scissors.
I don't own them myself.
I've only ever used them.
But yeah, umbilical scissors, which I have used three times
because I have three kids in hospital.
Okay, you haven't used the same.
It's not like you bought some especially.
No, they're labelled…
They're hanging up in the hospital and they're labelled
"property of defibrillation".
Do not touch.
He will be back for another one soon.
Yeah, I used the ones that were in the hospital.
I was asked if I'd want to cut the umbilical cord.
But did you say…
Did you say yes every time?
I would say yes because I was like, "Why would I… why?"
Oh, right.
Everyone said yes.
Why would I, though?
Why would I want to do something that a professional can do?
Will you offer the chance?
Yeah, of course.
I think they always offer the chance.
I frequently will sneak into hospitals
and ask if I can pretend to use…
Like, "Oh, when the time comes, can I do the cutting?"
You're subbed in.
You're there on the sidelines.
Yeah.
Is it quite thick and so grisly?
It is.
It's a bit odd and you're a bit nervous when you're doing it
because you think, "What if I get this wrong?"
Nothing can happen.
Well, you don't know that in the moment.
Unless you get really wrong and like,
"Shop your baby's willy off," or something.
Yeah.
That's not the umbilical cord.
It was a very well endowed baby.
That's so funny.
No, but you can…
I looked online.
You can buy from Amazon umbilical cord scissors
to use on your own at home,
say for home births, right?
No.
That would be good if you were opening
a new wing of a maternity ward.
You could, like, instead of a ribbon,
you could have an umbilical cord.
So if you have a newborn baby,
just slowly pull away from your mother.
Your mother just after birth.
Sorry.
Do you mind if we just move you to the ceremony room?
It's the grand opening.
Yeah.
But is there anything special about them
except a gimmick to get money out of people on Amazon?
These are used.
Are they any more special then?
Oh, they're specially shaped.
They're different types of scissors.
Yeah, to what you don't use, your classic scissors.
Oh, I think they're sort of curved.
I think they're sort of curved.
I thought they just need to be sharp.
Really?
No, I think they're slightly curved
and, like, half moon-shaped.
Yes.
Are they?
But, yeah, I had a one-star review.
This main pair that comes up.
Wait, is it one-star?
Baby's still attached.
He's four years old now.
Yeah, it basically said does not cut well.
Stiff to use needed several attempts to cut,
which is a bit terrifying.
But I was trying to look into them.
This is a very random tangent,
but I discovered a guy who said,
"Hey, when you're in the hospital
and you are offered to cut the baby's umbilical cord,
why not suggest biting it off
instead of using the scissors?"
And Brian Blessed.
Like Brian Blessed's style.
That's right.
He did that in a park.
Well, he did it when he said that he did.
He said that he did.
But this guy said that he did.
He said, "I went in.
I said to them, 'Is it cool if I do the umbilical cutting?'
He believed that because I started the baby with my seed,
this is me ending the process
by using my mouth to bite into it."
It's a bit.
He said it tastes like calamari,
the rubbery kind of...
It wouldn't taste like calamari.
Yes, it tastes like blood.
Yes, his wife was a squid.
[LAUGHTER]
Were you watching My Octopus Keeper
or whatever that thing is?
Yeah.
No, no.
He said it was basically like blood,
iron-like, the texture of it was calamari-like.
And apparently, if you ask, they might say yes.
So if anyone fancies it...
Worth asking.
They'll think you're a real weirdo,
but they might say yes.
Can I give you a riddle?
Yeah.
Okay.
2017.
Yes.
Right.
There's a guy in Vietnam.
He's 54 years old.
He has a road accident.
Yeah.
And there's...
This is not a good riddle.
There seems to be something sharp
inside his stomach.
Is it scissors?
I could wait.
Now I haven't finished the riddle.
[LAUGHTER]
He'd recently been to fucking a palace
and was licking the carpet.
[LAUGHTER]
Is that how they get...
The fucking impan is clean.
Yeah.
He says, "This happens.
I have to lick the floors."
[LAUGHTER]
Oh, that's the deep clean.
No, in the second hospital scant him,
and they found a six-inch pair of scissors
inside him.
Okay.
Which had been there since 1998.
Oh, did he have an operation?
The year of the most French thing
that has ever happened.
[LAUGHTER]
The year after Diana died.
The surgeon said, "Sacre bleu!"
Because he was actually watching
the World Cup at the same time.
No, 19 years.
This guy had had a six-inch pair of scissors
inside him and had had a little bit of stomach pain,
but basically nothing else.
Isn't that just...
Six inches is long.
And is it from having an operation
and someone dropped it in?
Yes, it was.
[LAUGHTER]
So the riddle is a bad one.
Please forget the riddle element.
But I just think that's stunning
that he'd had a previous road accident in 1998,
had an operation for it.
They'd left the scissors in and then,
and they only found it
as a result of the second road accident.
Right.
So that's kind of pleasing.
I think if you're a surgeon
and you need to put down the scissors for a second,
Yeah.
Put them on a tray.
Absolutely.
Don't put it on someone's spleen.
[LAUGHTER]
Well, that was the gross thing.
They had rusted and they had become stuck
to his nearby organs
because they'd been there so long.
Yeah, that's going to make him super sick.
He was all right.
Was he?
Yeah, he was fine.
It is weird that the body can withstand that size,
because it must have really misshapen
various bits of him,
but they obviously just stretch to accommodate them.
Yep.
Spine went, "Hey, all right, I'll take you."
Do you know what knob cutters are used for?
Knob cutters?
Yeah.
Is it a type of scissor?
Visectomies?
No.
Unix?
[LAUGHTER]
Knob cutters?
Nobs.
Oh, doors.
Door nobs.
Knob doors.
The type of cactus.
Nobs of butter.
Closer.
Oh.
Cactus, have nipples, but what has knobs?
What, a plant with a knob?
Yeah, just trees, I guess.
A tree.
Well, why would you use scissors on a tree?
You want to make it nice and smooth,
because you work for Yves Saint Laurent,
and he's mental.
Well, you would use shears
or you would use like a chainsaw, right?
A tiny tree, then.
It's got to be.
Bonsai.
They are used by Bonsai.
So great.
That's cool.
Gardeners, yeah.
They are.
The Bonsai scissor world is pretty amazing.
Well, they're like, the knob cutters are really cool looking,
because the bit which you cut
looks like it could be a tiny Sheffield,
like the world's smallest scissor.
Brilliant.
But then the handles are normal sized handles.
Because obviously you need to sort of--
To have your fingers in there.
Put your fingers in it,
but also you're cutting something really, really small.
That makes so much sense.
That's good.
That's a good thing for like a James Bond super villain
to say is like, you know,
when Bond's tied to the child or whatever.
Bring me the knob cutters.
Turn through Bonsai tree.
Gives them a little truth.
That's brilliant.
You would have to set up that Joe Kerrier in the movie.
Oh, yeah, I would ensure that I did.
Or put some subtitles explaining what they are.
Joe Kerrier's like,
"I don't know what you mean about the knob cutters."
And then Blow Felt's like,
"Well, actually, it's the name of, you know,
some scissors that use it Bonsai."
Now bring in the dildo cactus.
Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our very social media accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland on Instagram, James.
My Instagram is @NosageThingsJamesHarken.
Andy on Twitter @AndrewHunterM.
Yep, where you can get to us as a group.
Where, Anna?
You can go to Instagram @NosageThingasafish
or Twitter @NosageThing or email podcast.qi.com.
Yeah, and head to our website, nosagethingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
There is a link to our upcoming Thunder Nerds tour tickets.
They're still on sale.
Check out if we're coming to a city near you and book them now.
And also a link to Club Fish,
our secret place where we put up bonus episodes
and extra content.
It's really awesome.
Check it out.
If not, just come back here next week
where we'll have another episode
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)