[Music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from four undisclosed locations in the UK. My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with James
Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray and Anna Tushinsky and once again we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order here we go. Starting
with you, Anna. My fact this week is that during out-of-hours periods hospital CT scanners are
sometimes used to scan Egyptian mummies. Wow, so cool. It's so weird this is um because mummies
need scanning sometimes to find out what's inside them so it's much less invasive as you can imagine
than actually unwrapping a mummy which can sort of cause the mummies to disintegrate as you do it
and you want to know what jewels they've got in them or what state their bones are in stuff like that
and about well actually almost since the dawn of x-rays they realized this would be really useful
for scanning mummies and since the year 2000 apparently it's been a routine use for hospital
CT scanners is to use them on mummies there are various hospitals in the UK that do it I think
Manchester Children's Hospital does a very strong line in loaning its CT scanners out.
I remember I think it was Leeds Hospital I can't remember exactly but I read one of them saying
that they did it in the night or out of hours because they didn't want to scare the patients
which I think makes sense doesn't it? I love the idea of seeing the previous patient coming out
and then being desiccated and they're 2000 years old I'm not going in there.
I think it looks a bit late for that one to be honest so the scounds necessary.
So this one was in Spain right the specific story that you sent around to us because I found this
very specific one very fascinating the fact that this was a project that was done between
the Spanish National Museum of Archaeology and one of the university hospitals and they wanted to
scan three of the mummies that they had trying to identify who they were and really cool thing about
it is that they had to map out a specific route from the museum to the hospital so that they
went on roads that had no bumps on them so that they didn't damage the mum you know you don't want
to hit a speed bump break your mummy in half on the way. That's pretty sweet I once broke a rib
and I got a taxi home because I didn't realize I broke my rib and it's the most pain that I've ever
been in because the speed bumps everywhere in London isn't there yeah and tax drivers don't seem
to care about them and it was just every time you went over one it killed and then I read a bit later
that they thought they might use speed bumps as a way of telling if you've got appendicitis
so it's a really good way of telling because the speed bumps hurt you so much if you've got
something like appendicitis that it's almost as good a way of diagnosing it as almost any other
non-invasive way. Wow I think these are great though we should release these as part of GPS
sort of like Egyptologists should release the routes that have no bumps so that like not just
people with broken ribs but mummies to be you know pregnant women they can't go over bumps as well
you know we should be using this for a footage well no I mean it's not good for you it's not good
for you to go but it's so funny because you've got a bump and yet you can't go over a bump the bump
is within you already that is funny you should only have one one bump should never meet another
that's the rule the Spanish ones are really cool because they there were some Egyptian mummies and
there were some guanchi mummies which are ancient people from Tenerife and I didn't know that people
from Tenerife got turned into mummies they were buried in caves and the naturally dry air desiccated
them and dried them out so yeah and the Egyptian one they got when they scanned they discovered
that it was the Pharaoh Imhotep's high priest like what a score what a that's like to me that's like
panini stickers like you're like oh yes it's like a shiny priest yeah exactly it's a shiny
how did they tell that from a scan was he wearing a badge he was actually like weirdly he was wearing
a lot of amulets and there were lots of adornments where they could piece together who he was uh
from what he was wearing okay make sense because yeah they're often wrapped up with you know
possessions like rubies and jewels and sapphires and things like that aren't they so the scan
actually serves two purposes with the mummy you can see what they were buried with and so learn
a lot about the rituals and then you can see into their bones and see kind of what injuries they had
and so what sort of lives they led and also quite often you can see what it actually is so it turns
out when things are mummified and we find them we don't always know even whether it's a human or an
animal they brought one into the Kent Institute of Medicine and Surgery in 2018 which they all
thought was a mummified bird and put it through the scanner and it turned out that it was a miscarried
baby but that actually makes it the youngest mummy ever to be discovered that's amazing so it
tells you a lot have you heard about the crocodile shaped mummy that they found no no this was brought
in and it was i mean it was very clearly the shape of a crocodile it couldn't it was if it was a
Christmas present under the tree you would think oh i'm getting a crocodile basically but they looked
into it they scanned it right in the CT scanner and they discovered that it was not a crocodile
can you guess what it was oh an alligator no um a human sticking their arms out in a crocodile
mouth fashion oh yeah like an old school baby baby shark kind of like a baby shark impersonation
yes yeah it was actually eight crocodiles it was eight small crocodiles which had been mummified
in the shape of a big crocodile and i think this is where we get the cultural trope of the like
three small people in an overcoat yeah exactly but they're trying to get into an adult crocodile
movie crocodiles were hunted to be mummified as well weren't they which we didn't realize we
kind of thought that they just mummified dead crocodiles as and when they came upon them
but they've realized from CT scanning the mummified crocs they've realized that you
you must have had sort of crocodile hunters who would have to go out and beat crocodiles to death
and they smashed it the CT scan shows that their skulls have been smashed in and then rebuilt
so you kill it by smashing in its skull but then you kind of need to make it look like a proper
skull again it's not surprising they went for eight baby crocodiles they just came back saying oh
yeah i got another crocodile here i've actually pre-mummified it so there's no need to examine
very good um so CT scanners the the object themselves um a british invention at least
half so from a guy called godfrey and houndsfield who in the 70s was awarded a Nobel prize for it
and EMI were the people who developed the CT scanner and EMI is the very same EMI that is the
music company and when they yeah when they were developing this they needed more money to sort
of help the company to do this stuff and it just so happened that in 1957 EMI acquired capital
records which allowed them to distribute british music into america and it's 1957 the beetles
are about to arrive in 1962 a few years later and that is that helped raise the money for CT
scanners so the beetles are partially responsible for the reason that we have CT scanners i've read
quite a few places saying that's a myth and there's a paper which is called do we really need to thank
the beetles for financing the development of the computed tomography scanner i don't know if that's
the kind of tone that they had in mind when they wrote the title but they say um that EMI only paid
about 100 000 pounds into the into the development of the CT scanner whereas the government paid
in a lot more than that and so they say accordingly british taxpayers and officials of the british
dhss are to be thanked for the CT scanner the beetles input into the world's culture is valuable
but it does not require decoration by non-existent connection to the development of CT
i don't know hear me out hear me out hear me out who was paying a lot of tax due to very very
high government tax rates in the 1960s and 70s the beetles right the rod of stone's all they went
to france it was the beetles i've got to say i do i do agree with them that i think these guys are
being a little bit uppity in it and i think that the beetles you know it's 100 000 pounds and it
was at the start as well they gave houndsfield the money at the top and then the government came
in and gave them a lot more money later so i think it's kind of fair that the beetles had something
to say but sorry what it was a record label investing in CT scanners well because EMI stands for
electric and music industries and they originally an electrical and music company so they made
electrics and they made music and so this was like the electrical side of their brand and they
also did music stuff as well okay sounds legit yeah it sounds almost it's still loose i reckon but
yeah good on them thank you beetles for saving so many lives rockets get CT scanned and that's to
check that all their stuff is working so nasa and the navy use this system called actist systems
which are special rocket CT scanners and they are specially rigged up to spot floors in like the
engine parts and stuff like that and they doubled up as whale scanners very cool this guy called
ted cranford who's a whale expert and he became obsessed with the idea that he really wanted
to CT scan a whale and most whales don't fit into most conventional CT scanners and you could get
six tiny whales and put them in a big whale suit doesn't make any sense you've got to go the other
way round chop a whale into six parts uh anyway so first of all he needed to get hold of a whale
so apparently his mates knew that he was looking for a big old whale head to scan and they found
a dead sperm whale on a california beach and so these two friends of his borrowed a front end
loader like one of those trucks from a construction company nearby cut the head off this whale carried
it to a massive freezer somewhere in a marine laboratory in california called ted was like
well look we've got your whale head what now and then ted was like okay cool we need to find a
CT scanner and he convinced the navy to loan him their massive rocket scanner and it's revealed
lots of cool stuff so the whole point is to find out about whale vocalization so sperm whale clicks
are incredibly loud so he wants to look at how they make them and then how they hear and yeah
now he just shoves marine animals through CT scanners all the time he said the um i was really
an interview with him and he was saying he once was trying to dissect a dolphin head and he had to
do it in a deep freezer so he has to wear freezer gear and go into the deep freezer to dissect this
head uh but at the time the deep freeze was being shared by a giant skewer uh sort of swan-sized bird
from antarctica oh skewer i thought yeah we're having a giant kebab at the end of the day
no a skewer this this massive bird from the antarctic they just kept attacking him and
vomiting on him for four days as he tried to dissect this oh it was alive why was it live
in the freezer well it's from antarctic it's used to life exactly it wouldn't like it in the oven
but what it was okay the dolphin's dead i thought the dolphin was alive the dolphin no dolphin's
dead and it's not in water it's not in the wrong way around dolphin's dead in the freezer if you
put a dolphin in the freezer it will die if it's not already uh skewer's life yeah but yeah he's
a bit of a hero was the skewer kind of tied up do you think it must have been right that kind of
just been what kind of sick messed up scientist ties up a skewer in a freezer i was thinking you
know what i was thinking and yeah what i was thinking is and this won't go in but do you remember
on your stag do when we did the escape room with the zombie who was tied up oh yeah i was just
thinking that as well yes with the chain and he only gets so far i can imagine even more exciting
if it was a skewer yeah yeah and then if the key is hidden inside the head of a dead dolphin but
you have to get it into a c2 scanner to see where it is okay it's time for fact number two and that
is my fact my fact this week is that in 1973 british rail successfully designed and patented
a flying saucer wow that sounds awesome so um this was uh the late 1960s british rail commissioned
an engineer who was called charles osmond frederick and they does they commissioned him to design
a lifting platform uh for use and he took some time to develop it and then he came back to them
he lifted things too far it's exactly in 1973 he came back with what he claimed was a fully
functional flying fusion powered spinning flying saucer so it's uh it was a very exciting thing
he handed it in and not only did they not send him away and say he was crazy but they submitted it
to be patented and the government granted it it was successfully patented and it was given a number
and everything and it should still in theory be patented but they overran on the on the license
and they didn't renew um so unfortunately why on earth would you not renew a patent for a nuclear
fusion powered flying saucer yeah can i just when when you say they wanted a lifting platform what
did that mean i think you know when when you see construction workers outside and they go on that
little platform that looks like a cross ladder that raises up and up i think it's like one of those
they they obviously had a need for it somewhere in what they do got it and he decided a fusion
power because it's fusion powered wasn't it which is yeah fascinatingly ambitious given that what
humans have been trying to do for almost a century is create something that can be powered by fusion
based energy yeah he just thought sort it i reckon i'm on to it yeah to be honest i mean it was it was
fusion powered right it was ignited by laser beams uh and the lasers were energized by a homopolar
generator and it kind of feels like he's just been reading a load of science fiction books and
picked up a few words a gun owl you know that's a kind of thing isn't it why don't we say that i
mean well was incredibly detailed i think he i think he thought he knew that the science didn't
exist i think he was trying to predict the future of where science would go and the idea i think
british rail saw this this was a time when there was a lot of interest in space and they thought maybe
let's get ahead of the game here and make sure if if we suddenly discover all the things that he's
predicted sorry not predicted but needs that are not yet around if they suddenly come to
this this might actually work it feels a bit like patent trolling doesn't it because if i
tomorrow managed to come up with a way of making nuclear fusion work so it can power things i don't
want to have to pay 20 percent to british rail because they speculatively said that oh we invented
this thing that is going to be in the future james if you do that and i am not saying you will i'm
saying in fact that you won't but if you did do that you infuse like a hundred years from now
sorry to cross your dreams i feel like you should believe in me okay look as a physics
graduate i'm saying you are the most likely of the four of us to produce nuclear fusion however
but even if you did do that in a podcast a hundred years from now they would be able to say
did you know that actually we have british rail to thank for nuclear fusion it would be like
emi and the ct scan all over again yes they're the beetles yeah or what we'd be saying it's thanks
to a podcast wait a minute are we the beetles in this case i don't think we can say that i think
british rail is the beetles and we're sort of einstein
and people are going did you know it's not actually james harkin who we have to thank for fusion
it's british rail very good yeah and one of the reasons that we didn't know this until quite recently
so it was some like patent fans found it didn't they yeah but one of the reasons that we didn't
find it is because it contained the word nuclear in the patent and when you put the word nuclear in
your patent it kind of often gets given a secrecy order and so you need to go through an extra hoop
to look at those patents really yeah it looked really cool though um if you look at the drawings
on the patent it does look like a proper flying saucer and there's drawings on the inside there's
not proper descriptions of what the inside um how it would fully function it was more trying to focus
on the engineering side of it but it looks to some people who've who've sort of analyzed what
were drawn it looks like it could carry 60 people inside it the way that it looked like they would
be inside it is that if you picture like when you go to a fairground and there's that gravity tunnel
thing where you all stand against the wall and as it spins you get sucked to the wall it's sort of
like that the seats are the seats are arranged around the edge of the inside of the circular
saucer that's an uncomfortable way to travel if you're going by british rail and you have to be
stuck up against the side how are you going to get to the buffet car exactly also they don't work
on me genuinely it doesn't work on me genuinely doesn't work on me i've been on i've been on them
twice and i wouldn't go on again because everyone had to hold my hand as i slid down the wall and
everyone else is stuck up there i was just i just stayed on the floor the floor drops away
this is an even bigger claim than james saying he's going to invent nuclear fusion is that i'm
saying just the laws don't apply to him just this one law isn't it like so the coolest british rail
invention that i came across was uh did you guys know about the pub cars no i know so this is in
1949 british rail decided to launch carriages that were pubs and they were properly decked out like
well they went for moctuda design lovely and the outside of the carriage was all fake brick so it
looked like an idyllic village bricked up to the pub but they put pub signs up i think uh there are
a few of them made no they have names like the white horse the jolly tar the green man thomas the
tanked engine would be an awesome name for one very nice very good very very good but yeah this
happened you could go board your train and sit down have a bite insane yeah and it was it was
discontinued because everyone thought it was really tacky oh they're wrong i went to um i went to
universal studios in america right which is like a theme park isn't it and they have the harry potter
world there and you can get on the um is it called the hogwarts the hogwarts express uh and you can
pretend that you're going across the scottish countryside to get to hogwarts okay um but first
of all you have to queue up in an exact replica of king's cross and then um they have a shop which
is supposed to be exactly the same as a uk railway shop and they're so accurate they sold cans of
strongbow isn't that amazing they sold they had loads of like british brands of like i don't know
what british brands are but like candies and stuff like that round trees but they had cans of strongbow
i've never felt so at home in my life drunk eight-year-olds everywhere yeah running desperately
at platform nine and three quarters so many concussed children since you mentioned harry potter
i just want to say something about king's cross station because you know platform nine and three
quarters the thing that really pisses off harry potter fans about it when you go to king's cross
no where is it it's between platforms eight and nine so basically jk rowling guy station's confused
she meant houston she said king's cross and so they couldn't actually put platform nine and
three quarters between platforms nine and ten so it's between eight and nine and a harry potter
fan goes to king's cross is like oh my god this doesn't make any sense it's not eight and three
quarters wow king's cross could resolve this quite pressing problem because they have 13 platforms
they've got but they've got they've got 13 platforms but their platforms only go up to 11 so one of
them is nine and three quarters which is like a fake one but the other one they needed to add an
extra platform a few years ago and they needed to add it to the left hand side to the opposite side
of platform one and they didn't want to call it platform 12 because they thought that'll confuse
people because it's at the opposite end to like platform 10 11 etc so they called it platform zero
right so what king's cross can do is they rename platform zero platform one yeah as you would rename
platform one platform two etc etc etc you get to platform eight and nine and suddenly platform
nine and three quarters is in the right place it's a great idea i mean you only have one week
probably of people wanting to go to lutan and ended up in glasgow but then once that's happened
a few times people will get wise to it to be honest what's one week more of lost economic
activity for the uk at this point exactly should we talk about ufo's let's do it they're illegal
in chateau nerf de pape you are right will they disturb the grapes don't they that is actually
exactly why it is a really really well kind of yeah so chateau nerf de pape it's a town in southeast
france and they obviously make very good red wine and all the winemakers are quite protective of
their brand and then in the 1950s there was a load of reports in france of these what they called
cigar valance which means flying cigars and there were these kind of ufo's going around and people
saying that they'd seen martians and stuff like that it's just like one of these normal mass hysteria
things where everyone thought they saw ufo's but when that happened all the wine growers were
like well we can't have ufo's around here so they made a law saying that no ufo is allowed to land
in chateau nerf de pape and they're not even allowed to fly over and if any alien lands then
they will be arrested immediately and actually only a few years ago the mayor of chateau nerf de
pape said that they will keep the law on the books so it definitely does exist he said that they
want to keep it because it kind of gives them a little bit of publicity and stuff and it gets them
in the news every now and again when people realize this is the thing but yes if you're an alien then
you like your wine you can't go to chateau nerf de pape do you think do you think there are aliens
in alien air traffic control somewhere going oh we've really need to land in the sort of south
of france region oh but we you remember we can't do it in the pape area because of course
into planetary law i don't know how much they respect into planetary law i think it's a french
law isn't it question is have you ever heard of a ufo landing there Anna that is a good question
and i haven't done point proven point proven they respect it greatly um do you guys know that a
decline in christianity is directly responsible for a massive rise in flying sources in an interesting
way um so this is because in the 1940s there's a there was a belgian company called belgica
and it made communion wafers for church and a decline in christianity meant that there was
suddenly a lot less demand for communion wafers and so they were like well what do we do we've
got this technology but people aren't really buying it anymore and then what they realized was
they could take that paper in communion wafers sandwich some sherbet in between two bits of it
and what you've got there is a flying saucer no the confectionery left by all so hitting so flying
saucers are made from communion wafers same stuff i guess originate yeah yeah that is amazing and i've
got to say the church is really missing out on a way of getting the youth in isn't it yeah if those
wafers exploded in your mouth in the same way that flying sources do i might convert that is cool
okay it is time for fact number three and that is andy my fact is that in 2017 the u.s defense
secretary had a light installed in his bathroom which would turn on if north korea launched a
nuclear missile how stressful wow how stressful who was it that was james when james mattis that's
right jim mattis and this was at the time when north korea was launching it was the big sort of
north korean missile huha of 2017 and it needed urgent response obviously if they launched another
missile although detected doing another nuclear test and this light was installed in his bathroom
so he could see it from the shower if he was having a shower he would be able to immediately
jump out of the shower go downstairs get in the car and go and did he always have to shower in
the dark so that he'd be able to see this light really well i don't know what he had basically
his whole home was rigged up like this huge korean missile booby trap so there was a bell in his
kitchen that was one in his bedroom and i should say this is all from a new book called rage by
bob woodward who is an incredible veteran u.s reporter and these these bells went off on more
than one occasion and he had a car which had to be followed by an suv and inside the suv there was
a team plotting the flight path of any potential incoming nuclear missile and this was just his
life he had a very very stressful life and he slept he slept in his gym clothes didn't he he
had just had to be at the ready yeah time i don't think he should have showered in his clothes as
well otherwise we'll see how often did he end up naked in the emergency vehicles just on on missiles
generally it's astonishing when you look into the history of missile and missile alerts in
the last 70 years and you realize how many times we've come to the brink of essentially nuclear war
based on a what should have been a minor cock up isn't it so there have just been so many
false missile alarms and i think my favorite ones are well one of them was in 1960 when there was
so mid-cold war everyone is very tense to be fair there was radar u.s radar in greenland
which suddenly reported that there were dozens of soviet missiles coming over the horizon exactly
where they'd be expected to be coming from and they were attacking and so the u.s defense command
went into maximum alert um you know things were they were getting ready to retaliate and it turned
out to be the moon so it was all right it was a moon rise over norway which it happened that the
moon reflected back the radar uh in the same way the missile attack might have wow and it came back
with 99.9 percent certainty that they were under soviet attack and that's amazing that's poor
programming isn't it it's because you would think that the moon sometimes rises over norway
and you'd think there would be some kind of anti-moon protocol built into this program yeah
there was another one in 1979 where they believed that they were on the brink of of death as well
and it was um this one guy who was the national security advisor to president corridor so this
is in america where this happened um he woke up with the phone call saying that the soviets had
just launched 250 missiles and it was headed straight for them and he had this weird reaction
where he was in a house full of his family and he didn't bother to wake his wife up because he
assumed that there was no point in troubling her with the fear they were all going to be dead
in the next half hour or so so just leave them and um he sort of casually just accepted that death
was coming and then just waited in all the systems again sort of showed that this was a big mistake
and they couldn't work out what it was turns out it was a video game that had been put accidentally
into the system at norad and they were doing a simulation of what it would be like if they were
attacked but the system thought it was real and it was just a complete cock up yeah so this war
game was playing out and they all thought this was a real thing and they eventually worked that out
and carter never found out until years or at least months down the line that this had in fact happened
I can't imagine not waking up one spouse at a time when you think nuclear war is coming
well that's just your typical selfish attitude isn't it you're suffering you want her to suffer too
you want to be screaming with someone I guess he had a job to do though right like he had
he was the guy who was meant to check in on this you wouldn't want your whole family screaming
around you go as you try to remain calm one of the really scary things is that one of the things
he thought to do in that moment was and this was supposedly the quote I want to make sure that we'd
have company and the idea was he wanted to press a button of retaliation on the Soviets
before they all died so that that was wiped out as well so like like this misfire thing that could
have led to something real as well well that's why there's a lot of controversy still about the
fact that we still have all those cold war things in place which mean that they can retaliate within
minutes and but I think the terrifying thing about that one Dan was that it must have seemed so
perfect right because the the tape I think it was a technician accidentally put this tape into one of
the machines at NORAD which is the North American Aerospace Defense Command and it the whole point
of the simulation was to make it seem like the Soviets had launched the worst possible attack
you know every single nuclear facility was targeted every single missile was targeted
so it must have been like wow they've really got us this time yeah yeah they do have um it's not
just one person presses the button and then the missile goes they have a few safeguards so at any
time in America they have 90 what are called missile ears who are sitting on alert somewhere in the
desert wow they're all underground kind of in these silo places and they work in teams of two
and they each sit together in like on the wall it says a no-lone zone as in you're not allowed to
be alone because if you're on your own you might accidentally start World War 3 without you know
someone telling you not to yeah and you sit two of you in a room and there's an A side and a B
side and you each have a code which you're supposed to put in and if your codes match then that sets
off the bomb but also I think five of the people in the whole thing need to do it at the same time
in order for them to go off and there's 90 of them and in the US military it's mostly men who are
obviously in the in the military um but in that particular one there's a disproportionately high
number of women in that role and the US Air Force um did a big sort of press release in March 2016
because they had the first time that it was an all-female alert so all 90 people who were like in
charge of whether America sends missiles to its enemies were women and that was the first time
that happened all 90 yeah wow so they have an all together they have a team of quite a few hundred
and so normally it would be a mix but on this particular occasion they had the first ever
all-female team obviously you wouldn't want nuclear war to happen ever yeah it does happen then it
would be a nice win for equality if it was the last if it was yeah if I don't know but would it
that I mean some naysayers would say that if the one time when we actually started a nuclear war
was the first time it was all women working up that's a very good point it would I think it would
set back the cause of women working in missile silos across the world well fortunately there
would be no humans around to uh have that problem if there would be some man there was some man would
pop up saying ah if you remember we did try this yes some male cockroach there's that really sweet
story which I think is quite famous I didn't actually know it so I feel like I should mention it
but before norad was called norad it was called konad and konad was the continental air defense
command and one day the air force colonel harry shoup sitting in his office and he gets a phone
call which is on a line which basically suggests that the russians are attacking if this phone
rings the russians are attacking and at the end of the line which he grabs it up nervously expecting
the worse he hears a tiny little voice which says is this santa claus and he thinks what what the
hell's going on here and he barks into the phone back at them say we know what's going on and the
voice is crying he's going is this one of santa's elves and what had happened was there was a huge
mistake there was an advert that was placed in sears catalogue the sears advert which gave out the
number to call santa claus but they put the wrong number in there and the number they ended up giving
was this classified line that was dedicated to a russian missile attack and it's so funny it's
extraordinary that that happens what were the chances it's not just a random person in america
yeah and um what's wonderful about it though is that they decided to embrace it and that is a thing
now that you can call norad and ask them to track where santa is oh in the period of crisis so you
are going to say you can ask them to drop a bomb any way you like for christmas that's what you want
have you been good yes the naughty list consists of vladimir vladimirovich putin
okay and it's time for our final fact of the show and that is james my fact this week is that fashion
historian hillary davidson has invented the bill and ted test which judges the historical accuracy
of movie costumes by comparing them against the surprisingly accurate movie bill and ted's
excellent adventure so i did wonder why everyone in pride and prejudice is wearing backwards caps
well this is really interesting because um this historian um hillary davidson she was actually
writing a book about dress in the age of jane austin uh and when she was writing it there's a lot of
quite boring bits that you have to do of copy editing and indexing and stuff like that and
when she was doing her copy editing of the index as it happens um she was watching movies at the
same time because it was just such a boring tedious job uh and so she was watching bill and ted and
she got to the bit where they kidnapped baithoven and they she kind of looked at the extras and thought
wow they are actually really good they look just like they're supposed to look and so she thought
well that's it i'm a fashion historian i need a benchmark i need to decide what's good and what's
bad so this is my benchmark if you're making a proper regency production and you can't get
it as good as bill and ted then there's something wrong and so now on twitter she has @ bill and ted
test um where whenever she sees a new movie she rates it against bill and ted and sees whether it
passes or fails are there films which uh you know have failed the bill and ted test oh i didn't write
them down um i'm sorry i can't remember star wars star wars big fail but basically she she says there's
a few things you need to look forward the fab ring for instance so if they're wearing something that's
obviously polyester or something like that um then it just looks wrong and you can tell it but the
other thing is the hair so if your hair is um down and you're an adult woman then unless you are
unmarried and a virgin or you're a prostitute or you're mad then you would not have your hair down
for a woman in that kind of period that's a big risk in a singles bar isn't it i mean i think she's
unmarried and a virgin but it's possible she's a mad prostitute yeah and she wants to she does
say in um this interview in slate she she's stressing that she's not saying everyone has to be completely
historically accurate for everything um but sometimes it can if you're an expert it can put
you off a little bit by seeing you know someone wearing a like you say a baseball cap in the
middle of pride and prejudice yeah it might be worth saying for the one person who is not totally
familiar with bill and ted that the reason that it's a good benchmark is because they travel
in time right to lots of different yes um yeah lots of different time periods where they're wearing
the clothes of that period is that right i mean they're not wearing the clothes of that period
they stay in their own mufti throughout but they go and visit people like Beethoven and Socrates
and Napoleon and yeah they must really stand out yeah they do that's kind of where some of the comedy
comes in yeah i mean it is one of the greatest movies ever made in my opinion and it's one of
the probably half a dozen films before 2010 that i've actually seen i think that might be why you
think it's one of the greatest movies ever made if you compare them with the overall number of movies
made um it's so good but they do spend a portion of the movie in the future is that why you've allowed
that to be part of the movies you can watch james yes exactly i love that we have to thank for giving
us bill and ted the thriller post-apocalyptic author richard matheson uh so if you don't know
richard matheson he is the author of i am legend he is an author who steven king said is the greatest
influence uh that steven king has had by another author that is richard matheson he's he's the master
and sorry and if you don't know what i am legend is it's basically 2020 in a book
it's basically a worldwide apocalypse due to disease isn't it yeah exactly it's exactly that
and so richard matheson happens to be the father of chris matheson who is the co-writer and co-creator
along with um his partner solomon of bill and ted and bill and ted was meant to be just a throw
away sketch they had this idea they were going to play the characters live on stage and they
happened to just mention it to richard matheson saying this is the idea that we have for this
sketch and he said i actually think there's a whole movie in this and they thought oh god okay
that's interesting never thought to do that and they wrote up the movie and that's why we have the
most excellent in bogus adventures wasn't it wasn't it almost the most excellent bogus adventures
um or the most excellent adventures of bill ted and bob because initially in their improv group
and the hot it was like constant improvise wasn't it and uh there were three of them but the character
who was playing bob sort of lost interest in the whole concept and disappeared and so ended up just
being the two of them but it's also they were committed to the bill and ted conceit for years
before it materialized into a film they sort of used to like always like keep the improv going
they would write letters to each other in the characters of bill and ted i don't know if that's
a standard improv behaviour andy it's not okay i'm not constantly writing regency themed letters
to my buddies in the group it's a shame a lot of the things with bill and ted how it's come into
the culture is obviously through its language right so um anna if you haven't seen it they
speak in this real kind of surferish slang of saying like bodacious and triumphant and stuff
like that um and i looked in the oxford english dictionary and they're referenced about a dozen
times uh in the oxford english dictionary so they're referenced for um the phrase yes way
as in the opposite of no way oh wow yes way uh they're referenced in dude in the entry for dude
and also in the entry for second base and they're not first citations they're just kind of examples
but they are the first citation of party on so we don't know anyone else who said party on
before bill and ted did and they're the first citation outside of dictionaries of the word
dickweed um so it's it was mentioned outside dictionaries did you say yeah so sometimes
did a lexicographer invent the word dickweed sneak it in hope it would take off and then
sometimes the oed takes like words from slang dictionaries and puts it into the oed but they
didn't have the citation from there but they do have the citation from bill and ted which is
the first one where um bill says you killed ted you medieval dickweed and that's the first example
we have of someone using that in real life so bill and ted is back in the cinemas uh right now
as we speak face the music the third and i thought they'd been this ginormous gap between the last
movie and now that's all the bill and ted that we have but it turns out underneath there's been
so much there was an animated series which had kianu and alex winter and george carlin voicing
it can i just say that was one of the best cartoons i used to love as a kid i used to love
that so much that show didn't know it existed that's the only version of bill and ted that i've
seen is occasionally what really yeah it had an amazing theme tune as well you're gonna find the
theme tune did you see the live series then there was an action series live action series and they
cast people who when you look at the pictures look exactly like the guys but they also went into
theater there was bill and ted's excellent halloween adventure and musical adventure there were
board games there was the excellent board game and riff in time r i f f riff in time um and then
there was a whole comic book series that has been run for years which were written and drawn by a
guy called evan dorkin really yeah and i basically just said all of that so that i can say the word
evan dorkin i was thinking these are standard brand extensions i don't know where dan's going
with this it's always heading to the name dorkin i did find one fact about the comic book which is
that because they use a time traveling phone booth which people might think is a bit a bit of a rip
off from dr who they use the comic book to explain that actually um due to the way time travel works
dr who ripped off bill and ted despite having started in 1960 something that's a brilliant way
to get around the patents problem we had earlier i live the episode absolutely yeah but dr who is
also a time traveler and i would say a more adept time traveler than bill and ted though i haven't
seen it but he is very good at it so i would imagine he can always have claimed to have gone
back he's been to the beginning of the universe yes you know one place that dr who's never been
because he's an alien shat on earth the pap yes i want to see the episode of dr who where he lands
in shat on earth the pap and gets immediately arrested i wrote a such an endearing interview
with um kyana reeves which actually just came out recently but was an interview that he did
in 1987 which is when they were making bill and ted but i think no one knew who he was then
and then the film got delayed so the interview was never released at the time and uh it was for
the rap and he admitted that he wasn't a good actor in fact in it he said uh so i think the
interviewer who was steve steve pond asked him how long have you been acting and kyana reeves said
i don't really know if i'm acting now i'm pretty bad i mean i hate acting most of the time i do
it it's a god awful job just on old awesome movies um this isn't to do with bill and ted um
but our friend are you just using the word awesome as a connectively kind of is but you'll
see where i'm going because they kind of in the same um in the same genre ish so um our friend
justin gayner sent me an article which i'd missed from the guardian which a few people will have seen
about cool runnings then you obviously see this article it's absolutely brilliant it was an interview
with a few people including john turtletown who was the director and he gave some bits of trivia
about cool runnings which are amazing so it was translated around the world and in norway it was
translated as cold buttocks cool runnings and he said that after cool runnings he got sent
lots of similar kind of screenplays about sports uh and they were all kind of almost identical
and he said it got so bad that at one point i received a script called amanda without reading
a word i picked up the phone and said to my agent what kind of animal is it and what's wrong with
the kid there was a long pause before the reply came it's a horse and a brain tube okay that's it
that's all of our facts thank you so much for listening if you would like to get in contact
with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast we can be found
on our twitter accounts i'm on at shriverland andy at andrew hunter m james at james harkin
and anna you can email podcast at qi.com yep you can go to our group account which is at no such
thing or our website no such thing as a fish dot com all of our previous episodes are up there
links to bits of merchandise um and yeah that's it we'll be back again next week guys we hope
you're doing well we'll see you then goodbye