(phone rings)
(speaking in foreign language)
(playful music)
- Hi.
- Hi Andy.
Why are we here?
- What is this?
- We're not supposed to be recording right now.
- No, this is a special extraordinary session
of drop us a line.
- That's somewhere to be.
- I have nowhere.
- We're gonna go for like half an hour,
one hour tops, James.
No, this is short.
This is a little bonus extra episode of drop us a line.
- Hello, it's whoever I'm watching.
It's just going out to people on Patreon.
I don't need to say get a Patreon, do I?
You're already here.
- You're on it.
- Hello.
- Stay where you are.
- Don't move.
We did an episode a couple of weeks ago with Olga Koch
and you mentioned a fact, James,
about a boy called Colin Wallace.
- Colin Wallace, yeah.
He was the guy who kind of came up with the technology
behind the original Grub Hub.
Yeah, he sold his company and it got sold
and sold and sold and that became Grub Hub.
But the interesting thing about him was he first came up
with the idea when he was sat in a class at college
or school or something and he wanted a sandwich
and didn't know how to get a sandwich.
- And basically, as our podcast is no longer really
just about facts, but largely about turning things
into movies and pitching them to the wider mass.
- What business ideas?
- Our business ideas.
Yeah, we pitched some film ideas off the back of it
and we came up with some pretty good titles, I think.
- De-Bredtion.
- Not sure, yeah.
But it wasn't a detention wasn't he?
- No, no.
- But he was at school and you have detentions in schools.
- Exactly.
- And I think we ended up with something to do with Do.
- Do boys.
- Which I would be astonished if anyone managed to write him
with something better than Do by.
- Right, welcome to the next half an hour of your life.
(laughing)
We've had so much correspondence about this.
We normally would just do this in droppers of line
but it would be a whole episode of droppers of line.
So we thought let's just launch the boil now.
- So should we get into it?
- Yeah, so these are all the suggestions
for a better title.
- Exactly.
- And you say whether you think they're better or worse.
- Okay.
- We're the movie execs.
- Yeah, okay.
- And there's a young picture.
Louis Furry in Saskatoon.
- No, I don't think that works at all.
(laughing)
It's nothing to do with colour models, nothing to do with drop-up,
nothing to do with schools.
- Says the movie should be called "Sand Rich".
- Yes, that is good.
- "Sand Rich".
- That is good.
- If he was called Richard, that would have been good.
- That would be perfect.
- But it doesn't quite work for me.
- We can change the character's name.
That's fine.
- Is that a historical person's name?
- No, I don't mind him.
- He's gonna be Richard Shopsan,
which is, I think, I think that's--
- Put it in "The Maybe Fire".
- Yeah, okay, I'm gonna say it maybe.
That's the leader at the moment, I would say.
Christian Bereman, I just listened to the latest episode.
I really enjoyed it.
How about "The Rise of an Idea" brackets as in "Rybred"
as the name for your Grubhub founder movie?
- "Rybred" is a good idea.
Again, I think in "The Maybe Fire".
- In "The Maybe", 'cause "Bred" rises anyway,
so that was in its own right.
- I just think it's not very catchy in and of itself,
even not taken into account how bad the pun is.
- I know.
- Can't name a big movie that has a word "Rybred" in it.
- I don't know any.
- How's "The Rising Sun"?
If it was a song we were writing, he's in.
- "The Rise of Skywalker", is that one?
- Yes.
- But again, there's no "Bred" in it at all.
I'm gonna put it just below "Sand Rich".
- Okay.
- "Dean Blackwell" says,
"Sub-stitute student".
Obviously, substitute teacher makes more sense,
but you didn't say he was a child.
- You don't do you get "Sub-stitute students"?
- No, I don't think so.
- I'm sorry, Dean, that's in the no pile.
- I'm afraid, yeah.
- I'm starting a new pile and it's a no.
- I'm the honest.
When I first said, "Into the Maybe Pile",
my idea was to put them all in the "Maybe Pile",
but I'm afraid.
Actually.
- Okay.
Well, let's see if we get a third pile.
I'm optimistic that we get a "S" pile,
'cause Bronwyn Edwards says,
"No one to my astonishment suggested "Bredication".
- Yes.
- That is good.
- Yeah.
- "Bredication".
- "Bredication" is good.
It's sort of, if you were at a school about "Bred",
that would work.
- That's good.
- It's coming in the "Maybe Pile".
- Can I tell you the big problem of this?
- Yeah.
- Imagine the poster, right?
"Bredication".
How do you spell "Bred"?
- A good point.
- There's a rogue "A" isn't there?
- Yeah.
- It's not gonna work.
- She's left in the "A" in brackets.
- "Bredication".
- "Bred".
- Okay.
Well, you're not gonna like Matt Jarvis
from California Suggestion of "Class Bredsident".
- I mean, that's a firm "Yes".
- "Class Bredsident".
- "Bredsident".
- Love it.
- Okay.
- "You and Bully, Grub Club".
You're welcome.
He says, "Bit presumptuously, you and...
- Uh-huh.
- But I like it.
- Grub Club.
All right.
I'll put it in the maybe poll.
Caleb M.
Delivery Boy.
- Delivery Boy.
- I've got a guy oversold the...
- The guy oversold the...
- The guy oversold that.
- There is no pun in this case.
- Yeah, but Delivery Boy.
- Delivery.
- Sure.
But you've only taken one half of the story.
Like Delivery Boy, that's what he was.
- I guess he was 'cause he was a boy at the time.
I think he may have been in like engineering college
or something.
I don't know how...
I've imagined him as a nine-year-old.
We could age the character today.
- There are many things.
- That's fine.
- Gary Longhurst says, "You could call the movie Roll Call.
As it's about a child at school making an app.
So you can call to get food and a roll is a food sandwich.
And Roll Call is like taking the register at the beginning of the class."
- Yeah.
- So it seems to work on a couple of levels.
- I actually like the title, but didn't like the subtitle that you added at the end of it.
- Yeah.
- But you explained the title.
I don't think that's gonna work.
- You've lost them.
- The gig.
- Very Gary.
- With your delivery.
- I'm so sorry.
I'm normally much better at pitching than that.
God damn it.
Okay.
Roll Call is out.
- Oh cool.
Not bad.
- LA Brat I'm putting it in the maybe pile.
LA Branton.
The breadwinner.
- Hmm.
- Okay.
- Yep.
- It's good.
- It doesn't give us anything about the school days.
Does it?
- No.
You're right.
- It kind of misses out that quite important element.
- That's good point.
- And that's why it's going in the.
- Maybe pile.
- Mike Meyer.
- We don't need no regification.
(laughing)
- We do dust in.
- Oh come on.
- We do.
- I think that's good.
- It's good.
- That is good.
- We could take two of them and do in brackets.
We don't need no.
- Yeah.
- And then for education.
Again, it has the A problem.
- It does, it does.
- Yeah.
- James Darcy says.
The faxist sandwich on the net.
Sorry, I've had four beers.
- Oh.
- The faxist fact.
- Like fastest.
- Yeah, faxist.
- What's the, sorry?
- I need four beers to understand this.
- Do the spelling of it?
- fax, fax.
- Yeah.
- ESD.
- Oh, he did use fax machine.
- He used the fax machine.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Ah, okay.
- Why did you think that was in there?
(laughing)
- Because of the beers?
- I just thought if I said it confidently enough,
someone else would work out.
- Okay, so let's hear it.
The faxist.
- Your main job here, Andy, is to be an intermediary
between the ideas and coming to the executives.
You can't just read anything out without understanding it.
- This is great.
Oh, God.
For those of you who haven't seen this before,
I cry at every episode of Drops of the Like
'cause of these two clowns.
Oh, my God.
- Again, a bit angry with this meeting now.
- Okay, Rebecca Hutchins.
- Seed EO.
- Seed EO, but with Seed.
- Yeah, again, nothing about the schools in there.
- Luke Alexander says, this is just a casting note.
I'm thinking Timothy Chalamet as Colin Wallace
and Andy Circus is the sandwich.
I think that's good.
- That's not bad, yeah.
- Yeah, that's not bad.
- Okay, that works.
- Matt Swazo points out it's a boyopic.
- Yeah, sure.
- Okay.
- All right, these are all just extra words for the poster.
- Yeah, we've got to fetch this out.
We've got a lot of--
- Class president.
A boyopic.
(laughing)
Martin Newton suggests, okay, I'm just going to read it out
as it is, no pain, no gain, but pain is obviously
but like, par.
- Oh, like chocolate.
- No pan, no gan.
- That's the problem.
I'm so sorry.
No pan, no gan.
Well, I like it.
I'm putting it in the maybe pile.
- No.
- I think we've created a new meaning
of the word maybe in this show.
- Martin, we'll call you.
- Too much.
- God.
- Okay.
- Gareth Taylor, I think this is a contender.
Says honor roll.
- Honor, as in H-O-N-O-U-R.
- Okay.
- And that's an American school thing, right?
- Right.
- The honor roll.
- You've made it to the honor roll.
- And also it sounds like being honor roll.
As in things are improving, I'm honor roll.
- I think that's a finalist.
- Okay.
- Right, here's the final one.
- Catherine Radmer.
- Okay, have you saved the best to last?
- See for yourself.
- Says, I think it's not the worst to last.
- Okay.
- Catherine Radmer says, "Obviously, the Earl of Sandwich."
- Is he?
- He's not called Earl.
- Well, if he was called Earl, it would be a perfect
movie type of.
- The Earl of Sandwich.
- There's no called Rich either, as in the Sand Rich.
- No, no, but you get Rich.
- Okay, what about the Earl of Sand Rich?
- Too much.
- Where's the Earl?
I don't know where that's trying to
bung its way in here.
- Just he's become the King of the Sandwich world.
- I see.
- The Earl of Sandwich.
It's just not very American term.
Sorry, Catherine.
- Okay.
- I'm gonna tell you the three I've ticked.
- And there are only two of them.
(laughing)
- Where we got, it's down to our finalists.
Matt Jarvis from California with class-bredsident.
- It's stunning.
- And Gareth Taylor with honor roll.
- Yeah.
- There's no pun, no gun.
- Do you want no pun, no Gareth?
- It's certainly the tagline on the poster.
- I think for me, it has to be Dolby.
- The one Olga came up with before we started this whole
mad exercise.
- She's very good.
- She's good at what she does.
- I think all a roll for me.
- I don't know.
- I think that's really good.
I think it's really clever.
It's schoolly, but it's bread-y.
And that is the sweet spot.
And it's an existing thing all in one.
- Yeah.
- Okay, who was that?
- That was Gareth Taylor.
- And Gareth, you win what, two tickets to the premiere?
- Absolutely.
(laughing)
- And 40% of the grog's box of it receipts.
- Great.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Thank you so much for playing everybody,
especially you too.
- Thank you for your patience.
- And thank you to everyone.
You said it in these amazing suggestions.
- They're wonderful.
- Loved it.
- Thank you.
- We do this all the time.
We do it fortnightly, but longer.
It's called Drop as a Line.
If you join ClubVish, you'll be exposed to more of this stuff.
(laughing)
But for now, that's everything.
- I've got somewhere to be.
- Bye.
- I have no way to go.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]