(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
Anna Tyshinski and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
- My fact is that the man who invented
the underwater ejector seat once broke his tailbone
in six places while testing the system on the ground
rather than in the water.
- What an idiot.
- This was a bike called John Rawlins.
- Yeah.
- It was very eminent.
Well, I didn't know about him.
I was at a comedy gig a few weeks ago
and the comedians started talking to the guy next to me
in the audience.
And this guy started talking about
how he was either reading about or related to
the man who invented the underwater ejector seat.
And the comedian just made hay with it.
- Did he?
- Still a whale of a time.
- Had he been speaking to you previously?
- He said, he said, anything's better than that guy.
And he just, yeah, yeah, they spoke phrases actually.
- That's so amazing.
Wow.
- What a heckle.
- He just mentioned Sir John Rawlins.
I thought underwater ejector seat, I've never heard of that.
- No, I don't think of that as something
that has been invented, in fact.
- Right.
- Sir John Rawlins.
- You would be gutted, actually, Anna,
if you invented the underwater ejector seat,
which you would reasonably assume hasn't been invented yet.
- Yeah.
- You wanted to find out about this.
- I've drawn up a lot of patents.
I was about to apply.
This is devastating.
- But it's for, it is for planes.
But it's for underwater planes.
- Yeah.
- So.
- Well, no, no, no.
It's for planes that have crashed and gone underwater.
- Yeah.
- Underwater planes.
- Sorry.
- Yes, yes.
- So it basically, it works.
If a pilot is unconscious and the plane is sinking,
it'll pop out the pilot without the pilot
needing to do anything.
So that's very clever.
- Why not pop him out prior to hitting the water
and sinking, like I would argue an ejector seat
is built to do.
- I suppose the plane is thinking,
maybe he's, maybe he's all right.
- The plane is thinking, yeah, maybe he's still,
he or she will pull this round
and then the plane is into the water
and the plane realizes, I better step in.
- Okay.
I think it's usually the pilot
that presses the ejector seat button or pulls the lever.
I'm not sure the sentient plane has been invented yet.
- In this case, in this case, it's automatic.
- Yes, once it hits water.
But I think what happens is often,
if you're trying to land your plane,
you want to land it rather than eject
'cause then you can save the plane.
You can land planes on water as we've seen,
slowly landed there on the Hudson.
Maybe you try and do it,
but then you don't get it quite right
and you start sinking.
- Okay.
- Also, it's dangerous to eject
when you're too close to the ground anyway.
Like if you look at the survival rates of ejection
under a certain altitude, it's a lot lower.
So, you know, if you're too close to the water,
if you're just coming into land, you get into trouble.
- But they are amazing because, okay,
let's say you were parachuting out of a regular plane
and it was too low altitude.
The parachute wouldn't be able to get the grip
and so you would plummet and die.
But ejector seats are actually designed
so that you can eject from a plane
while it's on the ground and survive.
Yes, the rates are low.
- I didn't know that you could do that.
- Absolutely, yeah, yeah.
- I got a little working on what can propel you up high enough.
- It propels you up high enough and the parachute works.
And that's what they're designed to do.
- There are some, like not all of them do that, I think.
- No.
- But they do that.
- Yeah, you can.
And you actually, and this was available in the '80s.
I'm sure we'll get on to Rollins in a minute.
But this was in the '80s, there was a Soviet pilot
and he was flying down and his plane had rolled
and so the cockpit was now facing towards the ground.
And he was only a few feet from the ground.
Like he was like, I don't know how many,
but it was like, let's say less,
definitely less than 50 feet away from the ground.
But he's facing downwards, right?
- He didn't, yeah.
- You pressed the ejector seat,
fired him towards the ground.
Everyone thought he's a goner, obviously.
- Yeah.
- Like almost in a cartoon way.
- Did they go and look at the 20 feet deep hole
that had been drilled into the ground by his head?
- Can we guess?
- Yeah, go on.
- Marshmallow factory.
It's always a moth factory.
- Yeah, or a mattress factory.
- Yeah, exactly.
Just a bit further.
Just got to get directly over the old pillow mountain.
- Oh no, that's the broken glass factory.
- No, they had like an auto gyroscope system in their seat.
So as it pushed you out, it knew which way was up
and then it could fire rocket boosters,
which took him in the right direction
away from the ground.
And the amazing thing was that no one knew about this.
It was Soviet technology
and the Americans didn't know about it
and Europeans didn't know about it.
And it was live on television or shown on television.
So everyone thought he was dead.
And then suddenly when he survived,
everyone was like, holy shit, how did that happen?
- Yeah, that's amazing.
- They thought he was dead when he ejected,
but then they saw him spin around
and go back up in the end.
- I think they thought he was dead.
Everyone's eyes kind of followed the wreckage
and then they turned back and he was, ta-da.
- Yeah.
- What a trick.
- So cool.
- That was amazing.
- Quickly back on the original character in this,
John Rawlins.
So Sir John Rawlins, amazing character.
- Sir John Stuart, Peeps Rawlins.
- Peeps Rawlins because he was a descendant of Pete.
- Yeah.
- Pretty cool.
- Direct descendant.
- Apparently I couldn't find the family tree,
but his father was also hugely decorated
as a military person.
He comes from huge stock
and he designed the first protected helmets
using composite materials.
- He advised the British Standards Institute
on how to make motorcycle helmets, cycling helmets,
horse riding helmets, racing helmets.
So a lot of the helmets we wear today,
very, very slightly, thanks to some of his research.
- That's cool, so cool, isn't it?
- This is interesting about Rawlins
'cause I have often wondered before,
why are all these helmets different?
You know, horse riding and cycling,
it's gonna be very similar if you fall off head first.
Bet the same helmet will do it,
but do you think John just wanted to make us an extra buck
by- - It just looks so stupid.
- Diversifying.
- Wearing a bike helmet on a horse.
- Well, one of my second helmets looks
a lot like a horse helmet, doesn't it?
You know that orange one that I wear?
- It does, it does.
- I don't look stupid, Andy, do I?
- No, no, no, no.
(laughing)
I was trying to read more about the underwater ejector.
- Oh, sorry, I'll be saying ejection seat.
I think this is like a detectorist's thing.
- Yes, right.
- We'll get lots of letters saying it's an ejection seat.
I've seen lots of people saying ejection seat.
- I saw a few things online saying ejection, but yeah.
- I'm gonna keep saying it.
And then if you wanna contact James individually
for saying ejector, we'll just duke it out.
- I'm going off the James Bond name.
He would call it an ejector seat, wouldn't he?
- Yeah, absolutely would.
But that's Bond for you.
- It's such a never- - It's such a never-
- But I was reading about someone who ejected
in 1954, which was just before Rawlins invented
the underwater ejection seat.
- Yeah.
- And it was off an aircraft carrier,
a British aircraft carrier, right?
And their plane was a thing called the Westland Wyvern,
right?
You know, Wyvern is a mythical dragon-y creature.
Get this, it had folding wings.
There are these pictures of all the planes
on the aircraft carrier, and their wings,
just halfway across, just fold up like elbows.
- Okay.
- Like a table tennis table.
- Exactly, exactly like that.
- So they like to fly through some mountain-close mountains.
- That's exactly what it's for, right?
- That's it, yeah, yeah.
- Everyone breathe in, we're going through two mountains.
- No, it's a stash them on the decks of aircraft carriers.
You can store five planes where you could only store two
if they had their wings out.
But honestly, I've never seen it before.
The wings literally halfway along, they just fold up.
- Like a butterfly.
- Amazing.
- Or a finger.
In fact, they had two joints.
(laughing)
They had two joints in them, so it is exactly like a finger.
Because if you crook your finger in that creepy way,
that's what the wings do.
- Oh yeah, all right, well they should have done it.
- They could have closed your finger.
- Why didn't they do like a butterfly?
That would take up much less space.
- Yeah, you could have folded it right up.
- Do it at the shoulder.
Yeah, not the elbow, you idiots.
(laughing)
So I thought that the only underwater ejection seats
were ejection seats that were used underwater
having not been intended for it,
because that does seem to happen.
And I was reading a blog of a guy called Russ Pearson,
who, did you read about him?
- Russ is 1969, and he ejected in the Pacific
off the coast of California from an ejecto seat underwater.
So he'd crash landed.
I mean, it sounds like he definitely said,
I thought I was definitely gonna die,
'cause obviously I was 20 feet underwater.
I was sinking incredibly fast.
I just pressed a button and hoped for the best.
It broke his back at the time,
but I think he was too panicked to notice
while he was underwater.
And somehow, I think there was a boat suddenly
which turned a light on in the distance,
which told him where the surface was.
So he managed to swim up to the surface.
But he said the worst thing about ejecting underwater
in an ejecto seat is what do you have to have on you
that automatically is applied
when you eject from a plane in the air?
- Oxygen?
- Actually, oxygen is one thing.
- Lip balm.
- Like, what's applied to you?
- I haven't phrased this very well,
and I can understand the errors,
but I'm talking about a parachute.
- Oh, yeah.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- So it ejects you with a parachute.
He made it up to the surface,
but then the parachute just pulled him down and down again.
- Oh, no.
- And he just up there with a broken back parachute
pulling him down.
And then he said he felt something on his feet
and he thought that's a shark.
And so he tried to find his shark repellent,
which for some reason he was carrying in his pocket.
- He was a Batman from the 1960s.
- But he realized it was just the plane.
And then, yeah, he just about survived.
He managed to be evacuated on a medical plane.
- Pretty cool.
I have a cool thing.
So the first person to use an ejecto seat,
I think in the UK was a guy,
he was an Irish mechanic.
He was called Bernard Lynch.
And he did it in 1945.
And later he did 32 more ejections from planes
to test the stuff.
- Yeah, he was the guinea pig.
- He was the guinea pig.
- The ejecto seat guinea pig.
- Yeah, for the firm Martin Baker,
which is the British firm,
which makes thousands of ejecto seats and does all that.
Anyway, I got to speak to Bernard Lynch's son, Dermot.
I rang him up and we had a cool chat.
- Yeah, and he had some crazy adventures.
So once he landed in a field right
when he was testing an ejecto seat.
And then he just sort of left his parachute behind.
I think he tied it to a tree or something.
- Yeah.
- And he just went to the pub.
- Like a dog poo.
- Yeah, huge huge dog poo.
- I'm coming back to pick it up, okay?
Don't get dressed up.
- He just went to the pub.
And then the team turned up, obviously,
'cause they track broadly where you're going
and they're looking for it.
And so the team from the company arrived at the field,
thought, oh no, Bernard's, he's died somehow.
- He was evaporated.
- The tree ate him.
- They phoned his wife, they told him he was dead.
And then they found him in the pub.
- Straight away?
- That was premature.
- Before they found the bunny or anything.
They were just like, oh, I'm really sure.
He tied up his parachutes and then he died.
- Actually, I've got to say,
when you were 10 minutes late today, James,
they did call Paulina on that.
So you'll want to reassure her.
- Such a good point.
- Yeah, two hours later,
they found him in the parking lot.
- Two hours later.
- Wow.
- He was a legend and he subjected his body
to so much volunteering to do this.
'Cause he used to, before he had himself
fired out of actual planes,
they erected what sounds to me like one of those things
that are fairground where you're sitting
on a big, long bench and it lifts all the way up a pole.
And then it drops you really hard, do you know what I mean?
- Yeah, those fairground ones.
- I think he was like on a reverse version of that.
So he would sit--
- So he was on the pole.
- He was reverse polling.
No, he was on something that would look the same,
but it shoots you up incredibly fast.
So it was like a bench attached to a pole.
- It was more like, if we're talking fairground things,
it was more like the strongman kind of where you,
you slam the hammer out and you send the weight.
- He's sitting on the weight.
- That's brilliant.
- Yeah, he's bringing love to the top.
- He was only six inches tall, wasn't he?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- This worked.
But he used to just do that until it got too painful.
So they do it more and more with more and more force.
'Cause you need maximum force for an ejection seat
to get people out of harm's way.
And as soon as it got to such an agonizing level
that he was like, I don't think we can do this to pilots.
He'd say, that's max force.
Next up.
- He was very tough.
He did one thing, he refused to eject over water.
- Okay.
- He just wouldn't do it.
He just wouldn't do it.
And none of the experiments was he willing to--
- Oh, okay.
- No pubs.
- No water.
- What?
- No pubs.
(laughing)
- It was because he'd fallen in sheep dip when he was eight.
And it was a really traumatizing experience.
He might have nearly drowned or something.
- Really?
- He would form a pool of sheep dip.
- What's that?
- It's a chemical solution that you make sheep walk through
to, I think, keep them clean or antiseptic.
- It's quite different than an ocean.
- Yeah.
- So it's quite strange that you would project one
onto the other.
- Yeah.
- I guess it must just be a bit of drowning.
- Sounds more like that thing you go through
when you're going to a swimming pool.
- Yeah, it's like that.
- It is like that.
- Ah, yeah, yeah.
That's it.
Okay, but trauma.
- It was enough to traumatize Bernard, yeah.
- I think that's probably a fair enough request.
- If you're constantly being lobbed out of an ejector seat.
- Martin Baker, did he work for this guy?
- Yeah.
So they have a website, and on the website,
it has a counter that tells you how many lives
they've saved.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, isn't that cool?
Last time I checked, which was when I did this research
yesterday, it was 7,690 lives that they've saved.
- I wonder how soon after the ejector seat saving the life,
they do the counter.
It'd be cool if they did it in real time.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- As in they have some kind of thing in the chairs
that whatever.
- It actually, when you pull the lever
and you rock it out of the thing,
the chair automatically spits out a little form.
And you have to write.
I have had my life saved by this.
- Do you think it ever then goes down again?
'Cause sometimes, you know, you'll think you've saved
the life, and then they'll crash into a thorn bush
or something.
(laughing)
Or we think it's, it's like when a goal's disallowed,
you know, the goal the score goes up.
But they are actually, yeah, VAR says death.
- What if, what if that guy was run over by a car
on the way to the pub with that, with that discount?
- Yeah, yeah, I don't know.
- But they were called James Martin
and Valentine Baker, weren't they?
- Yeah, he was an amazing pilot, Valentine Baker.
He was Amy Johnson's flight instructor.
- Sorry, wait, is Amy Johnson was an aviator
from the 30s?
- Yeah, a sort of classic aviator from the,
God, the Amelia Earhart sort of period.
- She was, was she the first to fly across the Atlantic?
- God, I can't remember now.
- She was the first to do something.
- Fly to Australia?
- Fly to Australia, I think she crash landed on her way,
though I've seen footage of that.
- So Amy Johnson, I think I've been to the town
on the coast in Kent where she disappeared.
- Did she disappear as well?
- Yeah, yeah, I think she was flying,
oh gosh, where is it?
It's near, there was a Turkish restaurant we went to
and I had, I had, - Oh yeah, okay,
I know, that's the Turkish restaurant.
- I didn't remember it 'cause I ordered the Turnip Juice
as my drink for the meal.
- I've heard this story before.
And the waiter said, the waiter said are you sure,
are you sure you want the Turnip Juice?
I said, I'm here, I'm on the North Kent coast,
I want to experience Turkish culture as it was intended to
and it was absolutely tough.
- He didn't like it guys, spoiler, he didn't like it.
- Okay guys, so if you wanna know where this happened,
either Google where Amy Johnson crashed
or just check out Andy's history on TripAdvisor reviews
and you'll see it in there.
- I thank God you weren't asked to do the eulogy
at a funeral.
She was a wonderful person.
Can I quickly just mention yesterday?
- Hurn Bay, Hurn Bay, Hurn Bay, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- My wife once won a load of teddies
on a shooting gallery in Hurn Bay.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- So many good personal anecdotes in Hurn Bay.
- It's a rich place.
- I went there not long ago,
but yeah, but I was only making a connecting train
so I just stayed in the station.
- That's a better story than both lines.
(all laughing)
- I read an article about the ejection club
at the Waterbaker Run and it was,
they called it the only club where you have to be thrown out
to get in.
- Brilliant, that's really good.
- I got an alternative to an ejection seat here.
This is great.
This is a plane, it's an American plane
with the Douglas F3D Sky Night.
- All right.
- Do you have to say it like that?
- Yes, you do.
It was this year's plane and if you had to bail out,
it was a really small cruise, that's two-seater plane.
You're sitting next to each other, okay?
One is the pilot and one is...
- Co-pilot?
- No, genuinely doing something else like radar or something.
- Or getting some drinks.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- He's got a tiny trolley and he offers the pilot chicken
or fish about halfway through the flight.
- Do you want to buy any lottery cards?
We're selling lottery cards as for charity.
If you've got any spare change in the country
you've come from, you can buy these lottery cards.
- Both flying over Cambodia now, what are you doing?
(all laughing)
Yeah, but it's exactly that, you know.
So anyway, there's this plane, the Sky Night,
and if they had to bail out,
the crew didn't have an ejector seat in the plane.
What they had effectively was a slide.
- Oh, okay. - Going down and back.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So you would just have to pop out
between the engines of the plane.
It's, I mean, this sounds incredibly risky.
You did, obviously you'd have a parachute on
when you did that, ideally.
- Yeah, I do always want to, what's the next flavor?
- It sounds risky, but...
(all laughing)
- Are you sure you want to do this?
This looks pretty risky.
No, you're right, let's die instead.
Let's just crash.
- I'll have the chicken!
(all laughing)
- But sometimes they use this plane
to deploy commandos into the jungle.
So you'd have one pilot and one commando in the plane.
And at a certain point,
the commando just pops down the slide.
- Really? - It sounds so cool.
- It sounds amazing.
- Yeah, I think it was. - Did it work?
- I think it was incredibly dangerous.
- It wasn't used for long.
And I think 'cause it was first used in the A3D,
which came to stand for all three dead,
'cause that was three people who would be in the plane.
And I think it took a long time
'cause it was sort of behind the seats,
so you realized you were gonna crash
and then you had to sort of clamber over,
you weren't quite a lot of gear.
- Yeah, it's really cramped, yeah.
- Squeezing one after the other.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- 'Cause even now they say if you lose your phone
behind the seats, you're not allowed to get it yourself.
You have to get the attendant to come
and get your phone for you.
- And that's in case you fall down the chute
when you're trying, so. (laughing)
- It's just the last thing.
If you love ejector seats and they look so cool,
and I spent a lot of hours last night
trying to find the most affordable one,
but on eBay, they go--
- Can you try and eject other?
- They look so cool.
They sell them to just--
- Not going to the hospital, did I?
(laughing)
- Let me tell you an anecdote about Turkish breakfast.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that there is a school in Massachusetts
that has had all of its 7,000 light bulbs permanently on
for over a year and a half now
because no one knows how to turn them off.
(laughing)
So this is a lighting system that was installed
in Minnichalg Regional High School,
which is in Massachusetts.
And the idea was they were thinking,
how can we have a lighting system
that's gonna save us a lot of money?
And they came up with this.
They thought this is gonna save us
hundreds of thousands of dollars over the years.
Unfortunately--
- 'Cause it happened to be very efficiently built.
- Yeah, there were LED light bulbs.
There was, it had dimming qualities on it.
It was a great system that was energy efficient
in a way that usual light bulbs wouldn't be.
And so they decided to go for the system.
And then during the pandemic,
something in the system went faulty and failed,
which meant that the lights weren't dimming.
It meant they weren't going off altogether.
It meant basically that close to 7,000 of these light bulbs
were just remaining on.
Then it was discovered that actually
the hardware that was needed to fix it
wasn't available and they needed to order it from China,
which had a backlog of orders so they couldn't get it over.
So as we speak, it still hasn't been fixed.
They know the problem.
They've ordered the parts.
They're arriving.
I think they have them now,
but they're not putting them in till March.
And so--
- 'Cause they need experts to come and put them in
and they can't get them.
It is so mad.
'Cause it's like taxpayer funded school, obviously.
So every day you have a reminder
of what your taxes are going towards
as you walk past this brightly illuminated school.
- And it's costing thousands a month.
- 'Cause they turn the electricity off,
like as in every night,
when all the kids go away, you just...
(imitates electric sound)
- Yeah, you'd think so, right?
- Maybe, maybe there's health and safety reasons
why you can't do that.
- Feels like there must be something
that they can use that light for.
- Do you know what I mean?
I mean, there must be a use at night.
- Put solar panels in there.
(all laughing)
That's how I actually, all my electricity in my house
is I put solar panels underneath all my lights
and then keep my lights on all the time.
- Yeah, so it's a big problem.
It's costing them possibly tens of thousands of dollars
at this point.
I mean, it certainly has.
And some of the teachers try to fix it
by just taking the light bulbs out themselves.
Yeah, just going around. - Does that work?
- It does, but they only take out three or four
as opposed to the 7,000. - You can't do that every night.
Can you?
It's 7,000 bulbs?
You've got a shot.
- It's further ceiling lights.
You know, the recessed ceiling lights,
they're a complete pain in the ass to get in the screw.
- Yeah, exactly. - It's my two penny worth.
(all laughing)
It's being a bad lighting systems.
Actually, I had a look in the fish inbox,
podcast@qi.com, just to see if anyone
had written in about light bulbs.
Thank you, Paddy McCray, who wrote in quite a while ago now.
I hope you're still listening, Paddy.
This is an incredible fact.
It's about the terminal five at Heathrow, right?
- Oh yeah.
- Which has this beautiful high ceiling.
Like the bulbs are all about 120 feet in the air.
And between 2008 and 2013,
no bulbs were changed in the ceiling
because they didn't have a good way of doing it.
And at that point, about 60% of the bulbs had gone.
And so the reports say that they hired a team
of tightrope walkers because that was the only way.
- No. - That's so funny.
That can't be true. - That's untrue.
- I'm pretty, look, take it up with the Daily Telegraph,
who reported that a Cirque du Soleil style,
high level rope work firm had been engaged
in taking the bulbs. - So funny.
But then they would do some of them
and then some of them would be changed
by someone in a human cannonball.
And they would be fired up.
And then other ones, it would be trapeze guys.
- Pyramid of clowns, just all doing one,
very, very rescue there.
- That's so funny.
- I'm sure no one was in a costume at Heathrow.
- I was in Dubai recently
and there's lots of glass skyscrapers there.
And they're all, the window cleaners are all done by hand.
So they have people who are literally like on ropes
going down all of the highest buildings in the world,
just cleaning them.
- That's a fun job.
I've always thought that would be a fun job actually.
- I'm one of those harnesses.
- They call them rats,
'cause they're rope access technicians.
- The main company that does Burj Khalifa,
which is the highest building,
if you want to get a job there,
they show you like a video nasty
before you are allowed to apply.
And they show you like really awful examples
of people who almost fell and stuff.
And they're like, if you're okay with a video,
then you can have an interview.
- Right, do they show you Mission Impossible 4?
In which Tom Cruise climbs up the Burj Khalifa.
- And there's a sandstorm as well.
- Yeah, he's got some special sticky gloves
and they stop working.
I think he looks behind them
and there's a sandstorm approaching
and they go, whoa, better climb a bit faster.
- Well, isn't he responsible
for making one of these guys have to do extra work?
Because while he was up there,
he graffitied Katie Holmes' name.
Like, I love Katie Holmes.
Yeah, yeah, and they had to go and clean that off.
Yeah, that's great.
- When they first had the electric lights, Edison's ones,
you would have them in a building.
Obviously no one had seen them before.
And so there would be a sign often next to them
warning people not to try and light the light bulb
with a match.
- Wow, that's brilliant.
- I've seen one of these signs.
It says, this room is equipped with Edison electric light.
Do not attempt to light with match.
Simply turn key on wall by door.
The use of electricity for lighting
is in no way harmful to health,
nor does it affect the soundness of sleep.
- It does affect.
If you leave the lights on all night,
you're gonna have your sleep affected.
That's just a lie.
- It was a lie.
They didn't know at the time.
They didn't know any better.
- They didn't, lights on all night, insomnia.
- I didn't know why you had to have a light bulb.
Like, why you needed the glass, basically.
- Go on.
- Well, it's because it'll react with the oxygen,
the filament.
- To make a vacuum, right?
- So if you have an incandescent bulb,
this is the old, the good old fashioned, you know,
pre-EU.
- Oh good.
- Okay.
- Oh good, you're one of those.
- It's the one where you've got the bulb,
the tiny bit of wire,
and then you run it through the wire and that grows.
It's because the filament would react with oxygen
immediately and then burnouts really fast.
And if you, as James says, create a vacuum,
or fill it with an inert gas,
then it lasts longer.
But I just, I didn't know actually why.
I had this moment yesterday,
where it's kind of an anti-light bulb moment,
where I was thinking,
wait, hang on, why don't we just not have the bulb, right?
- Save our glass.
- I saved so much glass.
- And, yeah.
- What would the safety be outside of that,
in terms of if you went and touched it,
rather than burning it in half?
- But you wouldn't electrocute yourself, or?
- Yeah, and there's an electric current flowing through it.
- It's a small current, I think,
but you would burn yourself, it's so hot.
- The heat is so cool.
The level of heat that you have in your own room,
again, if you're using an incandescent bulb,
which you shouldn't be,
'cause obviously they're not as efficient,
but that filament gets to 2,200 degrees centigrade.
- Isn't it so weird to think
you're sitting in your sitting room,
just biding your time,
and there's something over there, which is that hot.
And also the filament is so long,
when you look inside an old bulb, it's two meters long.
- Really? - It's just really,
really thin, 0.2 millimeters thick.
This is an old tungsten filament.
- In Babylon, ancient Babylon.
- Yeah, yeah.
- If you wanted to buy enough oil
to light your front room with an oil lamp,
you would have to work for 41 hours
to burn for an hour.
- Oh, I see. - Okay, so 41 hours work,
you'd be able to buy enough oil
to make your light bulb for one hour.
- Okay, that is rubbish.
- In 1992, in America,
you could get the same amount of light
by working for less than one second.
- Wow.
- Imagine being a dad in ancient Babylon,
getting your family to go around turning off the light.
- That has taken 40 hours of work.
I've worked all week for one hour.
I come back into the room, no one's in the room.
(laughing)
- So we've never mentioned, actually,
the longest burning light bulb in the world,
which is kind of incredible,
the Livermore Centennial light bulb.
It's been burning non-stop brackets
with a couple of caveats, closed brackets, since 1901.
And I think one of the keys to a success is that it's four watts.
But it has to be on 24 hours a day
'cause it's in a fire station,
so it's to provide a bit of illumination for fire engines.
And Guinness says there's been one break in its operation
when it was taken from one station to another in the '70s.
And on that occasion, it had, apparently,
it says on its own website,
"A full police and fire truck escort to take it to its site."
- It's just the fire truck taking it to another place.
- I don't, you can't call that an escort
if you're bringing your own thing.
- Escort implied to me there was another fire truck
running alongside it,
kind of stopping anyone else from getting here,
like a bodyguard.
- I'm more, for the longest light bulb in the world,
I'm more interested in the fourth longest
lasting light bulb in the world.
Because it was, so this is a light bulb
that is in New York City, it's not there anymore.
But at the time, it was outside a place
called the Gasnik Supply, which was a hardware store.
And the owner, Jack Gasnik,
he was the guy who was trying to get it acknowledged
to be older than all of the other light bulbs.
But to the point of like, he was furious.
He was like, "There's no way that the Livermore light bulb
is an actual genuine light bulb."
He wrote to Dear Abby,
which was like one of those agony aunt things,
saying, "What do I do?
I've got a light bulb that's lasted longer."
- That must have been a nice day for Abby.
- Yeah.
- He's normally writing about people having affairs.
- He's like, "Oh, finally, a light bulb."
- Yeah.
And he wrote to Guinness saying,
"This is insane that you've given this record.
It's clearly a fake light bulb.
My light bulb."
- A fake light bulb?
- He's like a cardboard cashier.
- He thinks something was going on.
So he said that the bulb is not dark enough
to have burned consistently.
So he said, "Right away, I saw it was so clear.
It does not show any sign of carbonization.
A bulb that has burned 20, 30, 40 years
would be extremely dark from the carbon.
Two, the bulb is a brass-term knob socket.
You can't have a bulb burn continuously
in a brass-term knob socket.
- I strongly disagree.
- It would get so hot, it would burn the wires.
Yeah, so there was a big challenge
and no one accepted it.
- When you said this one isn't there anymore in New York,
has it gone off or is it, do we know what's happened to it?
- The whole of that block,
the half block was sort of taken down to the ground.
So as far as we know--
- By the sky in a rage.
- No, by Livermore and it's Mafia.
- There was a huge fire.
- You know when you try and build a new house
and they say, oh, sorry, there's some really,
like, there's some lizards here
that are going extinct or something.
It does feel like you shouldn't be able to knock down
a house that has the four-foldest light bulb in it.
- Yeah, absolutely, absolutely.
- Conservation.
- There is an older one in the UK, an older light bulb,
then the Livermore one, yeah.
- Is there?
- Yeah, but it just hasn't been on all the time.
- Oh, right.
- So this tragic person's just kept to use light bulb.
- Pretty much, yeah.
It's called the Ediswan light bulb.
It was first turned on in 1883 in Haitian in England
and it's owned by someone called Beth Crook,
or at least it was when I read this article.
But yeah, they don't really turn it on very often.
- I think that's sensible.
- Yeah, makes sense.
- I think they have special occasions.
- Well, some people think that the Livermore one
has lasted so long because it's never turned off.
Because when you turn something off,
sometimes it's like a surge of electricity
and stuff that can damage the filament.
Whereas this has always had four watts just--
- I did that with my computer.
- Yeah.
- If I turn it off, I think horrible things will happen.
So I just keep flogging it on for a few more years.
- I do the same with my car engine.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is Anna.
- My fact is that in 1955,
one person secretly bought almost all the onions in America.
(laughing)
This is a guy called Vince Kosuga
and he was an onion farmer in the 1930s.
And he thought, "I wanna take this bigger."
And so he decided to corner the entire onion market
of America by buying all of the onions.
And so then you've cornered the market,
you've got all the onions
so you can absolutely control the price of onions.
But the thing I find so incredible about this
is that in order to stop word spreading,
'cause as soon as word spreads that he's doing this,
then people selling him onions are gonna go,
"I'm gonna charge away more for these onions then."
It's not word spreading,
he would have had to do it completely in secret
and make sure none of the onion sellers
are talking to each other,
going, "Did that guy have Vince come through last?"
- So he would just go in with a different moustache
and a hat and stuff.
- I think so.
(laughing)
- So what he especially bought, he bought onions, yes,
but he also bought onions before they existed.
- Potential onions.
- Yeah, potential onions.
He bought onion futures.
- Conceptual onions.
The basic idea is you buy the right to buy
the future onions for an agreed price,
you say I'll buy 10 tons of onions from you next year
for a pound of kilo or whatever,
and then you have to do that.
- You're betting that the price will go up in that time
and you've already made the agreement
so you'll make the difference.
- And you could also be screwed though,
you'd have to still stick to that price
even if they were worth less at the time,
but if you bought all the onions,
- You can charge whatever price you want.
- Well, but then the weird trick he did was,
as well as cornering the onion market,
he didn't stop there, so he bought all the onions
and then he said to people who wanted to distribute onions,
you're gonna have to buy them off me for a huge price
'cause I'm the only one with them.
So they did that, he made shed loads of money there
and then he thought, sort it,
I'm gonna screw these guys over and flood the market anyway.
So then, stage two, he went to Chicago
with all the onions left over in his warehouse,
just lorry load after lorry load, dump them,
it sounds like just on the streets in giant sacks.
So flooding the market with onions,
plummeting the onion price down.
- Must have been like, onion Christmas.
Everyone just walks outside
and there's just onions everywhere.
- It's quite a shit Christmas actually, I think, isn't it?
Stocking filled with onions.
Yeah, the reason he did that
is 'cause he was betting on onion futures.
So he knew he was gonna do this,
so he bet that the price would go down.
- So he made eight and a half million at the time,
money at the time,
and for the first initial selling back to the farmer.
So he was kind of quits in anyway, right?
- Yeah, if you think about it,
you've done this brilliant scheme of buying all the onions.
You've made a ton of money,
but then you're left with all these onions, right?
- What are you gonna do?
- You need to get rid of the onions somehow,
but also make money out of them.
You could sell them at the normal price,
or you could do this betting
against the price going down thing.
- The betting thing was very clever, yeah.
- How amazing that he pulled it off just by the way.
This guy went around America
and managed to successfully collect every single,
virtually every single onion.
I mean, he was brought into Congress
because the farmers, once this scheme was discovered,
and particularly the second bit that you were mentioning, Anna,
about how he screwed them over,
they said to their congressman,
"You can't have someone doing this."
This is, we've always said this is gonna be the problem
with future trading and so on.
He's monopolized the market, this can't happen.
So it wasn't illegal though,
but he was brought into Congress,
and his lawyer said,
"Make sure you just don't lie about anything."
And they said, "We understand you own 97%
"of the onions in the United States."
And he said, "That's incorrect, 98%."
Like he was missing 2% of onions in the States.
- So onions are really good.
They keep for a really long time.
If you keep them dark and dry,
they keep for months and months and months on end
without going off.
But some of them did start to go off
because he had lots and lots of onions
in the oldies' warehouses.
And then supposedly,
Kasuga, he had the onions reconditioned
to clean them up a bit, repackage them.
- Set the few layers off and it'll be like,
"Yeah, peel off the mold on the outside."
- And then they were sent back into all the warehouses
in Chicago where they'd been stored in the first place.
But that was assumed to be even more onions
coming into the city.
We didn't realize those were the same ones as before.
People were like, "Oh my God, there are even more onions!"
And the prices really collapsed then.
And this onion mess that happened in Chicago,
it sounds absolutely bananas.
Orphans were receiving free onions in the streets.
The Chicago River was just taking load after load
of onions that were being chucked into it.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- The fish.
- Like breath.
- Just years after.
- They were like, "Fence, why are you crying?
You've just made millions of dollars."
- I'm a bit confused about why they were starting
to be handed out to everyone.
The price was nothing.
- But who's handing it out at this point?
Is it Vince?
- Well, let's say you run an orphanage
and you want to feed your orphans.
You're going to feed them with the thing
that costs 10p for a million.
- Got it, okay.
- Well, it is free in a sack that's been dumped
on your, not great fun for the orphans actually,
'cause once you've had 17 meals of just onion,
then it gets old.
- It's very versatile.
- Yeah.
- I think onions are one of those base foods.
- Who was it who said this about British cuisine?
I think it was Athena, actually,
Athena Kaplenu, our friend.
And she said that basically every English dish
begins with an English person cutting up an onion,
putting it in a pan with some oil,
and then we just decide what to do after that.
- Yeah, that's very true, yeah.
- You can't leave it on its own, though, can you?
It is very much a base, you know?
You've got to toss something else in.
- Onions soup.
- That's, yeah, yeah.
They're the closest.
- Onion soup is probably the closest
to a natural onion.
- Yeah, and really that's 90% cheese.
- In 1958, President Eisenhower signed
the Onion Futures Act that meant
that this could never happen again.
And it bans anyone from trading in onion futures, basically,
in the United States.
But the Onion Futures Act also bans people
from betting on the receipts of motion picture box office.
- Oh, why?
- So, according to the Onion Futures Act,
you're not allowed to trade in onion futures
or motion picture box office receipt futures.
- What the hell?
- So, onions and minions, they're the two areas.
- Brilliant, and that was because in 2010,
the Motion Picture Association of America lobbied
to stop people from being able
to do these futures in motion pictures.
And rather than doing a new act,
they just sort of lobbed it on the end of this onion act.
- I'm slightly confused about the aspect
of motion picture box office receipts,
because it's the idea that, I'll make,
James Cameron doing this by basically saying,
like, I'm gonna buy the rights to all future avatar movies.
And then he makes five avatar movies, flooding the market.
- That's pretty much what's happened.
- He controls all the avatar movies.
So, and then there are so many
that they're being given away for free
to orphans in the streets.
I'm slightly confused about that.
- Yeah, that's why-- - I thought it might be
like a producers thing where you buy them up
and then you make a deliberately shit film.
And then it doesn't get any box office receipts
and you bet against them.
- But there were some tax schemes that did that in the UK.
There were tax schemes investing money in.
Is why there was a rash of particularly bad British comedy
films made? - Well, it was actually
the way that that worked is that you got tax relief
if you invested in a British movie in the same way
that if you gave money to charity, you would.
- Yeah, and that's the avatar thing
that we talked about with Wayne Rooney.
- Oh, yes, yeah. - Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Someone that James and I know from back in the day,
Gareth Edwards, who made Rogue One, the Star Wars movie.
But his first movie that he made was called "Monster."
- That's a great film.
- It's a great film and that was a tax scheme.
That was the company that needed to offset some money
and that's how he was funded to make that movie.
- Well, that's the most entertaining tax scheme
I've ever seen. - Yeah, it was a brilliant movie.
- Brilliant movie, yeah, yeah, absolutely brilliant.
- Nutmeg, what, the Nutmeg monopoly?
Can we talk about that?
- Oh, right, sorry.
- I was looking up other historical monopolies
and the Spice Nutmeg was controlled
by the Dutch for-- - Classic.
- Decades, oh, a long time.
I think they even, that's the thing they traded
Manhattan for, the island of Manhattan.
They said, "No, the British had it."
And then they said, "No, we'll have that."
Sorry, they had it.
And then the British said, "We'd quite like an island."
They said, "Well, we want this random spice island
"in the Pacific from you." - Yeah, yeah.
Bander Island, was that something?
- Exactly, exactly.
The Bander Islands in Indonesia
and the Dutch secured them.
Not actually a bad deal trading Manhattan
for this spice island
because the sheer amount of value they extracted
by controlling, you know, really fiercely the Nutmeg trade
as in, you know, as with all colonial things,
they treated the local people appallingly,
killing people, importing their own farmers, all of this,
like clearing the islands, planting their own trees.
And then they got the monopoly in Nutmeg
and for about 150 years,
they controlled Nutmeg in clothes, pretty much worldwide.
They had almost all the Nutmeg in clothes on the planet.
Right, it's kind of 98% of it.
And if you stole a Nutmeg, they'd come after you,
they'd kill you.
They've ritually burned all their excess Nutmeg every year
in what must have been a lovely smelling.
- Yeah, nice. - Yeah, so nice.
- Christmas time, come on.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And the markup was about 60,000% between source
and street value of Nutmeg.
- Nice, that's a good markup.
- A good amount.
And if you had a small sackful, you were made for life.
- Right. - Basically.
- And this was just the bunch of Dutch people
who got this island basically.
- Yeah, exactly. - This company, great.
And this is before everyone knew it was bloody poisonous,
so you shouldn't owe them anything.
- Isn't it, I see, I have a distant memory of them also
as a result, having a monopoly over a certain type
of drug as a result of Nutmeg being used.
I wanna say MDMA.
They were basically the providers of MDMA
as a result of this.
- I think, well, the monopoly was broken
in the late 18th century, so I don't know.
- Yeah, yeah. (laughing)
- Yeah, no, you read Jane Austen a certain way.
You can tell they are.
- That was what caused the French Revolution, actually.
(laughing)
They're all off their tits.
- Wow.
- Okay, yeah.
- And the man who broke the monopoly,
or one of the men who broke the monopoly
was a Frenchman who called Pierre Poivre,
whose name pleasantly is Peter Pepper.
- Peter Pepper, yeah.
- Very nice. - Good on him.
- And he supposedly, he nicked one of the trees
out of the way that the Dutch hadn't spotted
and made off with it, and then seven years later,
well, he's broken, got nutmeg everywhere.
- What a shame his name wasn't Pierre Nutmeg.
- There is a theory that Peter Piper picked a pack
of pickled peppers as based on him.
- Right, I like that.
- I'm not sure it's true.
- But you can see where the theory came from.
(laughing)
- Just this fact is about sort of someone
controlling a market, they're not being any competition,
and it just reminded me of one of my favorite things.
And I think I learned this
listening to a Wondrium course ages ago, actually,
but in medieval times, the guilds were really, really strong.
So if you're trading produce in a town,
you have to be part of a guild.
This is in medieval England and France,
and not by the European countries.
And if you weren't a member of the guild,
you would not be allowed to sell.
You're carrot or bracelets or whatever.
And only two things I could think of.
But yeah, the guilds were so strict,
so they didn't want any competition
between any of their members.
You forget that capitalism today,
everyone's in competition all the time,
that was just anathema to them.
So they dictated everything you use to make your produce.
So if you're making your carrots,
you have to make them with the tool
that the guild says you have to make it with,
using the exact techniques.
You're not allowed to work
more than a certain number of working hours.
They'll monitor you.
Yeah, everything, machinery, everything.
And then you get to market
and you've done exactly the same as everyone else.
And you absolutely can't advertise,
which means you literally can't draw attention
to yourself at all.
- No.
- And there were guilds would forbid things like sneezing
or nodding at passers-by.
'Cause this was thought to be--
- That must have been tough for the pepper guilds.
(laughing)
- That poor man from the itching powder guild
has to stand ramrod still.
(laughing)
- That's amazing.
- Wow.
- I did not only want to do anything, really.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 1983,
an autograph hunter wrote to Steve Jobs.
Jobs replied saying that he didn't sign autographs,
but he signed that letter and it's sold last year
for half a million dollars.
(laughing)
- That's incredible.
- Did he put the stamp and put it through the post box
and then go, "Oh, damn it."
- I think he was knowing Lee.
It's written very much as if a gag, I would say.
- You may.
- You never know, though, you never know.
- He said, it's written.
He says, "I'm honored you were right,
but I'm afraid I don't sign autographs."
And it was sold at R.R. auctions.
That's the letter R.
I know my accent is a bit weird,
but R.R. auctions.
- So pirate auction signs, man.
(laughing)
- And they suggested that perhaps there was a photograph
or magazine enclosed in the original letter
and that he didn't sign that
as opposed to it being a joke.
But I agree, it does sound kind of like a joke,
doesn't it?
- It does.
I have an alternate theory about Jobs.
So I was reading a book from 1910
called Chats on Autographs by A.M. Broadley.
Just a little shout out to him.
He'll be really grateful for that.
- And he relates in this book,
the story of the Archbishop of York
who wrote back to an autograph hunter saying,
"Sir, I never give my autograph and never will."
And then signed it.
And maybe it was Steve Jobs doing a little tribute
to that.
(laughing)
- To the Archbishop of York.
- One of them, yeah, I don't know which one.
- Wow.
- Yeah, wow.
- Oh my God, and you're the first person ever to get that.
And he's finally can rest in peace.
- Wow.
- He was a huge fan of the Archbishops of Northern England.
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- I've read a few times
where people have tricked others into giving a signature
in almost the Steve Jobs-S kind of thing.
So for example, Lee Harvey Oswald's mother,
one of the ways that she used to make money
after the assassination was that she used to sell
her signature to people.
And got to a point where selling her signature
got her quite a good living if she could do it.
But what people who would interview her would always
trick her, it would be to get her to sign a release form
to the interview that they'd filmed or whatever.
And then that's how they would get their signature.
So yeah, there's all these tricky ways, isn't there,
of getting a celebrity signature if they don't give it.
'Cause if you don't, we've mentioned Steve Martin.
He has a card that he hands.
Jonah Hill does the same thing.
Instead of signing, if you approach Jonah Hill,
he just hands a card saying, "I just met Jonah Hill."
It was a total let down.
And that's just on his little business card.
- There's a famous story of Dennis Lilly,
the Australian fast bowler, Cricketer,
who met the queen and asked for her autograph.
So she was in Melbourne watching some test cricket
and then he sort of queued up and said,
"Can I get your autograph, mate?"
And there's actually a photo of him.
(laughing)
- That's pronounced ma'am.
- Well, in fact, that the first time he met her was earlier
and I think he said, "G'day, how are you going?"
And then chucked out his hand for a handshake.
So he had form with the queen.
- Yeah, what's Prince Harry's child called?
- Archie or Lilibet?
- Lilibet, it's actually named after Dennis Lilly.
(laughing)
- Made such an impression.
Well, he obviously did,
'cause he said, "Can I have your autograph?"
Someone took a photo, actually, of him
holding out a notebook and pen
and her looking a bit like,
"Probably not gonna do that."
And she said, "No, I'm sorry, it's against protocol."
But then a few weeks later,
he received in the post a photograph of that moment
when he asked for her autograph signed by the queen.
- No way! - Oh, yeah.
- On people who refuse autographs,
friend of the podcast, George Elliott,
she instructed her boyfriend, Henry Lewis,
to write point blank refusals to anyone who--
- Well, she would have to get a massive crayon
'cause she would have a huge hand in the room.
- There's novelty pencils, yeah.
(laughing)
Why, why did she refuse?
- She's busy.
- A little more confused, sorry.
- Also, she was quite confused about what her name was,
wasn't she?
I'm at George, I'm at Marianne Evans.
Have I got in another suit on him now?
- Yeah.
- Can I tell you, someone who collected autographs?
- Sure. - Queen Victoria.
- Oh, yeah. - Really?
- Yeah.
She had this cool thing.
I'd never heard of it before.
It was called an autograph fan.
And it's literally a fan,
and every separate blade of the fan,
you write a different person's signature on it.
- Oh, they write it.
(laughing)
- Even better, they write it on it.
- She was a great forger.
- But I just love the idea of Queen Victoria saying,
"Can I have your autograph to someone?"
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- It was mostly her children and prime ministers
and things like that. - Okay, okay.
- That's pretty cool.
Do we have the fans?
Are they in? - Yeah, we just, wow.
- I'd love to see those.
- Is that why they're called fans?
People who ask for autographs?
- Yeah, yeah.
It's a good legit question, I think.
- No, I knew it was not.
- I know, but why are they called fans?
- Fanatical.
- Oh, yeah.
- Or.
(laughing)
- One of the most expensive autographs
you can get is a Button Gwinnett.
- Button Gwinnett.
- If you ever have an autograph of Button Gwinnett,
it will cost at least $1 million.
- Button Gwinnett. - At least.
- Button Gwinnett.
Button as in the things that you fasten your clothes with
and Gwinnett exactly how you would expect to spell it.
- Can we guess?
You're leaving us hanging as if maybe
we could guess who this person is.
- So it's obvious, I reckon it's a,
oh no, it won't be a forger, would it?
This is the most expensive signature.
- It's not the most expensive,
but it will cost you at least a million dollars to get it.
- I think I know it.
- Ooh, go on.
- Is it Declaration of Independence?
- It is Declaration of Independence
and most people have,
or a lot of people who collect autographs of people
who sign the Declaration of Independence
will have 55 of the 56,
but Button Gwinnett is extremely rare.
He died quite soon afterwards in a duel.
Someone called him a scoundrel and a lying rascal
and he got in a duel and died.
And so there's like maybe a dozen
or half a dozen of his signatures out there.
And if you want the full set,
you're going to have to cuff up at least a million dollars
for it.
- It's like the rarest football sticker.
- Yeah.
- They've put it in six packs.
- It's amazing because he's like the least famous,
one of the least famous ones, right?
- Yeah.
- But he's still.
- By a long way.
- Although I was, well,
I was skimming the Declaration of Independence
and you haven't heard of most of them.
Trust me.
- Skimming.
- Why were you?
- I happen to be skimming.
I was actually.
(laughing)
I would just like to remind myself
of the principles of which the country is based.
- Everyone else on the buses on their phone.
Anna's on her scroll.
(laughing)
- I think if you're ever on Pointless Listener
and it comes up,
name someone from the Declaration of Independence,
but Gwyneth has got to be.
- Oh yes.
- This is a good one.
I reckon most people couldn't get me on the first six or seven.
But anyway, the reason I was skimming it
was because I was wondering about.
- That's right, get me on George Washington.
John Hancock.
- Yeah, just name the first few presidents.
- Ben Franklin, though, was he one as well?
- Was Gouverneur Morris,
who died with a whale bone off his penis.
- Yeah, he was.
- I think he was.
- He was on there.
- Poor guy.
- We've got that extra sentence there.
- We broke it.
- We just said Ben Franklin, John Adams.
Gouverneur Morris, the guy had the whale bone
off his penis and died.
(laughing)
- The English getting this Declaration of Independence
and reading it, going, it's the guy.
(laughing)
- It's actually part of the signature.
They've just added it on afterwards.
For anyone doubting who this is.
- John Hancock.
This is why I was browsing it for this,
'cause I was thinking about,
I wonder what interesting stuff it is
about the John Hancock.
- Oh yeah.
- The signature, you know, by word for a signature,
'cause he was the first person to sign it.
- Yeah.
- And there's not much,
but I hadn't really looked at the signatures there before.
And it's really like, you know,
if you sign someone's birthday card at work
and someone writes their own name incredibly big.
And it's like, did you not know the rest of us
were gonna have to sign this?
(laughing)
Way more than twice the size of the second biggest.
- John Adams has just written, get well soon.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- See you later.
We're just lovely working with you.
(laughing)
- There's just sport signatures.
- Yeah.
- There's Luka Doni, who's a basketball player.
- Genius.
- He's a big deal.
- Yeah.
- He's a genius.
- Mavericks.
- And he's signatures been making the news lately
because it broke a record for the most ever paid
for a basketball card at public auction.
- Okay, wow.
- Get these specific cards called logoman cards,
or logoman cards, the thing in the basketball world
where you have your NBA logo on this card
from your jersey.
- Feels like it'll be logoman then.
- It does, and yeah, some people say logo.
So you got your NBA logo.
(laughing)
Or your NBA logo.
- Yeah.
- It just depends where you come from, doesn't it?
- It does, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- Anyway.
(laughing)
- Are you gonna ask us to guess?
- Yes, okay, fine.
Well, that wasn't gonna be part of it, but sure.
So that's sold at most ever paid public auction
for basketball card.
How much do you think for?
November 22.
- $75 if it does.
(laughing)
- Well, Steve Jobs, half a mill.
Button Gwinnett, over one million.
I'm gonna say it would be somewhere in between the two.
I'll go for $700,000.
- Oh, I like that you've done that.
You've undershot it, and it's very generous of you.
So it went for 3.12 million and actually sold in private
the year before for 4.6 million,
which doesn't apply to the person who's lost.
- So someone just lost a huge loss in a year as well.
(laughing)
- What makes you think you've got this card
that you've paid $4 million for?
And a year later you're like,
you know what, I'm gonna sell it for 3 million.
What goes through your head?
- They must have come up on really hard time.
- I think what it was is it was initially bought
by Vince Kosuga, and then he sold it,
but then flooded the market
with all his other Luka signature.
- The orphans of Chicago were receiving
so many of these bloody basketball cards.
- Anyway, the thing I really like about this,
which makes me wanna laugh at the fate of whoever bought it,
is that his signatures keeps changing,
and it's changed a lot since his teens,
and there's a lot of chat
that actually it's not his signature.
- He said his hand replaced.
(laughing)
- Is that it?
- You're so close.
- Oh, the basketball has crippled his fingers over the years,
and it's changed the way he writes his name.
Someone's just forged it.
- That's the claim.
- He's died and been replaced by another.
Someone's just forged it.
- Okay, I think James has just said the, yeah.
- Keep going, Andy, keep going.
- People think he's got the Luka signature,
which is his old one, and the Lula one,
which is his new one, because it's more feminine.
Since he became president of Brazil.
- He's like he's been replaced by the president.
- That's the conspiracy theory.
- Wow, I love it.
- And as Dan says, he's a genius,
so I think he's gonna do a pretty good job.
Sorry, it's actually called the Lula one.
- Since he was replaced by the 80s singer.
(laughing)
- There's been a body swap comedy somewhere,
and anyway, it's thought that it's his mother's signature.
- Oh, interesting. - Oh, really?
- Someone else did that,
and in fact, we were talking about presidential signatures,
from Ronald Reagan, but when he was an actor,
not when he was president, he got his mum.
I think he paid his mum, or he asked the studio
to pay for his mum to sign all of his fan mail,
and it's now believed that pretty much everything he wrote
from the late 1930s to the late 1950s is suspect.
You can't trust any signature from that time.
(laughing)
Even his Christmas card was probably
him getting his mum to do it all.
- You know, the whole Berlin Wall thing and everything.
That was actually his mum. - It was all his mum, yeah.
- I'm so glad you clarified it.
I thought what you meant, Anna,
was not that his mum had written the fake signature,
but that he'd changed his signature to his mum's signature.
(laughing)
- Well, that's because when he was at school,
they sent the letter back saying
that he'd come to his homework.
He used to practice his mum's signature.
- Yeah, he knew it inside out, yeah.
I'm in the category of autograph collector.
- Yeah. - To a certain degree.
- Yeah, I like the occasional.
Yeah, if I could find one,
and I brought in a few of my favorite
from my collection just to show you.
- So, first off, I've just, you guys can't see
when I can see the dance bank from where I'm sitting,
and I know the story behind this one.
- So the first thing I have is a signed Beatles drumstick
from the drummer of the Beatles.
- Okay. - Yeah, Pete Best,
who was the original.
- Oh, you got the Pete Best, that's so cool.
- Yeah, so I don't remember buying this.
I woke up one day, and in the post came it,
and it turns out I was drunk in a car,
and on the way home, I bought a Pete Best.
- You got to stop doing that with the driving home.
Don't drink and drive and ebay.
(laughing)
- So that's the first thing.
So drummers love to sign a stick.
I like when signatures are appropriate to an item, you know?
This I found in a secondhand bookshop,
and I know I've shown you guys this before,
but for the listener,
what it is is a signed Stephen Hawking book.
Now, how would Stephen Hawking do his signature?
- Kiss, I was thinking, like put lipstick on him
and kiss the book.
- It's kind of close.
- It's not too far away.
What they used to do was is his assistant
would dip his thumb into some ink.
So I have the thumbprint of Stephen Hawking,
and it says thumbprint of Stephen Hawking
witnessed by Susan Maisie,
who must have been his assistant or a nurse at the time.
- It says, "I never give my thumbprint out,
"and I will not be doing so on this occasion."
(laughing)
So that's quite cool.
I found that for five quid in a secondhand bookshop.
- Here's the last one, which is interesting.
This is a baseball.
- Oh, yeah.
- Baseball signed by a Hall of Famer called Gaylord Perry.
- Oh, Gaylord Perry, yeah.
- Yeah, who is someone I'm fascinated with,
but we won't go into it now.
But what's interesting about this
is you can get baseballs that are worth more
if they're signed in certain ways.
So this is worth more than most baseballs
would be if he'd signed it differently.
So can you guess why this is worth more
signed by Gaylord Perry?
- He spelled his name wrong?
- No, no, correct spelling.
- So he signed it, there are two seams,
or the rather is one seam,
isn't there that goes all the way around?
And he signed it in the nice bow beautifully
between the point where the two seams
are closer to each other.
- So that's the first thing, that's absolutely right.
So this is what's known as the sweet spot of a baseball.
You can get a long signature right across
without having to break it up.
Nothing gets in the way.
The other thing is that it's a official ball American League,
which is not the NLB, right?
So this would be worth less
because it's an official Major League baseball.
So that shoots it down.
It has his details, Hall of Famer, 91 on it.
So if anyone's a world champion,
a world series champion or whatever,
if they add the detail, that's gonna make it more.
And then the last thing--
- How many, like if you put your name, address, phone number,
Twitter handle, it gets better and better.
- So there's one more thing
it's specifically to do with the signature
that makes this worth more
than a different baseball signature.
- Is it 'cause it's blue?
- Absolutely, it's blue ink.
- It looks nicer with the red scene.
- It will also stay on longer than black.
Black will rub off according to the experts
who auction baseballs off.
- I have assigned American football by Colin Kaepernick.
- Oh yeah.
- Which I got when he was an American footballer
and now he's a civil rights guy, right?
But it's signed in like silver writing.
And to be honest, I'm not sure it'll last
for another 10 years, I think it'll all rub off.
- Yeah.
- Still, it's so nice to get a signature
where you can say I got it when he was American football
and now he's a civil rights guy
rather than now he's a pedophile
or now he's in prison for massive tax fraud.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shriverland, Andy.
- @AndrewHunterM.
- James.
- @JamesHarkin.
- And Anna.
- You can email our podcast at qa.com.
- Yep, or go to our group account
which is at no such thing or our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
Also check out the portal to Club Fish,
our secret little behind the scenes land
where we add bonus content all the time
and have lots of fans chatting to each other.
It's a great place.
Check it out.
Otherwise, come back next week.
We'll be back with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)