(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski, Andrew Hunter Murray
and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
- My fact is that if you took all the hedges in Britain
and laid them end to end,
they would stretch to the moon and most of the way back.
(laughing)
- Not like that.
- Grappy ending to that.
(laughing)
How far back?
- Basically, figures vary about the exact length,
but it would definitely get you all the way there
and it would definitely not get you all the way back.
- All the alien sheep that you're kind of herding
into this gap between the earth and the moon,
they'd be able to escape from that last little gap.
- I don't think they would
because there's one layer of hedging solidly between the two.
- Yeah, but the thing is with fences,
you need them on both sides of a field.
- Yes, what I stupidly imagined is a sort of double row
of hedging that runs out halfway back,
but you don't actually, you don't need that.
- Basically, the UK has about 700,000 kilometers of hedges.
Some people say there are only about 500,000 kilometers
of hedges, so the figures do vary,
but it definitely is between one and two times the distance
between the earth and the moon, right?
That's quite a big discrepancy, 200,000 kilometers.
- Yeah, I mean, it's quite hard to survey.
There are quite good ways of measuring now,
as in you can use satellites to measure the distances.
- Who has the time, though,
to go through all the hedges from satellite imagery?
- It feels like you have the answer to that question.
I know you're just teaming me up.
(all laughing)
- And with that, James, quit the podcast
to start his hedge measuring career.
- I was just thinking that I think
if you have satellite imagery,
there's more important things to do than work out
whether it's 200,000 or 300,000 or whatever it was.
- It's true, it's true.
- I'm saying this, by the way,
as someone who has been active
in the hedge community in the past.
- What do you mean?
- When I lived in the countryside in the Lake District,
when I moved in, one of the first people to come around
was a couple saying, would you be interested
in getting involved with the hedges?
- Right.
- And it does sound like a swinging case,
but it certainly was.
(all laughing)
- Basically, in Silverdale, where I lived,
so it's just outside the Lake District,
the hedges were very important
'cause they have a lot of wildlife,
and we wanted to save them.
I only went to one or two meetings.
- So what happened at those meetings?
- Part of it, you might go around
picking stuff out of the hedges,
like cleaning the hedges and stuff.
But mostly, you're just trying to stop people
from cutting the hedges down.
- Or just vigilante wandering the countryside,
throwing yourselves at farmers.
- That was probably in the third meeting,
but all that stuff happened.
Like the Extinction Rebellion side of it,
I think that came later.
It was mostly just chatting about hedges.
- Was it, James, the National Hedge Laying Society?
- I don't recall very well, but I don't think so.
It was a long time ago, this.
- There are a few different hedge bodies.
- Yeah.
- But isn't this the one grand daddy body of hedging?
- I mean, the National Hedge Laying Society are huge.
- You wanted to talk about hedge laying, then, Andy,
which is different, of course,
to James's hedge rubbish clearance.
- The National Hedge Laying Society
and the National Hedge Maintenance Society
are the jets and the sharks of the hedge world.
Vicious, vicious knife fights
between them whenever they meet.
Life on the hedge.
- God.
- But it is really cool hedge laying.
I didn't know about it.
I didn't know what it was.
And it is literally making a hedge lie down, isn't it?
It's flaccidating a hedge, essentially.
- So the hedge pre-exists.
- A hedge has to pre-exist to lay a hedge, yes.
Otherwise, you're just building a hedge, I guess.
- So that's what I got confused about.
I thought you have to plant a hedge, don't you?
- Yeah, that's what I thought.
- Well, you're planting a hedge
into an already existing hedge.
So, basically, this is a way of maintaining the hedges,
which is very important that we do,
'cause they're so bi-diverse and stuff.
And so you've got to stop them growing too high, too tall,
because if the trees that make up a hedge
turn into mature trees, then they eventually die.
And also, they're trunks shoot up
and they don't have any foliage at the bottom
and there are big gaps in the hedge
and all the sheep get through.
And so what hedge laying is, it's really clever,
you turn the hedge from vertical to horizontal, essentially.
So you do this by kind of cutting the upright trunks
at the base, so you make a little slit in the upright trunk.
But you don't cut it all the way down to the bottom,
'cause you really don't wanna kill the trunk.
You gotta keep the sap flowing up it.
And when you split it, you can bend it over,
as you can imagine, like a hinge so that it lies down.
And then when you do that,
then it will start growing new hedgery upwards.
So you've got to keep on bending it over
so a new youthful bit shoots up.
- That's very clever, that's great, I didn't know that.
- And it's called "pleaching."
- "Pleaching."
- The "pleach" and the "ligger" is the bit
on the hedge that's horizontal, if you ever wanna.
- Wow, that's good new words.
- "Pleaching" and "liggering."
- "Pleaching."
Most hedges I've seen in the photos
while researching this,
they sort of look like they've been blown
to a 45 degree angle by the wind.
- It's very controversial, the angle at which you should
put it, and there are 35 different types of hedge laying,
and people say 30 degrees, 45 occasionally.
I don't know where you saw this hedge.
- It was on actually the official bodies website, so.
- Right, so they've made a statement with that angle.
- It's a good website, isn't it?
The National Hedge Laying Bodies website.
- I think that's being very kind, it's nice, it's pleasant.
- Wow.
- What do you think were its main drawbacks?
- To be honest, I looked at it and thought I might
get in touch and just give some suggestions.
I thought there was a lot of information missing.
There was a lot of, yeah, there was a lot more they could do
with their annual award for best hedge.
- What could they do?
- More photos, more understanding of what had happened.
If you're a novice, like me coming to it.
- Like match reports, 'cause they do have
an annual championship, you're right, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, the National Hedge Laying Championship.
- I did want a bit more pros, actually,
of what had happened in each year's championships.
They just give us the kind of winners
and the runners up.
- Can I, sorry, can I just ask a question?
Is it for the person who's best at bending the hedges
or is it for the actual best hedge?
- Great question.
I would have loved to have got the answer
as I read the website.
- I did get the answer from the website
because it's the former.
It's not the best, it's the person who's laying the hedge.
- Yeah.
- You have to scroll down, so there's a bar
at the side of the website often
and you get the down arrow at the bottom.
- Is that what it is?
- You get more, it's like turning a page
but on your laptop, it's amazing.
- 'Cause I presume like hedges are hundreds,
if not thousands of years old, right?
And they don't change that much from year to year.
So whatever's the best hedge in 2019 is likely
to be the best hedge in 2020 and 2021.
Do you know how to tell how old a hedge is?
No.
- Ask it nicely.
- There's a thing called Hooper's Rule.
No, it's very rude to ask a hedge its age.
- Oh, right, good to know.
- There's a thing called Hooper's Rule.
It's named after a guy called M.D. Hooper,
who is one of the people who invented it.
And you take a 30-yard stretch of hedge,
you count the number of species in it,
you multiply that number by 110 and then you add 30 years.
And that will tell you exactly how old a hedge is
and it's called Hooper's Rule.
And it was published in the '70s and almost immediately,
someone else did a publication saying it's complete bollocks.
(laughing)
At very best, it can give you an approximation
and you should always use village or council
or parish history.
- Also, that's gonna be a hell of a lot quicker
than counting meticulously.
All the species in a hedge.
- There's a guy, and this was in the article
that you sent Andy, where you found your fact from,
where he spent two years, he's a British ecologist,
spent two years looking at all of the species
inside one particular bit of hedgerow.
And he counted 2,070 in total over those years.
And this is not the wood.
This is like little ants and animals and so on.
- And he's amazing.
Robert Walton, he was challenged during a car journey
by another friend of his, another naturalist.
Not sure what the exact terms of the challenge were,
but it's basically why didn't you study that hedge
for a very long time?
(laughing)
And he spent a year on it and he's like,
"God, I'm still getting loads every single week."
So he spent another, spent a second year on it.
It was incredible.
He reckoned there were more than 3,000,
but he could only count 2,000
'cause they were with the naked eye
that he was looking at them.
2,000 species is the most detailed study
of a hedge ever made.
Ever.
I can't believe no one else has done this.
- Yeah, I know, it's weird, isn't it?
Well, that's what he was saying.
It's bizarre how important they are
that we know so little about what's in them, in a way.
And also, they've been quite denigrated hedges.
They've had a bad rep for ages.
Definitely, when I was growing up,
I thought that the hedge was often quite new, right?
'Cause you learned about enclosure.
This is the big deal.
God, it's drilled into you at school.
Enclosure, agricultural revolution.
You build hedges all around the fields
and there's this common misconception
and it's still on loads of sites today
that the hedges just came up in enclosure
when the landowners locked off their fields.
- I don't think every listener's gonna know about enclosure.
I think we should say a bit.
- No, that's, if you don't remember,
if you're not English and don't remember your year A history.
- So what is it?
I don't know this.
- In the agricultural revolution,
landowners decided to end the common land usage policies
that have been existing so far
where everyone could graze their animals and plant
when they wanted to do common land
and they enclose their land with fences and hedges.
And that's where a lot of people think,
this grand misconception arises,
that hedges were all planted.
So loads of hedges in the south of England
do come from the 17th and 18th century.
- You basically cut down the entire of year eight history
into about two sentences.
- There we go.
And now I've told you it's wrong.
(laughing)
They're all really old.
- Wow.
Welcome to year nine, bitches.
(laughing)
Everything is a lie.
- Forget what you heard.
- Like me in year eight,
I still stopped listening half way through.
What was I saying?
- Guarantee you can't find enclosure
10 seconds after hearing about it.
And so people thought we could cut them down
'cause they're new,
so they weren't part of the intrinsic landscape
that's full of these amazing,
ecosystem.
- A lot of them are like between parishes,
for instance,
which goes back thousands of years.
And even before that,
just people when we first got the sheep's over,
just trying to keep your sheep in one place kind of thing.
- They kind of function as motorways for species.
Mice get around the countryside on them.
The animals use them for navigation.
The birds nesting,
it's really vital that they exist.
And the UK destroyed about half of its hedging
in the 20th century.
So you would have been able to get to the moon
and back again.
And then maybe to the moon again,
in the good old days in the 1930s.
And the reason the UK destroyed half of its hedging,
give or take is because of Hitler.
- Oh, he always gets the blame, doesn't he?
- Get into that give or take.
- More I hear about that man.
- So the UK wanted to be quite food sufficient
after the Second World War,
because there had been a few problems
with food supplies during the war.
And so various governments incentivized farmers
to make their fields much bigger,
remove the hedges, join them all up,
just so you could grow larger amounts of crops.
And they were actually incentivized.
Farmers were paid to get rid of their hedges.
And only in the last 20 years,
I think has it been truly appreciated
just what a lot of damage this did to biodiversity
and all sorts of things.
And so now there are aims to build many more hedges,
not only to fight climate change,
but to build biodiversity.
- And against the Nazis.
- And to just keep the Nazis down,
just to stop and coming back.
- Do you want some other hedge words, by the way?
- Oh yeah.
- See, that is giving us some great hedge words.
These are actually words in the OED
that have the word hedge in them.
So to hedge hop, you know what hedge hopping is?
- Is that to, there's a field of hedgehogs
and you're not allowed to touch the ground.
It's like the floor is lava.
- It's a game.
- Yeah, you have to get to the other side.
- Trampling a hedgehog with every bound.
- I'm not saying it's a nice game, I'm just saying.
- Again, once you've torn the hedges down,
why don't you do this hedgehog trampling game?
- It's not that, thankfully.
It's a colloquial term for flying your aircraft
at a very low level,
so as if you're hopping over hedges.
- Oh, nice, lovely, got it.
- Hedge wine is very poor quality wine.
And in fact, hedge is used to mean poor quality.
And also hedge wench, do you know what a hedge wench is?
- Well, a wench is a lusty woman.
- And hedge is poor quality.
So it's a poor quality lusty woman.
(laughing)
- This is a bit more literal.
It's a sex worker who plays their trade in a hedge.
- Oh, golly.
- That's a painful, are people paying extra for that?
Or are you going to get a prickle?
- In a hedge.
- In a hedge, yeah.
- We could go back to my place actually,
just think about it now.
(laughing)
I do think the hedge is going to detract from the experience.
There are 2,000 species and they're all watching at the moment
and I don't like it.
Oh, God.
- A lot of ants up the bum.
Do you know what this proverb means?
It's good sheltering under an old hedge.
It's a very old American proverb.
- Does it mean literally exactly what it sounds like?
(laughing)
If you find an old hedge,
you're probably going to be sheltered quite nicely.
- It sounds like it does.
It's actually more cryptic than that.
It means it's good to marry an older woman.
She's the old hedge.
Cause I guess she's more experienced.
- Thicker.
(laughing)
- She's been laid by many men before.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in the 1940s,
prisoners of war in the US helped build a model
of the Mississippi basin
that was about twice the size of the Vatican.
- Wow.
- God, it's actually so many elements in that fact
that I'd be impressed if you got to the end of it.
But.
- So I don't know what a model of the Mississippi basin was
before hearing about this fact.
- Okay, does that mean you,
cause you know what a model is presumably.
- I certainly do.
- And you know what the Mississippi is.
But I'm conceptually incapable of joining those two together.
(laughing)
Is what we've learned.
- Well, for those of you who are, you know,
imaginationally absent at home,
it's a model of a river and it's surrounding land.
- But a river's made of water.
- Yeah.
- So for water in the model, they use water.
- They also have to model the banks
otherwise that's just a puddle on the floor.
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, yeah, I see, okay.
- So you've modeled everything surrounding the river,
basically, and then just pour water into it.
- All like the flood plains and stuff like that, right?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- All the land around it that might be affected by it.
- Exactly, yeah, yeah.
- Why did we want to muddle it, I guess?
- Well, we wanted to figure out how it worked
and get to know it better.
So this was called the Mississippi River Basin
Model Waterways Experiment Station near Clinton, Mississippi.
And it was built because the Mississippi was always flooding
and actually they just had a couple of really awful floods.
So in 1927, there was the worst flood in US history.
1937, another bad one.
And this guy called Eugene Raybold said,
the problem we're having is that whenever there's a flood,
we try and fix it,
and this is a problem with flooding today still,
but we try and fix it in the individual place
where there was a flood, so we'll build a levee or a dam.
But that's not understanding the river as a whole.
And that just has a knock on effect further down.
You're just kicking it further down the road.
So what we need to do is we need to build the whole river.
And he was quite sure on laborers
'cause everyone was fighting in the war,
for what there were,
were quite a lot of German and Italian prisoners of war.
And so they all must have been so confused
when they were carted to prisoner of war camp in Mississippi
and told to build the Mississippi River again.
- For those men getting home after the war,
after the, oh, Hans, we're so worried.
You know, you were kept as a prisoner of war.
It must have been awful.
What did they make you do?
Oh, you know, just really,
it was really difficult actually.
Yeah, but what were you doing, Hans?
Were you maybe picking cotton in the fields
or working in a mine?
Yeah, I mean, you know, we don't model, model building.
- Like that's, it's twice the size of the Vatican.
I reckon there was a lot of earth being moved around, right?
- Yeah, it's not model building,
like a wallhammer fanatic.
(all laughing)
- It wasn't a ground build, they didn't come to play with it.
Basically, that's what they were doing.
- It feels to me like I wouldn't personally
want to be part of that team, you know?
- Given the choice between that
and other prisoner of war labor,
like absolutely will be on model road.
- Team fake river.
- Model railway, I've given away my address there.
(all laughing)
- River modeling duty, yeah.
- How big was it, Anna?
Sorry, I missed that.
- So, I haven't actually said it.
I've just said it was about twice the size of the Vatican.
- But you know how big the Vatican is.
- And you know what twice is.
Can you not put those two concepts together?
- I can't actually think of how big the Vatican,
because the Vatican is a whole city, right?
Like it's big.
- It's difficult, it's difficult.
- But it's not a big city, you know that.
- Yeah, but okay, that still doesn't help.
- I reckon it's about a square kilometer, is it?
- It's, well, I can give you another measure.
It was also about the size of 120 football pitches.
It was 210 acres.
- Can we get it in hedges next time?
- Sorry, distance to the moon, it's, God knows.
- It's so huge, this thing.
The streams in this thing are eight miles long in total.
Like it's really big.
- Yeah, and the only way you could see it all
was from an observation point that was four stories tall,
wasn't it?
So you had to climb right the way up,
and then you could see the whole thing.
- Yeah.
- One gallon of water in the thing
represented 1.5 million gallons of water in the real world.
- Very cool. - So cool.
- I think five minutes of water running through the basin
simulated an entire day of water running through the Mississippi.
So you could quite quickly work out.
And it was super useful.
It was a few years after it was built.
There were some signs of flooding.
People were getting a bit nervous.
Signs of flooding in the Missouri River,
which is a tributary of the Mississippi,
longest river in the US.
And so they simulated what was happening in the little model.
And they said, oh, shit, yeah, it's
going to flood here and there, not too much there.
Build it down there.
And they did and saved a few million quid.
- That's amazing.
I was thinking about the songs, because it's really tied
into blues.
And it's also a river that comes up a lot in songs.
And for me, I love Jeff Buckley.
- Like Old Man River.
- Like Old Man River, Jeff Buckley drowned in the Mississippi.
- Did he?
- Yeah, and that, so for me, it's a river
that I've always noticed in songs.
So I was looking into it, and I found out that actually,
the Mississippi River actually had a sign to it,
a songwriter and singer called Charlie Maguire.
And he was the singing ranger.
- What's the job, sorry?
- He goes around.
- Yeah, he writes songs about the Mississippi.
- I better use the word hippie quite a lot.
- Dippy, are you going for a Dippy in the Mississippi?
It's going to get pretty nippy, get slippy, love.
We could do this job, it's pretty easy.
- Yeah, no, he wrote a lot of songs at his time.
So, and the songs would embody the story of the Mississippi.
So one song was called Great Mississippi.
That was about where it starts and where it ends.
- The route one.
- Rock strata.
- When was this guy's story?
- 2003.
- Oh, wow.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The singing ranger is the only person
that's ever been given this position.
And yeah, he wrote tons of songs, won lots of awards.
Not Grammys.
- No Grammys.
- Was it awards for best song about the Mississippi
written by the person employed by the songs about the Mississippi?
- I reckon we've got a chance this year
with the old nippy song.
- I had to completely agree.
- Here's a cool thing about the Mississippi.
It's a map that was published of the river.
And it was published in 1866.
And it's called The Ribbon Map of the Father of Waters.
And it's a strip map.
So the map was 11 feet long, but only three inches wide.
- Oh my gosh.
- I know.
It's really funny.
Strip maps used to be really big.
So that these just weren't really long.
- Really long.
If you were planning a specific trip,
and this is ages and centuries ago,
you might have a strip map.
If you were going on a pilgrimage to Jerusalem,
'cause it's basically one route.
And it says turn left at this town
and then go straight along here for another five miles
and then turn right at whatever.
And it was on a spool, basically.
So you just spool along as you went.
I think it was more for tourism purposes than for cartography.
- I might be wrong about this.
I think they used to have like GPS's of those, did they?
- Yes, they did.
I met the guy who owns loads of them.
I borrowed some from him.
And you put a wristwatch on exactly like James says,
like London to Brighton.
You just load in the cartridge for London to Brighton.
And then as you're driving along, you just wind on a bit.
- So clever. - So clever.
- Oh, wow.
- Crawly. - That's so cool.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- Yeah, really fun.
- What happens if there's a closed road?
- You're stuffed.
- Yeah, you're stuffed.
- You can only go in that.
It only tells you that you're on the right route.
- Or you need to have several,
the whole back of your car is full.
It's tiny. - Car refurbification.
- Exactly.
(laughing)
- James Robert Scott.
You know him?
- No.
- He was in West Quincee, Missouri
when there was a great flood of the Mississippi in 1993.
So there was flooding happening all over the place
and they'd put lots of sandbags in
and levees or levees or how he pronounced that.
Anyway, he decided that he was going to remove
some of the sandbags and basically allow an area to flood.
And it was very, no one died, but it's very dangerous.
And also, you know, lots of people lost land
and stuff like that.
He claimed that he did it because his town was in trouble
and he wanted to move the sandbags from one place to another
to try and, you know, keep his town safe.
But then apparently he told his friend
that he'd actually done it
so that he could strand his wife on the other side
of the river so that he could have an affair.
- So he could have an affair?
- Yeah.
- How long was he trying to strand her for?
- Well, a few weeks, he was hoping that it might happen.
Yeah. - Climacy.
- He maintains his innocence, I should say.
He's in prison, I found him guilty.
He's eligible for parole in 2023.
- And that's for the sandbag moving, not for the affair?
- Yes, I don't think it's illegal to have an affair.
- A very puritanical.
- No, because all the damage that it caused.
- Yeah, of course.
- It was billions of dollars of damage.
- What?
- One figure I read was 15 billion.
- How many sandbags did he move?
- Well, you only need--
- You only need to remove one finger from the dam
and then everything goes. - Yeah, that's true.
And you've got to be needing those fingers
when you're conducting your illicit extramarital affair.
(laughing)
- There are easier ways to have affairs, aren't there?
- It feels like-- - Ken Dark?
- Get a hedge.
- Why not?
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that one of the few historians
to use the term Dark Ages is Professor Ken Dark.
(laughing)
- It's funny.
- It's funny having a professor called Ken.
(laughing)
- I think that's funny enough.
- Why?
- What?
- My name's Ken Dark.
(laughing)
- Because Ken in Scots, Old Scots means knowledge,
like you're Ken, and so, and he's a professor.
So is that why you found funny about that?
- God, it does mean knowledge you're right.
And it makes me think that Ken of Barbie and Ken
has sunk a long way, hasn't he, since the Ken's view.
- Are they called the Dark Ages?
- After Ken.
- After Ken Dark.
- Or they're not.
- Should've called it the Ken Ages.
- This is just--
(laughing)
- Not Ken Ages.
- Ken Ages ago.
(laughing)
- Very good.
This is just a complete coincidence, really, I think.
So it's an article that I read on the website
of the University of Sheffield,
and it's about English heritage.
So they decided to do a handbook and some websites,
stuff like that, where they called the period
between 400 AD and 1066, the Dark Ages.
And then there was a huge sort of campaign
of a lot of Twitter historians saying,
and other historians, but saying,
you can't call it the Dark Ages.
What it does is it makes people think it's a terrible time
where people had an awful life and stuff like that.
And it was, that's not really what Dark Ages means,
but anyway, English heritage said that the reason
that we're calling it that is because there is
this professor called Professor Ken Dark,
and he calls it the Dark Ages.
He's a proper professor, so we should be able
to call it that as well.
A lot of people pointed out that the article
that Ken Dark wrote was slightly esoteric.
It was about the Byzantine era.
It wasn't about the British Dark Ages,
early modern period.
If you look at Ken Dark's work,
which I have done quite a lot,
you'll find that he's done something recently
where he talks about illuminating the Dark Ages
and trying to bring light into the Dark Ages.
And he's not calling them the Dark Ages
'cause his name is Ken Dark.
I just wanna make that really true.
- That's what you want do you think?
(laughing)
- There's an argument that they basically just
wanted to kind of shut down the argument
and say, "Here's some evidence, this is why we did it."
- And yet, if you asked any of those historians,
would you like to go and live in 430 AD forever?
You can't come back, it's not a cool history trip.
- Well, you can take your family.
- You can take your family.
- Well, for instance, there's one historian
called Charles West who said,
"If the term Dark Ages really must be used,
it should at least be reserved for periods
of true in-humanity and barbarity,
such as the 20th century."
- Oh, wow. - Oh, wow.
- I do think we've got very snowflakey
about the Dark Ages.
Come on, it's the one group of people
that we can still offend and they can never complain.
All right, it's people in history.
They can't do anything about it.
Just let's call them all ignorant.
Who cares, they're not coming back.
- Well, I think the point is that the word dark
is not supposed to be ignorant, right?
It's not supposed to be barbarian.
It's supposed to be a time
where we did not have much information about it.
And that's what it was originally,
but people have in the past like popular historians
of kind of in the 70s and 80s have said
that the Dark Ages was a time of darkness and difficulty.
- But I think they have, it has also been used
since the concept kind of arose of the Dark Ages
to be denigrating.
And there has always been this idea
that it's also very uncultured time.
- After the Romans.
- After the Romans, before the Renaissance.
- Before the Normans.
- They were doing bugger all then.
- It was Francesco Petraca, right?
- Petraca, yeah.
- Yeah, sorry.
- No, you're just giving him his proper fancy name.
- His proper fancy name, yeah.
- Petraca.
- And yeah, basically complaining
that there were no good books to read,
which I find amazing.
'Cause then it did as you say, it evolved.
- Petraca was just a guy, right?
- Yeah, just a guy.
(laughing)
- No, he's an Italian scholar.
I mean, he was big in the 14th century.
- Great poet.
- Yeah, I haven't read it, but.
- He wrote more than one.
- Get out.
- He was the official poet of the timer.
(laughing)
- But it does, as you say, sort of mean like,
it was when science was being brushed away
and religion was coming in.
- Yeah.
- And as a result, it was a Dark Age for the mind.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- As well as there being no records.
That's, it's been, yeah.
- And let's be honest.
- I'm full records of what was going on.
- Exactly, I know.
- Between 400 and 1056. - I completely agree.
I agree with you.
- There were other names given to the,
what are we calling them?
- Early Middle Ages. - Early Middle Ages, yeah.
- That were published in various books.
So they included the Barbarous Ages,
sounds pretty, you know.
The Obscure Ages, which I quite like.
(laughing)
Makes me sound quite cool.
The Monkish Ages, absolutely no argument with that.
The Muddy Ages, those were all various.
- Really?
- And then the Mississippi is known as the Old Muddy,
isn't it?
- Is it? - I think.
- Yeah.
- This would have been, yeah.
- Or the Big Muddy, I think maybe.
- The Big Muddy.
- No relation to the Muddy Ages.
(laughing)
- I don't think so.
- Also the Dark Ages could be used to describe the period
from 1100 BC to 750 BC,
which was between the collapse of the Bronze Age
civilization in Greece
and the beginning of the Archaic Age in Greece.
- Oh yeah, the Greek Dark Ages.
- Or it could be from the start of the universe
until 13.2 billion years ago,
which was between the start of the universe
and the creation of the first stars.
That's called the Dark Ages as well, so.
- Oh, but people get offended, don't they?
Those little lumps of dust in the air.
Get offended now, if we call them the Dark Ages.
- I just don't see that the little bits of dust
in the air are gonna be able to come back
and get offended.
I just don't see it.
- You guys are not taking into the account
that time travel will happen one day.
- And that bit for a bit of dust
will jump down my throats.
- Exactly.
I read in one book, this is a book called "Europa History",
that the Middle Ages originally meant the time
between the first coming of Jesus
and the second coming of Jesus.
And since the second coming hasn't as far as we know
happened, we're still technically in the Middle Ages now.
- That's very exciting.
- That's cool.
- Yeah, and thank God, 'cause I always get really anxious
that we're in the modern time
and there's nowhere to go after modern.
So that's good to know that we're actually still in the middle.
- So if anyone says that I'm middle-aged,
I could say yes, well, technically I'm middle-aged
because the second coming of Christ hasn't happened.
- But so are you.
(laughing)
- We're all like, yeah.
- One thing that the Dark Ages,
doing the finger quotes there, gave us,
which is quite exciting just in reference to literature,
was spaces in between words.
So every word, as we know, back in old literature,
used to be bunged together, no spaces,
really hard to tell what's the next word.
And it was in that period.
The monks started going, let's put a little,
we'll put a space in between those two words,
what do you reckon?
- So they didn't write books of their own,
but they did at least introduce some spaces
into the books that already existed.
- Yeah, it's funny 'cause these days,
you know, books have word counts, don't they?
You're like, oh, this book is 100,000 words.
Whereas I guess in those days,
we're like, how long is your manuscript?
Well, it's one word, like all the other,
all the other books.
Yeah, what a word, one very specific word.
- So word with you, oh, God, here we go.
- The Greek Dark Ages, I love the Greek Dark Ages.
- Are they called the Greek Ages,
is that contentious as well?
- Oh, probably.
- Who gives us stuff?
I'm signing up with T-Matter on this one, I've got it.
- Oh God, I feel like I'm in bad company now.
So they're such a mystery.
They are, as James was saying,
this period at the end of the Bronze Age.
And, but they, what I always loved about them
is that they happened because of the invasion
of the sea peoples, do you know about this?
And you will love the sea peoples down there, so great.
I actually can't believe that we haven't discussed them before.
- This is the class eight talk that I listened to.
- There we go.
- Basically, they're a group of people.
We don't know if they existed,
but they're currently historians,
best explanation for why in, what was it, 1100 BC.
Civilization just collapsed.
So we had this amazing, like big palace based states,
Mycenaeque empire.
- Minoans, they ever? - Exactly.
And then it all just vanished.
And also ancient Egypt as well, vanished overnight
and didn't come back until the Greeks worked out
to write an alphabet and stuff 400 years later,
got back on their feet.
And historians think it's 'cause there was someone
called the sea peoples waltzing around the Mediterranean,
strange beings who weren't invaded.
- Go on.
- So, okay, are they, were they of the sea
or were they just living on boats?
- Well, it's not.
- I mean, were they made of water?
- Sorry, what is the difference in your mind, Dan,
between being of the sea and living on a boat?
- Were they like Aquaman or were they a pirate on a boat?
- The more serious historians, I think,
is count the Merman, Merman-made explanation of sea peoples
and say they're probably just boating.
- What does Ken Dark say about that?
That's what I want to know.
- They obviously, the Dark Ages,
that aren't called the Dark Ages, were whole of Europe.
And it was partly this whole mini kingdoms thing,
everyone and his dog can be a king that defined them
because it was all so splintered and it was the Goths
and the Visigoths and the Ostrogoths
and the Norogoths and the Demigoths and stuff,
who were all fighting each other,
weren't they, for hundreds of years?
And the Vandals and the Allons,
which I think we've mentioned before.
The Allons tribe, who I didn't realize,
brought us Great Danes.
So that's something else the Dark Ages gave us.
The Allons, who were Iranian, were known for their--
- Well, it said the Great Danes aren't Danish.
- I think they must have taken root via Denmark
before they got there.
Before they evolved into what they are today.
They brought the fighting dogs that led to Great Danes.
But then the person who saw, I would say,
who kind of presaged the end of this non-Dark Ages,
Dark Ages, was probably Charlemagne, do we think?
As in he just unified Europe.
So he did that, it was a big deal.
And you know how he was crowned emperor?
- How, like, the ceremony or how we can't be--
- Yeah, yeah, the ceremony.
- No, oh, is he one of those strange people
who crowned themself?
- No, quite the opposite, apparently.
- It was crowned by someone else.
- There you go, at the end.
And in fact, he was crowned again as to his will,
according to the court scribe,
who might have been trying to make him sound really humble.
- So he was running away
while someone was chasing him with a crown.
- Exactly.
800 AD, Christmas Day, he'd gone to Rome,
and the Pope decided he's gonna crown him emperor
of this whole bunch of Western Europe.
And he sneaks up behind Charlemagne
while Charlemagne's praying
and pops a crown on his head.
And apparently Charlemagne just stood up and went,
"Oh my gosh, no, what, me?"
I couldn't, I couldn't possibly.
And then he became, you know, the greatest--
- It's a good story, isn't it?
- It's a good story.
- 'Cause like one of them's praying,
so he's holy, and he didn't really want it.
Well, actually probably happened.
They both got really pissed one night.
- Was it Charlemagne
who supposedly had the asbestos tablecloth?
- Oh yeah, that is him.
Yeah, yeah, I think so.
- That was sort of like his dinner party trick, wasn't it?
He would--
- He would throw it into a fire
so you wouldn't have to clean it
because asbestos doesn't burn.
So you put it in the fire,
it would kind of sterilize,
and then you pull it out again
and you could use it again.
- This was, of course, before they knew about mesothelioma,
the terrible lung disease
that they presumably all got back then.
- I think you only get that from little shards of asbestos.
If you have a full tablecloth, you'll be fine.
- You're all right.
- But if bits come off it, then you would help them.
I mean, I'm sure no one was living long enough
to worry about the long-term effects
of an asbestos table,
like there were more pressing health concerns than the age.
So they cleared the table.
- I don't know if, yes,
I don't know if he did that trick
where everything stayed underneath,
but even a kind of swipe.
- You haven't done that trick, by the way.
- No, I've tried it once.
- It's hard.
It is harder than you think.
- It does actually work.
- I think I've seen you do it.
- Yeah, well, I used to be a waiter
and I used to try it a lot.
And like most of the time you can't really do it.
And so there's a trick to it, but yeah.
- You were the most fired waiter
in the North of England, though, I love you.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the metal used
to make Grammy Award trophies is called Grammium.
(laughing)
- Amazing.
- What a coincidence.
(laughing)
- Well, this is a trademarked metal alloy, a zinc alloy,
that a guy called John Billings has patented.
And he is the guy who makes the Grammy Awards.
And he's made them for decades now.
And what I didn't realize was it's a little team
that assembles every year the Grammys.
And it's basically a one shop operation
where not only do they make these Grammys,
but then they put them in a van
and they drive 2,000 or something miles across the country
to deliver it personally.
John Billings himself would be sitting
in the car doing this.
And he is the Grammy man.
And it's-
- They use a strip map to get there.
So exciting.
One year they went off course, it was a disaster,
there were no Grammys.
- Yeah. And it's, yeah.
So this guy, he joined when he was quite young.
There was a previous person making the Grammys.
And since he took over,
he changed the design of the Grammys,
which is what they are today.
And he also came up with this new, stronger alloy
because all of the other previous Grammys
were quite flimsy and would break.
And he thought this needs to be, you know-
- Did they actually break?
Did people take Grammys home
and then you put them down and it just comes?
- They still do, yeah.
- They still break.
- But they broke a lot more easy.
I think it was so the Grammys,
if you don't know what they are,
it is a Grammophone that is the shape of the trophy.
And so obviously-
- And I suppose it's a music award in America as the other.
- Yeah, yeah.
It's the biggest music award in America.
And the trophy is in the shape of a Grammophone.
And it was particularly the arm that was with the stylus
on the end that was particularly flimsy.
And that was the bit when he redesigned it
that he wanted to get stronger.
- Adele, the singer once snapped part of her Grammy on stage.
She dropped it on stage and broke part of it off.
And in 2010, Taylor Swift was carrying four Grammys
and she dropped one of them and it broke into pieces.
And what happens is when it breaks into pieces,
you send it back and they fix it for you.
Mr. Billings fix it for you.
But she wrote oops on the side of the one she broke
and he now has that in his office on the side,
a Taylor Swift broken Grammy and he gave her a new one.
- That's great.
I wonder if she broke the, so the Grammys that we see-
- The stunt.
- There are stunt Grammys.
- And that's what he drives across the country as well.
He drives the stunt ones across the country.
That drives them back as well before and after each.
- Sorry, what is a stunt Grammy?
- A stunt Grammy is the one-
- It's one that can do amazing tricks.
So it throws us other skyscrapers, tightrope walks.
- So the idea is that the real Grammys
are going to be given to everyone who's won them,
need to have their name put on it and so on.
And they can't do that on the night.
So he drives the fake Grammys that you see them holding
at the award ceremony and then they give them back
and then the real Grammy.
- So those are not real Grammys?
- Well, they're obviously-
- Well, they used every single year.
The same ones are used every year.
So if you get a Grammy next year, Andy,
which I'm sure you're hoping for.
- I'm trying.
- You will get one that might have been had by Adele
a few years ago or by Taylor Swift or whatever.
'Cause when he gets the stunt Grammys home,
he cleans them with washing up liquid
to get rid of any fingerprints or anything like that.
And then just puts them into storage.
And then the next year he takes them back.
- Nice.
- So he just, every year drives a load of Grammys
across America then drives them back the other way?
- Yeah, you would think he would have a storage unit
where he could just leave them.
- Does seem like that would be sensible.
- It would be in the fishin', wouldn't it?
- Yeah.
- And then what does he do with the actual one?
Sorry, does he then post them out first class?
- I think he might also drive those ones as well.
- But then does he has to drive on every single home
of every single Grammy winner?
- No, I'm sure he takes them to Mr. Grammy
who then hands them over to the people.
- There's a distribution network, he thinks.
- Yeah, yeah, I think so.
- There will be someone--
- There's a GDPR issue if he knows
where all these people live as well.
- That would be an amazing bit of information to have.
Just all the addresses
of all the most famous musicians in the world.
- Yeah, so the Grammys.
This is a thing that started in the late 1950s
and the idea behind it was that they wanted to have
something that represented the output of musicians.
It was called the Grammy because they had a competition
where they asked the Americans what do you wanna call this?
And I think it was a girl who wrote in
and said these trophies are made out of Grammys,
so why don't we call it Grammys?
(laughing)
- She was, she, a bunch of people suggested it,
but she was the first person who's later got read
with the suggestion of Grammy.
- I think she was a New Orleans secretary
called Rose Trey Elizabeth Danner.
And she was given 25 free LPs as a gift
'cause lots of people are interested in Grammy
but her letter was open first.
But she lived until February, 2014.
So she could have seen Robin Thickey performing Blurred Lines.
(laughing)
- Robin Thickey.
- Yeah, I used to call him that.
And I now, on principle, refuse to call him Robin
by any other name.
- I reckon if you were at school with Robin Thickey,
that's what you would call him.
- Oh, what a Thickey.
- There have been some pretty tedious decisions
from the Grammy board over the years, haven't there?
- It feels like you've got a few of them.
Just leave there, Anna.
- Well, I was reading an article written in 1993.
So some of these wrongs have been corrected now.
But even so, a New York Times article written in 1993
about how they just never seemed to pick the right people.
So by 1993, here are people who hadn't won a Grammy.
Eric Clapton, The Beach Boys, The Supremes,
The Grateful Dead, The Jackson Five,
Led Zeppelin, Etta James, Queen, Van Morrison.
- The Queen.
- The Queen, the Queen has won the Grammys every year,
of course, lovely voice.
Jimi Hendrix and The Rolling Stones,
the only Grammy they ever won was Lifetime Achievement.
At that point, 'cause they sometimes do this thing
where I think the judges think years afterwards,
oh, shit, they did turn out to be really good.
So then they toss a light.
- Oh, God, let's have it.
- We forgot that.
(laughing)
- Those were busy years, though.
We're talking about, in terms of rock, you know,
Hendrix would have been up against the Beatles,
up against, that was a crowd.
- They didn't like rock, though.
That was always a thing with the Grammys.
They were almost set up as an antidote
to what they considered was, I think,
was called anti-music by the people
who wanted the Grammys to come about.
They wanted to celebrate quality music,
not anti-music like R&B and rock,
which, it was like, this is a flash in the pan.
- The most Grammys is by George Salty.
- George Salty?
- And Salty's ring, actually, has been twice voted
the greatest recording ever made.
- What?
- I don't know if you know Salty's ring.
- No.
- No?
- His cycle?
His ring cycle?
(laughing)
- It's Wagner, yeah.
He's a conductor, and so he's conducted lots and lots
of things, won loads and loads of Grammys,
won 31 as a recording artist.
And yeah, Salty's ring is one of the greatest
musical pieces ever made, and it's not funny in any way.
And he was the conductor at the Covent Garden opera house.
And when he first came here,
because obviously we're in Covent Garden at the moment,
there was like a clique in Covent Garden
that really, really hated him,
'cause they didn't like when new musical directors came in,
they really hated it.
And so when he first arrived,
people threw rotten vegetables at him in the street,
and his car was vandalized outside Covent Garden Theater
where the word Salty must go
scratched into his paintwork.
- Wow, that doesn't sound like the actions of opera fans.
- Ah, it's just cliques, isn't it?
You know, it's just groups of people
don't like outsiders coming in with their Salty ways.
- They called him the Screaming Skull.
- Yeah, really?
- But I don't know if that,
I don't think that was a criticism.
I think that was more like he was quite a vigorous man
and he was bald.
But you know, conductors,
they do a lot of like shouting and gesticulating.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So Screaming Skull.
- I really like the non-famous,
the non-televised Grammy categories,
I just think they're great.
'Cause there are so many,
I didn't realize there are dozens and dozens of categories.
- But things like Best Tropical Latin Album
or Best Contemporary Christian Music Performance/Song.
And there is a screening committee
which assesses whether or not
you are actually fitting into that category or not,
'cause it would be much easier, I think,
to get a Grammy for some of these things where--
- Yeah, but we can't put Led Zeppelin in the Christian--
- No, but we, the four of us,
could make a tropical Latin album.
- Are we good?
- Oh, I see.
- Just game the system that way
by entering some of the less popular categories.
- And would that be part of our Mississippi River oeuvre
or is the tropical Latin album like the follow-up?
- I don't think you are even as in the tropics, is it?
- I don't think, no, I don't think it could be.
- No, it's like not.
- But okay, here's one we could win, Best Album Notes.
- Oh yeah.
- Which really feels like a--
- I know a winner of that.
- Not personally, but I know someone who has won that award.
- Who?
- What are the album notes?
Are they the lyrics that you write in there?
- Do you know the sleeve notes that you used to get
in a CD or in an LP?
And young listeners would have completely--
- Yeah, I do.
Where you write Beyonce, I remember a Destiny's Child,
they all wrote how much they loved God.
I found it so boring reading those things.
- Well, they might not have won that year's Best Album Notes
category.
- Dan, who do you know?
Who's been there?
- Steve Martin, the comedian, has won them.
- I bet he's written some really good album notes, yeah.
- For his banjo albums, not for his comedy albums.
- You don't know. - It feels like
it played with strings.
- Do you know Steve Martin?
- No, that's when I said I know someone,
and then I qualified it by saying I don't know them.
- Right.
So it was the last a statement was true, yeah.
- Is aware of.
I know Robin Thickey, although I don't know
how to say his name.
(all laughing)
- It's very controversial the way they vote in the Grammys.
'Cause it's, well, until this year, it was super secret.
It sounds quite exciting.
And I think what used to happen was winners were decided
by this like 12,000 strong recording Academy,
bunch of voters who, they're like.
(all laughing)
- They all stand in a room and put their hands up
and stuff, right?
- Yeah, they crush in and, yeah, someone has to count them.
They, I guess it's probably done by post
and their musicians and music makers.
- Probably you, Val, these days.
(all laughing)
- It was in the 90s that it changed.
- John Billings goes around, gets them
in the back of the van, picks up the next one.
(all laughing)
- But that's just the fake ones that he brings.
So, yeah, it used to be done by this 12,000 strong
and bunch of voters.
But then I think partly because the awards
just kept going so wrong and they just kept giving it
to weird people.
They had to change the rules.
And I think the straw that broke the camel's back
came in the early 90s when over, album of the year was up
and Bruce Springsteen's "Born in the USA" was released
and "Princess Purple Rain" was released
and Lionel Richie's "Can't Slow Down" won.
And everyone said, we didn't like that.
That's not as good as the other two.
And so they formed a secret committee
which basically goes through all the 12,000 votes
and takes out the duds.
- Because actually you would think
that having a larger group, 12,000 would be more likely
to give you a democratic answer, right?
- Yeah, give you the best.
- But a democratic answer isn't necessarily
the best answer, James.
- Is that not right?
- Okay.
- That's my view.
(all laughing)
- My one way ticket to Russia is just to come through.
Anyway, people got quite pissed off
by the secret committee
because no one knew how they voted or why they voted.
And there's someone called The Weekend, I think.
- Oh, The Weekend.
- The Weekend.
- Oh, right.
(all laughing)
Well, it's spelled The Weekend.
- Weekend, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
(all laughing)
- They, he--
- Fred, the Robin picky, I believe.
(all laughing)
- This show has certainly weakened over the years, hasn't it?
- Yeah, so it's felt like Weekend.
Anyway, but without any, so he--
- Well, with two E's.
(all laughing)
- But not three.
Anyway, The Weekend got annoyed
that he hadn't got nominated.
- He's pronounced the Weckend.
(all laughing)
Ladies and gentlemen, The Weekend.
- I just, I want a new podcast
where we give Anna the name of all the partners
that are in the charts and see if she can pronounce them.
- They've asked me to read out the nominations next show.
- I'm quite nervous now.
- Lil Nas the 10th.
(all laughing)
- I did another one, no, I know the Lil Nas is.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland.
Andy.
- @andrewhunterm.
- James. - Hi, James Harkin.
- And Anna.
- You can hear my podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThingIsTheFish.com.
All of our previous episodes up there,
so do check them out and come back again next week.
We'll be here with another batch of facts.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)