(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Shriver.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the first submarine
to go around the world was only seen by one civilian,
a Filipino kayaker who saw the periscope
and thought it was a sea monster.
- It's pretty amazing because we have a photo of that man.
Like this is, it looks--
- Did they take the photo?
- So we'll get into the big story,
but there was a photographer on board.
And so anytime the periscope went up,
they took a photo of what the periscope was seeing.
And in this shot, you had a man sitting there
called Rufino.
- Yeah, and we also know more about him
'cause National Geographic went out looking for him.
- Yeah.
- And they found him and interviewed him.
And that's when they found out
that he thought it was a sea monster.
He immediately went home and painted the names
of Saints Peter and Paul on his boat
for protection against the sea monster.
- Sensible.
- And by amazing coincidence,
this submarine that we're about to talk about
started and ended at Saint Peter and Paul
Archipelago in the Atlantic.
- It's incredible to see this.
- What a coincidence.
- Yeah.
They've blown it wide open.
- Fervent evidence that we are living in a simulation.
- In a very unimaginative matrix.
So yeah, this is a 1960, we're talking.
Middle of the Cold War.
The Americans and the Soviets are not getting on very well,
but maybe there's gonna be a peace summit in Paris.
But before they do that,
the US decided to show off a bit and say,
we've got a new submarine that can go all the way
around the world with no one noticing it.
And so that's why they did it.
It was called Operation Sandblast.
- They could just say they'd done it, couldn't they?
But literally we sailed all the way around the world
underwater without anyone noticing.
- Yeah, but you're still here.
That's 'cause we went all the way around the world.
- Yeah, we just finished.
They just should have sent it underwater
and they just had it coming through a big tape at the end.
- Yeah.
- They were really hardcore bright.
So there were a couple of moments where it looked dodgy
where really they should have come up.
And they didn't.
There's one instance where there was a member of the crew
who had kidney stones,
and they did have to get him off the submarine,
sort of halfway through the mission.
And they-
- They fired him out of the torpedo.
- Basically, that might have been an option
because what they ended up doing
was putting up a bit of the submarine out of the water
for him to be collected from it
while keeping the main hull underneath.
- And they didn't know, like,
none of the crew knew what they were doing, did they?
Until they were out at sea, under sea.
There was just their captain captain beach.
It was quite nice giving it with sandblast.
- Amazing.
- Yeah.
- And giving it, they were at sea.
What's the sea surrounded by?
The beach.
- Yeah, and it's got a beach under it, arguably, as well.
- Well, let's discuss that, shall we?
- Where is the beach?
I don't want to go on your package beach holiday.
- Yeah, exactly.
I don't want to go on the picnic on the beach.
Everyone, get your scuba gear on.
But yeah, he didn't tell the crew
until they were out seeing underwater.
And I think the crew had just been told
to prepare to be away a little bit longer than usual.
And then they're going around the world.
- Yeah, they were told to get all the tax details in order
'cause it was going to go over the tax year
while they were away.
- Really?
- So they're like, whatever you do,
make sure you pay your tax
because you're not going to be back in time for it.
- It's a good excuse, though.
It's a very good excuse.
I love really like this.
So the submarines these days,
nuclear ones have their own way of making air on board.
But this one didn't have that capacity
'cause it was an early nuclear sub.
It had to have its own,
it had to have a snorkel, basically.
It would stick up the periscope and go,
(gasps)
and then go back down again every night.
- I actually, honestly,
this might just be a lying spot for me,
but I didn't realize what a nuclear submarine was.
I thought a nuclear submarine was a submarine
that had nuclear bombs on it.
I think because the British tried to once are,
that's why I thought they all were.
- I just want to say the missiles are tried
at the submarines of Vanguard.
Sorry.
- Sure.
- But yeah, no,
will it can be a sub with nuclear missiles on board?
- It can be, but by definition,
a nuclear submarine is something
which is powered by a nuclear reactor.
And what that means is you can just stay under water
for way longer,
and these days you can make your own oxygen
using the nuclear reactor
by taking in the sea water,
separating the hydrogen and oxygen,
and that means you could stay under water
for months and years.
- Right. - It's so cool.
- There are various problems
with the fact that we can now have submarines
under water forever, essentially.
There are various reasons why you can't do that.
So one of which is like all your clothes
get so dirty in the end, you run out
and people get claustrophobic and upset.
And another is rubbish.
I didn't know what they did with rubbish.
- Oh, on this? - On submarines.
- Oh, okay, yeah. - On sort of all submarines now,
they bring on board lots of metal sheets,
and then they have a special machine on board
that turns the sheets into a cylinder to be a bin,
'cause obviously if they just brought on loads of bins,
they take up too much space.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So then they throw-- - Space is in a premium, yeah.
- Space is a premium.
And then the bins all get secured
once they're filled with rubbish,
and then they just jettison them out of the submarine
with weights on them to take them to the bottom of the sea.
- To the bottom of the sea. - To the beach.
- To the beach! (laughing)
- The people sunbathing down there are pissed off about it.
- That's crazy, 'cause the whole point of a submarine
is that, I mean, the whole game of being in a submarine
is that you're being quiet and undetectable,
and enormous efforts are gone to
to make submarines quiet and undetectable,
but if they're just pooing out metal bins wherever they go.
- But you're not gonna see it.
- The ocean is big, Andy.
- No, I know, but the whole thing is,
I mean, the amazing lengths they go to not to be spotted.
- Well then, can I just say about the bins?
Given that you've raised the issue.
- Oh my God, you sound like my neighbors.
- What day do they go out again, is it?
- It's Tuesday this week, it's a bank holiday.
(laughing)
Some people on submarines say that they're so careful
about not drawing attention to themselves
that eggs, old eggs they haven't eaten,
are pre-broken before they're put
in the trash disposal unit,
because if they broke after being released,
they would generate enough sound
that they would be detectable.
- What?
That's how sensitive some other submarines are to noise.
- Really? - Really?
- Other submarines are constantly, yeah,
they don't hear an egg break.
They absolutely get so quiet down there.
- I've just, it's not that quiet under the water.
There's tons of animals down there.
- It's pretty noisy, it's a lot.
How about the engine running the submarine?
What are they doing about that?
- That's very heavily buffered.
- They put, you know, the egg boxes,
they put them around them.
(laughing)
- No, it is not how quiet they are.
And so for example, bubbles.
- Oh yeah?
- They put the bubbles through a diffuser
to spread them out before they release them.
- Oh wow.
- 'Cause otherwise there's a big plume of bubbles
at the surface, very obvious.
Oh, there's a submarine down there.
- Is that like, if you feel a big fart coming
and you somehow managed to let it go out
in a very slow little--
- It's exactly like that.
And spies, MI5 spies are trained to do that.
(laughing)
Just in case.
- They're the only ships that fly Jolly Rogers,
which I should have actually phrased as,
what flies a Jolly Roger?
- Submarines.
- I've screwed it up now, yeah,
but if you hadn't done the research
and I hadn't just said that, what would you have said?
- I've known that for years.
- Okay, but if you weren't a QI researcher.
- I just can't imagine the world where I would think.
(laughing)
I don't know that right now.
- I have a question.
- Yeah.
- Would be quite soggy.
(laughing)
- Kind of fly a flag under water.
- That's a good point.
They display it flattened.
I guess they fly it when they come up in triumph.
So I think traditionally if they've had a triumphant
a sojourn, what do you call it, expedition?
- Sojourn.
- I don't think they call it sojourn, yeah.
(laughing)
I think they're pretty sure it most was.
They go, "Subs, you're going on a sojourn
"into the Baltic Sea now."
- It's amazing.
There's no space on the submarine
'cause most people are wearing crevats.
The number of cigarette holders you have to have on board.
It just takes up loads of space.
- And then the actual battle itself
is called a box social.
(laughing)
- Whatever they're called, mission.
- Yeah, good, mission.
- They, when you come back and you've had a good one,
you have the, you fly it.
Fly the Jolly Roger.
- If you've sunk somebody else.
- I think if you've sunk someone else,
but now I think they quite often do it
'cause sinkings happen very rarely these days.
And it's because it's a like middle finger
to firstly Lord Admiral Sir Arthur Wilson
who complained in 1901.
As I'm sure you'll remember that submarines
were underhanded, unfair and damned un-English.
And then in 1914 someone sunk someone else in the war,
the great one.
And they came back flying the Jolly Roger to say,
"Screw you.
"You think we're underhand and piratee."
That's what we've done.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Interesting.
There's so many correspondence in the fish inbox,
fin box about nuclear submarines.
Almost all our listeners seem to be on nuclear submarines.
It's stunning.
- I didn't know the wifi was that good down there.
Amazing.
- Yeah.
- They must pre-download.
(laughing)
- Good point, yeah.
- Take a plunge.
- Yeah.
- What are they telling us?
- Okay, well.
- State secrets.
- We've got some secret correspondence actually.
Tim, I'll say Tim W writes.
It's okay 'cause his friend's brother
is learning to operate a nuclear submarine,
but you should not flush the loo at sea.
Why?
- Well, there was once a U-boat that was sunk
because they flushed, it was kernel-slit.
- That's it.
- Yes.
- And yeah, the whole thing went down.
- So that's a good reason not to do it.
But basically you shouldn't dump fresh water at sea.
- Okay.
- Because it has a different sonar signature to seawater.
It refracts sound waves differently.
And so it shows up as a massive blob.
- Oh, come on.
- Wow.
- It gives you away.
- And it just keeps samples of different ocean water
that they are traveling in.
- 'Cause space.
- That gets put into the system whenever there's.
- Space is limited.
No, that's a good idea.
That's a really good idea.
- Well, it's actually, it's quite interesting.
I didn't realize this about oceans.
This story of the submarine going around the world
has taught me this, that four days after
they were thought to be a sea monster in the Philippines,
they were going in the Lombok Strait
and then they were making their way into the Indian Ocean.
And then out of nowhere, they plunged
from periscope depth height to 125 feet in 40 seconds,
because the density of the saltwater is different
in the Indian Ocean than it is to the Lombok Strait
that they were coming through.
- Hang on, so it wasn't, it's not like there's a wall there
and they hit it and suddenly drop like a rice grain.
- I feel like it is, I think it is.
'Cause it came out of nowhere that they just plunged.
- I have a feeling that when you go from one ocean
to another, you do get those like quite solid blocks.
- Really?
- Yeah, because there's such different densities.
- They can't mix.
- Isn't that wild?
- It's crazy.
- I have a riddle for you.
- Yeah.
- The first people to successfully escape
from a submarine did it in 1851.
It was called La Plonge Marine Diver
and it was operated like a pedalo.
So there were three crew, two crew on the pedalo bit,
cycling along and then one bloke was captain.
Anyway, they sank in a test dive in Kiel Harbor
and they waited five hours for someone to rescue them.
No one came, there's an escape hatch,
but they can't push it open because they're underwater.
So the water pressure is too much.
And then the captain who was the inventor
and he was a guy called Wilhelm Bauer,
he grabbed a small valve, unscrewed it and whipped it open.
So water started coming in and his crewmates were like,
"What have you done?
"You've got mad, Wilhelm, you're going to kill us all."
Why did he do it?
- Is it the same reason as if you hold a straw,
the top of a straw and then put it in water,
the water stays in there because it releases pressure,
which means then there isn't pressure holding the door closed.
- Yes, 'cause what does the valve do?
It lets water in from the outside.
So as the water came in from the outside,
then it equalized the pressure.
So suddenly you've got water inside as well as out.
So there's a really horrible moment
where you all have to hold your breath
as the whole thing fills up with water
and you're suffocating to death
'cause the CO2 levels are so extreme.
And then suddenly it hit the pressure equality
and it went pop open and it fired them up onto the surface
in the middle of their funerals.
- What?
- Yeah, they were doing an impromptu service
'cause it had been over seven hours.
- Pretty quick, I'm sorry.
I would like more efforts to be made for me.
- He's been in that toilet 20 minutes,
should we have a beer or not?
- That doesn't make any sense, Adam.
- The ones with the new partners.
- They were having a service.
They assumed they were dead.
A little, not that the coffins weren't out yet.
- Have you seen the other way
that you can escape a submarine if it is sunk?
- You disguise yourself as an egg, I know this.
- No, what are the lifeboats of a submarine if it sinks?
- Like smaller submarines?
- Like torpedoes?
- No, it's a suit that you wear.
It's a life raft, but you're in the life raft.
- You are in the raft.
- And you have a picture homer working
in the nuclear power plant with that big helmet on,
but it's all fabric and he can see
through a window in his face.
It's, you could've just said picture a house chem suit
and there's no need to bring the Simpsons in.
That's another way, a more bland way
of giving the picture to the audience.
So you go out of the submarine and you slowly rise
and then you're just bobbing up there,
waiting to be rescued.
- But I think a lot of the time
if you're stuck, you're stuck, right?
- Yes, it's not soul proof this.
- Yeah, I think it's almost never that you can get out.
- We have one other person, right,
who actually was a sonar operator on a nuclear submarine.
This is so cool because with sonar, right,
what you can do is it lets you count the number
of blades on a propeller.
So you can guess what kind of ship something is
by your knowledge of the propeller.
- Because you fire your sonar at the propeller
and sometimes it hits and sometimes it misses.
- Pretty much.
And then you can make an educated guess as to the kind
of propeller and therefore what kind
of submarine you're observing.
So the whole game is to cover up the propeller
when you're in a public port for secrecy.
So no one knows how many blades you've got
on your propeller in case someone spots you.
And this, I should say it's a diesel electric submarine
as well, so it's slightly different.
But it's for sneaking around the Norwegian fjords
and for that kind of stuff.
And I love this, I'm just going to read this.
The snorkel has a valve at the top that automatically closes
if a wave goes over it, right?
The snorkel bit.
But then when that happens, the diesel engine suck loads
of the air from the rest of the submarine
and that means the air pressure drops.
So it really hurts everyone's ears on board.
But what that then means, if the air is moist,
the air spontaneously condenses
and it starts raining inside the submarine
because of the pressure changes that have happened.
So he says that's an amazing experience.
- Oh, wow.
On propellers, this is going from memory
so it might be wrong, but I think it's right.
There was an episode of, I think, Doctor Who
where they needed a submarine.
They got this model of submarine
and they looked at the propeller
and it was exactly the same as one of the most
secret submarines that the UK had.
And the UK defence were like, holy shit,
where did they get the designs from?
That's absolutely ridiculous.
And they brought these people into a questioning
and said, well, where did you get it from?
And it turned out they'd been to Woolworth's
and just bought a toy submarine and used it
and just by coincidence, it had the exact same
specifications as this British nuclear submarine.
- Oh my God.
- That's amazing.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the original
little mermaid production was almost delayed
because all of their underwater bubbles
got caught up in the Tiananmen Square incident.
- And tell me Dan, what exactly was the Tiananmen Square incident?
- It was a-
- For all of our global listeners.
- It was a sojourn by the Red Army.
- This was quite a surprising fact that the little mermaid,
which was the last entirely hand drawn
and hand coloured movie that Disney was producing,
decided that rather than photocopying
drawings of underwater bubbles,
they would have each individual bubble,
millions of them drawn by hand
and they couldn't do that on their own.
So they farmed that out to a company
that was called Pacific Rim in China.
- Great film, great film.
- And the offices of Pacific Rim happened to be
right next to Tiananmen Square
and when suddenly all the chaos broke out
in Tiananmen Square, all the protests
and all the military coming in,
the bubbles were still being drawn
and they were locked up in a safe there
and the producers didn't know
whether or not they were going to be able to get them out.
They didn't know how long this was going to last.
- And they're so fragile bubbles.
I mean, that will pop at the slightest tweak, won't it?
- Exactly, and it'll give away their location
if one goes off as well.
- If you look carefully, a lot of the bubbles
in the little mermaid are actually eggs
that have been just up to the user then, yeah, yeah.
But they did manage to get them out of the building.
They got them onto a ship.
So it's quite interesting there to ship
their bubbles back over to the States
and then they made it into the film, but it's, yeah.
- So if you look at the film,
so I was watching lots of clips, and once you know this,
there are shed loads of bubbles.
Every time they move, there's bubbles all over the shop.
- To be honest, like that's one of the best things
about the movie is the way they animated the water.
- Yeah, it's very good.
And it would have been worse, I think,
if they had done the photocopying.
- Agreed, agreed.
- 'Cause it was quite interesting.
So it's the Xerox process they called it,
which is a bit like photocopying,
but for animation and for film.
And they should have used that
'cause that's what people had been using.
I think the last film to use the hand-drawn method
was Sleeping Beauty, which was ages before that.
But when you photocopy stuff, it gives it a black outline.
And this was so interesting
because if you watch any Disney film
that was Sleeping Beauty in before,
so like Sleeping Beauty, Snow White, Pinocchio, Bambi,
there's no black lines around the cartoons.
So they're all like realistic.
Like I'm wearing a yellow jumper.
There's no black line around it.
There's just yellow jumper, then air.
And that's if you watch Sleeping Beauty, you'll see that.
Every film after that has black lines around the cartoon.
So they look more cartoon-y and less realistic.
And if you do want to sound like a big old snob,
you can just say is a very inferior period
of animation for Disney before they fixed it.
And sweetly, that was for Beauty and the Beast.
They brought the beauty back.
- The co-director of The Little Mermaid, John Musker, said,
'cause he was interviewed about the bubble thing.
And he said, "Yeah, no, we cared about the guy
"in front of the tank and that democracy might take root there.
"But we were wondering, what's going on with our bubbles?"
(laughing)
- In the next paragraph, he reveals he was joking.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
'Cause this was an incident where,
well, there was loads of protests in China,
pro-democracy protests,
and the Chinese government went in and killed a lot of people.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
James and I, you and I met Kate Adie,
who was there at the time. - I am.
- And the footage, The Little Mermaid premiere.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- She's always been heart-hitting, but I had no idea.
Right in the thick of it.
- Yeah, she's bubble-obsessed.
She was there, and the footage that was taken,
I think James, am I right in saying it's particularly
the footage of the man standing in front of the tank,
she had to get that back to a British embassy,
and she had some Chinese guards trying to take the camera,
at reals offer, so that she couldn't get through.
So she ended up kicking one of them in the nuts
and climbing over a wall in order to get into safety.
And yeah, so that's how we have the footage.
It was Kate Adie. - Oh, wow.
I didn't know that.
- I believe that's right.
It's certainly what she told us, yeah.
- Just a fact for Dan, about that,
the Simpsons, they have an episode where they go to China,
and in the middle of it, there is a picture on Tiananmen Square,
it says Tiananmen Square, on this site in 1989,
nothing happened, which is obviously about the fact
that references to it are banned in China,
but then Disney decided to omit that episode of The Simpsons,
so you can't watch that in China anyway.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- What's the Disney film that they made about Mermaid?
- Little Mermaid, Andy.
- Uh-uh.
(laughing)
- The first Disney film about a mermaid was Splash.
- You didn't say, you didn't set a specify first.
- Yeah, you didn't.
- You just said, what's the film they made?
- Oh, what was the first one?
It was Splash.
- Daryl Hanna.
- Daryl Hanna, and falling in love with Tom Hanks.
Who wouldn't?
- Walking out of the water with her bum out.
- Yeah.
- How it was a teenager when that came out.
- That must have been formative.
- I think they've re-edited it,
so she's got longer hair now.
So I'm afraid, James, the next time you--
- Really?
- You want to see Daryl Hanna's bum,
you'll have to do it some other way, basically.
Because, yeah, there's a waste to do that
on the internet these days.
I don't believe so.
No, yeah, so they made Splash way before
they made The Little Mermaid, like five years before.
They were trying to make films for grown-ups,
and this was their first one.
You know, she's a mermaid, Tom Hanks is a man,
and they fall for each other.
- But we've all seen Splash.
- It's the story of The Little Mermaid.
- I can't believe you're leading with that,
rather than the fact you just dropped in
that they've extended Daryl Hanna's hair
in the modern version to cover her bum.
- Oh, they didn't give her a hairy bum, they extended.
(laughing)
I misunderstood.
- You didn't say which hair they extended in best.
- Yeah, they've extended her back hair.
(laughing)
- Yeah, they've extended her bum hair,
and then they plait it into her head.
- Oh, God.
- The British Board of Film Classification
have some things to say about The Little Mermaid.
In the Additional Issues section of the website,
it says, "In one scene, a female character
"comically shakes her bottom,
"while singing about the importance of body language
"in attracting a man."
- Hmm.
And what's the issue there?
- Violet.
- Not woke.
(laughing)
I had a look at a lot of other Disney movies on the BBFC
to see what their additional issues are.
In Frozen, there is some very mild humor,
including reference to picking your nose and eating it.
(laughing)
- Which is offensive to children.
- It's on there.
- Wow.
- In Brave, there are moments of mild rude behavior,
such as a Scotsman burying his behind
by lifting his kilt.
(laughing)
- Well, they've extended his hair, so that's okay.
- And in Honey, I Struck the Kids,
which was also a Disney movie,
there are upsetting scenes when a friendly aunt is killed.
(laughing)
- So just beware.
- But this is someone's job.
- Wow.
'Cause there are those terrific Christian websites
which do this kind of forensic detail.
- Well, this is on the BBFC.
- Wow.
- I quite like how they did Ariel's whole look,
'cause Daryl Hannah played a part
in how Ariel looked as well.
- So she is the little mermaid, right?
- Yeah, so Ariel is the little mermaid.
Splash had come out,
and so they changed her hair color,
Ariel's hair color to red,
because the original hair color was too similar
to Daryl Hannah's.
So that had a very immediate influence on their movie.
The actress, Alyssa Milano, was the face model for Ariel.
There was a different body model who they had come in,
who was a comedian improviser,
who came in and would do all the scenes.
So you can see the footage of them doing the scenes,
so all the body movements were equaled.
- Is that Sherry Stoner?
- Sherry Stoner.
- Well, there are hardly any people alive
with the body of the little mermaid, aren't there?
(laughing)
There was actually very little competition for that.
- You're right, there is half of the body.
- A lot of her material as a stand-up
is about the fact that she has a massive tail.
(laughing)
- Yeah, exactly.
But the most interesting one is the hair
and how it moves in the water.
And that was inspired by the Space Shuttle astronaut,
Sally Ride.
They looked at her hair in zero gravity
to create the water look that they needed.
So yeah.
- Someone who gets a lot of shit is Sebastian
and the little mermaid.
- The crab.
- Yeah.
- The friendly Jamaican crab.
- Oh.
- Under the sea.
- What's Sebastian's accent?
- Jamaica.
- Incorrect.
- Caribbean.
- Well, I mean, you just broadened it.
So it's not fair.
(laughing)
So Sebastian, he was originally gonna be called Clarence
and he was gonna be like a posh English guy.
And they made a good move.
'Cause you can imagine he was really strict,
that Zazu type character.
You can imagine why they wanted to do that.
- Rowan Atkinson style voice.
- Exactly.
And then they thought, let's make him more fun.
So they decided to make him Jamaican.
But then they found the person to play him, Samuel E. Wright,
who'd just been in a film playing Dizzy Gillespie.
And Samuel E. Wright couldn't do a Jamaican accent,
but he could do a Trinidadian accent.
So actually, tell everyone you know,
he doesn't speak with a Jamaican accent.
- That's really interesting.
- He speaks with a Trinidadian accent.
- Because a few years later, when they made Cool Runnings,
they brought in these four Jamaican actors.
And they said, okay, can you do these lines?
And they said, well, you don't sound Jamaican.
And they're like, well, we actually are Jamaican.
This is how we talk.
And they're like, no, no, we need you to sound
like the crab from The Little Mermaid.
- No way!
James, we've pieced it together.
- It's amazing.
The producer basically said,
if you don't sound like Sebastian, I'm gonna get fired.
And so they all put on these kind of like fake Jamaican accents.
- That's amazing.
- That's bizarre.
- Wow.
- Okay, so the reason that the crab was made Jamaican,
let's say Jamaican, despite the accent,
was the songwriters were working literally
in the room next door to the animators.
And each other were influencing
how the movie was going along.
And one of the songwriters came in
and said to the filmmakers,
tell me about Sebastian the crab.
They said he's this British posh guy.
They said, can you make him something more Caribbean?
Can you make him Jamaican?
Because I think this song under the sea
will be great as like a Calypso-style song.
And the accent will go great with that.
And they changed it for that reason
'cause they were working in tandem together.
- So if you find a VHS of The Little Mermaid
and it has a drawing of the penis on the cover,
could be worth up to 30,000 pounds.
- Really?
- And it doesn't work if you just get one
and get it right on yourself.
- Is that true? - This is true.
- I thought this was sort of urban myth.
- There are mythy parts about it.
So there's a guy called Bill Morrison
who was drawing all the artwork,
a little mermaid who's doing all the different things.
And they said, can you do the VHS?
And they said it really last minute
and it was the middle of the night
and his deadline was just coming up there.
And he just sort of scribbled something together.
And it had to look like this sort of castle
in the background.
And castles have turrets.
And turrets can look phallic sometimes
if you're not concentrating.
- Your penises all have cretolations.
- Yeah.
- Yes, they do.
- Okay.
- How do you think we fire arrows out of them?
(laughing)
- When do you think the boiling oil comes from?
So he rushed to do it and then he made this thing
and no one noticed it for ages.
- So was it deliberate?
- No, no, that's the thing.
- It was just, yeah.
- The myth goes that it's some pissed off employee of Disney
who put a penis in there to piss everyone off.
In actual fact, it was this guy who was doing his best
and just happened to accidentally draw a penis
in the thing.
And then it basically came about that someone noticed it
once it had already been imprinted
and Disney were furious.
(laughing)
They're not really so relaxed about this kind of thing.
They said, if we find out who did that,
they're never gonna work for us again.
And this guy's company was,
this was most of their work doing stuff for Disney.
So in the end, you either kind of pretend
that you don't know anything about it
or you say, look, it was us, but it was an accident.
And that's what they did.
And eventually Disney sort of realized that they were,
it was an accident and they carried into it.
- Imagine the Dick Mountain ride at Disneyland.
(laughing)
- Very, very, very steep up.
Very, very, very steep down the other side.
- Good.
- And Bill Morrison won for Dan.
He left this company and went to work for the Simpsons
where he did some drawing for them.
So there you go.
- Is that why Homer Simpson's head
also looks like a penis?
(laughing)
- This was about bubbles in "The Little Mermaid"
in "Frozen", which is another princess movie.
Obviously not bubbles, but snow.
Snowflake, stuff like that.
And there is a thing down which I'm sure you know about
called the "Diatlov Pass" incident.
It's a conspiracy theory thing
about a load of kids who went walking
just outside of Katrinberg.
- And disappeared, doesn't mean anything.
- They disappeared and we never know what happened to them.
And last year, thanks to "Frozen",
we might have found out what happened to them.
And that's because the technology they used
to make the snow in "Frozen" was so amazing,
like the computer programs,
that you could use that to work out
what happens with avalanches.
There was a scientist called Johann Gaum,
who was from the Snow Avalanche Simulation Laboratory
in Switzerland.
And he saw "Frozen" and he thought,
"What they're doing is amazing."
And he went over and he said,
"Can I borrow your technology
"to show what happens with avalanches?"
And he tried it and using the lie of the land
in "Diatlov" and stuff like that,
he showed that it was possible
that these kids might have been taken away by an avalanche
as opposed to a Yeti or aliens
or whatever everyone else thought.
- Wow. - And that was "Frozen".
- That was "Frozen" that did it.
- 'Cause I thought you were gonna say
the other sort of wild theory about "Frozen"
is the reason that that title was picked for the movie
was to stop everyone from spreading the idea
that Disney was "Frozen" cryogenically.
So if you went on Google
and you put Disney, "Frozen",
you get the movie now as opposed to this-
- Walt Disney's head.
- Walt Disney's head has been-
- That's so cryogenically. - "Frozen" cryogenically, yeah.
That is a theory out there.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that the longest road tunnel in the world
is so long that the builders recruited a team of psychologists
to stop people crashing halfway through.
So this is a tunnel called the Ladal Tunnel in Norway,
and it is 24 kilometers long.
So what's that, 17, 18 miles?
It's quite, it's long.
- Yeah, it's the longest.
- It's been over 25 years now,
and it helps people drive between Oslo and Bergen.
And it's partly because Norway is so crinkly,
and it's hard to get around,
and the perilous crossing the mountain path is in winter.
So you either fly little distances in small planes,
which is a big way of getting around there,
or you drive, but this allows you to drive much straight up
'cause you're in a tunnel.
That's how tunnels work.
- Yeah, it helps goods get through as well.
- Completely, yeah, yeah, all of that.
So it was a very impressive engineering project, but--
- Do we know the effect of the psychologist,
like what they said, and what happened?
- Yeah, that's the important part there.
- Yeah, that's what they did.
They were consulted on how people can drive through
this tunnel and not go crackers,
because it's 20 minutes of the same lighting,
the same panels passing you, it's hypnotic, you're driving.
- I'm already going crackers just from you saying that.
- You've crashed into the wall, James, there we go,
you've hit the wall.
- And no radio signal.
Can't get radio forward in the middle of a tunnel, can you?
- Exactly. - Always the annoying thing
about tunnels. - That's true.
- It's like being in a nuclear submarine, basically.
- You should pre-download before you go through the tunnel.
- Pre-download before you go through.
- You've got to talk about this pre-download thing.
- So the shrinks, basically,
they were a crack team of shrinks were called in and said,
"Oh, yes."
And they said, they said--
- They were the people who were originally cast
in the place of Astrid.
- Yeah, they were, and they said,
"Well, you've got to break it up for people.
You've got to make it feel more varied."
- I'll be honest, Andy, I think,
without any psychological training,
I reckon breaking things up
so people don't get bored is pretty root one, isn't it?
- Like this bit of me speaking.
And you've just helped to do that
by breaking it up so that people at home
haven't crashed themselves.
- That's what this podcast is, is us breaking up
Andy's monotonous words for the listener.
- Okay, that's enough, Anna.
Okay, let's do another five colloases, Andy.
- Thank you.
- So basically, there are these mountain caves,
as they get called, strategically placed along.
And every five minutes, you get to another mountain cave.
The lighting all changes completely.
The road opens out and it looks like you're driving into
a sort of beautiful mountain pass.
It looks like there's daylight above you.
It's really gorgeous.
- I think it looks quite tri--
I would feel like the drugs had kicked in
as soon as I got to certain bits of it.
It's like avatar in there, all of a sudden.
- It is a bit.
- It's like you're in an aquarium,
like you're in the actual water with it surrounding you.
It's like mountainous-y dark blue, trippy as hell.
- I would want like, 'cause you're expecting a tunnel.
I'd go into that tunnel
and suddenly you're not really in a tunnel anymore.
I agree with that and I would freak the fuck out of me.
- You've had a lot of tunnel already.
You're filled to the back teeth with tunnel.
What you want is a bit of variety.
I mean, I don't think people frequently go do
lally halfway along a tunnel, so it clearly works.
- It is a good idea.
And I think one of the reasons it's a good idea,
them doing this,
is 'cause for the longest road tunnel in the world,
not many vehicles drive through it.
So a thousand vehicles a day.
So basically the chances are you're gonna be driving through
completely on your own,
which is what would freak you out, right?
Like if you're going behind a bunch of cars, it's fine.
- Have you ever been driving in like a place
which is so the same that you think maybe I have died?
- Yes, I have.
- I have done that.
- Oh my God.
- I was driving down the coast of Croatia
and there's all these inlets.
And you kind of go on an inlet
and you come background again and you drive for a bit
and you have another inlet and another inlet
and another inlet and they're almost all identical.
And like after about two hours of that,
you're just like, maybe I have died.
Maybe one of these times I missed the corner.
I was doing this forever.
- It's fractal.
- Yeah.
- Do you have that thing when you're driving
where you sort of come to and you realize,
"Oh, I just drove half an hour there."
You know, and then your conscious mind
reasserts yourself and you're like,
"Oh, and you've got a bloodied knife next to you
"on the outside of the seat."
And there's bags full of money in the boot.
- But not that bag.
Oh no.
I once, in fact, more than once
when I worked in an office as an accountant
would sort of come to at the desk
and not remember how I got there.
Like as in I just sort of, I got up,
got out of the house, got dressed,
drive the car all the way to the office,
sat down, started work without even realizing,
"Yeah, yeah, promise, yeah."
- Yeah, I see that.
Have you ever woken up midway through a fact on fish?
(laughing)
- I'm hopeful it might happen eventually on this.
It's called highway hypnosis.
And people noticed it all the way back to 1921
when it was called road hypnotism.
And basically what it is, is even when you're looking
at something, your eyes are making very slight movements
all the time.
Like your eyes are always like darting this way
and that and whatever.
And normally they're a response to something
that's happening outside as a bird go past or whatever.
But what happens when you're driving for ages
is your eyes start to go in this sort of predetermined pattern.
They start, they're still moving,
but they move left and right, then up, then down,
then left, then right, then up, then down and whatever.
And the thing is they don't really alert the brain properly.
The brain starts thinking that not really
anything is happening.
And then you start losing concentration.
- So you should roll your eyes
round and around and around.
- Well, you should take a break.
- Or have something, or watch something on your phone.
That's another.
(all laughing)
- As long as you pre-downloaded it though,
that's the impact of that.
- This tunnel, in 2000, I love this,
someone got married in the middle of the Laerdal tunnel.
Did you read this?
- No.
- It was a young couple, young Norwegian couple.
And the groom was called Ronny Rinder.
And he said that his mother-in-law had attended the wedding,
but she had been slightly skeptical about it.
And I just love this.
He said, "She's scared of two things, dogs and tunnels.
"We've recently bought two Alsatians,
"and now we've got married in the tunnel."
(all laughing)
And I would say maybe the psychologist shouldn't.
- Another thing they have in this tunnel
is a rumble strip in the middle of the road.
- Okay.
- And the idea is if you're driving along,
you slightly fear off to the middle.
You hear it rumble, it wakes you up.
These things were invented in 1955
by a guy called Harold Griffin.
And they were originally called Singing Shoulders.
(all laughing)
- That's better.
- But they caused a 44% reduction
on head-on fatal crashes if you have them on a road.
These are US figures.
- Wow.
- They should be the same in most countries.
- So head-on collisions are hugely caused
by falling asleep or losing concentration.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- Right.
- And there are large areas of Michigan
with no rumble strips.
So most places in America,
they have to have them now on highways,
but there are large areas of Michigan
with no rumble strips.
Po-kwa, why?
- Ooh.
- There's no double lane roads.
- That's good, in Michigan.
- No.
- They have to transport something
which is delicate, like eggs, to the market.
And if they hit the rumble strips,
they break all the eggs.
- All of that eggs for you.
- Exactly.
- And they're happy to have a full head-on collision
as long as they don't break a few eggs.
- That actually weirdly, more eggs get lost
by the rumble strips than in the full-on collision.
- Yeah.
- No, it's a certain group of people
who didn't want them to.
- The Amish.
- Who are the Amish?
(laughing)
- The Amish.
- Or Amish.
- I've never, in my knowledge, called the Amish.
- Really?
Do they not like rumble strips?
- It's the horses.
The horses don't like them
and they refuse to cross rumble strips
'cause it makes them hard to set their feet down
'cause of the way that they're...
- Really?
- You can't step over them.
- Not that broad.
- Yeah, but the horses just don't like it.
So, there are certain areas.
- They didn't even leave 'cause they didn't have a...
(laughing)
I was trying to do a rumble horse neck.
- That was really good.
- Didn't come out right, sorry.
- It weren't to be, you saw it, though.
What you're doing with your lips there.
- So, in any location in Michigan
where horse-drawn buggies utilise the roadway,
you're not supposed to use shoulder corrugations,
which is what they call them,
unless a crash history exists.
- Right.
London has a new tunnel.
In the week we record this.
- No.
- Yeah.
Have you guys been reading about the Silver Town Tunnel?
- No.
- Oh, it's so good.
It's great.
It's just next to the Blackwall Tunnel,
which is very, very traffic-y tunnel in London, basically.
It has to shut down, I think, 700 times a year.
It gets shut down 'cause the traffic just gets too crazy.
So, they've just opened another tunnel next to it,
but bikes can't go along it because it's for cars.
So, they're running a sort of bike bus for it.
But, it's amazing how they built it.
So, you know, TBMs, tunnel boring machines?
- Okay.
- The one that built this tunnel was called Jill,
after Jill Weiner,
who was London's first female bus driver.
- Okay.
- And they wanted two tunnels, right?
'Cause it's really big.
Stop me awning, James.
(laughing)
They wanted two big tunnels, right?
Normally, it's really hard to build two tunnels
with the same machine,
'cause turning it round down there is a bastard.
You know, it's really difficult.
- So, reverse, just get some wing mirrors on there.
- Or don't they famously come out the other side?
- Didn't they, sorry to interrupt,
but for the channel tunnel,
I think the boring machines, they just kept boring down.
- They sometimes do.
- And they buried them under the ground.
- Sometimes they do, yeah.
So, this one, they wanted to use it again.
They wanted to get good use out of this machine,
'cause it's a massive factory.
Like, it's huge underground thing.
So, they put it, I just love this, on nitrogen skates.
They put it on compressed nitrogen.
Like, some skates would rest on compressed nitrogen,
like a hovercraft.
And that allowed them to turn it round
in a special underground chamber.
And then go back the other way.
- They must have had to build a massive underground chamber.
I mean, 'cause these things are up to 170 meters long.
- So, I don't know what that chamber was like,
but it's crazy.
- Yeah, they are awesome.
And I think they do like to reuse them now.
They break up them up into little parts.
'Cause every one is like the width of the tunnel
that's specifically made for that one tunnel.
So, you can't really reuse the whole thing,
but you can take it apart and use it.
But yeah, in the olden days, they did random shit with it.
Like, as you say, in the channel tunnel,
one of them was just like buried.
Another one in 2004 was--
- So great.
I can't wait for archaeologists to find that.
That's going to be a great day for them.
- So, they literally just changed its directions
and it bore its way down to the bottom of the--
- I think it's going to come out in Australia sometime soon.
(all laughing)
- It's going to split the world in half.
- I think it actually went into more of a lay-by.
- Oh, it is buried on the--
- Yeah, and then they bricked it.
They bricked it up.
But it reminds me of that really sad Thomas Atank engine episode
where they bricked one of the engines in.
- Henry.
- Henry, he's very sad.
- Why'd they do that?
- He's been naughty.
- Oh, wow.
- He won't come out in the rain.
Anyway, we'll save that.
But there was another one in 2004.
One of the TBMs using the channel tunnel was sold on eBay.
There were obviously loads of prank bids,
but then it was actually sold for 39,999 pounds.
- What was posted in package then?
- That's such a good question, Dan.
You've hit the nail on the head.
I never thought I'd say this,
but if only the buyer had been as smart as you are,
'cause he bought it and he signed the contract
and everything and then he got an email from him
who was called Steddenum.
- Oh, no.
- Guess how much it was gonna cost him to collect it?
- I mean, an insane amount of money.
So he paid how much for the thing?
- He paid 40 grand.
- Which is a bargain.
Is it for a big tunnel machine?
Yeah, second hand.
Like that's a--
- Vintage.
- That's a really nice car, second hand, you know what I mean?
- Yeah.
- Or you get a machine that could dig a channel.
- I don't think they're that road worthy, but yeah.
- Okay, what was--
- Cost a quarter of a million pounds to move it.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- And can you back out on that sale?
Sometimes they're really strict on eBay about--
- You can't back out on the tunnel even.
You can't do anything.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that walking backwards
is healthier than walking forwards.
- Wow.
- With some caveats, like, you know,
don't do it at Russia on a main road.
It's for a railway tunnel.
(laughing)
- Railway tunnel.
This is just sort of a raft of stuff that's come out
in the last 20 years, I guess,
about the various advantages.
Most crucially, burns more calories.
So like the metabolic cost of walking backwards
seems to be significantly higher.
I think the first study was in 1995 that found this
and it found that oxygen intake and heart rate
of the various, I think it was 27 subjects,
increased between 38 and 119% walking backwards
compared to walking forwards.
- Okay, I have to say, I'm not massively surprised by that
given that for two million years
we've been evolving to walk forwards.
Like, doing something hard is harder
than doing something easy.
- I agree.
- It's like doing press-ups constantly
is harder than just lying there.
But that's because I'm involved with just lying there.
- You might as well say that walking like a kangaroo
is healthier than walking like a human.
(laughing)
- Basically, doing anything really difficult
that feels unnatural is better for you.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- I think so a lot of this stuff makes kind of perfect sense
because it's doing stuff that you're not used to doing, right?
So this is why it's often used in rehabilitation
for things like osteoarthritis
because let's say you've got knee problems
'cause you put too much pressure on your knees,
you go for runs, you're walking on tarmac a lot,
you start walking backwards,
suddenly you're putting pressure on different parts
that your quads are taking a lot more pressure
or if you've got plantar fasciitis in your heels,
oh my God, it's a pain, isn't it?
I feel for you.
But if you start walking backwards,
then you don't have such an impact on your heels.
- Did anyone do some walking backwards for this?
I did 15 minutes in my garden.
- Did you?
- 15 minutes, that's a lot.
- Yeah, well, I couldn't be bothered doing any research.
- I meant to say you look fantastic today.
- Thank you, well, you should see my heels.
(laughing)
- So how was it?
- Well, to be honest, I didn't really see much difference
in the 15 minutes I did.
Apart from, I would say it works slightly different muscles
in my legs, like my Achilles probably,
and my calf that normally wouldn't feel it
after 15 minutes walk.
I could feel it after.
- Also, your neighbors all think you're a witch now?
- Yeah.
- I'm no doubt.
(laughing)
- I did, because quite a lot of my neighbors' houses
overlook my garden.
And I didn't think, they probably think I'm a bit weird.
Yeah, they already know.
- Yeah, I'm sure you've done worse things in that garden.
(laughing)
- Where did those bags of money come from?
But it's quite good.
I read a few articles where it said that backwards running,
this post-book to backwards walking is quite good
in warming up if you're an athlete,
because it uses slightly different joints and tendons
as you would normally do.
Also, there was another person, an orthopedic specialist
called Nicole Hass, who in one of the papers she said,
that actually one of the main things is,
it's using your brain in a slightly different way.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause like one of the things you're doing quite a lot
when you're walking backwards, as I know,
is working out where everything is
and what you're not falling over.
'Cause my garden is not very big
and I had to do lots of laps of it to 15 minutes.
And all the time you're thinking,
where did I leave that barbecue?
- Yes, yes.
Well, next time you do it,
you should do what a man called Patrick Harmon did
when he took on a challenge to walk from San Francisco
to New York, which is he walked backwards,
but he had installed near the front of his chest
a car mirror so that he could see everything
that was behind him.
- I mean, it makes perfect sense, doesn't it?
- He said it was good for him.
So he did this in 1915?
- Yep.
- It took him about a year.
- Yeah, 290 days in total.
- About a year.
(laughing)
- A big chunk missing for the whole year.
- The bulk of a year.
(laughing)
- I'm really looking forward to going to your 60th birthday.
- Yeah, it's gonna be about 52.
(laughing)
- And he claimed that it had made his ankle so strong,
it would take a sledgehammer blow to sprain them.
So he clearly felt some kind of benefits.
- Yeah.
- It's interesting that he,
'cause he did that 1915, did you say?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause there was a guy called Pleny Wingo,
who he's the one in the Guinness World Record Book
because he walked 8,000 miles
from Santa Monica to Istanbul, so a bit further.
But I think he believed he was the first person
to come up with it.
- Twice as long, just when you say a bit further,
and almost a year.
- A bit further.
(laughing)
- Well, fact checker's striper today.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, more than actually, yeah.
- You don't want us doing down the backwards walkers,
do you?
They need to get there just as a--
- Some respect, please.
Pleny Wingo, yeah.
- He lost his business and--
- In the Great Depression.
So I'm so excited about it.
- We're gonna be seeing lots more
of this kind of great stuff soon.
(laughing)
So you're right, we're topical.
- Limber up.
He had the idea, 'cause he was listening to his daughter,
his 15 year old daughter,
her birthday party chatting to her friends saying,
everything that could ever be done has been done now,
'cause it was this age of stunts.
We've talked about flagpole sitting before,
everyone was sitting on flagpoles,
and we're crawling up mountains,
pushing peanuts up mountains with their noses.
And he said, "Not everything's been done.
"No one's ever walked backwards around the world."
And then he thought, "Bugger, now I've said that,
"I'll have to do it."
And he tried to do it, and he got as far as Turkey,
and then they kicked him out and told him to go home.
I don't think he did make his fortune.
It's very hard to tell.
- No, he didn't.
- It's pretty sure he didn't.
- He didn't.
- They said when he got to Turkey,
they said he had to leave the country for his own safety.
(laughing)
'Cause I think the idea was that people
were throwing things at him quite a lot.
- I'm surprised you got as far as that.
- Apparently, according to one article I read about him,
he was in New York City walking backwards,
and he agreed to walk backwards along the top ledge
of a 12 story building in return for money.
And then loads of people paid him to see him do this,
and he did it.
But the guy who was working with him
and collecting all the money off there,
onlookers just did a runner and took all his money off him.
- For the backwards runner.
- Well, if you're walking backwards,
it's hard to catch anyone, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- That's crazy.
- His wife left him, Mrs. Wingo.
- Oh no, I mean, I understand why she did it, but even so.
- But he was still walking backwards for decades.
So in 1976, he appeared on the Johnny Carson show,
one of these American talk shows saying,
"I'm doing it again!"
And he claimed he was gonna do another
sort of round the world thing.
That suggests that he didn't make his fortune
the first time.
- I don't think so.
- I think it does, sadly.
There is a profession who walked backwards
maybe more than any other.
And maybe, I'm not certain about this,
but it's a good, I think it's a good.
- Photographers?
- I don't know.
- Yeah, that's good.
- That's good content.
- I was reading a paper about sports people
and they said rugby league players,
handball athletes and soccer referees do a lot of baseball.
- Football referees is the one I saw.
- I think there's, is there not a famous one,
I think we might have even mentioned it before,
about at the White House,
it's people who are doing the tour guides,
they walk backwards forever.
- Pentagon, I think it was.
Yeah, where they have to memorize where the corner is
so that they can go around it.
Yeah. - Why?
- Is it so they keep an eye on people?
- Yeah.
- Oh.
- Just get the mirrors.
- Get the mirrors, exactly.
- But I've trained as a football referee
and for sure as part of the training,
they teach you how to run backwards well.
- Don't they?
- Yeah, or they don't teach you,
but they just say make sure you know how to run backwards.
(laughing)
- I used to do quite a lot, I'd say,
when I was like when I was a nipper.
- Yeah.
- I was running backwards or a referee.
- Running for the referee.
- Did a lot of, oh.
- Was that avoiding the wedgie as they chased you?
(laughing)
- Okay, okay, okay, you can't be wedgie.
- They could do a front wedgie.
- The front wedgie is horrible.
- It makes it look like a Disney tower.
(laughing)
- There's another group of people
who are becoming expert backward walkers in recent times,
and that is celebrities.
So Taylor Swift spends a lot of her time walking backwards
so that she can avoid the paparazzi taking photos of her.
- Is it so that they can't sell the photos
because they're trying to sell those photos
of her walking forward?
- Now, as in the paparazzi stood in one particular place
and you need to have your back to the paparazzo
so that they can't see your face.
I saw quite a recent news article
about her walking through the woods, right?
- Yeah, she went and did a whole mountain trail,
basically walking backwards
so that the paparazzi couldn't get shots of her.
- Back up ahead, she should do.
Back up ahead and hold for the eye.
- That's a good idea.
(laughing)
- But if someone's walking backwards,
so she's walking backwards
towards the paparazzi who were facing her.
- Let's say she's come out of the building,
there's paparazzi waiting outside.
She faces the other way to get in the car.
- But I would film that, and that's like...
- But it could be anyone.
It could be anyone with blonde hair.
- Oh, please.
I didn't know Taylor Swift asked anyone.
(laughing)
I wouldn't even recognize her face,
but there's an amazing woman called Justine Galloway.
I think we might have mentioned in our sports book
that we happened to write semi-recently.
She's a runner.
She's 44, and she used to run loads of marathons.
And then in 2011,
she was running her third Boston marathon,
and she got really good times.
And she suddenly her left leg
started staying up in the air too long,
sort of swung out to the left a bit,
and it just wasn't working properly.
And she basically got what is called runner's dystonia,
which is a bit like the yips in golf,
where you just suddenly kind of can't do it.
And within a few weeks, she couldn't run at all.
It's like this weird neurological issue
where your brain and your body will not connect at all.
And she was obviously devastating,
like running with her life.
And then she realized if she ran backwards, she was fine.
- Crazy.
- And now she's got the world record
for running a half marathon backwards.
- Does she do mirrors?
Or does she do?
- She does mirrors, yes.
- Does she, when you do a half marathon with her,
does she start at the end and go to the start?
She passes everyone halfway.
- Yeah, she always gets moaned down in the middle, so.
- So it is a competitive sport.
- Yeah, I mean, there are all sorts of records.
There aren't many full races of people running backwards,
but there's a guy called Aaron Yoda, who's the world's best.
- God hold her, he is.
- Runs backwards, speaks backwards.
(all laughing)
He's done a mile and five minutes, 54 seconds backwards,
which I'm quite sure is faster
than I could do a mile for four, for me, yeah, yeah.
- So walking backwards, right?
Imagine you're walking backwards
and stuff is happening in your peripheral vision.
Some people are better at noticing those things than others.
- Only if you're walking backwards?
- Only if you're walking backwards, yeah.
- Can we guess this?
- Is it like football, right?
- Scottish people.
- It's a class of people.
- I'd be a stud-ist if you went to that place.
- Is it a profession or a nationality?
- It's a hobby group.
- Oh, is that like birdwatchers or train spotters?
- Not them.
- Think of a hobby that slightly more normal people might do,
and the tunnel boring machine enthusiasts.
(all laughing)
Oh, what's a normal hobby?
It's something that cool people might do,
slightly more cool people than you.
It's people who play video games.
- Oh yeah, those jocks, those bloody jocks.
- So there was a study that was done.
- Are they cool?
Sorry, coming questions.
- I was just thinking cooler than boring enthusiasts.
- Oh, yeah.
- On a par for me.
- I actually was thinking,
I'd love to write a film script set on a tunnel boring machine.
I just think that'd be really cool.
- Like a really slow version of speed.
(all laughing)
- We gotta keep going at 0.25 miles an hour.
- It's gonna blow.
- So the thing is right,
they wanted to find out,
do people who play video games have better perception,
and especially people who play,
you know, like first person shooter games, okay?
So they tried that,
and they realized that actually,
people have equal perception.
If you, Andy, and someone who plays video games
are walking straight down a road,
then you equally can see things in your peripheral vision.
But for the people who play video games,
when you're going backwards,
they have much better perception.
And that's because in video games,
often these shooters, they are moving backwards.
Like when you move backwards on your joystick,
your character is so easy to do.
So they're seeing that quite often in their day-to-day hobby,
whereas we hardly ever see it,
'cause we hardly ever walk backwards.
That's cool, that's cool.
- I thought you were gonna say it
so that you had a peripheral view
on seeing whether or not your mom came in
to tell you to stop playing video games,
so you just built a better...
So video games are probably quite good.
(all laughing)
- Nature's joystick.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
- I'm on Instagram, on @Triberland, James.
- My Instagram is @NosageThingsJamesHarken.
- Andy.
- I'm on Blue Sky @AndrewHunterObe.
- Yeah, and if you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can go on Instagram to @NosageThingsafish,
Twitter @NosageThing, or email podcast.qr.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our website,
nosagethingsafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
You can get a link to merchandise to our live shows.
We've got a gig coming up in Sheffield in July.
Come see us there, or join Club Fish at a steal 2.99.
- While stocks last.
We have lots of bonus episodes up there.
Add free episodes as well if you want that.
Do check it out.
Otherwise, you just come back here next week.
We'll be back again with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)