(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode of Little Fish.
My name's Andrew Hunter Murray.
I'm joined by Dan Shriver and Anna Tijinsky
and we are here with some of your best facts
from the last seven days.
That's the whole intro.
- I like it.
- It's my first time and I'm wowed.
- I think Andy's very good at intros and that was a prime example.
- Well the outros are where I shine.
But anyway, let's get on, does anyone have an audience
fact they'd like to bring to the table?
- Yeah, I got one here, this is from Kauri Eaton
and this is my first Little Fish fact.
So it has to be really good, Kauri.
And it's the fact that up until 1999,
the state of Montana didn't have speed limit signs
along their highways.
The sign simply said, "Drive what is reasonable and prudent."
(laughing)
- I like that.
- Tree, the public like grown-ups.
And I'm sure they won't take the piss.
What kind of debate do you have with the cult
that's pulled you over when they don't think
that you have been driving?
- Well I think that's an interesting conversation, isn't it?
It was raining, but my time is very good.
I've been a hurry, I've only had one drink.
My wife is giving birth, so celebrating early.
- But every police car is followed by a philosopher car.
That's the nice thing, yes, right?
- I didn't talk about what is prudence.
- I wonder what the most unbelievable amount of excuses
were in one single car that was speeding.
A wife and labour, there were bees in the back.
- A brick fell on the accelerator.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Well you don't need excuses, there is no limit.
I've worked question, Kauri, the wording,
"Drive what is reasonable and prudent?"
- It's very cockney, it's London.
It's reasonable.
So I'm not sure that's exactly what they read,
but anyway, it's true, I've checked it.
And it was actually because there was a famous 55 mile
an hour speed limit in America.
What a snooze between the 70s and the 90s
because of the oil crisis.
- Oh really?
- So Nixon imposed, I know it could come again.
- Wow, look forward to that.
- Yes.
- Coming back.
- All electric car drivers will be allowed to go
at 300 miles an hour.
But then it was revoked in 1995
and Montana said, "Okay, we've forgotten how to do speed limits.
"Proper speed limits."
So we'll just say, "Drive however fast you like."
- Yeah, that's almost like if it was to do the gas,
it's drive at a patriotic speed.
One that will not disrupt the system around you.
Nice, very nice.
- Very nice.
- That's great car.
- Yeah, that's of another.
- Yeah, okay, well this one is from Mary Campbell,
who says, "Movie actor, Robert Redford,"
who was born in 1936,
was a Paul Barrow for liver eating Johnson,
a man who died in the year 1900.
And can we guess what he died of?
- I'm gonna have a punt at raw liver.
- Incorrect.
- Oh, yeah.
You've missed the bigger headline here,
which is that how was a man born in 1936,
bearing a man who died in 1900?
- Oh yeah, completely fast.
- I've got a guess.
- Guess it, long delayed funeral.
- It was a nightmare to organize, yeah.
- Absolutely.
- So you guess you have to come from a long way away, don't you?
- Exactly.
And then before you know, 45 years have passed, yeah.
The canopays, do you have liver?
Is that...
No, what it was is that this was quite a famous American.
This was a guy called John liver eating Johnston,
or Johnston, but he was really garrison.
So he was born garrison.
He changed his name to Johnston,
but then the newspapers misprinted his name as Johnston.
So he's sort of got three names.
I feel like we're focusing of the wrong element
of his name has already drilled out into it.
- Well, it's just a very confusing story
because this is one of those characters
who's sort of stuck in myth, you know?
He became famous because his obituary came out
and everyone found out about him,
but he didn't die for another 20 years
after his obituary came out.
- All right.
- Yes.
- Sorry, can we quickly talk about the liver eating thing?
I know this is elephant in the room.
- Okay, done.
This is the most confusing thing we could possibly introduce.
- It's really easy.
Okay, a man born in 1936,
buried a man who died in 1900,
whose name was either garrison Johnston or Johnston,
and he became famous in America 20 years before he died
because his obituary was released.
- Okay.
- What are you not getting?
- Nothing, nothing.
- Why was he famous?
- No further question.
- Okay.
So his obituary was accidentally released 20 years
before he died, and yes,
he wouldn't write an obituary for someone
unless they were already famous.
- That's not true because there are lots of people
when you read the times obituary's who you go,
wow, how did I never hear about this person?
They may have been famous in their own field.
- It's never someone who's just done nothing.
You never have the obituary,
big full page in the times, empty space.
- Absolutely.
- Born, lived, died.
So how'd he done anything?
- Yeah, I think John liver eating Johnston
had done something out of.
Yeah, he ate livers.
So this was...
- Because James edits this show and he's not on.
It's just incredible to see you laying this massive bear trap
for him so early on as well.
- He was an American frontiersman,
and he became famous because these myths
went around about him that he was killing
a lot of Native Americans of one particular tribe,
and it was in revenge of the fact
that they had murdered his wife.
And the idea was that he would kill them
and he would remove their liver.
And supposedly it was 300 of them that he'd done this with.
And this became a big myth about him
that kind of got spread around America.
- Was he liked or doesn't sound like a good?
- No, but also it's kind of a weird myth
because the interviewers and biographers have looked into it
and they say actually it was all myth
and actually he was friends with that tribe
and they shared liver with him from other animals,
so he was a good friend of theirs.
But he became particularly famous
because Robert Redford starred in a movie
about his life telling this story.
And at the time that that was happening,
there was a school, a middle school in America,
and the teacher was telling the story of this guy
who had died penniless and he died in an area of San Diego
where he was basically buried under a freeway.
But he'd said he'd love to be buried in the Rockies.
So there was a big push to have him re-buried
and as a result Robert Redford was a poor bearer.
- Because he'd played him in the film.
- Yeah, exactly.
- And he had to carry the coffin
from his original burial place to the Rockies.
- It's a long distance, yeah.
So what I said at the start, like long delayed funeral,
we could have just said yes to that.
- No, you can't just leave it at that, can you?
I mean, it was general enough that...
- No, it's fair enough.
Stunning, yeah.
- I still don't feel like we got to the bottom of it.
- Really, interesting.
- No, I do.
- Okay.
Here's one from John Lourish and John Rice.
I was talking with a friend who works
in the pool and technology industry.
She sells pool-related technology.
Okay, like swimming pool, the water pools.
She says one of their biggest clients
is Kerberg nuclear power station here in the Western Cape
of South Africa.
My fact is that Kerberg nuclear power station
uses kamikaze scuba rumbers to help clean the water
that's been used in the reactor.
So these are vacuum cleaners.
- Yeah.
- Water vacuum clean, wet vacuum cleaners,
'cause you get wet or dry ones, don't you?
- Yeah.
- And the filter units they have are unable to filter
out really small radioactive particles.
So these scuba diving underwater vacuum cleaners,
robots are sent in to just filter the water
and they're doomed because obviously
it's radioactive, they will break.
And apparently this is a really common solution
for nuclear reactor maintenance.
- Hang on, so they just clean as much as they possibly can
before they eventually expire?
- I know, and then they're radioactive
and then they have to be buried
with the radioactive waste.
- And Robert Redford always is the pool bear, right?
- Always.
(laughing)
- That's cool.
- Yeah, Selefield has a load of,
they found an old radioactive vacuum cleaner
that was buried at Selefield after an accident there.
- Yeah, it's quite, it's just a common thing.
It's like kitchen roll, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Once you use the kitchen roll,
you have to throw away the kitchen roll.
- No, I put it back on the preparation.
- It's so horrible.
- You sell the tape and it goes down here, yeah.
- Yeah, hang it up to dry.
- Oh, good to see that there's an underwater vacuum cleaner now.
You're gonna invest?
- Well, I should be dead for what I did
about two years ago.
(laughing)
- Had a broken washing machine,
and I managed to get the door open,
but there was a pool of water underneath it.
And I don't know what I was thinking,
but I thought I'll vacuum it out and finale saw me
and quickly explain that.
- A wipe shouting, you suck from the doorway.
(laughing)
- You can get wet/dry vacuum cleaners.
- Doesn't they can do both?
- Yes.
- They are pibious.
- Nice.
- That was the big revelation for me researching this fact.
- Yeah, that's good.
- I can't work out why I'd use that for if the bath is dirty,
but there's someone in it at the time, so I can't empty it.
- I mean, maybe that's really passive aggressive cleaning, isn't it?
(laughing)
- No, we love having you over, so please, feel at home.
- But I just imagine why did you for lunch
and now you're in my bath, then?
(laughing)
- Okay, another fact.
A fact for you from Paul Bernard.
A fact for you, he says,
related to an older segment you did about high-coupoetry,
so well that I remember that.
The Northern California town of Yukaya,
host an annual high-coup festival.
Can you guys guess why?
- It's a big Japanese population.
- No.
- Okay.
- Yukaya.
- Is this an enagram?
- Well, it's an enagram.
- It's an enagram.
- Yeah, a festival.
- Should I hike it?
(laughing)
- A hike-o.
- Yes.
- But that's not why it's cool, that.
It's named after a village, Native American village,
the pomo people called Yukaya,
but I guess they thought, you know what,
we're almost an enagram of high-coupoetry.
So let's do it.
They have a high-coup festival.
- Is it a palindrome?
- It's palindrome, yeah.
- Nice.
- Hold on, no, no, it's not a palindrome.
What do you mean?
It's high-couped backwards.
- But I don't even know if there's a word for what this is,
a reverse.
- It's, yes.
- Wrong way round.
Wrong way round work.
'Cause an enagram is just, you scramble the words.
- Yeah, you're right.
- That's my big deal.
Isn't that butchers speak in Australia
when they speak a word the wrong way round?
- Yes.
- Here's some fish a long time ago and we had Susie Denton,
talking about it, where they speak.
They speak backwards.
- That's difficult.
- To confuse customers.
- Okay.
- She'll lure them into buying low quality meat.
- I just thought it wouldn't tempt me at all.
I think it'd gone mad.
- This meat is wriggling with Tom Mags.
Should we have another letter?
This is from Alex from Manchester,
who says, on top of Cock Tobey,
which is one of the highest points
of the city center of Almaty and Kazakhstan,
stands a monument to the Beatles.
That's very nice.
- Yes, that's right.
- Do they play Kazakhstan?
- They never played Kazakhstan
and this is an interesting point, I guess,
that Alex is trying to mate.
That QI, or no such thing as a fish,
once covered that the furthest point on earth
from the ocean is in Urumki on the Kazakhstan Chinese border.
Otherwise known as the Eurasian pole of inaccessibility.
And this is a mere few hundred kilometers
from Cock Tobey in Almaty.
I'm going to claim that Cock Tobey
is the Beatles' pole of inaccessibility,
being the furthest point that a Beatles' monument exists
from a performance by any Beatles.
Lovely.
- Yeah, and they've said I'm open to being corrected
and I had a quick look.
Paul McCartney did play the Red Square.
He did play Russia, so okay.
It's still a great distance,
but I don't know whether or not there's anywhere closer.
- Did they go down under the Beatles?
- Just as really obvious.
- Absolutely, they did, okay.
But without Ringo, so if you miss an Abedal, does that count?
- Did he not go?
- What the hell?
- On the three of them went.
- Yeah, and they had another drummer come in
who was not Pete Best.
It was a different one.
- Yeah.
- Did anyone notice?
- Yeah, they were pretty famous at the time.
- I just heard the slam on Ringo.
- Yeah, but this was, do you know what this was?
This was largely Kazakhstan trying to say
that the Beatles have had an extraordinary influence
on Kazakhstan generally.
People would have started learning English
because they were listening to Beatles records.
And so this was done, I think in about 2007
that this monument was put up,
and it was also put up because they were trying to fix
the reputation of Kazakhstan from the damage
that Borat had done and the perception.
- I gotta say, a Beatles monument,
thousands of miles from anywhere there,
but it does sound like the sort of thing
you would set up in much the same way
that you're, where was it?
Your Laurel and Hardy themed ice cream parlor
in…
- In Kosovo.
- In Kosovo, yeah.
- You missed this, Anna.
- What?
- I'll tell you later, time.
- You don't need to.
- Here's a great one from Cash Howard.
The fact is, the Toko Tukon's beak
can comprise up to half the total surface area
of its body.
- Imagine the surface area of a Tukon.
- Yeah.
- Toko Tukon.
You've got me on the sun's beaches there, I'm not.
It's the one with the really, really big beak.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah.
- It could be just like a really…
- It could be decent.
- But it could be that this Tukon
has a really spiky beak.
- It's not that it's wrinkled.
- Oh, yeah.
- But its beak's tend not to be wrinkled.
- It's hard.
- It's going to be hard in the beak.
- Yeah, yeah.
Please write in if you know a bird
with an amazingly wrinkled beak.
But basically, what they use it for is so cool.
It's partly for heat transfer.
So it gets obviously very hot in the tropical environments
where they live.
And it uses it to pump heat out into the surrounding area.
So it's got this network of blood vessels under the surface.
And it just radiates heat out away from it.
Kind of like elephants do with their ears or that kind of thing.
It's basically a massive radiator.
They can pump out 400% of the heat that they are generating
if they are overheating.
So if you touch their beak, it would be noticeably hot
if it was a very hot day.
- I guess it would, yeah.
- You could use them as radiators, couldn't you?
- You could hang your socks on the beak of a Tukon.
- You could.
- They don't like that, though.
It's very disrespectful.
- It is.
- Points available for whoever can guess the newspaper headline
that I read when this scientific study was done and discovered.
- Tukon, play.
- Yeah, that's what I was going for.
- It's not bad.
- No, it's not good, though.
- A bird with a big air conditioning bill.
- Yeah.
- I don't think I would have got there, ever.
- Well, it's your first show back.
- Yeah, I'm rusty.
(laughs)
- I'll give you guys a fact.
This is from Crystal Lock.
And it's a baseball fact.
He says it's another baseball fact.
I don't know if you've had one from him before.
But his fact this time is that the first recorded mention
of the game baseball was actually in Gilford, not in America.
And it's in the diary of a guy called William Bray of Sheer.
- Wow.
- And yeah, it's very cool.
And he sent a link.
So I read it.
And he did say I'm biased towards his fact
'cause I helped run Gilford Baseball Club.
And it's a nice thing with a home of baseball globally.
- And still I'd say the MacArthur Baseball fans.
I mean, I've been to Gilford, and I know that's why I went there.
- Yeah, it's in the UK, it's worth saying.
Put a lot of overseas people.
We're saying it's not in America.
It's not far off.
We played Gilford.
Have we?
- We sure have years ago.
It was a lovely Gilford, actually.
It's a nice, nice bookshop.
- Yeah.
Oh, yes.
I do remember Gilford now.
- And home of baseball, of course.
- Yeah.
- That's why we played there.
And it's in a diary entry from the 31st of March, 1755.
It's on Easter Monday.
And Mr. Bray says, played baseball with a space between baseball
with a group of people having visited stoke church in the morning.
Drank tea stayed till late, weather cloudy.
So life has sort of not changed in England.
Cloudy weather.
- Gilford, anyway.
- Yes.
I will say, actually, it's not the first instance of baseball in this country
'cause another one was founded 2019 in Walton, on Thames and Surrey.
Again, in the UK.
And that was from 1749.
- Wow.
- And that.
But instead of a bat at the time, you used the palm of your hand to bat the ball.
- Oh, those are hard balls to hit her.
- Yeah.
I think the balls were a bit softer then.
But still, I don't think it's going as far as it.
- And largely the same rules.
A diamond with bases.
- I don't think they specified.
They were mostly commenting on the tea and the cake and stuff.
- The tea and the cake and stuff.
- Is that one more?
- Yeah, sure.
I go on here from Melissa Whitcom, who says,
"I've got a fact about sniffing feet."
According to the Guinness World Records,
Madeline Olbrecht from the USA has sniffed around 5,600 feet
and plenty of armpits in her career of 15 years working at a foot care
and footwear firm in Cincinnati, USA.
And I went into it and it's true.
This is a Guinness World Record.
It's a very Lucy Goosey Guinness World Record.
- Absolutely.
- Kind of observed that.
- Kind of, and also it says she sniffed approximately 5,600 feet
and an indeterminate number of armpits,
which doesn't feel like something...
- It's not scientific.
- No, but what it does sound like to me is something beatable.
- Anna, you and I are former Guinness World Record holders.
- Oh, okay.
- Are you sure?
- I think there must be something else out there.
Sniffing flowers?
- Maybe we'll still do it as a team,
but you can just be the witness to me doing the sniff.
- That's absolutely love to do that.
Who's going to provide the armpits?
- Well, you're already supplying.
- You're patient zero.
(laughing)
- I guess swimming pools and saunas and gyms
there'll be a few bare feet around.
- Yeah.
- You go sniffing around there.
- I love that.
- With your clicker.
- I live by the beach.
I just need to go for walks.
- Yeah.
- Oh, crawls.
- You've got to get up close.
(laughing)
- Oh, well, that's lovely.
Thank you, Melissa.
- Yeah, it's an appetizer.
- Why do you want to end on?
- Okay, that is all of your facts.
And now it's time for our facts to be issued to you
if you have joined Clubfish,
our exclusive members club,
and the friend of the podcast here,
then you get one of our headline facts allocated to you
in perpetuity.
And so we're going to dish out a few of those now.
Let's kick off with one going out to Grammarian.
And the fact is, before trains had corridors,
guards had to climb along the outside of the carriage
to check your ticket.
- Yeah.
- This is one of mine, I think.
- Very memorable facts.
- This was from a book,
I think it was called The Railways by Simon Bradley.
And it's an absolute stunner of a book.
It's so good.
And it's about the insane history of early,
it's about railways.
But these early trains,
you had to, the guard would just have to clamber
the outside of the train.
- I wonder what's the least.
- And you were locked in your carriage sometimes as well?
- They were low speeds, I guess.
- So it wasn't like being on a bullet train.
- I'm having to.
- Crawling past Tom Cruise is having a fight on the roof.
- It wasn't like that, I think.
But yeah, it was pretty scary, I reckon.
- It would be, any speed is scary
if you're grabbing the outside of the train.
- Yeah.
- This one's for Hannah Marie Christensen.
And this is that in the 1990s,
Tonga's official finance minister was also
its official court jester.
- Oh, I remember this, this was so long ago.
- Yes.
- This is vintage.
- All of these are going to be vintage.
Just heads up.
- Well, they'll be interesting to see
when I stop saying that was so long ago, won't it?
Wasn't he quite a questionable character it turned out?
- Committed some fraud.
- Yes.
- Or he certainly did a lot of dubious investing
and then fled the country.
- But we make it sound in our headline fact
like it's just a really fun light thing
and not a big criminal, which is what we do.
- That's what we do.
- We trivialize crime.
- Yeah.
- So I see myself.
- Should we have another?
- Yeah.
- Archie Craig.
This one goes out to you.
And the fact is that Kaiser Wilhelm,
once lost a valuable arms contract for Germany
because he slapped the king of Bulgaria on the bottom.
- Yes.
- This is yours, Anna.
- This is one of mine.
Yeah.
Yeah, he was just a bit of a lad.
A bit of a jack-of-a-lad.
- Yeah.
- And I can't, I don't think they were having an argument.
Were they?
I think he was just inappropriate.
- Exactly.
I think he was just incredibly inappropriate
with everyone around him and he didn't know how to behave.
- Yeah, yeah.
And we've all met people like that.
- Yeah.
- No, no names being mentioned.
- I see, but she was looking at Andy.
- Yeah, I know.
(laughing)
- Yeah, we did a whole thing about Kaiser Wilhelm,
who was eccentric.
- Yes, he was amazing, wasn't he?
- Yeah.
Also, Commander-in-Chief of the Royal Dragoons
at the start of the First World War.
- Was he?
- Yeah.
And was quickly demoted from that job.
There's a conflict of interest there, obviously.
And he would have been fighting on our side.
If he'd turned up.
- Oh, yes.
- Well, I would see Commander-in-Chief of the Royal Dragoons.
- Oh, 'cause they were cousins, weren't they?
They were all cousins.
- Oh, you give your cousins something.
You don't expect to go to war with him
a year later, kind of thing.
- Is the King, the Kaiser, and the Tsar?
I think might have all been cousins.
- Yeah, okay.
- A zoo incredibly awkward, anyway.
- Yes.
- Here's another one.
This one goes out to Tom, Tom, Tom, Tom.
Your fact is signs saying beware of pick pockets,
attract pick pockets.
I love this one.
And it's because people see the sign.
They pat the pockets.
They go, "Ah, there's my Fabricate egg."
- Yeah.
- And then the pick pocket sees that and could just have it.
- I need, did you mention Fabricate
because of that story recently?
- No.
- But did you not see that woman who, for her job,
for some reason, she had to be custodian of a Fabricate egg
for 24 hours or something.
- Yes.
- Took it home in a handbag, left her handbag on the floor
in a pub or something, and then a pick pocket
just wanged it away.
- Yes.
- You must have got home, opened the handbag,
and thought, "What's this piece of tap?"
- Oh, no.
I've overshot here.
I'm now going to be the subject of an international manhunt.
I just wanted someone's bag.
- Yes, that was an incredible story.
- It's extraordinary.
I want to hear the conversation with her boss the following day.
- I thought someone had swallowed one.
- What?
- No.
I haven't seen that story.
- I know.
- I've seen Fabricate.
- No, because they're big, aren't they?
In my head, the police were waiting for him to lay it.
You know, there was a...
Dad, I think you've created...
You've seen this in a cartoon.
- Did I dream this?
- No, you're thinking of...
You think you've...
Someone was fed bananas in India
so that they would shit out a bunch of...
- Something that they'd eat.
- Did you ever lose your rubies or something?
- Yeah, yeah.
- But that was many years ago.
I think that is...
- That's pretty different.
- That is saying.
Valiant effort to try and get down off the hook.
Doesn't work.
- Weirdly.
I saw a separate Fabricate X story recently,
which was...
I read the book about Prince Andrew.
- Big fan.
I just...
I just love the guy.
And I just want to get some life tips.
No, he was touring Russia.
And I think accounts of the visit
were just that he was shown around...
This is when relations were better.
And there wasn't a war on and all of this.
And he was just...
Not that that was stopping.
Anyway, he was just visiting.
And he was being shown around somewhere,
like the Hermitage or one of the, you know,
the royal palaces with the collection of stuff.
And apparently he was just heavily, heavily hinting
that he'd love to be given a Fabricate.
He'd love to own a Fabricate one day.
I was just trying to get a free Fabricate.
I got those.
- All right, just...
- Try a lot.
- The more I hear about this guy.
Yeah.
All right, let's have another one.
This one goes out to Ryan Jackson.
Ryan Jackson, your fact is now that no one is quite sure
how to say Louis Armstrong or Louis Armstrong.
- Are we not? - No, this...
And we did it on the show.
So basically, this was one of my facts.
And I was reading the fact that no one, including his wife,
was quite sure which version it was.
It changed all the time.
If he was announced on a show, it was one version.
There's multiple versions, I believe, of him saying it in different ways.
So there just wasn't one agreed version.
Oh, that's great. I love that.
Here's another one.
This one goes out to Grumbert,
the man with the Guinness World Record for the lowest voice
can hit notes so low only elephants can hear him.
- Okay. - Yeah.
I'm going to go sniff those feet over there.
You create a distraction.
Who's got the lowest voice out of the four of us?
I think you or me, but the question is who can go low.
Give me your lowest.
- Lowest. - That's for too low.
Yeah.
You can't just put a silly accent on the naked lower.
Weirdly, you're actually like the silly accent
is going to help you get those steps.
Well, it does because it helps bend your mouth into places.
Oh, there we go. Is that it?
This is the fact of a Steph DeLaurie.
The first thing was a parliament.
And it was the old thing in Iceland.
It's been going since the 10th century.
This is one of James's, wasn't it?
It was James's.
That's where we get the word thing, right?
It's from that parliament.
And it's become meaningless enough to just mean thing now.
Is that one of the many claims
to have been the first parliamentary democracy?
I think it was. Wasn't it?
Yeah.
I think it must have been.
And we did a load of stuff about Icelandic horses.
Do you remember this?
Yeah.
Are they the ones that have a special trot as well?
Icelandic horses, I think, have a special way of trotting
where they'd trot with their feet the other way round
to normal horses.
Something like that.
That sounds plausible, yes.
I think I do.
And it's got a special name, like trirting or something like that.
What we find, and you'll find, as we do,
more little fishes, Anna, is that it's amazing
what you do and don't remember.
And it's amazing.
Like Dan's story of the guy who swallowed a feather's hair
and the police were waiting for him to lay it.
You'll find that your mind is foggier than you thought.
When we did it with something we were asserted for like one day,
ten years ago, it turns out it can go anyway.
Yeah.
The difference is, is that I immediately got picked up on it
until you told that story about how we've got mismemories.
I mean, basically accepted Anna's premise that their horses have
backward legs.
Have they trot on one side of their body than the other?
And they were always falling over.
Yeah.
Something like that.
Anyway, have that fact.
Lovely.
And one more.
Yeah, here's the final fact.
This goes to Bronwyn.
One of the largest majorities in a Brazilian election
was won in 1958 by a rhino called Kakareko.
Kakareko.
I remember Kakareko.
Do you?
Yeah.
Still serving?
It's been a while since we did this fact.
Yeah, you'd think it was just a protest vote.
But no, he just had a very strong campaign.
Worker's rights, sorting out immigration.
Yeah, it was they ever, everyone hated the current leaders, didn't they?
Why don't we do more of that here, putting animals up for election?
That would be fun, wouldn't it?
I think that would have made the latest council elections in Britain
more entertaining.
Yeah, yeah.
Would you have voted for a rhino if there'd been one on your ballot paper?
Regardless of party.
I don't think I would.
Okay.
Killjoy.
But I just remember the details of this fact.
I think Kakareko means rubbish.
Yeah.
It does.
I don't think that was a part of the electoral pitch.
I don't think the pitch was I'm a rubbish candidate.
Okay.
I think it was I'm a rhino and you hate all the humans.
Yeah, you're right, actually, Anna.
I mean, given the choice, I probably would vote for a rhino.
There you go.
Yeah.
What's the headline?
We did the beak.
Eric conditioner.
He'll give you the horn.
And that's what you want.
Is it from your elected politician?
It's slightly too sexy.
I regret.
I regret saying that as a slogan.
I've got it.
To be a politician, you need thick skin.
Yes.
Very good.
Yeah.
That's it.
That is it.
And I'll give you the horn.
That's the scandal that makes you leave office.
That's when we take the rubbish out.
Okay.
That is it.
That is all of your facts.
If you would like to have a fish headline fact dedicated to you from now and forever more,
all you need to do is go to patreon.com/clubfish.
Even if you don't want to sign up to be a friend of the podcast, there is so much fun stuff on there.
There's a free tier where you get little extra videos and goodies and all sorts of bonus material.
And there's all sorts of other stuff on there.
patreon.com/clubfish.
And if you would like to submit a fact to be on little fish in future, just email podcast@QI.com.
We read absolutely every single one and we love receiving them.
So podcast@QI.com is the email to send it to.
That's it from us.
We'll see you in a few days for another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish.
Bye for now.
[Music]
[BLANK_AUDIO]