[MUSIC]
>> Hello, and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast this week coming to you live from the Edinburgh Fringe.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Anna Tyshyski, Andrew Honesomuri, and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite
facts from the last seven days, and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is my fact.
My fact is, earlier this year, the town of Midgeham was invaded by midges.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Super.
>> Yeah, so Midgeham is a- >> Midgeham, maybe.
>> Midgeham.
>> Maybe, absolutely maybe.
So yeah, Midgeham is located in West Berkshire.
>> [LAUGH]
>> This is a tiny town, it's got 350 people who live there.
And very recently, they were invaded by huge swarms of midges.
Obviously hilarious, but I should point out, as the article accentuates,
the population are not laughing because- >> [LAUGH]
>> Because the midges will fly into their mouths.
>> It's annoying, they can't walk out.
If they open their mouth, they're swallowing big mouthloads of midges.
That's what they're saying in the news report.
>> It's not biblical, it is- >> That's what they said.
>> It's as many midges as pretty much every single Scottish person
has dealt with in any place.
>> No, the people of Berkshire are not used to midges.
>> Exactly. >> They're not hardy like you.
They're sensitive souls.
>> They said you can't even walk without swallowing, okay, a few.
>> Okay, yeah, you- >> [LAUGH]
>> Also, I've just realized, it's the Edinburgh fridge.
So there'll be more people from Berkshire here than there are from Edinburgh.
>> [LAUGH]
>> It does sound bad.
It also did really affect the nearby village of Woolhampton,
but that doesn't have a funny name.
So it's got no airtime.
>> The invasion of sheep there two years ago was hysterical.
>> Mitchum, I think, having Googled it, is not interesting in any other way.
>> Wow. >> I'll go on trial, James.
>> My God.
>> Here we go.
>> Strap in.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Mitchum is Berkshire's least used railway station.
>> Interesting.
>> Yeah, and that's from 2020 to one, although, so
you might think it was due to lockdowns and stuff.
Actually, it was also Berkshire's least popular station in 2019 to 20.
>> Right.
>> And also, it's not in Mitchum, Mitchum station, it's just outside Mitchum.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Woolhampton?
>> It used to be called Woolhampton, but then people kept sending it stuff for
Woolhampton, which is much bigger and a long way away.
>> All right.
>> So they changed it.
>> Okay.
>> And okay, so that, yeah, I've got one more thing that has happened in Mitchum ever.
>> Yeah. >> Please.
>> Peter Gray, a 72-year-old farmer, saw a giant ice block of frozen human
urine smash into his lawn.
>> Oh, from an airplane?
>> Yes, from a plane.
>> [LAUGH]
>> No, from the mole people.
What do you think?
>> Pissing aliens.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So Mitchum, I did have a look at if it's been invaded by Mitchum before,
because I thought, this is the kind of thing that tabloid journalists just
desperately hope happens and make happen.
And there were two other incidents in the last 12 years where it is reported as
being invaded by Mitchum.
And I have to say, we haven't seen any invasion plans or got these stats.
So maybe that the people of Mitchum are just very wingy.
>> Out of curiosity, the first time it happened, did they find it funny?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Is that just jaded Mitchum now?
Going, yeah, yeah, yeah, first two times.
>> I think it is, yeah, it's hysterical, yeah.
And it was reported on both times as ironic, which is very upsetting.
>> You've got a big thing about this.
>> That's true, everyone has a big thing about this ever since.
Ever since the Larnis Morrissette invented having a big thing about it, then.
>> Because it's not ironic.
>> Well, indeed.
>> Right, has anyone, so who here has experienced Mitchus?
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Who here has been to Mitchum?
>> Get out.
>> What is their train station like?
>> Were you there when Berkshire Life sent a reporter to see just how quiet it really is?
>> [LAUGH]
>> I arrived before 8 AM on Wednesday and
what you presume would be the height of rush hour.
However, there was no one at the station at all.
There you go, you weren't there.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Does anyone here use the Mitch forecast?
>> So this is the thing, there's a Mitch forecast which some of the people here use.
>> Is it in Scotland, or UK?
>> It is in Scotland, yeah, yeah.
And the serious level is one to five.
One is the least serious, which is called no flies on me.
And number four is great, that's no mist, that's midges, it was really good.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I think it's entirely sponsored by Smidge,
which is the UK's number one of, as far as I could tell, two, mid-repellents.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Yeah, and they, it's a great-
>> That's cool, did you check out today's Mitch forecast?
>> No, I didn't.
>> Oh.
>> Did you? >> The cocky.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I didn't know it existed until 20 seconds ago.
>> I actually checked it out, and it's looking pretty good.
>> Yeah. >> For all this talk of how midges are so
bad throughout the summer, and sometimes they have two phases, I think.
But this year, they reckon they have a third.
And September, there might be a third hatching.
It's fine, it's mostly at twos.
And then I think one spot was at four.
So stay away from, I think it might have been sterling.
No, it's Glencoe, Glencoe, there you go.
>> Right, I'm not sure if I've ever encountered a midge.
>> No, you weren't.
>> Yeah, right.
>> It's pretty bad.
>> Okay, right, because supposedly, according to Scottish
midge studies, 40,000 of them can land on a single unprotected arm in one hour.
There are 37 different species in Scotland.
It has caused major problems here.
So there's an estimated 20% of working forestry days in Scotland are lost
because of the clouds of biting midges, you have to stop.
And it can cost up to 268 million pounds a year in lost tourism visits.
As a result of the reports of them being here.
>> Really?
>> However, what's very exciting is you do make up that money a bit
by the 41 million pounds that is brought in annually by visits to the Loch Ness Monster.
So.
>> What?
>> That's what Nessies bring into the table.
>> Yeah, but that's nothing to do with what we're talking about.
>> Completely non-relevant.
>> The Edinburgh Festival brings in lots of money.
That would be a more apt thing to say, ironically.
>> Yeah, but we're talking about animals.
>> Yeah, some which exist.
>> And some which are yet to.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> They're symbiotic, Nessie and midges.
I think that's what you're saying, isn't it?
They have a symbiotic relationship, so one can't exist without the other?
I'm pretty sure that must be down to the point.
Otherwise it would be completely.
>> You've been an insane thing to bring up.
>> You did say there's lots of species of midge.
>> Yeah.
>> They are often named after their penises.
Because they all have very distinct penises.
Well, they got all have distinct penises, but many of them do.
Other people that are named after their penises are Vikings.
So they're quite a lot.
We've done a fact in here before where there was a Viking called Small Penis.
And I just wondered if you guys wanted to have a game of midge or Viking.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Yeah, okay.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Sure.
>> Lovely. >> Yes, please.
>> That's what we're all here for.
So I'm going to give you the name of a name.
And it's either the scientific name of a midge, or it's the name of a Viking, okay?
>> Okay, okay.
>> Spiny penis.
>> A lot of the audience is saying Viking.
>> I'm going to go midge.
>> Yeah, I think midge, because they do have spiky penises, don't they?
>> I'm going to say Viking.
I'm going to say Viking.
>> Some of them do have spiny penises, and indeed this one does, because it's a midge.
>> Yes.
>> Nice.
>> But a penis.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Please, Viking, please.
>> Always dropping things with this penis.
>> Yeah.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Just use your hands, mate.
>> Or is it just but a penis?
Like, is it used in that?
>> Lovely.
>> We need the spelling.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> The answer is it was a Viking but a penis.
>> Butter penises.
What do we know Butter Penises story?
>> No, we don't know it.
It was just in a list of Viking names.
>> He was friends with Butter Balls, the Viking.
>> Right.
>> Yeah.
>> What about curvo penis?
>> Curvo?
>> Yeah.
>> Curvo.
Is that just a name, or does it describe the curveness, perhaps?
>> I'll say midge.
>> Viking.
>> I'm going Viking.
This side of the table is going Viking.
>> No, it was a midge.
It was discovered in 2011 by a guy called Wang.
>> Brilliant.
>> Super.
>> Nice.
>> And you could have had Barry Penis,
Dentopenis, Oxypenis, Convexipenis, and Dibilipenis.
They're all midges.
>> Oh, Barry Penis.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Well, here he comes, Barry Penis.
It's just a good, that's a good nickname.
>> It's really good.
You were saying James earlier, because we've got another James H on the tour,
and you're like, I need a nickname for this tour.
>> We're not making Barry Penis.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Brilliant.
>> Hey, here's the thing that the people at Midgham are missing, right?
>> Yes.
>> Because they've got food flying into their mouth.
>> Free.
>> You can eat midge.
>> Midgham.
>> Exactly.
>> So there's a thing which is, have you guys all heard of cunga cake?
>> Yes, African cake.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Fly cake.
>> Fly cake, and midges are used in that.
And so what you need to do is you need to turn your issue into a tissue.
What's the phrase?
>> That's good.
Turn your issue into a tissue.
>> Turn your issue into a tissue by you go out, and this is what they do when
they're making cunga cake.
You just bring a frying pan outside, and you coated it in the oil or in butter.
And you just wave it through the swarm, and they stick into it.
And then you just go home and cook it, and make that into a cake.
>> I think they squash it, they get loads and squash them down, right?
>> Yeah.
>> But I think the ones that happen in Africa, I know they have problems in
Midgham, but I think the ones in Africa are absolutely insane.
Like, as in you can hardly walk through them, there's just so many midges.
>> Right.
>> I think so.
>> Yeah, I think you're right, because it's sort of, they get more hatchings, and
you get like in places like Cameroon, you get a hatching every three weeks.
>> Yeah.
>> It's bad if you get what, three in a year.
>> Yeah, it's actually the warmer the places, the more hatchings they get.
>> Okay.
>> The baby midges are these tiny little lavas.
They look like little caterpillars.
And in the Goldenrod Goalmage, they have this amazing way of jumping,
where they get all their internal fluids, push them down to their tail,
turn themselves into a little sort of circle, and then hold on, hold on,
release, and then they jump into the air.
>> Okay, it's an absolutely amazing way to get about.
They can move 28 times more efficiently than a caterpillar can crawl.
>> Than one of the trams.
Are they still a joke?
No, okay, good.
>> If a sausage could jump that quickly.
>> Yes.
>> Then it could get to the top of the Great Pyramid at Giza in three seconds.
>> Oh my God.
>> Wow.
>> That is context.
>> That's incredible.
>> Imagine that sausage.
>> Their eggs are actually sausage shaped.
Well, their eggs biting midge eggs are either cigar, banana, or sausage shaped.
Which is a cool range of shapes for an egg.
>> They're all quite similar shapes.
>> Cigars and sausages.
>> Yes, cigar and sausage is a-
>> I was wondering about the difference.
I think it must be the ends, right?
>> It's the tapering, yeah, yeah.
>> The tapering.
>> Very few sausages, which sort of tail off at the end, yeah.
>> Yes. >> But cigars, loads.
>> Hey, we're gonna have to move on a sec, by the way.
>> Can I tell you an audience fact?
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> This is from a Scottish listener.
So it's Bev Clark, I don't suppose you're in.
Anyway, she sent in a fantastic fact, right?
This is actually about bats, but she submitted it as,
a pipistrel bat has to eat about one-sixth of its own body weight in midges every night to survive.
That is the equivalent to an average Scottish nine-year-old child having
to eat 23 tins of baked beans, one bean at a time, whilst flying every night.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Just get back.
>> Yeah, that's brilliant.
[MUSIC]
>> We do need to move on to our next fact.
So it is time for fact number two, and that is Anna.
>> My fact this week is that there are radar detectors, and
there are radar detector detectors, and there are radar detector detector detectors.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But as far as we know,
there are not yet any radar detectors, detectors, detectors, detectors.
>> But that's only because we don't have a radar to find it.
>> How would we know?
There's always going to be one more detectors than we know about.
>> I don't think so, right, because your radar is used by the cops.
>> So the police one with a traffic gun, that's a radar.
>> So then the police need to know if you're breaking the law by getting a detector.
So they have a detector detector detector, but if you get the next level up,
you're already breaking the law with your other detector, so they don't need the second one.
>> They don't need to know, that's a good point, and that is basically what it is.
So this is from radar that's sent out by speed cameras,
bounces off your car a couple of times, and then it sees how fast you're
traveling by working out what distance you've traveled in that time.
>> That's a radar detector.
>> No, that is just a speed camera.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And then you in your car, because you're a criminal in lots of places,
where these things are banned, you might have a device that's a radar detector.
>> And have you done your driving theory test yet or?
>> The theory test?
>> Yeah. >> No, no, no.
>> Well, I hope you're listening to this, because this all will come up.
>> Yeah, I did slightly blank out, what are we talking about?
>> Sorry. >> So I, if I'm driving and I put
a radar detector in my car, that's to tell me when there's a speed.
>> A speed camera. >> Exactly.
>> Okay, so then the police officer has a radar detector to see,
if you have a radar detector to see if he has a speeding camera.
>> So the police officer, well, not the police officer, the speed camera in it
has a detector that will detect if the driver has a detector.
>> So that's a detector detector?
>> Exactly, because it sends off little vibrations.
But the way of detecting in the camera is to vibrate a little bit itself.
So some of the radar detectors also have within them detector, detector, detectors.
And that's the complicated world of radar detectors, basically.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And the thing is, even in your car,
you might have a thing where in your sat nav, it tells you where there are speed
cameras. >> Yeah.
>> And that's perfectly legal in most places,
but not in all places.
So if you're driving in America, for instance, and you go into Virginia,
Mississippi, or Washington DC, technically you have to turn that off in your car.
Now, fuck knows how you do that.
But in theory, you would have to do that in order to.
>> Or you have to prove that you're ignoring it by speeding through every
speed camera. >> That's very cool.
>> Do you know what the fastest ever speeding ticket was?
>> I was in like, you were giving it two seconds after.
>> Sorry.
>> My god, you pedant.
>> I'm used to this stuff from James.
When it comes to Dan, I've got no defenses.
>> Is it, are we talking in the UK?
>> It is in the USA.
>> Okay, so the word is, would you want to have a guess?
>> Well, no cars would go more than 200 miles an hour.
>> Uh-huh, well, there's lots of stuff online saying the fastest ticket ever was
a sports car, it was a special sports car, it was in Texas.
It was in a 75 mile an hour zone and it was going at 242 miles an hour.
There's a lot of stuff on the internet saying that, I didn't find like,
the exact initial story behind it.
I have a theory that the fastest ever speeding ticket was someone who was
caught going at eight miles an hour because the speed limit was two miles
an hour at the time.
>> And that just makes them faster.
>> Well, relative to the limit, it's the fastest, I think, ever.
>> Four times the speed limit, that's crazy.
You wouldn't drive 120 in a 30, would you?
No.
>> So technically.
>> Okay, right.
>> Technically it is.
>> But that was the first one ever issued.
>> That's amazing.
>> It was 1896, whoa, that is the exact same year as the first ever speeding
ticket that was given over here in the UK.
>> This was in the UK.
>> Yeah.
>> How ironic.
>> Wait.
>> He started out talking about the US, but we did them.
>> It's in Petswood, very nearly used to.
>> Oh, yeah, God, I got to start listening, man.
>> That was, we're talking about the same thing here.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> It was in 1896.
>> And it was eight miles an hour.
>> Eight miles an hour.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> It was, supposedly he was followed by a police officer on a bike for five
miles.
>> There was a guy a couple of years ago called Nigel Mills, who was clock
speeding 88 miles an hour in his car, which was a.
>> A delorean.
>> Oh, brilliant.
>> A delorean, as the audience got.
He had to go to court, he paid his fine, but in court, he did deny that he was attempting
to break the space time continuum.
>> I learned something that I think probably I should have known, this definitely will be
in the theory, in fact, the thing that always accompanies speed cameras, which I didn't
know about, or the main speed cameras that you get, which as I'm sure you know are the
Gatso cameras, which are the big yellow boxes, although I think in Scotland, they're yellow
and red, diagonal stripes, is that right?
But they always are accompanied by lines on the road, which I just never noticed.
>> It's going so fast, it's just a blur, and also you're pissed out of your brain.
>> Yeah, you can't be expected to concentrate on this sort of thing when you're lying down.
So one way you could fool them is you could cover up the lines on the road before you
got to the speed camera.
>> Wait, do I have to park my car a mile back, walk up to it with a black cloth or something?
>> With a sheet or something that can cover the lines up, because basically what the lines
are doing, speed cameras do two things to make sure that you're speeding or not.
They send out some radar, and so it's like two pulses of radar, and they work out how
far away you are with each pulse of radar, and then they work out how far you've travelled
in the time it's sent out, the two pulses, but also they need a backup way of telling
how far you've travelled, so they also take two photos as you're travelling, and they
need to see where you were in the first photo and where you were in the second photo, and
then see how long it took you to get from one to the other.
>> I always wonder when I'm going past one of those, if I swerve into another lane, will
they not be able to take the second photo?
>> They're on every lane, sadly, so that's the white lines.
>> I don't think it's a different car with the same licence plate.
They can't put a glove on me legally.
>> I think you might have to go on the verge, and that's a whole nother contravention, but
they can only tell you because the lines are on a ruler, so they can tell how far up the
ruler you've gone.
>> Gatso is named after Maurice Gatsonides, who was a racing driver.
We very briefly mentioned him about nine and a half years ago.
His first speed gun that he invented was two rubber tyres on the road, and you still see
those.
When you're driving just around and around, there's just two little rubber lines.
They tell you how many cars are going along so that people can make rules and stuff like
that and check out what the speed limit is, but they also tell you the speed.
>> What do you mean rubber lines?
>> It's like two little rubber wires that go across the road.
>> Tiny cords.
I always assumed that they were testing whether they should put a speed camera in there, and
I would slow down for them because I don't want people to know how fast I normally drive
over that bit.
>> That's sensible.
They are doing that, but they're also checking how many cars go across there.
>> I've never noticed that.
Do I never look at the road?
>> Oh, my gosh.
He was a racing driver, and he invented the speed camera to speed himself up because he
wanted to know how fast he was going, and he would keep going around the corner loads
and loads of times, and his speed camera would say, "You're going at 60 miles an hour, 70
miles an hour, 80 miles an hour," and he would try and get as fast as possible.
He invented a charcoal-burning petrol generator during the German occupation of Holland, which
kept the country going.
He was part of the resistance during World War II.
He took up engineering after he was turned down as a pilot for KLM due to a mangled finger,
which he got after a bicycle accident as a child.
>> A mangled finger?
>> Yes.
>> I don't think that should discount you.
>> There were more picky in those days.
>> Right.
>> I don't know.
>> You couldn't even do it if you're ... I think they're very picky.
You can't even do it if you're short-sighted.
>> Can't you?
>> No.
He certainly couldn't back then.
>> But I'm short-sighted.
>> Well, I'm sorry to reign on your parade, Andy, but you're going to have to stick with
the podcast.
>> And he also invented his own car, which had a glass dome over the top of it to make
you think you were driving an airplane.
>> Oh, cool.
>> You know like that one that Homer Simpson makes?
>> Yes.
>> It's quite like that.
>> I've got another inventor just to bring up.
This is taking it to radar very quickly.
Have you guys heard of Dr. Robert Rhine's incredible radar designer?
So he sort of innovated the resolution of what radar and sonar images could achieve.
And the stuff that he did allowed for the Titanic to be found.
It was using his advanced technology to find the wreck of the Titanic, to find the Bismarck.
Absolutely incredible.
But what he applied using that sonar to most of all was his big passion, multiple expeditions,
to find the Loch Ness monster.
He went on like six, seven expeditions.
He found a perfumer to create a scent that would lure Nessie up from the Loch Ness.
>> The easiest day's work for that perfumer.
>> He trained dolphins to carry cameras that they could send through the Loch and try and
so forth.
I don't know if he ever actually did that, but that was the attempt.
And he was amazing.
Outside of sonar, he invented -- he patented a hinge that you could use for chopsticks.
And he tried to invent something that would stop tornadoes from materializing, but it
never happened.
Yeah, one of the great Nessie hunters, local hero.
Yeah.
>> I was really about radar, and I came across a really fun kind of paper that was written
in 1946.
This was a really short time after radar was basically invented.
So we only worked out how to use it usefully in the Second World War, and it was for use
in aircraft and aircraft detection.
And on boats and on submarines, they kept picking up ghosts or phantoms or something
they called them echoes.
And there's all these sources of people writing, speculating about what it might be.
So in Germany, there was speculation that it was probably a matter of sharply bounded
areas of discontinuity in the atmosphere.
Now, it turns out, what that's another word for is birds.
But they just couldn't put two and two together.
It's bizarre that in 1946, it's written like, actually, we've worked out that it was birds
all along.
>> Is it not true that radar was invented because they were trying to make a death ray?
>> I think that's true.
>> Interesting.
>> I think so.
So there was rumours that Germany had been making a death ray by firing radio waves at
people and it would just make them disappear.
And it was taken seriously by the British.
And they thought, well, we're going to need one of our own.
And they found this guy called Robert Watts at Watt.
And they asked him, can you make us a death ray, please?
And they offered him if he could zap a sheep from 100 paces away, they'd give him a thousand
pounds.
>> He did his experiments and realised that it was impossible.
But then he realised also that he could use this radio waves to bounce off things and
work out how far things were away.
>> Wow, that's incredible.
>> He must have considered trying to blag it by getting his friends to dig a hole near
the sheep.
>> Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is Andy.
My fact is that in 16th century Wales, there was a financial crisis which meant that lots
of families could no longer afford to keep a household bard.
>> Wow, very, huge wow.
And they, every, every house would have its own bard.
>> And now?
>> Or very few.
>> Yeah?
>> Very few.
You got to be pretty loaded in modern Wales to have your own bard.
Bards were, bards were big, big noise back in the day.
Bards were multi, they were multitaskers, weren't they?
>> Oh, they did it all.
I mean, they mostly, mostly read poems and played the harp.
But they probably helped with the washing up, if required.
>> Actually there was a medieval document called the Triads of Britain, and they say
that the three principal tasks of a bard is one, to learn and collect sciences.
The second is to teach, and the third is to make peace and put an end to all injury.
>> It's a big ream it, isn't it, as a jaw-bad, who's CB?
>> If there is heavy washing up, you will be, it will be really appreciated into a bit.
It was just an interesting, and it was also, it was a time where around this period the
Welsh language was kind of being demoted, and English was being promoted, and you know,
the aristocracy were anglicising, and there were a lot of popular poets at the time who
proper classical barads thought were trash, so they were nicknamed the, like the modern
poets, were called poets who sing at fares, gross, and some of them didn't even play
the harp.
>> Hang on, sorry, were these like the English-imported poets, or these are both parts?
>> I think that, I think that was like a newer, like, >> I would just associate poets with
a loot rather than a harp.
I associate harps with, like, angels and stuff.
>> I don't know what a loot is, that's my...
>> You see this big screen?
>> Yes, I do.
[laughter]
>> Yes.
>> That was a huge loot, like, I would say like a harp is more like at a wedding, you
see, so we're playing a big harp.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, it was the thing for bars, it wasn't it's a harp, the triple harp in fact, tended
to be what they played.
>> Little handheld, handheld drobbies, or?
>> Well, bigger than what...
[laughter]
>> Do you know what "jobby" means in Scotland?
>> Absolutely.
>> Good boy.
[laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry.
>> No offense.
Balance.
>> Yeah.
>> That's cool.
>> Yeah, yeah, three layers of twang, what are they called strings, Liz?
>> Is it like when a guitarist has two, you know, those awesome guitars with two necks
on it, or they layered on top of each other?
>> They're layered on top of each other, and in fact, I was interested to learn that "Deck
the Hall with Bows of Holly" was written by a bard, a Welsh bard.
>> What was it?
>> Yes, the most famous Welsh bard, John Parry, who was a blind bard as many works, they were
thought to have sort of extra sight, which gave him this wisdom to write.
But basically, we say that the job of the bard, they were pretending to cure all ills
or something, but basically, it was to massively kiss the ass of the posh people, wasn't it?
>> Yeah.
>> It was.
>> That was quite fascinating.
Particularly in Ireland, in fact, which had a huge barding history, you essentially
went around touting your wares to posh nobility, praising them, and writing verse about how
amazing they were, and how big their houses were, and how beautiful their wives were,
and how great their penises looked, and whatever it was, and that's how you got your gigs.
>> Lovely penis barry, just want to say it.
>> They could be quite dangerous bards, couldn't they?
There was an idea that their songs could bring up insurrection and stuff.
I think the English thought that a lot of the Welsh bards, they were a bit worried about
the Welsh bards.
>> Same with the Irish, in fact, they inspired the nobles to revolt.
>> I wouldn't be surprised if it was the same with the Scottish, I would say.
>> No, in those English.
>> No, the Scottish ones just loved English, actually, throughout history, yeah.
>> Yeah, yeah.
But let's try and get out of here alive.
>> Everyone's from Berkshire, it's fine.
>> In 1282, apparently, King Edward of England decided to get rid of all the bards in Wales
because he was worried that they might cause insurrection among the Welsh, and apparently
he had a massacre of 500 bards.
How did he lure them all to the same place?
Did he have a big, like, loot sale, and then advertised in loot?
>> Advertised in loot, brilliant.
>> That was a good joke about 30 years ago.
>> That's such a good joke, you don't remember loot, the magazine?
Then why didn't the four of you laugh?
>> It's so weird, though, this thing, right?
So apparently, he supposedly massacred these 500 bards.
No one really knows about it in England, no one really knows about it in Wales, but everyone
knows about it in Hungary.
Because there is a song that Hungarian school children memorize, and it's almost like a
nursery rhyme kind of thing, which is about the massacre of the 500 Welsh bards.
And so all Hungarian children know it, yeah.
>> You know, they're dangerous for other reasons as well, as well as possible insurrections.
They also were able to kill a rat by talking to it.
And this was a thing that has been written in multiple plays, Shakespeare references,
lots of plays reference it, and it was the idea that there was a very famous bard from
Ireland who came home one day, and some mice had eaten the meal that his wife had prepared
for him, and so he sort of went, "You fucking assholes," and they died.
And that became a thing that you would bring a bard over to your house, because you had
a mice problem.
>> No.
>> Yeah, and they would use their words purely to kill it.
>> That can't have lasted long, because the proof's really in the pudding when you get
the rodent guy around.
>> I don't believe it.
I just...
[laughter]
>> Do you know one of the most famous ever bards?
It was called YOLO.
>> No.
>> Yeah.
>> I-O-L-O.
His real name was Edward Williams, but he was...
He deeply loved Welsh...
He became a Welsh bardic scholar, basically, and a lot of what we know or what people thought
before they knew about bards in the 18th and 19th centuries is because of him.
And he also made up a lot of stuff and pretended it was by a 14th-century bard.
He did a lot of forging works.
But he held the first ever Welsh gorseth, which is the gathering of the bards in...
>> Wales.
>> Primrose Hill in North London.
He wanted to kind of show England and London that this was Welsh bardic culture and how
amazing it was, and he was responsible for a lot of England being kind of druid mad for
a long time.
>> He made a lot...
Yeah, as you say, he made a lot of it up, and no one knew that at the time.
It was sort of like in the 20...
Who is what?
The 18th century?
They found it in the 20th century through some academics reading into it and finding
out.
And he had all these details about his life that sounded so badass.
He said that he learned to read by watching his dad carve names into gravestones.
That was where he learned the alphabets, and that's where he learned to read.
>> Really?
Yeah, yeah.
>> Is it Mary Shelley or Mary Wollstonecraft who...
It's Mary Wollstonecraft, isn't it?
>> Oh, Mary Shelley.
>> Mary Shelley.
>> She had to write her name by tracing her mother's name on her gravestone.
>> Oh, yeah.
And she also lost her virginity on it as well.
>> Yes, she did.
>> Yeah, I touched it the other day.
It was amazing.
>> Pervert.
>> Very creepy.
>> Yeah, it was actually creepy, wasn't it?
>> Well, what did you touch it with?
>> Every country has their own bards, don't they?
Oh, every country has their own storytellers, and I think the reason they exist everywhere
is because they're a repository of knowledge for people who can't write or read, which
is sort of everyone until here and today.
And so I didn't realize that hula dancers are bards.
So a hula is not a dance.
It's a way of acting out a story which is being told at the same time, traditionally.
>> That's cool.
>> This is in Hawaii.
In Sicily, you have an ancient storytelling method passed down from one person to the
next, which is called kanto.
>> It's savage, Anna.
>> It's just improvised, sung verse and spoken prose.
The kanto, and there --
>> How's it spelled?
>> There's the bottom.
>> Yeah, I see it.
That's nailed on.
Andy, weren't you looking for a tourniquet name as well?
>> Wow.
>> I'm so sorry to doubt you, Anna.
Absolutely doesn't say that word.
I highly respected the Contistae, of course, who'd tell the stories of the kanto.
And there are lots of others as well.
>> Just put an O on the end to keep saying it, you had to stop doing that.
>> I've never had the courage to say it before.
I didn't realize this when we wanted to.
>> The Six Marks brother, who was not allowed on screen.
>> In 16th century France, they had an anagramata royale, whose job was they were with the royal
family, and whenever a dignitary would come, they would make an anagram of their names.
>> That's cool, isn't it?
>> Anna Tyshinski, could be Zayny Payne Skank.
>> A million miles off.
>> She's not Zayny.
>> Andrew Hunter Murray, untrue Rwanda Rhymer.
>> Untrue Rwanda Rhymer.
>> That's me.
>> And then Daniel Shriver, incredible ass.
>> Wait, did you say "incredible"?
>> You do have to put the H at the start, otherwise it doesn't work.
>> Wow, what's James Harkin?
>> There are no anagrams of that.
>> So, overseas storytellers, I was reading about the benshi of Japan, I never heard of
the benshi before.
During the 20th century, theaters, movie theaters in Japan, when all the movies were silent,
would hire these storytellers to come and talk over the movies and explain what was
going on or give their own narratives about what was going on.
So, yeah.
>> Don't invite a banshi, just have all the way through your film.
>> What's a banshi?
>> It's like a mythical screamer.
>> I would assume that you would be all over that.
>> Don't give him away into another fucking Loch Ness Monster fact.
We should talk about Scotland's national bard, Robbie Burns, shouldn't we, I guess.
And he's in tonight.
Some words from Burns' poems, and see if you can guess what they mean.
Swankies.
>> Translers.
>> Not a million miles away, but no.
Socks.
>> No, it's swaggering, strapping fellows who are in their prime.
>> Oh, great.
>> Okay.
>> We're looking at four of them tonight on stage.
>> Bickering brattle.
>> Oh, yes, that's good.
No, it's the way that a mouse runs along the floor.
So like this way, that way, this way, that way kind of thing.
>> Okay.
>> Trying to get away from the bard.
>> He's just tracing it.
>> Canty.
>> It's an Italian, it's a Sicilian form of traditional storytelling.
It's the excess of good spirit at the point of bursting into song.
And lunt.
>> Okay, right.
>> Lunt.
>> It's when you get lint, but in your crotch area.
>> Very annoying.
>> Oh, my God.
>> Yeah, that's a thing.
>> That's a thing.
>> Yeah, lint gathers on your clothes, isn't it?
>> Can I tell you the answer?
>> Yeah.
>> If you've got new pants, you'll experience lunt, yeah, no matter what you've got going
on down there.
>> Yeah.
>> It's to walk away while smoking.
>> Oh.
>> Okay.
>> That's not nearly as good as Anna's one.
>> Yeah.
>> Much prefer Anna's one.
>> Right.
>> We've got to move on in a second.
Before we do, this whole fact was about, basically, families not being able to afford things
anymore, people not being able to afford things anymore, and you know, some group of people
who've really experienced that hard in recent times, and thank you, James, I almost forgot
to mention, are Nessie hunters because things have got so expensive now in Scotland that
any of the local areas that rent out the holiday homes, the Airbnb's, the hotels, you can't
afford to go and sit by the lock anymore.
>> That's terrible.
>> And so as a result, yeah.
>> But the good news is you have as good a chance of finding it if you just stay at home.
>> Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show, and that is James.
>> Okay, my fact this week is that some whales communicate by wobbling their melons.
>> Oi, oi.
>> That's funny.
>> A skill exclusive to them and definitely does not occur with Loch Ness monsters.
So these are belugas, and there's a picture on the screen.
>> Beluga.
The funnest whale to say, I think.
>> Is it?
>> Oh, come on.
What's funnest?
Beluga.
Sperm.
>> Okay.
>> That is a good one.
>> That's a fun one to say.
>> We shouldn't spend the rest of this listing whale to say.
>> So they're white whales, they get the name from the Russian for white.
They have this kind of muscly bit of fat on the top of their head and they can contract
it and move it around, and we didn't really know why they were doing this, but a recent
study from the University of Rhode Island has found that they do it 34 times more often
during social interactions than they do otherwise.
So we think that they're communicating with each other.
>> Right.
>> I think that makes it.
It's like an interior hat they've got that they can kind of tip to a lady, and they've
got all these moves.
They can squish it up, and they can flatten it down, and they can move it round to the
side.
>> It's crazy.
>> They've got five moves, haven't they?
>> Which is good.
>> They can ripple it back and forth.
>> Really?
>> It's insane.
>> Have you seen a video?
>> I've seen a video.
>> Wow, so literally like a wave pool.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> It's brilliant.
What are they saying?
>> I don't know.
>> Nobody knows.
>> When they use them most often, and the shake, as in the wobble I guess, seems to be mostly
male towards females during courtship.
And I think then two of them, so there's flat lift, press, push, and shake.
I think a couple of them are more playful, and then push is maybe a bit more aggro.
So it's like having a language with only five words.
>> Okay.
Why haven't we worked out what those five words are then?
>> We only just figured out they do it.
Give them a chance.
>> Okay.
Apologies to the marine biologists.
They're the only whales that can nod.
I really like that.
>> Really?
>> Yeah, yeah.
All the other whales have got like fused necks, but they can go, uh-huh, to the hat to the
leg area.
Yeah.
>> I couldn't work out if that fused neck thing meant, because we have unfused necks.
>> Yes.
I've vertebrae, and mostly they've got bits in between them, meaning we can wiggle our
neck around.
>> Yeah.
I was trying to work out if that meant a beluga could look to one side while you were swimming
along next to it.
And I don't know how far they can move their heads.
>> It's a great question, but I think not.
>> Okay.
Okay.
So they are the most, they're the cats of the ocean, basically.
They're the most flexible whales there are.
>> Yeah.
>> They're also, they're nicknamed sea canaries, which I love.
>> Oh, yes.
Because they can make all sorts of noise.
They can whistle and sing and moo and click and squeal and --
>> And speak.
>> Speak.
>> Speak human words.
>> What do they know?
>> Yeah.
So there was a beluga whale called Nosey, and Nosey had been part of like the army was
kind of training him and stuff like that, because there is a bit of that that goes on
with the U.S. and with Russia or the Soviets.
And one time there was a Navy diver and he was underwater and someone said, "Get out!"
And he got out and he said, "Who said that?"
And it turned out none of the humans had said it, but this beluga whale had said it.
>> Really?
>> What are you talking about?
>> It's true, honestly.
And there was --
>> You got down's notes.
>> No.
In 2012, there was a paper called Spontaneous Human Speech Mimicry in a Citation, which
was about this particular beluga whale.
And we have actual evidence of it making sounds that are a bit like human voices.
>> Yeah, right.
>> So it's a bit like a parrot might copy you, that kind of thing.
>> Yeah, yeah.
Do you know where a lot of this studying is going on of these belugas?
>> In the water, isn't it?
>> Yes, in the water, but obviously you need them contained and you need to be studying
them, right?
So there is --
>> It's so suspicious of what you're going to say, Dan.
>> It's called the Mystic Aquarium.
>> And where is it?
>> In a village called Mystic.
>> Okay.
>> In Connecticut, yeah.
>> That's brilliant.
>> So annoying, because I thought that whole thing, that maybe they were looking into telepathy
or something like that, but actually it's just -- it's the town called Mystic.
>> Well, who named the town?
>> Oh, it's Summer.
>> The whales.
>> Oh.
>> No.
>> Okay.
>> Don't encourage it, Andy.
>> They're amazing.
They're amazing things.
>> Yeah.
>> They're really beautiful.
So they live in the Arctic and then they come down during the summer months and they feed
and breed and then they go back up, I think, during the winter months.
And the whole thing about a beluga is that they don't have a dorsal fin on their back,
right?
They don't have a poppy-uppy fin that, say, a killer whale does, and killer whales prey
on belugas.
They love to eat them, and part of the reason that the beluga is able to avoid the killer
whale is that they live under the sea ice in the Arctic.
So the sea ice is a really important environment for them, even if it's 96% sea ice and there
are these tiny cracks in the ice where there's sort of air above it.
They can approach that crack and they can stick their back up so their blowhole finds
that crack perfectly.
>> Ah.
>> They can breathe.
>> Oh, wow.
>> Because they're mammals and they have to breathe there.
>> Exactly.
And so that's how they avoid orcas, because the orcas can't follow, because the orcas
can't risk getting their fin stuck in sea ice and they can't be under sea ice that long.
>> It's kind of like hiding -- I'm trying to work out -- it's like hiding from a really
tall person in a short -- in a small -- in a low-roofed room, isn't it?
And every time the tall person tries to get in, they hit their head.
I mean, it is like that.
>> Yeah, but you need to very occasionally pop out of the room for something.
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
You have a snorkel leading up to the attic.
>> I don't think it needed a terribly complicated --
>> Just for anyone who didn't understand.
>> The lack of docile fin means that it's quite hard for them to steady themselves in the water.
>> To help that, they have love handles.
So they have bits of fat on their sides, and, again, they're attached to muscles, and they
can move them along their sides, and it helps them to be steady in the water.
>> Yeah, that's pretty amazing.
And their skin, as well, they go slowly off every year.
They just -- their skin goes a bit off yellow, and they just look a bit manky.
And so they have to swim to a bunch of rocks and sort of like grating cheese just grate
themselves away.
>> You mean like getting one of those files for your feet?
>> Yeah.
>> A full-body one.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Pretty cool idea.
>> 'Cause they go through seasonal malt, but it doesn't just come off, so they have to
go down and literally just rub themselves against rocks until --
>> It is quite gross, actually.
>> It's like you rubbing yourself against a gravestone.
>> God.
>> How do you know that my thing malts?
>> Oh, God.
>> God, that's a fucking odd sentence.
>> And you call me Barry Penis.
>> No, you're Kanto.
>> I'm Barry Penis.
>> No, I'm Barry Penis.
Fun fact about the film Spartacus.
>> I think we should say that all toothed whales have a melon.
It's not -- so belugas have the big one that sticks out that they're famous for, but all
toothed whales have one, and I think they must be used in communication, 'cause I think
it's for -- they obviously echolocate, and it's almost for transmitting their cliques.
But sperm whales have one as well, but theirs often gets called the junk.
Actually they have -- it's sort of split into two bits, so they've got their junk, and then
underneath they've got their sperm-assetti organ.
And I never knew why they were called sperm whales, and why -- so you know this sperm-assetti
organ is the organ that's kind of in their head -- oh, well, it's an organ in their head
filled with white liquid, and it's, we believe, for -- yeah, communicating.
>> And they keep that next to their junk.
>> They keep it next to their junk.
>> What is it for?
>> It is like the melon.
It is the melon, so we think it's for basically transmitting echolocation signals and helping
to control them as they leave.
>> And it would come back into, like, a chamber where it echoes around, and they can --
>> Wow, so cool.
>> That's so cool.
>> But the reason they're called sperm whales and the reason it's called sperm-assetti is
just because when they first found it, everyone thought it was their semen.
>> Really?
>> So whalers in the 19th century cracked open sperm whale heads when there's white stuff
in here.
That must be where they keep their sperm.
>> I was reading a thing, an exciting new idea about belugas, and it's a research paper
that's been released recently.
It is the idea that belugas could very well be the Loch Ness monster.
And it's called, "Could the Loch Ness monster also be the result of Lake River sightings
of belugas?"
And so someone has put forward --
>> That's a very sharp paper when the answer is just, "No."
>> Well, they're saying there's a lot of stuff that would be very similar.
The body length is kind of in a similar length, the two-meter length, the dorsal fin is absent.
That is a big thing that teeth are present, clearly visible, recognizable.
The paper has a bit that says problems.
One, geographical location.
That's an issue.
>> You do get belugas off the fjords that are out to the right of the Ness.
They do get them.
>> They go up rivers.
>> Exactly.
>> And they've been found in the Thames and so on.
>> They're slightly salt/freshwater agnostic.
>> Exactly.
>> So could the beluga whale actually be the Loch Ness monster?
>> What do you think?
>> Do you think?
>> Yeah, totally possible.
>> Who peer reviews the papers that you find online?
>> This was published on mysticacquarium.com.
That's such a rare four out of four for you.
>> We normally don't get that.
Yeah, it's very -- guys, that's impressive.
I heard the booze and that's -- I appreciate that.
We are going to have to wrap up fairly soon, guys.
Any more beluga?
>> Well, just what does a beluga have in common with a blonde in a joke that's offensive
to blonde people?
>> Do you remember that joke that's like there's a blonde with headphones on all the time?
I don't approve of this, by the way, if you're blonde, but headphones on all the time and
everyone's like why are you wearing headphones?
Why are you wearing headphones?
And eventually someone takes the headphones off and she dies.
What was the -- what were the headphones saying?
>> It's saying remember to breathe in and out.
>> Breathe in, breathe out, breathe in, breathe out, but beluga whales need the headphones.
In fact, all whales, they need -- breathing is not an unconscious thing.
They actually need to remember to breathe, not just to go to the top to breathe, which
they do need to do, but if they don't actually tell themselves to breathe every time they
do it, they just stop breathing and die.
>> What?
>> Yeah.
>> But is it genuinely a problem?
>> No, sometimes it happens in aquariums where they think they just decide that they've
had it and you can just stop breathing.
>> Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> It's so good to end on a fun one, isn't it?
It's so good to end on a fun one.
>> I think whale suicide is going to be a good punch now.
>> I think whales, like populations, getting a bit better, right, isn't it?
The whaling has gotten less and less as the years have gone on.
We have more whales now than we've had in recent years.
And the thing is, when they're more sort of spread out, they find each other formating
by singing, and now that there's more of them, they actually do less singing and they kind
of fight each other a lot more.
So that means that whales are whaling less due to less whaling.
>> Very nice.
>> Guys, I'm going to have to wrap us up.
That is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we've said over
the course of this podcast, we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @Shrieberland.
James.
>> @BurryPenis.
>> Andy.
>> I'm not saying Mike.
>> You've actually been banned recently, haven't you?
>> No, I've been let back on.
>> And @Ada, where can they get to us as a group?
>> You can go to Twitter, no such thing, or no such things as a fish on Instagram, or
you can email podcast.qi.com.
>> Or you can go to our website, no such thing as a fish.com.
All of our previous episodes are there.
We have a club called Club Fish.
If you haven't joined it yet, please do, and also check out all of our upcoming tour dates.
Thank you so much, Edinburgh.
This was the start of our Thundernurds Tour, and that was fucking awesome.
So thank you for being here.
We'll see you again soon.
Goodbye!
[MUSIC]
(upbeat music)