[MUSIC PLAYING]
Hi, everyone.
Welcome to this week's episode of "No, She's Thing as a Fish,"
where we were joined by the fantastic Angela Barnes.
Yeah, she's absolutely amazing.
She's been on fish before.
I didn't get to be on the show with her,
so I was very excited to sit down with her.
She's full of facts.
She's full of jokes.
And she's full of tour.
She's on tour now.
She's on tour twice, in fact.
She is doing her own tour, which is called "anxed."
And she's also touring with a British iconic series.
That's right, "The Archers."
Anyone who listens to Radio 4 will know that show,
and no other show.
And Andy's "The Naked Week" is available as well.
And she's doing a live version of that.
So if you go online, put in "The Archers" tour.
You'll find dates for that.
But go see "anxed."
She's a brilliant stand-up.
She's on tour right now.
So on the 11th of April, she's going to be in Cheshirem.
And then there's places like Hastings and "Hammelhamstead"
and "Iveybridge" Heriford.
A lot of these shows are nearly sold out
to get your tickets now.
"Hammelhamstead" is where all the hamsters live
that used to live in "Hammelhamstead."
Oh, yes, that's an interesting fact.
We should do that on the show.
Or we should pronounce places properly.
Anyway, if you want to go get those tickets,
go to Angela Barnes, comedy.co.uk,
and go see her life now.
One more thing, do join Clubfish.
Go to patreon.com/clubfish.
If you want to get involved with that community,
loads of extra stuff, merch, bonus material.
You know all about it.
If you don't know about it, go to patreon.com/clubfish
and you'll find out more about it.
OK, on with the podcast.
On with the show.
Hello, and welcome to another episode of "No Such Thing
as a Fish" a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and Angela Barnes.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Angela.
OK, so my fact is that the number four is orange
and a lot kinder, the number five, which
has an attitude problem.
Wow, are we talking about number blocks?
Yeah, I don't have children.
So I don't know what you're talking about there.
But I'm assuming that's a CBB question.
Four is orange and it's kind.
And it's kind.
But number five is quite aggressive and has an attitude problem.
OK, so what are you talking about?
I'm talking about synesthesia.
So you may have heard of synesthesia.
I'm a synesthet.
So I was diagnosed with synesthesia when I was 19 at university.
And I've got several types.
But the main one is graphene color synesthesia.
So that means that numbers, letters, days of the week,
any abstract concepts have a color.
And I always say, it doesn't mean I see auras.
I know I'm for Christ, but not that person.
It's hard to explain when you are a synesthene.
Because the reason I didn't know I had it till I was 19
is because we all just sort of assume everyone's brain
works broadly the same as ours.
And so I don't know--
I don't understand how you don't have colors.
Can I ask a question?
You may.
You have a sheet of paper in front of you.
I do.
It's black and white.
Yes.
When you look at that, is it like the colored in the letters?
Or is it whatever?
So some people have a sort of synesthesia which is projected.
So they do exactly that.
It sort of changes color when they look at it.
For me, it's very internal.
So it's in my mind's eye, if you like, one of the better words.
Yes.
So I'm currently part of a study at Sussex University.
There's Professor Julia Simner at Sussex Uni.
And she specializes in perception and synesthesia.
And I wrote to her a couple of years ago
because when I think every thought I have
is in a physical location from the real world.
So when I think about the number four, it's always in the sky.
But it's orange.
So it's all floating orange in the sky.
And so I contacted her to say, is this a form of synesthesia?
And she said, well, I've never heard of it,
but let's do a study.
And so they found a handful of people
that seemed to experience the same thing.
And so she's studying it.
She's calling it conception, location, synesthesia,
is what she's calling it.
But also, if you heard of Adam Zeman,
so he's the man who came up with the word aphantasia
for people who have no internal images.
Like me.
Oh, do you have aphantasia?
So Julia's very interested in that as well.
What a sandwich, I'm sitting in.
Right.
In between synesthesia and aphantasia.
I thought all the images that you don't have in my brain, basically.
It feels a bit greedy, really, actually.
I'll be honest.
Well, there was a massive coincidence.
It was about two years ago I contacted Julia.
And around the same time, Adam Zeman contacted her
and said, I've had someone get in touch
to describe this phenomenon about location when they're thinking.
And she said, oh, that must be Angela.
She contacted me as well.
And he said, no, it's someone else entirely.
And it just happened to be within the same two weeks.
So they're now both doing studies on this.
On telekinesis.
On telekinesis, if only with that.
It's morphic resonance, I think.
Yeah, actually.
Thank you.
Calling it, it's quite, he's calling it topo phantasia, which makes sense.
So there is a thing of, I mean, I'm not synesthesiatical.
A synesthetic.
A synesthesiatical.
But I don't have any phantasia.
But I do have the, I'm sure lots of people
have the location specific.
A sensory thing triggers a spatial memory.
So if I smell green chilies roasting, I'm in New Mexico.
And it's autumn, you know?
So that's very linked to memory.
So that's really common that when we smell something,
the thing with synesthesia is there isn't a link.
You've just described memory.
No, no, no.
And she was politely saying, it's a really common thing.
So for me, it's if I smell baked beans cooking,
I'm in my full canteen.
That's kind of, you're really common, Andy.
But it's, don't lie, man.
What I'm trying to say is it triggers a specific,
like a specific sensation triggers a really specific memory.
Prusky, yeah.
So what they think is with people with synesthesia
is what one of the, there's lots of theories
and they don't know exactly what causes synesthesia.
They do, they have worked out that it's hereditary
and then it's, to do with the X chromosome.
But what they think happens is that when you're a child
before you acquire language, you obviously
have to interpret the world around you in a different way
without words.
And so you have this extra white matter,
extra connections in your brain to different parts
of your brain.
And in most people, they sort of get pruned away
as you don't need them anymore.
Right.
And then, but with people with synesthesia,
those connections don't get pruned, they stay.
And so what it means is that you get a sort of an odd reaction
to a stimulus, and by odds, I just mean one that isn't typical.
So for someone with synesthesia, a part of my brain
gets triggered when I see a certain letter
or I hear something or whatever
that wouldn't normally be triggered in that situation.
And so it's just a hyper-connected brain.
Look, they call it.
And so there's lots of things to go with it,
like, misophonia, misekinesia, all these things.
People with synesthesia tend to do that.
So you hate to when people are chewing next to you?
I hate to when people are chewing next to you.
I have really strong misophonia.
I am synesthesiatic.
[LAUGHTER]
You can have misophonia, and yeah, it's really--
What about people putting their feet on the seats
on the train?
Is that a special power that I have to find that annoying?
Well, I think you're just a bit old man.
I don't think it could be that bad.
I think everyone should be angry with people
in their fields.
I think that's everything.
But misekinesia is something that, again, I only recently--
I had a meeting with Julia a couple of months ago,
just to sort of see how the study was going and stuff.
So I'm hoping to write a book about it.
And she told me about misekinesia, which really made me go,
oh, yes, I have that.
My husband is what I'd call a jiggula,
one of those feet just doesn't stop moving, consciously.
If I can see a part of his body moving out
of the corner of my eye, it drives me insane.
If I can just see a movement, and they call it misekinesia,
as she told me, it made me feel better about it.
It might make you feel better about your misophonia,
is that apparently it's the salience network in your brain,
which is activated when you have misophonia.
And it is the same reaction, basically.
She describes it to me as if a bear had walked in the room.
Yeah.
So it's sort of that ancient part of your brain being triggered.
That's right.
I'm really interested, Angela.
OK, so that's the colors we talked about a little bit.
But what is this about them having personality?
So that is something which is called
ordinal linguistic personification.
So some letters and numbers have personalities
to people as soon as they see it.
So most of the numbers I find quite friendly,
apart from number five.
Sorry, quick question.
If there were a room of, say, 20 people
who all had this particular type of synesthesia,
would you all agree the colors?
You've all got your own separate colors.
I think there are some trends, if you like,
to some colors are picked more often.
They don't really know why.
Yeah, for example, the days of the week
have very fixed colors for me.
Most people, if you ask them what colors Monday,
we'll say blue, yeah, because of the blue Monday
or the association.
So you can predict quite often what people will say.
But in synestheets, they're random.
There's another, which I find amazing.
I didn't know about all these varieties.
Oh, there's over 150 types of synesthesia
that they know of now.
So the one I love most is mirror touch synesthesia.
That's what it is, where you feel what someone else feels.
If you see it happening to them,
and there are a couple of amazing coast studies,
there's a woman called Carolyn.
She's a massage therapist,
and she remembers very clearly being three years old,
seeing, I think, a dog break its leg,
and she immediately felt blinding pain
in, I guess, one of her real, real, or front leg.
I guess, one of her legs.
One of her legs, and she felt enormous pain.
So she can't watch action movies
because she just feels so much what's going on.
But she's a massage therapist, so her job is terrific
because it feels like she's constantly being rough.
(laughing)
Really, she's massaging herself
as she doesn't feel so much of her.
She just picked the noises.
That would be awkward, isn't it?
(laughing)
And there's one other guy, a doctor called Joel Salinas,
and he's a doctor, and this is a big problem
in his line of work, because if he sees--
Oh, God, he's so sergent.
He saw someone having a cardiac arrest,
and he felt very, you know,
obviously you don't feel exactly what they do,
but you feel very strongly.
The patient died, and he did not.
So clearly there is a--
There's a, yeah.
I'm working on Fudge Fest.
(laughing)
Sometimes I know people with mirror sinuses
get just a tingling sensation,
so if they see someone hurt their arm,
they'll get a tingling in their arm,
or so it's not always a complete mirror,
but still in the same area.
I think I have the opposite of that,
because I took my daughter to nursery this morning,
and she fell off her scooter
and got a little scrape on her knee,
and I was like, come on, it doesn't hurt.
(laughing)
That's gonna be an 80s dad, I think you should be.
But we do, I think we all experience,
like if you want to picture the experience of it,
if you ever see someone kick really hard in the genitals,
that involuntary, or do yourself,
that must be what it feels like
for people all the time.
Also, yeah, yeah, yeah.
The only way I found out I had it
is I was doing linguistics at Sussex University,
and there was a lecture, Larry Trash,
who's sadly no longer with us,
but he did a lecture about language acquisition in children,
and they were talking about this theory that,
well, I just said earlier,
the connections die out, and then these people can,
and I remember sitting in that lecture,
going for everyone's, it has colors
from what you're talking about.
And then I came home, and I told my dad first,
and he said, well, surely everyone had,
I was like, okay, but now I can see there's a hereditary line.
And then when I told my mom,
she said, oh, that explains why you used to get so angry
at the magnetic letters when you were a kid,
you say we're the wrong color.
- It was a study in 2013 that looked at people in America
with synesthesia, and found that a lot of them
associated the same colors with letters
as those magnetic letters.
- Right.
- And a lot of people kind of pointed at that as saying,
well, this is, it's just made up, isn't it?
It's just like, the only reason you think A is red
is 'cause you have these magnets and you thought A is red.
And so James Wanatan, the UK Synesthesia Association,
is quite annoyed by it.
(laughing)
And he says, it's really annoying
that people try and explain it away.
But actually, it is interesting because these colors,
are they always the same?
Like you say, they're different for everyone.
But for you in particular, are your colors always,
have they been the same your whole life
'cause they do change for some people?
- So this is a really interesting point,
because up until recently, consistency was a way
of sort of confirming whether someone had synesthesia.
So what you would do, you would do the test
and then six months later you'd do it again
and then you'd do it again.
But the main reason they did that was because
there have been periods in time when being a synesthesia
has been fashionable.
And so because lots of people self-identified
as synesthesia who weren't synesthesia,
it was very difficult to do studies on synesthesia.
So the way they did it was to use this consistency idea.
But it doesn't necessarily mean that if it's not consistent,
you're not a synesthesia.
It just means if it isn't consistent,
then you definitely are.
- Yeah, I read a study of a woman just known as AB
who sees colors when she hears music.
It's a different tones, have different colors right.
But then the paper said, "So say she had a series
"of unfortunate events would be an understatement."
As a teenager, she sustained several concussions,
had migraines, contracted viral meningitis,
and was struck by lightning.
- Oh my God.
- Oh wow.
- She's born on a Friday to Thursday.
- Five luck is there.
But every time one of these things happened,
like the colors changed, but by the end, they all came back.
So it would change and then it would come back
and then it would change and then come back.
- So I find, I do a lot of crosswords.
I love cryptic crosswords and word puzzles and things.
And particularly, I don't even know the spelling bee
on New York Times.
Some days I can't do it because the letter is so arrogant
in the middle that I just go, (laughing)
- That's my excuse when I don't manage
to do a crossword as well.
I'm sorry, just, please don't review any of our books.
(laughing)
- Just in case.
- What is the most arrogant letter?
I've got three, A, H, M, but what is your last name?
- Wow.
(laughing)
- And took me a minute, but I've got those.
Now, the most arrogant letter is probably X.
- Yeah.
- I think so.
- Yeah, sorry.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, it keeps itself from self, yeah.
- So you've got graphene color,
which is your type of synesthesia.
So other people who supposedly had it
was Richard Feynman, the great physicist,
who used to see the equations in various different colors
as he was writing them.
Vladimir Nabakov also had that.
And then there's another one which is called
Chromesthesia, which is where you pair color with sound.
And a lot of musicians have this.
So supposedly, I mean, you get these lists online,
and so some of these might have just made it through
anecdotes, Lee, but aren't necessarily true.
But Stevie Wonder supposedly has it.
So he sees color when he's writing songs,
Beyonce has it, Charlie XCX.
- Jimmy Harrigan, Charlie XCX.
(laughing)
- And Jimmy Hendrix had it.
And apparently there was a chord,
which is known as the Hendrix chord,
it's also the purple chord,
'cause he would see purple when he wrote it,
and the song Purple Hayes is the Hayes.
And it's that chord is used a lot in that song.
- Oh nice.
- Yeah, nice.
- This is one I find most fascinating
that I don't experience.
Lexical gustatory, where people hear words
and taste certain tastes.
- So they might hear a trigger word,
and they somebody can taste licorice or strawberry.
- So the guy, who is it?
Was it you James and mentioned James Wanatan,
the president of the UK's Sinner's Thesia Association?
He has this, and he visited every tube,
overground, and documents like Railway Station
to find out what they tasted like.
He sounds like one of us, yeah.
(laughing)
Tom and Corrode, the sausage and egg,
King's Cross, Rich Fruitcake,
and he produced a tube match.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- The flavor's really good.
- That's really good.
- That's sort of the one I wish I had.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It's like a cool one.
- Yeah, there are.
- Sexual Sinner's Thesia.
- Well, I will say, I don't mind saying this
on an orgasm to have colours.
- Ah.
- So depending on intensity or what,
and it's usually through the red spectrum.
So it's usually red or orange.
So always say, my husband knows it's been a good night
if he says, "How was it for you?"
And I say burnt omba.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- Well that's a very, that's very farrow and bold as well.
Elephant's breath.
(laughing)
Very booty.
- Wow.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Andy.
- My fact is, in 1577, there was only one man in England
permitted to touch the queen.
- Mmm.
- The king?
- Yeah.
- No, it wasn't on them.
- No king, so we're on Queen Elizabeth I.
- Yeah, okay.
- Who for international listeners, kind of a big deal?
- Yeah.
- Virgin Queen.
- Virgin Queen, did she ever see burnt omba?
- We don't know.
- We don't.
(laughing)
- We don't know.
- It was quite burnt omba.
- That's true.
- Yeah.
- So I went to a gallery recently, which was in South London,
it's a Greenwich and they have a thing called the Queen's
gallery there.
It's amazing, lots of amazing artworks.
And there was one portrait of a courtier
from the 16th century, who was called Richard Drake.
And the little, you know, information panel said,
this guy was the only person permitted to touch the queen.
- Wow.
- And there was the master of the queen's horse,
so helping her mount onto her horse, that kind of thing.
And I think it was a cousin of Francis Drake.
- And to say, was he related to Francis Drake?
- Yeah, so they're quite a posh family.
- Yeah.
- And they had all sorts of connections and, you know,
built all sorts of things.
- How did he, did he sort of, like, go on all fours
so she could walk on his back?
- That was it.
- That was exactly it.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- No, he was throw her on.
It was amazing.
(laughing)
- Like, how'd we get around by the house?
- Like, do you do the hand thing where you stand?
- A Lego.
- That's the class we get, I think that is the class we get.
- I can absolutely imagine it being him on all fours
and she steps on his back.
- True, yeah, yeah.
- Or a piggyback.
(laughing)
- Shoulder-eyed, I think.
- Shoulder-eyed.
- Shoulder-eyed over to the horse and then, yeah.
- Right, she's a transver.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And me, whenever they think of Elizabeth I,
only has Miranda Richland here.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But we've never really spoken about her before
and she was the most interesting woman and monarch
and just crazy.
The last Tudor, that's interesting, end of her house
'cause she died without her.
So obviously the whole royal system changes after her
and we get James I of Scotland in as King next.
But daughter of Henry VIII.
- Daughter of Henry VIII.
Not expected to become Queen of Thor
because she was the daughter of Anne Boleyn.
- Yeah.
- Her dad beheaded her mum.
I mean, this is...
- That's some therapy, she's there, isn't she?
And also she was never legitimized.
I wish you, in law, like Henry VIII changed the succession law
so that she could succeed.
But he never officially changed it.
He's sort of declared it.
So there was, I think throughout her reign,
there were questions on her legitimacy.
- Yeah, how interesting, 'cause then her father,
Henry VIII, obviously lots of wives
and then Anne Boleyn was the second wife
and with his third wife, Jane Seymour,
he had Edward VI who was a son, so became heir,
but then after VI died after only a few years on the throne,
then there was some Mary,
Queen Mary, Catholic, all the religious stuff.
(laughing)
So her childhood was crazy
because she grew up in very, very rich circumstances
and then when her mother was executed
when she was under three years old, it all changed
and it was all taken away.
And supposedly after Anne Boleyn was beheaded her mother,
she, the young Elizabeth asked her governor,
why governor?
How happened yesterday, Lady Princess
and today but Lady Elizabeth?
- Possibly this is when she was two years and eight months.
- I find her a bit, okay, girl.
- I thought those people on Facebook, isn't it?
You'll never guess what little Tommy said this morning?
No, he didn't.
(laughing)
- Exactly.
- Interesting.
I was looking at some other people in Queen Elizabeth's cot.
So there was one of her favorites
was a woman called Lettice Nollies and Lettice.
Well, Lettice was in Queen Elizabeth's cot
for 15 to 20 years, which is 150 times longer
than Liz Truss was prime minister.
(laughing)
But she was like one of her absolute favorites
and then she married a Robert Dudley in secret.
A Robert Dudley was the bloke who Queen Elizabeth
really fancied and when she married this guy,
she was out, Queen Elizabeth said,
I don't wanna see you anymore.
But he was also, I think, the master of the horse
just before Richard Drake, he served a term.
So he would have, I don't know if he had the same privileges
of being the only man to be able to touch him.
- He must have been.
- He certainly touched him emotionally, don't he?
- Did Lettice, was she, he wasn't executed, right?
- She wasn't executed.
- We didn't know the head of Lettice.
(laughing)
- Okay, oh, I can't believe that Mark's straight into that one.
- I had to really force Mark away into that.
(laughing)
- We actually know a descendant of Lettice.
- Do we?
- I think the four of us must know this descendant of Lettice
because we happen to know the 13 times great grandson.
- Lettice.
- Oh, lettice, do you know who it is?
- It's not Whittaker, is it?
- It's Josh Whittaker.
- Yeah.
- It's a comedian Josh Whittaker.
- Oh, was that from the, who do you think you are?
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, that's great.
- Yeah.
- Exactly.
- We still have, you call them equaries
that look after the horses in the, in the royal household.
And the senior equity to Queen Camilla is called major rob treasurer.
Which, I don't think you should have them in the royal family.
(laughing)
- It's a bit on the nose, isn't it?
- Something's gone missing for the time London.
Okay, Brigand Rob Treasurer.
- It's either gonna be Paul Burrell or Rob Treasurer.
(laughing)
- And it was a big, it was a big roll of the Master of the Horses
back then.
- You know, if you think about, oh, you're in charge of the horses.
These days, just in charge of this sort of rich bit of your life, right?
But back then, that was, that's like looking after the cars.
That was looking after the transport to war.
That was looking after your main line of soldier.
- There's so many things.
- There's so many things, yes.
(laughing)
- And the main man.
- That's what he should have been called.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Master of the Horses.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, like, so back then, that was an incredibly important roll.
You would breeding, you were buying, you were purchasing.
It was type of army, wasn't it?
It was a whole bit of the army.
So, these days, less so.
Now it's about maintenance.
But still, horses very big within the world of the royals,
at least up until Queen Elizabeth II,
who, you know, she used to make sure that she was at
all the horse races.
- Oh yeah, she got racing, yeah.
- She owned so many horses.
She was obsessed with how her horses
were being bred.
She had, I feel like she won the Grand National
or something.
- Oh my goodness.
She won so much.
- I think, yeah.
She, I think, didn't she have a massive horse treadmill as well?
- Oh yeah.
- She had a tremble where 18 horses could exercise
at the same time.
- Wow.
- She made something impressive like that.
- I once did an after dinner at the Guards Polo Club.
- Ooh.
- A spectacular piece of missbooking.
(laughing)
- She was good to describe that.
It was one of the worst.
- Did they book you?
Your name is Barnes.
- Maybe.
(laughing)
- Was Andrew stable, not bad?
- I got there, this is a true story.
So this was 15 years ago.
So I was a brand new comedian
and I didn't know to say no to something like that.
(laughing)
And I turned up and for a start,
I went, I thought I could wear to this thing.
It was black tie up.
Duke of Edinburgh's Polo Club.
- Right.
- And so I went and bought a dress from Debenham,
which I thought was good enough.
And then I got there and went, "Oh, this doesn't count it."
- That's all.
And then anyway, I did the gig
and it was, you know, as expected, hard work.
And then as I was leaving,
a woman stopped me in the door.
She literally said to me,
"I knew when I saw you arrive,
"you must be the entertainer."
(laughing)
- Wow.
- I knew you could have been married
to a Polo player, not with that hair.
(laughing)
- What?
- It was all for that.
But with the money I made from that gig,
I went on holiday to Cuba.
- There we go.
- Who got the last laugh?
- Very nice.
- Okay.
- Gosh.
- Yeah, just what I was through.
- What a bunch of (beep)
- They were, it was funny.
'Cause I also did the thing that I now know
you don't do it after dinners or corporates.
But I was very green at the time.
And I sat and had dinner with them.
- When you say you were green,
was it on Tuesday?
- It was Tuesday.
(laughing)
- I go say, like, it is an elite of saying,
I slightly give the queen a pass
because it is the queen.
I feel like, okay, you know,
that's part of the job having lots of horses.
- Yeah.
- And I do like what a nerd she was about it
because she properly was.
She would even have CCTV cameras installed
at Sandringham's stud farm
so that she could see the birth of horses.
- Oh, she get an alert.
- She was really invested in it.
And also the names are so geeky.
So the families of various horses that she had.
So there was one called hypotenuse
who had falls that were called Geometrist,
equal sum, long side, Pythagorean.
There was Wink of an Eye who was the son of momentary
and her mother was fleeting memory.
So she had all these names.
Anyway, they're all being sold off
'cause I think Charles is not as into it.
And the guardian has estimated that if all the horses are sold,
it's gonna be roughly 27 million
that they'll make off the back.
- Wow.
- Yeah, he still keeps horses like ceremonial horses,
doesn't he, but he just doesn't do the horse races.
- Yes, so.
- He, in 2024, he appointed Captain Cat Anderson
as the first female equity to a sovereign in history.
- Wow.
- Progress.
(laughing)
- One step at a time, that's awesome.
- Something about not touching royals.
- Oh, yeah.
- I read a newspaper article from the early 20th century
and it said that in 1894 there was a footman
of the King of Spain who was in the palace
and young prince Alfonso was walking across
and then fell down some stairs
and this footman caught him and was immediately fired
to a touching a member of the royal family.
- Oh, really?
- Let him die.
(laughing)
- Let's go.
- Just let him go.
- Apparently the Queen mother then rewarded him
with the generous private pension,
but he didn't get his job back
'cause the rules were you just now allowed to touch them.
- How many royals have you guys touched?
Not one.
- I've met one, but I've not.
- You didn't touch?
- I didn't touch her, but I met the Queen.
- Oh.
- I tell you.
- Well, I say I met the Great.
- I was a student nurse and I was working
at the Homsen Hospital in Hackney.
She came to open a new bit of the,
it was a stroke-free habit unit I worked on.
- Right.
- And she, it was mad 'cause that day,
Hackney got tied it up.
I've never seen anything like it.
There were streets weepers out.
- Oh, that's the job.
- Oh, isn't it?
(laughing)
- That's what I hate.
- Right.
- Exactly.
- Or just the route that she was going.
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Not all of Hackney obviously.
- Oh, these buildings are arranged.
(laughing)
- But there was a lot.
- It was looking very pretty.
- Yeah, it was.
- All these artwork appeared in hospital the day before.
- Yeah.
- Or went again the day after tomorrow.
- Oh, I really, yeah.
Wherever she went, that artwork.
- Yeah.
- So weird, everywhere I go, I have the same painting.
(laughing)
- And it was like, was it Katherine the Great
who had the Potemkin villages that she thought
wherever she went?
The villages of Russia were so beautiful and stuff
because wherever she went,
they just built the bomb.
- And he, that was sort of cool to call Potemkin.
- Yeah.
- And he built these, like.
- But I wonder if the Queen thought that as well.
And the King thinks that it's just like,
oh, London's lovely.
- Lovely.
- Yeah.
- But he's London is gorgeous.
- He'll go 'cause everywhere she goes,
smells of fresh paint.
So she thinks that was what the world smells like, you know.
- Yeah, exactly.
- There was a man came round from the palace,
like the week before she came to teach us how to curtsy.
If we wanted to curtsy, we didn't have to,
but if you wanted to, you could.
And to teach us that it was man,
I'm with him, not man.
But none of us were allowed to take
and you'll leave that day.
So we all had to sort of line up.
And she did the class, she stopped in front of,
there's me in my uniform and a physiotherapist next to me.
And she stopped and looked at me and did the, what do you do?
It's like, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm not with that hair.
(laughing)
- Oh, the entertainment, right?
- Dad, you went the vast the question,
if you haven't touched a matter of.
- No, I just read, I was counting in my head.
I'm on four.
- You touched four, right?
- Yeah.
- It was when you were on the island, wasn't it?
(laughing)
- Sorry, I've been touched by four.
- Let me point to the bits they touched.
- The, no, the queen.
- I've touched the queen.
- I touched it.
- What?
- No, you're not allowed to touch the queen.
- You're not allowed to touch the queen.
- These be royal equery.
(laughing)
- Wish you're good.
- That's touching.
- Are you allowed to shake hands?
- That's very rare.
- What?
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- Well, that's, I mean.
- She must have liked you.
- Yeah, she must have taken to it.
- She only usually does fizz bumps, doesn't she?
(laughing)
- Since COVID it's been able to do this.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So I shook hands with the queen,
gave Philip a high five.
I had a thumb war with Edward.
(laughing)
And the old full body with Prins Andrew, yeah.
- How much of that is true, any of it?
- Oh, well, no, I shook the queen's hand.
I shook Philip's hand.
I shook Edward's hand.
And then I shook the form of Princess at Denmark's hand.
But when I was a kid, she was weirdly our neighbor
in Hong Kong before she was changed.
- We come from very different backgrounds.
- You're gonna say truth or lie.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the 10th best formula one driver
in the world can't drive.
(laughing)
When I say drive, I mean regular cars.
He can't drive regular cars.
Now this was Orvid Linblad and he is a very young
Formula One driver, he's 18.
And he was talking to Max Verstappen,
who also started very young.
In fact, will be forever the youngest Formula One driver
because rules have changed.
And you have to now be 18 and older.
And he was 17 when he was driving.
And they were having a chat and he said,
something about you driving, he said, no, I don't have a license.
And so he can sit behind the wheel of a Formula One car,
but he can't drive on a regular road.
- So do you get a different license for Formula One?
- Super license.
- Yeah, so the FIA, the federation international
Dautomobile, the FIA has to, they issue super licenses
for Formula One racing.
And so Orvid Linblad and Kimi Antonelli,
who drives from Mercedes, he was issued
an early super license as well in 2024.
- Point, no one's stopping you.
And so in the middle of a race, and say, excuse me, sir.
- Do you know how fast you were going back there?
- But you can get points on your super license.
And you can have a great, absolutely.
So it's a rolling 12 months.
So there was a point where, oh, who was it?
There was a driver who almost got,
'cause you get a race band.
It might be Max Verstappen, actually,
who had almost 12 points within a 12 month period.
And if you get that,
you get a race band.
- And what is it for?
- So it can be, if you do something really dangerous,
essentially, so if it's something where,
'cause there's normal penalties during racing,
you've got to stop going penalties,
you've got like five second penalties,
10 second penalties, starting for a grid place penalty.
So you start the next race, five grid places back
from where you qualify, and things like that.
But if you do something really bad,
you get points on your own.
- Interesting.
- You also get fined for swearing.
- You get, do you get fined for the race?
- It's hard to car. - It's hard to car.
- On the radio, because the radio message will broadcast.
So there really, and he's been,
because of Mahamid bin Suriyam,
who's the head of the F1,
he is a, you know, from a Muslim country, et cetera.
So he's been really hot on,
and the drivers really get a backlash about against him.
'Cause they're like, well, you try crashing it,
you know, 200 miles an hour and knots, whatever it feels like.
It feels like swearing is one thing,
but if you're going, fire! (laughing)
- No. - I think you turn a blind eye to that.
- I think you mean, fly! (laughing)
- But they, they, so they brought, sorry, they broadcast these.
- No, no, you can hear them talking to that. - Yeah, radio,
and they actually now have a show you can watch after the broadcast,
where they play all the, - Oh, just, that's all.
- Like the best of the radio message. - Something you even dry,
the whole thing. - The whole thing. (laughing)
- It's not trying, it's great. - Oh.
- A41 isn't dry, but be the radio messages are so funny.
- I'm pleasing. - But they're fighting back,
so they have like a driver's association,
and the driver's association are saying, you know,
if we swear, but it's to make a point,
as opposed to insulting someone, then that should be fine.
So Max Verstappen, who we've mentioned,
he was fine for saying his car was fucked
during a press conference. - I think his car was fucked,
but there you go. (laughing)
During a press conference, come on.
- Yeah. - One thing I like about this super license
is that you have to do a theory test.
- Really? - Get it as well, just like a normal license.
So yeah, there's a knowledge test,
which is on the international sporting code
and F1 sporting regulations.
And then on top of that, the team has to show
that you've driven at a certain speed
for a certain number of kilometers in a one-seater car.
- Right. - In order for you to get that.
And you need to quite often,
you need to have done well in other races
that are not Formula One.
- I see, I mean, it all makes sense, doesn't it?
I guess would there be a hazard perception test?
(laughing)
There's an elderly lady crossing the road
for five miles ahead of you,
but you'll be on her in three seconds, so what are you doing?
- So this is an interesting thing about the age.
So this guy is very young that we're talking about.
- Yes. - The first guy.
But there are also, there are very young,
and there are very old drivers at the moment,
is that right, somewhere in the '40s--
- Fernando Lanzar, we thought--
- Not that old just to say. - Far off, I think.
- Absolutely, absolutely.
- Louis Hamilton's '41 now, I think.
- Yeah, but that's a really big range within the sport.
And I think the oldest ever Formula One champion
was Juan Manuel Fangio of Argentina.
And so he was ages ago, he was racing, it was in the '50s.
And he did his last one in 1957, age 46 years old,
was I think his last victory.
And when he started, I just love,
I mean, because obviously Formula One is so technical,
it's amazingly complicated, there are incredibly clever teams
working on how to make the cars more aerodynamic
and all of this.
When he was doing his racing, helmets were made of cloth
until 1952, and helmets were made compulsory that year,
and they were made of papier-maché, I read.
I know, the pie shaped helmets.
You would get covered in suit inside your car
because the cars are much more basic and you won't protect it.
And of course, people died by the dozen, every single year.
- I love looking at the photographs from 1950s race,
it's not 1950, so it's 75 years of Formula One last year.
And there was a great exhibition that I went to,
and you look at the photos of the drivers from the '50s,
and they're fat, like, and since, you know,
in modern Formula One cars are the monocork chassis
and they're tiny drivers, everyone.
- I don't know that.
- You don't get a lot of junkies.
- I don't know.
- Because it's a tiny space they have to sit in,
and you want them light, because obviously,
you don't want them to weigh down the car.
You've got a weight limit for the car.
And it's just these fat bloats with beer bellies and fags.
I just like, don't you see that in Formula One now?
It's brilliant.
We look at those old pictures.
- I found a list of all the people
who have ever raced in Formula One.
Paddy driver.
- Brilliant.
- Paddy's face it in two races.
Scoring no points.
Scott Speed was the first American driver to race in Formula One
since Mike Landretti, that was in 2006.
Hans Stuck.
- This is a German guy.
He was really interesting,
'cause he was friends with Hitler.
And then after the war, if you were German,
you weren't allowed to be in Formula One.
And that's because you needed to be a member of a society.
And after the war, you weren't allowed new clubs in Germany.
No one was allowed to join a club
and Formula One club,
which you would need to join your international authority.
You weren't allowed to have them.
So he then went to Austria and he said,
"Oh, no, I'm Austrian."
So, I'm for that instead.
- That's very interesting.
- One thing I was reading about,
'cause I do find it quite exciting to watch Formula One.
But one thing I think I'd be more excited to watch
is the pre-season testing of Formula One.
Because this is where the cars are making,
in some cases, their debut with new mechanics and new things,
but they try and hide what that is
before the actual start of the Formula One.
- Sound bagging.
- Yeah. - Like what?
- Yeah.
- And so there's all these different methods that they use.
So, for example, you remember those ships
that were supposedly black and white
and all those vehicles. - On the dazzle ships.
- The dazzle ships, they do that with Formula One cars
so that you can't quite spot
where they might have rearranged certain positions.
- Or they'll change all the stickers.
So you think the exhaust is in one spot,
but actually it's in another.
They try as much as they can to disguise it,
just so you don't get what they've done to their new cars.
But on top of that, if they've signed a new rookie,
or if someone's trying to make a comeback,
what they'll often do is they'll have one
of their existing drivers lend their helmet.
And so they'll, I thought you'd get to say,
oh, I thought you'd have the same mission
and possible style rubber masks, that's a shame.
Well, they might be wearing four.
- Might be under the helmet, but a bit more.
- It's just in case.
- No, but they'll go out in the helmet of another driver.
So that they think, oh, it's just him doing his test.
- I think so. - Actually, it's someone.
- Though it sounds like the six inches shorter this year,
that's good. - Yeah, yeah.
- Wonder what he's done by.
- You would have spiced someone who's had
the was the same size though, right?
- Yeah.
- I don't know, why don't you win a monocop though.
Like I suppose they'll just do the design.
That's the sort of what you're sat in the bit around you.
But the preseason test, it was really interesting this year
because there's been a big wall change
in Formula One this year.
So from 2022 up to 2025, they had ground effect cars.
So we're really high downforce low floors.
And there's been a complete wall change now.
So basically, the reason engine manufacturers
put lots of money into Formula One is because it is a way
of sort of testing things to four road cars
and to advertise their road cars and everything in the future.
So there's always Formula One car development
has to sort of mirror in some ways
what's happening on the road.
- Right.
- And like proper Formula One fans don't really want that
'cause we want big old stinking V8 engines to make
that lovely noise that make your ears pop.
- You don't want the cars to have to plug in every 45 minutes.
- Exactly, I mean, I don't know if you've watched Formula E,
but it's really a tedious.
So, but this year's rule change.
- Let me calm down, calm down, calm down, calm down, calm down.
- Some of us enjoy watching fast chargers
doing their thing, okay?
- So the cars this now have this sort of energy recovery system.
So it's all about, they can harvest energy when they're breaking
and then employ it.
- Because they've all got batteries as well.
- They've all got batteries, so the hybrid era's been
since 2014 or so, so they had, before that,
from 2009 you had the CIRS system,
which was the kinetic energy recovery system,
and then that sort of involved, 'cause the thing is,
if you make the car too efficient,
you don't get overtakes and that's boring.
- I see.
- overtakes are the things you want.
So they're constantly changing the rules
to try and get more overtakes.
There is a button now that they can press
called the overtake button, which just means
they can use that energy they've harvested
to boost and overtake.
So when they use that function,
it's like a nitro button.
- It's basically, yeah, like it's like Mario Kart.
- Like your bullet in Mario Kart.
- Yeah, and it looks like that,
just when they press it and it just overtakes,
it looks like they're completely different formulas,
like they're just, oh, okay.
- Wow.
- Have they considered adding like shells and bananas?
(laughing)
What people would want, I think even Andy would want
- The curse thing that you mentioned,
obviously that or not, obviously,
but that's now in all electric cars, basically.
So the reason, one of the reasons you get so far
on your electric car without charging
is because it can regain energy from the braking system
and that began in Formula One.
- Yeah, the Formula One drivers,
they do all the, you know, they do lots of training,
obviously, because it's much more physical than it used to be.
I didn't know this.
What's the most important thing for a Formula One driver
to practice?
- Their neck muscles.
- It's neck day.
So when you're driving this car,
and you're going around the corners
and you're whizzing along and all of that,
supposedly your head weighs five times
what it normally does.
Partly the helmet.
Partly the gravitational force is acting on you.
And so often they can't buy normal clothes
'cause they've got this whacking great neck, basically.
- You feel like Formula One drivers, they're small
with these masks.
- They're all neck.
And those people who love metal music.
Head backers would make great Formula One drivers
because they're doing all this training.
So the images of them training their necks are so funny
'cause they'll release shots sometimes
of them wearing this mad brace.
Sort of big, like one of those helmets
you'd wear for a psychiatric experiment,
you know, with a thick rubber cord coming off it.
And at the other end of the rubber cord is a trainer
who is just hauling their neck every one direction
and they're trying to resist it.
- That I get mirrored touch since easier.
When I look at that, that makes my neck so.
- That's really so.
- Yeah, they're so strong and fit.
Now, like they sweat so much,
they lose so much weight during a race.
And particularly in the really like Singapore
or places where they're, it's really hot.
And they have water to drink in the car.
They have a water system but what I think people don't realize
is the water is right by the engine.
And so it's, after a couple of laps,
it's basically like tea.
It's like hot water in a hundred and two.
Damon Hill did once have tea in his famously.
And another great Damon Hill fact, if you want it.
- Yeah.
- They played a guitar solo on a deaf leopard track.
(laughs)
- What?
- So I grew up at Brown's hatch, basically.
I was there, both of my parents were there
and that's why I love motorsport,
particularly Formula One.
And I can remember going in,
the Kentigan is the name of the pub at Brown's hatch.
So it's a Pentagon and it's in Kent.
See what they're talking about.
- It's brilliant.
(laughs)
- And I remember after races going in there
and the human is band playing.
- Really?
What's deaf leopard again?
- A band.
- No, no, as in the white genre, they.
- Oh, like sort of hair rock, really.
- Yeah, probably some good head banging.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, that's right, yeah.
- Yeah.
- And there's also, I'm quite interested
in female Formula One driver.
- Oh, yeah.
- There have been female drivers in Formula One.
There's only ever been one female driver score points
in a Formula One race and that was Lele Lombardi.
She was an Italian driver and it was in 1975
and she scored half a point.
- Oh.
- And that was because if a race is less than 60% complete,
you only get half a point.
- Okay.
- And during the race there were fatalities.
Unfortunately, there was a German driver
who crashed into a spectator pit
and there was a fireman and a couple of journalists
and a spectator were killed.
So it was pretty.
But she scored half a point.
So she's the only person to have a score point.
But yeah, there's loads of really,
there's a little shout out to Alicia Pomoski
at the moment who's a Red Bull driver.
She's got a first poll last week
in the F1 Academy.
So there's lots of women drivers coming through now.
So hopefully in the next 10 years,
we'll see another.
- Very exciting.
- It's also, you think like smaller in general and average.
So like, you get lots of female jockeys for instance.
- Yeah.
- Absolutely.
- Let's make sense.
- The problem is, which is always part
of the problem with Formula One is money
because you have different type, you know,
some people get their seats in Formula One on Merit purely
and some get their seats in Formula One
because they also bring money.
It's so large, strong, for example,
who drives to Aston Martin.
A pretty terrible Formula One driver.
And there's lots of people much more deserving of that seat,
but he's dad owns the team.
What are you gonna do?
He basically bought the team for his son
to have a seat in Formula One.
- The thing is, you want a nice egalitarian sport
like Polo.
- Exactly, that's what you need.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 16th century London,
there was a chain of pubs that sold laxatives on tap.
(laughing)
- Any questions?
- So many.
So this is Queen Elizabeth could have gone to one of these pubs.
- Oh yeah, well, in fact, this person who made them,
Dr. William Butler, he was a physician to James I.
- Oh really?
- So only just after her.
- That's a fact, so.
- Wow.
- And he was definitely around at that time.
I'm not sure how often Queen Elizabeth went to the pub.
- Probably not much.
- Not that much, yeah, yeah.
- But he was a physician and he became famous
for various reasons we might go into.
But one of the things he did was make this thing
called purging ale, which had anacid, caraway,
licorice, and beer.
And if you went to quite a lot of pubs in London,
you would be able to get it on tap.
And it was good for you because you would purge your body.
It was medicinal, let's say.
- So it was in a beer.
It was, it was like beer, but with all this stuff in it,
it's like imagine them a nice cask pale ale
that you would get today, but with a few,
what's the opposite of a modium?
- He's like a, he's like a original hipster brewery
kind of character, isn't he?
- Now, I'd rather that than syrupy figs,
I think it sounds quite nice.
- Yeah, yeah.
And actually there's still a pub in London called
old Dr. Butler's head in Margate,
which claims to be associated with him
and that he sold his beer in that pub, right?
- Now, the actual truth is,
were not even certain if he made the beer himself,
it was definitely named after him,
and he was definitely a physician,
but it could be that he was just so famous
that they called it his beer.
- Yeah, no, we're not sure about that.
- Some pubs had his portrait hung up,
but again, it might have been just associated
with a famous doctor.
- A sort of license, his name, as kind of, yeah, yeah.
- It's a really interesting chap, this guy.
So he went to Claire College, Cambridge,
and did an arts degree.
And then for some reason, managed to get a physician's license,
and it's not certain how he got it,
they seem to have just given it to him.
And he just worked at a pub creed shop for ages in Cambridge.
And then one day, a local clergyman had fallen into
an opium-induced coma and been given up for dead.
And Butler killed a cow, put the priest inside the cow,
and the priest was cured.
And from that moment, he became famous.
- It's going to wake you up being put in a cow, isn't it, I think?
- Or it's going to make the opium-induced trip,
even wilder.
- What's the cow open?
- A cow open, and like, is it the referendum
where he kind of lives inside a bed?
- Yes, it does, it's a bit like that.
- My dog on the beach once,
she was running towards something, she's a little cock-a-peer.
She climbed inside a seal carcass.
The smell, I can still smell it now, and I think it was quite...
- Oh my God, that's a bath.
- Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
She was so proud of herself, you know?
That's amazing.
- A real career-defining moment, I think,
the placing of patients inside a cow.
- He was 68 at that stage,
and we see basically nothing of him throughout the whole of history
from his birth until this moment.
And then suddenly, at the age of 68,
he becomes nationally famous.
And so much so that King James I had a hunting injury,
and he said, "Get me the cow guy."
(all laughing)
- Because if the clergyman had died,
I don't think you can recover from that, going...
- But what's he got to lose it?
Sounds like he's not made a big success of his career so far.
- He's doing fine, yeah, but okay.
- If he died, but you just take him out the cow and pretend
you never did it.
- I think he'd have to stop.
- Yeah, it was like that when I got here.
(all laughing)
- I read somewhere, they called him an empiric physician.
- Oh yeah.
- Which meant he based his treatments not on any theory,
but purely on reasoning and experience.
- Yeah.
- It's not what you want from him.
- Don't drink it, you wanted to read some books.
- I guess so, yeah.
- Yeah.
- He had a few weird things.
If someone came to him with epilepsy,
he would shoot a couple of firearms close to their heads
to scare the condition out of them.
- Yep, it's like angry to the hiccups, isn't it?
(all laughing)
- If someone had AGU, which I guess is, what is AGU?
- Even Larry, kind of thing.
- Yeah.
- But he would push them into the terms
'cause like cold water therapy.
I mean, you still do cold water therapy today, weren't you?
- In Hoth Method, he was in Hoth Method.
(all laughing)
- Butler was there before them all.
- I did read one thing he did,
where there was a patient who had catar, severe catar.
- What's that?
- Flap.
- No, he's put it in.
(all laughing)
- Heavy sort of matter on the lungs.
- A sniffle thing.
- A sniffle.
- No, it's more, it's sort of a heavy, heavy air.
- Yeah, like Chasti, a really Chasti-thick condition, right?
- Yeah.
- And Butler said, right, you've got a smoke and ounce
of tobacco, which is a lot.
It took the patient 25 pipes of tobacco, one after the other.
- Very much like you, a parent catching you smoking
once a year, but apparently that completely cure the patient.
I mean, some citation needed, I think,
didn't come back for 17 years, didn't it?
- I mean, died of lung disease.
(all laughing)
- Didn't have a cold anymore, that was the most important thing.
- Well, this is the 1500s.
I mean, we are, it's probably in line with what?
- A lot of, yeah.
- Topters were practicing or trying or testing at the time.
I've got this new method with the cow.
- Well, oh great.
- He was a spicy fellow when you disagreed with him.
He was quite something, Butler.
So he got involved in a gold clipping affair.
So that is where, you know, coins are made of gold.
And if you clip off a little bit of the edge,
you've suddenly got this, you've still got the coin,
but you've got the gold as well, fantastic, you know?
- Yeah.
- If you do that, you can make it big.
- And that's why we have the edges on a pound coin.
- Exactly.
- I think Newton supposedly put those on.
- Exactly, yeah.
- Like, to stop people from clipping them.
- Exactly, so someone from, he was in Cambridge,
he was practicing in Cambridge, wasn't he?
And someone from Trinity College Cambridge,
a senior called Paul Thompson was sentenced to death
for this crime.
'Cause it was incredibly serious at the time,
interfering with the currency, big no no.
Butler wrote to him, I just loved this.
Okay, this is the quote he sent to him.
He just wrote to him, say, oh, you've been sentenced to death
and you've been caught doing this, well,
I've got a letter from Butler, maybe that'll cheer me up.
Butler wrote, your giddy headed, fantastic fiddling fingers
and scribbling pen directed by the motion
of your quick silver brain, without penitency,
pretending piety, practicing policy,
will bring you to a violent end.
As you have always lived a conceited wizard,
so now you will die, a niny hammer fool.
- Oh, wow.
- Yes.
- It's the next Hamilton.
- Burn.
- Yes.
- A niny hammer fool.
- Niny hammer.
- I loved that there was lots of plosives at the top.
There was a lot of very good to touch for your mic.
- Absolutely.
(laughing)
- It's quite nice that there's a pub still named after him
because the connection it seems
is that you could buy this laxative on tap there,
but actually he was known to basically be in the pub
all the time getting pissed.
And he had an assistant called Nell.
And Nell did a few things, but Nell's chief job
was to go and collect him at the end of the night,
drunk from the pub and sort of wheel him home
in a wheelbarrow or carry him or whatever method
he needed.
How many points of laxative ale have you heard?
Not many.
Well, haven't you?
- The fouls has tell a different story.
(laughing)
- Listen, I've got something about,
'cause I was really fascinated by the fact
it was laxative ale.
And the whole sort of brewing,
'cause you know it was women who first brewed bit,
so you had your ale wife's wood.
And there's something called groaning ale.
I don't know if you've heard of that.
Groaning ale, so when a woman was pregnant,
a local ale wife, so one of these local brewing women,
would brew a batch of really strong ale
for when she went into labor.
And when she went into labor, both her and the midwife
would drink the really strong ale
to help the whole process.
- Wow.
- I think that's something they should bring.
- Yeah, really good.
- Yeah, the midwife though, I'm not sure about that.
- It's true.
(laughing)
- Well, this was the thing, so beer at the time,
and we're talking like ages ago now,
I mean, sort of medieval, was home brood,
and you might put a pole above your door,
just saying you've got ale.
- And I like that, you've got ale.
(laughing)
- Oh my God, that's it.
- That's a rom-com we need to make that really good.
(laughing)
- Really good.
- And to the bar and to the stars, you've got ale.
- I'm game, bring somebody right there.
(laughing)
- And so there were bride ails as well as the groaning ails,
you know, an ale was almost an event
as well as an actual drink itself.
And then the black death happened,
and a third of the population died.
I mean, just absolutely devastating for everybody.
But it led to this big labor shortage,
peasants got suddenly got much better paid
because they were so much scarcer, you know.
- You needed someone to work on your farm,
but everyone was dead, so you could, like...
- Yeah, so in union terms and labor terms,
it was a brilliant thing, the black death.
(laughing)
But you know, status of living went up,
and that led to more permanent ale houses
'cause there was a bit more surplus.
- Ah.
- Supplies were, and that led to kind of better food
and better drink and more leisure.
And that was kind of the beginning of pub culture.
- Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
- It's really this idea of the whole binge Britain thing,
I find quite interesting,
'cause we've always been known as a nation of drinkers.
- Yes.
- So from the, in the eighth century,
St. Boniface, the missionary from Devon,
traveled Europe, and he wrote to the Archbishop of Canterbury
Cuthbert, and he says,
"In your diocese, the vice of drunkenness is too frequent."
This is an evil peculiar to pagans and to our race,
neither the Franks, nor the Gools, nor the Lombards,
nor the Romans, nor the Greeks commit it.
So we've always been...
- Ah, how mower, the Greeks.
- Right?
- They had other things that they would have had.
- They were the Greeks.
I love it.
And I read some really good, like I can't remember
when this was now, I should have really done,
but it was St. Bartholomew's Hospital.
Their records show that at one point,
sick children averaged three points of beer a day.
- Wow.
- For the sick children.
- How similar is beer now as it was then?
- It was weaker as well, right?
- In Budapest, yeah.
- So it was...
- And it changed when hops came along.
- Yeah.
- And that was a bit later.
- I think it was the idea that it had been through
a brewing process and it was safer.
- safer than just drinking straight out of the river.
- Yeah.
- That's the idea.
- So there's a good reason behind it, basically.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Small beer, they call it.
- Small beer, that's it.
- Small beer.
- Yeah.
- In 2020, Pennsylvania designated beer distributors
as a life-sustaining service.
(laughing)
- I can tell.
- And the idea is that because the people
who take the beer around also often provide
water, soda, and some food slash snacks.
(laughing)
So in some areas of the state, according to
communications director, Casey Smith.
In some areas of the state, there might be the only place
where you can move water around
is by moving beer at the same time.
- Absolutely.
Pork scratching is actually one of the four food groups.
It's very important.
(laughing)
- Does anyone else really want a beer?
- Yeah.
- Very anyone want a beer.
- Let's do it.
Well, let's wrap up and grab a beer.
(laughing)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can all be found online.
I'm on @Streiberland on Instagram.
James.
- My Instagram is No Suspengar's James Harkin.
- Andy.
- @AndreHunterM.
- Angela.
- Angela_Barnsey on Instagram.
- Nice.
And you're on tour now.
Not with one show, but two.
- Two shows.
I'm finishing off my tour, Angst, which finishes
the end of May.
And then from June to the end of the year,
I'm hosting The Archers Live at 75,
which I'm so excited about.
Some such an archers nerd.
- That's a radio show in the UK for international listeners,
and it's brilliant.
Yeah, if you want to get through to us as a group,
podcast@qy.com, send all of your emails there.
If you want to send us your favorite facts,
Andy will go through the inbox,
cherry pick the best, and bring them to our bonus episode,
which goes at every Monday called Little Fish.
So send them in there,
but if you've got general feedback that you want us to know about,
also send that because Andy picks the best of those
for our Behind the Scenes Mailbag episode,
which is called Drop Us Align,
and that's part of Club Fish,
which is our Private Members Club.
You'll find it on Patreon.
So just head to patreon.com/clubfish,
and there's multiple tiers there of things that you can do.
So you can join the Drop Us Align as an audio.
There's also a higher tier where you can get it as a video.
And then at the highest tier,
you become custodian of one of our headline facts
from the last 12 years of fish.
So much stuff there, check it all out.
We've also got a quiz coming up.
Ah, that's April the 14th,
and if you become a member of the highest tier of Club Fish,
you can get access to that too.
And just a reminder, that's patreon.com/clubfish.
Otherwise, hey, come back next week,
'cause we're gonna be back with another episode,
and we will see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)