(phone ringing)
- We don't want that.
We don't want that.
(upbeat music)
- Hi.
- Andy.
- Hello Andy.
- Hi everybody, welcome to the droppership.
- How are you today?
- Oh my god.
- What?
- I'm just being polite.
- Fine, thank you.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- You got the sound side.
- Sound put off.
- Welcome to droppershipline, our audience feedback show.
- And how are you, dear listener, slash viewer?
You're in for a treat.
- You're looking well.
- Thank you very much.
I'm feeling well.
- Good.
- I'm good too, just in case I was doing it.
- So sorry.
My name's Andrew Hunter-Marie, and this is Dan Triber.
- Yeah?
- That is my name.
- And James Harkin.
- Hi.
- Yeah.
And we have had some amazing correspondence
of feedback on the show.
- Exciting.
- It has been sloshing into the inbox.
- Hmm.
- Let's get into it.
- Yeah, let's do it.
- Okay, here we go.
Number one, new section.
- Okay.
Is that what it's called?
- We've got a whole bit about section days later on.
That's not this bit.
This bit is called "Swimming with the Fishes."
- Okay.
- Is it about someone who's died?
- It's about death.
It's about decomposition.
Because do you remember last time what,
I think it was you said James about pigs?
- Yeah, putting pigs into a forest.
A big, big old pile of them.
- Yeah.
- And then waiting to see what happens with them
as an analogy to humans.
- Yes.
- You had something about clothing.
- They put the pigs in winter clothing
or something to see what happens.
So if a human dies, you can kind of judge
how long ago it was that they died.
- Exactly.
Okay, so Max Spies or Spees writes,
"I'm the South African Tafonomist,
James mentioned in Little Fish."
- What?
My PhD was in forensic anthropology
and I looked at the effect of clothing
on seasonal decomposition rates in Cape Town,
including animal scavenging activity.
- Oh my gosh.
- As James mentioned,
this is to help estimate time
at since death in humans.
It's weird to hear several years
as worth of work reduced to one sentence,
but it's a good summary.
- But it shows you what you can achieve if you edit.
(laughing)
- Take that, Max.
- That's amazing.
- And I love this.
I can guarantee I listen to some fish
while out in the field collecting data for this study.
- Wow.
- Wonderful.
- I know.
- So he couldn't have happened without us in a way.
- In a way.
(laughing)
- And he adds yes, dressing the pigs was a challenge.
We had to buy large sizes
and have the clothing custom tailored to fit the pigs,
sowing them in on day one of the experiment.
- Wow, I know.
- Amazing.
- Yeah.
- God, I imagine.
- How a little show being listened to
while someone's sowing a pig into a jacket.
- Amazing.
- It's so exciting.
We're gonna have some bonus bream now.
- I thought we were gonna call it bonus bass.
- I was keen on bonus Maracuda.
- Hmm.
- Well, I read the emails, so I'm pulling rank.
- No, it's bonus fish of your choice.
Fish have all got bones, haven't they?
Bonus bone.
- Bonus bone?
- Okay, look.
Can we just...
- Okay.
- What's your bonus bone?
- Dries Bellynx writes,
"I've been re-listening to older episodes
and came again upon episode 513
where Stevie Martin says that goldfish grow
to fill their tank."
- Oh, yeah.
- But what Dries says is,
what most people don't know is that externally,
they grow that size, but internally,
their organs want to keep growing, but can't expand.
- No.
- And that's one of the reasons
most goldfish don't live long.
- No.
- I don't know if that's true, Andy, is it?
- I can't be true, I haven't checked.
- It can't support.
- It can't support?
- I suppose if you're a larger human,
you don't necessarily have a larger brain.
Like, as if I put on weight,
all my insides don't necessarily get bigger.
- Yeah, your gall bladder doesn't suddenly
become twice the size if you do.
And so it's just fat, I guess,
of this goldfish as it's going out, so...
- Yes, so.
- Did you look into this further?
- No.
- Okay.
- It sort of does make sense now that you say it.
- It does, like, yeah.
- But on the other hand,
like one big internal organ of a fish
is a swim bladder, right?
And if that stays the same size,
then it's gonna struggle to,
you know, not sink or not float.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So you think that would change?
- And we've got in our body,
we've got a lot of intestine, don't we?
Like, too much.
Almost suggests that we're meant to be inflated.
- Too much.
- We're meant to be inflated.
- Yeah.
- It's like that's trying to make a novelty balloon.
And it's got the filling wrong.
- Yeah.
- And this is why I don't do extra research
on the things that get sent in
because I find this much more engaging.
And we get to the science through natural conversation.
- Exactly.
This is kind of what this is how all science used to be done.
It was just three people who looked like us
and sitting around talking bollocks.
- Yeah.
- Very exciting.
- Right.
- Another bonus bone here.
- That's not a good name.
- And what is the section?
- What do you mean, what's in it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's like extra material and things that we mentioned.
- I see.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's not get yourself off the hook.
- Yeah.
- And it's not.
- But wasn't that real life earlier with the
real life completely different?
- Okay.
- Bonus bone is just here's some extra information.
- Right.
- Did you say we're going to get to the naming
of the sections later?
- Oh yeah.
- Right.
- I know.
- You do appear to be doing it right now.
- I think it shows eating itself.
I think that's what happens.
- Wait for later.
Oh my God.
We should have done the naming at the beginning.
So we all know what we're talking about.
I don't know why I've put it so late
in the running order for this show.
I just don't know why the naming of sections
has become such a big section of this show.
In fact, it's so much for sex you should have its own name.
- Okay.
You know what?
Screw it.
We're just going to do it now.
- I thought it was.
I thought it was called new section.
- I knew it.
- And you went into bonus bone.
- That was bonus bone.
I got sick.
Take it seriously.
Please.
- This is our career.
Sorry.
- People being good money.
- When you say it out loud.
- It's insane that this is our career.
- Yeah.
- Don't investigate it too much.
- Right, we come on now to the section naming section.
Okay, we're really happy.
- Do you have a name for it?
- No.
(laughing)
- I am welcoming submissions for the section.
- Okay.
- Podcast@QI.com.
Now, this is off the back of ROW, ROW, ROW, your boat.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Okay, which was--
- Which was a section about two different audience members
who disagreed with each other.
However, it turned out that they didn't disagree
with each other.
They both made very good points.
- So we got renamed, making very good points, yeah, about.
- Yeah.
Yeah.
Well, Amy Killan writes, "I was listening
"to drop us a line this morning,
"and observed the fight between two other listeners
"about pilot's eyes.
"I felt compelled to write in for the first time.
"So many first-timers in the inbox.
"It's really nice to know, lovely."
I can't believe you all missed "Fish-de-cuffs."
It was right there.
- Yeah.
- Instead of ROW, ROW, ROW brackets your boat.
- Well, I just want to thank Luke Burgess,
who also suggested "Fish-de-cuffs."
My friend, Henry Tassum, who suggests "Fish-fight."
Rich Childs, who says, "This or that."
Like an all-you-row-in.
Dario Pessequino, who suggests "Seem-and-scobbles."
- Yes.
- That's a good one.
- Who is the name of the first person who wrote it?
- Amy Killan.
- Killan.
We could name this section where we find the name of
the section after her.
Killan in the name of.
- Brilliant.
- It's very good.
I'm writing it down to explain the long pause.
- Can I also say, right?
I notice this in the last show, right?
There's a big section of this show,
which is you just writing stuff down.
But we record the show.
So you don't really need to write it down.
You could just go back and listen
and then write it down in your own time
and I'm wasting everyone else's.
- I don't listen to this stuff.
- No, that's a really good point, James.
Thank you.
Yeah, I should do my notes later on.
I never look over these notes again.
- No.
- I never ever.
I do that straight in the shredder after every recording.
Philip Muir from New Zealand suggests tackle box
for the fight, fight, fight, bit.
Which I do think is good.
'Cause that's what you have when you're fishing, isn't it?
tackle box.
Okay, so thanks Philip.
- That's right, right hook.
'Cause it's about someone being right.
- Oh my god.
- Can I write that one down?
- Well, it's shorter at least, so yeah.
- Sorry, Amy Killan.
Killan in the name of.
Right hook.
I think it's gonna be Siemens Gwobbles, but you know what?
We'll see, I guess.
We come to an email from Edward Carpenter of Florida.
- Cool.
- Yeah.
I was recently listening to your little fish
where you were discussing citric acids use in brown heroin.
- Oh yeah.
- And someone asked how much you would need to intake
to get your daily vitamin C.
- Yes.
- And Ed was done the maths.
- Oh, thank goodness.
- Yeah, apparently you need 15 milligrams
of citric acid for every 250 milligrams of brown heroin.
- Okay.
- So it's about 6% of the total mass.
And to get your RDA of vitamin C,
that means you would only need to intake 1.37 grams
of heroin.
How much is that?
Not much.
- It doesn't sound like much, does it?
- I don't know with heroin.
- I don't know what the serving suggestion is
with heroin.
- Yeah, but it's not like a cute waffle of it, is it?
- I don't know.
- It's small.
- It's not very heavy, is it?
- That guy's such sheltered lifestyle.
(laughing)
- Well, what is it?
- When you heat it up your spoon.
- What are you popping at?
- A spoon full, I suppose.
- This is why we need Anna back here.
(laughing)
- But then that's a great email I would thank you for that.
But Rachel Abbott, who worked in community drug treatment
for a decade, points out that heroin does not contain
vitamin C because citric acid does not contain vitamin C.
They're different things.
- Oh, other than that.
- Citric acid is not vitamin C.
A sorbic acid is vitamin C.
- Yeah.
- But they do sometimes give out sachets of vitamin C
to dissolve the heroin.
So she says, if you choose to dissolve your heroin
using a sorbic acid, then you will be getting
a bit of vitamin C.
But if you use citric acid to dissolve your heroin,
then you won't.
- This is all so confusing.
I think I'm just gonna go back to my vitamin C tablets.
(laughing)
- It seems more hassle than it's where I am.
- And that's how it really does.
- I think actually, even if you start
just taking 1.3 grams of heroin a day,
I reckon before long it's gonna be more, you know?
Good.
Thanks all.
- Great.
- What section was that?
- That was actually a little palette cleanser.
That was just the sort of--
- That's out of the sections.
- Yeah, yeah, heroin sorbae in between my courses.
(laughing)
Do you wanna buff in?
- Sure.
- This is experts who've written to us,
and I know that South African to fond of
the friend was one of those, but that was actually
in different sections of decomposition.
- It all makes sense.
- It's swimming with the fish, it's, yeah, yeah.
- It's really unusual because he actually would have
also fitted in to real life.
- Yes.
- And buff in, but yet you made a new section.
- That's what I was saying earlier.
- Yeah, yeah.
The whole show is actually just one section.
- Well, I suppose when you think of it,
that's really interesting.
- Yeah. (laughing)
- Okay, we've got a couple of brilliant buff fins.
The silica zone.
- Okay, silica. - Silica.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- Lauren Dacone Rodriguez, terrific name,
says that you mentioned that James, thanks to his cat ownership,
will use more silica gel.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause you can get fancy cat litter.
- May have silica crystals.
- And my cat only, who's on the best?
- Absolutely.
(laughing)
- But the cheaper gray clumping litter,
which I'm sure your cat's bottom has never seen.
- No, she'll hold it in rather than going up.
(laughing)
- That's made from bentonite clay, okay?
- Yes.
- So that's another silica base material
that forms a gel when it's wet, okay?
So far so boring, says Lauren.
That's not my note about Lauren's email, that's what Lauren says.
But bentonite has another much more exciting use
than soaking up cat pee,
and it's forgetting rid of nuclear waste.
- Really?
- Because it swells on contact with water,
and it's very plastic,
which helps to make it self-sealing.
So it adsorbs lots of radionute clides very strongly,
so it absorbs adsorbs it, it takes it in, glues to it,
protects the waste form, inhibits ground water flow,
it's brilliant, and it's going to be used,
maybe at the big nuclear disposal site in Finland.
- Right.
- 'Cause they're doing a cool,
I think it's an underground one.
Source, I did an entire PhD on bentonite clay
for nuclear waste disposal.
- Wow, am I own two cats?
(laughing)
- The silica, those little packs that we were talking about,
there's also that thing where, basically,
'cause it's taking in the water, right?
Inside, they've done it so that it changes color internally,
so you can tell when it's sort of,
okay, time to refresh the silica,
because this is absorbed as much as it can.
- Yeah, so it's got different stages of color.
- That's brilliant.
- Yeah, I wonder if these nuclear ones have that.
- Maybe, it's just glowing green.
- It's full of nuclear waste.
(laughing)
Oh, do you want to hear a really good bonus brim?
We're going back to bonus brim.
- We're back in bonus brim.
- Okay, great.
- This is from Agnes de Blaise.
- Okay.
Listen to episode 620, no such thing as gutter ice,
Sally Phillips.
- Yeah, really, okay.
- The discussion about cadavers on planes,
unlocked a memory from the 1990s
that I think may be up your alley.
- Oh, nice.
- This is a great story.
Back then, my ex had just earned his private pilot's license.
We were young, optimistic,
and planning a six-week lap of Australia
in a small, rented, four-seater, Piper Cherokee.
The plane had, let's say, modest range.
So my job was to confirm every possible refueling stop
on our path across the vast Australian nothingness.
- Yeah.
- Armed with the casserole book,
I rang my way across the country,
carefully ensuring we could land refuel
and not fall out of the sky.
- Yeah, makes sense.
- One of our plan stops was a tiny outback town
in New South Wales.
I'll spare the name,
just in case statutes of limitations apply.
- Oh, this is gonna get spicy.
- My initial contact was someone called Bob,
who passed me on to the local Jack of all trades.
This man, it transpired, was the only hardware store owner,
the only local builder, the only funeral home owner,
and the only undertaker for a very large surrounding region.
He also happened to own a light aircraft
and some fuel we could access.
Over TN stories, he explained a fascinating aviation work
around.
In Australia, private licenses for pilots are very expensive.
Commercial ones are exorbitant.
As the sole undertaker for remote properties and towns,
he was often called upon to collect bodies by plane, right?
- Yeah.
- However, transporting a body would technically make
a flight commercial and a commercial license is extremely expensive.
- Yes, I see.
- His solution?
- Is it weekend at Bernayset?
- He seated the deceased in the cockpit,
- Yeah.
- Hasn't a seat belt and longer than as a passenger.
No commercial activity, no rules broken,
just a very quiet co-pilot.
- It's nice though.
If you unfortunately sadly die,
you get one last going in airplane.
- That is pretty cool.
- It is good.
I think it's also quite good for a mystery story.
A small plane has crashed and both pilots have died.
But wait a second, this pilot died three weeks
before the flight took off.
- Yeah.
I think like the thing is that when you find that body
and it died before earlier,
your first thought is, well,
it must have died before they took off
and then they put it in the airplane and they flew it.
And that actually turns out to be also the solution.
- Yes, yeah.
When you find out that the main pilot was
the local undertaker and the funeral homeowner,
it all makes sense to me.
- It doesn't take Benoit Block to work that out.
- I think it's a short film, yeah.
It's short film is still a valid art medium.
- Absolutely.
- But when you look at the Oscars for the best short film,
they're not all short because they have no plot.
(laughing)
- That's true.
- Short film is a very, very vital
and urgent medium, especially for people
who don't have too much to say.
And I think I clearly don't.
I love the idea that all short films are just plots
that didn't work out and we're solved far too quickly.
(laughing)
- And the Oscar for the film that was only decided on
because it had quite a funny pun in the name goes to
- For the 50th year running, Andrew, Hunter Murray.
(laughing)
- We're now having a miscellaneous section.
- No name?
- No name yet.
But if you can think of a name for a miscellaneous section.
- Miscellaneous, okay.
- Yeah, seafood platter.
- That's good.
- That's really good.
- Seafood chatter.
- No.
- Yes.
- Del rise it down.
(laughing)
- I think the audience will need this time
to recover from all the laughing.
(laughing)
- Seafood chatter.
- Love it.
- I'm par with Seaman Squabble.
(laughing)
Grapefruit Street.
- Right, about priest clowns.
I think we had a brief--
- Oh yeah.
- I was trying to get this off the ground.
- You remember?
- Yeah, it's the Joan of Arc church in America.
- And there was a priest there who was a working clown.
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- I thought that was a very funny concept
and I was alone in that thought.
- Yeah.
- Grapefruit Street says, "I don't know any priest clowns."
Okay.
But I used to know an accountant who was a clown.
- Brackets.
- A clown-toned.
- Nice.
- That's good.
- That is good.
There's a big court case going on at the moment
between Elon Musk and Sam Altman
and one of the lawyers representing Elon Musk doubles
as a clown in his day job.
So he's got a clown lawyer.
- That's very funny.
- Yeah.
- And then he's got a clown car as well, the cyber truck.
- So thank you Grapefruit Street.
Brief email from Eldritch Steel.
- Oh yeah.
- Great name.
- Good name.
- A couple of images from my visit
to our late friend of the pod.
Eldritch has been in a little pilgrimage
to the grave of...
- Alan Thickey.
- No.
- Who, can you see the top right there?
- Proud Canadian, 1947 to 2016,
adored by his wife, loved by his son,
family and friends, forever missed.
- There you go.
- Oh, that nice.
- That is nice.
- Why are you the great guy?
- Yeah.
- Composer of theme tunes.
- Exactly.
- That's just really cool.
We've got listeners out there doing field work for us
visiting the grave of Alan Thickey.
- Yeah.
- David Tucker.
- Right.
- Since the obsession with the Now You See Me series
has continued.
(laughing)
- Here we go.
- I thought you all might like this fact.
This is just a cool fact about magic, okay?
It's not specifically Eisenberg or Haroldson based,
but buried in Cave Hill Cemetery in Louisville, Kentucky
where Muhammad Ali and Colonel Sanders are buried
is Harry Collins, his grave is hard to miss
as there is a life-size bronze statue of him.
When the curious look him up, as I did,
they find he was the official corporate magician
of Doritos Creators, the Frito Lay Company.
(laughing)
- He was the corporate magician of that company.
- There is a guy called Harry Collins.
He's dead now.
He was the official corporate magician of Frito Lay.
- Okay, I think that's great.
- That's really cool.
And of course, Muhammad Ali was a magician as well.
- Mm.
- Which we covered on the show.
But Muhammad Ali would do a magic trick to you,
but then reveal how it was done.
- Hush you in the mouth.
- Yes.
(laughing)
- If you were amazed enough, yeah.
- Because Islamic faith meant that he couldn't lie.
- Yeah, oh, that's why he had to give it away.
- Yes.
- Would you rather at your company have an accountant
or an official corporate magician?
- Well, I would say that if you have a clown
who's doing your accounts, that can cause problems.
- Yeah.
- You need someone sensible doing your accounts.
- Why are the latest quarterly figures written
on this balloon dog account of stuff?
- Where I want a magician who can make
those numbers disappear.
(laughing)
Very nice.
Medical acronyms, we mentioned those.
- Yeah.
- Oh, it was a fact we were giving away
to a friend of the podcast on a little fish.
- Okay.
- About little odd ladies.
- Yes, exactly.
- I see, yeah.
- And Emma Lyons writes in with some veterinary
medical acronyms.
- Okay.
- And she's called Lyons.
- Nice.
- So there's NQR, not quite right.
HBC hit by car.
Dude, defecating urinating, drinking, eating.
(laughing)
- Well, that's a good thing, presumably.
That means that all of the vital things
that I was talking about.
- Oh, right.
- Yes, you're absolutely right.
- I thought I meant all at once.
(laughing)
- But in fact, you know, that film,
everything everywhere I want to do.
(laughing)
It was a very messy day.
- I'm not a few, so don't know.
Nights were a bit of dude.
(laughing)
- And then Emma adds, there are those we would love to use,
but we can't any more because party pooper clients
can request their records and Google them.
- Wow, which is what we mentioned.
- Yeah, TF Bundy, totally F'd up,
but unfortunately not dead yet.
- Oh, okay.
- Probably quite good that you don't put that on the Nights.
And my favorites, Demito, dog more intelligent than owner.
(laughing)
And OWB, owner will bite.
- Wow. - Good.
- Okay, that's nice, nice to know.
Was that from, that's the research, yeah.
- Yeah, I remember that.
- I would believe it.
- Absolutely. - Very cool.
- Now we come to one of my favorite sections,
extreme fish.
- Okay.
- And we've got a few really good extreme fishes this time.
- So what have people been doing while listening to fish?
- Well, Pete says,
"I'm a regular listener of the pod.
I've listened to all of them in every format to date.
My wife, on the other hand, only listens
when your dulcet tones are playing in the car,
except when she's in labor.
And then she can't get enough of you.
Three and a half years ago, she binged your show
through the best part of a 48 hour labor."
- Wow.
Last week, we, brackets, she, went through the ordeal again.
- I'm listening to the show.
(laughing)
- And it's formidable and agonizing experience.
- I prayed for death at various points,
but eventually the credits were all there.
(laughing)
- Last week, she went through the ordeal again.
brackets, I suffered too.
The canteen was closed.
And once again, she insisted on listening
to the show non-stop.
So that's two labors.
We've helped this woman through.
- That's cool.
- Perhaps fish could be used more widely as pain relief.
(laughing)
Or maybe an X-Talk could be on labor wards.
- Yeah.
- Yes.
- I love that idea.
- Anyway, just wanted to say thanks
for helping us deliver our children.
I think that's unquestionably extreme.
- That's insane.
- That's extreme fish.
- And that's incredible.
That we've been part of.
- Were we there for the birth itself?
- Sounds like it.
- Right.
- I mean, he says non-stop.
- Yeah.
- Through the, for the best part of a 48 hour labor.
But promise the best.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Lovely.
Boris B writes,
"I've redacted Boris's surname
for just a slightly careful reason."
- I used to be prime minister of the UK.
(laughing)
- When I won Wimbledon.
- Pre-apology for not being succinct.
My excuse is that I'm currently incarcerated
in Jackson Correctional Institution.
- Wow.
- Okay.
- Medium security prison near Chippewa Falls
was concerned.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
- The Titanic.
- Ah.
- Jack is from the Titanic.
- Yes.
- That was your factor.
- Yeah.
- There wasn't a lake there at the time,
but there is now.
- That's right.
- Yeah.
- For drunk driving.
- Okay.
- So it says Boris.
Not sure if I should apologize for not having
an interesting or cool crime or just assume you're glad
that I'm not the UK's Charles Bronson.
But we have a call is coming from inside the big house.
- Okay.
- So yeah, Boris sends some facts about cranes
because they in Wisconsin have lots and lots of cranberries.
And the name of the cranberry comes from cranberry.
- Yeah.
- And there are two types of cranes there.
- Wait, sorry.
Is this the episode where we did, it is.
It would leave and where we talked about cranes.
- Yeah.
- So he's connecting cranes and the Chippewa.
- And the Chippewa.
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah.
- That's pretty good, isn't it?
- It's spooky.
- That is spooky.
- Yeah.
- And it's about the fact that whooping cranes were bred
by people dressing up in crane costumes
to teach the young cranes what to do.
Boris finishes, "I apologize if my facts aren't perfect.
This is all from memory.
I am in prison after all, and we don't have internet."
- Well.
- So how have you sent this email to us?
(laughing)
Injustice.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Not being funny.
- He must have escaped.
And that's why I'm not giving a surname.
- I imagine he probably got one of your bucks
and hollowed it out and then put a key inside.
- That's a good idea.
- Best use for them.
(laughing)
- So I wonder if we have more prison listeners.
- Yeah.
- If you're listening on one of those prison phones.
- Are you not familiar with prison phones up your bum?
- It's not.
- I can't mention on this podcast.
- Yeah, that's how you get a phone into a prison.
- Everyone?
- Everyone.
- No, with the small phones, yeah.
- You wouldn't get that.
- They specifically designed some
that can be smuggled into prisons.
- Yes, you'd struggle with one of the later iPhones.
(laughing)
- You don't want to go for the plus.
- No.
- iPhone 17 plus pro.
There's no phone up there.
(laughing)
- That's, that's big ass tonic.
- He's the scariest guy on the block.
(laughing)
- Comes in with a laptop.
- You really don't remember the prison bump phone.
- When did we do it?
- Oh, you know what I mean?
- It's already eight years ago.
- Yeah.
- You really don't remember this one conversation
you had eight years ago.
- I'll scream you, man.
I thought we were friends.
- Well, thank you, Boris.
- And the final extreme fish is
Theica von Ziano, who writes in saying,
"I'm a licensed dogger in Australia."
(laughing)
So apparently this is an Australian construction
and rigging thing.
- Dogger, is that?
- Yeah, dogging is foundational.
It means safely slinging loads to cranes and guiding lifts.
So you walk forward with a load like walking a dog
and that's the big thing.
- Right.
- And Theica writes, "When I was performing
my first solo aerial street show at the Edinburgh Festival
and was erecting my seven meter rig in Parliament Square,
a local comedian asked about my credentials.
I brightly replied, "Don't worry, I'm a licensed dogger."
Turns out in the UK, that means something very different.
(laughing)
- That's good.
- That's cool, but that took a major twist
from being someone who works as a dogger
to suddenly setting up an insane contraption at the Edinburgh
fringe.
- Theica is a very interesting correspondent.
- What was her name?
- Theica von Ziano.
- Great.
- Theica also writes, "You mentioned organs
shifting around the body, bin there."
- She's got a bin there.
(laughing)
- Why should you get to keep her phones?
- This was a big chat where we were saying,
"Can you move internal organs via massage?"
And surely not.
So what's this gonna say?
- Well, during my early solo aerial years,
I developed a trick involving a triple cartwheel spin
on the same side of my body.
- Who is this person?
- Sorry.
- Andy, why are you talking about the cartwheel?
If you're gonna do a cartwheel,
it really has to be both sides of your body
that do that cartwheel.
- Theica, I haven't seen the move,
but that's a really good point.
- I guess the side you're leading with?
- Okay.
- But later, during a routine ultrasound
for gynecological stuff, the sonographer told me
my kidney had shifted to the front of my body.
No pain, no symptoms, just relocated.
- Oh.
(laughing)
- No questions.
- I have no idea.
- I'm not taking any either.
- I don't think I have any.
- Honestly, I've now questioning the dog I think.
(laughing)
- Right, just a couple of very final names,
nommed of terms, Carrie Gong writes in
that the new New Zealand Minister for Energy
is called Simon Watts.
- Very nice.
- Lena Gellach points out that there's an author
called Dimitri Capitelman, who's last name literally
means chapter man, author, chapter man, decent.
Jane Crouch writes from Portland, Oregon,
that she was married in 1994 by a priest named
Father Pope, dressed for the job you want.
Jamie learned a bracket writes in
that her mum's friend has a last name,
her maiden name was Tor, T-O-R-R-E,
and she married someone whose surname was Hyman.
And it was the Tor Hyman wedding.
And she's double barred at, she's gone with Tor Hyman.
(laughing)
- Jesus.
- And finally, the absolute most exciting thing
comes from Ben Murray.
This is part of the things you think are named after someone,
but they're actually named after someone else
or something else.
- This is a title of your new book.
- Hour, hour new book.
- You're getting...
- I don't think so because Dan, at the same time,
is doing the competing people who pay stuff
on the top of house's book.
- Well, what's your book going to be?
- Mine will just be a normal book.
- Well, that's not going to sound.
I think that's a very good reverse psychology.
A normal book.
- And what's that next to your two?
That's going to fly out of the shelves.
- That's really, I'd say that's book a contender,
a normal book by a normal man.
(laughing)
- Oh, what's weird about this guy, nothing.
- Nothing.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Oh, things that you think are named after.
- Yeah.
- What was the example?
The children's Python, which is named after someone
called Children.
- Yes.
- Right.
- Ben Murray wrote a blog post about a product
called Valentine's Meat Juice.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- It's named after its creator who was named man Valentine.
(laughing)
- And what is it?
- Is it like a kind of a stock cube or something?
- It's part of a first world war Canadian food parcel.
So if you're a Canadian soldier in the war,
you would get a bit of Valentine's meat juice.
And the juice was a protein and nutrient-packed concoction
made from boiling beef bones.
- Yeah, so it's like oxo.
- Yeah, basically that.
It was marketed as a miracle cure.
And it made Valentine a fortune.
- Wow.
- So there you go.
So that's I think a sick thing in our book.
- Yeah.
- Our book.
(laughing)
- Crawling closer and closer to 1,000.
- Yeah.
- So excited.
- And that's it.
That's all of your fantastic emails.
- That's wonderful.
- Thank you so much.
- Rappers up, Andy.
(upbeat music)
- That's it for this episode of Drops of Line.
Thank you for listening.
If you did.
(laughing)
- I'm really dead drive, but James Arkin.
Welcome to another episode of Drops of Line.
- Go on, no!
- No!
- What?
You pointed at me.
Does it say do something?
- No.
- I'm doing it.
- I'm not start the fucking show again.
- Thank you for listening to it.
If you did, who's hearing that sentence?
If they're not listening.
- Good point.
- Hey, Andy, you're looking forward
to hosting your radio for series
that comes out of the next couple of months.
- Very much.
- I can tell you, you're a producer, isn't it?
(laughing)
I'm kept on a much tighter leash on that.
- The email to send your comments and queries to
ispodcast@QI.com.
Just a quick reminder, we're looking for a couple
of section names, namely the section naming section.
We don't have a good fish name for that.
Anything else that you guys especially want to hear
for next time?
- Comments about the show, queries for things
that we've gotten wrong, extra bits of information.
- Yeah.
- Bloody good at this.
- Extreme places where you're listening to fish.
- Yeah.
- Anything that you think will be interesting to our show.
- Maybe someone can script an outro for Andy.
(laughing)
- Okay, thanks very much, everyone.
Thanks, everybody.
Thanks, Dan and James.
Bye.
(upbeat music)