- They don't want it, I'll put it on like that.
(upbeat music)
- Hi.
- Hello.
- Oh yeah, you got it.
I was going to tell you what you have to do with this.
- That's the situation.
- I remember the high work.
- Welcome everybody to Drop us a Line.
- Look who it is, look who it is.
- Special edition.
- Me.
- It's Anna's first episode back on Drop us a Line,
which is now by the way the main thing we do, Anna.
Everything else is a front for Drop us a Line.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- This is the heroin behind the scenes.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Grocery shop, cool.
- So, so welcome.
- Thank you.
- Right, cut.
Welcome to Drop us a Line.
Our audience feedback show.
My name's Andrew Hunter Murray.
I'm here with Anna Tajinsky and James Harkin.
- Hi Andy.
- Hi guys.
- Hello.
- We've had some fantastic emails.
- That way.
- I'm not even exaggerating.
So we're going to start off with just a section,
one off section, the return of Anna,
because lots of people have been writing in.
- That's nice because when you first came on the podcast,
when you came back after your break,
the first thing you said is,
is there not gonna be like a special intro for me?
- Starting with fact number one, it's Anna Tajinsky.
- Just strip my facts straight,
or a little welcome back to me, Andrew.
- No.
- Come here and be called that one.
(laughing)
- Are you the factor?
- She won't say welcome back at her intro.
- Like a little speech or something.
- Welcome back, it's been awful without you.
- I know.
I've heard the episodes.
(laughing)
- Laya.
- The rather full my auntie though.
We're doing the intro three weeks late.
- I've been saving it up,
because there have been so many nice comments.
So let's have a few.
- Great.
- See if you can spot the theme of these comments.
- Okay.
- Sarah writes, love the podcast
and looking forward to Anna's return,
so that she can whip you boys back into shape.
- Frank Cardinali writes,
just wondering if you three are fearful of Anna's reaction
to what has become of the podcast in her absence.
(laughing)
- Fortunately, I've never listened to it.
- I love it, but it does have a feeling
of the kids running rampant while mum's been away.
Theo Warren, welcome back Anna.
Please get these guys back in line.
Anthony, can't wait to hear Anna back on the show.
Brackets, you guys are great,
but after a while the class needs a teacher.
- Wow.
- Okay, wait a second.
Look, I thought this is gonna be a big Anna's
so great fest, but I've been called a mum and a teacher.
- It's very, Anna is the disciplinarian.
- All right.
- Is what the lesson has been getting over the last 12 years.
Don't know how you've got that.
- 'Cause I thought myself as the chilled out
of fun-loving clown.
- Oh no.
(laughing)
But a correction from Didry Cooper, okay.
The podcast blurb in the Apple Podcast player
referred to Anna as a prodigal podcaster.
- Oh yeah.
- I saw that.
- prodigal means spending money or resources
freely and recklessly,
which is what the prodigal son did.
- Yeah.
- The story in the Bible.
He spent all his money and he had to come back and--
- I saw the blurb.
It angered me as well, Didry.
Don't get me wrong.
I felt like it wasn't a good start for me to open my return
by sending a furious WhatsApp message on our production group.
But yes, prodigal refers to the habits of the son who returns,
not the returning.
- Sure.
But I was merely using it as a metaphor
for you, so people would know that you did something similar
to what the son did, which was return.
- Yes.
- No, I get that.
I get that.
- But I think also you are wasteful and extravagant.
- Yeah, that's actually what takes, then, secretly.
- That's why I've had to come back to the show.
I didn't want to.
- Right.
Thanks, but no thanks.
Which I think you might have coined, Anna.
- So I could have sounds like me.
(laughing)
- Sounds a bit polite for you, really true.
Well, congratulations Rafael Alvarez.
Had an idea for a new tier of Club Vish.
- Okay.
That's nice.
- So we've got a dual citizenship, plenty more fish,
and then friend of the podcast.
Rafael is pitching "So of the podcast."
For an exorbitant amount of money,
members can claim one of a limited number of foes
of the podcast to curate or fight.
Haven't worked out the details.
A few examples to get it going.
Mark Twain, Adolf Hitler, Zoe Williams,
the guardian writer.
I mean, we have FIFA Zoe Williams.
She wrote a piece asking why we're such bros on this podcast.
And it was, I think, even if you disagree with that piece,
I think a Hitler and Mark Twain.
That's not--
- Hit the Mark Twain and Zoe.
What a weird dinner party.
- And the Treaty of Versailles.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Greg Wallace, of course, the podcast.
(laughing)
- He was for a small amount of time.
- See, we mentioned that.
- A few times as a father of the podcast.
- Did we call it before or after he became a co-operator?
- No, no, no.
- Oh, yeah, thanks. - Nothing yet.
(laughing)
For bonus, invective, people in this tier
can hear the uncensored clip in which Anna says,
"Which country has the ugliest men?
"And all the one in which Dan says,
"Which celebrity rejected a chance to meet Buzz Aldrin
"because they weren't a fan of space."
- Yeah, there's been a few of those reductions over the years.
- Yeah.
- But the thing to know is that I delete the original.
- So you can never go onto my hard drive
and find out who those celebrities are
because I delete them.
- That's good.
- Just in case someone steals my laptop,
slowly, so they can find out which celebrity is not into space.
- Which country has the ugliest men?
It's so weird, I really want to have access to that file.
So I know who I think has the ugliest men.
- Yeah.
- It must have been, I wouldn't have redacted it
if it was a country that we would never play in.
- Right. - Right.
- Oh, well, that limits it.
- I see.
- I feel like I would only do it if it was like,
Wales or something, so when we might play it, you might.
- It's not even a country, though.
Moving on, that's a joke.
People of Wales.
- Let's go on to, let's move on.
- Just a joke.
It's just a joke.
- To a bonus bream.
- Oh yeah.
- But it's also a get yourself off the hook.
- Oh, I'm not familiar with it, he's gone then.
- Okay, bonus bream is where we get extra information
about something that we said in the podcast.
Getting yourself off the hook is where we've made a mistake
and Andy tells us about it.
- Yeah.
- But you may be able to get yourself off the hook if it was.
- It's worth saying that all of these names
have lots of subnames that mean the same thing.
- Right, okay.
- Or sometimes the same name is two different things.
- I'm sad that I missed all the brainstorming sessions.
- There was no brainstorming.
- There was no brainstorming, there was one bream involved.
- Yeah, I feel weird, James, I don't know how you feel about it.
I feel weird like I'm presenting droppers alone too, Anna.
And I feel a bit nervous.
- I'm not surprised, you do.
- With good reason.
- Yeah.
- You're just in the, you're offstead, I think.
And I'm a teacher who's like been whossing around
for a long time, we haven't had that measure for measure.
- I'm just saying, if you thought it wasn't fun
being called a teacher, you've now gone to an offstead.
- I know.
- The one who fires the teachers.
- Right.
- And we've been dealing with a manageable class size of two,
but I've still screwed it all up.
I would say, okay.
Jamie writes, "I write in the confidence
that your apocas to appreciate
"extremely pedantic corrections."
- Is that enough?
- In your most recent episode, it was stated
that neither Oliver nor Richard Cromwell
could have observed the Chinese steam car.
- I believe it was you who said that, and it was me who said that.
While this is true, because it was in the 1680s.
While this is true of Oliver,
Richard Cromwell could in fact have observed it.
He reigned as Lord Protector for less than a year,
but then resigned and lived in exile
until the age of 85, dying in 1712.
And we've mentioned this before.
He was the longest-lived head of state
until Queen Elizabeth II.
- And did he go and live in China?
(laughing)
- That's right.
- Hey, here's the fun thing I read.
- This is bonus cream from me.
- Lucky.
- Who's the first European that you can think of who went to China?
- Marco Polo.
- Do you know, he wasn't of you kind of, obviously.
There were some people who went even as far back as ancient Greek.
Some people went to China.
But Marco Polo's dad and his uncle both went to China.
- No way.
- He wasn't even the first Polo to go to China.
- Yeah.
- That's really good.
- Isn't that amazing?
- They must have been so pissed off with him
when he got the book claiming he was a Nepo explorer.
- I should have known, 'cause in his memoirs,
he calls his dad drunk from a beach saying,
"Please find me out of here."
(laughing)
- Here's a bonus cream from Peter Blum.
- Oh yeah.
- In a recent episode, you noted,
"Earth is the only place with plate tectonics
"and that they thus may be necessary for life," right?
- Interesting.
- Did you know there is another hypothesis
which suggests that life is actually required
for plate tectonics, (laughing)
because little life is so abundant,
small like microorganisms,
that it creates things like mud and limestone.
And that sort of lubricates the plates
and that might kickstart the kind of tectonics we now have.
What a theory.
- It sounded silly, but when you explain it,
you explain that you're not just saying
that a human one day said, "Earthquakes!"
and it happened, then it makes sense, actually.
- It does.
- I love that all modern earth and rock are all made of animals.
I always love that chalk, like the reason chalk is white
is just 'cause it's skeletons.
The white cliffs of Dover is all just dead things.
- Yeah, as a boring old teacher, you would like chalk.
- You'd actually have an interactive whiteboard.
(laughing)
- That you've drawn on with permanent marker by mistake.
- Oh, Radioclam number one.
- Okay, Radioclam number one is where?
- Well, what are you thinking of?
- I was actually here for this.
- Radioclam number one.
- I really hoped it might have blown over in the nine months.
I've been gone, but--
- You've got fingers blown over.
- You've had any big boss shits as blown into where we are.
(laughing)
- Right, well, I didn't know it had turned into a segment.
- It started with a segment.
- What segment would it be, do you think?
What does it mean?
- It's something where we say,
well, what's this thing?
- And a million people write in and say,
"I'm so insulted, I'm this thing."
- Brilliant. - Kind of.
- Yeah.
- Just getting a lot of emails about the something.
- So what's the Radioclam this week?
- I'm gonna start with Laura Falkiner.
I'm writing it off the back of the later little fish
to let you know that rag-and-bone men,
brackets people are still going strong.
- Rag-and-bone people.
- They're not going strong.
(laughing)
- I don't know the context for where are they going strong.
So what happened was, I mentioned that when I was growing up,
we had rag-and-bone men, but in fairness,
they're not always men, but they're always known
as rag-and-bone men in where I came from.
By any way, we start had them growing up
and even into my 20s we had them.
And I mean, was very surprised by that.
- Yeah, and well, I've been schooled thoroughly.
Sheffield 2020 to 2022,
Laura Falkiner has seen evidence of them,
calling for any old iron.
She says, "James isn't old, he's just northern."
(laughing)
- That sounds like someone saying something
when they look at my face.
(laughing)
- Oh, you look old.
- I'm not old, I'm just northern.
- Rob Hardestie says, "I remember them on horse-drawn carts
"in the late '70s and early '80s in Rochtdale."
So maybe it was a northern thing.
Annie Self lives in the small rural town of Bungay.
Oh, and it's Bungay, not Bungay, sorry.
- I'm famous for having lots of Satanists,
not that I've ever met one, not that you know Annie.
- I really, are they like the Mason's or something?
- You don't know, I mean, you wouldn't mention it.
- You wouldn't mention it, but probably some people
mentioned it as soon as they meet.
You're high, I'm a Satanist actually.
- Oh yeah, I like it.
- But some people won't keep it.
- Like if you get out of the Satanist, they'll tell you
as they pull out your twitching heart
and rub it on a wall to open a portal to nether realms.
- But Annie says, "We have some guys come round
"in again in a flatbed truck shouting,
"any old iron, which is the proper--
- Annie old iron, Annie old iron, Annie old iron.
- See, that's a cockney song, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- And Lisa Surties has a slightly related thing
'cause she remembers them from Hartley Pool.
- It is going strong, that sounds like I take it back.
- But Lisa moved to Hartley Pool and says,
"We have some of the last sea colors.
"Twice a date, they drive a truck out to the beach
"when the tide is out.
"Gather the coal that has settled on the beach
"with shovels and load it into their truck every day."
So that's it.
- I think they're turds, aren't they?
(laughing)
- They burn the same, they burn sweeten the right.
And then Lisa says, "There are many places in the world
"where colder posits wash up on the beach."
Yeah, I think not.
But Hartley Pool is one of them.
- No way.
- It sluffs off and washes onto the beach.
- Sluffs off from nearby--
- From the colors' seats, the nearby seam of coal,
which is exposed at the seabed.
- Wow.
- So just, shh.
- That's fantastic.
- Daniel Painter says, "In Little Fish,
"you had a quick think of who is the most
"hatted modern day leader."
- Oh yeah, that's good.
- Does the Pope count?
(laughing)
- Oh, he has to.
- Yeah, he's winning, isn't he?
- What constitutes a hat?
- Are you thinking Skullcats for a chief rabbi or something?
- I'm thinking Skullcats, I'm thinking like Yata Arifats.
- You know what, that's what I said.
And they mocked me, I've not been up to date.
(laughing)
- With my world leaders.
- He's not old, he's just Palestinian.
(laughing)
- But someone else has similar cultural markers as I do.
- Do you think his son would do better
if he always wore a top hat?
- Yeah.
- Oh, without doubt?
(laughing)
- He would, wouldn't he?
- Anyway, look, we've got 50 pages of heath.
- Jesus Christ, Andy, 'cause I have to leave today.
- You think he'd do that?
- You go, when I say you go, not when the bell says you go.
(laughing)
- Right, let's come on to Both Fins.
- Oh, I'm so glad this is still in.
- Yeah.
- Experts, on stuff.
- Who've written in to school us?
- Mendel Skulski, what name?
- If he good, if he ran a ski school.
(laughing)
- Who says, "I run a small ski in school on the,"
just thought I'd offer a slight correction
on the kelp highway hypothesis.
- Okay, so this was the theory that humans moved down
the American coast to follow the seaweed.
- The West Coast where there was lots of seaweed.
- I think it was James who mentioned in passing
that people were surviving in transit writing kelp.
- I think it was, yeah. - I think it was me.
- I think it was no issue.
- It's quite likely that some kelp was being consumed,
but more likely it was all manner of seafood, fair point.
(laughing)
kelp houses lots of animal species, basically.
- No, yeah, I see that, but there's kelp and other stuff.
But he says, in case you're interested,
we, future ecologies, spent three whole episodes
talking about kelp and its ecological
and social entanglements.
- This is an ad for this guy's podcast.
- Well, I deduct that.
- I suppose so, yeah.
- Unless they pay us.
- Okay, but it's mental then has a great fact,
which is the reason I wanted to come to this.
It's the fact that sea otters were restored
to the West Coast of North America
after having been driven nearly to extinction
right sea otters are almost white though.
And they were restored not for ecological restoration,
but to evacuate them from impending US nuclear testing
in Alaska, that's just a cool fact about that.
- Yeah, nice.
- Right, I don't know what section this is.
Oh, it says "Misc" at the top here.
- Does everything need to be a section?
- Yeah, surely we should just talk.
- It does.
- Fischerlenius.
- No, it's Mussolanius.
- Oh, is that?
- Mussolanius.
- Really?
Did you just think of, or is it?
- No.
- No, but when I said it the first time,
I had just thought of it.
- Then I wrote it down as I've never remembered it since then.
(laughing)
- But I'm writing it down again now.
- There's a lot of writing stuff out in this podcast now.
- Okay, cool.
- How's the inspection going, Anna?
- It's time writing a lot of stuff down in here as well, I need.
- Okay, here's a question for you.
Haley Thompson, long time listener here.
I'm planning my first trip to the UK specifically to London.
- Okay.
- I often listen to older episodes of Fish While I'm Working
and I've been jotting down places to go that you've all
mentioned as possible destinations in anticipation.
- Yeah, anywhere else apart from weather spoons,
is just planning to go.
- It's not a weather spoon, she says.
(laughing)
- I'm planning to go to Dishroom.
- Oh yeah.
- Nice.
- The weather spoons of the East.
- That caught me thinking.
(laughing)
- I love that marketing idea.
- Yeah.
- That got me thinking, if you could all pick a spot
that you'd put on a fish tour of London or the UK,
what would it be and why?
So I thought I'd put you on the spot.
I like those next to Clear Patcher's Needles.
Those, is it the two lions?
- Sphinxes.
- Sphinxes, yeah.
Where Dan said you can put your finger in the bum holes.
- Yeah.
- That was like a moment of fish.
- That was great.
And actually, once you've finished there,
'cause that's on the embankment of the river,
and you should go to spend a lot of time near the river,
go to the Basel Jet Memorial,
which is by embankment tube.
And it's just sort of, it's quite rosy there, but it is.
- Just in a wall, isn't it?
- It's just in a wall and it's Joseph Basel Jet,
who built the sewers.
And it's on land that he reclaimed from the river.
What's your peccana?
- Oh, I would say go to the,
do you know what we did that episode on Thomas Hardy?
Thomas Hardy's grave.
So Thomas Hardy designed the graveyard in King's Cross,
was it at the time, but then it all got moved.
And now there's kind of a monument to it,
just behind King's Cross.
And it's this amazing kind of tree
with all these old gravestones sticking out of this.
- Spiraling around this.
- Yeah, that's pretty cool.
- Yeah, that's pretty good.
- Paul is corner of Westminsterrabby.
- Oh, that.
- Tower of London.
- I mean, they're just places.
- St. Paul's Cathedral.
- Yeah.
- That literally, they will be on your first page of Google.
- You're fantastic.
- London Eye.
- Today's it's London Eye.
- If you can get out of the city, Stonehenge is a good day.
- Shrek's adventure, if you can't.
- I tell you why, if you're coming from North America
and you've got a bit of time, spare Francis, nice.
- Yeah.
- London Zoo has a lot of animals from all over the world.
- Oh, yeah.
- You don't need to go anywhere once you've been there.
- Yeah.
- So there's a big friend.
- I mean, genuinely.
- So we live in a city of jewels.
- Sure.
- Wondon, that's what I call it, because it's wonderful, you know?
- Shotsy elf.
- This is a bit called Bad Romance, 'cause we've had romance, R-O-E.
- Yeah, I got it, yeah.
- Fish eggs.
- Yeah.
- And now this one's about Lady Gaga.
- This is the fact that Lady Gaga.
- Yeah.
- Sure, Lady Gaga.
- Alex Dean writes, "As a long time listener of the show,
"I've always hoped to one day work a fact
"from the podcast, organically, into real-life conversation.
"Unfortunately due to my terrible memory, I've never managed it,
"until the other day.
"While on a date, we walked past a model train shop."
- Wow.
- It's a lovely, lovely day.
- As we stopped to look in the window.
- Come back, come back.
We need to look in this window for a bit.
- I suddenly remembered a fact from the show
that I was delighted to finally deploy naturally
in everyday life.
I turned and explained to the Cole.
(laughing)
The Cole used in model railway exhibitions
is actually just small.
(laughing)
- Crossed up pieces of Cole.
- Zeta, I married him.
(laughing)
- She replied that that was one of the dullest things
she had ever heard.
(laughing)
- I don't know what to say, Alex.
It's how you tell 'em.
- But if she could get in touch with me,
I think we might get along pretty well.
- Isn't that wonderful?
- That's just lovely.
- Congratulations, Alex.
- Good luck getting back on the app, son.
- You're first to tell that.
(laughing)
- She's out there.
Ah.
There we go.
Logan writes, this is the thing that's sort of micro-clown.
There's a little clown.
- Okay.
- I'm listening to the drop of the line,
the episode in which people have written in about
having a difficult time telling,
Dan and Andy's voices apart.
- Oh yeah.
- I'm sure the inbox is bulging
with even more people contributing their thoughts
on the matter, sort of, actually.
A few people have written in saying, yeah,
can't tell Dan and Andy apart.
Logan says, I'm visually impaired
in a way that affects central visual acuity.
So Logan relies on voice and stature to identify anyone.
Logan works as a 9-1-1 dispatcher.
- So 9-9-9 for British listeners.
- Thanks.
- And I've got, and I've got very good at distinguishing voices.
I work with dozens of units throughout the week
and I can identify most of them by voice,
having never seen them.
- Great.
- I've listened to this podcast almost every day since 2019
and I still can't tell Dan and Andy's voices apart.
Isn't that weird?
- Wow.
- They don't even sound the same.
And I can tell that it's two different people talking.
But I can't for the life of me identify who is speaking.
- What?
- I know.
- That sort of implies they sound different to you.
But what they're saying is sort of so non-memorable
that you haven't managed to peg it to their name.
- Or memorable in the same way.
- Yeah.
- They just say the same sort of stuff all the time.
- The same, yeah, exactly.
- That's how big the slam, isn't it, Andy?
- Well, on someone.
- On someone.
Yeah.
I mean, no one has a problem identifying your voice, James.
- Yeah, that's so interesting.
- They do mistake you and I when they see pictures of us.
- Yep.
- And whose voices?
- That's true.
- And by think my actual voice, they would know it was James
but they might not know what I look like.
- Oh yeah.
- This is Andy speaking now.
- Oh, that's not here.
- Yeah.
- That's why he's not-
- It's the easiest today, Logan.
Yeah, yeah.
- Right, come on.
Get yourself off the hook.
Dave Wang writes, "Life long bilingual."
And that's not just a boast because also,
"Fisherless in the Sense Day One."
Dan's Chinese name should be Shry Bo,
which literally sounds like Shry Bo,
and means handsome Uncle.
- Ah, not Uncle Egg.
- Because Dan said his Chinese name was Uncle Egg.
And then Dan texted me separately saying,
"Oh man, I misspoke on fish."
So apologies if you get lots of emails.
We've had one.
I said my Chinese name is Uncle Egg,
which it is, but I didn't realise I just said my surname bit.
So it's Shry Bo at Dan in Chinese.
- Oh yeah, Dan does mean Egg,
because Dan doesn't miss testicles.
- Yeah.
- The whole name is, "Thanks, she Uncle Bo, Egg, Dan."
Sorry if the inbox gets flooded.
(laughing)
- Dan, flattering yourself.
A number of people who are listening to what you're saying.
(laughing)
Did you know that more than half the people on this earth
are fluent in at least two languages?
- Oh, that's amazing.
- That's good, isn't it? - It's so cool.
- It's good, isn't it? - Yeah.
- Western might people aren't great on that,
but most of the world doing well.
- Yeah.
- Well, a lot of Western might people
who don't have English as a first language are great on it.
- Yeah, also very good, yeah, yeah.
Just English speaking people out there.
- Moe's actor from India here.
I was listening to episode three, five, one.
No such thing as pop charts for bagpipers
in which you mentioned anyone, anyone, do you remember?
The world's longest cake.
(laughing)
- Oh yeah, I do remember that.
- Was it in Romania?
Or was that the world's longest sausage?
- Kerala, South India. - Oh, Kerala, okay.
- The record was broken in Kerala.
I happened to have moved to Kerala for work.
There is a bakery, a few hundred meters from my house,
which participated in the event.
- Wow.
- The cake was 5.3 kilometers long,
not 6.5, as you said.
- What?
- So we got the cake wrong by...
- How did we do that?
- A kilometer.
- 'Cause it's not like we looked at it
and estimated the length.
(laughing)
We will have got that information from Guinness, I guess, normally.
- I don't know, I don't know what...
- Maybe someone ate a kilometer of it before that.
(laughing)
- Come on, something good cake.
- Yeah, I don't think it's provided sources.
And I haven't checked.
So it'll have to be one of those mysteries.
- Yeah, we'll never know.
- Final clown, bombs dropping and the whistling noise they make.
I think I slightly screwed up the explanation of the...
- Doppler effect.
Jonathan, Commander Royal Navy.
- Cool.
- What an unusual surname.
(laughing)
- Says, if it's falling on you,
you might hear the increasing note,
but you won't be able to tell anyone about it.
But if it's dropping on someone else, then the mile away,
the pitch will drop down in the final stages,
because it's sliding down the opposite side of a triangle to you.
So this is the sound, the sound that survivors hear is relevant.
I'm gonna paraphrase and be brief,
because we've had so many long emails about the Doppler effect.
- Oh, how do we?
- And I'll cheerfully just roll over and say, yeah, sorry.
- Wait, why don't you sound what was...
- Also, I said pitch and frequency, and I confused those two,
and the whole thing was a cluster mistake.
- It was a real cluster mistake.
- Peter Drake, listening to your recent episode
of "Evolving Spermord Settie".
- Oh, yeah.
- I wondered when you'd get to Moby Dick,
a book famous for being comically obsessed with this fluid.
- Yeah.
- Andy, you got there first with the line "Eat It Ishmael",
but I'm afraid you misstepped.
The harpooner was not Ishmael,
but his bunk mate, Quikwegg.
I am sure many people have pointed this out.
(laughing)
Oh, I'm gonna...
Now on this occasion, I'm gonna stick out for myself.
(laughing)
Go on.
- I think, if I had said, "Eat It Quikwegg".
(laughing)
I would have received black faces.
- When you said that in a theater of 3,000 people,
you might get one English teacher pissing themselves,
and it's made his life.
He's thrilled.
- But genuinely, I could have said,
I could have said A-hab,
but that would have been another valid joke,
'cause people know about Captain A-hab.
But there were a team effort on doing that well.
(laughing)
I think it's fine to say the most famous,
call me Ishmael, other than three words of the book.
Just, yeah, so rejected.
- Oh.
- Important to be right.
- I think we've done a whole section on Moby Dick once.
- Yeah.
- So I would suggest to go back and find that
because it was a good idea.
- It wasn't a good idea.
- Yeah, it was.
- Mikey Giggler.
- Do you know what this is, Anna?
- Oh, what?
- It's where someone writes into us saying,
"I can't believe he didn't make a joke
that you could have made on the episode."
- Wait, Mike Giggler.
- Yeah.
- It's a reference to Private Eye.
- Right, okay, you know?
- I thought it was just a name of a correspondent that we had.
- No, this week's Mike Giggler is Chris Locke from Farnham.
- Uh-huh.
- I cannot believe.
(laughing)
- That you discussed the usage of whale meat
during World War II rationing,
and forgot to mention the song, Vera Lynn Sung,
specifically encouraging the population of the UK
to eat more of it.
- You mean whale meat again?
(laughing)
- Regardless of the place or time.
- Yeah.
- Very good.
- Yeah, nice one, Chris.
You got us.
- Yeah, it's a good one, actually.
- Yeah.
- Quite often, these are not very good.
- No, that's much better than you.
That's much better than the usual.
I can't believe you.
That's lovely.
I'm gonna steal that.
- Vindancation.
We've had a vindancation.
- Oh, this is where we vindicate something
that Dan said.
- That's right.
- I know, and I can tell how long you brainstormed that part.
- We had so many emails about this.
Tim Groves is a great example of this.
You know, I'm just gonna do his email.
I'm gonna take a punt here on being one
of a legion of listeners.
Correct.
Writing in about this.
I have just been listening to the episode of Little Fish
from the 25th of May,
while on a train to London to try a vegan fish taco.
Brackets.
Not important.
Close brackets.
And I was shocked to hear Andy and Anna ridicule Dan
for his vaguely remembered story
about a man swallowing a Faberier egg.
I also remembered this story
and a light search yielded the following.
BBC News.
Police recovered $19,000 Faberier egg swallowed
by New Zealand man.
- Okay.
- It was a an octopus-y-themed egg.
- It was a James Bond film.
- I know the James Bond film.
- Yeah, and I was in that.
- It was a plant appendant, I think.
And it was laid about a week after he swallowed it.
- Okay, so it wasn't a false.
I think the problem was we didn't mention
that it was appendent and actual Faberier eggs.
I mean, he worked this New Zealander
would literally look like a Kiwi.
- The enormous egg inside him.
- But Dan was right.
Someone had swallowed a Faberier thing.
- An octopus-y-themed Faberier.
- Yeah, I mean, I think maybe they branched out
from the original taste where it's all for royalty.
- All right, I think I kind of assumed
that it probably was based in facts
because it would be an amazing thing
for Dan to have made up.
He's got a funny outbreak though.
- Yeah, but no, completely fair.
Like, I doubled down and I teased him again.
So I feel better if I haven't done it.
- Did you mess with him and apologize?
- Oh.
- Although the inbox has been flooded by it.
So actually, I should do.
But I do the email, so it's fine.
- Why don't you...
- It's a camera.
Why don't you apologize to him now?
- Oh my god, what?
- It's like a hostage video.
- This is like Johnny Depp when he smuggled
with it and got a trigger or something.
- It's like a joke to show that I need help.
Dan, I'm really sorry.
No, I'm sorry, Dan.
And I hope you listen to this.
- If anyone's been held hostage here,
it's not you, Andy.
- Okay.
- Oh, Jesus.
- That's how I'm real.
- Dave Rule.
- Is this a segment?
- Or okay.
- Dave Rule says, "I wanted to follow up
and let you know how thrilled I am.
This has become such a phenomenon in its own right.
And how much joy it brings me
to hear Dan and James Squirm
whenever one of these comes up unexpectedly."
Dave Rule sent the first ever thing
that sounds like its name for one obvious reason,
but it's actually named after a person
with an amusingly apt name.
- Okay, good.
What?
- And what was his one?
- This was October 2025.
He sent a list of things unexpectedly named after people,
including also, I mean, some classics,
Main Street in San Francisco,
named for Charles Main, Snowflake, Arizona,
Taco Bell, named after Glen Bell.
- Okay.
- We've had seven more pages of this stuff
since the last drop.
Like, I don't know what to do.
It's what the people want.
It's just what people want.
- This needs to be a whole new podcast
that we don't do.
- Ah, no.
(laughing)
- You almost contractually
applies yourself into something there.
- Yeah.
- Turn that full stop into a comment pretty fast.
(laughing)
- Dan Painter, Penny's game
about flipping a coin, heads or tails, right?
Created by Walter Penny.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
Very good.
- Daniel Power.
There's a suburb of Sydney called Wallstonecraft, right?
- Uh-huh.
- And I knew Mary Wallstonecraft was an important feminist
and I joked, imagine if it was just named after some dude
instead of her.
Well, it turns out that Wallstonecraft,
the Sydney suburb, was named not after the early feminist
and important historical figure, Mary Wallstonecraft,
it's named after a man, Edward Wallstonecraft,
who's really only known for moving to Australia
to escape the notoriety of his Aunt Mary.
- That's so good.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, I think he was a big deal in his own right, but yeah.
- I don't see.
- Yeah.
- Anyway, I can sense the patience running thin here.
So I'm just going to keep salting them away for the book.
(laughing)
And when I'm on every till in every book shop
across the world.
- That Penny one is absolutely cracking.
- I know.
- This is really good.
This should be a book.
- I don't encourage him for fuck's sake.
- Oh, it should be a book.
- It should be a book.
- It should be...
- We can spend six months writing it.
- Six months.
- We'll get it.
- Are we doing it a bridge version?
How dare you?
This is a 10 year project.
The book is called a thousand and one.
Things that are named.
Have you not had that?
- What's the book called a thousand and one thing that...
- Well, this is an excellent point.
- Oh, no.
(laughing)
- It's something.
There's the main header.
And then the subtitle is a thousand and one.
The book of a thousand and one things.
- Yeah.
- I'm still working on it.
- That you think were named for a very obvious reason,
but were in fact named after a person
with an amusingly apt name.
- I think that's very catchy.
- Yeah, it's been proposed by Thomas Groves Bond
that this be called the Hunter Index.
Not named after the Hunter, these names,
but after Andrew Hunter Murray.
- Lovely.
- Yeah.
- All right, look.
We'll do more of these next time.
Thank you so much for everyone who said one thing.
I'm sorry we didn't get all of them.
The final closer goes to anonymous L.
Who says, "I believe that I speak for myself when I say."
(laughing)
It's funny.
That I actually quite enjoy the Inca here at Ramblings
and the way Andrew Hunter Murray runs
the "Trop and Settle" I show.
Especially the section naming section
and the book of things that are named and all that.
There's already been over 50 minutes of discussion
on the actual facts on the podcast,
so not too sure why the others want to do more.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- A little trade secret.
They want to do less.
(laughing)
We over-record every time.
I keep saying we'll be out with it an hour
and we never are.
- And not a missell.
- Yeah.
I think they didn't want the name in.
- No.
- But why would you with such a penis at begin?
(laughing)
- No, in the Roberts, we cut out of this show.
You know, you'll see.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- We're wrapping up.
- We're done.
How's the inspection going on?
- I would say special measures coming out.
- Special measures coming out for you.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Thank you for listening and watching.
If you'd like to send in your stories
and your romance good or bad
or your what else we've done.
I've got a list of things.
- Any comments about the show that we've done?
- Spicy meat.
Your riddle round about.
Your secret squid.
- It doesn't have to fall into one of these
like weirdly crowbar categories.
- And squabbles.
- No, it can't just be common squabbles.
(laughing)
- Send your Steven squabbles.
And then the music kicks in and out we go.
And it's podcasted at qi.com.
Okay, thanks everybody.
Bye.
(upbeat music)