- They don't want that, who don't want that, who don't?
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to "Droppers Align".
My name's Andrew Hunter Murray,
and this is James Arkin and Dan Shriver.
This is our audience feedback show.
If you're joining us for the first time,
welcome, some of you are watching,
some of you are listening.
Those are the two options.
Some of you are doing both.
- Good options.
- You're either listening or you're listening and watching.
But no, you're doing neither.
In which case, this doesn't apply to you.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- I should say, I don't want to put you off,
but I've started watching the new show last one laughing.
- Yeah.
- And I find it remarkable they can't laugh the whole way through.
So I thought I'd try today neither to smile or laugh.
- No problem.
- I just failed, and I want, yeah, yeah, me too.
- Oh, okay, and that's your face, is it?
Do they do faces?
- Oh, yeah, they do, yeah.
They have a safety face for if it's getting too much.
- Let's get into it.
We've got a lot of emails, and let's see if Dan can stay
completely neutral, facially.
I don't know what that is.
- I don't think that's neutral.
I ran.
- Let's feel that might be the orgasm face.
- For listeners at home.
- For listeners at home, we've just seen a face
that I never thought I'd see Dan do.
- Oh.
- Okay, what's going on?
- I don't know what, it's really hard.
- It's really hard, keep going.
- Well, let's keep going.
Let's just get straight in with an audience email.
Greg Bunk from Illinois writes.
(laughing)
Greg Bunk.
- What's funny about the name Greg Bunk, Dan?
- Obviously nothing, it's just Greg.
- Greg is a funny guy called Greg.
- Gotcha, that's a yellow card.
- That's a yellow card.
Just a bit of non-determ.
This is the new section we're going to call
"Nomenclatuna".
- Oh yeah, non-determinism.
- Does Greg say, "I had sex once"?
- No, he's not about him.
Greg found a non-determinist recently.
Man named William Shockley
was part of the team that first developed the transistor.
- Yes, and he had this his name.
- Greg Bunk, we've been over this.
- No, Shockley.
- William Shockley.
- Are you saying it's nominative
because they use electricity?
- Yeah, and you can get electric shock
if you touch electricity, as I understand it.
- Sure.
- Yeah.
Will Stevens writes about the Norwich City Council's
Parks team, which includes a Richard Green
and a Suzanne Parkinson.
Parks, and they're managed by a man named Paul Rapitz.
- Yeah.
- It's pretty good.
- That is good.
- Now, we've had one, we've got an early radio clown
from everyone.
- Okay.
- David Saunders.
Michael's soyfurt, sorry Michael.
I don't know how to say your surname.
David Hopkins, conflict about that one.
And Justin Ray, have all sent in the fact
that the UK defense attache to the UAE
who has been quite busy in recent days, says David,
is called Sandy Sandy Lans.
- Oh, that is good.
- That is good.
- Really good.
- Yeah.
- Sandy Sandy Lans.
- One more non-determ before we start.
Keith Bush of California writes, in 1963,
the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences
nominated a Bad Ham for an Acting Award.
Specifically, Mary Bad Ham, Badam.
- Yeah.
- She was in Tequila Mockingbird,
in which a key scene requires her to wear a ham costume.
- I don't remember that.
- Yeah, what's that thing?
- I don't know, I mean, the 60s Tequila Mockingbird.
I guess there's a tariff in a mental asylum.
- I think that's one of the cookies in the courtroom.
- Yeah.
- I think one of the jurors walked in in a ham costume
I wouldn't feel too.
- Yeah, so what's going on there?
- I can't remember.
- I have seen the film, but years and years and years ago.
But it's got the word ham painted on the front.
And it's spoiler alert saves her from a life attack.
So in the end, it proves to be a very good ham, says Keith.
- Damn it.
- That's nice.
- Yeah.
- I didn't give you time to think of that, Dan.
I just, motorbikes are straight through you.
What do you mean?
- Well, you said, "Damn it."
As though, oh, I wish I'd thought of that gag.
- No, damn it.
- I could smile, so I'm out of the game.
- I think only you were playing this game as well.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- No, no, I'm keeping tabs.
I'm on a red card, so back to the normal show now.
- Okay.
- You're allowed to smile, aren't you?
- You're not.
- Oh, no, no, no.
- You're smiling or laughing, misleading title, yeah.
And also in the film, there were actors including two Hamilton's
and one Bacon and Gregory Peck, of course, is the star.
And you get a Peck of Bacon, that's a quality of bacon.
- Is it?
- Yeah, actually.
- Peck of Bacon.
- You didn't know that.
- So those are your non-determins.
- Very nice.
- Non-miclituna, dealt with.
- Okay.
- Really nice.
- Would you like, I wanted to give you a choice now.
I wanted to choose your own adventure episode
of "Top of the Line."
I thought there might be a way of spicing ourselves up.
- Oh, great, cool.
- Yeah.
- I'd like some, get yourself off the hooks.
- Awesome.
- Extreme fish.
I hope we can put a reverb on my voice there.
- Yeah, sure.
- Extreme fish.
- Let's get ourselves off the hook
and then save the other one till later.
- Yeah, all right.
- Good shout.
- And I don't get a vote.
(laughing)
- Well, in other words, they say that.
It's 'cause I thought that you would think
that we would go for the extreme fish.
- Yeah.
- I'm trying to scuppy your plan.
- That's fair, yeah, I mean.
- But you're right, we're going to do them all eventually.
- So, yeah.
- It doesn't matter what order the cards are dealt, does it?
- Do we die at the end of one of these?
- At all of them.
- Okay.
- That's when Andy does the outro.
(laughing)
- I die for five to 10 minutes.
- Okay, Marie from DC writes.
- Comex.
- She doesn't say.
- Okay.
- Judge for yourself based on the contents.
- Cabal!
(laughing)
- Early nights.
You mentioned on the most recent episode
that one US state has an official state smell,
which of course is New Mexico.
- New Mexico, right.
- Chili's.
- James jokingly said that, no, New Mexico.
Not chili.
Chili doesn't have an official state smell.
- James jokingly suggested it was Washington, DC.
But I just wanted to point out that DC is not a state.
- Oh yeah.
- That's true.
- We are a district with no representation in Congress.
- No, I, I do.
- You idiot James.
- No, I know that.
I do know that.
However, the joke sort of depended on me saying that it was.
- 'Cause it was the stink of corruption.
- Stenture corruption.
- Yeah, yeah.
So it was a great joke.
- It was a great joke.
- Is it a certain area of the state of Maryland?
- Yeah.
- Oh, that is pretty strong as well, actually.
- Where people can vote in mayoral
and presidential elections,
but not in congressional ones.
- Yeah, no, I am aware of all that stuff,
but the joke format didn't really allow me to.
- I'm writing a new section then, which is,
yes, that was the joke.
And I think that might be not to be too fancy about it.
But you're in the hands of professionals here.
- No, I do see that a joke is always going to be better
if it's also factually true.
- Yeah.
- Disagree.
- Well, for some people like they can't get past
the cognitive dissonance, that's not really true.
So you're always going to lose a little bit of your audience
and actually for us, that's going to be a larger proportion
of the audience, the most comics.
- We're meant to believe that an Englishman and a Scotsman
are all walking into the same bar at the same time.
How big's the door?
It doesn't stack up.
- Yeah.
- You know?
- I'm just seeing a chicken cross a road.
- It's like, what a great point.
They live in coops.
- Yeah, they're in, yeah.
- You live in the houses, but you still cross roads.
- Yeah, let's go.
- Yeah, man.
- What is a house except a coop for a person right now?
- Oh, wow.
- Okay, here's another one.
Matthias Panzenberg, I feel like we've heard
from Matthias before.
- Yes, I think frequent correspondents of the podcast.
Because you didn't know when Tolkien died
in the last episode.
- What?
- Uh-oh.
- Apparently we said, when did he die?
I can't remember all something to us.
What is that effect?
- There is an easy way to remember,
which is also a little bit of a coincidence.
There's a poem of the ring in the book, Lord of the Rings.
Three rings for the Elven King's under the sky.
Seven for the dwarf lords in their halls of stone.
Nine for mortal men doomed to die.
One for the dark lord on his dark throat.
- And was he dead he died in 1973 on 1937, 1973?
- Really?
- 1973.
- Three, seven, nine, one.
The opening numbers, one, nine, seven, three.
- I'll be, honestly, I'm more likely to remember
the year that he died.
- That whole poem.
In fact, I might be able to remember some parts
of the poem, thanks to remembering his death.
They run the other way around.
- Absolutely, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So that's just a nice fact, though.
Thank you, Matthias.
- It's a brilliant fact.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- The Picasso died as well.
And--
- What are you suggesting?
- Someone was doing a very convoluted hit job
on something that we've not yet connected.
If anyone can make the connection dead.
- I'm on it.
- Yeah.
- I'll just tell you about what Henry Biggs suggested.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Back in episode 570-ish.
- That's a while ago now.
- Actually, no, this was much longer ago.
James' fact was that Jaguar created a concept car
that sounded like a Jaguar.
- Okay.
- Oh, that's in the last few years.
- Yeah, it's not like a Jaguar.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And he says, "I know this definitely isn't true.
"I'm gonna pick you up on this, Henry."
(laughing)
- I know that, Henry, I'm gonna say.
We specifically said the thing that you're saying
we didn't say in the show, 'cause I had a little check.
- I mean, I spoke to the people
who went to this company.
- James, I'm defending your honor already.
- You let me, just please, you hang back.
- Is this thing called get yourself off the hook
or let Andy get you off the hook?
- Good point, you know what?
- Yeah.
- Whoever you want to fight for your honor, James.
- Okay.
- I'm willing to do it.
Anyway, Henry Biggs writes.
- James' fact was that about this Jaguar sound like a Jaguar.
"I know this definitely isn't true," says Henry,
"because I wrote the press pack for the launch of the car
"at the Paris Motor Show."
- Okay, interesting.
- Speaking from authority.
In fact, the engine of the CX-75
was also conceptual.
EG made up.
And like most concept cars,
it was powered by an electric golf cart motor.
Maybe that's why you like the cars,
'cause you sense there was a golf cart involved.
But you said it was a concept car.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- You said at the time it was a concept car.
So I think you'll compete the off the hook.
- Okay, okay.
But here is a related fact in return, says Henry.
Here's the method.
- Oh, yeah.
- Feels good, doesn't it?
- Absolutely.
- My fact is about how great Andy Stoffels are.
(laughing)
Around the same time, Jaguar started fitting its cars
with exploding bonnets for pedestrian safety.
- How, okay.
I'm trying to work out how that would be safe.
- If you have a go.
- So we did a fact user gone no such thing as the news,
which was that some bonnets were being made sticky
so that if you crashed into it,
you didn't fling away.
You just went with the car wherever it was going.
So an exploding bonnet might love you higher into the air.
- He's got it.
- Away from the collision.
- Apparently if the car detects a collision
with a pedestrian, explosives would lift the bonnet upwards,
cushioning the impact.
I query, if you're being tossed high into the air,
how much safer you are because you will come down.
- I think the answer is that we don't have those
on all cars now.
- Yeah, yeah, presumably they didn't work that well.
- Yeah.
- I guess not.
- No.
- So thank you, Henry.
- I'm sorry, we gave you a bit of a slamming there.
- All right, time for James's book corner.
- Cool.
- Okay.
- What happens in this section?
- Talk about my book.
My Nana's book.
- Great.
- Not your Nana's book, just your book.
- Oh, which one?
- A normal Chris Brodie.
- A normal book.
- Oh, a tree.
- So we had a thing where you were going to write a book
of things which are named after not the things
that you would think they were named after,
according to their names.
Dan was going to write the book of people
who paid things on the top of houses.
- With no pictures.
- With no pictures, or worse.
And I was going to write a normal book.
- Yeah.
Well, Chris Brodie, let us know that in 2006,
two Dutch writers wrote a book titled,
"Ean Normal Book."
A normal book.
- That's good.
- For people who just wanted a normal book.
(laughing)
It's really good.
And they followed it some years later with,
in "Annda Book," another book.
- That's good.
- And then last year, they released it,
"Geen Book," not a book,
which is for people who don't want a book.
- Or was it still a book?
- I'm clear.
(laughing)
- That's, I like how this has become a thing
when what actually it was was someone asked me,
what's your book going to be about?
And my brain just went completely blank.
I just said a normal book.
- It was a complete failure.
- No, it was brilliant.
- How's it coming along, by the way?
- Oh, as you'd expect.
- Yeah, yeah.
It's always slow going at the start,
but once you get that, the bit between your teeth.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- Can't wait.
- It's time for extreme fish.
- Yeah!
- Yeah.
- Love extreme fish.
- We got a few good candidates today.
- Kiara.
- Right.
- Kiara here.
- Of La Sania.
- Slash, La Sania.
- In for me.
- There was a thing we did about.
- La Sania, yeah.
- Was it how he said it or how he's built it?
- Or both.
- I can't remember.
Was it about plurals?
- I think it was.
- It was infamous, whatever it was.
- Oh yeah.
(laughing)
- I just, in order to be infamous,
it has to be famous.
- Exactly, exactly.
- None of us can remember it.
- No, but the three people really on the entire earth
who really should remember it.
- Kiara remembers it.
- Is this the right show?
(laughing)
- It's been challenging.
- It's been challenging to write into.
- It says, also known as the Dutchess over on the fish gourd.
- Okay.
- Oh yeah, I know her.
- Okay, yep.
- I wanted to share that I actually used that story,
La Sania, Slash, La Sania into me,
to win over my partner when we met on hinge.
And it worked so well that I now have my very own La Sania
in the oven.
- Okay.
- She's expecting a baby.
- Yes.
- Oh, nice.
- Needless to say, I will be listening to no such thing
as a fish during labor in a few months.
- Oh, congratulations, Dutchess.
- That's amazing.
- First fish baby, maybe?
- Yeah.
- First fish baby.
- Very cool.
- Wow.
- If she has time, can she write back in with what the La Sania
story was?
(laughing)
- No, I should have tried.
- Cool to know.
- I should have tried to get down to the inbox.
It was a thing we said about the pluralization.
James has it.
- Yeah, I'm sure.
- Very cool.
- First, I think first fish baby.
- We've been going for 12 years.
- What is the definition of a fish baby?
- What is the count as a fish baby?
- In this, they met because of a fact.
- Yeah.
- Is there anything else to it?
- I used that story to win over my partner when we met on hinge.
- No, no fish story, no partner, no baby.
- So it doesn't have that many layers is what I'm saying.
- Oh my God.
Did you, we slowly, I was trying.
- I was hauling, hauling my stuff and ass over the ground
towards that butterflies.
- I thought James was being a bit mean about this.
It's lady's email.
Say this is not very kind.
- Oh, dude.
- Brilliant.
- Well congrats, that's very sorry.
- Absolutely.
Here's another extreme fish.
- David, no surname, I'm afraid, surname redacted.
- All right, it's not like share.
- David.
(laughing)
- Like the statue.
- I live in Italy.
(laughing)
- And it's really cold actually.
- David writes, "I am a policeman in Western Australia."
- Oh.
(laughing)
- The other ride.
- That's mad max stuff.
- Well, it's lambie del stuff.
- It's lambie del stuff, yeah.
- I was in the car with my partner listening to fish.
On duty it seems.
We came across a knife wielding idiot.
I jumped out of the car.
And because I'm old, I have hearing aids.
I started negotiating with the knife guy.
And then the podcast transferred from the car radio
to my hearing aids.
(laughing)
So there I am, holding a taser pointed at knife guy,
trying to tell him his day is about to become alive
with 30,000 volts boarding through his body.
We see they're quite strong in Australia, aren't they?
(laughing)
And I have you, Muppets, discussing how you should sign
off the podcast in my ear.
(laughing)
So knife guy goes down after being hit
with two prongs from a taser.
And I discovered that saying,
"Buy is the best way to sign off a podcast."
He's still listening to fish at this point.
I then finally got to my phone to allow me
to stop listening to Andy rant on about something
so I can handcuff this fellow.
If broadcast, please tell you his my surname.
I will be subject to the Cake Act.
(laughing)
- Oh, the Cake Act.
- Wow, let's remind everyone,
'cause that's such an obscure reference.
The Cake Act is when you make a mistake
as a police officer, you have to buy the entire police unit
that you work in the office cake.
And it can be anything from small chocolates to,
if it's a big blunder, a massive cake.
- Yeah.
- That's very cool.
- First fish arrest, I think.
- Yeah.
- Wow, really exciting.
- We had someone listening from Inside Prison last time.
- Yes, yeah.
- I was just thinking we've had first fish arrest,
first fish baby.
If you're reaching any other sort of big moments in life,
doing fish, we could create a full from birth to death.
That's great fish.
- So first fish baptism.
- Yeah.
- First fish circumcision.
- Yeah, yeah.
- First fish.
- Shag.
- No.
- No?
- I don't think anyone should have the first time
you should be listening to fish.
- Have you ever watched, I see clips of this.
- 'Cause you also want, sorry, you also have that, yeah.
- I see these clips online, is it,
I'm sorry, I haven't had clue,
which is where you have to say a phrase,
which you can say while you're in traffic,
jam and while having sex.
- Yeah.
- I wonder if there's any phrases you can say while doing fish
and while having sex and they both make sense.
- In no particular order?
Here we go.
- That's good.
- Yeah.
- Bye.
(all laughing)
- I'm a bit of semen squabbles.
- Oh, it worked here.
Oh.
- We lost them.
- No, I'm just, they're all coming to me now.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Come on then.
- No, I can't work out, I had to get it in.
- As it were.
(all laughing)
- Guys, we'll be going for 20.
Shall we move on?
(all laughing)
- Right, now it's time for, can you think of while I get it out?
- I'll tag on when I'm still doing that.
(all laughing)
- A title for the post bag,
where we've been sent a physical object.
- Oh, okay.
- Oh, so it's a physical.
- Fishical?
- Let's get fishical.
- Oh, that's a fishical.
- That's really good, yeah.
And that's the song.
- Yeah.
- Yep.
Yeah, good.
Is that your final answer?
Let's get fishical.
- Oh, okay, so it's a fishy thing.
- Like a sack of eggs.
- Fish, fingers, I think no.
- Fish, fingers.
- It's quite nice.
- It's quite nice 'cause it's so unexpected.
- The mermaid's purse.
That's the thing where sharks lay eggs
in its inner sort of strange receptacle.
- Okay.
- The mermaid's purse.
- That's quite lute.
- The egg itself is called the mermaid's purse, yeah.
- Finnail?
- Yeah, finnail.
Finnail.
- Okay.
- That's really good.
- Well, let's use it as an opener.
Right.
- This begins handwritten.
- Hello, darlings.
- It took me a while, but I finally made
your no such thing as a fish pasties.
(laughing)
- Can I ask you to get out?
- Look at that.
- Look at your lips out.
- Oh, wow.
Every serious, but less dancer has a stage name,
so I'll hope you don't mind,
but I decided to choose one for you.
I think we can be fairly sure it's unique.
- Just showing them to the camera here.
- These are great.
- Are they the same?
Can I look at the other one?
- Yeah.
- Oh, yeah, they are.
- Well done.
- Which thing does Everard think be?
- Pop 'em on.
- You don't have the rhythm.
- Some technique work needed for Dan, but they're really nice.
- But they're really swish.
- No such thing as Everard think be.
- I know.
- They're beautiful.
- And our correspondent, Mabel Syrup, adds,
"I leave you with one final burlesque fact.
"Pasties are not exclusively worn on the nipples.
"Many talented performers have evolved the art form
"to wear them on their bum cheeks,
"where they're genuinely known as assholes."
- Very nice.
- Mabel Syrup.
- So they're kind of made of foam, they're square.
They have our logo on it, says, "No such thing, guys."
And where it would say fish, it says, "Everard dig be."
And then they have golden tassels
that things you might find in an old pair of curtains.
And then on the inside, they're kind of attached
by some kind of glue, which I think would chafe.
- Interesting, yeah.
Also, they say, "Everard dig be."
- Yeah.
I mean, surely "Everard dig be" would be our stage name.
Definitely.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, sure.
- Absolutely.
And if you wanna send in some droggs of what you think,
Andy would look like as a hard dig be.
- I don't know.
- Hoggastic.
- Cue I?
- I think people are busy.
People have got lies, are they?
Okay, a quick trip to the section naming section.
I'm afraid.
- Oh, my favorite bit.
- Guys, this is what the people want, is it?
- I'm struggling to hold back a rising tide of this
in the inbox, where people are just,
people just want to name sections.
So section naming, Ben Hopkinson suggests
Nomin Clam Tour.
- Right.
- I think we've already done Nomin Clotuna, though, haven't we?
- Yeah, you made that one up.
- No, that was Jamie Blanchard.
- Oh, is it?
- Yeah.
- But Ben Hopkinson also suggests Spawn Hub.
- I didn't want the section done this though.
(laughing)
- Spawn Hub.
- It's nice.
- I said yeah.
- Like Frog Spawn.
- Must be, yeah.
Fish to fish, Spawn, I suppose they do.
- They do, don't they?
- Luke McNeil suggests the title
for a miscellaneous section.
- Misscale Anius.
What about muscle Anius, like a muscle?
- That's, but, sorry, that is a miscellaneous improvement.
- Yeah.
- It is slightly improvement.
No, Luke, Luke, you had to walk so that we could run.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- So thank you.
- Rex Buckingham.
- Amazing name. - Right now.
- For, you know, we have Rale, Rale, Rale,
brackets, your boat.
- Yeah.
- Suggests Fight Blub.
- Oh, okay.
I think that's really good.
- I'm up.
- That is Fight Chubb.
- Fight Chubb.
- Again, Rex.
(laughing)
- I'm really back on the line for him.
- We saw see this week.
I thought Wright Hook was the name that we landed on
for that one.
It was actually, but I forgot to write it down.
- This is why I have to write it down, James.
- I'm pretty sure you wrote it down last time.
(laughing)
- You don't think Fight Blub or Fight Chubb?
- Hi guys, great.
- Thank you.
- We haven't had much Fight Chubb actually today.
Kevin Rundle suggests to name that tuner,
which I think is really good.
- That is quite good for the section, name in section.
- Yeah.
- That is good. - Name that tuner.
- Siracle the house says finception.
For, I think the section where we're talking about
the names of the sections.
And that is good.
- No, it is good.
- Finception.
- Yeah, that's very good.
You've got to admit that, James.
- Sure.
- I feel like you're a very defensive person
when these names come up.
Like you're trying to find a way through
so that we can demolish them.
- He's just doing a second draft.
(laughing)
- Very good point.
- I have a script editor, that's my job.
- Yeah, quite right too.
Phil Beto and Ray Gorn both suggest Fischelanius.
But I think we've said Mussolanius.
- Mussolanius.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause we need variety on the use of the word fish.
- Yeah, you can't just show fish in everything.
(laughing)
- Actually, we're back in the bedroom.
- Bibblebub suggests renaming,
get yourself off the hook as talking Pollux.
(laughing)
- That's good.
- That's really good.
- That is good.
- Well, you've been talking Pollux.
(laughing)
And for an expert section where we've had,
you know, expertise come in.
Louisa T. suggests aficionados.
- Right.
- Yeah, it is nice.
It works.
- Yeah, it does.
It uses fish, which we've just said,
you know, we need to be sparing with.
But, I think that's really good.
And now, under suggests,
thank you again for your wonderful shows.
I very much enjoyed the second to last drop as a line
where I think the entire episode
focused on naming the sections.
Just a thing.
(laughing)
A bonus Patreon merch could perhaps be
a list of the different drop as a line sections
of their meanings.
It would help.
- All it is is I quite like the show
and I love getting messages in from people
where they add extra material or they pick us up on things.
And this to me is not pure.
It's not what I signed up for, Andy.
- Yeah, I guess the drop has changed.
It doesn't fit for you.
I know it's worse, because I'm still in its direction.
I don't even just stuck on trying to think
of things with a bedroom now.
So I'm not even present.
- No.
- Time for a bit of bonus bone.
(laughing)
It works.
- It does, it sort of does work.
- Oh dear.
- We found an email from Ben bonus, actually.
- What?
- Yeah.
Sorry, I just looked down thinking,
oh, I don't want to think about bonus bone.
I just looked at the word Ben bonus.
(laughing)
- Ben bonus.
- Bonus.
- B-o-n-i-s.
- Great.
- And what does Ben have to say?
- Well, I don't want to read your email just yet.
We'll come to it in a moment.
Because first, to get into his email,
we have to go through an email from Nick Wheel, okay.
Who's part of the Clubfish NYC chapter.
- Cool.
- New York City.
- I'd love to know if we have like chapters that connect,
you know?
- Let me grind.
- Yeah, that's exciting.
- If only we could connect people in each city
around the world who listen to fish,
maybe by going there and playing a show,
where they can meet up.
- Yeah.
- But without actually going ourselves.
Because we can't be on tour all the time.
We've got homes and lines and all of that.
But we could arrange meetups for people around the world.
- Is the idea you book out of pub,
but we don't show out.
- Yes.
- Okay.
- That's it.
(laughing)
- As I do every birthday.
- Yeah, that's it.
- What I'm imagining is just not happy to go to the pub.
(laughing)
- That's great.
- Yeah.
- Okay, so what does Mr. Wheel have to say?
- Wheel has to say.
There is a classic theme park design concept
called the Duel Loop, okay?
There's a park theme park layout,
which is a circle around a circle, okay?
- Right.
- Visitors enter a main circular path
that loops around a central circular core
of backstage space, okay?
And there are attractions and food and shops
around the outer edge of the loop.
So if you simply keep walking forward,
you will eventually pass everything in the park
and you'll wind up back where you started, okay?
- Okay, okay.
- It sounds like a perfectly descriptive name,
the Duel Loop, for a layout of concentric circles.
- It's named after Randall Duel.
- Nice.
- Very nice.
- After whom this show is named?
Drop us a line.
- Absolutely.
(laughing)
- Randall Duel.
- One of the most influential theme park designers
of the 20th century.
- That's really good.
- Have to run a lot of biggies, yeah.
- That's cool.
- So we're into the section of things
that are named after not what you think they will be named
after according to their existing names.
- Exactly.
We're writing our book.
And that was from Nick Wheel.
- And he's writing about concentric circles.
- Ah.
- Yeah, that's quite, that is quite something.
Ben Bonus.
- Oh yeah.
- Nice to hear from him again.
(laughing)
- Drop us a line.
You recently discussed, and he's upcoming book,
1,000, 1,000 things.
You would think, I call the name for the clearly obvious reason.
But actually, the name after a person.
I can't believe I didn't get into this year's last word laughing.
(laughing)
But actually the name after a person, those things.
- Yeah.
- And I have a fact for you.
- Thank you.
- The Pap smear.
- Oh yeah.
- At the, looks for the human papaloma virus
cancers of the cervix.
- Friend of the podcast.
- Really.
- Named after Papar Nicolau.
- That's it.
- Yeah.
- So it's a Pap smear, which is looking for papaloma virus,
but it was named after his inventor,
Greek doctor, Georgios Papar Nicolau.
- That's good.
- Very good.
- A paparoma.
- Straight in the book.
- Right in the book.
- Absolutely.
- Do you not remember him, Andy?
- I don't remember him.
- Do you remember the vernicular song about him?
- Yes.
- Papar Nicolau, da da da da da.
The cat said Joaquin now or something.
- Yeah.
- Oh, I had, I had genuinely forgot that
'cause we did that on the podcast, right?
- Yeah, we did.
- Nice.
Okay, so that's a great one, Ben, that's straight in.
And Seth Samuel's rights, I'm a regular listener,
writing to you from my home in Sacramento.
If you ever find yourself here,
you can take a walk through Land Park.
- Oh, that's for William Land.
- Yeah.
- Or go for a swim at the pond recreation area
named for William pond.
- Really?
- William Land and William pond.
- That's very good.
- Brilliant.
Might be the week's winner.
I think we've run out of time for today, guys.
- Oh, okay.
- Are we?
- Okay.
- But there's always more, there are always more bonus
brim.
I'm very sorry if we didn't get to your email,
if we didn't read your emails out,
because they were great too, and I've read all of them.
And they're bloody good.
- Yeah.
- Very love these.
It keeps me going.
This show, drop us a line.
- Yeah.
- In between, you know, other episodes of the show.
- This keeps me going.
- Yeah.
- We've heard from someone who's got the name Dorcus.
- Really?
- Yeah, Laura Holden, she's called Dorcus.
- Laura, she's got a middle name.
- Oh, really?
- Dorcus, yeah, really?
- We've heard about someone who,
you remember that restaurant at Alton Towers,
where the food goes in a roller coaster?
- Yes.
- Well, there's a restaurant in Prague,
which uses model trains to deliver your food and drink.
- Oh my god, it's Henry or whatever he's called.
- Percy, yeah.
- Percy, the green engine.
- That's from Susan Cockroon Brown,
that's her husband in the photo there.
- Amazing.
- So thank you, Susan.
So we've had a lot of fantastic emails
that we just, we just can't get to them all.
We heard, we had a great email about clown priests.
If you'll never know, you'll never know.
- Well, we, we do make this show once every two weeks.
You could bring it there next time.
- No.
- Nope.
- You sit down.
- Straight in the shredder.
Straight in the shredder.
I've written notes on them.
I never remember what I've written.
- No, thank you very much, everyone.
We are available on podcast@quil.com.
If you have anything to say about anything we've said,
we love hearing it.
If you're an expert, amazing.
If you're not.
If you're just...
- Just a schmo, just a schmo with a pun.
And if you hate the section,
please do say, we want to be a responsive to feedback.
I think we can all agree it's gone a bit far.
- Another sex word.
- There we go.
(laughs)
(upbeat music)
- The time next time is thank you to you guys,
Diana James and it's thank you.
No one thanks me.
No one ever thanks me on this show.
But, and they've had their chance and I'm gonna,
I'm gonna say that set.
- You know more, no more chances.
- Oh well.
- That's a shame.
- Well, I'm still thanking you
'cause you guys have been terrific.
- You're very welcome and I'm very kind.
- You're so welcome.
- Okay, that's fine.
That's fine.
We'll see you next time.
Bye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]