Hi everyone welcome to this week's episode of no such thing as a fish we have another very special guest for you today and
That guest is our very good friend Lucy Porter. You will remember Lucy from previous episodes on fish
I know you'll love her. She's so smart. She's so funny
In fact, she's got a stand-up show that is touring at this very moment
Which is called wake up call and really I'll be honest the best way to find out about that is to Google
Lucy Porter wake up call and you'll find all the dates, but she's doing the whole of the UK
It's definitely a show that's worth going to see. She also has a podcast called fingers on buzzers
It's all about quizzing and she does that with my very good old friend Jenny Ryan
It's a brilliant podcast so listen to that and she has a radio for stand-up special called Lucy Porter's lucky dip
Which is going out at 11 30 on March the 15th
It'll probably be on the BBC sounds app after that so again Google Lucy Potter's lucky dip and you'll find that and apart from that
Just enjoy the show so nothing more to say apart from on with the podcast on with the show. Oh hi Andy. I've been here the whole time
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden
My name is Dan Schreiber. I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray James Harkin and Lucy Porter
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in a particular order here
We go starting with fact number one and that is my fact
My fact this week is that it took the creator of the Rubik's Cube a month to solve it the first time he tried
It's so crazy you I would have thought after about 20 or 30 days you would just make a new one
So yeah invented 1974 he was a professor and he just had this idea
What if I could make something that was static on the inside but fluid on the outside and that's what gave him the idea and
He had a bash it it's later been worked out quite a famous number if you know Rubik's cubes that 43
Quintillion is the number of permutations that you can make on the Rubik's Cube
And so luckily he got there within a month. Yeah, it's pretty good. Well, I'll tell you what's weird. His prototype
Wasn't three by three. His prototype was two by two. So I've got that took him a month
That's the thing. Well, I'm curious to know if this is the one that took him a month because this is okay
So Dan's showing us an image and it's like four wooden blocks
That I've got various colors and numbers on it and they're held together almost by bits of wire
Yeah, there's a wire meshing inside and he took a month to do a Rubik's Cube
Yeah, that one's piss easy. Yeah, it's clever enough to make that you're clever enough to solve it. Yes
You can do a Rubik's Cube, James. I can I think you can Lucy
Well, I am yeah, my children obsessed with them
We've got hundreds in the house and all those weird one, you know
There's like weird different shaped ones and mirror ones where there's absolutely, you know
Colors on it and stuff. So this is a long way of me saying I should be
And I have at one point
That one's tough because it's got like Dan's mixing up one from the Transport Museum
I'd rather do the one with the colors
But the other thing is about the Rubik's Cube is that I find that when you're under pressure
It's almost impossible. Yes, because you do it kind of with muscle memory
Yes, and then as soon as you start thinking about it, you can't really do it at all
Yeah
I made a terrible decision when because I did learn to do it when my kids got into it and then I
Decided we were doing a live podcast recording of fingers on buzzers and I said, oh, I tell you what'll be fun
I'll solve a Rubik's Cube while we do this round, and it took about 15 minutes
Is there an algorithm basically? It's like a set pattern of moves that will help you work on the side you're working on
So layers, that's the key
Yeah, exactly so
It's layers not sides, so you can see at the moment that I've done the bottom layer
Right
Or the top layer
And then you do the middle one, then you do the top one
Remember when we went on only connect and they asked you for facts about yourself
And my fact was that I could do a Rubik's Cube in less than a minute
And the team that we were playing with apparently one of them said that he could do three Rubik's Cubes in 30 seconds
They decided they weren't going to use that fact
Made you look pretty foolish
But it's huge, the speed cubing because we had to get a timer so that we could record my kids' times
And also my kids said "Oh, can we have some Cubelube?"
And that's the moment that I was like "I'm sorry"
As a mother you've got to worry
Couldn't we have some Cubelube?
Is there a brand? Is it a specifically sold lube?
There is one of the best Cubelube, we didn't get good Cubelube
It's called Cubelube
Yeah, we got dodgy Cubelube
And it's allowed as well, it's allowed in competition
It's legit, it's like chalk on your hands if you're an athlete
Yes
Well there's just a piece about the, you know, there are so many cubes, the world, there we go
But listen, the change has just completed the rubies
That's why I've been silent for the last three minutes
But by the time I've edited this it'll be about twenty seconds
And it just listed the GAN 356 iCarry, the MoU RS3M Maglev, the GAN 11M Pro
And it's all, there's kind of FIFA of cubing
The World Cube Association
Are they corrupt?
They're hugely corrupt, millions and millions of dollars change hands
So 1981, the top selling book in America was a book that was called The Simple Solution to Rubik's Cube
It sold six million copies and it was the number one book of the year
It was massive, a guy called James G. Norris, he was a professor
He did it as a pamphlet for his university and then someone saw it
Said can you expand that into a like sixty four page book
So it wasn't that big, it was double the expansion of the pamphlet
And so he published it and in it he gives categories of what you're labeled as as a cuber if you manage to do it in certain times
So this is 1981, twenty minutes, if you did it in that time you were a whiz
Ten minutes, you were a speed demon
Five minutes, you were an expert
And three minutes, you were an emcee, the master of the cube
Oh that's what I am then, I can tell you
Yeah, you're a master of the cube
Well in the 80s you were a famous person
It's actually been updated since 2013
You're now adult
Yeah, unfortunately
Well you James, if you take longer than sixty seconds
I do, I take probably about a minute and a half first
Okay, I'm afraid you don't even qualify as a whiz at this point
Whereas a whiz was twenty minutes it's now sixty seconds
Speed demon has gone from ten minutes to forty seconds
Oh my god
An expert has gone from five minutes to fifteen to twenty five seconds
And the master of the cube which is now called world champion
From three minutes to three to five seconds
That's amazing the difference isn't it
I can't even pick it up within three seconds
My old arthritic fingers
Because I remember the original crates in the 80s
I'm old enough for that
But it was one of those things that boys would learn to do
And this is a terrible sexist generalisation
But it did tend to be boys would learn to do it thinking it would really impress the girls
And all girls just went meh
I found that I've never ever pressed a girl with a Rubik's cube
I impressed the QI's accountant once
With a few Rubik's cube tricks
But he wasn't my type
I did because I brought mine in today
So I did sit on the tube doing it
And people don't look at you with admiration
I'll be honest
Really?
It's pity
No honey, honey, we'll just have to get up at the next stop
Is she gonna do it?
The craze just is unbelievable
The 80s craze
So it was the UK toy of the year in 1980
And then again in 1981
As if they just thought
We're gonna give it to the cube again
So Dan, you were mentioning the books that sold out very well
So at one point in 1982
I think it was four or five different books on the New York Times bestsellers list
For Rubik's cube books
There was a boy called Patrick Bossert
Who was 13 years old
And wrote a book called You Can Do the Cube
And sold nearly a million copies of it
He was the youngest ever author on the New York Times bestseller list
It kind of came from nowhere, right?
Like Dan says, it was invented in 1974
And this was 1980
In 1981 it was absolutely huge
I looked on the newspaper archives
And the first mention of it
It doesn't even call it the Rubik's cube
It calls it the Hungarian magic cube
This was in 1979
This was in The Observer
And they said that at first most people tried to take the cube apart
But that is not the object
And it said if you even get one face done
Of the cube in 20 minutes
Then you've done well
And it says, but there are several people
Brackets, well at least three
That are able to solve the cube in less than five minutes
Dan, you mentioned that there are 43 quintillion different states
That you can have
The newspaper said, and this was in 1979
At one per microsecond
A computer would take around 3,000 million years
Just to count up the number of states
And in 2022
We got the first ever quintillion per second computer
So today a computer could reach it in just under a minute
I think what's extraordinary
The numbers are so bamboozlingly big
I remember reading an interview with Erno Rubik
Where he was talking about the fact that he'd invented
More kinds of Rubik's cubes now
There was a Snake Rubik's cube that he'd invented
Did you buy that Lucy?
I did have it
Rubik's snake, which sounds a bit dodgy now
Why did they call it the Snake and not the Rubik's tube?
Sorry, very nice
But he said that and this one has potentially even more permutations
And the guy writing the article just went
"Yeah, once you've hit 43 quintillion, I'm not impressed anymore"
But what's interesting, so very randomly
Day before yesterday I bumped into
A Rubik's cube Guinness world record holder
He's a guy called George
He holds two records, one which he's just done
Which I'm not allowed to reveal
I know, of course that
Rubik's cube Goss, I'll tell you guys after the show
The other one is that he has the most Rubik's cubes
Solved while riding on a skateboard
For, I think, like an hour or something
He did like 500 of them just going around a skate park
Quick question, Dan
Did he have on him a bag of 500 Rubik's cubes
Which he then had to get out of the skateboard?
Yeah, yeah, yeah
It wasn't like Santa, yeah
What he was was he had people stationed around the skate park
So he'd hand the solved one to the person
They would mix it back up and he'd grab a new one
As he was travelling around
So they mixed them back up again and so he used the same one
It feels kind of pointless
It's like a punishment for the gods, actually
It is, it is, it is
So he demonstrated one thing I found amazing
Which is to do with the bamboozling numbers
If I took this right now and I mixed this up
To give to him to solve
Whatever I've just done here
Is a combination that he will have never seen
In his life
The combination is unique because of the 43 quintillion
I just spent 2 and a half minutes in
I think what's extraordinary
Like when it started getting big
There was a big concern that is this thing solvable
So there was a world fair that he was taken to
And he's not a particular
He's quite a philosophical guy
He's quite sort of very serious
And he wasn't the best ambassador of what this item was
But they needed him there
To prove it could be solved
Otherwise it was the Americans, wasn't it?
Yeah, they got sent to an American toy company
And they thought this is a good toy
But it probably can't actually be done
And I think they sent an executive to Budapest
To meet Rubik
If you can solve this, we'll make it
We'll manufacture it and we'll distribute it
And then they sold 150 million in those 3 years
But they sold it thanks to the most famous
Hungarian at the time
So Rubik obviously couldn't really do all the press and stuff
Such a great question
I'm going chajagaboor
Was it?
Absolutely, chajagaboor
Rubik's Cube? That is not a Venn diagram
Amazing, right?
So this is the earliest mention of the actual phrase
Rubik's Cube I could find
This was from 1980
And chajagaboor had put on a party for the Rubik's Cube
Where she invited all of her Hollywood friends
Wow
With a buffet of Hungarian delicacies
That said, but he didn't say what I supposed
Goulash, but I'm not sure what else was there
Wow
Rubik's Cube was hired by the ideal toy
Corporation to promote
The Rubik's Cube
As she said, even if you can't solve it
The Cube feels so good in your hands
It may replace worry beads
Oh, nice
Like the original fidget spinner
Or like those new poppers
That is true, if you do just play with the Rubik's Cube
Even if you don't solve it
It is fun to play with, isn't it?
Especially if you've got Cube Lube
Oh, it flies through your hand
You know, I told him from quite early
And he said that children are better than adults
Solving it, which would you agree with that, Lucy?
Yeah, my own anecdotal experience
Who was saying all this? Was it Rubik?
That was Rubik saying that
He had a couple of reasons why he thought
That kids would be better
More nimble, wrists
I think purely physical terms
Smaller hands
I always think with technology
My kids will just pick up anything
And go "blah, blah, blah, blah"
Whereas I am hovering
I am tempted to think
And I overthink it
Maybe there's an impulsiveness
Yeah, I think overthinking
Is kind of one thing he said
He said it requires a certain innocence
That children had
Because adults will try out a pattern
And it doesn't quite work out
And they'll just never do that again
Whereas kids will keep trying things
The thing is with the Rubik's Cube
It is all algorithms and it's just repeating things
And so kids are good at that
He also said that kids
And I think this is probably quite true
Is at certain kids anyway
Will get very absorbed with one thing
And won't let anything else distract them
Just kind of concentrate on it and do it
And the other thing he said
Is that kids have good visual memory
And that is true
Children can have much better visual
Until around 10 or 11 or 12
They have almost idetic memories
That they can just remember things really well
He didn't mention nimble fingers
It's weird
Cos I know Rubik was Hungarian
In 1981
The spokesman at the Hungarian Embassy in London
Said the cube is our secret weapon
To pacify the West
Wow
There was even a cartoon
Did you guys see the cartoon?
Rubik's Cube, it's a sentient Rubik's Cube
That is an alien
So great and it was a Rubik's Cube
That was completely useless if it was out of position
And that could happen quite easily
If a passing pigeon knocked it
And it would become useless
But if it was in its right sold state
It was this powerful sentient thing
Could he change?
Could he solve himself or did he require?
He required
So it's called Rubik the Amazing Cube
And it has
I love it, his IMDB page has goofs
One of the goofs is
Even in its sold state
The colours of Rubik are often in the wrong position
The light is always across from yellow
Correct?
So it says in many of its sold states
The colours are sitting next to each other
That shouldn't be
What a blue colour
But it was actually
It was not a long lasting series
But it was very much praised
It sounds like such a long lasting form though
The family that
When trusted with the sentient cube
Was a Latino family
That was shown on TV really back then
So it was a very progressive show
It was seen as a
It's nice to see a family who aren't white
It's the leads in a cartoon
Bring it back it's what I'm saying
They didn't announce a film in 2010
Which I'm not sure
They did that with loads of them didn't they?
Like loads of toys
And they made one or two battleships they made
Battleships got made
But they also announced Ridley Scott's Monopoly
Which I don't think
Happened unless I really missed it
But they're about to do Tetris as a big series
They're about to do a big Netflix series about Tetris
I think Guess Who
Would be a very good one
Very instantly recognisable characters
A mystery, do you think like a mystery thing?
Yeah
Did the suspect
Wear a hat
Weirdest follow up to Knives Out
Operation that would be another good one
Operation, yeah
Gruelling harrowing medical job
It's his funny bone
Let's get the tweezers
Okay, it is time for fact number two
And that is Lucy
It is this fact
On at least three occasions in the last 16 years
The government of Shanghai has tried and failed
To stop people wearing pyjamas
Outdoors
Which seems
Famously Chinese authorities
Are so laissez-faire
The fact they've tried and failed is quite interesting
It doesn't say much for the all powerful machinery
Of the state
You can't even stop people wearing pyjamas out
I don't think they've sent the army in
They've just disapprovingly said
You shouldn't do this
They haven't really tried then
There's been several attempts
It's quite a big thing, particularly in Shanghai
For people to wear pyjamas
Out and about
They think it's partly because
In the early 20th century
It was a real status symbol to be able to
Afford imported pyjamas
So people would take to the streets
In their firing and are going look I can afford these
And slippers
They've got little teddy bears on them or whatever
And so it was sort of
A status symbol and then it's just become a thing
I mean I'm all into it
Because I wear pyjamas at all times
I'm doing a tour at the moment
In which I wear pyjamas so I'm very much on the side
On stage you're a pyjama
Because I decided during lockdown
There's nothing you can't
If I do a zoom and the other person is wearing something smart
I think you absolutely lose her
Why would you dress up
To have a meeting in your own home
Especially now you think if they're not wearing
Three layers and a blankie you think
Oh showing off you can afford heating
So what you're doing then is possibly
Doing in China as well
Which is you've got daytime pyjamas
And then you'll go home and you probably
Have nighttime pyjamas that you wear right
This is what they do in China so
These aren't the pyjamas they're waking up in
And just going out onto the street
They'll get out of their pyjamas to put on some pyjamas
To then go out into the street
Yeah they are the day wearer pyjamas
I can't say that for everyone but that's
For a lot of people
To be honest I would try and get away with
Going oh no these are my fancy pyjamas
No no I definitely didn't sleep in these
Definitely didn't
Have you ever done a school run or anything in your pyjamas Lucy
Well do you know I was on Five Live the other day
Because the Prime Minister's wife
Had gone and done the school run in her slippers
Except they were like five hundred
Pounds slippers
And Five Live phoned me up and said oh for our
Breakfast show tomorrow do you want to do a
Phoning about should you be allowed to wear
Slippers on the school run and of course
I'm desperate to promote my tours so I said yes
But the great thing was nobody cared
And it was one of those
It was lovely when you're part of a sort of
Supposedly controversial phoning that is not at all
Controversial
Did people just phone in and say I don't care
Yeah they just said well you can wear what you want
This is a tantrum do you know the most amazing radio phoning
I've ever heard
I was in a cab on the way somewhere or something
It was quite a long journey this was 2020
And it was if we get
A new royal yacht right
Should Prince Andrew be allowed
To go on it
There's not going to be a new royal yacht
Just not
And people had such strong opinions
This must have been in the first two months
Of 2020 I assume
It was yeah yeah
Events overtook
That one
Where do you stand on
Should Prince Andrew be allowed on the royal yacht
Oh god he's actually thinking about it
It's a tricky one isn't it
It's a taxpayer funded yacht
If they're buying their own yacht
I guess
But if I'm paying for this yacht
Yeah I think I am actually angry about it
I think I shouldn't be allowed to go on it
What if he's not allowed to come above decks
What if he's only allowed in the
I think he should be allowed to be in steerage
That's fine
You can't keep him hidden in a basement
You don't want to get on that yacht and discover Andrew
That's it
Oh god no
They used to use sign language on the old royal yacht
Yeah because they wanted to keep it quiet for the royals
And they had this complicated system of
Waving at each other
That's not typical BSL sign language
No sorry they had a royal yacht
Based hand language
Like the people on Ryanair
When they need a new tin of Pringles
They have a special sign that they make
The attendance
They have a secret sign language code
For whatever they've run out of
You'll notice it now next time you've got a flight
You can't wait
Paraboloid for a Pringle
I'm not party to the code
But I know that it exists
Like bookmakers
Bookmakers and the aircrew
Nice
I can get us back to pyjamas
The other thing they did on the royal yacht was
I think they wore soft sole shoes
The crew so they weren't stamping around the decks
And presumably infuriating Princess Margaret or something
So they had a specific
Well speaking of pyjamas
They did used to be
Outdoor things didn't they
Well they originated in
Like Persia
Ottoman Empire
And they were just basically
Loose fit trousers which you would tie around the waist
They were taken by the
Colonial British
And they realised that they were quite nice to sleep in
So that's how they became pyjamas
But Coco Chanel thought that we should wear them down the beach
And they became really fashionable
People wearing pyjamas down the beach
In the 1920s and 30s
Really? Yeah
There was a place called
I don't know how to pronounce it, it's in France
So it's J-U-A-N
I think it is
I think it's Huan Le Pan
I've seen it and not been able to pronounce it
It feels like Huan Le Pan
Feels like the nice way to say it
But it was called 'Pajamaland'
In English and 'Pajamapolis'
In French because there were so many people in pyjamas
On the beach in that town
I think it does come and go as a fashion
And there's pockets of it
I remember being in Cardiff for quite a long time
And there was one area of Cardiff
Where everybody went out in their pyjamas all the time
Is that right? Do they wear pyjamas
Or the ones they slept in?
I think sort of the ones they slept in
But it's a fine line between leisure wear
Shall I tell you about the various attempts
To shut down a pyjama wearing in China?
Oh yes, yeah
So in the 1990s
There was an education campaign
And they put signs up in Shanghai
Saying 'Please don't wear your pyjamas'
2008, the Rixin neighbourhood
In northeast Shanghai had a public campaign
Saying 'Don't wear your pyjamas'
But then, 2020
In Xuzhan city
Which is near to Shanghai
There was a social media post
Exposing uncivilised behaviour
Increasing the quality of residents
And the local government
Put out various pictures of people
Who were engaged in antisocial behaviour
Including seven people in pyjamas
And they used facial recognition technology
To find out who they were
And put their names up
Which, what you need there
Is you need pyjamas that have got some sort of balaclava
A sleep mask
A sleep mask exactly
But yeah, it does seem extraordinary
I think around the Shanghai World Expo
In 2010 as well, there was quite a campaign
To stop people wearing their pyjamas
Yeah, that was a big one, wasn't it?
The government at that one hired
500 members of the public
To volunteer to sort of stand at bus stops
And just, just if someone in pyjamas came along
Go 'Hey, that looks daggy
You need a change out of that, mate?'
Yeah, 500 alties
Do you know what kind of pyjamas
James Bond wears?
Or what he wears to bed?
Surely he doesn't wear anything
I mean, because I don't think pyjamas are sexy
Can they be sexy?
Well, great point
Because there are obviously fancy silk pyjamas
Which might be sexy
And the switch might not be
The pyjamas aren't sexy because they cling
Unless it's proper silk
Yeah, silk
That's a problem
All the balloons in the house
So Anthony Horowitz
Is a thriller writer
He writes lots and lots and lots of books
And he, for a while, was the
James Bond sequels
He was the official state's choice
And he wrote a couple of Bond books
And one of them was called Trigger Mortis
Great name
And in the start of the book, in the opening chapter
Anthony Horowitz wrote a description of Bond
Jumping out of bed, naked
And he sent this off to the flaming estate
And they got back it up and they said, 'You can't have that'
Because it's official Bond canon
In one of the books, I can't remember which one it is
I think it's 'You Only Live Twice' or something
Bond wears a bed jacket
Which is maybe the least sexy item
Of clothing you could possibly imagine
It kind of buttons up to the neck
And it goes down to the knees
The winky night shirt style
So he just rewrote it not saying that Bond was naked
He didn't describe the bed jacket
Because he thought that would be a way of destroying the character
Bond undid the top button of his night jacket
Bond hung up his night cap
On the side
He just imagine a little packet of Renny's in the pocket
Oh, there's a hand key in there
How long has that been in there for?
Interestingly, for a very long time
The classic trouser pajama
With the jacket button up kind of thing
For a long time, worn by men
And that changed during World War I
This is where women started wearing it
This is according to a professor
At the University of Glasgow called Lucy Whitmore
Who talked about the fact that zeppelin raids
Meant that whenever you heard the alarm
And you needed to run out of your house
It got to a point where
You became quite conscious of what you were wearing
You would come out in your nightie
You might look a bit dishevelled
And also it's not the most practical thing
To be running around in a nightie
So to begin with, at the start of it
It would be people would leave
Very nice looking jackets in a very good spot
So that as the raid was happening
And they would grab it and go out
And look fashionable
There was an old lady who suggested leaving
An emergency toupee by the door as well
So you could grab that on the way out
And then eventually people started wearing
Women rather started wearing pajamas
And the popular colour was dark blue
Because if you're outside
You obviously don't want any extras
Come on
You don't want to give away
I guess if you're being bombed
You want to do everything to stop yourself from being seen
Is that also why you need the toupee
To stop the bald head
And light reflecting back up
Dan Widley, I found the same zeppelin based
First World War fact in it
I went to the library and did a bit of research
There are a couple of books about the history of underclothes
And I sat there looking like a dirty old man
Sitting in the library
Or you did have your penis out
You should never
Believe me
But almost
Every page of the book had a
Line drawing of some corset
Or some girdle
Or something and I just started quickly flipping
Through the line, I'm just here for the pyjamas
Actually, I want the least sexy stuff
Do you know what though, anyone looking at that would go
That is the most adorable thing
If that's how you're getting your kicks
I'm looking at line drawings of ladies petticoats
It's not Andrew Tate
Let's be honest
And what did you find anything extra
On the underclothes
The onesie was sort of invented in that period
Wasn't it? We know Winston Churchill
He's still not wearing a onesie and that was
A World War one
He called his like a bilus
Siren suit
I think that was later
He meant siren suit because of the air raid sirens
I was thinking that he would sit on a rock and sing
Imagine if he had a lovely singing voice
We never really heard him sing
So I wanted to meet them on the beaches
We will seduce them on the beaches
Most men
Claim not to wear anything to bed
But you're doubting them
Okay, interesting
I am doubting them, I think
I think the dramas have a reputation of being a bit cosy
I think there is a sense
That men want to be thought of as being tough
And rugged and like I don't wear anything to bed
Even if it's minus four in the house or whatever
Is there not and now listen
I know nothing of the male anatomy
I'll put that right out there but is there not
Do things not get a bit twisted and I would
Imagine discomfort if you slept completely
Naked as a man, do things not
Is it not nice at all? Is it alright?
Is it alright? Good to know
Good to know, thanks for that
I've never been woken up by that
I've never twisted anything
It's got a trap under the bed again
Finally you're going to have to fold in the fibre game again
If you tried to leap out for an air raid
I feel like that was one of the weirdest moments
Ever on our podcast where you had
Three guys sitting here picturing ourselves
Naked in bed
There are four listeners now
The mental images
Please send in your fan art
Okay, it is time for fact number three
And that is Andy
My fact is the flow of the Amazon
Is so big that even a hundred miles
Into the Atlantic you could
Drink over the side of your ship
And the water would still be fresh
That's incredible, I love it
I should tell where I got this fact first
It's called Thomas Pueyo on Twitter
I couldn't believe it when I first read it
So I did a bit more looking
Some sources say the water is going to be a bit brackish
It might not be totally
Sparkling, Evian style fresh
But it would definitely be noticeably less salty
So you would not be able to see South America
If you were a hundred miles out
And you would still get water that was much less salty
If you were, let's say
You were sailing across the ocean
Before you knew where you were
You could keep tasting the water
And as it got less and less salty
You could almost find your way to the shore
What an incredible idea, yeah
To navigate your way there
Sailors must have worked that out though
Because they're very wise
There will be some sort of sailor rhyme
Like if the water tastes nice
If the water tastes nice
Brazil will be in a trice
If the water tastes salty
Then your
Compass is faulty
There you go
So every single day
The water that we're talking about
That sort of pushes out
Into the Atlantic
It's 17 billion metric tonnes
Of water that flows out
It's hard to work out what that is
What that equates to, if you were getting fresh water
In New York City
That's the daily amount for nine years
That would be used
Nine years worth of fresh water in New York City
Is what goes out daily
In the Atlantic
They should move New York
I don't know if that's practical
But it's weird that we can't somehow
Harvest it, it's just going
It's just disappearing
Becoming salty
It goes into the water cycle
And eventually rains down on us
Yeah, but we could use the planet alive
I think we've done enough mucking around
Actually, maybe we should just meet the Amazon
I actually disagree, I think a huge pike
At the mouth of the Amazon
That just takes it all the way to New York
Brilliant, not New York, but somewhere that needs fresh water
There's lots of places where they don't have water
Somewhere closer
Yeah, exactly
New Orleans
I can't see it not working
I'm just saying, it's a bit of a waste
That's 17 billion metric tonnes
It's a waste, I really don't think it's a waste
Donald Trump listening to this
Is going to be diverted to his golf courses
Anyway, the Amazon, it's big
It's big, it blows my mind
My mate's got a new Brazilian girlfriend
And he was saying, you know, you go to Brazil
It's just massive, mate
It's just massive
The thing I always find interesting
About the Amazon is that you can't build bridges
Yeah
Because it's too
Because the width of it
Varies so much
And it's so soft, crumbly at the edges
So it would have to be such a massive bridge
Because it would have to start
And so what, they just go across on boats and stuff
Yeah, yeah, yeah
I think they've built one now
There is one, but it's right up at the north
It's over a tributary
It's the Rio Negro
Which is a tributary of the Amazon
But it's before it joins the river proper
Basically, so there are no bridges across the Amazon-Amazon
Like you say, Lucy
During the wet season, the Amazon
Is 190 kilometres wide
But it's widest
That's why this is really wide
Imagine from here to Stoke
Maybe Stafford
That's further, in fact
My electric car wouldn't be able to drive
If there was a bridge that went over that net
They would have to be a charging point
On that bridge
Otherwise they wouldn't be able to get across
God, it's that wide, that is insane
I like that the Amazon River is part of
Effectively an Amazon River sandwich
It's the meat
Of a sandwich
In that
This is a tortured metaphor
I know what you're talking about and even I'm struggling
To come up with this
There's a river below it
And there's a river above it
There's more water above the Amazon River
In the clouds
Above the actual Amazon itself
The clouds follow the shape of the river
I believe so
It's water vapor stream, isn't it?
It's amazing
I think it's 20 billion tonnes of water
Yeah, and that's more water
Than it's actually in the river itself
They say
Isn't it something like a big tree
In the Amazon, perspires
Or transpires or whatever it is
A thousand litres of water in a day
One tree
And then underneath
You've got the Hamza
So secret underground river
You can only get to it
If you defeat an Aztec boss
On the final level
So
Under the Amazon there is a sort of aquifer
That is even wider
Even bigger
Even bolder, even fresher
It's Amazon 2, the revenge
The River Hamza named after the
Strictly winner this year obviously
Oh, not Abu Hamza
It's got a big hook in it
Ranger Hamza
It's quite recently discovered, isn't it?
So Hamza was the name of the head of the team
That discovered it, and it's
Very low down
4,000 metres below the river itself
Super slow moving
To the point where you can't really call it a river
Like, it's not flowing
It moves at one millimetre an hour
I relate to this river very hard
It's very slow, low down
If you drop something in it
You'll be reunited with it quite quickly
It won't be swept away
Suddenly
You game of poostics would be quite low stakes, wouldn't it?
Exactly
The Giant Amazon Leech
Which you find in the Amazon River
Do you think it's longer or shorter
Than the world's longest
Cattail?
No, I actually
Know the length of the leech
But I have no idea about the world's longest cattail
That's the difficulty of this quiz question
You actually need two quite arcade bits of knowledge
To even make a guess
I think the longest cattail is not that long
Really?
It's a domestic cat
Here we go
I think the leech is about a forearm
I think it's about 18 inches
The biggest giant leech
The longest ever cattail is longer or shorter than 18 inches
This gives it away a bit
It's a Ferndale cat
Well no, you've made it too easy
I don't want to submit an answer anymore
Is it exactly the same length?
Andy is spot on with the 18 inches
For the Amazon Leech
And the longest cattail
According to Guinness
Is 17 inches
Do you think
That the giant Amazon Leech
Is longer or shorter
Than the height
Of the world's tallest donut
Right, so
It's good now we know we've got 18 inches
Put the donut down flat
So not the diameter
Not the roundness, it's how tall it goes
I think the donut's taller
No, I think it's still the leech
Yeah, Andy knows his stuff
Tallest donut, 16 inches tall
It was quite wide and fairness
Yeah, but actually what's that foot and heart
I mean that's a tall donut
I could eat that then
I want the world's biggest donut
To be a donut that I was like
I couldn't eat that
You could make lovely donuts that big
Or like the ring road of a small town
Exactly
Oh this is a great quiz
Well I loved it, I had a great time
So this is the Amazon Tall Tower Observatory
This is a cool thing
And it's a really new thing as well actually
So it's an observatory
But not a space observatory
It's to look down at the Amazon
And so it's in the middle of the rainforest
And the trees are
What are tall trees, they're about 80 to 100 meters aren't they
A good tall tree is up to
You know it's a really tall tree 100 meters
And the tower, I think the tallest ever tree
Is about 120 meters, like the tallest ever measured
But this tower is 325 meters
Okay, it's about as tall as the Eiffel Tower
Which actually is really tall when you look at it
The Eiffel Tower
Wow busting some myths today out me
I never think of it as tall
But actually I went there
It's big, the Eiffel Tower
You can see it from a long way away
Exactly, and this is much thinner than the Eiffel Tower
It's just one needle going up
It looks mad this thing
I was up the Eiffel Tower once
In a restaurant
And we had a table next to the window
It was really nice, it was overlooking the bridge
And what you would see is
They had these guys playing
You know we have three cups and you have to hide the ball
And just taking loads of money
And then about every 20 minutes the police would turn up
And they would leg it
And then you could watch them go all the way down the river
Over the next bridge, back over again
And then back on the bridge and then start playing again
And then the police would turn up
It was like a cat and mouse
I really thought you were going to say that from your perspective
You could see which carpet was under
I just yelled
"Bettle on"
Your wife's down there looking up
You've got special cup ball sign language
You've developed
How's they doing it?
We have never been fucked before
What's done in that restaurant too? We didn't get a window seat
No, well you need to
Are there tables where you don't have window seats?
You're just looking at a big piece of iron
[Laughter]
They really saw you coming
Was it on the ground floor?
Did you get the basement table?
[Laughter]
Didn't know Peter Express was it
France?
Wow, oh that's funny
Is the restaurant still going?
I didn't even get into the restaurant
We need it, we'll go together
I'd love that
Oh yeah, this observatory is
325 metres
It's one metre taller than the Eiffel Tower
And it's got 1500 steps up
And it takes about an hour
to walk up to the top
I don't know if there's a lift actually
And basically it's just to sniff
the breath of the forest
They're measuring all the chemicals in the air
Where there are forest fires
They measure the concentrations and how dangerous that is
Deforestation
They can tell things about that
I think it's amazing
Imagine you go up and you've forgotten your glasses
[Laughter]
I can't even see the guy with the cup and the ball
OK, it is time for our final fact of the show
And that is James
OK, my fact this week
is that while playing a psychiatric patient
in one flew over the cuckoo's nest
Danny DeVito ended up becoming
a psychiatric patient himself
[Groans]
Was he going method?
Some people did go method
We might get to that
But DeVito's problem
really is quite sweet actually
He had recently
gotten together with Rhea Perlman
The amazing Rhea Perlman
And cheers right? Just to put
her head in your
Carla can cheers
And obviously they were filming
or not obviously but they were filming a long way away
from where she was
3000 miles in fact
and so he was really missed her
and in order to deal with that separation
he invented an imaginary friend to talk to at night
and he became a little bit
concerned about his mental health
perhaps because they were making this film
and there was a lot of it in the air
and so he decided to see the doctor
on set who was called Dr. Brooks
and asked for his advice and Dr. Brooks said
yeah don't worry about it as long as you're aware that it's an imaginary friend
imaginary friend is a perfectly normal
thing to have it's no problem at all
But also that doctor
the on set doctor was actually
in the movie of course
Was he? It was the weirdest thing was there
But an amazing man because he owned
the clinic in which they filmed it
so it's no wonder they were all a little bit
stir crazy because they were in an actual mental institution
filming this very intense
movie
He's the one who sort of checks in
Jack Nicholson's character, McMurphy at the start of the film
and interviews him and I think
I don't know if he was going to be in it
but he was really insistent that everyone in the institution
or the patients got involved with the film
he was quite forward thinking, you know
he took lots of the patients on expeditions
he took them white water rafting
and he taught them kind of to rappel down cliffs
and things like, I mean really
because this was in the 70s they were filming it
it was pretty progressive at the time
and I think about 90 inmates ended up involved in the film
in some capacity or another
I must say I haven't seen the film
It's pretty amazing
and I started reading the book this week
and got about a third of the way through
but I think the book's amazing
and apparently the film's even better
Tell you what was even better
it was a stage production
that was put on about 20 years ago
I was in a stage production
Who were you?
Were you the giant
Yes that's me, Chief Brompton
that was me
You know what though, so we did this basically
it was Christian Slater
from Heather's etc
came over and was Mc Murphy
and it was amazing
because at that time there weren't that many
Western shows with big Hollywood stars
Mc Murphy being Jack Dawkins' role in the movie
Exactly yes, the main guy
and I played
I played a nurse who had about two lines
and some of my friends came to see it
and they said, we just thought you were being modest
because I said I'm playing a nurse
he mumbled over the cookie's nest
you were just being modest and you were playing nurse ratchet
but you really were just
a nurse who has two lines
because Francis Barber was nurse ratchet
and Mackenzie Crook was in it
Mackenzie Crook?
He played Billy, the little shine
That's a good role for him
Shall we super quickly just say what the basic premise is?
Just for anyone who hasn't seen it
it's a bit confused
Jack Nicholson
it's been so long
Jack Nicholson plays Mc Murphy
who is this sort of tear away
who is sent to this
secure psychiatric facility
which nurse ratchet is this
horrible nurse who
rules with the reign of terror over everybody
There is one nice nurse though
who just has a couple of lines
To star of
the entire production
is that nice nurse
and then the Indian chief
spoilers are we worried about that
I think it came out quite a long time ago
So anyway
Jack Nicholson creates this air of chaos
and rebellion in the place and rebels against
nurse ratchet and then the chief
Brompton, the Native American chief
smothers him with a pillow
We should maybe say that Jack Nicholson's character
suffers a lobotomy
not just the chief Brompton wants to restore
order in the hospital
It's a mercy killing
and the whole sort of thing is
hey we're not mad, society's
mad and
there's a bit of a book where
Murphy finds out that all the patients
are allowed to leave if they want to, they just don't
He's incredibly freaked out by, he says
why don't you just go home, you're allowed
and he says I'm not ready to
It's amazing anyway
It was a very tense filming experience
in lots of ways as well because you had a lot of big personalities
You had Ken Casey
who wrote the book and then ended up hating the film
never watched it
He once started watching it when it was just on TV
and then he realised what filming he was watching and changed channel
I love that
He was channel flipping
and he was like oh what's this
This looks great, oh no
And then so the director was
Milos Forman and Jack Nicholson
and Milos Forman had a big disagreement
about Murphy's character
and basically it's very ordered
and then Jack Nicholson arrives
and he turns the place upside down and
Milos Forman wanted it to be more like it was already chaotic
and then he arrives and he sort of draws
the patients together and they become a team
and there was a big falling out over there
and they ended up talking to each other through the cinematographer
so it would have to be kind of
Can you tell
Jack Nicholson to act this way
I mean it just sounds so tense
Danny DeVito as well
I'm a huge fan of Danny DeVito
and I remembered him as Lou
in Taxi
the sort of doer dispatcher
but when he was in Matilda
he actually played Matilda
although he was playing a horrible dad
but he actually became like a really lovely
father figure to her
and then you know in Mum Play with the Cuckoo's Nest
you could argue that he actually
was playing a sort of psychiatric patient
but he was taking care of his mental health
what I'm saying is he's always the opposite
of how he appears and actually
in Twins
if you put him and Arnold Schwarzenegger together he's taller
What a film
he was inducted
into the New Jersey Hall of Fame
in 2010
so I thought I'd look at some other people who are in
New Jersey Hall of Fame
so you've got Buzz Aldrin
Frank Sinatra
Do you have to be from New Jersey can I just ask
Well Thomas Edison is there born in Ohio
Yogi Berra born in Missouri
Harriet Tubman born in Maryland
and Albert Einstein
not even born in America
so we've all got a shot at the New Jersey Hall of Fame
proud son of New Jersey
I think you have to have lived there for a while
because Einstein worked in Princeton of course
that's great
on one from over
it was nearly defeated by the Cold War
it didn't get turned into a film because of the Iron Curtain
you know this
this is cool
so the book came out in the early 60s
and Michael Douglas
no sorry
Kirk Douglas bought the rights
he was in the play
he was in the first play version
based on the play not on the book
which is maybe why Ken Casey hated the film
so Kirk Douglas was the initial Mc Murphy
which is mad it's so strange for him to imagine now
because it's so Jack Nicholson's role
and then he bought the rights
and he wrote to Milos Forman in Czechoslovakia
and said got this great play
got the rights to where I think it should be a film
I'll send you a copy of the book
Milos Forman said great
the book was then seized by Czech Customs
in 1963
and Forman was really annoyed
because Milos Forman never said thank you for the book
rude
it took a decade to sort out
this misunderstanding between them
the film was made in something like 1975
I think
it took a long time
and eventually Kirk Douglas gave the rights to his son Michael
who then said
shall we just try again with this book thing
do we think that the Czech Customs
didn't let the book go initially
because they were worried
that it was seditious
maybe it's not clear
maybe they just wanted to read it
I was wondering if it was like the Rubik's Cube
going in the opposite direction
I have no idea
I don't know what their reasoning was
Kessie was quite notorious
as a LSD proponent
he was quite famous with the counterculture of America
at that point
he had a bus that he used to take everyone on
what a radical free thinker
it was a psychedelic bus
oh my god a multicoloured bus
we have those all the time
London buses are bright red
that's what it represented
they were called the Merry Pranksters
and Tom Warf wrote a whole book about this
it was a non-fiction book about these guys
who just would go around
they used to do things like
they would have people playing flutes on the top of the bus
who would feel buses where people have been playing the flute
were they on LSD?
just a public safety warning
do not take acid on a London bus
it's not a friendly environment to do that
but it is possible it was the counterculture thing
and his name was very much associated with that
it has a good point
it's interesting because he was an author
already at this point Kessie
before he wrote One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest
and he was working on a book called Zoo
and in order to fund it he needed a job
so he worked at a psychiatric ward
in order to fund it
and the book idea came to him when one night he was in there
I think he was cleaning
and he was on peyote
and he was tripping and he saw a full-blown
Chief Broomden there
as a sort of vision
and a psychedelic part of his peyote
is it like a cactus or something?
yeah it's like a cactus which you
it's a drug
I know it is a word and I know it is a drug but I can't tell you the specifics
come on and do the big ol' squass
sorry not to hurt
but he said he saw a full-blown
Native American, he said Indian
Chief Broom, the solution, the whole mothering key to the novel
and that's how he wrote
the novel in the novel
and he's the main like the narrator
sorry and in the movie not
he's not and that's why Kessie
immediately hated it, it wasn't told from the perspective of him
he's a big character in it
but he's not
interestingly the guy who got the role of
Chief Broomden got it because
Michael Douglas was sitting next to a used car dealer
on a plane
and the used car dealer's dad was an acting agent
who had a load of Native American actors on his books
and the thing about Chief
Broomden is he's about eight feet tall
and Michael Douglas got a phone call saying
I just met the tallest Native American guy
you've ever seen
and it was Will, something I can't remember his name
anyway he got the role as Chief
Will Sampson
nice name for someone incredibly tall
and he's got long hair
so this movie was made
in an actual as we've said
hospital
that was originally it was called
the Oregon State Mental Hospital
it's since been renamed as now
Oregon State Hospital
and it's an interesting place
in its own right, it had
a really controversial bit
which was they found 5,000 canisters
of unclaimed human remains in there
and this was a lot of the patients
who had been cremated but no one
had come to collect them
and they put out the list, they found all the names of the people
and a lot of relatives, distant relatives
came and reclaimed them
and there was a documentary called
"Lust" that was made about it
it was pretty mad
but also they had a railroad
underneath the hospital
specifically built one so that they could deliver
items to different bits of the hospital
but also to transport patients
that they didn't want the members of the public
to have to come across if they were visiting the hospital
because they were worried something might go wrong
dangerous, you know, all that sort of stuff
and some of the tunnels possibly are still there
but you just walk them now or use bicycles
it's just Prince Andrew
in there now
and then they had a horrible thing
I found just horrible things about it
unfortunately, 1942
there was a mass poisoning by accident
they were serving scrambled eggs
and 47 people died from this
they used
instead of powdered milk
they used sodium fluoride
which is a poison you would use to kill cockroaches
and that was accidentally added to the scrambled eggs
and 47 died from that
in a kitchen
we had a Christmas party
and instead of putting white sauce
on the Christmas pudding, they put garlic sauce on
which is a very
less problematic version
of what you just said
it's good to know you can relate
I mean, just saying it's easily done
yeah, it's easily done
I want to use cube lube
instead of
instead of what?
it twisted sideways, didn't it?
should we just quickly mention Louise Fletcher
she played Nurse Fletcher
in the film and died last year sadly
but she was
amazing and she
I think she kept herself separate from the rest of the cast
didn't she, for a lot of the filming
so that she could be an icy
authority figure
and did you do that when you were in the play of Lucy?
she was an icy authority figure
in every situation
didn't she also take all the clothes off though
at one point
at the end of filming, wasn't it?
yeah, she'd go hey guys
look at this, all along I was fun
it was her saying
I'm fun, that's right
I think she had her underwear on
I don't think she was fully naked
she wasn't that much fun
I'm fun, but I'm not like fun
there must be a better way
to have cupcakes
to ingratiate yourself with their colleagues
just wait till the end of this podcast
there were two others
Anne Bancroft and Angela Lansbury
were both offered the role but turned it down
because they didn't want to appear so evil on screen
wow
this was in a no-bituary of Louise Fletcher that I read
and also
she was repeatedly turned down from roles
because she was 5 foot 10
and in those days a lot of the leading men
were much shorter than that
and she couldn't play roles opposite people
who were shorter or about the same height
and actually in the nurses' cap
she'll be more than 6 foot
and Jack Nilsson is quite a short guy
but it really works for the authority
for the sort of power struggle happening between them
she's brilliant
on Star Trek
yeah, that's right
she said that she found
her role so disturbing
that she also couldn't watch the film
on Star Trek
yeah
aliens are scary
did she, as Nurse Ratchet
she found it really hard
and she just found it too disturbing
to watch as a role
actually the last time I watched it
which was a couple of years ago, the person I was watching it with
sided with Nurse Ratchet
which didn't make me think, no, hang on
you've taken the wrong message there
and she said, no, no, no, look, the point is
someone's got to keep order
just take a job from where he was running the place
it would be an absolute mayhem
one last thing just about Ken Cassie
the author, because he was a pretty amazing author
his method for a certain period when he was writing
was to be completely
off his head on drugs
and he would write a crazy amount
then in the morning, he'd sober up and become his own editor
so he'd sort of say, okay
let's see what the author's written
and chop out all the junk
and get down to the good meat of it
wow, that's clever
apart from presumably the first draft was absolute junk
shit
just didn't make any sense at all
and then you'd think, hang on
what if the editor was drunk as well
but I'll do different drugs
then I'll make the copy editor will be sober
so that'll be fine
okay, as long as the printer is sober
it'll be fine
okay, that's it
that is all of our facts, thank you so much for listening
if you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course of this podcast
we can be found on our Twitter account
so I'm on @shrybeland
@andrewhunterm
@jamesharkin
that's right, where you can go to our group account
which is @no such thing
or you can email us at podcast@qi.com
also check out our website
no such thing as a fish.com
all of our previous episodes are up there
so you can listen to those
but most importantly of all, if you'd like to see Lucy in her pyjamas
make sure to get out
of your house and into
a comedy club to see "Wake Up Call"
it's the show that she's touring
and she's going to be going around the UK doing that
so go google it, see where she's going
and try and see it
okay, that's it, we're going to be back again next week with another episode
we'll see you then, goodbye
[music]
(upbeat music)