(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name's Dan Schreiber.
It is a three-person podcast this week.
Well, James is away on holiday.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that Essex Police
has a team of six officers trained to grow cannabis.
- What?
- And that's, yeah, it's what you're funding
with your taxpayer money. - My taxes.
Funding the old wacky-backy,
absolutely being grown by the police.
- By the police. - And they don't--
- It's outrageous.
- It's ridiculous, they don't even send you any.
- What's the deal?
- Well, this is an interesting bit of British law anyway,
which means that when the police make a big drug seizure,
then they can work out what the value of the drugs
would have been, and then claim that value
back from the drug dealer's assets as like a disincentive.
So it's like, hey, you've got 100 grand worth of drugs,
I'll take your 100 grand car, or whatever.
But they need to work out the value of the drugs.
The problem is, when they come to a cannabis farm
and it's not fully grown yet,
then they haven't matured yet,
they don't have that concentrated THC
that's what gives cannabis its potency,
then the dealers can claim it was never gonna be
very valuable, or it's actually all moldy,
it wasn't gonna work.
- So in court, the cheeky lawyers will jump in
and say, this was never gonna grow into anything,
so you can't take anything away.
- And it's actually discount November,
so you have to take half off of that.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You've got a voucher, if you've got the cannabis club card.
- Just use the offer code, fish, and check out.
- So they grow it themselves, basically, right?
To prove how much it's gonna be worth.
- Do they finish growing the whole crop?
- Yeah, so at the moment, and this is just Essex Police,
but I think other police forces are experimenting with it,
they bust the farm and they take the plants
and they put them in a special facility they have,
and they nurture, grow, and dry the plants properly,
and they've learned how to make it maximally profitable,
just like the drug dealers would,
assuming they're skilled cannabis growers,
and then they work out how much it's worth,
and then they burn it all.
- Yeah, okay, okay, good.
Not bit by bit, not joint by joint.
- Hey, in a series of small fires, yeah.
- You've got to think they siphon a tiny bit off,
write in to podcast.qi.com, and we won't tell anyone.
- Oh, I'll cross you off.
If you're a bank copper, just look out.
- Don't tell Andy, fine.
- So they've recovered over 300 million pounds worth
of what would be the trade for the cannabis
over the last six years, and so they'll grow it,
and they'll be like, okay, that on the street
is worth 53,000 pounds, that's what you owe now.
- Wow. - Yeah.
- Because street value's a tricky thing, isn't it?
'Cause obviously there's no price list you can look up,
which is why I don't partake,
because it's just too messy.
I want to know, you know,
that you don't have any consumer rights.
- You'll get a text message with a picture of the price list.
- Oh, okay.
Your dealers are going to have laminated menus.
You're going to have-- - I can't.
- And which wines would you recommend with this skunk?
I love, what I love about this fact is that
it's this sort of like lateral thinking way of policing,
which I find so interesting.
There's so many methods that are going on now
that we just don't even necessarily know about.
Like for example, the police have been collaborating
over the last 10 years with the national grid.
So the frequency of the electricity
that is being sent out to every home in England,
Scotland, Wales, it's typically about 50 hertz,
and that's the frequency that is being picked up
in the background of every audio recording.
If you're near a power source,
that's going to be there as a low buzz.
So in this room right now, we have electrical sockets.
Every recording like this recording is picking up.
The Hertz noise, very softly in the background.
Now, it's not always 50 hertz, there's fluctuations.
And that is because of the nature of supply and demand.
Like when people are watching TV
and it gets the ad breaks and lots of kettles go on,
there are small fluctuations that go on on the national grid.
And when that happens, it happens everywhere.
Which means if you're recording all of the national grid,
you're going to have timestamps
on all of these fluctuations.
So often now police, if they're in court
and there's a recording of criminals
that is being used, audio recording,
and they say that never happened
at this place at this time,
they listen to the frequency in the background
and they can match it to the exact time
at the national grid, isn't that insane?
Wow.
Isn't that nuts?
And that's been used in court
and that has busted people
who have claimed that the recordings were manufactured.
And it didn't happen when it was said to happen.
Oh my God, so cover up your plug sockets,
is what you're saying.
Do all your mugging by the trees.
Just be away from, and don't record it.
Don't worry, you're recording it.
Just don't record it.
Oh yeah, good point.
That's pretty good, isn't that stunning?
So that's called electric network frequency
and they've been doing it for 10 years now.
This makes my clever cop workaround thing
look much less impressive.
But this is what I quite like recently.
Did you see the two undercover policemen
who dressed up as Batman and Robin?
Okay, no.
It's not as high-tech, but it worked.
It was Inspector Darren Watson
and Police Constable Abdi Osman
and they were patrolling around London
and they're looking for scammers
who were playing illegal rigged gambling games
of tourists and getting loads of money off them.
But people knew their faces by then.
And so one of them said,
"I just remembered I had Batman and Robin costumes
"in my house, which could come in useful."
And they dressed up and they're so bad.
So there's pictures of them arresting these guys
that they've come up to.
And the guy dressed as Robin
is wearing a beige bucket hat with his Robin.
And the bucket hat is the only thing
that's concealing his face, actually.
So I don't know why he's wearing the full Robin gear.
He's wearing Robin gear.
- 'Cause I think if he was wearing a police officer's
outfit but a beige bucket hat,
the wrongs might still spot that.
- I suppose.
- But that's effective, isn't it?
- It works.
- I think that's really good.
I mean, you don't know how many people
are undercover officers.
Look around you, like all those living statues.
- Come on.
- Yeah.
- You're trying to tell me that not one of them is a fed.
Or who is a fake police officer the other way around?
Someone pretending to be a police officer.
So there was a thing.
Remember the TV show, "The Bill" 2010 that ended?
The police force basically had to buy all of the costumes
off of the bill because they were real police costumes.
- Really?
- Yeah, yeah.
- And burn them.
- Weirdly, they handed them out
and they were being worn by actual policemen.
So they reused the clothing of the bill, the TV show.
- They had so exciting for those clothes
'cause that's like a promotion, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- I do have this, now I've seen it in my head
as quite nice relationship.
And I think no one else sees that.
But basically that very famous day
of the last few years, drill music has become associated
with gang crime.
And the lyrics of drill songs will reference people
who've been murdered on the streets.
And like say, I'm going to get you to a rival gang.
- Would it say that kind of,
even that kind of foul language is you?
- I don't know if I go that far, but.
- Which one of us is going to just buckle
and actually ask what drill is?
- Not me.
- Okay, me, though, continue.
- Hang on, you guys don't listen to drill music
in your spare time.
- Is that like heavy rap, right?
In terms of like lyrically.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I listen to road works,
but that's because I'm really interested in infrastructure.
So, yeah.
- Yeah, that's exactly what I'm talking about.
You go on believing that that's what I'm referencing.
- Oh yeah, Silver Town Tunnel Classics.
Yeah, great.
Oh, Thames Tideway Tunnel.
Yeah, I'm digging it.
- Well, I really like the idea
that you would join the police and misunderstand this,
'cause in Manchester, basically,
the police have been recruited to,
and it's called the Excalibur Task Force,
which is trying to stop knife crime,
recruited to get lots of intelligence from drill music.
So, if you were employed by them,
I guess you would go and eavesdrop on building sites.
What you're meant to do is watch loads of YouTube videos
and then pick up the names that are being dropped
and figure out who's pissed off about what,
'cause it's referencing real things.
- Oh, right, okay, right.
- It's like pre-crime,
but the pre-crimes have maybe been turned into songs.
- Exactly.
And then just, yeah, so you know where to keep a watch out,
but then the drill artists know the police are watching them,
so then they'll reference the police in return.
So as long as they'll be like,
"Oh, you Excalibur naughty boys spying on us."
- Do they put out fake news as well?
Do they say--
- Well, they should, shouldn't they?
- Yeah, we're gonna get Mr. Banana tonight
down by the old co-op.
And actually, there is no Mr. Banana.
- So good.
- I mean, that kind of--
- If you said that just a bit faster,
you would have been a mighty drill artist, I would say.
(laughing)
- Can I tell you an example of maybe
the coolest detective ever?
- Oh, okay.
- Have you ever heard of the Roman emperor Tiberius?
- Yes.
- He once solved a crime by,
he turned detective in ancient Rome.
- Okay.
- I just love this so much.
There was this woman called Apronia, who was murdered.
Well, she fell from a high window and died.
And she was the wife of a praetor,
a very senior official called Sylvanus.
She was the daughter of a really senior general
in ancient Rome called Apronius.
She was Apronia.
So she was a very significant young woman
and very powerfully connected.
And her father thought,
I don't believe she fell out of this window and died.
I think she might've been pushed or thrown out of the window.
And he took the matter to the emperor Tiberius.
And Tiberius said, "I'm on the case."
And then investigated--
- Really?
- Went to the crime scene, questioned people.
This is a TV series begging to be made.
- Yeah.
- Stop pitching TV series.
- He's a cop, but he's also the emperor of Rome.
That's, yeah, I'm in.
- Did he put on a Batman costume to conceal
that he was in fact the emperor?
- I just think this has hit written all over it.
Like he's halfway through fingerprinting somewhere
and someone comes up like,
"Someone's invaded Gaul, what do we do?"
And he's got, "Oh, he's got trouble at home as well."
I just feel like this is a good series.
- How did he solve it?
- Well, I think he just decreed
that the guy was guilty.
(all laughing)
- You're always gonna get your end in every episode.
- How's he gonna solve this one?
He hasn't.
Okay, no worries.
- But anyone else is waiting for a genius reveal there.
- What's one more guy?
- Yeah, exactly.
- Supposedly he did things like this.
Like he crops up in plenty of lot.
Supposedly he investigated things like searches
for sea monsters and things like this.
He was interested in evidence and, you know,
but he decided that on the balance of probabilities,
Sylvanas was guilty, the husband, that is,
and Sylvanas then had someone cut his wrists and he died.
- Nice.
Well done, Type-Rus.
- You're a credit.
- Can I just quickly,
I know we're talking about the police now,
can I tell you one more of these cannabis-related facts?
- Oh, yeah.
- Because the scams are developing
that cannabis growers are using.
I just find some of them unbelievable.
And so last year, this happened,
a guy from North London, he was called Charles Reeves.
He'd been working abroad for a bit
and he'd let his flat out, his family home,
because he was going to be working overseas
for some months, I think.
He got back, he found, in his flat, can you guess?
- A cannabis farm.
- 10 tons of soil that he literally moved in.
10 tons of soil to grow cannabis in,
three feet deep on the floors.
- Wow.
- Imagine getting back to your home
three feet deep in a soil, a flat.
- You'd be so confused.
Is this a weird earthquake or something?
- Yeah, and there was obviously,
there was cannabis growing everywhere
and it had been abandoned
because he'd been coming back to it.
But they'd hacked into the electricity system
to bypass the meter,
'cause that's one of the other ways you catch cannabis farmers
is they use a huge amount of electricity
and so you spot unusual uses of electricity, basically.
- Right, that's so funny.
What does he do with it?
Does he sipen a bit off the top?
- I don't believe so.
- He's obsessed with the siphoning off the top.
- People have got to start siphoning.
I hate waste.
- Yeah.
- What do you want to do after you've smoked a joint?
You want to--
- Report yourself immediately to the police,
it's what I would do.
But what, is there something else you want to do?
- People want to eat a lot of food.
- You want to binge on some cakes.
- Cake, okay.
- And this is just my way of segueing
because have you guys heard of cake finds?
- No.
- This is a thing in the police force and they're huge.
So these are, if you do something wrong in the police
and it's big, like massive corruption
or whatever you get in real trouble,
if you do something wrong and it's small,
you get a cake find.
So examples of something that is a cake find
is spraying a colleague in the face
with incapacitant spray.
- Oh, wow.
- Filing a deceased report
and putting your own name on it by accident.
Someone did that, cake find.
Falling through a roof while searching a suspect's house.
These are all things that have caused cake finds
to be issued.
- I think you should be fine for that.
- No, 'cause that, you could die, right?
- Yeah.
- That one, that feels, yeah.
Oh, how soon is the fine levied on the person?
Is it like while you're waiting for the ambulance
to pick him up?
- It's once they're out of the coma,
I think you come up and gently say.
- Is there a gradation of cake finds?
Is it like we want something with three tiers,
like we want icing in between all the tiers
and we want some ruffles on the top?
- Maybe, but it's all decided on by the cake legislator
who's consulted on social media by any police force.
If you go to the cake legislator on Twitter,
then they'll have a policeman saying,
look, my colleague dropped the police car keys in the drain.
What does he get?
And the cake legislator will say,
that's a Krispy Kreme tray.
- Sorry, this is an account on Twitter,
which is, is it a real police officer behind this?
- Yeah, no one knows who it is,
but I think it was the telegraph
who interviewed them by email.
- But we believe they're a real police officer.
- God, is it just a kid pissing about
and the whole police force is just asking for it?
- But I like that, I like the mystery.
- Can I say one more thing?
Just one last thing before we move on.
This definitely would have resulted
in a lot of cake being brought to the police station.
This happened last year.
The UK's police and crime minister,
Dame Diana Johnson, had her purse stolen.
Her purse was stolen at an annual conference
for senior police officers,
where she was giving a speech on the current epidemic
of theft and shoplifting in the UK.
- Love this stuff.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for fact number two.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that in France,
there are some cars that are so tiny
that you don't even need a driver's license to drive them.
- Is this 'cause we all know you've had trouble
getting a driving license?
- I think that's the answer.
- I honestly, we was trying to look at shortcuts
of how do you get a license quicker.
And is that how you found this?
- Yeah, this is how this came up.
It was in France, you can get it as quick as seven hours.
Now this is not technically a real driving license
because it's not a license at all.
What this is, is if you don't mind not being in a real car,
going at a real speed,
but instead are happy to sit in a two-seater tiny car
going at a really slow pace, then this is what you can do.
- They're called "voitures sans permis", aren't they?
Literally a car without a license.
- Exactly.
- And they're amazing to look at.
They're not tiny, tiny, they're not like clown cars.
- They are slow, slow, 20 miles an hour max.
It's like a run fast, isn't it?
- Yeah, they're also known as "voiturettes",
literally little cars.
But they're everywhere in France,
and people have them and drive them around,
and they change hands as well.
So if someone loses their license,
they will get a VSP as they're called,
"voitures sans permis",
and then as soon as they get their license back,
maybe they'll pass that car on to someone else.
- Well, this is, I mean, this is the amazing thing.
You could lose your license
because you've been drink driving or whatever reason,
and you can literally get out of that car,
go down to a dealership, buy a smaller car,
and be back on the road instantly.
- You're meant to do a few extra layers, aren't you?
But I think in practice, often unofficially,
they're just bored and sold.
- Exactly, like in the back roads of rural France,
no one's really checking that.
- That's true.
Do you know you don't need a driving license
to be an F1 driver?
- Get out.
- Yeah, they changed the rules last year, actually.
- They liberalised that.
That's very against the grain of modern life, isn't it?
Normally, they're tightening things up,
saying, "Well, we've got to stop all this."
- They thought we've gone too far
demanding people have a normal driving license
to drive an F1 car.
- Wasn't there a kid in Belgium who was an F1 driver?
- So Kimmy Antonelli was the person
for whom I think they might have changed the rules
that last year, and he was 17 at the time,
didn't have a driving license,
but they wanted him to replace Lewis Hamilton,
which he now has done,
because Lewis Hamilton left Mercedes to go to Ferrari.
So this guy, this 17-year-old guy,
didn't have a license,
and yeah, you now don't need one.
You need to do other things,
like prove you're amazing at winning driving races
and be very good at karting or motorsports
and things like that.
But he, I mean, he did in fact end up
passing his driving test at the start of this year,
six weeks before competing in his first F1 race.
- Wow. - But isn't that amazing?
- That is amazing.
I suppose they're kind of different skills,
as in you're not as worried about traffic
when you're doing Formula One.
- It's like there's no indicating.
- Is it a three-point turn?
- Rarely roundabouts.
(laughing)
- Has she gone really off course?
- Did they have a thing where they can
just wee any time they like?
- I think you can do that in your own car anyway.
(laughing)
- That's a good point.
What are we thinking?
I do that all the time on my own car.
- Is that part of the test?
Is that why I failed my last test?
(laughing)
- No.
- I don't know if it's a number two.
- Is it?
(laughing)
There's no, surely there's no rule.
Like no one's thought of making that a rule
in the driving test.
- No one's thought of it.
- I don't know why you've said it.
Yeah, where, I think I assumed
that Formula One drivers have to have
a bottle to wean or something.
- I can't remember what they do.
- You think a Formula One driver,
going at the speeds they're going at,
are gonna pull out a Coke bottle
and try pissing to it and mid-drive.
That's what they have to do when they piss stop, don't they?
That's why sometimes they take away the lollipop
and the guy doesn't immediately drive off.
It's 'cause he's just shaking.
- He's just having a, wow.
I never knew how actually skilled these guys were
that they could manage to drive that while pissing.
- A lot of the crashes are because
they put their hand on the wrong thing.
(laughing)
- No, but surely drivers have only mid-race, don't they?
- I think it's a good question
'cause there are quite a long races on my car.
- They're really long and they have to drink,
they have to take in fluids.
- But we don't know the answer.
I think the truth is we don't know the answer here.
- Yeah, I think you would,
yeah, I don't think it'd be illegal.
- I can tell you that if you're--
- Just a very, very few races are lost
because someone's having a shit in the foot well.
I think that's fair.
- Almost never happens.
- There's no Paul O'Rike Cliff or Formula One racing.
- Is the person you were talking about
was his name Max Verstappen?
- No, so no, I was talking about Kimmy Antonelli.
Max Verstappen is the greatest driver ever
of the last 10 years.
- Belgian?
- Yeah, he's won everything.
- I thought he was Dutch.
- Sorry, I've never heard of him before.
He's a bunch of years ago, he was a 17 year old kid.
- Years ago he was 17, yes.
- Racing for the F1 didn't have an actual driver's license
back in Belgium.
So he could race the F1, but when he got back home,
he needed an adult with a license sitting with him
in the car while he was on his learners
in order to drive.
Yeah, so that was his two worlds.
- That's so funny.
- I can imagine it would be very hard
to transfer between the two.
- Yeah, and you do get in trouble
if you drive like you're a Formula One driver
on it through a town.
- Exactly.
- And rally driving, you can be banned.
There was a rally driver called Colin McRae
who was banned in the '90s,
but he actually could get a license.
And if you lose your license here,
you can get a license to compete
in competitive sports racing in another country.
So he got a license in Monaco,
even though he was banned for drink driving or speeding here.
And then he came back,
competed in rally driving races in Wales in 2002
without a license.
But rally driving is half public roads
and half private roads,
even though they shut them all.
On the public roads,
he had to swap with his co-driver
'cause he didn't have a license
to drive on public roads in the UK.
- Do they have to stop and get out?
- I can't find this out.
If anyone watched it,
I can't find out if they stop and they--
- 'Cause that would slow you down enough
to lose the race, I'm sure.
- There's got to be a Batman style chair swap
that can happen internally in the car
that you build in.
- Or one of those driving instructor cars
which have dual controls.
Yeah, but then you're driving on the wrong side of the car.
You're suddenly in an English car in Europe.
- Oh, that doesn't matter.
Like a left and right hand drive.
That's not going to make a big difference.
- If you're a good driver,
you thought you could handle that.
- You'll find all this out
when you have your first lesson down.
Don't worry about it.
You know, Norway,
it is very, very, very electric in its cars, right?
99% of new cars sales are electric.
The reason this has happened is,
in part, thanks to the band A-Ha.
- A-Ha?
- No, A-Ha.
- A-Ha.
(laughing)
- We could dance this dance all day.
I find this absolutely mad.
This is an amazing story, right?
They bought, I think, the first electric car in Norway,
back in the '80s,
when electric cars were really not a thing.
They bought it at a conference in Switzerland.
It was a converted Fiat Panda,
which had been converted to run on batteries.
And two of the guys from A-Ha,
they just thought it was very cool.
They drove it from the conference back to Norway.
And when they got it back,
they found there was no way of legally registering it
because Norway's traffic ministry
or whatever couldn't compute an electric car.
And Norway has loads of toll roads, right?
So they would drive it through the tolls,
that they would be fined
because they hadn't registered their car,
but they couldn't register their car.
So they'd get the fine.
They wouldn't pay the fine.
They kept driving through the toll roads.
Eventually, the car was confiscated.
It went to a police auction
where they bought the car back
because no one else wanted
to convert it to electric Fiat Panda.
They did this for several goes round
on the car being confiscated, fined, re-bought, all of that.
And eventually, the authorities just said,
"Oh, fine, we'll just abolish road tolls
"for electric cars."
And that was a big incentive to lots of people
to go electric.
- No way! - Because we then don't pay
the road tolls, yeah.
- Great.
- That's unbelievable.
- Uh-huh.
- Clever. - Isn't that stunning?
- Clever band.
And was that their plan all along?
- That was the plan all along.
- To solve the climate crisis.
- How many points do you need
on your license to lose your license?
- 12.
- 12, exactly.
Okay, that's the case.
If you get 12 points, you lose your license.
Except there are some people who have more points than that
and still haven't lost their license.
'Cause you can get exemptions if, for example,
you really need to drive to look after someone.
If you're a carer, all that kind of thing.
Or there's another urgent reason why you definitely need,
and you can persuade the authorities
that you need to keep driving.
And I find this stunning.
There are 10,000 people in the UK
who have more than 12 points on their license
and still have their license.
There is one 26-year-old from North Wales
who has, on his license, 229 points.
- No, there's not.
- Yes. - And can still drive.
- And still has a license.
I can't work it out fully.
But for example, if you speed,
let's say a speed limit's been changed from 30 to 20,
which happened in Wales and some bits of Wales recently,
and you drive through several cameras in one day,
you're technically speeding through all of them.
And let's say, 'cause the postal system's a bit slow,
you're doing that for two weeks
before the first thing catches up with you.
- What a terrible thing to do on your doorstep.
- Suddenly. - When you know.
- Right, so like two weeks later, after commuting,
let's say 20 miles each way and going 30 when, you know,
the limit's suddenly 20,
you're doing 150% of the speed limit.
Yeah, so for whatever reason.
- That's a slow post, though,
if he's racked up 220 points before he got the first letter.
- Yeah, but if every camera that you speed through
is three points, I can see it working out.
- I could just have a rack up.
My mum drove with 14 points on her license
for a couple of years.
- Oh, yeah?
- Yep, the way she got away with it
was when she should have lost her license.
And I'm not saying this wasn't justified.
Her lawyer argued that the school run
was a very important time to bond with her children.
- Oh my God. - And she would look
at his house on very important parent-child relationships.
- Are they serious?
- Yes, she was then banned properly two years later
when she was caught again, but yeah.
We got that extra two years of parent-child bonding
and I thought that was very important.
- She gets your names mixed up all the time.
(laughing)
- That's not true, Judith.
- Wow, I'm a huge fan of yours.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that under their main tongue,
lemurs have another tongue.
(laughing)
- Sexy.
- Lemurs have two tongues, yeah, sexy.
- Yeah? - Sexy stuff.
- That's cool.
- And this second tongue is just for guessing.
No, it's sadly not.
It's a cleaning structure.
But it's still a second tongue, it's called a sublingua.
So they have to think of a tooth comb,
which is this structure, I mean,
it's exactly as it sounds.
It's a group of teeth that look like a comb, fine.
And they use that for grooming,
so they run that tooth comb across their fur,
and it helps to pick out all the-
- And this is in the mouth.
- This is in the mouth, yeah.
But this tooth comb, like a normal comb, gets full of air.
- Yep.
- So how do you clean the comb?
You do it with your second tongue.
- It's a sublingua, which is an undertongue,
and it's specifically for cleaning out the tooth comb.
I don't know what they use to clean the tongue.
- Oh, yeah.
Hang on, does this mean that
do they have to get the undertongue up
and over the first tongue to clean it?
- No.
- Or do they swivel around the top tongues?
- No, they just sort of stick out their tongue.
It doesn't look as much like a tongue
as you and I are hoping.
It's a small and slightly harder,
like a more pointy structure.
But it is a sublingua.
- Are there many sublinguas in the natural world?
I couldn't really find many animals
that have more than one tongue.
- I'd be surprised just because lemurs are so weird
because they're on Madagascar,
and Madagascar is evolutionarily really quite separate,
because it's split off from Africa
and then from the Asian subcontinent.
90 million years ago, 180 million years,
it split from Africa.
Then 90 million years later, India left,
and it's just, Madagascar's just left there
hanging out for weird stuff to evolve.
- So that's amazing,
because it's something like 80% of the animals
that live there are just there,
nowhere else in the world, right?
- So lemurs, they all live in Madagascar.
Well, they're all from Madagascar anyway.
- From, yeah.
- I was recently on a visit to an animal park in Kent,
which was not in Madagascar,
but they did have lemurs, and it was amazing.
They're so cool.
There are more than 100 species,
and they're all native to Madagascar,
and I'm sure we'll get into it.
They're really endangered
because of mostly habitat loss
with a bit of climate change
and also human hunting thrown in.
So many of them are really threatened,
but they're absolutely unbelievable creatures.
They're so cool.
- They are, and every single one of them
seems to have their own unique thing
that's interesting about them.
We've spoken about this before on the podcast,
but a few of them are quite solitary animals.
So even within their family,
they will barely see each other.
And the only way they have any kind of communication
with each other is by having a pissing tree.
So they will go down at different times.
It's like if you live in a big house
with a lot of siblings and there's one toilet.
You know, it's like eight, 15 in the morning,
that's my slot.
So they go at different times and they will pee,
and they have a unique fingerprint, as it were,
with their urine, which means that if I was going,
I'd be like, "Handy's been, okay, I can smell."
- And what does that tell you
about what you're gonna do next?
Is that like, oh, he must be near Biogo to see him,
or quite kind? - It means they're okay.
It's like a checking in.
It's just like sending a WhatsApp to say,
"Hey, hope you're well."
It's like, "Oh, I know they're doing okay."
- But they just never wanna pee at the same time together.
- No, they don't wanna see each other.
- They have no interest. - That's very nice.
I personally like to have the bathroom to myself as well.
I'm funny in an old-fashioned like that, but...
- I invite the family.
Lemurs, yeah, lemurs very weird.
Ring-tailed lemurs, the sort of big ones, the famous ones,
and they make their own perfume.
So it's not just about secreting one scent.
They secrete, apparently, a strong but short-lived scent
in their wrists.
So, you know, odor-toilet doesn't last very long.
- Okay.
- So there's like an odor-toilet in their wrists,
and then they secrete a very long-lasting different scent
from their shoulder glands, like an odor-parfum.
And then they get their tails, and they dab their shoulders,
and they dab their wrists to mix the scents together
in what's known as a wrist-to-pit move in zoology.
And then they've got a perfume,
and then they waft it in the air.
- The tail?
- They waft their tail in the air.
Now they've mixed up the perfume.
- And that's their mating ritual,
or is that just general day-to-day?
- It's mating, and it's so clever, because it's telling,
I mean, I can't believe,
sometimes I wonder if I'm making this up,
but it's telling females their genetic makeup,
and the females smell it, and they know
if the male is too similar to them,
'cause obviously you want maximum genetic diversity
for your kids, so you sniff their perfume,
and it's like, "I also use Chanel."
- Get out.
- Then you're going to shag someone else.
- I don't suppose, at any point,
you read about the northern giant mouse lemur.
- No.
- Okay, this is another standout in the lemur tribe.
They've got testicles, which are the largest,
I believe, of any primate relative to body size.
- Okay.
- As a percentage, then,
what would you say your testicles are of your body weight?
- That's a very personal question, isn't it?
- That's so personal.
- He's just had mumps.
(laughing)
- Of my weight, what percentage?
- I'm not asking you to give away your weight.
I'm saying what proportion of your body weight is testicles.
- We're talking 15%.
(laughing)
- Yeah, you do need to.
- Dream on, mate.
For them, it's--
- What were yours to put into context?
- Sorry?
- What are yours?
- I don't, I think for humans, it's kind of 0.2%.
No, it's less than, it's much less than 1%, you know?
But for these guys, it's 5% of their body weight
is testicles.
- Wow.
- It's the equivalent of me,
and here's a fun home maths challenge,
you can work out how much I weigh,
it's the equivalent of me having testicles
that are 3.8 kilos between them.
- Right.
- It's a lot.
- Yeah.
And they were only discovered in 2005, these things.
And often, as they swing through the trees,
they will bump and bruise their testicles.
- Oh, that's a nice one.
- That's right.
- Oh, I've seen, my friend used to have a sausage dog
called Dave, and Dave lived upstairs in a flat,
and he had the longest dangling balls,
and this poor dog, we used to walk behind him on the stairs.
They would wallop the top of each step
as they were going on.
- I just see these dangling bells.
- Does he mind it?
Is it like every time he's going?
- So Blue, who owned Dave, would show people,
because he would say it's okay,
and he would flip Dave upside down and say,
"Look how hardened and leathery they've become,
"they're okay, he doesn't feel it anymore,
"it's like a real hard boxing bag now."
- That's what you want.
- But that's like so I can empathize.
But maybe they've got very leathery hardened testicles.
- Maybe, let's hope.
But it's because they have a system
where everyone has multiple partners,
male and female, and there's no mating season.
So they just need as much sperm as possible.
- They have to produce a lot of sperm and frequently mate,
and that's the way they pass their genes on.
It's a very competitive field.
- See, I guess a few of the lemurs have this kind of problem
where there's just one feature of them
that is just oddly grown, so that it suits the environment.
The I.I., which is probably the most famous
of the lemurs.
- That Norwegian band.
(laughing)
- What?
- Yeah, they're a tribute band, uh-huh, I.I.
They're a nautically themed uh-huh tribute band.
- So the I.I. has a tremendously long finger.
It uses the finger to get into trees and pick out grubs.
So like how hummingbirds will have a long nose
to suck like a straw, the I.I. uses its finger.
Its finger though is so long, it has the same thing
as it's walking along, it has to raise it up.
Otherwise, it basically trips on its own finger
as it's going along, and it's very delicate.
So, you know, it could sprain the finger,
or it could do major damage to it.
- I hadn't thought about that, 'cause it is,
it looks like E.T., the I.I.,
with that ridiculously long middle finger.
So it's about the size of a house cat,
but its middle finger is eight centimeters long.
So imagine a house cat, but with an eight centimeter long
middle finger, and yeah, 'cause you see,
when you see people who've got really good manicures,
I always think, how on earth do you get anything done?
But they, the whole time, must struggle.
But what's amazing about them is that they're only primates
that echolocate, and the way they do it
is by tapping on trees.
I kind of think this is cheating.
Basically, they tap on trees like woodpeckers
until they find a hollow bit, and then the hollow bit
tells them that that's the place where bugs
are probably living in when they eat it.
- Oh, I thought you said cheating?
- Yeah.
- Well, it's easier to tap on a wall
until you find a hollow bit, rather than--
- To frown and to go, mew, do you mean that kind of thing?
- I thought you meant like, just like, anyone, anyone in?
- Like the wolf at the little pig's door.
- Yeah, exactly.
- "Let me in, little bugs."
I just think it's not as impressive as bats
who can navigate all around the world,
and they're just tapping on a tree to find the bug.
- To learn that, though, is pretty,
they're the only ones that do that as well.
- I think that's the thing about lemurs,
is that they're all very well adapted
to the areas they find themselves in,
and they have also filled all the ecological niches
that might be filled by other animals.
So you were saying the I.I. fills a roll
that might be taken by a hummingbird.
Well, you know, so on Madagascar,
every biological function that might fit into a food web,
a lot of them are filled by different species of lemur,
who are really, really well adapted to do that.
But obviously, when the environment changes,
or when the habitat is lost, they really struggle,
because they're adapted for one specific environment.
- Yeah, yeah, it is wild.
Lemurs, what does that mean?
Lemur?
- Lemur.
- I think I know the answer.
It's Latin.
- Oh.
- For ghost.
- Okay, hear me out.
Emperor Tiberius has his toughest case yet.
(laughing)
It's a ghost.
- Something's been tapping my trees.
- So he just hangs a bunch of lemurs.
We move on.
Next episode.
- Yeah, they're called ghosts.
And then Linnaeus is the one who applied it to the lemurs,
because he thought their faces looked so ghostly.
And so they are the ghosts of Madagascar.
- Do you know what else means ghosts in the animal world?
- Weirdly, it's larvae, which I didn't know.
- Lavae.
- So lemurais and larvae are basically the same cluster
of things in Latin.
In ancient Rome, they were the two types
of evil ghosts you'd get.
Isn't that weird?
- Wow.
- Yeah, we do a bit of vilifying humans for hunting them,
or I find in some of the naturalist writing,
there's some vilifying humans for hunting them,
which I think is completely insane,
because 40 to 50% of people in Madagascar are malnourished,
which is pretty extraordinary.
- And also the early humans did not know
they were doing this, I don't know.
- They didn't know that, but yeah, but today,
like they're still hunted and eaten a lot today,
and that's one of the things that's putting them in danger.
And it's because over half of households in Madagascar
have understandably eaten lemur meat in the last year,
'cause that's the meat that's available,
and half of them are malnourished.
But there is this cool project,
which is the bacon bug project,
which is to farm succondry,
which are these still very cute little bugs
that have long, pink, trunk things on their noses
and like little furry backsides,
but they are delicious, tastes like bacon when fried,
and they've started farming them.
And in the pilot community where they've started farming them,
over the last three years,
they've reduced lemur hunting by 50%.
- Wow, that's great. - Which is pretty strong.
- Yeah.
- Can I give you one last lemur?
Yeah.
This is the red-fronted lemur,
and it does something pretty relatable.
It chews up poisonous millipedes.
That's not the relatable bit.
Actually, none of this is relatable.
It rubs the resulting goo on its genitals.
I said it wasn't relatable.
- No, no, keep going, this is my weekend.
- But it's so cool.
It's because they have lots of parasites,
and these millipedes have toxic goo in them,
if you chew them right.
So they chew the millipedes up just enough
that they release this really toxic orange slime,
and then they slather it all over their genitals,
their perianal region, and their tail,
and that kills off the parasites
that have been preying on the lemur,
and then they swallow the millipede whole,
so it's a tasty snack as well as a--
- Interesting. - Lovely.
Perianal. - Perianal.
- Perianal cream.
- They need to work on the markers for that snack, don't they?
- It just sounds like something from Nando's.
- Perianal. - Perianal.
- Well, this is not lemon and herb.
This is spicy hot.
And it also seems to create a little bit of a euphoria
or a narcotic sensation among them.
They've been seen chilling out after they've partaken.
- Really? - Does it?
Well, you put peri-peri up your arse,
then you will sometimes get a bit of a hit.
- Oh, it's hard when you have that flag sticking out, isn't it?
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and despite him being on holiday,
James has still sent in one for us to discuss,
so here it is, James.
- My fact this week is if you built a house
in a certain point of Italy,
you can live in 10 different towns at the same time.
Unfortunately, that point is in the middle of a volcano,
and I am currently at that volcano.
- Thanks, James. - Amazing stuff.
- We've never had an on-location fact.
- No. - James recorded this
at the place that the fact is about.
- Yeah, as he just said. - Yeah, I think he just mentioned.
- As he literally just said, just wanted to hammer it home.
- James is on a mountain now.
- He's not on a mountain, he's on an active volcano.
- No, not right now, 'cause this isn't live.
Sorry to ruin the illusion.
- Anna, where is your tradecraft?
Where is your stage ship?
- Sorry. - Huh?
- This is very cool though, isn't it?
So this is that the Italian province of Catania,
which is where Etna is,
is divided into municipalities,
and there are 10 municipalities,
and they all meet at the top of Etna.
And in fact, I think it's actually split at that peak
into 11 sections, 'cause one of the municipalities,
Bronte, scoops around and nicks two portions of it.
- Yeah, but basically it's 10, basically it's 10.
- No, I know, but Bronte gets two bites of the cherry,
and I think it's worth saying.
- Yeah, Mount Etna, I had never really read anything
about Mount Etna before.
I assumed it was a standard communal garden,
small volcano, it's a big volcano.
- It's a big one, yeah.
- It's two miles high from sea level.
- Yeah, yeah. - That's tall, it is.
- It's the original, it's the OG volcano.
- What, what do you mean?
- Well, Etna is where Vulcan lived,
so the god of the forge and iron smelting
and all that stuff, Vulcan lived in Etna,
and that's why volcanoes are called volcanoes.
It is the volcano. - Oh, my goodness.
And just quickly, we should say
about these 10 points that meet.
I mean, I gotta say, James, I don't understand this fact.
I don't know why you'd want to live
in 10 different towns at the same time.
Who you paying your council tax to?
And so, I mean, I get that these 10 provinces
or principalities or towns, they all meet at the same point,
but Etna is a really confusing place
because it sounds like it's, you know,
it sounds like your child's drawing of a volcano,
which is two slopes on either side
and a crater in the middle.
And Etna isn't really like that.
There are dozens of craters, you know,
and like new ones open up all the time
'cause it keeps on exploding and erupting.
So I find that really interesting.
There are more than 200 craters on Etna.
- God, that's a lot, isn't it?
- I know, it's many, many miles around,
but these places are so cool.
So Randaco was trilingual until the 16th century,
which was Greek in one area, Latin in another,
and Lombard in a third.
- Is that one of the 10 areas?
- That's one of the 10 areas.
There is Bronte, as you mentioned, Anna,
which is, as we've said before,
is where Nelson was created Duke of,
Admiral Horatio Nelson was made Duke of Bronte,
and we think it's where the Bronte sisters, their dad,
he used to be called Bronte, and he renamed himself Bronte,
maybe after Nelson or maybe after this area.
- Which in itself is named after a cyclops, isn't it?
Who lived there?
So the Bronte's dad is named after the cyclops.
- And Charlotte Bronte being named after a cyclops
is just so weird.
- It's very cool, yeah.
But what's amazing is it is an active volcano.
So like James, you know, just very happily
took his family up there on an active volcano.
But it's not like it's just people going up
at their own risk.
The whole area is a tourist destination.
You've got vineyards at the bottom of it,
where if there was an eruption,
absolutely would be taken out by it.
- You gotta pick those grapes fast, haven't you?
It's the lava rolls towards you.
- Just pick the big ones.
Just pick the big ones.
- This is between November and March.
I think those are the months.
There's two ski resorts that open up.
You can go skiing on an active volcano.
It's wild, yeah.
- Sometimes people ski alongside the lava when it's erupted.
- Cool. - That's mad.
- Really? - Yeah.
- Like racing it down.
- Kind of, yeah, yeah.
- And people do, people are quite annoying.
And I think they've introduced legislation now
because they do go much too close.
You're supposed to only be a certain distance
from the lava flow.
And you do have people who kind of cook their sausages
on it and stuff.
- Look, this is Italy.
It's the land of Romans.
People will cook their sausages on lava, you know?
- It's not it.
And it doesn't kill.
It's incredible.
And given how famous it is, and it's the OG,
it's only killed 77 people confirmed in its entire history.
- Confirmed kills, it's not James Bond.
- It's got a tally inside its craters.
- Are you sure about that?
- Yeah, I think so.
There's this insane account from the big 1669 eruption
where reports of it that came out much later
said that 10 to 20,000 people had been killed.
And still you see it on places like history.com,
Sky History Channel, get your facts right,
saying 20,000 people were killed.
- We're turning into a name and shame podcast now.
- I'm afraid so.
Because there are people that you can't accuse someone
of killing 20,000 people.
- Tiberias could, Tiberias could and would.
In fact, he would probably be on the scene of this.
- You're absolutely right.
- Yeah, have them all killed.
- Blame the volcano.
- Can I check on it?
Did you say why it didn't actually kill 20,000 people
in 1669?
- I think it's, I actually don't know,
but I think it's mostly slow moving
and people just leave.
It absolutely destroyed the area.
It ruined it economically for hundreds of years.
And still it's much, much less fertile
because of that eruption.
So they didn't get off scot-free.
- 'Cause I assumed that it always made the land more fertile
'cause it sometimes does with things like,
you know, the reason there are vineyards there
is because the soil is so rich and volcanic.
But I guess sometimes also it's just a dead-end wasteland
that it leaves behind.
So a lot of the time it is good for the--
- It's a fine balance, isn't it?
Do you know you don't want to overdo the lava?
- Exactly.
That one, that explosion, by the way,
is also as far as we can tell,
the first historical recorded attempt
to divert the lava stream as it's coming down.
So there was a town, Katania, one of the 10,
and they dug trenches above the village
in order to divert the stream of lava
as it was coming down.
Yeah, I mean, but as far back as that.
- I think, I believe that their neighboring town
was quite pissed off, wasn't it?
- 'Cause it went into them.
- Well, they re-diverted it.
They put a blockage up and it went back to Katania.
- It's like, it's like that, guys.
- Classic, classic neighbor behavior.
- Yeah.
- It does sound amazing,
'cause to deal with a flow of lava
is pretty challenging, even with modern technology.
And when you're dealing with it with shovels and pickaxes,
dealing, like making a trench like that,
it's just incredibly impressive.
They were wrapped in wet sheepskins
to protect themselves from the heat.
It's just, it's really impressive.
- It's crazy.
- We give the past a hard time sometimes,
but sometimes people are impressive, you know?
- No, they were hardcore.
- Yeah.
- So if you were gonna say how tall is Mount Etna,
the answer changes over the years.
I find that wild with volcanoes,
but basically off the back of certain eruptions.
So if you ask that question in 1865,
it was 170 feet higher than it is now,
because with the eruptions comes collapses internally
and it sort of goes up and down in size.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- But sometimes the act of erupting means
that it leaves lava around the rim,
which hardens and then makes it taller.
- Exactly, right?
- But sometimes it just blows the whole top off
and then gets shorter again.
That'd be cool to solve a crime,
like with your national grid thing, Dan,
of like, but what height was Etna
at the time of the offense?
- Yes.
- As we say, Etna has erupted loads of times,
200 times in the last three and a half thousand years.
- It's good.
- Once every 17 years, it's a really good score.
I think the most recent was 2021 when it threw up
12,000 tons of ash onto a local town.
- And so what happens in that moment?
You're in a surrounding town.
Do you evacuate immediately?
- You get help.
- It's not like Vesuvius back in the day
where you had to guess,
these days, officials are there, aren't they?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
A big government has taken over,
previously charming, like small government,
libertarian pastime of surviving volcanoes.
But the big thing they're scared of,
all the most terrifying prospect
is a flank eruption, apparently.
So if there's a lava fountain
that just goes up from the top,
again, classic volcano,
that is sometimes really bad, obviously.
But the worst thing is where the site just blows off.
And that's when you get a big river of lava
flowing down the side towards your town.
It's impossible.
- Right, okay.
- I found what I think is probably the greatest photo
of Mount Etna erupting, taken by a local, okay?
It was taken in 2013, November 8th,
and it was taken by a man called Luca Parmetana.
Luca Parmetana took it while he was in space
on board the International Space Station.
- Yes.
- Heading over it, it was erupting,
and he managed to get a photo.
And he's from Sicily.
So it's a perfect local to the area,
manages to get a space photo of it.
Luca Parmetana, he was the astronaut
who was almost the first person ever to drown in space.
If you remember, he was out on a spacewalk
and within his helmet, the water supply got loose
and the water started going into his helmet
and droplets went up his nostrils.
That's Luca Parmetana.
- A little bit less time adjusting your lens
and a little bit more time making sure your hood's done up.
Maybe Luca.
- There's always a critic, isn't there?
(laughing)
- That's an episode of Tiberius International Space.
- An astronaut drowns in space.
Tricky.
But did anyone here?
Doesn't matter.
Hang these six people for the crime.
See you next week.
- Of course, we're referring to it as a volcano,
and it's not definitely a volcano.
- Oh no.
- What?
- Are you kidding?
- This is according to a geologist
and he's called Carmelo Ferralito.
- Sounds legit.
- Exactly.
So he lives near it.
And so there's this confusion about it,
'cause it's always burping, very, very gassy.
It belches out more than seven million tons of steam
and CO2 and sulfur every year.
And everyone says that's 'cause of gas bubbles
that are released from the magma.
But Ferralito says that you'd need
about 10 times more lava to be coming out of it
to justify all those gas bubbles.
So where are they coming from?
So some people say,
ah, no, what's happening is a lot of the lava's coming out
and then going back into Etna.
And he says, if it was doing that,
Etna would be inflating like a child's balloon
every time it erupted, the lava's sinking back.
- Which it's not, I presume.
- It is not inflating like a balloon.
- So it's not a volcano?
- It's a hot spring.
And he says that--
- I would be so pissed off with my real estate agent
if I was sold the house next to a hot spring.
Only to find out it was an active volcano.
- You've already drawn up your star plan.
- They photographed it from the other side.
So you didn't see Etna as a background.
It was very clever.
And on the viewing they kept on cunningly misdirecting you.
I say, just come and have a look around here
at the garage.
I would say on that occasion, Dan, caveat emptor.
You know?
- This guy says that it can only be justified
by it being mostly water and CO2 and sulfur,
which makes up 70% of the volume that it's spewing out.
- I'm sorry, I'm sure he's really well qualified,
but it is a volcano, isn't it?
Because I've literally seen photos of it vomiting lava
over a wide area.
- You know, take it up with Carmelo.
- Carmelo, please.
- You've got to make an apias of somehow in this life.
- The town was completely demolished
by a local hot spring.
Was it?
- But everyone's skin was very smooth at the end of it.
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram @Sribeland.
Andy?
- I'm all blue.
Go ahead, Andrew.
- Hi, James.
- It's all about Edda.
- If you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can email a podcast at qi.com
or go to @NoSuchThingIsAfish on Instagram
or @NoSuchThing on Twitter.
- That's right.
And if you want to check out more of our stuff,
go to NoSuchThingIsAfish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
There's bits of merchandise.
There is a portal, the gateway
to our special secret club, Club Fish.
And you can get tickets to our live show.
So we're playing Sheffield in July,
but in June, we're going to be in Belgium.
We are playing the Nerdland Festival.
We've done it twice now.
It's very exciting.
We're going to be back again.
Leven Skira, who runs the whole festival,
has invited us back.
And so if you live near the area,
check out our site for tickets.
We're going to be there June 7th.
It's going to be great.
Come along.
Otherwise, just come back here.
We will have another episode for you
and we will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]