[Music]
Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode of No Such Thing as a Fish!
Before we start, a little bit of news that is very important to Anna and I, and
that is that our new book is finally out in
paperback! Woohoo! I know that might not seem like a big deal to you,
but honestly this is a real chance for us to get more people
reading this book. One very interesting thing to say is
that the book has had a name change. What used to be called
"Everything to Play For" is now called "A Load of Old
Balls - The QI History of Sport" by James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski. A lot of people
have said to us, "Why did you not call it that in the first place?"
I'm not sure if they're being rude, I hope not, because it is a book
full of the most interesting facts and stories about sport you can possibly
imagine. Even if you're not into sport, probably this
summer you will notice that everyone's off watching the Euros, everyone's off
watching the Olympics. Perhaps you don't really have much to say
to those people when it comes up at a dinner party,
we'll read our book and you will be the pinnacle of all sporting knowledge and
all quite interesting sporting knowledge at that. As you imagine from me and Anna,
it's just full of silly stories, fun facts. We spent so much time doing loads of
in-depth research in there that even if you are the kind of person who's
watching every single sporting event this summer, there will be loads of stuff
in there that you didn't know. So if you go to anywhere where you would
normally buy your books, then look for a load of old balls,
the QI History of Sport or search for our names, James Harkin and Anna
Tyshinski and you will find that book. Please do buy it, it would
mean the world to us if you did. Of course we're going on tour, don't forget
that people in Scotland, Wales, England, Ireland, New Zealand, Australia
do get your tickets very very soon. A lot of them are sold out. I know we've got
quite a few tickets left for the Scottish Dates in Edinburgh
and Glasgow and I think quite a few for the show in Cardiff.
So if you're in any of those cities then do get your tickets
but actually you know go to gnosisthingsthefish.com/live and you will
see all of the dates where we're playing and hopefully one of them will be
near you. Okay not much more to say apart from
on with the podcast.
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn. My name is Dan Shriver and
sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray, Anna Tyshinski and James Harkin and
once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four favourite
facts from the last seven days and in no particular order
here we go. Starting with fact number one and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that snooker games on cruise ships
are sometimes played with flat balls.
Are we talking about the balls on the table, are they?
The men playing. Yeah this is this is obvious when you think about it.
Oh it's so obvious. It's so obvious when you think about it. I don't really know
how you could place a nooker on a cruise ship with a ball-shaped ball
actually on a rough cruise ship. We'll get to that in a
sec because you can and there's a pretty awesome way that you do that but
this I got from a book that's written by an Australian comedian called Hung Lee.
It's called The Crappiest Refugee. He tells the story of
from immigrant boat to cruise ship comedian. Anyway he wrote this book and
inside the book he mentions that he's seeing a bunch of guys playing on a
pool table or a snooker table and they are hitting with puck-like objects
because obviously in the rough seas the balls are going to be rolling around
and so there will be cruise ships out there that have these tables on them.
And the idea I think is like you know air hockey, it's those kind of like
puck things, isn't it? Exactly. Now to your point Anna,
a modern day cruise ship does have pool tables or snooker tables,
billiards, but they use gyroscopic technology.
What? So it's amazing. No. It's honestly I've watched videos of it online.
It's so cool because basically while the rest of the ship is moving
the pool table isn't. That's insane. That's the top of the pool table.
That's a high-end cruise ship. It is incredible.
I've read stories of people finding it so fascinating that like staring to fire
sometimes people will just go and sit and watch it as it doesn't sway.
There's even stories of crew members that when they get particularly sick
they'll go and sleep on the pool table because the seasickness is getting to
them. It's not moving so you can have a restful night.
Which begs the question, why isn't every bed on a boat gyroscopic?
Probably price. Cost. Yeah.
How good is the correction mechanism? Like if you have a Titanic situation
how long can you continue with your game of snooker?
So it goes vertical. I see that.
So I met someone who was a dancer on cruise ships for a while.
This sounds like a good anecdote.
She did the musicals because they often have a theatre on board and
sometimes a show and she said that the most difficult one she'd ever done
was Starlight Express where you're on roller skates.
She said in rough weather you would set off across the stage and you didn't
know how soon you were going to arrive because it might be that you caught
the ship moved with you and suddenly you're there for half a second
or you're going against it and you just roll backwards.
So yeah snooker. It's a good sport. Mostly not played at sea.
Largely it's a land-based game isn't it? A land lovers game.
I did watch a tiktok yesterday just coincidentally of people playing on the
beach that looked really cool. Snooker.
It was pool actually but they kind of dug holes
for the pockets and then we just hit the bowls. Oh so they played on actual sand?
Yeah yeah. There's no facts to this but it did look pretty cool.
I'm amazed that snooker in any form has made it to tiktok because snooker is
famously quite a long game to watch. Tiktok is not a long format.
Andy honestly if you could see my tiktok it's just snooker, golf, cricket.
It's the dullest tiktok because he just suggests things that you like doesn't
it and it just works out what you like. I reckon if you were on tiktok which I
bet you're not but you would just get moss video after moss video.
Yeah that sounds very economic. It's amazing how it works.
But it is very slow isn't it? It's all rather it takes a long time.
You play lots of frames in the course of a match and it's interesting
because for anyone who doesn't follow snooker only one person is playing at a time.
That's weird. Will you play a frame right?
Well no. You play until you mess up and then the other guy gets to have a go.
But whoever your opponent is they have to stay in their chair.
They just stay in their chair watching you and you could be playing for hours if
you don't make a mistake. It's just psychological torture.
Are there any other games which are like that where I know tennis you're only
playing when your opponent is not playing. But usually it's quite soon before you're playing again
isn't it? I don't know actually but that is one of the main things about snooker is the
psychological angle of it. Although Ronnie O'Sullivan said he likes it
obviously because he's always going to be um Ronnie O'Sullivan.
Who's Ronnie O'Sullivan? I think he's a famous snooker player.
I would say Ronnie O'Sullivan and Don Bradman are the only two people.
I don't know what James thinks about this but who have excelled everyone else so
much in their sport that it's like whoa. So Ronnie O'Sullivan is the best snooker player ever.
And he hates the fact that it's so slow for instance because he's this
mercurial crazy character with an amazing history and he likes snooker to be super fast.
So I think he's got pretty much all the records for fastest break.
But yeah he's amazing and he's got such an interesting history.
His dad went to prison for murder when I think Ronnie was about 16.
Yeah he was a millionaire though so even though his dad went to prison for murder
he was from a very affluent background because his dad ran a lingerie shop or something like that.
I believe he may have called them lingerie shops in the newspaper ads when I think they were sex
shops. I mean potatoes and potatoes. You say potato I say vibrator.
Yeah so I think some of the other snooker players who came from
less affluent backgrounds kind of point to that and say you know we're working class but Ronnie
actually was quite rich when he was growing up. Interesting because he was heavily embedded
probably in that gang culture a bit. It was one of the Cray Brothers, the third Cray Brothers
driver who he murdered in a nightclub I think. Oh sorry the third Cray Brother.
Yeah I didn't know there was a third Cray but you hear about the Cray Twins.
I know he was very much the... It's like the third Chuckle Brother.
Yeah he and the third Cray Brother must have given each other a ride look sometimes across
the Eastern clubs. They both have that picture of Bramwell Bronte in their house.
Imagine a joke that has to craze the Chuckle Brothers and Bramwell Bronte in it.
We've got the Jonas Brothers as well. They've got the extra brother who's called Bonus Jonas
who is the one that just isn't in the band and does his own thing all the time.
Bonus Jonas. Snooker's got fairly sort of poshish sort of foundations doesn't it because it was
invented by supposedly, this is the big story, by Neville Chamberlain, not the Prime Minister,
but apparently a cousin. The reports are a bit dodgy but apparently he was in India in the 1800s
and he basically incorporated two existing games. There was one called Blackpool and there was
another which was called Pyramid and so one was played entirely with red balls and that was in
a pyramid shape so he goes 'I will love the pyramid shape' and then the other one had all the other
colour balls in it and he brought that over, smashed them into one big game with the pyramid
and then just kept yelling 'Snooker' at people as they were playing and by the end of the game
he'd called everyone 'Snooker' and so it stuck. Why did you call someone what did it mean? Did it
mean dickhead? I think it was a sort of term for an idiot, someone who was incompetent at whatever
task they were doing, a rookie. I see. It is weird though because he said he invented it in 1875.
He only said that in 1938 which is a substantial amount of time later that's what.
63 years later. 63 years later and he was an army officer already when he invented this
so he must be knocking on but the claim was accepted and I think it's sort of widely accepted
that that's where it comes from but also the other weird thing about Snooker, that name thing you
were saying Dan, is so if you snooker someone is it that I need to hit a red next but I'm behind the
yellow or whatever? Precisely. So that is unusual as well because it's a move in the game where you've
messed things up for someone else. Yeah. Which is, is that in Croquet like that?
It's a bit like that, you croquet and croquet someone. I think there is a connection between
Croquet and Snooker really. I think Snooker kind of grew out of Croquet like games. Yeah. And that's
why the that's why the table's green because it was like originally played on grass. Right.
The bays. The bays, yeah. Which has, has to have, do you know the difference between the bays
in Snooker and pool? I got a bit too into table makeup. Is it the nap? Yeah. I'm just going to
almost disqualify you from answering this question, James. I thought disclosure, I am very much into
snooze. Yeah. You're not allowed to answer any more quiz questions in this section. What's the
nap? So the nap is the way that the kind of hairs on the substance that the table is made of bend.
So basically in Snooker you have to have a nap and that means that it's a little bit like if you
imagine a velvet surface. In fact, if you look at those cushions over there. I'm having a nap
listening to this. Andy, this is fascinating stuff. Sorry, sorry. Go, go, go. Okay. You look
at those cushions over there. They're velvety. You stroke them one way and they look smooth. You
stroke them the other way and they look rough. Oh, okay. Yeah. And that's like a snooker table.
It has to have that effect and it really affects how the ball travels because as you can imagine
if the little hairs, fibres are standing up a certain way and depending on the angle at which
is hitting them, you really have to work with the nap. So if you aim for a shot in the middle
pocket, you have to aim slightly outside the pocket because the nap will make it naturally
bend towards the pocket. That's so interesting. So part of the gameplay is literally getting
your face close to the table and seeing how the nap is looking. No, it's always the same.
Yeah, it's always the same. Well, I actually read in a really furious blog that a man who
has heard of people who install their own tables putting the nap on back to front,
which is obviously an absolute disaster. Doesn't it just go the other way then? Or do you mean
upside down? No, I think he means it goes the other way. So it will go slow and it should go
fast. But you would be used to it. Like you would be very much used to it being one way.
Yeah, I've got a question. Are you allowed to comb the table before the get before your pot?
So before every frame, before every frame? Yeah, probably someone will come on and give the table
a quick comb. And also you are allowed to kind of flatten it. If you see a bit come up a little bit,
you are allowed to flatten it. Mid game. Yeah, mid shot, like not mid shot, but just before your
shot you're allowed to. Like a bit of the rugs rocked up. Yeah, you're just smoothing it out.
Mid shot would be like curling, wouldn't it? Yeah. That would be a game. So actually,
Snooker isn't played on a Snooker table. He's played on a Billiards table.
What? Because Billiards was invented before it and then Snooker was played on the Billiards
table and we still call it a Billiards table rather than a Snooker table officially.
So what gets played on a Snooker table? There's no such thing. There's no such thing as a
Snooker table. Well, it's just another word for a Billiards table, I guess. Right. That's great.
And what's Billiards? So Billiards is a game where you have three balls only on the table
and the rules say you get a point by either potting one of the balls
or by hitting one ball onto the other. Right. And then if you get a point, you get another go.
And you get another go and another go and another go until you stop getting points and then your
opponent comes on the table. Okay. So a bit like Snooker, your opponent sat there for quite a long
time just watching you play. Yeah. But in 1907, a new technique was discovered where, you know,
the pockets in Snooker where the ball goes into. Yeah. What this guy called Walter Lovejoy
managed to do was to get two balls stuck in the pocket. And so he could just tap these two balls
every time and they would always hit the cushion or hit each other. Oh, wow. And he could do that
again and again and again and again. And there was a game a bit later between Tom Chapman and Tom
Reese where Tom Reese managed to score 499,135 points by using this technique over 85 hours of 49
minutes. Wow. Oh, what a tedious person. Is it illegal now as a technique or? It's illegal as
a technique. And also like this record was never in the record books because all of the fans went
home, the referee went home and even his opponent went home. Wow. That's so good. I worry about
this guy's home life. It sounds like you didn't have much to go back to. I think it's great.
I didn't know the pocket Billiards was real. I thought it was a vulgar euphemism all my life and
actually it's a proper game. And what is it? It's just a smaller version of Billiards. Oh.
Or it's slang for messing around with yourself. I would stop playing pocket Billiards is what
you'd say to someone. Yeah. If they were masturbating in public. Yeah, right. Okay.
Just don't get them mixed up. That's how I say it. I thought I was getting away with it all this
time. I think I'm playing Billiards. Oh, dear.
Okay. It is time for fact number two and that is Anna. My fact this week is that one of the major
battles in the Cold War was to see who was better at squashing metal. Was it to get rid of the iron
curtain? Brilliant. Oh, my God. Lovely. This is the heavy press program, which sounds kind of like
a raunchy sexual program, but it wasn't. You get turned on by very different things to me, Anna.
No, I'm with Anna. It's coming around to my place for heavy press. I don't know. No,
I'm just going to say I'll do some pocket Billiards.
The heavy press program was launched by the US in response to the fact that the USSR in the
1950s, it believed, had got very good at squashing metal. And the good thing about squashing metal
is that it was a much better way of making airplanes. So it meant that you could put a huge
ingot into a machine and squash it into the shape you wanted for a big bit of wing or something.
And that would mean that it would be a lighter aircraft, that if you just nailed together lots
and lots of little bits, which is how you were making planes. I've seen images of this thing and
it's so impressive. It's a ginormous structure, the one in America that we're going to get onto,
which is a very famous one called the 50. You say it's very famous, but I think it's only known
because there's this one guy who's just written a series of amazing articles about it. It's one in
the Atlantic and other in the New York Times, who's just really into it. And that was in Cleveland,
Ohio. It still exists today. So I think that they made 10 machines in the US and they made four
pressing machines, whether you squash metal and six extrusion machines, where you squeeze it like
toothpaste. Wow. And I think eight of them are still going today. It's nuts. At the moment,
every single US military aircraft contains bits made by this 50 machine. By this one machine,
yeah. I mean, these are built in the 50s. They're still going today. The engineers of the 50 think
it's going to be going in total for about 110 years. Can I add squires called the 50? I think it
was because it would exert 50,000 tons of compressive force, which is the equivalent of being able
to lift up 500 blue whales. Wow. And it's massive. It's 87 meters high, so it looks huge. It's so
cool. Honestly, this really awoke something in me, this machine. This really brought my inner
Clarkson to the fore. It's just really the most amazing machine in the world. It's just so cool.
It is. I think it's the size and the majesty of them. And there are lots of them. So there are
those in the US. And then, well, as I said, in the Cold War, the reason it became a fight was
because Germany was actually the best at making them. So Germany had all this technology in the
Second World War for pressing metal that no one else had. And as part of the agreement after the
Second World War, we divided things up. And the USSR got their biggest heavy press. So they got the
30,000 pressing machine, 30,000 tonne pressing machine, whereas I think America only got about
10,000 tonne one. And I ended up reading all of these CIA documents, spying on how Russia was
using them and saying, what are they doing with this thing? They're incredibly boring, aside from
the word secret at the top. But yeah, they had to transport it back in four specially made train
carriages from Germany to the USSR. But yeah, America were like, oh no, they've got this now.
We'll have to make a big one. But it's all and it's partly it all partly relates back to the
First World War, right? So in the First World War, again, lots of post-war reparations, Treaty
of Versailles took a lot of things away from Germany. And there was a shortage of various
key materials for the German economy and for the armaments and all this. So they developed the
technique of press forging, which is where you press down on the diet just because it's more
efficient. And the one thing they'd been allowed to keep or one of the things they were allowed
to keep was their magnesium, right? The Allied power said we're not interested in your magnesium,
so you can have that. But the problem is that the previous method of forging things is basically
big hammer, smashes down, smashes up. Does it not explode if you hit magnesium?
If you put it, I think you put water on it, isn't it? But it does crack. It doesn't forge well
under the current forging conditions. And that's why Germany invented the technique of press forging
because they were working with the materials they had and also they had to be as efficient as possible.
So once again, shot yourselves in the foot with Versailles, didn't you, allies? But then actually,
in playing the long game, you got the technology back. So sort of a nice score draw for the Treaty
of Versailles. I think that's right, yes. I think the Treaty of Versailles is a foe of the podcast
because we give it a right kick in this show, don't we? True. The highest pressure ever achieved
is 770 gigapascals, which is more than twice the pressure in the inner core of the earth.
Okay. Yeah. What did we do it for? Well, it's just scientists in it.
They wanted to see what happens if you squash osmium really, really, really a lot.
And who's he? Richard Osmium. He's the Roman Richard Osmium.
It's the chemical element osmium and they really, really squashed it with all this pressure
and they found out that it does not change its crystal structure. Wow. Well, sometimes you're
going to go through that experiment to find out. It's as important to find out nothing as to find
out something. I wonder if it's especially tough osmium or is it especially dense? Okay, that's
cool. Surely. Otherwise, it seems silly if it's just. We'll start off by squashing a flump and see.
The biggest press now, I don't think get much press. It's in Vienna and it's made by an Italian
company who would have thought. Not me. I don't see any reason why the Italians would be good at
pressing. I suppose most industrial things like that are Russia and China, sometimes America,
and they do have the other big ones. But an Italian company have made it in Vienna and it's
called Tyson. Is it to make lasagna sheets? It is. They can make a meatball that is as dense as the sun.
And yeah, that exerts 100,000 tons of force, which is the equivalent of being able to lift up
100 Eiffel towers. Wow. Which is impressive. That is amazing. It is amazing. Is it used for the
same just making like sheets of metal for airplanes and stuff? Yeah, they do lots of stuff with like
oil and gas industry and wind turbines and nuclear and things you would imagine need loads of metal.
I was reading into humans crushing metal because that is, yeah, it's a thing. And it turns out
there's a lot of Guinness World Records for people who have done that in the past. So one of the
records I found was the most cans crushed with shoulder blades in one minute. Okay, so back
shoulder blades. Yeah, so you're sort of moving them together to create the crush. What do you
reckon in one minute? Well, okay, question. Yeah, is someone putting the cans in your shoulders after
you have to place them there yourself because that feels tough. So the records held by Fabrizio
Malito and another one for the Italians. Exactly. Yeah, crushing metal. It's just their forte.
And it was his brother, Frank, who would replenish the can in between the shoulder blades to be
crushed. 84. You're not far off. 68. 68. That's 10 more than someone managed to do it with their
head in one minute. So 58 achieved with their head. That's interesting, because if you ever
crush a can these days, it's really easy. It's very, and that used to be seen as like a pop-eye
or a manly roar kind of thing. It turns out that that did used to be that because cans were 40%
stronger back in the day in terms of the material and the strength and the thickness. This really
shows how old I am. But I remember when aluminium cans came in. And that they were much, much easier
to crush. It used to be that you could buy cans of pop and some of them would be aluminium and some
of them wouldn't be. Right. And the aluminium ones were way easier to crush. Were the previous ones
steel? I suppose they must have been. I'm not really sure, but I just remember Blue Peter had a thing
where everyone had to crush cans and send them for recycling in their 80s. Nice. And so we were
all into can-crushing back then. Before Tamagotchi, so that was what it was, wasn't it?
Can I read an introductory sentence to you? Yeah, sure. Is it from your new novel? It's
from a piece about another kind of forging, which is a thing called drop forging. And it's in
kadahi. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm pronouncing it wrong, Milwaukee. It begins like this, tucked away
in a kadahi warehouse. Something big has been pounding away since 1959. But this is a huge
great hammer. And this is the kind of thing where you just have a giant hammer to smash down on your
metal and get it into the shape you want. Right. And this one, it weighs one million pounds. And
it goes five floors above ground and also five floors below ground. So it's called a counterblow
hammer, which is meaning that you are whacking above sides. Oh, cool. Yeah, on the below at the
same time. Like a crocodile. It's so cool. It's just like flames and fire inside it. And it's just
smashing away at these objects. Yeah, yeah. Basically, that hammer, that gigantic hammer has
been in operation so long that you've got multiple generations of the same family who've been operating
that hammer. It's been going since 1959. So there was a guy interviewed for this article saying,
"Yeah, my grandfather worked on this hammer." I know. What would happen if you put just a person
in there? Oh, they'd be in trouble. They'd be in such trouble. They'd get just squished. But I'd
love to see what that like doesn't look like. Oh, no. It's not like when you frame Roger Rabbit.
You would not love to see that, I can say. You've become a perfect two-dimensional human.
It's a shame that's not on the list of options for like, you know, you've got classic burial,
cremation, obliterated pine, bash. The flattening. Can I tell you one thing about a cool destruction
engine from the 19th century? But this is great. This is, there was a great new scientist piece
about it, and it was called the Victorian Monster Destruction Engine. Not its official name.
But it was made by an engineer called David Cacoldi, who's Scottish. And he was the chief engineer
behind this machine, which existed to smash metal, to tear it, to twist it, to crunch it,
to bop it, you know, to do all of this. And it was because before his work, you could not test
the components of a bridge, say. So, you know, you just have to trust that the bridge you were
building was strong enough. Yeah, you've got some rivets, you need to know whether they're
going to hold if you put a load of pressure on it. How do you do that? Exactly that. And he built
this gigantic machine. It was 116 tons, which at the time was huge. And its entire job was to
tear things apart and it could measure the tonnage at which or the force that needed to be applied
before things broke. And this changed engineering because, you know, there was the Tay Bridge disaster
in Scotland. And they went down to the riverbed after this awful disaster had happened. Lots of
people died and it was a really tragic event. A really bad bit of poetry was written about it
famously by McGonagall. That's right. The Tay Bridge disaster disaster. And they went down and
they got some of the lugs that had attached the bridge rods to the supporting columns. And it was
found that they broke at 20 tons of pressure rather than the 60 that they should have done.
So that, you know, ruined the career of the engineer who had said, no, these are fine and
these are strong enough to support the bridge. So I feel like they should have used buttresses
as many a wise man confesses. It's a line from the poem. Is that genuinely a line from the poem?
That's good memory. All the poems you could have memorised.
But yeah, he made loads of bridges as well, didn't he? And they were shipped all over the
world because he was the first person ever to test these things. So the Sydney Harbour Bridge
was all tested, but in his one machine, at the various bridges in London, Hammersmith Bridge.
The family thing, like Generations, the Festival of Britain in the 1950s,
some of their structures were tested by his grandson. And I love this. It was certainly in
2014 there in a museum, I think it's in Southwark. And there used to be on the top floor a museum of
fractures, which was a collection of broken pieces of metal. But tragically during the Second World
War, a bomb fell on it. And all the pieces came back together. It was like, what am I supposed to
do with these? Find a pristine spitfire. Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is James.
Okay, my fact this week is that in 18th century America, you could tell a merchant from a lawyer
just by looking at their handwriting. So the lawyer would put little hearts over the eyes.
This is insane. The merchant was dollar sign. Yeah, it's crazy, isn't it? I just didn't know this.
It was in an article in The Atlantic, I read it, an article by Rachel Gutman Way. And she wrote that
there were different font types for different jobs. The handwriting of the merchants apparently
was supposed to reflect the efficiency and speed with which they worked. And lawyers would have
different scripts, aristocrats would have different scripts. And what would happen is,
it was, you would be in your guild or whatever, or you would be taught to do this job. And when
you were being taught it, they would teach you particular ways of writing. So as the years went
on, it would kind of get more and more enforced, this style of writing. Because doctors are the only
people today who have reputedly got a particular kind of handwriting, which is terrible. Yeah.
I don't think that's a font, is it? Barscript. I feel like journalists. I've seen journalists
doing fast writing. Short-hand. Yeah, short-hand, which feels very them. And that's a sort of
separate language to notate. But this is, you're talking about the English language written. Yeah,
so you would write the same words, but you'd be able to read them and you'd be able to say,
this person is a merchant, this person is a... Could you masquerade? If I was a merchant,
I'm wanting to pretend to be a lawyer. I suppose you could, but it's a bit like forging signatures.
Is I guess it's difficult, right? Because your signature, you do naturally without thinking,
whereas to forge it, it takes time and sometimes it's not very easy to do it exactly.
And you probably need other proofs that you're a lawyer. It probably wasn't that people would
hire a lawyer by saying, can you just write your name on a bit of paper? Looks like a lawyer's
handwriting to me. I'm in a Mrs Doubtfire scenario in my head. I'm the aristocrat and the nanny in
this, what I'm trying to do. Right. Well, one thing that might work there is that men and women had
different handwriting as well. That's so interesting. So men had more masculine handwriting
they were taught, or muscular handwriting. What does that even mean? Well, muscular handwriting,
according to someone called Carla Peterson, who is a professor of English at the University of
Maryland, they used more pressure on the pen. Just holes in the paper. 50,000 tons of force
on every letter. And women had more like an italic, cursive handwriting. What I thought was so
interesting about this fact is that I hadn't really considered until now the fact that we were all
taught a font. So basically the handwriting equivalent of font is script. And we were all
taught a script. And of course we were. And when you see writing from the olden days, like if I
look at collections of letters written by, like my grandparents had old letters written by their
grandparents from the 19th century, the handwriting is so different. And that's because official
styles changed. And so there was this thing called Spensarian scripts in the 1900s, which
President Garfield called the pride of our country. America's done so much stuff. That's
the biggest one. Is that the biggie? That's the biggest Spensarian. The guy who came up with this,
Platt Rogers Spencer, said he was inspired by pebbles on a beach and is sloping. It's got to
be at an exact angle of 52 degrees, sloping forwards and slightly rounded. Okay. And it
was that like basically Americans would write that like that. Yes. Because I know like, for
instance, my wife writes in a Russian font, which is different than an English font for sure.
Yes. Yeah, yeah. There's lots of chat about the different ways that different European
countries still write. So Platt Rogers Spencer spent so much time trying to get it to be the
standard writing style they were teaching in schools and so on. To the point where it feels
very missionary when he died, his sons then took textbooks of it and they sort of went out and
campaigned for it to be changed. Have you tried this font style? Even go to schools and hand them
and this sort of people start reading the books. No, don't read the words. Just look at the letters.
Yeah, exactly. So weird. Yeah. And then it did get taken over by a thing called Zana Bloso method,
and then that eventually got taken over by another. So we've got generational changes within how we
write. You can tell when texts come from right because you can, there's a thing called paleography.
Is that it? It's old writing and it's the study of old writing. Your course is in it because if
you look at a text from hundreds of years ago, even if it's in English, it's going to be really
hard to decipher. It's hard to recognize time travel, as I suppose, is that they have different
handwriting. Yes, it'd be so obvious if someone suddenly started writing in that gothic script
that as you say, you can barely read it. It looks so different, doesn't it? So hard to distinguish.
I was thinking people from the future might write, like for instance, in block capitals or something.
Hello. Oh, wow. Busted. So Spenserian just very quickly, before we wrap up on that,
that did go out and these other fonts took over, but it did embed itself in society,
and we see it virtually every day. So it was a win for Plat and Rogers.
It's understandable. Oh, yeah, it should be. Think of...
Ingredients lists on packets of food. Oh, they're always in handwriting, aren't they?
Okay, okay, okay. I'm just warming up. Something that's in handwriting. Yeah.
Okay, there was something on a banknote, like the code promise to pay the bearer.
No, it's a logo. It's a logo in handwriting. It is a great call.
It is a food and drink product and it is not anything that you've said. It's a drink.
Coke. Coke. Coke-a-cola. Coke-a-cola.
That lovely... You're right. That rounded cursive. That rounded cursive. I forgot what the question was.
So it was basically phased out Spenserian, but he managed to have an impact saying,
and Ford Cars is also the way that Ford has written is based on Spenserian.
That is great. What a legacy. That's a great legacy.
That's kind of time travel, but the normal way around, you know, like a survivor.
It's like those animals that you find, which, oh, we thought you went extinct 130 million years ago,
but here you are swimming around. Like a sealant camp of handwriting.
Yeah, it's a Coca-Cola camp.
Could you set me up for that, Joe? No.
I felt like it. I felt like I walked straight into a fur trap there.
We should probably say that handwriting evolves for practical reasons.
So it was all about these people saying, this is a quicker way to write,
and this is an easier way to write. This is an easier way to teach.
Or the reason that Gothic, which was invented in the 12th century-ish,
that was quite squashed up, and it was because there was parchment shortages,
and so you could fit much more on the page.
So it's all practicalities, which feels relevant when it's enforced today,
because people say, isn't it sad that no one learns proper cursive anymore,
and there are a number of American states that enforce it legally,
and there isn't really evidence that there's particularly a purpose.
Cursive has just joined up handwriting, right?
Yes. I can tell you a lot about someone, their handwriting.
Well, no, it can't really. But they can tell you how drunk they are.
Well, that's good. Of all these kind of graphology things,
which is you're supposed to be able to tell people's personality or whatever,
from their handwriting, most of it does seem to be mediopie,
but definitely for sure, the height of ascending letters,
height of descending letters, spacing between words, tremors,
bit of sick on the page, the height of the upper and lower case letters,
all changes depending on how much alcohol you've had.
That's good. That's very good.
That's got to be one of the most pointless studies ever done
writing declines with alcoholism.
Did you find the B.I.G.?
Notorious.
Notorious British Institute of Graphologists.
They're real.
They're pretty hardcore on there.
They are. That's really funny.
And their claim, and I think I'm not, I don't think it's backed up by solid evidence,
is that it's better than therapy, because actually with therapy,
you can only know what the client has told you.
Okay.
Whereas with graphology, you just look at the writing and you say,
"Well, that's disgusting. I can't believe you had that dream."
Or whatever, you know.
You're not a merchant, you're a lawyer.
We did a debunk of graphology on QI once and got very angry emails.
And letters didn't we?
And written.
Yeah, we got one letter from a graphologist saying that
some of the evidence is, if you get a pen and put it in your mouth
and try and write something on a piece of paper,
you'll use the same movements as if you were to do it with your hand.
Like so Andy would write it with his same sort of spidery hand writing
with his mouth as he would with his hand.
And that's evidence that it's coming directly from your brain
as opposed to being something in your hands or whatever, hasn't it?
Inherent in yourself the shape of your letters.
Is that claim true in either sense?
Like, is it true that there's any correlation to your mouth and hand
or that you could draw that conclusion?
All I'm giving is both sides of the story, like I'm on the BBC.
Good on you, mate.
But no, that's what they claim.
But of course, you know, I think these days we think that it's nonsense.
Unless you're listening to this podcast on BBC Sounds,
in which case, the jury's out.
I do wonder if we were able to bring back certain people from history
and just say, "Oh, I love your book," called that.
And they go, "That's not what that's called."
And it's because they're bad handwriting.
And there's a few cases where people claim this is a thing.
So apparently, Beethoven's piece for Elise.
Apparently, that's not the title.
What? It's called "Furry Leaves."
Apparently, it's for Therese.
No.
Yeah, it's Therese or Therese.
It's either that.
No way.
Yeah, but his handwriting is so dodgy that it just, it's,
well, we'll just go with Elise.
Are all the notes different as well?
That's so funny.
Well, if you're worried about bad handwriting,
which I always was in exams,
because I have quite a legible small handwriting,
and I always thought they're never going to read this gold.
I happened to be on the OCR,
which is one of the famous exam boards.
OCR exam board page, FAQ's page,
and they clarified examiners are experienced at reading
a wide range of handwriting.
And if one examiner can't read it,
it gets passed to another one, and so on.
Wow.
So I think if your handwriting's bad,
it just goes, gets passed to 20 different examiners.
That's so funny.
I knew where it would end up.
Where?
At the very end, there is a lady on the Isle of Man
who runs a firm called Transcription Services,
and almost no one does what she does.
She is just phenomenal at reading handwriting.
Really?
Specifically old writing.
Like the work by William Wiseworth,
the Brontes, John Dunn,
it's all passed to her in the Isle of Man,
and she's just amazing at it.
And that is paleography.
Yeah, one person who was really difficult to decipher
was Catherine Mansfield.
I was reading about the New Zealand short story person.
Her handwriting was so bad that when she died
and left 53 handwritten notebooks,
it took decades to decipher them.
Wow.
And the person who was doing it
once spent an entire week trying to decipher a single word.
So the way you write can kind of show where you're from.
I thought this was really interesting.
So the way you write a T, for instance,
which bit do you write first?
The width.
I don't even know.
I go the top.
I don't do the cross, basically.
You don't cross your T's?
No, I do that.
Oh, right.
OK, yeah.
You don't cross your T's, imagine that.
I'll see you in the burrow.
See you later.
So presumably, oh, Dan actually,
what do you write first?
Well.
You write all in capital, so it's kind of relevant.
Who writes the cross bit first?
Well.
What's the cross bit, do you mean?
The cross your T's, the bit that goes across.
I do.
You write the cross first?
OK, here, if I was writing that in lower case, I go.
Guys, do you know what's so fascinating about this?
Right.
Do it again.
What does Dan, what can Dan also write
that none of the rest of us can?
Brilliant books about weird beliefs.
All right, I don't think you can write this.
What can he speak and where was he brought up?
Oh.
Mandarin.
Australian slang.
Australian slang, yes.
It's Mandarin writers, writing lots of little short dashes.
And so it makes sense for them to write, when they learn English,
they tend to write the cross of the T first.
Because it's lots of little figures.
How interesting.
Whereas we would always write,
and there's lots of little stuff like that.
In Koreans, they write nine backwards.
Do you write your lines backwards, Dan?
No, I, well, I don't know.
You might tell me now that I do.
I write it like that.
No, that's like every other night tonight.
That's normal.
I wonder if I've got a cultural mesh going on,
because I will start that like that,
but then I'll do that to end it.
Wow.
Yeah.
Gosh.
Interesting, because I've never seen you write
in lower case before.
Yeah, I didn't know you could.
I am Casemore.
Wow.
I'm so sorry.
What do you think, the school I went to taught?
Well, let's not go there.
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that the sun is surrounded by a layer of moss.
Hey.
Is it?
Space moss.
I mean, it obviously isn't happening.
So this is a thing which industry experts, sun experts.
Industry?
Astronomers.
Big science brains.
They call moss.
I love this.
So this is in the sun's corona.
We're outside the sun itself,
and there are areas where the sun's magnetic field bursts out,
and gas flow, the gas that makes up the sun,
flows around these huge loops,
and then spears back down into the thing.
It's all really, it's awesome.
Anyway, and the moss is these sort of lacy patterns
around the corona and around those corona loops,
around the feet of them, if you like.
It's a term that NASA uses,
and lots of other astronomers use it.
Of all the sexy words you can use for lace-like structures,
to use moss, I feel like.
Yeah, what would you have gone for?
Well, lace.
Lingerie.
Lace.
Negligent.
That's quite a cool, yeah.
Yeah.
I do think of it when I was reading about it.
Yeah, you've described it pretty well there.
It looks like a rainbow,
if you look at these coronal loops,
and the moss is sort of at the bottom of them,
so it's like the gold at the bottom of a rainbow.
Very nice.
Lovely.
What's really weird is I read that this is the case.
There may be other reasons for it,
but the reason those loops come out, at all,
is largely to do with the rotation of the sun.
Right.
Yeah, so you've got basically,
it takes 25 days at the equator to rotate,
but at the poles, it takes 33 days.
So you have this bit overtaking the outside,
and it sort of snaps, and it creates these big loops.
It's sort of running past itself in a,
it's the weird rotation,
the double rotation of the planet.
Yeah, because it's all gas,
so it kind of feels natural, right,
that it would rotate at different levels.
But yeah, that chaos that's generated.
Yeah.
But it seems like we still don't know a lot about the sun,
which is quite exciting,
and they're still discovering stuff about it, aren't they?
I mean, this is all linked to that eternal mystery,
that why is the sun's atmosphere,
the bit just above the surface of the sun, so hot?
So I think we might have mentioned before.
So hotter than the surface or even the core?
It's the hottest there, is that what you're saying?
It's hotter than the surface, definitely.
I'm not sure if it's hotter than the very core.
Yeah, it's so much hotter.
So the surface of the sun is about 6,000 degrees Celsius.
I think we can all agree, very hot.
Yeah.
Well.
But the corona, the atmosphere, is 1 million and 6,000 degrees Celsius.
It's a million degrees hotter.
And do you know that even NASA says that there are flares,
which they think might be between 10 and 40 million degrees Celsius?
Wow, 40 million degrees.
So the sun's rotating, producing magnetic field, right?
Yeah.
And then these lines of magnetic force, they get tangled,
and they build up pressure and they snap.
And most of the energy goes outwards,
but some of it goes back inwards, into the sun.
And the particles in the sun's lower atmosphere,
they build up this pressure wave and it penetrates deep into the sun.
And it becomes a sunquake.
Just everything starts sounding like a cool title for a metal album.
Sunquake.
I've been going around singing Sunquake.
There's a group called the Solar Wind Sherpas,
who also sound pretty cool and metal.
So they're a band.
No, they're a group of scientists.
But just anything sun related, like coronal moss, or whatever.
That one doesn't quite work, I gotta say.
Okay.
It's not metal, I don't think that one.
No matter how much you put that voice on.
Okay, okay, okay.
Quite similarly, you get solar rain,
which is actually lumps of plasma
that fall down from these coronal rainbow loops.
And when they splash into the chromosphere,
the bit in between the atmosphere and the surface,
they make a big splash and they send up loads more plasma.
We are chromosphere.
This is our album, Solar Rain.
What about that?
Yeah, it's good.
We are the Solar Hedge Row.
What about that?
It's a bit rural, bit rustic, but nice.
Yeah, maybe like the muscles.
I mean, it's not that interesting.
It's just like filaments of mossy-like stuff from the sun
that create loops that go in like a line, like a hedge row might.
But it is an official term apparently.
That's cool.
Do you know who is the first person to take a photo
of these filaments on the sun?
Oh, it's almost.
Is someone we've heard of?
Oh, no.
That narrows it down.
You might have come across her name.
Annie Monda, she was called.
And she was married to Edward Walter Monda.
And she was probably the last of what was called the lady computers.
So towards the end of the 19th century,
this is obviously there were computers like for the space race and stuff like that.
But these were women who would do the calculations
when astronomers would come up with loads of data.
They would give them to the women
and the women would work them out and work out what was going on.
Amazing, right.
And also the Monda minimum is named after her,
which you might have heard,
which was a time in the 17th century when all sunspots disappeared.
Was that when it got very cold?
Yeah, the little ice age.
Exactly.
Was that the Monda minimum?
But it's named after her.
And her husband as well, yeah.
Yeah, that's awesome.
But so she's coming through data to find all this stuff.
So amateur photographer on the side.
She was also a photographer on the side, yeah, yeah.
And she and her husband did photographs of the sun.
And we're doing it all the time, basically.
Whenever there was a clear day,
they would go out and photograph the sun.
How do you photograph the sun with that?
You need a special filter to stop hurting your eyes, obviously.
There are lots of different ways of doing it.
And like, for instance, you can do it with a pinhole camera.
I think you could largely just point it in the direction
and press snap, can't you?
I think if you do that and you send the photos to Boots,
you're going to get a sticker on them.
In Britain, you can photograph the sun pretty easily.
The sort of vague, white dot on screen by Cloud.
That reminds me of the warnings
when there are eclipses about what they can do to your eyes.
I've been sort of mad to very extents over the years,
but I was reading about the eclipse in Melbourne in 1976.
I think it was.
When there was this doctor who sort of spread panic
around the city saying there could be an epidemic
of thousands of kids being completely blind.
Because all you need to do is look at that
for a couple of seconds and you can go blind.
Now, it's not, it is exaggerated, the scare mongering,
but it scared Melbourne into watching it from inside.
So 2 million of the 2.5 million people there
watched it on their tellies.
It is a problem, I think, with the eclipse,
which is it is bad for you.
And you can't say it's not bad for you,
but pretty much all the time everyone says
it's worse for you than it actually is.
I think that's the problem.
So when Trump famously looked at the sun,
that wouldn't have done.
It depends how long you do it for.
I think you can tell if it's doing damage.
Bloody left-wing media spinning these stories to make him--
We're not saying.
We're not saying you should go and look at the sun.
That's the problem is you can't say that.
You can't say go out and look at the sun.
Brilliant idea.
I would say give Trump a break.
That's what I'm saying.
But yeah, it's like you've looked at the sun
every now and then by accident for a second or so, right?
And you're like, oh, that hurt my eyes,
but you didn't go blind at any stage.
No, because it's the eclipse.
Isn't there a risk that people are going to try
and look for longer than the tiny, tiny glimpse
that might not do you any harm?
But it feels so much common sense
that the only people who do get in trouble,
and I think this was true in Britain when we had it in 1999,
are people who had lots of drugs.
So there was a girl who'd taken lots of speed
who stared at the eclipse for half an hour,
and she did have some permanent eye damage.
Isaac Newton, that was a story that he stared at the sun
in that sense impartially blinded.
That was deliberately for an experiment
to see what would happen if he stared at the sun.
So you can be very, very clever and also very, very stupid.
So I think it's just good to wear on the side of court
and say never look anywhere.
I think that's fair.
But I think one bit of good news is if you do go blind
for staring at the sun for too long,
is that there's a new invention
that allows blind people to enjoy eclipses.
Really?
Yeah, it's called light sound,
and it sort of measures and translates the sky's brightness
and turns it into music.
And so you can like put your headphones in,
and apparently it gives a really good impression
of the change of the sun
and the change of the brightness that's happening.
That was so cool.
Yeah.
That's amazing.
That's awesome.
Milosevic scared his people underground.
Slobodan.
Or Aston Villa striker Savo Milosevic.
I think it was Slobodan though,
of course I haven't written it down,
but whichever one was ruling Serbia in the 90s.
Yeah, he said that it would make you urinate really frequently
and get heart palpitations.
And everyone literally went inside,
pulled all their curtains down.
They were calling help lines saying,
is it safe to watch it on telly?
Wow.
That like no one went outside public transport all stopped.
So the whole of the rest of Europe flooded outside
to watch the eclipse,
and all of Serbia retreated underground and indoors.
Did he have motives that we know now?
Well, was that a weird, the urination thing?
Well, what was where did that come from?
No, I agree, because no, I don't know.
I don't know why.
There was actually a paper saying what were his motivations,
and I couldn't download the full thing.
So we'll never know.
No one, apart from people who could afford 24.99,
will ever know.
But I can tell you that animal rights activists
sent sunglasses to the chimps in the zoo.
So scared, were they?
Gosh.
Golly.
I think one of the coolest things I read
as part of this research is that you got the sun,
we're just staring at it,
we're trying to work out what's going on with it.
We got nothing to compare it to.
But we got nothing to compare it to.
And that's not true anymore.
And it's not been true for a while,
because the Kepler Space Telescope,
back when it was operating,
monitored 150,000 stars in the Milky Way,
and they found 369 suns that are incredibly similar to ours.
And so now we can look at other case studies,
as it were, and go,
"Oh, this is interesting.
That sun is very active at the moment."
And it wasn't 10, 11 years ago.
That must mean that it's running in phases.
So we can learn via these suns
that are billions of miles away about our own sun.
Yeah, because there are a lot of scientists
that look at our sun as a curiosity
compared to other suns,
in that they say it's spectacularly boring
in comparison to all the other suns
that we're seeing in the universe.
And they partially wonder if that's why we're here at all.
Yeah, that must be right.
Because if it starts spitting out stuff at us
every two or three years, we're going to die.
Exactly. So our sun is just not that active,
and that's been incredible for us.
It has. And I think actually with the election coming up,
sometimes you want a boring center of your universe,
don't you? Because it can be relied upon.
To not destroy you.
That is a political broadcast for Kier Starman.
Don't know what you're talking about.
We actually had someone write in who was a space weather forecaster.
Oh, I know.
To the fish inbox.
Really?
This is cool.
He's called Gavin Medley.
What? Dark with no weather again.
He works at the LASP,
which is the Laboratory for Atmospheric and Space Physics
at the University of Colorado.
And he was writing about the, you know,
if the sun emits a giant electromagnetic storm,
we won't get warning before it hits us.
But there are space weather instruments
that sit on spacecraft at Lagrange points,
and they just sit there in gravitational equilibrium.
And one of their goals is to collect data
to predict and warn about solar storms and flares,
which can take down our electrical structure.
And that's how we knew like a few weeks ago
when they had that big solar storm
that people in London couldn't see,
but everyone else in the country could see.
Yeah. The aurora.
The aurora. We know about that because of those things.
Yeah.
By the way, we're in the most exciting year for the sun
in 11 years, loads of sunspots.
Oh.
'Cause the sun switches poles every 11 years.
Yeah.
So the most boring year was 2019,
and that was like hardly any sunspots,
because the poles were just like perfectly aligned
north and south, and now we're in the most feisty year,
which I think might be why they've discovered this thing
that your main fact was about,
is because it feels like as a scientist,
it's the most thrilling time to look at the sun,
'cause so much mad shit's going on there.
So if one of these big coronal mass ejections hits us,
we're kind of buggered a little bit, right?
All of our electronics are going to fry,
and until they fix it, it's going to be pretty tough.
And we knew that this big one was coming a few weeks ago,
and I was in Wales in the middle of nowhere,
and so I got a load of cash out of the cash machine
just in case, all of the cash machines got back genuinely.
Just subtle prepper.
I love it.
Your cash is no good in the aftertimes.
But it'll get me home.
Like all I had to do was get home.
I have an electric car, right?
So if I'm stuck in Wales with an electric car,
and all the electrics are fried,
I am kind of buggered.
I'm not necessarily buggered if you have to stay in Wales, James.
Come on.
Good people of Wales.
Great place to be stranded for a while.
No, it's a great place to be,
but it's not ideal for the rest of my family if I'm in Wales.
James's electric tin opener is in London.
That's what he's getting back to.
Oh, he brings that with him.
I keep that in a lead-lined case,
a case of a coronal mass ejection.
But there's a theory, right?
So we could fire out a big loop of wire into space.
So the entire earth is covered by one wire.
Okay.
And then when the coronal mass ejection comes in,
which is basically charged particles,
then the wire can kind of ground it,
and it won't fry all of our electricity.
That's interesting.
It's a really good idea.
No one's really taken the idea seriously,
but they reckon that the loop would cost about $100 billion to make.
But if we did get hit by one of those coronal mass ejections,
which will happen sometime,
the cost will be way more than that.
Yeah.
Wait, wait, it'll be in the trillions.
It will fuck up our economy for years.
Actually, $100 billion.
Sounds a lot, but actually, you know,
a lot of things, when you read about it in the paper,
it's like $600 billion.
Oh, okay, yeah.
We clubbed together.
Yeah.
We didn't deal with that.
Well, how much did you get out of the cash point the other day?
There's a big queue behind James.
His limit's 200 a time.
It's only $20 million a time there.
Let me take out.
[Music]
Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @tribeland, on Instagram, Andy.
@andrewhunterm.
On X.
James?
No such thing as James Harkin on the TikToks.
And Anna?
You can get in touch with all of us
by going to @knowsuchthing on Twitter/X,
or going to @knowsuchthing as a fish on Instagram,
or you can email podcast at qi.com.
Yep, or you can go to our website.
Knowsuchthingasafish.com.
All of the previous episodes are up there.
There's a link to the portal, to the gateway of Club Fish,
our secret private members club.
And there are also links to our upcoming tour.
Thundernerds.
We're heading around Europe.
We're going to Ireland.
We're going to Australia.
We are going to New Zealand.
There are all the links up there.
We put on a couple of extra shows.
One in Sydney, one in London.
If you missed out on tickets for those, do check it out.
It's all up there.
Otherwise, just come back here next week.
We'll have another episode waiting for you.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)