(upbeat music)
- Hey, Clubfish members.
Welcome to your bonus compilation episode of Fish.
This is Biggie.
This week we got 40 plus minutes
and it has everything from, oh, I don't know,
weird lullabies to the evils of TV,
there's books on dogs, Captain Hook's Time at Eaton,
and there's Weird Yellow Blood,
Neighborly Psychic Readings.
It's got a ton, and a lot on Ethel Smythe.
You remember Ethel Smythe?
She's the brilliant conductor-composer.
She features heavily in this week's episode.
So enjoy all the bits that didn't make it
into the main show, and I'll see you on the other side.
- Emilyne Pankhurst had practised her stone throwing
in Ethel Smythe's garden.
- Had she? - Yeah.
- Supposedly, close by on Hook Heath,
which was just outside her house.
- Okay, yeah.
- Next to the golf course, by the way.
- Ooh.
- In case you're wondering.
- Are you going for power, or are you going for precision?
- I think a bit of both, if you're trying to smash a window.
- Yeah.
- At no point throwing it really hard,
nowhere near the window, but equally,
there's no point throwing it really softly at the window.
- You're right.
- Golfy, you really do have to nail the two, don't you?
- That's throwing.
- It's a lot of practise.
- Yeah, it's throwing.
- It didn't pay off.
Mrs. Pankhurst must have muffed up the shot
at 10 Downing Street.
- Oh, no.
- Yeah, very sad.
- Where'd it go?
- 11 Downing Street.
- Is it still there?
Are you wondering?
- No, churches aren't cross-shaped, are they?
- Usually, yeah.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- What, the layout, the ground layout was a cross?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- You see, you know that you get the main doors at the back,
and you go all the way up to the front with the altar,
and there's the head bit,
and then you've got the two arms across.
- Never noticed, never had an aerial view of why my church.
- You can see them from above.
- The nave and the tranceps.
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- And some churches have, you know, the head,
'cause it represents the cross that Christ on the cross,
by the blood.
- I made that connection.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Like knots and crosses, you see.
- The top bit is called the chancel, I think,
and some churches, they're not in a completely straight cross.
They've got the chancel, the head bit,
is tilted to one side,
and that represents the drooping head of Christ on the cross.
It's called a nodding chancel.
That's what it's called.
- I do not know that.
It's Christ being a bit hungry, getting a bit sad.
- A bit dying, I think.
- Yeah, I think it's not a snacky thing, it's a...
- Oh, can someone get me a snack?
- I'm feeling so hangry.
(laughing)
- Do you remember on this show, I'm sure I said this,
that I once went to an art gallery,
and there was, I thought someone had collapsed on the floor,
and I went and told the people and said,
"Oh, someone's collapsed,"
and it turned out to be an artwork, and it was a doll.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I think, very recently, I read in the news
that that happened again.
But this actually got in the news,
because the person saw the doll on the floor,
and called 999, and said that someone's collapsed
in the art gallery.
And then only when the ambulance came,
they realized that it was a doll.
- It's dangerous, 'cause is this a cry wolf situation,
where we're all gonna stop reporting crimes,
calling ambulances, trying to resuscitate people,
'cause we'll assume everything.
- Everything is an art, isn't it?
- Someone's broken into my house.
I don't think you need to send anyone round.
(laughing)
- It's so hard to know.
- They look like Tracy M in this.
- I feel very moved.
So I think actually on balance, it's fine.
- I wonder if in early days,
if people hadn't ever gone to an art gallery before,
they would see like the Mona Lisa and be like,
"Someone help her, she's stuck in a frame, in a wall."
(laughing)
- Yeah.
Have you guys heard of the interesting medieval job?
The Moss Reeve.
- Oh, Jesus.
(laughing)
I remember reading the Moss Reeves tale by Chaucer.
- And this is someone who adjudicated,
who was allowed to dig up Pete from Moslands.
- Is that right?
- Yeah, 'cause you can't just have it free
for a lot of the Moslands.
- So if I wanted to, if I wanted some Pete,
would I go there and then the Moss Wrangler would say,
"You're allowed this area or you're not allowed to,"
or whatever, or Moss Reeve.
Come on, not a Moss Wrangler.
That's very low in the hierarchy.
- Could you believe I'd already forgotten
what the word was at that stage?
- But here's the weird thing.
The two stars of the film, "The Matrix,"
are Keanu Reeves and Karrion Moss.
- That is amazing.
- Wow.
- Does that prove that we are living, in fact,
in a matrix designed by a Moss enthusiast?
- Yeah.
- She, you know, in her time,
she was obviously held back, to a certain extent,
as a woman composer.
She didn't get, you know,
when people were describing her music,
they would always give her criticisms.
You would never give a mail.
So, you know, it sounds too feminine
or she's trying to sound too masculine
or, you know, they would always bring her, you know,
sex into it.
So, it's quite nice that in 2018, she won a Grammy.
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- Yeah, she won a Grammy. - So cool.
- And it was for an opera that she wrote in 1930,
called "The Prison."
So, it was big news for old Ethel.
- It's quite nice for her,
'cause she said that the thing she was most afraid about
when she died was that she'd be forgotten.
Her music would be forgotten, sorry.
So, she was afraid of her music dying with her.
And it did, it died dead flat on its back
for like 50 years.
And now, there's this real revival.
She opened "Gleinborn" in 2020.
It's like the biggest opera festival in the UK, really.
She's played at the proms.
So, she is finally coming back.
But, yeah, they sound really interesting, her operas.
- Yeah, she's got cool song titles as well.
I mean, most of them are quite normal,
but there's one I came across
called "Variations on an Original Theme,
Brackets of an Exceedingly Dismal'd Nature."
Close brackets in D-flat major.
- Nice. - Nice little, yeah.
- That's cool.
- Actually, on "Deafness and Conductors,"
there was a thing of Beethoven
where he used to insist on conducting his own pieces
even after he went deaf.
And so, at the premiere of his ninth symphony,
he said, "I have to conduct this.
You know, it's my pièce de résistance."
And there was another conductor, Michael Umlauf,
who was on the sidelines,
who secretly told the orchestra, "Look at me.
Don't look at him." - Oh, really?
- Yeah.
And when the piece came to an end,
Beethoven didn't know it had finished,
and he kept on conducting.
And one of the musicians had to get up
and sort of nudge him.
- I remember seeing a movie where that was a scene
where he just continues on, and they've all stopped,
and he just, he's so into it, and he's waving about.
- I remember that.
There's a massive dog in it, wasn't there?
- Yes, that's right, yeah.
There's a Kenyan lullaby which has hyenas in it.
- Yeah. - And it goes,
"Well, I'll just say it.
Rock, rock, rock.
The baby who cries will be eaten by a hyena."
(laughing)
- No.
- Yeah.
And I only mentioned that, in particular,
because we talked about that.
Napoleon Bonaparte one, a few weeks ago now,
and it was he'll eat you, eat you.
- He'll eat your bones or something.
- Yeah, every, snap, snap, snap, yeah, yeah.
And I only mentioned that because we got an email
off the back of that, you know,
this Bonaparte era nursery rhyme, from a bloke,
and I didn't write his name down, I'm afraid,
but he wrote in saying,
"I have sung that lullaby to my own daughters
about Bonaparte, except in his yard,
it goes even further back than Bonaparte,
and it was originally about Oliver Cromwell, this rhyme.
- Wow.
- Oliver Cromwell was the bogeyman.
So there are a couple of children,
adults now, I believe, in Britain today,
who grew up with Cromwell era threats.
- So good.
- Yeah.
- With royalist parents, I assume.
(laughing)
- Yeah, you can say, yeah, yeah.
- Napoleon Bonaparte's better, he'll eat your Bonaparte.
- I know, it's great.
Never thought of this name like that.
- Or your Bonaparte, yeah, even scarier.
- Yeah.
- If you search who invented the ejector seat,
then you usually find someone called Everard Calthrop,
who seems to have had a patent in 1916,
and he was friends with Charles Rolls of Rolls Royce fame,
and Charles Rolls died in a biplane crash,
and he thought, well, I'm gonna invent
something that would have saved him.
Interesting thing about him is he also invented
the first modern parachute, and he patented that,
and he offered it to the British Air Force,
and the British Air Force decided
they didn't want parachutes in their planes
because they said it might impair
the fighting spirit of pilots.
So basically, if your pilots had a way to escape,
they might not fight hard enough.
- I can understand that, if I were a pilot,
I'd pretty much 10 seconds after taking off,
I'd be out of there.
- It's astonishing though, isn't it?
And this was in World War I,
and the British refused to let any of their pilots,
all the pilots wanted them,
the British refused to let their pilots have parachutes,
all the other countries had them,
because this guy, Cal Throp,
he thought, what the fuck is going on?
So he published his parachute,
he put it in the newspaper, he said,
look, this thing, it's amazing.
Everyone needs to have it.
The British said, no, our guys are not having it,
and every other country in the world said,
well, of course we're gonna have it.
- And who ended up winning that war, James?
Good old British and allied Italian as well,
yeah, various teams of French.
- It's so amazing, isn't it?
- But they would just do that.
- Yeah, that's incredible.
- So speaking of Dickens,
in the Tale of Two Cities, he writes,
"There was a king with a large jaw
"and a queen with a plain face on the throne of England."
And he's talking about Queen Charlotte there.
- Rude.
- Yeah, she's written about a lot at the time
as having a plain face.
But she was a patron of the arts,
she commissioned Mozart maybe for some stuff.
- Yeah, that's right, yeah.
- And there is a theory, which I must say
is not agreed by all historians,
that she might have had some African heritage
and might have been the first not completely white
member of the English royal family.
The idea is that the Portuguese side of her family
might have been related to someone called
Margarita de Castro, a Susa who was Moorish.
And the idea was that she might have had
some black heritage, but like I say,
not all historians do agree with that.
- Yeah, she had 15 kids.
- 15, yeah. - 15, yeah.
- That's a lot.
- Do they all make it?
No, they can't have fucking things.
- 13 made it past childhood.
So yeah, she lost two sadly quite early.
But 13, yeah.
- That's an unbelievable strike rate for those days.
Well done. - Yeah.
- Taking flights must have been tougher.
- Oh my god.
(all laughing)
Australia, no way.
- What kind of pram do you get?
Do you have to get one of those prams
with like 15 seats side by side?
- Oh yeah.
- I feel like they do especially make
those really long prams just for them.
Maybe I'm wrong, but I feel like I've seen them as like.
- I see them.
The ones I see, 'cause there's a nanny
who works across the road from where we live
and she looks after kids.
She always acquires a new kid.
And whenever she does this,
kind of just like a new feature on the pram.
It just gets higher and higher.
It's like babies sitting.
Yeah, it's just, it looks like a transformer
that's just got stuck.
- Is she building this herself?
- It feels like it.
But no, I think it's just sort of like extra extensions
to each bit of the pram.
- That's very cool.
- There's a big movement these days, obviously,
for trying to stop people
from smoking almost altogether.
New Zealand, for example,
if you were born in 2009,
you were no longer allowed to buy cigarettes.
It is extinct to anyone who is 2009 born and onwards.
- How old are they now, 14?
- Yeah, so, shouldn't be smoking at that age anyway.
- No, exactly.
- It is amazing though, isn't it?
That like, for us, it was always like
you had to look older to get cigarettes.
But for them, when they'll have to look younger,
when they're 30 years old,
they'll be like, are you 30 or 40?
And if you're 30...
- They will have to look older still.
- Oh yeah.
- They won't, no one will be going into shops like,
I'm five, I promise.
(laughing)
- But they have to keep looking older.
It's not like they can breathe a sigh of relief
when they hit sort of 20 and thing.
It's even at 50, they'll try to look 60.
Oh my God, what a pain.
- Yeah, you're gonna want to look older.
- Oh God, yeah, load of 50 or what.
And around, like they've got fake bus passes
and all of this and that.
- Yeah.
- Didn't put my foundation on today.
(laughing)
- I have a question for the three of you.
- Oh yeah.
- Have you ever watched something,
a series, for example, in a, like,
you've watched ahead without your partner knowing about it,
despite the fact you're meant to be watching it together?
- Yes.
- No.
- Okay, two yeses, one no.
There was a device developed in 2022
that was supposedly gonna deal with this thing.
- Oh yeah.
- This is a slightly weird thing.
It's a slightly PR thing.
- Is it called a divorce?
(laughing)
- So they claimed they'd done a survey
and that all of the people who had cheated
on their partners in television terms,
12% would-
- I was just glancing.
(laughing)
- 12% would re-watch later on with their partner
and just not admit.
I just sort of like go along.
Oh my God.
- That's what I do.
- So anyway, last year,
all right, I don't know why it was them who did it.
Cornetto, yes, that Cornetto, there's anyone Cornetto.
They claimed they had invented this device,
these rings that partners would wear
and that would then make you unable to watch on
in the series without your partner, if you saw what I mean.
So you have to be together with your partner,
both wearing your special Cornetto rings.
- But they obviously hadn't invented that, have they?
'Cause that's not the business they're in
and why would they do it if it were?
- I watched a very slick PR video,
which was certainly claimed to have made,
not released on April the 1st, I did check.
- Does anyone else feel like an ice cream?
I don't know why.
(laughing)
- So why did they, have you dug into
whether they've gotten any trouble
with the advertising standards agency
for making these wild claims?
- I haven't, I...
- Well, okay, someone dig into that please.
(laughing)
Actually, on TV based hoaxes,
in 1962 there was a hoax in Sweden
that tens of thousands of Swedish people fell for
and Swedish people today still remember
their parents doing this.
And this was the era of color TV
coming to various different countries.
Sweden didn't have color TV yet,
didn't get it until 1970, I don't think.
But in 1962, Sweden had one TV channel
and the only TV channel broadcasts an information video
presenting a technical expert called Kjell Stenson,
who said, "You can actually make your television broadcast
in color by stretching nylon stockings over the screen."
And it bends, 'cause it bends the wavelengths of light
in certain ways, which then reflect
what the original colors were going to be on the screen.
- That's very clever.
- So it is really very clever.
And thousands and thousands of people tried to do this
and people still remember their parents
were getting these nylon stockings
just ruining them, stretching them over the TV.
- That's so funny, that's a great,
it's a great April though, 'cause it's kind of,
it's certainly believable enough to me.
- It's low stakes, the worst is someone's going to
spoil a few pairs of ties.
- Your wife's pissed off when she comes,
she's got one pair of nylon stockings,
she was saving them for the ball.
- I always thought that John Logie Baird
was the inventor of the TV and there's probably
a lot of controversy about who the true inventor is,
but one person who does have a big claim to it
is a guy who was called Philo Farnsworth.
And he supposedly, according to the story, invented it.
He was like a farmer boy and he invented it
when he was 14 years old.
- Television. - What?
- On a farm.
He was a teenager, he invented it,
and then it got taken over with other people's inventions.
It became very bitter about it.
He had a few successes with it,
but like Silicon Valley people these days
who don't let their kids go and use computers
and stuff like that, he was exactly the same.
He didn't want his kids watching TV
'cause he just thought it was a terrible cursed item
that ruined you of any intellect or anything like that.
So his children have said things that you know,
he said there's nothing on it that's worthwhile
and we're not gonna watch it in this household,
I don't want you on as part of your intellectual diet.
And so he hated his invention throughout his whole life.
- He thought it was gonna like save the world
and stop all wars and stuff.
His idea was that it would be a place
where people could learn things
and learn things about different countries
and learn things about the world
and people would be so educated
they wouldn't want to have wars anymore.
- Right.
- At least he was disproven quickly, right?
'Cause presumably this was 1920s, 30s time.
So, you know, he didn't have to wait 50 years
before the next big war.
- No, yeah.
But he did, so he did hate it and hate it and hate it.
And then he turned around,
just a miracle day changed his mind.
- I can guess.
- Yeah.
- It's the first episode of Breaking Bad.
(laughing)
- No, it was the--
- I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
- It was the vertical TV.
He thought, no, it's not the vertical TV.
- So what was the day?
- The day was the day that Neil Armstrong--
- I was gonna say that!
- Stood on the moon.
- The day that he died, all right, yeah.
(laughing)
- Yeah, he watched Man Stand on the Moon
and he thought, I've done something good, actually.
That is extraordinary that we got to watch that through.
- I've never heard of this man before.
- I know, I hadn't either.
- Yeah.
- He's big in America, I would say,
like, Loggy Bird is more famous here
'cause, obviously, he's Scottish.
But Farm's Worth, I think, is more famous in the US.
- I mentioned Ringo Starr a second ago.
He actually is relevant because he is part
of that growing group of celebrities
that make announcements to say that,
and you might have remembered,
Ringo Starr did a video just saying,
"Please, don't send me anything more.
"I can't, peace and love, peace and love.
"I can't sign anything."
- It's pretty cringe.
It's saying, like, "Screw you guys.
"I don't wanna sign anything for you,
"peace and love, peace and love."
But I hate all of you, and I won't sign anything else.
- He doesn't say that.
That's absolutely scandalous.
- A paraphrasing what he says.
- Paul McCartney, supposedly, has done the same thing now.
He won't sign things anymore
because it just takes up so much of their life.
If you bumped into Ringo on the street,
he probably would sign a thing for you.
He's talking about people sending stuff to his house,
the responsibility of--
- His fans have made his career.
- Absolutely, but--
- I think it's pretty annoying.
- I think after, how old are they all now?
- They're in their 80s.
- Yeah, I think it's a big, old treadmill to be on.
I think anyone who's bought Ringo's Darcello album
should get stuff signed still,
'cause that's going on.
- But if you've only ever just watched one episode
of Thomas the Tank Engine, then that doesn't count.
- And Ringo Rahmer was an absolute classic
of the early 2000s, so don't you dare attack his solo work.
I went into Hatchards just down the road.
I was walking past it the other day.
It's a bookshop, it's like the royally appointed bookshop.
And outside was a sign saying signed copies
of Paul McCartney's lyrics book,
which came out last year inside.
And I dashed in 'cause I thought,
"Oh my God, this is amazing."
And I said, "I need to get one, how much are they?"
And it was printed on the sign.
I just hand looked, 10,000 pounds.
- Jesus.
- And I then did the classic styling and out go,
"Well, I'll have to check with my wife first."
(all laughing)
"I'll be back, just keep one for me,
"I'll be back in like half an hour."
- I once did that.
- And I was gonna say, "Have you ever checked with your wife
"about any of the awful purchases you've made?"
- I once went to a kimono shop in Kyoto,
just thinking I would buy a gift
for my mother-in-law who wanted a kimono.
And they looked at me a bit oddly,
and I said, "No, I really wanna buy one."
And they brought me in, and they showed me the catalog.
And they were all about the price of a car.
Every kimono.
- Oh, really?
- They're all tens of thousands of pounds,
every single one. - They're all bespoke, aren't they?
And they're so re-enwoven and beautiful.
- But it's like, God, how do you get that?
Well, I mean, they obviously knew
that I was not gonna pay myself.
It wasn't that embarrassing, but yeah.
- You didn't try the whole check with my wife.
- You just hacked it out.
- Did Virginia Wool write a book about a dog?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Flush. - Yeah.
- Because that's another thing that Wolf had in common
with Smythe, is that they both wrote books about dogs.
- Yeah. - Oh, yeah.
- Smythe wrote an entire book
about the dogs that she had owned in her life.
- An entire book?
- I think that is quite as well.
- Yeah. - 'Cause it could be a chapter
in your memoir, but she wrote loads of memoirs.
- And she had lots of dogs, didn't she?
- Yeah, loads of dogs.
- She had enough chapters.
- She had seven dogs called Pan.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Why did I forget the dogs the same name at this time?
We've talked about this before.
- When it was Pan one, Pan two, Pan three, Pan four,
like she didn't just keep it a Pan.
- Oh, that's fine then.
(laughing)
- They're at least numbered.
- I guess there's a nice thing
of the essential doghood continues, you know?
- The soul passes from one to the next.
- Well, kind of, yeah, because you know,
you own a dog and it's Pan and that's your dog,
and then the spirit moves into the new corporeal form.
- I wonder if they were the litter of,
if they were the, like calling your son Junior.
- Yeah. - Oh, yeah, maybe, yeah.
- Donald Trump, the third, whatever.
- Yeah. - She did say
that she never ever lost a golf ball when playing golf
because whenever it landed away from the fairway,
it was always retrieved by one of her dogs.
- Oh, brilliant.
- Just brings us back to golf. - Is that a legal move?
- As long as she still takes
stroke and distance for losing the ball, it's fine.
- So you can't train your dog to pick it up
and drop it in the hole?
- No, you can't do that.
(laughing)
- That's so good.
Can you really, if it, as in if they just find it,
so that she doesn't lose it,
but I mean, she has to count it as lost, really.
- No, maybe she doesn't, if the dog finds it.
- Oh. - Then that's allowed.
She's got three minutes, basically.
The dog's got three minutes to find the ball.
If the dog finds it, then you can carry on playing, I think.
- I think that would make me more inclined
to watch golf on TV.
If every golfer had their own animal.
- Yeah. - Where they had trained
with their own method. - Maybe like a truffle pig.
- Exactly, truffle pig.
- You could rub your balls in truffles before you played.
(laughing)
- Sparrowhawk, you dress your ball as a vole
and then wherever it goes, the hawk dives on it.
- It would be great if, before each round,
you sort of, there was a tumbola
to see which animal you got
and you didn't know which animal it's gonna be.
- It's like a caddy.
- Yes. - Or you just got
a random caddy, but it's a random animal.
- Yeah. - I'm so sorry.
You've got the goldfish. - The goldfish, yeah.
- The cat, so he's fucked up.
(laughing)
- The worm, oh, get out of that hole, for God's sake.
- There have always been fears about TV
going to ruin you in some way since its invention.
Like either the early days, it was like,
people will forget how to read straight away.
And the same thing we have today,
kids addicted to their phone screens,
their brains are gonna melt.
And also the fears about the medical stuff
that might happen to you.
This new technology always freaks people out.
And so in the 1960s, there was a proper scare in America
that everyone was having radiation from their TV screens
leaking out into their bodies.
And it was bad, because it was actually found
at quite high levels of something called X radiation
leaked out of color TVs, which they just got.
And there were official warnings,
there were congressmen advised people
to not stand close to their TVs.
We think that's where the whole,
you know, when you go to your kids,
you'll get square eyes.
- No, this is really interesting,
'cause this does happen even today with our TVs.
So, you know, LCD, liquid crystal display,
the liquid crystals leak, they leak out of the TV.
- Do they? - Yeah.
Genuinely, scientists examined some dust,
and they found that nearly half the samples they looked at
had liquid crystals in them.
- Really? - Yeah.
'Cause these things are all over the place.
- And what do they do?
Are they dangerous to us?
- Yeah, they mess you up.
- Wow. - No, I don't know.
I don't know if they've proved exactly
what long-term effects they'll have.
It doesn't feel good that we might have liquid crystals
in our bodies, you know?
- It doesn't feel that bad.
Crystal's quite nice, aren't they?
- Yeah, it sounds quite posh.
- Quite zen.
- Oh, great, oh, yeah.
- The early TVs, they were cathode ray tubes when they,
and that's basically a particle accelerator.
- Yeah. - Wow.
- Basically the same as the Large Hadron,
well, not exactly the same, but, you know,
it's not many steps from one to the other.
It's accelerating electrons at a screen to make a picture.
- Yeah, same idea.
And that's why on old TVs, you know,
you had to have that huge back,
which I didn't realize until, you know,
we do our cathode rays, because that's,
you had to have your cathode ray tube
at a certain distance from the back of the screen
so it could fire all the electrons
and it could reach around the screen.
- Right.
- And it also meant that to fire the electrons,
that had to be a vacuum.
- I imagined, and I haven't looked this up,
but that's why TV screens were always convex shapes,
because that makes them much stronger,
because the air pressure coming from the outside
is so great, because it's coming against zero air pressure
inside, because it's in a vacuum.
- That's how interesting.
- And so I'd guess if you smashed your old TV,
it would all just get sucked in.
- Sucked in.
- Everyone gets sucked into it, yeah.
- I think we started off on science
in that little section.
- And then we were into, honey,
I got sucked into the TV, one of the sequels.
- When rock stars used to throw their TVs
out of the window of hotel rooms,
what you didn't see is the people just pulled in.
- Yeah.
- So many deaths.
- Oh my God, yeah.
- That's how we always thought there were little people
inside the TV.
- Yeah, 'cause there were.
- Just poor souls that, yeah.
- That's what they are.
- Yeah.
- Oh man.
- Right.
- And there was also a trans-Siberian railway one,
where everyone got in a big luxurious railway carriage,
and they moved the paintings past the windows
of the sites you would see,
as you were on the trans-Siberian railway,
going to Vladivostok or wherever it was.
- Amazing, that's great.
- So cool.
- Yeah.
- I mean, bloody cinema came along.
- Well, the thing is, if these were available,
and they are, we wouldn't go to them.
So a lot of modern art is this kind of thing, isn't it?
At the Tate, there's an exhibition now.
Yeah, like Immersive Modern Art,
if you go into like big, yet light shows,
you get insulation.
- Yeah, you're on Kusama's one at the moment.
- Exactly.
- But it doesn't feel like it's showing you
what it's like to go on an interesting train journey.
And that's what I'm interested in watching.
- When I was in Orlando,
I'm going to say Universal Studios,
I got on a train and instead of the windows,
there were TV screens that made it look like
you were going to Hogwarts through Scotland.
- Yeah, brilliant.
- So that's kind of the same thing.
- Brilliant, yeah, that's what I like.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Like I'm up for it.
Get me on the plane.
- Yeah, Yori Kusama, who is, yeah,
she does have an exhibition on at the Tate Modern
at the moment.
She's 93 now, so she's been doing her,
you know, she's the one who does the pumpkins,
like spotty stuff, her famous thing.
Yeah, there are like pumpkin installations in Japan.
So in 2021, so when she was 91 or 92,
she became the first woman in the global top 10 ever artists.
So first ever woman in 2021.
- What's the top 10 ever, is that by box office?
- It's by auction sales.
So it's with the best annual auction total.
- She lives in a mental hospital in Tokyo,
doesn't she?
- She does, amazingly.
Yeah, she had.
- Like as a patient or wow.
- But she checked herself in.
- Yeah, she checked in herself, didn't she?
- Yeah, in like the 70s, I think.
She had extreme depression.
And actually one of the things that triggered it really badly
was she was an artist in the 40s, 50s, I guess,
and she eventually made it to America
and then created this whole new form of art.
No one took any notice of her,
female artists at the time, very difficult.
And then someone completely imitated what she was doing.
And that really tips her over the edge
and got very famous doing it.
So she tipped over the edge then.
And yeah, tried to commit suicide
and then decided in the 70s,
she found an art therapist in Japan running a hospital
which uses art to treat people.
And she's been living there ever since for 50 years.
And she walks her studios every day,
is probably the most successful female artist
on the planet, in fact is.
And then goes back to her mental hospital.
- The main reason I knew about her is
because she's mentioned in a lot of kids books now.
- Is she? - It's really weird.
I would say her and Frida Kahlo.
Basically, they have a good look to them, right?
And especially Yo-Yo and Kasama's work
is very accessible for kids
'cause it's lots of spots and very bright colors
and stuff like that.
And so it's kind of nice to see
that the young generation
are getting these kind of--
- Yeah, yeah, my friends took their baby to it actually
and everyone said they absolutely loved it.
- Captain Hook?
- Oh yeah.
- We've actually said before
what his last words are in Peter Pan.
Can you remember what they are?
- In the Disney film.
- Oh, oh!
- In the book, this is.
- Is it something about Eaton?
- It is, Floriat Etona, May Eaton Flourish,
which was the motto of Eaton School
'cause he went to Eaton, Captain Hook.
But why didn't know is that J.M. Barry kind of came up
with like a backstory of all this stuff
that he did at Eaton.
And apparently he went to the library
and took out all of the poetry from the Lakeland poets.
Don't know why.
He was in a football match and he got tackled
and it started bleeding the wound where he got tackled
and it all came out as yellow blood from his leg.
So he had yellow blood
and that's one of the things that turned him evil.
He was like really embarrassed by that.
- Did he have the hook when he was at Eaton?
- I don't believe so.
I think that came out of the crocodile.
- I've never done the crocodile eaton, yeah.
- And then after he did this whole stuff
with Peter Pan, apparently he came back
and he broke into Eaton school
and he stole all of his records
from the Eaton Society logs.
And the idea I think being that he didn't want
to embarrass his old school.
So he kind of took all the logs out
as if he'd never been there.
- So he does have some principles.
He's evil and awful,
but he doesn't want to embarrass Eaton.
- Was he called Captain Hook before he lost that name?
He had to replace it with a hook.
- What was his name?
- You're right, yeah.
- No, he had a name.
- James Hook?
- I know it's James Hook.
- No, I didn't.
- He's Captain James Hook,
but I didn't know if he had a previous surname.
- So do you think it was basically
nominative to terminism that caused the...
- Pretty much, yeah, yeah.
- Interesting.
- Wow, I'd love to see his session
with the careers advisor.
Well, you bleed yellow, you're evil.
- Well, you did go to Eaton, so you can be Prime Minister.
- Another TV innovation from the olden days
that we don't see much these days is the circular TV,
which may be worth bringing back.
So this was actually quite a big thing in America.
It never really came to the UK,
but I think it came about the late '40s
and then was around in the early '50s.
It was just a circle screen.
And I think there was an argument
that that was actually better
because the old school TVs were all cathode ray.
- So are you missing the corners of the shot
that's been filmed on a square camera lens,
or are you seeing a gap around the edges?
- Or do they film in with a circular lens?
- So I read a thing, I think on Reddit,
and someone very old must have been using Reddit
'cause they had used these,
which maybe happens on Reddit,
but they said you could adjust the rate
like the average ratio. - So zoom in a bit.
- So you could zoom in to cut some off
or you could zoom out to get some cut off.
- Well, those are the original,
part of the original remotes
before it was changing channels and stuff like that.
So it was a cable that was attached to your remote
and the function was for a zoom in and zoom out.
So possibly it's to do with the circular TVs.
- It'd be quite fun to zoom right in on someone's nose
and then the game is to guess everything
that's happening in the film as it goes along.
- And there was also an old one,
which in order to pick your channel,
you had to turn the button like you would a phone
if you were dialing your phone.
So it had that, you know, an old beautiful.
- What do you mean phone?
- So yeah, okay.
- Sorry, I'm very young, I don't know what you're talking about.
- Yeah, back in the day, those old phones
that you'd have to spin it around
that was the gizmo for the-
- When do you tell that on the remote?
- Yeah, on the remote.
So channel two when you go.
- There must be huge remotes or people had tiny fingers.
Do you have to use your child's fingers?
- Yes, you would need a child to watch TV.
- She'd have its finger in.
- No, 'cause your fingers fitted in a telephone thing.
It's the same-
- No, but a telephone was big.
One of those rotary phones.
- You don't need the rest of it.
Yeah, it was just a handheld thing.
It really works when you see the size of it.
- I believe you.
- Yeah.
Sorry, just quickly while we're on sort of terms
and what people call remotes,
we now and for, you know, since 1935 basically
have been known if we watch TV as the viewer.
And that's a term that we'll always use, you know,
people say you the viewer at home.
That's the word.
And that was a word that came to as a result of the BBC
having a subcommittee to decide
what word needed to be used for the viewer.
So the other things that it could have been
that were on the shortlist that could have made it
that we could be saying instead
was we could have been the glancer, the sighter,
the tele-observist, the visionnaire, or the witnesser.
- I like that.
I read that looker in was one of the options.
- The glancer implies they didn't have high hopes
for us being that focused on the TV.
It's just on the walk past.
Give it a quick glance.
Oh, that was the murderer.
Okay, move on.
- Just on conductors,
'cause Ethel's Mithe was also a conductor.
Beat time with a toothbrush, that kind of thing.
- Tiders off to a tree to make us have a better one.
- Exactly.
They often live for a very long time.
- Trees are also lightning conductors as well, aren't they?
Just, yeah.
- What trees live for a very long time as well?
- I want a cool nickname that would be the lightning conductor.
- Yes.
- That'd be great.
- 'Cause your nickname being lightning, of course.
All you need to do is learn to be a conductor
and damn it, can't be that hard, can it?
- Can't be that hard.
It's a stick being waved like it's a Harry Potter scene.
It's fine.
- And if you're conducting the London Philharmonic Orchestra,
and you'd like to tell them it's harder,
podcast at qi.com.
- So they live for ages?
- They live for ages.
They stay working into their 80s and 90s,
and there are lots of theories about why.
And obviously we noticed the ones that stay working
for until their 80s and 90s.
But there are lots of theories about why.
My favorite theory is that they flap their arms
for six hours a day, which is incredible aerobic exercise.
Because they've just got incredible upper body exercise.
Andy's doing an impression right now.
- Low blood pressure.
They're listening to beautiful music all day.
But it may, like I say,
it may be that we just noticed the long-lived ones.
'Cause some conductors actually died while conducting.
- Oh. - Which is very sad.
You know, there was a guy called Giuseppe Sinopoli
who died in 2001 while conducting an orchestra.
- Struck by lightning. - You can see it though.
It's very vigorous pursuit.
It's a little bit like Tommy Cooper dying on stage.
It's not actually that surprising
because it's such a vigorous act you're doing,
jumping up and down, bopping around, very stressed on.
Whenever you see a conductor, you think,
you're moving your body much more than is necessary.
And so, no wonder.
- There was someone who stabbed his own foot,
wasn't there, I can't remember who that was.
It was a famous one.
- Lili, Jean-Baptiste Lili.
- Lili, that's right, yeah.
- Sounds like you're doing it wrong.
- It was when they had this big staff
and he was beating time.
And it was a six foot staff you would use.
They hadn't rationalized it down to the baton.
It was very much like the old mobile phones
which were massive bricks.
It was like that, but for batons.
And he stabbed his foot, he pounded his foot
and they got gangried and then he died.
- Oh no.
- Yeah.
- It was the Gandalf to the Harry Potter wand of conducting.
That's very cool.
- Yeah, exactly.
Exactly, yeah, yeah.
- She lived quite late.
She made it into old age, Ethel.
And what's interesting is when I said earlier
that she got a Grammy,
the piece that she got it for, this 1930 opera,
she was 72 years old when she finished composing that.
Which is quite a late in the day composition
for any artist to then be given an award for, I would say.
Especially since she was deaf.
Very sad, she went deaf in her fifties,
lost her hearing and I think by the end of her life,
which is her eighties, was pretty much deaf.
Which is why she started doing things
like writing stories about her dogs
'cause she found music harder and harder.
And she also went out with,
it sounds like very high society people
from the list of her lovers.
There's Pauline Lady Trevelyan, Lady Mary Ponsonby,
Violet Gordon Woodhouse,
Winaretta Singer of Sewing Machine.
- Winaretta?
- I say no.
- Wow.
- The singer, Empress Eugenie.
- What?
- Yeah, quite a high class name there, yeah.
(laughing)
I read, so she had a friend who,
there was only one man she ever had an affair with
who was called Henry Brewster.
But then she also had an affair with Brewster's wife.
- Yes.
- And with Brewster's wife's sister.
- Which Brewster was fine with
and encouraged it seems like.
He was very tolerant.
- That is a very open-minded way of thinking about it.
- He seems like a really great guy, Brewster,
like the real tolerant.
- What did he do, who was he?
- He was basically her librettist,
so he wrote the lyrics to a lot of her operas
and they were really close friends.
- Does all this not make you think that perhaps
a spurned lover or perhaps the partner of a spurned lover
was the one who tied her to a tree?
(laughing)
Does seem that way.
- He's fine with it, he encourages my habits.
Yes, I have been here for four days.
(laughing)
- What would you rather not have?
Your big toe or your big thumb?
- A big toe.
- Yeah.
- But don't you lose or balance?
I guess you'd have an artificial toe put in its place.
- Well, what they do is they,
so you've moved your big toe to your thumb,
they move your other big toe to your other big toe,
and then they move your other thumb
to replace that big toe.
- Yes.
- And then they move your ear to replace the thumb.
- Yep.
- It's like a Rubik's Cube, isn't it?
Very frustrating, you can never line it all up.
- Maybe this is who Pablo Picasso was painting all this time.
(laughing)
- You know, we know the creator of Bing.
- Oh, fucking hell, do I know him?
- Yeah, do you remember in QI,
there was a guy called, he was an American inventor.
He was so cool.
Ted Dewan, he was...
- I do know him, 'cause I've seen the name
and I'm like, that name was, yeah, Ted Dewan.
- Yeah, yeah, he was always at the QI club.
He was a member.
- I hate that shit.
I was like, oh, I got so sick and then, oh my God.
- Check this out.
Just very quickly, I'm sorry, but just very quickly.
So R of Street has this WhatsApp group,
which I've recently joined.
And there's a lady on it who said,
"Does anyone have a cassette player?"
I've recently found an old cassette,
which is 26 years old,
from a medium reading that I had.
And I want to see how much of what she said is true.
So I got very excited.
I was like, yes, I totally want to get you.
So I lied and said, yeah,
I've got a cassette player converter thing.
And so I'm hopefully going to meet up with her to hear it
and see what... - Have you bought a cassette?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, just to, yeah, it's amazing.
- You have to be free.
- What? Check this out.
I was looking her name on the WhatsApp thing.
She's called Joe Clegg.
And I was like, God, that name just sounds so familiar.
And her photo looked a bit professionally taken.
So I thought, ooh, okay, maybe she is someone.
So I Googled her and it turns out
she's written 19 episodes of "Hey, Duggy".
(laughing)
Yeah, on my street.
She writes "Go Jedders" and "Hey, Duggy".
- Oh my God.
I love it if you just turn on the cassette
and it just goes, ah, woof, yeah, woof, woof.
(laughing)
- Hey, Duggy's actually been predicting the apocalypse
on every single episode.
- We can't understand what he says.
- I should do that.
That's so funny.
- Come on, enough.
- Okay, sorry, sorry.
- Suburban dad chat.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So the other thing about Ethel,
seeing as we're talking about other composers,
she was friends with Tchaikovsky.
And Tchaikovsky said of her that Ms. Smithe
is one of the few women composers
whom one can seriously consider
to be achieving something valuable
in the field of musical creation.
- Great.
- Yeah, it's a compliment of sorts.
- It is to her.
- Did you say one of the few composers
or one of the few women composers?
- Women composers.
- Oh, right, it's less of a compliment.
Got it.
- No, it's a compliment to her,
but not much of a compliment to the rest of womankind.
But he does also say that since, of course,
no English woman can be without her peculiarities
and eccentricities,
it is no wonder that Ms. Smithe displaced some two.
And he gave three peculiarities.
One, that she had a dog,
which she was inseparable from.
Two, was that she really liked hunting.
And three, that she liked Brahms.
'Cause Tchaikovsky hated Brahms.
He really, really hated him.
He thought his music was awful.
And when Tchaikovsky and Smithe used to hang out together,
they used to have nice conversations.
And then every now and then Tchaikovsky
would go over to the piano, play some Brahms,
and go, he can't seriously like this.
- Really?
- This is awful.
This is terrible.
And that was the only thing they disagreed about
was how good Brahms was.
- She's over here tied to a tree.
You can't think of any other peculiarities about me at all.
No, that's it, Brahms, that's it.
- But then a bit later, Tchaikovsky was invited
to a dinner at which Brahms was.
And he said he was a very nice person and stuff.
And he wrote to Smithe and said,
"In Hamburg, I spent a whole day in the company
"of your idol, Johannes Brahms."
So it was like the one thing that he wanted to say to her
was that, you know, he'd been to this guy
who he thought was terrible, but she liked.
- What did he say?
And in conclusion, he was a nice man, but still shit.
- Pretty much.
The exact words were, "He is a very agreeable man,
"even though my appreciation of his talent
"does not quite tally with yours."
- Well, I'm gonna come out and say it, Tchaikovsky.
I think Brahms is a lot better than you are, so.
- Than Tchaikovsky?
- Yeah, what are you gonna do about that?
Nothing, are you?
- There's a kind of sort of always meet your villains thing,
isn't there?
- Yeah.
- As in the best case scenario, you think they're nice.
Or worst case scenario, you get fuel
for your irrational hatred of them.
- Who's would yours be?
- My villain.
- Yeah, who's your villain?
- Can we say on this?
- Depends, is it Dan?
(laughing)
- I sort of don't want to slag off other people
in the same line of work as us.
- Yeah.
- Okay, that's tricky.
- Oh, right, no, you should have just gone
for a historical character or a cartoon character
or something, keep it safe.
- Well, my dad wrote a porno, don't do this anymore.
- Oh yeah, my dad wrote a porno, great, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Ooh, Jamie's not gonna like that.
(laughing)
- Guys, do you remember Jeremy?
- Yeah, of course, yes.
- He was on "No Such Thing as the News" guest star.
- He was a snail.
- He was a snail, he was a left-handed snail
and they're very rare left-handed snails
as we discussed on that show,
so they can't mate with any other snails
that aren't left-handed
and since they're very hard for them to mate,
it's 'cause of the way that they're oriented,
their genital organs don't match up.
But since then, he sadly died in 2017.
I believe they did find him a mate in the end,
but since then-- - Lasted longer
than our TV show.
(laughing)
- He was constantly recommissioned.
It's pretty dull, actually,
after a while, the Jeremy show,
but we now have a way of making him a mate,
so you can edit the genes of snails
using CRISPR gene editing.
The famous always talked about gene editing
and when they're eggs,
you can inject it with something
that tampers with its genes
and turns it into a lefty.
- That was incredible.
- That is really good.
- I only laughed there, I'm sorry, Anna,
but I laughed because when you said
we can now make him a mate,
I thought the answer was going to be
another new technology, 3D printing.
- Oh yeah. - And you print a shell
and then you just sort of ram the snail into that.
(laughing)
It doesn't work, does it?
- No, I don't think that would achieve
anything that they wanted to achieve.
- 'Cause they grow the shell, it's living.
They don't find them, they grow them right here.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's why it wouldn't work.
One of the reasons.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Just on Monopoly really quickly,
the World Championships of Monopoly,
the last World Championships,
won by a guy called Nicolo Falcone.
How long do you reckon the World Championship game
lasted of Monopoly?
- Oh, more than 12 hours.
- An hour and a half before someone
just overturned it, right?
He used the banker of cheating.
- Four minutes.
- It was 47 minutes.
- Ah, nice.
- But that's quite short, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- And apparently Nicolo Falcone said
that if you know the rules,
it shouldn't last so long.
Like, for instance, you can buy houses
when it's other people's turns.
You know, if you actually read the rules
and don't play it in the way that everyone plays it,
then it's actually not that long again.
- I read that you could win it in four moves
if you knew the rules inside out.
- And you were playing so much.
No, but that's it.
(laughing)
- Sorry.
- Dan, can I be the knight?
- Wait, I keep trying to buy people's bishops.
(upbeat music)
- And here we are on the other side.
That is it.
That is all of our bonus bits.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that have been said
over the course of this compilation,
we can all be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sriberland, James is on @JamesHarken,
and Andy is on @AndrewHunterM.
Anna is, of course, away on maternity now,
but if you'd like to write to the four of us,
you can get to us on podcast@QI.com.
Okay, Club Fishers, that's it for now.
We'll see you again next time with another compilation.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)