[Music]
Hi everyone, welcome to this episode of Notice Things A Fish, which we recorded live at the Royal
Institution in London. The venerable, venerable place where so many great scientists have been
over the years and now us. Although there was a great scientist there with us, we had a guest and
that was Professor Alice Roberts. Now if you follow science in Britain, if you follow science
communication, if you follow science on TV, you'll know all about Alice Roberts as she's absolutely
brilliant. We had such a good time doing the show with her and she does have a new book out,
actually. It's called Domination and it is all about the fall of the Roman Empire and the growth
of Christianity, absolutely brilliant book, as all of Alice's books are. And if you want to learn
more about her, then you can go to Alice-Hyphen-robots.co.uk and everything about her will be there.
I should just quickly add that we do have a special secret members club called Club Fish where
there's lots of extra stuff. If you feel like you haven't got your fix of fish at the moment,
loads of extra stuff on tears there. There's an excel version of this show and every show,
if you think that I do a terrible job editing the show and I need to be making it much, much
longer than there is the place to go for that. But yeah, there's loads of stuff there. So go to
patreon.com/nosusexafish if you would like to join. But really hope you enjoy this. We had such a great
time at the Royal Institution. I can't tell you how exciting it was to be there. I think it does come
through in the show itself. Anyway, happy new year and on with the podcast!
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast this week coming
to you live from the Royal Institution. My name is Dan Schreiber. I am sitting here with James
Tarkin, Andrew Huntamari and Professor Alice Roberts. And once again, we have gathered around the
microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in a particular order,
here we go, starting with fact number one and that is James. Okay, my fact this week is that the first
person to travel into the stratosphere did so with a pillow on his head. So for people at home who
can't see the image, this is two gentlemen and they have like a basket, a wicker basket and underneath
is the pillow and this was a trip by Auguste Picard and he wanted to work out some things about Cosmic
Rays which he might go into later but they Germans were he was setting off from didn't want him to go
up there. They tried to ban his assent but he was Swiss so he managed to get someone in Switzerland to
say no you're allowed to do it. But the Germans wouldn't have it and they said well okay you can go
up but you must wear helmets. They didn't have any helmets to hand so they cobbled some together.
And it's important to wear a helmet completely but also he was going eight or nine miles
up and if it didn't work out a helmet is not going to be the thing that does or doesn't make the
difference. No, I would think no. Again if there are any astronauts listening to keep your helmet on
yeah take my word for it you know. It's not like he wasn't wearing a helmet with like an oxygen
mask in there or anything like that right. It was literally just to cover his bones. Yeah. Did he
have a parachute? I do not think they did. Oh no. That would be more useful. Yeah no absolutely. When
did we invent the parachute? Was it invented in 1931? The guy who invented the modern parachute
because like Leonardo da Vinci had pictures of parachutes in his in his drawings right. Yeah. But the
modern parachute was invented in 1913 by a guy called Everad Calthrop and he offered it to the royal
flying car because this was during the or was it during the war just before the war. So in 1915
he offered it to the flying car and they said they didn't want to give them to the pilots because
it might impair the fighting spirit of the pilots. I think right. And they thought if they've got
parachutes then they'll just jump out. Yes. Yes. I always say if I'm going to be a racer just get rid
of the brakes. I will only encourage me to slow down my motor car. Do you know this has to be the
most accident Mr. Bean prone experiment I think I've ever read about. It's remarkable isn't it? It
is. Have you ever heard about this trip? This first trip to the stratosphere else with August Picard?
No. What happened? Well basically we'll get into what they were kind of trying to do which is
were they were trying to help Albert Einstein prove the theory of relativity and they thought we
can do that by heading up to the highest spot on earth. So Picard who everyone if you want a picture
what he's looking what he looks like at home picture professor calculus from the Tin Tin books because
because that's who it was based on. Yeah. Calculus was based on August Picard. He was this
eccentric but brilliant scientist and he's actually taller than calculuses in the Tin Tin
books. He's six foot six and Hershey had to make him smaller so he'd fit in the frames. Come on.
Yeah. That's just drawn him further away. Yeah. He's wonderful. Yeah. Picard. I just everything about him
sounds sort of wonderful. He never went anywhere without a slide rule and two wristwatches.
He decorated his home with prisms so he would be great to watch his. What one for what I don't need to
you know I mean one for what you know one for the time here and one for the time up up there.
You know what the reason I asked you is because I knew the answer and I thought you might do as well
no absolutely no but the reason he did is because he knew that if they didn't match then at least one
of them was wrong. Clever. Very clever. Clever. But this trip they made up they didn't a couple of
people had tried to get into the stratosphere before I think in planes and how high did you have to go?
I think it's about it's at least seven and a half miles so the air is pretty thin and pretty cold
and a couple of people had tried in planes and not done terribly well. Picard's innovation was a sealed
what do you call the sealed gondola with walls of aluminium that were I think three and a half
millimeters thick so it's quite fragile this thing carrying them up and above him and his assistant
Kipfer Paul Kipfer I believe a huge balloon filled with hydrogen and that expands and it carries him
up and it expands in the light of the sun and it carried them up and up and up and up and up and up
and as you said Dan one thing off from the start of going wrong well with nightmare. But even before
the mission started it started going wrong so Kipfer said he knew that the whole thing had got off
to a rough start when they were doing their final checks and he looked out the window and he saw
chimneys passing them from the top of houses. Oh yeah yeah yeah they're like oh so we've left like
they just didn't even know they had no idea that they'd taken off so immediately that was an issue
yep and they had this sort of half an hour crisis of there was a hole in the side of the gondola
which had to be pasted shut and they were very ingenious in the way they did it. Oh yeah the other
thing it might get extremely hot up there because you've got less you know protection against the
sun's rays so they had this little propeller on the side of the gondola their capsule so what that
meant was one side of the capsule was painted white and one was painted black and they thought well
look if we can turn it if we can turn the the white side towards the sun that'll reflect the
sun's light keep us nice and cool ever and if and that's ingenious unfortunately the propeller broke
and so they were then unable to control the temperature it got up to 40 degrees celsius in
there 104 Fahrenheit the water evaporated they had to lick the walls for moisture oh it's just a
matter how long were they out there they were for hours and the problem was they could all day yeah
they couldn't come down because the machine that was going to allow them to come down froze so
they could they were like well we're just here now and we just have to wait for it to take us back down
nightfall yeah when the sun goes down hydrogen cools and shrinks and allows them to descend yeah meanwhile
the balloon no they didn't bother they had a way of getting to the balloon no they couldn't because
they were closed inside meanwhile the barometer explodes the mercury within it falls to the ground
and because the material is made of this metal it starts eating the actual thing that they're
in on the floor I mean can you imagine you're in this just two of you one six foot six looks like
professor calculus doesn't know what time it is okay the um they press said that they died didn't
they yeah they've been up for so long they were expected to come back quicker than that so in the
newspapers that afternoon they said yeah they've gone that's it so like I've never been in a hot
air balloon I think you have have you done that before I haven't been up a couple of times in a
hot air balloon is it petrifying uh it's really lovely until you land why do I love it I mean I
love that kind of taking off and it's so quiet when you're out and you just hear dogs barking see that's
what I find scary yeah it's her priority because if you're the way you might go in the air like in a
plane or a helicopter it's noisy as hell isn't it it's just so peaceful but the thing is you just
can't steer them can you you go where the wind takes you yeah you're kind of you just relying on
that and then trying to find somewhere to land that doesn't involve a lot of cows usually right why
were you why were you doing it by the way for the show was that like a BBC budget thing or were you
now I don't think I'm done it for television oh you know I think I've just done it for fun right okay
there was fun until we landed okay doesn't the thing of the BBC budget that says we haven't
spent all of this years money yet get robots in a hot air balloon now do you know there was there
wasn't experiment that we tried to do years and years ago when I did coast back in 2005 when
they were trying to work out how many weather balloons they'd have to attach to me to lift me off
the ground and then it became obvious that actually it was too windy to do it and I was likely to be
kind of dragged off this key which we would it it was honestly the whole thing and this is picture
of me standing there looking utterly terrified and I think I've got about 14 weather balloons
attached to me and I'm just my toes just starting to lift off but we never actually at that point
you went no no I think actually this is a bad I would you got scared at 14 balloons being attached how
would they how would they've got you back down well this is the question so when they put these
14 on did you start to feel a little bit way yeah definitely yeah yeah yeah they landed Picard and
Kipfer they landed on a glacier and they weren't out of the woods even when they landed you know
and they had to have yes they were they were I'm like like yeah sorry yeah the tree line the love of
the tree line yeah but they had they had to I think hike down the glacier I was just this was 1931
we should say did they get the data though sorry they were up there to get some data they got the data
I think they did get the data they were studying cosmic rays because they were trying to support
Einstein's theories of relativity I think they did I think but by accident because they largely
were just trying to survive because from the get go they should have died and they they didn't like
the mercury there was a statement Picard just said out loud he was like if only I had a vacuum
cleaner and they realized that the whole of the of the actual ship if we can call it though the
gondola he called it was there was a hole in it where they opened it and acted like a vacuum and
sucked all the mercury out and then they stuffed some clothing to it and then it's like it's gene
Apollo 13 it's the original Apollo 13 basically yeah it is yeah yeah it sounds like there were a lot
of risks that they haven't thought I would have liked to see the risk assessment it sounds like
there's a lot of things they haven't thought about but they had thought about the possibility of
things falling on their head I know while all this has happened they're like and we've got these
baskets on our head what we found dead looking like idiots this is so in their vein of like
thing you know risk assessments and and thinking about what you might need to go up into the
stratosphere you would have thought that there need to be you know there needs to be a better set of
instructions for getting in that thing and going up there and you know not smashing your mercury
and that kind of thing yeah not making holes in the vessel that you're in so I had to look at some
safety instructions for various more everyday items and these are some real bits of safety advice
so one is on a buggy where it says remove child before folding these are real there's one on a
hairdryer that said do not use all sleeping on items of clothing do not iron clothes whilst wearing
them now oh that's because everybody pointing it down yeah so what you do done it
all the time I'll notice a crease and I will just lay down on the bit of the iron board and I'll
just separate it from where I need to be that you're not the same shape as an ironing bud but you
are the same shape as your own body so it's much better to do it on yourself yeah I can't encourage
people to do that chainsaws don't hold the wrong end and a microwave and this was apparently
following a very sad experiment where this had happened and then after that they had to put
the label on because there was some litigation which said that you should have had the label on
there to begin with otherwise you know and then this woman would have known not to do it do not dry
your pets in the microwave wow is it true that there are some animals that are small enough that
they can dodge the microwave so is if you have a pet aunt if you have a pet and listen to this guy
really your poor kid I know you want a pet I know you've asked for a pet for Christmas for years now
well great news I've finally decided it's got more legs to the cat yeah the idea I think in a
microwave the microwaves go in a certain pattern yeah and the wavelength is long enough that if you
put an ant in there it will find a bit that isn't going to cook it is it you have to yeah I think
you have to have to take this yeah otherwise it's like Takashi's castle they're just going around it
it's just one extra level of unfair on the end I will say as well like don't try that at home either
don't try that home yeah okay hey guys we need to move on very soon oh and when Apollo 11 took off
NASA worked out that if the rocket exploded it would fire Shrapnel three miles away so they sat
all the VIPs 3.5 miles away to most of it very nice but you're relying on their maths aren't you yeah
otherwise it was just the VIPs they allowed other people yeah everyone else's news we've got you
front row seats okay it is time for fact number two and that is Alice thank you very much so my
fact is basically an X fact so it is that people used to think that arteries carried air not blood
and that the airways themselves were full of fluid so for a very very long time people thought that
actually blood vessels were full of just air and in fact that's what artery means say artery means
air carrier air tearing in in Greek and I find this just astonishing as an anatomist because you
don't have to do much digging around in the body to work out that there's blood in the blood vessels
and air in the airways but this just went on and on and on do we know why do we know why people thought
it I think because sometimes if you are if you're dissecting a body and you've waited a while to
dissect it then maybe the arteries could be empty but I mean it just seems really really odd that
they didn't realise and obviously it took a long time to work out that the heart was pumping blood
around the body and then it was circulating so it's kind of there's just there's just misunderstanding
upon misunderstanding and what's interesting is that it's still in the words so the fact that
artery means air carrier and and then they're they're confused about the airways as well so they call
the the trachea the original word is actually arteria trachea so they're calling it an artery but
in order to differentiate it from other what they think are air carrying vessels they call it the
rough artery so arteria trachea so we still call it trachea we just missed the artery a bit of it
but they were totally confused about the whole thing I mean a lot of it goes back to Aristotle he did
he did a lot of great work and he knew quite a bit about how bodies were put together and then he
kind of made it up so he said he reckoned that the heart was making blood and they they could see
that blood was moving through some vessels and going through the periphery but then they thought
that the body was just consuming it so they thought blood was constantly being made and consumed by the
body and then as far as he was concerned the lungs were just to cool the heart down so the heart's
working so hard it's getting really hot so it needs the lungs to cool it down also the brain is
another radiator to help cool the blood it cool the heart as well and that's all the brain is
doing it's just a cooling mechanism yeah and you're thinking from your heart to see your heart is
your seat the seat of your emotions and your and your intellect yes doing a lot that's doing a lot
yeah if today I went to see a doctor who still believed this how how much of a difference would that
make on my survival like because they knew there was still blood in there yeah actually like it was
William Harvey who found out that the heart was pumping blood around the body and a lot of people
didn't really like the idea a lot of physicians because their theory kind of worked like it worked
for them do you know what I mean so him coming up with this new way that the heart works they kind of
resisted it quite a lot of the time and he put it in his book which is in Latin so I'm not going to
read it but it was he put it right I've seen it recently I've I went into the Royal College of
Physicians and they got out the first edition of the motor cordists on the on the the motion of the
heart and the way that the blood is moved around the body and it's just incredible and what he's
worked out that nobody else has worked out before is that veins carried blood back to the heart so that
so that he was going right yes blood he's being pushed out but it's also coming back again and he said
that there's a closed loop actually but he still didn't know why he still didn't know why blood
was being pumped off to the lungs and then coming back to the heart again they could see some
connections between arteries and veins in the in the gut so that they could see that happening
at some levels but they couldn't see capillaries and then it was a cornish doctor called John Mayo
who's a who's a hero of mine I think he's fantastic and he basically went well I think something's
going on in the lungs I think the blood's getting something out of the air I think tiny particles are
coming out of the air into the blood in the lungs and that's what's going on and that was a hundred
years before anybody knew us and then in the end there is a going through but it's just inside the blood
yeah count one for Aristotle I think well but anybody was talking about he's putting
shorthand but you know William Harvey was friends with Charles the first and Charles the
first used to get him dear to using his experiments because obviously kings have lots of deer at the
disposal and Harvey was there when Charles was people had this thing called scruffular and it was
thought that the king could touch you and it would make you better and William Harvey was one
of the people who was there sort of like with a note pad going yet they got better they got better they
got better and also Charles what did he definitely did that and also well okay Charles the first
sent him to Burnley in Lancashire and because there was a report of some witches there and he had
to go to Burnley and count their nipples now was that was he volunteering for this job but was he
just sent the king got him to do it because actually Charles wasn't massively into sort of burning
witches and killing witches like his predecessors had been so he wanted to do an actual you know just
check it out whether it was happening Harvey went over said these people are all completely normal
we shouldn't be killing them and they all got pardoned by Charles the first oh why would they
have had more nipples like with a super new ring nipples was the idea if you were in which you
needed extra nipples to feed your like black cat and the devil I'm afraid there's a known fact that
which is do have a nipple on their tailbone which is where the devil feeds right sorry it's a bit
well it's just science guys no that was the belief in the 17th century was it was all a bit sort
of like fruity stuff you know basically they'll find something if you think you're which they'll
find something especially if you go to Burnley I just hear the ghost of Faraday in this room going
what's happened to my institution so when when was it at what point did we realize blood was where
it is who was that who was that person it's just it's gradual it's a really gradual process so
Galen saw that arteries did contain blood so he was a physician in the first century he was
physician to Moxawelius and he was a surgeon for the gladiators as well so he worked out yeah he
worked out that these arteries didn't have air in them but they had to they had blood in them
but he still didn't understand the circulation so yeah that comes along much later then there's a
there's an arabic physician called Ibn al-Nafis in the 13th century who works out that there's a pulmonary
loop but he doesn't link it up with the rest of the circulation so it's pulmonary
it's gradually in the lungs yeah absolutely so it's just gradual steps so we often kind of put Harvey
up there but he's standing on the shoulders of giants I mean you always are in science aren't you
yes like gradual increments there was a thing wasn't there where people thought the blood went out
let's say the blood goes out to my hand and then back to the heart and the same blood goes out
to my hand and then back to it's kind of like a big hokey cokey action of like all the blood is
going out and then back in yeah I mean this is one of the things that I'm saying Harvey's time that
there was this idea that the blood was being made constantly and the not that it was coming back
actually but it was being made in the heart and then pushed out and he was working out the volume
of blood that was being pushed out by the heart and one of his arguments is actually there's too
much blood being pushed out for the body to actually potentially you know possibly absorb this much
so it must be coming back it can't be that it's all being pushed out and then other people
thought that the liver made it they thought because if you if you kind of look at what the liver's
doing it it's it's receiving all these nutrients from the gut you know and that is what it does so
it receives all the nutrients come from the veins from the gut go to the liver and then it does
a lot of processing of that and then the idea was that that then goes to the heart gets turned into
blood somewhere and then it's all about nutrients so they just had no idea about oxygen and that being
you know one of the primary reasons of blood circulating obviously it does take nutrients
around as well but the oxygen's pretty important well yeah but also like the worst steps for people
made mistakes as well and when they realized that there was nutrients as well as oxygen going
around the body there was a guy called Richard Lauer from Cornwall who thought that he could
inject soup into the veins of dogs and that would nourish them interesting yeah what flavor
not recorded but I'm afraid it wouldn't matter either way and it doesn't work so I again do not try
that at home bad for yeah bad for the dog yeah soup in the microwave pets out of the microwave yeah
that's but that would have been before soup was differentiated into flavors that was
there was only there was just like some soup and then I think it was it was the 18 oh I want to say
1860s when we got the first I feel like you're fixating on the wrong part
can I just want we're on heart sort of innovations around the heart as well can I tell you as
have you guys had a Werner Forstmann no such an interesting scientist so he was a young German doctor
who he theorized that you could study the heart by inserting a catheter into either an artery or
a vein and and pushing it towards the heart and then taking an extra of yourself and sort of seeing
the heart in more detail basically that was that was his premise and he was a very young doctor he
was about 25 when he came up with this idea he asked his bosses can I do this to a patient no no you
can't so he says what can I do it to myself his bosses say no so at this point he goes a bit rogue
and he just asks a nurse working in his hospital I need to do this to you so to put a catheter in
and and to all the way to the heart right he tells her he's going to do it to her she's sort of
strapped to a trolley but this is the thing he's not going to do it to her he only needs the nurse
because he's so he is so junior as a doctor he doesn't have access to catheters so she has opened
the catheter cabinet for him he sort of straps it to the table and then while she's trapped
out of the table she looks over and he's doing it to himself he's pushed a catheter all the way
into touching his own heart wow stunning he's done it in completely the wrong room to take a picture
of so they they she then has to unstrap her and she has to help carry all of his clubbo and all
the attached stuff like down two flights of stairs everyone's furious everyone's shouting at him
what are you doing wow sorry what year is this 20s I think yes roughly roughly the 20s maybe
1920s 1920s so we're still on this old it was last week yeah and like even as a colleague is trying
to wrestle this thing out of him say no you can't do this this is insane he goes tada and there it is
photo is taken x-ray image of his own heart you're amazing right it doesn't really go anywhere right
his career doesn't go especially well he's a like he's a German doctor he goes through
World War II as a German army doctor nothing he thinks has really come of his his sort of ideal
those years ago and then he gets these weird phone calls in 1956 from from foreign-accented people
saying yeah he's won a Nobel Prize he's won a Nobel Prize for this because it turns out other doctors
carried on his innovations and went further with it I'm sorry I'm just I'm just laughing about the
fact that we have mentioned the Nobel Prize recently in a couple of episodes and anytime we talk
about the phone call this is like the body of of science excellence and every time that one of
the three of us go go to board it all about so rude yeah so you won the Nobel Prize that's he won
a Nobel Prize for it yeah that is amazing I didn't know that story and I've just been making a series
on the history of arts hospital and looking at all the history there because it's 900 years old
just over 900 years old but look also looking at it as a modern hospital and it's obviously a big
cardiac center here in London and and it is there's so much of what's done with people's hearts now
is using catheters so advancing catheters three arteries sticking little stents into into coronary
arteries to open up again if people are you know people have got angina and they're not getting a
good enough blood supply to their hearts so he did the groundwork for that you know his that was
that was you know his bravery sticking that catheter into into a blood vessel and working out
that you can actually get that all the way to the heart and it's even people's lives today yeah yeah
we should move on in a second I just want to give a quick shout out we mentioned Galen what an
incredible character he is the writer of his period right like that's virtually the only medical
writing that has survived to our day he was a doctor as well as you mentioned before but he also
had these amazing inventions talking about the basket hat earlier that we were talking about with
Picard he invented the helmet hangover cure so it was he said if you had a hangover just put cabbage
on your head and wear the cabbage on your head and that would cure your hangover and he didn't get
a naval phrase he was overlooked unbelievable that's to call it down I guess yeah because I think
Babe Ruth always wore a cabbage leaf underneath his hat to call his head down he's been reading Galen
it's amazing it is time for fact number three and that is Andy my fact is that theoretically
electric cars could run on kryptonite so this is a very exciting discovery of this century
the 20s the the early 2000s there's a there's a mine in Serbia and a chemical was discovered
in there called jada right and its scientific name is sodium lithium boron silicate hydroxide with
fluorine and a scientist dr. Chris Stanley he's a mineralogist he looked on the web for that formula
after this huge deposit of this stuff was found he could only find that formula in one other place
and it's in superman returns and lexelitha steals a case of it from from a museum to try and beat
Superman whatever but basically this stuff jada right is a building block of lithium you can
refine lithium from it and this quantity of it in this mine in Serbia is so big that it can produce
I think 90% of the entirety of Europe's target of electric car batteries right it's a huge quantity
and yet the really weird thing is this stuff jada right is only found in this one mine in Serbia
yes it's never been found anywhere else in the world and it's basically the chemical recipe to
produce it is is very precise it's absolutely crazy so you need to find an alkaline rich terminal
lake and some lithium rich volcanic glass and while those two things are together they have to
transform clay materials into very specific rare crystalline structures I don't understand any of
that but this has been found out quite recently I think this year actually by two scientists called
Chris Stanley and Mike Rumsy but what that means now that they've worked that out we don't we don't
necessarily have to go to jada in Serbia to get it we can make it ourselves so Superman returns
don't know if you've seen it oh yeah it's this what's remarkable is that is where kryptonite was given
the chemical description the makers of the film brought someone in to come up with what it would
be made up of and that happened and was released only I think a few months before then the people who
released what jargonite was made up of released it so it was right it was like it was like when deep
impact an armageddon came out at the same time it was like no one had planned that yeah it's pretty
crazy and also in Superman returns there's it's the first Superman movie since the fourth Superman
movie and the final words in Superman 4 are I'll see you in 20 and then Superman returns was made 20
years later and not on purpose Alice you're giving me a look like you're saying keep talking about
Superman returns Dan and it's got to be on purpose surely you would think right but no apparently
it was so nice to see you on home territory finally Dan and none of this is anything to do with
krypton which is a completely innocuous noble gas which is an actual gas that's an actual element
and that was found in 1898 it's very unreactive with almost everything but you do occasionally
get it between the glass and double-pained windows do you yeah that's a use for krypton I mean don't
go don't rush home and just a warning Alice if you ever have a dinner at Andy's house this is
the kind of chat you get he takes you to his windows you know there's a bit of krypton it's really
interesting oh it was found it's so cool so William Bramsey and Morris Travers they Bramsey found
Argonne then he went on a bit of a streak identified helium and krypton and neon and xenon and radon
she's working the whole family of noble gases that only feels like he's learned how to do one thing
though oh like you don't like if your lip picks when someone's really good at swimming and then
when my 10 gold medals and it's like you're only good at swimming this is why James was fired from
the commentating job for the another medal what was it for oh swimming again swimming in a slightly
different way well done so apparently Batman keeps a bit of kryptonite in his belt at all time get
out yeah in case Superman goes evil again in case he goes evil again now where there are theories
that Superman gave him the kryptonite as a sort of insurance policy to say you can trust me I'm
you're okay Alice you're gonna I've never made a guest look like they want to leave the show
as much as you in 11 years of doing this quick so what else electric vehicles thank you yeah I got
them do you reckon they sat on fire more or less than normal petrol cars catch fire yeah oh well
they catch fire every 15 minutes I think I have read that you know yeah well actually like if you
look in the news as always like another car sat on fire electric car but there was a study done
this year that found they sat on fire much less it's about 20 times less than a petrol car they sat on
fire but the problem is that the fires are much more spectacular when they go up because lithium
batteries burn very very very hot and also once you put them out they can just sat on fire again
later really let's say they go into some water as well like the water and lithium reacts very badly
together and so what they do is when you if your car has been on fire in some departments in
America they'll submerge them in fresh water for 24 hours before they're certain that they
definitely won't catch fire again oh wow I am always a bit worried about this because at home we've
got an electric car and we've also got little RC cars as well what are they selling it little radio
control cars and they've got these batteries that you have to charge in a metal box so when I'm
charging out the batteries for my radio control car it's in a metal box when I'm charging at my
other car the actual car I just plug it in oh yeah I don't put it in a metal box the microwave
I think that's fine get all those ants out there can I tell you my favorite electric vehicle of the
year okay all right it's over the top gear job it's a really cool one okay no it's really cool
there's a big Australian mining company called Fortescue and they're on a huge sort of net zero
drive at the moment because you know mining is pretty bad for the environment in general a lot of
big vehicles burning lots of diesel blah blah blah Fortescue are testing out loads of electric stuff
at the moment and trying to get it all into their fleet one of the things they're testing is an
infinite train is that the circle line is they just the circle line it's a battery powered electric
train right it loads up with the load of iron ore I think whatever they're getting out of the ground
right it carries it to where it needs to be next you know loaded onto the next bit of the journey
right but it's it's on the slight downhill gradient because it's come to the sort of the top of
a big open cast mine so it goes downhill it does it breaks and it does regenerative breaking
to recharge the battery as it descends and then by the time it's got to the bottom and unloaded
all the stuff it was carrying it has gained enough charge to go all the way back around to the top
and get filled up again can you explain entropy to Andrew please at some point you're going to
lease some energy in terms of friction oh you'll top it up you'll top it up no no but it's because
it's so much heavier on the way down the regenerative breaking on the way down yeah it does charge
the battery up more than uh maybe not more than enough you'll need to charge it occasionally okay
I guess the laws of physics aka Alice that give me a bit of a look and that's fine I respect
I respect those laws what a cool alias for you Alice the laws of physics it's not pretty good
we need to move on to our final house I haven't even told you about my second favorite electric car
of the year it's a car that can it's thank you guys scattered scattered scattered but I'll take it
look mercury spealing pure this is a car it isn't electric car as well that's kind of incidental
to why it's so cool it can go upside down okay it genuinely can and the laws of physics don't have
anything to say about it unless I promise I think all cars can go upside down like if you drive
them particularly badly great point don't they say they're about f1 cars as well that when they're
in tunnels they go so fast that you can in theory drive out of the thing so really good cars and
especially formula one cars they exert they have a lot of downforce right yeah and the reason that's
good is more grip on the road this particular one is a fan car right it sucks air out from beneath it
there's basically got a skirt all the way around it but a very very efficient skirt it's a hovercraft
it's a hover caft it's a hot yeah yes um so the the car weighs a thousand kilos and it can
generate two thousand kilos of downforce and I've watched the training the sort of video where
they tested out earlier this year it drives onto this platform the platform just revolves upside
down right and the car stays okay and what is the use well um double double capacity on the black
wall tunnel easy yes I don't have a hovercraft once as well this is on coasty so they found all these
kind of like weird experiments to me to do so there's the one where they attached all the bleans
to me and tried to inflate me into here and then there's another one where they gave me a hovercraft
to drive myself and I was just on my own in this hovercraft fantastic um and I was driving and obviously
the nice thing about hovercraft is that you don't have to be on the ground you can be on the water
so I so I was on a beach obviously it was a coast it was everything had to be the seaside
and I just went off the beach on and went over the waves and went out to see and I realised I didn't
need I to turn around oh no I was just disappearing off into this because they filmed me because the
old goose picked hard of BBC two they thought it was quite amazing and then and there was a bit of a panic
and what happened in the end well eventually I did really I did work in it but it took me a while
and I had to kind of overcome that moment of panic and go right I must actually be able to do this
you didn't just go right around the world I thought they were only gigantic things with you know
yeah like a person hovercraft yeah amazing we used to in Hong Kong where I grew up to get from
Calo inside and various other islands you'd go by hovercraft and when I was born my dad
went back to Discovery Bay which is where we lived and he went to get back stuff that we needed
because it was a sort of emergency birth and so he he went back home and he was so tired that he
had an hour sleep got his stuff and came back to Hong Kong islands sitting on the hovercraft he
suddenly was really ill because he was so tired so he said can I just step outside and they said yes
so he went outside the back and he was breathing and he noticed that the hovercraft lifted
and started slowly moving so he went to go back inside and the door was locked and he traveled
the journey of Discovery Bay to Hong Kong which was about 20 30 minutes on the back of a hovercraft
holding on oh my god no one knew to let him back in the person forgot that they let him out
he did the entire journey on the back of the hovercraft and then when he landed there he fell
down onto the dock an ambulance was called they were bringing him to a local hospital he said take
me to Adventist that's where my wife is we've just had a baby took him there he got into the room
because he was like I know which room I'm going to so suddenly they're looking for an escape patient
because he just wandered off went into the room kicked my mum out of the bed and fell asleep
that's an origin story that Superman could be proud of it's time for our final fact of the show
and that is my fact my fact this week is that Pokemon was invented so that others could experience
the joy of insect hunting this is this is really cool so Pokemon was created by a man called Satoshi
Tajiri and as a kid he was an insect collector he was known as Dr. Bug and all the students would
look at his collections and they would trade bugs anyone else he was an entomologist an amateur
entomologist they would trade bugs with each other and he then was also very much into video games
he found a mentor who was the man who created Mario and created the legends of Zelda so like what a
team this guy then goes do you know I would love because all the areas that he grew up in as a kid
in Japan were being paved over all the bits where you could find insects were now no longer with any
nature around them and he thought I want to teach that experience of what it's like to be a collector
to understand the joy and so that was Pokemon it was him trying to teach kids the joy of collecting
pretty cool so I love that that's amazing yeah very cool when was that done do you say um it was
1996 96 it came out yeah because actually the number of people collecting insects has plunged
since the 1990s really and the articles I've read about it don't mention that people are doing
Pokemon instead I guess is possible but the problem is that like people are collect I mean maybe
it's not great to go around collecting insects I'm not judging on that but the decline of collecting
insects as a hobby is making conservation much more difficult because entomologists they used to
be given like hundreds of butterflies by people when they die they're like what we're going to do
with this we'll give them to the natural history museum or whatever but now they're having fewer
and fewer collections given to them right and it's citizen science as well that's probably
useful records and it's like that I think because I think there was another co-founder of Pokemon
Unichim Masuda also spend much of his time as a child collecting insects yeah so both of them did
yeah and uh it's so clearly and what was that 1970s Osaka and Tokyo it's just a huge hobby yeah
and but like Miyamoto who was the guy who invented Mario and Zelda Zelda basically came about because
he used to go he loved finding caves and going into caves and that gave him the idea of a fantasy
adventure so weirdly nature has informed the biggest video games there and I'm pretty sure I'm
right in saying that Pokemon is the biggest entertainment franchise of all time nothing comes close
really yeah Avengers and that whole Marvel franchise doesn't come close Mario doesn't even come close
it's Pokemon superman returns not insect collecting has given us a lot it has given us a great deal
the idea of daylight saving this was first coined by a young boy called George Hudson who was an
avid uh Kiwi insect collector and he worked in the post office and there wasn't much time in his day
to collect insects because he had a job and he hated it and so he wrote to the Wellington philosophical
society this is in the 1880s I believe hey during summer why don't we just shift the clocks back two
hours so we've all we've all got more time to go out and collect insects which we all love doing right
and um I don't think it took off sadly but I think he was the first to propose it as a as a notion
and specifically right I mean I'm I'm interested in this kind of insect collection thing and the
fact that that's dropped off because if that means killing insects that's probably a good idea yeah
I wonder if more people are fated golfing them because obviously we've got these amazing apps now
where you can fated golf insects and they'll identify them for you so I wonder if there's been a
kind of rise in that and that's a better way of collecting yes yeah it's like bird spotting isn't it
it's just seeing it and writing down and trusting that that's a true account of what you're saying
I think that's probably right uh yeah I really like Pokemon and the thing is uh well I've been asking
my son about it because he was he was madly into Pokemon but he said I'm not allowed to mention that
now because he's almost a teenager and it's not cool anymore um but the other cool thing that he
isn't too is nice such thing as a fish he's an enormous fan of nice yeah um but he told me that
there were one thousand and twenty five species and I didn't know this actually because um I didn't
know how many species are there but I didn't know that they evolved and I thought that was really
cool about it as well so I didn't know it was inspired by biology and insect collecting but I really
liked the fact it had this kind of biological idea wave and into it that over time those species
could change into other different forms there is a cancer gene called Pokemon or however there was
it was called p.o.k. erythroid myeloid ontogenic gene so it's p.o.k.e.m. or n um but then um Pokemon USA
threatened to lawsuit and they had to rename it it's now called
glue against the cancer gene no it gets p.o.k.e. I guess against the scientists.
There's a trend doing this though isn't there's a trend for naming genes after
yeah like Sonic the Hedgehog on Hedgehog genes yeah yeah but Pokemon USA we're not happy about this
and so it's now called z b t b seven oh orang in Japan you can sign legal documents with your
favorite Pokemon what do you mean um so they have this thing where you can sign your name
or you can have a thing called a hanko which is a personal seal so it's like um what would you
call that wax seal not a wax seal but like an ink block kind of thing oh yeah um so like a stamp
a stamp that was the word I was looking for so yeah an ink stamp they're called hanko and they
have only certain ones that you're allowed to use you gotta just use any old thing but very recently
in the last ten years they changed it so Pokemon's allowed as well so if you have a favorite Pokemon
and you have one of these stamps you can sign your probably if I was playing Pokemon too much made
the boss papers right with a hanko you know if you depole your name to something else but then you get
a criminal record you have to stick with that name oh yeah if you get a criminal record are you
not allowed to evolve in your Pokemon with your stamp you stuck as as charmander your whole time
that would be the criminals I'm sorry I'm really lost oh no some of them evolve evil no I don't know
what's going on it's okay it's okay it's okay sometimes to not know I'm gonna have some I'm gonna
have some questions afterwards Alice's sign if that's all right um yeah there was a woman recently
who changed her name to Pudzie Bear and then she sorry we're just on name changes now and she's
um she's been turned down for a passport and she's really annoyed about it yeah but you're not allowed
to have something covering your face like an eye patch lovely um on that insect collecting I was
reading about someone called Liz Fowler um in 2016 she went to St Helena to look for something called
Baza Levski's Crane Fly and they weren't sure if it was extinct on that no one had seen one for
45 years and why she was driving down the highway one of them flew through the window and landed on
her hand so cool uh and in 2014 there was a guy called Javier oh he was called Javier he was called
Javier his surname was Juanca now in we see that that is that's how you say it oh that's that's
pronounced Juanca right out it's there's a there's a group of people in Peru called the
Juanca people and there's a football team called Departivo Juanca oh is that the same name after the same
name after the same bunch of Juanca anyway yeah yeah yeah again we're fixated at the wrong
point of this fact yeah which is that while Javier was waiting for a bus and his pockets
he looked to the tree on his right and found the new species a spider mite which is what he was studying
so he was literally just waiting for a bus and there it was so cool so I think that's one of the
cool things about insect collecting is sometimes they just literally land in your lap yeah it
is amazing and but yeah it's fortune favors the prepared mind yeah you know if you hadn't been studying
spider mice there's no way he would so what I find very interesting about insect discovery yeah it's
another of these things kind of related to your fact honest about what what we knew when and the
misconceptions and so there's a very cool early entomologist her name was Maria Cibilla Mary and
she was brought born in Frankfurt in 1647 and she's the woman who absolutely nailed the evidence
that butterflies used to be caterpillars and vice versa oh right yeah and before that I think
it was quite open to debate because because it's mental because it's mental the idea that there's
a caterpillar and then it goes in a little cocoon and then it mushes its whole body up what comes out
like a beautiful butterfly yeah yeah it's crazy it is crazy because they didn't have pokemon to
sort of explain that science to them at the time but again it's one of these things it bit it seems
crazy but also it seems really really easy to work it out I mean it's like the whole thing about
Archie's carrying air you just go well yeah just keep it in a box and then one day there's a butterfly
but that's what she did she did it for several generations and I don't know why several generations
in a row you think as you say you think one would do it but no no butterflies from egg to adult again
does it else does it blow your mind in the way that I think it blows ours and possibly everyone else
that that can happen with a butterfly that it can go from this one state to this kind of soupy
goop and then become the other thing or does that just make sense it is amazing but I also think I
mean I'm absolutely obsessed with embryology and I've written books about embryology I teach embryology
and just this idea that we've gone each of us have gone from being a single cell you know
that we're all sitting here being trillions of cells it's not metamorphosis it's not the same as
insects but we've gone through this amazing transformation where you turn into something which looks
like a ball of cells and then it looks like a fluid filled ball of cells and it's a bit like a sausage
and then it grazes little stumpy arms and legs and then it's heart starts to be and it's just amazing
it's this incredible transformation and it involves a lot of origami like folding and and cells
moving around say migration of cells inside the body as well it's it's just incredible yeah it blows
my mind yeah cool I mean you could just set that but that this how you treat all your guests that
such such a dick such a dick oh my god do you know I you get to do the coolest job in the world by
the way which is you you get to go and see things that have been in the ground that have no one has
seen for sometimes hundreds of thousands of years millions of years I mean it's an astonishing thing
finding fossils finding all bones I know you've written a bunch of books about that there was one
because you probably can't collect them in the way that insect collectors keep them because there's
you've got to they belong to the country right and they have to go to a museum and yeah again it's
the experiences and the and the photographs and I came across a photograph myself the other day
holding LB1 the skull of the of homophysiancists from Lurangbura Cave in Indonesia and you know
things like that and it's incredible I remember doing that I was filming incredible human journey
for the BBC back in 2008 and turned up in Jakarta and it was talking to the curators of the museum
there and they said you know who are you what do you do and I said well I'm a biological
scientist and they said okay here's the coverage with LB1 in you can lay out the the fossils are not
it was just incredible yeah real privilege I read there's a thing that's in your latest book it's
in the prologue and it's just so cool this is 20 years ago you were hanging on the side of a cliff
and it's because this cliff kept dropping bones down onto the beach below because it was a cemetery
built on the edge of a cliff and the cliff has been eroding so as it grows yeah
the bones slowly emerge and drop down and you were I mean I just love where the the extra stories
to where collections are being made from that would be a collection of you know cliff drop bones
and it was an unnamed cemetery and that all relied on just ordinary people you know walking
on the beach and you know noticing that among the seaweed and bits of sea glass and whatever
else there were the occasional human bone great grief would you get like half a coffin poking out
and it was kind of the sort of yeah it's it was weird it was very ancient cemetery it was kind of
seventh century so it wasn't there weren't coffins it was a type of grave called a kissed grave where
you almost build the coffin in the ground so you dig the shaft down and then you put slabs of stone
and then you lay the body in so what we saw when we when we cleared all the undergrowth or overgrowth
they were the cliff edge away were these were these kind of perpendicular slabs of rocks sticking
out of a sandy rock face so it was kind of like red sandstone so they shouldn't have been there
well they weren't naturally there they they were part of these kiss graves yeah so we rescued
the bits of bone that were just dropping out and then laughed it there but we did usefully map the
extent of the cemetery above ground as well using geophysical equipment to scan the ground yeah very
cool this is so cool now it is amazing and we've just made another series of digging for Britain and
and you know that's just such a joy because it's current archaeology and it's what's just come out
to the ground and there are some oh my god I don't know I'm allowed to talk about it yeah maybe I can
there's this absolutely amazing find which is an iron age find and it is a type of trumpet from
the iron age where nobody's ever found a complete one and we have a complete one from Britain and it
is utterly astonishing it's amazing amazing that's very cool and the archaeologists when they started
excavating we're like oh we think we've got a bit of this thing called a carnix and then they were
excavating a bit more going we think maybe there's a bit more of it and they lifted it in a block
because it's very fragile really fragile ancient bronze work and they took it to your hospital to
x-ray it and then MRI scan it and of course you know that was an incredibly exciting day because they're
putting it through this MRI scanner and suddenly they realized they've got the whole thing in
that block okay that's it that is all of our facts thank you so much for
listening we're going to be back again next week with another episode but thank you to the royal
institution thank you so much to Alice Roberts Alice domination is out now it's out on paperback
yes very exciting to go online or into bookshops get her book and otherwise just come back next week
because we're going to be back with another episode we'll see you all thank you everyone here so
much goodbye. you