[phone ringing]
[music]
Hi!
Hi! Hello!
Hello.
Guy, in there ahead of you Andy.
Yeah, well...
Once it's been to the edit, which I don't actually do,
I hope someone will have changed that.
James has always gone first.
Hi everybody, welcome to Drops of Line.
Very long time no lines dropped.
Right?
We've got a lot of...
There's a bulging post-bag to be gone through.
Is there?
Oh my goodness.
I can see it in the corner of the room.
There's letters just popping out of them.
Huge. All of them from the British Institute of Graphology.
Very cross of what we've said.
I don't think we've said that yet.
No, no, no, they will.
Oh, dummy.
Oh, the British Association of Sidekicks.
We've written all sorts of letters.
Oh, so let's get into our fabulous correspondence.
First up, we mentioned Mexico recently.
I don't know if you remember that.
We said no one listened.
Yes.
Right.
And I would like to...
We said which...
I said it was in North America.
Yep.
And we discussed whether it might be in Central or South America.
But either way, it didn't matter because no one in Mexico listens.
Well, I'd just like to apologise to and thank...
Memo, Gerardo, Eilis, Gabriella, Gustavo, Cervantes,
Humberto, Juan, Rafael, Giovanni, Emilio, Cynthia and Jonathan.
Oh, so that wasn't one person.
Also, Pilius Stipe, amazing name.
Amazing name.
Pilius.
Pilius Stipe, who's from Mexico, but Mexico in New York.
Not Mexico, but Mexico.
OK, we're not going to count it.
But they all live in North America, that's the point.
Giovanni Zacharia writes, "Mexico is in North America.
"At least I hope so, given that it was part of NAFTA,
"the North American Free Trade Agreement from 1994 to 2020."
Fair point.
NAFTA sounds like the razzies for the BAFTAs here.
Yes!
Oh, I hope a few people turn up, hoping that's it in NAFTA.
And Ashley Hebert writes that they're not from Mexico,
but they're from Belize, Mexico's southern neighbour.
Well, that I believe is in Central America.
OK, so we've crossed the border now to Central America.
Very exciting.
What's her point writing in from Belize?
Or his, Ashley can be both.
Or his point writing in from Belize.
Ashley's point is simply they're from Belize.
Let's do a gig in Belize City.
That'd be amazing.
So does anyone here have a question or a point?
They just want to let us know they listen.
Yeah, I think that's nice.
And I think Belize possibly is the most unusual place
that I've heard that we have listeners.
If you think you're in the most unusual place in the world,
we have listeners, please tell us.
Are you in Guadalupe?
Are you in the Central African Republic?
Are you in Mauritania?
They're way not writing.
Definitely, do podcast.qr.com.
The ISS, that's what we need.
That's what my dad wrote a porno had.
And they had an astronaut string up episodes.
Here is a very long, long ago callback from Katie Cain,
who's a genealogist from the Chickasaw Nation.
I just joined Club Fish.
Welcome, Katie.
And I'm listening to the back catalog.
In the September 2023 drop us a line.
So we are going back a bit now.
Yol, I'm from Oklahoma, all right.
Speculate on who would be who on Frasier.
And actually, I think she's come up with a better casting.
Oh.
Was I here in that one?
Yeah.
September 2023?
Oh, maybe not.
No.
OK, well, we talked about who would be who on Frasier.
OK.
Oh, no, I'm so sad I missed this.
I know. Anna's been watching recently.
So--
I think I was the sofa.
Well, Katie's nail--
I think Katie's nailed it.
Clearly, Dan is Daphne.
She's psychic, and she has all these crazy stories.
Oh, OK.
Yeah, well, I think that.
Anna gives off more Lilith vibes than Roz.
Wow.
Ice queen.
Oh, my goodness.
An unethical, unemotional, bloodless--
I'll take that, Lilith.
--quite unsettling.
She's a laugh in a non-laughy kind of way.
I can't remember who that is.
She's Frasier's ex-wife.
Frasier's ex-wife.
OK.
Lys.
Maybe Neweath, you know her.
Oh, she's brilliant.
Yeah, she's amazing.
She's not Marius.
Oh, she listens to us, doesn't she?
I think she might know who I am.
Not sure if you listen to her.
I don't think she's a club fish member.
Right, if you are be me, though, amazing.
Anyway, so James is Martin Crane.
Andy is Niles.
Dan is Daphne.
Anna is Lilith.
Alex Bell is Ross.
And just to round it out, Jamie Morton is Frasier.
From my dad, Rhonda Porno.
What?
He's the main character.
I'm not sure if you think he's a bitch.
I'm just going to gloss over how I'm
the really old guy who can't watch Martin.
You shouldn't have tried to stop that robbery
and got yourself shot in the head.
Who are you?
Niles.
You're Niles.
Come on, Andy's obviously--
the only reason that Andy's reading this
is because he's Niles.
But Jamie, I think everything was quite good.
Questionable on James' one.
But really, not sitting with Jamie.
Martin likes drinking beer and watching sports.
He does this.
That's true.
He's pretty-- he defines himself as working class,
despite having a very comfortable life now.
Hey, I didn't have Sky Sports growing up.
How can I just say?
Your cat drinks every end.
So anyway, thank you, Katie.
I think that's not a bad casting.
Pretty good.
I'm trying it.
Can I just say all that the same but John Lai does Frasier?
Pretty good.
Here's a cool one from Z Rosewood.
Stunning name.
It's about being served fish and chips in a newspaper, right?
Oh, yes.
So we talked a bit about that.
And this is amazing.
I'm in the US, and quite frequently,
have had fake newspaper lining the basket or tray
when I've ordered fish and chips.
Does this happen in the UK?
Yeah, I've seen it.
I've seen it, yeah.
And it's only one side.
It's like grease-proof paper, but it's got pretend.
Just a print, like it's a one-pattern.
It's a tribute, isn't it?
And Z writes that it's like squiggly words and figures.
So it's sort of not actual stuff.
It'd be fun to get actual stories in there.
Surely, if you're going to bother doing that,
you've got to get someone at the chippy to write the stories.
Other fish and chip shop down the road
found to have rat infestation.
OK, here's another one.
Sean King writes, subject, who needs sheet music?
Oh, my god.
But no, the story has moved on.
This is really good.
Dan may like to know the classical music world is finally
taking his criticism on board.
Wow.
This year's proms is set to feature
a performance of Beethoven's "Night Symphony" from memory.
So fun.
Da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da.
It's a fair fit.
People are going to go nuts.
Oh, no.
Forgive me the night that I complied that joke.
Ditton.
Promp-pomp.
Oh, yeah. It was-- it was better.
James, this was better, actually,
even though yours was right out.
That's sorry.
Anyway, yeah, no, the blurb says it's
to mark the 200th anniversary with a signature
memorized presentation and performance from the all-
Imagine if they fuck it up.
Oh, it's great.
One person is going to do da, da, da, da, da, da, da.
They're going to do it.
They're all going to be lost.
The conductor's going to be walking into walls.
There's going to be the soon players toppling over.
Pomp-pomp's Bruce Springsteen saved the day.
[LAUGHTER]
Oh, anyway.
So, great.
Exciting.
Very exciting.
Ellie Rose writes, pretty sure you don't actually
want to know this, but Wendy's fries--
so we were talking about-- what was it?
Someone-- there was a murder case
that was kind of half-solved by the fact
that Wendy's fry was found during the autopsy, right?
Yeah, that's absolutely correct, yes.
And they're specific fries.
And I think we said, oh, we can't tell--
is there a difference between McDonald's and Wendy's,
which there obviously will be.
Exactly, and they looked at the nearby Wendy's
and found one of the criminals had been to a Wendy's.
It's like CCTV footage.
Yeah, exactly.
Well, Ellie Rose writes, pretty sure you don't actually
want to know this, but Wendy's fries
are one of the few fast food places
that leave the skin on potatoes.
Whereas Zachary Peters sends an alternative explanation,
how did the forensic investigators
know the fries were from Wendy's?
Easy, they were cold.
[LAUGHTER]
That's superb.
There you go.
That's balance, you see?
That's, you know, pro Wendy's and anti-Wendy's.
Absolutely.
Douglas Fudd writes, he's the professor
at the Schmidt College of Science and Technology
in Chapman University, California.
This is not a comment about Anna's Lawrence of Elabia,
Freudian slip.
So I don't know why Douglas opens with that actually,
but--
[LAUGHTER]
That's a dragon's bite there.
Yeah, it has to do with a witty comment that James made
when you were discussing Hitler's eagle's nest.
Oh, yeah.
Do you remember it?
Ari and B&B.
James made a joke about Ari and B&B, which was very funny.
Thank you.
And perhaps--
Thank you, Professor Fudge.
Yeah.
And perhaps funnier than he realized.
Oh, no, I knew it was good.
[LAUGHTER]
Well, an airy is another name for an eagle's nest.
An airy, yeah.
Which is-- many of your listeners
will know because it is a common crossword word.
I suppose it might have been intentional.
And if so, it was an impressive double pun.
If it wasn't, I just thought I'd point it out.
Yeah, thanks.
Yeah, I hadn't thought of that, although I do know what an airy is.
So it's even funnier than you realized.
Yeah.
That's good.
That's great.
You're operating at a high level now.
I am.
Your side conscious is beyond you.
The puns are so good that even I don't get them.
This is a riddle from a listener now.
Ooh, yes.
Riddle, Connor.
Riddle me this.
Why is the lighthouse in the Azores on the island of Fayal
abandoned as of the 1950s?
OK.
I feel like I might have heard this before.
Fayal in the Azores is a lighthouse.
OK, yeah.
Abandoned since the '50s.
What happened in the '50s?
Nuclear testing.
Something happened that meant this lighthouse
was no longer useful.
A historical event we might know about.
Is this the one where someone went missing?
It was like a murder case where suddenly
the three people who were running the lighthouse
just disappeared.
And so it's sort of a cold case still.
It's not that one, but that's very good.
I like that, yeah.
What makes a lighthouse useful?
It can stop ships from crashing into the rocks.
And what would stop a lighthouse from carrying out its function?
A bulb, big enough to sit in that.
If it was always daytime, you wouldn't need it.
OK, yeah.
Keep thinking.
So water.
Yeah.
But what's important for the ships to be able to see?
The rocks.
The light from the lighthouse.
Oh, the lighthouse, yeah.
Not the rocks.
The not the rocks.
They can't see the rocks.
No, that's why you've got to see the light.
So the bulb is burnt out and they can't afford anyone.
It's not the bulb burning out that stops
this lighthouse being visible from the short.
Oh, someone's built a wall in front of it.
Someone's built a new high-rise apartment right next to it
so you can't see it anymore.
Shall I tell you?
You're closer, James.
It went into disuse because a mountain
had sprang out of the ocean in front of it.
That's amazing.
That's brilliant.
It's called the Vulcao dos Capelinios.
And it was created.
With this mountain by a volcanic eruption in the '50s.
That's stunning.
That is amazing.
That's so good.
That's incredible.
If you want to hear us scrambling towards any other answers,
you can listen to us on Tom Scott's podcast
in a few weeks.
Yeah.
Which we're going to be on lateral.
Lateral.
We're going to be on the 100th episode.
It's really fun.
Very good fun.
Yeah.
Here's a thanks but no thanks.
I don't know if you remember what this format point is.
A suggestion is being made to the show.
Yeah.
We definitely won't do it.
Thanks.
No thanks.
So Matt T writes, on a recent walkthrough sandwich in Kent,
which is located near Ham, very good,
my friend mentioned his dad saw a cow with a window
in the side of its body.
Cool.
I've never seen one of those in real life.
Wow.
I can't remember why they've got windows.
So you can see inside them.
See how much milk is left.
It's neither of those things.
Like a slurpy machine.
Normally, you have to shake the cow upside down a bit
and say, oh, we need to go and get another cow.
They have imperial on one side and then
mention it on the other side, actually.
They're born like that.
Yes, so it's because-- so if you've got a sick cow,
then you can replace its stomach contents
with the stomach contents of a healthy cow,
and it'll get the nice healthy bacteria in the microbiome.
So to get the stuff out of the healthy cow,
you cut a little hole in its stomach,
so you can put your arm in when you need to take stuff out,
put it in the other cow.
It's a reusable window.
You just open the window.
Doesn't harm the cow.
Probably embarrasses it a bit.
So a slurpy cow with a window in it, cool.
Yes, cool.
And the mat goes on.
However, the reason I wanted to email--
a lot of curveballs.
It's about Abbott's joke about Lawrence of Arabia.
Anyway, the reason I wanted to email Matt says,
is to suggest a new format for bonus material.
Oh yeah, great.
My work for a legal technology company
that houses the world's laws, dating back to 1163.
And I'm always fascinated by interesting facts about the law.
Often, on fish, you have good law-related facts.
So how about a new format where you focus
on a single topic, such as the law,
or golf, for James, yetis, for Dan, et cetera.
Essentially, a topic deep dive.
Not a bad suggestion.
Yeah.
Let's cut this but out in case we use it.
We don't want to have to credit him.
I mean, essentially, we do that four times in every show,
don't we, deep dive, subject.
So who's going to say the phrase?
Thanks, but no thanks.
There we go.
No, it's a nice idea.
It is a nice idea.
No, really, thanks.
And also, it sounds like you've got loads of great law facts.
You send us good nuggets of original laws.
Here's one.
This is a good one.
From Chris Rowe, we talked about selling time, remember that?
Yeah.
And the barter system on another recent episode.
So this is great.
I used to live in Glastonbury, says Chris,
and was part of the Let's scheme, Local Exchange and Trading,
where people traded time.
The service you offered, like gardening,
would be listed in a directory.
Anyone in the scheme can request some gardening time,
if that's what you're offering.
And they would pay you a fixed amount per hour of credit,
and you would use your credits to buy another service
from this directory, right?
Yeah, that's cool.
If anyone left the scheme, the only thing lost was time.
It was all very altruistic.
However, it all fell apart for us
when some individuals said an hour of their time
was worth more because they were a piano teacher,
whereas you were a cleaner.
Well, actually, that's really interesting,
because I think we said when we discussed these utopian societies
that that is a problem that they constantly came up against.
It's like whose time is worth the most.
If you are able to build houses,
then maybe your time is more useful
than someone who makes podcasts.
Well, relevant.
Chris finishes with, "This was a moot point in any case,
"as, being Glastonbury, there were 17 people
"offering to massage your aura,
"and only one that could unblock your loo."
(laughing)
I think I said that I have a time bank in my village as well.
Yeah, that's right.
But it also doesn't work that well,
because loads of people want to offer their time,
but people don't really need stuff.
So they end up just having cake sales
where they give cakes to each other.
Have you offered your time?
No, no, I haven't. I would. I should.
What skills do you have, though?
You can't unblock a toilet, I reckon.
Just give them a one-man podcast.
One-woman podcast.
(laughing)
In exchange for doing my garden.
Here's Alan Williams.
What was said about the tuber part in Dvorak's,
is it Dvorak?
Dvorak. Dvorak, yeah.
What was said about the tuber part
in Dvorak's New World Symphony is Bollocks.
Oh, how interesting.
Okay, go on.
But I think we said that it,
did we say that it was a-
I think we said it was a story.
Yeah, it depends what he's saying, it's Bollocks.
So we would say-
It's not Bollocks from the Hovis adverts,
that's not Bollocks.
We said that there were seven tuber nights
at the beginning and seven at the end,
and it was because-
There was a rumour it was because
he wanted to keep the tuba player in the orchestra
so that he didn't shag his wife.
'Cause the tuba player had been falling in love
with Dvorak's wife?
Yeah, but that was real.
Was he in love shagging, it was, yeah.
Well, Alan disagrees strongly.
He says, "I was at a concert in Bramford
with the Hala conducted by Sir Mark Elder,
and he highlighted the fact that the tuber part
was just 40 notes at the beginning of the slow movement,
not two separate sequences of seven notes,
and he had the orchestra play the relevant section with
and without the tuber before performing the entire symphony.
This showed conclusively that these 40 notes
contributed significantly to the overall sound
and were very far from being superfluous.
Look, that's fair enough.
Sounds like it's a matter of opinion.
And, let's see a tuber player this guy,
'cause they are quite touchy.
He doesn't specify, there's a wrong tuber vibe
coming off of it.
But apparently Dvorak did a great favour to tuber players
'cause their rate of pay was usually dependent
on performances and sessions where they're required at.
So you get paid, yeah, they don't just get paid per note.
That'd be really weird to get,
but how do you still get paid in a piece?
- They don't get paid according to the time they spend playing.
The tuber part as a bonus is also extremely easy,
being very slow and merely wandering up and down scales.
It is kerching for the tuber player.
- I think I'd rather have to play most of it
than have to sit there silently getting a sore ass
listening to my up themselves violinist colleagues.
- It is quite dull to sit there
when you're not playing in an orchestra for sure.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Here is Kira Johnston from Scotland.
- Mm-hmm.
- I am writing from the break room in the hospital
where I work as a junior doctor,
where I'm currently catching a break
towards the end of a 12 hour night shift
and listening to episode 529.
- Yeah, did you hear that UK government 12 hour shift?
- Yeah, and also she's punishing herself
by listening to our podcast, I mean.
- I don't feel like you can really take it in
after that kind of session.
Get a good night's sleep, listen in the morning.
- Well, she says, "I thought you might be interested to know
that I'm not only carrying two pages or bleeps,
as we call them, but also a walkie-talkie."
- Oh, great.
- Really, a walkie-talkie?
- We've had a few emails from the pager community.
Bleeps pages are very useful
'cause they work without signal and everyone knows where to go.
Did we get any emails from anyone in the bleeper community
who is not a doctor or a nurse or, I don't remember.
- I think it's used by birdwatchers as well.
- How's it?
- I think there's a, yes, I think when they get a good Twitch,
they put a page out.
- Oh, that's nice.
- Something like that, I'm pretty sure.
- The networks are not there of sort of like UK Twitchers
or birdwatchers, sorry, they don't like the word Twitchers.
- These are the Twitchers 'cause they're just,
the bleepers tell you where the hot shit bird is.
So I think that's true, isn't it?
Please write in birdwatchers, isn't it?
Twitchers are people who just get excited
about an exotic bird that turns up on our--
- They complete the lists.
Twitchers just want to complete the lists.
Birdwatchers want to understand the feathered friends.
- I see, yes, yeah.
- The most complete is.
- Here's Paul Rosenthal.
- Yep.
- I just listened to--
- There's a lot of roses in this, in bars.
- Oh yeah, we had Z Rosewood, Paul Rosenthal, good spot.
- And then another one who was called Rose.
- Do we?
- Chris Rowe.
- Do you alphabetize all of these emails?
- Of course.
- R, R-O.
- I listened to your recent episode
describing American dry states
banning alcohol sales at 30,000 feet.
- Oh yes.
- I wanted to share a similar story at ground level.
I grew up in California for my freshman year of college
in 1973, traveled alone by train to New York.
On the second day of the uncomfortable three day journey,
old timers began walking up and down the train
announcing two hours to Kansas, then one hour to Kansas,
and ultimately 15 minutes to Kansas.
Kansas then banned the sale of alcohol,
but not the consumption.
So the bar had to close for as long as the train
was passing through Kansas.
But if you'd bought something, you could still drink it.
- That is a bit like on UK trains where they say,
"We're about to arrive in Carlisle
"when the train staff will change over,
"so you will not be able to buy the alcohol
"for the next 20 minutes."
(laughing)
And everyone in the carriage just furtively stands up
and shuffles down the character.
- And he says it was mid-afternoon when this happened,
but people rushed to the bar in panic
and started snapping up beer.
It didn't take long before the entire Amtrak train
was plastered.
Someone decided it would be appropriate
to hurl the empty beer bottles out of the window
into Kansas.
The windows were all sealed,
but that didn't stop pickled passengers
from clawing at the windows.
- Wow.
- That was terrifying.
- Yeah, that doesn't sound great.
- Pretty frightening story, yeah.
- But it does mean, presumably the announcement,
"We're not in Kansas anymore."
Had a very different tone on that train.
(laughing)
Yay!
- Oh, brilliant.
- That's so good.
- Ed Robinson.
- So it's another R.O.
- Yeah, I think Kandy's alphabetized all of the--
- It must be.
- Correspondence.
- Imagine if your inbox is in alphabetical order
rather than order of arrival.
- Yeah, what's wrong with that?
(laughing)
- So Ed Robinson writes, "In 2017 I was very interested
to hear in the latest episode that the Tin Opener
was invented several years after the invention of the tin."
I think we said some decades, didn't we?
This was a particular note to me,
as for most of my adult life,
I've been telling people as a bit of after-dinner trivia
that the tin was invented several years
after the invention of the tin opener.
I've never quite been able to explain to people why
they would have done that.
- I love that.
(laughing)
- So close.
- Just a classic half-remembering of a fact.
(laughing)
- It would be a better fact.
It would be an even more amazing fact.
- Of his stunning fact.
(laughing)
- The psychics again.
- Oh dear, love it.
Here's a Danish correspondent called Søren.
- Søren.
- Which is an anagram of Rose N.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- Something is going on.
- Søren B, a maritime pilot from Denmark.
Pretty cool.
- Okay.
- I've just listened to episode 42.
- Who does like aircraft carrier?
- No, I think that means that you,
so certain large ships,
when they're going out of a harbor,
they need a specific driver pilot to come in
and take them out.
- Sorry, of course.
- I think it's in there. - Yes, the harbor pilot.
- I also thought the pilot was sometimes just a word
to use for a person who captains a ship.
- Yeah.
- And I think it's that sort of very fine tune detail,
isn't it?
Episode 42.8, so Søren is a bit behind the curve.
You talk about squatting of ships
and how a cruise liner has to increase speed
to safely pass under the Great Belt Bridge.
- Oh yeah, that was a long time ago.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And Søren sails under the Great Belt Bridge almost daily.
- Really?
- It's just a cool thing.
- And he never knew this fact
and he's crashed into it every time.
(laughing)
- Is that the bridge between Copenhagen and Malmo,
that one?
- Between Ceyland and Sprogo, so don't know.
- Well, tack to Søren.
- Yeah, yeah, thank you, Søren.
- That's really cool though, that he drives that ship.
- Well, from sailing to dairy farms,
Clement de Menizes, right?
I've just listened to one of your wonderful
compilations on Club Fish, that's nice.
In it, Anna says that cows cannot lift one foot at a time.
I'm headheads, we're not on a dairy farm.
(laughing)
They've just been kicked in the bollocks by a cow.
That's so, I don't remember you ever saying that.
It's like, you're so unlikely, I would say that,
'cause it feels unlikely to be true.
- How would they walk anywhere if they can't lift one foot?
- They just slide everywhere.
- You do the two-legged, yeah.
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, that's fine, it's still.
- Even so.
- Who do you say that?
- I don't recall that.
- Whoa.
- I mean, the reason for the compilations are,
the reason we have that material is either it's not true
or it doesn't fit in the podcast.
- I think the compilations are all true.
I don't think we should advertise that they're--
- No, there's some times--
- I don't know if they're right.
- Sometimes if we don't get things quite right,
but it's still funny, then I'll go with it.
- There's a slightly lower barrier,
isn't there, to entry?
- Yeah.
- Great, a barrier that a cow couldn't get over,
for instance, if one of them lifted any of its feet.
- Clemens says, the reason you tip a cow,
I mean, you were talking about cow tipping, maybe?
- Okay.
- It's because it's much easier to put a shoe on
when they're on their side.
We still put shoes on cows to help with several foot problems.
And you can get special crushes that tip the cow over
to make hoof trimming easier.
- Okay.
So thank you, Clement.
- That's cool, okay, I do vaguely remember now
thinking about getting one foot of a cow up.
- Steve Bullock.
That's weird.
- I'm stuck here.
Can't move my feet.
- Stephen Bullock says, nestled in the latest episode,
among the talk of muffs, muff diving and muff warmers,
it was mentioned that on grand tours,
pigs would be employed to pre-warm beds for the taurers.
- Oh, okay, yeah.
- My now departed dad, who fancied himself
as entrepreneurially minded and grew up in poor circumstances,
always claimed with some pride that his first job
was as a child in the forties as a professional bed warmer
for his older brother and sister,
for which he was paid a hip in a week.
- Aw, that's nice.
- Were he still here, I'd have enjoyed pointing out
that he missed a trick by not subcontracting
to a pig or other animal.
The great irony though, is that he was known
as something of a womanizer,
and so went on to warm many a bed that was not his own
throughout his life.
- This is terrible.
- This has turned a corner, hasn't it?
This little eunuchy.
Good on in.
- There you go, thank you, Stephen.
- Got that practice of bed warming in early.
- That's ridiculous.
- Here's quite a niche one.
Pamela, Pamela Cowey?
Sorry, no, Pamela Cowey.
- Oh, my God.
- Dairy farmer, Bullock and Cowey.
- This is starting to blow a bit open.
- Whoa, yeah, yeah.
Nitrogen, the Haber process,
Haber, Billingham and Ammonia.
Billingham has two local non-league football teams,
Northern League Div 2.
One is called Billingham Town,
the other is called Billingham Synthonia.
Do you remember Billingham is where they have
that
- Yeah, and it's just closed down, I think.
- Right.
- Yeah.
- That makes all the nitrogen.
- Synthonia is a contraction of synthetic ammonia.
- Wow.
- That's awesome.
- The product made by ICI in Billingham
and with whom the club was associated.
Unable to afford the ground upgrading,
BS, Billingham Synthonia,
now play some 50 miles away in Stokesley.
- How ironic that they're named after something
used for fertile and fertilizing land
and they can't afford to upgrade their own.
- Brilliant.
And what lives on ground that you might fertilize?
- Cow's.
- Pamela Cowie.
- And once the cow creates its dung,
what can you first slice with that?
Roses.
- Yeah!
- Something weird has happened today.
- It's full circle.
- We've turned a corner.
- Yeah.
Bye.
(upbeat music)
Bye, everybody.
Bye, bye.
Goodbye.
Please email a podcast at qi.com.
If you want to contribute.
- Yeah.
- And why wouldn't you?
- Why wouldn't you?
- If your name ends with S,
because Andy will be hitting that bit of the alphabet
for next week's episode.
- Ends with S.
- Starts with S.
- I say ends with S.
- Yeah, you did it as odd, wasn't it?
- That's exciting.
- Yeah.
It's just coming at it from the other way.
- That's a good challenge, yeah.
- Is that a thanks note?
Yeah, thank you, everybody.
And thank you to the three of you.
- Got it.
(laughs)
- That's nice.
- It's great fun.
Oh, and to you, Andy, for doing all the hard work
and finding the emails and putting it together.
- Nothing.
- I do it for the love.
- Ah, okay, well then I retract.
(laughs)
- Bye.
(upbeat music)