(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here
with Anna Tyshensky, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and James Harkin.
Once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that ironing in Egypt
is traditionally a man's job, and they do it with their feet.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- And that's why we shouldn't let men do the ironing.
- Do they put the shirt on the ground,
or do they put their foot on the board?
- Yeah, good question.
- And also, do they use an iron,
or do they have really, really flat feet?
- Hot, hot feet.
Well, it's in the desert, right?
You just stand them the sand for 10 minutes
until your feet get warm.
- That's it.
No, they use an iron, a normal iron,
so these are people called the makwagi,
and the makwagi regal are specifically the foot ironers.
Makwami's iron, and it's been going on for hundreds of years,
and on every street corner, you'd have a man
who does your ironing, you take your ironing to him.
It's passed down from fathers to sons,
and traditionally it was done with feet,
so you'd have a big, heavy iron.
I read one reputable source saying
that the irons can weigh 40 kilos.
- What, 40 kilos?
- I know, it doesn't seem plausible, does it?
- Do they lift it with their feet?
- Well, they just push it. - They just push it,
and they look like a classic old iron,
so they're just an iron that's heated over coals,
or in a stove, right, like a big metal iron.
They're not plugged in.
- Not plugged in.
You kind of got that little water button
that you press or the steaming up there.
- Dan's trying to pretend that
ironing is a man's job in his household as well.
- I think, I could confidently say,
we all know I iron non-star.
- Dan is an obsessive, Dan and Andy, actually,
I feel like you spend half your life ironing,
it's quite sad, but it's not sad when these guys do it.
- I'm sorry, can I just say
that I don't just let my wife do all my ironing,
I just like to be creased.
- In answer to your question about the spray,
this is one of the coolest things,
and I was going back to old 19th century sources
when people visited Egypt and reported on it happening there,
to spritz the garments, so they're a bit wet.
They spit, and so now these days, I think--
- Terrific, all right, does that cost extra?
- There are accounts of the real pros,
the real traditional ones, having just a continuous spray
constantly coming from their lips.
- But if you were walking the streets,
looking for someone to do your ironing,
and presumably there might be a bunch of competition,
what you wanna see is just one old guy dribbling like crazy,
and that's the one you go for, right?
That's the best version.
- How did this industry fair during COVID?
(laughing)
- That's a really good question,
and I forgot to investigate.
- Actually, people used to spit on their irons
in the UK as well.
- Really?
- Yeah, yeah, so we're talking from the 17th century onwards,
we had something called sad irons,
and sad meant solid in those days.
So there were solid irons, and they're kind of pretty much,
you know, like when you play Monopoly and you're the iron,
it's that kind of thing.
So again, it's just like a piece of metal.
You put it in the fire until it's hot enough,
and then you would use it to iron things,
and to find out when it was hot enough,
you would spit on it.
And if the spit sort of laid and frosted around
and spat around on the iron,
then you knew it was ready to go.
- Interesting.
- But you don't want it too hot, presumably,
'cause then you burn your clothes.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- As well as the sad iron things,
there were slug irons, which I like as well,
where you have a slug of metal,
literally, I just didn't like an ingot of metal,
that you put in the fire for ages,
and you draw it out of the fire and shove it in the iron,
and that makes it hot.
- Nice.
- There were rough irons.
So they're called a goffering iron,
where you could iron fabrics into a scalloped edge.
So you know all those amazing Elizabethan ruffs?
- Yes.
- They had to be ironed into place, basically.
- I do your first level ironing,
which is I just want things flat and uncreased,
but there is an art to ironing,
where you do put in these ruffles.
You do put in the line on your trousers.
I aspire to be there.
You'll put a crease to the shirt sleeve though.
- Yeah, you might do.
- You gotta have a crease on the shirt sleeve.
- You gotta have a crease.
But here's the thing, back in the day,
ironing wasn't just for getting your clothes
to be uncreased, it was for cleaning as well.
So there's reports of, let's say during the Crimean War,
there's a report there where cannibals might be heated
and used as a makeshift iron.
And it wasn't so that people went,
you know, I want to look uncreased
when I'm going into battle.
It was because you would have things like lice
living on your clothes that you want to get rid of.
So it was burning it off, basically.
So it was doing a double job.
- It's very hard though to aim it correctly
for an ironing job.
So it just gets the ironing right.
It's a difficult method.
Can I ask Dan as the only other ironer in the room?
I suspect, another question about this.
What was your opinion on wrinkle-free shirts?
Sorry, James, I mean, James is wearing a collared shirt now
and it looks actually very nice.
- No, no, I've never really ironed any item of clothing
since I left a proper job about 25 years ago.
- Fair enough, fair enough.
And I live in a hope of getting a proper job.
So I'm constantly heading to interviews,
so I do mean those shirts.
(all laughing)
So what was the question again?
- Would you wear a wrinkle-free shirt,
like a non-iron shirt?
'Cause a lot of shirts sold these days are non-iron.
- I definitely wore those when I was at university, for sure.
It was the one thing, if I went to a men's wear shop,
I would look to see if it would need an iron or not.
- Really? - Yeah.
- Why would you? - And the clip on tie as well.
Don't talk to angry colleagues strangling you,
that's very helpful.
- I was talking about at university
whether we went clubbing,
we didn't always wear ties.
- How were you letting in?
- Ridiculous.
(all laughing)
We borrow one from the bounce scene,
he's going over to his jacket,
he's got a big rack of ties in there,
and he picks one that goes with your complexion and shirt.
- Yeah, okay.
- So wrink non-iron shirts are made with formaldehyde,
or they certainly used to be,
they've been treated with the special chemical,
which means that they don't crease, which is very clever.
- But they make you need to do a poo, right?
We've talked before about how formaldehyde
makes you need to poo, that is true.
I think the good thing is that the formaldehyde
is locked into the shirt,
so actually it doesn't do you any harm as the wearer,
but the people who made it,
people who worked in the non-iron shirt factories,
they all go quite sick, I think.
- Right, really?
- I think there's a higher proportion of cancer
in people who work in those factories
than in the general population.
- Well, they don't sound like good residents
that get used to them.
I don't know whether they've ironed out these problems yet,
but from what you're saying,
it sounds like that might still be a thing.
- The study with this of the incidence of cancer was 20 or nine.
- Okay, okay, okay.
- But yeah, ironing basically, okay,
so let's say you've got a cotton shirt,
it's made up of loads of fibres, chains of cellulose,
and when you put it in the washing machine,
the cellulose goes a bit wonky,
and it comes out and it's all creased,
and the ironing works by loosening these cellulose threads,
and when they're loose, when they're nice and--
- It's warm and relaxed.
- It's warm and relaxed, then they can get into a line,
you press them down and they'll stay in that line.
That's how it works.
- Interesting.
- But the non-iron ones,
the formaldehyde basically locks those cellulode fibres
in place.
- When you join the army, if you go to Sandhurst,
which is a very, very posh British army--
- Sprint's Harry's Place was an academy.
- Yeah, probably went to Sandhurst.
- You have to carry in your own ironing board.
- Really?
- Yeah, and I asked a friend of mine who went to Sandhurst,
and he said, "Yes, you do."
- Do you? - Of course you do.
- Of course you do, you don't bring your ironing board.
- Could you not share an ironing board between a barrack?
- There's simply so much ironing to do with.
You've got so many different kinds of uniform
as a modern, heroic, action-man type.
- Okay, yeah.
- And because they don't have so many cannonballs
in warfare these days.
(all laughing)
- You can't just wait for it to happen naturally.
- I was very hard with a cruise missile
to get a really crisp line on that track.
- I wonder if they're bulletproof
or if the fabric is Kevlar,
because that is a fantastic defense shield
that you could double up an ironing board with.
- Yeah, it's basically human size, isn't it?
- It is, that's a human-sized shield.
- You're suggesting people wear their ironing boards
into battle.
- Are we not talking about the front lines here?
We're just talking about back at the barracks.
- You don't do that. (all laughing)
- Here's a really British thing that I'd never heard of
before that used to happen in the past with ironing.
Some homes, and we still know a few examples of these homes,
had a room for ironing newspapers.
- Fantastic.
- That's the dream, that is the dream.
- Yeah, I read about this in Bill Bryson's book at home,
and it was featured, I think, in Downton Abbey,
but the idea was before the master of the house
would be given the newspapers,
the butler would take it into the ironing room,
and they would iron the newspapers, not for creases,
but to make sure that the ink becomes dry
and solid into the newspaper
so they can wear their white gloves
as they're leafing through the newspaper
and not worry about ink smudging on them.
- I didn't know that was why it was.
I think I honestly always thought it was to make
the newspapers nice and flat for the posh people.
- We should say ironing's at risk.
- What? - Sorry?
- Ironing's at risk, big risk.
- Right, what?
- From the youth.
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah.
- 30% of 18 to 34 year olds,
many of whom may be listening,
don't own an iron and never do any ironing.
- What do they do instead?
- I don't know.
- They do, like me, just be wrinkled.
- I think so, yeah.
And they will claim things like they're closed,
don't need ironing.
- They don't, our mind don't, and James' don't.
- Honestly, I would always wear mine flat.
So what I would do is I would wash my shirt,
and then just before it was dry,
then I would start wearing it,
and my natural body shape would flatten the shirt.
- I mean, it's clever.
- You want it to have that shape of your body.
You do, I mean, that's the point, isn't it?
If you iron it to a non-realistic standard
of a completely flat person,
which is not what any of us are.
- Of course it's gonna crease.
- My whole body is actually creased.
When I'm naked, I have these terrible creases all over.
- That's a good idea.
Although a better version would be to put it on someone
whose body you aspire to look like,
so that when you get it back,
you can feel what you want to eventually not break it.
- And your body can iron itself into the shirt.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- Speaking of nightclubs, as I was,
I am in boards are good for DJs.
Let's say you're an aspiring DJ.
You're going to a house party.
You've got your decks,
but you don't really wanna bring a big old sort of,
like all the stand.
- I'm a hog on your table.
- So what do you need?
- You need something that's flat,
but also you need it to be a very certain height.
- Yeah.
- You don't want the decks to be up at your eye level,
or at your knee level,
but the good thing about ironing boards is they're adjustable.
- Yes.
- There you go.
- That's so cool.
- So you look at interviews with DJs and they say,
oh yeah, my first ever DJ gig was on an ironing board.
- That's so funny.
And if you pop some, pop a pair of pants under the decks,
by the time your set's finished,
they'll be lovely and crisp.
That's your journey home.
- It's actually probably the heat of the decks.
- Might do it.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Do you think in the future,
they'll be looking at these ironing boards and saying,
did you know these used to be used for ironing?
(laughing)
- Before they became--
- With everyone's a DJ.
- On the DJ boards, yeah.
- There is actually a guy called DJ Ironing Board,
who built his rig that fits perfectly
on a normal ironing board and he does festivals and stuff.
- That's awesome.
- Oh, wow.
But I mean, you've got to be careful.
And that's so many times when I'm mid iron,
you hit the little handle underneath
that sends the entire thing down.
You don't want that.
- How do you do that?
I've never had that experience.
- Happens to be nonstop.
- I've never done it.
- No one else?
- No.
- Can I give you another use for an ironing board?
- Yeah.
- If you want to be Pope.
- Okay.
- Quite neat.
- Well, for instance, the most recent guy who was Pope
was Robert Provost, Pope Leo XIV.
And as a child, he played it being a priest
by using the family's ironing board as an altar,
according to his brother.
So he would get the ironing board up.
He would get a load of biscuits
and then put them there.
And his family would come round
and he would give them a Kit Kat and say,
"Buddy of Christ."
- Really?
- Oh my God.
- Are you serious?
- Absolutely.
- And again, you can alter the altar as you're growing up.
- Alter the altar.
- So it's all good.
- I mean, they must have thought he was on,
that was a pretty long shot
when he was a kid doing the Kit Kat thing.
But that's incredible.
Like, they're laughing on the other side of their face now.
- He works in mysterious ways.
- This is good news for the world of ironing
because actually the last Pope, Francis,
actively announced that ironing needed to stop
and so did in homes.
So there was a question about all these Italian kids
that weren't leaving home and what do I do
to get my son a job and get him out of the house?
And the Pope said, "Stop ironing for him."
And that was like-
- Like mums overlooked.
- Exactly.
Why would he leave home?
He's got his stuff being ironed every day by you.
You're mollycolling him.
- And an interesting thing to focus on as Pope,
but you know, they're focused on worse, I suppose.
- It turns out they're all obsessed.
- Another great world leader
who did a spot of ironing in her day, Margaret Thatcher.
- Really?
- Even after she was an MP,
she would iron her husband, Dennis's shirts, in parliament.
- In what?
- Not on the floor of the House of Commons.
- Okay.
- Just on the dispatch board.
- There is a desk there, actually, isn't there?
- Yeah.
- I think it's wooden.
I think that would be very bad for it.
- Yeah, you're right, you're right, you're right.
No, there was a ladies' room.
And this was a time when there were fewer female MPs
than there are now.
There was a need for women to have their own space in parliament.
And it had an ironing board in it,
and she frankly monopolised that iron.
- Well, she was a fan of monopolies.
- Yeah.
- Brilliant, absolutely brilliant.
That's the best batch of ironing monopolies
track you'll hear on any podcast this week.
- This week.
- But if he listens to "Off Lady" next week...
- They come up these days.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that 900 years ago,
England beat Scotland in a battle
with an earth horn super weapon,
which scattered the Scots by frightening their cows.
Lot to unpack.
- Yeah.
- What's an earth horn?
- Glad you asked.
It's not a common thing anymore.
This was word of the day
on the OED website the other day.
- Highly recommended, you know.
If you're listening to this,
just go over to the Oxford English Dictionary website
and see what the word of the day is.
And this is earth horn.
I think this was the first and maybe last time it was used.
- Yes, it's a hapax legomenon.
- Yeah.
- As in there's only one mention of it
in the whole of literature.
- The whole of literature, yeah.
So it didn't take off basically this earth horn,
like secret weapon, whatever it was.
Seems to have been a big horn.
- Despite working apparently.
- Yeah, you're right.
- You're absolutely right.
- The other thing to say as well
is it was only mentioned once and that was in 1338.
And it referred to a battle that happened in 1138.
- Okay.
- Yes, so.
- It's like the 200th anniversary of this battle.
- Finally, we're gonna uncover this secret weapon
that we used.
No one's mentioned it before now.
- And again, it's not completely clear from the OED source
why frightening the cows was a key factor
in the end of the battle.
- Okay.
Well, give us everything we know about it then
from the description.
- Definitely huge amount of it.
- That's it.
- It's a thing called the Derethorn.
- We don't know anything about the earth horn, definitely.
- We don't know if it was a sound.
I mean, horn implies it.
- And what do we know why earth?
Is it made of earth?
Is it comes from the earth?
- I can't stress enough, this was 900 years ago.
As James says, first recorded 200 years later
for the first and last time.
We really don't know much about it.
This is my challenge fact for the week.
- As I said, it happened in 1138.
So what was going on?
- What was going on was a thousand years of conflict
between England and Scotland on and off.
But quite a lot of on.
So what I found was the earliest battle recorded
between Angles and the Scots slash Picts,
that was in 596 AD.
- Wow.
- And the last battle between England and Scotland
as completely independent kingdoms was, when was it?
That was 1547, correct?
- This particular one that we're talking about,
the Battle of North Allerton,
also known as the Battle of the Standards.
This was that time when Henry had died Matilda
was maybe going to be our queen.
Stephen was maybe going to be the king.
There was a whole load of conflict
about who was going to take over.
And the Scots were on the side of Matilda.
And a lot of the Barons in England
were on the side of Stephen.
And so there was a big old battle
because the Scots wanted to help out
because Matilda was the daughter of a Scottish kick.
- I read that this battle took place on Calton Moor.
- Jesus.
- Is that interesting?
- That is interesting.
- Moor.
- Do you want to say that again?
- Calton Moor.
- You didn't want to stress the cow part.
- Well, that was obvious.
The Moor was going to be a bit more difficult.
- Yeah.
- No, I think that's really good, Dan.
- Yeah, that's very good.
- Give them lots of cows at the end of the battle.
- We talked about this when David Mitchell
was on the podcast.
- This era we did, yeah.
- If you've got your English history,
Kings and Queens ruler,
it's the bit that goes Willy, Willy, Harry, Steve.
It's the Steve bit, of course, King Stephen.
- And if you've got the ruler that goes all the way forward
and just to emphasise how much the Scots in English
didn't like each other back then,
and obviously it's all water on the bridge now,
but between 1040 and 1745,
33 out of the 36 English monarchs
either invaded or were invaded by Scotland,
which is strong.
It's a strong record, isn't it?
- So it's a long old skirmish.
- I know.
- Although it could have all been avoided,
or the worst bits could have been avoided,
if it weren't for just a small diplomatic cock-up.
So the worst phase,
and with all the famous battles,
like your Bannock Burns and your Mel Gibson's,
was 13th and 14th centuries,
and that was the Wars of Independence.
And it all kicked off when Alexander III of Scotland dies
in early 1290s.
And there were these two guys,
John Balliol and Robert Bruce,
who was the grandfather of the famous Robert Bruce.
- Sorry, it was one Robert the Bruce,
and the other one was just Robert Bruce.
- Yeah, that was his middle name.
- Yeah, you sometimes got to slip that in there
to differentiate.
- So no, there was a guy called John Balliol,
there was a guy called Robert Bruce.
Robert Bruce's grandson was also called Robert Bruce.
He's the famous one,
who for bad reasons we now call Robert the Bruce.
I think related to the fact that he was Robert the Bruce.
- He's brave heart for anyone who knows that movie.
This is Mel Gibson's granddad, Robert Bruce.
- Exactly.
They couldn't decide who was gonna be king.
So they asked Edward I of England,
as their neighbor and friend,
as an impartial observer,
to say which one of us should be king.
- Man, that's it, right.
- Edward I thought, great, here's my chance.
And he said, okay, I'll do that.
But first of all, I need to have legal authority
over Scotland to have this kind of authority
to decide who's king.
And so little legal loophole,
he gave himself authority over all of Scotland.
And then the rest is history.
He just started getting in the way all the time.
And what a cock up.
- Yeah, Berwick upon Tweed is the,
now, if you're heading north from England to Scotland,
it's pretty much the last English town you pass through.
- If you're heading on the east coast.
- If you're heading on the east coast, absolutely.
- Sorry, a big fan of the west coast mainline over here.
- I love the west coast mainline.
But for international listeners, let us simplify.
Just saying it's the last term before Scotland.
So Berwick upon Tweed, very, very northern English town.
It has changed hands 13 times over the last thousand years.
I mean, mostly like centuries ago.
And all the times it changed hands,
it wasn't just being captured in battles.
So in 1174, Scotland gave it to England
because William I had been captured.
And that was part of the ransom is like,
we want Berwick upon Tweed.
Then 20 years later, Scotland bought it back
'cause King Richard needed money for a crusade.
They're like, what can I flog off?
Oh, so Berwick upon Tweed, the Scots love that.
(laughing)
For about 200 years, once every 15 years, it changed hands.
- Do you think the people in Berwick upon Tweed
going about their lives, do you think they ever knew?
- They just say they're from Berwick.
A lot of people there just say I'm a Berwicker, you know.
There's a guy called Derek Sharman,
who's a local historian who says this a lot.
- Derek from Berwick?
- Derek from Berwick upon Tweed.
- He says that basically they're all just Berricas.
And actually, if you're from north of the river
and south of the river, that's kind of a distinguishable
sort of almost nationality as well.
- I was it, that's where the next big civil war
is happening, isn't it?
Edward I, who was the famous antagonist,
the hammer of the Scots.
- Hammer of the Scots.
- Long shanks, lots of nicknames.
He is still in Westminster Abbey,
buried just in a very plain lead casket,
not with the normal regalia of English monarchs.
- Is that to not upset the Scots?
- It's the absolute opposite, James, it's because--
- Oh, no.
- It's a properly wind them up.
- It's a really fucking piss them off.
No, I think it would give the Scots,
it would gratify them, 'cause basically,
he said I don't want to be buried properly
until the Scots are finally conquered.
And they haven't yet finally been conquered.
And so, no one's yet exhumed him
and buried him in a poor basket.
- Did they not consider when we beat them
in Euro 96-21 with that coal gas coin gold?
- People were battering away at Westminster Abbey
with spades.
(laughing)
- How interesting, yeah, Edward I,
the really interesting thing about him
is the Siege of Stirling Castle,
when he got this enormous trebuchet built.
So, a trebuchet is like a catapult,
and it was called the War Wolf.
It was 90 meters tall.
It took three months to build,
and the Scots, when they saw it sort of trundling up,
they went, "Oh, shit."
And they said, "It's okay, we surrender,
"we surrender, we surrender."
And King Edward went, "Oh, I've spent three months
"making this now, so we attack them anyway."
Even though they surrendered.
- Yeah, Deneep, it was basically going,
"Okay, I'm just going to test it though,
"and you're not allowed to leave the castle
"until the test is over."
Good Lord. - Yeah, pretty wild.
- Well, it's a great name, the War Wolf.
- Yeah. - Yeah, that is cool.
- You don't want to waste work like that, do you?
You know, you can see its point.
- We'll just wheel it on to the next place.
- I'll tell you what, the War Wolf was good
against this castle, but it was even better
against the castle made of sticks
and the castle made of straw.
- Hey. (laughs)
- Get it, I get it. - Yeah.
- One of the chief nobles who led the Scottish rebellions
after over the first little land grab there,
he was called Andrew Demore, or Andrew Murray.
- Oh, really? - Oh, really?
- He was like the other William Wallace.
- He was the one who wasn't William Wallace, basically.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - That's Demore.
(all laugh)
- Branickburn is where-- - Freedom.
- Freedom was won. - That was the moment?
- For Andrew Murray here, then deceased, but--
- Was it you or was it William Wallace?
- I think I was dead by this point.
- Right, you were. - I think it was
an earlier battle where I did very, very well, by the way,
but then I got injured and died.
- It was Sterling Bridge, in fact, sadly.
- That's so would be on your tooth, so I did.
- Very well, actually. (all laugh)
- Red like a four-star battle.
(all laugh)
- When you're killed in a fight, but you still did all right,
that's Demore, which has so many battles over the centuries.
It's kind of insane.
Scotland had a huge role in what gets called
the English Civil War, which turns out,
we shouldn't call the English Civil War,
it should be called the War of the Three Kingdoms.
- Is that the War of the Roses,
or is it the War of the Ramtheads versus Cavaliers?
- The War of the Roses ends in 1485,
with Henry III and Battle of Bosworth
and Henry VII taking over.
What gets called the English Civil War
is the 1640s, basically.
It started partly because Charles I,
who was basically a useless,
like imagine a useless king.
- Oh, you thought the Cromwell Kool-Aid, didn't you?
- He's a big floppy, rough, suspicious continental practices.
People worried, he was a Catholic, that kind of stuff.
- Imagine the ironing it took to get to that level.
(laughing)
- He had tried to interfere with the Church of Scotland,
and he'd tried to impose his own prayer books
on the Kirk in 1637.
This went down phenomenally badly.
It led to a thing called the Bishop's Wars,
where it just, like, Ecclesiast people.
- They all attacked diagonally.
(laughing)
- Superb.
- That's the best Bishop this week.
- This week.
- I don't know, you haven't heard parenting hell
this week, haven't you, Andy?
(laughing)
- And Scotland got so angry
about this prayer book difference
that they occupied Northern England,
and he had to not only back down,
he had to pay expenses,
which is so humiliating after a war.
- Pay expenses, what, like, we bought these train tickets
to get down to Leeds, can you?
- Pretty much, yes.
- We've not really, excuse me, 10 pounds 60 at Pratt.
(laughing)
- Who was this, guys?
- It was a sandwich and a drink,
it was expensive these days.
(laughing)
So Charles then had to ask for money from Parliament,
'cause of the war debt that had been imposed,
and that helped kick off the entire Civil War period.
And then at the end of it,
the English Execute Charles, Cromwell, comes in,
and the Scots are furious,
and that leads to another battle,
because they were so angry about,
as they saw it, their king.
Getting a say, chopped off.
- Yeah, I know. - Okay.
Do you know this William Wallace period?
Robert the Bruce.
Robert the Bruce don't hear too much about him these days,
but he influenced something great
in modern popular culture.
Someone was named after him.
- Someone was named after Robert Bruce, Bruce Fawceth.
- No. - Bruce Brinkstein.
- No.
- Robert...
- Mugabe.
- Okay.
- Is that, are we saying that's popular culture?
- Oh, his middle name, Winnie the Pooh.
(laughing)
- Now it's Bruce, and it is in the world of fiction.
- Bruce Almighty.
- Nope.
- Bruce.
- He's the most famous Bruce.
- Bruce Dickinson.
- The guy from Matilda, the fat kid.
- Yes, Anna.
- Bruce Banner from the Hulk.
- You're so close.
- Bruce.
- Superhero.
- Bruce, is he Australian?
- Oh, Bruce Wayne.
- Bruce Wayne.
- Who's Bruce Wayne?
- What do you mean, who's Bruce Wayne?
Oh, you only know Batman.
Okay, so Batman.
- Bruce Wayne is Batman?
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that in 1999,
the first ever TV ad made for Cats was broadcast on ITV
and had an estimated viewership of three million cats.
- Three million.
- Well, the numbers.
- 'Cause the number you sent around was seven million.
- Yeah, but then I did some additional research.
- Interestingly, I have two million.
- I have two million as well.
- I've had to go over my numbers quite a few times.
Basically, this was a commercial that was put together
by whiskers, the cat food people,
and they wanted to put something together
that was specifically for cats,
and so they asked someone what would generate
a cat's interest, and it turns out
an incredibly surreal 40-second animation
full of weird ping noises, little sounds,
a mouse running up, a line going up and down the screen,
very random stuff, and they made a big deal out of it.
It was a big promo thing,
and on the 27th of January, 1999,
there was an announcement just before it was coming on,
a pre-ad to say we were about to play
the first ever ad for Cats.
Get your cat, let's do this.
- I think it was also announced in like the newspapers
and stuff beforehand, 'cause I remember it happening.
- They had to advertise the advert.
It's like clever, really, 'cause you get publicity
out of the fact you're doing an advert.
That's very hard to do.
- They've won a lot of awards, basically, for innovation,
of getting the interest of the people
to make sure that their cats were in.
Now, the numbers are dodgy, obviously.
1999 was a period where it went from viewership
to households, so you don't know how many people
would be in a household.
So 2.2 people per household, roughly,
is what the ratings would suggest we're watching.
- How many cats?
- Well, let's get to Hang on, guys.
Don't have a head on the numbers, okay?
So we know what the numbers were
of the viewing figures that night.
It was 18,520,000.
That's what we're watching.
However, that's viewers, not households, right?
Okay, so if we're talking houses
that might have a cat in it, we've got to look at houses.
Yeah, so let's 2.2 people.
So you've got to bring that down, that number,
basically split that number in half, right?
Then it wasn't just shown on ITV that night.
It was also shown on Channel 4 and Channel 5.
So we need to add those in.
So that's 21.2 million viewers.
Split that in half, it's roughly 10.6 households.
- I'm not counting the Channel 5 viewers
'cause I remember Channel 5 in the '90s
and it was too blurry to make anything out.
- Okay.
- They didn't see any of those inches.
- And how many did it contain a cat,
I suppose, for the next one?
- Well, at that time, it's estimated
that a quarter of all houses in the UK had cats.
- And then what percentage of households
invited their cats into the room to watch when it happened?
- And do they have one cat or two cats?
So most houses had 1.6 cats.
So you then got to add those in.
- It was a gruesome time, the '90s.
- So roughly when you add all those numbers together,
in theory, there could be roughly around 3 million cats
that were in front of a screen in the room.
- So are you having 3 million as your number?
- I'm gonna go for 3 million
because I'm also gonna add in the fact
it was played in America
and so those numbers are gonna add up.
- Can I say, I think the number might be 3 million and one
because I let Harley watch it this week, my cat.
And if you wanna know what she thought of it,
then go on my TikTok or Instagram
'cause I'll put the video up.
- Oh, that's very exciting.
We'll add for another format within our show.
You're doing what the cat people did.
- Yeah, that's what you think is James Harkin, get on there.
- Wow, that's very good.
It was considered a success.
So successful, they released it on video, VHS.
- And I actually found it on eBay.
So this is the first ever commercial for cats.
- Oh my God.
- Officially released by Whiskers, an old VHS.
- Wow.
- And it reads--
- Why is everyone calling it the first ever
as though now we are inundated by cat adverts?
- Well, perhaps at the time they thought
this is gonna be massive, right?
So the back says thousands of cats
across the length and breadth of Britain.
Jumping, staring, cutting--
- Thousands of thousands.
- Thousands of cats.
So one in a thousand viewers of the advert
had any reaction whatsoever.
So yeah, so we don't know the numbers
and they've just muddied the waters even more.
- Amazing.
- It's advertising.
- Yeah, but it did good for them.
It did really good.
- Oh yeah.
You know what else did well for Whiskers?
Eight out of 10 cats.
- Really?
- That's one of theirs.
- Yeah.
- What do you mean that's one of theirs?
- Yeah, so there's a TV show Eight Out of 10 Cats
and Eight Out of 10 Cats does countdown,
but that came from a slogan by Whiskers,
which was, "Eight out of 10 cats prefer our product."
- Really?
- And they ran it for quite a lot of years
until the advertising standards authority
encouraged them to change it.
And they changed it to,
"Eight out of 10 owners who expressed a preference
said that their cat prefers it."
And the problem was that basically
they'd been doing this Eight Out of 10 Cats for ages
and everyone knew at the time.
And then they went up to nine out of 10 cats.
So they did a survey in 2001
and they thought that actually now it's nine out of 10.
And when they did that, the people at Friskies,
who is another cat food company, said,
"Oh, we're not having this."
And they went to the ASA and they said
that this is a biased survey
and it wasn't a fair reflection.
- Well, if it's eight out of 10 owners
who expressed a preference,
that leads to other questions, doesn't it?
How many owners express a preference?
- Absolutely.
- Yeah, that's fair enough.
But does this mean that Jimmy Carr
has to change the title of the show as well, surely?
- Yeah, let's do it.
- Yeah. - Cool.
Let's get in contact.
They were very good whiskers, by the way,
with their promotion in 1999 specifically.
So over in Australia,
there was an Aussie rules footballer called Gary Hawking
who changed his name by depot to whiskers.
And the idea was that as he was playing,
they had no choice but to say,
"Oh, whiskers has got the ball."
- Did they do that or did they just use his old name?
Like that's what happens when football teams
change the name of the stadium to a company name.
People just call it the old name.
- Yep, the AFL were very against calling them whiskers
and really stuck to Gary Hawking.
They were paid a couple of hundred grand
in order to advertise them generally.
And this was a sort of extra move by Gary Hawking
'cause he thought, "It's gonna be funny."
And it made news stories.
It did the job right.
Like that's all that this needs to do.
- It's like when the snooker player, Jimmy White,
changed his name to Jimmy Brown to advertise HP Source.
- Oh, did he? - Yeah.
- One of us should change our names to something.
- I have changed my name years ago to Maserati,
but no one, they keep asking me to stop.
No one here uses it, nightmare.
- Videos actually look cracked, cats.
This TV advert would have looked rubbish
because they see so much better than us.
They see about a hundred frames a second.
So we only need to see 20 frames a second
for stuff to look smooth to us.
And I think TV is about 24 or TV is 30 and films are 24.
So to cats, it's just gonna look like
a series of photographs.
- So cat videos in general,
can you think of a role, famous role
that was inspired by cat videos?
- Catwoman.
- Well, there's no fun if you're gonna get it immediately.
When Anne Hathaway, the actress, she played catwoman.
- It's just 'cause we did the Batman thing together.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Wow.
- But catwoman isn't an actual cat.
- Well, no, but she's gone to justify her fee somehow, Anna.
So she's gonna say, well, I spent a couple of weeks
looking at cat videos online.
Absolutely another million quid.
- Daniel Day-Lewis went for the same party,
just sat there licking his ass for three weeks.
(laughing)
- Thank you, Mr. Day-Lewis.
We've actually received enough half mice.
(laughing)
- But that way going with Hathaway, I'm sorry.
- She fits the suit better.
(laughing)
- That's been done by a bunch of them.
Tom Holland studied the movements of a spider
in order to--
- Such a shit.
- Robert Downey Jr. watched ironing videos non-stop.
(laughing)
- It's something to say in an interview, isn't it?
- You run out of stuff to say in interviews, yeah.
- I read a really good article.
It was like an inside look at
the Waltham Pet Care Science Institute at Melton-Mowbury,
which is the science arm of Mars Pet Care,
which is where all of our pet food comes from.
Mars makes it all.
They go to such great lengths to look after their cats there
and to test really advanced foods on them.
They found out that cats prefer Asian cuisine
because their favorite flavors are,
well, you can probably guess.
- Plum sauce.
(laughing)
- Plum sauce, the same flavor, yeah.
- Umami.
And the new one, kukumi.
- Yeah, kukumi, yeah.
I'm sorry, for those of us not up on our flavors,
what's that?
- So it's, I think it's like fullness and richness.
- Kukumi.
- Yeah, they keep--
- It's not like a flavor so much as an enhanced,
and it is officially a flavor,
but it's like enhances salty things and rising like MSG.
- No, that's sumami.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- And once all the cats are tested on at Melton-Mowbury
at this site, they get taken home and adopted
by one of the people who work there.
- Wow.
- And in other words, they get turned into pot pies.
Yeah, we know what you mean.
(laughing)
- They're very good owners to the extent
that one of the research scientists called Scott McGrane
adopted a cat and then noticed when he took it home
that the cat was a bit perplexed by his telly
'cause they had never seen one before.
And since then they've installed loads of TVs,
a TV room for the cats there.
- Why?
- So that when they get adopted,
they don't get confused by TVs.
- Is that a massive like safeguarding welfare thing
for cats being confused by TVs?
When they go to their forever homes,
is that really a problem for them?
- The RSPCA is clamping down, yes.
- Can I just say Scott McGrane is very much a name
you would come up with if you were trying to come up
with a name for a Scottish person and failing.
(laughing)
- Scott, you've been mentioned on the show this week.
- Listen in.
- You know, cats falling off things
and flipping the right way up and landing on the feet.
- Yeah, they land on the feet.
- So this was a physics puzzle
for much of the 19th century, how it happens.
'Cause there was a scientist called George Gabriel Stokes.
James, you did math, you may have heard of him.
- Yeah, Stokes Equation, I've heard of that.
Yeah, it's about fluid mechanics or something.
- Okay, perfect.
So he was a Lucacean Professor of Maths at Cambridge
and other holders of the role were people like Isaac Newton,
Stephen Hawking. - Oh, Hawking, yeah.
- So big brain, George Gabriel Stokes.
He and his colleague, James Clark Maxwell,
another big physics name, they were there at the same time.
And they could not work out, right, cats,
if you drop them, they fall onto their feet, how?
Because they seem to be violating the law
about the conservation of angular momentum,
which is if something rotates,
it has to have something to rotate against,
which rotates the opposite way, right?
- Yeah, got it.
- So how does the cat rotate with nothing to push against?
- Let's say you jump off a diving board.
You've pushed off against that
and you use that kind of a momentum
to twizz around in the air.
- Exactly.
- But if the cat's just falling, how do they do that?
- Yeah, exactly.
- Can I just ask a further clarifying question?
If I didn't dive off the diving board,
if I let myself just fall forward,
can I swing around to my back?
- I think Andy's about to answer.
- Right, yeah.
- But the judges will mug you down for that, Dan.
(all laughing)
- I've just proved Maxwell's theorem.
- Two, two, George.
(all laughing)
- So this was so interesting,
like how on earth are they doing it?
It turns out what the cats do as they start to drop, right?
It uses its own mass to rotate around.
How?
It flips in its four legs, it pulls them in,
and that means, like a gymnast,
its top half spins faster,
then it flips out its four limbs
and it flips in its back limbs
and now its back half is revolving faster.
And it like switches back and forth between those two,
so it creates its own momentum using its limbs like an athlete.
So that is how the cat rotates.
- And it can do that as quick as falling off this table
that we're recording or something.
- Yeah, right.
- I mean, so quickly.
In 1998, there was an Italian researcher
who dropped a cat called Esther 600 times
and determined that.
- RSPCA had to get involved at some stage.
- They're too busy with the telly thing.
(all laughing)
- Who are you in for?
Introducing a cat to my home
without briefing it about the TV.
- Me, oh no, I dropped mine 600 times.
- Anyway, it came to the very important conclusion.
She could fall on her feet when she was dropped
from anywhere between two and six feet,
but not from one foot.
So it was only from two feet up,
they could do all this math with gymnastics in the air.
- And I read the same thing, Anna, it was so good.
He dropped Esther from the height of one foot
100 times in a row
to make sure she definitely couldn't do it.
And she didn't land on her feet once.
- Yeah.
- It's much bigger than the sample size
that you statistically need.
- I know, he did write in his paper.
I want to thank the cat Esther
for her initial cooperation in this experiment.
(all laughing)
So we didn't get an answer to my question.
Would if I fell off a diving board,
do humans have the muscles to do what cats do?
- I'll hand over to James, he's got a physics degree.
(all laughing)
- I think that you would not be able to do that.
- Maybe not fast enough.
- I would think if you trained for long enough,
you might be able to.
'Cause the physics is there, right?
It is possible, but I think it would take training.
- 'Cause you're not flexible enough,
like we can't shift our bodies like a cat.
'Cause they have got, not extra vertebrae,
but you know what I mean, they can move,
they can very flex a lot.
- They're very flexible, yeah.
- I think, yeah, with training,
other way I thought of it,
and I think I skinned it more than Andy,
so this is probably wrong,
but I thought of it as like squeezing a cat like a sponge.
You know, when you squeeze a sponge out,
you have to turn it in two different directions at once,
don't you?
And that's the only way
that it's going to be able to twist around it.
- Okay, so Dan, stand up.
How easy is it for you to twist your top half
in one direction and your bottom half
in the other direction?
- Yeah, you see like, this part.
Oh, dear.
- Oh, wow.
- Uh-oh.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- Holy moly.
- Oh, wow.
- I'm still doing up there.
- Dan, that is going to be the TikTok craze,
dance craze of 2025.
(laughing)
- Did you film a change?
Can I make a cameo?
- That is amazing.
- Ow.
- I'm sorry about that, Dan.
- No, that's fine.
- Do you think if you were sat holding a cat right now,
and I took a photo,
and then we put it on your dating profile,
people would find you more attractive or less attractive.
Let's say women.
- Okay, well, first off,
my wife doesn't know about that account.
So let's, yeah, I'd say they think you're more attractive.
- With a cat?
- Absolutely.
- I would say maybe less.
- Yeah, Anna.
- I asked the woman in the room, I'm going to say less.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Yeah, it's a good feeling.
- Women view men as less masculine,
higher in neuroticism, agreeableness and openness,
but less datable.
- I wonder if I'm not getting any swipes.
- Friend material.
- Less flexible.
No, it doesn't.
(laughing)
- And is there like a league table of animals?
Like if I pose with a water bowl, am I?
(laughing)
- Oh yeah.
- Or a mink, or a koala must be?
- Do you remember when you did your first Edinburgh show,
and I wanted you to do a poster
where you were completely naked,
but with a water bowl over your privates,
and we were going to call it socks and gloves
and cock and bowl.
- Yeah, I do, I do.
(laughing)
- Why did you never go for that?
- Why did you not do that?
- Just ran out of time on the shoot, mate.
(laughing)
- That's such a shame, I had the vault.
- Can I ask James a question?
- Yeah.
- As the cat owner in the room.
- Do you want a cat owner, no?
- Half done in the past.
- Okay, well as a current cat owner, James,
would you buy a matching outfit for yourself and your cat?
- No, my cat only wears what God gave her.
- Okay.
- And she insists on not being ironed every day
since she's so very different.
- No, I would never buy clothes for animals really.
- Then you're part of the nine in 10 in your age group
who would not buy a matching outfit for yourself
and your cat, whereas a third of 19 to 28 year olds
would do that.
- Really?
- Yeah, that's the Instagram generation, isn't it?
- Would they be able to get the clothes on the cat, though?
That's my question.
- I don't know, it depends on the clothes, doesn't it,
as well, if it's a shapeless sort of Bernouce
or a Moomoo or something, it might be quite easy.
(laughing)
- I don't know why the two items of clothing
came to my mind were a Bernouce or a Moomoo.
- What are they?
- What is a Bernouce?
- It's a sort of North African desert car business.
Lawrence of Arabia might have got around in a Bernouce.
- Have you ever seen that show, "Mr. and Mrs."
where you write it down and your partner's gonna have
to guess what you said?
One, two items of clothing as Andy.
- I'm gonna go for shirts and pats, I'm afraid not.
He went for a Bernouce.
(laughing)
- You must be kicking yourself.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that America's
newest of the year, 1973, who also invented a contraption
that allowed him to sunbathe in sub-zero temperatures
was a man called Dick Bacon.
- The name's Bacon.
- Dick Bacon.
- What a guy.
- Oh, Dick Bacon is an absolute legend.
So I found this in an obituary of Dick Bacon.
- You always find out about these people too late, right?
- He spent his life on Lake Michigan sunbathing
and anyone who has been to Lake Michigan
or lives there knows that in the winter
it gets very, very cold.
But the newspaper said that he set up a series
of reflective shields to protect him from the wind
and inside the temperature would get
high enough for him to tan.
- Still gonna be pretty cold, though, isn't it?
And it was naked, wasn't it?
- He was actually usually bathed in a small swimsuit
but that was just to keep on the right side of the law
and he definitely preferred to be nude.
He began his nudism when he was 25.
He worked as a live model at the University of Wisconsin
but he didn't want tan lines.
He thought it was unfair on the people drawing him
that they had to draw in the tan lines.
So he thought, well, I'm just gonna not wear any clothes
anymore, that's amazing.
And he basically just went, okay, how do I make it
so that every single day I can be out there
all year round?
So he worked in a brewery.
He always took the second and third shifts in there.
So he always had the morning free.
So he was a morning...
- That's interesting.
- So just every day, go get the sun as it's going up.
He married someone and he had this line
that I just absolutely love.
He met this girl and she said, "What's your name?"
And he replied, "Bacon, wanna strip?"
And that works on two levels.
- Yeah, I think...
- Like a strip of bacon.
And strip hasn't taken your clothes off.
- I'm a nudist.
Let's go strip.
Wow, that's just a wonderful double entendre.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It's very strong.
- That is good.
- In fact, it's better than fancy some porky.
(laughing)
- It's better than that.
- It is better than that.
He won nudist of the year in 73, like I said,
but he won that by accident.
(laughing)
- No, stop.
- Okay, he did.
- He did too far.
- He did.
- He just so happened to be in this place called Naked City
when the competition was taking place.
He didn't deliberately go there for the competition.
And he said after his win,
they interviewed him in the newspapers
and they said that he was aiming to reach his natural color.
Although the Daily Herald where I read this said
that he was already a deep red.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- The idea of having a natural color is a bit weird,
isn't it?
Do we have a natural color?
- Yeah, good point.
- 'Cause you turn, it depends
whether you've been in the sun or not.
- Yeah, exactly.
- My natural color is incredibly pale,
but that's because I haven't been in the sun.
- Well, you're looking tan today, I would say.
- Well, I'm trying to sort that out.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I thought that's why I got this Bernouce with me.
(laughing)
He was arrested a lot, Mr. Bacon.
- He was, yeah.
- For nude bathing and lewd and lascivious behavior,
but he was a campaigner.
He was saying this isn't harming people.
This is a natural, healthy,
almost sporting way of living in harmony with the elements.
I completely backed that.
- And he was in very good shape.
In fact, I was recently on a nudist beach,
a partially nudist beach, not by choice.
- Partly nudist, that's just a beach.
(laughing)
You were on a partially nudist beach, not by choice.
The plot is thickening.
- I was on a beach where a lot of people were nudist,
including myself, but there were a lot of nudists.
And it's completely fine,
but they're not all in amazing shape,
whereas he was like a gladiator, wasn't he?
- Yeah, I guess he would be
if he won all the awards that he has.
- Well, he won Mr. Nude America.
He won Mr. Nude Apollo, Mr. Nude Galaxy.
- Are any of these awards big awards?
- The galaxy?
Yeah, I think it might be.
- Yeah.
- You know, if you put fact 50 sun cream on,
will it stop your skin aging?
- I guess so, probably.
- Or make it age more slowly?
Nothing can stop your skin aging, guys.
- Well, I would have thought that UV rays might age your skin
and so the lotion might stop that.
- Yeah, you're more leathery, right?
- They absolutely do age your skin, but only UVA waves.
So what they don't tell you on the sun creams
is that when they say the factor,
UV rays are split into UVA and UVB
and it's basically about the wavelengths.
So UVB have shorter wavelengths
and they're the ones that cause sunburn
and they're the most carcinogenic.
So when you've got factor X sun cream,
it's just blocking the UVB rays or sorry, reducing them,
but it doesn't refer to UVA
and they're the ones that cause skin aging.
They're the ones that go deeper
and make you wrinkly and crusty.
So you need to look at the star rating as well.
If you want to not go wrinking, crusty.
- I've never seen a star rating on my sun cream.
- They often don't have them.
- Do they not?
- If they don't have a star rating,
does that mean they don't protect against the UVA?
- I think I believe it does, yeah, careful.
- Okay, can I run a tanning practice past you guys?
- Yes, please.
- Have any of you heard of or you two done testicle tanning?
- Jesus Christ, was it last week or the week before
when you were talking about perineal tanning?
- Yeah, testicle tanning is completely different.
- Of course.
- This is actually, it's not sunlight.
You don't have to go down to the beach and bury yourself.
- I always, I do do that, but I always iron mine first.
(laughing)
It does take one of those 40 kilogram irons to get them flat.
- This is actually, it's not even a real tanning.
It's a very dubious medical thing.
It's just blasting red light at your knackers
and claiming that it'll improve your testosterone
and a load of male energy and hormones and stuff.
- Is that, and people are doing this,
are they, in their bucket loads?
- Not, thankfully, I don't think it's very popular,
but it is the kind of thing that a lot of dubious Americans
have basically glommed onto and started saying is a good idea.
And it's not done.
- Well, unless you want to save the poor life drawing class,
which apparently was Dick Bacon's motivation,
you can't draw two shades of skin color.
(laughing)
Well, this is very similar to perineum tanning.
- Which we did talk about a couple of weeks ago.
- Right under the podcast, very scientifically.
- Yeah, but I wasn't there.
And so I insist on revisiting it.
And there was something I found interesting about this
'cause it's mostly obviously just a TikTok nonsense thing
where there's like one person who says it's a really good
thing to expose your bum hole to the sun.
And after 30 seconds, you get the same benefits
that you get exposing your body for a day and it's nonsense.
And there is Josh Brolin, the actor, put a thing up saying--
- So he's Thanos and Avengers.
And yeah, no country for old men.
He's in that if you want to picture his face.
- Yes, and he put a thing up that--
- That is the part of who I want to picture,
I must have been in this fact.
(laughing)
- Thanos, more likely.
- He said, "Don't try this on your Thanos
because I did it and my pocket hole is crazily burnt."
I mean, he obviously didn't, he's taking the piss.
I assume he's not an insane person.
But what I quite like is that, you know,
conspiracy theories always come from a kernel of truth.
And the woman who started this said,
"It's an ancient Taoist practice
to bathe your bum hole in the sun."
And actually, it does come from this idea in Taoism.
So Taoism is like ancient Chinese philosophy, basically.
And the Hui Yin is the collection point
of all Yin energy in your body.
And that is your perineum.
So all of Yin, you know, you got Yin and Yang,
the two opposing forces that work together.
Yin is all gathered in your perineum.
And they do believe that it's good to bathe
in sunlight and moonlight for wellness.
And so, you know, there's a kernel of truth in this bullocks.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Brazil, home of great tanning culture.
- Yeah.
- Do you know what the fashionable bikini is
to wear in Brazil at the moment?
- Is it like a full body, like a bikini,
but it's very, very stiff.
So your arms go out like Christ the Redeemer.
- Oh, wow. - That's true.
- It's a stanched banoosophagus.
(both laughing)
- Is it?
- Well, okay.
Like Brazilian.
- Yeah.
- You would think, okay, very thongy.
- It's very thongy.
- Oh, is it that borat one?
Is it that big? - It's not the mankini.
- Not the mankini.
- What's it made of?
What fabric is it made of?
- Cashmere.
- No.
(both laughing)
- I love it.
- I know.
Spider silk.
- Just one piece of spider silk up the crack.
(both laughing)
- Oh, you already feel that.
The aim of it is to give you
incredibly crisp turn lines.
- So something that blocks all of the--
- It blocks really effectively.
- So like a lead or a hazmat suit.
- I'm gonna tell you.
I'm gonna tell you.
- Yeah.
- It's electrical tape.
- Do you give yourself a Brazilian when you take it off?
- Well, what you need is this thing,
the Marquina De Fita, the little tape mark,
and you go to a salon,
they will put literally tape a bikini onto you,
and they'll give you a little bit of fabric
for your nips and stuff like that.
- Of course, 'cause I was thinking like,
lead is the same as the swimming costume.
They all block it, but what you need is for your body
not to be able to shift underneath it at all.
Is that right?
- Exactly, so it's just that one bit of skin
that is covered with the fabric.
- So you could super glue your swimming costume
to yourself as well.
- Well, look, there are all sorts of roads to the answer.
Yes, but this is--
- But this is the biggie?
- There are salons where you just go
and people go up to the roof.
You pay about eight quid,
which includes a breakfast buffet.
- What?
- I would do this.
- Eight quid?
- I know how cheap that is, travel lunch.
- You're not gonna be--
- And they don't do anything to your nips.
- You're not gonna be beach body ready
after a full English.
(laughing)
- Yeah, and then people lie there
and they spray you with water every now and again
and that's how you get those incredibly crisp lines.
- Hey, sugar nips.
- Thank you, yes, sweetie possum, yes, go on.
Do you know what sugar nips are?
I read this today and I'd never heard it before.
- No, I thought it was just something,
how you used it just then.
- Me too, right?
So sugar nips were like a little pair of scissors
you would use.
And if you had a block of sugar in your house
or sugar loaf, they would call it.
In fact, sugar loaf mountain just outside Rio,
but you would have a sugar loaf on your table
and you would use your sugar nips
to nip off a little bit of sugar.
- That's incredible.
- Wow.
- Yeah, I'd never heard that before.
- That is a kind, that's 'cause you guys know
I like a rare bit of croqueries, cutlery.
- I'm surprised and disappointed
that you weren't familiar with them
and in fact don't own a pair, Andy.
- No, and I'm actually now regretting it
'cause I could have bought you some for your birthday.
- I'm gonna hop straight on eBay after this
to go with the asparagus tongs and the butter spade.
- Probably when you Google sugar nips.
(laughing)
- I'll take my chances.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with us
about the things we've said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our very social media accounts.
I'm on Shriverland on Instagram, James.
- My TikTok, no such thing as James Harkin.
- Andy.
- I'm on Instagram @andruhonderem.
And Anna, to get to us as a group, they go too.
- You can go to Instagram @nosuchthingasafish
or @nosuchthingontwitter or email podcast@qi.com.
- Yeah, and check out our website.
We've got a kick-ass website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
All our previous episodes are up there.
There's lots of merch that you can buy up there.
You can see if we're gonna be doing any live shows
in the coming year.
Check it out there.
And of course, there's Club Fish,
which is our wonderful hidden private members club
where we put a lot of bonus episodes up and so on.
It's great fun, check it out.
Otherwise, just come back here next week.
We'll be back with another episode
and we will see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)