Hello and welcome to another episode of "No Such Thing as a Fish Presents International Factbowl"
brought to you by the QIELS in association with visitingland.com
My name's Andy and I'm here with three of the QIELS.
They are in no particular order, Anna, James and Anne.
And today's match is a humdinger, it's going to be Italy versus Switzerland.
So, there's the whistle, interesting facts about Italy. Take it away.
I love the fact that in Italy they have a word for the Act symbol,
which we kind of don't want, it's commonly used, and their word is "Tiocchiola",
which means snail, because obviously it looks like a snail.
- That is very good. - It's nice.
And paparazzi, the word paparazzi, you guys know what that means in Italian?
- Is it buzzing insect? - Yeah, it's buzzing mosquito.
- It's from La Dolceviacita, isn't it? - Yeah, it's named after the paparazzi character.
- Turumasu means "pick me up". - Yes.
- Susie, you're right, she lunches, she gets you through there.
- If you want to pick me up, yeah.
I read that confetti, obviously it's in Italian sounding world,
but it was also invented in Italy, but it was originally candid spices
and Italian families would throw it from their balconies to the crowds below.
- Oh, that's cool. - That's good, yeah.
A 10% of all food stolen in Italy is parmesan cheese. Wow.
- It is pretty pricey.
When McDonald's first opened in Italy,
they opened in Roman 1986, and everyone was furious.
And the designer Valentino tried to close it down, because it was too noisy,
and there was an unbearable smell of fried fruit fouling the air.
- That's great. - What? That doesn't sound like McDonald's, I know.
- I read the grand opening of their McDonald's.
People stood outside handing out pasta.
- Yes, it is what... - There was a traditional Italian food
and they said, "This is what you should be eating, none of these burgers."
- Even now, they don't want foreign food coming into Italy.
There was a politician called...
I don't know what his first name was, I think, is Mr. Zaya.
And he was trying to stop all foreign food from coming in,
and someone asked him, "Have you ever eaten a cabab?"
And he said, "No, and I defy anyone to prove the contrary."
I prefer the dishes of my native Veneto, and I even refuse to eat a pineapple.
- Wow. - That is great.
- Yeah, pineapple pizza. - Pineapple pizza. - Oh, yeah.
- And the other thing, tomatoes are native to Italy, are they?
- Well, pasta isn't a traditional Italian dish at all.
It was brought over by the Arabs in the 13th century, wasn't it?
And they adopted it as their own.
But it used to be eaten with honey and sugar.
Before the 17th, 18th century, pasta wasn't eaten with tomato sauce.
It was dipped in honey and sugar. - Oh, I don't want to try that.
- Mussolini wanted all Italians to eat rice, not pasta.
And he had a national day for rice.
And there was the national rice board, which brought free bags of rice to people.
And it really wanted to encourage them, so they could be self-sufficient.
- Do they also have a national cheese board? - Very good.
My favorite kind of Italian pasta is strasopretti,
which are these little things which I think they look like corn.
And the literal translation for strasopretti is priest stranglers.
- Not cool. - Didn't chew a batter mean slipper?
- Yes, it does. - And it was invented really recently, as well.
- Yeah, 1982. - 1982, yeah.
- My favorite Italian food fact is actually also a football fact.
Maybe it's not allowed. - No, I love it.
- We average about one football fact per podcast, so I don't worry about that.
- Okay, can I claim this week's?
There was a football match.
It was Scotland versus Italy.
And the Scotland fans chanted, "We're going to deep fry your pizzas."
- Speaking about football chants, there was a match.
It was nappily against Verona.
And the Verona fans were singing, "We hope that Vesuvius goes off."
And the nappily fans were singing "Juliette is a whore."
- Wow. Wow.
- Okay, I have a question for you.
Name something that happened in Italy between the 5th and 14th of October 1542.
- A new Pope. - No.
- Was Leonardo da Vinci died? - Nothing.
- Did they have a calendar jump and they switched their days?
- Exactly, nothing happened.
Nothing happened between the 5th and the 14th of October in that year.
Pope Gregory ordered that those days should not happen
so that they can make up for previously inaccurate calendars
and get with the program.
- Do you know where the easiest place to get cocaine in Italy is?
- Yes, but I cannot tell you on this podcast,
because the next time I go, it'll be swamped.
- No, the easiest place is the air.
Researchers have tested the air in Rome
and found that there are traces of cocaine,
also cannabis, nicotine and caffeine.
- He's walking around with your mouth open, like a bear trying to catch that.
- And the cocaine just jumps in.
- The mafia is still very dominant, isn't it, in Italy?
I think 80% of small businesses in the capital of Sicily pay a pizza,
protection money? - 80%.
- 80%. It's a lot, isn't it?
Across the whole of Southern Italy,
the mafia makes more than 20 billion a year through extortion.
- Whoa. - And Coulieroni,
Coulieroni, the town in Sicily, has got a petition to change its name
because of the negative connotations.
- Oh, nice air. - Yeah.
- Speaking of the mafia, did you hear the terrible thing that they did last year?
They kidnapped the world's smallest pony.
- Oh, not bad. - And not bad in someone's bed?
- That is too far.
- They believe that a very small bet.
- It was 63 centimeters tall animal named Charlie,
and he was taken from his stall in Citadel Castello.
- Did they get him back?
- I'm not sure, actually. I couldn't find.
- If anyone knows what happened to Charlie, you can call this number.
- Charlie, if you're out there, we're not angry.
Okay, just come back. - We're just disappointed.
- Okay, that means that at halftime,
it's time for our mid-match quiz,
brought to you by VisitEngland.com.
We've got three questions relating in some way or another to England,
so who would like to go first?
- I have one. - Yeah, Anne.
- I had a brilliant time a few weeks ago.
I went to Cadbury World in Birmingham,
and they had lots of great information,
and they had a bit about how the Mayans use cocoa beans as currency.
They didn't have coins,
so it cost two cocoa beans for a pumpkin,
but how many for a rabbit?
- Okay, Anne's is on a postcard. James?
- Okay, my question is, in old Cheshire,
what did they mean when they said "sparrow farts"?
- Do they mean the farts of sparrows?
- Maybe you'll have to tune in to find out.
- I'm gonna be here. - Oh, yeah.
- Anna?
- So during World War II,
for what did MI6 use human semen?
- Oh, I thought it was most of the navy who you see.
- Very good.
- Okay, so that's the halftime quiz over,
so we will give away the answers at the end,
and now it's time for the second half of the match,
which is Switzerland.
- Every year they have an annual Santa Claus World Championship,
called Toe World.
- Is this our Santa Claus? It's selected.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Is it? - Yeah, there's gonna be a channel five reality show coming soon.
- Switzerland is the only country to have enough nuclear shelters
for its entire population.
- Wow. - Wow, yeah.
You can't name your child,
pineapple or banana or fairy tale or whatever it is
that everyone who's famous these days names their children
if you're in Switzerland, because you have to choose
from them and approve a list of baby names.
- But the country has been neutral since about the mid-14th century.
They used to be quite an aggressive territorial expansionist power,
and then they had one really unpleasant battle
or a few battles in the 14th century.
And they said, "Right, actually, we're not doing this anymore."
And they just formed the boundaries,
almost completely in modern Switzerland soon after that,
and they just have not gone involved since then.
- They have had the odd little battle in between themselves,
the cantons. - Oh, yeah.
- There was a battle between Zurich and Zug,
rather nicely, in 1529.
War was declared, but before any fighting could take place,
the two teams or the two groups of soldiers sat down,
settled their differences and called off the war,
and the soldiers from both sides sat on the border
and shared a cauldron of milk soup.
- Wow.
One thing I really like is that senior soldiers in the Swiss Army,
they have flowers instead of stars.
I made you general who would have two stars on his epilets
in other NATO countries,
would have two Adelweiss on his epilets in Switzerland.
- Oh, that's good. - That's awesome.
Speaking of keeping yourself to yourself,
I read about a block of flats near Zurich.
This is for people who claim to suffer
from hypersensitivity to chemicals
and electromagnetic radiation,
and there are apartments there that have been designed specifically,
so there's no smoking, no perfume, no mobile phones,
and it's supposed to be for people who find
that they're allergic to modern life.
- I might use allergic to modern life,
as my excuse for not being on Twitter hence.
- One thing I love about Switzerland
is that the racking vac falls where Sherlock Holmes
fell to his death are in Switzerland.
So the Sherlock Holmes society go on a pilgrimage
to the racking vac falls where they reenact the fall,
but with dummies, not with real people.
And one thing I learned from reading about it
was that apparently in 1910,
Sherlock Holmes books were banned from station booksellers,
because they're having a bad effect on the Swiss youth.
- What? - Apparently jumping off the falls, possibly.
- They weren't all just smoking pipes
and wearing those funny hats.
- And solving crime in a slightly annoying way.
- Yeah, so Switzerland was where Conan Doyle,
Arthur Conan Doyle popularised skiing.
I think he'd discovered it on holiday in Norway,
and then he was in Switzerland, and he looked around
and thought, "Look, mountains, snow.
"I know what I'm gonna do here."
And he found two other people in Switzerland that skied,
but they could only ski by night,
because they were mocked so massively by the Swiss masses,
for doing such a weird thing.
But then Conan Doyle was a big popular guy,
and he started doing it in a court of honor.
- Yeah, skiing by night doesn't sound particularly safe, does it?
- No, I guess that's why people mock them.
- But that's where the very brightly coloured ski wear began.
- Yeah.
- Okay, so one really fun thing.
This is a lot of my facts are from a book called Swiss Watching,
I read last year, which is really good.
So if you're into Switzerland, I recommend you read it.
In Switzerland, people tend to rent their graves
for about 20 or 25 years, rather than buying them,
and then the spaces used again.
And all the old headstones are broken up to make gravel.
But the idea is there's so little space,
'cause Switzerland is so mountainous, there's almost no flat space,
and when there's a limited amount of space
for people to die in, basically.
- And there's youth in Asia's legal.
They're dropping like flies, so...
- They should do like they do in Tibet,
just put their bodies up at the top of their mountains
and let the birds eat them.
- That's gonna traumatise the skiers.
- Well, Swiss celebrity is a six-legged calf called Lily,
who I would urge everyone to look up, 'cause she's...
- Well, Lily the calf, go.
- Yes, so we're just two extra legs hanging off her back.
- And she's a celebrity, you say.
- Yeah, they don't have a lot going for them.
- No, well, which program does she...
- I think she hosts a 10 o'clock news, really, yeah.
- Either they don't have many celebrities,
or they've got so many that literally even a six-legged cow
can achieve fame.
- All right, I'm a celebrity, get these legs on me.
- For the animal welfare, it's this brilliant fact
that you aren't allowed to keep a solitary guinea pig
in Switzerland.
- Oh. - You have to give it a friend.
If you're a guinea pig, dies.
You're two. You can rent one.
If you mate, so you're one.
- We're coming out to full-time now,
so any extra facts that you want to get them in?
Get them in now.
- In 1474, a rooster in Switzerland
was prosecuted by law in the city of Basel for laying an egg.
Because obviously roosters can't lay eggs.
Now, in modern interpretation, might say,
it was actually a chicken that had been passing for a rooster.
But the animal was sentenced in a solemn judicial proceeding
and condemned to be burned alive
for the heinous and unnatural crime of laying an egg.
The execution took place, according to eyewitness accounts,
with as great solemnity as it would have been observed
in consigning a heretic to the flames
and was witnessed by an immense crowd of townsman and peasants.
- It was witnessed by a great number of peasants
who were cooking vegetables at the same time.
- Pravee, preparing a white wine sauce.
- That's the final whistle, so now it's time for the answers
to our mid-match quiz brought to you by visit england.com
and your question was first.
- So, my question was the Mayans use cocoa beans as currency
so they didn't have coins.
And it took two cocoa beans for a pumpkin.
How many for a rabbit?
- It'll be 10 cocoa beans to buy a rabbit.
- Although legally, in the Mayan culture,
I think you had to buy two rabbits by law.
- So that is the 20s.
- So it's always got a new 20s.
- Wow, great fact.
You're in the Capri's world.
- Capri world, next long place.
- James, my question was in old Cheshire,
what did the word "sparrow farts" mean?
And it meant very early in the morning.
- Yeah, you would be up with the sparrow farts.
- Nice. - Anna?
- My question was in World War II,
what did MI6 use human semen for?
And they used it, well, I guess one of the functions it had
was to be used as invisible ink for transmitting letters.
Yes, it is so.
- God, even Fleming didn't write that up in the James Conberg stiny.
Bond dipped his quail into the ink well.
Okay, there are your answers.
And if you'd like to win a load of QI goodies,
we've got lots of things which we are giving away via
thevisitengling.com website.
So check it out and you can see what there is for you to win there.
So at the end of the match, I'm going to give the arbitrary job of picking a winner
to Anna, Anna, who wins?
- I am going to go with Switzerland,
because don't want my bankier being shut down.
- Excellent.
Okay, that's everything from today.
We hope you've enjoyed listening.
If you'd like to get hold of any of us,
you can do so on Twitter and is on...
- I'm Miller_Anne.
- James is at Headshaped.
- I'm at Andrew Hunter M.
Anna is still not on Twitter,
but if you want to...
- If you want, you can tweet @quikipedia and I'll reply to you there.
- Okay, we have another match coming up tomorrow,
which is James.
- That will be Nigeria versus Bosnia and Herzegovina.
- Well, one against two, all right.
Hope you've enjoyed listening.
Thanks very much, Antunim, for another one of these tomorrow.