[Theme Music]
Hello, and welcome to another episode of "No Such Thing as a Fish" a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Culvernt Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with Anichesinski, James Harkin, and Alex Bell.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in an open-tacular order, here we go, starting with you, James.
My fat this week is that scientists at MIT have invented an artificial intelligence that can see into the future,
but it can only tell two seconds into the future.
[Laughter]
Totally useless.
What's it reported about?
It knew you were going to say that.
[Laughter]
So this is really cool, so what they did was, they got this algorithm to watch TV shows like the office and the Big Bang Theory.
Okay, and it watched what people did when they met each other, so did you go in for a hug or a kiss or a handshake or a high-five,
and then when you showed them a picture of two people coming near each other, it could work out what they were going to do,
whether they were going to high-five, whether they were going to hug, whether they were going to kiss, or whatever.
So that's basically as far as this has gone so far.
It's still pretty good for an AI.
Yeah, and I'm surprised it was able to do this based on the office and the Big Bang Theory, both of which are about totally socially inept people.
I wouldn't have thought given those correct views.
It's not the best source material to use for an AI.
Maybe it may be AI feel more comfortable watching something closer to their kind of robotic way, so it's like, okay, we're not so different.
You and us humans.
Yeah, and also, I think that is quite a useful thing, because how many times have you gone in for a hug to someone and they tried to high-five you and slap you in the face or...
Or the kiss/hanshake thing is pretty awkward at times.
Well, in the article, it said that the AI could only get it right 42% of the time, which I was reading wasn't very high, but then I realized I get it right about maybe 2% of the time.
Apparently, normal humans get it right 71% of the time, but obviously that doesn't apply to you.
I think as Alex goes in for the kiss every single time.
And it will get better, won't it, because it'll keep on watching. It'll get better, and 43% of the time versus 71% of the time is not that bad.
Considering all they've done is got it to watch these two things, whereas most humans have had a lot of social interaction to get to where we are, which is still not that good.
The thing it might do in hospitals, if it gets really good, is anticipate a couple of seconds in advance, whether someone, for instance, is about to fall over, like an old person on the way to the loo, and then swoop in and catch them.
Maybe they should show him lots of episodes of Miranda, where she falls down all the time, would you like to learn that?
Intermediate level, you can see it coming right off.
If it weren't Miranda, it would try to save you every step you took.
Yeah, if you sort of missed a bean episode, it would probably either explode or not let you out the house, so check this out.
There's another AI robotic thing, which plays scissors paper, rock, and beats humans 100% of the time.
- No, it has 100%. - 100% breaks the rules, though. It makes me so angry at this machine.
- It doesn't break the rules. - Yeah, it does. It waits to see what you're doing, and then very quickly...
No, no, no, no, no. No, that's not quite right, because it technically is doing that, but if you're a good game player as well, you would be looking at someone's hand to monitor where you think they're going to go.
So it has a camera on it, which is able to work out hand movements of people and what most likely handshake they're about to take, but it can make a split second decision so that it's at the same time.
It's a microsecond afterwards, because it's seen the way your hand is moving, so it's decided a microsecond afterwards.
- Is it not indistinguishable to humans? - Of course, but it is cheating.
- It is because rock paper scissors is fundamentally a game of chance. It's like a coin source, you're supposed to try and...
- You use it to decide things that way. - No, because all it's doing is it's calling your tell, it's seeing the handshake that you're bringing.
- It's not cheating. - It is. A hundred percent of the time becomes cheating, because you can work out what's more or less likely.
- I mean, it's cracked it. It knows how to win a game. It's done the impossible.
- This is war. - Wait, what did James say? What do you think?
- Do you know how we should decide it? - I think it is.
It does look like you're about to high-five done, but I'm not sure what's going to happen.
- So, Robot was arrested recently in September for taking part in a political rally.
It seems a bit dodgy. This was in Russia, and this is actually a robot that I think might have come up before.
You guys might have heard about its promo bot, and it's the one that escaped from its enclosure twice in, I think, about July this year.
- Oh, yeah, but didn't we work out that that was actually... - That's done.
- ...the clues in the name, promo. - Yeah, the clues in the name.
But then it did it again, and then the mechanics at promo bot said that they were trying to reprogram it to stop it escaping.
- Okay. - So, they're just really sticking to their story.
- Right. - But now it's taken part in a political rally,
because this robot-supported parliamentary candidate, Valerie Kalachev,
so he went to Moscow and started collecting people's views on politics, asking them what they thought.
- Again, it escaped you did it by itself. I was just going around interviewing people.
- I believe it might have been programmed to do this part. - A dream to be a political correspondent.
- After it was arrested, did it escape from prison?
- It probably has done now, yeah. - They did put handcuffs on it, apparently.
- They must have, like, idiots, those policemen handcuffing a robot.
- That would have been a fun moment of, and otherwise,
probably depressing, arresting situation.
- I guess you're right. - That's one of the hardest-to-career.
- I mean, I had to handcuff, you know, 25 people at a political protest,
but I did handcuff a robot, and that actually really made me smile.
- This is just one bit of delay. - You're right.
- Also, in robot news, they have set this year in July a new dancing robot
Guinness World Record, 1,000 and 7 robots danced together for a minute,
and that was what was needed.
And so it was synchronized. You can see a video online.
- It did. - It was in China, and it was a Qingdao beer festival.
So I guess they were trying to just get headlines for it.
But you can see all these tiny little robots,
lots of kinds that you would buy in a shop that make sort of small movements.
They're all doing a dance, and some fall over, so they're discounted,
but they're still dancing while they're top there.
- You know those like flour, and when you play music,
they just kind of dance to the music.
Do you remember them from the 90s? - Yes.
- If you put 1,050 of those down, would that be able to technically beat the record?
- I think they're effectively, that's the robots,
effectively, that they used anyway. - They were built to dance.
They can't do anything else. - Yeah, so they put down 1,040,
but they lost 33. - I have danced with a robot.
- You have a robot? - You have Asimov, right?
- Asimov. - Sorry, Asimov.
No, yeah, we had Asimov who was built by Honda, I think, was he?
And he came on QI, and during the warm-up,
I did a little dance with him, and he kind of just follows your dance patterns,
I think. I think that's how it worked.
- I know a thing about Asimov, which a guest on our show,
from quite a few episodes ago, "Leave and Skyra", Belgian comedian and scientist.
He was telling me that Asimov, they've programmed him to speak something like,
I don't know, let's say 30 languages, it might be less,
so that whenever they bring him over to different countries for conferences,
he's able to do a lecture in their language.
But he has one special setting for when he's in Italy,
which is that they've programmed his arms to gesticulate,
so that when he's talking, it feels more,
because that's how in Italy, they feel more humanized
than the robot standing still. - That's quite cool.
- Yeah, I love it. - And he's also worships the office,
so you can do the David Brent dance.
- Okay, here's something amazing about telling the future.
- Okay. - There was a study done by a US intelligence group
called the Good Judgment Project, and what they did is they got a load of people,
about more than 2,000 people, and they started asking them
of things about world events, like, will Robert Mugabi still be
the head of Zimbabwe in two years' time, or whatever?
Like, a load of different things, and a load of people may guess is,
and eventually they siphoned off the top 2% who were doing the best,
and then they put them in a separate group and compared them to everyone else,
and found that that group was four times more accurate than anyone else,
and they're saying that this proves that in humans,
there is a thing called super forecasters,
and these are people who are better than normal humans
at first seeing the future. - Wow.
- And are they all on bright and pure with a crystal ball,
charging people £10 to make their fortune?
- It's weird, they all had different jobs, like,
one of the best ones was a pharmacist,
they come from different walks of life and everything.
- So when you surround these people up and take them out of the met office,
they should all be the weather forecasters,
if they're gentle, it's definitely better.
- Well, God, is that how you would use people who have this incredible,
the right new world order?
- Without a human who could see into the future.
- Take him to the met office immediately.
- His warning is about a massacre, and no, no, is it going to be cloudy?
- Apparently what these guys are particularly good at is being open-minded,
which you can kind of imagine, it means that they don't let their world views
judge their predictions, and also they change their mind fast and often.
So whenever...
- To correct their wrong prediction?
- Yeah, well it is, kind of like that.
So they get something wrong, one time, and a normal human might kind of stubbornly stick
with the same similar kind of predictions, but then these people go, well actually,
you know, I've seen that that happens in the past now, so I'm going to change my mind this time.
- Oh, okay, I was thinking more like football matches, where they're like,
okay Manchester United is going to win this one, Liverpool School night.
- Do you know what, I'm actually thinking that maybe...
- Oh, I'm going to go for rock, no scissors.
- We need to put one of those people against the machine.
- (laughs)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Alex.
- My fact this week is that Big Ben is falling over.
- We should get out of here.
- We're not that close.
- No, we're out of reach.
- Yeah, yeah, what do you mean?
- Okay, well technically the Elizabeth Tower, not Big Ben, obviously, don't write in.
But when they built it, when they built the House of Parliament,
they built it straight obviously, and then I think as soon as the building settled,
it was a little bit leany, and it's got linear and linear, as in,
it's been leaning over more and more away from the House of Parliament,
and they've worked out that if it keeps falling over, at the rate it is falling over,
in about 4,000 years time it'll be leaning as much as the leaning tower of Pisa.
- Really? How many years?
- 4,000, so it's not like super urgent.
- So they are going to restore it now, aren't they?
There's this big House of Parliament restoration going on, which is costing billions,
and they're about to start working on that as well, the Elizabeth Tower.
So anyone overseas who wants to see it, and it's pure unscatholded form,
you better get over quick, because beginning of January 2017,
they're going to start scaffolding it.
Yeah, and it's going to be scaffolded for three years,
but it's going to take six months to just put the scaffolding up.
- Is that nice? Yeah, six months.
- What, and they're going to push it back the right way?
- No, I think they're doing basic restoration.
I don't think they can do anything about that.
- I don't know, but it's causing cracks in the offices next to it,
because it's basically pulling the wall away.
So they're going to fill those up for a start.
- The Big Ben Tower has a prison in it that they keep naughty MPs in.
- Does it?
- Yes, it does.
- They have a prison room, if an MP breaches codes of conduct,
they'll get put in there.
And the last time it was used in 1880,
was when Charles Bradlaw and atheist refused to swear allegiance
to Queen Victoria on the Bible.
- Wow.
- And he was kept in the prison room overnight.
- And no MP.
- Every hour, every quarter of an hour, it rings.
- You're right. You're right.
- You're not going to get my sleep, are you?
- I'll be tortured, that's like a torture.
It's like how they play Barney, Guantanamo, yes.
- That'll be why MPs behave so well.
These days, it's terrified of the noise.
It used to make a different sound, didn't it?
When it was originally built, it chimed differently.
So it was built in May 1859.
- Did it go bonk?
- No, so it was made and the thing that crashes into the bell
to make the bonking sounds worked for a few weeks
and then immediately broke the bell.
And the crack in the bell is still there
from where it broke it.
And so they had to realign it, didn't they?
Which, for some reason, took them three or four years.
And then they made it bang the bell on a different point of it.
So we'll never hear the tone that Big Ben originally made.
- Did you know that the Big Ben Chimes have words?
They have lyrics.
- No, they mean words.
- Yeah, they do.
It's...
- It's half past two.
It's quarter two, nine.
- It's all through this hour, Lord be my guide
and by thy power, no foot shall slide.
- Hang on, but it doesn't say that
I've never heard those words broadcasting
and often performed, no, here that's true.
- Here's another one, play up Pompey.
The partsmith fans sing, play up Pompey.
Pompey, play up.
Like that.
- Oh really?
- Same tune.
Just, play up has him play better.
Sorry.
- Oh, Pompey.
- Oh, Pompey is a nickname for partsmith FC.
- Got it.
- Did you know that you can hear Big Ben Chimes
before it chimes?
- Oh, is that those future predicting people?
- No, it's not.
- Because that's an easy prediction.
I feel like it's gonna chime in about five seconds.
It's not, no, so the BBC, for anyone who doesn't know,
the BBC broadcast the Bongs Live at six o'clock every day.
So they have a speaker installed inside the tower
and that has direct link to the BBC broadcasting center.
So if you have an FM radio
and you go and stand even really close to Big Ben,
so like on Westminster Bridge, for example,
and you listen to the FM radio,
the FM radio signals are so much faster
than the sound waves in the air,
that the sound of the Bongs will go into the microphone
all the way to the BBC
and be broadcast always your radio faster
than it just coming through the air at you.
So if you were standing on Westminster Bridge
and you listened to an FM radio and Big Ben Chimes,
you would hear it on the radio a split second
before you would actually hear it in your other ear.
- That's really cool.
- It's really cool.
- Yeah.
Well done, the radio.
Doesn't get enough appreciation today for you tonight.
- This is so impressive.
- Do you know on Wikipedia,
there's a big long list of leaning towers.
So you can just see every leaning tower in the world.
- That's good.
- There's a nice one in Australia.
This is called the leaning tower of Jingen.
It's purposefully built to be leaning
and it's built at the gravity discovery center
and they wanted to make it so that when you went
to the gravity discovery center
that you could replicate by climbing the top Galileo's
experiments on the leaning tower pizza.
Yeah, so you could actually go up
and you drop stuff down a sheet.
- So the idea with Galileo is that he supposedly,
although we don't think this happens,
dropped two balls from the leaning tower of pizza
and there were different weights,
but they landed at the same time
and that was proof that things will fall at the same rate
not dependence on the mass.
- You know buildings in Amsterdam tilt deliberately as well.
And do you know where that is?
- No.
- So these are buildings in Amsterdam that face the canal.
They're many hundreds of years old
and the reason they're built at a slight tilt
is that they're tilting towards the canal
and that's so that they could winch goods up
from the canal to the upper windows.
And it's also so that if houses flooded,
which they often did,
then the first couple of floors might get full of water
and you need to evacuate your goods really quickly.
And faster than carrying them all upstairs
was if you just got them onto a platform outside the window
and winch those goods up to a higher level.
And the only way you can do that
without breaking the windows on the way up
and having it crashed into the wall
is to have the building lean
so that you can pull the goods up directly.
- Yeah, 'cause if you go to Amsterdam,
you see that a lot of the houses have got winches
on the front of them, haven't they?
At the very top, they got a little winch.
And the reason was, I think this is right,
I might be wrong, but I think they came up with their law
that the amount of tax you paid was dependent
on the front of your house, how wide that was.
And so people wanted really, really thin houses
so they paid less tax.
And so they would be thin and long
and they would be tall as well.
So that was fine, but then they needed to get,
if you need to get a sofa up to the top floor,
that's gonna be really tough
because you're gonna have a really thin staircase going up there.
And so the way they did it was to winch it all up.
And if you look now in Amsterdam,
they have all these winches at the top of the houses.
- This is so cool.
I feel like our facts have just married each other.
And married.
They also actually in Amsterdam,
they had to have a law preventing houses
from being too tilted in the end
'cause everyone was going, you know, 45 degree angles.
- Actually, it's a really thin house,
but it's tilted 90 degrees there.
(laughing)
There's a tilted structure in Yucatrinburg in Russia.
It's a massive TV tower.
And it is the tallest abandoned structure in the world.
- Oh really? - And they started building it.
They got it really, really high.
And then the Soviet Union fell.
And then they were like, okay,
we're not gonna do this anymore.
And it's still there.
- I'm intentionally leaning.
- Yeah, I'm unintentional.
It's very slightly leaning.
- And did the Soviet Union fall
because it itself was on?
(laughing)
- It was leaning too far to the left.
Yeah.
(laughing)
My friend, who you all know, Marina is from Yucatrinburg.
And this is right near her house.
And she says that everyone from there absolutely hates it.
And really wants it to get pulled down as soon as possible.
- Right.
And Nudge sounds like it.
- Yeah, I'm safe.
- One of the buildings that is on the list
of the list of leaning towers on Wikipedia
is this one that is a current story.
It's a news story with the San Francisco Millennium Tower.
So they're still trying to deal with it.
It keeps leaning further and further
'cause it's sinking into the ground.
And it was found out.
It was about six years ago they started noticing it.
It was a lady called Pamela Buttery,
who was up in her room.
And she was on the 57th floor
and she was trying to play golf in her room.
- Every time she put the ball down,
it just dribbled away from her
towards the end of the room.
And she had to go and collect.
And she's like, "Why, what's wrong with my floor?"
- It's a bit annoying for Pamela Buttery
'cause presumably if she's got tilting floors,
she's gonna be slipping all over them all this time.
- Yeah.
- Sure.
But yes, she falls over, she falls over,
she'll fall face down as well.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
And that is Chazinski.
- My fact this week is that when Asperin Tablet
was first introduced, people were unsure how to take them.
So one patient ended up strapping them to his head
to cure a headache.
(laughing)
- Did it work?
- We actually have no reports on that.
So I read this in an article in the Independent
from 2005 by a journalist called David Randall,
who, and I'd love to know more on it.
So David, if you're listening, please get in touch.
But this was a drug called Aspero
and this was devised in 1915
and it was called Aspero because the Asperin name
was taken by Bayer.
But it was the same as Asperin.
- So Asperin is, it's like saying Jekuzi or Hoover.
They are.
- Technically, yeah, but didn't Bayer lose the copyright
to lose the trademark to it because they literally let
anyone use it and they never sued anyone.
- I think they lost it in the Treaty of Versailles.
- Yeah, really weird.
- Yes.
- Well, actually the interesting thing about Germans
and Asperin is that its invention is put down
to a guy called Felix Hoffman.
And if you look at Bayer's official history of Asperin,
it still says that he invented it.
And actually, it's pretty much widely accepted now
since about 1999 that it was, in fact, created and tested
by a guy called Arthur Aikengrun.
And I'm probably pronouncing that wrong.
And he tested it in 1899 and he wrote a paper in 1949
saying that he just told Hoffman what to do.
Hoffman didn't even know what he was doing.
But Aikengrum was Jewish.
And so he wasn't ever included in the official narrative
and Hoffman was this Aryan kind of guy.
And it didn't come out until just over 10 years ago.
And still, if you look it up, Hoffman
is the person who's mainly credited as inventing it.
- I thought it was Hoffman.
- Yeah.
- I was just thinking by strapping your aspirin to your head,
it might work still as a placebo.
- Yeah, that's what I was thinking.
I bet the person did feel better.
- Yeah.
- Did it individual tablets or just a whole box?
- Doesn't matter.
If you believed it was going to work,
you could strap an empty box to your head
that it would still work a little bit.
- Yeah.
- For me to believe it, I need the aspirin
to be touching my skin.
I think I'd have to take it out of the packaging.
- Okay.
- Yeah, it's a placebo pharmacy as you just stare
at the product behind the counter
and just visualize them going into you.
- That'd be great.
I've got a magic pharmacy.
All these things work from a distance.
You don't only have to take any of them.
You get the placebo effect.
And my business goes immediately out of business
'cause I don't sell anything to be asked.
- You can charge them to look.
And you can charge them more to look at branded aspirin
than you charge them to look at unbranded.
And that's true because branded aspirin does better,
doesn't it, than non-branded aspirin?
Because people believe that it's somehow more potent
because it's got a brand attached to it.
- It is insane that literally the same thing in Tesco
costs 30p, that also costs three pounds or whatever
and people so often buy the three pounds.
And Tesco even colors it so it looks
like the Neurofen packet.
- Oh, the packet.
- And then it makes its aspirin red
so it looks like branded aspirin packet.
- But it actually does work.
So you pay an extra, actually makes it work better.
It was a study by Braithwaite and Cooper in 1981
that showed that that was true.
- I was thinking it's good that they don't make
the tablets themselves silver because imagine
you're being attacked by werewolf.
You accidentally mistaken your aspirin tablets
with your silver bullets that you're using to kill it.
And then you end up just curing.
- That's the problem, isn't it?
But instead they've made them look like children's sweets.
- I can't seem to risk with that.
(laughing)
- It's not nearly as dangerous as the werewolf situation.
I think we cannot agree.
- Hey, I was reading in the new QI book, The Factbook.
There's a fact in there that I've been thinking about
for weeks, which I just think it's so odd.
- I can't believe that it's true.
95% of people on earth have at least one thing wrong with them.
So that's quite amazing, but flip that round.
That means there are 5% of people on this planet
with absolutely nothing wrong with them.
How is that possible?
- Yeah, I don't think it can be.
- That is impossible, right?
5% of people are like, how are you?
Absolutely fine.
It's impossible.
- Yeah.
- But maybe they're just people who are extremely stoic.
And so when they asked them in the survey,
they said, you know, what's wrong with you?
They're like, fine, I'm fine.
(laughing)
They're just, they're organs hanging out.
Collapse can't move.
Fine, I'm fine.
(laughing)
But yeah, anyway, so sorry, just to round up.
Apparently it was the first thing that was,
it was the first matter that was sold on mass in tablet form.
And so it wasn't widely accepted.
Even though I think people have been swallowing things
for hundreds of years, it wasn't widely accepted.
This would be the way to swallow it.
And like I say, I couldn't find any more information
on this poor man who strapped one to his head.
So if anyone knows, here is descended from him.
- He died of a headache immediately afterwards.
- And so was never heard of again.
- Aspirin is called a wonder drug by a lot of people
because it's been very recently discovered
that it does all these other incredible things.
So a lot of people over a certain age
or with blood clotting issues are told to take an aspirin a day
because it stops platelets from clotting.
And a third of them.
- That sounds like a really crap version
of an apple a day keeps the top far away.
(laughing)
- And aspirin a day keeps the platelets from clotting.
Yay.
(laughing)
- That was the trick.
But a third of all people who are at risk
from cardiac arrest or cardiac incident
will not have that cardiac incident
if they take an aspirin every day.
Isn't that amazing?
- Apparently if your car is broken down.
- It can't fix a car down.
- You just strap it to the top of the car.
(laughing)
- Apparently if you've got any jump leads on you
and no one is passing by to help you
and you happen to have some aspirin on you,
if you put the aspirin two tablets into the battery itself,
the basically the sulfuric acid within the battery
will mix with the aspirin.
And who kickstarted it back into life?
I read this in a reader's digest article.
I haven't tested it.
I can't get further than it could.
- The fact that dosage is the same for cars and humans.
- Take two tissues to it before Alice will keep your car running.
(laughing)
- Just say drop two, your aspirin tablets.
- Another thing it helps to get running is a collider.
Like not the large hadron collider
but there is another collider in Illinois.
They're all like little switches they put aspirins on.
And the idea is if there was a leak,
the water would drop down, it would dissolve the aspirin
and then the switches would be able to switch back
and it would turn off automatically.
- I was just kind of like there's all like resistors
or trip switches, something when the metal
is supposed to basically it destroys the connection
if the currents - Yeah it's like a fuse box kind of thing.
- Wow.
We're getting near the end of the year
and obviously New Year's Eve in America,
there's huge traditions of dropping things
in Manhattan, sorry in New York Times Square,
it's what they dropped the ball.
There's a place in America called Myers Town in Pennsylvania
where you can see a giant aspirin tablet dropped.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And that brings us into the New Year
and the reason is is because the Bayer health care plant
is there and so it's such a big part of the town
and probably employees so many people who live there.
So yeah, they just drop a giant into a giant glass of water
or a giant mouth.
- Yeah.
- Is it real aspirin?
Like if I went and chip some off, would that sell mine?
- No, that would be so cool though, but no, it's fake.
It's really weird, there's a list you can go on
of things that are dropped at New Year in America
and Pennsylvania has so many.
So in certain places you can see a beaver dropped,
a canal boat dropped, Indy car dropped.
It's like a theme that each town has on their own.
- Wow.
- Yeah, but one is the aspirin.
- Probeaver.
- It's a stuffed beaver, it's not a real beaver.
- Yeah, but still poor ol beaver who got killed and stuff.
- Oh yeah, yeah, that's true.
And that's in beaver town in Pennsylvania.
- I don't think that's a coincidence.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is my fact, my fact this week is that
the first British plans to put a human on the moon
was made by Oliver Cromwell's brother-in-law.
- This is so cool.
- This is back in the 1600s.
- Yeah, he wouldn't have really had the means to do so,
I don't think.
- No, he didn't at all.
I mean, I think you're right, yeah.
(laughing)
- This is Dr. John Wilkins.
This is not in any way a nutcase of who just,
we happened to have found documents of some crazy machine
that was built.
This is a really respected clergyman philosopher, author,
helped found the Royal Society.
It was a really big deal back in the day.
- It's quite a famous polymath, I think.
- Yeah, he was, yeah, and he was a big champion
of the latest ideas about space and one of the young.
- What were the latest ideas about space
in the 17th century?
- Well, I guess Galileo had telescopes trained at the moon
and he wrote two books about the moon
and his thoughts about what actually was going on.
He thought it was a solid object
and he got a lot wrong, but you always do
in those, when there's limited science
and you're trying to break ground.
- Although to be clear, the moon is a solid object.
That was one of the things he did not get wrong, right?
- What?
(laughing)
- So how did he try and get to the moon?
- Okay, so his idea was that you could build a space chariot
and he was using obviously the technology of his time
and his theory was that as soon as you got 20 miles
up into the air, magnetism of earth and gravity
loses itself, so that's why you can stay up there.
The reason he thought that is because
why do clouds stay in the air?
And he thought as high as they were,
that's where you no longer suffered
to the pull of earth's magnetism.
- I mean, that's pretty good logic
considering the information you had available.
- Yeah, so he thought if you could just get up to that point
then you'd be able to float off into space
and go to the moon and you would adjust to the air,
then you'd breathe the air of angels.
This is where the kind of religious side comes in,
but it made sense that that's how angels breathed.
They just got used to it.
And then you go to the moon and you would trade
for spices and so on with the people who lived on the moon.
You thought there were people that might live on the moon
and we could trade with them.
- And sorry, this very easy problem
of getting the initial 20 miles up into the air,
how was he surmounting that?
- Well, okay, so-- - Flying chariot.
- Yeah, so the flying chariot, so it was meant to use
clockwork gears, it was gunpowder.
The idea was that it was going to be propelled
using gunpowder and springs.
- And springs, yeah, the Akmi space chariot.
- But he was a very rational sensible person
in this age that was actually kind of a perfectly
reasonable thing to think.
And his greatest interest was making a unifying language
for the world, wasn't it?
- So he did lots of work on creating
like what we have now at Esperanto,
which obviously we all speak.
- He also designed a decimal system
which the metric system was then based on and built off.
So, you know--
- His language was quite interesting.
Every time you added a new letter to a word,
it would change the meaning,
but your meaning would be related to the previous word.
So the word D-E-D would be an element,
but then when you put a B on the end,
Deb, that would mean fire.
And then Deb would mean a flame.
So each one was related to the previous.
And the whole idea of it was you would be able to see a word
and knowing the basic building blocks of how his language works,
you could work out pretty much what it kind of meant.
So if it began with D, you would know it was in this part
of, you know, semantics.
And if it began with X, you would know this or with J,
you would know that.
- That's clever.
- So to a much smaller extent,
you can do that with English,
and that you know if something is, you know,
it's got a diminutive on the front, or a kind of, like, something,
it has been suffixes.
But the core word is usually you can completely round them,
or come from a really random source,
so you can't deduce it right from the beginning.
- Sure, so I suppose if you hear a word that has Hydro
at the start of it, you know,
it's going to be something to do with water.
- Didn't he also say that eating wouldn't be necessary
when we got to space because there's no gravity
and the reason we have to eat on Earth
is that the gravity pulls your food through your body
and makes it fall out.
So you have to keep eating more.
- It's so wonderful, but he was genuinely, I mean,
I have to say, when I saw this fact,
I thought this time- - Wait a minute.
So there are some animals whose mouth and anus
are on about the same level,
like a dog, for instance, or a cat.
- Yeah.
- Maybe he tried to train animals not to sit down
because as soon as they sit down,
that suddenly grab a seed out of it.
- Right, dogs don't poo when they're standing up to them.
They kind of move the bum down.
- Oh my gosh. - It's clever.
- Of course they do.
It all makes sense.
- Maybe he was right.
(laughing)
- But he didn't like all of this theoretical stuff.
He did, he worked out the distance to the moon
to a degree of accuracy of 99.9%
using just trigonometry.
- That is incredible.
- He's so impressive.
- And I'm quite surprised that of the, you know,
the British space program,
that there's not a big statue of this guy outside.
- Well, we don't really have that much of a space problem.
- No, we have one.
- We have one that goes all the way back to the 17th century.
- And it kind of ended there.
(laughing)
- That's true.
- We've done pretty much nothing of it.
We have one, we have the,
the Prospero satellite.
We've got one British maze satellite
that was launched to the British made rocket.
Everything else is basically being
we've given something.
- Everything else is basically chariots.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you would like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @triberland.
James.
- @egshaped.
- Alex.
- @AlexBell_.
- And Shizinski.
- You can email podcasts@ky.com.
- Yep, you can go to our group podcast account,
which is @kypodcast or you can go to our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
We've got all of our previous episodes up there.
And you can also go to our other website,
which is no such thing as the news.com.
That has all of our previous TV show episodes,
which is just finished.
It's not out anymore.
And if you're missing it, that's where all the episodes are.
Okay, we will be back again next week with another show.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
(bright music)
[MUSIC]