(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covran Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
Anna Tyshinski and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
for this time for a very special, somewhat sad episode.
- Poignant.
- Poignant episode.
A very sad announcement that we have to make is that--
- A happy announcement, no?
I think it's a happy announcement.
- Is it?
- It's very confusing.
- Well, Anna Tyshinski is leaving the show.
So it's a--
- I'm delighted.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, for nine months, temporarily.
- Temporarily, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
She's going away for a while to think about
what she's done and then, then she can come back.
- And what specifically she's done--
- Yes, is--
- Is created a baby.
- She has.
She's been collaborating on another project
with another person.
- It's very low effort, so much less work than the podcast.
And I hope that it continues that way.
- That it does.
Anyway, we thought we would commemorate this tragedy.
I think it's a tragedy that she's going.
- Joyfully.
- That she's going.
- Joyful news.
- That's obviously happy stuff, yeah.
But not for us, not for the listener.
- Not for Dan.
- Not for me.
- I honestly feel like I am secretly dying
and no one's told me.
(laughing)
The person who's been leaving drinks tonight,
people who say, "You went down as a leaving thing."
- As someone who's been in this situation,
or a similar situation 12 months ago,
metaphorically, it's the end.
- I'm gonna be dead inside from now on, aren't I?
- I'm afraid so.
- You've gone for two weeks, though, on paternity.
Should we have done a missing?
James is off.
(laughing)
Do the best of.
- And look, we should say that's what we're here to do.
We're here to commemorate our wonderful buddy.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- A very daffy word.
- So, can we say, "Celebrate," you know?
- It's not sad occasion. - It's not eulogy.
- Well, yeah.
So we thought what we'd do is we would present
our three favorite facts this time, not four.
It's sort of get used to the idea that she's not here.
And share with you some of the greatest moments
that she's had over the last nine years of fish.
Nine years we've been doing this.
- Nine years.
- It's coming up to it in March of this year.
So yeah, we're on the brink.
- So.
- Oh, God, I'm going out.
- You're coming back.
You're coming back in nine months
and there's a very exciting roster of guests
actually presenting lined up to replace you.
So, you know.
- Wow.
Let's not use the word "replace."
(laughing)
- Would you jump into a grave that quickly?
Sarah Pascoe?
(laughing)
- They could jump into someone's grave.
Isn't that what you do?
(laughing)
- Wait.
- I don't think if you're replacing them,
you climb into that coffin with them.
- You're right.
- What's the phrase?
- Jump into their bed?
- No.
- Pick up their shoes.
- Pick up their shoes?
- Fill the dead man's shoes.
- I wouldn't piss on their shoes if they were dead.
That's the phrase.
- Is it?
- No, it's like.
- I think it's maternity cover.
I think that's the word we're looking for.
- They haven't even cleaned up the funeral meat yet.
- She's not even cold.
- I'm sorry.
They haven't cleaned up her funeral meat?
(laughing)
- I think that's actually.
I think that's from Hamlet.
Oh, no, they...
- Yeah, no, it is.
There's a thing about funeral meats.
In the wedding, they reuse the stuff
for Hamlet's dad's funeral for the wedding
to Hamlet's dad's brother.
- Have you heard of cheesy funeral potatoes?
(laughing)
- Sounds yummy, though.
- It's a thing they do in Utah, I think.
And it's basically potatoes,
cream, cheese, and corn flakes all together.
And it's what you have in funerals.
And the idea is that it's the kind of thing
that a typical Utah family,
typical Mormon family would have in the lada.
And everyone would have these four
or five different things.
I think chicken soup is one of them as well,
but you put them all together
and it's like the meal that you have at a funeral, so.
- Really?
Hold on, you don't mix the chicken soup with the...
- Yeah, I don't get it.
- You just put it in the chicken soup.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And then you put corn flakes on top.
- We're here basically to have your
cheesy funeral potato meats, and that's lovely.
- I think chicken soup's quite an incentive thing to have
'cause that traditionally makes you better,
but of course at a funeral,
it's too late for that, isn't it?
- Absolutely right.
Sorry, this, we've broken the format.
- We're gonna do our three favorite facts
about Anna Tyshinski, each one of us presenting it.
And why don't we start with you, James?
- Okay, well, my fact this week is that
in order to get into the United States,
Anna Tyshinski had to tell a fact about a dead president.
(laughing)
- Am I, I'm never allowed there again.
- They let you in, surprisingly, despite it.
- They did.
- It was, or border control, or whatever it is.
- Yeah, I actually can't remember the context
where they made me say it.
- Well.
- We'd landed, hadn't we?
- We'd landed, so we had to get a visa
as something like people of exceptional talent
or something like that.
- Yeah, it was like we were Julia Roberts or something.
She wouldn't need one, of course,
'cause she is American, but.
- So we went to the American embassy
and we had to prove to them that we had exceptional talent,
or they were exceptionally famous or something.
And the woman at the window just said,
"Notice things of fish, I never heard of you."
- That's right.
- Yeah, and immediately we were on the back foot.
But anyway, eventually we managed to convince them
that we should go to America and get a visa to work there
so that we could do our show.
But when we got to the passport control,
the visa said that we were a comedy podcast.
And the guy said to you, Anna, as you walked up,
he said, "Well, what do you do?"
And you said, "Well, it's a kind of about facts."
And he said, "Well, tell me a fact then."
And the only thing you could think about
was something about the murderer of a president.
- Yeah.
The only thing I can usually think about
is President Garfield's anus,
but all the more so when you're landing in the home
of President Garfield.
So yeah, I told him that when President Garfield
was assassinated, it was a slow process
and he spent the last month of his life
eating through his anus,
which I'm sure you're all familiar with
if you remember episode one.
- Yeah. - Second ever fact on the show.
- How did he react?
- The border control. - President Garfield, yeah.
(laughing)
- There were a lot of funeral potatoes that week.
- I think he did what most border control people do,
which is be very unimpressed and slightly threatening.
I think it was like, "Okay, go on ahead then, ma'am."
- Wow. - Wow.
- Which is the reaction I've always wanted
to all of our podcast facts, so.
- Do you know, weirdly, this fact about President Garfield
was I remember the exact moment that you told me that fact.
I can remember the exact spot of the office.
Yeah, because we were getting ready to do
what was still a run-through of the show
and we used that segment in the very first episode,
but I remember you had sent around your facts
and your fact was about President Garfield
and it was to do with the fact
that he spent three months on his death bed
and they tried to cure him.
I can't remember your wording, but it wasn't great.
It was sort of like, we need that.
- Just a quick note, Anna.
(laughing)
- That's what this is gonna be.
This is an intervention.
What to think about over the next nine months.
- Don't be holding that in for nine years.
- Yeah.
- I've got a big list. - You can do this
for everyone from episode one.
- We're starting, let's start.
Episode one will be here. - Okay, it's surprising.
Tell me what I should have said.
- I can't remember what you said to me at the time,
but I said to you, "I love the story.
Is there any other way of expressing it?"
And you literally in a beat said, "Oh, what about this?
For the last three months of his life,
he ate everything through his anus."
And I remember genuinely, it was a bit of a thunderbolt,
kind of like, "Oh my God, we're gonna have a hit
on our hands." It was just so beautifully crafted.
Yeah, I really felt it.
I'm just telling the origin story here.
- What a strange, inspirational moment.
I don't think a lot of great inventors could emphasize
with that moment being the one.
- It was thunderbolt.
- And that's why we were so nearly called
the President Garfield Anus Cust.
- Well, it's such a shame that we changed the name.
- To be honest, when we were thinking of our first book,
James and I, when we were brainstorming ideas
for the title, "The President's Anus."
- I remember "The President's Anus" coming up
quite a bit, being tossed about.
- It feels like it's going to be tossed.
- As it was.
- It feels like the beginning of a title,
"The President's Anus."
It feels like it should be,
"The President's Anus is missing."
Or some--
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, but one of my favorite things of that tour,
so we did a big, it was our first ever American tour.
First and only American tour.
- Yeah.
- Pulled yourself back from saying a big American tour
'cause it was five days.
- Well, for us, it was super exciting.
We were up on Times Square.
We got to play New York.
We played Washington.
We stayed in the--
- Watergate.
- The Watergate Hotel.
- Yeah.
- Where they had, like, remember they had the,
the pencils, like, please steal this pencil.
- Oh, the room keys.
- And the room keys.
- Said I was stolen from the Watergate Hotel.
- That's right, yeah.
All the light bulbs, like, pillows I brought home.
That's the same thing, weirdly.
- And those documents from the White House, though.
Yeah, but my favorite thing of all
was when we were staying in New York.
And I just remember seeing Anna one morning
and her looking unbelievably abused
because she was holding a bill in her hand
for a basic bit of laundry
that she had sent to the hotel.
- Oh, my God.
- Which came to $240.
- It was more than that.
It was more than that.
I think it was, like, $400.
- Oh, my God.
- And I thought it was complimentary.
I just, I don't know.
- They just put a bag outside your door, didn't they?
With laundry written on it.
Just shove it in.
- Yeah, you just put stuff in.
I don't know.
We always send premier ins when we're in the UK.
We're not used to this.
So yeah, it tossed all my clothes from the whole tour in.
(laughing)
- You had enough clothes.
You didn't really need it all done.
- Absolutely not when we were going home the next day.
- Sometimes it's lovely to get home
with a fresh case of clothes.
It feels incredible.
- Anyway, so we made a loss on that tour, didn't we?
- Yeah, we did.
- I know, I should say, just to make you think kindly
of these people, you're stuck with the next nine months
that they agreed that that could be split that loss
over the whole tour group rather than just me taking it.
- Did we?
- Yeah, yeah, and I think--
- Yeah, sorry about that.
- I think the tour pretty much dead on broke even.
- Yeah, right.
- But we would have been in the black if it had--
- I owe you all a hundred pounds.
- Yeah, yeah.
I think, no, I think I didn't pipe up
because when I went back to England,
I bought so many books that my overweight money allowance
was something like $1,000 or something.
It was ridiculous.
- We didn't take the hit for that though, did we?
- I think you might have done.
- I think we might have done, yeah.
- Well, if I'm gonna take the laundry hit, I was, I thought.
- Andy, we should have gone for the huckers
and the cocaine that we sent.
(laughing)
- I only ate one meal a day in America
'cause I was so concerned about making a loss.
(laughing)
- We made him walk all the way from Boston to New York.
- I took one pair of pants and I wore it inside, outside,
back to front, upside down.
Now I know I was on tour with, you know, Elton John.
- Yeah, so sorry about that.
- Wow.
- But yeah, didn't get evicted from the country.
No, what's the cool when you get evicted?
Deported.
- Deported.
- Didn't get deported for talking about
presidential assassination, so actually helped us get in.
So if you are trying to get into America,
give it a go.
- Okay, well, the point of this show, I think,
is that we're gonna play some of Anna's best bits.
And so--
- It's a very short show.
- It should be a very short show.
So let's do a little bit now,
beginning with President Garfield's anus.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, fact number two, Anna, this one's yours.
- Yeah, so for the last month of his life,
US President James Garfield ate everything
through his anus.
(all laughing)
- We will get letters from a lot of people here.
- That is mine.
Yeah, I mean, I wasn't there,
but this is what the doctors tell me.
(all laughing)
No, so James Garfield was, as everyone obviously knows,
shot in July, 1881, and he lived for a further 80 days.
He was shot in the small, in the, like, small of his back
and once in the arm.
So doctors now say he would have been at our hospital
about two or three days later.
But obviously, 'cause medicine was not quite as advanced
as it is now.
In 1881, they just invited, like,
dozens of doctors to his bedside
who all prodded around trying to find this bullet.
They didn't know where the bullet had gone in his body.
So they gathered around, prodded about,
made him worse and worse.
He stopped being able to eat.
And obviously, if you stop being able to consume food
in those days, they just shoved it up your arse.
And so that's what they did.
- So does that work?
- It does not work, no.
It was widely discredited in the early 30s.
And I think you get about an eighth of the nutrition
from some of the food.
But there's some food that you can't absorb at all.
- What I love is the list of foods
that he was fed in his mother.
- Oh, that's good, yeah.
- Beef, bouillon, egg yolks, milk.
- Egg yolks.
- Wait a second, guys.
Egg yolks, it was only true for a while.
'Cause I was reading the doctor at the time
his report on it.
So yeah, he was fed egg yolks for a bit of time.
And then all the surgeons complained
that it was causing annoying and offensive plateaus.
And so they ceased feeding him egg yolks.
And it deprecated.
- So they stopped it because it was annoying them.
Not the other way around.
(laughing)
Guys, I'd be quite happy to eat an egg with my mouth.
That's all right by you guys.
- Apparently it's illegal to move sheep in whales
until they've been checked to see
whether they carry traces of the fallout from Chernobyl.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- On this particular subject,
I have a question for you guys.
- Oh yeah?
- Why shouldn't you buy trousers from the Northern Ukraine?
- I don't know.
Why shouldn't you buy trousers from the Northern Ukraine?
- Chernobyl fallout.
(laughing)
- Ladies and gentlemen, that is the joke.
- Yeah, just so you know,
just as a little inside bit of behind the scenes
information here, Anna has consistently for the last,
what, 14 podcasts said that same joke
and we've cut it out every single episode.
- Anna has refused to have it in the podcast.
- This is a day.
- And you will not hear it in this one either.
- Yeah.
- Unless someone else said it.
- It's the best joke ever.
Ambrose Pare, who was a famous doctor in the 15th century,
saw a beggar in Paris who was begging him for money
and who did so by, I don't actually know if we can put this
out, it's so gross.
- Let's just say it anyway.
- Who did so by, she begged by lifting her skirts
to reveal a prolapsed rectum.
It was a horrid sight, he says.
It was over half a foot long leaking pasta light fluid
over her legs and garments.
But his companion then attacked the woman and said,
you're a big faker, you don't look sick enough
to have a prolapsed rectum.
- You have to be pretty confident that you're right
in that situation.
- Yeah, I know prolapsed rectums and that madame.
- He beat this woman to the ground and eventually
she was forced to reveal that it was actually
the prolapsed rectum of an ox.
But she put inside her some boxes.
- It was actually a prolapsed rectum.
- It was, it wasn't prolapsed.
- He felt pretty silly then, didn't he?
(all laughing)
- That's not a human prolapsed rectum.
It was the prolapsed rectum of an ox.
- Yeah, she'd put up her own bum though.
I think, oh my God.
- I think you've gone to the trouble of doing that.
I really think you've earned your 50 cents or whatever.
- Absolutely.
But the lifting of her skirts as well.
She could just have a sign saying,
prolapsed rectum, please help.
- Wait, so if you saw someone with a sign saying,
(all laughing)
that's probably how she starts it.
And she's like, no one is buying this at all.
- Except Andy.
I can show it to you, no need.
Absolutely believe you.
- The thing is though, I would pay,
I would pay 50p not to see a prolapsed rectum.
- That is a fair point.
- She should have done that.
- We should move on.
- When they were building the New York subway,
the guys who were building it were called sand hogs
'cause they dug through lots of sand.
And I was reading a newspaper report from 1916
and it was about this guy called Marshall Mabee
who was working in the tunnel to dig the subway.
And there was a pocket of compressed air
which suddenly kind of escaped.
So he's got this big shield up in the tunnel in front of him
and they're using this shield to push forward
and make the tunnel bigger.
And he said he saw an 18-inch pocket of air suddenly appear
and it sucked him towards it.
He was sucked into it.
He was blasted up through the ground.
So he was blasted up through 12 feet of riverbed
and then blasted up through the river itself
and then hurled up 25 feet in the air above the river.
- He wasn't grinding through earth, 12 feet of earth.
- Yeah, that's what riverbed's made of.
It's less, it's more plausible for him to be blasted
through 12 feet of earth and 12 feet of concrete or steel
or whatever.
No, no, no, I was thinking was it just a tunnel?
Like it was a hole that he was blasted through.
It just happened to be going, don't believe it.
- So here we go, let me,
there's a whole interview with him and everything.
There's a nice interview with his wife saying,
it's okay, he's fine.
He's looking forward to going back to work.
This is what the New York Times said at the time.
There's a pocket of compressed air
to prevent the river's bottom from caving in.
So they have some, God, I don't know how that works.
- But somehow it happened, guys,
and this compressed air got loose
and he saw an 18-inch hole
and before he knew it, he was being sucked towards it.
Two of his colleagues actually also got sucked in
and they did perish.
And he survived by blasting up,
putting his arm out in front of him
and blasting up through the riverbed.
- I don't believe it.
- 12 feet of riverbed and then got shot through
and then out in the air.
There's enough force left over,
shot through the river itself and then you had 25 feet.
- 25 feet?
- The New York Times is a very retro.
- What year is it?
- Yeah, and what date was this?
- February 1916, all right, not April.
Yeah, it was a little bit insane,
but there you go, there's a picture of the guy.
Pictures don't lie.
- What, mid-flight?
- No, not mid-flight.
(laughs)
- That's extraordinary.
- Did you say that was in New York?
- Yeah, it was soft ground,
so that's why they were called the sound.
- Oh, well, if it was soft ground, I see, yeah.
It was still a riverbed, though, wasn't it?
- 25 feet after 12 beds of--
- And a river.
- I don't know how it possibly happened.
So there was a woman in South Korea recently
who was eating squid, so we all eat squid.
We call it calamari for reasons I don't understand,
but she was eating some boiled squid in a restaurant,
and she suddenly felt a pain in her tongue,
and it turned out the squid wasn't quite dead,
and it was a male squid,
and it had deposited its sperm packet into her tongue,
so she felt horrible pain in her tongue,
and then felt lots of stuff crawling around
inside her tongue, and had to go to hospital,
and they took out a whole bunch of sperm.
And apparently this does happen a bit,
like there's been reports in Japan of it happening.
- Oh, that's so fucked up.
I will never fucking do that shit again.
- Oh my god.
- Yeah.
- Fuck it now.
(all laughing)
- Fuck that.
- Ventritarianism, here you come.
- I don't think we've mentioned this before.
This year KFC have released a novel for the first time.
- What?
- It's a novel starring the Colonel,
and it's a Milsen Boone-style romance,
and it's called "Tender Wings of Desire."
- He is a sexy man.
- Well, we ascertained before we started
recording this podcast that you quite fancy
Richard Nixon.
- Oh yeah.
- How did we miss that when we got to that?
- We didn't ascertain that.
That's warping of the truth.
- Oh, I'm sorry.
- I find him not unattractive, given that there was an incident.
- But for Andy, that's pretty much someone saying
you're attractive.
That's the best I can hope for these days.
- I'm not physically repulsed by him.
Great, Dave.
He said in an interview that something like,
"I know how I look.
I'm under no illusions about my appearance,
so I'll have to be good in other ways."
And I read that interview,
and I thought, "Well, he is good in other ways,
isn't he?
Lots of ways that Richard Nixon is a very good man."
- What would you say your--
- Yeah, what are your top five ways
where she's a great guy, Hannah?
- When British author William Haslitt died,
his landlady was so keen to re-let his room
that she hid his body under the bed
while she showed new tenants around.
- And he's still there under that bed, isn't he?
- He's still there, yeah.
But he was a big deal,
and people used to go just to the Haslitt Hotel
just because that's where he lived.
Seamus Heaney used to go there, obsessed with him,
and they would have meet-ups there
just to be able to be in the sort of presence
of the location of this great person
who everyone seems to have forgotten,
except it turns out, you, Hannah, just--
- I mean, people know what him Haslitt is,
but I did happen to take a book of his essays
on my gap here, which I know is,
I just told these guys back stage, I know.
One of those guys was gonna mention it,
so I thought I'd get in there.
- Which drug were you taking when you were reading it?
- The essays themselves were my drug, James.
- What am I on?
I'm on chapter three.
- I mean, they didn't come in chapters, but whatever.
- You know, in shopping centers
where the fish eat your dead skin?
- I've had that once,
and all I could think while I was having it
was reincarnation and just looking
at the guy, "What the fuck did you do in your last life
"that you have come back to eat my feet?"
- This is--
- I had it once, and I think I've told you guys this,
but I had it once in Cambodia,
and they had to ask me to take my feet out of the pond,
'cause you put your feet in with like five other people,
and my feet is so disgusting
that they were all coming to my feet,
and no one else was getting their money's worth.
(audience laughing)
That's a real, real, actually low point.
- Proud-wise, me.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for fact number two about Anna Tyshinski,
and that is Andy.
- Well, my fact is a crowdsourced fact.
- Yeah.
- So, as you know, there's a Discord.
If you don't know Discord,
it's a website where you chat about stuff.
Is that what it is?
- Why did you bother explaining if you have no idea?
It's a forum, it's a forum to chat.
There is a fish Discord, the fish cord,
and as part of Anna's commemoration episode.
- Morning, morning episode, I think, yeah.
- Morning sickness, hi-o.
(laughing)
Dan, I think you asked for some of Anna's best bits.
- Yeah.
- And asked what listeners, you know,
fish fans wanted to hear again.
I mean, various bits.
- You can make a compilation of Anna saying her own surname.
- Correctly.
- When do you say your own surname?
- Yeah, I don't know if you can make a compilation out of that.
- You can certainly make a compilation of the evolution
of my pronunciation of your surname.
- Yeah, a lot of people got quite sad
when you evolved from pronouncing it,
well, as some people said wrongly, Tyshinski to Tyshinski.
- Well, yeah, and I always say that it was a bit of a,
it was a bit unfair on me because you were right here
to tell me I was saying it wrong for about six years,
and no one did.
No one did, your dad didn't, your mom didn't,
anytime any of your family came to our show,
no one would say, by the way,
do you think you might be able to pronounce
the surname correctly?
No one said anything.
And yours was a surname that I specifically,
if I would say, like, next fact is James,
next fact is Andy, I would say next fact, Tyshinski.
I would always say your surname.
So it was always coming up.
- But I think, do you remember them?
Oh, Larry really liked it.
'Cause then he had the Schreiber and Tyshinski cops,
maybe who were trying to find the president's anus.
- To your cops, yeah, we got to get to the bottom
of this big laundry bill, Tyshinski.
- Oh, nice, yeah.
What's your pronunciation?
- I say Tyshinski, but you can also say Tyshinski,
or a lot of people do say Tyshinski,
and it's weird that people assume that's the way
you could say it.
It's quite different starting with a chub.
- It's P-T, yeah.
You don't call it a charodactyl, do you?
- You don't, I don't know, or a charmigan.
But I should say for actual Polish listeners
that it's Tyshinski, so you're supposed to say the P.
So I don't pronounce it right, either.
- Okay, there we go.
- And I sort of should also be Ptazinska, 'cause I'm a girl.
- Oh, no way.
- Wow.
- I am.
(laughing)
- I don't remember this suggestion for a clip to play.
Episode 342, no such thing as a presidential fight club.
Anna refers to a child as a wimp because he had asthma.
- And that child, ladies and gentlemen,
grew up to be a podcaster, Andrew Hudson.
(laughing)
- There's probably some context that I haven't seen
in the reports of that myself,
and I'm sure there's a reasonable explanation,
but I'm gonna refer it to a committee
that we will investigate.
- You'll end up being suspended for nine months.
It's perfect, it's a perfect crime.
So funny what people remember, like one person wrote,
"I can't remember which episode."
So this is them, like they've literally
bankless in their head, you can't remember which episode,
but Anna calling Matanus to Tunis, mootie tootie.
(laughing)
- Lives rent free in my brain.
Mootie tootie tootie tootie tootie tootie.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I don't remember this bit at all,
and neither does the person who said it.
I don't remember the episode,
but it was about some female animal drinking semen,
and Anna was like, yeah, relatable.
Sometimes the tap is just too far away.
(laughing)
Don't recall that.
- Just a few times at uni, and a terrible hangover is,
there's a cut by the bed, what are you gonna do?
- Fill me up love before you go, but then do go.
(laughing)
- Yeah, I mean, you've had a lot of feedback
about your kind of quite dirty-ish potty mouth,
I would say.
- I feel like I'm the least potty.
- I think people just notice it more when you do it.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I think that's it, it's everyday sexism.
- Well, actually, there's a bit of a debate,
even on the Discord about you, Anna.
So, one person says,
if you go back and listen to the first year's episodes,
Anna's so restrained and polite in comparison,
and then she gets comfortable
and the sarcasm starts to flow, okay?
Now, someone has replied to that saying,
"I'm on episode 39, she has never been polite."
(laughing)
- I think there is one episode,
I remember editing it, where you're polite
for about two thirds of the episode,
and then for the final third of the episode,
you just go completely off the rails.
- Really?
- And it was the episode when you drank
a pint of champagne before the show.
- Oh no, God, that wasn't the only one,
one of our first live shows.
- I think it might have been our actual first live show,
or maybe our second.
- It was like, it was a Christmas one,
and it was an Aces and Aces.
- Aces and Aces.
- In North London.
- That's right.
- And you can really, you can pinpoint
the exact second that the champagne hits.
- What's confusing is that I'm sure Dan and I
drunk pints of champagne for that,
and I also am sure that Dan
is more of a lightweight than I am.
- Yeah, but the difference is
that Dan is never coherent.
(laughing)
- You can't tell.
- Yes.
- That's a beauty.
- Exactly, I'm bulletproof.
- I'm drunk now, no one's noticed.
(laughing)
- Episode 261.
- Oh yeah.
- Dan's talking about Scott of the Antarctic
taking two gramophones with him.
Anna, he was a fucking idiot, wasn't he?
(laughing)
- You gotta stand by that, it's not surprising he died.
You know, he didn't take two gramophones.
Amundsen.
- Amundsen.
- Yeah, yeah.
Actually, I hate saying that name so much,
I could never say it.
- You said it quite weird.
- I know.
- Amundsen.
(laughing)
- I don't know why I see it coming up in my head.
Is this how you feel down with all words?
- Yeah, yeah, I do.
I see them coming up on the page
and you gotta make a decision.
You're either gonna try and pronounce it correctly,
get it wrong, or, and check it out
and get it wrong just for that,
or you just gotta run through it.
You just gotta, you gotta.
- It reminds me, and I know this is a podcast about Anna,
but it does remind me of the first audiobook that we did,
(laughing)
which was just after you'd had your first baby
and were very short on sleep.
And Dan kept pronouncing the word January, February.
(laughing)
- Like six times.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- We were like, Dan, Dan, you said February.
Can you just do it again?
- Oh, sorry, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Okay, here we go.
- February.
(laughing)
- It was remarkable.
It was really something.
- And we had to change the whole article at the end,
didn't we, to something that happened in February?
- I used to love those books
'cause they were the books of the year
and it was like things that happened
between January and December that year.
Obviously, the book came out in November,
so it's usually January to September or October.
But Andy used to always come in
with things that had happened the previous year.
And Anna would be like, no, this was last year.
And he's like, yeah, but it was late 20, come on, it was December.
- My reasoning here
is that you're doing one of these books a year.
Each book has to have a 12 month catchment area.
It's the book of, not the calendar year,
not the calendar year,
but the, like the school year or the school year.
- Yeah, the financial year.
- That's right, the school year.
- You started in September.
- Everyone understands,
otherwise you're knocking out a third of your own material.
- Why didn't we name it the book of the school year,
actually?
(laughing)
- So honest.
- The book of the financial year
would have really set those sales rocketing.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Have we got one last one, Andy or?
- Anna is among the 10% of people
who can lick their own nose.
- What?
- Oh.
- We did a, okay.
- Oh my God, yeah.
- She's doing it, she's doing it.
- We did a fact about Buddha
and how Buddha could stick his tongue through his ear.
- Into his ear, that was it.
- Yeah.
- And then you showed us that.
- And had lots of other stuff that I don't have, though.
- Weird body part anomalies.
I also actually have a lot,
but they're less sort of magical than Buddha's.
And more like get medical help.
(laughing)
- That's good though, touching your nose.
I can't do that.
- Your tongue barely gets out of your mouth.
- I think I'm tongue tied.
- Oh, really?
- And that's why you're so bad at breastfeeding, isn't it?
- Yes.
(laughing)
- But I'm still trying.
- Yeah, good on you.
- That's it, we'll get you there.
- Oh, that's a bristly experience, Dan.
You're very bearded.
(laughing)
- That's so rough.
- Yeah, it's not good for the--
- It's because of breast and rash happening there.
- Highly sanded boobs up here there.
(laughing)
- The nipples almost gone all together.
It's just a flat, floppy out potato.
(laughing)
- It's just a flat potato.
- Can we have some more of Anna, please?
(laughing)
Classic Czazinski.
- Okay, well, I'll have a look on the archives.
Let's see if we can find some of the things
that you've mentioned in the next little Anna compilation.
(upbeat music)
- My fact is that the way to recognize the Buddha
is to look out for his webbed feet,
a tongue that can reach his ears,
and withdrawn genitalia.
- That's a good excuse on a date.
- No, no, no, it's not small.
I'm just, I'm the Buddha, I'm the reincarnated Buddha.
- Oh yeah, then show me your tongue,
'cause I could get on board with this.
(laughing)
- I read that female beetles,
they quench their thirst through sex,
and it's because of the semen and the fluids in the semen,
'cause they get very dehydrated,
and so when they have sex,
it's actually just like having a drink for them.
- That's the reason we all do it, Dan.
(laughing)
- Sometimes the tap is too far away.
- A few people who were farmers
who were involved in castrating lambs
when they were born got very ill very quickly,
and there was 12 people who got ill,
but they worked out that two of them got ill
because they were castrating with an old method
that still goes on these days,
not completely, but in the 1800s all the time.
They castrate using their teeth,
so these are, yeah, these are humans who go,
and two of these guys were castrating these lambs
with their teeth, and they got very ill.
- One of my best friends has done that in Australia.
- Really? - West Australia, yep.
- Did they get ill?
- Well, he's pretty insane, but he's not sick.
- What, I think he is sick, yeah.
(laughing)
- And they go by on a conveyor belt, right,
and you lie underneath them,
and you just whip him off on by one.
- What?
- Yeah.
- Well, you come up like Jaws,
like you just bite off their balls?
- Is your friend Australian?
- He lived in Australia for a year.
- Well, he was British.
- Yeah.
- Feels like they kind of saw him coming, didn't they?
- Yeah, we all do this, mate.
(laughing)
- This guy looks like he'll bite the balls off anything.
- I just don't get wrestling.
- What?
- It doesn't make any sense to me.
We've covered it before on this podcast,
and I find it impossible to research,
'cause everything you read about it,
you're like, is this real?
Did this really happen?
The confusion of real sport and fake acting is bewildering.
Like, there's this fight between him and Hulk Hogan,
which was this really famous fight,
and apparently it was super controversial.
It was in 1988, and there was a referee,
a famous referee called Dave Hebner,
who was refereed wrestling matches,
and he happened to have an identical twin.
- Oh, yes.
- And they tracked down for this match.
- The referee?
- Yeah, the referee had an identical twin.
- Okay, he didn't really, I think.
- No, he did really.
I've seen the actual pictures, either he did,
or there's some amazing Photoshopping going on,
but he had this identical twin,
and so, right, Andre the Giant's agent
got Dave, who was supposed to referee the match,
locked him in a cupboard, and then bribed Earl,
his identical twin, to referee the game instead,
and he did, and then he made Andre the Giant won,
and then Dave broke out of his closet,
and then him and his identical twin brother
had a big fight afterwards in front of the crowd.
- This is the weirdest conversation.
- I really wanna hear Anna doing the Coventry of WWF.
- I don't understand any of this.
Is that real?
Oh my God.
- But there's storylines, there's storylines.
You go to the theater all the time,
are you standing up and going,
"What the fuck is going on here?"
- No, no, no, because in the write-ups of the theater,
it doesn't say, and there was an incredibly
controversial moment when Hamlet's mother
remarried Hamlet's uncle, and the audience couldn't,
you're like, "Okay, this is a story."
There was in the Wikipedia page, there's this one.
Was it controversial, or was it all made up?
- It's all made up.
- It's all made up, it's all made up.
- Then why is it controversial?
- It's controversial in the world of wrestling.
- Which is a fake world.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Okay. - Now you're getting it.
(all laughing)
- No, it is weird how it's presented as true.
You know, normally it plays, there is a synopsis,
and normally when you go out of the play,
the thing doesn't keep happening out.
- No, but I just think it's amazing
that we found the edge of Anna's comfort zone.
- Yeah.
- I never thought we'd get there.
- Who would know as pro wrestling is fake?
(all laughing)
- The town choir championships.
I just think this is so amazing
that these kind of things have the budget for this.
- I've been there once.
- What?
(all laughing)
- Did not place.
- What?
Do you know where they were held, the last ones?
- The one I went to was in either Lancashire
or Yorkshire, I can't remember.
- Cool, the last one was in Bermuda, so I feel like.
(all laughing)
- Do you ever get the feeling you chose the wrong year?
- I mean, who was paying for town choir, it's good.
Anyway, this year, it's the first time a Brit
has won the town choir championship.
It was very exciting.
- Mark Wiley beat off 24 other contestants.
(all laughing)
- And they were like, "Oh, yay!"
- It's one of the requirements these days.
(all laughing)
He actually said.
- For legal reasons, we have to correct that.
(all laughing)
- Sorry, so this guy won over and above
24 other contestants.
What he won was an awful lot of rum, he said.
(all laughing)
Which I needed for medicinal purposes.
He explained which is understandable
after the trauma he'd undergone, so.
(all laughing)
- Okay, it's time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that we're sitting here
in the Covent Garden office.
This is a important room to us,
and it's the last time the four of us
are ever gonna be in this room together doing the podcast
'cause Anna's going off and the offices are moving.
But it's also important for another reason
because in 2022, Anna and I set a Guinness World Record
right here in this room.
We became the world record holders of the longest
anyone has ever played.
Keep the balloon in the air, tennis game between two people.
- That was amazing. - In history.
- I remember that three weeks when you were doing that,
it was just 'cause we were coming
and we'd have to work around you.
- Record the podcast each week.
- Oh my God, it was so hard.
It was tough, wasn't it?
- And not sleeping to that level.
I mean, the amount of Red Bull that we had to.
- Yeah, yeah. - Yeah, yeah.
By the third week, I just was really surprised
you were still doing it.
- Yeah, so that was the rehearsal.
When we actually did it, it was 80 minutes
we lost it, 80 minutes for keeping a balloon in there.
- And do you still have that record?
- We've been beaten.
- Oh no. - Yep, we've been beaten.
Someone beat us by eight seconds.
With, I would argue, an unfair advantage.
They had a giant balloon.
It was like the size of a beach ball.
- It should be a restriction on balloon size.
- Well, you should have read the small print.
- I should have read the small print, yeah.
But one thing we did manage to do
is make it into a physical Guinness World Record book.
So there's a picture of me and Anna
in the Guinness World Records 2023.
- That's not us, what?
- What, that's, that's-
- Oh there, sorry, I was gonna get that bloke below.
- Who was the chicken in your mind when I was-
(all laughing)
- That's your man holding a chicken.
- What about, is that Irving Finkel above you?
- That is Irving Finkel.
- And what does it say?
Oldest depiction of a ghost.
- Oldest depiction of a ghost.
- You're really on the best page here, right?
- Well, what you'll notice as well
is I'm responsible for that ghost
getting the Guinness World Record, yeah.
- Tell us how.
- I took Craig Glende, who is the Guinness World Records
editor-in-chief to the British Museum
to meet the world's oldest ghost
to give it a Guinness World Record.
- I wonder if you're the only person in that book, Dan,
who's got two world records.
- And that's possible.
- Is Usain Bolt in there?
- No, you can't claim the same world record
as Irving Finkel.
You didn't find the oldest ghost.
- No, no, I just got the oldest ghost.
- I just, you know.
- I'm sorry, Dan, can I just check this book?
Can I just have a quick look at it?
So this is, Guinness World Records 2023.
- Yeah.
- And it's about an event that happened in 2022.
(all laughing)
- And this is maybe the most successful book in history.
- Oh, okay.
Maybe it's all right sometimes.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, but so we did that.
We did that here in this room.
- This ghost was depicted 2,500 years ago.
(all laughing)
- Yes, yes, the world's oldest ghost
is not going to have appeared in 2023.
(all laughing)
But yeah, it's, and Anna, that's for you,
'cause I know you don't have a copy.
So I want you to have,
because obviously you don't have a copy.
You're not interested in this kind of stuff.
So yeah, so now we're forcing a copy onto you.
- I mean, we did, we cheated, didn't we?
- We did cheat, we didn't cheat.
- Oh, hello.
- What are you talking about?
We didn't cheat.
- Well, we're friends with Craig, who's fantastic,
who organizes all the Guinness stuff,
and he gave us a tip-off
that no one's tried to break this category,
but it is a category.
So as long as you get over an hour.
So Ashley, we went for 20 minutes more than we needed to,
which showed a lot of commitment,
'cause it was pub time by then.
- It's right, yeah, and Anna drank the whole way through.
There's a big glass of wine in her hand.
I think I had a beer, but it was,
I can't quite remember now.
It was daunting.
It was very scary.
It's very scary keeping a balloon in the air, wasn't it?
Do you remember the like, the-
- I'm sorry, what is riding on it really?
I mean, if you-
- There was a bomb inside and it touches the ground.
- You literally could've just tried again the next day,
or the next hour.
- Do you know how tedious it is,
saying that we're just down Shriver for almost two hours.
(all laughing)
- The record should have been
the person who spent the most time with that Shriver.
(all laughing)
- Even the Goat pissed off after 20 minutes.
I'll tell you what, there's been a lot of adventures
where Anna has been the kind of,
the butt of the story, I would say, to an extent.
Like Little Adventures.
- The Garfield Danes of the Stories.
- The ass, we will be missing the ass soon.
- What are you talking about?
- I just, I get a bit upset
because I wasn't there for some of my favorite ones,
and James was.
James, you two have had quite a few adventures.
Well, there was the time that Anna flipped over
her bike by canal, knocked her teeth out,
and you had to rescue her outside a pub because-
- I wouldn't say I rescued her.
I took her to the hospital.
- Yeah, that was very nice of you
'cause they didn't have a phone on me or anything,
and so I had to wait for a pass by to come.
- Who do you think knocked you off the bike?
(all laughing)
- Well, can I just say on that?
'Cause it was quite funny, 'cause we're in A&E,
and we were just sat there waiting for you to be seen,
and you just come back from Ireland,
you've been on holiday in Ireland,
and you were telling me a story about what had happened,
and for some reason you'd upset someone who ran a shop,
and you upset this woman so much
that she started shouting at you, saying,
"Who the hell do you think you are?"
And when you told me the story,
you said it in a really thick Irish accent.
- I could do it now.
- Well, let's not do that, but you said it
just as the doctor was coming from behind you
to say, "Anatoshinsky, where are you?"
And so all he saw was me and you,
you with your face covered in blood,
and you yelling at me, "Who the hell do you think you are?"
And we just looked like some kind of domestic abuse couple.
- Oh, my God.
- Yes, we're working on our issues.
Just fix my jaw, let's get out of here.
- He would have heard then you go to an English accent
and think, "Okay, she's seriously wobbly,
something's happened, we need to keep her in."
- You just gotta have foreign accents in real life.
- Exactly, yeah.
- Who's the president?
- Or the T-sock, you know.
(all laughing)
- But the best story, and I don't know if you're gonna say it,
I just wanna tear it up and say,
"I hope you'll say it."
And it's the regret of my life, I wasn't there for it,
is when James and Anna went to a university
in order to tell the students Canterbury,
and you stayed the night in a hotel,
and Anna got a bit drunk.
(all laughing)
- I don't think I should tell the story.
- I should have, I don't know.
- I'll tell you what I remember of it,
which is that James and I went and,
yeah, Alan Davies was doing a show at Canterbury.
You went to do something.
- I think he just got like an honorary degree
or something like that.
- Yes, he had, and so he was being interviewed,
and it was great.
And so we went for some moral support.
Me, James, Alan, and--
- John Lloyd?
- John Lloyd.
- Alan went to support himself.
(all laughing)
Do you know what, I'm gonna come along for moral support.
- For moral support.
- Afterwards, we had quite a lot to drink in some hotel bar,
and we were staying in this place
that was actually next to the cathedral, which was awesome.
- It was almost like part of the cathedral, wasn't it?
- It was kind of appended to it.
- Certainly a place where I wouldn't do anything.
(all laughing)
- God might judge adversely.
So great night.
I guess at about three o'clock,
we sort of went to, we tried to bed,
and I have this thing often.
- In the morning.
(all laughing)
Bloody hell.
I didn't know that.
I thought it was all happened around 11 p.m., 11.30.
Three.
- Woo.
And he's always stopped at that bit of the story,
just jaw on the floor, can't hear anything else.
- Okay, go on, go on.
- So I really love looking round places
and sneaking into places that maybe I'm not supposed to be in,
and like disuse rooms and buildings,
and sometimes use buildings, whatever.
And so I wasn't really tired,
and I thought I'd go for a wander.
So I remember first of all,
pushing open a lot of doors in my hotel corridor
to see what opened.
(all laughing)
Managing to get into a sort of weird garden
out of a fire escape,
and then climbing over a fence into the cathedral,
kind of the cathedral, then wandering around there.
And then what happens often with me is,
you're drunk and you're in this place,
you're not allowed to be in,
and you're like, "Well, I guess I'll go back now."
So climbed back over the fence, went back upstairs,
and I pushed another door in the hotel,
and ended up in this lecture theater,
where I sort of fanied around for a bit,
looked in all the cupboards,
trying to see what I could see really.
- You found a lot of candy, didn't you?
- I found a lot of sweets.
I found a massive bag of different colored sweets,
and I thought what would be so amusing would be,
if I took these all back to my room,
and I just took all the green ones out,
and then I just put it back in the room,
and that's when I freak the shit out
of whoever comes to get the sweets next time,
and also greens my favorite color of sweet.
So I spent about half an hour in my room
with a huge bag, taking out all the green sweets.
And then I went to put the bag of sweets back,
because I don't want to just steal all people's sweets.
And then as I was leaving the room,
having replaced the bag of sweets,
I just saw this massive whiteboard
at the front of the room,
and so I thought, okay, I'll just grab a marker pen.
I grabbed a marker pen and I wrote in big letters,
yippee-ki-ay, motherfuckers,
in capitals on this whiteboard.
And then that was actually ideal timing,
because I heard someone coming down the corridor,
and doing a bit of a, "Oi, and what are you doing?"
And so then I legged it and it was a member of staff,
so I legged it back to my room and she sort of chased me.
- So then you went to bed, right?
I've been asleep this whole time.
I woke up the next morning to check out,
and you were like a naughty school girl
sat in the corner of the reception,
being bollocked by someone.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it transpired.
It was actually very unlucky,
because it hadn't been a whiteboard.
It had been a built-in white screen
that was part of the wall.
(laughing)
I'd written on it in indelible, unremovable ink,
in large letters, yippee-ki-ay, motherfuckers.
A die-hard quote, oh, I do remember that from the night
before when I was chased by the security guard,
I was going, "It's a quote from die-hard."
(laughing)
To excuse it, like, "I'm not saying
"yippee-ki-ay, motherfuckers."
It's a quote. - It's a quote.
- Anyway, the push comes to shove.
"The next morning, at 9 a.m., there was a church group
"who had booked that room."
(laughing)
- That did seem to be the truth of the matter.
- They walked in.
- Someone desperately scrubbing off the bottom of the pot.
- They couldn't scrub it off, they had to cover it up.
They had to cover it up with a curtain.
And I was charged a small amount of money
for the repairs to the room.
- Less, in fact, probably,
than one small bag of laundry in New York City.
Pretty good going.
- It was the funniest thing that I've ever experienced,
being on the train coming back
and you having to ring up our boss to tell them,
because I think it had come off the company credit cards
or something, so you knew that they were gonna find out.
- No, they told our accountant at work.
So actually, the first thing I knew was,
just empathize for a minute with me, please.
I'd gone to bed incredibly drunk about four in the morning.
My phone rang at 8 a.m.
and I saw it was Liz, our lovely accountant.
And imagine the heart sinking
when I saw Liz's name come up.
I thought, I don't know what's happening.
(laughing)
Huff and rumble, and yeah, I picked up
and the hotel had indeed called her.
Yeah, it was tough.
I thought it was gonna be fired, actually.
We laughed now, guys, but this could have been
the end of the podcast.
- 'Cause I remember pretty much all the way from,
like, let's say, well, for about half an hour
on the train back, you're like,
"I'm gonna get fired, what are we gonna do?"
- Yeah.
- There'll be no more podcasts,
'cause I won't be able to do this anymore.
- Yeah, yeah, I'm probably going to prison.
- Yeah.
- And to hell.
Let's not forget the cathedral's right next door.
- Yeah.
- It's the greatest story ever told.
- Anyway, good luck getting those stories
out of these so-called guests you're having on in my house.
(laughing)
Is there a pass going to do that?
Yeah, she probably would.
She would have been up for it.
- Oh, well, let's have, why don't we do
one more batch of "Best of Anna"
and just hear a bit more from "The Greatest Hits"
from the last nine years, Anna Tyshensky.
(upbeat music)
- I was having a look at the Reverend Richard Coles'
autobiography, or biography.
And he was saying, it was just a throwaway line
that I then looked into.
He was saying that a lot of vickers have funny names,
and he was saying he knew someone who insisted
on everyone, even bishops, calling them the Reverend Gazz.
And so then I thought, "I wonder what funny names
there have been in the church over the years?"
There's this blog, the blog of St. Chrysostom's church
in Manchester, and it's really good.
You know when people put proper effort
into quite an obscure thing?
And there's a piece on funny names of church leaders
throughout history, and there are some such good ones.
So I like this anecdote, which is Henry Joy Fiennes Clinton,
who was a rector in the early 20th century,
who went to see the Bishop of London,
and the bishop said, "Take a chair, Clinton,"
to which he replied, "It's Fiennes Clinton."
And the bishop said, "In that case, take two."
And so it's just, I think that was funny from a bishop.
Come on, it's a... It's Bishapuma.
It's Bishapuma. It's Bishapuma, yeah.
Okay, we won't get him on the podcast.
Just this is his audition tape, and I thought...
Oh, no, come on, give us more zingers.
Right, wow.
Okay.
Okay, what about this?
The very Reverend Gonville-Obey French Baytag,
but French is spelled with a small F and two of them.
Is that important for the anecdote?
There's no anecdote.
It's just the word "French" spelled slightly differently.
No, Anna, we want you to tell us every single one you've found.
This is literally all I've got now.
It's just a super, not very amusing name.
Okay, Father John Brabazan, Brabazan Loutha.
Come on. It's two Brabazans.
Brabazan, Brabazan.
Oh, my God, I'm just picturing Jimmy Carr
at the Habersmith Apollo.
The next act is a fucking killer act.
She's got some amazing anecdotes.
Anna Tashinsky, everybody.
Duh-duh-duh-duh-duh.
We've got Father Page Turner, we've got Father Pickles.
Page Turner, open with Page Turner.
That's great. Father Pickles is funny as well.
I'll reorder the set.
Father Careful, Father Christmas.
Okay.
So that's the one I should stick with, Father Christmas.
You don't think stick with any of it.
Okay.
Have you guys heard of St Andrew Undershaft?
LAUGHTER
I can't believe...
You just said a name way funnier than Anna's 20 minutes.
Just upstage the full day of work.
I'm so sorry.
I've been delving into church, aren't I?
This is right under your nose the whole time.
On the subject of people being allergic to things,
I went on to...
I continued my search.
And I went to Yahoo Answers,
because people often ask questions.
The best site on the internet.
This was the question.
So, "My girlfriend is allergic to almost every animal
"you'd find in a petting zoo.
"If she inhales air that is around a horse,
"she can be hospitalized.
"Now, she loves giraffes.
"Does anyone think she'd be allergic to them too?
"I was thinking of surprising her on her birthday
"with a trip to the local zoo to pet a giraffe."
And the reply, the top-rated reply,
because that's how it works on Yahoo Answers,
the most voted to reply,
"If she's allergic to almost every animal
"I guarantee you the zoo will contain more than just giraffes.
"Why don't you do something less stupid?"
LAUGHTER
So, where did you take her in the end, then?
I did, I did.
LAUGHTER
Britain's leading female table tennis player
is this woman, this girl, called Tintin Ho.
And do you guys...
Can you guess why she's called that?
She's got a quiff, Tintin.
That's why I was... No, I was thinking Tintin.
Got a small dog called Snowy.
Confusingly, it's not related to the character of Tintin.
Wait, she hangs out with an old fisherman called Captain Haddock.
Again, it's not like a thing.
She has a pair of twins that she hangs out with
called the Thompson twins.
You can't just stop us making Tintin jokes, Anna, immediately.
She's got her father is called Herge.
Right, as I have made quite clear, it's not related to Tintin,
and there must be other avenues you can pursue.
She's Belgian, you know?
Right, I'm just going to tell you, OK?
No, no, no, no, no. I feel like we're close.
She's made up ten.
Yeah, he's found something different, but incorrect.
No, it's because her dad is obsessed with table tennis.
And actually, that's kind of weird.
Sorry, hang on. It's coming, it's coming.
I was so sure you were going to say her dad is obsessed with Tintin.
I wish I hadn't brought this up.
He's obsessed with table tennis.
And the initials of table tennis are TT.
So we called her Tintin, and, in fact, her brother is called Ping.
And she said it was between her being called Tintin
and her being called Pong when she was born.
Wow. And so she says that she is delighted that she didn't get bombed.
You can't have two kids who call them Ping and Pong.
The social services will get involved.
You would think.
Aber, in 1976, they had the number one spot for 39 weeks,
and after 12 weeks of it, their version of Top of the Pops
just stopped showing the music video,
because you've seen it for 12 weeks, guys.
In Australia, that one. Yeah, fans absolutely rioted.
And that was on the Australian version of Top of the Pops,
which was called Countdown.
Yeah. Well, when you say fans rioted, did I say rioted?
Yeah. I meant, "were furious."
One complaint was registered with the ABC.
No, but generally, look, when they toured, one mother ran
and she put her baby down on the road
so that their tour caravan would stop and she could get an autograph.
Whoa. Right.
There was a hotel which cut up their bedsheets after they'd left,
and they sold it via newspaper.
Oh, they do that all the time. Yeah, they did that with the Beatles as well.
Did they? I've got about six of them. Not the baby thing, though.
I just wanted you to know we will not succumb to that kind of blackmail.
If there's a baby in front of our tour bus, we're going straight over it.
Who knows fish policy, right?
(LAUGHTER)
It's very important to get that clear from the outset.
That's good.
It's very controversial the way they vote in the Grammys.
Oh, yeah.
Because, well, until this year, it was super secret.
It sounds quite exciting.
And I think what used to happen was,
winners were decided by this, like, 12,000 strong
Recording Academy bunch of voters.
But then, I think, partly because the awards just kept going so wrong,
and they just kept giving it to weird people.
They had to change the rules, and I think the straw that broke the camel's back
came in the early '90s when "Album of the Year" was up,
and Bruce Springsteen's "Born in the USA" was released,
and "Princess Purple Rain" was released,
and Lionel Richie's "Can't Slow Down" won.
And everyone said, "We don't like that. That's not as good as the other two."
And so they formed a secret committee,
which basically goes through all the 12,000 votes and takes out the duds.
Because, actually, you would think that having a larger group, 12,000,
would be more likely to give you a democratic answer, right?
Yeah.
But a democratic answer isn't necessarily the best answer, James.
Is that not right?
That's my view, and my one-way ticket to Russia has just come through.
Anyway, people got quite pissed off by the secret committee
because no one knew how they voted or why they voted,
and there's someone called the Weekend, I think.
Oh, the Weekend.
The Weekend.
Oh, right.
Well, it's spelled the Weekend.
Yeah, yeah.
Um, so...
This show has certainly weakened over the years, hasn't it?
Yeah, so it's spelled like Weekend, anyway, but without any.
So, um, he...
Well, with two E's.
But not three.
Anyway, the Weekend got annoyed that he hadn't got nominated.
I think it's pronounced the Weckend.
Ladies and gentlemen, the Weekend.
I just...
I want a new podcast where we give Anna the name of all the partners
that are in the charts and see if she can pronounce them.
They've asked me to read out the nominations next year.
I'm quite nervous now.
Lil Nas the Tenth?
I didn't know there were nine other Lil Nases.
I know how to artificially inseminate a cow
based on researching for this podcast.
Cool.
So, about 5% of dairy cows in this country,
when they have to be inseminated,
they get inseminated just by semen rather than the actual bull.
And for some reason, I found myself reading
this really in-depth farmer's guide to how to do it.
And what I didn't realise was, so you get a semen gun,
which you put the semen in.
Imagine you bring your semen gun to a gunfight.
No!
Dammit.
You bring your semen gun to the insemination fight,
but what you do is, you have to...
So, there are two entries into a cow.
So, it's much like a human's...
Yeah.
You've got the...
Oh, sorry.
There are three now.
Oh, sorry, there are three.
We're in Devon.
Something tells me you're not the biggest expert in this room
on the number of ways into a cow.
I know that people in Devon know all these secret ways,
but there are two entries...
There are two entries into the back of a cow, officially.
And so, you know, one is the rectum, as we all have.
Stop, Professor. Let me write this down.
Children, wouldn't you be quiet?
You've got the rectum, and then you've got the sex tubes,
and they're different...
All right, the cervix.
But what you do is, amazingly, when you're inseminating a cow,
you obviously have to stick the gun in the cervix,
but the way you navigate the gun
into the uterine horns, as they're called,
is you have to put your other arm that's not holding the gun
into the rectum.
And so, it's so amazing.
And they say you shove your arm into the rectum,
insert your arm into the rectum,
get someone else to hold the cow's tail aside while you do this.
No, it would be a bald farmer who tried using one foot
to pin the cow's tail.
This is the worst game of Twister I've ever played.
It says "left hand sex tubes."
Anyway, look.
It just feels like this lesson isn't going to end,
so you essentially use your rectum arm
to navigate your semen gun,
which is in the vaginal canal,
and you push it through.
So you've got your arm in the rectum,
and it's pushing against the other canal
so that it gets into the uterus,
and it's called rectovaginal insemination.
And that's lesson over. Enjoy.
Well, there we go.
There it is, some of the best of Anna Tyshinski's best bits.
I was trying to think, you know,
is there some way that we could keep a bit of you here, you know?
Oh, God, my God.
Is there some way...
We want her to give us the finger.
Give us the finger.
Just in spirit, you know? Just in spirit.
She's been metaphorically giving everyone the finger
for the last nine years.
I'll tell you what, though.
I thought hard about it.
I thought, "How do we keep a bit of Anna here?"
And I worked it out.
I suddenly remembered the weirdest story
I have ever heard involving Anna Tyshinski,
and it is this.
There was a Christmas party that Anna once went to,
and part of the party, they said,
"We're going to do a really fun thing.
We're going to do a raffle.
You're just going to take a ticket,
and you're going to get a present,
so everyone bring a present so you can give it to someone."
So, I was talking to the friend today who I bumped into.
She gave a scarf, for example.
Right.
Yeah, normal things.
Normal things were handed around.
This person, whose name is Lenny,
received her number and received her prize in the raffle.
I never met Lenny.
And this is the prize that Anna had donated.
It is her teeth.
Oh, my God!
That fell out of her mouth.
Lenny hasn't treasured and kept the teeth.
WTS.
She has.
They're in her home.
I went to her home today to pick it up.
This is Lenny didn't know who Anna was.
She opens up her present,
and there are teeth from one of the other party members there.
Were these the teeth that got knocked out
when James went to get you from...
Yeah.
Yeah, so these are the teeth.
They got removed.
I thought they were in the canal.
They're in the canal.
We weren't looking for them.
We did.
The fully knocked out ones were in the canal,
and they were the ones that had to get taken out later.
Bloody hell.
Yeah, so Anna thought it'd be normal
to give in a raffle prize her teeth away.
Now, Polly, who is the partner of Lenny,
tried to get rid of Anna's teeth to begin with
because she has a fear of teeth.
She literally hates the tapping of teeth.
It was the worst present that could have arrived into the house.
But as a result,
for the last couple of years since they've had these teeth,
Lenny hides your teeth all over the house to surprise Polly.
If she goes to sleep, she'll put it under her pillow.
If she's opening a pencil case,
the teeth will be inside the pencil case.
Reverse tooth fairy, basically.
And then they almost got given away in another raffle very recently,
but Lenny decided to keep them because she was having too much time.
How much did you pay for those, and have you told your wife?
But so, now, while you're gone, you are here.
There'll be a bit of Anna's always with us.
What we're going to do is we're going to make Sarah Pasco put some of those.
Every time there's a guest,
we're going to make them shove them into their face.
It's going to make the book all sound very weird, isn't it?
But it's worth it to get a bit of me.
Oh, well, I'm so honoured that my teeth have had such a life beyond me, actually.
I know. It's really exciting.
It's a weird story, Dan.
That's a weird story.
You're responsible too, Anna.
James is the only one who gets off Scott for it.
No, actually, you were involved in the losing of the teeth.
What? I was not.
I'm the only one here who doesn't have any involved with this mad,
batshit, teeth raffle story.
You will.
I won't.
You're the next chapter.
Anyway, let's wrap up.
That is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you want to get in contact with any of us about the weird ass stories
that we've said over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Sribeland, Andy at Andrew Hunter, and James.
Hi, James Harkin.
And Anna.
No, you don't say anything.
You're gone.
Yeah, I mean, you can email ScottStackUI.com,
but good luck me ever seeing it.
Yeah.
And you'll see it and do a good impersonation
when you reply, right?
Yeah, that's right.
You'll be wearing the team every time you reply to an email.
I'll time the emails all to go out between 3 and 5 a.m.
and everyone will end Yippee-ki-yay, motherfucker.
Yeah, we're going to our group account at no such thing.
And we'll be back again next week with a really exciting guest
as part of our big rotation of awesome guests,
starting with Sarah Pasco.
And we'll be back with that episode next week.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)