[Bell]
Do you know what it is? Who do you want to work at?
Hello and welcome to another episode of
No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
this week coming to you from the wilderness festival!
[Cheering]
My name is Dan Schreiber and I'm sitting here with Ani Chazinski, James
Harkin and Andrew Hunter Murray and once again we have gathered around the
microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go. Starting with our first
fact, this week that's my fact. My fact is, according to a new scientific
study, the best way to perform CPR is to do it while humming
the Macarena. How cool is that? And I think they recommend humming it because
they probably don't believe if you're trying to save someone life and you're
going "hamadamba temadamba temamakarena, you're the right person to be doing it."
Are they even chalyrics? Are you just dead then?
Does anyone know the actual lyrics? I think everyone knows the word macarena
and know what the word in that song is. Yeah, exactly. But it's what it is about
this song is that it has a BPM so every song has a B per minute and this BPM
is 103 and as a result, when they're trying to teach people the perfect
counts that you need on a chest as you're trying to save someone's life,
the macarena happens to be the perfect amount. And before that, they used to
think it was staying alive by the beaches. That's right.
Because that's about 103 or 104 as well. Yeah. But actually also maybe it's
supposed to be about 100 is the best, right? But macarena is good because
everyone kind of knows the beat of that so it's good to do. But I thought I'd
look at some others that are 100 beats per minute. So if anyone's having a
heart attack, you should try these ones. Crazy and loved by Beyoncé.
Yeah. Independent women by Destiny's Child.
Any of these work. Hips don't lie by Shakira. That's my favourite.
Or my chemical romance dead. Yeah. Not a good one.
That's not a good one. I've found a few more. So Simon and Garfunkel bridge over
Troubled Water. If it's just a nice mood, you want to chill everyone out with that?
Sometimes the situation doesn't need something fun.
Okay. Sometimes poignancy is needed.
Well, the way they sing that on the X Factor, which is the slowest song in the
history of time. Oh, okay. Well, how about this one?
It doesn't have any beat. It doesn't have any beat. You just, you'd pause on
Lacka Bridge. That is how you do slow.
Da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da
It gets to the next. It's a good way of multitasking and fair sharing. So Macarena is by lost Del Rio. Yes
Okay, and this is very much a one-hit wonder isn't it? They never had any other hits. Oh James
I have got at least one of the other hits right here on my paper. What? It's Macarena Christmas
It's released about 18 months after Macarena and it is a kiddie not the worst song ever released
It's a it's a medley of jingle bells joined to the world rude off the Red Nose reindeer and the Macarena
Wow, and they just break off and they do a bit of Macarena
I'm at least I think five or six albums. One of them was Macarena non-stop
Which the compilation album it only has eight tracks and five of them at the Macarena
But you know what's amazing about lost Del Rio this band they got together in
1964 I believe it was 62 or 64 the same year that the Rolling Stones got together
Okay, they had their hit 32 years into their career
That was finally they were like should we give up I'm sure we're gonna hit it one day mates
Let's do it and they did and then they must have thought wow
We've made it and that was the end of their career. Yeah
That's still going that's still performing. But are they I when I'm researching this I read an article from
1999 the headline of which was does anyone remember the Macarena? I mean, and that's what was that what a stupid article
Everyone remembers the Macarena I watched a video you know you come see these on YouTube where they show teenagers stuff from the 90s
Or whatever and see if they know what it is. Yeah, every single one of them knew what the Macarena was
Yeah, no one knew the band, but they all knew the song. Yeah, and in 2003 so that's 10 years after the record was released
They were still making a quarter of a million dollars a year royalties. Wow
And it's extraordinary the original Macarena dance there was an original this that was the second dance
It was when they made the video when there was a remix done of the song the first one was an incredibly complicated flamingo dance
That was done in clubs. You would have to be an expert in order to do it
It had doubled the amount of moves that the original
Verse had was invented by a don't like a random aerobic teacher or dance teacher or something. Yeah, me a fire
Yeah, yeah, yeah, or me a fry. She was in the video clip and so she wanted something that kids could dance to and adults
Who have to go to nightclubs, but don't know how to dance could dance to so the four of us bow to her
You've saved us actually Macarena. It's about a woman called Macarena
But the name Macarena was originally Mac Delayna and it was just a word for like a sensuous woman and it comes from Mary Mac Delayna
Then it was a word for any kind of prostitute and then it was a word for a sensuous woman, right?
So really it should be hey Mac Delayna hey prostitute
Well, and it's about a woman who prostitute in the song the lyrics are actually the woman saying
Don't worry about my boyfriend. He's gone off to fight
You two are his best mates. Do you want to shag and said is that Macarena?
It's not a good message to be sending 12 year olds at this goes no
This is this is just a little nugget. I enjoyed it went to number one in France
It went to number one in a number of countries, but not in the UK not in the UK
because because it was the world by
TLC no one to be by the spice girls. No
Wow, that's bad look wasn't it because it's like the biggest song of all time
But yeah, I'm up against there was a big there was a big gospel around the room at that 20-year-old chopped news. Yeah
Hey guys and blood be to aces to number one as well
How do you think they were probably sad but quietly confident going? It's all right
We've got Macarena Christmas in the bag. We'll be
We'll be back and then to become one came out they have
So in France they went to number one. Do you know what song they knocked off the number one?
Oh, it's a French song. No, no, it's gonna regret re-en the only French time anyone knows
It was the theme tune to the ex files. Oh, yeah
That was number one that was number one in France. I think that was the one that you oh it did well in the UK
Isn't that tubular bells Mike feel Mike old field did a cover of it later. How weird is that?
You're thinking the exorcist. Yeah. Yeah. Should we talk about CPR?
Yes
If you have a problem with CPR as in so a lot of people are quite light and it's you need a lot of pressure to get
Someone's just deep enough to get the blood flowing while you wait for the ambulance
So if you are like a tip is to jump on the person who you're trying to administer you could actually be doing the macarena
Well, kind of yes you could
Wow, sorry. I say tip and I like there's no medical advice on this stage. I think I was better say yes
Don't use this tip. There is a doctor though who does recommend using the feet
I think people have said especially if you're a bit older
You've lost some of your muscle strength and but also advice now or advice releasing 2010
It's always changing is don't do the breathing anymore none of the snogging you just do the hands to the heart
Don't you just do the heart. So you're doing a bit there isn't so much fun. Yeah, exactly just the jumping up and down
The mouth to mouth one is really weird because it kind of was discovered in the 18th century
And then it just got forgotten about for about 50 to 100 years and basically no one did it at all
And then it came back and the reason they stopped it is because they realized what was coming out of your mouth when you breathe
And it's carbon dioxide and they were saying well, what's the point of breathing carbon dioxide into someone's lungs because they breathe oxygen
Yeah, and you know what the answer is to know why that's not true
No, it's because when you breathe in and breathe out you actually only absorb about 40% of the oxygen sort of still plenty of oxygen in your breath
Any kind of oxygen is better than okay, so how long if we started it?
So if someone breathed in at the edge of the room here and then they passed the breath around the room
How long would it be before there was no point in that exercise? I think it's worth a try, isn't it? All right. I feel an experiment coming up. Okay. I think we should start with that topless guy. You're in that old
But people that tried all sorts of weird CPR over the ages
They used to be the barrel type where you there was a big round barrel and you were sort of strapped to it
Face down with your stomach over the barrel and I don't know how you did this so quickly when someone's obviously dying of a heart attack in front of you
And then as the person who's saving them you sort of stood in between their legs and you roll them
On and off the barrel, don't you? And it was the idea was that it eventually forced your heart into going in really?
Yeah, yeah, it's like one of those did you ever go to playgrounds where you would run on a barrel that span round and round
Yeah, but I've seen cartoons where that helped. Right
That will that's medical advice from the Victorian age
Hey, we need to move on to our next fact shortly. Oh, can I just there was so you know how people are always giving mouth to mouth and CPR to animals
Weirdly successfully. Yeah, I've no
Yeah, you know how people are always giving mouth to mouth to animals. Weirdly successful. There was a guy this you're gonna talk about the guy this year with the
Frog there's a guy this year who did it with a frog after the frog happening here. Oh, is this your fact? No, it's not mine
Actually mine was the one I was gonna say down. Let's do your effect. You do the frog thing. Let's
No, this was a this was a deer and it was a deer who was drowning in a swimming pool and an RSP-ZA officer was called and he got the deer out of the pool
And he gave it chest compressions and see CPR and mouth to mouth. Give it the kiss of life until it choked
He said it properly like in films coughed water into his mouth
And then and then he started choking it then had to give him CPR
Where does the frog come into this? Yeah
And you know the deer got up he brushed it down and then he said the deer looked at him and then ran away
Sweet, yeah, it's a good story, I know, but I just wonder has anything happened with any smaller maybe amphibious?
No, it hasn't I think we're moving on interestingly a frog
This is a great story. There was a I can't wait this guy was walking just
Minding his own business when he came across a snake on the ground and the snake was choking
And he thought I'm not gonna give CPR to a snake. How could you tell a snake is choking? It was sort of like doing that
Okay, yeah, yeah, and suddenly out of its mouth shoots a frog
So it swallowed the frog, but the the frog forced its way back out
Okay, but in the process died the man saw the frog and he gave CPR to the frog and he brought it back to life
Yeah, and he brought the rope home. What happens to this snake?
He doesn't feature in the rest of the story
All right, look we need to be about to our next fact it is time for fact number two and that is Chazinsky
My fact this week is that Donald Trump negotiated an extremely bad deal for himself when he wrote the art of the deal
This is because a so Tony Schwartz was a guy who ghost wrote the art of the deal with Trump and he gave a talk a while back
And he openly said Trump negotiated an extremely bad deal with me. I got a great deal out of it
He didn't unheard of things so there was an advance of half a million dollars for the art of the deal and Trump gave his
Ghostwriter 50% of the advance and then 50% of all the royalties
So this guy has just been making millions and millions from this book
This is unheard of in publishing. I think someone who a negotiating professor
Called Deepak Malhotra said there is not a better deal out there in the world for ghost writing
And then when the book came out Trump hosted an absolutely massive party then he and Trump tower
I think it was there was a big red carpet loads of celebrities came
There was a giant cake replica of Trump tower and then he went to his ghost writer and he went well
You owe me 50% for the price of this party and the ghost writer went, I don't think so
And he ended up paying about a thousand pounds just fed the drinks that him and his friends
Do you know what the inspiration for the book was for the book the art of the deal?
No, there was an article all about Trump in GQ and it was a popular article as in that issue of GQ
So well because Trump was on the front cover. He was a businessman at the time and then they thought
Why don't we see if we can turn this into a book?
So they tested out what the book would look like they designed a dummy cover and then it had a picture of him
looking heroic on the front and then they wrapped it around a thick Russian novel and thought what it would look like a
thick Russian novel
Guys the clues were there from the stars. Wow. No, okay. All right. Oh, we go
What's exciting is you've all heard something that won't be in the actual show and we release it so that's
He has a bad record of deal-making though, right? He's this was actually an article by Jonathan Frieden
I think in the Guardian pointed out his deal-making history, but so the apprentice first series extremely successful
So he asked for an increase in what he was paid. I think it's per episode. He got 50 grand
He asked for an increase to one million dollars
That's good deal-making, isn't it? That sounds like a deal-making. He ended up with 60 grand
But no, a lot of people say not a good deal-maker someone else who's done a deal with him said he seems way too keen
You've got to seem cool. He sort of paces around the room like he's wearing a sign saying desperate and who said that Vladimir
What was he called?
He chose to remain anonymous
Do you know he he released a novel years ago? Yeah called Trump Tower and and then he
Effectively unreleased it in that the novel still exists, but he took his name off
So it was ghost-ridden by someone else and he had his name though
It was a Donald Trump book. It was called Trump Tower and it was a it was a book based on an idea for a TV show that he developed
Which was meant to be Trump Tower done like the TV show Dallas or all those American soaps
It was the life of all the people that worked in Trump Tower and they got a pilot
But the pilot didn't get made so they ended up doing this book and on the front
It said it was the sexiest novel of the decade. Wow. Which decade?
It was 2011 was it was it was old 2011. It's a current. It's he's he's predicted
We still cannot top the sexiness of this book. Wow. It was an erotic novel, wasn't it? Yeah, that's novel and so I was reading some snippets of it
It is this is how erotic it is
So someone walks into a room a guest in Trump Tower and sees at least six women not wearing tops and says I must be dead
I've gone to boob heaven
That's an actual line in an actual novel
He's just very quickly. He's also really good for books Donald Trump because anytime he tweets about a book
That he doesn't like it does really well
So for example fire and fury became massive off the back of him taking it down
Yeah, and there was a very famous. He's a civil rights icon in America called John Lewis and he wrote a number of books
And he wrote a tweet saying I don't think he's fit for president and Trump took him down massively as a result
The sales increase of his books were over a hundred thousand percent
And in the weekend of the tweet seven of the top 20 books were attributed to John Lewis all his books just rose to the top
Wow, he's actually good for book sales if he hates you
The John Lewis Brown is very different in America, isn't it?
Yes, yeah, I've got a couple of bad deals from history. Okay, I've researched so the fact being that
Trump negotiated a bad deal for the order of the deal. I thought this was quite fun
There's a in America the NFL. There's a team the Green Bay Packers and they had a player called Mirror
MIRER
Yeah, I never heard of it. Okay. He was he was a big deal back in the day and his contract
He was so wanted by this team that his agent put a clause in the contract that they eventually the team had to sign and the clause was
That my mirror would be paid under all conditions, and then this is the clause up to and including the end of the world
Including the end of the world
So if some people survived and he was one of them and they were one of them
They would still pay him for all the apocalyptic future that they lived through
They were the last two people other
I've got a bad deal. Oh, yeah, so there's a famous story about the Dutch buying Manhattan Island from the Native Americans for a very small amount of money and
Them's thinking oh these Native Americans they don't understand the value of property
They don't stand the contact of property rights. They absolutely did the problem was the Dutch bought Manhattan from the Canasi Native Americans
Who happened to live next door in Long Island and did not live in Manhattan?
They only use the island of Manhattan to get drunk in
The Dutch showed up and they offered to buy the place on these people saying is this your place? Oh great. We'll buy this for it
So it's like going to a pub and offering a random man standing outside the pub quite drunk
100,000 pounds for this building. I got another sporty one
This is a there's a Swedish soccer player called Stefan Schwartz. Do you remember him James?
So he was paid a four million pound deal with Sunderland for the English Premier League the condition that he had to sign when he was signing
Which for him was a bad deal is he was not allowed to go to space
That was the oh
Yeah, he wanted to be a space Taurus. He was obsessed with going to space
They were like he's obsessed so much. We just have to say no you've got to play football. Yeah, we're gonna
Put that in the contract to me. That's a deal breaker - is it right?
We need to move on to our next facts. We do that. Okay. It is time for fact number three and that is Andy
My fact is that on the bio tapestry you can tell how important someone is by the size of their horse's penis
Um, so there's a professor at the University of Oxford. He's called George Garnett
He has gone through the bio tapestry the whole thing rigorously counting the horses and their penises
And the human there are the same number of penises as
Well, it might be some female horses. There are some female horses. I've got they didn't have penises. Yeah
I think they all work for full you
Um, I think they're written out. I think they might be hidden by a leg or yeah
Sometimes someone standing in front of the horse or a musically holding a vase in front of the horse
Yeah, or the horse is wearing a pair of novelty trousers
Or it's a pantomime horse and they famously don't have penis. Well, they have two some of them
Oh, my horses. Very good point. Um, so he counted all of these and he points out that
King Harold
Who came second in the Battle of Hastings? He has a horse which has a very large penis
But there's one larger horse penis and that belongs to William the Conqueror
So it's a it's a clear the the man who wins the battle has the largest horse's penis
Wow, and this is new right this is a brother. No, no Tubby 66
This is this is new. This is new research. This is breaking. This is to lot of people in the room
This is like this is like the Spice Girls and the Macarena all over again. Yeah
Yeah, so this is very exciting previously neglected research he counted all the human ones as well
He did sorry. There are four and a half would you say?
But I think what happened was a lot of people have kind of paid attention to this in the past because in Victorian times
They were all edited out
Yeah, and there is one guy who had a pair of underpants drawn on him or tapestry on him by the Victorians
That was in the in the English one, right? There's an English wrap. Yeah, sorry in the replica
Yeah, exactly, but this is the first time people have looked at all of them including the horse ones
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so I can believe the so I don't actually know much about the Bay of Tapestry
Not being English myself, so this yeah, and it's a frequent topic of conversation in English hubs of children
I am so lost at dinner parties every time it comes up. I walk around the festival site here
You'll find tools 300 people talking about the buyers
Actually, it gets a bit boring sometimes, you know
But I so I literally had no knowledge of it all so it's fascinating to know that this thing was a it was
68 70 meters long. Yep, which is incredibly long if you put that into context
That's about 30 meters less than 100. No, it's like that would take you saying both roughly seven seconds to run
Yeah, the fastest man running at the Bayer tapestry
The the thing is as well as that a turns out it's not a tapestry at all. No, it's embroidery
So it's got the wrong name
But also if you read the whole thing up until recently when they when they decided to fix this the final scene is missing
Imagine reading 70 meters of story and getting to the final scene and someone's ripped the page out as in the
Williams coronation isn't it? Yeah, yeah, and they added it so they finished was it 2013?
I think yeah, and they did it on an on an island on a channel island
There was over a hundred four hundred people that did it and one of the stitches was done by Prince Charles
So despite the fact it lives over in France made using British royalty
And a lot of people think it was made in Britain anyway in Kent and a lot of people think it was made completely by women because of the
Penises in fact, so historians think that there are there is the occasional erect penis on a dead soldier
And the theory is that the tapestry or embroidery was therefore stitched by women and the women were ridiculing the men for the fact that they used
War to show off their manhood, so it was thought to be kind of a satirical thing when we're saying you idiots
So the people used to fight with no trousers. Yeah, really. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah
No, there was a battle wasn't there were the English had terrible dysentery of the area of the trousers
That was Henry the fifth so it was about as you call it was about a magical
Yeah, but so why are they naked people in there if people were trousers the naked people are mostly in the margins
Yes, so there's the main bit there's the main strip of the biotapestry
Yeah, I think the main story of the battle and then at the top and the bottom there are these margins
This is an amazing thing where they're I love the embroidery because you when you see old art you assume
Oh, it must be done perfect, you know the perspective and everything and there's a couple of moments in the tapestry where they've run out of space
So there's a there's four people holding a chest on on four sticks or two sticks rather four of them and
There's three of them that are nicely done, but they went a bit too high on the tapestry. So the fourth guy's head
Just making a quick cameo into the tapestry when really it should have been gone
My favorite part the biotapestry is the bit where Odo Earl of Kent is
Whispering to William telling him what to do in the battle and it kind of makes him look like he's really the important person
He was the architects of the whole invasion
But it turns out that it seems like it was him who commissioned the tapestry. I gave himself a massive role in that although and he was
Quite interesting wasn't he because he was never seen with spears or anything in the tapestry because he was a bishop
And bishop's one allowed a shed blood. So instead he's always seen with a massive club
So they're allowed to beat people around the head which apparently didn't draw any blood
Yeah, have you seen the reviews of the biotapestry?
They're great. They're well trip advisor reviews everything in the world
And as with all things the most funny reviews are the one star ones. So there is a complaint actor. There is actually one star. Isn't the Haley's comic?
Anyway, I feel like you're going to say something funny. Yeah, well, you know
Thunder stolen
No, so the reviews are things like so one review says we went on a visit to the biotapestry
Big learning curve for some people
We were walking along looking at the tapestry not much to see to be honest
All of a sudden I see a large phallic object sewn on the tapestry
This attraction is not displayed as containing adult content
We have very young children who can see the penis which is an outrage
I wanted to learn about medieval battles not medieval penises
That's one star one star and there's another one star review which just says 9 quid and 40 minutes to see a carpet
9 quid in seven seconds for who say molasses. It was very blurry
I like the little touches in the tapestry because people used to add kind of slide digs at people or what they thought of certain figures in it
So there's one there's one really nice but actually we're herald when herald first went over to see willing the concurrent front
Him and his men then got in boats to go back across the channel to Britain
And there's such a good picture of him and all his men holding up their kind of hose
And all their stockings and everything and they've taken their shoes off. They're carrying their shoes
And they're carrying their pets and stuff in their arms because they're waiting through the water to get to their boats
And it's just it's just exactly like you know when you wrote a beach and you sort of wonder what that's
They brought pets with them one person had a dog under his arm and another person was holding a bird which seems that necessary
Maybe a helper war dog or a snipper dog or something. Yeah, you know Nigel Farage was his favorite tie is a Bayer tapestry tie
Because it reminds him of the last time Britain was invaded how long is it?
It's the same way. Yeah, it's an exact replica to scale. Yeah, right. So it's just constantly
Dranging behind him. He has some bridesmaids who carried it all the time
That's interesting because when I was looking at an old old bishop of Bayer who was the guy who commissioned this
I went on to the BBC website and they said that he was the least popular figure in Kent's history
But then I looked up other people from Kent who were unpopular and Nigel Farage
It's from Kent as well as the most unpopular person Nasty Nick from Big Brother One. Oh
Don't tell these guys. They didn't even know about the Spice Girls chart history yet
Nasty Nick will blow their mind
We should move on to our final fact shortly anything before we do yeah should go for it
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show and that is James. Okay, and my fact this week is that if you're a slough
Every time you go for a poo, it's more painful than childbirth
Is that you impersonating child? I was just trying it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Is that more painful than human childbirth?
I believe it is because actually slough childbirth is not that painful because baby sloths are super small
They're about 14 ounces
Whereas slough poo's are at least twice as big maybe more
And they can lose up to one third of their body weight during death. Oh god
They do it once a week
It's the equivalent of if I did a poo there would be too big to check into a Thompson's flight
I mean what's the purpose of your visit for a start?
And the stomachs physically shrink every time they do it
But how do we have someone laid a woman mid-labor next to a slow mid-poo and what judge the volume of the screaming?
I think how do we know you're right? I mean to be honest there's a bit of you know suposition going on here
But basically it's the size and this is what we've said this before unlike other animals
Sloths they only do this once a week
They go down from the bottom of their tree
And they do this and it can take like up to 50 days for the food to go through the system
Because they're trying to get every single bit of nutrient out of it
And so by the time it comes out, it's absolutely huge. It's just fibrous mass
And it obviously must be extremely painful. Yeah
And it's super heavy isn't it?
So um well obviously like a third of their body weight and the problem with being a sloth is that you're upside down
Basically all of your life and so your poo's all gone to the bottom waiting to come out
And then it would the only thing that stops it all from crushing the rest of their organs is that
Their bowels and everything like that literally hooks onto their ribcage
Yeah, or onto the sides of their body because otherwise you know if it was loose hanging like ours are as soon as the sloth turns upside down
This enormous weight of feces would crash all of the rest of its organs
So all of its organs are kind of yeah hooked on
It's amazing and then it goes down to the bottom of the tree does it's business and goes back up again
And traveling back up must feel amazing, wasn't it?
Oh yeah
They do a little dance before they have a poo every time as well
And that's unusual for sloths is it?
Yes
Why do they have to dig a little hole in the ground?
And it must the jiggly must help, wasn't it?
I'm sure it does yeah yeah
And the thing is the reason one of the reasons we think that they do this just once a week
Is because it's extremely dangerous for them to go to the toilet
Because they're nice and safe in their little tree
No one can see them the really well camouflaged
They're really slow no one can see them move
But of course when they go down to do this they're really kind of vulnerable
And apparently more than half of sloth fatalities occur when they are doing their business
Well that's the thing so their main predators are both I think tigers and eagles
Yeah
What a bad luck right?
Like imagine that being your predator
You've got two predators as I, oh so it's like a type of ant and a sausage dog
That would be fine
An eagle
What organism are you possibly thinking of?
So this is the weird thing
When they're in captivity
Sloths have a poo once every day
Which suggests that they really really want to have a poo once every day
And that in captivity they know they're safe they can do
Because when you're in the wild the shame of dying
Basically they're all dying like Elvis Presley died aren't they
They're half of them dying on the toilet you don't want to risk that
And we don't know why they go down to the bottom
Well there's a great theory
Okay so the theory is they have this algae on them which grows
And some of these species of algae are specific to a single species of sloth
So it's quite specific stuff
But they're in this weird love triangle with some algae and some moths
So they go down to the ground
There are these moths which live in their fur
And because sloths move so slowly they can never groom themselves to get rid of the moths
Because as soon as they move their claw over to their arm
The moths just walks out of the way
So that's because they can fly moths
Yeah exactly
It's a bit of a kick in the teeth
It's a bit walk away from them
I know they just stroll off they don't care
So the moths lay their eggs in the poo of the sloths
Right
And then the the moths live
They fly up when they hatch into the sloths fur
They live there
They die
That algae that we talked about
Grows because of the nutrients released when the moths die
So the moth die they release nitrogen and the algae feeds on that
And we think that the algae is beneficial to the sloths
We don't know how
But it's either because it camouflages them
Or because maybe they groom themselves that they might eat it
Although that's a bit controversial
Also it can apparently contains some agents that kind of work against things like malaria
Right okay so whatever it's doing
It's definitely helping the sloth survive
Yeah so that's why they need to go down is for the moth life cycle
And then the moths feed the algae and the algae help the sloth
No but I don't risk that just for the sake of nurturing a few moths
Who might poo green all over you
And maybe camouflage your maybe not
No just one
Well another theory is that they go down and they do their business
And that is kind of telling the female sloths where they are
And there's information in that dung that tells them that they're fit
And good people to mate with
And so maybe it's like a sloth tinder kind of thing
Yeah wow it's like a reproductive system thing where they're going
I'm photol I'm ready so actually they go down a lot more
Than they usually would when they're ready for a child
And as a result they build this mountain of poo going
I want babies and that's what they see in the like
Whoa look how awesome this is and then they go up the tree
That is an alarming tip the profile
Just huge steaming calls of poo
Everything is not tinder it's a different pineapple
If you work with sloths you're not allowed to wear perfume
Because their hair is so absorbent
So they can have algae growing inside their own hair
It's very weird it grows on the outside and also on the inside
So if you wear perfume it can get into their fur basically
And it stays with them for weeks
So you're not allowed to wear perfume
You're not allowed to wear things like suntan lotion
Which is a problem because of where they live
And you're not even allowed to wear anti mosquitos spray
If you're cuddling sloths we're living
And you have to get very good at climbing trees
Apparently there's I think the person who's done a lot on sloths recently
Who's often in new scientists and stuff
Is someone called Rebecca Cliff
Who took a tree climbing course
And still said that it was impossible
She was outsmarted and outpaced by the sloths
Because by the time she got out the tree
They'd be on a different tree
And she found that she had to get Guatemalan free climbers
To go and get the sloths for her when she wanted to study
I read one article about sloths in trees
And that is that what they do is equivalent
You know those gymnasts who do that kind of
It's like a crucifix position on the rings
They're like oh yeah
Which is unbelievably hard for humans to do
Apparently sloths just do that really easily
They can just do it all of them do that all the time
Right
But they do fall out quite a lot
Do they?
This is one thing she said was
If you see a sloth fall out of a tree
Which happens alarmingly often
I mean they seem to just be popping out
There was a story that babies would fall out
Because they mistake their own limbs for tree branches
They're held onto their limbs and fall
But I don't know if that's true
It's not true unfortunately
I mean fortunately but it's
No no no it's probably a myth
But the babies do fall out quite a bit
And if they do fall out
The mothers will not go down and get them
The babies are dead at that point
Whereas they will go down to take a poo
They will not go down and fetch their baby
So infant mortality very high
Because
So I've read they can be really fast
They want to be
Really what? Sorry
Fast I read that the top speed of a sloth
Is 15 miles per hour
Oh come on
Yeah
Faster than a pet
That's if they're falling out of a tree
I can believe that
But supposedly I read this from a zoologist
It's a it's a double bluff basically
Their slowness is real
It takes them 30 days to digest a leaf
They are a slow being
But when something is threatening them
They're able to be very speedy
She said faster than a cat can run
On the street
No way
Yeah
Probably no, probably no
There is a self-help book that came out of the last year or so
Called "Be more sloth"
It's by Alison Davis
And she says that you should be more still
You should turn things upside down
Be more intentional
Be kind to yourselves
And be more positive
Which apparently these are all things that sloths do
And have a very very very high fiber diet
Well she says on the front cover
The winner of the race isn't always the one who comes first
Incorrect
Yeah
That's the definition of the winner of the race
Okay that's it that is all of our facts
Thank you so much for listening
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
About the things that we have said over the course of this podcast
We can be found on our Twitter accounts
I'm on @shardland
James
That's James Huckett
Andy
I'm Andrew Hunderham
And Shazinsky
Can you mark podcast at qi.com
Yep
Or go to our group account at no such thing
We'll see you again
Goodbye
Bye
Bye bye
(audience applauding)