we run it on qi a few years ago yeah um which was there's no such thing as a fish
yeah nice such thing as a fish no seriously it's in the Oxford dictionary of underwater life
he says it right there first paragraph no such thing as a fish
hello welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish a weekly podcast coming to you
from the qi offices in covert garden my name is dan shriver i'm sitting here with james harkin
anatcha zinsky and alex bell and once again we've gathered around the microphone with our
favorite facts from the last seven days and in no particular order here we go
okay let's start with fact number one anatcha zinsky so my fact is that alexander the great
band bids in battle to combat beard pulling how long were the bids i'm not sure actually i
do know they were fashionable before that so he actually was a proponent of bids before one battle
where he was leading the mass adonians and it was his troops versus the Persians and the Persians
started grabbing his troops bids and pulling them off their horses and killing them all taking
them prisoner and there's one anecdote of one of the opposing troops grabs a guy's beard and holds
it there while he decapitates him which quite a useful word to capitating someone so yeah no
bids in battle after that that was that was just one battle where half the soldiers died because of
beers we're going to shave and guys that are going what i didn't think he was that bad yeah i thought it's
good battle guys but a lot of kills in that and the thing about alexander i read somewhere else that
one of the reasons he might have done it is that he was only 20 years old at the time and all of the
other soldiers were older than him and one way that you showed authority if your older was by
having a big beard and so he didn't want these other guys to have beards because he wanted to have
the authority over them yeah he was really sure as well it wasn't he so maybe let's see yeah so he
should have made them all sort of like stand on their knees all the time and limp around not good in
battle is it yeah another time where war killed bids was world war one people stopped wearing
stop wearing bids yeah you wear a beard don't you stop wearing bids in world war one because they
were prone to lice which is an ideal in the trenches one useful beard was the first guy who swam
from jonna grotesque to lanzand he grew a massive beard to protect his face from jellyfish stings
oh smart that's clever isn't it another useful beard um was black bids beard oh yeah
there's a beard too much there um he apparently used to adorn his beard with slow burning fuses
to make himself look more intimidating in battle so he decorated himself like a big scary Christmas tree
so he lived his hairy face on fire i know it's quite dangerous isn't it he would put fuses
for dynamite and things slow burning ones stick them in his hand his beard and light them up
apparently that made him look even scarier yeah it would i guess yeah slash easy to spot and slightly
ridiculous slash it has a high chance of setting your face on fire and then you look like an idiot
bids have really weird though aren't they they've just gone in and out of fashion so wildly since
the beginning of civilization like ancient Rome i don't think people were pro bids because it was
a sign of slough and leaners and you weren't looking after yourself and then other points in time
they've been a sign of manliness so i think medieval times it was a sign of virility well there was
that study recently about um how women find beards attractive and but only up until a certain
number of people have beards and once you go over that number then they don't find them attractive
anymore and apparently we are post that number now so wearing a beard is not attractive anymore
i think Jeremy Paxman tipped the balance did he agree that was a straw that broke the cows back
the impact was really regretting his beard now though because he made a big point to the fact that
you should be allowed to have a beard on tv and then there's the um the blf have you heard of
the blf is it the beard liberation front yeah i feel like you heard of it well did they go
on cutting off people's beard no they're they're they're free that beard they're letting them loose
on the more yeah now they want to encourage beards they think it's one of the great sort of like
glass ceilings of every job in the world that if you have a beard it stops you from getting higher
in a company or getting you on tv or they treat it as if it's like worse than the glass ceiling for
women or or race or anything beards yeah they said that bearded women's even worse bearded women
don't get many bearded women on panel shows do you don't you don't well there was the saint
willger fortis wasn't there who was an english saint who there are paintings of her that were
mistaken for jesus for a long time she looks exactly like jesus she was crucified and she had
this big long beard and actually she's just a female saint who grew a beard do you remember that guy
who went to the darts and he looked like jesus and he had to get kicked out no why was he kicked out
just really quickly what happened it was a few years ago you know how darts matches get quite rowdy
no they do uh and so there's a match going on and then some of the crowd who are very drunk and
having a good time notice that one of the other members of the crowd looked a bit like jesus
and then suddenly it spread and everyone was going jesus jesus to this guy and it was put in the
darts players off so much that the guy who looked like jesus got escorted out to the venue
oh my god that's really unfair yeah escort the people out who are chanting it i know but that
was everyone yeah so it was either just him left or he was left speaking of jesus in the first
six centuries of christianity all images of him look like an angelic sort of roman statue look like
a god with curly blonde hair and no facial hair at all and it was only in about i think
the twelfth century that we suddenly decided to change him into this guy with a big long beard who
was scrawny and skinny and um just back to women quickly with beards um i uh i found this great thing
in the in squire the qi um fact database uh which did you guys read this about the twelfth century
indian scripture the koka it's called it's a twelfth century indian scripture um it basically says
it recommends that uh augman should not marry a woman with a beard i was one of the like the main
things in the scripture but just all of the other you shouldn't marry redheads uh you shouldn't
marry anyone who sighs laughs or cries at meals um any girl with inverted nipples uneven breasts
flat ears spindle legs or who is scrawny girls whose big toes are disproportionately small
girls who make the ground shake when they walk past and my favorite any girl named after a mountain
a tree a river or a bird someone standards it too high up there it's like oh you know what i really
like everything about you you're non inverted nipples you're non spindly legs but i'm afraid
Mrs. Tams is nothing i can do about it we have to talk about your girlfriend oak tree
i'm not sure about her there was a 16th century um uh austrian mayor i think he was a sort of leader
of a town called at hand steiniger who's um supposedly how one of the longest bids in history
oh yeah and he he's also famous having supposedly one of the most ironic deaths as well which was
he died by falling down the stairs and breaking his neck after tripping over his beard um he was
running to attend a fire uh in the city and he forgot to pick up his beard and tuck it into his
breast pocket as he used it so yeah guide oh very dangerous dangerous things so i feel sorry for
roman boys who used to have to their first their first little sprouting which i imagine for men
is quite an exciting event used to be whisked up to the temple to devote it to the gods which must
be quite irritating you finally see a whisker appearing on your face after all those years and your
mums like all right get it off we're giving it to the gods i imagine there's my ends listening to
this going oh what you become a man and you're taken up there and you lose a little bit of your hat
tweezed out yeah i have my bowels removed yeah i don't love my son and daughters head off
first world roman problem yeah you know they're not allowed um the yankees don't allow beards for their
players the baseball team the baseball team in america new york yankees uh for very long time now they've
not allowed any player to have a beard so many players who have said that they want to join the Yankees
say uh there's no way i'm losing my beard that's definitely gonna stay they're just gonna have to
break the rule for me and then they always backtrack like months later when they're finally signed and
going they're offered like a ten yeah yeah exactly they go okay i guess i'll just lose that beard then
that's like kind of like i think dreadlocks were a problem for an australian rugby union player
who had long dreadlocks and people always used to tackle him by pulling on his dreadlocks and i
believe the manager at one point said you gotta get rid of those guys this is really jeopardizing our
game it was naughty rules player this is going completely off topic now but he um so i don't really
know the rules of us he rules very well but you catch the ball a lot you jump up and catch the ball
don't you yeah and the ball was kept hitting his little finger and he dislocated it so many times
that every time he caught the ball it would really give him pain on this little finger and so he
had it amputated just to make it easier just to be a better player that's right devotion to the game
there was another player but not for Aussie rules but for um for rugby league in australia who his trick
fingers as well was that in a scrum uh he'd put his finger up people's butts and they would
drop the ball and he would always get the ball aside and everyone kept complaining about it but no
one really believed it and they finally caught him with his finger up someone and he got banned from
the game for quite a long called brown handed okay time to move on to fact number two that is my
fact and my fact this week is that psychopaths don't experience contagious yawning like the rest of us
if if you're not a psychopath was that a real honor fake one that's fake one telling you
they did this test with dogs where they had 29 dogs experience a yawn to see if they would
yawn back and 21 out of 29 dogs yawned back and they only yawned when it was a genuine yawn if a
human just went ugh when their mouth opened they didn't yawn back yeah it's weird i do think it's
amazing that yawning is contagious in the human community in the dog community and between humans
and dogs as well yes that's ridiculous although i wonder if a dog makes a human yawn yawning is so
contagious that humans can yawn just by reading the word yawn or thinking about yawning sometimes
so if you see a dog yawning and you know it's a yawn then i bet that's contagious yeah basically
anyone listening to this podcast now is probably yawning and it's not just because of your terrible
facts wow is it zero i think it's amazing yawning is a mystery we don't know why we yawn there are
over 20 scientific theories for why we yawn and none of them is agreed upon yeah i think that's
fascinating that's amazing really weird now the latest theory is that it cools your brain
so you're warning it to get sucked in so you're more in winter because you suck in the cool air
and it goes through your nasal tissue and through your throat and it's when your brain's too hot
the engine greets thought that it was your soul trying to escape that's why you're supposed to put
your hand over your mouth pretty they thought your soul would escape when you were sneezing as well
in fact people that's why they say bless you isn't it yeah that makes more sense to me because you're
pushing it out i would have thought that you're sucking it in it just sounds like people thought they
had this soul inside them that was just trying to get out in any way possible yeah did you just
fart no my soul was escaping but also if you failed to put your hand in front of your mouth and you
sneezed did they just consider you someone who'd then lost their soul good one dick head your
soul got out and the rest of their life was just the rest of your life you're waiting for someone
else to sneeze and put your mouth right next to their mouth i got your soul hey jane's just
yawn was that oh yeah you're on my back oh my god it wasn't it was a genuine one is that a genuine
one oh yeah no it wasn't it was really it can't be he's a psychopath yeah should we judge why is it
that psychopaths don't yawn contagiously do we think because i know autistic people and schizophrenia
are much less likely to yawn contagiously as well but do we know why as far as i know it's to do
with empathy and i find that a weird thing because i don't think that yawning was a way of showcasing
emotion to each other so there's a guy a neuroscientist called james fallon and he was he'd worked out what
people's brains look like if they're certain types of people and he worked out what's a psychopath's
brains look like and he had a load of different brain scans next to him and he saw one that definitely
looked like a psychopath and it was his own brain scan so he worked out that he was a psychopath
himself which is quite a cool thing and then did he go on a killing spree well no he's they didn't
interview with him and then he said oh you know what i'd never realised i was a psychopath until then
but then he said i'm obnoxiously competitive i won't let my grandchildren win games i'm kind of
an asshole and i do jerky things that piss people off so the clues were there falling into place
ants yawn when they wake up do they yeah yeah they do like it looks like they're yawn so they wake
up when they stretch all their legs and they open their mouth as if they are adorable as that so it's
weird how many animals do it there was a study in 1994 and i haven't been able to find anything
subsequent to that that's disproved it that found that the only vertebrates that don't yawn are
giraffes there's the 2011 ignoble prize for physiology was won by a couple of scientists who did
a study called no evidence of contagious yawning in the red-footed tortoise yeah really all psychopaths
funny fear afraid if fetuses yawn in the first trimester which i find amazing because if you think
how tiny a fetuses is in the first three months of pregnancy and it's yawning already people don't
know why are we pretty boring in there i guess there's an antidepressant called an afronil one of
the side effects of which is spontaneous orgasms triggered by yawning okay so you couldn't use the excuse
I'm too tired because it would immediately be disproved yeah they've invented a yawn activated
coffee machine which was tried out to hannersburg airport last year i think which instead of paying
you just had to go up to it and it has a facial recognition thing and if you genuinely yawned then
it gives you some coffee oh but then surely the first person does a genuine yawn everyone else in the
queue with cash yeah and they go out of business immediately yeah it's weird like something that
i've experienced for years which until looking into this fact i didn't realize was a thing is that
if i do a stand-up gig i always yawned before the gig i always like just have this
massive yawn and i just thought that's okay and that's i don't know what that is it must be a
me getting the adrenaline ready or something but it seems counterintuitive because it makes it seem
like you're tired and people if they see you yawning they're going oh you're not really that bothered
about this gig no i think it's an anxiety thing maybe it's a way of your body really wanting more
oxygen you know you hyperventilate when you're anxious yeah yeah i think maybe it's another way
for body doing that yeah they found they found that um Olympic athletes the majority of them were
yawn before their events uh concert violinists were yawned before uh concerto um they even found
there was a guy in the army who monitored um uh army special forces jumping out of planes
parachuting and they would all yawn as they would walk up to the door and he did a study on it to
see if it was like it was just like a camera though they might have been going yeah actually
sure on a mo his real name was um guy aflay which means one who yawns really that was a good link wow
as you crowbar around to that i did notice on online when i googled world's longest yawn because i
thought i bet someone's got that record i don't think anyone does have that record but all of those
kind of onion wannabe websites that are trying to write satirical news stories that seems to be the
most popular choice of news so longest yawn recorded as man realizes oasis are forming again like
and they all try and it was a recorded three minute yawn that's how boring the news of them
reforming was seems to be recorded as another article about the longest yawn it's exactly someone
needs to write that one okay time for fact number three and that is James okay my fact is the big
bang was quieter than a motorhead concert so how loud is a motorhead concert i don't really know
what they are the motorhead was uh and is a um a metal band who have a very famous lead singer
called lemmy yeah and they sung the song the ace of spades yeah they're quite loud then
yeah so they apparently reach uh regularly reach around 126 decibels and according to an article
in focus magazine that i read the other day uh the big bang was about 120 decibels really now i
don't really understand exactly what that means but i went on on the internet and had a look around
and i found this a website telescoper.wordpress.com it's a blog by a physicist and basically they've
managed to by looking at the background radiation of the universe they've managed to work out that
there were some sound waves there and they managed to work out how loud those sound waves would have
been and according to them it was about 120 decibels and well there's no one there to hear it
yes and these sound waves whether they'd be able to be heard by human ears anyway i don't know but
you know i don't pretend to be able to completely 100% understand this so i'm going to what i'm
going to do is i'm going to post a link to this guy's blog on my um twitter feed at x-shaped um people
can make their own minds up so a blue whale which is the loudest animal in existence can give
other cool that 188 decibels so that's much louder than the big bang and also loud enough to wrap to
your ear drums if you heard it in fact isn't it yeah anything a bit over 100 100 and 120 that's going
to hurt your ears yeah yeah the subject of concerts apparently one of the reasons the Beatles
stopped touring was because their concerts weren't loud enough during their 1964 tour which was their
last tour the audience was just screamed so loudly all the way through for the entire evening that
no one could hear the music and the Beatles came to the conclusion that their concerts weren't about
the music anymore and they tried all this different equipment they still can get it to work so they
decided to stop touring that was one of the reasons uh bands now have monitors on stage that play the
music back to them so they can hear their sound levels and what they sound like they didn't have
that back then so there was a really famous Beatles gig where they played it in a baseball stadium in
America where it was so loud screaming of the fans they couldn't hear themselves play so it wasn't
even that the fans couldn't hear them they couldn't hear themselves and they were just completely out of
tune the whole time yeah yeah yeah the world's loudest scream that is a British record it's held by
a lady called Jill Drake from Tentadon in Kent oh I come from there do you yeah oh you might have
heard her yeah um she set the record with 129 decibels in the year 2000 hang on she yelled
louder than the big bang motor head to be fair pretend it is a pretty awful place
and um the funny thing is that she didn't know that she was good at screaming but she was on a trip
to London when the Millennium dome was there and they just happened to be having a shouting and screaming
competition so she thought well I'm here I'm on holiday I might as well check and then she did it
and she found that she had a real skill for it and now she's got the world record
okay we skill at screaming does it like on her CV or something yeah well how is that a skill I
think Alicia the best in the world is something I seem to remember that she made the record and
just beat out the other competitor who was her twin sister is that right yeah I'm pretty sure her
twin sister is the second loudest screamer her parents must have been so sick of them yeah
the loudest noise recorded in model all the loudest noise that we know of happening in modern
history was the eruption of Krakato in 1883 and it could be well it reverberated around the world seven
times I think it could be detected on instruments going seven times around but it could be heard
three thousand miles away wow so it's an Indonesia and it could be heard in Western Australia
didn't it burst people's eardrums yeah any one within a 10 mile radius um their eardrums explode
all right that's insane yeah um I've got one motor head fact which is that yeah they recently
uh rocked so hard at a concert that one of the guys head banging uh it got a blood clot in his
brain as a result of the like absolute just head banging that was going on yeah and he survived
so it's now a it's now a mark of awesomeness both to the fan and the band that they rocked a guy so
hard that his brain spasms Kagan and Aguism there was that thing about um was it madness who I think
they did a thing at Finnsbury Park where everyone was stumping up and down so much that they caused
an earthquake and very small earthquake it might have been that that was also in a in a football stadium
in America what's it yeah yeah where they were stepping so hard at the chiefs cancity chiefs
that that happened quite recently yeah so they triggered an actual earthquake as in it was measured
it was measured yeah everyone played no no no no crazy although is the Richter is at the Richter
scale there's not so no news anymore yeah it's a moment magnitude scale now yeah but it's
pretty much yeah if anyone got any last facts they want to chuck in um so these guys called penzius and
Wilson were awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1978 because they detected the cosmic fog
that's meant to be a signature of the big bang so that's what we study to work out what we think
happened in the big bang and two pigeons had to die in order for them to work this out so they had
the horn antenna to detect it and it kept on showing higher temperature than expected when they
were looking at this cosmic fog and they thought oh is it the pigeon poo in the horn antenna so they
gave the pigeon to a pigeon fancier and said take these pigeons away and pigeon fancier took them away
let them go so they returned the horn antenna nested in there again and so they shot the pigeons but
I just think if you've got two physicists and you're a pigeon fancier you go my one job is to keep
these two pigeons out of the horn antenna while these guys try to work out the universe and he
copped it up yeah but what was interesting about that was that I thought the usually these kind of
things happen to be that some of the things they discovered something amazing and it turns out to be
actually the pigeon shuttle over the equipment and ruined it and that was it it was actually the
other way around with this because they thought the pigeon and it turned out to be they discovered
the background cosmic radiation universe they just didn't realize it who was it I've
completely forgotten his name now but there was a physicist who spent years studying Venus who
looking through Venus and a telescope and he thought he was looking at canals on Venus and it turned
up he was actually he'd actually had his telescope incorrectly calibrate and he was looking at
cataracts in his eyes and the love vessels are in his eyes for years and years and we're studying these
and it's really sad actually because yeah and there's maps of Venus isn't that he drew and actually
it's a map of the inside of his own eyeball yeah that's so cool have you guys heard about the
mysterious hum apparently it a mysterious hum go greas not true though is it um well it's true
that people think it exists yeah there's a lot of people reporting that there's this low hum that's
appearing in certain bits of the planet and a lot of people are experiencing it and no one knows
where the hum is coming from is it detected on sound detecting equipment I don't know enough about it
sometimes these facts are better when you don't read into them the electromagnetic radiation
for Sun makes it noise the really interesting sound I was going to submit it for M series actually
who music um check out if you go on YouTube and type in some sounds yeah music of this first the
earth does as well there's a there's a note there's a definite note I think it fluctuates um yeah
basically anything that's anything that's vibrating will bring a noise sound the earth emits an
ear piercing combination of shrieks and whistles apparently and that's just from Tencenton
okay time to move on to our final fact and that is Alex my fact is that Pixar accidentally
deleted Toy Story 2 halfway through making it oh how how yeah okay so this is a really great story
okay so um basically everyone in Pixar there are over a hundred people working on the film at the time
um and um they all had access to the the the files at the same time it there was no sort of protection
and this was a while ago so it was quite simple computer systems someone literally just typed in
the wrong command and the computer by accident realized that they'd accidentally told the
computer to delete the whole film and that it was doing that um they then quickly sent emails around
being like shit please can someone help me I think I've just deleted Toy Story 2 um they then rang
downstairs to the place where the servers were and was they just said unplug the machine as quickly
as you can so they did so they turned it off and turned it on again which is the solution to everything
when they turned it back on they found that nearly all of the movie had been deleted oh my god um so
they started panicking and they started asking everyone does anyone have any bits of the film at home
um because apparently the whole film only took up 10 gigabytes with the the all the information
took took to make it which was still a large amount in that time but a 13 minute episode of the case
series of qi is 13 gigabytes on our server so that's you know that's more than all of the information
to render Toy Story 2 and um so that so they thought they'd lost the entire film until they remembered
that um one of their employee one of the animators was on maternity leave and had been given a computer
to work on from home which had the entire film on and it only been backed up two weeks ago so they
drove around to her house they wrapped up the computer in blankets and put it in the back of a Volvo
and drove it back to Pixar with the whole film on it and it was estimated to be worth about 100 million
dollars that computer because it it had all of the work on it was any copy i like the way you you
specified it was a Volvo as well yeah i know there's something about a Volvo isn't it it's just
known as the the hundred million dollar Volvo because it was just like everyone was just holding
the computer and they strapped it in the seat off and they were incredibly worried that it was all
gonna be destroyed. Jovey 2 miles an hour. The whole story is slightly undermined by the fact that
they finished the film and it was all fine and then Pixar decided to start again basically from scratch
because the story wasn't good enough. Yeah i love that. I love that about Pixar i think i mean that's
such a testament to their quality controls they just looked at it and said actually no let's start
again. It was their second feature film so they were really wanted to get it right so they did
redo it but even to the point where they were getting to the final product they they were going
to release it on vhs it was going to be a director vhs they weren't confident that it was going to
yeah they certainly weren't confident Billy Crystal turned down the role of voicing woody and he says
that's the biggest mistake he ever made in his career which was just a voice over all. Bill Murray was
also approached and he turned it well he didn't turn it down he missed the phone call because Bill
Murray has a system whereby he doesn't have an agent he has an answer phone message a system that
you can leave your requests for him to be in your movie on and he missed out on that phone call
that day maybe yes yes they deleted it halfway through yeah so he would have been in it and he says
that was the big regret of his career as well. Pixar are great there's that i think this might
be in the next series of qi but that lunch that the four big cheeses that Pixar had in 1994
where so it was John Lacer to Pete doctor Andrew Stanton and Joe Rand they had one lunch
and at that lunch they came up with the ideas and the rough storyline sketches for a bugs life
monster zinc finding Nemo and Wolley which just made you wonder what they did for the subsequent ten years
if that's all covered in a lunch but it takes them like six years to make a single movie
yeah it's very arduous yeah like Tom Hanks was doing the voice over for it when he was filming
sleepless in Seattle and that feels like that was 30 years ago even though it's something like 20
and you know forest gump when he was doing forest gump he was still doing the voice over for it
just doesn't feel as old as those movies are that i read this and i i don't really know enough about
films to know if it's true but he was doing philadelphia at the same time and he refused to do any
toy story bet at the same time because he didn't think he should be doing comedy voice over while
he was doing a yes that's what i read and it was in the period where he was doing philadelphia
and forest gump and he felt like these aren't the appropriate movies so what was he worried about
that he was going to accidentally be funny in the really serious yeah maybe in the middle of
philadelphia you might bring out his um you're my favorite deputy bus light he was originally called
lunar larry oh i don't know yeah he was called lunar larry and then he had a brief period as tempis
and then morph they went to bars more but there's a very famous more for ready who's the famous
more Tony Hart's little um plastic in the 70s oh really very famous maybe they found out about that
Tony Hart from heartbeat um he's the guy who invented morph yeah and he also drew the um picture for
blue peter you know the little ship yeah think and um he got a one-off flat fee of 50 pounds or
something like this but if he'd have got like just one p for every time they used it on a badge or
on something else like that he would be at multi-millionaire by now that's like i read the story
the other day about the men who designed the mcdonalds golden arches oh yeah have you have you
any idea what his name is surely that's he created one of the most iconic yeah runald yeah it wasn't
and i don't know his name either i read it but i can't remember it now but um he was offered by the
brothers that he could get a flat fee or he could have a additional royalty for every time a new
mcdonalds open and he said maldo the flat fee i can't see this going any bigger yeah on the opposite
end of the scale there's the guy who painted the mural at facebook when facebook had just started
and he was paid in facebook shares i think so he's now a multi-millionaire or something ridiculous
yeah um just heading back to toy story too quickly what i love about this fact is i love just hearing
the behind-the-scenes stories of these these kind of disasters or early stages of things that we've
become to know and love and i love just in animation generally i was i was reading up recently about
some early disney movies and um Alice in Wonderland the original early version scripts i don't know
if it was the very first one but certainly in the very early stages do you know who was the author
of the script for the animation all this hoxley really yeah he wrote a bunch of versions of it and then
it just didn't make it through into the end and also uh the uh the lion king was originally called
king of the jungle it still says on all their press uh king of the jungle you know just in the taglines
but they dropped it because they suddenly realized that there are no lions in the jungle
therefore you can't have it but it was pitched the movie was pitched itself as bambian africa meets
hamlet and it became nicknamed bamblet when they were making it it is based on hamlet isn't it i
haven't watched line yeah you can see a lot of similarities when you watch it bambi itself was going to
be uh in the scene spoiler alert where his mum get shot then it was the scene was originally going
to be bambi saw his mum get shot and saw her being dragged away by hunters and leaving behind a pool
of blood as the bloodied carcass was dragged away along the meadow and then they thought that
she that's probably disturbing enough as well on top of that as well the uh the movie who frame roger
abbot it turned out that they were going to make the killer of bambi's mother the evil guy in who
frame roger abbot and that was going to be revealed in the movie and they decided to drop that at the
last minute we just we just recorded the rest recent series the museum of curiosity and one of the
guests was Richard Williams who's the head animator yeah of course yeah yeah so one of the guests
was Richard Williams who was the main animator a really big animator and he was the main guy he
basically drew roger abbot and jeska rabbit and i was talking to him afterwards in the pub and
i was asking about all of these hidden because in roger abbot especially it's a it's a family film
but there are a lot of single frames where there's some really dark stuff going on and one of them is
jeska rabbit pulled out of a cab at one point and um and like her skirt goes up and you see
everything and there's a big controversy about this when they recently re-released the film and
basically what happened was uh Richard Williams um drew her falling out and her skirt went up a
bit but you didn't it wasn't actually explicit you didn't see anything in the 2004 i think
re-release of the film on dbd some new animators went in and made it explicit and drew some stuff there
but didn't tell anyone and Richard got the blame for it they also they also put in that movie there was
some graffiti on the wall which said for a good time this is roughly what it said for a good time
called allyson wonderland and the number that they put underneath was but the phone number of
michael isner the head of disney at the time it was his actual number and they had to subsequently
take that out as well from that movie on the subject of pornographic broadcasting um the concast is
a massive american broadcasting company and they're responsible for loads and loads of american
watching television and um they they they have a really bad history of accidentally broadcasting
hardcore pornography and really inappropriate times so one time they did it during the super bowl
about thirty seconds one another time was on uh Cartoon Network and the film was on the Disney channel
they just accidentally replaced programs with pornographic hardcore no yeah wow um i was looking at
sort of the you know tiny technical mistakes that could have had huge repercussions like the fact
that last year there was a typo in a sign outside of the Oregon teacher standards and practices
commission and the sign read Oregon teacher standards and practices commission without a d
right so just a d missing and a guy got so angry about this that he resolved to explode it with a
pressure cooker bomb and so he marched in brandishing this bomb into the teacher standards commission
said i can't believe there's a typo in this and it's outrageous i'm exploding this bomb now
went to explode at the bomb didn't explode so then he wrote furious letters to everyone and
campaigned about the fact that the bomb making instructions on the internet also riddled with typos
and it was for that reason his bomb hadn't worked so the typo caused the crisis but then it also saved
the crisis from happening so i don't know who signed you on tiny toy story fact one of the working
titles for toy story was toys in the hood with a z for toys first good catch 22 was originally going
to be called catch 11 but it was around the same time that oceans 11 the first oceans 11 came out
and so there was a concern that it was going to be confused but i remember it was called catch 18
for a while yeah they they toyed with catch 18 so after they discarded catch 11 they went for
a number of other options well so they had a meeting uh Joseph heller we could you come into the
office we love the book yeah really good uh we need a new number for the title it's like the work in
the way up it's like catch 11 know there's oceans 11 okay catch 12 well there's also oceans 12
okay 13 well actually a follow 13 okay that's it that's all our facts thanks everyone for listening
if you want to get in contact with us about any of the things that we've said over the course of
this podcast we can all be reached on Twitter i'm on @triberland james at headshade Alex at Alex
fellow on the school chazinski uh you can email podcast at qi dot com or you can go onto our page no
such thing as a fish dot com where we're gonna have all the other episodes up there as well as pages
on each of those episodes with links and videos and so on and uh you can just explore that so thanks
for listening we'll be back again next week and see you then goodbye
if you hold on to me you can also love me you so time to get together sure we can do if you hold on to me
and I'll hold on to you