- Hi, everybody, just before we start this week's show,
we have a little announcement.
- Yes, we do.
I'm announcing that Andy, you need to just close your ears
for a quick moment.
I just need to mention something privately to the listeners.
- Okay.
- Obviously, I don't want Andy to hear this,
but I'm reading a new book at the moment called "Bad Deeds"
by Andrew Hunter Murray.
And it is so annoying 'cause it's kept me up extremely late
every night for the last seven days.
It's so gripping.
It's this new novel.
It's a sequel to the last one that many of you might have read,
breaking and entering.
It doesn't matter if you haven't read it,
it is also a brilliant standalone book.
And it's an absolute page turner, thrilling stuff.
Obviously, with a lot of the trademark,
Andrew Hunter Murray, wit.
I feel like I was watching an action film for parts of it.
It's amazing.
Get it now and now pretend I never said anything.
Andy, you can open your ears again.
- Hello.
- Hi, I was just having a private chat,
but you've got a book out.
- Yes, it's called "Bad Deeds".
It's out today.
We're recording this on the day of publication.
It's a thriller set between London's dodgy property market
and the wilds of rural Scotland.
There's all sorts of skull dugory in Mayhem and "Bad Deeds".
And the only other thing I'll say is,
if you're an audiobook sort of person,
you might like to know that the person
who reads the audiobook is friend of the parish
and former guest on this show, it's Phil Dunster.
And he doesn't absolutely terrific job.
So if you like audiobooks, maybe give that a go.
- And where can people buy at grocery stores or?
- Well, I would say your local independent bookshop,
but I will accept any sale is terrific.
Thank you very much.
So whether you're buying it offline or on,
but no, do pop down to your local bookshop
and ask them for like 10 to 12 copies is a good start.
- There you go, 10 to 12 copies of "Bad Deeds".
Seriously, do it now.
You will not regret it.
Okay, on with the show.
- On with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
with no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Anna Toshinsky,
Andrew Hunter Murray and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 17th century Sweden,
Sami Shaman's had to work in secret.
Unfortunately, most of their work involved constant drumming.
(laughing)
- Sami Shaman sounds like an end of the peer kind of magician.
- Yeah. (laughing)
- That's true.
- Hi, it's Sami Shaman's
and here is my magical drum
because they did have magical drums, the Sami.
They are a group of people who live in Norway, Sweden,
Finland and Northern Russia.
And they still live there today.
But they started off with Hunter Gatherers,
went into reindeer herding and they move around with the reindeer.
But one of the most important people in the community
was the Shaman, who is known as a no-idee.
And the no-idee would communicate between the worlds
by using this drum.
And he would kind of bang, bang, bang and get in such a rhythm
that he would get into some kind of weird sort of trance.
And I say he, 'cause it was always a he.
And they felt like they could transform
into other creatures, transform into the wind,
all this kind of stuff.
And they were persecuted by Christian missionaries
and the Christian missionaries just basically said,
we're having that drum.
And they took the drums off them.
- Confiscated them.
- Confiscated them, destroyed most of them.
There's not many of them left,
but there is one in the British Museum,
which is where I read about this whole story.
- They are engraved or painted with pictures.
And I think there's a way you can do divination
as in the Sami Shaman would strike the drum
with a hammer that is made of an engraved reindeer antler.
- These reindeer are very big to you.
And then that makes a little brass ring
that you've got dance across the surface of the drum.
And how far it goes or what it lands on tells you,
or tells him, 'cause it is always a him.
(laughing)
- Woke hasn't yet.
- Woke hasn't yet come for the Sami Shaman world, basically.
And that tells you the future, you know.
- Or I did read an account from 1674,
which I think is the earliest account we have
of more Southern people by a guy called John Sheffa,
who said they also sometimes use the drums
to decide what animal to sacrifice to their gods.
So he said each drum would be covered
in lots of pictures of animals of birds and fish and stuff.
And then there was a kind of a pole attached to the drum,
then at the top of it, a little brass frog,
and you bang the drum, and when the brass frog fell off,
whatever animal it landed on,
whatever animal the frog chose was the one that you had to kill.
- That's great.
- It's like a wheel of fortune kind of thing, isn't it?
- Yes.
- You're not proposing taking this action,
so it's like a ritual of putting it on ITV at prime time.
- I'm afraid I am.
Well, which of these celebrities will we sacrifice?
- These images that you said and the Sami sort of would,
once they started getting persecuted by the missionaries,
they would like say, oh, this isn't a reindeer,
this is a cross.
And they would slightly sort of change all the drawings
to make them more Christian in the hope
that they wouldn't get taken.
But they did all pretty much all get taken.
There's not that many of them left.
- I mean, I heard much of the Sami,
but I realized a kind of classic fact is to do with the Sami,
which is the word Paul Roncoo Semmer,
which is the distance a reindeer can travel
before it needs to stop and urinate.
- That's kind of a classic thing
that you see online, Susie Dent tweets about that word
quite often.
- But as a reindeer age, is that distance well shrugged?
You know?
- Yes.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Many of your middle aged male reindeer
will stop just in case it's nice to have stopped when you can.
- Also, like your reindeer will walk for a long time
and then once they break the seal,
then that's gonna be a move just like that.
- How would I say breaking the seal?
I don't mean like with a cleverer.
The missionaries really didn't like the way
the Siberians used their own urine to guide the reindeer.
Because what they would do is they would urinate
into a seal skin, carry it around with them.
And then if the reindeer wandered off,
you would pour a bit of your urine on the floor
and then the reindeer would come back
'cause they liked the salt and the minerals and stuff like that.
And so, yeah, the fact that they were doing
this urinely stuff, the missionaries were like,
"Yeah, that's not really an outbuck."
- What, I mean, where does the Bible say,
don't piss into a bag and then spill it on the floor
when your reindeer runs away?
I don't think so, anyway.
- It's a little bit too cut.
- Yeah.
- You want to have red.
- You want to have all the salt and stuff.
- So the reindeer do eat the yellows, no?
- Yeah, they do.
They like to lick the, that's do a lot of animals.
- Yeah.
- It'd be a good way to attract the old man in the coat.
Have you heard of him?
- No.
- Of the communes.
- Is it you?
- It sounds like Dan with his, with his creepy coat.
I'm pushing my new business.
- Do you need a kid's birthday party?
Absolutely ruined.
Well, you need the old man in the coat.
- Well, you need a dude who's pissed out the front of your house
and I'll come and lick it.
- And once they know you as in hamster teeth.
- Yes, they know man in the coat.
- It's what they call polar bears.
The Sammy.
- Oh.
- Or God's Dog.
- It's the other name.
- It's a taboo.
They don't want to give it its real name.
So, it's got a code name.
- God's Dog is very good.
- God's Dog is wonderful, yeah.
- There's definitely a belief that polar bears can speak English,
but not very well, kind of as well as a toddler.
So, the belief is that they don't understand metaphors.
So, when you're talking about how you're going to hunt a bear,
that's why you have to use metaphors like the fur clad one.
- Do you also say, "Oh, it looks like over there
"selling I.C.E.C.R.E."? - I was reading just another thing on how the Christian missionaries dealt with them in this earlier count from 1674 John Sheffa.
He was Christian, so he had lots of comments about the Sammy and how they weren't very good at being Christians.
And he said, "They stick at several points of Christianity, namely the resurrection of the dead and the immortality of the soul."
And I just like that immediately after what he said.
And they worship the sun, chiefly for its light and its heat, believing all things are made by its means.
- Oh, I do this. - It's such a brilliant tone of patronizing disdain.
I don't know why they can't get the whole resurrection of the dead thing.
Also, they think the sun's really important.
- That's really funny.
So, Linnaeus was a big fan of the Sammy.
Linnaeus, the guy who named all the animals, basically,
just to say God creates and Linnaeus puts into categories.
But he went to visit them and they had a big effect on him.
So, after that, he decided to just walk around in Sammy clothing all the time, even when he was back home.
- Yeah, yeah. - He looked at it, didn't he?
- Obviously, it was a different time.
But if I have just been to China and then I come back dressed like a Chinese person,
it's not going to work, is it?
- I think to be fair, he basically wore, he basically thought this whole reindeer coats for coats works.
And wore a lot of reindeer head to toe, didn't he?
And he did carry the drum, which to be fair, we've seen a bit appropriatory.
- Yeah, I think we all know somebody's had a gap here and got a bit to it.
- Yeah.
- Why are you looking at me like that?
- I've got, I've never had a gap here.
I just have a gap two weeks after that.
- Yeah, you're the guy dressed in a kimono to the end, okay?
- And done, by the way, that Papua New Guinea god for your wearing.
- Thank you, I know you're tiddened by that big coat.
- Oh yeah, Linnaeus, one thing that he really liked about them is that the men would carry
around a sweet smelling fungus to attract women.
Just in the same way that I might spray, Link's Africa, myself.
They would do this with a fungus.
And he said, "In other parts of the world, you must be wooed with coffee and chocolate,
preserves and sweets, wines and dainties, jewels and pearls.
Here you are satisfied with a little withered fungus."
- Well, it is very cold.
- Just to think about drumming and drums, as we were on the Sami and their drums, I found
this absolutely wild.
Drums are many thousands of years old, right?
- Yeah.
- I mean, we found ancient drums from civilizations all over the world.
The drum kit wasn't invented until the 20th century.
- Are you telling me no one had ever thought of, like, I can use my other hand for this as
well?
- When are the first drum silos that you can think of?
They're all quite recent.
- I just think maybe you all did them and didn't manage to record them on to cassette tape
back in the day.
- Maybe, maybe.
- It's interesting.
- It's wild, isn't it?
- Yeah, maybe.
- I think the jury's out on that one, I would say.
You can speak in drum if you're a certain type of person from a certain type of place with
a certain type of language in West Africa.
Drum languages were quite common, probably less so now, but this is in languages specifically
which they're very tonal.
So you can make a drum that can play lots of different tones.
And so I think the Bulu dialect of the Bantu language is a very good example of this where
they'd have a drum where if you bang it at a different place along it, it makes a different
tone.
And therefore you can transmit messages up to 20 miles, apparently.
And everyone would have a drum name, so you'd give someone their drum name, you'd bang on
the drum, their drum name, so you know, they're talking to you.
- It's like having a special knock on the door.
Like I always knock on the door, the same like, yeah, I mean, it's not like a lot of people
would do a similar thing, but if you heard that knock, there's a good chance it's going
to be interesting.
- That's really interesting.
- And if you don't hear a knock at all, that's down in a big coat outside front.
But you're then knocking to yourself, if I were a Bantu person, I'd use that knock for
you then.
That would be my way of saying, "Way James."
- If we were on university challenge, I would buzz in and they'd go, "And they'd know
it was me to answer then."
- Yes, exactly.
- Parking fish.
Why have we never done university challenges as a team?
We've just never been asked, Andy, and also they don't do podcast teams.
- We're not a university.
- We're not a university teams.
- Yeah, but what the hell?
- And we'd be very bad.
- That's a broader truth than I think we're obviously, which is that it would be so much fun.
- And our insistence on being addressed by our drum names, I think, is also like...
- Podcast challenge on the other hand, it seems like a good idea.
- Edit this out of the podcast.
We're going to do, we're going to do pot diversity challenge.
University pod challenge.
- We're going to do it.
- We'll think of a name, yeah.
- Don't edit this out.
I don't want to do that.
Keep it in.
So someone else steals the idea.
- One thing I read about these drumming languages in Africa is you drum, a phrase or
a song or something that everyone knows what it means and everyone knows the context of
it, rather than just doing individual words.
- Yeah, I mean, yeah.
- I mean, it's very weird because it already seems difficult to convey stuff by a drum
rather than words.
And the fact that they've overcomplicated it by then saying you can use these metaphorical
phrases.
But it does seem to work.
- For instance, like, let's say I wanted a cake, I could go that, that, that, that, and
you would know, like...
- Maybe it's simpler.
Okay.
- Or you'd be like, budooch, the local comics here, like that would be a good drum name for
a local comedian.
- Yeah.
- Here comes Sammy Shaman.
(laughter)
- One of my close friends is a drummer, professionally.
- Oh, yeah.
- And one of the big things about drummers is that they have a bad reputation.
- Yeah.
- Not a bad reputation, but just a reputation maybe for being not stupid, not the brightest
member of the band.
- I'm not saying they are.
I've said that's what their reputation is.
- Right.
- Besides, they won't be listening to this podcast, it's way too high-brow.
- So I asked him for some drummer jokes.
- Oh, yeah.
- I just thought you might like something.
- Yeah, go on then.
- What do you call someone who hangs around musicians?
- A drummer.
(laughter)
- How can you tell if the stage is level?
- The drummer is dribbling out of both sides of his mouth.
How do you know when there's a drummer at the door?
- I don't know.
- The knock gets faster and they don't know when to come in.
What's the difference between a drummer and a savings bond?
- I don't know.
- One of them will mature and make money.
- I think what this needs is a pedum tissue.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is Andy.
- My fact is, from 1990 to 2018, there was an award given out every year for the most
human human.
- You sounded so robotic.
(laughter)
- This was a prize that was given out.
It was a subsection of a bigger prize, right?
And it's all to do with the Turing test.
So for anyone who hasn't heard of that before,
that's the idea that Alan Turing, brilliant computer scientist,
proposed in the '50s that the way you would be able to tell
when we had artificial intelligence is if a human is conversing
with someone who's unseen and they are unable to tell
whether they're talking to a person or a computer.
That's when we'll have true artificial intelligence.
- Which I would say is now, right?
- Oh yeah, people are falling in love with AI's left-right
and said, "We've way past the Turing test."
So by that metric, we've done it.
- So when we started this podcast, it wasn't true.
- Absolutely, absolutely.
Yeah, so that's the idea of the Turing test.
And there was an annual prize during those years starting in 1990,
called the Lubner Prize, where people would bring along
their own chatbots, and they would be training them
and improving them every year.
And if your chatbot managed to fool a human judge,
you would win a prize.
There would be several thousand dollars for the most human computer.
But as part of that, you obviously had to have some humans
being behind the screen, chatting back for the judges
to have any sense of like, are you talking to a computer or a human?
Sometimes you'd be talking to one, sometimes the other.
And as a separate prize, the judges would pick the human chatter
who was most convincingly human and give them a hundred dollars
or some small prize.
- I think this is a problem with the experiment,
because if the human is then changing their attitude
and the way that they respond because they're trying to get a prize,
then that changes the experiment, right?
- And that is what happened, right?
Brian Christian, who won the most human prize,
he wrote a whole book about it,
and part of the book was telling how he prepared to be human
as part of the test.
And so he did study to be human, to win it.
- That feels like it's kind of cheating.
Isn't the whole point of that?
You've got to be yourself.
- The rising to an exam is not cheating.
And if the exam is, are you a human?
It's completely reasonable to prep.
- But we're testing the computers, right?
- Yeah.
- If the whole point of the exam is to test the marking system
and you change your answers to make them completely wrong
or completely right, then that's not a very good way
of testing the marking system.
- I think he was just practicing being himself
and being authentic in conversation
and being truly human.
- How would you do it?
- I prep several hours a day for all of my conversations.
- You use the same person as Keir Starman, David.
- If you wanted to pretend to be human,
what would you do?
'Cause I'd feel like you would just do something really dumb,
right?
- Yeah.
- That's a great question, James.
I'm so glad you asked me.
But what do you think?
- Here's the issue though.
If you've got very specific loves and so on
as a person and you bring them to the exam,
you might lose.
So one person was altered as a robot
when they were a human
because they knew far too much about Shakespeare.
They said no human could possibly know this much about Shakespeare.
It just so happens, it was a Shakespeare expert
on the other side who was a human.
- Really the way to do it now
and this is my optimistic theory about where the world's going.
The only way to convince people your human
is to actually see them
because the only place that robots haven't managed
to achieve anything like human resemblance
is in the physical world, right?
They still can barely move.
I mean, I know there's all sorts of claims every year.
- I mean, they play football and they fold laundry
and whatever.
If you watch them try and even run marathons,
they still don't look very human.
- But they just won the marathon.
- I know, but they didn't look like humans when they did.
So I would say--
- Pop a big coat on that guy who run the marathon.
People will think Dan's would need to rest in time.
- I would say if you put that robot
'cause it was all over the news
and it was in channels.
It's top story in the news that day.
If you put that robot next to Phoebe from France running,
you would not be able to distinguish the term.
- It's a real slown Phoebe.
But this is a thing about robot technology, right?
Is that they've managed to mimic our brains unbelievably well,
but physically actually it turns out
that it's very, very difficult still.
And so I think people are gonna be driven off their computers
back into the real world.
- It's a nice optimistic idea.
- Offly not by driverless cars.
Because there's a situation in Atlanta earlier this year
where 50 Waymo driverless taxis
drove through the same area between six and seven o'clock
because someone had put a children a play sign in the road
which wasn't supposed to be there
and they would drive into the road
and then they'd try and get out and then they'd see that side
and they'd go back in the other direction again
and they'd just be driving in circles and circles and circles.
- So they can't?
- So it kind of, as they can see,
a children a play sign and know that that's something actually.
- But it's like you can kind of hack it
to kind of make them drive around these circles
and get lost because they're not thinking.
- Can I tell you just a quick thing
about this guy, Lerdner, who set up the prize?
- Yeah.
- Because he was, I don't know if you read it into him,
he was very eccentric.
- Yeah.
- So it was treated, like Sirius A.I. people said,
this is just a stunt, you know.
He gave out a medal with Alan Turing on one side
and him on the other, you know.
He was, there was this amazing,
he's sadly died about 10 years ago now
but he was a very interesting cookie.
So there was this piece about him in 2011.
He had made his living in portable crowd control fencing
and roll up disco dance floors.
That was his main line of work.
- Cool.
- I know, cool, right?
- That is, yeah.
- And he wanted to sponsor the prize
because his idea was true artificial intelligence
will free the world from work, you know.
Very optimistic that there won't be any work anymore.
But his other speech after the competition was all about
his plans to revolutionize public transport
using roller coasters.
He says a roller coaster is the ideal transport system.
It could work and it would solve many of society's problems
whether it can be implemented or does another matter.
- Hi, Henry.
- What's the driverless car except a kind of slightly
shaped roller coaster?
- Lots of tube.
- Lots of the underground, the path for a roller coaster, really.
- Yeah, the key difference with a roller coaster
is that you always end up where you started.
That feels like the tube is a bit better than a roller coaster.
- Well, circle like function.
- Function.
- Function, they fly every time you came into work.
You could buy a photo up yourself on the way to work.
That would be great.
- Yeah.
- I interviewed Labna.
I met him.
- Did you?
- Yeah, it was online, I met him.
I interviewed him.
- Did you do it?
- It was him.
- Yeah, it could have been a chap.
But it was him who I interviewed alongside Mitsuku,
who was the chap bot that had won the Lone Prize.
He'll got first place in the Lone Prize five times.
And it's the final champion because it stopped in 2019, I think.
But yeah, very eccentric character, even to look at.
Like a Dali-esque mustache and he had two big passions.
It was roller coasters and it was making prostitution
seen as something as a normal day-to-day thing
that you would just go within your marriage and go,
I'm just going to go to the brothel.
- You must be this tall too, go on this ride.
(all laughing)
- Don't take a photo of me halfway through.
- I know I'm focusing on the prostitution.
- You may get wet.
- Scream if you want to go faster.
(all laughing)
- I know you want to carry on, Anna,
but we've got a few more of these.
(all laughing)
- Oh, I'm not good.
I was sick twice, I'm a hat fell off.
(all laughing)
- You must keep your arms inside at all times.
- Let's let them get it out of their systems.
(all laughing)
- Here's an interesting thing about that hot dog dress before.
- Here's an interesting thing we're talking about love
and talking about AI.
There was a guy called Robert Epstein.
In 2006, he was looking online for love
and he found and fell in love with a Russian woman.
They exchanged love letters and so on.
And for about four months, it was going back and forth
until he finally realized hang on,
is this a real person and it wasn't.
It was an AI bot that he was an expert in the field of.
- He is the co-founder of the Logna Prize, Robert Epstein.
(all laughing)
- This is a good 16 years after this prize had been set up.
He fell in love with an AI bot online.
- Oh my God.
- Yeah, basically almost anyone susceptible to it, I think.
- Yeah.
On time, the difference between humans and robots,
how good are you at proving you're a human online
with the recaptures?
- Oh, you mean like which of these is a bot kind of thing?
- Exactly, how many traffic lights in there?
- Click the traffic lights.
- You know what I think?
I reckon I've got it wrong before and it's let me pass.
- That's because robots are better at it.
- Really?
- Yeah, the constant problem they have
is trying to get ahead of the AI
'cause AI works out how to hack it over and over again.
And basically, by 2014, 99% of bots
could solve the distorted letter ones
where they said, you know, type the letters you see.
And in 2023, there was a study that found
that bots are better than people at the picture ones.
By some degrees, so when you're showing the image,
78% of the time, people got it right.
100% of the time, the bots got it right.
- I thought the point was that they'd get you to do this,
but while you're doing it,
they're checking your browser history
to make sure you've not been going on the same website
500,000 times.
- Oh, usually the reason.
- Well, I thought it was, but.
- Sometimes usually the reason you get a capture
is because your browser history isn't human enough.
So the only way to get around it now, really,
is to allow cookies, browse the internet for five minutes,
and then go on to the website that you want to go on,
'cause then they see that you've browse the internet
like something.
'Cause it used to be that they could tell
if you were too slow clicking the mouse, you're a human.
- I'd like deliberately wobble my mouse a little bit,
so it looks like human.
- None of that works anymore.
The robots have learned to act like an idiot, like a human.
- I thought we were just training it.
I mean, I know that that was the idea.
- The idea was we were teaching the AI
what traffic lights look like in every single--
- We are as well, but--
- So that's still happening.
We're still training them, right?
- Yeah.
- Is this sometimes why when I get to the end of page 18
or a Google search for Moss, let's say?
It says, come on, are you a human?
Do you ever get that?
You get to the end of--
- Yeah, I really do.
- 'Cause nobody clicks through 18 pages of Moss results.
- I think that will be why, yes.
- Remember there was the big thing where Watson,
the IBM AI computer went on jeopardy,
and there was a whole thing about jeopardy.
There was a big complaint from the makers of Watson,
who said they rewrote the questions
so that it didn't allow for it to do it.
So for example, an example given is in 2002,
M&M signed this rapper to a seven-figure deal,
obviously worth a lot more than his name implies.
- 50 cents. - 50 cents.
- What's his 50 cents?
- Dammit.
- And Watson would be able to figure that out,
but they rewrote it to lose 2002 and M&M in there.
So it relied on you to make a connection of a pun
from the second half of the--
- But surely the quiz question is basically,
do you know that 50 cents is one of M&M's
stable of rappers, isn't it?
- No, I think any name, any musician with money in their name,
a low denomination in their name,
'cause I didn't know that about the stable of rappers,
but I didn't know that 50 cents is--
- I suppose, yeah, the thing is with those questions
is they give you two different ways
of getting to the answer, right?
- Yes, yeah.
- Either with the pun or with the knowledge.
- Yeah, and that's why they complaint.
But it's interesting.
I'd put it into chat GPT this morning just to see
what it would give if I gave the question
without 2002 and M&M and it, you know,
of course immediately came up, probably 50 cents,
a seven-figure deal is worth far more than 50 cents.
Was it logical?
- Oh, yeah, so it can do that now.
- I sort of overexposed the jokes.
- Yes.
- Oh dear.
(all laughing)
- Maybe I too have an AI.
- I gave AI a lateral thinking puzzle
and it couldn't crack it, so that was satisfying.
- This was triggered by the fact that--
I was wondering if Roll Dole was a vegetarian,
'cause I just read--
- Book of Physics, it was very anti-hunting.
So I said, "Is Roll Dole a Vegetarian?"
And Google AI said, "There were many clues in his books
"that suggest he's a vegetarian."
For instance, "Fantastic Mr. Fox is vegetarian."
And obviously, I thought,
well, the whole plot of "Fantastic Mr. Fox"
is by him eating meat so I don't know if he is.
- That's a bit where he breaks into a bomb,
just kills two chickens instantly.
- He's like, "I'm a flexitarian chicken, basically."
That's not real meat, is it?
Like, obviously the carbon footprint of chicken
is a lot better than beef.
(all laughing)
So I know that's that faulty.
So I tried Claude, the anthropic AI,
on this riddle, which I always just love.
So it's, and you have to write it down,
but imagine you have one, three, and five in a row,
and then directly beneath it, write two, four.
- The words.
- No, the new numbers has to be numerical, two, and four.
And then a question mark directly beneath the five.
- Okay, yeah.
- And it's like, what's the question mark?
- Six.
- So you think it's six.
So obviously that's what AI says to me first and I say.
But you can see Claude tells you it's working,
so it's like, it says, sussing out lateral thinking options.
No, is it six?
And you say no, it's not six.
- I think it was five again.
- I gave it so many clues.
Still didn't get it.
I'll give you guys a clue.
It's not a number and it's related to cars.
And this is kind of an example of what AI is to.
- It's an R for reverse.
- It's an R.
- Oh, come on.
- And that's 'cause robots don't drive cars.
- But I don't like the annuals.
(all laughing)
- In fairness, I think six is a legitimate answer
to that question.
- Completely, but it's when you tell it, it's not six.
And the thing about AI is it's overconfidence.
So one point it said, I've got it.
It's F.
- Right.
- You know when AI is really, I've done it now.
- Sorry, AI's overconfidence.
Maybe I too am an AI.
(all laughing)
- Isn't Dahl a vegetarian curry?
- Oh yes.
- Yeah, so roll Dahl, if not a vegetarian at least.
- Why?
- Is a vegetarian curry.
- Very good.
- And AI can't make proper jokes.
Maybe you too, Dab.
(all laughing)
- Or an AI.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, there's time for fact number three.
And that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the only ride
at France's second most popular theme park
is a two-year-old caracel.
- Yeah.
- Well, I've just taken my daughter to Disneyland in Shanghai,
10-hour flight, however much money it costs, trains,
all that stuff, and all she wanted to do
is go on the caracel.
- Oh really?
(all laughing)
- We've been on the caracel four times.
- Right, now back on the plane.
- So this sounds perfect.
- Yeah.
- There you go, it would've been a slightly cheaper caracel
than the one you went to, well done.
And that's all it is.
- So why is this such a shit that you buy?
(all laughing)
- It's Puerto Fue and it's the second best
after Disneyland Paris, obviously,
which trumps everything.
But this is a theme park that was set up in the 1970s.
It gets over three million visitors a year.
It's the eighth most popular in Europe,
and it's basically a place where they do historical
reenactments.
And it began in the 70s when this guy Philippe de Villiers,
who I'm sure will come and talk about,
found a ribbon castle as he do stumble upon a lot in France.
And he thought, I'm gonna stage a reenactment
of this thing called the Von Day rebellion,
which was a counter-revolutionary rebellion
round about the French, well, at the time of the French
revolution.
So he stage a reenactment, it got bigger and bigger.
And now it's 60 shows that act out historical events
from all across history and all across geography.
It's got these four period villages.
So when you stay there, you stay in a period village.
- It does sound amazing.
- It sounds absolutely incredible.
I'm desperate to go.
- I want to say someone recently that didn't have any of this,
but it was faithfully, medievally themed.
And the restaurants for things like the Night Tafaran.
- And that wet your appetite, did it?
- Yeah, what are you saying?
- Yeah, I'm saying I could see myself.
- This sounds better, is what you're saying.
- I'm saying this sounds better, yeah.
- Even then, Tafaran, there is plenty available
for people like you in the UK right now,
if you want to get involved in the medieval scene.
- Yeah.
- It's also sort of reenactment's going on.
- Really?
- I'll put you in touch with something.
- Thank you.
- But none of them at this level, though.
And this I suppose is less like you reenact it
as you watch other people.
So there's shows that--
- It's all just watching that.
- Did anyone else watch an hour long YouTube video
of someone going from each of the reenactments?
- No.
- Okay, I did.
(laughing)
- To begin with, it's--
- I like the way you're reenacting the reenactments.
I was like, yeah, yeah.
- I thought you would get a bit fatigued
with the amount of reenactment that you're watching
if you decide it.
- Come on.
- Yeah, I think it loses about 35 minutes in,
I sort of regretted my decision to watch the full hour.
- But that's what the carousel is for.
- I think it's like a pallet cleanser.
- Yeah, surely live, it's more exciting.
And you know, you're caught up in the sweep of French history.
- Kind of, yeah.
- I think so.
- But you're quite far away.
So it's sort of like watching a very like well-produced
Panto at a distance.
- I mean, it's epic, three million people a year
can't be wrong, then.
- Oh, have you read the TripAdvisor reviews?
- They're very strong.
- They're very strong, yeah.
- They're gonna build one in the UK.
- They are?
- Oh, yeah.
- For sure.
- Bister.
(laughing)
- And we're gonna have hotels, three hotels,
each themed around different periods in British history.
Just wondering if you had any favourites.
- Ooh.
- I was thinking COVID era.
- Yeah.
- Absolutely.
- No toilet paper.
(laughing)
- It's a general strike.
- General strike.
- Just three days for the price of five.
- Lovely.
- Yeah.
- I mean, there'll be a two to one won't there.
'Cause it's British history.
- Yeah.
- British history.
- It's so weird that people obsessed with the tutors
when the revolution happened the next century.
And it's our go revolution.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, everyone shaved their heads.
- Which revolution do you mean?
- The round table.
- Civil war.
- Yeah.
- So half of the people shaved their heads.
- Sorry, yeah.
- That's everyone.
There's no war, is there?
Everyone just agree all the time.
- Swinging 60s at the end.
- Oh yeah.
- I think that'd be a cool one.
- I bet they would do that, wouldn't they?
Like have a little so whole vibe.
- I would say.
- Outrageously the French one, Pudafu has the King Arthur stuff.
- I have no idea how they've managed to swing
getting King the rights to King Arthur.
- So he's not very litigious.
(laughing)
- Maybe a state must be trading, surely.
- I just think what, like,
is there an estate for King Arthur?
- No, I'm joking, I'm joking.
- It feels like there could be.
It feels like there could be.
- It feels like there could be like, I can't tell.
- I think like there was quite a bit of Frenchy stuff
going on in those Arthurian tales.
- Yeah.
- And the Mort D'Arthur is dressed
in half in French and all of this.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, yeah, yeah.
- And it's famously a historical
this place to be fair.
The makers tend to say we're just trying to entertain.
- Are they trying to entertain?
- Well, there's the big question.
- Oh.
- It's controversial.
- Trying to sneak in right wing propaganda to families.
'Cause that's what some people say.
- Oh, it's what some people claim
and the fact that it was founded quite,
quite an extreme right wing politician
is neither here nor there, I don't think.
- Well, he's not there anymore.
'Cause it's run by another guy, his son, I think,
called Nicolas, who described Vladimir Putin
as having sweet eyes and sweet words.
- Oh.
- Cool, cool, cool, cool, cool, cool. - Yeah. (laughing)
- I saw by coincidence, because we've been
plenty of this for a week or two,
there was an article in Harper's magazine this week,
where author Nat Segnit went to this place.
And he said it was a bit like hanging out
with an exceptionally charismatic and entertaining friend,
whose opinions only strike you as objectionable
in retrospect. - Oh. - That's funny.
- So what is the idea?
Is it that it's presenting a particular slant on history?
- It's very pro Catholic, it's very pro French monarchy.
It's very sort of like looking back at the past
and wasn't France great in the past
and shouldn't we go back to France being great again?
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's very into old school France. - Right.
- But fun, and that's how the right wing get you
if you make it fun.
- The craziest thing about this theme park, in my opinion,
is when you get there, you get a little booklet,
you know, the free booklet that tells you
the map of everywhere that you're gonna go.
And it's in multiple languages.
And at the top of each one of them
has the date of the day that you're going on,
which means they print them every single day
for the day that you're visiting the thing from.
- To you, that's the craziest thing about this.
In shame, how ancient has deep, weird, like,
political parts? - How much ink will we waste in here?
How much, how many trees have been chopped down
so that we can go?
- Yeah, but they probably are quite good at knowing
how many people have booked in for that day.
So they just don't know how many to press on the printer.
That view is the weirdest thing I've ever seen.
- That's the weirdest thing I've ever seen.
- Also, they can do it.
- Surely they can print all of them
and then just print the date separately.
- I think it's like an additional stamp as well.
- It could be a little man in a booth
who just stamps on the date.
- It doesn't look, it looks very printed on right.
- I just think it's that, I think, Dan,
this implies you think whenever you've scrunched up
a brochure and throw it away,
you think someone's going around all the bins,
taking them all out, ironing them
and reusing them the next day.
- Oh, I'm thinking they've got a big batch
in the warehouse.
They don't have to go, where's the guy
with the printing for today?
We've got 10,000 people in today.
How many guys should we print do you think?
Should we do about 10,000?
- Yes. - Oh yeah, let's print 10,000 every day.
- It's down, this is the amazing thing about time.
They know which date is coming.
So today is the 9th.
- What if it's so unwedish?
- It's huge cancellations
because it's raining too much or something.
- What if COVID happened
and they've got suddenly 365 days worth?
- For 2026, do they put 2026 or just 26?
'Cause if it's just 26, they can reuse it in a hundred years.
- See, okay, now we're talking, okay.
Maybe it's not so weird.
- By which time, the great French government will have risen
and taken over the world again.
- The Bourbon Monarchy will be restored again.
I mean, yeah, it's very interesting and strange.
And I think the reason that it's not very well known
about certainly in the UK is that 85% of the visitors
are French.
Loads of French people holiday within France.
And it's, obviously, it's so about France
that it's naturally appealing to the French people.
- Yeah.
- I think so.
I think there is one in Spain as well, isn't there?
- Yes, there is.
- But if don't want in Spain, if don't want in France,
they're gonna do one in the UK.
- Yes.
- Apparently the Spanish one is quite politically conservative
on just how good a thing the colonization of the Americas was.
- Oh, is it?
- And it depicts the European saying,
well, we'll only go ahead and colonize
if you guys really want us to.
And as long as we're gonna treat you really, really nicely,
that's sort of written into the show.
- Yeah.
- It's like the weather spoons of theme parks.
- Yes.
- They're all, you know, you get your cheap riddles,
but you've got a political agenda.
You've got a,
- Well, it's sift three when you're in there.
- I can't believe it.
- About weather spoons again.
But the weather spoons often, they dish out magazines
and have the proprietors views in them,
which is quite rare for a pub.
You know, you don't normally get like a strongly angled magazine.
- Yeah, wait, wasn't that your point?
- Yeah, I'm over-explaining.
I just think people won't know
that there's a weather spoons newspaper.
- Sorry, got it, yes.
- International listens for it.
- I mean, by now everyone internationally knows
about weather spoons.
Sorry to keep talking about it, but.
(laughing)
- You know what they don't do?
They don't stamp the date on every single newspaper.
'Cause they're not in not cases.
- Do you know who does?
- Newspapers, Dad.
- It's not a daily newspaper.
(laughing)
- I'm just quickly on the one in the UK,
which should be fine 'cause we don't have
an awkward colonial history.
So I doubt I'll be only controversial in that.
But it's planned for, yeah, Bucknell,
which is near Bista.
And they're obviously residents who are very against it
and residents who are very pro-it
and I just like the fact that it is in Oxfordshire
and the residents are led on the pro side
by a woman called Caroline Chipperfield,
Twitty and on the panty side by Flo van Diemann van Thor,
which shows how really Oxfordshire.
- Speak for England, Florida, yeah.
(laughing)
- Yeah, that's very interesting, yeah.
- On reenactments in 2014,
there was a World War II reenactment
that we're gonna do in Bansley in Yorkshire.
But it had to get cancelled
because people would be wearing Nazi insignia.
And so the council stopped it,
but said that they would be able to reschedule
if they did a World War II reenactment
with no Nazi elements whatsoever.
- Mm, right.
- That's very funny.
- Very good.
- I think reenactments really interesting,
like for example, civil war reenactments,
quite often as they're sort of digging holes in the ground,
they'll actually find the bones of a fallen soldier
from the civil war, this is in America.
- Okay.
- And that will then be brought back to a museum and so on.
And so they're digging up artifacts
as they are doing reenactments of civil war.
- Why are they digging holes as part of civil war reenactment?
Was that a major, was there a lot of tunneling
in the civil war?
- I'm not sure.
Some of them maybe just dig a hole.
Maybe to poo in, I don't know, you know.
I don't know what the outdoor retreating situation is.
- I'm not using that part of the,
they did not have that in the civil war.
- Oh my God, I have a fact about portals
in war reenactments, yeah.
- You know how in the American civil war,
and in fact in loads of wars,
some women have donned men's clothes
and they've gone into, you know that's a thing that happens.
And some women in the American civil war
dressed as men and fought in battles, right?
In 1989, there was an American woman
called Lauren Cook Burgess
and she had to fight a discrimination lawsuit
'cause she had been banned from taking part
in a US civil war reenactment.
She had dressed as a male soldier
to try and sneak into the reenactment of the war
and then she was caught coming out of a women's Lou
and was told off and told to go and put a dress on
'cause there were no female soldiers in the war.
She said yes, there were female soldiers,
dressed as men in the war, I'm doing that.
- Yeah.
- And she had to fight a four year court battle
and won the case.
She eventually won and was allowed officially to be on the pit.
- It is a bit mad that they're saying
you can only do it if it's really true
to what happened in the past,
but she is coming out of a portal.
- I know.
(laughing)
- Exactly, yeah, I know.
- Civil war reenactments are obviously a big deal
but there's one particularly moving one I read about
which was in 1913, an early one.
This is in a Kenburn documentary
and two armies restaged the picket charge
which was when Confederates tried to break through Union ranks,
the Unionists descended on them and defeated them.
Anyway, it was reenacted by veterans from the Civil War
and it is 1913.
- So that's 50 years.
- 50th anniversary.
And they came and it was an amazing moment.
So they all knew how to do it.
There was no arguments about accuracy.
- So there's veterans from both sides?
- Veterans from both sides
and the ones who on the Union side
were there waiting behind trees and stuff
ready to ambush and the ones on the Confederate side
charged through the fields and were descended upon
but as they descended when they met
rather than killing each other,
they all hugged each other and burst into tears.
- Oh wow.
- Was it much of a chart how old were these men?
- It was a 100 years later.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it wasn't as fast as they had once been.
- That's cool.
- That's very amazing moment.
- Unless you were there on the sidelines
to watch the reenactment, that would have sucked.
- What just was this?
- Yeah, mushy shit.
(laughing)
- You don't want to have an hour of that, are you on YouTube?
Imagine 57 minutes into your YouTube video.
You're like, finally they're gonna kill each other.
- There's this, this is woke up mad.
- The first 57 minutes is the charge.
(laughing)
- It's gonna be so good.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that John Williams,
the composer of soundtracks,
like Jaws, Star Wars and Indiana Jones,
doesn't actually like film music.
- Oh.
- Doesn't like it.
- This is probably the finest,
certainly the most decorated person
in the world of Hollywood soundtracking.
And he says, I'd never liked film music very much.
He said, it can be good, but it usually isn't,
other than maybe an eight minute stretch here and there.
I think that the music just isn't there,
that what we think of as this precious gift film music is,
we're remembering it in some kind of nostalgic way.
- Well, he's like a proper composer
of non-film music as well as film music, right?
- Yeah.
- Is that right?
- Well, his main hobby from the day job
of the film music is composing concertos and symphonies.
- And I think he sees the film music as just a job,
but the concertos is the main thing that he likes to do that.
- He does see it as just a job, yeah.
- But he's very good at his job.
He's had 54 Oscar nominations.
That's more than any other living person.
I think he's only one five though.
So that's a lot of losses, isn't it?
- Not that good.
- Yeah, so the only other person who's had more
is Walt Disney, who had 59.
But Walt Disney's a lot of them are for cartoons.
And they were all like, for instance, in 1938,
he was nominated four times in the same best cartoon category.
So like, he boosted up his numbers basically
by just being the only person who is making good cartoons.
- Did they cut to like a shot, four different shots
on the screen of Walt Disney from different angles?
And when it's announced, three of them look really pissed off
while they're throwing.
In that 1938, there were only five nominations
for best cartoon, and he got four of them.
And the only one he didn't make was Paramount's
"Hunky and Spunky."
- Right.
- That's my favorite.
- Oh, yeah.
- And he is right, generally, isn't he?
Like, it's always so annoying
when classic FM, if anyone who works over listening,
does classic FM at the movies.
Because the point in his film music is only good
when you're watching the film.
Because it's meant to be background
to the thing that's happening.
- I'm not sure everyone,
I'm not sure everyone agrees with you Anna.
- Oh, really?
- I disagree, yeah.
- I will sometimes pop on the score of "Mission Impossible"
- Can I just say, I agree with you.
But I pick a lot of our listeners by not.
And listen, if you're hearing this
and you don't agree with Anna,
a lot of people are like you, you don't need to write them.
(laughing)
- Right, to Andy, feel free.
- It's a growing thing.
Lots of concerts are put on of exclusively film music.
And I mean, the one's "John Williams" has come up with,
when you think of the theme tune of "Jaws" or "Trassic Park,"
they're so memorable, they're so easily called to mind.
- And people like music that they've heard lots of times,
a lot of people do.
- Yeah.
- There's some kind of effect, isn't it?
Like the exposure effect.
- Yeah.
- The more you hear something, the more you like it.
And so if people hear a lot of film,
there's a lot of times they're gonna like them.
- Yeah.
He doesn't even like films very much, "John Williams."
He says, "I was never a movie buff or movie fan."
Then as now.
- Yeah.
- So he says he's never sat through any of the Star Wars films,
at least not all the way through, but like it's in fairness to him.
He says, in the interview I read, he said,
"He not watched them, but I'm not particularly proud of that.
I have to say."
So he's not like one of these people's like,
"Oh, I'm just too smart to watch Star Wars."
- I've never seen Star Wars.
- Yeah, but like, 'cause there are a lot of people like that, right?
But he's like, "Well, you know, I feel a bit embarrassed
that I haven't watched it, which I think is quite a nice stance."
- Yeah, I think it's more common as well
than we realize that directors and people
who have to watch the footage so much,
because he does compose to the footage.
He's watched it probably more than anyone else,
just not in the final package, right?
- Yes.
- He was a session musician, by the way,
before he probably got into composing his own stuff.
And there's one iconic song that I just didn't know
he played a part in.
He was the piano on the song "Peter Gunn" by Henry Mancini.
- Yeah, you do. - That's him on the piano.
- I don't know what that is. - Sorry, neither do I.
- Do you know what it is? - Even with your amazing rendition.
- It's used as the theme tune,
all the motif in the film "The Blue Brothers".
It crops up again and again and again and that.
So that's interesting.
- Well, maybe it's my singing a bit,
but yeah, it's used in a lot of adverts.
- So you're honest, it sounded like one of those drum names,
- Yes. - Yes. - Baroque in the middle. - You get somewhere out there,
a Sammy person just went, "Yes". - Who said that?
- His son, Joseph, is the lead singer in the band "Toto".
- Oh, cool. - Although not when they did the only song
that "Toto" is 94. - That's true.
- He wasn't there when they released "Africa".
But he was the singing voice of Simba in "The Lion King".
- Yeah. - And he is also scored
some films like his father.
So he scored "Embrace the Vampire",
"The Legend of Gator Force", "Soccer Dog",
"Real Estate Superman", and "Fat Beach",
which is considered one of the best hip-hop beach movies
of all time, according to Wikipedia.
- Yeah, yeah, that's nothing.
- Dancing, why aren't we talking about this guy?
- Yeah. - He's the real legend.
- Finally, "Real Estate Superman",
he's getting some air on our podcast.
- "Real Estate Superman" says,
"Just like what I've had these ideas for a cup show".
(laughing)
- Now hear me out, guys.
- He goes into a modest two-better with potential,
and he comes out as Superman, spins around.
- The first person to produce a record from a film score
was someone called Anne Renel,
with a film called "Ladies in Retirement",
and we have slightly come across her before,
almost, because she wrote additional lyrics
to the song "Who's Afraid of the Big Bad Wolf".
But arguably the first female person
who did a score of her movie was "Friend of the Podcast".
- Oh, oh, oh, oh, Alice Guy.
- Hey, Guy? - Hey, Guy, yeah.
- For no way.
- So, hey, Guy, she made some sound films,
and her's were more like soundscapes than the music,
but she would like, there's one that she did
called "Cand Harmony", where a guy comes in
and tries to persuade the father of a girl
that he wants to marry, that he should be allowed to marry her,
and he pretends to play the violin
while someone underneath the table is actually playing the violin.
- Oh, no. - And that was a guy
who came up with that.
- So good. - Was that really early days?
Was that really early days?
- Well, she was the first female director.
- Yes, I think you talked about her last time I was away,
but she was like almost the first director, wasn't she?
- Yeah, she's, she's come up on the podcast a few times.
- Yeah, and so let's, if we're talking early film,
there is a theory that goes that the reason soundtracks
happened at all was to distract the audience
from getting annoyed by the amazing amount of rockets
being caused by the projector.
So it gave you something to focus your attention away
and cover up that noise.
It's a theory that other people say that no.
- It's also, you're trying to reflect
what the world is like in a film.
- Yeah.
- That's the other theory.
- It's quite cool that original soundtracks were sheet music
that was handed to the local, the in-house musician
who would just play the tune.
- Would they have the date of the show?
(laughing)
- Oh, no.
- They tended not to play it, right?
So it was always women.
This is in the old Nickelodeons.
And they'd be given sheet music and generally they ignored it
and they would improvise.
So you got to see the film and improvise along.
So you didn't know what kind of a film you were getting.
One day you might get a horror.
The next day it might be a comedy.
'Cause basically, although genre of a film is almost dictated
by the music, isn't it?
If you put funny music over a horror film,
it's no longer a horror film.
And the lady at the piano and the Nickelodeon
could just...
- She got the power, that's really cool.
- The power.
- Yeah.
I've got a fact about another very big soundtrack film guy
of Van Gellis, big name within the world.
He did Blade Runner, Charitz of Fire, stuff like that.
His music's very sought out.
Like he's just loved as a musician.
He did a lot of stuff separate to a soundtracking.
But there's one piece that he did,
which was roughly 12 hours long,
that fans have been trying to find
because it's quite scarce.
And it was when he did a straight to VHS thing.
It was three VHSs that the music was spread over
called Micro Neurosurgery with Videotapes,
Spinal Space Occupying Lesions by Dr. Sturgios Tegos,
Medical Publications.
And it was a friend of his who was a spinal surgeon
who wanted to show all of his techniques.
And so he got Van Gellis to make a soundtrack
'cause it's gorgeous.
- Yeah, 'cause it's incredibly boring watching him
just do it.
That's what he figured.
And so this has only ever been released on these VHSs,
but obviously it wasn't a big print run of the videos.
- Yeah, yeah.
- But have you managed to buy one?
- eBay is, I'm gonna have to finish soon
because the auction's about to end.
- And.
- That, like that, Charitz of Fire theme tune,
even as a skeptic of movie soundtrack,
and that is pretty, it's the top one, isn't it?
- Hold on, give it to me.
- Do-do-do-do-do-do, yeah.
- It starts with the dum-dum-dum-dum.
- So I think the problem just to cut just a circle
back around to the start.
The problem with this is that
everyone knows the little hook, right?
So everyone knows the bit they like.
And I agree, that was fun to hit,
but the rest of the tune is often a bit background.
And you have to listen to all of it
when they do classic FM at the music.
- But all the great composers have probably
just one bit of the now-low symphonies,
but they think I've really nailed that bit.
- If you've ever been to the opera,
everyone sits there through four hours of the fucking thing.
And then they get to the bit that goes,
do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do, yeah.
And then everyone in the crowd just sits up
because they've got to a bit that they recognize.
And then just leave after, do-do-do-do, go.
- This podcast is like that, I don't know.
It's an hour long.
There'll be one bit where Dan's explaining something.
- Okay, and you're saying that as the highlight.
- I'm saying that that's what people are tuning in for.
That's when they set up, yeah.
Can I tell you one of my favorite scoring stories all the time?
So we all know The Snowman.
- Of course, yeah.
- I'm walking in the air.
- Beautiful.
- Thank you.
- Totally, totally beloved in the UK.
I don't know if it's famous around the whole world,
but it's a really iconic, beautiful story about a boy
who makes a snowman, the snowman comes to life
and they go walking in the air, they fly through the air.
He was scored by a guy called Howard Blake,
and he came up with the idea because he had been
seriously overworked, right?
He was composing so much and working so hard.
He went down to Cornwall and he lived for three months
in a single heart with just a bed and a one bar fire.
Living a really rustic, much slower pace of life.
- Lovely.
- And one of the last jobs he was offered before it,
before he decided to do this, was a comedy called Percy
about a man with a 14 inch penis.
And he just thought, maybe I need a break.
- Oh.
- From work.
- Was Ali Jones also in that one?
- I don't know.
(all laughing)
- I think that was run by Michael Palin and Terry Jones.
- Was that it?
- I think.
- Oh wow.
- Pulling from knowledge.
- Python knowledge.
- Yeah, amazing knowledge.
I mean, who knows that much about Python?
You must be AI.
(all laughing)
Ironically, massive Python.
And he wrote it, he literally was walking on the beach
when he thought of walking in the air
and he'd jotted it down on an envelope.
- Really?
- Because it's not many snowmen and even English.
- No, no, no, no.
But I was thinking, you know, we talked a little while ago
about the Bailey Bridge, that kind of bridge
called the Bailey Bridge.
It might have been on a little fish.
- Yeah, yeah.
- 'Cause the guy who came up with that was an amazing
prefab bridge that was incredible in the Second World War.
He jotted his design down on the back of an envelope.
- Oh yeah.
- So my pitch is, it's maybe a museum of all the envelopes.
I know it's a book of the envelopes.
- Right.
- Right?
- Like all the things that have been drawn on an envelope.
You get those envelopes together.
- Specifically envelopes?
- Yes.
- Well, that can, like people are drawn on that can,
there's lots of things.
- That's a rival museum.
- Five packets.
- Yeah, I think it's gotta be, I think back of an envelope.
- Could you remember the Welkin Institute?
We saw the paper of which the first DNA sequence,
the drawing of how that would look, the DNA strands.
That was just on the back of a discarded bit of paper.
- Yeah.
- But not an envelope.
- I'm sorry, I think that's not allowed.
- Yeah, fair enough.
Why do you do this to yourself?
(laughing)
Make it a little bit broader and it'll make it
so much easier to write.
- It just won't be the same book.
'Cause the title is Back of an envelope, you know?
- Yeah.
- And the guy, the guy is like.
- Just call it Back of a dot, dot, dot.
And then that kind of encapsulates them all.
- I don't think it works.
'Cause I came up with the idea for the book
and then wrote it down on the back of an envelope.
Right?
So it did.
- Well, I know you wrote it on your notes here.
We saw you do it.
- So anyway, that's, yeah.
- What was the fact?
- I forgot now how we got here.
The guy, how and Blake, who came up with.
- I was walking from the snowman,
wrote it down on the back of an envelope.
- Was he walking down to the post office
to post the envelope?
Why is he walking with an envelope?
- Yeah.
- Like that's weird.
- That's so many many questions and questions.
- No one carries, even in the '80s,
no, it's just walking around with envelopes.
- No, you might have a receipt in your pocket
or like a bit of paper or something.
- I think that's what's gonna make my book so special.
- Yes.
- The mystery of it all.
- Yeah.
- What, who's got these envelopes?
Why is it always envelopes?
What's going on?
- But it never is.
That's why you can't fill the book.
That's a problem.
- Well, that's, that's a second order problem, I think.
First order is meeting publishers.
- I think there's a photo of you
in every publishing house in London
and say, "Do you not let this bad in?"
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can all be found online.
I'm on Shriberland on Instagram, James.
- No, sister's James Hackett on Instagram.
- Andy.
- At Andrew Hunterham.
- And you can get to us as a group.
Anna, how?
- You can email pukus@QI.com
or an app, no such thing as a fish on Instagram.
- Yep, that's right.
So yeah, if you want to take part in one of our other shows,
for example, Little Fish podcast@QI.com,
as Anna says, is the place to send your best facts
that you found out or perhaps you have feedback
about things that we've said, experiences related
to the podcast, do write into us
because we will bring those emails to drop us a line,
which is our special bonus episode
that sits within Club Fish, our private members club,
and you can find out all about Club Fish
by going to patreon.com/clubfish.
Check it out now.
Otherwise, just come back next week
because we will be back with another episode
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)