(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Shriver.
I'm sitting here with Anna Tyshinski, Andrew Hunter Murray
and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
of our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that to combat people sleeping
during church, priests used to employ a sluggered waker
who would walk around the congregation poking people awake
with a very long stick.
- Brilliant.
- Yeah, this is an amazing thing.
I was reading-- - Fancy that job, Andy?
- I think it sounds quite fun.
- Yeah, it does, doesn't it?
- You wouldn't make many friends,
but you're not in the business to make friends.
- Oh no.
- You're in the business to keep people awake,
listening to the sermon.
- Exactly.
I reckon you'd be great at it, yeah.
- Why?
- You've just got authority about you
and we all respect you so much.
- When you put it like that, I suppose,
yeah, I would be a prettiest.
You think I like correcting people
for minor errors they've made?
- Yeah, and you really piss people off,
so it sort of feels--
(all laughing)
- You're not losing anything, you know, people.
- I've already got zero status in this society.
- Yeah, the congregation don't like you anyway.
- I mean, I'm disliked enough that it doesn't matter if I'm,
yeah.
- And you always walk around with a massive stick,
prod people with it.
- Actually, that's an even better reason, yeah.
How long was the stick, do we know?
- Well, in some cases, they'd be 10 feet long,
because you've got long pews, don't you?
Very long pews, so if you've got someone
at the end of a pew and you need to reach them,
you've got your stick needing to--
- That's the slugger maker saying, isn't it?
I would touch him with a 10-foot pole.
(all laughing)
- I read about this in a book that I was checking out
called "Old Church Life" by a guy called William Andrews,
and it's a very old book, and it's full of really odd,
quirky little nuggets about the church back in the day.
And so these people would be paid good money to go around.
- Well, money.
- Well, but money, yeah, yeah.
- They were paid.
- I think for a lot of--
- I thought they were the wealthiest,
most high status people in society, but yeah.
- They were, and although some of them were given
a small amount of land to live on near the church.
- Nice.
- And in one case, there's a place called Yule Grave
in the Midlands, and they had one who was entitled
to a hat, as well as the small wage.
And then one in Wakefield, who also got hats, shoes,
and hoses, like that's part of the job.
- They turned sleepfield into Wakefield.
- Brilliant.
- That's what they had on their batch.
(all laughing)
- It is a part-time job.
You wouldn't expect it to pay a full salary.
It's only when there's a sermon on, isn't it?
- Absolutely, yeah.
And often they did other things, other jobs as well,
and that was just a bit of it.
But sometimes women got separate treatment,
and nicer treatment, so sometimes they'd have a stick
with a knob on one end and a little brush on the other.
And as a woman, you got a little tickle.
Whereas a man, you got knobs around the face.
(all laughing)
- Everyday sexism.
- There's a guy called Obadiah Turner,
who wrote a journal.
He was from Massachusetts, living around 1640s.
And he in particular had a fox's tail
on one side of his stick.
And on the other one, he had a long thorn,
which he used to prick people.
So it wasn't just a little whack around the head.
He actually stabbed you with it.
And he said there was someone called Mr. Tompkins,
who fell asleep.
And he pricked him with his long prick.
And the guy woke up and said, "Bust the woodchuck!"
And apparently he'd been dreaming
about a woodchuck biting his hand.
When actually, you know when you're asleep,
and you kind of integrate the alarm into your dream?
- Yes.
- Well that's what he'd done.
- Is he saying bastard woodchuck?
- Bus the woodchuck.
- That's a good church.
It's a good church appropriate, swear, swear.
- Yeah.
- You haven't said anything wrong.
- It's a midst oath, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Do you think it was more or less annoying
for the priest giving the sermon
that rather than have people falling asleep quietly,
it was just a constant cacophony of,
"Ow, fuck, bust the woodchuck!"
(laughing)
- That's a good point.
I'm not sure it was about being annoyed
so much as the people in the church
are supposed to be listening to the word of God.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- So, who's got ultimate authority over this system?
Is it the sluggard waker has autonomy
and is allowed to basically stand at the front
and see people falling asleep?
Or does the priest have to say,
"There, pew three, seat four."
- No, the priest is doing his gig.
- Yeah, okay, okay.
- Yeah, yeah, sluggard's there
to make sure it all goes smoothly.
- That's a skill of the job,
it's the only skill of the job,
it's spotting the sleeping people.
If this priest has to keep telling you,
then you're being fired.
- Here's a person who needed a bit of skill,
Betty Finch, who was a sluggard waker in Warrington.
She was known locally as the bobber,
because the way that she woke people up
is she had a fishing rod,
and she had a little bob,
like a little weight on the end of her fishing rod,
and she used to swing it round
and wake people up with the rod.
- And if you did it repeatedly,
she got hooked into your cheek
and just reeled you up.
(all laughing)
- She was the only,
I've found a few names of the actual people given that up.
She was the only woman with a job I found.
So, I feel like a very sort of male dominated industry.
- Yeah.
And as I said,
they did often have other roles in the church,
and they, one of them seemed to be dog whipping,
which was an important thing to do,
because in church services, in times of yore,
and we're talking about a long period of time,
sluggard wakers existed, I think.
- Yeah, yeah, 1600s. - So for many months of years.
So, farmers would often, if they're going to church,
they'd be like, well, I'm gonna use this chance
to bring all my sheep, sell them at market.
So, they go sell the sheep at market,
go to church,
and they've got all their sheep dogs in church.
So, you've just got a bunch of sheep dogs running around.
So, yeah, the sluggard waker also
whips the dogs out of the church during services.
Well, can we give the proper name of this position?
The knock nobler.
- The knock nobler.
- What's that name?
- That's the person who has to chase the dogs out of church.
- Distracting, I would have thought.
- That's like the Benny Hill show down there.
(laughing)
- Yeah, then no, that's the knock nobler,
or the dog noper, that was another one.
Who just has to get in there and whip the dogs,
and they have special tools as well.
So, the dog whipper, who might also be the sluggard waker,
was sometimes issued with a special set of tongs
for those hard to reach dogs.
If the dog had hidden in a crevice or something
in the church, you'd have to use the tongs.
- Yeah, I've seen those.
- We have been, this is really exciting,
we've been somewhere which has a dog whippers flat.
- What's a flat?
- A flat like an apartment.
- Oh, right.
- So, we've been somewhere, was it the Sidney Opera House?
- That's right.
Yeah, very late with you when it was being built,
they thought that's just okay.
No, it's Exeter, we went to Exeter on tour last year.
And Exeter's got a cathedral, a lovely cathedral,
which I visited.
Didn't see any of you guys there, yeah.
No praying.
(all laughing)
- Well, we had confidence in our research.
We didn't really feel like we had to go and get help
from the Almighty.
- I was like, please, God, please,
I just need one good fact about lasagnas.
- Well, it's not an actual apartment, it's a room.
But it is a room, it's a really nicely placed room.
So, as you go into the cathedral,
it's just above you there.
And it looks out onto the nave.
It's a viewing spot basically.
So you can be on 24-hour shift looking for dogs
in the cathedral.
- What, and then you have to descend quickly
as soon as you see a dog.
- Yeah, there's a pole, you slide down it, yeah.
- Swing on a zipline.
- That's cool.
- Do you think that's where whippets come from?
They maybe were the worst-behaved whippets.
- And you needed to whip it often.
- Oh, really?
- No.
- Definitely the origin.
- I think it did really used to piss priests off, by the way.
I know we're saying, would they go through the...
- It really did, and there was in American Boston
in the 1600s, there was such fury from a priest over there
that he suggested that a cage be made
so that you would drag the sleeping person into it
and cage them up like a bird
and just let them have to wake up and deal with that.
And that was off the back of someone being woken up
and in a rage, attacking the sluggered waker,
or tithing man as they were often...
- Tithing man.
- Tithing man, as they were often called in America.
- They're called that, interesting.
'Cause a tithe is the bit of your income you give
to the church, a tenth of your income.
- So probably, as well as doing this,
they collected the money.
- They're actually very busy people, the sluggered wakers.
- They also rang the curfew bell.
So we had, in this country, a curfew bell
against early medieval times,
which was, I think the original aim of it was
to keep people from having rebellious, seditious meetings.
But anyway, it was quite useful because it stopped fires
'cause curfew, literally coming from the French,
I think, to cover the fire.
Couvre-feur is like time to cover your fires now.
And it tended to be eight o'clock.
And so at eight p.m. every evening,
then you'd have the curfew bell rang.
It was like cover your fires and go to bed early.
- Even for Andy, who's famously not a night owl,
you wouldn't want to have to be in at eight o'clock every day.
- Even I normally make it to the watershed at nine p.m.
(laughing)
- What, half an hour of root TV?
Praying for your sins of watching it afterwards.
- Have you guys heard of the role of the beggar banger?
- Beggar banger.
- Banger?
- The beggar banger.
Yeah.
- No, what was that?
- It's not as exciting as it sounds.
It's someone who was responsible for controlling
the length of stay of any unwanted strangers in the parish.
- Okay.
- They were known as the beggar banger.
- Was that employed by the church?
'Cause that's not a very churchy,
welcoming thing to do.
As a church, you are supposed to embrace
particularly beggars and paupers, aren't you?
- Charity has its limits, Anna, and you know.
- As Jesus said.
(laughing)
Are you guys aware of Acts of the Apostles,
chapter 20, verse seven to 12?
- Can you just stop me off and I'll--
- Okay, so Paul was preaching.
- Oh, yeah.
- Okay, and he was preaching, he was doing this speech,
and it was a very long speech.
And there's a guy called Eutychus.
And Eutychus was listening,
but it was a really, really boring speech.
So he fell asleep in the middle of St. Paul's preaching.
And as he fell asleep,
he fell out of a third-floor window and died.
(laughing)
So this is what the Bible says will happen to you
if you fall asleep while someone's preaching.
- And that's why churches are always on the ground floor.
- Yeah, you get very few on the top of skyscrapers.
- Yeah.
- Just thinking a third-floor window is pretty,
is a risky place to risk falling asleep.
- Well, quite, probably don't sit there
if St. Paul's doing it for some reason.
Anyway, luckily Paul went down, picked him up,
brought him upstairs and said,
"Oh, don't worry, he's fine."
Even though everyone could see he was dead.
But then a bit later, he did come back alive.
- Oh, wow.
- Any more explanation on that?
He just--
- It's the Bible, Dan.
That's the kind of thing that happens in the Bible.
- Yeah, zombies, very common.
- I've read this book.
Have you guys heard of Pew Openers as a job?
- No.
- A Pew Opener was someone who basically was an usher.
He would collect you at the front.
He would walk you to your pew
and they used to have little doors.
And he would open up the door
and he would allow you to not have to do that on your own.
And he got paid a very minimal amount for doing that.
And you could also pew rent.
So you could rent the actual row that you wanted.
You know, he was a concierge kind of character.
- That's quite interesting.
'Cause if you go to church,
you'll find that the same people every week
go to the same church, right?
And they all tend to sit in the same places.
And if a new person comes into the church
and sits in one of those places, there are eruptions.
- Do you think the Pew Opener would say, excuse me,
I think that's actually where, madam?
'Cause you certainly, and I imagine he did this mostly
for the wealthy families.
They would have their own pewies where they would sit.
And he'd be the one guiding them to them.
- Have you guys ever been to a church
with a boxed pew system?
- No, what's that?
- Those are good.
So, you know, pews are in rows normally.
And some church, some Georgian and earlier churches
would have boxed pews.
So it's kind of a little pen that you sit in.
- So the Murrays don't have to sit with the riffraff?
- Well, you know, or any surname, any family.
Yeah, yeah, any family of good standing.
No, no, no, but that was it.
(laughing)
We once did an ostentatious photo shoot in a church
which had those.
That was very, very interesting.
- That's what they were made for.
(laughing)
Do you know someone else whose job it was
to guide you to your seat?
- Yeah, it could be.
It would be the deaconess.
And the deaconess seems to be one of the only official
church jobs you could get as a woman.
And from like really early church time.
And basically, so one of her jobs would be
to guide you to your pew.
Another job would be like you'd help distribute communion.
You could take communion to people in the community
who couldn't make it to church.
And they were basically ordained.
And the reason they came into being really
was to stop male church officials
from seeing naked women.
So their initial job was baptism.
Because, yeah.
Because baptism was almost always adults then.
- Right.
- And it was--
- You could always get your kit off.
- You got your kit off, you went into a river,
and it was very improper for a male priest
to be seeing a company of women into the water.
So that would be her job.
She'd undress the woman, hold the veil up
so none of the clergy could see.
Go into the water with her, baptize her,
and pop out again.
- That's awesome.
- Do you guys know what a pedo-baptist is?
- Here we go.
- That's someone who baptizes children?
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's, you're very close.
It's someone who believes in baptizing children.
Yeah, there's a big divide in the church
for pedo-baptists and credo-baptists.
- Did they have John the Baptist
and John the pedo-baptist?
- Yeah, it's funny.
Only one of them's made it to the big time, hasn't he?
- What was the other--
- Credo-baptists.
And there are people who believe
you should only be baptized once you have been able
to come to an adult understanding of God on your own.
- Because credo is Latin for I believe, right?
And so the idea is that you can say yourself
that you believe that as opposed to a child
who doesn't really understand what it all means.
- What have they done to deserve that?
- Well, I always thought it was just about
protecting them to get into heaven, so.
- Ah, that's interesting,
because it seems like Hannah and I are credos.
- Yeah.
- But damn, it sounds from what you're saying.
- Big ol' pedos.
(laughing)
- Interesting.
- I've never heard those.
- Those terms.
No, I don't think they get bandied around, actually.
I don't know why.
- I said I'm a credophile.
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the Queen of France
once pranked a girl at court by secretly taking in her clothes
to make her think she was pregnant.
This is this great, yeah, pretty mean.
This is this great, great story
from the memoir of Hortense Mancini,
and she was one of the Mancini sisters who were so fun,
but her uncle was a guy called Cardinal Mazarin,
who was the closest person to the royal family in France,
really, and Cardinal Mazarin decided
that he would start teasing his six-year-old niece.
- That's the thing, that's the thing.
You hear this fact and you think,
"Oh, it's a clever prank to play on someone
who's probably, what, 20 or maybe a T.A."
That's not a six-year-old.
- Yeah, that's what makes it so funny.
So there's this girl called Marianne, who's six-year-old,
and she's the person who's writing the account, Hortense.
It's her little sister, and Cardinal Mazarin says,
"Hey, you've got an admirer,
and he's got you pregnant, hasn't he?"
And then they would take her clothes away
and secretly take them in so they got tighter and tighter,
so she thought that she was pregnant,
and the whole court got in on this gag, you know?
It was just hilarity for everyone in the court.
- Bullion, isn't it, really?
- Oh, look, it's a fine line, isn't it?
Between are you laughing with her or laughing at her?
- Yeah, it's a fine line, and I think they crossed it.
- Anyway, the queen, it was Anne of Austria,
and she was the queen mother at that time.
She had been married to King Louis,
and then she'd been the queen regent,
so she was referred to as the queen.
She turned up by the six-year-old's bedside,
the consulter said, "Gosh, yes, you are a pregnant, aren't you?"
And then they planted a live infant in her bed,
which we think was a baby of one of the servants.
- This is next level, I think.
- Yeah, this is Jeremy Beedle level.
- This is crazy, though, yeah.
This is amazing, and then, what happened next?
- Well, the queen offered to be the godmother,
said, "Well done, you."
And then, I think they probably, at some point, came clean.
I don't think they made her raise the child.
I think the person whose child it was would have objected.
- Well, they asked her who the father was, didn't they?
And she said it could only either be the king
or the conch de gouiche.
- Yes.
- Because they were the only ones who she'd kissed.
- And she was, it was quite sweet.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Although the conch de gouiche was a known absolute playboy.
So...
- Right, right.
She wouldn't have known that, she's six.
- She said that, he just gave a little kiss on the cheek.
I quite like this in the memoirs from Hortense,
who was three years older than her at the time,
so she would have been nine.
And she said, "She was very proud
"to know the truth of the matter,
"and I never tired of laughing about it,
"just to show that I knew it."
Which is such a relatable thing
when you're a slightly older sibling,
doing that over-the-top laughing to be like,
"Yeah, I get it."
- "Oh, yeah, I get it."
- "Yeah, yeah, yeah.
"Yeah, I kissed."
- "Please don't do this kind of thing to me.
"I feel like an idiot."
- I was looking up pregnancy pranks.
- Oh, yeah, cool.
- There aren't many good ones.
It's mostly pranks that you,
if you're pregnant, can pull on people around you.
- Oh, right.
It's not like, 'cause you could throw a water balloon
at someone in the night,
and then they think their waters are broken.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah.
- That's one.
- If you're pregnant, you could walk around
with like a doll hanging between your legs.
So it looks as if you're--
- Right.
- You've given birth without noticing.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, these are all about the level of the ones I found.
The only one I found that was any good potentially
was using your pregnancy to help someone else
with their pregnancy prank,
where you can pee on their pregnancy test.
- Oh, yes.
- So it'll come up as a yes.
- Yes, right.
- And then she'll be able to say to whoever, you know,
"That's really funny." - Oh, look at me, yeah.
- Here's the thing that men don't really know
much about pregnancy tests.
So you could literally probably just take a vape
and draw a line on it and say, "Hey, look, I'm pregnant."
- You can take a COVID test.
I'm not pregnant, but you do have COVID.
(all laughing)
This book is, it was published in 1675.
And I guess at the time,
it's sort of quite sort of timely we're talking about it.
It's sort of the Prince Harry memoir of its day,
to an extent, because it was very much a--
- What an amazing attempt to make this book relevant
to absolutely other than that.
- I mean, it just totally is.
- Absolutely bang on.
- It just totally is.
- Who is this?
- That's what it was.
- Hortense.
- Yeah, Hortense.
- Did she get a frostbyss and penis?
- Well, no, this was the first time that, you know,
this is someone who was amongst the royals.
She was almost basically a queen at one point.
And it was a book that was published
when women weren't really writing books either
about their personal life.
And so when it came out, it was a huge bit of news.
It was--
- And it was scandalous.
- Yeah.
- And she filled it with gossip.
It would have been like with Prince Harry's book,
going out and everyone going,
"Oh, wow, you've actually said that.
God, cool."
- Wow.
- I've never heard of her prior to reading up on this,
but she wrote her autobiography.
And then a couple of years later,
her sister wrote her autobiography as well.
And as you say, they led just an incredibly,
interestingly bizarre, fun, but also quite tragic light.
They were in marriages, which were very unloved
and which fell apart.
They had to flee the country from time to time
because of being exiled as a result
of their dubious affairs and so on,
and their husbands being furious.
It's a real rollicking adventure.
- Well, let's quickly mention this husband
that she had in front-- - Yes.
- Who appears to have been slightly unhinged.
- Oh man, yeah.
- He believed that milkmaid shouldn't touch cow's udders
in case they became aroused by them.
- Yeah, there are a couple of accounts of this.
This is just, let's give his name.
He's called Amon Chal Duller Port Duller Mayeray.
All right, that was his name.
And he was incredibly rich, wasn't he?
- He was.
He was like the richest man in Europe, pretty much.
- Yeah.
And he, so I read that account that he was worried
about milkmaids finding milking sexy,
but then I read another account saying he worried
that men might get aroused
by the sight of milkmaids doing their milking.
- Yes.
- I actually think, Hortense didn't rise
about any of these things, actually.
These all came from a guy called Abbey de Choisy,
who was, he wrote his memoirs and they came out
after he died and they're all about the story
of how he went to live in the countryside in France,
pretended to be a woman and seduced a load of young girls.
And he apparently was friends with Perot
who wrote a lot of fairy tales.
So we think actually a lot of it might not have been true.
- Okay, interesting.
- But he was the one who wrote all this stuff
about this crazy guy.
- And he was basically the idea with Armand Charle
was that he was incredibly pious, wasn't he?
And very religious.
And I imposed really strict rules like that.
So I thought everyone was gonna be aroused all the time,
did things like he had a collection of priceless works
of art that he'd inherited.
And in fact, from Cardinal Mazarin.
And he went around knocking all their genitals off
because he thought the genitals were improper.
You know, he'd slashed tapestries.
He'd painted black bits of penis and balls and nipple
on various paintings.
- There are so many different accounts.
So one of the things I read is that he did that specifically
because he was worried that she, Hortense,
was gonna get aroused by them.
- To be fair, she did have quite a few affairs.
- She did, she had a time. - To be fair, she had a time.
- She was leaving around.
- And she almost married Charles II
when I mentioned before that she almost became queen.
So Cardinal Mazarin, who was sort of,
he was their uncle and he was very much taking them
around town and trying to set them up and arrange marriages.
Charles II met Hortense, fell in love with her
and thought, I've got to marry her, made the offer.
And he said, no, because Charles II was an exile.
And he said, no, you've got, you know, you got your name,
but you've got no money, you've got no title.
I don't know your prospects.
And so he denied it.
And then only a few months later, even weeks,
Charles II suddenly is restored back as king.
And so Mazarin comes running back saying,
actually Hortense would love to take your offer.
And he says, no, I'm afraid that's not going to happen.
- Such a shame.
- Yeah.
- This could have been a queen of England.
- Yeah, a little bit.
- They did hang out in England.
Hortense definitely fled to England
and spent a lot of time at court.
And she was super fun, livened the whole place up.
And the thing is, they were this Italian family.
And we should say they were called the Mazarinettes
and there were seven of them all together.
And they were the seven nieces of the Cardinal.
And they all looked quite different.
They were dark skinned when everyone was very pale skinned.
- They looked similar to each other,
but different to normal other people.
- To normal noble women, yes, who were all very pale.
They all seemed to have the same name.
There were two Laura's, two Anne-Marie's and one Marianne,
which is quite confusing.
But yeah, they were fun and Hortense especially.
So at one point when she ran away from Armand Charles,
she ended up in a convent,
or I think she was put in a convent
to try and make her behave.
But she became best friends with this woman
called Manmoselle de Cossel,
who maybe she was in a relationship with
or had a little fling with.
Maybe they were just really close friends.
And they sort of played practical jokes
on the nuns quite a lot.
- They all thought they were pregnant.
- They, yeah.
I promised I haven't had sex all the nuns.
Yeah, she did things like she filled two chests with water
and apparently the water leaked through
onto the nun's beds.
But she had this really cool adventure in the convent
where her husband came to try and kidnap her away
when he found she was misbehaving.
And her, Manmoselle Cossel, found,
it's like the stuff of fantasies.
They found a little hole in a grate in the parlor
which they could just squeeze through to escape.
And so they squeezed through this grate
and they climbed out the outside.
And then they actually realized it was a false alarm
and their friends were visiting, not her husband.
- This is the story of the sound of music.
(laughing)
This is, there are baddies in a convent,
squeezing through a gate, come on.
- Yep, well then they squeezed back in
'cause they were like,
"Oh, we're gonna look stupid, it's just our mates."
And she got stuck in this grate
between two iron bars for about 20 minutes.
And Manmoselle Cossel, that's like tug her out
and then they ended up covered in soot
on the parlor floor, snogging.
No, I've embellished some of the ending, but yeah, sounds fun.
- After she died, her husband caught up with her
and had wanted actually to repatriate her for ages,
but hadn't managed to do it. - It's so much easier
to catch up with someone after they die.
- Well, exactly, it's really, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Well, he caught up with her, he caught her body,
he put it in a sealed coffin, great, fair play,
it's what you meant to do.
And then he just carried it around Europe
on a sort of weird posthumous honeymoon
to all the places they had been together in life
for four months, a long time.
And then eventually, he left her in a country churchyard
and then eventually when he died later,
they were buried next to each other.
I don't know how she would have felt about that.
- And then during the revolution,
they got chucked in the sand.
- Yeah, so it has a...
- An unhappy ending, not a few other people.
(laughing)
- Obviously, you know, I'm a big fan of the aristocracy.
- I read an article that she introduced champagne to Britain.
- I read that. - Yeah, I think popularized.
- Popularized, yeah. - Oh, really?
- I think she was fun.
- Oh my God, then this is the most fun thing about her.
I did all this reading and then finally, at the end,
find this one article which talks about
this extraordinary saloon that she opened up in the 17th.
- I think Salon.
- I think a saloon is a Wild West Indian car.
- Is it not a saloon? - It's a saloon.
- No, no, no, all the ladies in London used to come.
They had to leave their guns in the car.
- And at those swinging doors,
the piano player, they would stop when Hortense walked in.
That's it, yeah.
So we're calling it Salon, so really.
- Let's go with Salon for the moment.
- Let's call it for that, yeah.
- Because it was kind of French,
so let's say a saloon, but with a French angle, like Salon.
So let's land on Salon.
- I mean, that's definitely.
- That's what they were called.
- That's what like Salons, very popular in those days.
Have Salon.
- So she ran this, let me get to the fucking facts.
She's 17th century London.
She had basically this extraordinary like book club
that she ran next to St. James's Palace
and all the ladies who were encouraging not to do this,
to have intellectual conversation, to read books
and discuss them with each other,
to share their ideas, their philosophies would go.
They would drink champagne
and they would do all this stuff together.
And she was just such a,
the article describes her as an influencer of the time.
- Definitely.
The interesting thing was these Salons
were massive in France, weren't they?
They were like a huge thing in France at the time
and all the middle class and upper class women
would go to these Salons and kind of learn things,
but she was the one who brought it to London.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause it didn't exist here at the time.
- Yeah, you could say that really podcasts
are the Salons of the present day.
- It wasn't.
- Well, we're discussing things.
- We allow one woman on our podcast.
- That's true.
- Yes, traditionally a male environment.
- Okay.
It's loose.
- It's a discussion, isn't it?
We've all got champagne.
- Oh, God, yeah, I wouldn't come to this
if that wasn't promised.
- But she, I mean, this was how great her influence was,
particularly with quite obscure texts.
If she introduced a text to be read,
it would get round town
that this was like something that was amazing
and it would boost up a big run of it with translations
because people suddenly were going,
what are they reading there?
And we have to be part of that.
- It was very much the Richard and Judy's Book Club
of its day.
- Yes, exactly.
That's what it was.
- That's more of a salon.
- Yeah, that is a book club.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- The one interesting about Hortense, if you Google her,
the first image, the painting that comes up of her
is of her looking very beautiful
and then just a little nipple hanging out from the move.
Did you see that?
- Yeah, yeah.
- And there's only a few paintings of her that are around,
but that's one of the surviving ones.
- I think that might be just your history
is deciding what pictures you get.
- Yeah, that's possible.
- It's interesting you'd have that painted in
to an official portrait, not official,
but a portrait of you ends up with a bit of nipple in.
It's just a general portrait that you get done
to show that you're a sexy person, like Janet Jackson.
- Yeah, that was why she did that, wasn't it?
- But the thing is with Janet Jackson,
it was a malfunction, right, where she quickly covered up.
But with a painting, you'd have to sit there
for about three days.
- That's a hell of a malfunction.
- We'll accidentally follow it out.
(laughing)
- Maybe the artist was just too embarrassed.
You know when like someone has green in their teeth
and they just, you'd want to say, but you don't say it,
he's like, "Oh, I just got to paint it in, I guess."
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that according
to their origin story, the Minions serve
the most evil person on earth,
but they were conveniently frozen in a cave
and unable to serve anyone between 1933 and 1945.
(laughing)
- Wow, is this official Minions' Canon?
- I believe it is.
- Yeah, where is it?
- Yeah, it's in the movie.
- It's in the movie, it's in the second movie, yeah.
- Oh, wow.
- The dates, you've altered the dates there,
but that is part of the period when they were frozen.
- I gave the dates for Hitler,
and half of them the dates for the Minions.
- Exactly.
- But basically, there's this thing on the internet
that people keep doing this meme where they say,
"Ah, the Minions, they serve the most evil person,
"but what were they doing during World War II?"
And it's like a big joke that,
"Ah, they haven't thought of this,
"but of course they have thought of it,
"and it is in the movie, which I haven't seen."
- Yeah, so we should say who the Minions are,
but there's these little yellow creatures
who are in the film Despicable Me,
and then all the other sequels.
- And then the film Minions.
- So they were henchmen that got their own
spin-off series, and Minions was 2015,
and in the opening sequence, it tells you the history,
so it says that they serve various evil masters
from the T-Rex all the way through to--
- When did they get out of the cave?
Sorry to interrupt you, Dan.
- So they go into the cave in 1812.
That's when they first go in,
and they emerge in 1968, I think,
to avoid being so obviously avoiding the Nazis.
- So 1812 would have been just after
Napoleon's retreat from Moscow.
- Yeah, yeah, well, it's very cold
in when they were treating, so--
- Exactly. - There we go.
- All right, I'm going with the lore.
I love it.
- I wonder who they're serving now,
who's the most evil person on a--
- Few candidates, aren't there?
None in this room, sorry, I'm looking around, I'm sorry.
(laughing)
The director, one of the co-directors of the films,
is Pierre Coffin, Peter Coffin.
- Peter Coffin, yeah.
- But his name doesn't actually,
Coffin in French doesn't mean Coffin.
- What does it mean?
- I don't think it means anything,
but the word "Couffin" means basket,
which is very close, so I really thought
it was called Peter Coffin,
and then I thought it was called Peter Basket,
and actually, he isn't called either.
(laughing)
- But he does the voices of lots of the Minions, right?
- Lots of them, yeah.
- All of them apart from Baby One, yeah.
- Well, there's Jermaine Clement
from Flight of the Comcords does one.
- Does he voice them?
- No, one, literally one Minion,
and then this guy, and someone else,
but this guy does 899 Minions.
- Oh, wow, I think so, there's another director,
there's a co-director of the film,
so I think that's another-- - Yeah,
who also does some Minion voices.
- The language sounds so difficult to do,
'cause every word is, I think,
a real word from one language or another.
- I think there's some gibberish in there.
- There's gibberish as well.
- It's mixed in with loads of other languages.
- But they sound so funny to listen to,
I just, I love the sound of the Minion's language,
like it's really funny.
- Have you seen them all?
- No, I haven't seen any of them, I've just watched some.
- Yeah, I've seen Minions in bits,
you know, you walk in and out
while the kid's watching a movie,
and then you're asked to leave the cinema
'cause where's your kid, you know,
and it's like, "All right, I'm outta here, jeez."
- Yeah, he's cool, Coffin,
and I think that one of the reasons
that the Minions speak this combination of languages
is that he is very multilingual, I think,
so he's like half Indonesian, half French,
grew up in Cambodia and Japan,
and, yeah, invented this language.
And interestingly, when it's dubbed into other languages,
it gets changed, because you notice
that they say English words enough,
you're like, "Oh, they must be talking about toast now,"
or bananas, famously.
But in other languages, they'll sub those words
for that language. - Interesting.
So they'll still use the Indonesian
and the different places,
but then whenever there was an English word,
they use whatever country you're in the world.
- Yeah, yeah. - Oh, that's interesting.
- Or just drop in more local words where they can.
- That's cool.
Yeah, his mom was a famous novelist, wasn't she?
- Was she?
- N.H.Dini, Coffin's mom, was called.
I'd never heard of her inside of this,
but she is an Indonesian novelist and feminist.
- Very nice.
- At least two of the Minions' films
have been banned or altered by censors in China.
- Oh, really? - Who dislike various aspects
of the plot.
So there's, and I just, I really like this.
So the film, The Rise of Gru,
which I think is one of the most recent ones,
the Chinese censors added an entirely different bit
of the film at the end of it,
clarifying that one of the characters
who previously been involved in a heist in the film,
you know, fictional film, fictional heist, everything,
was caught and served 20 years in prison for the heist.
I mean, fuck yeah. - That's so good.
(laughing)
- They also say that Gru returned to his family
and his biggest accomplishment was his free children.
- Gosh.
- And apparently the reason that they've done this,
most people think is to promote China's three child policy.
- Oh no.
- Which they've been trying to do
to increase the birth rate over the last few years.
- Wow. - Guys.
- I was reading about other animated villains
of various guys. - Oh great, okay.
- And so Scar, The Lion King.
- Yeah.
- No spoilers, please, I haven't seen it.
- I think I can avoid spoilers.
- Great.
- Who is sexier, Scar or Mufasa?
- According to just us or you?
- According to you.
- Are they both lions?
- Yep.
- Mufasa.
- Okay, it says equal to the lions.
- I find them both equally attractive at the lions.
- Lions can be more or less sexier than each other.
They're apparently completely impossible
for James to compete.
(laughing)
- I thought it was a subjective question.
- Do you find all, you must think there are some animals
which are sexier than other animals in the same species.
- Have that buff kangaroo.
(laughing)
- I'm not sure that that is true.
- Do you think of all humans as being equally sexy?
- Absolutely.
(laughing)
- Apart from my wife of course,
they're slightly less sexy than other animals.
(laughing)
- Wait, doesn't your cat have a modeling contract though?
- No, she doesn't.
She has appeared in some adverts.
- So you must think she's sexy.
- You don't have to be sexy to be in an advert.
That's not what they are always cast for.
- No, you're right.
- But the difference here is--
- Captain Bird's work.
What a terrible example of the sexiest man on TV.
- He's so hot, yeah.
(laughing)
- Can I just say I don't find my cat sexy?
- Yeah, you're allowed to say this.
It can be a model and not sexy.
It's the human personality,
which is adding to the sexiness of these characters as well.
- Well, they've got voices, haven't they?
Yeah, they're human voices.
And I'm speaking in English, yeah, yeah.
- For me, I would say that physically,
Mufasa definitely sexier,
but in terms of personality and voice,
Scar, of course, is more sexy.
- Okay, well.
- Scar's like old and manky looks.
- No, but I know that's why I said.
- No, I know.
No, no, and he personality-wise is evil.
- Okay, well, can I say one of you is right and wrong?
- Mufasa is less sexy than Scar.
Scar is the sexier one, physically,
and would be in the real world as well.
In fact, specifically in the real world.
So this is a study about
what makes a lion sexy or unsexy.
And for years, they've been thinking about-
- Come on, you're talking from a lion's perspective.
That was the whole point.
- This is about what, main darkness.
- Right, yeah.
- 'Cause some lions have really, really light mains,
and some have really, really dark ones.
You know, scientists have been trying to work out for years.
What does this have any effect at all?
And they just introduced these fake lions,
and they could sort the mains around.
And you could attach them with Velcro,
so you could whip off a mane and then reattach it.
And the dark mains were very much preferred
by the lady lions, lionesses, as they're also known.
But interestingly, dark-mained lions
have more abnormal sperm,
because they have heat stress,
because their mains are so dark,
they keep absorbing sunlight,
and they have to eat smaller meals as well,
because they get more heat stress,
and if they eat a massive, great meal,
you know, it warms you up.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- You know, sometimes you have a huge meal.
- I'm so hot on that.
- Oh, no, no, no, no, mate, sperm are deformed.
(all laughing)
Would you like a dessert?
No, they're deformed enough already.
(all laughing)
- That's why I make my husband,
dye his hair peroxide blonde before every meal.
(all laughing)
You've got to watch out.
- I'm sure that peroxide's good for him.
(all laughing)
- Lex Luthor, do you know what made him evil?
He's the villain in the Superman universe.
- I actually don't.
No, I don't have a handle on what he came from.
- What is he?
He's just like a rich guy.
- He's a rich guy, but he was a scientist,
and it was basically Superman made him bald,
and that is why.
- Bald?
- Yeah.
- As in no hair.
- So he used to have a huge amount of ginger hair on his head,
and there was an incident between Superman and Lex Luthor,
where they were in a science lab.
Lex Luthor was trying to make something really good.
Superman had to blow it out
because something went a bit wrong,
and in the big Superman blow that he did,
it just pushed these chemicals onto Lex Luthor's head,
made him bald.
He was so furious, he became a supervillain.
- And that's an overreaction.
- It's an overreaction.
- He's got temper issues with us.
- What's amazing is this is a retroactive story
to explain why he suddenly goes bald,
because you know part of like comic book artistry,
they would hand it to sort of as it was ghost artists
to come in and do the sort of comic strips and help them.
One of the guys who was in charge of it one week,
mistaken Lex Luthor for one of the bald henchmen
and accidentally drew Lex Luthor as a bald headed man.
And so it was a total mistake
and it ran for a couple of weeks.
It went out and then another one went out
and that just had to be it.
So he had no hair.
So the only reason he's bald is an artistic mistake.
- Who the hell is proof reading this?
That's like releasing a few scenes from The Lion King
where a hyena plays Scar and no one notices.
And then what?
- Lex Luthor would buck the trend of most supervillains
because villains in fiction and particularly depictions
of villains are generally more pointy than heroes.
Yeah, there's the sense of, you know,
you can draw Mickey Mouse with three circles.
- But if he was bad, it would be triangles.
- Well, yeah.
So I was reading an explanation about this,
about the graphology of films and so on.
Darth Vader literally has a triangle
on the front of his face.
- Oh yeah, he does.
- More scary.
- But more sexy very often.
I mean, they genuinely are made to be a bit attractive,
I think.
- Sorry, Darth Vader.
- He's got a dark main Darth Vader actually.
So he is more attractive to female Vaders.
- Yeah, he was king of the prize.
More like, more than women actually.
- Is he not sexy Darth Vader?
- Darth Vader?
- He's got a sexy voice, doesn't he?
- Have you seen Under the Helmet?
- I haven't seen any of the-
- Okay, no.
- Don't look under the helmet.
- Keep that helmet on.
If you're making out with Darth Vader,
just keep that helmet on.
- Yeah.
- I think in Disney films,
the female villains are acknowledged as sexy
in fact there's a book called The Enchanted Screen,
the Unknown History of Fairytale Films.
- Who are you thinking of?
- Which says-
- That woman in The Little Mermaid.
The big octopus.
- That's what she learned, yeah.
- Pick the one example that she does in the film.
Although she's got some nice lipstick on.
- There's arguments about whether or not she's an octopus
because she's only got six arms.
But then-
- Human arms or octopus?
- Well, here's the thing.
- She's got tentacles, hasn't she?
- Right.
- She has tentacles.
The argument is she does have two human arms,
which makes it eight, which, yeah.
- Hang on, isn't there a QI fact
that octopuses have six legs and two arms?
- Two, like pedipals, yeah.
- Yeah, because they use their legs to walk
and they use their arms to grab things.
- So they've got it bang on.
- She's a perfect octopus.
Six legs, two arms.
- Yeah, I guess so, except that she's a myrrh something, right?
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So I don't know, do you count the human part
in with the octopus part?
- That's right.
- I don't know, I don't know.
- Anna, I think you were saying something about-
- I don't know that you're spending too much time
on some weird forums, Dan.
(laughing)
I was just saying that in "Snow White,"
that queen in "Snow White" is acknowledged,
according to this book, it says,
"As is well-known, animators all preferred drawing her
"when they were making "Snow White"
"because she was very complex as a woman
"and much more erotic than "Snow White."
And she isn't everything in "Corrella de Vil," she is,
and it's sort of-
- They're kind of glamorous, yeah.
- They're glamorous, certainly, yeah.
- Maybe it's glam.
- I think it's glam, yeah.
- They're glamorous, they're powerful, they're independent,
they know what they want.
They want to skin dogs to make a coat.
I like a woman with ambitions.
(laughing)
- And he's old, you know what I'm saying, yeah.
- One thing that they do often have, villains,
I think this is more men than women, actually,
but they often have terrible skin.
And dermatologists are not happy about this,
'cause they say it may foster a tendency
towards prejudice in society.
Because all the bad guys in movies have bad skin,
if you see someone with bad skin,
you're gonna think they're bad.
And really, there's quite a lot of people
who are saying that really, you shouldn't do this.
We should stop having scars, we should stop having-
- Yes.
- I'm trying to think you have bad skin.
- Well, for example, almost all James Bond villains,
even in the- - I think in Christoph Waltz
in "Anything He's In," as like-
- Exactly. - Scars, doesn't he?
- But the most recent Bond movie has two villains,
both of whom have facial disfigurements,
"Have You About Them" has one in a previous film,
and it's like- - The bad is Roger Rabbit.
- There is a lot of it when you start looking.
- I thought you just meant acne.
'Cause I think, I mean, scars are kind of cool,
but being covered in acne,
I can see that that would like be insulting.
- No, no, no, no, but it's lots of people
who suffered facial scarring for whatever reason.
And then you see film after film after film,
the baddie is a baddie because they've suffered
some facial scarring. - Two face, the Joker.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Yeah, man is full of it as well.
- When you start, you do realize, yeah, this is mad.
- Yeah, that's true.
- Just another backstory,
and another World War II related backstory, Donald Duck.
There's a theory about him that I quite like, so basically.
- Is there anything to do with this cock-screw-shaped penis?
(both laughing)
Like the old ducks are.
- I think you can probably make it to do with that,
I believe in you.
But before World War II, Donald Duck existed,
obviously as part of the Disney franchise,
lots of shorts with him,
but he was quite a light-hearted, fun-loving duck.
- Can I just quickly say, lots of shorts, but no trousers.
- Very good. - Thank you.
- Thank you for that.
So as we know now, Donald Duck, bad temper, right?
That's what he's famous for,
he's always shouting at his nephews.
He's very...
(mimicking duck noises)
- That's uncanny change, that's a good impression.
- Really good, yeah.
- I didn't know you could do that.
- It's not a good tempered noise.
It's not a happy noise.
So he changed, and the theory is that he,
it was the war that changed him
because he is the only character in the Disney franchise
who actually saw active service.
- Stop it!
(laughing)
- He was on the beaches at Normandy.
He only wanted a piece of bread.
(laughing)
What do you mean he saw active service?
- He saw all those cartoons.
- You know all the propaganda cartoons
that Disney released during the war?
Loads and loads of propaganda cartoons.
So all the characters featured in these,
but they didn't go actually into battle
except Donald Duck, who did.
- In which theatre?
- What do you mean?
- In which theatre of the war did he fight?
- He, the Pacific.
- Sorry, I didn't say that.
- I actually think it might have been the Pacific.
- Well, he is a duck.
He would make sense for him to be in the water.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
He should be, maybe, if he's in any of the services.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But I can't remember to be fair,
but he's seen serving, shown serving in the US military
in one of the propaganda films,
fighting an air battle against the Nazis.
- Oh, an air battle?
- Well, he is a duck after all.
(laughing)
Makes sense that he should be in the air floss.
- He's the perfect weapon.
(laughing)
- He doesn't even need a plane.
- No, wow.
And you're saying that he's got PTSD, effectively.
- Well, straight after the World War II,
his temper got worse.
He became very sensitive to loud noises.
You know, if his nephews make a racket,
he gets upset, and that's the idea.
And actually, in a recent duck tales,
he had to have anger management courses.
- Wow.
- So that's the theory.
He's got PTSD from the war,
and all the evidence is there, I think.
- Whenever anyone was shooting, they would go, "Duck!"
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that every barge firm on the River Thames
used to have its own signature whistle.
- Oh my God.
(laughing)
- Oh, that's very cool.
- Yeah.
- This fact, Andy, I reckon,
if you put all of your facts into an AI,
(laughing)
this is what they might come up with.
- London whistling and a means of transport,
this is not very popular anymore, yep.
- Yeah, seemingly dull.
- But really interesting when you get into it.
- Well, let's find out.
- Yeah, exactly, you'd be the judge at home.
- So anyway, this was on a British library blog post
about the decline of whistling,
which is absolutely meat and drink to me, obviously.
And it's about Lighterman.
Lighterman were the men, almost exclusively,
who steered barges to their destinations,
and barges are basically flat-bottom boats
that were used to transport lots of cargo.
So you might dock your ship in the river,
'cause there isn't a proper dock,
you just drop it in the middle of the river,
and then you have to unload it,
and the barges are the things that go back and forth,
emptying them out or loading them up.
And there were different barge firms,
and every barge firm had its own whistle,
and it was so you could identify yourself at night.
There we go.
- Who's was that?
- Yeah, that's the sexiest of all the barge firms.
James obviously doesn't see any difference
between sexiness and barge firms.
- To me, barges are all the same.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so barges, barges are great.
The apprenticeship used to be five years long,
just for the Thames.
- Oh, Anna's been on a barge.
You've looked after a barge, haven't you?
- Yeah, well, a canal boat,
so not one of the big Thames barges,
which you had to sail.
- Oh, narrow. - Must be the same.
- No, James, please.
We're gonna get deeply into the difference
between a narrow boat, a barge, all of it.
(laughing)
- But the apprenticeships lasted for so long,
didn't they?
So they were introduced, I think, in 1555,
and that was when Parliament established
the company of Waterman and Lightman,
because they needed to regulate the industry,
and I think it only stopped maybe 500 years later.
- I think it was 2007, the government suggested.
Maybe we don't need to spend five years learning.
- More so more than 500 years, exactly.
I mean, it is tough, but come on.
Also, there are no working barges on the Thames anymore,
so it does seem quite weird to be doing that.
- I think it's a good thing
that we stopped people learning how to barge
and getting them to do maths instead these days.
(laughing)
- Well, it takes just two years of training now
and six months of local knowledge training, which is--
- But then there are people just trashing barges
into each other and--
- Yeah, it's woefully inadequate, it's ridiculous.
- We've seen the Thames here.
- So you're saying there's no barges these days,
but they're clearly barged.
- Well, there are barges for other purposes,
so it's not really for freight anymore,
it's for tourism, or for taking restaurant barges,
or I don't think there are any that are having
iron deposited from Europe and carrying them up.
- There were two, right?
- You had the Lighterman,
which is carrying all those goods back and forth,
but then you had the Waterman,
who were the people that carried people across,
which was a massively important thing back in the day,
because getting across from the south side of London
to the north was an incredibly hard thing sometimes.
- Or the other way.
- Or the other way, even if you, why would you go south?
(laughing)
- Good point.
- I live south.
(laughing)
Yeah, so people like Peeps write about it,
saying it was the quickest way to get across,
because often the clogging on the bridges
would be so great, it was just--
- What you say bridges was bridge, wasn't it?
- Bridge, London Bridge, was the only one east of Kingston,
which is a lot of river with one bridge across it,
so they were massively important.
And get this, I love this, so loads of their trade
came from transporting people to the theater,
so that was why you would go to the South Bank,
it's 'cause it was where all the theaters were,
so that was a huge bit of trade for the Waterman.
And then when Covent Garden set up,
where we're recording this podcast,
their trade suffered massively,
'cause there was suddenly theaters north of the river,
and no one had to cross the river
anymore to go and see a show.
- But you could still get carried down the river, couldn't you?
If you lived in Chelsea and you had to get to Covent Garden.
- Oh yeah, that's true,
although there were other means of getting
from Chelsea to Covent Garden.
So they were so angry about the loss of their trade,
and they campaigned so much to Charles I,
when he was king, that in 1635,
he banned taxi cabs in the city,
unless they were traveling three miles out of the city.
- No way, to keep the barges in business.
- Keep the barges happy.
- I try to find any notable lighter men.
So the closest I found, well, Danny Dyer,
who's a quite famous character,
his family, he came from a long line of lighter men.
- Really, is that right?
- That's interesting, that seems classic.
- But one that I thought was a bit relevant to us
was I found that a comedian came from a long line of lighter men,
and it was a comedian who was called Malcolm Hardy.
And during the boom of alternative comedy
in London, particularly, he was a great voice,
and he used to open clubs,
and they were known as dangerous clubs
because you would have heckles from the audience,
he would heckle the act coming.
You know, I don't know about the next act,
they might be a bit shit, I think they are.
Please welcome to the stage, you know,
and then bring you down to the stage.
(laughing)
- Cheers, Malcolm, thank you.
- So he was an amazing character,
and he wasn't a lightsman himself,
but he did live on the Thames.
He had a boat that he lived on,
and sadly, quite a few years ago,
he fell into the Thames and died.
But what is interesting about Malcolm Hardy
is he's very relevant to us,
and even the listeners of this show,
because he opened up a club in Greenwich called Up the Creek,
which is where we do all of our live shows often in London,
and that is the Malcolm Hardy Club.
- Have you heard of the Trojan barge?
- No. - No.
- So this was during the 80 years war,
and the Anglo-Spanish war,
'cause they kind of coincided with each other,
and it was the city of Braida,
and the Dutch and the English were trying to capture it,
and the way they did it was with a Trojan barge.
There was a canal or a small, like a shallow river
that went into the city,
and they had a barge with a load of peat in it,
a load of moss. - Nice.
- One for you, and they all hid underneath the peat,
and they got into the city,
and then jumped out and then took the city.
- That's brilliant.
- And it was kind of like one of the turning points of that war.
- Really? - Yeah.
- So wait, when you say that barge with a load of peat,
they didn't put peat on top of the barge and disguise it.
They did, they disguised the barge.
- They hid underneath, no, no, the barge,
everyone knew it was a barge.
Everyone knew it was a barge full of peat,
but what they didn't know is that there were soldiers
in between the barge and the peat.
- That's incredible.
- And the soldiers used the peat to kind of hide themselves
even once they got off the barge,
so the people of Braida would be attacked by moss men.
- This is like the moving forest in my birth base.
- Yes, it's been attacked by a bunch of peat.
- That's very tall.
- That is so cool.
But did they have to snorkel through the peat?
'Cause peat, I think, was being very heavy, very dark.
If you're lying with peat, basically buried under peat,
that's not good for you.
- Probably the amount of peat above them
wasn't so much that they all suffocated.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, I see that.
- Yeah, I was just imagining like a little flat hat
that you're kind of wearing.
- Yeah, but you can't have too little peat
'cause otherwise they'll see.
Wait, isn't there something under that peat?
- Probably a folding locks amount of peat that they used.
And that was the amount that they used, I think.
- Brilliant.
Well, that's military planning for you.
That's your guess, Chris.
- They actually did do a previous run
with another peat barge.
So yeah, they did it with just like one or two soldiers
to see if it was gonna work.
And it did work.
And then the next time they did it properly.
- That's so funny.
What do those soldiers then do once they're in the city?
But there are only two of them.
Peat, get your peat!
Anyone want some peat?
Fellow Braida people.
- I don't have any frame of reference
to the '80 Years War.
- No, and nor do I in this short paragraph that I've written.
But yeah, it was basically the,
I think it was just, I'm gonna be wrong,
but I think it was just before the Glorious Revolution.
So I think it was whenever that was.
- '60, '88.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's one of those mid-European mid-century wars.
- Yeah, they all merged.
- The '80 Years War, the Hundred Years War,
the '27 Years War.
- They weren't very creative with the names, were they?
- I've got one more barge, I think, for you.
- Yeah.
- This is actually sent in by a listener.
This is sent in by Hannah Watson a while ago.
In 2004, there was a sightseeing barge trip
happening in Texas, right, on a lake called Lake Travis.
There were 60 people on board.
Unfortunately, the barge then passed a place
called Hippie Hollow, which contains what was certainly then
the only public nude beach in Texas.
Every single person on the barge moved to one side
of the boat in the hope of seeing somebody naked.
And it capsized, and it fits them all in the water.
- Beautiful.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland, James.
- @JamesHarken.
- Andy.
- @AndrewHunterM.
- And Anna.
- You can email podcast.qi.com.
- That's right, where you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website,
NoSuchThingAsAfish.com.
It's got all of our previous episodes up there.
It's also got a link to Club Fish,
our secret members club,
where you can hear all sorts of bonus content.
Do that now.
Otherwise, come back here next week.
We've got another episode waiting for you.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)