(upbeat music)
Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish.
Anna Tyshinski is still off on her hollybabs.
And so we have for you a very, very special guest.
It is Melanie Bracewell.
Now those of you down under will know who Melanie is.
She is a regular on television in Australia and New Zealand.
She's recently been on New Zealand Taskmaster.
If anyone outside of New Zealand has naughtily managed
to get hold of that on the tubes.
(laughs)
You'll know her from that.
But we've actually known Mel for many, many years.
We first met her when we did our New Zealand tour
many years ago.
We've been wanting to get her on the podcast
for ages and ages.
And finally she is in the UK and she came on the show.
And actually that brings me to the fact
that she is touring the UK at the moment.
So if you listen to this podcast, you like what you hear.
I know you will 'cause she's absolutely brilliant.
She's so funny.
Then definitely get down to one of her gigs.
You'll have to get in there fast
because she is already right in the middle of that tour.
But if you listen to this as soon as it comes out
then you just about have enough time
to get to her gigs in Stafford, Edinburgh,
Glasgow, London, Cambridge and Birmingham.
That's all happening in the next week or so.
And of course if you are in Australia or New Zealand
then she's doing loads of gigs down there.
And actually in the UK she'll be back
to do the Edinburgh Festival in the summer.
So if you want to know any more about Melanie
go to melaniebracewell.com.
And if you want to know where she's playing
then go to melaniebracewell.com/gigs.
Really hope you enjoy the show.
I'm absolutely certain you will.
So let's just say on with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Melanie Bracewell.
And once again we have gathered round the microphones
with our four favourite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Mel.
- Yes, my fact this week is that a study of magpies
in Australia has revealed that magpies
do not like to be studied.
So this was a study that they did
at the University of the Sunshine Coast.
They were trying to track flight patterns
and things of magpies.
They developed these very special trackers
that are only 1% of a magpies body weight.
This is perfect and they put these trackers on the birds
and they quickly just started pecking them away
and they went, oh, they're not being very successful.
It'll be okay.
And then the other magpies came
and just helped them peck the trackers off of them.
So at first they were sort of, you know,
you scratch my back, I'll scratch yours
and they were pecking them off each other.
But then they found that other magpies
who didn't even have a tracker in the first place
were helping the other magpies to get rid of their trackers.
So they were showing behaviors of like ultrism.
And so they were like, actually,
this is quite a good study.
- Oh, so that's how they know.
I was hoping they'd decoded like some calls of theirs
and they would translate this piece off, mate.
- Probably, yeah.
- Actually, you know, 1% of your body weight
would be almost a kilo.
- What are my clothes?
What are my clothes weigh?
I don't know.
- Let's weigh your clothes now.
- No, let's not take them all off now and weigh them.
(laughing)
- But you do have a good point
because magpies do have a reputation for being dicks.
They, but falsely.
So basically only eight to 10% of magpies will swoop people.
Only the male magpies and only in one month of the year.
- Hashtag not all magpies.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Well, this is a really interesting thing
because magpies are over on this side of the planet as well.
But Aussie magpies,
they're actually a different species to the European magpie.
That's just not anything to do with each other.
So I remember saying to people,
oh, magpie swoop and that being an alien concept here,
but you live in Australia.
You know the danger, the fear of walking down a street
and a magpie swooping on you.
- And the problem is, because they're very smart
and they recognize faces,
if they decide that they don't like you,
they will target you.
So some people will just get swooped every day
on their way to work.
And so that's why they've earned that reputation.
- Have you been swooped?
- I have been swooped once in my life,
but my boyfriend loves birds a lot.
And he has decided when we first moved to Australia,
he was gonna become friends with all the magpies.
So that's the other thing,
because they can recognize your face,
you can actually make a friend for life.
And they stay in the same neighborhood.
So if you move into a neighborhood
and there are magpies there,
they will be the same magpies for like 20 years.
- See, it's really high stakes when you move in.
You've got a chance to make a good impression.
And if you blow it, long-term grudges are held.
- I know you mean, but they only usually live
for about five years.
- Can't the family, like in the mafia,
remember and bear a grudge?
Didn't we save, I mean, that was crows,
we were talking about ages and ages ago,
I think crows, bear a grudge.
- They do, yes.
And the school children are often targeted by magpies
because they often wear school uniforms.
So if one child has thrown a rock at a magpie,
they will then view all children as threats.
And so they'll just attack.
Same with like if they determine
if you're wearing like something covering your face
or your head, say a bicelmet.
They view that as a threat of like,
what are you hiding from?
And then they will then swoop you for that.
- Does anyone come across Emma Glenfield
when you're doing this research?
- No.
- So we were talking about school kids.
She was in Australia and she'd been watching people
be swooped by these magpies.
And she thought, it seems to me like they're going
for bold people more, the bold teachers,
they seem to be going for the bold teachers.
And she asked her mom, is this a thing?
And her mom said, well, I don't know if it's a thing,
you know, do your homework or whatever.
And anyway, she decided to do a study.
So she went to her school
and she watched as these magpies swooped people
and then did a survey of anyone who'd been swooped saying,
you know, how tall are you?
What's your hairstyle?
What sex are you?
All that kind of stuff.
- What's your hairstyle?
None.
(laughing)
- Well, then she's supposed to have 100 people
around the school, but then it went online
and she got 30,000 people to participate
on her survey online.
And she found that statistically,
magpies are more likely to go for bold people.
And according to a magpie expert called Darryl Jones,
her study is the first time anyone's ever examined this link.
And so she's doing brand new science
and learn this about people.
- So you know what bold people should do then?
Draw a face on the back of their head.
- What?
- Magpies are less likely to go at anything that has eyes.
And so if they're swooping from behind,
they're just seeing a bold head all together.
- Oh, that could be icy.
- Yeah, so there are a few things
that people think they've worked out
that magpies won't sweep out.
One is if you have eyes at the back of your head.
So people often cyclists might often wear glasses,
sunglasses on the back of their head facing that way
to give the impression there are eyes there.
- A bit like in, is it in Africa,
we might have said before,
where they draw eyes on the bums of cows?
- Yes, exactly.
- Stop them being attacked by lions.
- Yeah.
- That's why that.
- 'Cause you can't be sneaked up on.
- It's so funny, they're a protected national species.
So if a magpie attacks you, you can't attack it back.
- You kind of just have to let it happen.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- That's funny.
- And so what they do then is if they've identified
an aggressive magpie, they have to ship him out of there.
But there's a minimum distance,
which is like 25 kilometers.
So because they'll just fly back.
- They don't respect the restraining order.
- Have you heard of the Windsor Road monster?
- No.
- That's an Australian magpie, specific one,
which was especially aggressive
and had to be put down in the end.
But it took a very long time.
I have to say, the Windsor Road monster
has given multiple chances to learn and change.
And it attacks, well, there were more than 40 complaints.
One person had a heart attack shortly after being swooped,
which is not the fact.
- You know, there could be other things happening
in that person's life that makes them more susceptible
to a heart attack.
- That's not true.
- It's not necessarily the--
- That's true, that's true.
But it didn't, no, you're right.
But it was going for people's faces.
It was going under cyclist's helmets to get them.
It was even for an Australian magpie,
it was being especially aggressive.
- You're bowled under there, mate.
- What's going on?
Where are you hiding?
- They're just trying to protect their ground.
They spend most of their life just protecting their area.
So they choose their radius, and it's quite small.
And they will just spend the whole time just standing,
like, as bounces on the edge of their patch,
being like, don't come in here all the time.
- So there was one cyclist who I read about
called Dr. Richard Osborne,
who came up with this new cycle helmet.
- I don't think I've seen this.
- Does it have a face on it?
- No, it doesn't have a face.
Can you guess what it is?
He uses a thing I have around my house
to scare them away.
- So I know this, so I won't guess.
- Yeah, okay, melts out.
- I could have seemed really smart.
- Oh, stop using James' personality to look out for it.
- It was a golf club.
- What do you know about things that happened in my life
in the last two weeks?
- The last two weeks?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
All my family members.
- Your kid has had a birthday.
- Yeah.
- Your daughter's two years old.
- So you see, you put the hours in with people then.
- What a way to find out that's your daughter's birthday.
(all laughing)
- Oh no, Uncle Dan hasn't forgotten about you.
No, no, he's been very busy.
I'm sure the gifts on its way.
- Oh my God.
- She built a helmet to ward Dan away, I think, yeah.
- Does the bike have a mortal baby pinioned on top of it?
- A little bit or a doll.
- It has, you know, these party blowers
where you blow them and they go, pfft.
And they kind of stick out.
He has those attached to his helmet
and there's a tube attached to them.
So the, and Magpie comes there,
he blows into the tube and they all go, pfft.
- Is this what you were thinking, though?
- No.
(all laughing)
- I just see the guy who had tied a lot of cable ties
to his hair.
- That's very funny.
- And does he, has it sort of caught on?
- Yeah, well, no, it's not caught on
because he looks like an idiot,
but you said it seemed a bit safer than carrying a stick
and waving it around, which was his other option.
- Yeah, or having spikes, which a lot of people do,
they're not sharp spikes, but they are sticky out.
- Is that right?
- Yeah, yeah, just as a deterrent.
- The best thing to do is to just be nice to them.
- Yeah.
- Because they will remember you being nice.
So what happens is people run away and they go,
oh, you are guilty, why are you running?
Therefore, it just fills this prophecy in their head.
- But to be nice to them, if you're in their area,
so you just, how can you be nice?
- You just feed them.
You just leave them out like little peanuts and things.
That's what my boyfriend has been trying to do,
like leaving peanuts outside our yard and getting them to come.
And yes, and then when they like you,
they'll bring their kids along to be like,
here's my kids, you miss the good day.
- One nice thing that you can do for them
is actually something that will get you in trouble with them,
which is if you see one of their babies struggling
and you go to help it,
they will view that as you hurting their babies
'cause they haven't introduced you to it.
So be careful how nice you are.
- And that's why you didn't give a gift.
As nice as they viewed as a threat.
- Playgrounds, playgrounds are like that, you know.
- Are they?
- Well, if you see a child that's struggling
and you go over to help it,
their parents might think,
"Who's this guy who's approaching my child?"
- Yes.
(laughing)
- "This guy's left the fence.
"I can't remember not to wear my costume
"when I'm doing that."
(laughing)
- I'm weighing my clothes.
- Do you have lots of superstitions about them in Australia?
- I have heard of these superstitions,
but I don't think I follow them in my day to day life.
- 'Cause that's pretty much what they're well known for here,
right?
- Yeah, I follow quite a few.
- So when you see one,
do you say like, "Hello, Mr. Magpie.
"Where's your wife?" or something?
- Good morning, my Lord,
and how's your wife and children?
Yes.
- Right.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And do you do that?
- I do, yeah.
- And what about if you see one on its own?
Seeing two is fine, three is fine, whatever.
And one on its own, bad luck, so you just quickly, you know.
- 'Cause in Australia, that's a lot to get out
while it's coming for your eyes, isn't it?
- Yeah, exactly, that's very, ah!
That's it, yeah, that's what I'm gonna say, yeah.
But no, there are all these things,
like the magpie landed on the cross
when Christ was being crucified,
or the tongue of a magpie contains a drop of blood
from the devil himself.
- I think if they open their mouth,
there is a little bit of red in there, isn't there?
I think that's why they associated with Jesus.
- And that's why if you scratch its tongue
with the edge of a silver sixpence
and put a drop of blood into the wound,
it will gain the power of speech.
(all laughing)
- We've all been there.
- There's so much slander about them
from back in the day, particularly religious.
So the one about the crucifix, apparently,
it was the only bird not to cry
when Jesus was crucified, and that was big news.
And then in the 19th century, there was a vicar
who said it was the only bird
that refused to go on Noah's Ark,
rather it just wanted, it hung outside swearing instead.
In France, the idea is that a magpie
is a reincarnated evil nun.
- I can see it, I guess.
(all laughing)
- British magpies eat a lot of dog poo.
- Oh, wow. - Yeah.
Even if there's other food around,
they'll eat the dog. - Really?
- Yeah, yeah.
And to such the extent that people in parks
have noticed that they'll,
'cause they're quite smart, obviously, magpies,
they'll go to the dog poo bins,
pull out a bag of dog poo,
rip open the bag of dog poo,
and then have a little snack.
- Oh, my God. - Oh, my God.
- That's some self-respect.
- What? - That was awful.
- It was nutritious. - Might taste great.
- I've never tried it, I don't know if it's good or not.
- Oh. (all laughing)
- I just wanted to say, we don't know.
- You said, "Might taste great."
- Yeah. - And I heard you saying,
"Mine tastes great."
(all laughing)
- Actually, I'm just gonna gloss on the move past it,
'cause, you know, we've got a guest.
- You guys at a park,
is that you're trying to go through the dog poo,
you're naked at a playground.
(all laughing)
It's a whole image.
- James has got a party before he was scammed out his head.
- Yeah. - Oh, my God.
- They do have them in New Zealand.
- They do, yes. - My pies, don't they?
But they've come over from Australia.
Apparently, no one's trying to get rid of them in New Zealand.
You know, like in New Zealand,
there's quite a lot of invasive species
and they're trying to get rid of them.
Well, they're not doing it with my pies
because it's too hard, basically.
- Yeah. - You get rid of two magpies
from an area and then the next two will move in.
But apparently, what I read is they've got
a bad reputation in New Zealand, these magpies,
because they're big, showy, noisy,
and according to the article, it must be said, "Australian."
- Oh, yes. (laughing)
That really does rub us the wrong way.
That's how I can understand it.
(laughing)
- Did you hear of these acclimatisation societies?
- Yes. - 'Cause that was,
they're Australian magpies,
but they were introduced to New Zealand by societies saying,
I'm not sure what the rationale was actually,
'cause it was not as though they were gonna be hunted or--
- Well, they thought that there wasn't enough
nice animals in New Zealand.
- And in fact, I've heard that a lot, yeah, famously.
- Yeah, well, they were like, you know, there's not--
- There's no endemic mammals to New Zealand,
apart from a bat, so any mammals weren't really there.
- They got there, and they're like, "Where's the rabbits?"
- Yeah. - You know,
"Where's the tweeting birds?"
We don't know where they are.
- But I feel like it's such a bird-heavy place,
or certainly would have been in the 19th century,
as in, why would you introduce more birds, you know?
- Yeah, they're like, maybe some that can fly
would be useful. - Yeah, exactly.
Like the cacophore, that's a New Zealand one as well.
- Yeah, but a lot of them kind of hide
in the middle of the night. - Yeah, yeah.
- Even the kiwi bird, I don't think I've ever seen one.
- Really? - You go to the zoo,
and they say they're in there, but I don't reckon they are.
I think it's just they've put a red light
in a cave-looking area, and they go, "There's kiwi in there."
(all laugh)
- Tasmanian devils, I've gone every year
to see a Tasmanian devil at Taronga Zoo in Sydney,
and you never see one.
- You never see them spinning around like a tornado.
- Yeah, no, no, no, no.
- You do hear a little bit of that in the background, but yeah.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the sport of netball
was invented because its creator thought basketball
made women grow better and lose control.
- Wow, as a player of both sports,
I will say this is true.
(laughs)
I play social netball, you know,
and it's always very wholesome.
The slogan of netball is just, "Here if you need,"
it's so beautiful.
That's just what you say a lot, you know,
when you pass the ball, you go, "Here if you need,"
like, you know, like, "Pass them on me,"
you say, "Here if you need," like, "I'm over here."
It's very wholesome, but then I play basketball
and I become a feral beast.
(all laugh)
- It's so interesting.
- So what's the key difference that causes that?
- I don't know if this is--
- Well, basketball is technically no contact.
- But you're trying to take the ball off someone
and you can run beside them.
So basics of netball is once you catch the ball,
you can't move.
If you're taking a shot, no one can defend you.
- They can, with three feet away.
- From three feet away, which is, I would argue,
too many feet.
(all laugh)
- And you can't dribble along the court.
- You can't dribble, okay, okay, okay, okay.
- So anyway, this all comes from a woman called Clara Bear
who was working at Newcombe College in New Orleans,
and she'd been asked to come up with a new sport
for women to play because this was an old women's school.
And she decided, she came up with a few ideas,
but her main one was to adapt sports
of being played by men.
So basketball had just become really popular,
been invented by James Naismith a few years earlier.
And so she wrote to him and asked for the rules.
She got the rules and said, right,
we're gonna play basketball.
But anyone who was there said it was a mad game
in which the women grew bitter and lost control.
Even she herself said it was not entirely satisfactory.
And so she thought, well, I'm gonna have to invent
a new game which doesn't have all this stuff
because this is just not appropriate to women.
And so she came up with that ball.
- Interesting.
You say that netball is a non-contact sport,
but I don't think it actually is
because non-contact would be something like tennis
where you genuinely don't touch anyone else.
But netball, there are certain rules.
So if I was to run into the space to get the ball
and someone else is running in
and I shoulder barge them on the way,
that is really one of the rules of the game.
Like there is, the art of learning to play netball
is to learn how to be very aggressive
within the confines of the rules.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, okay.
Yeah, we used to play it at school.
And I went to a city.
Yeah, I went to a Steiner school.
So I think that was more,
feels like a made up Steiner sport, really.
Steiner's a very hippie non-competitive kind of thing.
And it feels like instead of basketball,
let's do netball instead.
- So can I check a few more rules?
- Yeah.
- So Mel, is there still no shouting
or talking during the game?
Is that still observed?
- Interesting.
Where is that from?
Is that from the most recent rule?
- That was from Clara Bear's founding rules
right off the game.
- You can't talk back to the umpire,
so you couldn't say, "Oh, what was that?"
- In the first rules for sure,
if you spoke, if you said anything in the game,
it was a foul.
- Oh, wow!
- Even here if you need.
- Yeah, you won't have to say that.
- I read no falling over was also a rid, which I can't.
- Don't struggle to compute.
- That seems a bit harsh, doesn't it?
- Yeah, it does.
- It's a weird rule that there's sort of a hangover there.
If you catch the ball and you fall over,
you're not allowed to move with the ball,
but if you are on the ground,
you can't throw the ball from the ground.
- What?
- So you have to make your way back up to standing
before you can throw the ball.
But you have to keep your feet planted.
So where your feet landed when you fell over,
you have to just weirdly stand up.
- Do you look like one of those inflatable car selling
balloon guns?
- You just have to rise up, yeah.
- That's great, that's brilliant.
- That's a good rule, I like that.
- She also said no needlessly rough play was in her rules.
And all shots had to be taken with one hand.
Because there was a thought that by throwing it
with two hands, it was unladylike
and might somehow make women less feminine was the idea.
- I read there would be inclination of the shoulders forward
with consequent flattening of the chest.
- Precisely, yeah.
- And that would not be a graceful position for girls.
- That's what they said.
But it's interesting because the one-handed throw
was in netball from the very start,
they had one-handed throw.
But in basketball, there was none of it
until about the 1930s.
It was all two-handed throwing into the baskets.
- As a rule, was it?
- No, it's just that was the way.
- That was the way they did it, yeah.
- Yeah, I love as well that she basically,
she originally was starting basketball
as a female version of it.
And she called it basketball.
She just changed it to QUE.
- Well, I think what happened there is,
she wrote to Naismith who came up with the original thing.
And she said, here's my new sport, what do you think?
It's women's basketball.
And he wrote back saying, well,
it's not really the same as basketball.
So you should change the name a little bit.
And she said, okay, I'll change it to basketball.
- And then part of the rules were developed
because she just misunderstood what he'd sent back.
There were dots all over it.
And she took that to mean seven different zones.
So you would be stuck in your zone.
And that got applied to the initial rules.
- We should not still change.
- Yeah, yeah, a goalkeeper is still in one-third of the court.
A center can go in most of the court, but not the two.
It's very complicated.
- It's not very sociable, is it?
Like if, yeah, there's some people who never really see it.
- Exactly.
Like I will chat to a goal shooter as a goalkeeper a lot,
but I will never see my team's goal shooter.
I just go, oh, well done.
(all laughing)
- But it's safe and the women look very womenly as a result.
- What a relief.
- The vision has remained from Clara Bear.
- Do you play volleyball as well, Mel?
- I don't.
I just play netball and basketball, yeah.
- 'Cause apparently volleyball may have been nicked
basically a month after the first game of Newcombe ball,
which was another, Clara Bear invented Newcombe ball,
but you throw the ball into the other team's area
so it hits the floor.
- Yes.
- Without them being able to catch it.
One month after that first game was written up,
William Morgan, the YMCA director in the USA,
he invented volleyball.
And it was basically apparently for older businessmen
on their lunch hour, was how it was described.
Which I think it has not stayed true to
over the years, volleyball.
- You know beach volleyball?
- Yeah.
- There's an official rule that you're only allowed
to wear one watch.
- Oh, really?
- It's in the actual rules.
It says only one watch allowed.
- What possible advantage do you gain from two watches?
- What do you think?
- How interesting.
- Do you know what time it is in another part of the club?
(all laughing)
- Do you know the answer?
- I think I do, yeah.
- Okay, so what advantage would you have?
- I mean, you'd never get a point.
- I have a punt.
Is it that people were doing sponsorship deals
with multiple watch companies?
- I can't believe that today.
- Interesting.
- Oh, that's great.
- 'Cause there's actually some rules
about how many temporary tattoos you're allowed
because people use those for appetizers.
- No.
- Obviously, don't have--
- Small real estate.
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- It's so funny, isn't it?
- Because netball is so big in New Zealand and Australia.
I wasn't sure how much you guys knew about the sport.
I know you play in England.
You've got a very popular team.
But I was like, oh, I wonder what some unknown facts
about netball.
So of course, I looked it up and I found an article titled
"Fascinating Facts About Netball That You Never Knew."
Number one was, "How long is a netball game?"
(all laughing)
- Okay, well, let's try.
Does anyone here know how long it is?
- Actually, I do not know.
I would guess it's 80 minutes.
- Oh, I think it's less.
I've watched games, but I can't remember how long they were.
I reckon maybe 60 minutes and quarters.
- Yeah, that's what I'm thinking.
I'm trying to work out, is it quarters as well?
And so I'm gonna say 60,
'cause I heard you just say yes.
(all laughing)
- Yes, I acknowledge your answer and it's incorrect.
No, no, it is actually.
It's for 15 minute quarters.
- Fascinating fact.
- Yes, fascinating fact.
- Number two, "What is netball?"
(all laughing)
I think it's a real entry-level article,
that I had come across.
- I love the way that the first thing you need to learn
is how long it is.
And then the second one is, "What is it?"
It's like, "Do you wanna play netball?"
Well, how long will it be?
(all laughing)
- 60 minutes.
It's got two watches on.
(all laughing)
- You're right.
So I grew up in Oz for my teenage years.
Netball was massive there,
and I assumed it was globally massive.
It's an American invention, but in America,
it's not really played.
It's getting back now,
and particularly Aussies and New Zealanders
keep going over to schools to try and reintegrate it.
So Ross Day is someone who went over to try and get it done.
And she said, "What are the biggest challenges?"
I can't believe this is true.
Must be target cheek.
She says, "One of the biggest challenges
"is that when we're pitching netball,
"is that because of our accents being Aussie and New Zealand,
"everyone thinks we're saying nipple."
- Yes, I get this, I will say something about nipple,
and I'll be like, "Oh, that was a great netball play."
And it has a whole different meaning.
And the comments, people are like,
"What are you talking about?"
- Wow, so someone will come up to you and say,
"Do you want a better nipple play?"
And you go, "How long will it be?"
(all laughing)
- Wait, quick double check.
It is what you think it is.
What is nipple?
(all laughing)
- That's so funny.
- I like the early forms of basketball
were interesting as well.
I like how they first started with a peach basket,
but they didn't think to put a hole in the bottom.
So, in the early games, they would have to stop the game
to go retrieve the ball from the basket
and climb up a ladder.
- I suppose, in a way, if you have a hole,
it's not always certain if the ball's gone in.
- Yeah, that is true.
- Is that producing netball?
- Sometimes, if I shoot in it,
'cause you go for the swish sound,
but sometimes you could just shoot so far
that it just hits the net and makes that sound anyway.
And you go, "Oh, okay, I know."
(all laughing)
- In football, in soccer, there's been this thing
where you have a board next to the goal.
I think it was in Queen's Park Rangers,
and they scored a goal, and it hit the board,
and then bounced straight back out again,
and the goal didn't get given, because, yeah.
- I don't understand how that,
so it hit the board next to the--
- So, it's gone into the net?
- Yeah, sorry, I didn't explain that very well.
So, you've got the goal, the goal post,
and you've got the net,
but then you've got an advertising board
right behind the goal.
And so, the ball goes in, hits the advertising board,
bounces straight back out again,
and the referee goes, "Well, I didn't see it go in."
- Oh!
- And it happened quite recently
where there was a hole in the net,
as in one that wasn't supposed to be there,
a bigger than the normal hole.
(all laughing)
And the ball went in, and it went through the hole,
and no one could tell whether it had gone in or not.
That's good.
- That's a good thing for a goalie to do
when the action's happening up the other end.
(all laughing)
It's like somebody's saw through the net,
and then you'll be behind the saw.
(all laughing)
- Like Wiley Clay.
- Did you, when you were sort of part
of the New Zealand netball scene,
did you, do you know anyone who played for the Master Baiters?
(all laughing)
Do you remember this?
- No.
- Okay. - I mean--
- It was just a cheeky little fun New Zealand thing,
but there was a Sydney World Masters games
where all netball teams were coming,
and there was a lot of New Zealand teams
that were coming over,
and they named themselves the Master Baiters,
and-- - Why?
- Well, it was a Masters,
and they were baiting, so with the Master Baiters.
- Yeah, the second baiting?
- Yeah, that was it. - What were they baiting?
- Baiting the other teams.
- Oh, I see. - Okay.
- I didn't come up with it.
(all laughing)
- I like how the sport of netball's evolved quite a lot.
There's different versions of this fast five,
which is basically, they've made it more like basketball.
There's five people on the court,
and there's, you can shoot three-point,
or two-pointers and things.
The Northern Mystics used a new move
called the Harrison Hoist,
because you have to be three feet away,
and so they had been practicing like a cheerleader lift,
and so she'd lifted her up,
and she was able to bat the ball over there
as it was going into the hoop. - Is that allowed?
- And yeah, it's allowed.
It was in the rules of the game,
and they were going to go,
"Oh, we'll save this for the finals,"
but then they were like,
"Okay, we might not get a final,"
so they had to do it in like a qualifying match.
It's one of those things that they don't do all the time now,
because in theory, if you knew it was coming,
you could kind of counter it,
'cause you could only have two defenders in the circle,
so they had to use all of their resources,
but if you didn't see it coming,
you were like, "Ah, just a shot,"
and then suddenly she's in the sky.
- So it's like a rugby throw-in, basically.
- Yeah, like a line-out. - The way that, yeah,
they lifted into the air.
- You're not allowed to do that in football, by the way.
- Yeah, wow. - It's in the rules,
officially in the rules.
- Isn't it? - Yeah.
- Piggybacks. - If you--
- Fogging like a true athlete.
(all laughing)
- It's in the air, and you wanna head the ball in,
and you think, "Well, I'm gonna give my mate a piggyback."
It's not allowed, it's un-gentlemanly conduct,
it's called, it's an indirect free kick to the other team,
and both players should be cautioned.
- Get out. - Get out.
- Wow. - That's unfair.
I think you've got the weather ball
to put together a piggyback in that time,
and you should be allowed to do it.
- That was in my, 'cause I trained as a football referee,
and that was one of the questions that came up,
it's like, "What do you do in this situation?"
- Wow. - You give him a stern finger.
(all laughing)
- I really wanna watch Andy's version of football, though.
It's a corner kick, he's gone for the piggyback,
it's gone in, oh no, someone sawed through the back of that,
and it has gone right through, no points.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is Andy.
My fact is that when the asteroid
which wiped out the dinosaurs hit,
there was a brief burst of radiation so strong
it would have immediately cooked some dinosaurs through.
- Whoa, like an air fryer.
- Yes, exactly, like an air fryer.
- This is, it's much less fun
than I've made it sound for the dinosaurs,
but what a, you know, for a brief--
- For like, the mammals survived, did they?
So could they have come out and eaten some dinosaur cooked?
- Yes, yes, they probably could, yeah.
- But you say for a brief moment,
so it was perfectly cooked and then they were charred
beyond oblivion, is that it?
'Cause you could say, oh here is my roast for a brief moment.
It was amazing, but it is a pile of ash now.
- Yeah, no, you're right, you're absolutely right.
I think a lot of, there weren't precise settings on.
This is from a fantastic book I've just read.
It's called Not the End of the World by Hannah Ritchie,
and it's about completely different stuff actually,
it's about sustainability and the big planetary challenges,
but she's writing in this bit about, you know,
extinction events and how fascinating
some of those have been over the past,
and this is about the dinosaurs,
65 million years ago, '66?
- '66.
- A while ago, and the asteroid hits.
- It was an old book that you read, wasn't it?
- Yeah, that's right.
(all laughing)
- Thing hits, there's a shockwave
that moves 17,000 miles an hour.
It's quite hard to get your head around some of this stuff.
And then this huge amount, like cubic miles of rock
get lifted up by the impact.
They then, so they've been liquidized
into these little glass balls,
which go all the way around the planet immediately,
and then that falls.
- It literally, the kind of sky falls down, you know.
- Yeah, rain's glass.
- Yeah, liquid rock, basically.
And lots of it gets blasted by friction in the atmosphere
'cause it's coming back into the atmosphere, if you see.
- Right.
- So then the energy is released as infrared radiation,
which turns into this massive blast of heat.
- Thank you.
- And if you were a dinosaur out in the open,
it's bad news, and it's really interesting
'cause why didn't everything burn immediately at that point?
And basically, there was a study in 2016
by a scientist called Sean Gulick,
who found out that either it was like being in a toaster
for a few hours, or a pizza oven for a few minutes.
It's bad news if you were out in the open.
- Okay, wow.
- So would there be some dinosaurs
who were the furthest away that would be nicely cooked?
- Yeah.
(all laughing)
- Medium round. - Just medium round, yes.
- So they get cooked by the radiation,
the innards are just completely just, they're cooked,
but so they die immediately,
or is it kind of like radiation where--
- If you were out in the open,
there's a very good chance you would have died at that point
'cause it's such a blast of searing heat
for such a, for a relatively long time.
Longer than you'd be comfortable with.
- It's not just like a sauna.
- No, it's just--
(all laughing)
- For a brief moment in time,
the muscles were very relaxed.
(all laughing)
- It is nuts reading about it.
- Yeah.
- I mean, it was pretty striking.
- It was a big old rock, wasn't it?
- A big old rock.
I found one weird thing, this slide.
Right, so I think we've said before,
it was the size of Mount Everest, the rock there.
And it was traveling 20 times the speed of a bullet.
It was really, really huge.
- Big and fast.
And it was so big and fast that when it arrived,
it was pushing the atmosphere in front of it so rapidly
that the crater from the impact started to form
before it hit.
- Oh yeah.
- It just pushed the surface of the earth down.
- Oh my God, it's amazing, that, isn't it?
- Yeah, it's insane.
I became friends recently with the dinosaur hunter,
who, well, she's a paleontologist,
who's the person who has verified
that the asteroid landed in spring.
I think you guys met her very briefly in Belgium.
- Oh yeah.
- When we were at Nerdland, at the festival.
It was all to do with the specific fish
that as it was being carried in the tsunamis,
which was not just water, it was also earth,
like an earth tsunami.
The glass that had come down went into,
through the filters of the fish,
like went through the mouth and were inside.
So when they found the fossilized versions of these fish,
they found the glass.
And these specific fish are the type of fish
that have growths in their body that change per season.
- Oh, that's so handy.
- So during spring, yeah.
So during spring, they grow these extra little things.
So they spotted that and they went,
well, that could only happen in spring.
Therefore, in spring on the side of the planet that it's on,
that's where that happened.
- That is amazing.
- Really nuts.
- It is nuts.
- That's hot.
You know, you're gonna deal with an asteroid
and hay fever at the same time.
(all laughing)
I was looking at extinct meat,
'cause a cultivated meat company in Australia
made a mammoth meatball last year.
- Oh, yes, I heard about this, yeah.
- Using a DNA sequence from the mammoth myoglobin,
which is the protein that gives the meat its flavor,
and filled in a few gaps using elephant DNA,
and then they made this meatball.
They did not eat the meatball.
- Really?
- They just put it on display to be like,
this is a mammoth meatball.
I don't know, I think they were just,
they were like, we haven't really tested this,
whether this is safe for human consumption.
- Oh, really?
- So we'll just make the meatball,
I guess, probably to get a bit of press.
- Is it the size of a normal meatball?
'Cause you think if it was a mammoth meatball,
you would deliberately make it much bigger,
wouldn't you?
- Yeah, exactly.
- I didn't get, it wasn't next to like a can of Coke,
so I'm not sure.
(laughing)
- But it loves regular meatball science.
- Maybe you wouldn't, 'cause then it would just confuse
the purchaser or the person looking at it,
go, oh, I get it, it's mammoth, it's big.
It's like, we're just not even considering
the extraordinary science that has got into this.
- I would have eaten that.
- You wouldn't?
- Without knowing the health implications.
- It's interesting.
- Okay, but I feel like they've grown it.
No animals have been harmed.
- Yeah.
- So I'm a veggie, but I would love to.
- Yes, I think the same thing,
'cause my boyfriend's vegetarian and he says
that if we reached the point where we could just have
cultivated meat made from the actual cells,
then he'd go, oh, it's fine, I'll eat that.
And I think it's come a long way in the last few years.
I think the first patty they made,
like a mince patty, a salad just with mince patties,
was I think $300,000, so quite an expensive burger.
But it's come down now where they think
that they could, you know, release these things.
- To like 200,000.
- Yeah.
- Release them into supermarkets, so it's rapidly.
- I experimented quite a lot with those.
I tried some salmon the other day,
which I have to say was not there.
- Oh yeah, it's like the fake salmon.
- I'm saying it's not to do.
- It's not the like made from actual.
- I'm sorry, yeah, that's fine.
- I think they just keep adding salt
until it has some kind of flavor that explains.
- I had a vegan Domino's pepperoni pizza
a couple of nights ago, that's not an ad.
And I could not taste the difference.
- Really?
- Genuinely could not taste the difference.
- I will just say for the listeners at home,
he does have a Domino's tetu or something.
(all laughing)
- He's trying to show off.
- He's wearing two watches,
one of which seems to be a Domino's pizza.
- Yeah, what's that?
Oh, pizza time.
(all laughing)
- Can I ask, did it have cheese on it?
- It did, well, no, but it had vegan cheese.
- It has vegan cheese on it.
- Yeah, yeah.
- It's a vegan pizza, yeah.
- They used to have a vegan pizzerics,
but seeing as we're talking about pizzas now,
they used to have a vegan pizzerics best
down the road from here,
which only sold vegan pizzas.
And it was the most disgusting thing though.
- The cheese, like they just couldn't do good vegan cheese.
Maybe they can now.
- It's all about the mouthfeel.
- That's the, and the stretch.
- That's your tinder bio.
(all laughing)
- The mouthfeeling, the stretch.
- I found an essay in a scientific journal
called Evolution, Education and Outreach,
and it asked, which items a Jewish time traveler
would be able to eat because they were kosher or not?
- Yeah, okay.
- Can you guess the headline of this article?
- 50 points to anyone who does, is gettable.
- Oh, is it a pun?
Back to the juicer.
- The juicer, that's not that.
So it's about the food.
It's about the food that you might be eating.
- Is it to do with time travel?
- It's to do with a very famous
dinosaur-based franchise.
(all laughing)
- Jurassic pork.
(all exclaiming)
- Beautiful.
- Jurassic pork.
- And it was, that's a good headline.
- Yeah, that's good.
- And it was about what basically a Jewish time traveler
who wanted to eat contemporaneous food
would be allowed to eat.
And basically very few dinosaurs are kosher,
it turns out.
- Oh, wow.
- Some of them are birds.
But even the bird ones lack the sort of toe
that you have to, if you're allowed to eat
particular meats that are kosher,
it's 'cause they're like chicken.
They've got a particular opposable toe, I think.
- Right.
- Mice are not allowed.
That's probably not relevant now.
- So sorry, Jew-rasic pork.
- They actually just went with Jurassic.
- They just went with Jurassic?
- Yeah.
- What, Jew-rasic pork?
- I think they were correct in that.
I think Jurassic pork is...
- It's sitting there.
- Yeah, I guess so.
- It's like a complaints letter.
(laughing)
- We said earlier, 65, 66 million years ago
with the extinction of the dinosaurs.
- Sure.
- But do you know how long ago that is in a galactic year?
- Ooh.
- I'd never heard of a galactic year before.
- There must be something to do with the traveling
through the galaxy.
- Yeah, so how long it takes the galaxy to go on once?
- Exactly.
- I think it's three years ago in galaxy years.
- Galactic year is 225 million years, roughly.
- Sort of 10.
- Yeah.
- Incorrect.
- Really?
- So the dinosaurs were here 3.5 months ago.
- Oh wow.
- In a galactic year.
- The dinosaurs were on Earth,
but if you had a time machine,
like, you know what does Doctor Who have?
It's like a TARDIS, yeah.
You go into the TARDIS
and you come back exactly in the same position in space,
but different time, the Earth won't be here anymore.
- Yeah, we'll be further in space.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, so you have to-
- And if Doctor Who was going through-
(laughing)
- Sorry, I was just trying to appeal.
- Oh my goodness.
- Yeah.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that in the 1980s,
you could download video games over the radio.
- Okay.
- What?
- Yeah.
- To a certain generation, that's gonna be like,
there used to be a thing called MySpace.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Have you heard of DVDs?
- I was alive in the 1980s and I never heard that.
- Yeah, no, I didn't think of this either.
This was the very early days of computers
whereby hard drives were incredibly expensive.
So they used to have an audio cassette,
like you would in a stereo.
You could put a cassette in
and that's where you would keep all the data
of programs that you were loading up.
So someone made the connection that actually,
if you're able to record onto a cassette,
you should be able to transfer
multiple different kinds of data over the radio.
And why not video games?
So what people used to do is they used to tune in
to radio shows that basically just played data over the waves.
You'd put your cassette in and you would press record
and then you take it out, put it in your computer
and there's your video game.
- So these were dedicated radio stations
and wasn't like, that was talking here.
(laughing)
- It was now time for Tetris.
So what did the audio sound like?
- Well, for people probably older than you,
but younger than me, it would sound like,
you know, when you had dial-up internet
and a fax came through on a phone line,
it's just like...
Yeah, it's exactly that.
- And the computer just takes that
and if it's a high sound, it's a one
and if it's a low sound, it's a zero
and it just turns it into zeros and ones
and makes games out of it.
- Yeah, and to be fair, that could be confused
as a very popular type of...
- Yes, exactly.
- Techno.
(laughing)
Yeah, so this was done for ages
and then suddenly, obviously modern technology
and prices, you know, the equivalent
of the Mammoth Berger coming down from 300,000,
they suddenly were able to afford to have hard drives
and computers and so it slowly got wiped out.
But yeah, that was the thing that happened.
It's bizarre to think that you could take a video game,
Grand Theft Auto, by just listening to the radio
and recording it.
I'm not used to the idea that data could be transmitted
in ways that we can hear and understand.
- It's so strong, yes, yeah.
- And obviously data could be transmitted
in ways we can hear and understand
'cause I'm talking to you all as I understand.
But yeah, yeah, and there was weird things
that were done using this kind of novelty, I guess it was,
Radio West, do you ever hear of Radio West?
I think it's BBC and they just called it Radio West.
So it's sort of you get your local BBC in an area.
There used to be a host who was called,
ooh, what was he called?
Sorry, hang on a sec.
There used to be a host called Joe Tozzer,
who used to work for--
(laughing)
- How did you forget that name?
- And then at number six this week,
Joe Tozzer and the master-paters.
(laughing)
- So funny.
- Sorry, Joe, if you're listening.
But also, how was school?
Was that, that was a rough one.
- How do you spell it?
- It could be Tozzer.
- Tozzer, yeah.
- I'm sure he says Tozzer.
- I was in "Fade Tozzer" from Steps.
- Okay.
- We're a piece of good together,
it was definitely a different name for that.
- Tozzer.
- Yeah, he are.
- Oh yeah, Tozzer.
- You said he went with Tozzer.
(laughing)
- Sorry, Joe.
- But yeah, so he once broadcast the data sounds
of what ended up being a pixel image
of one of Charlie's Angels Angels.
So the star Sheryl Land.
So you recorded it down, put it into your computer
and slowly it pixelated together,
40 by 80 pixels of the star.
- 40 by 80.
- It's actually resolution, it is.
- Is that a boob or a head?
(laughing)
- And of course you could do it with vinyl as well.
And there was some computer game magazines
that would put little vinyls
on front of the magazine.
And it would just play this noise
which your computer then would recognize as zeros and ones
and would turn into a game.
It's all 'cause you didn't have enough memory
on your computer.
- It's exactly that, yeah.
- So your memory had to be on your cassette.
- Yeah.
- What are the limitations of it now?
So in theory, could we do it for a more complex game
than Tetris or Pong or--
- You could for sure, I reckon.
But the problem is,
'cause I used to have one of these computers
with the cassettes on,
it would take about 30 minutes
to load any game onto your computer.
And they were all really shit games.
They were fun, but the graphics were terrible and whatever.
And often you would get to the end of the 30 minutes
and one of its zeros or ones would have been read wrong
and the whole thing would be knackered.
You'd have to start again.
And so if you wanted to put like Grand Theft Auto
on today, you'd probably have to make it play
for about 40 years.
- Yeah, okay, all right.
- That would be great to know
'cause the game is so massive.
You're a gamer, aren't you?
- I'm a little bit of a gamer, yes.
Can we get Baldur's Gate 3 in audio form?
- They did end up releasing very specific audio blank cassettes
that you could get called basic code.
So it would guarantee compatibility with your computer
as opposed to I imagine there were a few audio cassettes
out there that didn't quite do it.
And so, yeah, you would tune into either like DataRama
or HobbyScoop, which were specific radio stations
that-- - That's amazing.
- But you can just put on Radio 4
and listen to the shipping forecast
and make that into your own game.
I find, you know.
- We used to do this as kids, actually.
And we would have to guess whether it was rising slowly
or, you know, I don't know if it's the pressure
or something, they go, "Dogger 75, rising slowly."
We had to guess what it was gonna be.
- That's good.
Who's the host of the shipping forecast?
- I don't think it's got a host per se.
- Well, the person who reads--
- I don't know.
- I can't remember.
I think it's been the same person for about 40 years.
- She's very famous.
Yeah, she's married, I think, to Claire Bolding.
She, I was on a show with her once
and I was asked, "Do you wanna have any questions for her
"about the shipping forecast?"
I didn't know what to ask 'cause I'd never heard it.
So I said, "What's your favorite ship?"
(laughing)
That's a good question.
- It's a good question.
Did she have an answer?
- No, she was like, "You haven't heard my show, have you?"
I said, "No, I haven't, food."
- And she said, "What's your favorite fish?"
- Yeah.
- Did you hear of the game Great Britain Limited?
I was looking at some early spectrum games.
- No.
- In Great Britain Limited,
it was a government simulation
where you managed the British economy and--
- I love it.
- Wow.
- There's no way to win.
- It was very--
- Did they give Lys Trassa a go there?
(laughing)
- This was easy.
- Yeah, you would like change little things
and then the inflation would go up
or the unemployment would go down or vice versa.
And then every five years you would have an election
and depending on how well you've done,
it would say you've been kicked out
or you've got another five years.
- Wow, that is so funny.
That's really good.
What was that?
- '80s, yeah, early '80s.
- Wow, and it was government-made?
- No, it was just--
- Oh, okay.
- A lot of these games in the '80s,
they were just made by kids in the bedrooms.
- Yeah, which was mad.
I went over to the home of a rider friend of my other friends
and she was like, "I want you to meet him.
"He's really cool."
We went over and he just pulled out a whole archive
of cassettes of games he invented.
- Wow.
- Yeah, and that was the first time I ever learned
that games could be put on an audio cassette.
- It was a good time for creativity,
but just in a very shitty medium.
(laughing)
- Much like the podcast.
Do you have any really weird games, Mel?
- Do I have any weird games at one point?
'Cause I have quite an addictive personality
when it comes to games.
There is a very stupid game on Steam called Cookie Clicker.
And it's literally a cookie and you just click it
and you get another cookie.
But then you keep clicking and then you can buy
like a cafe that makes cookies.
So you just, it's basic.
I feel like it feeds the endorphins in your brain
because you just like keep clicking
and then you can buy like an automatic clicker
with the cookies and then it will automatically
click it for you.
And then you can buy a factory of cookies.
And you keep, and it's-
- But you have to keep clicking.
- But you could leave it for like an hour
because you've run an automated system.
And then you come back and you're like,
I've got four billion cookies.
And it just feeds the endorphins in your brain
because you're like, I'm doing,
I'm getting better at this game.
- Do you say it's on Steam?
- It's on Steam, a lot of that.
- What is Steam?
- Steam is just-
- Oh, that's so embarrassing.
But just for the other people who don't know what it is.
- It's for those idiots listening at home.
- No, just kidding. Steam is just a game library, essentially.
So it's, if you're on a PC, you can download games
and almost all games, unless they're like console exclusive
will be on Steam that you can download.
- And a console?
(laughing)
- Are you taking you guys out gamers?
- I've actually lost Steam.
- You have got Steam.
- Do you?
- What games do you play?
- Don't play many games on it.
- No, really?
- I play Fortnite, all right?
I play Fortnite against eight year olds
around the world, I'm a lose.
- I tried Fortnite and I was just too embarrassed
to continue, 'cause the skill cap of that game is so high
and these 14 year olds that have been playing
since they were nine are just so good
that you couldn't possibly just start a game now
and be anywhere near as good as them.
So it's just, you know?
- If I put myself in the mind of a 14 year old
playing this game, would it be immediately obvious
which one Andy was?
- Oh yeah, yeah, I think so.
- I'm the guy hiding in one of the buildings,
just trying to have a nice afternoon.
There's a cookie, I'm trying to click on that.
- Yeah.
- He's soaring out the bed from a minute.
(laughing)
- Trying to escape.
- Here's a fact about the guy who invented
video games, arguably, and it's sent in by,
listen to this, it's sent in by Grant Wyn Jones,
who's sent in the fact that nuclear bombs
and video games were created by the same guy.
- Yeah, that's actually a deleted scene from
Oppenheimer. - Oppenheimer.
(laughing)
- Well, it's not Oppenheimer,
but it's a guy called William Higginbotham,
great name, who did invent the first screen-based
video game, it was called Tennis for Two,
and it was in 1958.
- Sounds like Pong, right?
- It's pretty Pong-y, it's like 2D tennis.
There was nothing to play it on,
so you had to play it on an oscilloscope,
which is a device to measure voltage waves,
and that, because there were no consoles,
no screens, no, nothing.
And he also worked on the Manhattan Project,
and he was in charge of the team
which made the electronic triggers
for the first nuclear bombs.
So, that's the fact, it stacks up.
- That's great. - And he played
the accordion as well.
And his daughter wrote a memoir about him
called Accordion to Willy, which is...
(laughing)
- While we're talking about sort of like
the founding figures of video gaming,
one person who's known as the father
of the video games industry,
and I believe this is the person who kind of took it away
from PC and said, the television,
why are we not getting it on the television,
was an engineer and inventor,
and his name was Ralph Baer.
- Oh, spelled the same as Clara.
- Yes, and a translation that they are...
No, they're not, I couldn't find any relation.
I was so excited when I saw the connection, name, but no.
- That's so funny. - Nothing, yeah.
- Last game that I played to any regularity
was Mario Kart, N64. - Oh yeah.
- And there's a really nice economic theory
that the world should be like Mario Kart.
- Okay, they're all like,
I can kind of see what you mean.
- Oh really? - Yeah.
If you're in the front in a game of Mario Kart,
your power-ups are less powerful.
So if you're first, you will get like,
maybe a banana peel to throw behind you, which, yeah.
But then if you're last, you will get a power-up
that's like turns you on a torpedo.
- A giant bullet guy, yeah. - Yeah, a giant bullet guy
that can go to the top, or the blue shell,
which automatically wipes out the person in first.
So I guess in the sense that it kind of
evens things out in society a little more.
- Exactly, it's like Reverse Iron Rand, basically.
And it's known as rubberbanding.
And the idea is that anyone at the back of society
gets a huge boost, and it helps everyone in society,
especially as those people at the bottom
tend to be like farmers or people who are helping
at the base of everything.
And apparently that would be a great way of doing it,
apart from good luck finding anyone to vote for it.
(all laughing)
- That's really interesting.
- That's a lovely idea. - I like that theory, yeah.
- In 2004, someone made a device that is a Game Boy,
and the Game Boy is also attached to kind of a thing
that goes over your mouth, which gives you nitrous oxide
and basically makes you pass out.
And this was for children. - What was the function of?
- To stop them playing?
- No, no, not to stop them playing.
- But as in you have enough nitrous oxide,
you do well enough at the game, you pass out,
you stop playing the Game Boy?
- No, it's not that.
Any other thoughts why you might do this?
It's for children.
- It's for children. - For children to pass out.
- So if they're going into surgery and they need to--
- Oh! - Oh my gosh!
- Got it in one damn, yeah.
So the idea is it's hard to give kids anesthesia
and keep them calm while you're doing it.
If you give them a Game Boy to play,
then they're distracted and they get the anesthesia.
And it was designed, but never--
- Never used. - Never used.
- Well, it's unfair on children who are not good at video,
like I'm not very good at video games.
So I would still be on lying there.
- Now it's later, the surgeon's ready to go home.
I might as well--
- It's just the tutorial, come on!
(laughing)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @Streiberland, Andy.
- At Andrew Hunter M.
- James. - At James Harkin.
- And Mel. - At Melanie Bracewell.
- Nice, or you can get to our group account on Twitter
by going to @NoSuchThing,
or you can email us at podcast@qi.com.
And if you wanna just hear all of the episodes
and find out about our secret membership club,
which is called Clubbish,
you can go to NoSuchThingAsAfish.com
and you can find all of our previous episodes there,
as well as the Doors to the Secret Members Club.
Mel, you're on tour right now in the UK.
- Yes, touring around the UK.
And then I'll be touring Australia,
and then I'm coming back for Edinburgh in August.
- Amazing. - So, I'm hopping around.
- So, have we found dates?
- Melaniebracewell.com/gigs, I think.
- Yes.
- Okay, that's it.
We'll be back again next week,
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)