[Music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski,
and once again we have gathered around the microphones with our four favourite facts
from the last seven days and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one and that is Anna.
My fact this week is that for at least 80 years,
the same thundercloud has been raining off the north coast of Australia.
It's called Hector the Convector.
Brilliant.
Or he's called Hector the Convector.
Is it actually he?
He's called Hector.
Yeah. Oh, clouds don't have.
A lot of the press does give him a...
Please, let's not get into pronouns for clouds.
She's called Hector, it's fine.
He's called Hector, like it must be a he, right?
Fair enough, it's a joke actually.
He should be called Cumulo Nimbus the Cumulo Nimbus.
Is it really a convector, a cloud?
I don't really know what convector means.
It does work by convection, yeah, as sort of, I mean all clouds do, but there's all...
Culeo Nimbus, Culeo Nimbus.
Yeah, you said Culeo Nimbus the Cumulo Nimbus.
No, he didn't. You made that joke up into your own head.
That's good.
Yeah, better than what Andy said, which is just the name of the type of cloud.
I set him up, you tougher man.
Andy's correct, he is a Cumulo Nimbus,
but he does also form through the power of convection,
which, you know, is as hot air currents go up.
We know how clouds form, right?
Yeah.
He...
Bagley.
If you don't know, ask your 12-year-old niece, nephew, daughter, son.
We'll probably go into it in more depth.
So, get excited about that.
But yeah, he builds up over the Tiwi Islands, Tiwi, which are...
It's a really cute word.
It is a cute word.
It's north of Darwin, right?
It's a little island off Australia.
Yes, and it's at three in the afternoon every single day from September to April,
which is before the rainy season, and then during the rainy season, he appears.
You can set your watch by it.
So, here's my question, right?
You know the, like, the never-ending super, whatever it's called,
the immortal soup, where it's just always been the same soup, and they just keep it.
So, you eat the soup, and then there's a little bit left,
and then they add more water and more vegetables and stuff.
So, the sum of it is...
There's some of it always in.
This cloud does disappear.
Hector does go away.
He's only there for the months that you just said, right?
September 3rd to April.
So, how can you say that it's the same Hector?
Well, Dan, not a single cell in your body, of course,
is the same as the cells in your body you were born with.
So, how can we say it's the same Dan?
That's true.
But it is the same.
And also, Dan disappears for six months every year, doesn't he?
It's incredibly annoying for our recording channel.
I guess it's formed by the same forces every day.
Yeah, I was looking for named clouds, and there are so few.
Oh, yeah, that is surprising, isn't it?
I think considering the things that just transiently appear
and then disappear in a matter of minutes.
I just thought there must be a shortlist on Wikipedia
of celebrity clouds.
The one I can think of is the Tablecloth or the Table Mountain.
Oh, that's good.
I didn't know about that.
I didn't find that one.
What did you get, Dan?
Nothing.
[LAUGHTER]
Well, it's good you brought up.
The only one I found was the Lake Maracaibo one
in western Venezuela, and that's an everlasting storm,
which is there about 260 nights a year.
So, again, we mentioned it about eight years ago.
It was a long, long time ago.
And it's at a point where a river empties into the lake,
Lake Maracaibo, and sailors have used it
for centuries to navigate, because you can see it
from 200 miles away.
And that's what Hector had a role in World War II,
was part of the war effort, because Hector was helping
navigate Australian pilots or any pilots
that were coming in via Australia and Papua New Guinea.
So any pilot, meaning he was kind of a Swiss cloud, basically.
The neutral.
Yeah, he didn't disappear, practically,
when the Nazis turned up.
You know how, when you see a cloud from above,
it looks a bit flat.
So there's satellite, they've been talking really high up,
shots from down up.
Even when you're flying over in an aeroplane,
it kind of looks bumpy-ish, but quite flat.
Absolutely right, it does, doesn't it?
And if you look from above, they're sort of these big disks
of cloud, which you can kind of see they're lumpy beneath,
and then they just top out, and it's really weird.
So the reason for that, I've been on this fantastic blog
called cloudsandclimate.com.
Can't recommend it enough.
It's by a cloud scientist from Imperial College.
They form in rising air, right, which is warmer.
And as the air rises, it stays a bit warmer
than the surrounding air.
So you get this cloud forming.
And then, at about 15 kilometers high,
it hits the tropopause, okay?
And that is a bit of the atmosphere
where the temperature starts to increase again,
so the cloud stops rising.
So that's why these clouds are shaped like anvils.
The tropopause is the bit where the height is limited.
And it's why you get higher clouds over the equator,
'cause the tropopause is higher over the equator.
So that's why the very biggest thunder clouds
happen near the equator,
'cause they've just got more room to grow
before the temperature naturally limits them again.
- That's really interesting.
- That makes a lot of sense,
'cause it gets a bit warmer, doesn't it?
So it's like a knife slicing the top off
when you hit the tropopause.
- Exactly, exactly like that.
- Nice.
- I discovered, by the way, I'm very lucky to be alive
because I do a thing that should have killed me long ago.
And when I started researching this,
I thought lightning was connected to Hector.
But if I'm at home and if it's raining
and it's a big storm outside,
I often would like to have like a hot bath,
like, you know, you're stuck inside.
I do that a lot.
- It turns out that's really dangerous over there.
- I think it's not really dangerous.
- It's not really dangerous?
- I should have died, it is a stretch, isn't it?
One of the things in your life
should have killed you.
- What a daredevil, Dan Trover.
Another bath despite it being rainy outside.
I just didn't know this was a possibility
that basically the ground near your home,
if it's hit by a lightning bolt,
it can be a conductor to bring it through the pipes
into your, yeah.
- What?
- I know, right, so there's examples.
Okay, in November 2007, a bolt struck a teenager
who was washing her hair at home in Blandford, England.
It hit her wrist and it knocked the shower head
out of her hand.
2001, Josephine Martine of Deal, England
was blown out of her bathtub by a lightning bolt.
- No.
- Yeah, the mother of three had been soaking
in her bathtub during a thunderstorm,
was catapulted naked through the air by a force of a bolt
landing on the other side of the bathroom.
- Good Lord.
- Yeah.
- Were they fine or did they?
- Well, yeah, she survived 'cause there's a quote from her,
so I think she's too.
- Okay, yeah.
Shout out to the quote, isn't it?
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Sorry, what, how does it hit?
Sorry.
- What pipes?
- It hits your, what, the pipes that take water
into your house?
- Mine are all plastic.
- Oh, well, you're okay then.
But if you live in an old house.
- Oh, you're sort of copper and white.
- Weirdly, even though being in the bath
in a lightning storm is a marginally,
not one percent more dangerous
than not being in the bath, do you know where the most?
- I just stand outside with the golf club,
holding it in the air and going,
"Well, at least I'm not in the bath."
Like, "Dangerous Dan."
(laughing)
- Do you know where the safest place to be
is during a lightning storm?
- Oh.
- There are sort of lots of answers to this question.
- Well, I'll say like, one thing you're often told
is in your car because it has other wheels.
- Yes, that's good.
- Faraday cage sort of filament.
- I'm gonna say under the earth, deep in earth.
- You're thinking more along the right sort of scope
that I was looking for rather than James's.
- Right, practical.
- Yeah, practical, this isn't practical.
- Fort Knox or something like this, like a place,
is it a particular place?
- No, I'm gonna tell you, it's the sea.
Lightning does not strike at the sea.
- Well, I've seen lightning striking in the city.
- It strikes, I think I've got a photo of it.
- It strikes a 10th as often.
I will backtrack slightly.
(laughing)
It strikes a 10th as often at sea as it does on land.
It is very rare and which I think is really interesting.
- What is a bath but a tiny sea?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Here's the thing,
if you're a bit scared of lightning like a lot of people are,
but you think, well, if I can't see it, I'll be okay.
You're not okay 'cause there's a thing called dark lightning.
And this is a shock of energy
that can carry a million times more energy
than visible lightning.
But if you get shocked, you might not even notice.
- What?
- It's so weird 'cause it's radiation,
it's not electricity, it's radiation hitting you.
It can give you a maximum safe lifetime dose
of ionizing radiation in a single instant.
So it might make you sick.
- So it's gonna give you the amount
that you'd need to have accumulated over your life.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Once, really.
So you'll need to avoid all radiation for evermore.
- Which is impossible, I'm afraid.
- Don't go outside.
- Don't eat bananas.
- Don't go to Cornwall?
- Don't go to Cornwall's a bit more radioactive, isn't it?
- It is.
- Yeah, but there's radiation everywhere.
So you're more likely to get cancers and stuff like that.
- Okay, right.
The thing is, there's one dark lightning occurrence
for every thousand flashes.
We know 'cause of science,
but we don't know whether people have been hit by it
because there's no physical, you know, you can't feel it.
- Can we counter it?
Like if there's a lightning storm on the way,
can I get my kids in some sort of anti-dark lightning suit
that we all wear?
Like a--
- You can wear one of those hats with a little windmill on it
and reindeer.
- Dance kids already wear those.
(all laughing)
To protect against the heat and it's the whole thing.
- You can all climb into a microwave.
(all laughing)
- 'Cause that doesn't let any radiation out, does it?
- Oh, there we go.
(all laughing)
- That way, quick, into the microwave.
- I already don't trust microwaves.
I don't understand that.
The whole thing where you can see the little holes
and they're like, oh, the radioactive bits
are just a bit bigger than the hole
and can't get out, fuck off.
What if they make a hole?
- What are you talking about?
So there's a mesh in a microwave,
which is big enough that microwaves,
because of the wavelength, can't get out.
Often that's why no radiation leaks,
even though there was a massive conspiracy theory.
And I think the seventies, which dad still believes.
- Was that a conspiracy theory?
- Oh, yeah.
- Oh, wow.
- But you came up with it independently.
This is like convergent evolution or whatever.
(all laughing)
- You know, we've never talked about Colonel William Rankin,
who do you guys know?
- Chief Oliver.
- We've never mentioned him.
- What?
- I don't know who that is, sorry.
- So basically, no pilot has ever flown through
cumulonimbus and succeeded,
which I think is really interesting
because they're a common cloud,
but if you see one in a plane,
you cannot get through it
because they're so huge and so dangerous.
And only one person until 2007, actually,
is known to have fallen all the way through one and survived.
And it is Lieutenant Colonel William Rankin.
- But he didn't have a great time of it.
- No, he wouldn't do it again.
(all laughing)
- One star review.
The engine of his fighter jet failed in 1959.
And so he jumped out of the plane
and went through the cloud.
And it's an insane situation to be in.
He got frostbite immediately.
I'll just split a second.
Decompression meant that his eyes, ears,
nose, and mouth started bleeding profusely.
His abdomen swelled, he vomited.
He's in the middle of a cloud
getting buffeted around by the cloud.
- Yeah, didn't he physically swell up?
Like he's just like a balloon sort of getting blown up?
- I think he did.
It was amazing for those things
that just looked so fluffy.
- I know.
- I mean, they look quite benign.
- But also you can't,
you don't just fall through that cloud.
- Oh, okay.
- It keeps you in it.
It's like a washing machine.
- Oh, 'cause of the correction.
- Your injection, yeah.
- Yeah.
- Especially because the buffeting of the cloud
flicked a switch on his parachute somehow
and opened it prematurely.
- No!
- So he's stuck in his cloud.
- Oh, wow.
- He had to hold his breath to avoid drowning
at repeated moments.
Anyway, he was in there for 40 minutes.
- Oh my God.
- It's gone up and down and up and down.
Awful.
- And then he got out and he wrote a book about it.
- And he survived.
- Yeah.
- James, do you remember?
I think there was one other story of someone
who might have got it.
She was a paraglider and she got sucked up into it.
- Yeah, cloud sucked.
- Eva Visnierska.
- Right.
- She did get sucked up.
And in fact, she was up there for three and a half hours.
- Oh my God.
(all laughing)
Did we ever talk?
I don't think we did about the Hunger Tonga explosion
in the Pacific.
No.
This was big news,
but not as big as it should have been.
- Basically.
- Very recently.
- Very recently, 2021.
End of 2021.
It's an underwater volcano, basically.
And it went off and it blasted through
150 meters of sea water, right?
That's how far below the surface it is.
It then sent a plume of ash 36 miles into the air.
- Yeah, it's mental.
- Wow.
Five billion kilos of matter every second.
Five billion kilos every second.
- It's amazing, really.
- I remember it happening and thinking,
okay, that's, do you remember when that happened
with Krakatoa?
- Krakatoa, yeah.
When Krakatoa went off, basically there was no summer
for like three years, right?
And I thought that was gonna happen with this one,
but it just seems to have petered out a bit.
- I know.
- It was so bizarre.
And then it produced the most intense lightning storm
ever on the planet and higher than any lightning
it had ever been.
- Did it cause by the ash?
That big ash cloud?
- Yeah, this was 19 miles in the air.
- Wow.
- There was lightning going off.
- What?
- And over 11 hours of this particular storm,
there were 192,000 flashes of lightning.
Observe.
- Crazy.
- It's insane.
- And you say this was over the sea, was it?
(all laughing)
- I'm afraid.
I'm afraid it was.
- Don't think so.
(all laughing)
I must have been a trigger for the light.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is Andy.
- My fact is that during the Second World War,
a Polish pilot was shot down over Southern England
and he and his parachute landed in the grounds
of a very respectable tennis club.
He was immediately then signed in as a guest,
offered a racket, lent some white flannels
and thrashed his opponents until the RAF came to collect him.
(all laughing)
- Rankin would have been so jealous of his.
This is possibly the best parachute landing
anyone's ever made.
Supposedly, I think it was a longstanding match
and someone hadn't turned up.
It was a doubles match.
- Oh, I see.
- Oh, perfect.
(all laughing)
That's amazing.
Oh, no, there's only three of us.
We can't play.
Wait a minute.
(all laughing)
- This is so weird.
I should say what this is from.
This is from Anthony Beaver's book "The Second World War",
which is so long and so good.
It's amazing.
- Oh, it's good though.
There's only a couple of hundred pages in.
I'm in the foothill.
You're gonna be hearing a lot more facts.
- I'm gonna say, when you're writing your review,
start with so good.
Robin, so long, so good.
- I've been looking at it on my shelf
for about nearly a year thinking I can never.
And then I've just started.
Anyway, it's great.
It's really good.
This is what I would say is the lighter facts in the book.
It's pretty harrowing.
- He goes heavy, Beaver.
Well done.
- I know.
But this is a light bit of beef and it's great.
Anyway, and this is all about the Polish pilots
who fought with the RAF during the Second World War.
Poland was invaded by Germany and the Soviet Union
simultaneously right at the start.
And yes, of course, you think it started 1930s
with the Japanese invasion of Manchuria.
- I kind of think it started with the Treaty of Versailles.
- I'm so glad we're having this chat.
But the Polish armed forces were defeated
pretty rapidly a few weeks
and tens of thousands of soldiers of the pilot went
to France, big mistake,
because several months later,
France was also overrun.
And then so the Polish pilots hadn't been deployed enough.
So they went to England.
They were quite annoyed at this point.
Quite, quite keen to get back in the fray.
- Like annoyed with the Nazis,
not just generally annoyed, weren't they?
- I think they're a bit annoyed with the Soviets as well.
- Yeah.
- And the Soviets, yep.
- It was a time of justifiable annoyance
was the hallmark of the, yeah.
And just a large chunk of the RAF actually was Polish
during the Battle of Britain.
When they finally arrived in the UK
and they were put up with the RAF,
the RAF people thought these guys are going to be terrible.
Why are we bringing them in?
They've been defeated twice.
They're not going to be any good.
The language barrier didn't help
because they obviously couldn't communicate
if they're good by chatting to them.
So they said about training them,
but they did it almost in a slightly mocking sense.
So in order to teach them their kind of patterns in the sky,
they put them on tricycles and got them riding around.
Meanwhile, the Polish guys are thinking, what is this?
- Well, little tricycles, like little plastic.
- Actual tricycles, they were heavily kitted out.
So the tricycles had things like speedometers,
compasses, radios.
So they were very, very tooled up tricycles, but...
- I think this was a standard way of training pilots.
It wasn't just that they thought,
oh, we'll just put the Polish people on here.
- That was a good way. - Well, I think so.
But the Polish pilots, though, it was ridiculous
because they were already trained up in this way.
- Yeah, right.
- And they fought in a slightly different way,
which is that they would get up much closer
to enemy planes in dogfights,
which made you more accurate, but was more dangerous.
So my grandad was in the Squadron 307, I think it was.
It was called the Eagle Owls
'cause they were the only night fighter squadron
of the Polish squadrons, but he flew Mosquitoes,
which were the only wooden planes.
And people thought they were mad as well at first.
It was Haveland, was the guy who made them,
and it was called the Wooden Wonder.
At first, they thought, we can't do this.
It'll just be so fragile.
And it turned out to be brilliant.
And the thing about them was they were completely unarmed.
It's just carrying a bomb, but it's incredibly light
because it's got no arms on it.
And it just relies on the fact that 'cause it's very light,
it can get away quickly, so they're very, very zippy.
- Like a Mosquito, I suppose.
- Like a Mosquito.
They were painted blue to match the sky
'cause they were quite quiet as well, so you could--
- Were they the ones, there was a plane,
and they needed a lot of furniture joiners, basically,
to make them, because they were made of wood.
And oh, wow, it was something like that.
- I was at the Aerospace Museum in Bristol last weekend.
And if you look at these old planes
made out of canvas and wood and stuff,
do you think how on earth does that stay out?
- Yeah, it's extraordinary cool.
- It looks nicer as well, though, than Mosquito,
'cause it is made of wood,
so I think everyone would have stopped to admire it.
I got really confused reading an article
which showed, actually, from his squadron,
which showed a picture of one of the other people in it
standing next to his plane and had four swastikas on it.
And I couldn't, it took me ages to work out
why there were four swastikas on it, do you know?
- I do, actually.
- Yeah, go on, yeah, I didn't know this.
- Basically, it was an intimidation tactic,
so you would put your kill list on the side of your plane.
So as people were flying up beside you,
they'd go, "Oh my God, he's killed six Nazis."
- Oh, you put a swastika on every time you killed a Nazi?
- Yeah, you'd paint on the outside body.
- Those people who were doing riots,
it's the UK last week, with swastikas on their body,
had they all been attacking Nazis as well.
- That's absolutely correct.
- It wouldn't necessarily be just swastikas,
it'd be skulls and so on, and there were different weights,
so you would have a skull that was colored
in a certain way that said, "That's a death."
The next one might be, "I damaged the plane."
It was like a whole sort of like,
a bit of reading time for the enemy to catch up on.
- They were very rarely flying alongside each other
for that long, to be honest.
- But it is a bit of a Wikipedia entry
that you can see like, "Oh!"
- And then they became famous as being really sort of brave
and full of daring do, and that kind of stuff, didn't they?
- I think they were the most important in the battle of Britain.
A Polish squadron was the most important squadron
down the West Coast.
- And that's why if you drive out of London
to the West these days on the A-40,
you always see the Polish War Memorial,
which is one of the roundabouts,
which I've always seen and never really knew
why Polish War Memorial and not all the other countries.
- Who is that?
I can't see that.
- Haven't you, you'd know if you grew up in my family,
'cause every time we passed it on the way out of London,
my dad would go, "Oh, I forgot again."
- Probably Polish the War Memorial.
- Oh, Polish, I see.
- Yeah, Polish War Memorial.
- That was good.
- Yeah, and it's all in capitals and stuff.
Oh, that's a good joke if you're ever on the M-40.
- That's a great M-40 joke.
There's quite a few stories of these pilots
who had to bail and landed in various places.
So the tennis match is a great one.
There was another pilot who,
he landed in a South London back garden
and there was a girl waiting out there as she landed.
They got married two months later.
So that was really good.
- So she's like, "Oh, you know what?
"It's a shame that I don't have someone to get my--"
- Who's that?
- Good men don't just fall out of the sky, honey.
You'll be waiting there ages.
There was a third guy who he landed
and the people around him and the town
thought that he was enemy,
so they were going in to lynch him
and as they were getting close to him,
he just went, "Fuck off."
And they went, "Oh, he's one of ours."
- Like no German would know how to say, "Fuck off."
(all laugh)
- Tennis in war?
- Yeah, okay.
- Oh, wow. - Was this a tennis court?
- Sure, yeah.
- Well, you know Roland Garros?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- So what's that?
- It's where the French opens hell.
- Yeah, right.
Did you know Roland Garros was a man?
He developed the first single seat fighter plane
which was fitted with a machine gun.
That was his thing.
That's why they named the stadium after him
'cause he was a war hero
and they built the stadium in the '20s.
- It's quite a weird leap
as in to decide to name a tennis stadium
after some months of that, but yeah.
- It was a weird leap.
And he was, but he was a sort of pioneering pilot.
He was the first person to fly across the Mediterranean
in about 1913, so very, very early stuff.
The problem was guns were always behind the propeller.
- Oh yeah. - And that was a big
problem in the end. - Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
- You shoot your propeller off, oh no.
- So annoying. - So did he invent
the rotation? - No, he did not invent
the clever system which allows you to fire
in between the propellers passing.
- What a, imagine the genius
who thought of that. - Well no, he just,
he and his mechanic developed a similar system,
but it was like a wedge which deflected
the occasional rounds which did hit the propeller.
- Oh, I see. - So it was very much
a forge job, and then I think it was a German engineer
who actually thought, no, you developed
the system to fire between.
- And can we just say before Dan says,
what a genius who thought of that.
I think a lot of people had thought of that before.
That was like, first thing you think is,
well, we should just get it to fire between them.
I think it's actually putting that into action
that proved difficult.
- I clearly met the person who pulled it off.
(all laughing)
- Only thing, light bulb moment, guys.
We should just fly to the moon.
- Yeah, anyway, that was his,
his innovation was sort of not quite
working that out, basically.
- But do you know he has a tennis connection?
- Who? - Who?
- Roland Garros, there's this amazing story
which happened on April the 1st, but was real.
So he was this incredibly famous fly.
He went down over France, 1915,
and he was flying this plane he designed,
so he tried to burn it so the Germans
didn't get hold of the technology,
but failed, and they did.
And he was in a German prison of war camp,
and he sent these coded message back to France
to arrange for the delivery of two tennis rackets.
And within the tennis racket handles hollowed out,
were in one handle a map of Germany,
and in the other handle a felt hat
to use as a disguise for escaping.
(all laughing)
- You're gonna look like a Frenchman
if you're wearing a felt hat.
- Yeah, that's where they went wrong.
- You've got two tennis rackets handles worth of stuff.
I guess a map is a good thing to pick.
- A map is a good one.
- Yeah, I think a felt hat feels like
a needless waste of a racket.
(all laughing)
- What would you put in it, Andy?
A sausage?
(all laughing)
Everyone's gonna believe you're a German
if you're waving a sausage around.
- That's it.
- And it's just the right shape.
- Yeah, just a giant pepper army.
- Yeah, not thin sausage, but yeah.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- Well, no, it didn't, went with a felt hat.
And actually, I don't think he used it.
He ended up making his own costume
to mimic the guard's costumes
and then walked out dressed as a guard.
- What a legend.
- Yeah. - That's great.
- Speaking of clothing and tennis,
this is not about war,
but it's a story that I really like.
Pat Stewart, who was a tennis player in the '60s,
she was single and she was playing at Wimbledon
and she wanted a boyfriend.
And so she embroidered her phone number on her knickers.
And the hope was that the paparazzi
would take photos of it
and then someone would give her a call.
- And?
- It seems like no one did.
- Oh.
- Although she did a few months later meet
and marry a cricketer called John Edric,
but they did divorce a few months later.
But it's quite a nice way to advertise yourself, isn't it?
It's quite forward.
- Yeah, it's not everyone's type.
- I would almost be a bit intimidated
by someone that confident in themselves.
- And I think a lot of the Wimbledon audience
might feel the same way.
I think maybe she hasn't chosen her audience.
- I just do, right?
Actually, I've got to put on a telegram.
- Have you heard of Hans Reddle?
I'm looking at you especially,
James and Anna, sports people.
- No, I don't think so.
- Well, of course he got to the fourth round
of the men's singles in Wimbledon in 1947.
So I'm surprised you haven't heard that.
- Oh, Hans Reddle.
(laughing)
- No, Reddle.
Sorry, different name.
But it's quite impressive for a particular reason,
which is that he had one arm.
And he had lost his other arm in the Battle of Stalingrad.
- Really?
- He seemed to be fighting, I presume,
in the German army, he was Austrian.
And he was given special dispensation
to touch the ball twice every time.
- Come on.
- Oh, sorry.
- I'm watching you touch the ball.
- Every time he served.
So he would toss the ball into the air with his racket.
- Oh, then serve.
- 'Cause otherwise, it does make it quite a lot easier.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that things named
after May West include a soda bottle,
a gas pump, a parachute malfunction,
and a graph that explains the nuclear fission of uranium.
(laughing)
- What a lady.
- What's that?
(laughing)
- A parachute.
- She didn't invent all these things.
She came up with the idea, of course,
but she didn't actually.
- I know what you're gonna say.
It's not an item that is designed to be a malfunction.
A parachute malfunction is interesting.
- Did you take this off my parachute actually?
(laughing)
- The parachute one is basically,
it makes your canopy stick out in quite a suggestive way.
And most of these, if not all of them,
I'd use the fact that May West was famous
for an hourglass figure.
- Oh, really?
I thought the gas pump would be,
'cause she was like pump, pump, pump, pumping away.
- Oh.
(laughing)
- In the bedroom?
- No, as in working hard in the industry.
- Oh, right.
- No, it was because it has like a slim waist kind of thing.
- I see.
- And the graph of the products of nuclear fission
of uranium is basically two sort of normal distribution curves.
So it's like a pair of boobs.
- Oh, okay.
She was actually quite a sort of slim,
straight up and down lady.
She wasn't actually a sort of Jessica Rabbit style.
- She wasn't Jessica Rabbit style
because that is just impossible.
- 'Cause it's cartoon.
- Cartoon, yeah, okay.
- But, yeah, I mean, yeah.
- I haven't studied her, actually,
I can picture her face, but I haven't studied her body.
I just assumed she had that.
It was that all over the place.
- Well, I read that.
I'd like to clarify,
I haven't been studying pictures of Maywest.
I just, I'm, yeah, I would say she was--
- She was curvaceous.
- Oh, okay.
- And she had the thin waist.
- Okay.
- In actual fact, I believe the word curvaceous
was coined specifically for her.
- No.
- Pretty interesting.
- Yeah, if you look in the OED,
basically all of the first few citations are about her.
And the earliest one says,
"A new word has been coined to fit the personality
"of Maywest.
"The word curvaceous is a combination of curves
"and vivacious to have Miss West's chief characteristic."
- That's incredible.
That's so good.
I had no idea that's where the word came from.
That's brilliant.
- Yes, 'cause we don't assume the vivacious bit.
You can't just have big boobs and big hips.
You've got to have the character to go with it.
- Yeah.
- Correct.
- Is that a lesson for you ladies,
an anti-feminist lesson?
(all laughing)
- Yeah, when I say that to women on the tube.
- There's no point just having big boobs.
I weren't your personality.
I'm just asking you for your tickets, sir.
(all laughing)
- Okay.
I mean, so there was another thing named after her
in the, actually, Sakamawbo,
some twin turreted combat tanks.
- Yes.
- Yes, reasons.
- A live jacket,
which makes you look like you've got big boobs.
- Yeah.
- The grip she had on the 20th century.
We should step back and say who she is,
because she was a great comedian of her time.
And her time would have been the 1930s and so on.
She was in movies, she wrote novels, she wrote plays.
She has so many one-liners
and they were the kind of lines that you just saw.
You wouldn't get away with that at the time.
- I used to be snow white, but I drifted.
All of that stuff.
- Without the noise.
- No, with the noise.
- With the noise.
- That's the way that we're coming back
to your comedy noise again, which we mentioned last week.
- Can you do when I'm good, I'm good,
but when I'm bad, I'm better.
- When I'm good, I'm very, very good.
But when I'm bad, I'm better.
- Ooh, whacka, whacka, whacka, whacka.
- Very whacka.
Is that a guy in your pocket?
I think that was her.
- She did say that in a film in the end,
but I don't think it was the first instance.
She said it in the film weirdly in the seventh,
like the last film she did
or one of the last films she did.
- Oh yeah, yeah, she did a film at the edge of about 80,
but she was described in her obituary as a sex personality.
It was a big part of her character and her persona.
- Yeah, I think it's really weird that if you think of people
who push the boundaries of comedy,
Lenny Bruce will be someone,
we've spoken about him on the show before,
who was jailed because he was saying words
that you weren't allowed to say on stage concepts.
That's what Mae West was doing.
And she was in fact jailed for, meant to be 10 days.
In the end, it was eight days
'cause she got off a good behavior.
- One wonders what that good behavior was.
- Oh yeah, I got off a good behavior, I know I got off.
- Someone else got off as well.
- But yeah, she wrote a Broadway play in 1926 called Sex.
And the production was taken up by the city officials
as offensive.
They said, "You're gonna go to jail or pay a fine."
And she said, "Put me in jail."
'Cause she thought the publicity would be great.
But she also meant it.
She was like, "I should be saying this on stage.
This is fine."
She doesn't get the credit.
- I read something really interesting about sex, the play.
I thought it was banned because it itself was so lurid
and so sexy and too pornographic,
but it had been on for about a year in New York
before they stormed in and banned it, been on for a while.
But the thing that had happened was
she'd written another play called Drag.
And that was showing somewhere else, I think in Connecticut.
And that was all about homosexuality.
You know, it's called Drag.
It ends in this huge, big drag show.
It's about lots of gay relationships happening.
The lead character is a guy who's in the closet.
And I believe that the authorities in New York
couldn't clamp down on that
because it was outside their jurisdiction,
but they really didn't want to get into New York.
So they then clamped down on sex.
- And the New York Times called it a crude
and inept play, cheaply produced and polyactive.
- Is that a sex or drag?
- That was sex.
- But of course, because it was being banned,
everyone wanted to see it.
And it became really, really popular.
Another thing was that it had African-American music in it.
And that was seen as hot jazz.
That was the other thing.
You know, it features lots of sexy stuff.
There is prostitution, there are pimps,
there are corrupt cops who are not in themselves sexy,
I suppose.
(all laughing)
It sounds pretty sexy.
Sorry.
I'm showing my predilections there.
Anyway, but the point was that her character,
because she played a lady of the night
and she really doesn't have anything to apologise for.
And she played a woman who thinks
she has nothing to apologise for.
And you were allowed to show grime and semeness
as long as everyone repents hard at the end.
And she didn't, you know.
So I think that was another part of the moral objection to it.
- Yeah, literally people must have been just on the floor
with shop, she was doing all this
and sticking out for every minority there was
because she considered herself kind of among them.
She'd come from the society's underbelly really,
hadn't she?
Her dad was a street fighter, I think.
- Yeah, he was.
He was a boxer, yeah.
- Who was, although he went on to be a masseuse, weirdly.
- That's interesting.
Did he keep the gloves on?
Do you reckon?
(all laughing)
- Just like your predilection to get there.
- People asked for it, I think he'd go for it.
- That makes sense.
You can't box anymore,
but you've been in the industry
where they don't have lots of masseuses.
- Let me pound you in the ring.
That kind of stuff.
(all laughing)
- Okay, he also became a special policeman,
which I'm not quite sure what that means,
but it sounds like he might also be up your street, Andy.
(all laughing)
- Another sexy is a corrupt one, but yeah.
That's a dirty cough, no doubt, yeah.
- Can I just say back to sex, just on that?
So the group that was campaigning against the play sex
was called the New York Society for the Suppression of Vice.
And they were founded by the world's greatest prude,
called Anthony Cornstock, a self-given nickname, I think.
And he had been inspired by the death of a friend
who'd become addicted to pornography
and masturbated himself to death.
- No.
- Or so he thought.
- Sad on the gravestone.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, so he thought that that's what had happened.
And he decided to start the society for prudery.
And it was these guys who stopped sex.
- I didn't know, I didn't know that.
That's incredible. - I've heard the name
Cornstock. - You'll know the Cornstock law,
I think, which was an American thing
which stopped you from having any obscene material,
but it stopped you from sending anything
through the post as well.
And what that meant was you couldn't send
any contraception leaflets or anything like that.
So it's part of that whole song.
- Cornstock was a nickname, did you say?
- No, that was his surname.
His nickname was the world's greatest prude.
- Oh, okay, when you said Cornstock,
I was like, oh, that's a weird nickname.
(all laughing)
But also, it just made me think
when you said the masturbation thing.
I thought, oh, Cornstock, is that?
'Cause Cornflakes was an anti-masturbation thing.
Was it all about corn? - Your mind is incredible, Deb.
All the effort that you put
into making these unbelievably great connections
wouldn't be necessary if you just listened a bit more.
(all laughing)
- It's really amazing. - It's the shittest Colombo.
- That's so embarrassing about his friend as well.
- I know. - He keeps going around saying,
"This is in honor of my friend."
"Wrightfully, dive masturbating."
- Yeah, it feels like he didn't really like that guy, didn't it?
- No, he was just having a bath
and he got hit by lightning.
(all laughing)
- Mae West loved having an enema.
So when she was in her vaudeville days
and she used to go to the bathrooms,
she was saying this, like, filthy, I'd never using these.
And so she used to give herself a daily enema
so that she didn't have to deal with them.
And that became part of her,
if you were doing a movie with her.
So Tony Curtis talks about this.
He says on the last film that she did,
"Sex Tet," which he was in,
he said that she would get her makeup done
and then always, 11 a.m. approximately in the morning,
she would then have the final bit of getting ready,
which was to have her enema,
and then she was ready for the set.
- And then she said,
"I keep my friends close, but my enemas closer."
- Nice. - Whack-a-whack-a-whack.
- She did a really strong line in objectifying men,
which I think we approve of,
'cause obviously women were used to being objectified
for thousands of years.
After her sort of Hollywood career,
she set up a vagus review of sort of
these bulging, beefy muscle men
so that women could come and look at them.
'Cause she said, you know,
"Men have always had something to look at,
"now it's time for the wives to have something."
- I think it's basically magic Mike
that she sort of invented.
I know there were muscle shows before that.
It's like "Mr. Universe" and stuff that Charles Atlas was in.
- Charles Atlas and Eugene Sandoval.
So there were muscle men before,
but I think she kind of turned it into a show.
- She turned it into more of a sexy thing.
- Coca-Cola bottles used to be called
Maywest bottles as well, by the way.
- So the first thing in my fact was soda bottles
are named after her, and that was what I'm talking about.
- Yeah, and I thought, 'cause it said
that it was inspired by her, and that's not true.
That just sort of got around.
But on Coca-Cola's website, they describe it.
These used to be called Maywest.
So they were designed to look a bit like coca beans,
and then they decided that they needed to be more curvy
because they kept rolling off the conveyor belts.
So remember we talked about conveyor belts last week,
and so they kept rolling off the conveyor belts,
and so they changed the shape very slightly
so that they rolled over an axis and went straight
rather than kind of rolling off to the left or the right.
So that's why the modern Coca-Cola bottle looks like it is.
- That's great, practical.
- She came to the UK once with a play.
It was actually in 1947, which is the year that that guy,
Reddle, got to the fourth round of the men's singles
at Wimbledon with one arm.
- Wow, what were the chances?
- That's not why she was here.
She arrived, and for her first press conference,
she arrived, she said, "I want every man in England
"to come up and see me."
Especially this big Ben character I hear about.
Brilliant. - Great, nice.
- Anyway, when she was here, she did her play, obviously,
but she also went to a boxing match.
She went to the Dunlop factory,
where she signed an inflatable life jacket.
- Yeah. - And I love this.
She went to the opening
of the British philatelic exhibition in Glasgow.
There was a stamp exhibition on, and she was there.
- I think that she confused the word philately with philatio.
- I mean, that's what happened, yeah.
- Philately will get you nowhere, boys.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that in 2013,
a survey revealed that 97% of students
studying Finnish at Vienna University
were mainly doing so because of their love
for the country's death metal bands.
And most of them, by the way, sing in English,
so there's no real point in doing that.
But yeah, death metal from Finland is responsible
as the main reason for all these students
studying the language. - I can see that, yeah.
- In a way. - Yeah.
- Can you? - I can actually.
- I find the lyrics in metal music
quite difficult to make out, and I don't know.
And I speak the language of English,
which is the language I hear a lot of death metal in.
- That's true. - Yeah, well,
yeah, what's interesting as well is that
I had to listen to a bunch of the bands that were cited.
Children of Bodham is a massive band,
and I listened to some of their songs,
it's very clear what they're saying.
- For listeners, that wasn't very clear what you said,
it's Bodham, not Bottom, isn't it?
- Oh, I said Bodham. - I know you did.
- Oh, right. - But it does sound
a bit like Children of Bodham.
- Maybe that's what they're going for.
Little bum joke?
- Little bum bum joke?
- The maywests of modern Finland.
(all laughing)
Yeah, Stradivarius is another band, and him,
and yeah, they all sing in English,
and I listen to them, and yeah, it's quite clear.
It is quite clear. - Oh, is it?
- Yeah, yeah. - That's all they're saying.
- Yeah, I would say so.
Finland does seem to have a unique affinity
for heavy metal, though.
- Yeah, it really does. - Yeah.
The figures wobble around a bit,
but one recent tish figure was that there are
53 and a half metal bands per 100,000 people in Finland,
and that is, that's a lot.
The UK has about five metal bands per 100,000 people,
so Finland--
- It still feels like a lot to me.
- Yes. - Enough.
It feels like too many to me.
- No, you're right, five per 100,000 people.
- If I think about the population of what,
I don't know, Bolton must be about 200,000,
so that means we've got 10 metal bands in Bolton.
It feels like a lot.
- Yeah. - Does it?
I mean, there could be real amateur
just doing an open mic night.
We're not talking charting bands necessarily, I don't--
- Maybe, I think you're right.
- They work in Tesco on the weekdays.
- There's a town called Lemmy in Finland,
which has 3,000 people in this.
It's called Lemmy.
- What?
- After the guy from the town.
- Yeah, no, great point.
It's spelled a bit differently, but it is called Lemmy.
Anyway, they've got 3,000 people
and they have 13 metal bands.
That really is the, that's the metal center of the universe.
That is the core, you know.
- Amazing, it's called Lemmy.
- Yeah.
- They have a church of heavy metal,
and there's a guy who does metal mass,
so this very cool pastor who looks like a heavy metal fan,
but then he's a Lutheran pastor,
and he puts on the correct robes,
and he started in 2006 just adapting traditional hymns,
so he keeps the lyrics the same, you know,
the creed and the color around it,
but turns them into heavy metal soil.
- Oh, thanks, bride, I'm beautiful.
- Exactly.
- That's great.
- That's really good.
- It sounds really cool, it's really popular.
- Heavy Sorus, another cool one.
They're a Finnish heavy metal band
where they're all dressed as dido-saws
and the songs are for children.
- Oh.
(laughing)
- Their album, (speaks in foreign language)
which means "Night of the Dinosaurs"
was the second most popular album in Finland in 2010.
- Wow.
- Nice.
- And their members include Millie Pilly,
Confymompi, Riffy Raffy, and Muffy Puffy.
(laughing)
And according to their website,
they were in eggs in the Cretaceous period,
but they somehow fossilized,
and then came out of the eggs and survived,
and then started a rock group.
- That's quite cool.
- That's very cool.
- Although someone has pointed out
that Muffy Puffy is a stegosaurus,
and Confymompi is an apatosaurus
who lived in the Jurassic period in that Cretaceous.
- Got to do your research
instead of your dinosaur marathon.
- Yeah.
- Muffy Puffy.
- Lordy's from there as well.
- Yeah, Lordy.
- The Eurovision Song Contest winner.
He calls himself Mr. Lordy,
and he started the band when he met the other members
while he was running a Finnish kiss cruise
because he was the president of Kiss Army Finland.
He sounds incredible, Mr. Lordy,
as in I think he's basically
one of the great geeks of our world.
He's a comic book illustrator,
he's a graphic designer,
he's a special effects makeup artist.
- Like, I think if you look at metal music,
it's obviously not true of everyone,
but I think there is a crossover of nerdyness
for people who like metal.
- Oh, God, yeah.
- Well, Corey Taylor, when he came in for the 100th episode,
arrived in a doctor who, or a Sherlock T-shirt.
- Yeah, there's another man of misfit, I guess,
being into metal.
It's not mainstream, except in Finland,
where it basically has crossed over into it,
but I think it's if you don't fit into the mainstream,
you go for it.
And they also are famous in QI circles
for hosting the first ever
heavy metal knitting world championships.
- Oh, yes.
- They do do that.
- It is a bit stupid, that, isn't it?
- Hey.
- What's, um, what is it?
- It's just literally doing heavy metal and knitting.
There doesn't seem to be-
- There's no extra bit.
- No.
- But is it like chess boxing where you do one minute
of one and then one minute of the other?
- No, you do them simultaneously.
But they are judged and they're actually judged
on quite interesting criteria.
- Sorry, how can you do them simultaneously?
- So, at least one member of your band
has to be knitting something at the same time
as performing and you are judged on various things,
but partly on the piece of knitting
that you produce by the end of your set.
- Everyone I know who knits, they're like,
oh, look at this scarf.
I've been working on it for four months.
What have we, are they coming in with the final,
like, one day of knitting that's needed
for the scarf or are they starting?
- That's such, it's quite small,
but they also do seem to go quite fast
in the ones I saw.
Maybe there was some clever video editing.
- That's the tempo of heavy metal, isn't it?
It probably does encourage speed.
- Yes, you have to do it in time with the songs, of course.
You want to judge for that, so.
- Can I ask, do people ever do the knitting
with their own bodies?
And what I mean by that, sorry, what I mean is,
do people ever get a maypole in the middle of the stage
and then they've all got a ribbon
and they move around the stage while they play?
- That's not really knitting, so much as crocheting.
(laughing)
- Because I watched "The Wicked Man" recently
for the first time, there's a great maypole scene in that.
And that's sort of, "The Wicked Man"
bleeds into that world, doesn't it?
- It's more platting, I think.
- 'Cause it does feel like, for all the men in metal,
usually have large, gigantic beards, low hanging.
That's what should be being knitted while they're doing.
Someone should be working up.
(laughing)
- They probably accidentally catch someone's beard
sometimes and knit it into their jumper.
- Sorry, baseball, you're part of it now.
You can never take the jumper off.
- I look forward to Andy's Morris dancing
platting competition.
(laughing)
In 2019, Metallica played a gig in Finland,
which was attended by 1% of everyone in the country.
- Ooh, I remember that happening in Iceland as well,
I think, like it was an enormous percentage.
- That's very cool.
'Cause there are five and a half million Finns
and they had 55,000 in the audience for that gig.
So the numbers do stack up.
- Yeah, well done, Metallica.
- Do you wanna play a game of Finnish metal band
or game of thrones episode?
- Yes.
- Ah, okay, of course.
- No, I've seen every episode of Finland,
so I'm confident about this.
- Throne of chaos.
- Band.
- Andy, you've seen every episode.
- I think band, I think band.
- Game of thrones, then.
- It is a band.
They were unable to make commercial headway
and broke up in August, 2005.
- Okay.
- Winter sun.
- Game of thrones.
- I'll say band.
- It's a band.
It's not really death metal, says the singer.
It's very difficult for me to label it,
but if someone put a gun to my forehead,
I would probably say something like
extreme melodic, majestic metal.
- If I think it'll just annoy whoever's put a gun
to your head at this point, that's an irritating.
- The pointy end.
- Thrones.
- I'll say thrones.
- Metal.
- It is thrones.
- Ay.
- It refers to a sword fighting lesson
that John gave to Arya before the farewell,
where he says, "stick them with the pointy end."
- Do you remember that note?
You say it?
- Yeah.
- Isn't it nice?
- But there's a lot of fun Finnish band names.
- Pierre Gunt.
(laughing)
- You know it, Gunt.
- Does Gunt mean the same thing in Finland as it does here?
- I looked it up in the Oxford English Dictionary,
and it doesn't mean anything in this country.
- Don't know what you're talking about, James.
- But it's obviously based on Greek's Pierre Gents,
but also it's guns in Finnish.
- I see.
- Climidia with a K.
- Ooh.
- Los Bastardos, Finlandesses.
(laughing)
- Brilliant names.
- Those are great names.
- That's very good.
- I'm Finnish language.
- Oh yeah.
- I see.
- It's really hard.
- Yeah.
- Like it's really, really difficult.
- For what reason?
- It's very complicated.
(laughing)
- It's got 15 different cases.
- Okay.
- And lots of people leave after arriving
because it's just like language complexities,
also bureaucracy and attacks.
- Lots of people leave after a lot of people move there
and then go, "Oh, sod this."
- Students who arrive, 36% of them leave within a year
of finishing their studies,
so they don't stay on and make a life.
- And there's another reason which is,
I don't think anyone's tired of this,
but in Finland, apparently, there's almost no small talk.
You just pay for your coffee and you shut up.
- I only learned one word of Finnish when I was there,
and it's kitos, which means thank you.
And the way I remembered it is
'cause it's like mosquitoes, but without the moss bit.
- Oh really?
- Right.
- And that's how they told it,
'cause I actually got that through some small talk
in a cafe.
(laughing)
- They were eating it.
- I was gonna say, we are gonna get letters
off the back of that.
- I don't think we are.
- I think I've read quite a lot about Finnish culture before.
I think it became a thing in China
to call yourself spiritually Finnish,
and it's a very popular meme.
A lot of Chinese people tapped into this.
It's got millions of views.
The idea is that they like their own space.
They're very taciturn, and I've never seen,
and I've read so many accounts of Finns
being asked about this.
I've never seen anyone say, this is bullshit.
We're all incredibly friendly.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- So do write in.
- It's not unfriendly, yeah.
It's just very, it's just quiet.
- Which country did I get a few emails
'cause I said they don't talk about the weather
'cause they have so much.
- That was somewhere in Scandinavia.
- Yeah, yeah, definitely got emails off the back of that.
- Just on the language, it is a really interesting language.
It's the Uralic language,
which means it came from the Urals,
and there are kind of three main Uralic languages.
Finnish, Estonian, which makes sort of sense
because that's--
- Right next to each other.
- You swim across.
- Yeah, swim across a small bit of water.
And then Hungarian.
- So weird.
- Which is, there's like four countries in between them
if you follow them down.
- And it's four countries,
but they're four pretty big countries as well.
- Yeah, it's so mad.
I think it's because it starts in the Urals
to the east of both of them,
and then some people went just directly west,
and I don't know why it didn't sort of drop bits of itself
along the way in Ukraine or in bits of Russia,
but it didn't.
- But I think also like the Soviet Union,
they basically banned any other language, didn't they?
- Yeah, you're right, maybe that's--
- So I think a lot of the smaller pockets just died out.
- They got it, that's probably it.
Yeah, and didn't quite reach Hungary that rule,
even though obviously Hungary--
- I believe so.
- Being in part of the Eastern Bloc.
But you're hungry just sitting there
in the same language family as the Finns,
but unable to reach them.
- Wild, sob.
- The oldest writing in the Finnish family of languages,
which was found in the Urals, is very metal, actually.
If you translate it into English,
it translates as God's arrow, ten is your name,
the arrow is God's own, the doom God leads.
- That's brilliant.
- And to go back to a former thing
that we were talking about,
we reckon that it was a magic spell
to stop lightning from getting you.
You might say it in the bath, for instance.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it was found in Novgorod.
- Dan has a rubber duck with those words.
(all laughing)
- Well, rubber, that'll be good.
- Yes, put that rubber duck under your ass.
- Yeah.
- To avoid lightning.
- Well, Dan, why have you got a rubber duck
up your ass?
(all laughing)
- I tell you, I was in the bath.
It was raining outside.
(all laughing)
- You're coming too careful.
- They invented the happy or not buttons.
- The happy or not buttons.
- Oh, so when you're in an airport
and you go through security and you have to say,
did I have a good time or did I have a great time?
(all laughing)
There's like some little faces
and you press one under.
- Exactly, that's a finished person,
which I think is interesting
because they're known for being quite deadpan,
although they're always also found
to be the happiest country in the world, confusingly.
But yes, it was a finished guy
who invented them,
marvelous and bad customer service.
And they've just been hugely kind of revolutionary
for customer service in a lot of places.
- Have they?
- Yeah, because it changes how the staff acts.
So Heathrow was their big break in 2012,
called this finished guy.
They said, can we have a couple of these or try them out?
They got nine.
Within, I think within two days,
Heathrow called the finished guy back and said,
we need to shed loads of these right now
'cause the staff insecurity had gone from being kind of sullen,
occasionally a bit rude or just blanking customers.
- Could I just say, for the next time I go through Heathrow,
I've always found them to be lovely.
- Yeah, see, they instill this kind of fear in people.
- Did this guy invent it
because him and all the rest of the finished people
hate small talks so much
that they're like even a machine
to ask that basic question is what I would prefer?
- It could be, I actually thought it might be related
'cause it's so quick and you don't need to do any kind of
interacting at all, yeah.
But it does make the staff, I think that's really interesting.
Subconsciously, as soon as you're aware,
that button's there for people's satisfaction to be logged.
The staff give a little gag and they'll actually--
- Can I ask a question about those?
I know you're not the expert in them
and you've only read this thing, but--
- It's been about three and a half minutes
reading about them actually, so there we go.
- So when I walk out of security
and I've gone through really quickly
'cause I'm a good person who takes my belt off
before I go through and--
- Trousers down your ass.
(laughing)
- You're showing your phone number
to all the security people.
- Let me put the rose rubber gloves on you.
(laughing)
And I press the smiley button
and I press it like 10 times
'cause I had such a good time.
- Yeah.
- Does that count as 10 or do you think it doesn't?
- Well, James, as the three and a half minutes,
well, I do know the answer to that.
There is a little time restriction on it,
which means that, for instance,
staff or you can't cheat it,
so you can't log lots and lots in a row quickly,
but you could keep coming back.
You could go get your cost to come back.
- While you were saying that,
all I could picture was what would it be like
to get gloved at an airport?
I could see my session ending with them going,
"Okay, there's nothing there.
You're free to go, Mr. Shriver.
Here's your rubber duck by the way."
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
Okay, that is it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on @Shriverland on Instagram, James.
- My Instagram is @NosageThingsJamesHarkin.
- And Andy.
- I'm @AndyHunterM on Twitter.
- Yep, and if you want to get to us as a group,
where do they go, Anna?
- We're @NoSuchThing on Twitter
or @NoSuchThingAsAfish on Instagram,
or you can email podcast@QI.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
Check it out.
All previous episodes are up there.
You can get a link to our secret club, clubfish.
There's a Discord, there's bonus episodes.
It's really great.
And you'll also find the link
to all the upcoming tour dates for our Thundernur Tour,
which is beginning very soon.
So have a look at the list,
see if we're coming to a city near you
and come and join the dorkery.
Otherwise, just come back next week.
We'll be back with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)