- They don't want it, they don't want it.
(playful music)
- Hi.
- Hey Andy, how's it going guys?
- It's going well, thank you.
- How are you guys?
- Just in a really good show with Maddie Motte.
- Yes, and that'll be out before long.
- Yeah.
- But for now, welcome to Drop us a Line.
Our audience feedback show is Drop us a Line.
- We all knew this was coming.
(laughing)
- I knew when you sent the email the other day saying,
"Guys, we need to do an episode of Drop us a Line."
That's when I first knew.
- Can you please put your fingers out
and start fabricating some emails for me to read out
in a music way?
(laughing)
Thank you everyone for listening
and for watching Drop us a Line.
The inbox is bulging.
- Beautiful.
- It's full of your fantastic correspondence,
which has been flooding in to podcast@qiu.com.
- So Wednesday afternoon.
- Yeah.
- We're in Central London.
- Yeah, in the QI office, as we always are.
- Yeah, I'm just trying to set the scenes.
- Yeah, nice.
- This is James, I'm Dan.
- I'm Andy.
- Yep.
- I think the scene is set.
- Start of February, in 2026, yeah.
- AD.
(laughing)
- I think everyone's had the context they need.
- No, that's it.
- That's it.
Let's get to the emails.
- Just a quick, fun name to start.
Thought that'd be nice.
- Okay.
- And the correspondence are...
- Actually, he has got a great name,
but he's written in about another person
with a great name.
- Rob Shanks.
- Great name.
- Right.
18th century MP, Gregory Turner was a noted book collector.
And when his great uncle, Sir Gregory Page,
died without any children,
Gregory Turner inherited the estate,
but he was required to take on the name.
So he became...
- Yep.
- Beautiful.
- Sir Gregory Page Turner.
- It's good.
- That's really good.
- Who was the correspondent called?
- Rob Shanks.
- Sense his name.
- I'm gonna rob your Shanks.
(laughing)
- Shank is a verb in golf.
- Oh, is it?
- The bit where the shaft hits the head is called the huzzle.
And if when you hit the ball,
you accidentally hit the huzzle,
the ball goes off in a weird direction
and it's called a shank.
- That's really good.
So Rob Shanks.
Brilliant.
- Very good.
- Well, he points out, if you are a book collector
and you then become a Gregory Page Turner,
is this a rare case of determinative nominism?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It's good.
- Really good.
- Very strong.
- We're off the blocks.
- Yeah.
- Rick Romalli.
- Right.
Now don't worry, you're gonna get deja vu when I read this out.
- Okay.
- Just thought you'd want to know that Northwest,
which is in Southeast North Carolina,
is due east of due west.
Exactly as one would expect.
- So we did have a very similar fact a few weeks ago.
I don't think it was exactly the same.
- No.
We mentioned two places that are both in South Carolina.
Right?
But this fact, I've written it down to explain.
We mentioned Dew West, which is in South Carolina.
- Okay.
- And it's relationship to another place in South Carolina
called North.
- Yep.
- A North is southeast of Dew West,
but they're both in South Carolina.
But this fact is about a place in Southeast North Carolina
called Northwest, which is due east
of South Carolina's Dew West.
- No questions.
- Okay, no questions.
- That's very complicated.
- I think I made it pretty clear.
- No, you did.
- It was good.
- It was very good.
- Should we have another?
- Yeah.
- Caitlin Foukes.
- Yep.
- Arguably.
- Yes.
- She points out she is sort of a sentence person.
(laughing)
- She says, "Am I disqualified due to the necessity
for a humorous mispronunciation?"
- Caitlin.
- Not on this show.
- Welcome.
(laughing)
- Caitlin writes, "I was listening to the latest drop
"as a line, and as so often happens,
"James' face blindness was mentioned.
"I was thinking that, of course,
"though he can't picture himself or anyone else,
"he will know things like,
"James has curly hair."
- What's a terrible example?
- That's such a bad example.
- I no longer have curly hair.
- Listeners, James no longer has curly hair.
But Danway's glasses, or Caitlin says,
and he looks like a stickman.
Very funny Caitlin.
- Very true.
- So this naturally made I think of a cool game.
The game is Guess Who.
- My suggestion is that you make James play Guess Who,
but entirely with the most important people of his life,
in his life.
He has a picture of the person,
and all the little tiles have names.
He spends the game trying to work out
which of the people he loves his faces he's looking at
using only memorized propositions about their appearance
and yes, no questions.
- I can mostly do that in fairness
of people I know really well, I can recognize them.
Due to the fact that I know my wife has a fringe.
- Exactly.
- I'm on there.
- James, once you said to me,
hey, was Fonella at this very random train station
on this day at this time?
And I was like, I happen to know that she was.
And you recognized her from, she was in the distance.
You were with Paulina.
You recognized her from her walk as she was walking away.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
She also had a head in the hands going,
and that fucking damn.
(all laughing)
- I keep telling her to stop doing that, public.
- That's too obvious.
- That's interesting.
Yeah, I can recognize people's gate quite well.
- You should work for the CIA.
- Should I?
- Who's to say you don't already?
- Uh-huh.
- Well, they do complicated things like that, don't they?
- Do they?
- I don't know.
- Ask him.
(all laughing)
- That's exactly what someone working for the CIA would say.
- Very good point.
(all laughing)
- Seems like, I mean, one of us doesn't work for the CIA.
- I don't love the CIA.
- But it's always the one you least expect, isn't it?
- Guys, can we just drop the pretence?
This has been a CIA podcast for 12 years.
- Right.
- It was a thick, thick dossier about each of us
written by the other two.
(all laughing)
- And, of course, runs the CIA.
Tony Elmquist says, "Hi, guys, writing this in real time
while listening to "Drop us a Line."
"Danic Dotes."
That's the show.
That is all.
- Just my stories.
- I think so.
- Right.
- "Danic Dotes." - Good.
- Yeah.
- I feel like that's your BBC One Primetime show,
where you and my guests on and simply tell things about your life.
(all laughing)
So I asked them a question, and before they answer, I say,
"I tell you why I ask." - This is the show.
- Yeah, that's what the show's called.
- I tell you why I ask.
- No, it's called "Danic Dotes." (all laughing)
- That's how we got here in the show. - That's how we got there.
- Okay.
- No, no, no, I'll tell you why I ask, is good.
But I think that can be your cat phrase
within the show, "Danic Dotes."
- Yes. - I think that's a genuinely
a funny idea for a show.
- Okay, well, good suggestion.
- Good suggestion. - "Danic Dotes."
- Good suggestion, as a show. - Thank you.
- "Jamison Davies" sends in,
fun little bit of bonus "Bream."
It's my new name for the extra-fact bit.
- Bonus "Bream."
- Can you think of another fish beginning with "B"?
- Baracuda. - Baracuda.
- "Burnus Bass," "Burnus Baracuda."
Yep, those are both good.
And maybe this format...
(all laughing)
Maybe this bit will evolve over the next few weeks.
- Yeah, yeah. - Yeah.
- "Jamison" writes in.
I'm sure a lot of folks will write in about this.
I don't know how to tell you, "Jamison," you're the first.
Almost never when someone says,
"I'm so sorry, I'm probably troughing through
like 40,000 emails about this."
They always are the only one who's sent to the Zen.
- Yeah. - But as a New Yorker,
I have to point out the best building height related pun.
- Oh yeah. - Oh, okay, you said.
- This is to do the fact that we did a fact
when Olga Hock was on, which was all about in Japan,
height of its tallest tower, the sky tree.
- The sky tree is the exact same number
as a pun of the old area it's from.
- Okay. - Well...
- It was one of those in New York.
- It was one of those slap bang.
One world trade center.
- Oh yeah. - It's only one meter high.
- That's right.
But through an incredible optical illusion,
they made it look massive.
No, formerly known as the Freedom Tower.
It was made to be 17, 76 feet tall.
Referencing, of course, when we declared independence
from you lot.
- And how's it going?
- Sorry. - Sorry.
We've got a new in real life bit.
- Great. - Okay, remind me what that is.
- We've spoken about a subject.
Someone in real life has experienced that subject.
And so they can report back on it.
- Well, Francis O'Donnell has been living in real life.
Love the show.
I listen to every podcast most more than once.
- Every podcast.
- Every podcast we've made.
- I think everyone we've made.
- Okay.
- Could not believe you were talking about Pete and Bogs.
- Oh yeah.
- I am one of these people who heats my house with Pete.
You're one of the two percent of people in Ireland.
- That's right. - Yeah.
- When my dad bought the land for my house in Connemara
and I was speaking part of Ireland,
we were given a piece of land in the bog
that we were free to take Pete from.
We call it turf.
My grandfather used to cut his turf by hand
with a special long shovel.
Nowadays it's done with massive machines.
As is everything in this industrial world.
(laughing)
- Well, not in the digital world that we live in.
- In the digital world.
- It was slightly beyond the industrial world.
Some might argue.
- We are, we are, we are, we are.
- I'm sure the people of Ireland are as well.
(laughing)
- No, that's not what I was, oh my God.
- No, I'm the bad guy.
And he adds, Francis adds, just FYI,
there is still heaps of Irish whiskey made using Pete.
In fact, I've had pizza made with Pete instead of wood
and let me tell you, it tastes awful.
(laughing)
- Pizza, is it spelled that way as well?
- It's not.
- Oh, what?
- It should be.
- Come on.
- I think it tastes so bad that no one known as bothered
even using that slap obvious name.
- Oh, that's great.
- Pizza is crying out to be made.
Will Taylor writes in about another of Dan's secret lives
revealed.
- Okay.
- I'm a Brit living in New York.
I have been listening to your show since basically
the beginning and I enjoy the show even more now.
I live abroad as it's a little connection with home.
- Oh.
- I'm sure I look a little weird giggling to myself
while walking about town with the podcast in my ears,
but if there's one place in the world
where no one cares how mad you look,
it's New York City.
(laughing)
- This is relevant, I'm setting the scene.
- Yeah.
- I normally leave out the bits,
we will say how marvellous we are.
- What year did he write?
- This year?
- AD.
(laughing)
AD, so I'm just...
- AD, just setting the scene.
- Absolutely.
- I was listening to last week's show
while walking into the office.
I nearly fell over when I walked right past Dan
just as he was talking in my ears about fish being
the number one comedy podcast.
A closer look revealed it was not Dan IRL,
but an advert on the bus stop.
It turns out Dan is moonlighting
as a D or model.
(laughing)
- As you can see in the attached photo,
it definitely is Dan, even if he tries to deny it.
Over to you guys.
- Okay.
(laughing)
- I mean, it's just another generic.
- Do you know what these...
- It's uncanny.
- I have a family WhatsApp with all the Shribers,
the ones in Austria's, the ones that live in different countries,
and there's a constant thing where it's known as Hot Dan,
where scene Hot Dan again, it's getting a lot of work,
and I'll always get sent things like this.
- Yeah. - Hot Dan.
- Hot Dan is thriving.
- The specs, the hair, the frown, the beard.
- The frown.
(laughing)
- It's got, it's got the frowning.
- The slightly constipated look.
(laughing)
- The dribble.
- Yeah, it's you.
- I do see the similarity.
But, I guess who this guy came up, you'd say it's Dan.
- In context, if we were on tour, in Australia,
and we were just arrived at the theater in Brisbane,
and I walked through the door,
and that person came over and said,
"Oh, James, you're here.
"I would assume it was you."
- Okay, I would do a show with this guy.
- No problem.
- I would like to.
- If I had a context, I think if not in context,
I wouldn't recognise either of you, but I think...
- I'd say, Dan, you're looking really well.
You've been using that cream I gave you, whatever.
- You've got a little bit of dribble just on the side.
- No, he's cleaned off the dribble, wow.
- Dan's had his host this morning, hasn't he?
- Let's do a tour where there's always a different me
on stage before I come on,
but I'm not gonna tell you guys which shows it's happening.
So it's like two or three times over a 12-show tour,
and see if you notice it.
- Well, is that guy for the Muppets?
(laughing)
- Guy smiley sitting on stage.
- Hot Dan.
- Hot Dan's on stage.
- Well, as your hot Dan's, poke us to qi.com.
Let's live and up that inbox a bit.
(laughing)
Brilliant, so thank you, Will.
- Hey, I did a bit of real life this week.
- Tommy.
- Would you mind if I mention it quickly?
- I was... - That like that?
- A Danic joke.
- So I was in it.
- Anyway, ask.
(laughing)
- I went to a brilliant second-hand bookshop
that I always go to called Michael's Books.
It's in Ramsgate.
Absolutely love it.
And I went to get my bus,
and I could see in the distance the local weather spoons.
And a thing that came up in my head was,
I wonder what the closest table to the toilet is.
(laughing)
Because we mentioned on the last drop of the line,
the, as part of the top trumps cards that they make,
one of the options is closest steps to the toilet.
- So is this someone in Ramsgate, sorry, Mark?
- In Ramsgate.
- The giant one, right?
- The giant one in Ramsgate.
- So I imagine you approached you else,
the Matrix D, good evening.
Yeah, I'd like a table for one, please.
- Yeah, the toilets.
- I assume all the tables will be taken in that area,
but if you have something close.
- You slip in with 20, you say,
there's anything you can do for me to get me close
to that toilet.
- Yeah.
- So I went in, I went upstairs,
I found the closest table to the toilets,
sat down with my pint of ruddles, and-
(laughing)
- Oh my God, that's all I think is stealth, Mark.
- I should have said, we walked into this, James.
We walked smack into it.
- I didn't drink ruddles,
I just had an orange juice lemonade,
I'm not drinking at the moment, so it felt a shame.
- Damn, it felt a shame.
- Sonella doesn't listen to this show,
you can tell us how many pint of ruddles you had.
And so I sat there, and so I now know
how many steps it takes to get there.
- Okay, are we gonna have a guess?
- Yeah, why don't you have a guess?
- I think it would take 70 steps.
- 70 steps.
- 'Cause they are usually a long way from the seats.
- And Dan does walk with tiny little steps.
- I do, I do, because leaving a trailer dribble
behind me is like a snail, like a slug.
- No, but I presume that if you're going to the Lou,
you'll have taken down your trousers first as a precaution.
So naturally your steps are a bit smaller, aren't they?
- Or we've been to the pub together before,
that is exactly how I do it.
(laughing)
- So 70 steps, I'll say, I'll do a classic down,
I'll say two million.
- Okay, I'll say 150.
- 150.
- So from the closest table, from the closest table,
I know what's gonna happen.
It took me 15 steps, however, I know what the official number is
because while I was ordering my lemonade and orange juice,
I discovered that you can also buy six pines of ruttles.
- Oh, the top Trumps cards for the weather spins.
- Wow.
- And so it's officially 22 steps.
And I thought, okay, well that must be the least amount
of steps that you can get there.
- This is amazing.
- Well it turns out that there's a lot of these pubs
that two steps it requires to get to the pub.
- I can understand that.
- Okay, well can you--
- A lot of weather spins have an open drain
around the edge of the room though.
- Yeah, and you can just pop over there.
- What makes sense?
- I actually, as soon as I walk through the front door,
I pull my pants down, my ankles.
- You've got to mark your territory.
That's the thing.
Dan, I'm so impressed that you bought these.
- I wouldn't have, but the proceeds go to charity.
- These aren't as--
- They're very boring.
- They're very boring categories.
- Very boring.
- These can be judged.
- One interesting thing is on the back,
I said, oh, you could have different carpets on there.
In actual fact, they've got the Ramsgate weather spins.
- Yes, your Ramsgate one, isn't it?
- I suppose that's the flagship one.
It's the largest in the fleet.
- But let me tell you one extra thing
that happened on the way in.
- As I walked in, there's a big bookcase
of free books that get given away.
I naturally, anywhere I walk, if there's free books,
I walk up to it.
So I walk up to it and I see this book sitting there.
The spoils are played by Jesse Eisenberg of Now You See Me.
So I'm now sitting upstairs with my Jesse Eisenberg book.
- What is going on?
- Mapping out the steps and I open up the book.
- Oh my god.
- And it is a signed edition of Jesse Eisenberg.
- And we recognize that signature
from the Now You See Me signed card.
- My now collection of Jesse Eisenberg signed memorabilia.
- Yeah, so there's something going on here.
I don't know what it is.
- I genuinely felt as if you had come down to Ramsgate
and left this book in there.
- But that was the way of forcing that card
into your hand.
- Honestly, I think it's not much for Foss
to put Jesse Eisenberg book in dance local Roodle Center.
- No, who's gonna pick that up?
- That book's not seeing any other figure prints on it.
- I've sat this up three years ago.
- He's been sat in that pub.
- Oh, a play by Jesse Eisenberg.
- Can't believe this didn't leap off the shelf.
That's amazing.
That's so funny.
- Yeah, so a little adventure.
- Really good.
Victoria Keen has a little correction for us.
I wonder if it's a full-harkening,
but we were slightly insensitive about something.
- Oh dear.
- Well, judge for yourself.
- Long time listen to here and I'm so sorry to write in.
I was listening to not one,
but two recent drop-as-align episodes
where the procedure to turn a breach baby,
so where the baby is the wrong way,
and it needs to be turned.
It's called external cephalic version,
like, you know, inversion, reversion, you know,
turning, cephalic has in the head.
- Right, okay, yeah, I got it.
And externalism on the outside, yeah, right, right.
Was described as a massage.
I felt compelled to write as it is absolutely not a massage.
- That's painful as hell.
I've had two breach babies turned by ECV,
and as any person who's been through it will tell you,
it is highly uncomfortable.
They offer gas and air during the procedure.
That's how painful it is.
- Can I say I've had one massage in my life
and I was very uncomfortable as well.
- So actually, Victoria, James has his own cross-to-bear.
- Yeah.
- And did she go horse riding afterwards?
- I don't think so.
Poor man.
So, you know, she just says it was uncomfortable,
but definitely worth it.
She's not trying to put anyone out.
Was it work brilliantly for her medical procedure, yes,
but a massage, absolutely not.
Apologies, Victoria.
We stand corrected.
- I really like that as part of that fact
about how the baby turns around,
is that something I always say to someone
if they're expecting their first child,
when they're holding the baby,
always tap the baby's bum with a rhythm of a heartbeat
because their bum will have been right next to the heartbeat
in the final stages of the pregnancy,
and that's where they feel most comfortable,
like they're back in the womb.
So just a little bum, do-dum, do-dum, do-dum.
- And how do you do it?
- 'Cause I remember you doing it.
- And this is medically.
- Dr. Shriver.
- Yes.
- Stands other bright-dive BBC show.
(laughing)
There's a strange man in here, tapping baby's bum.
- How long does this bum tapping soothing affect last?
'Cause I remember you telling it to me.
- My, my mum still does it to me, Jaly.
(laughing)
- That's, considering she's in Sydney, that's...
- She has a surrogate, it comes over.
- She has one of those, you know, those hands
that was invented by what she called?
- Margaret Atwoods.
- Margaret Atwoods for signing things remotely.
She's got one of those for tapping thumbs.
- Good Lord.
- I don't know.
- Two weeks, Andy?
- Oh, I think it lasts.
- Okay.
- Tom writes in, "Right, we've got a fish fight."
- Cool.
- And that's not the title, obviously.
(laughing)
- What do you mean?
Is this a new section?
- It's a new section.
- What's the theme?
- We've got two people writing in saying
almost completely opposite things about the same subject.
- Okay.
- Which I love.
- Yeah.
- It just goes to show.
- It would be a very boring world if we were all alike.
- What about argument, Connor?
- Can it be fished up a bit?
- Um.
- Fight.
- Rao.
- Rao, Rao.
- Rao, Rao, your boat.
(laughing)
- I'm writing it down.
- I didn't need to write Rao three times.
That's eating up our time, isn't it?
- Okay, Rao, Rao, Rao, your boat, brilliant.
- Tom in the blue corner against Colin Aspery
in the red corner.
Tom writes, "Loving the new episode,
no such thing as de-bredsion."
- Colin says, "I hate it."
(laughing)
- But a minor correction to Andy's comments
about fight-a-pilots in the Tokyo section.
Do you remember I said fight-a-pilots
can move their eyes independently?
- Oh yeah.
- Yes, Tom says it's a patchy helicopter crew
who need that eye independence
because the helmet they wear includes,
I'm just gonna read this directly because it's bizarre.
The helmet includes a molecule that tracks
where the eye is looking and this molecule
can be slaved to the 30 millimeter gun
underneath the helicopter for targeting.
This way, the gun can simply look at the target
to aim the weapon, which makes things faster and easier
than some kind of handheld system.
- Yeah, clever.
- So you're right eye, just look at something,
and then you fire?
- Yeah, right.
- That's nuts.
- Yeah, that's interesting.
But what if you get it mixed up?
- What do you mean?
- What if you forget the eye?
That's doing it, you know what I mean?
- Both eyes are gonna be looking
in the same direction, generally.
- Oh, that's the point though.
- Oh, so you got independent eyes?
- I think the right eye, let's say,
is the one that's wearing the molecule,
which is, you know, wired up to the gun.
What if you accidentally use your left eye
and you look down at the end of the sandwich
so then you blow up your own sandwich?
- These people are very highly trained.
- Time to understand that.
- They've cut to go through years and years and years
of training, even just to fly the helicopter,
let alone be in these terrible situations
where you're in a dogfight against an enemy.
- Yes.
- You can blow you up at any second.
- Probably they know which eye is which.
- And probably it's not a time for sandwiches.
- No.
- Yeah, I hear you.
- Okay, it sounds like you're in Colin's corner.
(laughing)
- Yeah, I hated the show as well.
- Right.
- Colin, Asbury, or to give him his full title,
"Major, Loki, Asbury, US Air Force."
- Here we go.
- What does that mean?
Is it an is that a code name?
- I think Loki is a call sign.
- Oh.
- L-O-K-I, like the God of mischief though.
So who knows if he's telling the truth.
- That's true.
- Let's assume he is.
Colin says it might seem like fighter pilots
are looking at multiple things at once,
but actually that's not quite correct.
I am a fighter pilot for the US Air Force.
I was stationed in England at Lake and Heath.
- Yeah.
- When I happened upon the podcast,
and we use what is called a composite cross check
to keep track of all the screens and gauges and everything.
So you need to always be watching a few things,
and that's the hub where you're always looking at,
and then there are other sensors and screens
which are kind of out on spokes away from the hub, right?
So your eyes never really split,
but if I want a younger pilot to be looking at two things at once,
I tell them to lobster eye.
- Lobster eye.
- Yeah, implying they should look at two things at once,
but it's just not possible.
So you shift your hub a little bit to a new bit of equipment,
and now you need to look slightly differently
to keep your eyes on the flight instruments
keeping the planes upright.
- So it seems like vice pilots don't do this
possibly Apache pilots do?
- It sounds like that is exactly right.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- So it wasn't much of a fight.
- No, two separate points were made.
- And they both were against what you said.
This was a vice pilots do.
- Okay, so we're going to rename it two separate points
well made.
(laughing)
- Your boat.
- Really good.
Right.
- Okay.
Do you remember we talked about that Joan of Arc chapel?
- Yeah.
- It was, they picked it up in France
and they dropped it off in Wisconsin.
- That's exactly right.
- A couple of emails are coming about this.
Mark Lee says, "I was listening to your recent podcast
about this church in Milwaukee
that Joan of Arc prayed in.
In a similar vein, the cottage that kept in cook
of explorer fame grew up in is in Melbourne, Australia.
A place he himself never visited.
- I'm gonna stop you there, says Andy.
(laughing)
- I'll see why I read this email up.
- We happen to know that you've been to that place.
- I've been to that place.
I've been to that cottage.
- Yeah.
- And I think it's his parents cottage.
So it's a cottage that I think he never lived in.
And it's a place that he never went.
- Okay.
- It's basically karaoke at this point.
You're just the same thing that you're saying.
- I've got it.
- You tell the anecdote.
- Just like to say, I got in trouble for saying
that I'd been to this cottage last time.
We had correspondents saying you're a bad
sort of colonialist basically.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I only went because I like old stone cottages.
- Yeah.
- I'm not trying to fly the flag for Captain Cook far from.
- Have you got any anecdotes you want to tell
in the next episode of Drop us a Line?
If we know what they are now,
people could send in emails that can post you
in that direction.
(laughing)
- Well, you know I've only got two or three.
So it'll be one of the other two.
- Yeah, yeah.
- If you've got anything to say about
the judge lays it be then doing that one.
(laughing)
- Oh dear.
Well, Mandy Tothil, I think,
sends in this fact about the Joan of Arc Chapel,
which sadly, it's not as good an email
'cause it doesn't bring me on to home turf.
She says, "I was excited to hear this fact just now.
The Joan of Arc Chapel is on the campus
of the Jesuit University I attended, Marquette.
We had a campus legend priest who performed mass
every Tuesday night in the chapel for decades.
He was also a professional clown."
- That's great.
- That's good.
I was just thinking a clown priest is a good idea.
- Clown priest.
- You know?
- Yeah.
- Did you know?
(laughing)
- No, Andy's got a joke here, that one.
- Oh, come on.
(laughing)
- I'm sorry.
- Why do you think he's reading this out?
- I don't know if he's read a joke
that will come at me at this section.
- Idiot, please.
- So you hear me out, right?
(laughing)
- My show, my show is going to be called Hear Me Out,
where I'm desperately trying to get a word in.
While Dan is in the studio next door.
- So I'm showing the listings, we'll have to say,
not a repeat, just similar anecdotes.
(laughing)
I've seen this episode, I don't know.
- Okay, go on, what's the joke about clowns and priests?
- It's just a funny idea, a clown who's a priest.
- Because you're taking the blood of Christ.
- Oh, Squirt, Squirty Flower, in your face?
- Yeah.
- You're doing confession, there are big shoes
sticking out of the booth.
- That's funny.
- It's funny.
- Come on, guys.
Don't let me die on my heart's out here.
Someone come up with something classy.
I tried to pivot away, and you too.
And he twisted the wind for a bit.
- Wow.
- That is bullshit.
- That is some bullshit.
(laughing)
- I bust my ass, going through these emails,
trying to find things I can talk about of the manquim.
And this is the things I get.
Three and a half years of grinding toil
through these mad emails.
- Which I love, podcast@ky.com.
(laughing)
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Yeah.
- Thank you, Mandy.
(laughing)
- All right, a few more.
I've been, I've got something wrong.
- I'll do it.
- Insigning up to do this show,
and no one appreciates my anecdotes.
- No, Shambeer Kant from South Africa.
So his big fan of the podcast.
I'm really embarrassed about this, guys.
I decided to look further into Lillie Allen's
crypto-mist fortune.
- Oh, yeah.
- So she was often hundreds of thousands
of Bitcoin to do a gig.
She would have been the wealthiest.
She would have been Newklier armed at this point.
She would have had so much money.
And there's a comment in a Reddit thread
that just points out that at the time we're talking about,
there were only 1.6 million Bitcoin mind.
And this guy Satoshi, who we think invented it,
owned nearly a million of the 1.6 million.
So there was only about six to 900,000 Bitcoin
in circulation, not owned by Satoshi.
So how could Lillie Allen be offered a third
of the existing free currency?
A quarter of the supply.
- So it seems unlikely that it was that many.
- It seems unlikely that it was that many.
- Who's it come from that story?
Was it Lillie Allen herself?
- She tweeted and then deleted the tweet
that she was offered hundreds of thousands
of Bitcoin to do that gig.
- Right.
- And someone else pointed out plot twist,
maybe Satoshi himself wanted to pay Lillie Allen
a quarter of all this currency to do one gig.
- Or maybe.
- 'Cause no one knows who Satoshi is.
- Yes, that's right.
- Lillie Allen.
- Lillie Allen is Satoshi.
- Trying to pay herself.
- Well, it's the second life.
- That's the second life.
- You see, this is why they signed us up to the CIA.
- Absolutely.
(laughing)
- Yeah, the line not in the CIA now.
I'm busy counting my steps at Weathers Foods
and you guys are, damn, yeah, we got it.
- I'm really big job for you actually.
- Yes, there's a Ruttles budget.
Don't worry.
- Ah, Inspector Schreiber, you're here.
- Yes, and what I've decided is that the murderer
could not have been Lillie Allen
because the toilet is two steps away from the table.
There is simply no way.
She could have reached it in time.
- But then again, is this your copy of Jesse Eisenberg's play?
- I've got to watch these films.
I've got to watch them.
- Got to.
- Right, Dan, you got something wrong.
Barry Sawtell has a get yourself off the hook.
On the most recent episode, Dan made the startling claim
that Paul Hogan was a rigger on the Sydney Harbour Bridge
as it was being built.
Given it opened in 1932, this is quite unlikely.
- Oh, as they were fixing bits.
- It's true that he was a rigger on the bridge
just sometime after it was built.
I suspect you will hear this a lot
from your Australian listeners.
We actually did.
We actually got this one.
- Oh, wow.
- We had about five people, Paul Hogan,
Truth is writing and saying.
- I work as a rodeo clown noise and not quite enough.
- I don't think it's quite clear.
The fence required to be a rodeo clown.
I don't think it's funny.
Think about a clown though.
- There was a priest once in Milwaukee.
(laughing)
- I believe that my photo is in the Sydney Harbour Bridge.
- Ah.
- Like museum.
- Yeah.
- The sort of like the hall of fame.
Yeah, as you walked through.
- Well, celebrities who visited.
- Yeah, yeah.
Because I did it.
- I went up there when we were in Sydney
and one of the guitar guides recognized me from fish.
And I think I got it for free,
which was really nice.
I offered to pay, but they,
- You're entrance.
- They gave me the entrance for free.
And then I had to do some,
I think I did something to camera.
And then they apparently put my picture up saying
I was in the celebrity hall of fame.
I don't want to go back because I feel what actually happened
is it went to somewhat a bit higher up
and they went, "This guy is not famous enough to go."
- I was in the hall of fame.
- Paul Hogan probably.
(laughing)
- I don't know.
- It's a very old black-and-white photo, of course,
'cause it was 1930 when you guys were working on it.
- I think it's like, yeah, it's just like,
"So let's see what to see it when you go past."
- I did see it, but I didn't recall who was in there.
- 'Cause you and I have been to another hall of fame, right?
- Yes, we have.
- In Brisbane.
- The Koala.
- The Koala Sanctuary.
- Yes, Lone Pine, Koala Sanctuary.
And there's a photo of me in James,
looking like we've just adopted a Koala.
We're both cradling in between us.
- I've seen that photo.
What that's up on there, a wall.
- I don't think so, but they have a wall.
- I don't remember Jimmy was in that.
Jimmy Carr was in that wall for sure with Koala.
- They had some properly famous people there.
We just had a picture taken with a Koala, and it was lovely.
- I got sent a photo the other day of us on a wall.
Now, do you remember when we released our vinyl?
We did a gig in Kingston at a record shop.
- Yeah, they took a, no, it was Beggar's Bankway, I think it's called.
They took a photo, Polaroid of us,
and we're still on the wall there.
- Oh, yeah.
- People actually go in and steal those
if they're people they like.
- We're the only photo on the wall, actually.
Big blank space around us.
- Oh, dear.
- Yeah.
- Right, guys, we've come to the end of the show.
Bye.
Right, that's it.
We'll be back in two weeks.
If there's anything that comes up for you in the meantime,
please email it to podcast@koa.com.
Dan and Andy.
- Yep, Dan and Andy.
- Yep, take it, bye.
James, anything to add?
- No.
- Right, right, see you next time.
Bye.
(upbeat music)