- Hi everyone, just before we start this show,
we've got an incredibly exciting announcement to make.
- It is so exciting, especially for people
who like to watch live comedy podcast fact shows.
- What a great description of our show, James.
It's like you've been rehearsing that for years.
Yes, we are going on tour to do our comedy live podcast fact
show. We are going all over the UK and Ireland
and we are then going to Australia.
- And then we are going to New Zealand.
- Indeed we are. When are we doing this?
I hear you ask. Well, we are starting off going to Edinburgh
to just perform the podcast in August.
- Yes. And then we will go to Bristol, Dublin, Glasgow,
Newcastle, Cardiff, London, Manchester.
We'll play all those places in the UK and Ireland.
And then we are going down under in November.
- Is that your attempt at almost doing an Australian accent?
- I pulled out of it at the last second.
- I think that was a wise choice.
- Well, we're going to go to Adelaide Perth,
Brisbane, Sydney, Melbourne, Auckland, Wellington
and Christchurch. But Anna, how do people get tickets?
- They can go to knowsuchthingsafish.com/fishtour
where you'll find links to any venue that you want to attend.
Or why not come to all of them?
- Why not? Indeed, I'll be at all of them.
- So will I.
- So, dude, come along to the show.
It's going to be so much fun.
We can't wait to get back on tour.
Come to those gigs. Come and say hi.
We'll see you there.
- Okay. On with the show.
- On with the podcast.
- Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber. I'm sitting here with James Harkin,
Anna Tyshinski and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in 1974,
thousands of swallows migrated over the Alps by train and plane.
- Wow. - But not automobile.
- This is amazing. Yes, it was 1974.
And there was bad weather all over the Alps.
And this meant that insects were quite hard to find.
They were dying and not being born.
And the swallows were getting really hungry and cold.
And this meant that they couldn't fly very well.
And bizarrely, it was the police in Zurich,
who for some reason drew attention to this.
- This is a crime against nature.
- Well, exactly. Yeah.
Not too much crime in Zurich at the time, I guess.
And so they said...
(laughing)
- Quickly qualify that because it's a hot place these days.
- Yeah.
And so they said these swallows are having a bad time.
And this thing was organized to fly them over the Alps
or take them by train and Swiss Air flew 10,000 of them.
- Oh, how interesting.
You see, when you said the fact,
I thought it was like just a normal swallow
was flying along and then jumped on a train.
You know, like sometimes animals jump on trains.
- Like pigeons. Yeah.
- Oh, don't open this.
- I know this was, I can't believe you've gone there.
- Or on planes or something,
but you're saying actual flights were put on.
- Yes, sorry.
- You can see, 'cause swallows, I guess, fly in formation.
So if one goes on a train,
I guess they'd all follow onto the train.
And that would just be a terrifying train journey
for a lot of passengers.
But no, flights were put on.
Swiss Air put on lots of flights.
And then lots more thousands, in fact,
were taken under the Alps or through a tunnel through the Alps.
- Where do they go to swallows?
- They were going to the Mediterranean
to get a bit warmer.
So they were flown to Nice, Marseille, Barcelona.
They got the train.
And yeah.
- It's very nice.
It's a very heartwarming story.
It's a lovely tale.
And I learned it from a heartwarming place,
which is a book that my mum got me years ago
called The Little Book of the Dawn Chorus.
It's made of cardboard, and it's about 10 pages long.
And each page is a big picture of a bird.
And then you press a button next to that picture,
and it makes the noise of that bird.
- Isn't it a children's book?
Doesn't sound like a grown-up's book.
- I think children probably enjoy it for the most part.
- Are you getting all of your facts these days
from bedtime reading to your kid?
You had "Goodnight, Moon."
- You had "Sweet Packets."
- "Goodnight, Moon."
- Oh, yours was "Goodnight, Moon."
Sorry.
- God, what was my "Sweet Packets" like?
- You said you found a fact on the side of a sweetie
that you were--
- Oh, my God.
- Your research has gone downhill a lot.
- It's a bit ropey, isn't it, actually?
Yeah.
- You do get birds going by ship all around the world.
- Okay.
- And that is more in what I thought the fact was.
In the flying along, they get a bit tired,
and they just sit on a ship for a while.
- No.
- And then they go on the ship for a bit,
and then they fly off again.
- That's clever.
- And we found out this because they put tracking signals
on birds, and they went,
"Well, this one started going really slowly,
"and exactly in the same direction as that tanker
"that we know goes in this direction."
- So funny.
- And so, yeah, apparently it is quite common.
If you get injured a little bit,
or if you're flying along and you get to a bit of turbulence
that you can't really fly through very well,
you might just drop down, go on a boat for a few days.
- That's so good.
- Nice.
- Fly off again.
- I saw a video the other day of it was either a hawker
or an eagle is giant, and there's a guy who's gliding,
and then it just perches on his frame
and just kind of like chills out for a second
to get a break and then goes off again.
It's the most insane footage.
- Do you think the hawk knows
that it's like a glider or whatever?
- I don't know.
- Or do you think it thinks it's a really big bird?
- Yeah.
- In which case, do hawks also land on really big birds?
- That was gonna be my next question.
Do they have resting stations on like, yeah, a flock of birds?
- And there's a blue tit on the hawk,
and then a butterfly on the blue tit.
- I guess you do that kind of
when you're flying in formation, right?
Because you're directly behind someone
and you're kind of hitching the lift
a little bit on the guy in front.
- A bit, but if you did climb
onto the back of the guy in front,
I think you'd be a noise.
- There is a theory that would work,
which is if you had flights, let's say from London to Zurich,
there were 10 flights every day, whatever.
If you were to get them all to go at the same time,
then you could have them flying behind each other,
like geese or like swallows or whatever,
and that would save us loads and loads of fuel.
- That's so cool.
- Oh, we're using the tailwind.
- Yeah, you basically, well, there's no turbulence,
it's like a slipstream.
- Yeah, sorry, slipstream is what I mean.
We're using the literally less air in the way.
- Yeah, and the only reason we don't do that
is because people like Dan are scared of flying.
- Yeah, I'm not on for it.
If the one in front breaks hard, then I'm going back a bit.
- If you put those air brakes on, that's okay.
- But what if you just, what if we were,
we arranged that all the sort of nervous people
get to go in the front plane, so they're fine.
- Oh, what if one of them, they're first?
- Oh, yeah, yeah, no, all right.
- Well, the sleezers go at the back.
- See, this is why it's not happening.
This is why, because people can't get along.
- But apparently we have the technology.
- That's a great idea. - That's a great idea.
- It's a really good idea.
- You don't have to leave at the same time.
- Yeah, that's a problem. - I think convenient,
sometimes you want to leave at different times.
- I think it's great.
I think I might have mentioned this before.
I would like it if you know when you're in,
if you're sitting in traffic in a car.
Right, technically, as soon as the light goes green,
it should be fine for everyone
to just jam on the accelerator to full, right?
- Yes. - Because as everyone accelerates,
the gaps also accelerate to the same amount.
- Yeah, yeah, but what about me reading my phone at the front?
(all laughing)
- That's what's called a New York second.
A New York, a New York second is the time
between the lights going green
and someone directly behind you beeping you,
the second it goes green to get me to move.
- Am I the only person who, when I'm sat second in line
and the other person hasn't noticed,
I don't beep and I'm just like,
you know what, I'm not gonna beep.
I'm gonna be a good citizen and I'm not gonna honk.
I'm gonna let them notice by themselves.
- How long does that last?
- Just for a friend. - Until it goes red again.
- Yeah, I don't think-- - I'll just let them do it.
- I think you might be the only person.
- Are you doing it if someone's behind you as well?
- Yeah. - Wow.
- No, I've never-- - Usually the person
behind me will beep.
- Exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So what you're doing is you're saving yourself
the effort of a beep because you know
that the person behind you will probably
get around to it. - I'm just following
the highway code.
- You're not supposed to be-- - No, you're looking at your phone
at the traffic light.
(laughing)
- That's not what you're supposed to use your heart for.
Tell people that lights have changed.
- No, that's true.
It's only if there's an imminent threat to life,
isn't it, that you're meant to--
- Yeah, to let someone know where you are as well.
- Right, yeah, yeah.
- So you are letting them know where you are.
You're saying, "I'm here and I'm not happy about it."
Birds.
- I feel like ab migration.
- What's that? - Ab migration.
- Ab migration.
It's basically when you're a bird
and you're migrating from one place to another,
but you accidentally join the wrong flock
and you just follow them to wherever they're going
and you end up in complete with the wrong part of the world.
- Oh, so they don't realize there's not a halfway through.
- No, until they get there.
- Yeah, right.
- Oh, shit.
- There's no one I can track here.
(laughing)
Does that really happen?
- It does happen, yeah.
- I, this is a very old fact,
but I discovered it's not on our show.
So I'm just plopping it in our show
'cause it's something we all know.
But in France, if your pet snail gets a train,
it needs its own ticket.
It has to pay for a ticket and it costs seven euro.
- Seven euro.
- Seven euro, which is, a dog is 20.
So--
- Do you think that's cheap?
- Well, it depends where you're going to.
But if you're going all the way from, you know,
niece to breast, seven euros is an absolute steal.
- But not for a snail.
- Well, how long is it gonna take to walk?
(laughing)
- I guess.
You're just so used to hearing about European trains
being so cheap and amazing and, you know.
Well, that's striking.
I mean, especially 'cause if you've got a few snails,
that'll rack up quite quickly.
Well, what I'm confused about is one person
is only allowed one animal.
So one animal per person.
So, right, I think you're only allowed
your favorite snail to come.
- You must be able to claim it's a wild snail.
If you just put the snail down next to you
and say, "It's nothing to do with me."
(laughing)
- Yeah, but then he gets kicked off for fair evasion
and then you've lost your favorite snail.
- He's like, "Anna, Anna!"
(laughing)
We've known each other for years!
- Honestly, it's a different Anna.
(laughing)
James, did you, sorry, I have to ask.
When you just used the example of going from niece to breast,
was it 'cause in your head,
you were saying the words, "Nice breast."
(laughing)
- Great question, great question.
- That's what I've assumed.
You've just got nice breast,
nice breast going through your head at all times,
and you thought, "I can use this."
- Genuinely, I thought of what is the most
southeasterly town and what is the most
north-westernly town I could think of.
And that was it.
- Okay. - That is good.
- Yeah, very strong.
- I have a link.
I have a link.
- Yeah.
- Patricia Highsmith, the writer.
- Oh, yeah. - Of the town of Mr. Ripley.
Didn't she keep pet snails?
- I think she would turn up places with them in a handbag,
and I think she would let them crawl around her.
- I think she hid some under her breasts
when she was going from one country to another,
so she didn't have to.
- Yeah, exactly. - Really?
- Oh, there you go. - Her nice breasts.
So there we go. - Yeah.
- We've come full circle.
- There we are. - And we have my train.
- Birds and trains.
- Yeah.
- So Japanese trains.
What's the first thing you think?
- Fast.
- Shinkansen.
- Exactly, you've all said the right thing.
- Fast. - On time.
- Shinkansen, bullet train.
No, no, no, stop.
- I know more.
- Well, fair enough.
There was a problem with the bullet trains, right?
They were very, they were fast.
That was great.
But they were causing these sonic booms
when they came out of tunnels
'cause they pushed the air ahead
and like a cork out of a bottle,
the air just pops out really loud,
hundreds of meters away.
It was so loud.
It was like miserable to live anywhere near these trains.
And they were on overhead wires as well.
And then the chief engineer who was called A.G. Nakatsu,
he was interested in owls and how owls move quietly
'cause owls have these little structures
on their feathers called fimbrii.
- They make like vortices and stuff.
- Exactly, they break down the air
into sort of micro-turbulances.
And he said to his team, "This is the future."
And every Japanese train has an owl strapped to the front.
That's right.
It's very cruel.
- And instead of a holland, they go, "Whoo-hoo!"
- So there are these wing grafts put on the trains
and then to deal with the train coming out of the tunnel
and having the sort of cork popping sonic boom effect,
he looked to kingfishers
'cause they dive into the water with no splash.
If you've ever seen a really slow image of a video
of kingfishers just dive again, no ripple.
So he changed the body shape of the front of the train
and they are quieter and they have less air resistance,
they use less energy, they cost less, they use less fuel.
- You know what birds also do, fly.
So he could have put wings on it.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, and it all came from that?
- Very cool.
- All the trains are based on birds.
- Basically birds.
- Oh, yeah.
- In China, they have a tunnel
that they're building at the moment for trains.
It's 12 meters across this tunnel,
but due to the movement of the Earth's crust,
it's shrinking and it's currently now
less than three meters across.
- What?
- Because the Earth's plates are squishing it together.
- Oh no.
- Isn't that amazing?
- That's incredible.
- Hang on, so this is a train tunnel
that was built 12 meters across.
- They're currently in the middle of building it.
It was supposed to be ready to go in like next year,
but they keep going back and it's smaller again.
- How can I be confusing?
Do you think you were unpunked or something?
You were like, what is going on?
This was massive.
- Are they gonna have to make the train
one of those very small novelty steam trains?
- Everybody off the big train.
Isn't that weird?
- That's so good.
- And they put loads of concrete supports in,
they just got smashed.
- Yeah, 'cause these are tectonic plates.
- Are they moving that?
I didn't know bits of Earth were moving that fast.
- Well, let me introduce you to Earthquakes.
- Nice.
- It's nice to meet you.
(laughing)
- But this is, yeah, I mean,
there are some parts of the Earth that are moving.
I mean, this is not like moving.
You can't see it moving.
- And they're still sticking with it?
They're not just gonna get a new mountain.
- I think what they're gonna do at the moment
is they're just gonna wait
and hopefully it's gonna stop moving soon
and then they're gonna be able to build it.
- Wow.
- Just predict, nearby.
- Well, hang on, hang on, hang on.
- All they need to do is wait long enough
and then the movement will go so much
that the tunnel will--
- Start making itself.
- It will reverse, exactly.
And it'll start getting bigger again.
'Cause all the concrete will have gone through
to the other side.
Do you see what I mean?
- That makes no more sense
with the accompanying hand gestures
that we can see than it does to the listener.
- Okay, fine, fine.
- Do you know the Snowdon Mountain Railway?
So for the broad listeners,
there's Snowdonia is the highest mountain in Wales
and has a train going up it,
which is kind of famous
'cause it's a way you can cheat to get to the top.
But did you guys know that it was built in the 1890s
and it's very first trip.
All the trains on it crashed
and out to close immediately for a year.
- Oh no, no.
- For a year.
- Yeah, 1896.
So there were two trains
that went on this inaugural journey.
They got off the top of Snowdon.
One was released to go down.
They completely lost control.
The engine of it derailed
and the driver and the guy
who was spooning coal into it or whatever,
both leapt off it.
- Shuffling?
- Shuffling.
- Spooning coal.
We can't get the power it's so in.
Use the dessert spoon.
Stop with the teaspoon.
- Oh, I thought differently.
I thought whether the conductor is in bed with coal.
Stop hugging that coal and get out here.
- Yeah, look, I don't work in the rail industry.
- Stoking.
The stoker and the driver
both threw themselves off the engine
just as it flew over a cliff
and hulled down onto the, you know, ground below.
- Wow.
- A few hundred meters.
And then the carriage is careering down on its own.
- Oh, my goodness.
- The rail.
So all these passengers are on the carriage.
- But ahead, there's a point.
And there are five people strapped to the track.
(laughing)
- There was actually, there was one,
there was a one death
because there was one guy on the carriage
who saw the driver and stoker leap off the engine.
So the guy in the carriage thought,
well, I better do that as well.
So he just threw himself out of the carriage
and sadly plummeted into his death.
- I know it's a use in the one who died, right?
- Whereas the rest of the carriages eventually slowed down.
- Once they entered a tunnel,
which gradually grew closer.
Riding them to a halt.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is Andy.
My fact is that in 1827,
a shop opened in Cincinnati
where the principal currency was time itself.
(laughing)
- I'm just remembering,
we only let you do this fact, didn't we?
Because we knew you would do that.
- Yeah, we wanted to see. - We wanted to see.
- Yeah, and you did.
- It's a good fact as well.
- Thank you.
This is a place called the Cincinnati Time Store
and it was created by a guy called Josiah Warren,
who was a utopian and a socialist.
And he would now be described as an anarchist,
but I don't think the phrase really existed at the time.
Basically, his idea was,
I'm going to sell things for what they cost me.
And the only thing I'm going to add to the price
is the value of the time I've spent on this stuff.
So he claimed basically labor
was the only true currency, if you like.
- So it's like the time of people coming into the shop
and deciding what to get,
the time of him wrapping it up,
the time of him weighing stuff,
the time of him bringing stuff from the back room
into the front light, all that kind of stuff.
- All of that, and it involves quite a lot of calculation.
And also, I love this,
the longer he spent with the customer,
the more it would cost the customer
because his time was worth money.
- So if I'm behind that customer
that's taking so much time,
(laughing)
do I have to pay less or?
- Yeah, they haven't noticed.
You're in your car, do you honk your horn?
Even though it's costing.
I think he had a timer dial
so that as he stayed in the shop for ages saying,
"Oh, I don't know if I want the big one or the small one."
- Yeah, it's sort of notch up because this is his time.
- It actually seems more aggressive
even though it's a utopian, cheapening thing.
- But he said that it went through so many customers
since such a quick amount of time
that he could shut the shop halfway through the day
because he'd done basically the full days
worth of money that he needed to earn.
- Yeah, which is pretty nuts.
You can't do that with a shop.
What if I want to get to the shop at 3.30
and they've just closed at mid-dig?
So they've gone, "We've had enough customers for the day."
- Well, go to like a square capitalist shop
and not to the utopian anarchist.
- That's fine.
He was also, and I don't think
this is how he'd like to be characterised,
but he was just like a modern day lawyer
in the sense of time, wasn't he?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause that's what you get with lawyers.
The more time he spent with them,
the more they charge.
You're having--
- And sex workers.
(laughing)
So you've got to rush through both, haven't you?
- I assume.
(laughing)
Never used a lawyer, so I'm not sure if that's the same.
For the first few days when he opened it,
he didn't have a single customer.
- Really?
- Yeah, and he asked his brother, George,
to come and make some purchases for his family.
- Clever.
- And then George came and told his friends
and then George's friends came.
And then in the first week,
he'd made $5 worth of sales.
- Is that a lot?
It was in the 18s, 20s, wasn't it?
- Even in those days, it wasn't enough to live off,
but it took off relatively quickly after that.
There was a guy who had another shop around McCona,
who kind of came in and said,
"You're putting me out of business, mate."
- Yeah.
- Oh, really?
- And he said, "Well, maybe you could show me how to do it."
And Josiah Warren, so I said,
"Okay, well this is what I'm doing."
And the guy copied his system.
- I think the idea is that time also
has a slightly variable value.
So nobody profits from anyone else's labor is the idea.
You don't get to just add a huge whack
to the amount of time you spend on something
because the time is the currency.
But also, if a job is harder or more disgusting,
I think it would be worth more time.
So for example, I love making the show.
So probably an hour and a half recording,
I will actually only get paid half an hour of time
because it's so much fun to do.
- We're responding to the emails that people send in.
How much would you--
- A quintuple, yeah, I'll make it back.
- That's why I get paid five times as much as you, isn't it, Andy?
I hate making this show.
So two hours recording, I actually get paid.
- Do you know why that was the case?
Because actually, this idea was not new.
But the reason that he had different amounts
of different people is because he'd previously been
in another utopia called New Harmony.
And at New Harmony, that had failed
because anyone who was good at like building houses
just decided, wait a minute, I'm getting paid the same
as the people who are doing something
which isn't skillful at all.
And actually, it all fell apart because of that.
And so he decided that his new utopias and new ideas
were gonna be slightly different
and have a slightly different thing
where different skills paid different amounts.
- So he took over this small little town
called Modern Times.
- The place is called Modern Times.
- It's called Modern Times, it's a name.
They had like 150 people who signed up
to the idea of living in this utopia.
- So that started off a bit dodgily
because he had this big group of people who were all utopians.
And then one of them began to advocate
for plurality of wives.
Another one believed that clothing was a superfluity.
So he didn't have to wear any clothes.
And there was another one who thought
that actually you shouldn't really eat properly,
you should just eat beans and nothing else.
- Oh no.
- And yeah, it was basically attracted all these people
who had all these different ideas outside of the mainstream.
And at the very start, it went really badly
and the newspapers were saying this is gonna be a disaster
but it did prosper in the end.
- Did it?
Even though it sounds like a load of farty naked sleazy men.
- They got rid of the farty ones and the sleazy ones.
- Okay.
- They got rid of the dwarfs.
(all laughing)
And then in the end it did falter
but it was because there was a huge panic
in the mid-19th century and then the civil war
and then that was where it fell apart.
- Yeah.
But it did according to their like press, you know,
it went for 13 years solidly.
They didn't have government, they didn't have law,
no police, but they didn't have any reported crime or violence.
- Well, if you've got no law,
you're not gonna have any reported crime.
- Yeah, that's just from supposedly the people.
- A naked man stole my third wife.
(all laughing)
- Josiah Warren also invented a lamp, time lamp.
Just a non-time lamp.
It burned over time, but again,
it had a utopian idea at its core,
which was to save people money.
So it was made of lard instead of tallow
and it burned much more efficiently.
But the good thing about this lamp
is that the patent for it was destroyed
in a fire at the patent factory in 1836.
- That's very funny.
Isn't that true of like the fire extinguisher?
- That's correct, it's the same fire.
- It was the same fire.
- Well, it was this huge, it was an incredibly famous fire
and there are these things called the ex patents,
which are the first 10,000 patents.
And I know I should be saying patents, sorry,
but the first 10,000 patents ever issued
and they were all destroyed in this fire,
this massive fire at the US patent office.
- It feels like there's a good plot for a movie
or something in there where they're rediscovered
actually that we've made copies.
- Yeah. - Someone made copies
and all these new technologies turn up.
- Yeah, the ex patent man.
- Yeah, that's quite good.
- That's excellent.
- He made a newspaper as well, Warren, in 1833.
So a few years after the shop,
for which he built his own printing press
and cast all the type himself.
He does seem to have been very practical, practically minded.
- He also invented a new kind of music.
- Did he, what was that?
- Wrap.
(all laughing)
- Gangster rap.
- No, it was called mathematical notation.
- Okay.
- And it was a way of using maths
as opposed to using do-re-mi-far-sol-r-t-do
was using numbers.
- How interesting.
He's described as an anarchist
and my impression of an anarchist is very different
to what it sounds like he was.
- What do you think of an anarchist?
- I guess an anarchist would be someone who's raising hell,
like suffragettes were being anarchists
when they were bombing places.
- And that's a metaphorical anarchist.
- Yeah, right.
- An anarchist would be just someone who doesn't believe
there should be any leaders in society.
- Suffragettes are very much not anarchist
'cause they wanted to actively get into the role
of electing leaders, yes.
- It's very weird.
So anarchism is, 'cause everyone calls for an anarchist,
is this big school of thought, exactly as James says,
it's not, we don't want leaders,
no sort of state structures,
people doing things for themselves and their neighbors
is the basic idea behind it.
But also there is a kind of extreme end of it
in the 1890s, it was a big worry across Europe,
the anarchists, who were mostly basically young men
throwing these kind of like classic bombs,
which are sort of big back black wool.
- Cherry bombs.
- Yeah, with bomb written on the side
and with a fuse sticking out of it
and throwing them at sort of elected leaders
or royals across Europe.
- Wiley Coyote.
- Yeah, it is like that, but it was a genuine fear
'cause that was the sort of extreme end of anarchism.
But President William McKinley,
one of the four presidents assassinated,
shot by an anarchist.
And his assassin was a guy called Leon Chogosh,
who was, this is very dark, this,
he was tried and executed.
And then his body was destroyed by acid
so that fellow anarchists wouldn't have a body to venerate
or to turn into a martyr.
So they literally poured acid into the coffin.
- Wow.
- Put it in the coffin, close the coffin up,
pour acid in, and then burned all his clothes
and possessions after that.
- Wow.
- I know.
- Don't do that again.
(laughing)
- And then we get the sex pistols,
kind of calms down the world of Anarchy, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- The illusion of an anarchist.
- If you buy it, if you buy a t-shirt of it,
it's not as anarchic as, yeah.
(laughing)
- I was looking into the idea of swapping money for time
and seeing if that's been used anywhere else.
And I found an example,
which is something that's been trialed in 2019 in Estonia.
They've had a huge problem with speeding drivers.
So people are speeding, they're getting tickets,
and then they are just paying the fine
because they can afford to do it.
And so in Estonia, they thought,
instead of giving them a fine,
what if anyone who's caught speeding
has to do a 45 to 60 minute timeout?
And now they're really late to where they need to go.
They have no choice but to do this.
- That's great.
- 57% of people actually said
they preferred the idea of having the timeout.
So the biggest problem they have is,
- Meanwhile, James has pulled in behind the guy
who's been stopped for speeding.
He doesn't mind.
(laughing)
- How are you policing that?
- This is what they're trying to work out
because it takes a lot of people
to have to sit there for an hour.
It's not practical, but it's a great idea
because no matter how rich you are, time is time,
you can't get past that.
- It's not practical, guys.
Well, what you could do is,
you could put some clamps on the car
and so they can't go anywhere
and then come back an hour later and take it off.
- But most speeders are called by cameras, aren't they?
Maybe out of every camera,
it could drop a sort of big net that catches the car.
- Yeah, that's much more practical.
- Yes, I'm a craxit.
- Hiring some unemployed people to do the same work.
Kind of like detention for grown-ups, basically.
- I have a related fact because it's about Estonia.
I was in Estonia relatively recently, last year in Tallinn,
and I went to the Museum of Banned Books.
- Oh, cool, yeah.
- So it's a museum, but it's also a shop.
You can buy books that have been banned from around the world.
And I asked for one particular book
and they had it hidden behind the desk,
as it wasn't on display.
Can you guess what the book is?
So they had every banned book from around the world.
And I said, "Oh, do you have this one?"
And they went, "We do, but it's behind the desk.
We're not allowed to put it on display."
Oh, we're not putting it on display.
- Is it a famous book?
Will you definitely have heard of it?
- It's famous, but whether you've heard of it,
I don't know. - How?
- I mean, it's very on topic from what we're talking about.
- Oh, okay, so a time-related thing maybe.
- Or an anarchist's book.
- The anarchist's cookbook.
- Correct. - Oh!
- The anarchist's cookbook is in the Museum of Banned Books,
but isn't on display. - Why not?
- Because it's so dangerous.
- What is it? - What is it?
- It's a way of making bombs, basically.
- Okay.
- Also making illicit drugs,
ways of freaking telecommunication devices.
So this was written by a guy called Powell,
whose first name I can't remember,
but anyway, he reneged on it when he got older.
It was published in 1971, and by 1976,
he'd converted to Anglicanism
and tried to get his book taken from circulation.
And in 2011, he and his wife,
Och and Kasuma Powell,
founded a thing called Next Frontier Inclusion,
which was a non-profit organization for children
with learning disabilities.
But he did that in a way to atone for this book
that he'd written, which he can't control
because he doesn't own the copyright to it anymore.
It's out there, and that's it.
- Did he do an anarchist thing with the copyright
or something, or did it just,
it just got out of there and it's been replicated?
- No, it was the amount of time
it just sort of went to the publisher.
- Silly boy, think before you publish.
- I really thought you were going to say
the book that you couldn't access, James,
was Tintin and the Soviets.
- Oh, that is true.
Like, I went to the Tintin shop in London
and they wouldn't, they would sell it to me,
but again, it was not on display.
- You have a knack of finding things behind the counter.
(laughing)
It's interesting.
You can work out what will most freak out any shopkeeper.
- But that they will own, you know.
- But they will own, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I was just looking at money,
the times when money's been abolished.
Do you know the only country to abolish money?
- Oh, I'm going to say Bhutan.
- Oh, I have some boots of these kinds.
- Okay, I'd like to change my choice to,
let's say a communist one.
- Yeah.
- Cuba.
- Oh, no, Angola.
- You've got the right,
and he's got the right first letter.
It's definitely less utopian than Bhutan.
- Columbia.
- Well, it's, I'm just going to tell you.
Same number of syllables.
- Begins with C.
- Yep. - Begins with C.
- All syllables. - Columbia.
- Oh, no, it's, yeah, same number of syllables.
Four syllables. - Four syllables.
- Cambodia.
- Very good.
- Under the Khmerz, was it?
- Cambodia, under the Khmerz, Pol Pot,
who decided to ban money in 1975 when he came into power,
and within three weeks, there was a new currency,
but then he decided that he didn't want a new currency,
so he blew up the central bank.
I mean, obviously he did some absolutely appalling things
alongside this, but yeah, blew up the central bank,
and money flooded through the streets,
and people were using it because Cambodia
was in a terrible state by that point because of them.
We were burning money for fire and warrants.
- How interesting, wow. - Because it didn't exist.
- When I was in Cambodia,
which I admittedly was quite a while ago,
you would really just buy stuff in dollars.
- Yeah, same, yeah.
Do you know the commonest denomination of US dollars?
- One dollar, it must be one dollar.
- Used to be, in 2016, it was replaced.
It's now the second most common.
- I'm going to go all the way, the thousand dollar.
- I'm going to go in the middle, the seven dollar.
(laughing)
- And you've gone too far into the realms of unreality.
- It's a hundred, it's going to be a hundred.
- It's a hundred, it's the hundred dollar banknote.
Isn't that insane?
A hundred dollar bills make up almost 80%
of the value of dollars worldwide,
and they are now the most commonly circulated bill,
and it's almost all held outside of the US.
- It's a lot of crime though, isn't it?
- It's a lot of crime. - It's a lot of art,
fraudsters, and drug money,
because it's large amounts of value in a relatively small--
- Still counts. - It's finicky to do that
with all one dollar bills, if you're paying for it.
- Yeah.
- Like 800 kilos of cocaine, and you're at the counter,
and the guy in front of you is paying him once.
It's annoying.
(laughing)
- James, just sitting there happily.
- You take your time, buddy.
- It's all right, I'm going to be buying this stuff
he has behind the counter.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the 2023 Nobel Prize
for Chemistry was won for discovering something
that has been used in stained glass window making
for a thousand years.
Glass, it was.
- Whoa. - Discovered that.
- It was a really late award.
- We didn't know where it came from before.
- No one knew what glass was.
- Amazing. - And then they were like,
"Oh, it's in all those windows as well."
No, it wasn't that.
It was Quantum Dots.
It was won by Maungi G. Bowendi, Louis E. Bruce,
and Alexei Ekimov, and they discovered Quantum Dots,
which are tiny, tiny particles.
You fire light into them, and depending on their size,
they re-emit light of a different color.
It's all due to this thing we call science.
(laughing)
Talking about that, and Quantum Science at that.
We don't need to really go into all that stuff today,
but scientists have looked at glass back
from the 10th century and found tiny bits of gold,
tiny bits of silver, and they act in the same way
that Quantum Dots act.
When the sunlight comes in, they enhance the red light
and enhance the yellow light.
- And it's the size of the Quantum Dot,
which are only, there are a few nanometers across,
and the bigger ones emit a different color
when light is fired at them than the smaller ones.
It's basically--
- It took quite a long time for me to understand it,
but there's a really good explanation in the article
that was sent by the American Chemical Society's president,
Judith Goyardun, G-I-O-R-T.
- Ironically, pronouncing her name is more difficult
than the Quantum Mechanics.
- Judith Jordan, and she says to think of it
like a little box, so basically the particle is the box,
and you have the electrons bashing off the sides
of the walls of the box on the inside,
but when you've got a big box, it's gonna take longer
for the electrons to bash into the size.
When the particle is shrunk down,
the electrons are bashing quicker and quicker,
and that's where it's emitting the different color, basically.
So it's to do with the size of the box
and the electrons smashing into the sides.
- It is hard, it's hard to understand.
- The thing is, they glow.
They're very exciting 'cause they glow,
and they're very colorful,
and the reason they've won the Nobel Prize
is 'cause they basically made television a bit better.
As far as I can tell.
- We're gonna have cool quantum tellies, QLEDs.
- QLEDs, and it's the same principle as a normal LED TV,
which is that light is shone from behind onto the dots.
They glow in different colors,
and you're watching your show
and you don't really need to think about it.
- But like if you think about an old computer screen
or something, you could only really get like blue
and yellow and magenta, like a printer.
You only get those colors, and to make any other color,
you have to mix them up in different amounts,
and you will be able to get a certain number of colors,
but these QLEDs can show you way more colors,
more colors than you could possibly imagine.
- Yes. - Yes.
- Like teal.
- Wow. - Incredible.
- I can't imagine that. - Now with teals.
- Incredible. - Yeah.
- And mauve.
- Yeah.
- Puce.
- And we should just say in defense
of the Nobel Prize-winning scientists
that they are used for other things as well.
They're gonna hopefully revolutionize the world of medicine
because you're gonna be able to spot the colors
on the inside of the body,
so they're gonna be used for diagnosing certain bits
of the body. - What?
- Yeah. - How do you mean?
- I don't know if you've explained that the right way,
it's spot the colors on the inside of the body.
- Do you mean send markers into the body
that can identify- - Exactly.
- It's like, "Oh, you've got a green liver.
You've got an orange pancreas."
- It's the leave to highlight spots
where you need to monitor and make sure that things,
and that's the opening application of it,
just on nanotechnology and medicine,
and this is another cool use of nanotech.
This is nano shells.
So these are hollow gold or silver spheres
wrapped around silica.
Okay, so I think they are hollow,
but they're two layers. - Okay.
- Like a Ferrero Rocher, but small.
But so small that you could eat lots and it wouldn't matter.
So if you fire light at these nano shells,
they heat up massively,
'cause they're made of gold and silver, right?
So the idea is, if you have someone who's got cancer,
you can inject the tumor with these nano shells,
then you fire infrared light.
Now, the light passes through the water in your cells
because the water in your cells
doesn't absorb much infrared light.
These nano shells absorb huge amounts of infrared light.
They heat up massively and it kills the tumor off, right?
So if you can, yeah,
and they're experimenting at the moment on raw chicken,
but the hope is that it'll make the leap
from raw chicken to people.
It's a really clever idea.
- Are they basically cooking chicken
by putting these nano dots inside it?
- Effectively, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- That's clever.
- Very cool. - That's really good.
- It's a good idea.
- Quicker cooking in better tellies.
- When Ekimov first came up with the idea of quantum dots,
he was working at the Vavilyev State Optical Institute
in Soviet Russia.
And he had got these special glass objects,
semiconductor glass objects, known as shot glasses.
- Whee!
- Sorry.
- Isn't that cool?
They were known as shot glasses
and they were lots of different colors
and he developed the theories to explain their color.
And the interesting thing about those shot glasses
is they were made by a company founded by Otto Schott.
Okay, and that company still exists
and they made 90% of the first one billion COVID vaccine bottles.
- Wow.
- So 90% of the first billion COVID vaccines
were delivered in shot glasses.
- Lovely, beautiful. - That's really cool.
- That's great, so funny.
- Ekimov, who you mentioned,
as you say, he was in Soviet Union in 1981
when he became, in fact, the first person, I think,
to generate these quantum dots and to identify them
and learn how to generate them.
But it's just one of those amazing things.
It's so weird how often you read about this,
I guess, when we do what we do,
things happening simultaneously.
It just shows how predictable a path humans are on, I think,
because is it Bruce?
Do you pronounce it, do you know?
- That's how I pronounced it.
- Cool.
- It could be brew.
- Brew, okay.
- Fancy a brew?
- Fancy a brew in your shot glass.
- Is that Scottish?
- Scouts, I think.
- I don't know, I don't know.
(all laughing)
At exactly the same time in America,
Louis Bruce was working on the similar thing
and he came up with it pretty much a year later, I think.
And the interesting thing was,
I hadn't realised at the Soviet Union,
if you did science there at the time,
it basically didn't get anywhere
because you had to publish it in extremely obscure journals
that no Western scientists were really reading
'cause it was all thought it was a bit backwards.
- And in Russian as well.
- And in Russian, which, you know, a lot of us can't read.
And so Bruce, a year or two later,
read this thing in a journal and good on him,
he read it and was like,
"Oh, that guy's done the thing I did a bit before me."
So got in touch with him, wrote him a letter to say,
"Shall we hook up?"
- A very, what?
That's, wow.
- Then they had a beautiful romance blast.
- Wow.
(all laughing)
- Amongi Balwadi, who was the third person
who won the Nobel Prize,
failed his first chemistry test at Harvard.
And he was specifically the chemist who came on board
to sort of make what the other two had discovered
become practically applicable.
And yeah, he did a speech recently saying,
he failed the chemistry test
and actually got the worst grade in his whole class.
And said, "That could have destroyed me,
"but I decided that it wouldn't."
And it was such a...
- I decided that it wouldn't.
- I decided.
And that's the lesson.
Good luck, guys.
There was like, there's a book about archery,
about the best way to be an archer,
like a really old one.
And the first line is, "First, decide to succeed."
- Wow, that's so good.
- That's awesome.
I really like that these three winners, by the way,
they all advanced it in a slightly different way.
Each brought something new to it.
And I do like that the Nobel Prize system works like that,
that it's not just the person
who's found the application to the thing,
it's the person who identified it.
It's like giving a goal score in football,
not only to the person who's kicked or headed the ball in,
but to the assist.
And then even to someone who passed it to the assist.
- The whole team gets that goal.
It actually, football does work like that,
because goals are not given to individual players.
You're schooling me on football.
- But increasingly, you do find out
who the assist was for every goal.
- Yeah.
- And when you do, yeah.
- Yeah, you always do.
- And when they talk about, let's say,
Mbappe's done whatever he's done this season,
they'll say he's got this many goals and this many assists,
and they will mention it each time.
- Oh, I see.
- And I think it kind of began from fancy football,
because you get points for how many goals your player scored,
but they wanted to give points
to the people who were creating the goals,
and they get to them as well.
- Really? - Wow.
- Well, I've forgotten that it wasn't always like that.
- Definitely not, yeah.
- The Nobel Prize for Medicine this year,
or last year in 2023,
was given to Kathleen Caracol and Drew Weisman
for some mRNA vaccine stuff for COVID,
but they had the initial manuscript rejected by nature
and by science. - Really?
- No way.
- And they were rejected by nature.
- Do you mean by the journals, "Nature and Science"?
- Yes. (laughing)
- Also, "God and Man" were rejected.
(laughing)
Your work.
- Yeah, so "Nature" the journal rejected it within 24 hours.
- Oh.
- And so they didn't even send it to any reviewers or whatever.
They just got the letter through the post
and went, "This is shit."
- Really? - And just threw it away.
- Wow.
- What did you say it was for?
It was for mRNA?
- It was for developing more effective mRNA vaccines
against COVID-19.
- I just, I really worry about sort of Trump
listening to this and going,
"See, I told you, nature and science agree with me."
- But what it was is that they didn't think
that it was a big enough advancement.
They thought they were just kind of repeating old things
that people had already said,
but actually later on they realized
that it was actually a big, big advancement.
The 2023 Nobel Prize for Physics,
which was won by Pierre Agostini,
Ferench Kraus and Anne Wheelier,
is a way of measuring things
with atto-second pulses of light.
An atto-second is even shorter than a nanosecond.
It's extremely, extremely short amount of time.
In fact, it's one quintillionth of a second.
And if you wanted to have a quick meeting
with every insect on earth,
but had to complete all the meetings in one second,
then each insect would get an atto-second of your time.
- Oh.
Food for thought.
- And they managed to make these pulses of light,
each one an atto-second in length.
And that means that if you think about a movie
has however many frames per second,
if you can make one every atto-second,
then suddenly you can see things
that are happening almost instantaneously.
- I just find that when I'm watching films,
and I don't mean to denigrate these people,
but I find the colors fine
and the speed at which I see things happening is fine.
- You're still confused about the plot 10 minutes in.
It doesn't matter.
- I'm sorry.
I should say that these atto-second stuff
will not be used to--
- To fill the next born identity, right, okay.
- It means that you can see like photosynthesis
happening in real time.
- Hang on, are you saying it also won't be used
to give lots of insects performance reviews?
(laughing)
- None of that.
- What is the point then?
I don't need to see photosynthesis happening in real time.
I'm sure it's really useful.
- Well, Anne-Louis Li said that basic research
is very important because you never know
what applications will be found in 50 years' time.
We don't know what they'll be,
but something, this kind of technology
will change our lives, but we don't know how yet.
- We'll be kicking ourselves when the ninth born film
is filmed using this method,
and you can see him punch the guy as it happens,
rather than slightly after it happens.
- But can we address the heated debate on nano?
- Oh yeah, I'm sure. - Oh, great.
- Yeah, so this is nano technology.
This was also written in the birth of nano technology.
How do you spell it?
- N-A-N-O, no, no.
- Sometimes yes, and sometimes no.
- Oh my God, I got really into this etymology.
- Sometimes no, and sometimes nah.
(laughing)
- So it first appeared in biology as nano with a double N,
1909, this is niche stuff.
- I've never seen it spelled with double N.
- N-A-N-N-O. - Yes.
- Or N-N-A-N-O, no, no.
(laughing)
- I think you know the answer to that question.
- All right.
- So the reason you haven't seen it
is 'cause it was used in zoology,
and it was in biology, it is used with a double N.
It's much rarer in biology, and it just meant very small,
and it's 'cause nano in Greek meant dwarf.
So nano bacteria, nano plankton,
that it just became a tiny thing to mean tiny.
Then physics took it on, but there's a rule in physics,
which I didn't know about, which is very niche,
but very exciting, which is that
if something is a multiple of something,
so let's say you've got a meter,
if you're saying a thousand meters, what's that?
- Kilometer. - A kilometer.
And that, you use the Greek, so kilometer,
kilo is from Greek. - Okay.
- If it's a submultiple, a factor,
like a thousandth of a meter, what do we say?
- Millie.
- Because if it's a submultiple,
exactly we use the Latin. - What?
- So they shouldn't have used the double N in nano
because that was the Greek. - Oh my God.
- Whereas the Latin for dwarf uses a single N, nanos,
and so the physicists who were adhering to convention
changed it to a single N.
Aren't you delighted? - There is no other podcast
is blowing shit wide open like this.
- Anna, I'm so sorry, I actually heard that fact
on Shagged Married Anoid last week.
(all laughing)
But it was Shagged Married Anoid
with only one N, because...
- That'll be my spin-off.
- Shagged Married Anoid, the batteries podcast.
- Yeah. - Beautiful, that's your spin-off.
- There we go. - Shagged Married Anoid,
which is mine about my sinus problems.
(all laughing)
- Shagged Married Anoid, for Dan.
- Oh no, that's mean.
- You're lucky, I don't know what that word means.
It's another word for wife guy.
- That's it, okay.
- Shagged Married, really happy, love my wife.
(all laughing)
- Make love, marriage.
- Marry, then make love.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for a final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that right
at the southernmost point of Sweden,
you will find a statue of Umar Thurman's naked granny.
- I'm gonna say, as a guess,
that it will not be her when she was a granny.
It might have been her in earlier life.
- Yeah, you would say that in the correct way, yes.
(all laughing)
- I'm like that.
- Yeah, she was a model.
Her grandmother was a model called Birgit Holmquist,
and the sculptor, who wanted to make the statue,
hired her as a model,
and it's positioned right on this little seaside port
in this town, which is called Smigahuk, outside of--
- Trellarborgs.
- Outside of Trellarborgs.
- Yeah.
- Is it more, is basically,
if you go past the new granny statue,
you are leaving Sweden.
- No, I don't, I'm not sure it's--
- It's a nice statue.
- It's a beautiful statue, you know.
- Is it full naked?
- She has, yeah.
- No fig leaf or anything?
- Nope.
- Good on it.
- No, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Okay, wow.
Do we know anything else about this woman?
Did the statues all over the world of her,
or was she just that and then gone?
- No, I mean, you know, she was a model,
but really the Thurman family,
like they're all such fascinating people.
- I reckon it started with these guys.
- Yeah.
- So she was a great Swedish beauty,
but not from like an extremely rich family
or anything like that.
But she married a Westphalian baron
called Karl von Schlbrugge.
- Lovely.
- And Karl von Schlbrugge had a monocle.
He was a baron.
- Of course he did.
- He was briefly jailed by the Nazis
for refusing to denounce his business partners
who were Jewish and Bridget used her Swedish nationality
to kind of say, oh, look, he's Swedish as well.
He needs to come out.
And they managed to get him out of prison.
And then they moved off to,
I think they went to Mexico or China
or something like that away from the war.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And yeah, that was basically the start of the dynasty.
- Basically they fled Nazi Germany
at what is now clearly the most socially acceptable time
and we've done that which is in the 1930s
rather than in 1945 halfway through.
I moved to Central South America at the, yeah, yeah.
- You've got to specify, don't you?
Oh, I moved to South America from Nazi Germany.
When?
(laughing)
- Because actually there was another German
living in Mexico at the same time
with a very, very similar name who was a Nazi spy.
And some people on the internet think it's the same person.
I'm pretty sure it isn't the same person.
- Von Schlbrugge's.
- I'm also pretty sure that Mexico isn't South America,
by the way, in case someone complains about it.
- Is Central America?
- No, it's North America.
- What?
(laughing)
Then what's Canada?
Sorry, great point, great point, great point, great point.
Sorry, sorry to all that.
Do we have listeners in Mexico?
I don't know, I don't think I've ever had an email
from anyone in Mexico.
- Okay, if you're in Mexico.
- Yeah, right in, absolutely.
- Right in, please.
- So, okay, that's the Schlbrugge's.
And then Uma Thurman's mum, so their daughter,
was Nina Von Schlbrugge.
And she was also a model
'cause she was very good looking.
'Cause she had monocle jeans.
- Monocle jeans.
And she was a model in Manhattan.
And she modeled for Dali, Salvador Dali, I think.
- Yeah, she was very old. - Yeah, she was wild, wasn't she?
She, as in the life that she led
and the names that come up,
so before she married her husband
that would lead to Uma and her brothers,
she was married very briefly to Timothy Leary,
who she was introduced to by Salvador Dali.
So Timothy Leary, for those who don't know him,
he led the big push for psychedelics and LSD
and counterculture in America in the '60s.
- Briefly was correct.
- Yeah.
- They were married very briefly.
They separated during the honeymoon.
- No.
- Leary said, we had time travel
through a few mythic incarnations,
played out magical dramas in panoramic realms.
Now we would have to rise
to that most complex human art, gentle separation.
- Right.
- Yeah, I'd leave him too, actually.
- So he's describing.
And she met her then next husband, Uma's dad,
while she was at a house trying to get Leary
to sign the divorce papers.
So he was there for other reasons,
trying to get Leary to do something.
- Well, I read that Robert Thurman,
who was Uma Thurman's dad, obviously,
was only present at that house
where Nina was trying to persuade him to sign the papers.
He was there trying to stop Leary
taking so many drugs.
- How did that go?
- I don't know.
Not very well.
- That's funny.
- Leary's the guy who coined the phrase,
"Soon in, turn on, drop out."
- That's right.
- So he's a big counter-culture guy.
But then Robert Thurman is even more interesting
than Timothy Leary.
He's kind of an Indiana Jones style scholar of Buddhism.
And he's very cool.
- He seems to be one of the people who made Buddhism cool
in the 20th century, really.
Kind of one of the leading popularizers of it in the US.
So he seemed to have a revelation in 1961
when he was changing a flat tire.
And he said the tire iron flicked up into his eye.
And he went into a coma for three days.
So I must have flicked up quite hard.
He woke up and he'd lost an eye.
But as he says, he lost one eye
but gained a thousand more as he pushed it.
- Oh, wow.
- And that's when he gave up.
- That's a botched surgery, isn't it?
(all laugh)
- Yeah.
I think the surgeon was on LSD at the time.
- Dr. Leary, not you.
(all laugh)
- I don't know, he was one of a playboy
and he gave up his old playboy lifestyle,
hitchhiked to India and thought,
"I really want to become a Buddhist monk."
- That's kind of what the Buddha did though.
The Buddha was a sort of playboy prince, wasn't he?
- Yeah, that's right.
- But Thurman supposedly became the first American
to become officially a Buddhist monk.
Like to be recognized as one.
- Yeah.
- Do you know how long he lasted?
- How long?
- I think less than a year.
- Oh, God.
- He met this lama.
So he flew back from India to America,
met this lama and was like,
"I've been in India and I'm desperate
"to become a Buddhist monk.
"I'm going to be amazing at it."
The lama kept saying,
"I'm looking at your karma
"and you don't have monk in you.
"I promise you've got great things destined."
- You haven't got lama karma?
- Yeah, I haven't got lama karma, that's what he said.
But Robert kept on saying,
"No, I really want to do it."
So eventually the lama took him to meet the Dalai lama,
the big lama, as he's otherwise known.
- Boss lama.
- Boss lama, yeah, boss level,
who did ordain him as a monk
and literally within 18 months, he resigned.
- Why, why?
- The monk lifestyle he decided wasn't for him.
- Yeah, he's still leading.
He's still massive.
- He's still leading the movement.
The Dalai Lama was very like,
"Yeah, cool, good move, mate."
- The best mate, yes.
He and the Dalai Lama are very close
and he's the president of Tibet House US,
which is the main Tibetan organization in the USA.
So they've a bet with each other
to see if they can both live until the year 2048.
- Or it's getting closer.
Do you know how old that would make them both?
'Cause I think he's in--
- Robert Thurman is in his 80s.
- One of them will be 107, I think, maybe Thurman.
- That was interesting.
- Is it what happened?
They said, "Are you gonna live until this date?"
And he said, "Yeah."
And he said, "Want Tibet?"
And he said, "Yes, I do."
And then Xi Jinping said, "Well done."
- That is too good.
- Uma Thurman sounds like the least interesting
member of her own family.
I'd presume she was a relatively interesting person,
but all these antecedents are so interesting.
- Yeah, they're awesome.
So James, just on the topic of Uma Thurman,
you have been watching her entire output of movies, right?
- I've started, yeah.
But I only started two days ago,
so I've watched "Kill Bill One" and "Kill Bill Two."
- Right.
- Has any of you seen "Even Cowgirls Get the Blues?"
- No.
- Oh, I think that's, I mean,
it's based on an amazing book.
- Have you read it?
- No, no, I have it at home.
- It's the kind of book you would have read, actually.
- Yeah, "Tom Robbins."
- Yeah, very good, very good.
No, it's probably in a very bad film.
But I just love the concept.
It's just about a woman with unusually long thumbs.
And so it's called "Even Cowgirls Get the Blues."
- But it's an Uma Thurman film, sorry.
- It's an Uma Thurman film.
She plays this girl with very long thumbs.
- That's interesting.
She doesn't have long thumbs in real life, I don't think.
- So I think she might have had to wear prosthetic thumbs.
No, she doesn't have...
- She has big feet, doesn't she?
- She's got massive feet.
- Yeah, that's why she's in all of...
What's his name?
Who does those films?
- Tarantino.
Yeah, because he likes feet, doesn't he?
- Does he?
- I think so.
- Because there's lots of shots of her feet
in these two movies, I can say that.
She has size 11 feet, and that's American.
- What's that in old money?
- 12, I don't know, 10.
- Yeah, it's one either side.
- Well, that's big either way.
- I don't know if it's that.
- That's very big, I agree.
- Thank you.
- She can't have size 12 feet.
- No, it's gotta be 10.
- But 10 would be very big.
It's still a good fact.
- You don't need to write it and tell us, by the way,
we will have been able to Google the conversions
after this one.
- Oh no, do not write it, please don't waste your time.
- I don't wanna wake up to 15 emails
about all subject like Uma Thurman feet pics.
- I don't want that, if you're in Mexico,
then tell us what size 10 is in your country.
(laughing)
- And also, which America are you really in?
- Oh dear, do you wanna hear about
another very attractive Swedish woman
who was turned into a statue?
- Okay, okay.
- Well, not turned into, the model for.
- Can we guess?
- Absolutely not.
- Brigitte Bardot.
- No, she's not a famous one.
- Ulrika Johnson.
- She's still quite famous, I'd say.
- Oh yeah.
- Do you feel like you're not being listened to, Andy?
- No, no, no, no, no, no.
This is Pitt Karin Err's daughter, okay?
- Oh.
- She was a Swedish young woman.
She was incredibly beautiful.
She's just, the whole story about her is just,
there was this, she was a milkmaid.
And the whole story is basically, she was just so fit.
So she went to Stockholm to work for a year.
And basically, no one could believe
how attractive this milkmaid was.
- And the bar is high in Sweden as well, don't you get?
That's not like being the most attractive person in (beep)
- Wow.
- So why would you name, leave that place out.
Leave that place name out.
- That was, bleep it out, no one will ever know
the place name that I have there.
Sorry, she was the most attractive person in Stockholm.
- So she was just so fit, basically.
- We get it, we get it, she's hot.
- But the stories are like the Crown Prince visitor
incognito to ask for some milk,
because he just wanted to look at this milkmaid.
And he forgot to bring a container.
So she gave him a sort of scolding.
- With hot milk?
- Not a scolding, sorry.
- A scolding.
- She created traffic jams, cause she was so beautiful.
People was doing a go slow as they went past.
- Or was that just James not moving with his horse and cart?
- Yeah.
And there's a statue of her in Sweden now.
And I think part of the reason she was apparently so beautiful
was that she hadn't had some more pox.
- Oh, okay.
- So the bar was slightly lower.
- Yes, she had had cow pox.
And she was accused actually of having sold more
than just milk, you know what I mean?
But that was real trick, trick.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Milkshake.
- Actually, she hadn't been selling any,
she hadn't been-
- Any of her milkshake?
- Right, yeah, she'd been selling milk
and she was just accused.
- Her milkshake brought the king to the yard.
- Yeah.
- And he's like, "Oh, do you have a spare bowl?"
(laughing)
- What's the most famous statue in Scandinavia?
- Do you have the answer?
- Yeah.
- The Copenhagen mermaid?
- The little mermaid, yeah.
Probably an advert for Carlsberg.
- Oh, no.
- Yeah.
It was commissioned by the founder of Carlsberg,
Jacob Christian Carlsberg.
And he basically said,
"Well, you know, I've got the best beer in the country,
so I'm gonna do this nice little statue
for everyone to see.
And when they see it, they'll remember me
and remember my beer."
- Oh dear, that's fucked up, isn't it?
Because one of those adverts, which is very memorable,
that you've got no idea what it was for.
- Yeah, yeah.
It's probably the best mermaid statue in the world.
- Nice. - Very good.
He hired a sculpture called Edvard Ericsson to create it.
And he hired a ballerina called Ellen Price,
who is very, very famous in Sweden
at the time to model for it.
But she was unwilling to get naked.
And so the face is hers
and the body is Mr. Ericsson's wife.
- Really?
- Wow, what about the tail?
(laughing)
- No, that's his wife.
- That's his wife.
(laughing)
- I've just got one more celebrity grandparent fact.
- Oh yeah.
- Drew Barrymore's grandfather's corpse was stolen.
So this is John Barrymore, who was a very famous actor.
In the, he was the, John's 1922 hamlet,
which you probably remember was the greatest hamlet
maybe ever.
- Yeah, that was a good one.
- It really was, he was a famous actor.
He was ruined by alcoholism and died in 1942,
relatively young.
His mates were people like Errol Flynn.
And Errol Flynn wrote in his memoir
that after Barrymore died,
their friend got his body, obtained his body
and hid it for Errol Flynn to find to freak him out.
So propped him up in a chair
and then they spent the night playing poker with it.
- Is that what we can the Bernys is based on?
- Do you know what, I think largely it is.
Cause it was, it was not only Errol Flynn,
it was David Nevin.
And I want to say Orson Welles,
someone in that territory of fame.
- There was a group of them.
- I think it is because I haven't really heard
of any of those people and I've never seen Weekend at Bernys.
I'm not really sure what happens in it,
but I still kind of knew that fact.
- Wait, so it's Weekend at Bernys about them playing.
- I think it's about a dead body.
- Keeping a dead body.
- Their body dies and they need to keep a holiday going.
And so they string him up and they use his dead body.
Yeah.
- There we go.
That's sort of what they did,
except just to have a fun gamer poker with him.
- Wow.
- Confirmed by Drew Barrymore in 2020.
- That's right.
- Good Lord.
- Yeah, that's pretty cool.
- If I die, please don't do that.
Don't do another podcast.
- What do you want us to do with your dead body then?
Shall we, we could prop it up and do something fun,
prop it up and collect some moths with you.
- Yeah, lovely.
- Or the acid thing.
Let's just burn you.
(laughing)
- Wow, what a dark term this podcast took at the end.
- It's time to go to our group therapy session now.
And just shoot that over.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram, on @shrieberland, James.
- My Twitter is @jamesharkin.
- Andy.
- Mine is @andrewhontareb.
- And Anna, where can they get us as a group?
- You can get us on Twitter, on @knowsdutchthing
or on Instagram, @knowsdutchthing as a fish.
Or you can email podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our website,
Knowsdutchthingasafish.com.
All the previous episodes are up there,
as well as a link into the portal
that will get you to Club Fish,
our private members club,
where we post lots of bonus episodes
and lots of fun things go up there.
So do check that out.
Otherwise, come back here next week.
We have another episode coming up.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
you