(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, happy new year.
We have a little favor to ask you
before we start with the 2013 episodes
of "No Such Thing as a Fish."
- 2013 episodes?
- Is that not, oh, what year is it?
- James, oh my God, this is so sad.
You've just woken up from a coma
and you haven't realized that 10 years have passed.
- No, no, you mean this is an episode two
of "No Such Thing as a Fish"?
- I'm so sorry, but you're gonna be delighted
with how far we've come in the interim.
- Wow, well, what have we done while I've been in a coma?
Have we told the world?
Have we made some books?
Have we won any national comedy awards?
- Well, do you know, it's funny, you should mention that.
That's the one thing we haven't quite done yet.
And we're delighted to have you back.
We've had to simulate your presence for the last decade.
Delighted to have you back to help us win them
'cause that is what we're supposed to be talking about
right now.
It is the national comedy awards
and we are on the long list.
"No Such Thing as a Fish" for best comedy podcast.
We would absolutely love to get to the shortlist.
If by any chance you like this show and you're here,
so maybe you do, if you could go to qi.com/vote
and vote for us, we'd be hugely grateful.
- That's right.
We would love to get on that shortlist.
So please, please do vote.
It'll take no time at all.
You can click through all the other bits.
Like, we're quite near the end.
So if you don't know who was the best supporting actor
in a foreign sitcom this year, then it doesn't matter.
You can just click past it, get to the podcast bit,
click on "No Such Thing as a Fish," put your email in,
bish bash bosh, job done.
And we might get nominated for an award.
I'm going back to sleep.
Enjoy the show.
On with the podcast.
- On with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing as a Fish,"
a weekly podcast this week, coming to you live
from the Bloomsbury Theater in London.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray, and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered round the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is my fact,
my fact this week, is that originally Popeye,
the sailor man, got his powers, not from eating spinach,
but by rubbing a lucky magic hen.
- I love the fact that you need to specify Popeye,
the sailor man.
Oh, Popeye, that's how Popeye, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So this is Popeye, we obviously know the great,
(speaking in foreign language)
- I think that was the chicken.
- That was the chicken, was that the chicken?
- So Popeye the sailor man,
and he was a cartoon back in the early 1900s,
and when he originally--
- And also beyond, if you're remembering Popeye,
and thinking, "Shit, am I that old?"
He lasted even beyond the early 1900s.
- I don't know if he's still on TV, he might be,
but we all still know him, he's such an iconic character,
and obviously he derived all of his powers from spinach,
but when the comic strip that he first appeared in
was happening, he wasn't a main character,
he was this sort of peripheral character
who was introduced to the series.
And there's an episode where he finds himself
hired by Olive Oil, who becomes his girlfriend
and eventual wife, by her brother who's called Caster Oil,
who sails a ship to Dice Island,
where he intends to make a lot of money in a casino
by rubbing the head of a lucky hen,
and when he gets there, Popeye gets shot by someone.
So the first time we ever see him
getting supernatural strength is when after he's shot,
this little whiffle hen comes by,
and he goes, "Wow, whiffle hen."
Don't know how he talks actually, I can't remember.
There's something like that?
- Yeah.
- Ah, cock, cock, cock.
And he rubs the hen's head,
and then he gets the supernatural power,
and he takes out the shooter with some punches,
and that's the very first moment.
- It was a comic strip, right?
- Yeah, it was a comic strip.
- So we wouldn't have known how he spoke, I guess.
It was just, "Whatever's in your head is how he spoke."
- That's a very nice thought.
Isn't there an American restaurant called Popeyes?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Isn't there a chicken restaurant?
- Oh yeah.
I go in there, rubbing their chickens.
(laughing)
- You've been told.
- Spinnich didn't come in until quite a lot later,
did it?
- It was a few years later, yeah.
- I think it was 1932.
- Yeah, yeah.
- And Popeye, like you say,
I think this comic book series started in the teens,
the mid teens, 15 or 16,
but I think Popeye became the main character
in the early 20s.
So until then, I think he was just relying
on normal strength.
- Well, he's very strong.
I mean, he's very strong normally,
but when he has a spirit, he gets extra strong.
That's the whole point of those forearms, you know.
- Yes.
- Well, wait a minute,
because your biceps are what make you strong.
- This has always been the bewildering thing about Popeye.
- So he's got massive forearms,
and the muscles in your forearms
are the ones that control your fingers.
So he's just a brilliant pianist.
(laughing)
- Well, don't do a thumb war with Popeye,
is what you're saying?
I did not know that Popeye was Jewish.
Is he?
- Popeye was Jewish.
Popeye was Jewish.
So Elsie Seagal was the original cartoonist
who drew Popeye.
He was Jewish and there was a lot of,
there were a lot of sort of very, very subtle Jewish references
and sort of jokes in the strip.
Yeah, and to such an extent that in Fascist Italy,
'cause the cartoon was popular across the world.
It was so, so popular.
When it appeared in Fascist Italy,
the creator's name, Seagal, was taken off it,
because they were pessimistic and so, you know, so, yeah, yeah.
But they still had to have the Popeye.
- Are you saying Popeye the sailor was Jewish
or that Seagal was Jewish?
- Well, Seagal was Jewish and there are lots of references.
It's a very sort of Jewish inflected
and influenced cartoon.
There's no actual scene of Popeye, you know,
having Yom Kippur or whatever.
(laughing)
- That's amazing.
'Cause weirdly, later on in the Popeye run,
there was a thing where the original animators
were no longer animating it and it was outsourced
and it was outsourced to Prague
in order for them to make the cartoon.
So there was a whole series
where Tom and Jerry was made in Prague and so on.
And none of the animators out there had seen it.
And this was because there was no money to do it.
So there was a run of 13 episodes,
which are often called the worst 13 episodes.
- Of Popeye?
- Of Tom and Jerry because no one had really seen it.
But Popeye was done there as well.
But the thing was, all of the people,
this is a credits thing, who animated in Prague,
had to have their names changed to American names
because they didn't want audiences
thinking a communist country at the time
was infiltrating communist ideas
into their Popeye and Tom and Jerry cartoon.
- Also, isn't it landlocked, Chair Republic?
So like, how would you have a sailor man there?
- Oh, I guess in land waterways, can I?
- The Danube.
- The Danube, yeah, canal-based.
- Popeye, Danube, man.
- Yeah.
Well, Mongolia has a navy, doesn't it, as well,
despite being landlocked.
- It does, yeah.
And Bolivia as well.
- And Bolivia, yeah.
- Captain Von Trapp is in the sound of music.
He's a, is he an admiral or something?
Or a captain in the navy of the landlocked Austria?
- It makes more sense if you're going to have a sailor man
to have him on a coast, in a coastal country.
- It's weird.
You know how we normally try and blow shit wide open?
We seem to have closed shit wide shut there.
- Yeah.
- I like it.
- That's what we should do.
Closed shit wide shut.
(laughing)
- Just on chicken rubbing, specifically,
there is an Orthodox Jewish ritual called kapparot,
where you wave a rooster over someone's head,
and you say a particular prayer,
and then you slaughter the rooster,
and you get the slaughtered rooster to charity,
and it's an atonement ritual for whoever's having the
chicken waver over there.
- Do you rub it on their heads,
or your own head?
- I don't think you rub it specifically.
You just sort of waft it around above them.
But maybe, maybe the Wiffelhen is a very subtle reference
to the traditional Jewish kapparot ritual.
- Yeah, it could be.
- It's almost certainly not.
- There's also, there was an old English bit of folklore
where if you wanted to stop your baby
from getting chicken pox, you would rub it with a chicken.
(laughing)
So it could have been that.
- Right.
- Yeah?
I'm so glad we're on chicken rubbing stuff,
'cause I actually did quite a lot of...
- Chicken rubbing, right.
- I can feel a personal anecdote coming up.
(laughing)
So chickens will sometimes flirt with each other
by rubbing themselves on the ground.
- Okay.
- So like, yeah, yeah.
So there's this thing called preening oil,
which comes out of a kind of gland above the beak.
And it contains lots of information about the birds' genes
and about it, you know, how suitable it is
as a mate and things like that.
And so sometimes a cockerel will wipe itself
on the ground, for example,
to just show it didn't leave it sent
for a prospective mate.
- Like a genome sequencing act.
It leaves its genome sequence on the ground
for the male to look at and say,
"Oh, you're not prone to sickle cell anemia.
Thank God."
(laughing)
- Yeah, I guess so, yeah.
- The Etruscans used to rub chickens.
- So glad we're doing all this chicken rubbing stuff,
'cause this is great.
Go on, go on.
- So the Etruscans, and then the Romans after them,
but they used chickens for divination.
They thought they were kind of quite holy.
And for good luck, you would get a chicken.
It was always a dead chicken that you would rub,
but you would rub it for good luck.
And that's probably where we get the idea
of the wishbone from these guys as well.
You know, like, if you cook a chicken, you get the bone out.
People used to rub those little bones for luck as well.
- Wow.
- And that's why we do that.
- And now we just snap 'em.
- Now we just snap 'em.
- Rub it too hard.
You don't want that to happen in most rubbing situations.
- So they get snapped.
(laughing)
- The hen in Popeye.
Sorry to stop us from talking about.
I've just got one more chicken rubbing paste.
- Of course you do.
- Yeah, yeah.
No, no, please get it out.
I'd hate for the...
- Listener to miss out on your golden research.
- Appalachian chicken rubbing rituals,
and I just thought that would be a nice thing.
So there are lots of Kentucky waltz superstitions.
You know, when you have a waltz.
- Right, yeah.
- I don't know what Kentucky waltz is though.
It's deep fried, isn't it?
(laughing)
- There are so many traditions or superstitions
about what you do with your waltz
to make it disappear in Kentucky specifically.
Yeah, so, I mean, it's mostly rubbed something on it.
So, you know, it might be a chicken gizzard
or a chicken intestine,
but also bacon rind,
or beef steak,
or one bean,
or three beans.
- Just don't accidentally rub two beans
on it, whatever you do.
- Oh, no, no.
- Then you come out and waltz.
- You get double waltz, yeah, yeah.
Kill a cat.
That's bad stuff.
Take it to a graveyard at midnight,
and then rub the cat on the waltz,
and also it gets rid of the waltz.
- It feels like you go with a one bean.
(laughing)
- It's a sort of step change process.
You know, you try one bean out of three beans,
then you kill a cat and take it to a graveyard.
(laughing)
Anyway.
- You were gonna say on Popeye's chicken.
- Sorry, Popeye, yeah.
- I wanted to drag it back to Popeye, apparently.
- No, no, no, that's fine.
Let's do more rubbing chickens.
What else you got?
- Oh, sure, thank you, Dad.
Well, okay, back, back, back, back.
Sorry, my mistake.
No, so in the cartoon,
we've got this mystical chicken,
but it's not the only--
- In the comic strip, you mean?
- Sorry, in the comic strip,
and it's not the only animal in the comic strip
that had these sort of paranormal mystical powers.
There was also a dog called Eugene the Jeep.
And this was in a 1936 Thimble Theater comic strip,
and that's what Popeye was part of.
- I don't think he was a dog per se.
He looked like a dog.
- We don't fully know what he was,
and it led to one of the most existential,
brilliant comic strips that I think the creator ever wrote.
The headline of it was, "What's a Jeep?"
Eugene the Jeep, what's a Jeep?
And this is what the comic strip for kids said,
"A Jeep is an animal living in a three-dimensional world,
"in this case, our world,
"but really belongs to a fourth-dimensional world."
Here's what happened.
A number of Jeep life sails were somehow forced
through a dimensional barrier into our world.
They combined at a favorable time
with the life cells of the African hooey hound.
The electrical vibrations of that hooey hound cell
and the foreign cell were the same.
They are a kind of kindred cell.
In fact, all things are to some extent relative,
whether they be this or some other world.
Now you see.
(audience laughing)
For what, for six-year-olds, that is.
He was based on a Polish person, wasn't he?
Which again, Popeye was,
which I imagine they'd have had to cover up
when they wanted there to be
none of these communist influences.
But this guy sounds like a bit of a legend.
Frank "Rocky" Fiegel, who was from Segar's hometown.
So he lived in Chester, Illinois,
which is where Segar came from.
But his parents were Polish immigrants.
And there's one remaining photo of him,
and he does look like Popeye, but it's very hard to tell
'cause he's basically got a pipe
and he's bald.
And so--
- I think he definitely looks like Popeye.
- He looks like Popeye,
and he was constantly getting into fights,
and, which basically is what Popeye does, right?
He smokes, he gets into fights.
- Well, he was a boxer, wasn't he, I think?
- He was a boxer, but and a nice guy, though.
Constantly starting fights,
but a nice guy and always protected the children.
- We're talking about the sailor now, right?
- We're talking about Fiegel, the sailor.
And apparently, according to his biographies--
- Sorry, that Popeye is a sailor as well.
- Oh, sorry, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, sorry.
- He did actually say at the very start,
"Popeye the sailor."
- Quite specifically, you see why I added it now, Andy.
- And actually, this guy wasn't a sailor.
- The Polish-- what?
- No, he wasn't a sailor.
He was just a down and up guy.
- So just a guy who liked getting into fights
is the inspiration.
- Yeah, okay.
- Maybe he didn't spend so much time
checking out a rubbing chicken patch, you know?
- But he used to get sent money, apparently.
His assistant, Seagal's assistant,
said they used to send him a little bit of money
to say thanks for inspiring the character of Popeye.
- Wow.
- Seagal said this to the Randolph County Herald newspaper
that it was based on this guy.
And there was another person in the town
called John William Shushet,
who was supposedly what Wimpy was based on.
- Oh, yeah.
- So you know Wimpy, the character
who's, "I gladly pay you Tuesday for a hamburger today,"
and all that.
He's always in debt and he's always eaten hamburgers.
And according to this historian,
John William Shushet also liked hamburgers.
- Interesting.
- Open and shut case.
- Shut this shit in my clothes.
(audience laughing)
- His name means joke, sweetly.
- Seagal.
- Or figure.
- Oh, yeah.
- His name is prank or joke.
- Which is kind of what Popeye is.
- That was pretty funny.
- A comic strip.
- Well, there is a serious point behind Popeye.
So there was a psychoanalytic piece done about him
in an American paper in 1932.
This is a paper called The Post Dispatch.
It was a really, really famous paper at the time.
You may not realize it,
but Popeye is a suppressed desire.
He personifies the desire most of us have
both to be strong and to sock
some of the unpleasant people we encounter.
A desire suppressed because we lack Popeye's muscles.
(audience groans)
- Although Popeye himself says
he would never hit anyone as hard as he could
'cause it's wrong to kill people.
There's actually quite a sweet.
- Wait, there's the cartoon character now.
- Yeah, yeah, the cartoon character.
- Okay, okay.
- The cartoon character wrote a letter
to a paper in the 1930s saying,
and I suppose Seagull probably helped him write it,
saying he'd never hit anyone as hard as he could
because it's wrong to kill people.
And he said he's been shot 120 times,
but when bullets go through him,
it doesn't bother him at all,
except that he always has to block up the hole
with a cork 'cause he doesn't like drafts
blowing through him.
(audience laughs)
- Beautiful.
- Yeah, people complained about the fighting
'cause it was teaching kids to fight.
So after that, he carried on fighting,
but only for the honor of old ladies and children.
Later strips.
- Children have honor.
(audience laughs)
- Yeah.
- I guess so, original honor.
- All right, yeah.
- Old babies have.
- But he was really positive for spinach eating at the time.
- Yeah.
- There were reports, and I don't know how accurate they were,
but during the Great Depression,
they said that the uptake in children
who were interested in eating food like spinach,
well, specifically spinach, was 33%.
And that bumped it up to sort of like the third most
requested food or favorite food of a child during that time.
- Yeah, the insane claim is that there was a survey done
which asked children what they liked to eat.
Their first thing was turkey,
and their second thing was ice cream,
and then they claimed spinach.
- Yeah.
- So it was seems very important.
(audience laughs)
- And then Popeye later on in the cartoons,
he stopped eating the spinach directly out of the can.
So you know he would like squeeze the can in the,
but apparently they were worried that children
might copy this and might get a can of spinach
and eat directly from it and cut their mouth.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that's the kind of thing I would have done,
actually, I think that's fair.
- I need to move us on to our next comment.
- Can we mention very quickly the madness of the film,
Popeye, which is just one thing about it.
So there's the Robin Williams film, 1980,
and it's not very good, apparently.
I haven't seen it.
- It's absolutely brilliant.
I've seen it five times.
It's really good.
It's a classic, Robin Williams' first film.
It's amazing.
- Yeah, agreed.
It's great.
- It's mad.
- All right, it's two against one.
- It's insane.
- But I have better taste.
No, I haven't seen it, so it might be great.
But anyway, the crazy thing about it
is what it was like to film it.
So the producer was a guy called Robert Evans.
Everyone who worked tonight admits
that they were basically rolling in cocaine
the entire time.
And at one point,
and they were all bringing cocaine on set,
they'd open up like camera packs
and just cocaine would fall out of cameras.
- I haven't seen this film either,
but is that what he does instead of spinach?
- Yeah.
- Yes, it is, yeah.
And Robert Evans had some luggage that was full of cocaine
that he was bringing with him to the set.
And it went missing at the airport,
as bags sometimes do.
And he thought, oh, shit.
A, we're not gonna get our Coke.
And B, if someone finds that luggage, I'm in trouble.
And so what he did was he basically
convinced the Maltese Prime Minister at the time,
a guy called Dominic Mintoff,
to do an exhaustive search of basically the country
to try and find his bags.
And so Mintoff said, "Why on earth would I do that?"
And he said, "Ah, well, I'm very good friends
"with Henry Kissinger,
"and Kissinger's written you a personal note,
"which is inside that luggage."
And I'd really love to give it to you.
So it's really important that we track it down
so you can read his lovely letter.
So he did.
His ego was flattered enough.
He tracked it down for him.
And then immediately, as soon as he'd done it,
Robert Evans had to fly back to the US,
meet up with Henry Kissinger,
and say, "Look, Henry, I'm so sorry,
"but you have to write a fake letter
"to the leader of Malta,
"saying what a great guy he is.
"Long story short, cocaine luggage situation.
"Do you mind?"
And Kissinger was very reluctant,
'cause Mintoff was an ally of Gaddafi.
It would have been very weird for him
to write an affectionate letter,
but he capitulated to save the shit/good film.
He wrote a fake letter.
Did he really?
Well, it sounds like he wrote... just wrote a letter.
He wrote a letter.
If you're Henry Kissinger and you are writing a letter,
that's a letter.
I guess it's fake. He backdated it.
Oh, OK, that is fake.
Oh, yeah, that's because I did a fakery.
It's mad.
I've just got a few more facts about chicken rubbing.
We don't have time, Andy.
MUSIC
It is time for fact number two,
and that is Anna.
My fact this week is that Marcel Proust
once woke up the members of a famous string quartet at midnight
and made them all come back to his house
to play a specific piece for him.
Because he... Oh, wow, that's so cool.
It's such a cool thing to be able to do.
And this is before he was even really famous.
How did he do that?
He just, I guess, people were more willing to do shit
back in the day.
It was sort of pre-telephones, right, this period?
Yeah, you know...
Not everyone's got a telephone.
Well, no one's calling them.
Yeah, he's going around to their house.
Yeah, so four individual houses in the middle of the night
to wake them up.
It's 11 p.m. He loved chamber music.
It's crazier than the Kissinger letter, I think.
I don't know how you would organise that.
Basically, at 11 p.m. he thought,
"I'd love to listen to César Franc's String Quartet in D Major.
"And nothing will stop me."
And so he knocked on the door of the leading French violinist
in Paris at the time, Gaston Poulet,
who was in his pyjamas and answered the door.
And Proust said, "I've got a taxi waiting downstairs.
"We're going to pick up your three mates
"and you're going to play me this piece."
And so, yeah, he went around all their houses.
One of them, the violist, was sceptical, apparently,
because Proust was...
He was wrapped in a big blanket
and he was eating mashed potato.
The whole time, in his cab.
But they all got in.
Proust had a very weird life.
Shall we just say, Proust is...
Lots of new years, yeah.
So, author of one of the greatest,
certainly one of the longest novels ever written,
Alasherst de Tompeh do in Search of Lost Time.
And, you know, that's about it.
All that was his main thing,
because he spent a long time writing it and then he died.
And a huge eccentric in that he...
His eccentricities were sort of half-born out
of the illnesses that he had in his life.
But he famously wrote all these books in bed.
He rarely went to sleep.
He was allergic to dust.
He was allergic to so many things.
He had cork walls on his room at home
because he tried to keep out any allergies from getting to him.
He had really bad asthma, didn't he,
which he took cigarettes for.
Yeah. Classic.
I've already had up to ten asthma attacks a day,
each one lasting up to an hour.
Yeah. Wow.
It's unbelievable that he wrote one of the longer books ever written,
considering how much time he just spent having asthma, basically.
Yeah. But that was the thing.
By then, you would get these cigarettes,
and they would have, like, opium in them and stuff.
So, you know, they weren't that bad,
but they were going into your lungs.
But, yeah. And you said about telephones, Dan.
So, it was... They did have telephones, then.
They weren't, obviously, super popular,
but it was a time... Do you remember we talked about this music
that used to play through the telephone?
Yeah, that's right. In America, the... Yeah.
It's like the first Spotify, in a way.
Exactly. They had this in France, and Proust had it,
because he was in bed the whole time. Wow.
And so, he had this kind of wires set up to an earpiece,
and he would listen to music.
So, hang on. When you woke up the members of the String Quartet,
he literally had functioning opera coming into his room.
It wasn't that functioning, to be honest.
Like, there was one time when there was a really loud crowd,
and he thought that that was the song,
because you couldn't really tell what was happening.
So, everyone was cheering. He was, "Oh, that was beautiful."
And they were like, "No, no, that wasn't the song."
But this was called the Theatrophon,
and it was very popular in France at the time.
Also very popular in Budapest.
And there was Harper's Weekly said that this system in Budapest
had made it the city that was full of illiterate, blind, bedridden
and incurably lazy people,
because they were all at home just listening to this music.
That feels like quite a personal...
That's a bit of a sub-tweet on Proust himself, isn't it?
I mean, that's what he was... Well, it was a little bit, yeah.
I think they were more slugging off the entire city of Budapest.
Oh, yeah.
So, Proust's sort of habits when he was writing.
So, he went to bed in 1909,
and he basically stayed there until 19... I think, 22?
22, I think he's 19.
And he wrote for 13 years, and one of his...
And also, he couldn't get a publisher.
He wrote the first volume, really struggled to get it published.
No publishers were interested.
He had to self-publish it, you know, at his own expense.
I think he inherited quite a lot of money, so he was quite well-healed.
And there was one person who believed in him and championed the work
and wrote a lot of brilliant, you know, reviews saying,
"You have to read this author. He is changing the face of literature."
And that person was Marcel Proust, under an assumed name.
Really?
He paid for his own early reviews in lots of newspapers.
Yeah, he wrote them in longhand,
and then he secretly had them typed up by his publisher,
so there was no paper trail.
And he described his own work as a little masterpiece.
He said, "What Monsieur Proust sees and feels is completely original."
I always think of it as the French trying to get one up on the British and Irish,
because I feel like we have James Joyce,
and there's this impenetrable, you know, 1,000-plus-page tome
that we all attempt to get through at some point and then mostly fail.
And then they have Proust, where they just did that.
And then he wrote six more volumes, exactly the same on top of it.
Well, I think Proust came first, or certainly his first book was published before Joyce.
Because, like Candy says, it was self-published,
but he went to a publisher to try and get it published,
this guy called Gaston Gallimard.
And Gallimard passed it on to a reader, and the reader just, it was really long,
so he just opened it up on a random page, page 62,
and what he found was a boring and overwritten description of a cup of herbal tea.
[LAUGHTER]
So he declined it, and then Proust had to do the self-publishing thing.
But then, 10 years later, Gallimard got another novel.
It was a very long Irish novel, and it was James Joyce's Ulysses, so...
Because I already regretted it for years,
like the guy who turned down the Beatles.
He apologized, yeah, he did apologize afterwards, yeah.
They did meet once.
Proust and James Joyce.
Yeah, 1922, it was the year that he died.
But it was one of the few times he actually went out, I think,
and he went to a dinner party, and James Joyce was there.
And then all I know is, I think James Joyce got quite pissed
and tried to invite himself back to Proust's house,
and Proust had to sneak away.
But do you have more detail?
Well, all I've read about the encounter
is that they hadn't actually read each other's books.
Oh, yeah, really?
One of the counter of two of the greatest minds ever.
They had nothing to say.
That's so funny.
There was a guy, before he wrote his mega series of books,
he translated a couple of books, and Ruskin,
he was a huge fan of Ruskin, right?
And when Ruskin passed away,
Proust decided that he wanted to make French translations
of two of the books, except he didn't speak any English.
So he had to ask his mum to translate it for him.
And then he did a proper, better translation
of his mum's translation of the book.
Oh, my God, he bloody loved his mum.
My God, if anyone's a mummy's boy.
Yeah, 'cause he lived with his parents until they both died,
which is fine.
And he used to write letters to his mum from bed
when he couldn't sleep saying, you know, "Mother, I'm so sorry,
"I won't be able to get up and spend breakfast with you,
"and nothing would make me happier."
2,000 pages later, he won't get to the point.
But his dad was quite strange,
and subjected him to this quite strange experience
when he was about 16,
which was that he was very worried about his son,
Marcel's masturbation, and...
Too much, not enough, yeah.
I just didn't think he was doing enough.
Doing it weird.
I thought you'd have this fact.
Love the rubbing cock facts.
(LAUGHTER)
There were no chickens involved,
but he was a doctor, Dr. Adrian Proust,
and it was a time when people thought masturbation was bad,
and Dr. Proust thought that it could lead to homosexuality,
'cause Proust was gay, in fact,
and so I think that his parents might have thought,
"Oh, God, we think he might be gay."
And so they said to cure him when he was 16.
His dad gave him 10 francs, sent him to a brothel,
and said, "Here you go, have sex with a prostitute,
"at female, please, and that will stop this awful masturbation habit."
-10 francs? -Yeah.
-So much that, is it? I don't know. -Well, back in the day,
you're not going to splash out on the first experience,
'cause it's got nothing to do with it. -Don't be disgusting, Anna.
Well, speaking of which he didn't, it was a failure.
This is why we know about it,
'cause Marcel Proust wrote a letter to his grandfather the next day,
saying, "I'm really sorry, I need to borrow 13 francs off you.
"Papa gave me 10 francs so I can get rid of this dreadful masturbation habit.
"But what I did was I turned up,
"I broke the prostitute's three franc chamber pot, embarrassing,
"and then I was so embarrassed that I couldn't perform,
"and so now I need to go back and try again,
"but I also need to pay her for her chamber pot."
-So... -Amazing.
Poor guy.
We have this impression of him as very sort of ill and constantly retiring to his bed.
-He did once fight a duel in his life. -Oh, yeah.
Yeah, and it was clearly something that mattered to him a lot.
He fought a duel when someone accused him of being gay, of having had a gay affair.
And his accuser was a literary critic who was called Jean Lorraine,
who was also gay, so to be clear, this is two gay guys having a duel
because one of them said to the other, "You are gay."
-Yeah. -And they both survived, didn't they?
-They both survived, they both shot and... -They both missed.
Marcel shot first, he went in the sort of region of his feet,
but didn't get him, and the other guy missed outright.
-But you kind of, I guess, have to think about the times. -Of course, yeah.
He was outing him for something that might have got him killed anyway
for being a homosexual, maybe his dad having written what he wrote was a...
-Yeah, it's... -It was a tough show.
He had a tough life, didn't he, Marcel, or Marcel?
-Yeah. -Yeah.
He once diagnosed himself with a brain disorder
and said that the only way to cure it was by drilling loads of holes into his skull.
-Oh, dear. -Did he do that?
He begged a doctor to do it, and the doctor, quite responsible for doctors at the time,
said, "I'm not going to do that."
-Yeah. -Well, in fairness, that's around 1910, that was standard.
-Mm-hmm. -Yeah, they were trapanning around that time.
-Yeah. -Oh, yeah, yeah, someone won a Nobel Prize for it.
-That's right, they did, yeah. -The main, main character
in Alarashesh Tapatopadu was going to be the Madeleine.
So the whole point of it is... Not the whole point, but I read the very start,
he's kind of got this Madeleine cake, and he has a bite of it,
and suddenly he remembers all the history and things that happened
because this evoked such a memory from him.
-So I thought I'd look into Madeleines. -Oh, yeah.
Apparently invented by a young girl called Madeleine,
who stood in for the chef to the Duke of Lorraine.
We're not quite sure why, but the chef wasn't there,
and they were like, "You, in."
And she only knew one recipe, and that was her grandmother's recipe for cakes,
and so that's all she made, and so she just made loads and loads of these,
and they were named after her, apparently.
And in 2006, there was a thing called Café Europa,
it was an EU thing, where every country in Europe
had to give their best cake or their best sweet thing,
and then they would celebrate them all, and France gave them Madeleine.
-Really? Because they're quite crap. -Oh, really?
Yeah, they're just... Do you guys know what they are?
-They're like a little sponge cake. -I've not had one.
You would have had one. They're just so boring.
You idiot, Dan. Of course you've had one.
Ironically, they're very easy to forget.
Yes.
They're like a tiny little sponge cake.
They're shaped like a scallop, a shell, you know, a seashell.
-They're shaped like that. -Yeah, yeah, okay.
But in the original book, it was a bit of toast, originally.
I thought, "This needs a rewrite."
I just wondered if you wanted to guess some other countries
-and what they did for their sweet things. -Oh, my God, yeah.
Because France has so much France, it's the land of cakes, you know?
The Eclair. I would have submitted the Eclair.
Well, you didn't. Have they didn't?
Yeah. Did they win? Did they win with the Madeleine?
It wasn't a competition. It was just like...
What's the point of it, then? What is it?
What's the point of anything if it isn't a competition?
You know, this isn't a competition, Andy.
No one wins this out of the four of us at the end.
Don't be ridiculous. We've been scoring for the last 450 episodes.
-I'm definitely confident. -I actually can imagine Andy going home
and having a little white barge when he puts that in.
Another great win, Andy. Well done.
The soul metric is a number of chicken-rubbing references
made throughout the show.
OK, so what other countries have made it?
I mean, yeah, just that. They're all relatively easy to guess. Belgium.
-It has to be a sweet thing. -Croissant?
-Croissants in Belgium. -Sweet chips.
Sweet chips.
Like, honey... Honeyfried.
-Waffles. -Waffles, waffles, waffles.
Portugal, pastel de nata, for instance.
Don't give it all away. Don't give it all away.
I just thought we'd go straight, maybe, to the UK.
Can you guess what the UK gets? Bloody hell.
Oh, that sort of pink Tottenham cake that you get in Gregg's.
It's very nice.
It's so nice.
I don't know what that is.
I'm pretty sure it wasn't from Gregg's.
OK, OK. Victoria's sponge cake.
No, no.
Thick Norf.
-Thick Norf? -Thick Norf?
-Oh, those buns. -Fervent Norf.
-Scottish... -Scottish roll.
[LAUGHTER]
A Scotch egg.
They misunderstood the category and they gave a Scotch egg.
A deep-fried Mars bar.
[LAUGHTER]
-A haggis. -A haggis.
-A sweet haggis. -A sweet...
What, and sausage roll was fine?
-You said sausage roll. -That was me?
Oh, my God.
It was shortbread.
Oh, OK.
And Denmark went for the Danish pastry,
even though they were invented in Austria.
-Ooh. -Sneaky.
And who won?
[LAUGHTER]
I think the Madeleine bit
is really only famous because
it's so near the beginning.
It's the only bit anyone's got to.
I have to say I have read
and intend to when I have
a period of time off next year.
Read properly, but I researched it on Purdue
because I think people are really hard on it,
even at the time they said it was impenetrable.
And I think it's really fun to read from the 40 pages I read.
But the Madeleine does come up within those 40 pages,
and it's not that relevant after that.
But he did, it shows how much he agonised
over everything, that as you said, Andy,
it was a piece of toast for a bit.
It was also a piece of stale bread,
which is quite, I don't know why you would eat that.
It was...
It was a sausage roll at one stage, wasn't it?
[LAUGHTER]
OK, it is time
for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that in the 1920s,
a smart young man would have two handkerchiefs,
a blower and a shower.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah.
It's disgusting.
What's the difference between them?
Yes, there is a difference.
So, I got this from, I was reading an old novel
called Green Banks by Dorothy Whipple,
which is great, she's great,
and there's a scene in it where there's a young man
waiting for his girlfriend,
and he talks about having his blower in his shower,
and I just peaked my interest.
[LAUGHTER]
It's very funny.
It's hard to google.
So, the shower is the one you have
in your top pocket, the sort of pocket square
that looks incredibly neat and jazzy,
and then the blower is the one
you keep up your sleeve with all the snot on it,
and that's the difference between them.
Could the shower become a blower?
Oh, yes.
Absolutely.
But you couldn't make a blower a shower, could you?
No. No.
You can blow a shower, but you can't show a blower.
[LAUGHTER]
I disagree.
It depends on where you're blowing on the blower.
If you blow on the blower in, like, a top corner,
and then you fold it down, half of it,
it's like an iceberg, a shower.
There's a lot of it below the surface area.
Well, okay.
Yeah, just don't blow on the show bit of your blower.
But it could start to come through the pocket, you know, like...
How?
If you've got enough... How stocky are you?
If you've got that cold, then you don't want
to snot seeping out of the bottom of your pocket
with the shower proudly seeping out the top.
No, that's true. Yeah.
I say keep them separate. I say keep them separate.
Dan's the one who's proposed this Maverick system where you can...
[LAUGHTER]
But it's rare, this usage of these phrases,
but it did exist at the time.
It crops up in the New York Times in 1927,
and it's a report about the handkerchief
being something from ancient China, you know, originally,
the only show was not blowers.
And it didn't used to be for that, did it?
We only actually started blowing anything into handkerchiefs
in about 400 years ago.
And it seems like a long time ago.
But we had handkerchiefs long before that,
or kerchiefs, which are just...
It's just a word for something that wraps
around your head, in fact.
A headkerchief?
Well, this is what's so weird.
A kerchief is literally a head covering,
chief head, and then ker was covering.
And so now we have a hand-head covering,
is the word?
Is a head covering you hold in your hand, basically.
Yeah.
I always thought that kerchief,
when people say it, as they often do,
was an abbreviation of handkerchief.
Didn't know it had gone the other way.
We know the first person, possibly,
who blew their nose on a handkerchief.
Kidding, really? What?
Well, we know the first person who wrote about it.
And this was a guy called Desiderius Erasmus,
who we have mentioned once or twice before.
The philosopher?
The philosopher and religious scholar.
But he also, and we have said this before,
he wrote a best-selling book
on etiquette.
And at one stage, it was a best-selling book
in the whole of Europe for dozens and dozens,
if not 100 years after the Bible.
Basically, the Bible and then this.
And in this book, it said stuff like,
"Do not be afraid of vomiting.
It is not vomiting, but holding vomits
in your throat that's foul."
Mmm.
Politely disagree.
OK. Well, let's see.
Having been up and down some high streets
on an early Sunday morning,
sometimes you do wish people had held it
in their throat a bit.
He also said, "If you cannot swallow
a piece of food, turn around discreetly
and throw it somewhere."
Oh, that is good advice.
That's good. And finally,
"Do not move back and forth on your chair.
Whoever does that gives the impression
of constantly breaking or trying
to break wind."
Just America.
Oh, I think it was him, sorry,
who said, "Because this was just about the time
when handkerchiefs were starting to be blown
noses on."
Have noses blown on them.
And so, some didn't, some didn't.
And he said, "If you need to blow your nose,
you can do it on the floor, not a table."
On the floor? On the floor? Yeah.
Blow your nose on the floor? Oh, right.
Put your finger to your nostril and blow it
in the direction. Yeah, sorry.
You don't have to rub your face against the floor.
Yeah, exactly.
But he said, "If it is visible,
you do have to keep stepping over it
and on it until it's gone away."
Yeah. And he was basically, because people
were doing that or wiping out on their clothes
and he said, "This was an improvement," which I think
even Andy will admit. Yeah.
The handkerchief? Yeah. Definitely an improvement.
No, no, they're blowing on the floor compared to blowing on your clothes
because I would say blowing, I'd probably do a subtle blow
into my cuff rather than onto the floor, wouldn't you?
Depends on the scale of the blow.
Yeah, it depends. I just think it's completely...
Sounds like with your leaking handkerchiefs
as a dangerous manoeuvre.
There was a thing that I read, which is that
there was a period where people weren't carrying
two handkerchiefs on them, but 30.
This was actually as part of
defence against
bullets. So what this was is,
in the late 1800s,
there was a physician called George E. Goodfellow.
He lived in Tomb Zone, Arizona,
or certainly was there at the time,
and there was a post-mortem that was done on a man
who'd been shot, and there was a silk handkerchief
in his breast pocket, and they realised
that the silk handkerchief had
significantly helped for the bullet
to penetrate less. It was like, wow, that dented
the force of which it went. So he thought,
"What if we dressed
in lots of handkerchiefs, then
we would never die?" So he invented
what was... This is such a chaotic...
premature bulletproof vest,
whereby you wore 30 layers
of handkerchiefs on your body.
Yeah, and I think
it worked. I think people were shocked.
He did, until he got a really heavy cold,
and he just had to keep pulling around.
He became less and less safe.
Did people actually wear it?
Or was it just him trying to market his product?
It was him just experimenting with the idea
of bulletproof vests didn't need
to be metal plating, which is what everyone
was using at this point. The problem is
30 handkerchief vests weighed
much more than a metal plating, so...
But it is... It is white.
No Morris Dancer has ever been shot.
Because they've got the skills to move the handkerchief
into position at the right time.
So, handkerchief.
Yeah. The word "hanky-panky".
Oh, OK.
Does it come... Is it related to handkerchiefs?
It has nothing to do
with handkerchiefs.
It's not short for handkerchief-pankerchief.
LAUGHTER
No, it's not.
Can it be now?
Yeah. I just
imagined Andy going back home to his wife.
Little bit of handkerchief-pankerchief.
LAUGHTER
I'm only wearing 27 layers
of handkerchiefs tonight, darling.
Oh...
Is there a factor in that?
Not really, guys.
It's that handkerchief-panky
has nothing to do with sex.
It's completely originally meant juggling
or trickery.
But still nothing to do with handkerchiefs
because you would think...
It's maybe related to hocus-pocus.
Right. Hocus-pocus, hanky-panky.
That's a very sleazy magician, sorry.
Hocus-pocus, hanky-panky.
LAUGHTER
Have you guys heard of the
Valsalva effect?
No. The Valsalva effect
is something that we've probably all done.
We must have all done this, which is
when your ears are blocked
or you're on a plane and you get descending,
there's action of holding your nose
and holding your mouth
and blowing to get your ears popping.
That's what you do to equalize as well, isn't it?
Yeah. So it's the opposite of blowing your nose.
You're sucking in...
You're using the pressure that's shooting inwards.
So that's used for a number of things.
It's for relieving your ears.
It's for people with abnormal heart rhythms.
They use it to relieve chest pain.
They say if you do have
abnormal heart problems that you should always
consult a doctor before doing that,
just to make sure that you don't
make the situation worse.
But another thing that it's used for
is for people who suffer from premature ejaculation.
Oh, really?
Because I have very bad sinuses
and have...
..and literally do that
Valsalva effect, I would say about
20 times a day.
Right.
I don't want to know what person or link you're making
to what bit of get-first is coming.
I want to know what's coming.
Not you.
You manage it.
Yeah, so pretty exciting, isn't it?
So you're supposed to do that mid-to-sex?
I think... I couldn't see where they said
if it was before or during,
but I imagine it's during, and I'm not sure
how you can disguise that as a sexy thing.
So next time you're having handkerchief,
handkerchief at home maybe.
Try it out and let us know
if it's before or during that it's required.
They are sexy things, though, aren't they?
Handkerchiefs. They were used
for sexy purposes back in the day.
In the 19th century, there were another one of these things
where there was a whole language behind handkerchiefs
that lovers could use to convey
messages to each other.
And there's actually a book, because we've talked before,
I think about the language of flowers.
If you sent flowers in a certain arrangement,
it meant different things.
Fans, the language of fans.
If your fan is three-quarters open, it means I'd like a handjob
but not a blowjob or whatever.
As you see, the woman with the fan.
So actually, anyway...
You're an absolute menace
in the summer, aren't you, Anna?
LAUGHTER
Question one, if you just want to keep cool.
Being pounced on.
There's a book published in 1879
called "A Complete Guide
to Glertation, Containing Handkerchief,
a Glove, Fan and Paracel Flirtations
and a Complete Language
of Flowers". So we have to assume everyone
memorized this at the time, so they understood
what each other was saying.
But drawing a handkerchief across your forehead,
do you know what that means?
Sweaty. Yeah.
It either means you're sweating profusely
or it means we are being watched.
Oh.
Don't jump me.
Across the cheeks was "I Love You".
Face cheeks?
LAUGHTER
The face cheeks, yes.
It's worth knowing.
Yeah. It doesn't actually...
This is where the problems can come, if you don't know.
I didn't actually note down the arse cheeks one,
so you'll have to just decide for yourselves.
Through the hands, if someone, you're talking to someone,
they'll weave a handkerchief through their hands.
Oh, yeah. I hate you.
Oh! Really?
It's horrible.
There was another one later in the 1970s,
which was in the LGBTQ community.
And you might wear
different handkerchiefs or bandanas,
and the colour might tell you what your fetish was.
So if you're in a club with like-minded people,
it would tell them what you're thinking.
Also, cartoon characters tend to wear
hankies and bandanas around their necks
because necks are quite hard to draw.
Oh, really?
And so... Oh, no.
Fred Flintstone wears a light blue sort of
cloth around his neck.
Apparently, he's into fallatio.
LAUGHTER
I'll rattle through these.
Fred from Scooby-Doo,
red, fisting, and...
Oh!
Captain Pugwash,
light cream, rimming.
So...
It's just if they happen to be in a club,
then that's what we've got.
Wow.
OK, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
OK, my fact this week is that in the 1960s,
owners of a theme park in Pennsylvania
had guards with plastic bats
in the Tunnel of Love ride
who were instructed to give an admonishing
thwack to any bear bums
that they saw.
LAUGHTER
Cover that with a handkerchief now!
So this is a true thing that happened.
In actual fact, it didn't just happen in Pennsylvania.
It happened in a few different places.
And when you're saying plastic bats,
I'm thinking of table tennis bats.
I'm not thinking of a plastic
winged mammal bat.
LAUGHTER
I have seen them. They are table tennis bats.
Nice. Some of them were actually almost in the shape
of a hand, you know, like one of those big, sort of foam hands.
Yeah.
It was plastic, and they would whack the bums like that.
Oh, wow. And it's cos they didn't want people
making out all worse in their Tunnels of Love.
No, handkerchief, handkerchief. No.
LAUGHTER
So this was an article.
Originally, I read this in Mental Floss,
and I followed it up and found an article
in the Pittsburgh City Paper.
And this is about a place called Kenneword Theme Park.
And there is a ride there called The Old Mill.
It was constructed in 1901.
It's the oldest roller coaster in the whole place.
And it's one of these, you know, like a log flume,
where you're going in the water,
but there's no up and down bits.
You're just kind of slowly going round in the water.
Yeah.
And there's like things to see on the side.
So there might be scary things.
There might be skeletons, or there might be sexy things,
or whatever.
Yeah. Yeah? Yeah.
Yeah, fair enough.
And then I found this YouTuber
called Defunctland,
and he's done a video on this,
and it's one of the best videos I've ever seen
in my entire life on YouTube.
It's all about this place.
And he found an article from 1934
saying that this Tunnel of Love
was a really good place for people to make out.
And he found other Tunnels of Love
where people were whacking birdbombs.
And he asked people,
"Have you or anyone you know
ever kissed
or had sex
on the Tunnel of Love
in Kennywood?"
And he tweeted saying that
"I have received the most explicit,
disgusting and shocking emails
I have ever read."
[laughter]
So this was really...
And there are newspaper articles from the 30s, 40s, 50s,
60s, even, all of them saying
this is the place to go and make out.
This is where kids make out.
This is so famous for that.
It's only six minutes long, the ride.
Four minutes more than I need, buddy.
[laughter]
Well, I've got a technique with a nose.
I wonder for how many people
who got slapped on the butt by the ping-pong paddle,
that turned into
a sort of exciting new fetish that they didn't realise.
I think there might have been a bit of that.
There must have been so many Christmases where
they were going, "Yeah, yeah, I've got some ping-pong paddles.
I don't know, I just want to get into the sport."
There's no reason.
Can I say something incredibly boring
about this theme park, Kennywood?
Yeah.
So it was a trolley park originally,
and a few weeks ago on the podcast we mentioned trams.
Yeah.
That episode hasn't gone out yet,
but we will have recently mentioned trams.
[laughter]
And what's a trolley park?
I'm so glad you asked, Dan.
It is a miniature adventure park,
or a park with rides,
that's put at the end of a trolley line.
So trolley is just an American word for a tram, basically.
And it was to encourage people
to use the trolley car network at weekends.
So you would normally use them to get to work,
but at the weekend they weren't being used,
so they put something to attract people.
Exactly.
And so, sorry, I just thought we were all having so much fun,
and I just wanted to talk about tram infrastructure.
[laughter]
No, it's a good pallet cleanser.
Any more on this?
Well, just one other ride that there was
at Kennywood in the early days,
which was, sorry, not a ride.
There was one thing, an attraction called the House of Mystery,
but no one knows what it was.
[laughter]
That's pretty good.
Did no one ever come out of it?
It's been lost to history, unfortunately.
And there was one thing called spring water,
which was just a water fountain,
the stream of water coming from a spring.
There was a tin cup you could use to get a drink,
but you could use the water,
so that you would just get an electric shock
every time you tried to have a drink.
That was entertainment.
These rides are tunnels of love,
which you don't really see much anymore.
In fact, I don't think I've ever seen one myself,
a fairground ride or a theme park or whatever.
There's a few, like, in the UK.
Yeah, yeah.
But they're basically the equivalent of rides
that we've all seen at parks where you essentially get on them
when you can't be asked a cue for one of the good rides again,
and so you just sit on this really slow, boring boat.
And so they were often haunted rides
that were converted to tunnels of love or vice versa, weren't they?
So I think this one, at Kennywood,
went on to become hard-headed Harold,
horrendously humorous, haunted hideaway.
That's right.
It sounds like a worse ride.
They also branded it as a Panama Canal.
So you would go down here,
and it was this few going along the Panama Canal.
That's great.
It is, but the Panama Canal is literally just a canal.
There's no fun stuff on either side.
No, you're right.
And then in the end,
it was rebranded as Garfield's Nightmare Ride.
All of these...
Cat. Yeah.
Or President James Garfield.
Who wastes everything through his anus
for the last three months of his life.
Weird ride.
But I want to ride.
This guy, Defunkland,
who did this amazing video,
he said that he thinks, after getting all these emails,
that there are at least two people
who were conceived on that ride.
Oh, great, really?
And Kennywood Theme Park now uses the slogan,
"Welcome to the family."
But that's just a coincidence.
That's okay.
The Tunnel of Love, really.
I've read something saying there used to be hundreds,
as in maybe 700 across the USA.
Yeah, the USA is big, but that has a lot of Tunnels of Love.
But it all sort of sadly came into an end
because of the sexual revolution.
Yeah, but that's the thing.
The humanity became liberalised.
So basically you could snog in public.
You didn't have to go into a tunnel.
And because they were such a shit ride,
that was really the only good thing about them.
Another strike against the sexual revolution.
Do you guys know what was the fastest way to travel
in the entire world in 1880?
I'm going to say Tunnel of Love.
That is a ridiculous thing to say.
I don't know if everything was slow at the time.
Maybe there was a point in 1880 where all trains broke.
All the horses in the lane.
All the horses died.
Was it?
I'm just kind of...
Because I know this sneaky man, what he does.
I start seeking.
Was it an underground train system
that was one of the first of its kind,
underground in Paris that led to the Louvre?
And so it was the Tunnel of Love.
The Louvre?
He's seeking. He's not the Riddler.
OK, I'm going to have a pun.
Fastest trains at the time.
In America, they were only about 30 or 40 miles an hour.
In the UK, I think we had up to about 60 or 70 miles an hour.
I'm talking about something that was going at 112 miles an hour.
And this was public transport.
It was something you could travel on.
Because if you jump off the Eiffel Tower or something...
I wouldn't say jumping off the Eiffel Tower is transport.
And in 1880, definitely not.
Another bad commute, darling.
OK, no, no, but I think...
So the Tunnel of Love is a kind of boat ride that you go on.
Is it something like a log flume?
It's exactly a log flume.
So I found an article in the Chicago Herald in 1886
that told of a group of loggers, right?
So they're at the top of a mountain,
and they created these flumes.
They were kind of metal flumes,
which they would send the logs down,
and they would all go down to the bottom,
and that's where they would process them.
You cut them at the top, you would send them down.
Really, really steep.
Now, at the end of the day,
all of these workers would get on one of these logs
and fly down.
OK, there was a quote, and they said,
"We all looked at our watches.
We had made 16 miles in eight minutes and 40 seconds."
So that is an average speed of 112 miles an hour.
But they did come down there.
It's so terrifying.
There was a journalist in 1875, I think,
who went to report on the Nevada log flumes,
and they looked so cool,
and there is video footage of the logs going down them,
and they were built really high on scaffolding into the air,
like 70 feet in the air,
and they were these channels, which they zoomed down.
And yeah, this journalist said,
"Does anyone ever go down it?"
And they said, "Yeah, yeah, you can totally do that."
Now, I still don't know if the log was on this one,
actually did go down it, or they were pranking the journalist,
because the journalist said, "OK, I will."
The two owners of the log flume said,
"All right, well, if you're doing it, I guess we'll do it."
And none of the loggers agreed to get in with them.
And as they pushed him off, one of the loggers shouted,
"A flume has no element of safety.
You cannot stop. You cannot lessen your speed.
You have only to sit still, shut your eyes,
say your prayers, and wait for eternity. Bye!"
Smile for the camera.
And that's what their log flume rides are based on, those, right?
Right, yeah, yeah.
I think they've all shut down other log flumes,
but I think there was one operating relatively recently
in Washington, in the state of Washington,
which took an hour to go along, so it might have been a bit slower.
Yeah, yeah, they weren't all really steep,
just the ones on mountains were.
Lassie went on that one.
She did an episode of Lassie where Lassie went on a log flume.
OK, great.
Nice. Good.
She deserves a break.
Is Lassie a she? Yeah.
I didn't know that. Lassie.
Oh, Lassie.
It's in the name. It is in the name.
Jane Austen could have gone on a log flume.
That's the exciting...
It's one of my main interests is whether Jane Austen
could have done any of the tech we talk about.
So she was alive when...
But not the ride, the log flume, the actual log flume thing.
A tunneled boat ride.
This was a ride, actually. It was in France in 1817,
which is the year Austen died,
so she wouldn't have had a great time on it.
What a way to go.
She died of something completely sort of ordinary and sad,
but if she died on a log flume,
it would have been perfect.
It was called the Soet du Niagara Falls,
and it was a boat which fell down a slope into a basin of water.
I mean, it's pretty much a classic log flume.
Anyway, Jane Austen could have...
I have a Red Mansfield Park. Is that about a theme park?
LAUGHTER
I can't believe you thought of Mansfield Park.
I was going through sense and sensibility.
No, that doesn't work.
Have you guys heard of...
There's a sex theme park in South Korea called Bloodland.
Have you seen it? No.
It's amazing. We say it's a theme park.
It's kind of like a sculpture park,
and it's just lots of penises and lots of people in positions of sex.
So it's not... You can't ride them, as it were.
There.
No, I don't think so.
Yeah, you can... Well, they do say there's a few hands-on exhibits,
such as the masturbation cycle,
which is you basically spin a thing
and you move their hands for them as part of this little exhibit.
It's a statue kind of thing. Right.
And then there's this really weird thing,
and I couldn't find anything more about it.
I searched quite a bit. It's this giant...
It's like a five-foot tall see-through penis
with sort of like computer workings all inside of it,
and it's just got a little plaque next to it,
and it's got a lot of words in Korean, which obviously I can't read.
But then there's only one English word on it, as far as I could see,
and the word is "terminator."
And that's...
I don't know if they're saying that's his particular penis,
or if it's a penis of the future coming back to our time to...
Would he have donated his penis? I haven't seen "terminator."
Is that the sort of thing that the character would do?
Yeah, I'll be back until I'm back. How's this?
Yeah, that's on Jeju Island, isn't it?
Yeah.
Originally, Jeju Island was like a honeymoon destination,
but it was... After the Korean War, there was a lot of arranged marriages,
so a lot of the couples had never seen each other or really met each other before,
and so they would go to this honeymoon destination,
and they were really inexperienced.
They didn't really know what to do,
and so they had... All the hotels had professional icebreakers
who would kind of sit next to you.
If you're having dinner at a restaurant and you're being a bit awkward,
- you're going to get a sensation again. - God, that's a great idea.
Sorry, you would be the worst human on earth as an icebreaker.
Did you know there was a trolley system on there?
Where are you going? Come back.
I'm saying I need one, not that I could be one.
I don't want to talk about traps any more than you do.
It's all I can think of.
Wow. This really is a cry for help.
OK, that is it. That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shriberland, Andy.
Trams, trams, trams.
- James. - @JamesHarken.
- And Anna. - You can email podcast.qi.com.
Or you can go to our group account, which is @NoSuchThing.
Or our website, nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
You can also find the link to Club Fish,
which is our very exciting behind-the-scenes membership club.
There's all some things on there, extra episodes of behind-the-scenes
sort of correspondence episodes and quizzes.
There's also access to our Discord, where you can discuss all interesting things,
like how Andy would make a great icebreaker, whatever it is you wanted to chat about.
And also, there's a lot of really fun merch up there.
So do go there.
I want to thank you so much, Bloomsbury, for this great show.
Thank you so much for having us.
And we'll be back again with another episode next week, everyone.
And we'll see you then. Good bye!
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)