(upbeat music)
- Hey, Club Fishers, Dan here.
Welcome to your secret bonus bit of content.
We have a compilation for you this week,
which is quite exciting,
'cause we haven't done a compilation in ages.
And actually, as a result of not having done it
for such a long time, there's a huge backlog.
We have so much unused archive.
And what you're gonna get today is a special one
because it's gonna be populated entirely
in every single clip with an old friend of the show,
very familiar voice,
but I think you're gonna be quite excited to hear again.
She's a good one.
So I hope you enjoy it.
And also just wanna quickly say thank you
to everyone who's bought tickets to come see us
at the Soho Theater for both July and August.
We're doing 11 shows each night with a new special guest.
And they're basically sold out every single show.
There's only a few tickets remaining.
And if you want to try and come to one of those,
then please head to knowsuchthingasafish.com/live.
And you'll find the link there to the Soho Theater
and you'll be able to get the tickets.
However, if you can't make that,
but you're thinking, "But I am in London in September."
Well, good news.
We're very excited to announce
that we are gonna be once again
playing the London Podcast Festival.
This happens at King's Place.
It's such a fun event
because all the British podcasts get to come together
and do their live shows.
And we get to be one of them.
And if you wanna come see that,
we're gonna be doing that on the 14th of September
at 7 p.m.
So all you need to do is go to
knowsuchthingasafish.com/podfest
and you'll be able to get tickets there.
I would do that ASAP
because we haven't announced this anywhere else yet.
It's gonna be announced on the main show on Friday.
So you've got a few days to get in there early
and snap up all the tickets.
If you're thinking, "God damn it, another London show.
When am I gonna be able to see fish outside of there?"
We're very sorry.
This is just how it has to be for the moment,
except for the fact to say
that this show is gonna be streamed online.
So you could be anywhere,
anywhere in the world and watch it.
So all you need to do is head to that link,
knowsuchthingasafish.com/podfest
and you will be able to buy
an option for online streaming.
So go and do that.
Buy tickets to the live show itself.
If you do happen to be in London,
we love doing these London Podcast Fest shows.
They're really, really funny.
They're full of facts,
dorkery, bad puns and more, as it says in the briefing.
And hopefully we'll see some of you there.
Otherwise, please enjoy this bonus bit of content
with our good mate, Anna Tyshinski.
- I was talking to someone about
a blood transfusion the other day
and she was saying that afterwards,
the energy, this kind of revitalize,
she was like, "I felt like I was 20 again."
I was just like, "I wonder if it gives the--"
- Was it the queen?
- Yeah. - You were talking too.
(laughing)
- And she has lizard blood, which is extremely,
yeah, you'd really get a kick off that.
- Another animal that drinks blood is the lamprey, the fish.
Supposedly the most bloodthirsty of all the fish,
according to a Michigan newspaper in 1955.
- That's a very honest of you to say.
- Well, I thought it was quite a strong claim.
But anyway, lots of royals and stuff
would eat lampries, right?
- Was it Henry II?
- I mean, the first, I think.
- The first?
- The first surfeit of lampries.
- He died from a surfeit of lampries.
But in all the jubilee celebrations throughout history,
they've always had lamprey pie in Britain.
And Queen Elizabeth's platinum jubilee was the first,
since records began, that didn't have lamprey pie.
And that's because lampries are kind of endangered
at the moment, especially in Europe.
It's really hard to get hold of lampries.
- For her diamond jubilee in 2012, they had lamprey pie,
but they brought the lampries in from North America
where they're slightly less endangered.
- But I can't believe they were still making lamprey pie,
which sounds like an incredibly old fashioned
18th century thing.
- Well, lampries still exist and pies still exist, right?
- Yeah, but you don't, it's not on as many menus
as it was in the 1600s.
Let's face it, I've never had lamprey pie.
- I can't picture a lamprey, by the way.
- It's like an eel, but then if you look at its face,
it looks like an alien from a movie.
- It's like a sea leech, basically.
They're just long, gross tubes with nasty mouths.
- But like the mouth is...
- Yes, I know them now.
- Right, so for the listener, they don't have a jaw,
so they don't have a normal mouth
that goes snap, snap, snap like ours,
but they've got a perfect circle,
and then it's covered in teeth,
and then also they've got a tongue,
which is also covered in teeth.
And so the way they suck blood,
and they suck a hell of a lot, don't they?
They latch onto a big fish, like a 40 pound fish,
they can drain it dry.
So a giant carp, they can drain dry
by just latching on, sucking on,
and then they drill their toothed tongue into the fish,
probing like a boar hole.
- It's so gross.
- There's a horror movie from 2014 called
Blood Lake, Attack of the Killer Lamprey's Brickhead,
in which the mare gets eaten by a lamprey
who comes up and bites him from his toilet.
- Awesome.
- Oh my.
- Toiler alert, sorry.
- They sound like the ocean Mongolian death worm, basically,
and they look exactly like them.
- I think like pretty much all these horror film monsters
that are long and with lots of teeth
must be based on lampreys, right?
- Yeah, so are we saying that the royals like lampreys
because they contain the blood that they need?
Is that why lamprey pie is such a treat for the royals?
- It must be.
- 'Cause we've made them sound absolutely disgusting to eat,
as in that these horrible blood tube alien things.
- Yeah, you'd want it hidden under the crust of a pie, I think.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, it's not the most.
- The most disgusting blanket of anonymity of the pastry, yeah.
- Well, just while we're on fishy things that drink blood,
you guys will have heard of the candiru, I'm sure.
These are the fish that don't swim up your penis.
(all laughing)
- Like all other fish.
- The one species.
- There are actually competitions to see what fish
you can get up there.
Some people get sharks up their penises and they really brag.
- I had an orca up there.
(all laughing)
- Awkward.
- So these, they're a kind of catfish.
- And the one thing they're famous for is the myth
that they will swim up your penis and.
- Are you saying it's definitely a myth then?
'Cause I know that the idea that they can swim up
the stream of urine as you're urinating into the water
is definitely a myth.
- That's what I thought was the myth, yeah.
- Well, so what the classic modus operandi is,
they will infiltrate the slits of the gills
of a larger catfish.
They'll grip onto the flesh inside,
they'll break a blood vessel,
they'll drink from the blood vessel
and then they'll swim out of the gills again.
That's what they normally do.
So obviously, the idea is that, you know,
they think a penis looks a bit like a fish's gill
and they swim into it, they're drawn to it.
Fish urinate through their gills, so.
- There we go.
- We'll urinate through our penises.
- Exactly.
- Half of us.
- It's so easy to see what the mistakes are.
- Better to be circumcised, I reckon,
if you're up against one of these guys.
I think it looks less gill-like, but continue.
(all laughing)
- Okay, there's how it is.
- That's my opinion.
- There's how it is.
Health and cosmetic tip for the week.
- Tune in next week to find out what that shit thing is.
Say then.
- I'm not going to your fish, my goodness.
- Is your penis too gill-like?
Have you considered?
(all laughing)
Sorry, do go on.
- The point is that the candiru has only once
swam up someone's urethra.
- That's enough.
- That's more than most fish.
(all laughing)
- But then it died.
So it wasn't a, it died and was able to be,
it was removed.
I imagine it was removed, actually.
- Why did it die?
- I don't know why it died.
Are you saying it's just one individual curious fish
that did this and the rest of his species
would never do it?
- Yeah, I think so.
Although actually this is only once
in the medical literature.
- Yeah.
- See, I imagine because if it swims into a catfish gill,
it remains in water.
So it has water around it.
If it swam into someone's penis,
they probably jumped out of the water
and then now it's out of its habitat, right?
- Might well do.
That might well be the case.
- Yeah.
- Anyway, it's not something to worry about much.
(all laughing)
- Did you guys know that Timothy Dalton went out
with K.A.D.?
- Really?
- No.
- So K.A.D., the war correspondent.
- K.A.D., very famous British war correspondent,
the ultimate war correspondent, really.
They went out, they were in national youth theater together
or so they were in a theater group together.
And--
- Since when have we become Hello Magazine?
(all laughing)
- I quite like it.
- This is the weirdest section of Hello Magazine.
(all laughing)
- I really want to start like a gossip magazine
or podcast but about like really like obscure
where people no one cares about
like K.A.D.'s form of sex life.
She said of Timothy Dalton,
he was a very shy young man
but I even sewed up his tights for him
while they were on.
(all laughing)
- Wow.
- You're saying it as if it's a very sexy thing.
- Guys.
- I think sewing up someone's tights
is actually the least sexual thing you can do.
- With a pair of tights at least.
- Yeah.
- While they're on, I mean if you're sewing it up
towards the crotch area.
- He didn't say that, I couldn't be in the toe.
- She could have stuck a pin through his cock.
I mean, it might not be sexy at all.
- That can be sexy.
- Yeah.
- Oh God.
(all laughing)
- It's K.A.D., it's sexy.
- Yeah.
- No, it's not.
- Anyway, so that's some hot gauze.
- That is hot gauze.
- That's hot fresh, fresh from the mid 1980s.
- Yeah.
- One famous scientist in this kind of plant sentience area
is Suzanne Simard.
We've spoken before about her work
with mycorrhizal networks.
So the idea that you've got lots of trees
and they have their roots
and on the roots they have funguses
and the fungus can kind of talk to each other
and that means the trees can talk to each other
and that means that if one tree is in trouble
with something they can pass on the message
to all the other trees, like an internet of plants.
- Get out of here.
I can't.
(all laughing)
- But some of her more recent stuff is that she's worked out
that kind of the patterns that these networks of trees create
are very, very similar to the patterns
in your neural network in your brain.
And so the trees in like a forest
is really, really similar to a human brain.
- What?
- And not only that, some of the chemicals
that they move between the roots are glutamates
and glutamates are also the neurotransmitters
that you use in your brain.
So it's almost like underneath the trees,
there is something that's not just analogous to a brain
but is also structured like a brain
and uses the same chemicals as a brain.
- What we're saying is the planet,
the trees are the brain of the world.
- No, the trees are like an upside down person
with the brain at the bottom and the legs in the air.
- The trees are the hair and under the skull, soil,
is the brain.
- I prefer legs in the air.
(all laughing)
- It's more fun anyway.
- Legs in the air is always more fun.
- So the trees are the--
- Legs.
- The trunks of the trees are the legs of the planet.
So the roots of the brain.
- Right?
- Yeah.
- You're really struggling with this.
Have you had a stroke?
- I'm just gonna stretch it out to the whole world.
So the trees, this network is the planet's brain effectively.
- Yes.
- I think that's what James was saying.
- Sure.
(all laughing)
- I think just next time you see a forest,
think of it as a bunch of legs waving in the air
and you'll enjoy your walk a bit more.
- And the genitals, I guess,
'cause that's where you pollinate, right?
So upside down with the balls in the air.
- Good point, yeah.
- Well, I'm gonna close my eyes the next time I see a tree.
(all laughing)
- Peep brood.
- Did you guys see the thing about the real life vampires?
As in people who drink blood?
- No.
- I've seen a documentary on them.
They're mostly quite weird.
- Not professionally, I was about to say,
but kind of as a compelled to do it.
- As a hobby.
- As a hobby, it is a hobby, yeah, yeah.
You need to get lots of health certificates
and things these days,
from the people whose blood you're drinking,
'cause you can get all sorts of diseases through blood.
It's an incredibly unsafe thing to do, it's general.
- Yeah, I read an article about the Atlanta Vampire Alliance
and they said that there are at least 5,000 people
in the U.S. that identify as real vampires at the moment,
but not all of them actually drink blood, apparently,
'cause you're trying to get life force from someone,
apparently some of them think that you can still
be a vampire, but get the life force
by giving someone a massage.
- What?
- No.
- Cheesy.
- That's what they say.
You're collecting the psychic energy of someone,
but instead of taking it through the blood,
'cause that's a bit icky,
you can do it through a nice little massage.
- I think you've got, there's gotta be some ingested
of some part of that.
You could maybe eat their dandruff.
(laughing)
A friendly veggie vampire.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
- What do they do then?
Do they sleep in coffins?
Do they sleep in the day?
Do they--
- They meet online and talkbots,
and then occasionally have in-person meetings
where they talk about.
Talk about.
- Massaging each other.
- It's mostly drinking blood based, though, isn't it?
Rather than, they don't do the garlic thing or the--
- They can be seen in mirrors.
(laughing)
- They're not dead.
- Not destroyed in light.
- Yeah.
- Cape sails have not rocketed.
- Right.
But those party teeth.
- They've all bought them, yeah.
- Those are apparently not good to drink blood with.
Vampire bats don't have those.
Their sharp teeth are right at the front.
They do have some sharpened teeth,
but they're right at the front,
and they just scratch until there's blood exposed,
and then they lap it up.
- Oh, okay.
- Yeah, cute, really.
- And they're more likely to bite you
on your big toe, aren't they?
- Oh, you're right.
- They tend to not fly onto you, bats,
and then eat you from your neck.
They tend to land a fair distance away from you.
You might be lying down,
sunbathing or sleeping or something,
and then they walk up to you on the ground,
and then they just kind of grab any exposed little bit,
which might be your fertile, your big toe.
- You can see why Bram Stoker sexed it up a bit.
Rather than just saying Dracula's sucking away on your toes.
I don't know, yeah.
- The fetishist out there, like a hood.
- I didn't know (beep) was a vampire.
(all laughing)
- There's the lawsuit bell, ding-a-ling.
- I can hear the lawyers making money, money, money.
- One good time to be selfish is if you have a partner
who's very altruistic.
So it's, you don't want two altruistic people
in a relationship or two selfish people,
but it is useful to have one selfish person
and one altruistic person in the specific time
that you're trying to work out what movie to watch
or what restaurant to go to or something like that.
- Who should have the last chip?
Because otherwise, if both of you are too altruistic,
you end up, neither of you have any chips.
If you're both greedy, you end up fighting.
(all laughing)
So this was a study, I mean, it's quite, you know,
obvious that that would happen,
but there was a study that proved it.
They got people to watch a load of clips of different shows,
like for instance, clips of Saturday Night Live,
some that are funny, some that are more interesting,
some that are more, you know, like horror films and stuff.
And they rated how much they liked each one.
And they also did surveys to measure how selfish they were.
And then a few weeks later, they were divided into pairs.
And when you got two selfish people together
or two altruistic people together,
it turned out that whatever they chose to watch
was something that neither of them liked.
When they looked at their old survey,
they found that actually neither of you liked this,
but you ended up watching something kind of,
you compromised to something that neither of you liked.
- God, I've been in that situation so many times.
Have you not all done that?
(all laughing)
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
- No, I think I'm the selfish one.
- Oh my God, you're always in there
watching something you love and you're poor white,
grinding away for another Arnold Schwarzenegger.
- It's just the Tom Cruise mission impossible marathons.
- Back to back, yeah.
- Can we at least watch a different mission impossible?
- No.
Six is the best.
- Yep.
- Can we split the chip in half, Andy?
(all laughing)
- It's already disappearing down my throat.
Have you guys heard of Sabbath mode?
- No.
- This is cool.
Lots of dishwashers are Sabbath mode.
And it's because there's this big argument in Judaism
about electricity on the Sabbath Shabbat.
If you turn on a light,
are you technically igniting a fire band?
Or are you theoretically cooking something also banned?
Or are you completing a product?
The product is incandescent light, also banned.
So this is a big problem.
And in 1998, Whirlpool's KitchenAid line of products,
they introduced Sabbath mode.
And it's basically just, I mean, it's just timers, isn't it?
- But they did that with a lot of products in America.
And they do things like with,
if you, 'cause America and New York, let's say,
there's a lot of high-rise buildings
and a lot of people living in flats.
So if you have an elderly Jewish family
that are living on the fifth floor,
how do they get up if they can't press
the elevator button to take them up?
So on Sabbath, the elevators are designed
so that they just stop at every floor on that day.
And it means that you can get in there without touching it.
But I like the Sabbath Goy,
which is what I guess all of us would be,
which is if you have friends who are Jewish
and they are very strict on Sabbath day
and they can't touch things,
they're not explicitly allowed to ask
for you to do something on their behalf.
But they can kind of subtly suggest it like,
"Oh, I want to be greater."
- There's a bloody dark in here.
(all laughing)
- I think not one or two,
'cause I used to live up in Tottenham
and I never did 'cause I was usually at work,
but my housemate used to sometimes be asked
to go around to our neighbor's house
to switch stuff on for them,
which I didn't realize we could have been like,
"Actually, pal, you're breaking your own laws there,"
by asking.
- How strictly you take care of it.
- There's so much to it.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- They're obviously taking it quite strictly enough
not to do it themselves, but not quite.
That's where they've drawn the line.
- Everyone draws the line somewhere, don't they?
- But did they explicitly,
do we know the language that was used?
- I don't actually know.
Maybe it was a hint.
- Yeah.
- I'm gonna have to draw that.
Well, someone's gonna have to draw me a line.
(all laughing)
- So, here's a cool thing about the first film,
the first avatar.
It was filmed on this massive great set.
It was like a hanger
and it was called The Volume, this huge space, right?
And it was where another great project
had been put together.
- Can we guess?
- Massive hanger in California.
- It was where they made the space shuttle.
- Oh, you're so close.
It's aeronautics.
- It's where the Wright brothers made the first plane.
- It's in between those two.
- Concorde?
- Oh, good.
- Have you heard of The Spruce Goose?
- Oh, yeah.
- How are you?
- The largest plane in the world was made in the hanger
where the largest movie in the world
went on to be made, yeah.
- Wasn't it The Largest Seaplane?
Is it The Largest plane in the world?
- It was humongous, wasn't it?
And it's made out of wood.
- It was made in almost entirely out of wood.
And I think at the time it was the largest plane,
as in the Boeing 747 was bigger,
but that was 30 years before the 747.
90% birch and then some rice paper
and some aluminum paint over the top of it.
And it was also--
- It was rice paper?
- Yeah, rice paper was involved in the construction.
- And the passengers also had eating the plane.
(all laughing)
- And it was 1942, you started making it.
And it was, or he'd been working on it for years.
And he spent, how would he use this as the,
again, eccentric.
- Very eccentric.
Used to measure his carrots before he ate them and stuff.
- Yeah, he used to keep bottles of whee with him.
- Yeah, he had a sad decline.
He became very isolated and obsessive.
And you know, had a--
- Well, this was part of it, I think, wasn't it?
- Well, it was the sort of grand project
that might have pushed him quite far.
- And played by Leonardo DiCaprio in a movie
who also play the aviator.
But isn't that weird that the aviator,
what does that almost exactly the same as?
- Avatar.
- It's the Avatar aviator.
- It was the West Country Avatar, wasn't it?
(all laughing)
- And it cost about $300 million in modern money,
slightly more than the film Avatar.
Isn't that weird?
- More than that.
- Yeah, yeah, and the wings were 11 feet deep.
You could walk comfortably inside the wings.
Guess how long it flew for in total?
Total aggregate time?
- I thought it only flew once.
- Well, maybe it flew a few times,
but yeah, maybe a couple of hours.
- 30 seconds.
- 30 seconds, absolutely.
- It had one test flight where--
- We'd travel us on board, right?
- Well, it was a test flight
just seeing if it could handle moving around,
basically, on the water, and then it did take off.
And there was always a question over
whether Howard Hughes had actually planned that all along
and flew once in 1947 for half a minute, and that was it.
- So weird, we got a tweet, actually, last night, I think,
just before, as we were researching this show,
from a guy called Chris Nobel, who follows us on Twitter,
who was pointing us to a thread, did you see it?
A thread on Twitter of loads of interesting facts
about punctuation.
It was by someone called @CulturalTutor,
and some of my favorite things were,
well, I really didn't know how old the @ symbol was,
and I don't think we've mentioned that before.
- I think it's an old shipping thing.
- I thought it was an accountancy thing.
So it's like five bushels at one pound each.
- You actually could both be right,
'cause it served lots of purposes over the years
from medieval times.
So it was used in medieval Bulgaria for the A in Amen.
If you couldn't be asked to write Amen at the end of a prayer,
you just do the @ symbol.
Yep, it was an abbreviation for a weight in Spain,
and it was, by the 17th century, actually, in France,
it was being used as short for @.
So that symbol all the way around.
Isn't that so weird?
Yeah, I do see that in lots of old medieval texts, yes.
- It feels like if you're doing a prayer,
you shouldn't be just taking shortcuts all the time.
- I don't know why.
You've struggled all the way to the end.
The power and the glory, blah, blah, blah.
Let's get out of the church.
- Was that the only one?
- No, so other good stuff.
I liked the oldest punctuation mark in history
that stayed unchanged as the asterisk.
- Oh, okay.
- I think it's been quite modern.
But yeah, it was used to correct a piece of Homer
in the second century BC.
- So was it used as a footnote,
as in that's where the correction
would appear underneath?
Wow, that's cool. - Yeah, in the same way,
I believe, yeah. - That's good.
- And I also didn't know that.
I mean, this is really too nerdy
and no one's gonna care except weird pettance.
But you know the possessive apostrophe--
- And presumably there's a person who tweeted it.
- And me, so at least I'm with the same.
- Probably our entire listenership, I would think.
- Exactly.
You all know it's a compliment.
The possessive apostrophe is actually--
- Come out, come out, come out.
(laughing)
- The possessive apostrophe is actually exactly the same
as the apostrophe that denotes a missing letter.
So you know if you say it's with an apostrophe,
to mean it is, 'cause you're denoting
that the I is missing. - Yeah, right.
- Actually, the possessive one, as in Andy's jumper,
it used to be that you'd write a possessive as ES.
And so it would be A-N-D-Y-E-S, jumper.
- Andy's jumper. - Yeah.
And then they just, you started using the,
or we've missed out the E here.
And so it's the same, look, it's the same thing.
- It's like a genitive ending in other languages.
- It's a genitive ending, yeah.
- Interesting.
- So that is interesting for a few--
- That's a nice funny bit to end the section on.
(humming)
(laughing)
- Would you rather have a general anaesthetic
or watch an episode of Only Fools and Horses?
(laughing)
- Definitely the anaesthetic.
- Which episode is it?
The one where Delboy falls through the bars?
- Yeah, of course.
- I can watch that.
(laughing)
- This was a thing that was tried in the year 2010.
It was--
- Did they really?
- Yeah. - Well, they tried
to knock you out by watching Only Fools and Horses.
- Well, they, so it was a study
on what makes people need less anaesthesia
and watching DVDs seemed to genuinely help
and mean people could get by with a local anaesthetic
rather than a general.
So you'd normally need to be knocked out
for these procedures, but people were,
it was a doctor called Nick Pace who,
and he just brought in his own DVDs from home.
So we also had Blue Planet and Mamma Mia
and other things and some of them.
- But it looked a taste, Nick.
Nice.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
He contains multitudes and basically it works
and distraction through whatever means
means you need less anaesthesia.
And there's been a recent study
which had VR headsets and also meant
that people need way less anaesthesia
'cause they just put you on a calm mountain top.
- At all, yeah.
- Oh, they don't put you inside Pecker.
(laughing)
- All right, Dave.
- You are Triggers Broome and you're moving along.
- You did that with Billy Conley,
playing Billy Conley to patients, didn't they?
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- They medically proved that Billy Conley
makes you feel less pain.
And I think what they did was they made them put their hands
in like a cold ice bucket or something
and they felt it less
when they had Billy's comedy being played to them.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- But Nick Pace said that some patients were disappointed
because the operation ended
before they got to the end of their DVD
of "Opening Fools and Horses."
- Really?
(laughing)
- I've just one more thing on the Imara people
who are indigenous Bolivians, which is really cool.
So they're really well-known,
the women for their really amazing knitting skills,
hundreds of years.
They've been hand knitting really intricate stuff.
And there was this great story,
I think it was about 10 years ago
where doctors have been trying to solve this problem
in Bolivia for ages of there being 10 times as many babies
as is the norm born with holes in their hearts.
And it's 'cause of the high altitude.
So something happens in utero.
And it's a problem you often need to operate on them.
And a doctor designed these,
like they look like actually mini top hats,
which you put up somebody in a catheter
and it travels up to the heart
and it blocks up the hole.
- It travels up to the heart.
- I know, it's kind of amazing.
Anyway, it's made with tiny intricate bits of wire
and it has to be knitted.
And it's too intricate for a machine to do it.
And so this guy thought, "Hey, who's really good at knitting?"
And he called up the Imara women and said,
"Can you start knitting really, really tiny wire hats
"to put in baby's hearts to block their holes up?"
And they did.
So this is what they do now.
No more woolly hats for the Imara kids, but...
- That is pretty amazing.
- But warm hearts.
- But warm.
- Oh, God.
- Really warm heart, that story.
- That is gross.
(laughing)
- Well, I've just got one more thing about
on the subject of gruesome animal trophies being worn.
- Oh yeah.
- This is actually, it's not a thing being worn,
but it is a Bolivian thing.
There's a big tradition in Bolivia of llama fetuses.
This is a huge, huge deal.
Yeah, yeah.
- Of wearing them?
- Not wearing them, no, that's the thing,
but they are incredibly lucky.
So they're sold in so-called witch's markets.
- Yeah, really?
- I think they're called sulus,
I'm probably pronouncing that wrong,
but they, and you know,
there are all stages of development.
They can be very, very tiny,
or they can be kind of miniature llamas, basically,
with wool on them.
And if you know what's good for you,
you'll bury one in the foundations of your house.
- Right, really?
- Very lucky, very auspicious property, yeah.
- Oh, God, 'cause you wouldn't think at looking at a llama.
I've never seen a llama fetus, but I don't imagine it looks like it.
- They're not very, they're not as cute as llamas.
- No, no, no.
- But it's the first question you'll ask
in a state agent in Bolivia is-
- On right move.
- Absolutely.
- Can you filter by that?
- There's a special box.
(all laughing)
- llama fetus check, two bathrooms check, yeah.
- You guys come across Peter Hicks.
- Peter Hicks, no.
- He was really famous in 1963,
because he kept getting annoyed with parking tickets
that he was getting in his van.
And so he parked it up in Short's Gardens,
which is just up the road from here.
And he put on a device,
which electrocuted traffic wardens in it.
- Oh, wow.
- Yeah.
And he just, he became this massive core celebrity
that if ever a traffic warden went to give him a ticket,
they would get electrocuted.
And I saw an interview with his son,
and he said he used to deliberately drive around
and park in a place where he knew he would get a ticket.
And it would always be somewhere outside a pub.
And then him and his mates would sit in the pub watching
and waiting for a traffic warden to come along.
- Presumably a pile of dead traffic warden
be filled by the car.
- He said that it's harmless,
apart from a bit of a flash in a nasty jog.
- You have fallen into your own pedantic trap
that you always lay between electrocuted and electrified
and implied that he was just murdering traffic wardens.
- That's true, yeah, that's true.
They were electrified.
But he told the press,
until someone tells me what law I'm breaking,
I shall keep up my private war.
And of course, they soon told him
exactly what law he was breaking.
I didn't know how much they were worth,
'cause snail slime is useful for beauty and stuff, right?
I think we might have mentioned it before,
but you can farm snails and you can extract the slime
and people put it on their faces
and they think it makes them look younger.
But the global snail beauty market
is worth $340 million,
which is about the same as Zoom is worth.
- Wow. - Wow.
- Yeah, so you could,
if you're the guy who owns or girl who owns Zoom,
I don't know who owns Zoom,
you could sell it and buy all of the snail beauty products
in the entire world.
- And would you recommend that as a business choice?
- It's just a would you rather, really, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- You'll have $340 million,
but there's gonna be a snail chasing you,
trying to make you look younger forever.
- Trying to claim the money,
'cause guys, do you know how much the snail see
of that money?
- Yeah, none.
- It's nothing.
- It's nothing, it's not expensive,
but they must get sort of living,
they must get treated quite well
compared with snails and the water.
- A nice lettuce leaf.
- Yeah, well, that's one of the big things,
'cause it used to be to extract the mucus,
you needed to basically force the snail
in order to produce it
and you would do things like throw vinegar on a snail
and that would make it in distress,
kind of produce the mucus.
Not really nice and it always dies afterwards.
And so there's a place, it's in Italy,
called the International Snail Breeding Institute,
and there's a guy there who has basically come up
with the concept of how you could treat them effectively
to a day spa and get better fluids out of them.
So here's the thing, happy snails produce better mucus.
They produce it and it's more, it's richer,
it's basically they're happy to give it out,
whereas in the petrified vinegary version,
they're like, well, and it just, it's not good.
- I imagine it's equally useful
for making you look younger, though.
- Yeah.
- Do you think it doesn't make you look younger?
- I shouldn't have thought so.
- You think it does?
- I just think it does, but I've no evidence for it.
- That explains why you've got
10 snails on your face right now.
(laughing)
I don't think any of those things work, do they?
- I don't know.
- It seems unlikely.
- As you say, it's a big industry
and one thing, if you do use snail mucus on your face,
if you're listening right now,
make sure that whatever you buy
doesn't say extract of snail slime slash mucus
because it's effectively a watered down version.
It's like, let's imagine ribena in like ribena
in the ribena with water.
- It's squash.
- It's a snail squash.
- But given that neither is remotely effective,
then you might as well get the cheaper one.
- Why are we all alienating future advertisers like this?
What are we doing?
- You can get dried powder made from the snail slime.
I don't know how useful that is,
but it sells for $58,000 per kilo,
which is 75 times more expensive than silver.
- What?
And what's that for?
Is that for the skin as well?
- That's for the skin as well.
Most of the article says it costs more than gold,
but gold has just overtaken it quite recently.
- That'd be good to smuggle
'cause no one would think to look for it.
Like the cocaine dog would come by and you'd be fine
because it's not cocaine.
- The cocaine snail, though.
(all laughing)
- The trial of those didn't work as well,
did it in airports.
(all laughing)
- It was three days later.
- Hey.
(all laughing)
- I lost in a pub quiz recently
to a group called the Big Titty Committee.
(all laughing)
Oh my God.
- It's pretty sad, isn't it?
- That is, yeah.
- It's a bad time.
- It's quite a good tactic in a pub quiz though,
to stand up with a really stupid name.
But actually you've been reading the Encyclopedia all day.
Whatever it is you do in a pub quiz, you know.
I would love it if every movie had
what happened to all these characters after the film.
- Would you?
Because my wife hates them.
- Oh, really?
- She really, like, properly, as in,
you know, there's a few things in your life,
we do quite a lot of things, haven't we,
that really, really, really gets you,
even though most people don't care about them.
- Well, I don't know what you mean,
I'm a very relaxed guy, I'm not easily irritated.
- Well, with Polina, it's these things at the end,
and she reckons that if you're a storyteller,
you shouldn't need them.
Like, the story should go from the start to the finish,
and you shouldn't have to add extra little bits at the end
to say, oh, by the way, here's a bit we didn't fit in
that you need to know in order for the rest of the story
to make sense.
- And it's always, you would only ever see that,
or I've only ever seen that in non-fiction stuff,
like film documentaries, right,
where it's like this person was released from prison
and lived happily ever after.
- I'm saying I want it in all films.
I want, at the end of Die Hard, I want to see,
John McClane went on to be in three more terrorist incidents
(laughing)
with steadily decreasing dramatic effects.
- But then I agree with that kind of, with that,
because you then lose, I remember seeing years ago,
there was a young Indiana Jones TV series,
and you see Indiana Jones as a very old man telling a story.
And I thought, well, okay, shit,
now I know he dies as a very old man.
I would rather not know where Indiana Jones met his ending.
And I know we have movies coming out now,
the latest one's coming out.
- 'Cause like, for instance, when you went to the cinema
and that big boulder was chasing him,
you're like, he's gonna get away.
(laughing)
I've seen him.
- Barge Haulers was a job, and they used to be naked.
- Barge Haulers, was that?
- Oh, yes.
- Was it when you're like on the bank of the canal,
like tugging along at the river?
- Tugging the barge, yeah.
This was, I was reading about barge Haulers,
which was a job in lots of countries.
And in China on the Yangtze, then they would, what?
- Yangtze, like, it sounds like Yangtze,
you're tugging someone on the Yangtze, you're naked.
- That's where it comes from, yeah.
But Yangtze didn't have a bridge until 1957.
And motor transport, not that common around,
especially like upper reaches of a 3000 kilometer long Yangtze.
And so the Haulers would haul your boat for you,
and they'd be naked.
'Cause wearing clothes hurt your skin.
- Oh, yeah.
(laughing)
- Not the act of hauling a massive boat up a river.
No, no, no.
- No, no, it's the bloody gloves.
(laughing)
- Oh, the chaffing.
- They just wanted to feel that soft rope on their skin.
I think also they ended up in the water hell of a lot.
So you don't get in the water too close.
- Oh, yeah, but they did, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Oh, I've fallen in them all wet.
(laughing)
- I've been breaking Chinese accent, you done?
- Okay, that's it for this week's episode.
I hope you enjoyed hearing Anna's voice again,
and I hope you enjoyed the general riffs.
As I said at the top, we are gonna be doing live shows.
Unfortunately, not with Anna, 'cause she will be away still,
but we do have some extraordinarily exciting guests
for the London Run at the Soho Theater,
and of course for our one-off show at King's Place.
So for the Soho shows,
head to knowsuchthingasafish.com/live,
and that's gonna get you to the link
to get you to the Soho tickets.
Only a few left, so do get in there quick.
And also, for the London show at King's Place,
London Podcast Festival,
if you wanna get in there quick before the general public,
go now, because we're gonna be announcing it
on Friday's show, so this is your head start.
And there you can find tickets,
not only for the live show, but for online streaming too.
So you will be able to watch it from anywhere in the world,
and all you need to do to get that
is go to knowsuchthingasafish.com/podfest.
Do it now, come see us live, come say hi.
We'd love to meet all of the Clubfish members.
Okay, we will see you another time,
another place with another bonus bit of secret content,
and until then, we'll catch you on a regular show.
Bye.
(upbeat music)