(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
Anna Tyshinski, and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered
around the microphones with our four favorite facts
from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
- My fact this week is that there was a job
in the 19th century, which just involved looking at the sea
and being able to tell when there were pilchards
under the surface.
(laughing)
- Amazing.
So were they, they weren't sticking their head
under the sea.
- No, don't be crazy, James.
- Okay.
- Little bit of inside baseball.
- Dan told us before we started recording
that's what he thought the job was.
- Yeah, and I told you before the recording specifically,
so it wouldn't get mentioned on the recording,
and look at us now.
This is an amazing job.
And it's not like they're sitting like a lifeguard
on a boat looking down.
They're up on a hill.
- They are.
- They're not even in the sea.
- So I should say where this comes from.
It comes from this brilliant blog called About 1816,
which is by an author called James Hobson,
who's written loads of books about George and Britain.
There's one about stage coaches,
which I was reading recently.
And he also writes about Cornish-piltered culture
in the 18th century.
- An obvious crossover.
- And well, there were these,
it was this huge part of Cornwall's economy
in the 18th century was piltered fishing
because they were these fish that came to the coast
by the million, millions and millions of them.
This job was called being a hewer,
literally like hue and cry, you know, shouting.
And they would stand on the high points along the coast.
And when they saw this moving patch of purpley,
oily color on the surface,
they knew that was the sign that there was the huge,
I was about to say flock,
a shoal of pilchards underneath it.
And maybe there was some sea birds hanging around it as well.
And then they would blow a special trumpet
or they would wave their little flags
and they would shout, go and get the pilchards
to the fishermen.
And then the fishermen would go and.
- No, they would, they would shout, hever.
- Trick.
- Yeah, hever.
- What does that mean, hever?
- It's an old word meaning fish and carnage.
- Ah, fish.
- But now you get hever cake
if you go to a Cornish bakery.
- But it's not fish cake.
It's just related to the cake that was baked
for these fishermen when they would leave for the day out.
- Oh, okay, yeah.
- And the trumpet thing, by the way,
hewing is an old word for trumpeting,
according to the OED.
- Apparently, yes.
- And it's not, this is not like your regular trumpet.
This was a four foot trumpet.
- Was it?
- Yes, huge.
- I know this.
- And they had these flags as well.
So they would wave semaphore flags,
which had special meanings to communicate to the boats,
like go over there or come this way a bit or whatever.
- 'Cause then they directed the boats, didn't they?
- Yeah, exactly.
- Which they'd seen them.
'Cause Wilkie Collins, obviously,
and I'm famous, Victorian author,
but he also wrote a bunch of essays
and one of them was about these hewers.
And he described them as feverishly waving
two cloth-covered bushes,
acting the part of a maniac of the most dangerous character.
'Cause they're just standing on a cliffside.
- Cloth-covered bushes, like before they had flags,
they had to cover a bush in cloth.
It's weird.
They could have just waved around the cloth,
if you would think.
- Yeah.
What would they, presumably,
if you had spotted, you've sounded your horn,
you've got your semaphore flag out, bush.
Presumably, you've sounded the horn
because you've seen pilchards.
Okay?
You've seen them over that way.
- Otherwise, you're gonna lose your job as a killer.
- You're gonna lose your job, exactly.
It's the main purpose of the job.
You've pointed your flag at the direction.
What semaphore needs to happen?
What are you trying to communicate with the semaphore?
- You're telling the boats where they are specifically.
So you're saying go to the right, go to the left,
go out to sea, come closer.
- Okay.
- Just drop your nets there, kind of thing.
- Yeah.
- It was probably less complex semaphore
and more just pointing a flag to the right or to the left.
- I'm pretty sure it was proper.
It was proper.
I've looked up the signals.
Yeah, yeah, I've looked up the signals.
So it wasn't just, you know, left for left.
- So what were they?
I take it back.
- I mean, this is the worst possible medium
to communicate what the semaphore signals were.
- You can explain.
- You know.
But it's just like you said, James,
there will be go east or go right off,
which means go straight out.
It doesn't mean go right.
And cast net.
- Oh, yeah.
- Also, they could get messages to ships.
So they could signal to a man on board a ship
that his wife had had a baby.
- Ah.
- Yeah.
- In semaphore language.
- I don't know what the semaphore for that was.
(laughing)
- That's so good.
- They're seriously oily.
I've never really understood when people talk about
oily fish and the non-oily fish,
and they're bang on about oily fish being really good for you.
What really, what the difference was,
but that's why they were prized.
So in the 19th century,
they were prized for their oil for lamps, weren't they?
- Yeah.
- And so that would just be sold
and that would fund the whole industry.
- Yeah.
- And you'd have these filtered palaces.
- Yes.
- Where they put all the fish in a barrel,
put 6,000 fish in a huge hog-seed barrel.
And then I think you squeeze down on the fish
and all the oil comes out and drains off into the gutters.
And then that's barreled up separately.
- Yeah, right.
- And you burnt, you can use it for lamps and things like that.
- Well, they used to just hand them out as well
to anyone who was quite poor.
So as the boats would come back in,
there's reports that you would have locals standing
in the water just waiting for it to come in and say,
"Can you please just give me Pilchards?"
And the person who was on the ship would feel
it was honor-bound to give the Pilchards.
So they would just hand them out.
And then at the palaces as well,
there would be the poor waiting outside
and they would be waiting for fish
that had like broken backs or that were diseased
or you know, the ones that were being shot.
- They must have derived from these 30 million Pilchards
with little x-ray machines.
See if they've broken their spine.
- Well, this one's got a bit of a cuff.
- That's the paw.
- Cross the line.
- But the only thing kids used to go to the beaches
with plastic bags and kind of scoop them out of the water.
But it's not just today.
- Plastic bags?
- But not plastic.
(laughing)
- Quite century and now, Cornwall is, you know,
quite behind the times in some aspects,
but in others, unbelievably advanced.
- It had the Tesco plastic bags early in the 1400s.
- They had the oil to make it from, didn't they?
'Cause it was a bloody Pilchard.
- Yes, exactly.
Sorry, not plastic bags, other bags, non-plastic bags.
- But yeah, so it was back in the 1800s, it was massive.
And in 1871, they were exporting
roughly 16,000 tons per year.
Now, that declined massively in Cornwall,
massively, massively, to the point of the 90s
where they were only landing about six tons in total.
So from 16,000 to six tons, and that's the early 90s.
But then that all changed when a man called Nutty Nowhere
came along and he reinvigorated the whole thing
by rebranding the Pilchard.
- I've seen Nutty Nowhere.
I think he's making some strong claims.
- Huge claims.
- Well, he's basically just a random fisherman.
Is he from the South Coast?
- Yes, what's he climbing?
- He's from Cadwyth?
- Oh, he's from Cadwyth.
Okay, yeah, I go to Cadwyth every year.
I probably met him down the pub.
And I don't know if he's a guy
who's reformed the whole industry.
I mean, it's not like everyone's eating Pilchards
for every meal, right?
- No, but I mean, a lot of people,
when you read interviews, sort of claim that he called them
Cornish Sardines, that suddenly was like,
"Ooh, that sounds a bit posh."
- Well, someone called them that.
They have had a rebrand.
- Yeah, exactly.
It wasn't him, but it was in that.
Well, actually, no, it was him.
- It wasn't him.
It was a guy called Nick Howell, I believe, in the '90s,
who, yeah, realized that Pilchards had a bad reputation.
They're called Sardines on the continent.
And so, yeah, they were called.
And Pilchards are just adult Sardines,
what we call Sardines, Pilchards are like adult versions
of that, aren't they? - And they're all herring.
- And they're all types of herring.
- What was his connection then to Nutty Nowhere?
- 'Cause Nutty Nowhere was--
- I don't know who Nutty Nowhere is.
- Oh, Nutty Nowhere's a guy called Martin Ellis,
and he was basically the only--
(laughing)
- Why do you keep calling him Nutty Nowhere?
- Well, that's what he calls himself.
It's his nickname.
And he kind of--
- Yeah, he collected two of every nuts, didn't he?
(laughing)
Saved them when there was a big flood.
- Exactly.
- Two peanuts.
- Well, ironically, apparently, his ship sank,
so I don't think, that's the story.
Did you read this?
- No.
- He took in too much Pilchard.
It's got too heavy, and his ship went down,
and it had to be rescued,
and the helicopter had to come in to do it.
- The helicopter's rescuing a whole ship.
(laughing)
- I think him and the Pilchards, possibly.
- Oh, sir.
(laughing)
- Take the Pilchards first.
- But this one's gonna broken back.
I don't care.
- Women in Pilchards first.
(laughing)
- Yeah, but the point is, I can't find any record
of a helicopter picking up a Pilchard man called Nutty Nowhere.
So it's the story that's told to him.
- I think they do a lot of rescues out in Cornwall.
- But they log them as well.
There's a log rescues.
- You do have to log the rescues.
It's frowned on to just go around rescuing people
and they're not telling anyone.
- Did you check Nutty Nowhere and his actual name,
Martin, whenever it is?
- Good point, I just did Nutty Nowhere.
I should go back and check Martin Ellis.
- They wouldn't put it on the form, would they?
Like, person rescues.
- It was a massive list.
There was six tons of Pilchard that I had to get through
before his name came.
(laughing)
Every individual one.
- Every Pilchard.
- I mean, actually, Billy, Sarah.
(laughing)
They are elsewhere.
It's not just Cornwall that has a monopoly on them.
And I actually, when I was looking at my Pilchard can
and realized it came from South Africa,
I thought, "I wonder how many there are?"
And there are shed loads in South Africa
and they've turned it into a big tourist industry there.
And the Sardine Harvest, the Pilchard Harvest,
is so massive that sometimes they don't need nets
'cause the sea just dumps piles on the beach.
- Oh, wow.
- The sea retreats.
- Also, just like a tractor or a dump truck.
- Exactly, scoop it up.
And yeah, they've got sort of festival days
where they invite tourists to come and take part
in various Sardine marches and stuff like that.
No one knows why they go there.
But it's kind of a mystery because the shores
of like Northern South Africa where they hang out
are not very appealing to Sardines.
- And do we know why they come to Cornwall?
Are they mating, or are they feeding?
- Oh, we don't know.
I think it's for feeding.
I think they're coming.
Which way would they be coming?
I think it's for feeding.
- But that African Sardine run that you mentioned, Anna,
that might be the biggest biological movement on the planet
'cause there's also the East African wildebeest herds.
Obviously, your individual wildebeest,
lot bigger than your individual Pilchard.
But there are so many Pilchards
that they might outweigh all the wildebeest.
It's hard to tell.
- It's one of those classic,
would you rather fight one wildebeest
or a thousand Pilchards?
- It depends where you're fighting them.
If you're in the sea,
I'll take on the wildebeest.
(laughing)
- 'Cause they've challenged you.
You are the one who gets to choose the location.
I would choose actually a hot air balloon for either.
For either fight.
- That's clever.
- Playing it really safe.
Don't even back yourself against the Pilchards
on the desert.
(laughing)
- Why take the risk?
- They have a tendency of disappearing and reappearing.
So I think people keep blaming the decline
of Pilchard industry on like people's declining tastes.
But they just bugger off sometimes.
This is the thing with oily fish,
is why you can't depend on them.
'Cause they slip through your fingers.
'Cause the reason they're,
it's not 'cause of that.
The reason they're oily is 'cause they have to have loads
of fat in their body because they're the fish
that migrate huge distances in massive shoals.
So that's why you've got these oily fish.
They're fish that pelagic,
that live in the middle part of the sea,
as opposed to all your white fish,
which live at the bottom.
- Good word.
- Which I think very much.
I didn't make it up myself.
(laughing)
But thank you.
So these shoals sometimes migrate somewhere different.
So in 1820, we say the industry was massive.
In 1820, they all disappeared and went to Ireland.
And the Cornish were really furious.
And there were articles written in the 1820s saying,
you know, this is a complete disaster.
The Irish don't like Pilchards.
They're just flocking to Ireland and the Irish are saying,
we think these are disgusting.
- The Irish do have their own hewers though,
and they have their special laws for their hewers.
- So I think it's got Pilchard fanciings gone up and down.
So they have sometimes had a big hewering tradition.
And then it just went out of fashion.
- Okay.
There's a special law in Ireland that if you're a hewer,
you're allowed to stand on any private property
to do your job.
- No way.
- What?
- I mean, you can't go into the middle of Dublin.
Like just stand in someone's house.
- I need to come into your bedroom now.
(laughing)
- Presumably it's someone's property that's on the coast.
- I got reason to believe there are five million Pilchards
in this room.
Let me in.
Let me into this bank vault right now.
Help me with my trumpet.
Can I just ask on the hewers that you said it was a job,
but they, I mean, the Pilchards just turn up
at one stage in the autumn, right?
So what do they do for the,
it's very seasonal this job, isn't it?
- It is seasonal work.
You're absolutely right.
I don't, I imagine they had a kind of portfolio career.
- They might be a trumpeter for the rest of the year.
- Yeah, absolutely.
Or a Bush, Semaphore instructor.
I mean, there's all sorts of stuff they could do
with their skills, you know.
But they had, yeah, they did get paid a guinea week
during the good times.
So maybe it was one of those jobs where,
much like a tourist season today actually,
you know, it's very big in the high seas.
And then you just sort of, you know.
- Could be a signalman.
- Yes. - A woman.
- Yeah, on the railways.
On the railways, for example.
- On the railways. - At the airports.
- At the airports, yep.
- Could be a plastic bag maker.
- Yeah.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the sound designer
for the movie King Richard is called Richard King.
- So good.
- Yeah, so good.
- So great.
Did you just, did you just spot this?
- No, this was a buddy of mine, Ali Plum.
He's the BBC Radio One music reviewer and interviewer.
He spotted it and he told me about it.
And yeah, Richard King is, you know,
he's actually quite famous as you can imagine.
He's part of this big movie.
- He's won for Oscars.
And he's, you know, he's been the sound designer for movies
like The Latest Wonder Woman 1984,
Tenet Dunkirk.
So he's very tied in with Christopher Nolan.
He did Interstellar with him.
- Do we know if Richard King only took the job
because he enjoyed the symmetry of the name?
- Oh, I've got a good reason why he might.
Tenet is all about things being backwards
as well as forwards.
- Palindromic.
- King Richard, Richard King.
That's, it explains why he took the job
as well as him being a massively respected sound engineer
and him needing the work.
But for Tenet, this is one specific thing.
So I haven't seen Tenet.
It sounds, so some things happen backwards
even though the world is happening forwards.
- Yeah, you kind of got two parallel things
that happen in one goes forward and one goes backwards.
- Why haven't I watched it?
But they had to make reverse gunshots.
So they tried playing all the sound effects they had.
You know, they have a sound effect of a gun,
which is a bang.
And then.
- Why didn't they just use you for that?
(laughing)
- But it's, but it sounded rubbish.
It sounded cheap and stupid
when they just played the sounds backwards.
So they had to generate new sounds of what, you know,
playing, taking off might sound like backwards,
but forwards. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Interesting. - It's so weird.
- 'Cause they could have just taken the original one
and made it go backwards, right?
'Cause they have that technology,
but it doesn't quite sound right.
- They have the technology to make sound rewind.
You're kidding. - It's amazing.
- I haven't been able to share this with the rest of us.
- 20 years ago, they had that.
But the thing is that King Richard is about tennis
and that movie is Tenet.
So maybe he's just looking his way through the fix.
- He's definitely got a word thing.
He's the Susie Dent of the sound engineer world.
- Sounds like.
- I don't know.
I wonder if this movie does
because they had a carpenter called James Crane.
Carpenter's might use cranes,
might, and they--
- Why?
I thought it was a carpeting emergency frame
for me to look like, oh yeah.
- Okay, look, this is--
- The viewer was stuck somewhere in Ireland.
- This is the one I'm opening with.
(laughing)
They had an ellen safety manager called Guinevere Aid,
like first aid.
- Yeah, that's good.
- I think that's good, yeah.
The tennis racket stringer was called Jeffrey Ibatuon.
- That's not true.
- Ibatuon.
- How are you spelling it?
How much of your words for pronunciation?
- No, no, I-B-A-T-U-A-N.
Ibatuon.
- Oh, wow.
- Okay, that's extremely good.
I would definitely have opened with Ibatuon
rather than James Crane, the carpenter.
(laughing)
If he'd been called James Plane,
I'd have been absolutely on board.
- I'll be honest, like I was working on
just basically all the people who worked on this show
on IMDB and it was Slim Pickings.
(laughing)
- It was Slim Pickings on it.
I love him.
So sound design has a nickname,
which is used within the industry, which is called Foley.
So you're a Foley artist.
Foley sounds within movies.
It's really amazing.
And particularly if you read interviews with Richard King,
he can make something that is quite a boring sound.
Some of these seem like, wow,
what a day that must have been of picking the sound
for this tiny thing that I would never think about.
If you're in a room and a door needs to be opened, right?
You would think, okay, there's probably just this bank
of sound where it's just door opens.
And he talks about it saying, no, the variety is endless.
You have doors that are opened because maybe they're open
because there's a baby sleeping in the room.
So it's a soft opening.
So he's like, you don't only have just the creaks
of a door speed opening, you have emotional content
to the opening of the door.
And he's like, so I have like, you know,
he's got thousands of doors that he's collected.
- The door, the happy door, the furious door.
- Drunk door, Terminator 2 I was reading about.
The opening scene of Terminator 2,
there's a sort of exoskeleton terminator walking
in a apocalypse over all these skulls and stuff.
So the ambient sound that you hear in that scene,
if you watch that scene next time,
is you've got someone having put a microphone
just next to the crack in the door
at George Lucas' Skywalker Ranch
and just getting the ambience of the outside.
And that's mixed with someone going, whoosh,
with their mouth, whoosh.
So that's what you're hearing in the background.
And then when this exoskeleton is standing
on all of these human skulls,
that's pistachio nuts being crushed.
So those are the elements that you see in that scene.
And just how they get to thinking a pistachio nut
can be a better sound than a real skull being crushed.
(laughing)
- Sometimes easy to access pistachio nut shells,
down natural skulls, isn't it, in different places?
- If you get a pistachio nut, you know how they're like
slightly open on one end,
if you just squeeze the slightly open end,
then the lever mechanism will open the other end
and you can just pull the top shell off
and then just get to the inside without kind of pressure.
- Are you sure that actually works?
- Yeah, I do. - Does it?
- Yeah. - Really?
- You would have been fired by Richard King
immediately when you handed in your sound effects.
- What the fuck is this, James?
- What I'm just thinking is,
when you watch actual tennis, right,
someone does a serve and you hear the noise
of the serve and it's quite,
you know, you would know that noise if you heard it, right?
But I remember reading that sometimes in sports, on TV,
they add the sounds in later, right?
I don't know if this is true,
but I remember reading that when a dart hits a dartboard,
if you imagine yourself playing darts,
they don't make that "foof" when it hits it, right?
But then some people do that.
And I remember reading that in horse racing,
there's no microphones on the far side,
so there's no way you could make that sound.
So I thought that they use "Wilder Beast."
- They do. - That's crazy.
- They absolutely, they play that in.
- It's the sound of a stampeding "Wilder Beast."
And they play it, they don't play it for the audience
in the, you know. - No, obviously live.
- On TV. - They play it over TV, yeah.
So this is insane.
I was reading about a guy called Dennis Baxter,
who was the sound designer for the Olympics in 2012.
And in fact, multiple Olympic games.
And this is exactly the problem, James,
because loads of places,
they don't have microphones for the whole thing.
But they have to add microphones wherever they can,
and then sometimes cheat a bit.
So for the balance beams,
they would put microphones on the beam.
So no audience would ever hear the creaking
and the movement of the beam. - Yeah, yeah.
- But you do on TV.
And then for the archery,
they had a microphone on the target.
They had a microphone next to the archer for the launch.
And they also put one in between
on the arrow's path to capture the swoosh.
- Oh, so that's why they're catching the actual sound there.
They're not, 'cause for me,
I would probably get like a ruler
on the side of a table and then twang it.
(all laughing)
- That's genius. - Yeah.
But you're right, they fake it sometimes.
So Dennis Baxter, he did the boat race for a while.
- Oh, was this in an interview with him?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, I've heard this, amazing.
- The boat race, if you're actually in the boats
or on the bank, what it sounds like
is the engines of the support boats
and the helicopters flying overhead.
And if you play that on TV,
it would be an incredibly weird experience.
So he went out before the boat race.
He recorded clean swishing rowing sounds.
And that's what you're hearing.
You're hearing Dennis Baxter rowing
or someone being recorded live. - Well, he cheated.
That's amazing. - Yeah, yeah.
- How cool is that?
- And it is the tennis as well.
It's a really precise job working out
when to up the volume of the ball hitting sound
and when to decrease it.
And it depends completely on the tension
and also the crowd sound.
And I think he does ground sounds as well.
And yeah, he talks about you have to sense
how tense a moment it is and then reduce the crowd sound
or sense that everyone's getting really excited
and then you bring up the crowd sound
and then you make the sound of the tennis ball
hitting the ground a bit less, the crowd a bit higher.
- Is there someone doing the moaning as well?
(laughing)
- That's his wife actually.
- I was reading about Foley
and there was actually a film made about Foley art itself
and it's called Burberry and Sound Studio.
It was a horror film that was made in about 2012.
It had some famous actors in it.
It was meant to be okay.
Anyway, it was partly about Foley art.
So the main character is working in a movie studio
and he's coming up with sound effects.
And in this film, he has to come up with the sound effects
for these really gory horror scenes.
And he has to come up with these sound effects
by smashing up pieces of fruit, the classic.
So he's shown in this film,
smashing up watermelons or mangoes or whatever it takes.
But they realized when making this film
that the sound of fruit smashing up,
it does not actually sound enough
like the sound of fruit smashing up.
- So they had to find some skulls
and break them in, didn't they?
- They couldn't get the skulls,
but the sound of the fruit smashing up is made
with pieces of wet cloth and bits of wood being bashed around.
- That's amazing.
- That's so funny.
- How better is that?
- We keep saying Jack Foley was a real person as well.
This was the person who created the idea
that you could overdub within the sort of
behind the scenes of the movie, the post-production.
And his first job when he did it was he was working
on a movie which was showboat.
And his first, I think one of his first things
that he did for it was he walked as three people.
So he had a cane and he had his own footsteps
and he managed to match the footsteps
of three people walking using both just his feet and a cane.
And that was the moment when they went, oh my God,
this is, what is this?
And he started experimenting more of it.
- Was it three one-legged people?
- No, I guess you can move your feet quite fast
to be in time with all of the feet, can't you?
- So did he get people to close their eyes
and say three people are gonna come in and out of this room
and then did the three gates and then said it was all me?
- Oh, I see.
No, I think he just showed them the product
of the recording, matched with the film.
- He could have been an incredible master criminal, you know.
- Make it look like a burglary was five people,
but actually it was one.
- Make it sound like a burglary was five people, you know?
- That's true.
- He's no good with an eyewitness.
- No, he could only operate under conditions
of pitch black darkness.
But they would, you know, afterwards the security guard
who'd been blindfolded.
- He could rob spec savers.
- Exactly.
Again, everyone would have to be blindfolded
and in the area as well.
But then they would say afterwards, oh yeah,
15 large-
- Will the Beast.
- Will the Beast came in to the shop
and took all the glasses.
- Or herring, we're not sure which.
- But he could do them so accurately
and then 'cause they'd never look for Jack Foley.
- So he died when he was 76 years old
and he reckoned he had a long career in movies.
- Well, or did he?
Did he just make it sound like he died
to continue his crime spree?
- Good call, yeah.
That's a cold case, we don't know.
But he reckoned he did 5,000 miles of walking
in the time of his career for films.
He doesn't say whether or not that was like,
I was walking to buy some pistachios
or I assume it's the footsteps
that have appeared on our screens.
- Yeah, I would assume so, I don't know.
- But also his voice was on movies.
He is responsible for the first ever, we believe,
Tarzan Cole, the very first, yeah,
Tarzan the Tiger in 1929 was the first movie
and it wasn't that though.
- Was it not?
- No, it was just him going, ee-ah!
And that was supposedly Jack Foley.
It's sort of a bit lost whether or not it was him
because I think the footage itself has been lost.
It's one of those lost films.
Cole, the one that we know that goes, ee-ah!
It's like a palindrome, isn't it?
That's the fun facts about that.
- And it's trademarked.
It's owned by the Edgar Rice Burrows family
and they've got the exact, it's like nine calls
or 10 calls, isn't it?
And it's an exhale in it.
- Well, after Tenet and Tennis,
Richard King can do Tarzan next, yeah.
- The film just about the Tarzan Cole.
How would you, what would the title of that film be?
- If it was just about the Cole.
(all laughing)
- I was just wondering how you'd spell the film name.
Just goes away.
- R-E-R-E-R-E-R, I think.
(all laughing)
- You'd think it was a hospital drama.
- Right, right, right, right.
(all laughing)
- Should we talk about the William sisters?
- Yeah.
- So this movie, King Richard,
the King Richard in the title is the father
of Venus and Serena Williams.
And he, I don't think it gives anything away
for the movie to say he was a very hot housing father
who really wanted his children to be tennis players
at a very, very young age.
He'd never had any training,
but he taught them how to become great tennis players
and they were the greatest of all time.
I read an interview with Venus from 1991.
This was in Sports Illustrated.
And even then she knew she wanted to be a tennis player.
She was a brilliant tennis player.
They said, "What would you like to be when you grow up?"
She's like, "I want to be a tennis player."
Or an archeologist or an astronaut who travels to Jupiter.
- Cool.
- Wow.
- That was her three possible things she wanted to be.
And I looked it up 'cause I wondered,
and this is true, both Venus and Serena
have now owned properties in the town of Jupiter, Florida.
- No.
- So they kind of went,
'cause a lot of sports people live in Jupiter,
so, and they, yeah.
- Very nice.
- That's great.
- Isn't that the Jupiter she meant
when she was five years old, is it?
(all laughing)
Just happens to be an astronaut,
but living in a tennis place.
- That's amazing.
- Venus Williams, one of the two Williams sisters.
- That's right.
- Owns a quarter of a dolphin.
(all laughing)
- A Miami dolphin?
- A Miami dolphin, the American football team.
She has a stake in the Miami dolphins,
and it's quite a small stake.
- With Serena?
- Yeah, but I think, so it's about,
it's less than 1% that they own or that she owns.
But anyway, if you include all the spare players
they would have, it would work out
at one quarter of one dolphin.
- Amazing.
- Wow.
(all laughing)
- Wait, and it's both of them that own it then, is it?
- It's quite hard to find the exact chapter of verse
on how much they own or whether they own it together.
- You can understand why that hasn't been
too extensively reported on, I guess,
with all the stuff out there about the Williams sisters.
(all laughing)
In 1995, Serena was 14,
and she wanted to go pro,
and she was too young by the rules.
And so she filed a lawsuit,
an antitrust lawsuit against the WTA, I think.
- Really?
- Saying I should be able to play.
And actually, their dad had a bit of a vault vass
in their early teens because he suddenly realized
that tennis can really screw you up.
And the junior tennis circuit,
all the parents were just awful.
There was a little bit of racism around.
And he actually said to, I think Venus,
I don't think you should become a tennis player.
But she must have thought, well, thanks a lot, dad.
(all laughing)
I don't think even nothing else for 12 years.
But yeah, Serena tries to do this lawsuit
to say that you have to let me in, even though I'm 14.
- So that was Serena was it?
- Sorry, Serena did this lawsuit thing.
- So at that stage, Venus will have already become pro, right?
So maybe that was the reason, because yeah, in the movie,
a lot of it is about how he doesn't want them to become pros.
He doesn't, he don't want them to play any matches
until they become professional, really.
They play when they're like 10 years old
and then they don't play again until they're professional.
- Except they play with him, don't they?
- Well, they were a lot of practice.
- Practice, yeah.
(all laughing)
- They never touched a rocket again.
- But how do you go pro without going up a system
to get to the pro?
- Well, they were so good.
They basically had a pro, they had a trainer
and they were really, really good.
And there was one game,
one of her first ever games, Venus,
she lost against the Rancho Sanchez Vicario,
and this is part of the movie.
And they kind of slightly changed what happened in the movie.
But anyway, she lost this game
and then they interviewed her afterwards and said,
"Well, you know, how is this loss
against one of the best players in the world?
How's it compared to the other times
when you've lost in other games?"
And she went, "Well, I've never lost before."
(all laughing)
She'd never lost a match in any of her junior things.
And then she stopped playing and then she became pro.
And so, yeah, she'd never ever lost a match
before at that stage.
- Amazing.
Yeah, so Richard, the dad,
he basically decided that he was gonna turn his two girls.
And he had a family before.
This was his second marriage
and two new kids to the family.
He was watching TV and he saw that a tennis player
could earn $40,000 a week.
And he thought, "My God, that sounds amazing.
I'm gonna train my girls up to do that."
And he wrote up the 78-page training manual
for Serena and Venus that he had everything
that he'd learned in there and how he needed them to be.
He did a really interesting thing.
And I say interesting, it's terrible.
He had his kids play Venus and Serena out in the public
and he would pay local kids to come and jeer at them,
to yell at them as they were playing
so that they could get used to the idea of crowds
being against them and having to push through it.
So there are people out there right now
who have an anecdote, which is I was paid as a child
to jeer at Serena.
I think my family might have been doing that at fish gigs.
- What kind of prodigy were they attempting
to turn you into and where did it go wrong?
- Okay, it is time for fact number three and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that there is a tree in Pakistan
that has been under arrest for more than 120 years.
- And still no charges brought?
- No, that's Tony Blair levels of, you know,
what's it called?
The thing that Tony Blair did with habeas corpus suspension.
- That is such an obscure reference
to Blair era home office policy.
- Guys, we all remember it.
- Oh, sorry.
- And they're all still outraged.
- Yep, sorry.
- Anyway, yes, apparently no habeas corpus
when it comes to trees in Pakistan.
This is, well, is this true?
I mean, there is a tree.
There's a tree in Pakistan that is undoubtedly true.
It's a Banyan tree.
It's undoubtedly true that the tree is chained up.
And it's undoubtedly true that there is a board
on the tree that says I am under arrest.
One evening a British officer heavily drunk
thought I was moving from my original location
and ordered mess sergeant to arrest me.
And since then I am under arrest.
All that is true.
This officer is supposedly called James Squid.
I have no evidence that there was ever anyone
called James Squid.
- I looked as well.
I couldn't find any.
- Nothing in the newspaper archives,
nothing in old books, nothing.
- Also, it just feels like Squid wasn't anyone's surname.
- Well, it is.
There are people called Squid.
I looked on one of those genealogy websites
where you can see families.
Squid was a surname back in the day,
but there's no notable Squids.
If you go to Wikipedia, notable Squids.
- Notable Squids, empty page.
- Empty page.
- Wow, sorted out the Squids.
- Jimmy Wales.
- Well, he's only interested in the larger marine levels.
- Wow, James Squid.
- And this is a thing that certainly the people
who live in the Landikatal,
which is the place where this tree is,
which is in the Khyber region of northern Pakistan
near the border with Afghanistan,
the people there, it's the story,
the local story is that this happened.
And I think one reason possibly that it's still there
is they wanted to remind people of the colonial times
and the bad things that the British colonists
brought to the area.
And yeah, remember the bad times.
- I've got a question.
- Yeah.
- What's it chained to?
- The ground.
- The ground, I see.
And the reason it's changed to the ground
is because so that it can't run away.
Because the reason James Squid had it arrested
is while he was riding home one night, it leapt at him.
It made a sudden movement.
And he's like, whoa there.
- It was quite a windy night, wasn't it?
(laughing)
- So he claims drunkenly, supposedly drunkenly.
And I say supposedly it's about a possible fictional human.
It's a possible fictional human.
- We don't even believe the fictional human's drunk story.
- It sounds like James Squid has a lot of questions
to answer himself, but can't answer them.
- Yeah, it's said to have.
- Well, they can walk, can't they?
- They can.
- So, and they do walk quite slowly.
- Sorry, could we unpack this a bit?
- Yeah, so they possibly don't walk fast enough
to jump out at you on a dark night,
but they are an extraordinary tree.
They're known as Strangler Figs,
because the way they grow is they start out as a seed
that's put out of a bird or whatever,
or blown onto the branch of another tree,
and then they drop their roots from that branch.
- That's the crate, have you guys heard that before?
I'd never heard of that.
That is extraordinary.
It just takes over a tree from the outside.
- Yeah, it kills it.
- Yes, and then it kills the inner tree.
The banyan then becomes what's called a columnar tree.
So there's a hollow column in the middle of it
where the previous tree was,
and then all sorts of animals get to live
inside that hollow bit.
- It's like the magic faraway tree.
- But the walking.
- Yeah, what's the walking?
I still don't believe they walk.
- So the walking is if you've got your original root
that's been dropped from the branch of a tree,
and that embeds itself, and that's essentially the trunk,
and then it's rooted into the ground,
and then it grows up again from the roots and it grows out.
So you have these things that look like forests
of lots of trees that are just one tree
because it keeps on growing up from the roots
and then dropping roots down again and then going up again.
And then often the original trunk will get diseased
and have to be removed.
And then I say that that's walking
because it's lifted up that leg
and taken it out of that position
and moved it to the next position.
- It hasn't moved it to the next position,
it's just been removed.
It's just died a bit apitated.
- But the new trunk.
- It's grown another leg.
- The roots that come down,
one of those will become the major trunk.
- Yes, that's right.
I was forgetting that definition of walking
where I have my leg apitated,
but then I grow a new leg,
which I put somewhere slightly different.
And then do this a series of times over a century
and end up going about 10 feet.
Yes, walking, love to go for a walk.
(all laughing)
- Look, when you're a tree,
you have to take everything you get, right?
- That's true, that's true.
- It's not running.
(all laughing)
- I saw a massive banyan tree this morning.
- Yeah?
- It's humongous, it's in India.
- How big?
- We're talking about 4.7 acres.
But this is how big it is,
what Anna was mentioning about the idea
that these roots grow back out through the ground.
So they're called aerial roots.
They look like their own trees.
This one has 2,800 of them.
That's how many it's grown.
And the original trunk, like Anna was mentioning
about the other one,
also has been diseased and chopped away.
So even the original leg is no longer there.
- They're pretty amazing.
They're so big that these trees,
these really, really massive ones,
I reckon shelter 20,000 people.
So let's say it's raining
and you're with 19,999 friends
and you all need to keep dry.
You can just all slip underneath one of these trees.
- Or you're Jack Foley.
You've just pulled off a job
and you need to make it sound like
there are 20,000 of you hiding under a tree.
(all laughing)
Yeah, I understand.
- Yeah, yeah.
20,000 people though, that is a lot of people.
- That's a lot.
- If you think of most lower division football stadiums,
Tremere Rovers who I support,
like that's twice as many,
more than twice as many of people
who go and watch Tremere every week.
- So people could leave Tremere one week
and all hide under the same tree
and the next week a completely different crowd of fans
could turn up, join the initial crowd
under the previous tree.
- And the other crowd are like,
"What was the scar cause we just missed the match
cause we're hiding under this tree."
- Or in fact, cause I think the biggest one
is about three football pitches.
So you could all crowd around the outside of the tree
and then three teams could play
three different matches underneath it.
Although there are shed loads of branches in the way
so actually that wouldn't work.
- Hang on, three football pitches,
you can get six teams on there, can't you?
- That's such good football knowledge.
- I'm not a football expert
but I think you can have two teams on the same pitch
and it fits a really exciting match.
(laughing)
- So there's a story that there's a prison
in the Shabakodar area
and it's called Shabakodar Fort.
And in the 1800s, 1840,
there was a group of warriors that attacked it
and they went inside and there was a big clash
and it went on all night long
and the Sikh people who were in there fought back
and they managed to get them out.
But there was this huge thing going,
"How the hell did they get in here?
"Someone's responsible for this, they need to pay."
And so they had a big court case as it were,
like a big inquisition into working out who did this.
And they came up with a verdict.
And the verdict was it was the fault
of the wooden doors that let them in.
And as a result, the wooden doors have been arrested
and have been hanging in the tower,
chained up much like this tree ever since the 1840s
and they're still chained up.
- Wow, that's the scapegoat, isn't it?
The scape door. - Yes.
- Not the escape door.
That's awful if you try and get out through the scape door
and you just walk into the door recently.
- So wow, this might be a thing,
like a trend of chaining up trees or wood.
- Yes.
- I've not heard of it happening anywhere else.
I did look for arrested trees and you don't find any others.
- No, no, and this slightly predates your tree as well
by about 40 years or so.
- And also these are wooden doors,
so they were trees a lot before that.
- Yeah, we don't know how old the doors were.
- We don't know.
- Food for thought.
- Do some Banyan trees have bells hanging off them
so you can ring the bell to access the spirit
at the top of them?
- Cool.
- What is the spirit, is it a helpful spirit?
- Goddess, well they're very sacred.
So yeah, it's a positive thing.
There's lots of mythology around them
'cause they are quite extraordinary trees.
They feature quite heavily in Hindu mythology, in fact.
I think there's Hindu texts from like 500 BC
that say the entire universe is an upside down Banyan tree.
And so it's growing from the heavens down to us
and then it's leaves a little aphorisms,
little bits of wisdom.
And there's, I mean, women wrap threads around them,
don't they, there's a festival in India.
Vat Purnima, which I think means Banyan full moon
and married women go for three days
and hang out with Banyan trees,
wrapping threads around them as a way of--
- Why?
- 'Cause they love their husband so much.
It's pretty gross.
- There is, yeah, a lot of it is,
it's a bit like, what do you call it,
like a Hindu almost, right?
'Cause all the women go together.
- But a married woman, a Hindu.
- But they're only married, yeah.
- That's an, I reckon that's the next place
for the Hindu market to go.
- The Banyan trees?
- No, just like married Hindus.
I think that could be a huge thing.
- So what are you celebrating then?
- Getting away from your husband for a bit, probably.
- Yeah, nice.
- How much you love him?
- Oh, sorry, yeah.
Well, that's how it's sold,
but everyone who goes on it knows
we're going for a fun party.
- Well, if we love our husband so much,
why we go to a strip club in Blackpool?
(all laughing)
- There's a tree in the middle of it.
- Stop tying ribbons to that.
(all laughing)
- To that guy's trunk.
Oh my God, he's got an aerial route.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show.
That is Anna.
- My fact this week is that Pad Thai
was invented as part of a fascist government initiative.
- Wow.
- And every time you eat it,
you are supporting fascism.
- Oh, shit.
- Yeah, I know, awkward, 'cause it's delicious.
- Well, this last time you all had Pad Thai,
I reckon that I had it this weekend.
- About two weeks ago.
- Yeah, same.
- Yeah.
- I'm not sure I've ever had Pad Thai.
- Well, you're very liberal out here.
- 'Cause of my principles.
(all laughing)
- This is an amazing thing.
It's from Thailand, hence the name.
And it was essentially invented,
sort of by the leader of Thailand,
a guy called Phoeban, full name Luang Phoeban Songkram.
And he was a big populist leader in the 1930s,
that era of big populist leaders who became fascists.
And so--
- Thank God we got out of that era.
(all laughing)
- Well, indeed.
- How times have changed.
And he became essentially dictator of Thailand in 1938.
And he was very anti-China, a very nationalist,
as was the way with sort of fascist-leaning dictators.
And he wanted to stamp tiness onto everything
and make everything very Thai.
There were loads of Chinese people in Thailand at the time.
They tended to sell most of the street food, for instance.
So all the food had Chinese influences.
He wanted to scratch that and create this new dish.
And it's not totally clear who invented it.
His son claims that it was in their household
that it was invented and they used to have it
as a family together.
Other people say maybe he ran a competition to invent it.
But essentially, he published and promoted this recipe
for Pad Thai to incorporate lots of nice Thai tweaks
and made everyone eat it.
- That's interesting.
I did read that it's not Thai,
that it's a Chinese meal which has been sort of adopted.
- Did you see that?
- Well, it is because China and Thailand
are all kind of noodle or rice-based stuff.
It does use Chinese noodles.
It basically took Chinese noodle dishes
and added lots of tiness to it.
So the Thai bits are things like the palm sugar,
that real nice sweet sugariness,
the chili tamarind flavor that you get.
That was all Thai.
- Also, bean sprouts, you don't really,
is very Thai, which is on top.
- But yeah, it wasn't like a pizza.
They had to work with what they had.
And what they had was the same ingredients as Chinese food.
- Yeah, actually, you were saying about the food vendors,
all being Chinese, any foreign food vendors
were banned by Phoeban.
They said, "You're not allowed to do that."
And the government kind of bought a load of food carts
and then got people to run them and said,
"Right, you've got to sell Pad Thai from these food carts."
They made it so that everyone had to eat
at certain times every day
and you were allowed no more than four meals a day
because this was the Thai way as opposed to the Chinese way.
You were supposed to--
- It's not that rigorous, is it?
- How many meals a day?
- I was like, "Well, snacks are allowed."
- I think that might not be, I don't think so.
- I have some pretty hefty snacks.
I only have three meals a day,
but if you add in snacks, I'm shading snacks.
- I think you're not allowed,
you wouldn't be allowed in 1930s Thailand.
He was the one who changed the name to Thailand from Siam.
- Yes.
- He mandated that everyone had to sleep
six to eight hours a day,
which apparently was also a Thai thing
as opposed to a Chinese thing.
And he said that everyone had to wear hats.
- How was the Chinese eating 15 meals a day
and sleeping for 21 hours?
- It appears that way.
- It wasn't even just hats.
You had to make sure you wore shoes.
If there were photos of people without hats and shoes in them,
they were painted on onto the actual photo itself.
- Really?
- Yeah, all these, he made sure that,
and this was an order that you had to kiss.
This is if you were a male worker,
you had to kiss your wife before you left for work.
That was part of the mandate.
- I do think that's nice.
- If you have to, it takes the meaning off it.
- You're absolutely right.
- If you go to work and give your wife a kiss
and she knows that if you don't do it,
you're gonna be arrested.
I think it takes a lot of love out there.
- And sometimes you've had a tiff
and you actually want to make a point.
- Yeah.
- And you're like, I hate you so much.
I'm willing to be arrested
by the fascist governments of Thailand.
- That actually really makes the point much more effectively.
They're just saying, sorry, train, gotta go, gotta go.
- Well, the reason we all think it's nice
is 'cause we are Westerners
and that's why he was trying to--
- Oh, he was trying to Westernize.
- Yeah, it was just absolutely bang on classic,
but like desperately trying to Westernize and modernize,
partly because, partly our fault he came about
because Thailand or Siam had never been conquered,
never really been colonized by the West
unlike pretty much everywhere else in that area.
- Sounds like it was explicitly not our fault.
- No, but wait for it.
- Oh, no.
It felt like they were in danger of being colonized
'cause we weren't over that phase of history at the time
and they were like, the reason we haven't been colonized
is because we're really cultured, we're civilized,
you know, Westerners think that we don't need to be colonized
and we need to kind of persuade the West
not to invade us by Westernizing and modernizing massively
and that's gonna mean kissing our wives
and that's why the Brits didn't invade Thailand.
We saw they were kissing their wives as they left
and that was the idea.
- And wearing hats.
- And wearing hats, yeah.
- Can't possibly arrest all these good chaps
who are going around wearing hats and kissing their wives.
- Precisely.
- Wow.
- You've got a British mentality of the 1930s.
- Yeah, it's not the first time I've heard that either.
- He banned listening to American and European music though.
Why would he do that?
- Well, again, he wanted to get the Thai culture.
- Okay, I guess so.
- He ordered every single household
to have a picture of him in their homes,
classic fascist behavior, that's vintage stuff
and also theater and cinema audiences
had to bow to an image of him
before each viewing of the screening of the film
or the performance of the play.
- Really?
- Oh, well that's fine, 'cause 1930s cinema and theater.
- You had to bow to Boris Johnson
before you see one man, two governors.
- You got to stand up and sing "God Save the Queen"
in the cinemas before a movie
and at the end of the movie, that's what happened here.
Like, it's not any different.
- They said that same thing, yeah.
He had to use forks and spoons, national cutlery,
got rid of chopsticks.
Again, it's this weird hybrid of persuading the West
that we're Westernized and modern,
but also keeping real Tainas.
Typhoon with forks and spoons.
And also, they went through all these popular songs
and they took out, if any popular folk songs
mentioned other ethnicities that weren't Thai,
they were rewritten.
So, if you were Lao or if you were Burmese,
'cause there were lots of different ethnicities
in Thailand at the time, then couldn't sing it anymore.
- Really? - Wow.
- So if you had the song "The Irish Rover",
did they rewrite it as the Thai Rover?
- Yeah, and that was one of the most popular songs
at the time.
(laughing)
- I don't think of any other songs
which had an ethnicity of them.
- See.
- But so, they would send the artist back into the studio.
It wouldn't be like the DJ at the radio station
would just come in and just say a new word
over a song playing.
- Well, this is where Andy's Foley Artist comes in,
isn't it?
They employed Jack Foley to say the word Thai
over everything else.
- Actually, it doesn't sound like Thai
if you say the word Thai.
You have to say the word Swiss,
because that better creates the sound of the word Thai.
(laughing)
- Anyway, it was a fascist bad guy.
- Yeah.
- They had a noodles song as well.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, Thai, 'cause it's, do you wanna hear it?
- Yes, please.
- It sounds so fun.
- I love two, three, four.
- Noodles, noodles, noodles, it's how it starts.
Thai vegetables are wealth in the ground.
You can find it anywhere.
Keep buying and selling as Thai people
always help each other.
Noodles, noodles.
I imagine something's been lost in translation,
but the tune.
(laughing)
- Do you know we've only just worked out
how to break a noodle in half?
(laughing)
- Not true.
- Scientists have, well, okay, 2018.
(laughing)
Four years ago, this is like a straight noodle
or a bit of spaghetti,
and it's just impossible to snap it in half
if you try doing it.
- Oh, yeah.
- It's really interesting.
If you're at home now,
like get a piece of long piece of spaghetti,
a long spaghetti.
(laughing)
You hold both ends of it and then start to bend, right?
Until it snaps,
you'll find that the two bits in your hand
stay in your hand,
and then the bit in the middle comes out,
so it doesn't break into two pieces.
It always breaks into three.
It's really interesting.
- That is interesting.
Although if you hold it in the middle, you can.
- Yeah, yeah.
- That's what they learned in 2018.
(laughing)
- Andy, if only you'd been there.
I mean, you could have saved thousands of pounds.
- Yeah.
- So I think I'm a really famous scientist.
- Richard Feynman was,
he was obsessed with this problem.
So he used to stay up all night,
repeatedly snapping strands of spaghetti.
Incredibly famous physicists, Richard Feynman.
- And he died in what, the 80s or 90s,
so he never, he's not alive to the graduate.
See the 2018 innovation, what happened?
- Well, he died clutching a noodle.
It flew into his eye and through to his brain.
We figured out why you can't do it in 2006,
and that's to do with this kickback wave
that travels through the spaghetti when you snap it
and smashes it up.
But it then took another 12 years
to figure out how to overcome it.
The way you overcome it is you twist the spaghetti 280 degrees.
So almost a full all the way around.
And then you break it gently, slowly.
And that solves your problem.
- Yeah, I think if you are at home and you do try that,
sometimes you break it and it does go into two
and you're really disappointed.
But I think that might be because you've got either too much
or too little moisture in your spaghetti.
- Yeah, if you try it just without the twist.
- I'm just saying, don't write it.
If you break your spaghetti and it breaks it's too straight away,
then don't write it.
- It's your fault is what we're saying.
Yeah, yeah.
So are there any, it feels like a stupid question.
Are there any applications for this?
- Got loads.
- Yeah, yeah.
- But that's pretty much time to go through.
- Probably military, PAE systems have probably bought it.
- You make drones out of a snap spaghetti now, yeah.
- Is it the same principle for anything
that is one big long stick?
As in I'm trying to think of someone doing a pole vote.
No, sorry.
- A pole vote.
- No, no, I think pole.
- Yeah, yeah, a vaulting pole.
They're at one end and we do see them snap
and they tend to snap in two, I think.
- Do they snap?
- Yeah, they have snapped from time to time.
No, I think it's because the spaghetti
has got a certain tensile strength that it works,
but particularly well with that, I think.
- Okay, how about in the last year,
a woman was burgled in a helicopter was dispatched
to the scene of this burglary.
- Yeah, right.
- That's a, so it wasn't in Britain then, oh.
- No, it was because of police funding.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Yeah, and the only thing is.
- We were allowed to make references to Tony Blair's
home office, "Happiest Corpus" policies,
but I'm not allowed to comment on police cuts now.
- Can you just say how many police cuts
do you think you would not have to have
before we could get a helicopter
going to every burglary that happens?
- All I'm saying is, James,
this is a stand for election,
that's going to be one of my flagship policies,
chopper at your house within seven minutes
of the burglary happening.
- Well this actually, this story does weak
of an overfunded police force,
because the only things that were stolen
were eight pot noodles.
Not just individual noodles,
pot noodles, but like, you know.
- They dispatched a helicopter.
- Packets, I don't think they knew at the time
that it was just pot noodles that had been taken
and women just saw.
- Was this woman the queen?
- Yeah, she loved.
- So we learned earlier that they were using helicopters
to lift up pilchards from the water.
- Yeah, nutty knower.
- So you know, and it's like,
- What are you saying, we've got spare helicopters
coming out of our ears?
- Seems like it.
- Yeah, I think she didn't know at the time
she just saw this burglar in her garden
having leapt out of her house, I guess,
called the police, they were like,
oh God, emergency.
And it was only later when they interviewed her,
they said, what's been taken?
And she said, well, actually eight pot noodles.
And she said they took all the beef
and tomato flavored ones,
but didn't take the chicken and mushroom ones.
- Really, that, yeah, I understand that.
- I was going to say, yeah.
- Have you heard of Watana Panic?
- Say it again.
- Watana Panic.
- No.
- Watana, it's in Thailand.
It's a noodle soup joint.
Maybe the Watana family, I don't know.
But it's a place where you can buy noodle soup
and they're one of these places where every day
they take the last bit of the previous soup
and put it into the next soup, like a perpetual soup.
And so whenever you, whatever you buy,
if you get some of this beef noodles,
you might be having stuff from, you know,
50 years ago.
Isn't it cool?
- That's really cool.
- How long it's been going on?
- It's been going three generations.
We think 45 years and counting.
But I was reading about these perpetual soups
and there's some claims.
One of them apparently, there was,
there's one story that there was a perpetual stew
in Perpignan in France
that was going from the 15th century until World War Two.
- What, then the Nazis bombed it?
- They ran out of ingredients due to the German occupation
and had to stop the stew.
- You could just water it.
I would have thought you just water it down
until it's basically water,
but keep the stew technically, it's still the stew.
But you've got bigger things on your mind
when the Nazis are rolling in, so that's fair enough.
- Yeah, you do.
There was one in Normandy
that apparently was over 300 years old.
This is kind of turned,
this is an article in a newspaper called The Navhyn Times,
which is from Goa.
I couldn't find it anywhere else,
so God knows if this is true.
- They've got an unbelievably good Normandy correspondent.
(laughing)
- Wait till I tell you why it is,
because it's so unlikely.
But also, what a weird thing to make up.
They said that in Normandy,
they had a pot which had been bubbling away
for over 300 years.
It was in a Cistercian abbey,
and researchers went into this soup
and like took some tests,
and they said that there was still some ingredients
in there that had been in the stew for 350 years.
- What, James, what you're reading
is the Indian equivalent of the daily experience.
(laughing)
- But it is like that thing, isn't it?
Where if you, every glass of water you drink
has been through a dinosaur.
- Yeah, okay.
- Or, and Hitler.
- And Hitler, yeah.
- Which is why I've stopped drinking water, actually.
Yeah, is there a filter for that?
(laughing)
Fittler, it's cool.
- It hasn't been through,
I mean, Hitler didn't drink that much.
I don't think every glass of water--
- I think he was a T-Total.
- Or is it, is that a thing that is enough?
- There's enough molecules.
- Yeah.
- Sorry, sorry, I just remembered.
It's not the whole glass of water.
It's one molecule.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland,
Andy-- - @AndrewHunter.
- James-- - @JamesHarkin.
- And Anna-- - You can email
podcast.qi.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website,
NoSuchThingAsAfish.com.
All the previous episodes are up there,
so do check them out,
and we will be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)