[music]
Ho ho ho!
Hello, Clubfishers!
It's not further Christmas, it's me, it's Andy.
Uh, hello, just wanted to say
hope you had a lovely break,
hope you had a very nice Christmas,
hope you have a fantastic new year when it comes,
hope all sorts of nice things for you,
and most importantly of all, hope you enjoy
this latest bit of Clubfish.
This is a new compilation,
it's all the best bits that didn't make it into our touring shows,
we went on tour all over Scotland and Wales in the autumn,
and we've been sitting on these bits,
that sounds rude,
but we've been keeping these bits just for you,
if your middle name is Lenezra,
if you like Blenny's,
if you've ever cycled a thousand miles,
for not a very good reason,
if you've got more than one spleen,
this is for you,
hope you enjoy it,
and we'll see you next time.
[Music]
Just a fact that kind of brings together
a couple of the facts,
so about cars and about cardboard,
so this is the Solar and Interstellar Rocket Car,
built by Daniel D. Hungerford in 1929,
and it was a rocket powered car,
which he managed to get licensed in the state of New York,
and it went 70 miles an hour
and shot out a 20-foot flame
from the back of it as it drove,
and it was made out of cardboard and linoleum.
Wow.
Oh dear.
And why do you think he made his rocket car
out of cardboard and linoleum?
Well, lighter?
Lighter is a good idea,
but he said,
"In case of trouble,
I wanted to be able to kick my way out."
That's so good.
That's amazing.
Yeah?
It existed.
Why don't we all have one?
It got two miles to the gallon.
That's why we don't all have one.
So the guy who was the lead developer of Excel itself
was a guy called Doug Klunder,
and he sounds like a bit of a character,
so they were just developing Excel,
it was all going to be very exciting.
He was the only one who understood
lots of the components of it,
and then suddenly he completely quit.
There was a little bit of a debate
over whether they should go with Microsoft or Apple,
something like that.
So he quit and went to become a lettuce farmer.
And he took an ill-fated job in lettuce farming.
Ill-fated?
I don't know why it was...
He didn't die.
Come on, but we need details, yeah.
He didn't drown in lettuce
because he came back in the end.
But before he left,
he just left them a three-day-long video lecture
in how to work Excel.
Imagine every time you have to work Excel.
Three days long?
You cannot get to watch this whole video.
Oh, my God.
Klunder.
Three days?
I was looking at some other experts in this kind of field.
So the best speed typer.
Okay, how many words a minute do you reckon you can do?
Well, a decent standard is kind of 60 or 70.
Yeah, mine's about 60, I would say, and I'm okay.
Do you get to pick the words?
You do not.
No, they randomly come up.
Oh, okay.
You can't just write "I" a hundred times in a minute.
I'll say 110, someone really good.
Well, there was recently a competition,
and the winner was someone called Anthony "Chack" Ermillin,
and they got 210 words per minute.
What?
But that's not even the record.
The record is 216 words per minute,
and that was done in 1946 by a woman called Stella Perjunis.
Wow.
And she's in tonight, clapping herself on an egotistical twat.
But she actually became quite famous in the late 40s
for having been such an amazing typer,
and she got a job at IBM,
and they had a new electric typewriter,
and she was like the face,
or rather the fingers of the electric typewriter.
That's a great use, darling.
They're making me the face?
No.
This is about parts of names.
I've just looked into middle names a bit.
Okay, yeah.
So there is a trend of people,
almost all fathers,
claiming that they have given their daughter
the beautiful middle name, Lanesra.
Have you heard of this?
No. Lanesra.
And it's a lovely middle name,
but the reason that people, like dads,
are claiming they've managed
to get it into their daughter's name
is because it's arsenal backwards.
Oh, it's not a thing.
That's great.
Yeah.
So have people actually caught that name?
You said there's a...
We don't know,
because it's never happened three times in a year,
because that's when it shows up on official stats.
I see.
So if you're out there and you're called Lanesra,
please get in touch with us.
You'll probably be under five years old, so...
(laughter)
Yeah.
But people changing middle names.
That's a big thing.
And deep poll stations always get inundated
with people who want to do specifically
for middle names.
And I was looking at the deep poll website,
which is deeppoll.org.uk.
And it was saying,
it's got a lot of lists about
how you change your name,
how you do this stuff.
And then it just only says deep poll trivia.
And it's...
There's only one fact in there,
in their big list,
which is one of the most popular
middle names added is danger.
Inspiration of which comes from Austin Powers.
So it says, yeah,
every week we issue at least one deep poll
to someone who comes in to say,
"Danger is my middle name."
Apparently, according to the once a week that happens.
That's a good fact.
From deep poll, like whoever's researching,
they're lazy,
but at least when they do the work,
they come up with the goods.
Well, what happens if one week someone doesn't?
Do they have to remove their only bit of trivia?
Yeah, how rigorous are they?
The last thing is, there's a quiz from me,
and then, sorry.
You got a quiz.
Macaulay Culkin changed his middle name.
Okay.
Yeah.
So what do you think he changed his middle name to?
I think it was Carson to begin with.
Carson?
Yeah.
Okay.
Is it something to do with Home Alone?
No.
That's not Kevin.
No, it's not Kevin.
Okay.
No.
You're not going to guess it.
We're not going to guess it.
People need to go home one day.
So this is...
He says this has been done.
Macaulay Culkin's middle name
is now Macaulay Culkin.
So he is now Macaulay Culkin Culkin.
That's his name.
So great.
Good on him.
He did it as an internet vote.
He put up a bunch of names that he got.
He did like a Bodebuck boat face.
The other options were Shark Week.
The McRibbers back.
Yeah, and Macaulay Culkin.
And that was so good.
You can eat zebraspiders as well.
Well, as in humans can.
Humans can.
But more Thai zebraspiders,
which are a lot bigger than these.
Right.
So if you go to Thailand,
you might see them in street markets.
You can buy these Thai zebraspiders.
And if you buy a steak
and you want to know how well done it is,
you know, there's a trick
where you can touch your finger with your thumb
and then which finger you touch tells you
whether it's well done, medium rare, rare, and whatever.
Well, there's a trick with Thai zebraspiders
and you cook them
and it's how much the legs are curled up
indicates how well cooked it is.
So if you like it well done,
then you have the legs really curled up.
And if you like it a bit more rare than the legs.
I think I'll just have the salad.
You want to go on more?
Okay, now I'm going for the Costa Rican Zebra Tarantula.
I just think we should mention him
because I find it weird
that quite a lot of things are named after zebras.
By the way, I don't think we've said
that the reason we're calling it a zebra spider
is because it's stripy,
which maybe you figured out,
but it's worth saying.
But zebra tarantulas are so cool.
We just found out recently that
while all spiders have a spinnerette,
like they're basically their spinning wheel
on their backs or on their abdomen,
these zebra tarantulas have little spinning wheels
on the ends of all of their feet.
And they have multiple ones.
So on the end of every foot,
they have loads of other tiny feet
and each tiny foot on the end of each foot
can shoot out little bits of silk.
And this means that if you've got
the most flawlessly smooth window you can imagine
and you get a zebra tarantula,
it can just climb up it willy-nilly
because it shoots these little bits of silk
out of its every tiny foot.
Wow.
Yeah.
God, Spider-Man wasn't bitten by that spider
and just grew all these tiny hands on his fingers.
No, that'd be a cool movie, actually.
It would, yeah.
It'd be more attractive, Ridley.
Yeah. Okay, I need to move us on to...
Just me? Okay.
Okay.
Another cat woman, a cat person,
is someone called Kate Bird Soul Johnson
who, according to Sotheby's,
was possibly America's greatest cat enthusiast.
She owned 350 Persian and Angora cats.
They all had a group of servants who would lack after them.
She was a multi-multi-millionaire.
She also owned a load of parrots and cockatoos
but she only owed them so that they would entertain the cats.
And she commissioned the world's largest ever cat painting,
which was six feet by 8.5 feet.
It was so heavy that when she put it on the wall,
they had to reinforce the wall
so that it wouldn't bring the wall down.
Wait, what was it painted on?
It must have been something very heavy.
Yeah, it must have been a painting on lead panels or something.
So it was plywood, so I don't know.
I think she needs to contact a structural engineer about this.
All of her.
Perhaps the cats are peeing on the wall a lot, I don't know.
But anyway, it sold recently for $826,000 this cat painting.
Wow.
She commissioned a guy called Carl Kaler
to paint these cats,
paid him an absolute fortune to do it.
And he spent three years studying cat poses
before he painted this painting.
Well, can I ask, the picture, have you seen?
Does it contain all 300?
No, it contains about 40 of the cats.
Like one of them in particular in the middle
is really sort of proud,
and then the other ones are like around.
Right.
Oh, amazing.
It feels beatable.
Six feet by eight.
Go for it.
Mudskippers are another cool fish that get very aggressive.
The males get very territorial and aggressive with each other.
And one of the cool things about mudskippers
is they live almost entirely on land.
So they're one of these incredible fish
that just like slide around the rocks using their fins,
propelling themselves along.
They can actually, using the pectoral fins on their chest,
they can propel themselves,
I think, 50 centimeters in the air,
just in one jump.
Wow, wow.
They can simply leap.
And it's amazing watching them fight.
So if one encroaches on another's territory,
they just, it's like a martial arts film.
They just like flip upside down.
They jab each other.
They karate chop each other.
And then there's one video where one of them
looks like he's being defeated.
And then he just gets his big mouth
and sucks onto the other one
and picks him up with his mouth
and then just starts, you know,
judging him around with his face
and then tosses him away.
It's an incredible move.
And this is all on land.
Yeah, yeah, it's all on rocks.
Yeah, yeah.
Early.
It's pretty cool.
It's like WWF for fish world.
Wait, so he, it's the same,
sorry, were they the same species or were they the same?
Yeah, same species, two males.
So one's got a finishing move
where they just latch their lips on.
Yeah.
Like a good suction plumbing thing.
Exactly.
Okay, that's, yeah, that's a powerful end move.
You'd watch that, wouldn't you?
If that was a move in wrestling.
I'd watch everything we've said here.
Okay, I'm going to give you one last thing
and see if you've, you'd watch this.
Yeah.
Okay.
This is, have you heard of mouth brooders?
Mouth brooders?
Are these the frogs?
Keep asking them out.
Yeah, it's, it's like, it's a family.
It's a load of different species.
Some are frogs, some are fish.
They keep the eggs in their mouth until they hatch.
The fertilized ones, I should say.
But there is a fish, which I've never heard of before.
It's synodontis multipunctatus,
and it's called the cuckoo catfish.
And what it does is it, it cuckoos.
Wow.
Another fish called the thick lipped.
Is it situlid?
Is that how we say it?
Chick lid, I think.
Chick lid, okay, chick lid.
It cuckoos another fish called the thick lipped chick lid,
right?
So that fish is a mouth brooder, okay?
And what the catfish does is,
as the female victim is laying her eggs,
the catfish will sneak under
and lay her own eggs right nearby.
And then the chick lid just scoops both up
and keeps them in her mouth until they hatch.
But the cuckoo catfish eggs hatch first,
and then they eat the other eggs in her mouth,
in the mother's mouth,
and then they just escape out of the mouth
and off they go.
That's incredible.
That is, it's also, it's a catfish,
so she has literally been catfished the mouth brooder.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Wow.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's so funny.
I thought you were going to say that it's a child
that gets born inside the mouth,
and just occasionally when it opens its mouth,
the child goes just comes out, and they're back in.
Like the cuckoo club fish.
Like the cuckoo club, yeah.
Wow.
But that's as cool.
I'd watch both that, but more mine.
Have you guys heard of the barred chin blenny?
No.
This is really good.
Okay, so the female lays the eggs,
and then the male is often left in charge
until the eggs hatch, okay?
So that's relatively unusual in the animal kingdom.
You know, the males don't,
or frequently just go off right here.
These ones do though, right?
These ones look after the eggs, I believe.
Yeah, blenny's do generally.
Oh, Jane, sorry.
In the case of the barred chin blenny,
this usually works really well this system,
except if the female leaves under a certain number of eggs,
if she has left fewer than a thousand eggs,
the male will tend to just eat all the eggs himself.
What?
Because he can't be bothered to look after them,
and he wants to breed again as soon as possible.
So...
That's amazing, but what that says to me
is that he can kind of tell the difference between a thousand,
not a thousand and a thousand and one,
but like between...
Yeah, between a thousand and two thousand though,
I'm sure it can, yeah.
No, it's impressive, you're right.
And it is the male's way of saying,
like middle finger up at that woman
who's only brought him a thousand eggs, isn't it?
It's him saying, "All right, I'm not going to bother.
If you're giving me this shit, I'm just going to eat it.
I want five grand or your best offer."
That's basically why they do it.
And there are some female blenny's who try to get around this
and start out who's going to eat their eggs
by bringing the male a sample sort of fake egg collection first.
So they'll generate a few eggs,
drop it off with the male,
be like, "Could you just look after these for a few days?
Go away, come back."
If the male's eating them,
they'll be like, "Cool, not the dad for me."
And then find another one.
That's a trick.
Yeah.
Years ago, when I lived in a flat that was always renting,
there was a cat flap in the door.
And so this cat that lived in the premises used to come in
and it really liked me.
It always used to come every night.
And I think it liked me because I never let it...
I never touched it, but I always let it touch me.
So I used to...
Again, that HR meeting.
I think we do need to have it again.
Yeah.
So I used to be just sitting on a sofa
and it would come and jump on my stomach
and it would sort of knead my stomach.
And I think it did something.
I don't know for its hands somehow, hands.
Knuckles?
Pause?
Yeah.
Yeah, for its...
I don't know what it did,
but it would come and it would knead me for about 20 minutes.
It sometimes looked like it was doing a job,
like, "Oh, Jesus Christ, I need to knead this guy."
And then it would leave and then it would come back every day,
roughly the same time, just to give me a good old kneading.
Wow.
Yeah.
But it liked me, I would say.
The interesting thing, though, actually with the Dutch clogs
is we're not quite sure when they first came in
because whenever you would have clogs,
when they wore out, what would you do with them?
You wouldn't keep them, of course.
Your house is fuelled by fire.
You would just throw the clogs on the fire.
Oh, okay, yeah.
And so we really don't have that many old versions of it
from old, like, Netherlands.
Yeah, yeah.
James, you've been to a lot of museums in your life, right?
I certainly have.
You're constantly going,
"Have you yet visited, in the Netherlands,
the International Wooden Shoe Museum?"
I'm afraid not, no.
You've not?
No.
Where is it?
It's in Ilde, L-D-E.
Okay.
They have 2,200 different wooden shoes and footwear
from 43 different countries.
And that's the most interesting thing
I could find out about it.
I can see why you thought I might have gone there.
Well, because we know that once you go to these places,
they're actually really exciting.
But I've got to say, on paper, I've done this dish for you.
Dan, actually, I looked up the same
International Wooden Shoe Museum.
Yeah.
I think it might be called Ilde.
Ilde.
And I couldn't find out anything either.
If you search for funny, you would get the humor article.
That's a redirect, right?
Yeah.
So you can type in one thing
and it'll take you to what Wikipedia thinks you mean.
Some of these have existed and then been removed.
So, for instance, if you search for Emperor of Wikipedia,
you would get--
Jimmy Wells.
Jimmy Wells, exactly.
If you search for King who died with a hot poker up at the ass--
Over the second?
Over the second, yeah.
But now if you type that in, it won't know what you mean.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
And if you search for 22.86 centimeter nails--
Nine-inch nails?
Nine-inch nails.
Very nice.
Who the fuck is going, "What's the name of that panda game?"
Is it 20--
That's amazing.
That's a great quiz, by the way.
Redirect, where it's just, yeah.
That's a really good quiz.
Do you want another quiz, quickly?
Yeah, let's do it.
If you search for sex symbol on Wikipedia,
whose photograph do you see?
Andrew Murray.
Obviously, you're not.
Someone extremely sexy.
Andrew Ma.
Is that just a personal--
Anyone in the audience?
OK.
I think we've got it over there.
Marilyn Monroe.
That's correct.
Comedian.
Jerry Seinfelds.
Nope.
It's actually two comedians.
Malcolm and Wise.
Hale and Pace.
Andrew Ma and Emily Makeless.
Anton Deck.
No, it's Laurel and Hardy.
Ah, yeah.
And if you search for red hair.
Ron Weasley.
Real name.
Ron Weasley is good.
Oh, Rupert Grimm.
Well done, Andy.
Rupert Grimm says the right answer.
I got it right.
Well done, Andy.
Thank you.
Do you know, Richard III helped out with Game of Thrones?
How did he come out?
Well, he was.
So, basically, in a lot of ways, he wasn't a very nice guy.
History is true there.
And one of the things he did when he was king
is he made his--
he wanted to humiliate this woman called Jane Shaw.
Now, Jane Shaw had been the previous king,
his dead brother, Edward's mistress.
He didn't like her for various reasons.
So, he thought she was plotting against him
with his enemies.
And also, apparently, she was extremely merry,
very fun, very witty.
And the speculation that-- because Richard wasn't that.
He was kind of pissed off that she was.
Anyway, so he said, "I'm going to humiliate this woman
"for being so promiscuous and seducing my dead brother."
And so, he made her walk in just her underwear
through the streets of London
carrying this one little candle,
like, all the way through the streets of London
to completely humiliate her.
And this is, you know, a literal walk of shame.
And that happens in Game of Thrones.
And George R.R. Martin said he based Cersei Lannister,
I think, does it?
Oh, really?
Yes, he did.
Yeah, thank you.
Yes, does a walk of shame in Game of Thrones,
which is imitating that.
Amazing.
Have you heard of a cocktail called the Smoker's Cough?
No.
It's Jägermeister and Mayonnaise.
Lovely.
Yeah.
Why, it just looks like Flemish.
It looks really rough, yeah, yeah.
It's the only one that's slightly worse than that
I've heard of is the Cement Mixer.
Oh, I've had that.
Yeah, which is Baileys and lime juice.
Yeah, yeah.
And the lime juice makes the Baileys curdle.
So, you can chew it and drink it.
Mostly, you just spit it out.
Yes.
I need to wrap us up in a sec, guys.
Oh, they were also the first company
to ever advertise a football jersey.
Oh, yeah?
Jägermeister.
They advertised, in Europe, at least,
it was Eintracht Bronze Spike,
and they were really allowed to.
So, what they did was,
they got rid of Eintracht's actual symbol
and just put the Jägermeister symbol there
and said, "Well, that's our symbol now."
So clever.
Three years later,
they had the first ever one in the UK
and it was Kettering Town.
And they tried to use the same trick.
And so, Kettering Town replaced the symbol
with Kettering Tires.
And the idea was, they would do that.
The FA would have none of it.
And they said, "Right, we're going to,
you know, we're going to kick you out of the league
if you don't get rid of the advertising."
And so, the guy who owned it changed it to,
it just said Kettering Tee on the front of the jersey.
And he said, "The Tee stands for town."
But actually, everyone knew
that it stood for Kettering Tires.
Clever.
That is clever.
I feel really bad for Kettering
that it actually does got a laugh in and of itself
when you mentioned the name Kettering.
Come on.
You know, if you want to get shoes on a cow,
you have to tip it over.
No, really?
Yeah, yeah.
And this was, they had to do it a lot
back in the days of droving
when you had to put shoes on your cows.
You had to put shoes on your cows?
Well, if you were droving them to market,
so, you know, many, many miles,
then you'd put shoes on the cows to protect their feet.
Do you mean the metal hoove kind things?
Or like?
Yeah, I think, not the steel, not pink stilettos.
More like horse shoes.
But because they can't lift one foot at a time,
you'd have to get an extremely strong couple of men
or women to push the cow over
in order to get the shoes on its feet.
That's, wow.
I know.
It's a horrible visit to the shoe shop for calves.
Yeah, that's fair.
Is it hard to get a cow back up?
It feels like it's easier to get it down
than to raise it back up.
That's why cow tipping is more fun than cow lifting, I guess.
That's why it's not fun.
That's why it's not a thing.
Let's go and look.
When you were a student, you went around
just lifting up cows, didn't you, Alex?
Yeah, yeah, me and 30 buddies
failing to lift a single calf.
It's like the end of Glastonbury you come in
just to clean up every morning.
So if you had a balloon on the International Space Station
and you blew it up,
you wouldn't need helium to keep it upright,
like it just, because there's no gravity,
so it just hangs in there.
So that's pretty exciting that you're saving on helium
if you're having a party, but...
That's a good point.
But you've got to get all your friends up
to the ISS, though.
That's going to be costly.
Yeah, there's a lot of logistical issues.
Absolutely.
You're allowed one friend.
But here's the problem.
Oh, there isn't another problem with this scheme, is there?
Well, I would argue this is the main problem, yeah.
If you were blowing a balloon up on the International Space Station,
the problem is that once you blow into the balloon,
so the way that balloons work on Earth
is that the reason they blow up
is because you're pushing air into it.
So you're expanding the rubber itself, the balloon itself, right?
Because the air, once it stops, it just hangs there.
But in space, things don't stop.
You give it propulsion, right?
So as soon as you blow into a balloon,
the air you've blown in doesn't stop.
It just continues to expand the balloon
because it's pushing outwards
because it doesn't have anything to stop its motion.
So as soon as you blow into a balloon,
it immediately expands to the biggest it can and pops.
That would be in actual space as opposed to the space station, right?
That's in actual outer space, or...
Yeah, we can have the party outside, yeah.
We can't waste the patio that NASA have installed.
Is that you're talking about the pressure,
the air pressure outside being so little?
I guess so, but I don't understand.
Are you just saying that when you blow,
when you blow a stream of air from your mouth,
it just keeps moving in this direction?
The propulsion of the air that you've gone...
inside the balloon.
If you're trying to do one of those long balloons
to make a sausage dog, that's actually very convenient.
So in a way, the party is back on.
But wait, I don't understand,
because when you exhale on the International Space Station,
it's not like you can never stop exhaling.
You blow into a balloon,
and then the balloon material stops the air from falling out,
and then you inhale it again.
So you're saying the party's off?
I'm saying we've got to get to the ISS and try this out ourselves.
I was hoping that you guys would just accept this as a fact,
but I can see there's holes.
And parties cancelled, parties aren't.
You're not coming to my space party.
That's what I'm saying.
Can I just do my favourite croissant story of this year?
Obviously, I have one for each year.
But did you guys read about the man
who travelled 1,400 kilometres for a croissant?
No.
So this is this guy.
He's a Belgian guy called Albert van Limbergen.
He's from Liège in Belgium.
And he's obsessed, as many people are, with lavender, weird.
So he loves the smell, he loves the taste,
he loves the appearance.
And he was just listening to the radio one day,
reading the paper,
and he read about a patisserie in France
that was doing lavender-infused croissants.
So he thought the sensible thing to do is,
I've got to get one of these croissants.
I'm going to get on my bike and ride 1,400 kilometres
in order to do that.
And he did it.
And it involved going up 1,200-metre mountain.
That's higher than any mountain in England,
just to access this croissant.
He cycled 12 hours a day,
100 kilometres a day,
camped at night,
met this baker at the other end called Frédéric,
who makes the lavender croissants.
And they chatted, apparently, about lavender and also life.
So that covers all conversations.
He was then asked, and then he had the croissants.
And he was asked, "Oh God, how was the croissants?
Was it worth it?"
And he said, "To be honest,
they would have been better if they put pastry cream in it
like we do in Belgium."
Other famous people that made people go crazy,
obviously the Beatles.
And the Beatles in 1963,
they played their first ever gig in Glasgow.
And when they came here,
15 people came to that gig, right?
They returned October of that very same year,
and they played the Odeon.
And it was so chaotic.
It was basically the concert where it went nuts.
And it was in Glasgow at the Odeon
that they believed the first time
the word "Beetlemania" was ever used.
So that whole global thing
started as a result of a gig in Glasgow,
which is very cool.
The Glasgow is just desperately trying to compensate.
What I find amazing reading about all the...
Because the screams of all the audience,
predominantly it was girls screaming,
their decibels, they would say, were so loud
that if a plane, if a 747 was flying 100 feet above you,
you wouldn't notice.
It's like that louder thing.
I thought you were going to say
that people in the aeroplane would go, "What's that?"
Yeah.
Why are we flying so low to the city?
What's going on?
What I find amazing is the screams,
and we've all...
If you've ever seen any footage of "Beetlemania"
and it's going crazy, you'll see that footage.
But back in the day when the Beatles used to play,
there used to be a thing that happened in the UK
where at the start of a gig,
everyone would stand up to sing "God Save the Queen."
Oh, yeah, yeah.
And then that would happen at the end of concerts.
It would happen at the cinema.
It would happen...
You guys did do that before we started tonight, didn't you?
Yes, yeah.
And so at the end of Beatles' concerts,
they used to...
The screaming fans, we've seen how crazy would go.
Yeah, yeah.
"God Save the Queen" would come on.
Everyone would go silent.
They would respect it as soon as it finished.
Again, why afterwards?
Just containing it, which is phenomenal containment.
Good way to quell a riot.
I think the police should use it more often.
I think they used that as the moment
for the Beatles to escape from the buildings
so that they could get out because no one could move,
no one could do anything.
So that was actually used as a tactic to get them out
before they were mobbed by the audience coming on stage.
Yeah.
Pretty clever.
Just quickly on sort of extra things you can have.
10% of us here, about 40 people in this room,
you will have an extra spleen.
And you won't know it.
How can we find out?
Medicine, I suppose.
As in, I don't think we can do it tonight
by like a question and answer process.
Is that a useful thing to have an extra spleen?
Not at all.
Doesn't it?
You're doubly angry as a person, maybe.
You know, like splenetic.
Lovely.
No, I don't think it does.
They're very small.
They're called accessory spleens.
They're normally,
they're much smaller than your actual spleen.
They're about one centimetre across.
But there is also a syndrome
where you have not just one spleen, not just two.
You have multiple spleens.
And that is called, genuinely called poly spleenia.
Isn't that cool?
Lovely.
Nice name.
Another nice name.
Yeah, like Arsenal Backwards.
Poly spleenia.
We have messed up family.
Yeah, poly spleenia.
I do need to move us on.
Well, just a three-headed lamb was born in 1577.
Breaking news.
And finally.
A couple of interesting things about it.
Though it had three heads,
and if one of them bleated,
the other two would always bleed alongside it.
So they kind of sing in harmony a little bit.
Like Hanson.
Yeah.
Bleed.
And it was written about by a friend of the podcast,
Amboise Poiret Pare,
who you might remember.
He was the guy who wrote about the woman
who pretended to have a prolapsed rectum.
Oh!
Do you remember that?
Yes.
I mean, you would really have to be a fan of the podcast
to remember that.
Go back and listen to the first 100 episodes.
But he wrote this amazing book
about these kind of animals with two heads or whatever.
And apparently in that time,
it was thought that if an animal was born like that,
then it would be some kind of terrible event would happen.
So apparently in Florence,
there was a cult that was born with a man's face,
and immediately they went to war with Pisa.
I mean, hang on.
There definitely wasn't a cult
that was born with a man's face, was there?
According to Amboise Pare.
Wow. We should have talked about that the whole time.
Do you know there's a record?
I haven't actually written this down,
but I've got the rough memory of it in my head.
There's a record for the quickest someone
has fallen asleep under a situation
where it's sort of like they were on stage
and it was like, "Go! Try and fall asleep."
Oh, how interesting.
Yeah, so what do you think the record is for that?
Well, I think on average,
I fall asleep after about six to eight minutes.
That's fast.
Yeah.
But with the pressure of audience and a...
There's no pressure.
If we say James now...
Yeah, I'll say five minutes.
I'll advance a bit.
Yeah, so it was about 17 minutes.
Wow.
17 minutes.
Yeah, I think it's the pressure of the stage
and the kind of...
I don't know, mate.
During a lot of these live recordings,
I could do it in about 10 seconds, I reckon.
Some other people who might have discovered Helium before,
Janssen, who I was talking about,
this is three authors and scientists of sort
called Annie Bessens, Charles Ledbetter,
and Korup Malanj, Jin Rajdeza.
And they wrote a book called "A Cult Chemistry"
and they claimed that using clairvoyance,
they could slow down the vibration of atoms
and see the atoms and be able to tell what the elements are.
Wow. That's amazing.
All right.
Yeah.
Well, I've got Dan.
Anyone else?
I'm not sure.
They said that they did this very, very early
and they claimed to see four different gases
in a mix of, you just, air.
And they were asked, "What are these four gases?"
And they knew what hydrogen, oxygen and nitrogen
had all been discovered at that time,
so they knew it would be those.
But there was a fourth one, what could it be?
And they said, "What is it?"
And they said, "Well, the atoms don't have labels on them.
How are we supposed to know?"
Anyway, soon afterwards, Helium was discovered
and they said, "That's what it was."
That's awesome.
Great.
But originally, they called that element a cultum.
Oh, that's great.
Should have stuck with that.
Much better name.
That's not dissimilar to the Mongolian brothers.
So when they first had the idea,
one of the brothers first had the idea for the hot-air balloon,
he was staring at women's underwear, hanging over a fire, right?
Sorry, what?
Yeah, sorry.
Yeah, so he was sitting by a fire.
Was he exploring the nature of crime at the time?
It was his laundry and it was his wife's bloomers
and they were hanging over the fire.
Oh, that's clever.
And they were picking up from the flame underneath,
this sort of wind.
And so he thought, "Oh, I wonder if that could be something that could..."
No.
But what's amazing about that is he thought,
and so did his brother, that the reason that they were lifting up
was that the gas itself from the fire was a special new kind of gas,
which they called Montgolfier gas.
And the idea was that it had an element of levity about it
that was special, that was different to everything else.
So they did this whole process of getting us into the air
and hot-air balloons,
believing they'd discovered a mystical gas that doesn't exist now.
That's really interesting.
Oh, sorry, guys.
Sorry, Montgolfier.
No gas for you this time.
There's one interesting sort of spooky thing about Richard III,
and that is that there's...
I only learned this by doing this research this week,
and that is that there's a theory that Leicester City won the Premier League
with the help from Richard III's ghost.
Oh, yes.
And on the Leicester City website,
they have a lot of evidence as to why this is the case.
Really? Right.
So one bit of evidence is that on the day Richard III's body was found,
there was a football match in Blackburn
where a certain former non-league striker opened his scoring account
with his first ever league goal.
And who opened his scoring account on that day?
It was Jamie Vardy's account.
Oh!
One person's on the chair.
[LAUGHTER]
Andy, he was the captain of Leicester.
I read the legal news, and I think Jamie Vardy is.
[LAUGHTER]
What I find quite amazing as well is there's a huge discrepancy,
as we know, between women football players and male football players
and the pay range that they get.
And the Lionesses who won this year,
some of them, the day jobs that they have to do and still do
as a result of the pay not being enough maybe to sustain their whole life,
that's obviously going to change now,
and going forward, that's getting better.
But Jill Scott runs a coffee shop in Manchester,
and she was right back in the coffee shop afterwards.
There was photos of her just sweeping the floors
and running this small little coffee shop that she has.
And this, you know, can you imagine Ronaldo going back
to run his, like, pawn shop, you know?
Or like--
Sorry?
What?
We're the WN.
[LAUGHTER]
We don't think much of Ronaldo,
but, you know, I don't think we're going to accuse him of that.
[LAUGHTER]
The other thing, I think these people are quite lazy.
Yeah, good point, yeah.
These philosophers, like Socrates, Jesus, Confucius, Buddha.
That's lazy, stop.
Lazy, lazy, lazy.
[LAUGHTER]
None of them bothered to write their own shit down.
They just hoped some poor disciple behind them would write it all down.
Well, good thing those were all very small movements
with no followers in the world today.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, now Anna.
Oh, man.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Ho, ho, ho.
It's still me.
It's still Andy.
So that's it.
That's it for this week's Clubfish.
Really hope you liked it.
And we'll see you next time for another drop as a line.
If you want to find out anything more about any of the stuff that we do,
you can find it all on knowsuchthing@fish.com.
And we really hope you've had a lovely time being members of Clubfish.
Thank you so much again for joining.
It means the world to us that so many people have joined.
And are enjoying the stuff and right to us as well.
So if you want to drop us a line, we are podcast@qi.com.
Thanks so much.
See you next time.
Happy New Year when it comes.
Bye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]