[upbeat music]
[speaking in foreign language]
Hello and welcome back to another episode of "No Such Thing"
as a fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Andrew Hunter Murray and I'm sitting here
with Anna Tajinsky, James Harkin and Alex Bell.
And we have gathered our favorite facts
from the last seven days, so in no particular order,
here we go, starting with you, Anna.
- My fact this week is that the second president
of the United States of America used to inspect London's Dung.
[laughing]
- Why did John Adams go around inspecting Dung?
- The reason he did it, he obviously was a farmer
and he was inspecting--
- Obviously, this little manufacturer was also
the president of the United States.
- He's most famous for his farming days.
No, sorry, he's obvious from his diaries
that he's a farmer because he--
- He's a farmer from his diaries, yeah.
[laughing]
- Well, look at all that.
- Was it sort of 25th March, did some more farming today?
Is that what gives it away?
- That was my first clue, yeah.
25th March, milk to cow.
- When all the people of America let me get back to my farm.
[laughing]
- He was a farmer and so he was inspecting it
to compare it to his own Dung and he pointed out--
- So his own Dung?
[laughing]
- This is not normal behavior in a person.
- Well, and he's questioning.
- He's an absolute fruit loop, let's try.
- It's amazing that they let him mentally unstable
with the president of America.
- That will never happen again.
[laughing]
- He was a very stable man and had many stables of his own.
He inspected the Dung in order to compare it to the manure
he kept on his own farm and in fact he concluded
that the manure on the edgeware road, he wrote of it,
"This may be good manure, but it is not equal to mine."
- Wow.
- Yeah, so he had better manure.
He had some manure from the Boston marshes
which he considered superior.
- And yeah, this fact was sent in actually
by a guy called Mark David who sent me
some of John Adams diaries.
And he said in his diary, "In one of my common walks
along the edgeware road, there are fine meadows
belonging to a noted cowkeeper, plentifully manured.
I have carefully examined the manure
and found it to be composed of straw
and Dung from the stables of streets of London
and then he goes through all the stuff
that's in the manure, so he's really gone through it
with his hands, properly getting in there,
to live up edgeware road in that direction,
and it's not like that anymore."
- Do you ever find any of John Adams's Dung
lying around your house?
- I don't know, who's it?
- It's on your doorstep, though, and it was on fire in the back.
That's the main thing.
- I wasn't John Adams's own Dung just to be clear.
He didn't take a poo by the side of the road
and then expect guys.
- Well, what if he'd accidentally swallowed a tooth
or something and he wanted it for his collection?
- As hypothetical situations go, Andy?
- I don't know, I think you're most likely
to swallow a tooth if you get pushed in the face.
- And if you were wandering around inspecting poo
on the streets of London, you might.
(laughing)
- And if I got punched in the face,
I'd be likely to poo myself.
(laughing)
- This is why I never got to boxy bites.
Gets very messy.
- That was absolutely stinks in there.
- He was a lawyer originally.
Before he was a president, and I'm not sure
if he was a farmer at the same time as he was a lawyer,
but he was a really bad lawyer.
So in his first year, he had one client,
and it took him three years before he won a case
in front of a jury.
- Wow.
- Yeah, I don't think it was a really long trial either.
I think it was just, it took him a very long time.
- One thing he was a liar for was the Boston Massacre,
wasn't it?
I think quite famously that.
- What was that?
- I think it was something like there was a crowd of people,
and there was some British soldiers,
and the crowd started throwing snowballs at the soldiers.
- Was it snowballs?
- I think so.
- And then other stuff as well, like the animals and stuff.
And then the soldiers, when snowball fights get out of hand,
(laughing)
is that a reindeer come towards me?
And then the British soldiers got angry and shot them,
which is obviously worse than snowballs or reindeer's,
and they were arrested,
and I think Adams got them off.
- He did get them off.
- Yeah.
- Not one of them went to prison thanks to his defense of them.
Are we saying that he was kind of partly responsible
for the American Revolution starting?
- I think he was certainly a player.
- Wow.
- And he was pro-revolution as well, wasn't he?
He just defended the Brits because he wanted to uphold
the rule of law, so he thought they had a right
to equal representation.
- Yeah, true.
- Good man.
- When he was in Boston, he also wrote political theory essays
for the Boston newspapers under the nom de bloom,
Humphrey Plough Jogger.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- Humphrey Turd Sifter was the first draft name.
(laughing)
- So Jefferson was his main rival and he fought Jefferson
for the title of second president of the US,
and he won, and then Jefferson beat him at the next election.
And then when they both retired,
they spent the rest of their lives writing letters
to each other.
- It should have been me.
(laughing)
- But didn't they, during one of the elections,
didn't they really fight, like really badly?
- Yeah.
- I thought Jefferson called him a hermaphrodite or something.
- Yes, he did.
Yeah, they had a really, really vicious campaign.
And he, so Jefferson accused Adams of being a hideous,
hermaphroditical character who smuggled prostitutes
into the country, so he said he was smuggling prostitutes
in from England, into America.
And he said that he was planning to marry one of the sons
of King George and that he was a royalist.
Which actually, there could be some foundation to that
because one of the things that Adams got mocked for
when he was president was that he thought the president
should be referred to as his royal highness or your majesty
was something like that, 'cause he pointed out
the presidents, you get presidents of golf clubs
and other really tedious things.
And it wasn't a nobel enough title.
- Yeah, one of his suggestions was his highness,
the president of the United States of America
and protector of the rights of the same.
- There you go.
- Yeah.
- So we were talking about Adams and Jefferson being friends,
even though they called each other homaphrodites
and said there were English prostitutes, a foot.
They died on the same day and they died on the 50th anniversary
of the signing of the Declaration of Independence,
4th of July, what would it be, 1826?
And they were both absolutely determined
to stay alive until then.
And Jefferson died just after noon.
And Adams awoke soon after Jefferson had died
and he was in a separate place at the time.
And he said, with great effort,
Thomas Jefferson survives as though at least one of the architects
of the revolution is still alive,
even though he didn't know that Jefferson had already died.
And then he died a few hours later.
- And then, do you think anyone,
do you think there was a really awkward pause
around his bedside when he said Jefferson survives?
- Actually, no.
- Should we tell him, is it cruel?
- Yeah, I don't think he ever knew, which is nice.
- He died thinking that Jefferson still survives today.
- Really?
(all laughing)
- On his diary writing and his prolific letter writing
and diary keeping, apparently Congress made fun of him
because he went to Paris at one point
and wrote a lot in his diary about how,
- How great the done was.
- Oh yeah, how great.
How much he admired the French aristocracy,
all this kind of really a few stuff
about how great Paris was.
And then he sent it along with his report
of what was going on in Paris to Congress,
possibly accidentally.
I would not sure whether it was supposed to be part of the report
or not.
- It's a diary.
- Just read it aloud and make fun of him in Congress.
- It's just like a 12 year old girl in a school.
- Wow, if anyone's mum's ever read their diary,
they can take solace in this,
probably the worst moment of his life
when he realised that had happened.
- I bet he never got over that.
I bet that's why he had to become president
was to erase the memory of his diary.
Oh god, that's embarrassing.
- Well, it was, okay, so there was nothing too humiliating.
It wasn't like, oh dad walked in on me masturbating
this morning.
It must have learned to lock the door.
It was there was nothing too awful in it.
- No, he said that one of the French gentlemen...
- What do you won't believe?
The prostitutes they have here in France.
I think they complimented him a lot
and one of the men called him the Washington negotiation.
Oh, and he wrote that down.
And he was like, oh, I really like him.
He's so nice.
And that's like retweeting praise of yourself, isn't it?
And then posting the retweet to Congress.
- Yeah.
- Copying in Congress.
- We should move on, but just one quick,
anyone got anything on Dung or droppings?
- Yes.
- Go on, drop it in.
- Bert Reynolds once dropped a helicopter full of horse manure
on the national enquirer.
- Did he?
- Yeah.
- Why did he do that?
- They'd been writing a lot of stories about him
and they weren't accurate.
So he decided, he said this.
I thought it was only fitting.
On Christmas Eve, my pilot and I loaded my helicopter
with manure from my ranch, flew over the building
and watched it cascade down their giant Christmas tree.
Isn't that amazing?
- The children would have probably thought
he was Santa Claus.
(laughing)
- You know, there was a moose dropping festival
in Tal Keetner in Alaska.
- So is this for dropping mooses or for--
- Bert Reynolds flies over the town in a helicopter.
- No, that's, but that's such a good question, James.
And it's exactly the same question
that confused Peter, the animal rights organization.
So it was a festival that was canceled in 2009,
but it was basically where people used to throw moose
droppings out of helicopters flying over the top
and people took bets on whereabouts they'd land
and would bet how close they'd get to a target.
But Peter got confused and assumed that it did involve
hurling moose, life moose, from helicopters.
- Loving them into helicopters, coaxing the moose
into an aircraft.
- Every time they hear about animal droppings,
this is just what they usually do.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, we should move on.
So it's time for fact number two now
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that you can be blocked
from getting a Swiss passport if your neighbours
find you too annoying.
So this has come about, this is a news article
that's been quite recent and it is in the canton
of Argao in Switzerland and there was a lady
who is a vegan and she has been complaining
about the way that cows are treated
and various different things in this area.
- Why does this weird man keep sifting through their menu?
- It's their own business.
- And the locals are not very happy with her
because they think that she's invading their way of life
and the rules say that when you apply for a passport,
your neighbours can give you a reference,
either good or bad and they've given her a bad reference
and it's stopping her from getting a passport
and so now it has to go to the next level
so that she can apply elsewhere.
- She's lived there since she was eight.
- And all her children are Swiss.
- Yeah.
- But she's a really big campaigner.
One of the things she campaigns to get,
she does campaign against putting bells
around the cows next.
She also campaigns against piglet racing,
which is a thing that happens in Switzerland.
- I wonder if she campaigns about cow droppings.
(laughing)
- That's a thing that happens.
Cowls just walk over cliffs in Switzerland all the time.
They walk off mountains and then the other cows think,
oh, maybe Bessie found some better grass over there
and then you get up to 40 cows at a time
just plunging off cliffs to their death.
- You always thought the smart thing for neighbours
to do would be to give her a really glowing reference
and ensure that she does have the ability
to leave the country, wouldn't it?
- You're right.
Because having the passport means
that you immediately are forced to emigrate, I think.
It does allow you to leave, though, doesn't it?
That's the thing.
- Exactly.
- That's true.
I think actually she does have a passport
for another country.
- And nationality is Dutch as she must have
a Dutch passport and she's got children there,
so she can't remain.
- It's weird there.
The law in Switzerland is that in order to apply
for a passport, you have to first become
a resident of your local town, basically.
It's called Hematort.
Hematort, Hematort, Hematort, Hematort.
I would pick the right one.
Yeah, so all the foreign nationals
have to become a citizen of the town they were living in
and they have to live there for at least 12 years.
And then up until 2003, the whole town could vote
on whether they would become new citizens or not.
- Would vote on whether someone could become a new citizen?
- Yeah, absolutely.
So a whole town would vote on it.
And so until 2003, it was everyone in the town.
Then they realised actually people were just being
a bit racist because they didn't actually know
these people, they would just make a judgment
based on which country they came from.
So they changed the law so that it's then a sort of committee
when you get references from people who know them
and they're judged specifically on them as a person.
But it still means that it's really difficult to get into.
There was a family in 2006, a family from Kosovo
as a nice citizenship because one of the reasons
was that they dressed inappropriately
'cause they wore too many tracksuits around town.
And the other one is that they didn't systematically
greet people passing them on the streets.
- Now that is a weird thing.
So if you go to a party in Switzerland,
when you arrive, you have to go around the room
saying hello and shaking hands with everybody else
at the party.
And then there's a huge incentive to arrive on time
'cause if you get there on time,
everyone comes up to you and says hello
and you don't have to go around saying hi.
- Actually, you want to go early, don't you, really?
- Yeah.
- So does this kind of game theory going on and off?
What time do you arrive?
- Yeah.
- I would actually rather get their lace
because if you arrive first, then that means
all your conversations are going to be interrupted
by the next arrival coming up and shaking your hand.
Whereas if you arrive last,
you get all the handshakes out the way immediately
and you can get on with your conversations in peace.
That's my top tip for Swiss people out there.
- It's very good.
- Yeah, thank you.
- This woman who's been rejected, she's writing a book
and the title of it is "Selkie Annève"
or "The Lady Who Annoyes".
(laughing)
- So she's embracing it, that's nice.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, grace.
- What about the cowbells though?
Like they do, they are incredibly loud, aren't they?
- I think that is right.
It's like a hundred decibels, aren't they?
And it's round your neck the whole time.
You can't get away with it.
I'd just jump off a cliff and I'd follow you.
(laughing)
- Just on passports, there was a nine-year-old girl
who recently got into Turkey on a toy passport.
This was in 2013 and she was from Wales
and she had her own passport.
She was traveling with her parents
but she also had the passport that belonged
her teddy bear unicorn, her soft toy unicorn
and her mum accidentally pulled that out
instead handed over to the authorities
who'd really stamped it and let her in.
- It must have been roughly the same size
in shape and colour as a normal passport.
Which is quite a...
- Well, they've got a unicorn on the front, anyway.
- British pastries.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Oh my God, I didn't know we had royalty visiting
your Highness, welcome to Turkey.
(laughing)
- Can we quickly talk about how until recently
so it's learned was rigged to explode
if an army invaded.
- Yes, I think we can,
because that's going to need a lot of justification.
So since the Second World War,
the Muslims have had a really stringent plan
for what would happen if they were invaded
because they're a famously neutral country.
The main kind of plan is for everyone in Switzerland
to withdraw from the cities
and fight a guerrilla war from the Alps
if an army was to evade.
And all of the tunnels through the mountains
and all of the bridges were all rigged with explosives
so that they could be blown up
and it would be very difficult to get around
the country, very difficult to get into
the country in the mountains.
And they have also some other plans
like they have enough nuclear bunkers
for every citizen of Switzerland.
So presumably this woman is going to be any person
who doesn't know where to go.
- Last fall, please.
- I thought this unicorn was last fall.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, we've got to move on.
It's time for fact number three
and that is my fact.
My fact is that there are people
in the houses of parliament constantly looking for fire.
- You phrase that like, they're smokers
in the lights and have a light.
- There are 24 fire patrol officers
who go around the house of parliament.
They do it in shifts, obviously.
And the Palace of Westminster
is basically only able to be used
because they're working.
So if they weren't there,
then the building would not comply
with the 2005 fire safety order.
So they are easily the 24 most important people
in the houses of parliament.
- So you say that the fire people have had to be installed
because of this 2005 piece of health and safety regulation.
- I do say that.
- You do say that and yet I think that.
- No, here we go.
- Effectively, crown properties are exempt
from health and safety regulations.
So they still have to abide by them.
But you can't prosecute the crown properties
for not abiding by them.
The only thing you can do is censure them.
So if they don't abide by these rules,
you go to this incredibly long process
that you would go through usually
where someone else might go to prison at the end
or be arrested or fined.
But with the crown, they just get a formal censure.
- Basically, this is about how
Shonky the houses of parliament are.
- They're falling to bits, aren't they?
- They really are, yeah.
- There was a report in 2012
that said if it wasn't closed,
they'd recommend demolishing it and starting again.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- Do they often find fires in their hunt?
- They do, yeah.
- Do they?
- So there have been 60 incidents since 2008,
which have had the potential to cause a serious fire.
- Yeah, so that is completely insane.
How incompetent are the people in the houses of parliament
no need to answer that.
- That's right.
(all laughing)
- Well, there's just a very old building
and there are lots of bits which are kind of fire hazards
and which, you know, it's a huge place as well.
- There's a lot of kind of it was built obviously before.
It's a bit of electricity,
so the wires are all kind of budged in
to where all the items are.
- Yeah, really loose.
- And there's loads of,
basically nothing gets uninstalled,
so anytime old wiring is replaced,
they don't take out the old wiring.
So there's tons of flammable material sitting there
and there's loads of us bestos.
I mean, that's not flammable,
but there's tons of us bestos.
- It's sort of everywhere.
It's not just in the walls.
There's us bestos inside the lightswitches
and things like that.
- They just shut it in.
- Absolutely everywhere.
- Of the 3,000 windows in the Palace of Westminster,
nearly all of them don't close properly.
- Nice.
- What's that for, I'm so badly built.
- I guess, does that mean if there's a fire,
yeah, more air will get in,
I suppose, to make the fire worse.
- And I think the shutters don't open properly.
The windows don't close and the shutters don't open,
'cause I think they built radiators.
I was reading the report on why it needs redoing
and one of the things in it
said that they built radiators in the nooks
that are supposed to house the shutters at some point.
So now when you try to open the shutters,
there's a radiator in the way.
- Wow.
Sometimes MPs misvotes
because they get stuck in lifts.
- Really?
- Well, it's happened at least once.
- Yeah, I don't know when I say sometimes,
I mean, one time.
- The legislation only passed by seven votes
and so if there was like a chance of,
if more people couldn't get that.
- I mean, if they'd all been in that lake.
- I used to work for an MSP in Scotland
and he once pressed the wrong button on his voting thing
and voted the wrong way
in a vote that came down to one vote.
(gasps)
- Man, that's a sheepish email to IT support.
(laughs)
- And then what terrible law passed because of that?
- So Scottish independence upcoming, that's all him.
(laughs)
No, it was about green energy, I think.
- I once worked in house apartment for a while
and on my first day, someone came in
and the office I was working in and took off his shoe
and threw it at a mouse in the corner
'cause they have a really bad mass problem.
- Really, yeah.
- Wow, what a...
- It was like, oh, hi.
- I literally cartoon based way to deal with that.
(laughs)
- According to MP Ben Bradshaw,
there is urine leaking in the house's apartment,
specifically into his office.
A couple of years ago, he tweeted that urine seems
to be pouring through the ceiling
into my commons office for the second day running.
There was some piping with holes in it
in the room above him and the smell was only made bearable
by his staff wearing strong perfume.
(laughs)
- Apparently the roof of the Hall of Westminster
there aren't really sure why it's still up
because they thought that it was originally built
with columns 'cause at the time during 13th and 14th century,
we didn't think that they had the technology
to make a roof that was wider than the beams it was made of
and it doesn't have columns anymore,
but they recently had a look at it
and they think that there were never any columns
so they're unsure as to why it's up there
and how it's staying up.
- Is this gonna be like in a cartoon
when the building real light is gonna be standing up?
- It's freewheeling in the air for a bit
and then, yeah, that's so weird.
- I know.
- So just on fire safety,
has anyone seen the fire safety slide
that's been installed in Shanghai?
So it's basically like a slide you see in a playground
and it goes around the stairwell
and when it's not in use,
then it's up vertically kind of attached to the banisters.
- Why is it not in use?
- Who?
- Yeah, who would have used it?
- What a spiral slide in a massive building.
I think, oh, we won't bother using this.
- James, this is not for the purposes of recreation,
it's a health and safety issue.
The only time you would ever want to use the slide
is in a case of a fire,
in which case it takes 14 seconds to descend the five stories.
- Oh, that is so cool.
Is there a penalty for improper use?
- I bet that happens to me.
- Almost, yeah.
- That is really 14 seconds for five stories.
- Well, I was trying to work out,
I reckon I could run downstairs in that.
- Absolutely, you're not married.
You could, three seconds per story.
- Oh, I don't know.
- I take four stairs at a time, I can do it.
- I think you could fall that distance at that time.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for a final fact for the show
and that is Alex.
- My fact this week is that the cookie monster
isn't allowed to eat cookies.
- Since his diabetes, diagnosis.
- No, why not?
- Well, he cookies are actually bad for the fabric,
but he is made out of,
so he actually eats rice cakes,
disguised to look like cookies disguised, yeah.
I think he knows, but yeah.
- But it will be quite a powerful message
about childhood healthy eating.
If he did eat cookies and slowly
he's always skin degrading and rotting away
over the next six months of the show, no?
- What did teach children that if you eat too many cookies,
your fur will fall off.
- I've never actually seen it,
but obviously I was supposed to be educational, aren't they?
And they're good at dealing with the heart hitting issues.
I think they're covering the Trump election, as we speak.
- They did have a character called Donald Grump.
- So good, yeah.
- Based on Donald Trump,
and it was when the apprentice first became popular,
and he was a Muppet with a bright orange quaffer,
who had the most trash of any grouch in the world,
and he had his name on every piece of trash in town.
- He was played by Oscar the Grouch,
and he's like, "I have more trash than you, get it?"
- I don't know who Oscar the Grouch is.
- All right, he's the guy who lives in the bin,
he's really grumpy.
- Okay, you think you've never watched it?
- I bet everyone else knows Oscar the Grouch is.
- Yeah, it's true, actually Oscar the Grouch is quite,
even if you'd never seen it,
I'm surprised you'd never come across him,
but he'd come across Big Bird.
- Yeah, so I've heard of Big Bird,
and I've heard of Elmo,
and I've heard of Burton Ernie,
but that's only because they're referenced in Friends,
which I have seen.
- And you must have the cooking monster as well?
- I think I thought that was the same as Big Bird.
- He's appeared on every, like he's appeared on news night,
he's appeared on BBC Breakfast,
he's done more political shows than most people
in this country.
- It's me Corbin.
(laughter)
- Took a long time for us to get in the German Corbin giant.
Poppets don't have a sexual orientation,
and Sesame Street had to make that clear,
because apparently there are lots of rumors
that Burton Ernie or a gay couple.
- 'Cause they share a bed.
- Oh, right, okay, so I can see where those rumors came from.
- Okay, so there were rumors about that,
and they said they're just friends,
and poppets don't have a sexual orientation.
- They don't exist below the waist.
They only have a top half.
- Big Bird exists below the waist.
- Yeah, I've seen--
- He's not poppets.
- And I guess, unless he belongs to the 3% of birds
that do have a penis, Big Bird will have a cloaca,
which he will press against the cloaca
or of other big birds.
- They are educational,
presumably they've discussed the cloaca
of Big Bird at some point in the show.
So Big Bird is flightless,
and isn't it true?
I read someone said this week that flightless birds
have a bladder, is that right?
- Flightless, the only bird with a bladder is the ostrich.
- And that's because bladder's a heavy,
like birds can't normally have them
because it would weigh them down.
- Yes.
- But Big Bird could possibly have a bladder.
- He could have a bladder, is anyone ever seen him we?
(laughing)
- No, he's not a grumpass.
- Is it Elmo the only non-human
to testify in the course of law?
- Where did the defendant tickle you?
(laughing)
- No, it was during a campaign
for increased funding for music programs
and he testified that there should be indeed that.
Does he sing, is he involved?
Does he see musicals?
- He's, yeah, he's sing, yeah, they all sing.
- I hope he'll sing.
- So there's a list of puppets
that have been in Sesame Street and Muppets as well.
But there's a list and there was one called Anna.
- Hey.
- This was in the Spanish version of Sesame Street
and it says that Anna had a know it all attitude.
- Wow.
- Based on me, I'm not gonna lie.
But it's a justified attitude, isn't it?
- Alex Bell, there was one called Bell
who was in the Brazilian co-production of Sesame Street
and Bell was an imaginative hot pink monster girl.
- Sounds better, right?
That's my online profile.
(laughing)
- And there was one called Murray Monster.
- What was that?
- And he was the host of the word on the street segment
and he was a boisterous red orange muppet.
(laughing)
- In the Nigerian version of Sesame Street,
the star muppet is called Kami
and Kami is HIV positive to remove the stigma
of talking about dealing with the hardest issues, yeah.
- That's so good.
- I know.
- Another responsible thing they do
is they make a whole set program called Talk Listen Connect
and it's for children with parents in the military
and they broadcast that to them
to teach them about how much they're gonna miss their parents
and how it's okay and how, for instance,
like amputees coming back from war zones,
their children might be a bit traumatized by seeing that.
And so there was a lovely story of a father
who came back from Afghanistan, I think,
and he'd had three of his limbs amputated
and he was really worried and they showed him
the Sesame Street video that had been made
to educate his children about his condition
and he burst into tears apparently.
He was so happy that he had a good way
of communicating it to his child.
- Oh my goodness.
- Some of the muppets are actually made
of army surplus material.
I watched that until I came in three ages ago
and I just remembered it.
- The Cookie Monster has a British cousin
- Really? - Called the Biscuit Bastard.
(all laughing)
- You are half right.
- Oh really?
- It's the Biscuit Monster.
- Oh okay.
- Biscuit Bastard would be good.
That could educate children about how it's okay
if your parents aren't mad.
(all laughing)
- That's hilarious.
- Does he actually feature on the American show then?
- He was only in one episode where he came
to visit the Cookie Monster.
- Okay. - Yeah.
He was on holiday.
- Tried to get himself a job as Donald Grumps
representative in the year.
(all laughing)
- We could talk about Biscuits,
but do you think I can I just say one thing
about Biscuits then?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Dunking Biscuits was originally done in wine.
The first evidence we have of Biscuit Dunking
was Wafers that the Romans softened in wine.
- Oh. - Wow.
- And before dunking in tea even there was dunking in beer
because in the Royal Navy you would have had hard
Biscuits that were really, really hard
and you couldn't eat them very well.
So people would dunk them in their beer to soften them up.
- Oh, that's very interesting.
- Wafers in wine.
Oh, you'll have to dunk your wafer in your wine at church.
Drink me.
- You're not, no.
The idea of putting wafers directly into people's mouths.
- Yeah.
- That came because they were worried
that people would take them in their hands,
hide them away and use them for magic pulsions.
- I thought you were going to say use them
slowly over time, build their own Christ at home.
(laughing)
- I was reading about Simon Pope who's a Biscuit designer
and tester.
- And that's the best job in the world.
(laughing)
- Honestly, his job, so his job includes eating,
tasting biscuits from 472 packets of biscuits every year.
So he says he tastes 30 biscuits a day.
- Wow.
- He says he often doesn't swallow them
because I guess for health reasons.
So he says he'll nibble on them
to check for things like taste, texture and firmness.
- He says he sometimes does have biscuits at work
because it's important to test them in situ.
- I need to test this batch in Las Vegas.
- I'm afraid.
(laughing)
- Travel expenses are enormous.
- He's in the plane.
He's got a seat next to him
which just has a pack of biscuits on it.
(laughing)
- He's always going around the world,
help not big news.
(laughing)
- I think we might be done today.
- I think so too.
- Today's your return, guys.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
We hope you've enjoyed it.
We will be back again next week
with another selection of our favorite facts.
So until then, it's goodbye from us
and you can follow us on Twitter if you'd like.
We are on James at Egg Shaped.
Alex at Alex Bell Under School.
I'm on @AndrewHunterM
and you can follow our group account
which is @QiPodcast.
Anna, you can email podcast@Qi.com
and I just quickly wanna say,
I got very behind on some emails towards the end of last year.
So I really apologize if you've done that.
I will try and get back to all emails, henceforth.
Sorry if you haven't heard of me.
- Okay, that'll end from hundreds more emails.
(laughing)
You can also go to our website
which is no such thing as a fish.com.
You can also watch our TV show,
no such thing as the news if you go to the website
which is no such thing as the news.com.
Okay, thanks again for listening and goodbye.
(upbeat music)