[Bell]
[Applause]
Welcome to another episode
No such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast
This week coming to you from the Soho Theatre
in Central London, my name is Dad Shriver
I'm sitting here with James Harkin, Andy Murray
and Anne Chazinski
and once again we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order
here we go
starting with you, Andy Murray
My thing this week is that
when you have a tattoo lasered off
you end up pooing it out
[Laughter]
So that happens
Does it still have the same design on the floor?
[Laughter]
So yeah, this happens
So when you have a tattoo
it goes into the middle layer of the skin
which is called the dermis
and when it's lasered off
the beams of like they heat up the ink
and it breaks down into tiny particles
and those go into the bloodstream
and then they are excreted via the liver
and the digestive system
and that's how they get out of you
I just think that's amazing
That says something about how little you want the tattoo anymore
doesn't it?
So do you know what tattoos are made out of
like the ink? Do you know where that comes from?
Okay, well there was a lady on Facebook
who got a tattoo
a vegan on her inner lip
and then her friends pointed out
that actually most black ink of tattoos
is made from burnt animal bones
[Laughter]
Oh god
she's going to see that every time she looks in the mirror
Every time she eats anything
Yeah, that's the worst part
You can get vegan tattoos
but they're very rare
Indeed, right
The oldest tattoo we know of is on a lip, isn't it?
A tattoo of a thin pencil moustache
[Laughter]
tattooed onto the upper lip
of a 7,000 year old mummy
from Chile
What, like a little French kind of
I'm not sure if it has the gap down the middle
that a pencil moustache is supposed to have
Do they have to have the gap down the middle?
No, I'm not sure
I think somebody's never been able to grow a moustache
I don't know, damn
It's not a moustache
Yeah, my grandmother has tattooed eyebrows
It's a huge heart
[Laughter]
Does she, like, permanently look surprised?
I don't know where her
original eyebrows went though
That's what I don't know
Did she poo them out?
I do think you're going to say a grandmother had a thin pencil moustache
[Laughter]
Kind of a cruising to share
So the thing on tattoos being quite sort of
the stereotype of them being for sailors
or for criminals
or whatever it is
The headline tattoos are not just for sailors anymore
has appeared in print every decade
since the mid 19th century
Every decade, there's the rash of articles
saying they've entered the mainstream
So today more teachers
have their members of the armed forces
By 14% to 9%
But it used to be like 90% of sailors had tattoos
Wasn't it?
Something like that
The 19th century probably
One thing that it was good for was
it meant that you could identify a sailor who had drowned
because you'd be able to identify them by their tattoos
and they were actually used
in that way
So you could tell that he had a tattoo that said
"I have drowned"
He has a lot of tattoos
The first one says "help"
The third one says "bubbubble"
And the other thing that they thought the sailors
is if you had hold tattooed on your knuckles on one hand
and fast on the other hand
then it would help you hold on to ropes better
Well we, you could stop drowning
as a sailor apparently
was to have a pig tattooed on your knee
and then a cock
as in a wrist, a tattooed on your right leg somewhere
and they had the saying
that was "pig on the knee"
"save it see a cock on the right never lose a fight"
So this is what those animals can swim
or fight very well
Speaking of cocks and tattoos
Yeah God
Sometimes when I want to find out some facts for this show
I'll go back to the old QI topboards
and see what I wrote in the past
and I touched the tattoos
and I found something that Dan posted in 2005
and this is what he said
He said "I was told today
that if a man was to have a tattoo done on his penis
then he was entitled to three tattoos
for the rest of his life
from anywhere in the world
in any tattooing power
No questions asked
This is what used to pass the QI research back in the day
So I have a confession
It's not just my grandmother with a tattoo
Well I had a look
and there are one or two tattoo parlors
that will claim that they will do that
whether they will or not
I don't know but it's not everyone in the world all the time
It's a very difficult thing to Google by the way
But very easy to Google, it's very difficult to forget
I shouldn't have gotten Google images really for that
But I found a story about a 21-year-old from Iran
who paid a tattoo artist to put the letter "M" for his girlfriend's last name
and the Persian phrase for "Good luck with your journeys"
on his penis
and he fell pain for eight days
and then his penis became permanently semi erect
so he couldn't get it to go down
He lived with it
and he didn't know what to do
He just became permanently semi erect
so he couldn't get it to go down
He lived with it for three months before getting medical help
and doctors tried shunting the penis
to drain excess blood
Not sure what shunting
And then it didn't work
and so the patient decided
he was fine with the condition
and declined further treatment
Wow
So they were quite a high society thing
weren't they in the 19th century
and at the turn of so
in about 1900
New York newspaper estimator
that 75% of society ladies in New York had tattoos
75%
What kind of tattoos? Like practical ones
or
practical tattoos
Don't back away
Step up
You get medical tattoos
and we think that some of the oldest tattoos ever
which are 5,000 years old
the 3,000 BC we found bodies
where there's a body in the house
which has tattoos over his joints
and they looked at the skeleton
and he had osteoarthritis in those joints
So it's like a kind of
That's what I meant by it actually
because the mercury astronauts are apparently as well
No, no, no, but I looked into
whether or not astronauts had any tattoos
You're like I'm saying a lot of things
that it's just me agreeing with
mercury astronauts
They would have them
in just like sensor locations
basically for whenever they had to monitor their health
so they knew where they were
Kind of like putting a bit of tape on the ground
as a mark for an actor
There was a guy who's arrested
by Canada's border services agency
with the letters H-A-T-E
on his knuckles
and he claimed that it stood far
through eternity
That's very good
Quick thinking
One moment used to an internet translation to
translate "I Love David" into Hebrew
She later discovered
she inadvertently had the phrase
"Babylon is the world's leading dictionary
and translation software"
on her back
Forever
But she doesn't have a free account with Babylon forever
David Beckham has
Victoria Beckham's name miss belt
tattooed on his body in Hindi
Oh dear
Samantha Cameron has a tattoo
Yeah, she's cooler than all of us
Hello, Dan's grandmother
Sorry
Is it a practical tattoo?
It's a dolphin on her ankle
Is that practical?
Yeah, that's cool
Was that just a holiday that she took once
To a dolphin area?
To a dolphin area
Oh, just you go into that and you get a tattoo
No, I don't mean it's like
Is anyone going to camera it?
No, I'll go
Quick tattoo that dolphin
So I can live this memory forever
There's an American guy
who has over a thousand tattoos
based on Disney characters
including all 101 and 101 Dalmatians
Which I don't
There must be tiny though
with the Dalmatians
Well, obviously none of his life's size
But I mean
How many, to buy the single
The area of a body by a thousand is not much room you've got
Yeah, so I mean I think it is to scale
But it is scaled down
And he has a system
So he has all the evil characters
are below his knees
All the undersea characters are below his belly
So I don't know
But then all the evil characters are under the sea
So I don't know how he works that out
Wow
Anyway, he gets copyrighted by a Disney
Like Disney's allowed him to do it
Oh really? He's the only person
Why is it illegal to do a Disney tattoo?
I think when you've got that many of them
What would they do?
Make you put it out? Oh yeah
We're going to have to move on to our next fact
So if anyone has anything more than they want to add
On mistakes in tattoos
John Caru, who's a footballer? Yeah, John Caru
John Caru, he got a tattoo saying
He wanted to say my life, my rules
So he got Mavie Meeregler
But he got the accent wrong on regular
He got an acute accent instead of a grave one
Which translates as my life, my menstruation
(Laughter)
Okay, it's time for our second fact of the evening
And that fact is Chazinski's
Yeah, my fact is that the man who invented the airship
Used to hold dinner parties with ten-foot-high chairs
So that his guests could experience the joy of flight
(Laughter)
This guy is amazing, presenting like Alberto Santos-Dumel
And first of all, he decided to have hanging from the ceiling
Which he could understand was more reminiscent of flight
But one of his first dinner parties
He put all his guests hanging from the ceiling
And the ceiling collapsed
So he's...
(Laughter)
So after all the funerals of the previous guests
Weirdly, no one wanted to come to the next party
And the TV was fine
So the wake will be at mine, I've organised a nice dinner
(Laughter)
Wow
Yeah, he was great
He was an inventor, he grew up on a plantation in Brazil
And he invented a toy motor powered functioning aeroplane
Which was quite a long time before
He invented in the late 19th century
And then he moved to Paris and became a celebrity
Because he invented the airship
Which attracted attention
And used to invite celebrities and royalty to his house
And have these wacky dinner parties
And they'd have to mount their seats on ladders
(Laughter)
Yeah, he was so famous in his time
At the time said, "When the names of all those
Who have occupied outstanding positions in the world
Have been forgotten
There will be a name which will remain in our memory
That of Santos Dumont
(Laughter)
He does sound like an amazing guy
He sounds unbelievable, actually
As in, he had his own airship in Paris
When no one else had any means of flight
He was just flying around the streets of Paris
He would just stop at a cafe
Tether it
And then go down to the cafe
And say, "Well, so you like that, and fly off
It is in the late 19th century, early 20th century
He just did it
What was he tethering to
All right, rooftops
Yeah, it wasn't huge, when you look at photos of it
It's not a massive airship
It's like the size of the one and one or the hoodie
There was one man airship, I think, a personal airship
He would go past ladies bedrooms
And they would throw their underwear out of the window
(Laughter)
That's how famous he was
He was also super generous
So he was responsible for the first woman ever to take flight
Because there was a princess
She was a princess of some foreign country
Came to visit Paris, took an interest in his airship
Said, "Wouldn't mine go up one of those?"
And he taught her to fly one
And then he had her flying one through the streets of Paris
And he cycled blue shouting her instructions
And she did so
And this was the first woman to fly
Wow, I actually, it sounds way worse to think of mentoring their underwear
At her
Oh, Jesus!
He invented other things as well
I know the 10th of a chair, no one talks about it
No one mentions the 10th of a chair
We've all got one
And we've all got the motorised skis to get him back up and mounted
Really? And he invented it a sling shot
Which would throw life belts out from sinking ships
So that everyone could have a life belt
He also invented a racing airship
Which was similar to his airship
But he never raced it because he had no one to race against
(Laughter)
That is so sad
He could have just made two, couldn't he?
Can I bring it to dinner parties very quickly?
I just want to talk about my favourite dinner party host
From History, which is William Buckland
He's a very exciting character
He studied fossils and he was a geologist
But he also went on this massive mission
To eat every single thing in the animal kingdom
He was just like "I need to have everything his favourite"
So if you went to his house for dinner
You would end up having things like Elephant's trunk
Or mice on toast was his favourite thing
And he knew food so like he knew animal food
Everything about them so well
That he was once invited to go to this church
Where they thought a saint's blood was on the ground of this church
And he came over there
And he had a look at it and he was like
Because it was just his patch on the ground of the heart's the saint's blood
He leaned down, he licked it
And he came back up and went
"I was about urine"
He just knew
But also the worst guest to have at a dinner party in that respect
Because he went to this party which was Lord Harcourt
His the Archbishop of York
And at the dinner, Harcourt was like
"I've got this amazing relic that I want to show you all
And he brought out what was the heart of Louis XVI in a box
And within seconds Bucklinges grabbed it and he ate it"
But you say worse than he has ever
Very few dinner hosts bring the heart of a dead king
To the table
I would say worse than a host ever
Okay, here's another dinner party thing
Though a christening of Louis XIV's grandson
He created a cake
Sorry, there was a great chef called Antoine Karam
Who created a cake
And the cake was made out of own paste
Pastry and clockwork
And I loved clockwork
I love it so much
And it's so hard to get these days in paste trees
Every Greg's I go into
And they had clockwork
Because this cake on top of it had a baby juke
Entering the world through a marzipan vagina
That is quite a centipede system
So it was him
It was celebrating him
The child, yeah. It was a model of his mother
Giving birth to him
Yes, through a marzipan with clockwork
Don't get thy Greg's to you
No, no, wow
I was reading that back in the day
When furniture was just suddenly being
Introduced to the idea of us having it in our homes and stuff
Wait, wait, wait
I know, so very excited
When furniture was being introduced
To the idea
Of having it in our homes
It was a short for furniture
It wasn't domesticated until the 1500s
The beautiful days when
You know, freestanding shazes
Were just roamed the belt
Oh, come on
There are a wild chair these days
There are only
400 Louis Catoll's tables left in the wild
Sorry, sorry don't come
I know that was my fact
Apparently when we started introducing furniture
Like covers would just be put in the middle of the room
As opposed to against the wall now
And dinner tables
We didn't used to have legs to dinner tables
You would have people come and sit
If you were having a party
There would be a big board like this that you would bring out
And you would put it on your legs
So they would just be sat on your legs
And that's why apparently there were boards
And you would be a border
And apparently borders who stay in your house
That would hold the table up
Yeah, you'd hold the table up with your legs
I read this in Bill Bryson's book at home
He used to say that carpets
Before we used to walk on them you just have them on your wall
And you'd go, "It's my carpet"
And if you had a special guest
And you'd take it down from the wall
And you'd put it for them to walk on
And chairs used to be against the walls
You would have chairs against the walls
Because at night when you didn't have electricity
You would not trip over stuff in the middle of your room
But if you had chairs all over the shop
You should be asleep
They would get up halfway through the night wouldn't they?
Because people used to sleep in two different sections
And they'd get up and have sex
Or give it a crossword
You're very comfortable, aren't you?
Oh, we're going to have to move on
Should we move on as anyone got anything else?
I quite like the inactivity chair
Which has recently been invented
Which is a chair with only two legs
And it is basically so that you live in fear while you sit on it
And constantly be doing a balancing act
And I think the idea is that you can exercise
While also being seated but it sounds awful
Anyway, invest in one if you're looking to improve your health
I always think I'm not afraid enough when I'm sitting down
Stop the podcast
We have an emergency announcement to make
And this is it
Ladies and gentlemen, I've no such thing as a fish
Was produced with the help of Squarespace
Which is that award-winning website builder
That has 24/7 support, e-commerce, beautiful templates
It just makes it really easy to tell your story
However tedious, that story may be
To the world
Give your story a voice by going to squarespace.com
And use the offer code fish
To save 10% of your order
Okay, back to the podcast
Okay, time for fact number three, that is my fact
My fact this week is that a new scientific study has concluded
That there are too many scientific studies
It's basically the study was saying that it's doing a thing now
Where so many studies are coming out in science
That it's diminishing the attention that gets given to a actual good study
Because it's drawing headlines away from them
And studies are going so sort of minute into these little...
I don't know, like
There's great ones that we've read in the past
That we've talked about in the office and stuff
A study that showed that the fish herring
That they fought
To communicate with each other
That's how they talk
And that's a study and that might get in the way of say
Yeah, but that could be a good study
Because like you might want to know if there's a lot
So I think it was in Scandinavia somewhere
They heard a lot of like bubbles underneath the sea
And they thought it might have been like a Russian submarine or something like that
But it turned out to be herring communicating by farting to each other
And if you hadn't done the study you wouldn't know that that was a thing
So probably saved World War II
Russia and the whole world
Okay, so that was a bad example
Right
There are lots of studies that seem to be taking attention away
So it's the idea that we forget as well
Yes, so we might have cracked everything five years ago
But just not noticed at the time
And now we're carrying on and on with more studies
And we do study some of our relevance
I'm not we personally
But the Royal Society of Chemistry
Last year published 11 steps on how to make the perfect cup of tea
Which definitively determined after releasing this paper
That you are supposed to put the milk in first
To avoid de-napturation of the milk
We actually have big arguments in the queue
I'm facing our hearts to make tea
And I can sense a lot of anger
Oh my god, that was the British League ever
There was a palpable...
It wasn't a hiss
It was an intake of bread, isn't it?
I think we all felt that
So I am with the bread intake
Because I obviously think that was a travesty
So just to dress you got the milk in first
But that is what they say, that's the safer way to do it
It's also explained in this study
Three more tea deaths in World War II
So the single most downloaded paper in the history of the journal
Is it PLOS?
Mets and PLOS?
Is the 2005 paper
Why most published research findings are false?
That's quite good, isn't it?
So there's a guy who's written a lot of studies about falsehoods in science
And his name is John Ioanidis
And as a boy, he was already doing research on research
As it were, he was doing meta-research
And when he was a child, he came up with a love numbers system
To work out how affectionate he was about his own family
And he said, "My mother was getting a thousand and twenty four point four two
My grandmother, 173.73
It's not amazing
Yeah, he said basically that all the statistics in all these papers are a bit dubious
But then a lot of people who said actually his statistics are a bit dubious as well
So yeah, controversial
It is certainly, sorry, I assume he was talking about publication bias
So the publication bias is a major problem in scientific studies, isn't it?
Because the only positive results tend to be published
And about 90% of studies that are done actually yield negative results
Which aren't as headline-grabbing
And there are journals now which are like the journal of negative results
Which is just people who have done experiments and gone
We found nothing
Nothing has been achieved here
And there's also a guy called Mark Shrym at Harvard who wanted to see how easy it would be to get something published
And so he published an article
And he made one up using randomtextgenerator.com
And the article was called "Cuckoo for Coco Puffs"
And it was by Pinkerton A. LeBrain and Orson Wells
And he submitted it to 37 journals over two weeks and it was accepted by 17 of them
Wow!
Pinkerton A. LeBrain
It's an ominative determinism isn't it? Cause you know you have a name like LeBrain
You're going to be a scientist
There's a journal called Brain, isn't it? Do you remember that?
There's a journal called Brain and there's a guy who used to be the head of Brain who was called Head
And we had it was
And then he left Brain
And then when he left being the head of Brain, Head was replaced as the head of Brain by a guy called Brain
There's a website called "Retraction Watch" which is fun because they pay attention to people quietly retracting their research when it turns out to be wrong
Oh wow
That is done
Yeah, it was set up by these two journalists called Ivan Oranski and Adam Marcus and their absolute heroes
And the top one or two retraction holders are both anesthesiologists for what it's worth
One scientist in Japan who has had to retract 183 papers out of 212
Oh wow, so publishing him is so much
But his name is Captain Orson, it's the way it's used
It must be right
So I went on to DailyMail.co.uk and searched for according to a recent study
If there weren't two then he wouldn't be
And here were the first five things I found
And even sharks can be shy according to a new study
We have covered on the podcast that sharks can have friends
So that's not...
That's not gonna be a shy shot
And study reveals the tactics we use to avoid being head on the low
Oh, that's great
Any test for them? Any test? They only read the headlines so...
Another one was bump in the night, send in the wife
One in five men pretend to be asleep when hearing a possible intruder
Fortunately, it's always always furniture
But they haven't placed safely by the wall
We're gonna have to be born
Okay, one more thing, I look to other things that there's too many of
And there was a study done
It said three quarters of viewers of television have cited confusion over the proliferation of choice
As the reason they miss shows
As in there's so many channels they always miss TV shows
It's just flicking desperately between them and they can't find the right one
So I had a look at all the different channels on my TV system on Sky
And I found one which I'd never seen before
It's pavershoes.tv
And it's Sky Channel 669
And their programs include
Sensational sandals
Or pretty impumps
And classic clogs
Sounds like the best shot I've ever done
You know I'm a Q-I on this
That's great
That's 669
Put it in the UK at 667
That's a shoe size trophy
All right, we're gonna have to move on to our final facts
How did the shoe material go on?
(Laughter)
Typical final fact of the evening that is James
Okay, my fact is that you should never pick up a desert tortoise
If you do, it can pee itself to death
(Laughter)
Yeah, so what they do is they store urine in the bladder
Which they can then draw upon because they live in the desert
So they need as much water as they can get
And if you pick them up, they can get so scared
That they will evacuate their bladder
As they wet themselves
And then they can die of dehydration
Because they keep
Something like 40% of their body mass
Is kept as the urine
That then translates into a sort of like rehydrated water
Not rehydrated
It's really really diluted I think
So it's not too acidic or it doesn't damage them
But it's just a way that something can live in the desert
But obviously then they don't expect people to just come and pick them up
And then they die
But yeah, desert tortoises, pretty cool
They live around the Las Vegas area, around the bladder, around that
They dig basins to catch rainwater
Another way they get water
And they always know where they are
Whatever it looks like, it's gonna rain
They're always found next to these places
That they've dug waiting for the water to come
So they can immediately drink it
And weirdly, this is really strange
Humans are not so likely to die
When they're in the children or teenagers
Or whatever and you get more likely to die as you get older
But weirdly, desert tortoises
They are less likely to die
As the time goes on
The older they get, the less likely they are to die
Yeah, so that's why they live for so long
That's true of these places
One was so old, I read this in
Apparently there's a bit of contention about whether or not this is true or not
But one of Dara...
What we do is we'll cut that out
And put it at the start of every fight
Basically there was a tortoise called Harriet
Which belonged to Charles Darwin
So the contentionist bit is did that belong to Charles Darwin
They're not fully sure
But Harriet had a bit of a travelled life after Darwin
Or whoever got her
Ended up in Australia Zoo
And ended up being looked after by Steve Irwin
So Steve Irwin and Charles Darwin
Are connected within one lifetime
Wow, yeah that is pretty good
There was a tortoise called
There was a tortoise called Adweiter
Who lived to the age of 255
And that meant that this tortoise was born before the USA existed
And the death was announced on CNN
Wow
So there's some quite good footage of
A tortoise is living each other's buns like dogs
Because they secrete pheromones from like the Chloacher of that area
And there's quite good footage of a female tortoise
Crawling over a lettuce
And then secreasing her scent as she goes
And then a male tortoise really enthusiastically trying to have sex with the lettuce
Because we see
Wow
Lettuce was used to... they did think it was an aphrodisiap
Didn't they? In ancient Egypt
Tortuses and people did yeah
It's because they used to grow quite tall
They used to have wild lettuce
Which was really tall
And it wasn't like a normal boring modern lettuce
It was quite exciting
And it's secrete in a white sap
It's secrete in a white sap
And it tasted peppery and it was, yeah
And it was a stem and it's secrete, you know
Lettuce used to be better
Apparently tortoises can use touch screen
Technology now
They could touch things
Because no, because they found
They found that tortoises are actually a lot more clever than they believe them to be originally
For example, in mazes, they're fantastic in mazes
They can remember multiple destinations in one single route
Which often rats can't do
And now they're teaching them to use touch screen technology to
To create spotify lists
To create music
Because they've got great taste of music
Captain Orson published in his recent paper
I haven't seen the retraction list, I don't know if it was in that
But he, so if they need more food
And they give them grapes and apples and stuff
They press the right button
That highlights itself
So they go into a card of
And just
Wild lettuce
Oh, by the way
Apparently, so I've always been confused
Between what a tortoise and a turtle is
Oh yeah
And so I'm just going to say in case
Everyone here doesn't know the difference
But a tortoise has feet
And a turtle has flippers
So now we know
That's a very good wave
I thought they should have been called ninja tortoises
Because they have feet
Oh yeah
God, I think you've redeemed yourself with your eyes
What was amazing about that was it took ages for everyone to go
It's dumb, is it?
Definitely sound it
So on ways of staying hydrated in the desert
Where there's no water and no rain
There are lots of very cool ways of doing it
So there are some beetles
Which when night is just turning it today
They stand very still and they let fog condense on their bodies
And then they can drink it because it slowly coalesces onto them
And then they have enough water
To get them through the day
And then the beetles
Is fogstown beetles
Someone thought that was the best name on that day that they could come up with
Every time you see animals and their names
It's always like
There's a tortoise called the big headed tortoise
Like that was a fairies in all creative metres
Well he told me it was the best tortoise ever
Some other tortoise names while we're here
The pancake tortoise
The geometric tortoise
The impressed tortoise
Who hangs around with the big head tortoise I guess
And this guy I really like him
The wolf volcano giant tortoise
It just sounds like the four best things
Yeah
He's got a really good PR manager
Other ways of
So other desert animals that have like good ways of storing their water
So road runners urinate out their eyes
What?
Like they cannot see that in the cartoon
It's how they excrete their salt
Because you use up a lot of water
You lose a lot of water when you urinate
So they just lose it through their eyes
Also mountain goats you've got to be really careful now
Apparently in there is mountain goats like in North America
Because they really like human urine
Because they realise they don't have a natural salt
A natural thing they eat that provides them with their salt
But they have worked out that mountain is
We and that has salt in it
And so they will spot human
Mountain ears and follow them until they go to take away
And then they will sometimes
More of them
And attempt to eat drinks there
Oh god
Excretion, yeah you've got to look out
Where do they more?
No I don't know where
Don't turtles pee through their mouth
Sometimes pee through their mouth
And there are some uh the Fitzroy River turtle
Breeze through his amus
It's a really cool turtle
It's Australian I think and um yeah it is
It's in the Fitzroy River
And it lives in water which has a lot of oxygen in it
And um it's uh it's clowical orifice
Goes two thirds of the way along it
And it gets 68% of his oxygen through his bottom
Wow
Did you know a tart ice was once the fastest animal in the world
No it wasn't
He really was
Are you talking I can I guess
Would you tell it?
No is it the space thing?
It is the space thing
It looks like we're gonna big edit turtles in the room
I'm very close
This was in 1968
And the um Soviet sent out a spaceship with um
From Kazakhstan with a tortoise on it
And it was the first animal in deep space
And it travelled around the moon before returning to earth
Seven days later so for that shot about the time
It was the fastest animal in the world
There were also wine flies, mealworms
And a few other things but that was the main one
That was the headline grabber wasn't it?
No mealworms
I was there too
But they were the first life forms as well
To get around to the moon
So your fact was about things wetting themselves in a way
And we don't know why
There's no evolutionary reason why a lot of animals wet themselves
When they're afraid and it's really weird
But when they're being chased by lions
Not reasonable
Well one theory is that it might like send the lions off
Because they have to send somewhere else
I think that's one theory
But don't they surely they chase the scent until they reach the bottom
So you pee and then the lion will stop and go
Oh there's a smell of gazelle pee there
And then I mean that's just one theory
What is with humans when you get shocked I think is
Like somehow your brain gets overridden by the shock
And normally your brain is like you always want to pee
And your brain is saying no don't pee on stage
But you're shocked so much that you end up wetting yourself
It's weird there's a bit of the brain called the pontine micurition centre
Which is constantly saying let's go let's do it
Really yeah when you're bladder is full
It makes the decision to empty the bladder
And then but the prefrontal cortex always overrides the desire
But when you get really really really stressed
The limbic system overrides the prefrontal cortex
And so the signals get confused
And then you know it's like
It's all cold and you're ashamed
But we don't know why
It's long to stand off with
And we're going to have to wrap up
Okay well I think
Okay so there was a guy whose taught us had a swollen penis
And he didn't have the money to pay for the operation
And so he went on to one of these kickstart style things
And he needed 200 pounds
And he reached his target in less than 24 hours
And he went over he went up to 555 pounds
And he ended up to 555 pounds in the end people like really club together
And paid for it
And when you gave your money you could put a little note about what you wanted to say
And one person said
"I hope he gets the report done soon
I know what it's like having it in large penis"
That is not so nice
But at least he gave some money
So we have that totals doing well
And we're going to have to wrap up
So that's it that's all of our facts
Thanks so much for being here
If you want to get in contact with any of us about the things we've said
You can get us all on our twitter accounts
I'm on @Triberland James
@XHAPESAndy
@UnderHunterM
And we've got about 53 episodes up on
No such thing as fish.com
You can listen to those previous episodes there
For our final live show at the Soho Theatre next week
And yeah, we'll see you again next time
Goodbye, thanks so much
Thank you
[Applause]
[Music]
[BLANK_AUDIO]