(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covern Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski,
Andrew Hunter Murray and James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered round the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 1910,
the World Health Organization tried to ban kissing.
- Wow.
You think that'd be a bigger story
given such a huge organization, right?
- Especially as it happened 30 years before they existed.
- Yes.
- You would think so.
Thank you.
- What's going on here?
- If you listen very carefully,
you will have heard me say the world's health organization
as opposed to the more commonly known
world health organization.
And this was an organization.
And when I say an organization,
I mean really one woman in America called Imogene Recton.
And she decided that everyone should stop kissing.
And she got all the newspapers and invented a load
of badges and pledges and stuff like that.
And really thought that if people stopped kissing,
then maybe we could stop the spread of disease,
things like consumption, typhus, all that kind of stuff.
- Yeah.
- She kind of, she kind of been completely wrong.
- If everyone stopped kissing everyone else,
we'd have fewer diseases.
- Yeah.
- Well, we did try it for half a year in 2020,
if you remember.
- And no one got a cold.
So, you know, I'm just saying maybe the cost
is greater than the benefit.
- Yeah, but I feel like she was almost ahead of her time
understanding then about exchange of possible germs.
I mean, our mouths are rank.
We've got like billions of bacteria in them.
I know a lot of them are probably good bacteria.
But I think there was a study done that had people drink
like a yakult or a probiotic drink
and then had them snog their partner.
And they found the 80 million bacteria transferred
from one face to the other.
- Bacteria is tiny though.
Yeah, 80 million.
- 80 million.
- We don't know how much that is, do we?
- Is there everything where it's like,
oh, three bacteria transferred, it's gonna be big, right?
- It's such a good point.
- Even if three bacteria transferred before long,
there's gonna be more than,
there's gonna be four, five, six.
- There you go, that's true, there you go.
- They are rampant.
- She does sound amazing.
- Yeah.
- Imogene as well.
- Imogene.
- Weirdly, some newspapers call her Imogene,
but I think they might be misprints.
'Cause most of them say Imogene.
- She got a lot of support.
She got some support.
She got a thousand acolytes,
which I think is a good hit rate
for this slightly dramatic campaign.
- She's got a number of acolytes.
- Yeah.
Well, including 70 brides
who declined to be kissed at their own weddings.
- Which I think, yeah.
- Yeah.
- You may now kiss a bride.
No, you may not.
- Yeah.
- So in the article that you sent over, James,
when you found this,
there was a nice little thing that she,
it starts off by saying that she'd convinced her husband
of the risks associated with promiscuous kissing,
which sounds like she had a bit of a dog in the race
to begin with.
Yeah, she had a husband.
- So he was a big kisser, right?
- Well, I think what it sounds like,
reading further into the article,
is that kissing on the lips and kissing generally
was much more what you just did.
If you had parties at the house,
everyone would kiss each other on the lips.
Women would kiss each other,
men would kiss men.
- 1910.
- That's my party.
- That's what her husband was telling her anyway.
First of all, the keys go in the bowl,
then we start kissing,
and then we'll see what happens.
- Yeah, I don't think men were snogging each other that much.
By 1910, there've been phases when the kiss has been in,
but I think her husband's been just spinning out yarn.
- I did just throw that in.
I have to admit,
it was definitely said women were kissing women.
I thought, well, men should be kissing men.
- I was in France recently.
I saw, I was in the South of France,
and I was in a particularly kissy region.
- Oh yeah.
- It was a very kissy region.
I think I saw some people kissing four times.
- Yeah.
- But there's more.
- Way more.
- I think you do get, there are fives definitely.
- I've had a good five or six.
- You've had a six kiss.
- Yeah, I lived in France for three months
with my grandmother in 2003.
I've had a six.
You start counting when it.
- Six.
- Six, I've had a six.
Maybe she wanted to give me six.
- I've seen a five.
- Your grandmother.
(laughing)
- No, her oldie mates.
- All the grandmas at the retirement.
Maybe they forget.
Maybe they forgot.
(laughing)
Halfway through, they're like, ah.
- What am I on?
- I'm gonna start again.
- You can be stuck in the old people's name for hours,
go on you.
- Think about older people kissing.
This was actually one of Imogene's theories.
And she thought that if she could stop older people
from kissing each other,
and actually more like stopping them from kissing children,
then eventually when the older generation died out,
so kissing would die out.
'Cause the children wouldn't have got it
into their system that it's a thing that you do.
That was her plan.
- That's interesting.
Probably would have worked if she'd, again, if.
- If she's got more than a thousand acolytes.
- Yeah.
- Look at this cultural thing, you know, it's a learned thing.
- We assume it is.
Yeah, I think there's some debate, isn't there?
But I think we assume it's a learned thing largely
because about just over half of societies don't do it.
- Yeah.
So the number is 46% do do it of cultures
that were looked at to see whether lip to lip kissing
was a thing.
- But what's a culture?
- As in is Britain one culture?
- No, no, no, it's not like Britain.
It's obviously tiny minorities of people
'cause the vast majority of people on earth do kiss now
because we're a globalized society.
But if you go to an Amazonian tribe
or Papua New Guinea or something.
- Yeah, right.
- I think it's particularly uncommon
in parts of China, parts of Mongolia.
That area is quite uncommon.
- So it was 168 cultures from around the world.
This was a professor of anthropology
at the University of Nevada, Las Vegas,
which I assume is a serious university.
- I just associated it with gambling.
I don't know why.
- Las Vegas, it does do all the stuff.
- That university is a very wealthy one actually
'cause one year, a few decades ago,
they put everything on red.
And yeah, I could use it out now.
- The first person who kind of observed
that a lot of these cultures don't do mouth to mouth kissing
was a guy called Paul Denjoy.
So it's de-apostrophe and then enjoy.
- Don't enjoy.
- It's such a good name.
He said that some people considered it an abomination
and a form of cannibalism.
- Oh, come on.
That's someone kissing too hard.
- It's a step on the road,
it's a step on the road to cannibalism.
It's a slippery slope.
- So just back to Imogen very quickly.
I read a lot of newspaper articles about her
because in 1910 and 1911, she was everywhere.
Obviously, the newspapers saw this story
that they're trying to ban kissing and they loved it.
She was known as the foe of oculation in the press.
Oculation being another word for kissing.
And in August of 1910,
she tried to organize a no kiss August,
which you know, it's like, no drink January
or whatever they call it in November.
I reckon this might be the first of those.
In 1910, it must be early.
But then by 1912, there were no more mentions
of her on newspapers.com.
So after two years, the press weren't interested anymore.
- Do we know any more about her story at all?
Like, do we know when she died or?
- I know when someone with her name died.
Well, I couldn't tell if it was definitely her.
So, I'm not really sure.
She kind of went away after that.
- Two hemorrhageans.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- 13% of people, so they've been accidentally
kissed on the mouth at work.
- How does that?
- Dan says, "Oh, yeah."
Dan gets around kissing people on the mouth all the time.
- Sometimes the turn comes too sharply.
- An air kiss, to another air kiss.
- Especially when you're doing seven.
- I found someone else who has an anti-kissing rule.
- Oh, yeah? - Oh, yeah.
- And it's Champion Whistlers.
Specifically one Champion Whistler,
who's a guy called Christopher Ullman,
who I think has won at the International Whistlers Convention.
And there are lots of different kinds of whistling.
And he says he has a no-kissing rule
for 24 hours before a performance.
- Interesting.
- Well, he must have a lot of whistling groupies.
- Yeah, he sounds great.
He says it makes your lips mushy kissing before a performance.
So he doesn't lick his lips,
which I'm very impressed by.
- God, that's amazing.
Now, they must be dry, parched, and dry
by the time he's whistling.
- But then they must be like a solid whistle, right?
- Have you got dry lips?
I think it's very hard to whistle, isn't it?
- Is it?
What does he say, Andy?
- I don't actually know how he moises them.
I've only got other details,
like he can do Mozart's oboe concerto, the oboe part,
but whistling, which is hard.
- I think most people can do any part, right?
- Yeah, most people can whistle any tune.
- If it's a tune, it's whistleable.
- The problem is none of us knows Mozart's oboe concerto.
- That piece, that's a good point.
That's a very good point.
- So when his stooge in the crowd goes,
I bet no one here can do that.
(all laughing)
- And then he does it and everyone's like,
is that that, is that that?
- Better to do a plane engine though, or a drill,
or, you know, something that doesn't sound like a whistle.
- Yeah.
- Exactly.
- What would the point, what was that?
- It was a drill.
- That was Beethoven's.
(all laughing)
- All right, well, we're just currently driven
by this guy's whole career.
- No, but it's interesting because I, you know, how would you...
- It can't be his career.
(all laughing)
- It's unclear.
It's unclear.
(all laughing)
- I know he's got all these groupies,
but really, you make it looking out for.
- They asked him, in this interview,
if his family gets sick of the whistling,
and he said, "I actually don't whistle
"around the house very much.
"Random, idle whistling is very annoying."
- Well, that's, someone's told him that a lot of times.
In 1921, in the newspapers,
there was a worry about people kissing freckled girls
on the cheeks.
Can you guess why that might be dangerous?
This was in the newspapers.
- Freckles come off, they go on your lips.
You get a lip covered in freckles, can't eat you stuff.
- Or would they thought to be contagious, I guess, is the...
- Freckles?
- Yeah, in the 1920s.
(all laughing)
- Was this a justified thing, or was it a great...
Okay, so it's justified.
Freckled girls.
- Because, because, because they are out in the sun,
so they are wearing what, back in the 1920s,
was radioactive sunscreen.
- You're so close.
- Yeah, so the sunscreen had chemicals in it.
- No, no, don't carry on with the wrong answer.
- Okay, okay, just try...
- Radioactive sunscreen, which meant that to kiss them
would give radiation, and you'd become...
- Yeah, have a radioactive part.
- Oh, okay.
- It's the being outside part.
- No.
- Poisonous makeup.
- Almost.
Basically, there was a antifreckle medication
that people were using to try and get rid of their freckles,
and it was toxic if ingested.
And so there was a danger, according to the newspapers,
if you kissed a freckled girl on the cheek,
you might get sick.
- Oh, my gosh.
- That's awful, 'cause the girls are gonna think
that their medication isn't working at all,
'cause still no one's kissing them.
- Yeah.
- Alternatives to kissing,
which people have had to come up with,
these poor societies that don't have kissing.
Darwin, who met a lot of people in his life,
different peoples,
listed a bunch of alternatives to kissing in cultures,
and he listed rubbing of noses,
like which lapplanders he's known as do,
rubbing or patting of the arms, breasts, or stomachs,
or one man striking his own face
with the hands or feet of another.
- Like a slap, proper slap.
- It's like, why are you hitting yourself?
Why are you hitting yourself?
- Oh, right.
- Well, actually, it's not you hitting yourself,
it's me grabbing your hand
and then hitting me in the face with your hand.
- You are actually hitting yourself, yeah.
- Why are you hitting me?
Why are you hitting me?
- Yeah, why are you hitting me?
- Was that a game?
Why are you hitting me?
(laughing)
- It was a cat phrase, you could say, yeah, yeah.
- Can I talk about very quickly
some other public health stuff?
- Yeah.
- Especially done by American women.
So this is a group of middle-class women from Manhattan
called the Ladies Health Protective Association.
And they, basically, there was a huge pile of manure
in the middle of New York, okay?
They covered two blocks and stood 30 feet tall.
- I was picturing much smaller when you said there was a pile.
(laughing)
- That's incredible.
- Like the Godzilla.
- So what they would do is, obviously,
a lot of horses in those days, right?
They would collect the manure from stables
and they would sell it as fertilizer to farmers
who were just outside the city,
but they needed someone to keep it
and so they just kept it in the middle of the street.
It was this guy called, weirdly enough,
he was called Michael Caine.
(laughing)
But Caine, as in Harry Caine, with a K.
But anyway, Michael Caine had this huge manure pile
and he was making loads of money.
He was making $300,000 a year,
which today is about $8 million from this manure pile.
And his brother-in-law was a New York state senator,
so everyone thought there was nothing
they could do about it.
Anyway, this Ladies Health Protective Association
came along and did a court case
and amazingly, they won it.
They basically called it a nuisance
and by the law, there was no way that he could get around it
because of this technical thing they called it.
And not only that, the Board of Health denied any permits
for any manure dumps in the whole city.
So that's why, if you go to New York now,
there's not a 30-foot pile.
- I've always wondered why there's not a 30-foot pile.
- And this group then turned to spitting.
Sorry, they turned to stop spitting, okay.
And that was when New York became the first city
in the world that banned spitting.
- Isn't it true that in the middle of the Central Park,
there was a massive reservoir of spit?
- Disgusting.
- Okay, on with the podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that after King Charles I was decapitated,
he was recapitated.
- Oh, you just made that word up.
- Yeah, so King Charles I,
only King who's ever been executed,
I guess loads of them have been killed in battles
and things like that.
But it was in 1649 and it was just after the English Civil War
and obviously huge move, you know, big old move.
- Big deal.
- Political chaos, yeah.
But the King's body basically had to be seen
and the authorities, the sort of Republican authorities
wanted to say, look, he's definitely dead
and he's not coming back.
So they employed a surgeon after the execution
to stitch the head back on.
- I would have thought that if I'd have seen
his body without the head,
that would be even more proof that he wasn't alive.
- That's a good point.
- It sort of looks like he was kind of coming back
in the head that's meant to be off with suddenly back on.
- Anyway, I should say quickly where I got this from,
I've been reading a book.
It's actually from a novel.
It's called "Act of Oblivion"
and it's all about the hunt for the regicides.
- Is it by Thomas Harris?
- No, by Robert Harris.
- Robert Harris, yeah, yeah.
- So basically, and it describes in incredibly gory detail
the death of the King and also the death of the regicides
who the people who signed the death warrant and all this
and who really, they really put through the ringer.
- Yeah, this is, we should say for internationalists,
they didn't put them through the ringer
as soon as they'd killed the King.
It wasn't like you've executed the King
and now we're gonna execute you.
It was when the restoration happened.
So there was a brief period
where everyone was pro-killing the monarchy.
And then sadly, yeah, after a decade, monarchy came back
and then all the regicides got hunted down sadly.
- Sadly, Aniseh, sadly monarchy came back.
- From the perspective of a round head,
I was adopting the character of Oliver Cromwell.
- So I didn't know anything about Charles the First
having not grown up in this country.
So I am one of these foreign listeners, as it were,
that you mentioned, Anna.
And it struck me that what a big deal it was
to kill the King off the back of a trial.
'Cause there's all this stuff.
And Oliver Cromwell is a name
that is very much part of the decision
to bring him to trial and have him execute.
- A key player.
- And the story gets quite gruesome
when we talk about what happened to him and the others
some 30 years later after the death.
- Only 10 years later.
- Sorry, 10 years later.
- Okay, so 1649, Charles was killed.
And then recapitated, right?
1650, I think it was eight, Oliver Cromwell died
after less than 10 years in office.
And then two years later, the monarchy is restored, 1660.
Then at that point, Oliver Cromwell is dug up
and decapitated.
So both Charles and Cromwell had a head-altering situation.
- They should have switched the rounds.
It was freaking Friday.
- Freaking Friday.
- It was his son, was it King Charles II,
who was a direct son of Charles I,
who then was the person in charge of the monarchy once?
- The person in charge of the monarchy or the king?
(all laughing)
- Well, that's surprising that it disappeared for 11 years.
I mean, that is a pretty big deal.
It wasn't just overthrowing the monarchy,
it was overthrowing all of the monarchy.
- It was the other deal.
- It was one of the biggest things
that's ever happened in England's history.
- I was just saying, as a foreigner,
you don't follow, sorry, good up to date
on Charles the first.
- You have lived here for about 20 years now.
I feel like you should have some point.
- Yeah, it should have been as I was coming to immigration.
- Did you not have to do an exam to get into the UK?
- No, a British.
- Well, do you want to know something really interesting?
It's not in a lot of the citizenship tests,
or at least a couple of years ago,
there was a really good article on--
- Maybe question number one.
(laughing)
- There was a really good article on history today
about how it wasn't in the test for new immigrants.
There was nothing about the civil war,
anything like that, and missed that whole period.
And someone asked immigration,
why isn't this included?
And they said the wounds are still too fresh.
So I spoke first and said,
the assumption is that we are all anti-cromwell.
Obviously parliamentarian,
didn't believe in the divine right of kings.
The reason that Charles the first was overthrown
was because he really went hard
on the divine right of kings as well.
He loved it, didn't he?
Like he prorogued parliament for 11 years,
didn't want to ask them anything,
and then told them to give him loads of money.
He was into absolutist monarchy.
- And when they put him on trial,
he was like, well, you can't put me on trial
because God put me here, so.
- Yeah.
And now I think Cromwell is a bit of a villain
to almost everyone.
But in another country, he would be a hero.
And in fact, in America, he's remembered quite heroically.
- He's still got a statue outside of parliament.
- Yeah, which is surprising.
So he's not, yeah, and that wasn't toppled
in the old topples of statues period
that we went through quite recently.
- No, it wouldn't be.
- After he died, his, or rather after he died,
was dug up and then posthumously re-executed.
His body and a couple of comrades,
they were hanged, beheaded,
and then the heads were placed on spikes.
His head stayed on a spike for 25 years.
- That is the most amazing.
For me, the most amazing thing about this whole thing.
- It's a long time.
- But for 25 years, whenever you came to London,
you could go and look at a head on the spike.
And if you came back 25 years later, it would still be there.
- It's amazing.
Like, I think about all the shops near my house.
Most of them are less than five years old
'cause they just all got-
- The turnover.
- Yeah.
- It was much less than those days.
You got a lot of custom in the same place for a head.
- Amazing.
- But one person who lived through the whole thing
was Oliver Cromwell's son, Richard.
So when Cromwell died, he happened so often
with rulers, tyrants, newly established raids.
Anyway, they try and hand over to their kids.
- So let's get rid of the monarchy.
It's ridiculous that someone could have the divine right
to rule, but when I die, I want my kids to have it.
- I actually do think Napoleon too
is a good name for an emperor.
So, and anyway, so Richard Cromwell resigned.
He was not up to the job.
I mean, he was not, you know, as zealous as his father
and he didn't have the authority.
So he was kicked out in 1659, one year later,
and he just lived out his life.
He died in 1712.
I think he moved overseas.
- I think if your dad's head was on the spike
in London, you probably would move out of town.
- You wouldn't say in London, would you?
- But get this, he died in 1712.
He lived an incredibly long time.
So he saw the whole thing and he was the longest-lived
British head of state until the year 2012
when he was overtaken by Queen Elizabeth the second prime.
When she was 85.
So that's the age he lived to.
So for a long time, the longest-lived head of state
was Richard Cromwell.
- That's really funny.
- Do you know where Oliver Cromwell's head is now?
- Oh, was it reburied with the rest of him?
- No, it was buried in Cambridge University now.
- Okay, so I read this in a Giles Brandrith book
and I tweeted him to ask him if this was true
and he tweeted me back.
So I said, "My memory of it goes like this.
"There is a relic of Oliver Cromwell
"kept by the chief whip or prime minister.
"Have I made that up?"
I probably have.
He wrote back, "It's in the drawers at Checkers."
So my memory is that the skull of--
- The skull of Oliver Cromwell is in Checkers.
- Is in a drawer.
- In a drawer.
- And I think I've read it in Brandrith's autobiography,
his diaries of his time as a politician.
And in it he says he goes to Checkers and the drawers open
and they let you see and stroke the skull.
- Stroke the skull.
- So what I have in my notes is that one day
there was a storm and the head blew off the spike
and they thought, "You know what?
"It's been here for 25 years.
"We probably don't need to put it back up again.
"Everyone's seen it now."
- They get the idea.
- Yeah, they get it again.
- Exactly.
- And then the skull was sort of taken away
and it was just kind of sold in auction after auction
and went through a load of families.
But then it was buried at Sydney Sussex College,
Cambridge in 1960.
- Interesting.
- That's what I've got.
But I mean, probably like with these things,
there's probably 20 of those skulls around there.
- Yeah, and I don't specify what relic I mean.
He could have thought it might have been a finger
or something in my head.
It's his head.
- Oh well, maybe it's not the head.
That's more normal if it's a finger.
'Cause I can't think of a drawer that could even fit a skull.
- Oh, I think you can't think of a drawer that could fit a skull.
- I can't imagine.
- Are you gonna pull out of that?
- I should pull out of that.
I suppose I'm imagining a desk drawer
and there's old desks and tiny drawers.
- The bottom drawer,
universe standard wooden desk will be a bit bigger.
- But even if that didn't exist,
it doesn't take much imagination to take a drawer
and make it slightly deeper.
- My head, ironically, my head is not big enough
to get around this concept.
- Have you ever seen a filing cabinet because...
- Oh, no, don't.
It's too much.
- You're gonna flip your lid.
- I can't take it.
So Anna's amazing Freaky Friday idea,
which I actually think is a brilliant idea.
- Thank you.
- Maybe could have been truish
because when Cromwell's head got put on the spike,
there was a big rumour around that actually it wasn't his head
and that they'd mistakenly got on the wrong one
and it was probably some old King of England.
They didn't specify which one it was.
'Cause it was, he was originally buried.
Was it in Westminster Abbey, I think?
- Right, yeah.
- So there was loads of other Kings there
and they thought that they dug up the wrong thing
and just put an old King's head there.
- Surely you just pick the roundest head.
- Brilliant.
- Brilliant, yeah.
- Round head joke.
- It's a round head joke.
- Oh, very nice.
- They did used to toss them in all together a bit.
Like actually there was obviously a conundrum
after Charles was decapitated
because they don't wanna create a martyr of him
by having it either be a big thing bearing him
or not bearing him at all.
So I think they took him away to Windsor
and they entered him in Henry VIII's tomb, weirdly.
- Wow.
- And then in 1813 they decided to dig him up again.
I think this was to check.
- Again, again.
- He was there, again.
- Right, okay.
- Just the first time again.
- Oh, okay, sorry, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And it was George III's physician,
Henry Halford, who was kind of leading the exhumation.
And he ended up with Charles's vertebra
and some beard and some of his teeth.
- Beard.
- Which is, yeah, some beard.
- I'm surprised the beard is still extant
after all that time.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that seems weird, doesn't it?
- From how many years?
- How many years, did we say?
- Yeah, well, this was 1813, so it's 100 years.
- 160 years.
- What?
- So he says that they went,
"Oh, it's not worth opening the coffin again.
"Do you mind just keeping these?"
And he kept them.
Other people who were there say that he went in
and nicked all the stuff and hung onto it.
But then his grandson returned it.
It was the 1890s and he went to the Prince of Wales
and said, "Well, look, we've got these bits
"of Charles I, do you want them?"
- The story, the QI facts that we always say
about this is that they used the vertebrae as a salt holder.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, so if you ever went for dinner
at Sir Henry Hulford's house and you wanted some salt,
it would be a little dish,
but when you looked at it closely,
it would be part of his backbone.
- Wow. - That's,
and you can fit that in a cupboard.
(all laughing)
- The eventual outcomes for the regicides
who were the people who'd signed the death warrant,
basically, were bad.
So I think a lot of them are disemboweled.
- They're bad.
- They were not good.
- They were courted.
- They were, yeah, hanged until not quite dead
and then had the genitals removed
and then were disemboweled.
- Still alive, still conscious.
- While still alive, got to the lie.
But if you got away, then it could be okay.
And interestingly, if you live in Connecticut near,
I think in New Haven,
then there are three streets called Dixwell Avenue,
a Wally Avenue and Goff Street.
- Dixwell.
- Dixwell and Wally.
- Wally.
- And what was the other one?
- Dixwell, Wally and Goff.
(all laughing)
- They were the worst surveyors that I ever had for life.
- But Wally and Goff are the two
that are in this book, Active Oblivion.
- Are they?
- Dixwell was the doubt, apparently.
(all laughing)
- Well, they all ended up in this place
and they liked them so much in America,
obviously, 'cause America aren't that pro monarchy,
that they named these streets after them.
- Yeah, they were in very, very religious,
puritanical communities,
which were already very uncertain about monarchy
and wanted development.
- It was kind of the place where they could go,
wasn't it, when they were safe?
There was another place in North America
named after someone connected to this story.
So the wife of Charles I was Henrietta Marie.
She was a French Catholic princess.
She got married by proxy, which is quite cool.
So Charles I wasn't there when she got married.
So he had a proxy who was George Villiers,
the first Duke of Buckingham,
but George Villiers wasn't available either.
So they got another proxie, her name was Charles de Lorraine,
who was the Duke of Chavres.
And basically, they got married
with this guy pretending to be the king.
And in those days, you could do that.
- I think we've said before, haven't we?
There were various rituals, if you marry a proxie,
like you, as the proxy would,
maybe have to touch the person's thigh.
I think that happened.
- You have to lie in bed and touch the thigh.
- Lie in bed and be witness with them.
Yeah, yeah.
- So the king only met his wife three months later at Dover.
So they'd been married for three months when he met her.
- That's so funny.
- And one of these areas in North America
where Catholics felt safe where they could go
was named after Henrietta Marie,
and it was Maryland, or Maryland, or Maryland.
And we always say this name,
and we always pronounce it wrong on this podcast,
and the people of Maryland always write to us.
But now I actually think that because it's named
after Henrietta Marie, it should be called Marie-Land.
- Yeah.
- So that's why I will be covering it from now on.
- Excellent, very nice.
- Especially because she didn't like Mary, actually.
'Cause she was French, and she was very French.
And she was beginning English.
She didn't like being called Mary.
- So the English used to call her Mary as like a micknail.
- And she said, no, I'm French.
Mary's not my name.
I don't even like the name Mary, fair enough.
Mary is a better name than Mary, I-M-O.
- Can we talk a bit about the execution itself?
Why is it such an interesting,
I mean, what an extraordinary,
I mean, one of the weirdest days ever to happen
in English history, you know?
It was on whiteboard, it was not far from here.
So when it happened, the executioner had to wear a disguise,
because the executioner's never been identified for sure.
- Do you not just mean like a hud?
- No, I don't.
I mean a wig, a fake beard, a sailor's costume.
- Yeah, confusing details here.
- I'm clear as to why, and fishnets over the face.
- Okay.
- So afterwards, after the restoration,
there was a big manhunt for who was the exact executioner,
'cause we're gonna kill him.
- There must have been a lot of sailors
getting rid of their fishnets just in case they can't.
- Well, the executioner was never properly identified.
One guy was sentenced to death for it,
but then the sentence was overturned.
- And one guy claimed to be,
and then wrote that they can't remember about that.
- There's a museum in London
that has a few of these relics from the execution,
including a shirt that belonged to Charles the First,
that they believe.
You know, they can't actually work out properly,
but all his bits of clothing was sort of torn off him,
and handed round and orchid.
- That's the museum of London, isn't it?
- The museum of London, yeah.
And among those items, they have a patched leather shoe
of a man called John Big,
and they believe that Big was the executioner.
At least that's one of the theories.
- Okay, Mr. Big.
- Mr. Big, yeah.
- That's what that whole thing, it was an analogy.
- The Sex and the City character, Mr. Big.
- It was an analogy for the English Civil War.
- Yeah, that's very interesting.
- Can't believe you didn't see that.
- So I guess, I guess, what's our name is it, Carrie?
- Guess it.
- Carrie Fishnet, Carrie Fishnet.
But they thought that would be too obvious.
- Oh my God.
- I don't think it's Carrie Fishnet.
- Is she called Carrie Bradshaw?
- Oh, Carrie Fishnet is a different person, isn't it?
- I think it's Carrie Bradshaw.
- She called Carrie Bradshaw, well, interestingly,
John Bradshaw was the parliamentary commissioner
who tried Charles I in Westminster at all.
- You are joking.
- No.
- I can't believe we're actually blowing this shit wide.
(laughing)
- This is huge.
- Bradshaw and Big.
- If any of us had ever properly watched Sex and the City,
we'd be all over it right now.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in World War II,
a Finnish soldier got tired in the Arctic,
so took the entire platoons,
rations of methamphetamine,
and subsequently skied 400 kilometers to safety.
(laughing)
- It's extraordinary.
- It's the power of uppers.
- It's insane the story.
- It's a really insane story.
So this is a chap called Aimo Koyvanen,
and it was a time when Finland was all with the Soviet Union.
It was mid-Second World War.
Finland was sort of on Germany's side,
all with the Soviet Union, and he's fighting
in this very cold area with his platoon,
and he had been tasked with keeping
his entire group supply of pervitin, which is meth.
And it was so crucial in the Second World War,
everyone was bloody taking it,
and he was really, really tired,
and I think the Soviets were coming and chasing them,
and he was told to lead them to make tracks
and lead them away so they could escape.
And he was at the front,
and he said in his memory of it that,
so plausible.
(laughing)
He said, especially 'cause first of all he said,
I didn't wanna take them 'cause I was kind of against that,
I disapproved of drugs, so I tried not to,
but then I got so knackered that,
look, I just tipped a pill into my hand,
what I hoped was a pill, but I was wearing mittens,
and so quite a few came out,
turns out all 30 of the pills came out,
and then because he wanted to hide
what he was doing from his comrades,
he just ate them all.
(laughing)
- You're being shot at, it's stressful.
- I'm just, I'm just gonna have all the tic-tacs basically.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- If you pour a lot of tic-tacs in your hands,
let's say you only want two, but accidentally rive come out,
you're not gonna put them back in the tic-tac.
- Exactly.
- Especially if you're being shot at.
- You're being shot at.
- As I usually am when I eat tic-tacs.
- Just drop them in the snow, anything.
- And then it goes Sonic the Hedgehog, 'cause suddenly,
- I don't, I was thinking--
- He just eats this.
- I was thinking of Popeye when Popeye had just finished,
(laughing)
suddenly turned into a mutant absolute, like, yeah.
He basically, as it goes, he received the hit in one swoop,
and the hit, by the way, lasts for a very long time.
- When you take a normal amount of meth,
it can last a few days, so I think--
- He took an OD level of it, is what they say right.
And I figure that the OD level would come to you in one hit.
This kind of just plays out over a number of days,
and he goes speeding away, and they're trying to,
they're trying to chase him, and they eventually--
- He's collected all his rings.
(laughing)
- And they can't keep up, and the music goes really fast,
and they're chasing him still, and he's just going off,
and then this is the craziest bit,
which presumably you've got more on, Anna,
'cause I just couldn't believe it, so I stopped reading.
He blacks out.
(laughing)
He blacks out, and keeps going.
- Basically, a few days later, he kind of was like,
"Oh, where am I?"
- Yeah.
- And it turned out they'd been doing that.
(laughing)
- He may have collapsed multiple times on the way.
Basically, one of the things I found surprising
in his account is that he said,
"You felt amazing for a bit."
Quite a short time, I think,
where he'd speed like something, the hedgehog,
and then he said, "Something very unexpected happened.
"I completely lost the plot
"and started hallucinating and collapsing.
"I would say that's not unexpected
"if you have taken 30 pills of Beth."
But then, the mystery is what happened
to the people with him, and I think,
'cause what proceeded this was actually
an argument between him and his men.
And he blacks out, and the next thing he remembers,
he wakes up and he's completely on his own.
So, one sort of suspects, they had a chat
and said, "This guy's been so annoying right now.
"He's a massive liability."
- Post-meth, post-him-taking of the pills.
- Post-meth, yeah.
Well, they took all his ammunition off him, didn't they?
- Yeah, yeah.
And his food supplies, so he woke up and had nothing.
- Well, then he started skiing towards,
he saw some allies in the distance
and started skiing towards them,
much too late, realized he's their Russians.
- Yeah.
- But he's still got the drugs on him.
- He skis through them and past them, keeps going.
- He said they were so confused,
they just moved, they should have shot him,
and they just moved their legs out
the way to let him get past.
- Excuse me, he spent all night
trying to get to a distant farm window,
which turned out to be the North Star.
(laughing)
- And then, he survived, didn't he,
by chewing on some tree, like a cactus-style?
- He boiled pine needles at one point,
so he still had delicious pine tea, had some pine tea,
but he was really starving.
It was only at the very end
where he somehow had found a hut,
finally there's cabin in the woods,
and first of all, it's so funny.
He says, "I lit a fire in the middle of the cabin."
It's still clearly high, so didn't know
what he was doing, lit a fire in the middle
of a wooden cabin, and it just set fire to the cabin.
And he said, "I just sat next to the fire
"and followed it around as it burned the cabin down,
"gradually, the whole cabin collapsed around him."
- How many days into the trip,
and I mean the trip?
- Well, he just doesn't know.
I think about five days, but he has no idea.
He only realized when he came out of it,
it had been two weeks.
And yeah, on his last day, he was about to starve to death,
and a J flew past, and he whacked it with a ski pole,
and ate a raw J.
- Again, not the actions of someone
who's completely with it.
I mean, the ability to beat a bird out of the sky is unusual.
- It was a stick, that's hard though.
- It was a stick.
- Those ski poles are quite thin.
- People don't go on pheasant shoots
with just a ski pole, do they?
- No, they're pros, yeah, yeah.
Was this before or after he got blown up?
Sorry.
- That was after.
- Oh yeah, that's right.
- So he was sat on fire, and then he was blown up,
and then he had the J, right?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
'Cause he found another little building,
and so it was a German post,
but the Germans had retreated from it,
and they had attached mines to it.
So he basically shredded his entire foot
in the first explosion,
and then he sort of hopped around,
and he opened a door, and then that was also mined,
and supposedly he came to about, you know,
many meters away, he'd been blasted across,
but he was still holding the door lock,
like in a cartoon.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's the most extraordinary story.
- Do we think true?
- I can't imagine any of it's true,
I think he was sitting at home.
- Because we knew he was anti-drugs, right?
Maybe he's come up with all this
of his adult dude drug stuff.
- Oh, this is like a finished 40s talk to Frank thing.
- Yes.
- I think we know, 'cause we know from his associates
that the first bit happened and the last bit happened,
but I suppose the only account we have
of the in-between bit is his.
- With a guy with a lot of drugs in his body,
that's all we've got.
- But he must have had a shredded foot, right?
- Yeah, yeah, the blown off first.
- And he must have been holding a doorknob.
(laughing)
- Must have had a bloody ski pole with him.
- Oh, dead Jane.
- He just kind of looked at all these things,
like, right, I'm gonna have to make a story up about these.
- But anyway, somehow he made it,
I mean, eventually he was found by his allies,
who were the Germans or the Finnish,
and taken to hospital and--
- Apparently his heart rate was still 200 beats per minute
at that stage. - God, it's a lot.
- It's a lot.
- It's incredible he lived.
- It's extraordinary. - And then he drove
to the ripe old age, you know,
who just wore it in the '70s and then, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Anyway, he was mad, but the use of meth was,
it was big, wasn't it?
The Germans were particularly into it.
- Yeah.
- But everyone did it.
- Well, I was reading you could get these pills
called Forced March, which were quite common,
even like at the start of the 20th century.
So they were a blend of cocaine and caffeine.
I mean, I don't know why you need a caffeine
at the point where you've had all the cocaine,
but it was basically, it was sold publicly,
it was sold by the Wellcome, actually,
or by Burrow's Wellcome, who was one of the Wellcome family.
- Oh, really?
- It was a pharmaceutical family there, yeah.
- Yeah, they took them to the,
on the Antarctic Expeditions, the Forced March.
- Yeah, cocaine, opium. - Yeah, Scott and Shackleton,
but they took specifically Forced March,
which I think they've got to market it in a gentle way,
or maybe that's what you want is Forced March.
- I think that's what you need in motivation, right?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- I can't march anymore.
- Yeah, yeah, right.
- I've had some Forced March.
And did they use that,
'cause they use that, the Germans use that in the war.
Did the Brits use that as well, and the Allies generally?
- I think the Allies,
I think there was meth use all around, yeah, yeah.
The meth pills that were synthesized in the 30s.
- But maybe not for everybody, for people who,
I mean, obviously not for everybody,
but you know, as in maybe it would be for pilots,
rather than for standard...
- I think it was pilots to stay awake.
I think that's why the Allies use it, for sure.
- That's so interesting.
- So off the back of this,
I was just looking into supplies
that you take in the Arctic,
as in what you have to keep you going.
And, I mean, it seems like it was either cocaine or biscuits.
I said, no, it's like...
- It sounds like a student's fantasy, doesn't it?
- Yeah, you're right.
- What's on offer today?
- Same.
- So, get this, Captain Scott, right?
Scott of the Antarctic did loads of expeditions there.
He took some specially made biscuits,
which were glucose enriched,
and they're made by a firm called Huntley and Palmer.
But he set off with digestive, rich tea,
piti beurre, fancy lunch, ginger nuts,
as well as emergency Antarctic and small captain biscuits.
And later in his trip,
he got resupplied with more biscuits.
- I actually think that they're some of the worst biscuits
you've just named, like digestives and rich tea.
Where's the... - Rich tea, ginger nuts.
- The jammie dodger. - Jammie dodger, come on.
- Well, tragically, this was a pre-jammie dodger world.
I mean, maybe he would have made it back if he had to.
- On the first all-female expedition to the North Pole,
every woman involved eight four penguins per day.
- Wow.
- They don't have penguins, do they?
- They brought penguins from the Antarctic to the Arctic
solely to mince them up and eat them.
- Yeah, they're cruel,
and that's why they haven't sent women back to the North Pole.
This is, of course, biscuit penguins.
They were sponsored by McVitie's.
And so, McVitie's provided them with the hot nail down number,
maybe, but thousands of penguins, I believe,
and one of the women said they were told
to eat four penguins a day.
- Interesting, according to the biography,
Frigid Women by Sue Richards and Victoria Richards.
- That's brilliant.
- So this was two of the women who went on it.
They were given six biscuits per person per day
for the expedition.
- Oh, really?
Maybe the person who I read,
they got their biscuits nicks before they gave them to her.
- Yeah, that comes to yet.
- Interesting, because that many,
it must have been loads of days they were traveling.
- It was, it was a relay,
so it meant that four women at a time were going,
and then they would be airlifted out,
and the next slot would be airlifted
into wherever they were.
- That's cool.
- Yeah.
- I was thinking you could wear the biscuits
as a kind of extra layer of warmth,
but maybe not. - Wear the biscuits?
- Well, it's like you could make it,
'cause they're quite flat, aren't they?
They're kind of a waistcoat that was lined with penguins.
- And actually, they're two biscuits,
and in between there's like a little bit of chocolate
or something, right?
- Well, insulation, I'm thinking.
- Yeah, exactly.
- It just sounds like you're one of the members on the trip
who misheard wearing the biscuits,
and you've emerged covered in penguins.
- What year was this, by the way?
- It was 1997, and so I've got a question for you.
Remembering that it's 1997, and they're British,
and thinking what was happening in 1997 at the time,
what do you think the newspapers nicknamed them?
- The hand-owners.
- Blair's frozen women.
- Go away from politics.
- Oh, the spice girls were big.
- Ah.
- And they were in the Arctic.
- Yeah, so.
- Cold, frozen spices?
- No, no, no.
- Wait, wait, say it again, say the ingredients.
- The spice girls were big.
- Yep.
- Girl power, girl power.
- They're going to the North Pole.
What nicknamed them?
- Girl polar, girl polar.
- Ziggazig Arctic.
- Jesus Christ.
- Girl polar.
- Wanna be the North Poles.
- No.
- To become, 16 become, no, two.
- Literally everyone listening has got this.
- Okay, okay, well done everyone.
- What do you get of the Arctic?
- Snow.
- As well as snow.
- Ice.
- Icey spice.
- Ice girls.
- The ice girls.
- Woohoo.
- Pew, pew, pew.
- Ice one down.
- Wow, straight away, straight in there.
- Sonic, Sonic Shriver.
- That's incredible.
- And one of the patrons of the ice girls
was Dawn French, the comedian.
- Yeah.
- And she told the press that she'd actually made the cut
to be on the expedition, but she decided to stay at home
and comfort all the husbands.
(laughing)
- That's so good, I'm sure you know that.
- One of the husbands dumped his wife while she was out there.
- Oh, while she was out there?
- Yeah.
- She's married to Dawn French now.
(laughing)
- What, was it Lenny Henry?
- It was, yeah.
No, this was Anne who had triplets
and she'd never had any experience before.
She's this amazing explorer now.
- And Daniels, yeah.
- And Daniels, never done anything before.
But she, when they finished the expedition,
all the other women had letters from home
and she didn't have one
and it was a sign that her husband had decided to go on.
- Oh my gosh.
- I was talking to you about Rosie Stancer.
- Is she one of the--
- There's one of the arctic,
one of the frigid women, as the book has it.
So she was on it.
So get this, she's,
I think she's quite posh, like her--
- Ash ice.
- Posh ice, brilliant.
- Brilliant.
- So she, like Anne Daniels,
she went on to do a lot of other expeditions.
She did one, the Snickers South Pole Solo
and the Mars North Pole Solo.
So these are all chocolate and biscuit sponsored.
But her grandfather was also a wannabe, thank you, explorer.
He was the fourth Earl of Granville, right?
And he wanted to be a polar explorer,
but he was thwarted.
Can you guess why?
It was something about his body.
- He had a weird sort of inner ear thing,
but whenever he wanted to go north, he always went south.
- That's a very creative one, better than what I've got.
Shall I tell you?
- Yeah, yeah.
- He was too tall.
- Did he?
- To go on an arctic--
- Could you hit your head on the top of the earth?
(laughing)
- 'Cause he wouldn't fit in the tent.
He was too tall for the tent.
- So his feet would be sticking out.
- Yeah, and that would obviously kill
all the men in the tent with the cold.
- Could he not do like the kind of, the embryo position?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- He was, he was, I mean, maybe this was an excuse
and it was his personality,
but he thought he was too tall to fit in the expedition tent.
- I thought he was five foot eight.
- No, no, too tall.
- Could you get a bigger tent?
- No!
- No, they don't exist.
My cob knobs bring something that doesn't exist, mate.
- I can't believe you just called
the feet all possessed in the embryo position.
- I know, I can't remember.
- The embryo position.
- Yeah.
- We've got a phrase for that.
(laughing)
- So I read a story which is that
and Daniel's mother triplets,
one of her things to keep her going
was to just say her kid's names over and over again.
How loud the triplets just repeat their names.
- Baby ice.
(laughing)
- But they had very near death experiences.
It was so hairy.
- Scary ice.
(laughing)
- Jesus.
- Okay, now we just cross off three.
We've got two more to get, yeah.
Done posh, we've done scary, and we've done baby.
So that leaves sporty and ginger.
- Sporty and ginger.
- Wait, oh they didn't take ginger nuts.
They took the penguins.
- Yeah.
- Damn it.
- They're all sporty.
- Okay.
- But yeah, the mother daughter,
the daughter rung her mom to say,
"Hey, I'm doing this Arctic expedition."
And the mom says, her daughter invited her,
the daughter says, she definitely didn't invite her mom,
but her mom decided to go.
But they both fell through the ice at one point.
So the Arctic moves.
They didn't quite realize how much when you're exploring,
it shifts and moves and the ice was creaking
and they're wearing skis and they both fell through the ice
and had to like swim in the skis.
- What?
- And she said she just remembered,
while also towing these supply wagons,
they all had a supply wagon they had to tow behind them.
- And they survived?
- Yeah, they somehow survived.
Incredibly.
But then it sounds like God was watching
'cause they ended up, two of them ended up
managing to climb out onto one side of the ice,
but their group was on the other.
So they were on either side of a river
and they just walked either side of this river
and they were getting more and more divergent
and they realized they were not gonna be able
to get back to each other.
And then suddenly the ice started moving
and the river closed up and the ice joined together.
- Wow.
- But it would have been very precarious
as in to walk across that is quite nerve wracking.
You would have had to tread.
You would have had to walk quite gingerly, spice.
Ice, ice.
James saw that coming from such a distance.
- What's that on the horizon?
Is it the North Pole?
No, is that these junk?
- Oh, it doesn't feel as good when you get there.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the crowd science expert
who designed and mapped out the cue
is called Professor Keith Still.
- Did you try and say keep?
It sounds like keep.
- So his name's Keith Still.
It looks like keep still.
Would you say it in a weird way?
- What's the cues do?
They moved, I think.
- But this one famously was a very long one
that required you to keep still.
- Actually we tried to keep walking for about five months.
- It did, but what were you doing when you weren't walking?
- I suppose you would keep still.
- That's right.
- They always say keep still.
- This is the cue for Elizabeth II.
- This is the passing of the queen.
There was this extraordinary cue
that lasted somewhere between five miles onwards.
And if you were in it,
if you were someone who came to London
to be part of it,
you could be waiting between nine and 24 hours
to eventually get to the front of the cue.
- Professor Keith Still is someone who helps.
- You could say his name normally,
now we've done the facts.
- We've explained the joke,
which always works.
Now let's just call him by his name.
- So he is from Burton and Kendall in Cumbria
and his job is a crowd scientist.
So for the last 30 years,
he's been doing this as a job
and he was the person who was in charge of creating
a line that was gonna be one that meant
that people felt safe
and that they had toilet stops along the way.
And he had to, and you know, medical assistants
and he had to devise it for something
that was twice the length.
- Where would it have come?
- I don't know.
I'm not sure if we were ever--
- Into the English Channel.
When you dropped it into the English Channel.
- Because they did stop it at one point,
they said we're at capacity.
So they didn't use the proposed route.
But then what they had was a pen
where a sort of secondary cue started
where you could then go from that second cue.
- Cue for the cue.
- Cue for the cue, exactly.
- God, yeah, I remember that happened.
I didn't go clubbing very much as a student.
- You're a stonisher now.
- No, no, no, it's true.
But there was, I think partly
because one of the first times I went--
- Your friends said you were too tall, didn't they?
- Yeah, apparently the club had a very low ceiling.
- They always do, yeah.
- Yeah, I would have hated it.
No, there was a club called The Bridge,
which was you'd go to.
And there was a, you'd cue up for ages
and I did cue up for ages.
And then you get into, I got in
and it turned out that the club I got into
was actually a cue for the actual club.
- No.
- Yeah, there was this whole,
and it had a bar and everything,
but it was basically the cue for The Bridge
as in you get given a ticket
and when they called out certain tickets
you could go into the actual club.
But I cue for about 40 minutes
to get into the cue club, which was rubbish.
- You must feel like an absolute chump.
I've been to The Bridge multiple times.
I don't remember the old double cue.
- Oh well, Anna probably walks up to the front
and says, "I'm Anna Szczenski."
- Yeah, they let me in the back hugely.
- And you're DJing, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- It is actually quite impressive the level of standing.
So I hadn't really thought about the fact
that you would be actually standing up
'cause you are constantly moving,
so you can't really sit down.
You were standing up for 24 hours.
And lots of people needed medical treatment.
291 people needed medical assistance
just on one day with 17 having to go to hospital.
- No man, it's a lot.
- Dehydrating and fainting, it is quite a lot.
- Of course they could have just not had a cue.
I mean, these days we do have systems
to stop people from having to cue
for miles and miles and miles.
- What, like booking in?
- Yeah, you could have just gone on the website,
said, "I'm gonna come between one o'clock and two o'clock."
And then the cue would never have gotten longer than an hour.
- Why is the fun in that?
What would the news have done for a week?
- That's the point, isn't it?
The point is that it's like this ceremonial thing
that they wanted to show how much,
how important it was and stuff.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Professor Still, Keith Still.
(laughing)
He got into queuing, first of all, several decades ago.
He was at a Freddie Mercury gig.
It was an AIDS awareness gig, and it was at Wembley,
and he and his friends, they were stuck in queue for hours,
and his friends were all quite annoyed.
And he was quite mathematically minded
and thought, "Oh, God, this is really interesting, actually."
And so he got into queuing, and he then is--
- Interestingly, queuing for the Queen.
- Yeah!
(gasping)
- And queuing for Queen.
- Oh my God!
We've blown the shit wide open.
His next thing he did, he went to Wembley Stadium,
and he got special permission
from the whoever's running the grounds,
and he would spend his weekends, for ages,
sitting above the players' tunnel, watching the crowds.
- Oh!
The match was going on, but he's not watching it.
- I think he wouldn't have been paying any attention
to the match, yeah.
You just see this guy sitting above the, yeah.
- He can't, he said of the queue,
the one, the recent queue,
he would not have been able to withstand
the length of time it required to get to the front.
He himself can no longer queue within--
- Even queue.
- The queues he decides.
- Yeah.
- Because he's old.
- He's got an arthritic hip.
- Yeah.
- That must require him to keep still
more often than he'd like.
- Absolutely.
- It's funny 'cause he's got a lovely website,
and he lists his hobbies on it.
- Does he?
I didn't see his website.
- Oh, yeah, it's a great website.
Yeah, he owns multiple motorbikes,
and he plays bowls.
- Does he?
- That was quite a rare combo, I think,
like having a Harley-Davidson
and playing crown green bowls.
- Is it?
- Well, one seems quite hard to call.
- No, you're right.
In Hell's Angels, they were famous for their bowls, Matt.
- Sorry, they're the only people at motorbike.
I forgot that as well.
- He's got a big Harley-Davidson.
He's got a--
- I associate both with real ale pubs.
- I bet he loves a real ale.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Some other animals, queue, I didn't know this.
- Okay.
- Yeah, so--
- Hunts, probably, I reckon.
- Hunts.
- Yeah, must do, yeah.
Fish, queue, there are fish which queue.
Yeah, there's small goby fish, right?
They have this thing where they have a mating queue.
Okay, this is really, this is a bit sexy, actually.
So only the top male and female mate, right?
And all the other females have to wait in a queue
before they can have sex.
I think with the top male, but maybe it's actually,
there's a queue, there's a sort of queue of males,
I don't know.
But basically, to organize the queue,
they do it by a pecking order of sexiness.
And sexiness is body mass for them.
So the biggest female is the sexiest one
and gets to have sex first, right?
And then the next biggest and so on.
And they can measure, you know how in school
you had to line up for fire drills and things
with a height order.
- Did you, okay?
- Well, we did, yeah.
- Well, you're not too tall for that.
- I was always left to burn, wasn't it?
(laughing)
But the fish can tell their body mass, right?
So if the difference is more than 5% of their body mass,
like between one female and the next,
they will queue neatly, right?
And because they know who's bigger they can see.
- Well, 'cause they've all got scales, haven't they?
(laughing)
- But if the difference is smaller than 5%
between two females in the queue,
the smaller one will try and queue jump.
And we'll sort of say, this is, there's enough,
there's a small enough difference, I think I could do it.
And then the bigger one will drive it out of the group.
We'll sort of force it out of the queue.
They'll have a fight.
- Well, I think during that fight they both lose weight.
(laughing)
- This is what they, okay.
- Okay, it's similar to that.
Smaller fish will sometimes adjust their own size.
They will lose weight to avoid presenting a challenge
to the fish that's bigger than them.
So they don't get in a fight and they don't queue jump.
They say, right, I'll just shrink my own body.
- How do they do that?
- I guess they don't eat for a while.
- Oh, in the lead up to the queue, not as in, okay.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Not on the spot.
They can't do like a special, like shit everything else.
- Famous queue, when McDonald's opened in Moscow.
- Oh yeah.
- In 1990, people queued for six hours to get a McDonald's.
They served 30,000 people on the first day.
And one Big Mac cost 3.75 rubles.
And a monthly wage was 150 rubles.
So that is the equivalent today
of a Big Mac costing 52 pounds, 78 pence.
- Wow. - Wow.
- Yeah, and people queued for six hours to get that.
- Jesus.
- 'Cause if someone tells you it's that expensive,
you think it must be worth it.
- Exactly, yeah.
There was 700 seats inside and 200 outside of this,
this McDonald's in Pushkin Sky Square.
And so 900 people, that's about the same as a Globe Theater.
It was the largest McDonald's in the world
until McDonald's left Russia.
- Wow. - Wow.
- But in a sense, isn't McDonald's really the,
you know, the theater sort of space for,
- Keep going, you're getting there.
- You know, it's like.
- I've got no idea where you're going.
- I'm wondering where you're going to believe in him.
- Believe in him.
- He can do this.
- You know, what do you see at McDonald's late night?
You see drama.
- Yeah.
- You know, you go to a McDonald's,
and all human life is there, kind of like a theater.
- My Beth is a Macbeth, I love her Macbeth too.
- So much there for you, Andy.
- That was what you were going for.
- I feel like I did a lot of work in the midfield there,
and I just slaughtered at home.
I'm happy with that. - The shearer of your jokes.
We did on QI once that the way we load airplanes
is totally wrong.
So you know when you get, you're waiting for a plane
and they say, if you're in rows 50 to 70,
please come forward now.
And they load the back first, which seems to make sense.
Well, actually, that's the least efficient way to do it.
It's way more efficient just to say,
everyone randomly get on the plane.
- Go, go, go, go, go, go, go, close the door in four minutes.
Go.
- You mean the easy jet system.
(laughing)
- Leave the kids go.
- Well, the great thing is if you have kids,
you get to the front of the queue.
- Yeah, although that is one of the best ways to do it
is to make sure the slow loaders,
i.e. people with kids do get on first.
- That's why they do it, I guess.
- But yeah, someone studied it mathematically
and realized that loading from the back
is actually slower than doing it randomly
'cause people bunch up and they block each other,
but you're not loading the empty spaces.
And actually, one really good way to do it
is do window seats, then aisle seats, then middle seats.
- Oh, cool.
- Vice versa.
- Yeah, that's mad.
- I mean, it is an insane way of doing it.
- That's insane.
- 'Cause you're with, let's say you're three people
going on a plane, a family.
- Yeah.
- All right, just dad first.
(laughing)
- Now the four-year-old on their own.
Families are like,
"I do think that is a cool way of doing it."
Because then, everyone's slotted,
everyone goes to the end of their row where the windows are
and no one's faffing about in the corridor bit of the plane.
- They're not doing it on purpose, Andy.
They just need to get their bags into the--
- I'm not sure the window seat knocks that out
because you still need to get your bag into the top bit.
- Well, I think the key thing to do
is everyone just carries the bag with them
and just holds it in their arms until the plane's taken off.
Then you can put it up in the racks, Vove.
- I don't think you're allowed to hold the bags
in your arms, especially if you're on an emergency exit seat.
- Yeah, that's true, yeah.
- Andy, I'm afraid, I'm afraid to sit in front of you.
Anyway.
- Oh, well, don't fly.
(laughing)
- I was reading a website called LineLogic
and they specialize in looking at public guidances
and line management solutions.
And so they go into businesses and try and sort out
how they can best manage their crowds and stuff.
And they say that the word faffing directly relates
to the idea of getting to the front of a queue
and then waiting for that person
who's just in front of you, who's paid
to sort of gather their things together.
The faffing that they do of sort of like
putting their wallet back and stuff.
- Well, like that's the first instance
of the word faffing.
- It's what this website is.
- What is this website?
Who are these people?
- It's LineLogic.
- What are their credentials?
- I'm back 'em, that's great.
- But they say that faffing time
takes roughly 3.17 seconds.
That's the average faff that you'll have, yeah.
- That's plausible.
'Cause you can pride yourself on being a non-faffer
once you're at the front of a queue.
Right now I've got my wallet, I'm ready,
I'm ready to put the card away,
I'm ready to grab the thing, go, you know.
Or you can faff.
- Yeah.
- I wonder which you are, Andy.
(laughing)
- I pride myself on my non-faffing.
- You really amazed us, really.
- Oh, you guys were expecting that, I see, yeah.
- It felt like a weighted survey
when you explained the difference between the two.
- Because they do say some people are absolutely awesome
and they always know exactly how to leave a check out.
- And you get these complete arseholes.
- Well, I panic am annoying the people behind me, basically.
- Yeah, yeah.
- The time when you finished your transaction
feels, you know, longer to you.
- I agree, I often rush off without my shopping.
(laughing)
- But I feel you're the type of personality
that would wanna make sure that was acknowledged.
And then so you would somehow waste the person
behind you's time going.
- Wait, why am I--
- No worries, get in out of your way there so quickly.
- Oh, just don't worry, just another day being a hero, yeah.
- I reckon you just go, "Beep!"
- Yeah.
- Three seconds, 24, very good.
- Enjoy that extra second I'll say you do.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found on our Twitter account.
So I'm gonna add Shriverland, Andy.
- @andrewhunterm.
- James. - @JamesHarken.
- And Anna.
- You can email podcast.qi.com.
- Yep, or go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThingIsAfish.com.
Check out all the previous episodes up there.
Also, check out Club Fish,
the exciting hidden behind the scenes membership club,
where we put extra content, extra fun shows,
and you'll also get ad-free episodes.
Check it out now and join today.
Otherwise, come back next week.
We're gonna be back with another episode
and we will see you then.
A good bye.
(upbeat music)
(gentle music)