(upbeat music)
- Hey, Club Fish members.
Welcome to this week's bonus bit of content.
We have got a compilation episode for you today.
But before we get into it,
I just wanna quickly remind some of you
who may have missed the news
that we are going to do a live show,
July 6th at the Crossed Wires Festival,
which is a festival that was co-created
by our good friend Alice Levine of My Dad Wrote a Porno.
They started last year, it was a massive success.
They're coming back this year
and we were really excited to be invited,
so we're gonna be doing a live recording.
Now, we didn't do Sheffield on our tour last year.
We really missed out on getting to that bit of the country.
So if you're in that area, come along.
We're doing a full live recording.
There'll be a few extra fun bits thrown in as well.
And if you wanna get tickets,
go to nosuchthingasafish.com.
You'll find all the links there.
And why not check out what other podcasts are on.
It is genuinely a great pod festival.
All right, well, let's get to the compilation.
Here are the best of the outtakes
that never made it to the main show.
Here we go.
(upbeat music)
- She had been told the gaitnesses.
She turned up to the unveiling of the Statue of Liberty.
- Oh yeah.
- Which I really liked.
She turned that she was not invited.
But she turned up on a cattle barge.
So she turned up on a barge with a megaphone,
shouting that it was a gigantic lie,
a travesty and a mockery
to make the representation of Liberty a woman
when actual women had so few rights at the time.
So that was her, that was her prototype.
- She's shackled though, isn't she?
- Oh, is she broken her shackles?
- I don't think she's shackled.
- Is she not?
- I should know, I've been up it.
And I don't know.
- Yeah, but that's what you're on the inside.
You can't see me outside, can you, from there?
- Oh, and I haven't been up it either.
Sorry, I was missing one.
What just happened?
I've been near it.
- Oh yeah, we all bit, we went together.
We were near it when we went to do yard.
- I've been closer than that.
- I love you.
- Yeah, yeah, but she's not, I don't think she,
I'm pretty sure she's not shackled.
- I don't think she's shackled.
- I thought one of her legs had a shackle on it,
but maybe I'm wrong.
- She's got slippers that I know that much.
- Slippers.
- I think they're more sandals.
- Yeah, slip-ons, like the open toad.
You could see her feet.
- Yeah.
- She's a woman in comfortable shoes.
- While you stayed outside,
you got one of those wiki feet things going on.
(laughing)
- So, true feminists should campaign
for the Statue of Liberty to be a man?
- Yeah, and yet, and yet my campaign has done nothing.
(laughing)
- I have one more caddy called Daft Willy Gunn.
He is an old school one in Scotland.
He was from the 19th century, early 19th century.
He always wore four coats, three or four pairs of trousers.
- It is cold in Scotland.
- It is cold.
He couldn't afford like a big coat or anything,
so he just wore like lots of small ones.
- To false economy.
(laughing)
Spend the money on a good coat.
- He would only eat milk and soft bread rolls his whole life.
And he would be in St Andrews in Scotland.
And then when the golf season finished,
he would walk off and no one knew where he went.
He just presumably walked home somewhere.
And then when the season started, he walked back again.
And that was it.
- He's a really great train.
- And then one day, they stumbled upon a grave,
which said he died in 1522.
(laughing)
- Well, one day in 1820, he walked north, never to return.
And to this day, nobody knows what happened to him.
- He's still out there.
- That's great.
- Do you know that fact?
Have I ever said it on this?
I don't think I have.
It was during the Winter War, I think,
between Russia and Finland.
And there was a guy who was captured.
And it turned out that he was trying to hide in the snow
by putting doilies on his head.
(laughing)
And he reckoned it worked for ages
because they were white doilies and no one could see him.
- But why had he taken so many doilies to a comfort zone?
I said, did he just think,
I know this is gonna work.
- I think he might have plundered them from houses.
- Really, of course, 'cause you would get doilies.
I mean, you don't get doilies anymore.
It's a really, really sad fact.
I mean, you get sort of weak doilies on trains these days,
but even then only on nice trains, they're not very good.
- Let's make me think if you're Jewish
and you have a Yamaha,
do you, if you were going certain places with the army,
would you match it to your environment?
You're going somewhere winter, where are white?
- Like a Kamoka.
(laughing)
- But in all these scenarios,
and in this one that you've described,
you didn't really have to bury yourself up to the eyebrows.
- I think it was more like his hair
would show up against the snow,
but you maybe had a white coat.
- Did he get caught when some Russians turned up
and thought, oh, a lovely comfy armchair.
I'll just put my left arm here.
- He doesn't put like double T on that.
(laughing)
- Wait a minute, what's a doily doing here?
You know what, I only half remembered the story, so.
- Wait, is a doily's for your head, isn't it?
Is it a coaster?
- No, a doily is the thing you put on a table
and you put, it's a bit bigger than a coaster,
but you put your tea pot on it.
- What am I thinking of here?
- I think-- - I'm lazy.
- An anti-McCassar. - An anti-McCassar.
- I'm so sorry. - I think I'm an anti-McCassar.
- An anti-McCassar is the thing you don't get anymore.
I've got doily's coming out of my arse.
(laughing)
- It's weird that they're the same material though,
so you obviously it was material-based confusion.
Anyway. - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I don't think a doily would work as an anti-McCassar
'cause it's got holes in it,
so all the MacCassar juice would get on the chair.
- You're right.
- What's a MacCassar?
- So MacCassar is like-- - Oh, God.
- We have gone off topic, haven't we?
- MacCassar is hair oil that in the 19th century,
you'd have lots of, you'd slather yourself.
- Yeah, yeah. - You'd make memory.
So that's why the anti--
- We don't need to combine this in the 19th century.
- Sorry, you popped your tiger balm in your hair.
Your anti-McCassar is when you go on the train
or at a chair, you sit in a comfy chair,
you need a layer of cloth between your head
and the fabric of the chair
so that the oil doesn't soak into the chair itself.
So that's an anti-McCassar.
James is right, a doily is the kind of coaster.
- Is that what they put on airplanes when you say--
- Yeah, anti-McCassar. - That's an anti-McCassar.
- Should we talk about L Frank Baum? - Yeah, sure.
- I've only got anti-McCassar material.
Do you know how scientists,
if they've got a healer monster to test its health levels,
how they test them?
- Okay, so I'm gonna give you a clue.
- Tremel is classic.
- Nice, that's good.
It's actually not to test how fit they are in a gym sense.
It's more like how many reserves do they have?
How long do they get to last in the desert?
- Tales of conference, 'cause that's where they keep their friends.
It's related to Archimedes.
- They put it in a bath and how much water comes out.
- It's exactly it.
They dunk their tail in a cup of water
and then you just measure how much comes out
and then you know how fat the tail is.
- It was a bit of an easy clue.
I'll have to, sorry about that.
But you know, I didn't want it to go on forever.
It was gonna be a fun game, was it?
- So they are venomous, right?
And I think only two people are recorded
to have ever died, one last year and one in 1930.
And, but the reason they're not very dangerous
is that they don't have a mechanism to inject their venom.
What they've got is they've got teeth with grooves in
and they have to bite into you
and then just chew up and down and up and down
and up and down and flood their mouth with venom
and chew the venom into you.
So it's quite hard for them to have a victim.
So they've got, it's very inefficient.
- I read it takes like 15 minutes.
- Well, the guy who died last year,
he'd been bitten for four minutes.
- Yeah, there was a suggestion
that you might have had an allergic reaction.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, it can be quite scary, I think.
There was a 1959 movie called The Giant Healer Monster,
which apparently features a Mexican bearded lizard
instead of a healer monster.
- You wouldn't get away with that these days.
- Beard, no, exactly.
You have to skin an actual healer monster, don't you?
But it was the first ever double feature film
where you paid for one film and you got two.
- Oh, right, that's great.
- And it was the first ever film
that was shot and produced in Dallas.
- Really? - Wow.
- But the double feature that you got
was the giant healer monster.
And the other one was called The Killer Shrews.
- Oh, wow.
Which one, headlines?
- I mean, it's gotta be a double headline now.
- It is a double headline.
Yeah, I watched the trailer for the Healer Monster movie.
It's wild, it's wonderful.
Actually, I lie, I watched it for the remake in 2012,
simply called Healer with an exclamation mark.
- Yeah, it's unbelievable these things get remade.
It was at the time acknowledged as an unbelievably bad film.
Who's remaking it?
- So what, and it's as bad?
- Did they not remake The Killer Shrews?
- Oh, I didn't check that, I should have.
- It's in development help, yeah, yeah.
- Just on strong materials.
This is the stiffest material.
It's all about the hardest.
There's also the strongest,
and that's like how much can you hang off something,
basically.
Strongest natural material, thought for ages and ages.
- Spider silk?
- Spider silk, spider silk.
- Wow.
- I can just imagine Anna as the host of University Challenge.
Someone gets an answer like, "Oh, wow, isn't it?
"The Chilling Milton, oh."
- Well, I've always been so skeptical about this,
and I know scientists have always claimed it,
but I've just passed so many spiders webs,
and often I pull at them and they break.
- You're unbelievably strong, Anna.
- I am, I am.
- You're like Godzilla.
- I'm Hercules, yes.
- Friend of the flies, Anna Tijinski.
- I liberate them.
I get it, it's pound for pound, they're very thin,
but it seems so unlikely.
And anyway, they've been supplanted recently,
and I believe this much more.
- They always say ants are really strong,
but I just stand on them and they're fucking squished.
- It's like I don't understand proportionality.
Anyway, it was recently found
that the strongest material is limpid teeth.
So you know limpids, like the common limpid
that you see on beaches?
Their teeth, they're actually on their tongue,
like we were talking about a bit earlier with mollusks.
They've got this tongue,
and they use it for the same purpose as parrotfish,
which is just a scrape algae off the rocks.
And apparently the comparison
is a single string of spaghetti holding,
the scientists said 3,500 kilogram bags of sugar,
which I didn't think was that good a comparison.
So I'm deciding to say it's like a string of spaghetti
holding a large walrus,
or my car with five adults inside, if you know my car.
- Wow.
- I know your car.
- Yeah, I know your car.
- They imagine that with five adults.
- It's not like the small,
it's a normal, small-ish size car, right?
- It's a sco de fab, yeah.
- Yeah.
- I'm not ashamed to say it.
(all laughing)
- That's amazing.
- Cut spaghetti?
- I think it doesn't matter
'cause it's about the width of it.
- It doesn't matter.
- You've been trying this Italian restaurant.
(all laughing)
- It's a nightmare.
- It's really hard to turn it around at four,
'cause of it.
(all laughing)
- It's al dente.
- I'll tell you one last,
this is an alternative actually to a Zempig,
'cause you know, others are available,
but much better, Vibes.
- Oh, okay.
- Which is an acronym that stands for
the Vibrating Ingestible Bioelectric Simulator.
- Okay.
- And it is a pill that you swallow
that wiggles and tickles and jiggles inside you
and makes you think you're full.
It's called, like, it's a battery,
a motor, a little vibrating motor,
and a membrane, and when you swallow it,
the membrane dissolves.
- You know what it sounds like to me, Andy?
- A magic bean, and I've got a lot to sell you.
(all laughing)
- And well, it's been tested in the last couple of years,
in 2023, it's been tested on pigs,
hasn't got to human trials yet,
but they ate 40% less.
- And pigs love to eat, like, they're overweight.
- They love to eat,
and it's been tested on young Yorkshire pigs, apparently.
(all laughing)
It basically means that your stomach
has been jiggled around and it thinks,
oh, there must be loads of food in here.
- Really?
- And then, yeah.
- Wow, but then what do I have to eat
to get rid of that thing?
- You just eat another one,
and then push it the first one through, that's fine.
- Right, okay, and then just eat a big one and a big one.
- Wow, what a weird poo that will feel like,
'cause it's vibrating out your butt.
(all laughing)
- Here's an interesting thing,
avalanches are not nearly as deadly as they used to be,
and more than half of people who are stuck
in avalanches survive these days.
- Wow.
- Yeah, and they've got loads of new survival devices
that you can have that if you're skiing off-piste,
you might have them with you.
- One of them, which is really cool,
is a thing called the avalanche airbag system,
and what you do is when you're skiing
and you see an avalanche coming,
you go, oh, shit, and you pull a toggle,
and it just puts an airbag around you
like you're in a car, like you're in a sob,
but it makes you massive.
It puts this huge airbag around you,
and can you guess how it works?
This is really amazing.
- Is it something to do with pressure up in the mountains?
Well, how it's inflating?
- So you know when you get muesli, for instance,
you get a big box of muesli,
and at the top are all like the big nuts and stuff,
but at the bottom are all the little grainy bits
that you don't really want to eat.
- Yeah, this effect has got a name, this effect.
- Yeah, it's called like the Brazil nut effect
or something like that.
Well, this makes you really big,
and so when the avalanche is coming down,
like a Brazil nut, you float to the top
and all the small bits of snow go to the bottom.
- Wow.
- Isn't that amazing?
It's called the principle of inverse segregation.
- Wow.
- And so it keeps you near the top,
and it makes you easier to find.
- And while you're waiting,
you've got all that muesli to get you to buy.
(laughing)
- Have many people done that on purpose?
'Cause I'd imagine it would be tempting.
- It's been used in Europe for over 10 years.
- No, sorry, as in for fun.
- Oh, for fun?
- 'Cause you would have thought
that would be unbelievably good fun.
- It feels like avalanche chasers
are gonna be a thing, right?
Like tornado hunters.
- Yeah, like surfing on the top of an avalanche
in your big bubble, how great would that be?
- I'm gonna say don't try it at home anyway.
- You can't.
(laughing)
- Do you know the most famous frostbite sufferer
of all time?
- Randall Fiennes.
- Yeah, I would have said him.
- More famous, even more famous than Randall Fiennes.
- Brian Blessed.
- Think more famous.
- Barack Obama.
- More famous.
- David Asenborough.
- God.
- Albert Einstein.
- Joey Essex.
- God.
- God?
- There was a study in 2004
by a couple of neo-intelligence
who decreed that the baby--
- Sorry, Joey Essex came at the end.
(laughing)
- Just about to think
of the most famous person I could think of.
- The study found that the baby Jesus
almost certainly had hypothermia as a baby.
- Oh, and then by extension.
- No?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Not God, God.
- Well, now he is one of the three gods
that's a kid that makes a god.
- Well, it depends which one you find.
- Basically, they looked at a load of,
they looked at a load of old masters paintings
from the National Gallery,
which loads of them are feature of--
- Oh, and of course they were painted life, weren't they?
(laughing)
There was like, there was an ox and an ass
and three shepherds and a load of fucking painters
in the car, wasn't there?
- But you never see them.
It's like a press gallery, you know.
So yeah, 90% of these paintings depicted Jesus
as either naked or scantily clad.
And given that the temperature in Bethlehem
in late December is about seven Celsius,
like, and 60% of the paintings, he's on the floor.
You think, why have you put the baby on the floor?
Don't put the baby on the floor.
- He wasn't born on Christmas Day though.
I know that according to the rules he was,
but I think we don't think he was.
- No, okay, but either way, it's clearly a risk.
And they said that the,
can you guess the explanation they provided?
I really like this as to why it might have been all right.
'Cause he was God.
- Why he survived it.
- Maybe the halo warmed him up.
- They said maybe the halo suggested a neutral thermal zone.
- Yes, very.
- Like ready-brek makes you glow in the dark.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
- Sorry.
- Oh, you're too young to remember those adverts
from the 1980s.
Like a kid would eat the ready-brek
and then they would go to school
and they would just have a glow around them all day.
- It was a few, it sort of looks a bit nuclear,
doesn't it?
- It does now you think about it, yeah.
- And it was the 80s, it was a time of anxiety.
- Surprised it worked.
- That's why porridge is now so much more popular
than ready-brek.
- Yeah.
- You're out and it's cold and it's really cold
and you're in big trouble.
You're riding your horse along, yeah.
- Oh, okay.
I was on the night out in Leeds in my head
and now I'm, well, you can still be on the night out in Leeds.
- These are the bar with Joey Essex.
Buying beers for everyone.
- I just remember that's the coldest I've ever been
after a night out in Leeds.
So that's where I am.
- Okay, go on.
- But you're on your horse.
- I'm on my horse.
- You're on your way home, back to the premier Inn.
- Premier Inn, yeah.
- There's no room at the premier Inn.
(laughing)
Outside there's a baby who's been put on the floor,
which is a very bad idea.
- Okay.
- Your horse dies under you.
- Oh, your horse died.
- On your way back to the premier Inn.
- Probably punched by a Leeds United fan.
Over my head.
It's really cold.
It's a long way to go to the premier Inn.
- Yeah.
- What do you do?
- Well, I would have walked.
- Oh, you do the Leen under camp here thing.
- You can't open your horse and sleep inside.
- Exactly.
- Oh, I see.
- Oh.
- Wait, is that a klaxon?
- It's not really.
It has been done once at least that we know of
by a missionary in America who in 1860,
he did lose a leg.
He had to have leg amputated.
- Okay.
- But he did survive.
But I was reading, do you remember the bit in Star Wars
where Luke Skywalker has to cut open his big fluffy,
no, his sort of pack animal.
- That's right.
- And then he gets shoved in it.
- Okay.
- But I read an article saying it wouldn't work.
You would really don't have long
even if you cut open your horse and get it.
- Hang on, are you saying it would work?
So it's how one person's done it and achieved it,
but broadly--
- You couldn't do it overnight.
- It must depend how cold it is.
'Cause if it's like, let's say it's 10 degrees,
it's a bit nippy.
(all laughing)
Probably you can cut open your horse
and it'll just give you enough wax to keep--
- That would be fine.
- That headline then becomes, was this necessary?
(all laughing)
- There's a taboo against pointing at rainbows
from around the world.
Lots of different cultures have this.
The Mizo of Myanmar, they think that if you point
at a rainbow, you have to immediately point
at a hen's basket to stop having some bad luck.
In Malayang region of Papua New Guinea,
if a child accidentally points at a rainbow,
they must go and find an old man
(all laughing)
and pull his finger.
- Accidently, if you accidentally point at a rainbow,
it just feels so unlikely that you'll--
(all laughing)
- It does, and there's a group in Ecuador
that if you point at a rainbow, your shoulder will ache.
And in the Ivory Coast, there's a group where
if you're twins and one of you points at a rainbow,
then you must apply crushed mushrooms to your face.
- Oh, you wouldn't like that?
- No, and the idea is basically rainbows,
like to us, they're like happy unicorns, rainbows and stuff,
but to a lot of people, they're otherworldly weird things
and pointing is always bad, really.
You shouldn't point at people or things.
- Right. - Yeah.
- If you do point at a rainbow for long enough,
you will get a sore shoulder.
- That's true, they're quite ephemeral things, though.
- I think that you're right, they almost never last long enough
that you'd get a sore shoulder by pointing.
- Does the culture that has pulling an old man's finger
have the same thing that we have when you pull it?
- I did look and I don't (all laughing)
I mean, we shouldn't laugh at these things,
but I mean, 'cause it's people and like it's old, you know.
- It's actually, yeah, it's incredibly serious.
- It's serious, yeah.
- But it is, that is objectively funny.
- It is.
You know, one person who can withstand
these extraordinary cold temperatures
and he's become quite famous, Wim Hof,
I don't know if anyone's read that book.
- Yeah, the method.
- The method, Wim Hof method.
So he climbed to an altitude of 7,200 meters
on Mount Everest wearing nothing but shorts and shoes.
At one point he had to change to some boots,
but that was it that he put on.
He also completed a marathon above the Arctic Circle
in Finland at close to minus 20,
dressed in nothing but shorts as well.
Is it a pretty, what, tops off?
- Yeah, yeah, and he's sort of is able
to withstand these things, hence this people doing it.
It's been, it's had a lot of controversy about it
in recent times, 'cause a lot of people have either died
or become ill off the back of it, but he can do it.
He demonstrably can do it.
But according to his biographer,
something he didn't get right was he was swimming
in a fountain in Amsterdam and he decided on a Wim,
oh, on a Wim, to give himself an, brilliant,
to give himself an enema on the nozzle of the jet
in the fountain.
- What?
- Something I believe that he might have done before,
but what he didn't know was that earlier that day
they turned the power up on the spout itself.
And as he sat on the nozzle, it cut through his colon
and his testines, they say like a water knife,
it kind of just went into him.
Yeah, and he had to be rushed to hospital
by his son, Michael.
- Why was his son there?
- Well, they're hanging out.
He goes, I'm gonna quick swim in the fountain.
- I'm just gonna say, I think that there would be a clue
that they'd upped the pressure by the fact
that the water's going miles in the air.
- Yeah.
- But it sounds to me like they upped the pressure.
The moment it came up was as his bum was in there already.
- Was it the vertical nozzle?
- Yes.
- Was he, was he blasted into the air
and sat in a cartoon style at the top of the fountain
for a while.
- I haven't imagined him and all his mates going
to Las Vegas and sitting at the Bellagio
as all their fountains go up.
- What you can't see in that famous scene
at the end of "Ocean's Eleven"
where they're all watching the Bellagio fountains
is Wim Hof at the top of them.
(laughing)
- But apparently when he got there,
he's so hard this guy.
He could go up Mount Everest in no top, in no shoes.
In shorts, they didn't know how serious the injury was
because he was like, "Ah, tis butter, internal scratch."
- He now has a semi-colon.
(laughing)
- So it took ages until he fainted with pain.
And then after they did all the stuff on him,
he didn't have any antibiotics during recovery
because he's such a hard man.
- Oh yeah.
- It's not hard to disregard antibiotic
like germ theory is real, sorry.
I've gone right off him now.
I was actually with him even in the fountain store.
I think, okay, he's a crazy guy.
- He's trying to suppress antibiotic resistance.
That's a good thing.
- He doesn't need antibiotics.
People should never take them
unless they absolutely need them.
- I reckon Vim Hof takes like just four of them
and then doesn't take the last three.
(laughing)
He sounds like that kind of guy to me.
Is he still alive?
- He is.
- Yeah.
- Still good.
- In that case, I don't think he does that.
(laughing)
- It wasn't everywhere.
They thought water was good for you.
So in America, I was reading the 18th century,
people thought cold water,
if you drank cold water, you would die.
And there was a French guy visiting Philadelphia
who said that several people die each year
drinking the cold pumped water.
And so everyone's told to leave it out to warm.
And there are printed hand bills distributed everywhere
and posters put up next to all water pumps saying,
do not drink this straight away.
Do not drink this cold.
You must leave this to warm up.
But he said, all these teachings are ignored.
And so of course, there is death all over the place.
- Again, water.
- It's just not having the experiment time
to work it out properly.
- You just think like,
surely one or two people drank it and didn't die.
- He thinks.
- And people thought, what happened there?
- No one believed him.
- But maybe you got lucky,
you got a random bit of warm water in there.
'Cause I've got a tap at home,
which is so cold that I want to die when I drink from it.
It's really bad.
- Right.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, okay.
(laughing)
- Thank you.
Somewhere there's a fan listening to our show
who's piecing all these very micro bits
of detail.
They've got like a big board.
Tap produces cold water.
Let's sit that next.
- That's taps at home.
(laughing)
- For what?
The most boring obituary ever written.
- Just slowly piecing together who mysterious Murray is.
- That's podcasting.
It's nice to get to know people, isn't it?
As you listen to them.
- Oh yeah.
- We know two things about you now.
You've got very cold taps
and you piss in the shower.
That's it.
(laughing)
- Did you know that the inventor of the Brooklyn Bridge?
I'm gonna say inventor, I mean engineer.
- Yeah.
- Like to wrap himself in a damp cold sheet.
His name was John Roebling.
- Why did you do the sheet thing?
- No further data.
- Cool.
- Cool himself down.
- Probably.
- Like people just did used to think way
for you're too hot or too cold
and that was a massive problem.
And I guess it is if you've got hypothermia
or a massive fever it is.
But people thought like, you know,
if you were sick, you could make yourself colder
or hotter and that would cure you.
- Yeah.
- They didn't have cow pole.
(laughing)
- I was looking at another thing
that was happening around the same time in London
and this was a man called Banks
who had a horse called Morocco
and it had shoes of silver
and it could dance to music, count and answer questions
and do all sorts of tricks.
And it once apparently climbed up St. Paul's Cathedral.
It was really, really popular.
Everyone in London loved this horse
and everyone whenever it was on display
would go and see it.
And then it went to Italy
and he and the horse and the master
were both burned on charges of sorcery.
- Oh, that's a bad tool.
(laughing)
- It's a risky run with magic tricks in those days, isn't it?
Either you entertain people
or you're a witch who always ends in your fox.
- Darren Brown's birth to death in New Zealand.
- One more thing about Formula One
is if you play the sound of a Formula One race
to a Formula One driver and they're blindfolded,
they can tell where the track is.
- What is in what corners?
They can draw you a track.
- Well, they'll know because they know the track so well.
So if they like, if it goes,
(imitates sound)
and then it goes a bit quieter for a bit
and then it goes louder and then quieter and louder
and then quieter, they'll go, that's Monza.
- And that's without the commentary, right?
(laughing)
- Okay.
- That's nice.
I love that there's a great thing you can watch online
where Broadway dancers will have to stand in front
of the stage and behind them,
someone is doing one of the dance routines
and they have to join the dance routine
only by the sound of the steps.
It's incredible and they get it right so much.
They're hearing the patterns and then they leap into it
and they match it.
- Do you reckon, Dan, you could watch the three of us
doing a podcast.
You'll just see in our mouths moving,
but you can't hear what we're saying.
Do you reckon you could sort of join in and jump in
at the right time and say the most sensible things?
- Yeah, yeah, I'd be like,
James is right, golf is interesting actually.
- Yeah.
- Don never jumps in anyway saying
the most sensible things.
It's sort of irrelevant whether you can hear us or not.
- This is how I run my whole game on this show.
- I'm not convinced he's heard anything we've said
for the last 10 years.
- Do you know the saltiest big body of water in the world?
- Dead Sea.
- It's not, in fact, it's this really cool thing.
So there are a couple of Antarctica
that are the saltiest in the world,
but you can't swim in them or anything obviously
'cause they're in Antarctica.
But there is a place called Lake Retba in Senegal,
which is 40% saltiness compared to Dead Sea is 34%.
- And you know how you sink in the Dead Sea, Anna?
We've said this before.
- We have, I know.
- The only passage, you reckon you might float in this
40% out?
- I've put my tickets.
I'm going to Senegal next week.
You have to find someone else.
I must find out.
- Wait, so what do you say 40% saltiness?
Is it 40% salt?
- Yeah, 40% concentration.
- Wow.
- And it's also pink.
- Oh.
- Cool, right?
It's double whammy.
And you can swim in it and people go and bathe in it.
- Cool.
- And it's got a special algae that makes it sort of orangey.
It's one of those ones that says it's pink
and all the photos look bright pink.
And then you read the one blogger who says,
I went there and everyone's enhanced their photos
enormously, but still you can float in it, you know?
- That's cool.
- You can walk around in it.
- Very cool.
- That's nice.
- Yeah.
- I've been to one in, where was it?
Maybe it was in America where like animals go in there
and then they turn to salt.
- Were they petrify or were they?
- But actually like it turns out it's a bit of a myth.
Like they die through natural causes
and then slowly the salt sort of grows on their body.
But people say, oh, this, you know,
pelican drank a little bit of water and they turned to salt.
That doesn't happen.
- So they still believe this stuff in America?
- It's what we've said.
- I'm not sure anyone really believes it, but yeah.
- They believe a little mad stuff in America and in Britain.
I mean, that wouldn't be the craziest thing, would it?
- No.
- They believe today.
- In fact, when I went there, there was like an overlooking
road and you could put like your business cards there
for some reason, people were doing it.
And I had some fish ones, so I put them there.
So we have made our mark.
- Right, we haven't heard from them yet.
(laughing)
- They've all turned to salt.
- Saltified.
- The wife of Lot is there.
(laughing)
- Do you know Henry VIII executed all the horses
that were too short?
- Is that like a eugenics thing?
- Basically, yeah.
He decided that the horse stock was getting a bit shit.
- That's early for eugenics as well, isn't it?
- He's a pioneer.
- He is a pioneer in his day and I respect it.
(laughing)
- Finally a tick for the horrific reputation
of Henry VIII.
- This is the actual Parliamentary Act,
the Breed of Horses Act, 1535.
No stallion under 15 hands was allowed to exist anymore
and no mare under 13 hands, which is quite, you know,
it's quite big.
- So it's like an active thing, not just they die out,
just that you have to actively off your horse.
- There were culls every year.
- It's terrible when you're on the part land.
You're too short.
- I would try and get around it.
- Yeah, you would put three horses in a trench cull.
(laughing)
- I would paint the horse with,
is it vertical stripes or horizontal stripes?
- To make them a little taller?
- Yeah, I wish I would carry around,
I would make the horse carry around a smaller horse,
would I?
- Yeah.
- Or then you have to kill off that horse.
- I would hire someone with small hands
so the horse cleared the bar.
- Yes.
- That worked?
- Maybe that's why horseshoes were invented
was little platform shoes for horses to save them.
- They used to look like the Spice Girls, didn't they?
- Yes.
- Mars was quite important in early Rome, wasn't he?
And he was associated with woodpeckers,
which meant that there was a law
against eating woodpeckers in ancient Rome.
- Yeah.
- It doesn't feel like a law that would impact
many people's lives too drastically.
- Oh, they're so delicious.
(laughing)
- For all we know, they're incredibly yummy.
- Yeah, yeah.
I doubt it.
They've got those strong skulls to withstand all the pecking.
- They scramble themselves.
(laughing)
- I think woodpecker tongs was a thing
for a while, people would eat woodpecker tongs.
They're very long, aren't they?
- They've got tongs so long
that they wrap around their brains.
- Yeah, yes.
- It was to protect their brain in part.
- Sorry.
- I think it is.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I thought you meant woodpecker tongs
like as a piece of cutlery
with which you ate woodpeckers,
specifically like you have, you know.
(laughing)
- No, woodpecker fork.
- Mrs. Jones is coming round
and get the woodpecker tongs.
Oh, no, we, oh, what a faux pas.
(laughing)
- Just annoying, unannoying car noises.
The car horn, quite annoying now,
used to be so much worse.
So the word klaxon in fact comes from,
was invented for cars.
- Jeremy klaxon, yes.
(laughing)
- Yes.
- He invented it.
- Oh, why hasn't he changed his name?
He should.
So this was sort of pre-war, pre-Second World War.
Cars had horns that were like klaxons.
So, you know, the klaxon noise is like a woo.
- A woo-ga.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it was that.
But you, was I saying to you guys last week
that my grandma always honked the horn
when she turned, when she took corners?
Well, that used to be the rule.
You'd be fined if you didn't,
because there was no other way of knowing
when car engines weren't as big.
And so they were constantly,
whenever anyone turned a corner,
when everyone was coming up to a junction,
whenever you were about to park,
you beeped your, woo-ga.
- That is annoying.
- And people hated it.
- It's kind of like the legacy
of the man with the red flag.
- Yes.
- A little bit.
- But less annoying, the man with the red flag.
I don't think I'd mind that as much.
It's a bit like, beep, beep, vehicle reversing.
- So, do you know who the godfather of backing up is?
- Like the godfather of soul.
- Yeah, just like that.
- Do you mean the sound or literally backing up a car?
- The sound that's made when you back up a car,
the beeping, when you're reversing.
- So, who's the godfather of creating that sound?
I don't get what you're asking.
- It's a man called Ed Peterson.
- Okay.
- Oh, I was just about to say him.
- So, he was the pioneer in the West,
and he may have been beaten to it
by Matthew Saburo Yamaguchi in 1953.
But Peterson noticed, he was working at a dam,
a construction project, huge construction project.
And he noticed, gosh, people keep being killed or injured
when really heavy vehicles reverse into them.
If only there was some, and he said the flag men
were just not doing their jobs.
And that was the system.
Weirdly, the, you know, like waving flags around
saying, look out, someone's reversing.
That system wasn't working.
- I can't believe if you're holding a flag to wave
and a person about to get run over,
why aren't you also going,
there's a car, it's about to run you over,
there's a car, quick, get out of the way.
- I don't know.
Maybe they're standing at a distance.
- Probably a union thing.
- Yeah, a union thing.
- We won't pay them extra for that.
- Anyway, just wanted to give him his credit.
Ed Peterson, all right.
- Do you know who has the best car horns?
- Ooh.
- What country?
- Oh, is there a country where it's, you know,
it leaps south like in "Jukes of Huzzard"?
Ha da da da da da da da da da da da da da da da da da
- Ah, so you're interpreting it differently to how I mean.
- The best.
- So, by best, it's long lasting, louder.
This is in India.
- Yeah, it is in India, and the reason is that
because the culture of driving there
has a much more emphasis on the beeping when you're in,
and so they need cars, they actually make,
like Audi make stronger, better horns
so that they don't run them down
with the amount that they're using them.
- That is, they do use it properly in India.
They use it to tell you, "I'm about to drive into you."
- You're in danger, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Well, that implies that incredibly bad drivers,
if they're always using it properly,
but they're always using it.
- I think it's so busy traffic-wise.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And the way to cross the road is just to get cracking.
- It's like British Kettles, they're long lasting.
This is personal anecdote, but--
- British Kettles.
- British Kettles. - Best in the world.
- Yeah, I was just confused by the analogy.
- Well, I'm just remembering
because Dan's wife has bought like 20 Kettles.
- Yeah, she keeps buying European ones
because they look nice and they keep dying
'cause they can't keep up with the British tea consuming.
- Out of the kilowatts.
- Yeah. - It's an anecdote,
it's just gone flooding back.
(all laughing)
- Did you come across the car that Cadillac invented
which had a working toilet in it?
- Oh.
- Sorry, not Cadillac invented.
One random bloke modified so that he could,
this was a guy called Louis Matta
and he wanted to drive 10,000 kilometers without stopping.
LA to New York and back.
- Right, so he must have put the toilet on the driving seat.
- He put the toilet,
well, there were a couple of them in the car.
- How long does it take to drive that distance?
- It must be like 10 days.
- That would be 1,000 kilometers a day,
maybe a bit longer than that, I think that's quite a bit.
- Yeah.
- He will have to stop at some stage to sleep, right?
- Well, no, but there were a couple of them in the car.
So they would shift into the driving seat.
This was in 1952, for God knows why he wanted to do this.
But he'd been in the Navy, he was an engineer
and it had a toilet, it had a shower,
it had a TV, a fridge and a sink
and they were escorted when they were in a town
by the local police who would help them
through the traffic lights.
So they could literally keep moving for this time.
- It's just like a caravan really.
- It's just like a caravan, except I love this.
What's another flaw in this plan?
- We have to let out what you're carrying.
- Now I assume he's got a shed load of petrol
that's filling up the car.
- He can refuel on the go, that's cool.
And what if the worst happens, you burst a tire,
they had a system to change a tire
while the car was driving.
- Wow, it's so cool, as Jack would lift up one tire
and this tiny little supermarket trolley wheel
would take that corner of the car
and then his friends would like lean over the side
and change the tire and then change it back
and then you just pop it back up.
- You would be impossible to steer
if it's got a supermarket trolley wheel on it.
(all laughing)
- The laziest all of this bit of observational comedy
that's ever been made.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our outtakes.
We hope you enjoyed that.
You got any comments, you got any questions,
you got any extra facts,
why not send them to podcast@qi.com?
And if they are seen by Andy,
they might make their way onto an upcoming
Drop Us a Line episode.
We love getting your emails,
so please do send them in.
Do remember, the CrossWire's Festival,
6th of July in Sheffield.
Get your tickets at our website,
no such thing as a fish.com.
Otherwise come back in a couple of weeks,
we'll have another bonus episode ready
for you club fishers.
Until then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)