(upbeat music)
Hey, Club Fish members, how you doing?
It's Dan here.
Hope you're well.
Welcome to your bonus bit of content.
This is a compilation episode that we have for you today,
all the best bits that didn't make it into the main episode,
largely 'cause they just didn't fit the narrative.
So, hope you enjoy it.
But before we get to it, just a quick reminder,
if you happen to be in Sheffield,
we're gonna be there doing fish live
at the Crossed Wires Festival.
Alice Levine put together this awesome podcast festival.
There's gonna be multiple shows down there.
So, if you're around on the 6th of July,
we're gonna be there from 2 p.m. recording a live show.
Do come along, it's gonna be lots of fun.
Tickets are available at crossedwires.live,
or you can go to knowsuchthingasafish.com
and just find all the relevant links there.
Okay, that's it.
Let's get to the main episode now.
Here we go.
The best of the bits that didn't make it on with the show.
(upbeat music)
- Hi, everybody, Andy here.
Welcome to an audience fact special episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish.
You have all been sending your facts to podcast@qi.com.
Is that the address?
- That's the address.
That's what I say every week, so I hope so.
- Well, they've been getting through,
and they've been coming in thick and fast.
And we've creamed off the ones on the top,
and we're gonna be reading them out
and sharing them back with you now.
- It's harder than it looks, isn't it, Andy?
- It's a very difficult job.
Damn, this is amazing.
(laughing)
- I'm happy to be here.
Do you wanna mention who else is here?
(laughing)
- Where are we as well?
And how often does this podcast go out?
- God.
- Can I tell you one last thing about the boss for us?
- Yeah.
- Constantinople and how it was defended.
There's one weakness in a naval sense.
There's a waterway which is calm and navigable.
And basically, if you could sail your ships in there.
- Oh, like a harbour.
- Yeah, you could invade,
and it would be incredibly easy to invade.
So how did Constantinople, as it was then,
solve this problem?
- Cannons.
- Great idea.
Arguably better than what they came up with.
(laughing)
- Crocodiles.
- Crocodiles, good call.
- That's good.
- So I was going to tell you about the chain of the Golden Horn.
- Okay.
- They had a massive chain just across the water.
- Yeah.
- Like a rope barrier outside a nightclub.
- I thought didn't this work though?
- Actually, I'm being unfair.
It worked better than you'd think it would.
It's about half a mile long.
- Okay.
- Just this huge chain across the water,
and then they can lower it
if someone approaches who's friendly.
And then what?
Joink it up again.
- They were quite common, those things, I think.
- Okay.
- Yeah, I've heard of them before.
I heard of one.
This is in like British history,
but there was one of them somewhere
where someone was in a boat
and they went in the boat towards this chain
and they're going to hit it.
And what happened was everyone on the boat
ran to the back of the boat,
so it lifted the front of it.
So they went over it
and then everyone ran to the front.
- Surely not.
That was like a heralded to story if I ever heard one.
- I think it is a story,
like I remember where it's from.
- It's good.
- That's great.
- There was a report in Scientific American in 1858
about a healthy person called Mr. Gru,
but he was born without a sternum or a breastbone.
And so you could see completely clearly his heart
and part of his lungs.
So it was just a thin layer of skin around it.
And so he'd be exhibited in theaters around Europe
for a few years and in lecture halls
because it really helped doctors know
about the structure of the heart and how it beat
'cause he'd literally stand at the front of a lecture hall
and you'd be sitting at the back
and you could see his heart boom-bombing
and bouncing out of his chest.
- 'Cause he didn't grew properly.
He was just--
- Wow, good stuff.
Yeah.
- It wasn't Gru the name of the guy from Despicable Me.
- Yeah, yes.
- And so did he have this?
And then he thought he was so exceptional
that he decided to take over the world with his minions.
- And that's what that's based on.
- Yes.
- There we go.
- What kind of full circle?
- Did he have ribs?
And if so, where did they meet?
- I think maybe the ribs didn't meet.
No breastbone.
- It feels like they wouldn't meet.
- Yeah.
- They just sort of stop.
- Big hole.
- It just floats.
That feels very painful.
- There are muscles between your ribs.
So it would stay in place.
- Right.
- It wouldn't be good to like,
my daughter likes to jump on my chest.
That wouldn't be great.
- Oh.
- You have to just limit that.
- Yeah.
- And if he coughed or sneezed,
then his lung really bounced out of his chest.
You really see it as long.
- And if he really fancied someone like Jessica Rabbit,
walking past his heart really pumped out of his chest.
- There was actually a really sad study
about which bits of their lives people would skip.
Like if they could say skip ahead five minutes
for about 10 minutes.
I've found that people would skip a huge proportion of it.
Obviously, 'cause most of your life is just drudgery.
Like if we could skip to the end of this guys,
we wouldn't, wouldn't we?
- Well, people listening could just fast forward to the answer.
- If only we could.
- Accessory breasts.
That's another thing.
- Accessory.
- Okay.
So you know the classic total recall three boobed lady,
three boobs is a thing.
But like Andy's saying,
you might not know where to find it.
So it's quite possible that you have three lactating breasts.
But in the image that I saw,
which to be fair was a drawing,
a lady was breastfeeding her child
and then thigh feeding her other child
because the breast had criss.
- Was this something real?
- Yeah.
- This isn't from one of your manga.
(all laughing)
- That's collection of erotic manga
is unparalleled in this hemisphere.
- Saint Jerome was a famous translator.
- Really?
- Not through like audio.
He would translate the Bible into the Vulgate.
And what he did was he took the sort of Hebrew Bible
and then he put it into Latin,
but he'd put it into a way that everyone could understand.
So he put, he changed some of the words
that maybe he shouldn't have done.
So there was a, in fact, a Greek word, which was Maschia,
which meant like Messiah.
And he changed it to Christos,
meaning anointed.
But actually the more reasonable way of translating that
would be unctus, meaning anointed.
And that is why we call Jesus Christ, Jesus Christ,
because of that translation.
- Oh, wow.
So we should call him unctus.
- Jesus unct.
Yeah.
Unctiano Ronaldo.
- What's that doing?
- It should be like,
anyone called Christian or anything like that
should be unctiano, really.
- That's so funny.
- He is quite an oily man.
- Well, exactly.
- But isn't it amazing like one little bit of translation
can change so much in history?
- That's where we get Christopher from as well, isn't it?
- Yeah, Christian and everything.
- No, unctophosan, for example.
(both laughing)
- Unctophosan.
- The only thing I know about Saint Jerome
is that he apparently told,
I think this is in the realms of maybe true,
maybe not be true.
He told nuns not to eat beans
because he thought the flatulence that they would produce
is so close to their front, bottom,
that they might induce orgasms accidentally
off the tickling sensation of the fart.
So he said, "Tony beans, nuns."
And he went back to translating the Bible.
(both laughing)
- There's a story told by John Sessions on QI
in one of the early series that you guys might remember
which I always love.
And I actually don't know,
I think his source would have been,
he's been told by someone else
who was told by Gandhi himself, probably.
That's what I'm assuming.
But basically in the scene,
so there are 300,000 extras, as you say,
and Richard Attenborough's the director.
And the person who's organizing all the extras
in the whole scene is this other guy called David Tomlin
who's overseeing this funeral scene.
So Gandhi's just died and Attenborough says to Tomlin,
"You've got to tell these 300,000 extras
how they're gonna behave."
And Gandhi's just died, the hero,
like the ultimate icon of their country.
This is the worst news they've ever heard.
They're devastated, their lives have fallen apart
before their very eyes.
Can you possibly convey to them how they have to act?
So David Tomlin just turned around to this crowd
and said, "Right, listen up, Gandhi's dead
and you're all fucking sad."
(both laughing)
- Wow.
- Yeah, it works.
- That's very good.
- So there are three bridges now,
I think spanning the Bosphorus
and built at various different times.
But the 1973 one, the first one was the Game Changer.
In 1960s, you had to wait two and a half hours to cross,
I think by car, but it was just so clogged.
And then for vans and lorries,
it was days you had to wait to cross by boat
before the bridges happened.
- Oh yeah.
- And I listened to this amazing interview with Harvey Binney,
who's one of the architects, British guy.
He's retired now obviously, because it was a long time ago.
And he was interviewed by the BBC
and here's a good riddle, me this.
- Oh, hey, go on.
- The distance between the tops of the two towers,
'cause it's a suspension bridge.
It's got two towers spanning the middle of it,
is different at the top and at the bottom.
Riddle me this, the...
- Sorry, so as in you take the top
and then you go straight down that pole to the bottom.
- But those towers are not straight.
- Well, they are straight.
- Oh.
- Or is it the curvature of the earth?
- The earth is not straight.
- That was right, what I said.
- Yeah.
- Because they had to build both towers absolutely straight,
but it's such a distance apart
that if you build them both straight,
the curvature of the earth comes into play.
And it's about 10 centimetres different at the top.
- Who's it?
- And he said, look, we did have to take that into account
because you don't want to end up with like 10 centimetres.
You don't want to miss 10 centimetres of cable.
- It's long, but it's not that long.
- The earth doesn't feel that curved, does it?
- I know, the earth is more curved than you'd think.
- The earth is a lot more curved than dad thinks.
- Hell yeah.
(all laughing)
- Only joking, I'll need that.
- We're just constantly losing giant containers
off the back of sherps.
- Why don't they pick it?
- You'd want to fish them out and see what's in each one.
- You would, right?
- It could be a container of baked beans,
a container of Barbies.
- That is a fun format for a TV show.
- How does it work, sorry?
- They already do this.
- Well, it's a team of celebrities.
- But there is one of these that exists,
but it's on land, right?
Where you go into containers and you open them much.
- That's it, it's an American show.
And you get like, you take an old container unit
that's not been claimed.
Or it's like--
- It's run out, they've paid their rent.
- Yeah, that doesn't download for this show.
- And a load of experts can look inside,
but they can't go in, they can't open anything up.
So you just have to bid an amount for it
based on what you think might be in there.
- Yeah, what is it called, you've told me.
- Nothing wrong with liking a really good show, you know?
- It's called Storage Wars.
- Storage Wars.
- Can I just say if the producers of Storage Wars
are listening and they want a celebrity to come on,
then Dan is available.
- I am available.
- It's more outlandish, isn't it?
I'll send you in this little rowing boat
to the middle of Pacific Ocean to find a container.
- The thing about heartbeats is
some people can hear their own heartbeats
better than others, and this is called entereception.
And it's the ability to interpret signals
from inside your body, so.
- I'm so hoping you don't say this means
they're gonna die prematurely
because I hear my heartbeats so loudly all the time.
- You're more likely to report having anxiety
if you do that, and you're more likely to,
if your heartbeat changes slightly,
to think it's something to be worried about,
whereas actually normally people's heartbeats
do change quite a lot throughout the course of a day.
And actually the best thing is to have a medium.
You wanna sometimes hear it a little bit,
but not be obsessed with it, basically.
- So are you concerned about it sometimes, Anna?
- No, I don't get concerned.
I just, it keeps me awake.
Sometimes 'cause you lie down on your pillow,
you can always hear it in your ear.
- So do you, yeah, do you hear it internally
or can you hear it outwardly?
- Hear it out?
What, like, hear it before you get to my shirt?
- Yeah, can you, no.
That's physically, I mean, can you hear the noise?
- You're not a cartoon character, Anna.
Could your husband hear the noise
or is it through your inner ear?
- I've never asked him, but I snore so loudly
that I think it would cover up any noise I'm making.
- You're like the Telltale Heart by Edgar Ellingham.
- Oh, yeah.
- You're like that your whole life.
- I am.
Hang on, what does the heart tell?
It beats and it tells someone.
- He's murdered someone.
- He's murdered the old man.
Oh, it happens right away.
It's sort of straight away, he kills the old man
'cause he's got this weird eye.
The old man has a weird eye.
The guy hates that this old man has this weird eye
and he gets obsessed with it
and he decides, "Oh, am I gonna have to kill the old man?"
I mean, I think I just live in the same building
or something, it's always his landlord or something.
But he kills him and then he keeps hearing it.
He buries it under the floorboards
and he keeps hearing his heartbeat.
And some people come around to investigate.
We've heard there's been an old man murdered.
Boom, boom, boom, boom, boom, boom, boom.
He's like, "Can you not hear that?"
- No one else can hear it.
- Like, "No, no, Hannah's in the car now."
(all laughing)
- I was actually looking up.
'Cause I was thinking I like eel in Japanese restaurants,
which is the only context I've really had it,
but obviously it used to be a huge thing.
You'd mostly in London and Cockneys
and everyone ate Jelly Deal, right?
You'd have pie mash and eel shops or whatever.
- That's right.
- And I was wondering, was it nice?
And honestly, I've been through so many forums
where people were reminiscing about eating it
and not a single person has said it wasn't disgusting.
- And presumably if you're posting on those forums,
you're a kind of nostalgia called buffer.
- Exactly.
- Like that I would think is the prime territory.
- You're desperate to say,
"Oh, it was better in the good old days."
And they all just had to know it was rank.
I thought after Brexit, I thought we're gonna get it back.
- Did you?
- I thought, yeah, that was the sunlit uplands
that I was looking for.
- That's what you voted for, wasn't it?
- Bring back the Jelly Deals.
- No, actually, Brexit has stuffed the eel thing.
- Oh no.
- I'm so sorry, it has.
- Wasted boat jams.
- I'm sure you guys are familiar
with the Sustainable Eel Group.
Basically, we used to ship 10 million eels a year to Europe.
Legally, this isn't trafficked.
And more than half of that was for rewilding.
'Cause if you get an eel swimming into the seven asteroid,
it's screwed, right?
It's like, it can't get up the seven asteroid tour
but it's spawning ground.
The river is too blocked up.
But there are loads of places in Europe
where you can introduce Neil, it'll swim up,
it'll find a cracking place to spawn, whatever.
And you've done a great job there.
But Brexit has ruined it, so.
- 'Cause they can't fill in the paperwork and stuff.
- It's okay.
Yeah, they can't fill in the paperwork.
'Cause it basically trade barriers.
- Yeah, it's a bit of a pain.
- Does your heart really go bum-bum-bum?
Does it just go bum and you've just heard
the bum-bum in movies?
Or is it an echo?
Is the bum-bum-bum?
- If you've got a very hollow body.
- Yeah.
- For a hollow head.
- I'm just testing now.
- It does go bum-bum sometimes.
I might be too very hard, I think.
- I can only hear the,
the moment I can only hear the bum.
- Yeah.
- Well, you'll be using your pulse.
- You're not listening to your.
- But it's like, for instance, if you listen.
- Wait, what do you think the heart is?
- Well, I think the heart,
the bum-bum I associate with heart, not with my pulse.
I know that you can feel the pulse.
But you can't say, oh, I can hear my heart
by touching your veins on your wrist.
- Yeah.
- Okay, hang on.
- This has all got a bit stoner,
but go on, James, bring it back.
- Well, I doubt I will.
But it's like with a clock.
You know, a clock ticks, but it doesn't talk.
It just goes tick, tick, tick.
'Cause it's the same mechanism doing it all the time.
But if you listen to it, you can almost hear a talk,
even though there's not one there
because you're expecting it.
- I was playing it cool by agreeing with you,
but I absolutely thought there was a talk.
(laughing)
- I thought in every clock,
they'd entered two different tones just before.
- I thought the pendulum, yeah,
I assumed for years and years and years.
When the pendulum goes one way,
that makes a tick sound.
And then, I don't know, inside the glass cabinet,
there's something which makes it sound
a bit different going the other way.
- It's weird that you've still got that pendulum watch.
- There is a different kind of eel,
which does a similar-ish thing.
It's called a snake eel.
And they have a very pointy tip on their tail.
And they use it in a slightly different way.
They use it just to power out of the stomach of the fish,
which is eaten them sideways.
And then they just go out of the stomach.
- Oh, like pierce it.
- They just pierce it, they just go through.
- Well, that sounds not very good for the fish.
- Well, it's not good for anyone
'cause they can't get through the rib cage
once they're through the stomach.
So they just end up stuck in there.
- That's like a blooper from the alien movies.
(laughing)
The alien's like, "I'm stuck, we're gonna have to do this again."
- Yeah, and the fish doesn't even notice.
Fish can cope with a lot of stuff.
- Something piercing a big hole in its stomach
and then landing up squirming around in its rib cage.
I don't know whether they don't notice,
but they definitely don't take any action.
- They play it cool.
- They play it cool, yeah.
- Good on 'em.
- You know, if you eat mussels as a human,
you put them in the pot and it's boiling water.
- Oh, yes, and they often come back out, don't they?
Quite soon afterwards.
- But you're not supposed to eat the closed ones
'cause they might come out.
Well, that is actually true.
If you see an enemy, if you eat a mussel and it's closed,
then the mussel can just go through your body
and come out the other end
and the mussel will still be fine.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah.
- Whereas normally what they'll do is
they'll bring in the mussel and the shell
and then they'll eat the mussel and eject the shell,
but if it's closed, they can't get us the mussel.
- Do the enemies, anemones, eat the whole thing
and then just sort it out inside?
- Yes, they do.
- 'Cause that's a more dignified way of eating, I think.
- Yeah.
- Now, if you could do that with a lobster.
- If you could do that with a Big Mac
and you put in the entire, the burger
and the bit of plastic that comes, that goes around it.
- With the plastic on the cheese.
- Or if you could, yeah.
(laughing)
Or if you could do it with a Kinder Egg
and then you could eat the whole thing
and you could even make the tie inside you.
- I love that.
(laughing)
Just open your mouth.
There's a little mechanical wiggle on there.
50% of eel consumed on the planet is eaten in Japan.
- It's big.
- And if you go to a Japanese restaurant,
they'll always have, they have eel on the menu.
But the nice news is that 35% of Japanese people
are willing to eat cultured eel.
- As in--
- What eel that goes to the theater?
- That's right.
(laughing)
It costs more because obviously you've seen
the prices of the restaurant these days, all right.
(laughing)
No, you can, it's saffron-lay-miz.
It liked Hamilton.
It didn't love it.
Like, it wasn't five stars.
But no, it's like, you can grow really good eel now.
You know, the art of it, like growing meats
which are of different varieties.
The eel you can get now is really realistic.
- We're at like fake eel.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Oh, wow, really?
- It looks like it, it tastes like it, all of that, you know.
So that might be quite good.
- And how many Japanese people are willing to eat that?
- Over a third.
- That's good figures.
That's much better than like proportions of American people
who would be willing to eat fake meat.
I suspect culture meat.
- Yeah, but we all say we're willing to eat kangaroo testicles
until we're actually on.
I'm a celebrity to get me out of here.
(laughing)
And then you don't want to, you're right, you're right.
- Alfred Hitchcock was terrified of eggs, had ovo-phobia.
So he said the white round thing without any holes.
That's how he referred to eggs.
And when you break it inside,
there's that yellow thing round without any holes.
So I think he likes holes and he doesn't like eggs.
- Did he like ping pong balls?
- Yeah, I don't know.
He's no mention on ping pong balls,
but what's interesting is his favorite breakfast
was quiche lorraine, and he used to make it himself.
- What?
- Yeah, so he would have to deal with this phobia
until the egg no longer resembled an egg,
and then he was fine with it.
- Stick a hole in it.
- Stick a hole in it, yeah.
- So that says to me it wasn't that serious.
Was it being still making his own quiche lorraine?
- No, 'cause I think it's a sort of you face your fears
and then it goes quite quickly once you get the fear.
For him, it was the shape and the lack of holes.
- No, no, I know, but if I like,
I don't like a house spider,
and I can't just like go and kill a house spider really fast
and be like, well, it was really quick,
so it doesn't matter, I can't go near it.
- The other day Anna, a house spider fell on me
as I was sitting up in bed from the ceiling.
And it was-
- You told me this before,
I didn't enjoy the story at the time,
I'm not enjoying it now.
- It was a four inch, it was big.
- I don't like it.
- And I was shirtless.
- That's not four inches, what's going on?
(all laughing)
So Lowell Bender writes,
"If you haven't already covered this,
I'd like you to know that some US banks
have their own zip code."
- Ah, nice. - It's cool, isn't it?
And then they write,
"I came across this because for reasons unknown to me,
meetup.com defaulted to that zip code,
but I'm in and then they give their own zip code."
- Which is?
- Well, this might be a call for help really.
- Yeah, what's-
- What's meetup.com?
- Well, it sounds like a dating site.
- It does, doesn't it?
- And it then sounds like he's trying to give his address
on the podcast, or she, or they.
So I wonder if this is just a trick
to try and get some fish lists.
- Yeah, get some free meetups.
- Are we being cat-fished right now?
- Wait, I'm so confused.
So this person went on a dating site
and ended up accidentally booking in a date with a bank.
(all laughing)
Went to meet their date,
had put misleading pictures up of a not bank,
and then arrived and it was a bank.
- No, it's- - Come over and make a deposit.
- I bet the innuendo is going to be-
- What's the safe word?
There we go.
- Yeah, there we go.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Put 'em up.
(all laughing)
- This is a stick up.
- I make the same mistake every week when we do this,
and then I go home and I get sushi
for the thing next to the station,
you know, which comes with soy sauce and wasabi sauce,
and it's always 'round the train.
So I squeeze in and then you have to get the chopsticks out
and you have to open the soy sauce,
and you have to open the sauce and it goes just everywhere.
- And you have to ask someone to hold your finger bowl
and it's, you had to take your shoes off as well.
It's nightmare.
- But you know when you started you're like,
people will think I've given up if I don't keep going.
So I'm always covered in soy sauce and it stinks.
- I don't think people think about you that much.
I don't mean to offend,
but just most people are busy with their own stuff.
They're not going to think that woman's only,
that woman stopped eating her sushi halfway.
What's going on?
- Is that top podcaster, Anna Tosinski,
eating half a sushi?
- She's quit, isn't she?
She's too embarrassed to finish it.
- When's she going to eat the other half of it?
(all laughing)
- It's for her dinner.
- Oh shit, I missed my stuff.
(all laughing)
- It was worth it.
It was worth it.
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that after Chernobyl,
nearby children were tweeted,
and they taught, they taught.
Putty tat, oh dear.
- Good.
- Someone sent us a tweet this morning, actually,
Sean Gibson, and it was referring to,
it's just a headline from the Intelligencia Journal
in Pennsylvania, from 1913.
Self-rising bed exceeds expectations
and throws inventor out of the window.
(all laughing)
No more information given.
- Brilliant, they need it.
- The thing that you have always done for hiccups,
since I was Tony, is you drink some water upside down.
- Yeah, all of that stuff is rubbish.
- No, it works.
- No, it doesn't, Andy.
- It's just a distraction technique.
- It works for me.
- No, it doesn't.
- You're still hiccuping.
(all laughing)
You've been doing it all day.
- I'm not.
- My headline fact this week,
is from Jeffrey Partica, or Partica, or Party car.
- Party car, yeah.
- Party car, yeah, it's Party car.
- Remember when we went to Dublin
and we got in a party car?
- Yeah, that was great.
- That was cool.
- The taxi.
- Unintentionally, we got in a--
- I did not remember that.
- We got a taxi home from a gig,
and then the guy just pressed a button,
and all the lights started going off,
and there was like a disco ball,
and they started playing music.
- It just went thundersly disco.
- They always do that in taxis for me.
- It's very cool.
- All right, one of you don't remember, yeah.
- Electric eels are not a type of eel.
- Are they not?
- No, they're not.
- I don't assume they were.
- They're just an electric fish that's very long.
But I thought I'd read about them anyway.
There's this absolutely hero called Ken Katania,
who's worked out what it feels like
to be attacked by an electric eel,
and he says that being attacked by a large electric eel
is like being tasered by nine tasers at the same time.
Well, what he did was he stuck his arm into a tank
with a small eel, and did it 10 times,
and he reckons because he knows how electric eels work,
you could just extrapolate from the small eel
to the size of a normal eel.
So if you get bitten by a small electric eel,
it's about the same as touching a horse fence.
So do you know what that's like?
- I do, actually, yeah.
- 'Cause you like to steal horses, don't you?
- I don't know, I used to raise on the podcast,
but yeah, I'm a horse wrestler.
- You've touched an electrified horse fence.
- Yeah, well, 'cause you know, when you're a kid,
we used to line up, so one of you touches the fence,
and then everyone holds onto the other one's shoulders,
and then you--
- Okay, so it's a bit of a shock, it's not a, yeah.
- It's quite a shock.
- Hang on, if you're holding it normally,
does it not shock you at all,
because you're earthed with your rubber shoes and rubber?
- The earthing is the problem, right?
'Cause it goes through your body together.
- Oh, sorry.
So you're not wearing your big wellies at this point?
- No, no, the whole point is to shock you
and all your friends in a line.
- Anyway, electrical is worse, he says,
but he hasn't actually had the balls
to sting himself with a proper big one.
- No, because actually, if you're tazored by nine tazers,
you're probably gonna die.
- Yeah.
- No, not a good idea, very not.
(laughing)
- And one interesting thing is that they use their electricity
for electro-location, so they can, a bit like Sonar,
they can kind of fire their electric field around
and then feel where everything is.
So, 'cause it's so dark and muddy down there,
that's how they can see where everything is.
But the sensors that they use, it's not exactly the same,
but it's very, very similar principles
to how your mobile phone works.
So you know how there's sensors in there
that kind of can tell that your finger's there
and it's all about capacitors and blah, blah, blah.
I'm not gonna go into it now,
but it's basically the same technology
as electric heels use to find their way around.
- You see, you've got all your clever computers
and all your internets in the old days.
We got around just with eel tech.
(laughing)
And we jelly 'em up at the end of the day
and it was absolutely horrible.
(laughing)
- Isn't it weird that when you have a vasectomy
and then you produce semen,
what would you think that looks like?
'Cause you know when you think about, you picture semen.
- Yeah.
- And you think that that's--
- I can't picture anything in my head,
but I'm not even gonna try this one.
- It probably looks absolutely identical.
Yeah, maybe, or just a bit more watery.
- That's what I would have thought it looks more watery
'cause it looks more transparent maybe.
- Maybe it doesn't have those green bits.
(laughing)
- We've still got the chunky cheesy bits, right?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
It's a different chew they need to cut, James.
- I thought it doesn't sparkle.
(laughing)
- Well, in a way, it doesn't sparkle.
- It doesn't sing.
It doesn't make that weird singing sound.
(laughing)
- It's just from screaming as they go.
- Don't do it!
- You're on it!
(laughing)
- I go to Valhalla!
We will fight them on the beach.
- So Anna--
- This hasn't got more I wanted to.
It's just the same.
- Where did you want it to go?
Where on earth did you want that to go?
(upbeat music)
- Okey-dokey.
Hope you enjoyed that compilation.
If you wanna get in contact with any of us
about the things that we said on this episode,
why not write to us?
At podcast@qi.com.
And we will cherry pick some of the best emails
that you've sent in about this and the main episodes
and use them in a future Drop Us Align episode.
All right, Club Fish members, that is it.
Take care.
We will see you soon.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)