[MUSIC]
Hello, and welcome to another episode of "No Such Thing as a Fish"
a weekly podcast coming to you from the QI offices in Covern Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I'm sitting here with James Harkin, Andy Murray, and Anagy Zinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite
facts from the last seven days and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, Juzinski.
>> My fact is that only 28% of people know when they're being flirted with.
>> I never know, ever.
>> Do you think you think people are flirting or they aren't with you?
>> Aren't.
>> They aren't.
Yeah, so this is the interesting thing.
People never seem so, they've done this study recently, which looked at 52
heterosexual women, 52 heterosexual men.
And they put them in pairs together and made them have a conversation.
And then afterwards they asked them if they'd flirted with the other person.
And then they asked them if they thought the other person had been flirting with them.
And lots of people flirted and only 28% of people realized they were doing it.
And in women, it was 18%.
>> Wow.
>> Was that who knew that they were flirting with someone else or that someone else was flirting with them?
>> When people flirted with other people, they were aware of it.
>> Well, sometimes they're not, I think.
>> Sometimes you accidentally flirt.
>> Yes, sometimes people are just so flirtatious.
>> I go accused of that of flirting when I'm not.
>> Yeah, James always says.
>> I do say that to you a lot.
And by the way, get your hand off my leg.
>> This is an interesting thing about flirting.
So men are perceived as being better at flirting when these are some of the behaviors
that they engage in when women think, oh, he's flirting and he's good at it.
So for a start, actually looking at the person that you want to flirt with,
that is a solid gold winner, that's really good.
Also positioning your body that it takes up more space.
And doing what's called non-reciprocated touching to surrounding men.
So this includes playfully shoving, touching, or elbowing the ribs of other men around you.
Supposedly helps you flirt with a woman that you're interested in on the other side of a bar or something.
>> Really?
>> Yeah, you probably should know the person when you're shoving them, right?
>> Yeah, so what happens is there's a massive bar fight going on at the other side of the bar.
And they go, wow, stop flirting with me, guys.
>> Here's the last thing that this study identified as supposedly a really good sign is the men who are good at it.
Changed their location in the bar more frequently.
Where's he gone?
>> So is that just literally playing hard to get?
>> I suppose so.
>> You try to walk over to him, he's suddenly in a different place.
>> Playing hard to find.
>> Let's take the thing out of there, let's do that.
>> You know how you think you're not flirting and you are, Dan?
>> Yeah.
>> Some people think that they're flirting when they're not.
>> What is it? >> This is called signal amplification bias.
And it's where you think that your gestures are making it really clear that you're doing some pretty heavy duty flirting.
But obviously, the other person has no idea.
So it's like when I'm in a bar and I'm running around into lots of different positions.
>> The other person just hasn't noticed it.
>> But she'd run the men in the face.
>> Yeah, well, I mean, that's why the study has ended up showing that people don't know if they've been flirted with because people don't flirt properly.
Because the whole, it's kind of self-defeating flirting because the whole point of it really is to be subtle, isn't it?
The whole point of flirting is to kind of conceal and protect, conceal what you're trying to do and protect yourself.
Because you don't just walk up to someone and go, I fancy you, do you want to have sex?
>> So evolutionarily, the idea, I think, is that it could be socially costly to kind of just go up to someone and say,
you want to have sex with them.
Because if they say no, then you could get excluded from the group or whatever.
And it seems to be like a uniquely human thing.
Other animals don't seem to do it.
But I read one article about the idea that other animals don't really flirt.
And it said, if other animals were to flirt, would we even be able to detect it?
>> Well, we can't detect when we're doing it.
>> Let's look at the head of ourselves, is this mouse flirting?
I mean, folks on that woman over there.
>> But I think around all over the floor, it looks like it's flirting.
>> But there was a natural history museum exhibition that went on where their whole premise was that animals do flirt.
And obviously, they must have just been putting a nice little spin on it.
But there are examples of sort of romantic gestures, it seems.
>> The idea with flirting is it's something which you wouldn't really be able to tell
unless you can just about kind of pick up on it.
>> Oh, I disagree, I think flirting can be absolutely outright.
>> No, it is, it's a defense mechanism, rather than saying.
Because animals just go up to each other and say, let's sleep together.
That's what all of their flirting is.
>> Look, the Amazonian River Dolphin, it brings a bouquet of waterweeds.
>> Yeah, that's not subtle, it's not what you're bouquet of waterweeds.
>> That's what they want it.
>> Okay, okay, how about there's a haddock that hums.
>> Again, that's not really flirting.
>> Well, if you're going over them.
>> Yeah, I think that could be.
>> If she says, well, you just, no, I was just humming, I was just talking about it.
It's just subtle, that's a subtle signal.
>> Yeah. >> And with you, Dan.
>> Flirting is quite a good way of trying to suss out whether someone's going to be worthwhile
without actually inviting them to jump into bed with you.
>> Right. >> Because you might decide halfway through
the flirting encounter that actually, no, this guy's not right.
>> Not sure how this fits with your stats.
But men over perceived flirting and women under perceived flirting.
And the reason is because men, if they over perceived and they don't get it right,
then they just move on to the next one.
And it doesn't really matter.
Whereas if women over perceived, then they might have sex with an undesirable man and
end up with weedy children and burdened.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I think that's very plausible.
And that's definitely what the study showed.
16% of women recognize some people with flirting, but way more men did.
>> Right. >> So the, because it is quite costly for
humans if you sleep with the wrong person who turns out to be a bit of a weed.
And doesn't give you good offspring because that's like a nine month gestation period.
And then you've got to raise this kid who's weedy and shit like the dad.
So they still under, underestimated it.
>> Right.
The word flirting, the word flirting used to actually mean hitting somebody.
>> Did it?
>> Yeah.
>> It also meant to turn up one's nose or sneer at.
>> Really?
>> That's the verb anyway.
>> It's really, it's really changed, yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> But since the fifth, I think in the 1560s, Samuel Johnson described the noun
flirt as it's always a female and it's a pert young Hussie.
I also liked their alternatives to flirting, which were when it came to mean being,
it meant being nimble often and I think that came to be nimble conversationally.
And you could also say someone was a flirty gig or a flirt, Gillian.
Which I quite like to mean an unconstant woman.
>> Wow.
>> They have a flirty gig.
>> This is weird.
Scientists found that men find happiness very attractive in a woman.
But women find it one of the less attractive things in a man.
>> What happiness?
>> Yeah, apparently.
And shame, sort of doing what's called shameful displays or displays of shame,
was more attractive to women than happiness.
>> What's a shameful display?
>> Oh, I'm so embarrassed, oh, I can't do this.
>> Okay.
>> But you know, which explains you grand in a way?
>> It's not dropping your trousers and going.
>> No, that's a penis.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I like this, there was, I think this is in scientific American saying research.
A split types of touching into three categories.
So there's merely friendly, there's plausible deniability, which is what we were talking about.
Like if someone's like, are you flirting with me, you can go, no, obviously not.
And then there's going nuclear and plausible deniability includes an arm touch or
a shoulder or a waist touch.
>> What's going nuclear kind of flirt?
>> Face touch, which would be a bit weird, wouldn't it?
If you just in a pub with someone, they leaned over and touched you on the face.
>> Yeah, mid-chat though, it's not weird.
>> Don't if you ever do that to me.
>> [LAUGH]
>> You're going to be in serious trouble.
>> If you had like a thing on your head, I'd be like, you got a thing on your head.
>> You can't just touch people's faces mid conversation, I'm constantly touching faces.
>> You can't do that.
>> I don't even ask, I go right in, I don't.
>> Why?
Because it's a very personal bit of the body.
>> I've got a thing on their face.
>> What's this thing you keep going on about?
>> Yeah, if you've got a thing on their face, I think that's okay.
>> I'm not leaving this until we just attain what the thing is.
It might be like sometimes people get glitter on their face or a bit of plough.
Why do I get the feeling that you go around with a bit of glitter at your pockets, about people's faces?
>> I don't think it's weird to touch a face, I'm just putting that out there.
>> I'd touch a bus driver's face, I would touch that's why they've had to put the screens in these days.
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, time for fact number two, and that is James.
>> Okay, my fact this week is that ancient Sumerian beer was as thick as porridge and was drunk through a straw.
>> That's so good.
>> It's good, although it was as thick as porridge, what kind of heavy-duty straw, is it like McDonald's milkshake?
>> Yeah, that's the view, right?
>> The oldest straw that they've ever found was Sumerian.
It was found in a tomb dated 3,000 BCE, and it was a gold tube inlaid with Lapis Lazuli.
>> Gold?
>> Wow, wow.
>> And the thing is, this beer was kind of fermented bread, so it's a bit like vast that they have in Russia.
And it was really, really thick, but you wanted to drink mostly the liquid bit, and so you had the straw to stop the bread from going into your mouth.
So you just got the liquid bit.
And they reckon that that's why the straw was invented in general, probably for drinking beer.
>> That's cool, and I think- >> That's very cool.
>> Wasn't that first one, it was two men sharing a drink, wasn't it, in the Sumerian tomb, which is nice.
>> Was it?
>> You can't share a straw, though.
>> I think they had a straw each.
>> Okay, cool.
>> And well, wasn't because they found the oldest depiction of a straw, and they also found the oldest straw, didn't they?
And the depiction had a picture of two men sharing a beer.
>> Yeah, so this is probably not the first beer in the world that we know of, because that was probably ancient Chinese.
That was called kui, but this is in the, in the, let's say, near West, and it was Sumerian, and they had a few different words for beer.
It was Sikaru, Dida, or a beer.
>> The way- >> No!
>> E-B-I-R was one of the names for the- >> No, fancy beer.
>> Cool. >> That's pretty cool, isn't it?
That also meant beer mug, and they thought that beer was a gift from the gods to promote human happiness and well-being.
And the first brewers were, they were pre-stasses.
>> So the ancient Egyptians used to say to each other, to greet each other day-to-day, they'd say bread and beer, and that basically meant everything is good in life.
>> Oh, cool as that.
>> Yeah, we should start doing that again.
>> Bread and beer.
>> Isn't there quite a long-running debate?
I mean, I think there is quite a long-running debate about whether bread came first or beer came first, and a lot of archaeologists think that we have evidence to suggest that beer was brewed before bread was made.
>> And one followed on from the other.
>> Actually, the oldest bread maker was actually found in a tomb, which contained the oldest depiction of a bread maker.
>> [LAUGH]
>> There are loads of guys who try and recreate very ancient beers, and they find the right sort of chemicals in tombs and things like that, and they speculate that this might have been beer or that this contained the sort of flavorings that were to be that they know around the area, so they try and remake all these things.
They even do things like killing goats to make fresh wine skins at the time.
>> Wow, that's so cool.
>> Well, not for the goats, not for the goat.
No, but they have things like genuinely beer used to have things like olive oil, cheese, or carrot, or hemp, all kinds of stuff will be added to it.
>> I don't want to go to a party that these guys are throwing, I'm going to get a cheesy olive oil beer.
>> There is one guy in Oregon who's a brewer, and he made beer with yeast harvest him from his own beard.
>> Cool.
>> Yeah.
>> How did that taste?
>> It's just yeast, you know.
Most yeast in the rest of the world is found on animals and insects and rotting fruit, so it's not necessarily any grosser.
Even though it seems like it is.
>> Yeah, it does.
>> There was some 170 year old beer found in a shipwreck just off the coast of Finland, either this year or last year, wasn't there.
And the divers who went down and they uncovered it.
I think there were six bottles of beer and they decided to taste it, and it was pretty disgusting, I think.
>> It's always disgusting whenever they do this.
>> I never learned.
We found some 5,000 year old honey too, giving it like, "Oh, it's disgusting."
>> You say that, but it could have been disgusting in the first place.
>> Indeed, and it probably was.
>> They did when they analysed it, they said that it would have had hints of sourd milk and burnt rubber with some rose-like notes and a goatee taste.
>> A goatee, as in a beard goatee.
>> I'm one of those people that I love a novelty beer, I love the variety of new beers that we have.
>> I don't know if I go to an off license and I see that Iron Maiden has a beer or ACDC, I'm going to buy that one.
Did you know that Hansen the band released a beer?
>> No.
>> Was it called "mhops"?
>> Yes.
>> Oh, yes it was.
>> How good was that?
>> Yeah.
>> I was going to say they should have done a soft drink called "mhops".
>> Oh, yeah.
>> They could see, like, mist there's a whole range of drinks that they could have done.
>> Or a range of cleaning items called "mhops".
>> It's been gone for a while.
>> Yep, yep.
>> Also, one that I'd love to get my hands on, because it's a bit of a historical, or historically, it'll be a bit of a famous beer.
Do you know that David Cameron gave the Coalition Cabinet a beer?
>> Wait, really?
>> Around?
>> No, no.
They just want beer between them, that's austerity.
>> No, after the final session of the Coalition Cabinet, they got goody bags as they left.
And inside one of the goody bags was a Coalition beer, which was called co-ale-ishen beer.
And it had on it, on the back, it said, "An unconventional pairing.
This experimental beer has astonished outers and exceeded expectations.
Time for some creative thinking with this carefully crafted beer.
Hints of oak and zesty lemon deliver a truly distinctive refreshing flavor that lasts the distance."
>> Makes you feel sick after a very short time.
>> Yeah.
>> I was trying to look for which country drinks most beer was just having a few little looks.
>> People say it's Czech Republic.
>> Yep, that's true.
So, as I was looking into this, I also found out what country drinks most wine, the Vatican.
>> Oh, yeah, of course.
>> The Vatican, yeah.
>> But they are really the biggest consumers of Jesus' blood.
>> Oh, that's they are also that, yeah, that's true, I forgot about that.
But they also, the Vatican have their own Vatican beer.
They have a brewery that's not too far away from them.
And they have, they bring in cases and they love beer.
Apparently, and it's only slightly a rumor, but when they, when they were deciding on the last pope,
there was enough bottles for each of the people who were deciding, what would you call them?
>> Are they cardinals who do it, but there's a lot of specials.
>> Yeah, the electors basically.
There was enough beer for one of them each.
>> The A electors.
>> Oh, my goodness.
>> I just wanted to kill that because I've got really bad but down there.
And this is why puns ruin all conversations.
>> Yeah.
>> Because just for anyone listening, James and Andy, we're looking into the sky, not listening
to a word that Dan was saying, desperately grappling for some pathetic pun relating to
popes and beer.
And I think it's really inconsiderate to the speaker.
>> And he's still doing it.
>> Okay, time for fact number three, and that is Andrew Hunter Murray.
>> My fact is that baby turtles coordinate when they're going to hatch from within their
eggshells.
>> Wow.
>> It's incredible.
>> It's so amazing.
>> They talk to each other.
>> Yeah.
Scientists listen to the eggs to see if they made any noise from within the shells.
And they do.
And they actually found more than 300 different noises coming from them.
And I don't know if all of those mean anything or have particular meanings.
But there was one sound which came only from nests which had only eggs in.
So there was some which had only eggs and there was some which had a mixture of eggs
and already hatched babies.
And they believe that the babies were communicating so that they could coordinate when they all
hatch together because when they hatch there's a great advantage to having strength in numbers
because the journey from the point where they hatched to the sea is so dangerous and there
are so many predators who just hang around waiting as the article I read put it.
While some babies will be picked off by predators, a bird can only eat so many sea turtles at
a time.
How do they coordinate the hatching?
Is there a leader?
Is there one leading turtle?
Just a leader.
All right guys, come on.
We can do this.
Leonardo.
I saw a really good, I'd come up with where this was but four really good pie charts which
was the teenage mutant ninja turtles proportion that they're famous for being artists compared
to proportion that they're famous for being turtles.
It's quite cool.
We're done a tell-o, obviously a tiny sliver of famous artists.
So on communicating with things before they hatch, this is so called birds do the same thing.
And some birds called superb fairy wrens, which we must have mentioned before, the mothers
sing to the eggs to teach them a password which they have to use when they hatch if they want
food.
Wow.
And it's because loads of cuckoos lay their eggs in superb fairy wrennests and it's-
What's the password?
Cucko.
And it's normally a single unique note that the cheques know.
And what it means is that cuckoos are laid later on and they hatch earlier as well.
So they only get about two days to learn the password which is normally not enough for
them to actually process it and learn it.
And Ren embryos have about five days.
So if the cucko hatches and pushes out the other eggs, the parents can test it with the
password.
Cuckoos doesn't know the password and the parents can just abandon it and fly off and make
a new nest and a new life.
Just one more quite cool thing about eggs that I like.
So sand gobyfish, which you'd recognise that you see them in Europe.
It's the responsibility of the male gobyfish to guard the eggs when they've been laid by
the female.
But he gets really impatient because he wants to have sex with as many females as he can
and spread his seed as often as he can so the female gobyfish is like, "I've laid the
eggs now.
Can you guard these until they hatch?"
And he knows that the bigger the egg is, the longer it takes to hatch, so he just eats all
the bigger ones.
Oh.
Because he probably will have to wait for them.
It's bad, isn't it?
And usually the bigger ones are going to be the stronger healthier offspring.
But he mongers them right up.
There's an octopus who's recently been discovered just stating its egg or protecting its
egg for four and a half years.
Yeah.
And supposedly they get so hungry that they nearly starve and they have to eat their
own arms to survive while they're protecting their offspring from predators.
Wow.
Yeah.
And for often they're so knackered at the end of this that when their offspring have
eventually gone swam away independently, they're just pretty easy prey.
Yeah, I think they waste away, so they didn't they and die.
Isn't that amazing?
Yeah.
This is really off topic.
But I read the other day that there is some jellyfish and if they lose an arm, then it's
like some animals can grow arms back.
But they can't do that.
But what they can do is shuffle around all the other arms so that they're now symmetrical
again so they can go up like swim properly.
What, it not looks stupid?
That is amazing.
I know.
Can I just say quickly my favorite discovery about turtles this week?
Scientists haven't yet properly decided on whether or not turtles have a penis or a
fallace.
What?
It's the same thing.
Apparently it's not because penis should be restricted to mammals yet.
They want to call it a penis.
I read this in an article called terrifying sex organs of male turtles and I think I've
seen the film of that.
I do it to be honest.
I asked Anna to read this article because I couldn't understand all the big words and
so I don't know the answer to that.
No one could, it's not a, it's a, it's a very, it's full of like really zoological words.
Yeah.
That's a trick though because the title sounds really kind of accessible.
It's an incredibly deceptive title.
Yeah, it's in scientific American.
This is an article from, so if anyone wants to read it and explain it to me.
No.
It's fine.
It's just very dense about how like their organs work.
There were a couple of good things in that article though.
So I like the fact that they referred to as the intramidant organ.
When they're having this debate as to whether it's the fallace or the penis, it's
called the intramidant organ, as in the organ that sends something in, in Latin, which is
quite cool.
The other thing that I think there was a spin-off article from this that it uncovered is
if you google a cross section of a turtle penis, it looks exactly like a teenage mutant
in the turtle head.
You're doing it now.
Doing it now.
With the bandana and everything.
It's got the bandana.
Oh my god.
Donatello.
Oh, it's Thomas.
Oh my god.
With the bandana.
We'll have to put this up on the Twitter page.
Definitely.
I'll put it up on mine.
Yeah.
It'll be on QI podcast.
Yes.
QI podcast.
So we were saying before about how turtles kind of hatch and all go down to the sea at the
same time.
Well, one problem that they have in Florida is people are accidentally drowning baby
tortoises because go for tortoises nest in sand dunes near to the sea and people keep
finding these little totuses and think they're turtles and so put them back in the sea.
Oh my god.
And they just drown because they can't swim.
That's so frustrating.
That's horrible.
In the town of Hilton Head Island, I'm not quite sure where this is, I think it's
in America somewhere.
There was a man who was proposing to his future wife and little load of candles on the
edge of the beach and she said yes and they retired to the room and they killed 60 baby
sea turtles.
Oh my god.
Oh.
Why?
Because they were attracted to the light.
They were disorientated by the light and some tracks repeatedly encircled the lanterns where
the hatchlings eventually succumbed to ghost craps.
Oh my god.
What are they?
Moths.
What's this light thing?
I've never heard this before.
Yeah.
Any other animal getting attracted to light.
Well, the thing is, there was one species of sea turtle who hatched during the day and that's
really problematic, obviously, because you know, they just just straight out.
Yeah.
Is that a bad omen?
Do you think you cancel the wedding the next day when you emerge from your tent and see just
dozens of tortoise carcasses?
I don't normally believe in omen, but that is a bad sign.
Sorry darling, I know we have been dating for 10 years and finally you've said yes, but
there's a couple of dead animals.
So I wouldn't be willing to take the risk of saying another quite funny turtle story is...
Got how many died in this one?
They're already really endangered, all seven species of sea turtle.
And here we are, casually making light of the death of more.
Well, include me out.
Go on.
Okay, we've included Andy out, but for everyone else.
So in somewhere in China, I remember where there was a drunk guy known only as Wang, the
article says.
So I don't think he wanted to identify himself in full.
He got really drunk, ran into the seafood section of a restaurant, dunked his head in the
fish tank and tried to kiss a turtle, at which point the turtle clamped onto his mouth.
Would you like to go?
He had to go to hospital, I think, I know he had to be freed by having the turtle decapitated.
What?
What the fuck?
Say, that was going so well.
Okay, time to move on to our final fact of the show and that's my fact.
My fact this week is that the playwright Henrik Ibsen's last words were to his nurse.
She said to him that she thought he seemed to be looking better and he replied on the contrary
and died.
It turns out that that's not as exciting as I want it to be and that he actually died
the next day.
But those were the last words he said.
So I think he must have lapsed into a coma or a-
Oh, he thought they were pretty good words.
Just going to sit on those.
I think I should collect a series of last words just so that I've got 20 or 30 things to
say on my deathbed and if I say one, I can just cross it off the list and then I'll go
on with the next one.
Oh yeah, yes.
If everything you ever say is extremely piffy and witty, then it doesn't matter when
you die.
Okay, but we're dealing with the real world here and I have to make allowances.
His last words were a terrible story about dead turtles.
His last words were a long pause where he was trying to come up with a pun relating the
Pope to death in some way.
I think if you constantly peve your conversations with desperate attempts at last words, your
death might come sooner than you expect.
So the thing about last words, when you suddenly put a sort of researcher's eye onto it,
you realize that no one ever said any of the things that everyone thinks they said on their
deathbed.
Oscar Wilde.
Either this wallpaper goes or I do.
And the actual thing he said was this wallpaper and I are fighting a duel to the death, either
it goes or I do.
Not the last thing he said.
Not even close.
I mean, that was I think in the days preceding his death.
Dylan Thomas was said to have said, I've had 18 straight whiskeys, I believe that's the
record.
And that's where those were his last words.
It's such a good last line.
It's an amazing last line.
I think there's some controversy now because Dylan Thomas was often assumed to have died
of alcohol poisoning and his family and other people say quite strongly that he didn't.
He just died of pneumonia and his agent spread about this kind of falsehood because his agent
was actually a bit lax in looking after Dylan Thomas in the days preceding his death.
So wanted to make it seem like he was a hope to have drunk it.
His agent should have made it.
What a magnificent agent I've got.
I've always thought that.
And now that he's freed up to work with other people, you should all apply.
I think probably by favorite last words.
And again, who knows if these were genuinely said, but it was by French poet slash diplomat
died in 1955 called Paul Claudel.
And his last words were, doctor, do you think it was the sausage?
I looked up Paul Claudel just to see who he was.
He's the opening line from his obituary.
Paul Claudel was a misogynist at anti-Soviet and it is lather foam.
That's the opening sentence.
Opening sentence of what?
His obituary.
It wasn't written by his agent.
Was it?
No, exactly.
This is a saying that's going, could he put and a poet in there?
One time when we do know people's last words and when it's going to be something quite
pithy is when people know they're going to die.
So people on death row.
Yes.
And so there's a few famous ones of that.
There was a murderer called James French when he was on the electric chair.
He shouted, hey, fellas, how about this for a headline for tomorrow's paper French fries?
It's a cracking one.
And another one who did pretty much the same joke was called George Apple.
And when he was being executed, he said, well, gentlemen, you are about to see a baked apple.
That is sort of copying things.
Well, I don't know who came first, actually.
Yeah.
He was in the line behind them.
Oh, that's pretty good.
That's what happened if Andy heard some last lines that he was up next.
Well, the name isn't at all food related.
So I'd be third in line going, oh, my God, what am I going to do?
Murray Mints.
What?
Have you been sliced to pieces?
I just sound odd, but can I request the guilty?
It's just very pun thing.
I just have one more last words thing, which actually is just, I just wanted to mention
Nero's last words only because I read something else about Nero this week, which I loved and
didn't know.
So Nero, quite famously, was supposed to have said, I can't remember who claimed it, someone
who was with him when he died said that Nero's last words were, what an artist the world
is losing in me.
But something else, oh, it's Cassius Dio, who was with him when he died.
But another thing I learned about Nero this week was he was kind of a, like, some people
say he was the words for the world's first known SNM propagator.
And he liked to have himself dressed up in animal skins, like exotic animal furs.
And he'd have people lock him in an enclosure in a cage.
And then he'd, like, get himself all worked up, and then he'd like to be released from this
enclosure.
And he'd gallop around like a wild beast.
And there'd be a bunch of men hung up in stocks around him, and he'd attack their genitals
and bite them off for fun, yeah, still not as weird as someone touching your face, though.
Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thanks so much for listening.
If you want to get in contact with any of us about the things we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on Twitter.
I'm on @Sriberland, James, @Xshaped, Andy @Andrew Hunter M. Chazinski.
You can email podcast@QI.com.
Yep, and you can also get us on @QIPodcast.
You can also go to nosuchthingasoffish.com, where we've got all of our previous episodes.
We've also got a link to all the live shows that we're going to be doing.
So go there, check it out.
We'll be back again next week with another episode.
See you then.
Goodbye.
[Music]
[BLANK_AUDIO]