(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I'm sitting here
with Anna Tyshensky, James Harkin, and Andrew Hunter Murray,
and once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Andy.
My fact is that thousands of soldiers who died
at Waterloo were turned into sugar.
- Incredible.
- It's a horrible fact about a horrible battle.
- Wow. - It's incredible.
- It's really bad. - I'm mad this one.
- Yeah, how do you turn a person into sugar?
That seems very unlikely.
- Well, firstly-- - I'll ask you for a friend.
- You have to lure them to Waterloo in 1815, kill them.
- Oh, so I have to be French?
- Well, oh, I'm so glad we got onto this already.
There are so many nationalities who fought at Waterloo.
- Oh yeah.
- Actually, most of the English army was German.
- Isn't that nice? - Yeah, I didn't realize that.
- Two thirds were German speaking as a first language,
lots of Dutch soldiers as well.
- Belgian, yeah, they were just brought in, weren't they?
Sort of, we don't have enough, can you fight?
- If you're listening to this in Europe,
probably your nationality was represented at Waterloo
in some capacity or another.
- Yeah, yeah. - And more than the Brits,
who constituted about 12% of the British led army.
- Oh, it was about a third, it was about a third.
- Estimates may vary.
- Oh, they do, they vary-- - I think at the lower end,
we think maybe only, you know.
- So what are we saying in case you don't like
British sugar, don't worry.
There is multinational sugar in it.
- Well, it was, they set up a sugar factory
pretty much on the battlefield.
I mean, it was all a bit--
- Can I refer you to my earlier question?
- How does one turn a human into some sugar?
- All right, thank you.
- Because sugar is a thing that grows in the ground
in sugar beet or sugar cane, and then you harvest it,
and there are no humans involved.
- That's true, that's true.
But what you do need to do is filter sugar syrup
when you're making the sugar.
So this was something, basically,
very, very few bodies have been found
on the battlefield at Waterloo.
Like, suspiciously few.
- Isn't it just, yeah. - Two full skeletons,
of 20,000 of them.
- Are we sure it wasn't just Napoleon and Wellington?
Just coming at it.
- And they just really over-engaged,
like, whoever won really told the much bigger lie
about what had happened there.
- It's the greatest prank in history.
Let's really pull the wool over those 21st century idiots eyes.
- No, so there were lots of graves,
and there were huge graves,
but only a few bones have been found.
Like, as you say, two full skeletons,
they found three legs relatively recently,
as well recently, which was near one of the hospitals.
So those were probably amputated legs on the day.
- Oh, right, so it's not that it was Napoleon versus Wellington,
and one of them had three legs.
- Yeah, that's what I was hoping.
One of the skeletons was a tripod.
- But you're right, there should have been huge numbers
of dead people, or bodies in the ground.
And the theory is, and this is quite a recent theory
that's been developed, is that in the aftermath of the battle,
the local residents, or the sort of local peasants,
they dug up the corpses, and they sold the bones
to people working in the sugar beet industry,
because the bones were really valuable at the time,
and normally animal bones were used.
You would cook the bones.
That made a powder called noir animal,
which you could use to filter the sugar syrup
and make lovely, clean sugar.
So these days, noir animal is still used,
but animal bones, and also not in sugar,
it's used for other products and things.
So sugar these days hasn't been in any bones.
- Sugar is vegan.
- Don't worry, yeah, vegetarians worldwide.
But the theory is that local peasants
just dug up the bodies and used the bones
for this industry, and it's a pretty
compelling theory at the moment.
- 'Cause we've known for ages
that they took the teeth out of people, didn't they?
- Yeah.
- And they used them for false teeth,
and so false teeth were known as waterloo teeth.
- Yeah, waterloo ivory. - For hundreds of years.
- Such a, yeah, it's so dark.
- Very macabre, yeah.
- And they did write about the sugar thing
back in the 1800s, or it was a German newspaper
that actually wrote, you should be using honey to sweeten food
and avoid risk of having your great-grandfather's atoms
dissolved in your coffee one fine morning.
- Wow.
- I like that, I quite like that idea
of recycling your grandparents into your body.
- Absolutely, yeah, yeah.
- And in 1822, there was an article in The Observer
that said, "It is now ascertained beyond the doubt
by actual experiments on an extensive scale
that a dead soldier is a most valuable article of commerce."
And they were talking about the fact
that they were ground up and used as fertilizer.
- Yes, they were, weren't they?
They covered the fields of Europe.
- I suppose, in a way, it's recycling.
- Yeah, good on them. - Isn't it?
- Like, once you're dead, like, do you really care?
- Exactly.
- A controversial question.
- Wow, it's not that controversial.
Once you're dead, I'm pretty sure you don't care.
Unless you're a ghost, I suppose.
- A woman does one care.
Some people care what happens to, you know, the dead.
- There was a single-- - Uncontroversial.
- There was a single, The Bone Rush.
And it was partly because, it was actually partly
because of Britain, because Britain blockaded sugar.
Right, 'cause most sugar came from places
like the West Indies, which were British colonies
at the time, and Britain had blockaded that,
so not much sugar could get to Europe.
So Europe set up a big sugar beet industry
that was a kind of way of making sugar
that didn't rely on shipping.
So that, and then that needed the bones.
So, in a sense-- - So thank God for Waterloo.
- In a sense, it's our fault.
- Yeah, yeah. - In a sense.
- In a sense. - In a sense.
Waterloo, I can't believe,
I can't believe we've hardly talked about Waterloo before.
I'm so excited.
I can't believe we're only gonna do one section on it.
Like, the rest is history, guys.
They would get eight episodes out of the Battle of Waterloo.
And we have to cram it into 15 minutes.
It's not fair.
- I think you're optimistic about 15 minutes,
I'll be honest. - Yeah.
- I'm looking at some of the other facts coming up,
and I reckon they might be a bit longer.
- Oh no, it's so interesting. - You're allowed one fact, Andy.
- No, we've gotta go through the whole--
- What's your fave?
What's your fave Waterloo fact?
Apart from the headline, obviously, which--
- Oh, man. - My definition is.
- I'm quite interested in the cavalry charges and stuff,
and the farmhouse at the centre of it all,
and all that.
And the stuff that doesn't make very good stuff for our show,
I suppose. - You have brought a lot of
toy soldiers onto the table today.
(laughing)
- Well, there is.
Have you heard of the Siborn model?
- No. - No.
- This is so cool.
This is like, I tried to stick to mostly the aftermath
of the battle, rather than in-depth troop movements.
You're welcome.
But there was a captain called William Siborn,
who made a huge model of the Battle of Waterloo,
15 years after it had happened.
And he spent eight weeks on the battlefield itself,
just researching.
He took seven years to make it.
He made, well, he certainly put 80,000 model soldiers
on this 400-square-foot model.
It's massive.
- In a way, though, what we've got is one guy going
to the battlefield saying, "Okay, I need to know
where everyone was so I can make the model."
But at the same time, all of the locals are coming in,
moving all the bodies around and taking all the bodies
and stuff.
That must have been really awkward.
- Yeah, I'm sure he was very--
And actually, 15 years afterwards was around the time
they were doing the sugar harvesting.
And he interviewed dozens of soldiers saying,
"Where were you at 7 p.m. on the 18th of June, 1815?"
But he really went into detail.
And then he assumed the government was gonna pay for it
'cause it was his life's work.
And the government kind of had said we'll pay for it,
but kind of didn't.
And Wellington was annoyed 'cause the model had
too many Prussians is the theory.
So he died poor and broke just with this 400-square-foot model
of the Battle of Waterloo at 7 p.m.
- Do we still have it?
- It's in the National Army Museum now,
which is in Chelsea.
So it does still exist.
Yeah, yeah.
- It's incredible.
- It's awesome, but it kind of ruined his life.
- Yeah, wow.
- We should probably say Waterloo happened
because Napoleon had been dealt with,
defeated by the combined Allied powers,
and he'd been sent away to Elba,
where he was given, which is a little island off Italy,
where he was given command of the island.
He was also given a small army and navy.
What are you thinking?
This is the best military commander in history.
He's got a small army and navy.
He can't possibly--
- Who gave that to him, the British?
- I don't, I think it was like a sort of Allied decision.
Like they just said, we'll just, it's fine.
He'll step down.
He won't want to come back.
- What a weird, like a desert island disk luxury island.
- Elba is not that far away.
That's the crazy thing.
Like it's quite close.
I've been there.
It's quite close to Italy.
It's really easy to get back.
So obviously he does a few, like he improves Elba a bit,
just sort of fixes it in various ways.
Then he comes back, like straight back,
but only with a small army.
- Only with a small army.
- And then, so this is in 1815.
It's called the Hundred Days between him,
like leaving Elba and getting to where he's eventually defeated
because everyone has suddenly scrambled back into action.
But, and the Bourbon monarchy has been restored.
It's Louis the 18th, I think,
who's been put on the throne of France.
Slightly embarrassing, obviously.
He's just sort of sidled back onto the throne.
And as soon as Napoleon lands in France,
Louis the 18th sends two big forces led by two marshals
who like Napoleon's generals were all called marshals.
Sends two marshals.
As soon as they meet Napoleon, they change sides.
Like instantly, he just says, look, it's me.
It's Napoleon, Bonie's back.
Let's go. - Come on, guys.
- And they just change sides.
And he's in charge of France again.
And the monarchy flees again.
And then all of Europe has to wake up and scramble and,
you know, draw him to Waterloo and try and defeat him.
- And they're basically led by a duo of Wellington and Blucher.
And they were really different characters.
- How are they?
- So Wellington sounds like a bit of a dick, maybe,
to hang out with, but really good general.
So his forces didn't really love him
because he was quite cold, quite arrogant.
- The iron duke.
- The iron duke, yes.
You're never going to love someone called the iron duke
go to parties with him.
Whereas Blucher was more very brave,
not a good strategist, didn't plan ahead.
- He was the disco bald duke.
- Exactly, yes.
So, and he was called Papa Blucher by his men.
And they loved and trusted him.
But yeah, Wellington quite cocky, apparently.
- And the interesting thing about Blucher,
one of the interesting things is he invented a type of boot.
Didn't he?
So just like Wellington did.
So Wellington had his boot.
- Hang on, that's not his boot, is it?
The Wellington boot?
- It's named after him.
Yeah, and he was--
- But he didn't invent it.
- Well, yeah, I'm sure he wanted--
- He wanted people to have a special kind of boot
to go into battle with.
- Yeah, right, yeah.
- And it was two boots each.
- Yeah.
- One of us had three.
(all laughing)
- And he, yeah, he didn't do the designing
or the making of it or anything like that,
but it was his idea, I think.
- Yeah.
- And there were wellies.
- Yeah, yeah.
- They were proper boots.
- Yeah, it wasn't like a farmer.
- Yeah, that's what I'm thinking of, but yeah, yeah.
- Imagine squelching into--
(all laughing)
- Or like some shiny ones,
like with rainbows on like you get in Glastonbury.
(all laughing)
- Napoleon actually lost
'cause he wore his kitten heels on the day of the battle
and he got stuck in some mud.
- So he was in Crocs.
- Blucher had a boot, too.
- Yeah, so Wellington had his boot,
but they weren't, that hadn't been invented
at the Battle of Waterloo, but Blucher's boot had been.
So the Blucher army went in in Blucher's boots,
but the Wellington army didn't go out in Wellington boots
'cause they hadn't been invented.
- The idea of generals having their kind of their merch.
- It's a good idea.
- You can imagine the final speech
on the morning of the battle.
And if you put in the offer code Blucher,
you'll get 10 marks off the price of your first pair.
(all laughing)
- But no, it was this huge,
like it was 200,000 men crammed into about five square miles.
Like it was a very, very, very deadly battle,
like lots of casualties, hence all the bodies.
I think 50,000 were killed or seriously injured.
It was really sort of bloody.
- It took place over about four days.
Waterloo was on the final day
and there were three small battles leading up
to the big final confrontation.
- And not in Waterloo as well, we should say.
- No, nearby, yeah.
- It's like with Roswell, with the alien incident.
- All right.
- It was because the aliens were brought back to Roswell,
it's called Roswell.
- Oh my gosh.
- This was the information was sent from Waterloo.
- I thought it was safe from you.
I thought this fact was, like this is a damn proof fact.
There's no way he's gonna be able to get onto yesterday.
- So the tripod came down onto the battlefield.
That's interesting.
So that was where his office was.
- That's where they were stationed, yeah.
And basically, as it says, it's like the official report
had the date line and the location on it
and Waterloo was the location and so forth, yeah.
- Which was close.
- It was super close.
- Roswell was right next door to Corona, you know.
- Corona?
- That's where, yeah.
- What?
- I know, right?
- Get out.
- No one else has been pushing this conspiracy
like I have, so I'm glad we're all aboard.
- But yes, aliens gave us the Corona virus.
- Wow.
- This was the end of the Napoleonic War, or was it?
There was actually another battle afterwards
which France won in the Napoleonic War.
So France won the last battle of the Napoleonic War.
- Get out.
- The Battle of Wavre.
And what happened was it was French reinforcements
coming to Waterloo and they met up with the Prussians
and there was a big battle, but what they didn't realize
is the Battle of Waterloo had already finished.
And so Napoleon had lost, but there was another battle
going on to bring reinforcements.
France won that.
Brilliant, let's go.
Oh, it's finished.
- Wow, so that is so interesting.
I didn't know that.
- Yeah.
- So technically, if you win the last battle of the war,
does it mean that you win the whole war?
- I reckon if it's like winner stays on.
- It's last goal wins.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Are we trying to get more Frenchness for this war?
It's good, isn't it?
- I'm not counting it.
- Andy, you've probably got a few more minutes.
- Stop, stop, stop.
- I'll never talk about Waterloo ever again.
- There are a few Joan of Arc types at Waterloo,
a few women, yes.
They seem to be mostly on the Prussian side actually.
There was a woman called Eleanor Prochaska
and Friederike, I think she called herself Frederick,
wasn't her actual name, Kruger.
And they just cut their hair.
- Freddy Kruger.
(laughing)
- Did I not?
- Oh my God.
- Wow.
- Is that real?
- I'm trying to welcome Dan back into the conversation.
- Yeah, Freddy Kruger, that was where he got famous.
- That's so good, 'cause there's also a famous water skier
called Freddy Kruger.
- Really?
- There's this person at the battle.
We're only one away from an only connect question.
(laughing)
- Oh, wow.
Well, there you go, Victoria Corrin, if you're listening.
Frederick Kruger cut her hair, went and fought at Waterloo,
gave herself away, apparently one account said
when she spoke in a particularly high voice suddenly.
- I'll find you in your dreams, I'm coming for you.
- My God.
- Don't go for it.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that puffer fish
don't have a functioning stomach,
so they digest food in their rectum.
Much like President Garfield.
- Yes. - Oh, wow.
- I hadn't made that connection.
- Or those people on a boat one time, you know,
who like put food up the bum.
- Did they?
- I don't remember this.
- Do you remember?
- I don't think Hannah was there.
- This is one of your yacht parties, isn't it?
(all laughing)
- It was they put turtle blood up their anus.
- Oh, yes, the shipwrecked family.
- That's right, the enemas, the total enemas.
- So we've got President Garfield, those guys,
the puffer fish were just one away
from an only connect question, if you're listening, Victoria.
- So do they like President Garfield
put the food up their bums?
- No, they do not.
- Okay.
- Um, puffer fish get the name because they puff up.
- Yeah.
- If they're in danger, they make themselves much bigger
by sucking in a load of water and just becoming a big ball.
Now, in order to do that, they've lost their stomach
because the stomach would get in the way of this skill.
- You mean evolutionarily or just every time they pop up
their stomach disappears.
- Evolutionarily or by design from God.
They have lost their stomach.
And so the way that they eat is they get the food
into their body and they absorb the nutrients
when it's going down their throat,
when it's going in their intestines
and also when it's going into their rectum.
They have enzymes that break down the food.
They have, you know, they have an acidic mucus
all the way down the digestive system.
But the reason that they don't have a stomach
is to have a stomach you need to have a sphincter
on either side and it to be a bag.
And they don't have that particular thing.
- They've only got one sphincter.
- They only have one sphincter.
- In that system.
- And then the mouth is the other one.
- It's really interesting when you think, you know,
we're all just a bag with two sphincters.
- We are, really.
Yeah, we're a Chutira stone.
As in the mouth comes first and then the anus comes
and then all the other bits come.
- And there's the tube stuff.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- There's humbling stuff, isn't it?
- It is, yeah.
But they're very, I didn't really, they're awesome.
I really like puff fish.
- Puff fish are awesome.
- Yeah, they're great.
- That's so cool.
- They're quite silly, I think.
- They're very silly.
- I think as a defense mechanism,
I think inflating yourself like a balloon rather.
And I think basically they had to evolve that
because they're not very good swimmers.
And so instead they just puff themselves up to this
too big to eat, like a comedy animal.
- They're the only fish that my daughter can recognize,
the only species of fish.
- Oh, really?
- Oh, wow.
- That's a fact.
- That's a good fact.
- As in if you give her a picture of loads of fish,
she'll recognize that they're fish,
but if puff fish will go puff a fish.
Pfft.
- Oh, nice.
- I used to have a puff a fish as a kid as a pet.
- No.
- Yeah.
- Really?
- I was dead, but I was given it in Hong Kong on the--
- Was it inflated?
- Yeah, it was.
It was inflated and a guy had caught it
and I went, it was a fishing village in Hong Kong
and he gave it to me.
It was dead.
He gave it to me in a bag.
And I brought it home and I kept it in it.
We had a fridge for some reason in the hallway
of the building that we lived in.
So it was like on the group staircase.
So I used to go every day and visit my puff a fish
and just open it and see it.
- What the hell?
- Does it count as a pet if it's dead?
- I think I, because I visited it, that's how I count it.
I kind of like, yeah.
And it's stunk out the whole building.
I didn't recognize 'cause I was so used to the smell
and no one could locate it
where the smell was coming from.
- How could they not locate it if it was in the fridge?
When someone else opened the fridge, didn't they say?
- Well, I guess no one did.
No one opened the fridge.
- No one ever opened the fridge.
- 'Cause it was our fridge.
No one touched our fridge.
- Right, right, right.
- So how old were you?
- I was about eight.
- So how come your parents opened the fridge, right?
Did your parents never say, you know what, Dan?
I think it's time you threw out this dead puff a fish.
- They just didn't tell them.
So they just didn't know where this thing was coming from.
- Probably after a while it would have got a load
of flies and worms and stuff in it, right?
- It was pretty rotten, yeah.
- So your parents would have to, after a while go,
"Dan, I've got bad news.
Your dead puff a fish is alive."
(all laughing)
- Yeah, so true.
- Anna, William, I've actually got a puff a fish anecdote.
It's not as good as these twos.
My daughter can recognize/I used to have a dead pet one.
But I was at an antiques market a couple of months ago.
And one of the items on sale there was a puff a fish lamp
where someone had inflated puff a fish
and then, I don't know how, got a light bulb into it.
- Oh, one of the sphinxes probably opened together.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But I didn't buy it.
- Did you not?
- I don't regret not buying it
'cause it was a pretty macabre thing.
- Wow, this is amazing.
So Andy's got a puff a fish story.
You've got one, I've got one.
If we can get Anna one, we'll have another question.
(all laughing)
- This is gonna be the most esoteric episode
of an already quite esoteric show.
- All right, tune in for my spin-off documentary.
Anna finds a puff a fish story.
- Anna and the blowfish.
Is the blowfish the same as a puff a fish?
- Yes.
- And they're the same as Fugu.
- Yeah, I think the Fugu are traditionally dead as well,
but less rotten than Dan.
- 'Cause this is one of their defenses, the puffing up,
but it's not their only defense
because they're incredibly poisonous.
- Is it a defense though, if you can't use,
they can't shoot their livers out of themselves, right?
Which is what is most of the toxins.
- I believe not.
- Yeah, but it's a defense.
- The advertiser that you're poisonous
with what you look like, I suppose.
- Yeah, okay, right.
- You know, there's a thing in Japan where,
so puff a fish and Fugu,
there's different species of puff a fish, right?
I think there's like 200 species
and they all look a bit different.
Fugu is a big one in Japan.
It's a delicacy.
We all know it to be dangerous,
if not prepared by the correct chef
because of all these toxins and poisons.
And you do get trained as a chef.
You've got to be over 20,
you've got to spend years in an academy doing it.
- Can I just quickly say?
You don't.
- Exactly, this is the problem.
- It's regionally specific.
So in some areas of Japan, you have to, as Dan says,
you do a written test, you do a practical test,
you do all sorts of stuff.
Another bit of Japan, just go to a lecture.
- Yeah, you can do it within an hour.
- Can you do it on Zoom?
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- You can get a license.
- 'Cause that'd be great, 'cause you could just watch it
and then put your camera so no one can see you
and then you can just go to the pub.
- Yeah, so chefs keep wanting to have regulations put in place.
So I read an article, 2009,
hundreds of people were poisoned
by badly prepared Fugu, 34 of them died.
- Wow.
- Yeah, there was one guy,
sorry, there was a group of men in Northern Japan
who, when they ate grilled blowfish testicles,
found themselves very, very ill
because of unlicensed chefs.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- But what?
- I just realized I've made a mistake.
That was before the new license system in 2019.
- Yeah, so yes.
- It used to be regionally specific.
I believe maybe now you can no longer
just go to the Zoom lecture.
- And that was for a long time
and thousands of people were dying.
- What's wrong with us though?
It can't, is it curiosity?
It can't be that good.
What's wrong with us that we want to eat it?
- I think it's tasty.
- It can be that tasty.
- Gives you a bit of a buzz.
It makes your mouth tingle.
- But I think, and the liver's the best bit
and you're not allowed to eat that, I don't think.
Odal, are you?
Even if you're serving Fugu.
- I think you have to remove the,
well, it's meant to be.
- 'Cause they serve, so like in 2011,
there was a woman in a restaurant
who specifically said to the chef,
please give me the liver.
I know you're not supposed to, but do it.
And I think they do, so he did.
And then she ended up going to hospital.
- And there was a famous actor,
a Japanese Kabuki theater actor
called Mitsuguro Bando, the eighth.
And in 1975, he went to a Fugu restaurant
and he persuaded one of the chefs
that he had developed a natural resistance to the toxin.
He built it up and he asked the chef,
can you do me some Fugu livers?
And he got the plate, he ate four Fugu livers,
then he died.
- Yeah, right.
- So I don't think he had,
whether he thought he had built up a resistance or not,
he hadn't.
- The other thing is that these days
you can make harmless Fugu.
So they get the poison by eating the special bacteria.
So if you can make your Fugu fish grow up in a place
where this bacteria doesn't exist,
then it's not gonna be poisonous.
- It's amazing. - It's not the same.
It's not the same.
- Well, as chefs say, it seems insane.
We can now breed Fugu that tastes the same,
but don't poison you.
And one chef was asked about it and said,
no, I'm not gonna serve it.
It's obviously more than a little exciting
to go to a restaurant knowing it might be
the last meal you ever eat.
Where's the enjoyment in eating something
with no risk in it?
- Yeah, I completely agree.
You know how you said it's different regionally
in some places, in Shimono-Seki area,
it's not called Fugu, it's called Fuku.
- Oh. - Whoa.
- Seems not appropriate.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause that's actually your last words
to the chef when you're done.
(all laughing)
I don't think you know that you've been poisoned
until about 25 minutes later.
- Yep.
- So I think you've got time to get the bill.
You have to pay it.
And then you realize, as you're leaving,
hang on a second.
- As someone who's been to a puff fish restaurant,
they are very quick with the bill.
(all laughing)
- So you only had a starter 'cause there was nothing
that wasn't Fugu on the menu.
I think I've mentioned this before.
- And you thought you were gonna have the chicken nuggets
and they were the testicles?
- It was the testicles.
But now that I've heard that the testicles
are poisonous and killed someone,
I'm kind of glad that I didn't.
- They're served separately often.
They often have like a soul Fugu meal.
- Yeah. - Right.
- And it starts off with some sashimi slices.
So just little raw slices arranged to look like a crane
about to take flight, which is a symbol of longevity.
- How I run it.
(all laughing)
- And then you get some Fugu stew,
Fugu and rice porridge and hot sake
with grilled Fugu fin in it and the testicles on the side.
- And Fugu jelly and Fugu ice cream.
- Oh, lovely.
It was the Fugu hundreds of thousands
and then a Fugu mint.
(all laughing)
- Have you ever tried puffer fish semen,
which is another delicacy?
- Okay.
- No.
- Do you not have mayonnaise with your nuggets?
(all laughing)
- Is it poisonous?
- Probably.
- I don't have no idea.
No, I think that--
- It's milk in the UK, milk on toast.
- Yeah, it was delicious.
- What?
- Milks is a relatively common, not these days.
- No.
- Like a hundred years ago
in the northeast of England, you would eat milk for sure.
- Stop it.
- No, definitely.
- So I think my mom always eats and then goes,
it's ridiculous that people don't have this
every day these days.
(all laughing)
- Come by actually, in my testicle in Metro.
- Come by.
- You know, Milton Keynes,
that was named after the economist Keynes, John Keynes.
- He was ejaculated on by a fish.
(all laughing)
- And named the town after him.
- Oh, God.
- That is torture.
(all laughing)
- I feel like we should talk about live pufferfish.
- Yeah, okay.
- 'Cause they're quite nice when they're alive
and they make crop circles.
- Oh, yes.
- Which are stunning and worth looking at.
And we only realized this recently.
So we found these--
- It's amazing they can get that far in land.
It's stunning.
(all laughing)
- Well, there is a theory that the Roswell aliens
actually were pufferfish.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, there's not.
But they do make these extraordinary,
they look like perfect fossils.
You know, you get the typical--
- Like ammonites.
- Like ammonite fossils.
Yeah, on the floor of the ocean,
they're perfectly symmetrical.
They're concentric rings with kind of spokes
coming out from them and beautiful patterns.
And they were discovered in 1995
and no one knew what they were.
They were just these mysterious things
on the floor of the ocean.
And it was only in 2013 that someone was down there
doing a dive off the coast of Japan somewhere
and went, hey, there's this pufferfish
flapping its fins with the, and making this pattern.
- Was it a mating thing,
or is that a different situation?
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah, 'cause there was an amazing answer
for a piece on it, wasn't it?
- So the female gets to sit
in the middle of these concentric circles
and if she likes it, she gives an egg up
and he gives a sperm up.
And in about one second, that's mating done.
- Yeah.
- And if not, she doesn't.
- There is one theory that all she cares about
is how much sand is there.
- Yeah, right.
- And she doesn't care about all these beautiful
kind of circles and that.
And the fact is that the circles are a byproduct
of the fact that you have to do that
to get all the sand into the middle.
You just have to do it in a certain order.
- So is it like, it's like the equivalent of,
actually, my wife isn't interested in my model railway.
It's that I've got a nice home,
which the model railway is in.
- It's a really good fight.
Yeah, yeah, that's almost.
- Foolish analogy.
- I've got some questions to ask.
I've got to go home, actually.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is, as there used to be no way
of duplicating a record,
one of the best selling songs of the 1890s
had to be recorded over 10,000 times by the same singer.
- That's amazing.
- What is air in the recording studio, it must have been.
- Well, days, eight days, eight days,
and weeks and months,
because basically every single record
that you used to make back in the day was a master copy.
That's what got sold.
There was no way of then recording that
into being another record.
In the way that we have now, yeah.
- So it's quite nice in a way
because your record's different to everyone else's.
- Yeah, exactly.
You literally have a bespoke record.
- If there's a little fart in the background,
that's just for you.
- Yeah, so there were no mics or no amplifiers.
You had to just yell into the horn of the phonograph.
And if you were particularly wealthy,
you were able to get four or five horns around you.
And so you could make up to five copies of a single song.
So it's thought that the best selling single of the 1890s
was sung by a guy who was an African-American
called George Washington Johnson.
And he was a street singer on the New York streets.
He was just doing it for pennies.
And he used to sing a couple of songs
which were very, very backward and racist.
And I think that's why people didn't mind
a black singer being that well distributed.
It was called, you know, one was, what were they called?
- You don't need to read that out.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- They did some lyrics.
Yeah.
No, but there was a lot of,
it was a lot of taking himself down within the song.
But one of the songs, which was the laughing song,
that was the biggest song of the time.
It sold 50,000 copies.
So it said that he did copies
that were like four to five horns in one go.
And it sold 50,000.
So at minimum, he sang it 10,000 times.
- Amazing.
- But it was probably more than, yeah.
- Was the laughing song just laughing?
- No, that was the chorus.
- So people might know it actually.
I reckon people listen to this, some of them will know it
because it was covered loads of times,
especially in the UK, a slightly different version called "The Laughing Policeman" song.
- Oh yeah! - Which I love as a child.
- Me too! - Well, it's exactly the same.
It's the same song, but obviously they removed all of the racist stuff
and replaced it with a fat policeman who goes, "Wah! Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha."
And that's the song. - It's great. - Yeah.
- But when I was reading about this, I thought, "How... I can't believe the things that entertained people in the 1890s, and now you're right. We found that very entertaining in our childhood. Good on him."
- Yeah, Johnson, George Washington Johnson, he had quite a sad end because they worked out how to replicate music, and he no longer had a job for life, basically.
- Yeah, because there were no royalties. - No, exactly.
- So you got paid for doing your recording, but once they managed to just copy stuff, then you'd never got any money anymore.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Like Spotify of its day. - Yeah.
- Ooh, controversial for our largest distribution outlet. - Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha. - Yeah, he had a... He had a... The middle bit where he was singing the song might have been the only kind of peaceful bit of his life, really, because he was born in 1846 into slavery. He was made to be the best friend of the child of the family, so he sort of had...
- The playmate thing for the white family. - Yeah, so he then was freed, and he went to New York, where he lived in Hell's Kitchen, and he was doing all this stuff where he was sort of, you know, on the street singing. Then this big moment happens where he gets to sing all these songs, as James points out, then they work out how to duplicate it. So his career is dead after, you know, sitting in a booth 20,000 times, minimum, singing this stuff. And then life gets really weird for him, as Andy points out. He was charged with murder. He was never convicted, but he was brought onto it.
- Yeah. - He was brought onto him.
- Both of his wives died suddenly when living with him, and yeah, he was charged with trying to murder one of them, well, actually murdering one of them. I did read a report of an altercation he had with his wife, and this was in the Earth newspaper in 1899, and its headline was "Too Much Whistling," because his main thing was whistling, right?
- Yeah. - And he was famous on the streets of New York for whistling. And it said, "George Rottington Johnson is in trouble," because he couldn't restrain his disposition to whistle at all times.
He crawled with his wife, because she got tired of him whistling all over the house, so she shot him, and he thumped her, and died the next night. So that was a story in what I assume was a tabloid equivalent. He whistled too much. She shot him. He hit her.
- And then she died. - And then she died.
- Right. - In the olden days, you could just make a living from being really good at whistling.
- I was just thinking that. - Yeah, but you don't have to code or anything. - No.
- You could just whistle. - There was a guy called Freeman Davis, who was known as Brother Bones, who was a shoeshine boy, and people noticed how good he was at whistling. And he would also play his shoeshine instruments, like the spoons you might do.
And he became really famous, and his whistling became the theme song of the Harlem Club Trotters.
There was Sibyl Sanderson Fagan, who was one of the most famous whistlers in America in the 1920s, and she would do whistling of birdsong, so you would buy a vinyl and it would just be her pretending to be a thrush or a mockingbird or something.
She left her husband, who was a playwright called Eugene P. Bardin, because she claimed that he had drugged her on her wedding day. And so she got married because she said that she'd been drugged into getting married.
- He drugged her into the marriage? I thought he meant after the wedding had happened, then he drugged her. Oh my goodness.
- There was Fred Lowry, who was a professional whistler in the 40s and 50s, who was blinded by Scala Fever at the age of two, then became a whistler, and then he later went away from pop music and became a religious whistler.
- Oh, religious whistler. - Yeah, he would go to churches and whistle hymns instead of whistling pop songs. - Nice.
- But yeah, it's just amazing that you've got all these people who, all they could do was whistle. I'm not all we could do is podcast, so it's... - Exactly, yeah, yeah.
- I can whistle. - Oh yeah? Let's hear your thrush. - Oh my thrush. Oh shit, I've got thrush.
- Well, there wasn't the first Eurovision. The Half Time Act was a troop of whistlers called the Rossignols, I think, yeah.
- Oh, that means Nightingale in French. - Oh, there we go. Okay, well, that is all coming together.
- Yeah, yeah, so it's a big deal. - If you say in French "J'ai les Rossignols", which I think means "I have Rossignols",
it means there's a problem with your car, because it's like you have Nightingales in your engine and it's making a weird tweeting noise.
- Nice. - The earliest sound recording we have, we actually only heard a few years ago, but it was from way earlier than we thought.
It was like 20 years before Edison in 1857, and it was a French guy called Edouard-Lon Scott de Matam V, and he basically recorded sound,
but he didn't know how to play it back. He hadn't invented the instrument to transmit it in, so he just recorded it onto a bit of paper.
- That takes a lot of trust when you go to the dragons. Not honestly, I have recorded sound, just can't hear it. It's fine.
- You can show them the paper and give it, this would sound amazing if you try to imagine it, and we managed to engineer it in 2008 to play.
- Wow, his piece of paper. - His piece of paper is 1860 piece of paper.
- Indicated. - Yeah, it was covered in soot and the sound waves were etched in.
- Vinyl is PVC, and that was invented or first synthesized by a guy, a German chemist called Eugene Bauman in 1872, and he had been making some vinyl chloride in a flask and had just left it on a shelf for a few days,
maybe a few weeks, the sunlight had got on it, and then there was a white compound in there, and he thought, I wonder what this is, and that turned out to be PVC.
- Wow. - Did he then stick his arm in the flask to try and get it out, and it formed a sexy PVC glove, and he realized this has huge implications for the erotic clothing industry.
- Well, that is the story, that's really what happened. Eugene Bauman also identified the sauce for the smells in urine, and proved the active ingredients in your thyroid gland, which is what stops you from getting goiters.
- Oh. - So just a few things about him. - Wow, what a range. - It's all chemistry. - What do you lead with, though? - On the CV.
- Oh, I know why Pee smells, I know why Piss smells. - If you're sat next to someone at a wedding, and they say, what do you do? You say, I'm a chemist, and they go, oh, have you chemisted anything that I might know, then what is for a smell?
- Have you ever smelled some piss? I know why. - Your best man is very rude. - Oh, dear.
- I don't think we've ever mentioned Chichester Bell before, because I didn't know about him anyway. - Is that person? - He's Alexander Graham Bell's brother. - Stop it.
- Really? - He's also a phonograph pioneer. - Chichester Bell, what a name. - He invented the earliest voicemail. Round about the time his brother, Alex, was working on phones. Yeah, he invented voicemail, and the way it worked was, it was a phonograph cylinder that you recorded your voice onto.
- So the grooves are all in the right place, and then you just posted it to your friend. - The problem is that they would get it, and they'd be like, oh, who's it from? And they go, Chichester Bell, and they go, fuck off. That's just spam, mate.
- OK, it is time for our final fact of the show, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the US government maintains a database of dad jokes.
- What an excellent fact. - There we are, we're off the blocks again. - There we go.
- Three guys absolutely straining for a dad joke there. - I don't know why I presented this fact, because there's promises to be held in the next 20 minutes with you guys.
But this is on a website that's run by the Office of Family Assistance, which is a government resource for fathers, basically, for families, and they have a website within that called the National Responsible Fatherhood Clearinghouse.
And if you go to that website, which I would recommend, then you can click on dad resources, and you can submit your own dad jokes, and you can click, give me a joke, and they'll give you a dad joke.
You can click, give me another, they'll give you another. I don't know how long it goes on for, or I sat there for about half an hour.
- If you go to the mum section of this website, is it all practical stuff? Like how to feed a baby, how to change a baby, how to keep a baby alive.
- It's a load of your mum jokes.
- And yeah, I thought that was really interesting. And I guess the idea is that being a father is perhaps something people need help with, of course, as they do with all the bits of parenting.
And it's a useful skill to have in your back pocket as a dad, being able to whip out a really bad, really inoffensive joke, which seems to basically be the definition is that they're bad and they're not offensive.
- Yeah, so they give you a bunch of the jokes with the reveals on the site. All right, so here's the first one that came up that I saw. What do you call a man with a rubber toe?
- Ah, Roberto.
- Roberto, yes.
- I don't think that's a dad joke, actually. I would say, so my definition of a dad joke is a joke where it is in response to something a child often says, and you always repeat it all the time, all the time, all the time.
So for instance, Anna's mum joke, which is, can you turn on the light and then your mum goes and flirts with the light and she's like, are you turned on yet?
- Yes.
- I think that's a dad joke because it's something that kids will always say.
- I have an actual dad joke that I do, and I've been doing for six years now, every single time it's said, and it's whenever it's kind of getting to the evening and Fenella says, can you draw the curtains?
- Okay.
- I always say.
- Can I have a pencil?
- I'd love to, but I don't have a pencil.
- Yeah, that's a dad joke, I think.
- Interesting, I think they're two strounds of dad-jokism, which is a complex being, I agree that is one, but then I think, I remember, you know, my dad's whole jokes and they seem to very much fall into the dad-joke category of what does a dog call the thing on top of a house?
- Ruff.
- Would he regularly say it?
- Yeah, I think these are things that you regularly say.
- I kind of feel like they're more cracker jokes, like Christmas cracker jokes.
- Well, there's a thin line, there's a really nice theory about why dad jokes are good. This is great.
- Why, they're good?
- Well, no, not, sorry, why they happen.
- They are good.
- Well, no, I mean your one about the curtains was amazing.
- Another pencil, please.
- Brilliant.
- Gets a laugh every time.
- So the idea is that, this is from the British Psychological Society. I personally, I'm not sure I buy it, but I like it.
It's that by continually telling their children jokes that are so bad they're embarrassing, fathers may be pushing their children's limits of how much embarrassment they can handle.
- That's great.
- Showing your child that embarrassment isn't fatal because the child is mortified here.
And if you're, you know, your child is adolescent, which feels again a bit like the ship has sailed in terms of, you know, dad jokes normally when a child is five or five.
But there's a, the sort of theory builds because the theory is if your child has been exposed to years of awful jokes by this point and has shown that dad can cope with people not caring that people think dad is an idiot,
the children will be able to be themselves better.
- How interesting.
- But it's more for the benefit of the dad.
- I don't know. I feel like, well, James, I feel like you wrote this up in a book for one of the QI books.
- I did, yeah, QI books. So I read quite a few theories, that one included.
Another one about why they happen is when you have a kid who's two years old, like I do almost, basically they'll laugh at anything, like literally anything.
If I say to my daughter, like she wants to read Mogg, and I say, do you want to read Moog? She will piss herself laughing.
And then if I'm like, oh, do you want to read the very hurri-coud-de-poudre?
She'll just find it the funniest thing in the world, right?
And the idea being-
- You're making her racist against buildings.
- I'm still not over water leaving.
- It's very true.
- The thing is, the kids will laugh at almost anything.
And then as a dad, that kind of builds your confidence. And then as you get older, you're like, this idiot will laugh at everything.
And she always laughed at whatever I said, Moog instead of Mogg.
So I'm going to keep doing it. And you just keep doing it and keep doing it.
And then as the kids get older, they realize this isn't funny at all.
And that's when they realize that they're dad jokes.
- Wow. Does the dadness of the joke depend on the child understanding it's not funny?
- I think someone has to be on the outside knowing that it's not funny. It might be my wife.
- She would know it's a dad joke. But the other thing is like quite often they're kind of wordplay-ish.
And there's a theory that by doing this wordplay again and again and again, it helps to teach language skills.
- Yeah.
- I'll buy that.
- Yeah, exactly that.
And I think also it teaches them a joke structure and it just brings funniness to the house.
It's just a great way to keep things funny in the house.
- I still think that I really like them. I'm very fond of them.
I think by definition, a dad joke isn't funny.
That's what it is. It's a joke that's kind of predictable.
So I read an article by a linguist about dad jokes.
And I thought the example that she used was not a dad joke for me because I thought it was actually funny.
- It wasn't the Bunga Bunga one, was it?
We can't have that again. The left is the last time.
- Oh, it's privately inoffensive, okay? It doesn't cross that boundary.
But the joke is that a man comes up to a widow at the funeral of his old friend and he says to the widow,
"Do you mind if I say a word?" And she nods and the man clears his throat and says gently,
"Plethora." And the wife smiles sadly and replies,
"Thanks. That means a lot."
- I think that's a very good joke.
- It's a good joke. It's too good. It's too good.
- Can I give you some examples of dad jokes?
When I was writing this article for the QI book, I asked my followers on Twitter for some dad jokes.
So I'll give you the kid saying something and you have to say what the dad says as a joke.
- Oh, yeah, okay.
- So Adam Sear said that he would say, "Are you all right, dad?"
- No, I've got a left-hand side as well.
- No, I'm half left.
- Chris Emerson, our friend Chris Emerson, said he would say to his dad, "I'm off."
- Off what?
- Off com.
- And the dad would reply, "I wondered what that smell was."
- Oh, that's good.
- And Cardinal Grumpy, I think perhaps not his real name.
- Senior prelate in the Catholic Church.
- If they said, "I'm thirsty," so their dad, what would be the reply?
- I'm dad. Nice to meet you.
- Pretty close.
- Oh, no, it's Wednesday.
- Oh, put them together.
- Hi, I'm Wednesday. Chased the date.
- Friday. No, you're not. You're Friday.
- You're pretty much that. Who else is Friday?
Okay, I'm going to give it you. So he says, "Dad, I'm thirsty."
Dad says, "Please to meet you Thursday. I'm Friday, and he's Robin St. Crusoe."
- Oh.
- Wow, that's a really well-read kid.
- Do you want to hear one of the first-ever "Your Mum" jokes?
- Yeah, go on.
- Was it like Babylonian? Is it like as far back as that?
- There is one, and it's from a partial bit of text.
- So it's not really clear what the entire joke is.
- Right.
- But there is another one from 100AD, which is Rabbi Eliezer,
was said to have gone and interrupted a man who had been reading a banned text,
which was Ezekiel 23, by asking him,
"Why don't you go out and proclaim the abominations of your mother?"
- Is that a "Your Mum" joke?
- It's a prototype.
- Yeah, absolutely a "Your Mum" joke.
- Did you find it extremely funny? Judging by the look on your face.
- The sad thing is, I'm afraid, for the listeners,
is that you'll all now remember all of these really bad jokes that we've told,
more than you remember a good joke,
because studies show that you remember bad jokes more than good jokes
because of the way they work, because they are predictable.
The reason that we can kind of guess the endings to the dad jokes that James asked for
is that they are formulaic, good for teaching kids how these patterns work,
but the definition of good humor that makes you actually laugh is that you subvert that,
like pull the rug out from under someone's feet.
It's unexpected. So you never remember them.
So it's so annoying. You'll only ever remember shit jokes.
- So it's like, are you all right, dad?
No, I have a terrible, incurable disease,
and I won't be with you in a week's time.
You got that from the new Ricky Gervais special, didn't you?
That subverts the non.
- It does. I think it does still have to be funny.
- All right, OK.
They exist in other languages.
In France, as a child, if you say what, what, what, what,
they wouldn't understand you because they're French.
But if they say it in French, they say "quoi".
And any self-respecting dad will reply "foi",
"quoi", "foi", "foi", "foi", which means hairdresser, "quoi", "foi".
And in Spain, if a dad sees some soy milk,
he might say "holla milk, soy papi".
- Lovely. - Yes, very good.
Because "soy" means "I am", so it means "hi, milk", "I'm dad".
- Nice, very nice. - Very nice.
That's the "I'm hungry, hi, hungry, I'm dad"
is in nine states of America the most ticked as used dad joke.
- Oh, nice. - That's a proper dad joke.
OK, this is like the parenting test you get
after your kid's one or something, you're back to the GP.
Please check this box. Can they walk? Can they talk?
How many times have you told this joke?
I nearly got got researching this fact.
It was a report on NPR, obviously really well-respected radio station
and great source of lots of stuff.
And it was about a list of Roman jokes,
ancient Roman jokes that have been found.
And it was a scroll found in an amphitheatre
and they'd done some amazing analysis.
You know the X-ray of scroll and they managed
without unrolling it to scan what's inside.
And it was all these phrases found in Latin
and like a translation was, "Did you hear the rumour about butter?"
"Oh, well, I'm not going to spread it."
I thought you were going to say, "Butter? I hardly knew her."
It was a bit more PG than that, this scroll.
And then I got really far into this article
and then eventually I got to the claim that Caesar had turned up
and addressed a crowd of senators who were angry with him
by asking them, "What did the cucumber say to the pickle?"
And I realised, I looked at the day, it was an April the first article.
And what did he say?
"You mean a great deal to me."
"Oh, good grief."
"Why are you getting your knives out?"
So he did deserve it after all.
It is weird that these exist all around the world though,
this stereotype, or in so many different countries.
Like Japan has old man jokes, which are oyaji,
old man, then gyagu joke.
-Gyagu, like gag? -Yeah, like gag.
That's how they make a lot of words in Japanese,
don't they? They take an English word.
So at the end, in Japanese,
every word has to end with a vowel or an N.
Like very new, yeah, so it's like a new word.
T-shirt too, is T-shirt.
Okay, very easy to guess.
This is like an extremely easy test.
It's not much of a quiz, is it?
Korea, they have middle-aged man jokes,
literally middle-aged man jokes.
Danish has various different versions.
They've got uncle humor, onkel humor.
I would say we've been advertising Babel for quite a long time,
but it seems like you could just say words slightly
in an accent, and that works.
What's the Danish one though?
Because my step-grandfather's Danish,
and he always used to do whatever their version is.
Oh, well, uncle humor is onkel humor,
but for him, I think he would be more far vittagede,
which is grandfather humor.
Father humor, so at the end of every meal,
whenever the waiter came over to get our plates,
they'd say, "Are you finished?"
And he'd say, "No, I'm Danish."
Wow, that is very good.
Would you like some water? No, fish fucking it.
I was a bit young for that, I was eight.
That's a WC Fields joke, isn't it?
Yeah, that's all right.
Guys, do you know what a BJ joke is?
Dude, yeah, I do.
I don't think you do.
BJ joke, so what could it be?
Boris Johnson?
Yeah, it is technically one of those as well, I suppose.
Just shot for bad joke?
It's one of those, it's none of those.
This is in one study, at least,
which seemed to use the officially accepted academic terms for jokes.
This is a 2016 study, because I was looking at whether men and women
do find different jokes funny,
because it's such a gender-based concept, the dad joke.
And so there's a study that looked at whether they did,
and they divided jokes into EJs, AJs and BJs, which are...
Excellent adequate in bed.
It should be that.
It's exaggeration jokes, ambiguity jokes,
and bridging inference jokes.
And so BJs are the bridging inference,
and that basically means that they require you to actually get the joke.
So when you listen to the joke, you have to attribute an intention to another.
So an example would be,
Jack's dream of becoming a writer comes true when his books finally publish.
He asks his friend, "Have you read my book yet?"
His friend said, "Yes, and I bought one."
And Jack happily responded, "Oh, that was you!"
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
Yeah, it's kind of a bad joke that we've sort of all made about the rest books.
That's how you tell them.
You really didn't sell that one at all.
I think even Will would have been like, "I'm sorry, auntie Anna, no."
It wasn't good, was it? I'm sorry.
Why is that a BJ?
Because we're inferring from the joke that he doesn't sell many of his books.
That he's only told one.
And you so thankfully gave him a blowjob.
You did that with every book that you sold.
Didn't you? 10,000 blowjabs.
A bit like George Washington Johnson.
You could do five at the same time. That's the impressive thing.
OK, that's it. That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram @shriberlandjames.
My Instagram is @nosexthinkersjamesharkin.
Andy.
I don't have Instagram, but I'm on Twitter @andrianterab.
Yeah, or if you want to get to us as a group, where do they go, Anna?
You can email podcast@qi.com or you can tweet @nosuchthing.
That's right.
Yep, or you can just go to our website, nosuchthingasafish.com.
All of the previous episodes are up there.
A link to the gateway to the portal that is Club Fish is up there as well.
Do check it out.
What's a really fun bonus episode that's pumped out every fortnight.
Otherwise, just come back here because we'll be back with another episode
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)