(upbeat music)
Hi everyone, welcome to another episode of No Such Things
of Fish.
Andrew Hunter Murray is away on holiday
looking for rare species of moss
or perhaps covering his entire house in solar panels.
I'm not sure what he's doing, but he's not here.
And so in his place, we have the founder of QI, John Lloyd.
Now you'll all know John because he's been on this show
many, many times, but if you're a new listener,
then he is, he's like a master of British comedy
over the last 40, 50 years.
He was instrumental in things like not the nine o'clock news,
black-hatter, QI of course, spitting image.
If you were a fan of that back in the day,
there's a really nice anecdote later on in this episode
where he talks about that.
Basically, he's an all-round genius
and I'm sure you'll enjoy his talents on this week's show.
I should quickly say, because I know he would want me to,
that his son, Harry, who is a good friend of all of us,
he is in a band and they have a new single out.
The band is called Waiting for Smith.
So if you're interested in that,
then go to anywhere where you get your music
or any bit of social media search for Waiting for Smith
and you will find all about that.
Anyway, without further ado,
let us continue with another episode
of No Such Things as a Fish with Mr. John Lloyd
on with a podcast.
(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Things as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Hoburn.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Anna Tyshinski
and John Lloyd.
And once again, we have gathered round the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Lloydy.
- So my fact is that Picasso inhaled his first cigar
on the day he was born.
(laughing)
So Picasso was born at home on the 25th of October, 1881.
He had a very difficult birth
and he was unusually small and undeveloped.
The midwife wrote him off as stillborn.
- Oh no. - Right.
- And literally parked him on a side table
while she looked after his mum.
- Right.
- And it was fortunate because Picasso's uncle,
his father's brother, Salvador Ruiz Blasco,
who was also a doctor, happened to be there.
And he was smoking a cigar as you do in those doors.
- Of course, yep.
- And he strode over and puffed a great waft of smoke
into Picasso's face and the baby went,
(screaming)
- Oh really? - In a horrible face.
- Okay.
- And then he lasered a huge yell and saved his life.
- Wow. - Okay.
- So he didn't enjoy his first smoke.
Like many of us, it sounds like
he didn't embrace it first time round.
- Well, he came round quickly
'cause he was a lifelong smoker.
In fact, he smoked until seven years before his death,
age 91, but tellingly, he never inhaled.
- Is that right?
- So there you are.
- The Bill Clinton.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Yeah, he died in 1973.
- Yeah.
- Which I worked out meant that he could, in theory,
have met Pharrell Williams, the pop star.
- Okay.
- And do you think they would have got along?
- Well, Pharrell was only three days old
when Picasso died and for all that time,
Pharrell was in Virginia and Picasso was in France.
So at least one of them
would have had to make quite a lengthy trip.
- Yes.
- Or a Zoom call.
- A Zoom call, yeah.
- What are you thinking we're missing out on
by them not meeting?
Why them two specifically?
- Well, I just think Pharrell
is a very, very modern day name, right?
- Yes, right.
- And Picasso, for anyone who was born
after he died, like myself,
he feels like someone in the past.
Do you know what I mean?
So I think it's quite surprising
that those two could, in theory, have met.
- And, of course, Virginia, the home of tobacco,
Virginia ready-rubbed and so on.
- What a good point.
- It would have got on really well.
- Yes.
(laughing)
He was baptized Pablo Diego, Jose Francisco de Palo,
Juan Nepum Maceno, Crispiniano Maria de los Remedios,
de la Santissima Trinidad Rui Picasso.
- Actually not, because the priest made--
- Well, you could have said that before I started.
(laughing)
- The priest made a spelling mistake.
- Oh, did he?
- He was supposed to be called Crispiniano,
because St. Crispin's Day, the 25th of October,
was the day he was born.
And the priest made a spelling mistake
and called him Chipriano.
- Chipriano, which is a brand of crisps.
(laughing)
- His first word, there's a legend behind that,
that his mother says, which is that it was pencil.
So he seems like a child of destiny, in a way.
Yeah, I'm not allowed to do the accent
on the show anymore, John,
so I might as well pronounce the English versions.
- Is that like for penis in Spanish as well?
I think it might be.
- Is it?
- Well, pencil means little penis, doesn't it, penicillus?
- Yeah, we'll never know which he was referring to
at the age of one and a half.
- They both could have been quite prescient, couldn't they?
- They were sort of his two leading tools, I would say.
(laughing)
We should say, for anyone who's already switched off,
'cause we're talking about Picasso,
his reputation has taken a bit of a dive,
hasn't it, the last 10 years?
I hadn't quite realized how much his mistresses
were in basically all of his art.
So it was sort of all about his sex life and his shagging.
And a lot of people do criticize the way
that he exploited women and, you know,
people say women were tools to be exploited for his art.
And he did once say, every time I change wives,
I should burn the last one so that, you know,
you can wipe the slate clean.
- The last wife or the last painting?
- The last wife.
- Oh, okay.
And he only actually married twice,
but I think he's referring to all his mistresses then.
- Two types of women, he said, goddesses and doormats.
Yeah.
- One of his early lovers, Francoise Chilot,
is part of one of my favorite facts,
which is that she later married Jonah Salk,
who developed the polio jab.
- Oh, that's a good fact.
- Yeah.
- So she was basically Picasso's muse,
and then she married this guy who saved the world
a little bit really,
'cause so many people were dying of polio in those days.
But people asked her later why she was attracted
to such outstanding men.
And she replied,
"I think I am just as interesting as they.
"Lions mate with lions, they don't mate with mice."
- That's very good.
- But wasn't she the only muse who left him?
- Yes, she was immune to his charms.
She's such a,
she's a nice person to read about
after I suppose all these women who ended up
according to some accounts destroyed.
She just said, "He didn't know me very well at all.
"I'm very secretive, I smile politely, but I don't agree.
"And I didn't invest my narcissism
"in being represented by him.
"I couldn't care less."
- Yeah.
- And walked off.
- She wrote a book about him, a very famous book,
"Life with Picasso."
I actually read it when I was like 15 years old,
I saw it in a library, it's an amazing book.
And it basically caused a lot of problems
when it came out,
because no one wanted to know this side about Picasso.
When it was released,
there were 40 intellectuals who signed a petition
to have it banned and scrapped and pulped.
- But were there intellectuals?
- Yeah, yeah.
- They thought his reputation will--
- Yeah, including one of the major biographers
who wrote numerous volumes on Picasso's life afterwards,
saying that this should be in like a tabloid
as opposed to a book shop.
- Is that John Richardson?
- Yeah, John Richardson.
- From A.R.10 Cats and Scatham.
- Yeah, he was fuming, he was furious.
But interestingly, she was asked about this
in her 90s about this biography.
And she said, "All these men who wrote that
had never met me, didn't know what I was talking about."
And she and John Richardson became really good friends,
despite him slagging it off.
- How interesting.
- Yeah, and you will see her on "Capture Countdown."
- When Rachel Riley's off of a tourniquet.
- Yeah.
And yeah, Richardson argued that his art
was almost parodying the mitchismo of Andalusian males
rather than him actually being like that.
Which I don't believe.
- Yes, very.
- It's a really interesting thing.
I always believe that when you're at work,
if you're going to do it well, you mustn't have an ego.
And I used to say for years and years,
Picasso famously didn't behave terribly well
in all sorts of ways.
But I'm guessing that when he went in front of the easel,
that all went away.
And years later, I found this wonderful quote saying,
"When I enter my studio,
"I leave my personality outside the door
"as a Muslim leaves his slippers outside the mosque."
- He did spend a lot of time at the easel though, didn't he?
Like, it's hard to find the exact number of works
that he did, but it was a lot.
- It's insane.
- 147,800, but that's not exact.
It's...
- That's according to the official website.
Yeah, they've done counting up and they,
and we've lost a lot of it because in his early days,
he used to burn his bits of art to keep his fire going.
- Yeah, along with his wives.
Yeah, they taught them all on the boom fire.
- I worked out that that's one work of art
for every five hours, 25 minutes of his life.
If he started as a baby and carried on going
until he met Pharrell that time.
- Which once you've had your first smoke,
you might as well end up with a paintbrush.
He also was responsible for a major art theft,
which I hadn't realized because we'd mentioned before
on the show that he was accused of stealing the Mona Lisa.
- He was interviewed by the police, right?
- Yes. - He was.
- Yes.
- Because a pollinair, his friend,
shopped him to the police.
- Yes.
- And Picasso then went to court and denied
he'd ever met him, even though he's one of his best friends.
- It's serious.
- It's quite a low moment, isn't it?
In their friendship, in their moral lives.
- That's probably the best indication of the power
that Picasso had that he thought he could jedi his way
through, like...
- The thing was, when he described the person
who actually stole it, the police did a sketch
and the noses on this side of his face
and the eyebrows on this side.
- But there's more to it, isn't there?
- Well, there is more to it, yes, because...
So that was 1911, but actually in 1907,
there were these two Iberian statues
stolen from the Louvre.
And I think there's just been a book written
which puts all the pieces together,
but Picasso had first spotted them in about 1904,
fallen in love with them, told all his mates,
love these statues.
They were put in storage.
Then they disappeared.
Turned out they'd been stolen by this chap called Pierre.
And he was mates with Picasso and the dodgy Apollinaire.
- He was Apollinaire's secretary, I think.
- He was Apollinaire's secretary, yes.
But it turned, basically,
Picasso's lover at the time, Fernanda Olivier,
said that he had all lots of artworks around his house.
And then he had these two statue heads
under some clothes in his wardrobe.
And she asked him about them once and he said,
"Oh, we shouldn't display them anywhere too prominent."
And it turned out to be these two stolen statues
from the Louvre.
- But we assume that Pierre had given them to Picasso.
Maybe Picasso had asked him to steal them.
Some people say that Pierre couldn't have carried them
both out under his coat, which is what he claimed.
So maybe Picasso was there.
- It's a lot easier to steal stuff
from the Louvre in those days, wasn't it?
- I was a piece of this, yeah.
- Yeah, the lousy security, didn't they?
- Yeah, I think there was a story
that Pierre once once said to his girlfriend,
"I'm going to the Louvre today.
Do you want me to pick anything else for you?"
(laughing)
And then ironically, Picasso is the most stolen artist
in history now.
But I think it's largely 'cause he made so much, right?
- You can't help stealing one, you pick up a sketch.
- Yeah, and following the secretary
had something to do with it, I'm sure.
Shifting his stuff back to...
- So even when he was in his 70s and 80s,
he was quite a womanizer, Picasso.
And whenever anyone came to his house who he fancied,
he would make a little sculpture of a little man
with an enormous phallus and then give it to them
as like a love gift.
- Right.
- Did that work a high percentage of the time?
- It didn't work so often because he quite often
did it in front of his wife.
And anyone who'd been given this phallic item
was not allowed back in the house.
'Cause his wife would just be like,
"Well, you're obviously not coming back."
- Yeah, yeah.
- And again, this is going to John Richardson.
- John Richardson.
- To say, given all these sort of anecdotal things
and the naughtiness that he was an extraordinary painter
and those two statues he mentioned inspired him
for Les Demoiselles d'Avignon.
- Yeah, which is a great painting.
- Is described by John Golding, the art critic,
as the greatest painting of the 20th century.
It's so influential.
- It's kind of cool for him to take,
like looking back at it now,
if the ends justify the means,
it's fine that he stole those things
if they inspired those great works.
- Yeah, and no one gave us just about
two random Iberian statues
from 2000 years ago in storage.
- Remind me to not have James as my lawyer.
We were going to do a fact about them
in the podcast the next week.
- He used to make some of his paints as well.
There's a particular brown that he made,
which we only now know what the secret source was.
- HP.
- No, not quite.
- It was his three-year-old daughter's poo.
- Oh, come on, Dan, no.
- Poocasso, they called the article.
Yeah, he used to say that the best feces as well
would be from a mother who the infant was being breastfed.
- Well, I would say that like,
this is a three-year-old child, right?
But definitely the poo of a much younger baby
is a color that you can't really see anywhere else
in the world. - Oh, true, yes.
- I never see the felt tip the same color
as a nappy from a two-month-old.
- Well, you've seen my tie, though, it's very similar.
- Listeners, John is wearing a tie,
which is like 50 shades of feces.
- But nice, orangey baby feces, the harmless kind.
- He also, I mean, we're talking about his paintings,
but he predicted in his own lifetime
that he would be more known for his poetry than his paintings.
- Poocasso. - Yeah, after his death.
He wrote over 300 poems,
and he also wrote two surrealist plays.
- He can't really have believed,
'cause he was incredibly famous for his paintings
throughout his life.
And no one was going, "Do you know what, Poocasso?
"People should make more of your poems.
"Did he really think?" - Well, he just,
he probably thought they'll forget about it one day
and my poems will live on after me.
- I think this is a common theme with artists, though.
You know, rock bands who always pick the wrong songs
gonna be successful and hate the one that's famous.
- Yeah, John Richardson, as always,
they're asking him in interviews about,
"Hey, I've done cuts to this countdown."
And they never ask him about his Poocasso,
but at first they don't.
- But like that author, Karen Doyle, quote,
"You must have touched before that if in 100 years
"I'm remembered just for Sherlock Holmes,
"I would have considered my life a failure."
- Yeah, sorry, mate, embrace it.
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week
is that the national song of St. Helena
was written by a man who had never been there.
He based his lyrics on a postcard that he had seen.
- Incredible.
Let's hear it.
- ♪ God save our great, no ♪
That is the national anthem of St. Helena
because it's a British territory.
- So did he base it on the stamp of the postcard?
- He wrote another anthem called "My St. Helena Island"
and is kind of the de facto anthem.
It's not the official national anthem,
but it's the one that all saints, as they're known as,
in St. Helena would sing.
And it was written by an American
who is better known for his appearances
on the eight out of 10 cats does countdown
called David Mitchell.
- It's stunning.
- David Mitchell, he was nicknamed Old Saddle Bags
and he was a DJ on a sentient island,
which is, I was gonna say nearby, it's not nearby,
but it's the nearest place to St. Helena,
St. Helena's in the middle of the ocean.
He became friends with some people from St. Helena
and they suggested that he writes a song for them.
And he was a bit reluctant to do that
'cause he's never been there,
but they sent him some postcards and he wrote this song.
And that's what happened.
It goes, "My heart is drifting southwards
"to my home down in the sea,
"to the Isle of St. Helena,
"where my loved ones wait for me.
"We're having a lovely time,
"whether it's changeable, food is awful, wish you were here."
(laughing)
- That's great.
- Genius.
- It's really good.
And he recorded them officially, the songs,
and they made records of it.
And he sent a bunch of records
and pictures of himself to St. Helena as part of like,
"Here's the merch that you can have."
But he's not really known anywhere,
even in his hometown, in Memphis.
But yeah, he's someone who's still around.
I mean, it's not that long ago, right?
So--
- I think he's dead, isn't he?
- Oh, okay, the site, I saw.
- I think his family, he's recently dead, I think.
- Right, okay.
- But I might be wrong about that, so I'll check.
- But nobody's blown sick arse smoke in his face yet,
so you can't tell.
(laughing)
- It's interesting in postcards,
because both Matisse and Picasso used postcards
to inspire some of their greatest work.
- Did they?
- So Les Demoiselles d'Avignon, for example,
was based on a postcard that Picasso found, yeah.
- Was it?
I did not know that last night.
- And did you know that it's not the only
national anthem or national song,
'cause it's not strictly the national anthem
that was written by somebody who'd never been there?
Did you know that?
Guinea Bissau on the West Coast of Africa.
The music was written by a Chinese guy called Xiao Hei,
because the words were written by a separatist leader
of the African party called Amal Khakabral,
who was the leader of the African party
for the independence of Guinea Bissau and Cape Verde.
- Wow.
- And in 1963, he went on a delegation to China
and they met this guy, Xiao Hei,
and asked him to write the music.
- Really?
- Yeah, literally last year in 2024,
Xi Jinping held a welcome ceremony
for the current president of Guinea Bissau,
who's a guy called Imaro Sosoko Mbalo,
and they played the anthem.
This is our well-beloved motherland.
- It feels like it's got an edge to it
when you're being hosted by Xi Jinping
as the president of Tiny Guinea Bissau.
And he's saying, here's your national anthem,
we wrote it, by the way, don't forget it.
- Well, if anyone doesn't know where Saint Helena is,
basically from Guinea Bissau, head west,
and it's pretty much the first place you get to,
is like a tiny island in the middle of the Atlantic.
- It's so isolated when you look on a map.
If you go on your Google Maps or whatever on your phone,
it is insanely isolated.
- We cannot find a way of getting there,
we'll get a lot when you try a direction.
- Exactly, and there's a lot of,
I watched a few tourist videos for it,
where they said, you can achieve all you need to see
in a single day, but why not stay for three?
It's just such a...
- Well, 'cause that's when the next boat leaves.
- Yeah, possibly, right, yeah.
- I should just say thanks to my sister-in-law's best friend,
who gave me a lot of information about Saint Helena,
'cause she lives there.
The national dish of Saint Helena is tomato paste sandwiches.
They're called bread and dance.
And the idea is that if you're at a wedding,
there'll be a big sort of table with a load of goodies on,
and everyone will dance around it,
and then you'll eat something from the table,
and it's usually some bread and stuff.
- Dipton, tomato tapenade. - Yeah, pretty much.
Because it's really hard to get a hold of fresh stuff there.
Basically once a month, you get a boat that comes in
with fresh fruit and vegetables,
and everyone legs it to the shop.
Six pack of watsits, which is £2 at Poundland,
in the UK, is £4 on Saint Helena,
and a box of corn flakes that's £2.85 in the UK
is £7 in Saint Helena.
- But there's not that much else to spend your money on,
so you're not complaining, are you?
- No, there's not a lot going on.
But two very famous residents,
as most people, if they think of Saint Helena,
Napoleon being exiled there after Waterloo in 1815.
And the other famous resident, you know who that is?
- No. - Jonathan the Giant Tortoise.
- Oh, yeah. - Who lives in the grounds
of the governor's official residence, and he's 192.
- Jonathan's still alive. - Yeah.
- Still going pretty amazing. - Yeah.
- Was five when Queen Victoria was crowned.
- Probably he's died quite a few times,
and they've just replaced him with another tortoise.
- No, no. - Like SEO trot.
- Yeah. - He's not.
He's terribly well, if I've got a quote about him.
- From him? - Yeah.
No, it's from his vet.
- He said, "Cowabunga, dude."
- It's from his vet.
Jonathan is now blind, but he still has a tremendous libido.
- No, so that's your Picasso note.
- Oh, yeah, no, sorry.
- Kind of started off with the East India Company,
who were doing lots of trade with the East and with Europe,
and they needed somewhere to stop on the way,
'cause there's no Suez Canal in those days,
so you go all the way around Africa,
and they would always call it St Helena on the way,
and eventually they decided to put a colony down there,
and the first laws included God was to be worshipped
and served diligently,
and semen were not allowed to stay on the island
without permission.
- Oh, really?
- If you were caught harboring a sailor,
you'd be fined five pounds.
- What's wrong with sailors?
Should be inviting people, I would have thought.
- Yeah, I think they just didn't want anyone
coming on the island who wasn't supposed to be there.
- Okay. - Right?
- Given it was only sailors who were going by.
- Yeah, yeah, who else are you gonna get, swimmers?
- Yeah.
- Do you know what the postcode is, on St Helena?
- No, that's good, what?
- Well, it's STHL1ZZ, the point being,
it's a Royal Mail postcode,
and it had its own postcode, I think,
but apparently people kept writing to St Helena,
and Mail kept going to St Helens in Merseyside,
which is quite actually quite a long way to go from there.
- That's brilliant.
- Hard to know what to do with that mail
when it drops through your doorstep,
so they go from a Royal Mail postcode.
- 'Cause that was the only way you could really get there
for a very long time, which was the RMS St Helena,
and it was the Royal Mail ship
that would bring all the post over,
so you would sort of jump onto that in order to get over.
- And someone tried to post themselves
out of St Helena, actually, didn't they?
- Did they?
- Yes, so another thing that was useful by the Brits
was in the Boar War, 1900 to 1902,
they sent 6,000 Boar prisoners of war to this tiny place.
God knows how they suddenly accommodated them,
and there was one prisoner of war called Andrés Smorenberg,
who made this crate, and he wrote on it,
"Curios Only" inside here, and then he climbed in,
and he got the crate put in a place
where it was gonna be picked up by a passing mail ship,
put a fake address on in London,
filled it with like clothes and matches and water,
and bedded down for the 20-day journey.
And sadly, even though, that's what I said,
even though he marked it with care and this side up,
it was tossed around quite badly,
and he was very severely concussed,
and then when they landed at Ascension Island,
they got out sort of an unconscious damaged man
and sent him straight back to St Helena.
- Oh, so he didn't die, okay.
- He didn't die, no, but--
- They left him in someone's bin area for a few days.
(laughing)
- So St Helena and the RMS St Helena, the boat
that you used to get there on,
both, of course, named after the actual St Helena,
which I'm sure you knew,
the mother of the Emperor Constantine, and also a saint,
famous for discovering parts of the true cross,
which she excavated from the Holy Land
when she was visiting there.
She excavated three crosses, actually,
but she knew she'd got the real one
when it created a miracle
by curing a sick woman who touched it.
But not only that, she also discovered the true nails
that were holding the cross and Jesus onto the cross.
- The true hammer that was used to bang the nails in.
- No, no, that isn't mentioned in my research,
but the nails were there, and also uniquely,
the Holy Rope that Jesus was tied to the cross with,
which is unique, it's the only relic of the Holy Rope.
- How interesting, because I was taught at school
that he was nailed and that the other thieves were tied,
and he wasn't tied.
- It could have been one of the thieves is--
- I mean, it's all made up, isn't it?
- Well, we don't know where she was born,
but that's the thing, and there's an old British legend
that she was a British princess.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- The daughter of old King Cole of Colchester.
- Of old Mary the Old Soul, babe.
- Yes, and Colchester has, on its coat of arms,
it has the three nails that she discovered.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Oh, wow.
- That's very good.
Well, this is interesting.
So where do you think the second largest collection
of St. Helinian's saints?
- Saints is what they're called.
- The saints are.
- Well, I'm gonna say St. Helin's, I reckon.
- And Merseyside, they got distracted.
- It's not, it's Swindon.
- Is it?
- No.
- Swindolina, as it's known to the locals in Swindon.
- Oh, no.
- Like St. Helina, Swindolina.
- Swindolina, there's about a fifth
of what the current population
in actual St. Helina is in Swindon.
So there's like 800 people there.
- What are they doing there?
- Well, they were all given British nationalship
in 2002 after the Falkland Wars.
And so if you want to go meet locals from St. Helina,
go to Swindon.
- How cool.
- Didn't John Richardson move to Swindon?
- He did move to Swindon.
- He did move there, he moved there
because he worked out that it had the best transport links
in the whole of the UK.
- Yeah, to get into London
and to get to the gigs he'd needed to.
That's right, God, he's more prolific
than we've given him credit for, really.
- Oh, we're trying to get him on this show.
What's going on there?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that to go into
the BBC's sound department in Made of Vale,
you have to walk down a set of steps
that are each one third concrete,
one third carpet and one third wood.
This is amazing.
I saw this fact, I should say,
when I was just scrolling through Facebook earlier this year
and Tony Wei, who I'm friends with, he's a movie star.
He's in The Edge of Tomorrow, the Tom Cruise movie.
- All right, Plank.
- Yeah, he's also in a lot of British sitcoms,
black books and anything you can think of after life
with Ricky Gervais, he's a great actor.
He was there and he took a photo event and showed it
and it's pretty amazing.
So when I say that the staircase is a third of each.
- It's like you've got a runner down the middle
but either side is different.
- That's a very good way of putting it.
Yeah, so this is where the BBC do their foley,
which is the sound effects,
the extra noises that go into TV, radio and movies.
And they have a whole bottom floor there,
which is pretty extraordinary when you get a walk through it.
So I watched a video of Sean Keveney doing it,
the radio.
- Another friend of yours, is he done?
- Actually is, yeah, he actually is.
So they have a kitchen that's set up and it's all mic'd up
and so you can make tea and you can slam cupboards
and you can move bottles.
So anytime they need that, that's all done there.
They have a room where it's just full of seaweed and sand
and little mats that you can walk on
that can create the sound of the ocean,
the forest with the magnetic tapes or compressed snow
when you throw the mat on top of sand.
- Seaweed. - That's great.
- Yeah, I mean, now that you say that.
- What noise is the seaweed making?
- Yeah.
- Is that just the sound of seaweed?
- That's a really good point.
It must be artificial.
It looked exactly like seaweed in the-
- Is it seaweed inside the water?
- No, no, this is just on the floor.
- That the seaweed would just dry out in about two minutes.
- Well, they've probably got a seaweed person
who, the interns job on your first day.
- I know it wouldn't have been seaweed.
- So when I worked in radio and when I started,
we used to use quarter inch tape, recording tape
for lots of effects like walking through grass.
- Yeah. - You'd rustle that.
- Well, that's what they had though.
Yeah, all this tape that was in piles.
And I messaged Tony to say,
is there anything else that you saw there?
And he said there's also a foley coat.
So it's made of different fabrics.
It's a coat you put on, made of different fabrics
with different kinds of zips and fastenings attached
to replicate any kind of clothing sound that you want,
but all in one coat.
- That looks like it would be a really cool coat.
- No, Anna.
How often have you been getting off a train
and you're like, I need my ticket
and you've only got five pockets.
You've no idea which pocket it's in.
- And you're making a mad array of noises.
(laughing)
Sorry, guys.
- So I wonder if that foley coat was used,
there's a very famous story about Mrs. Dale's diary,
which was the sort of forerunner of the arches way back when.
They were trying to get the sound
of somebody opening a parcel.
Mrs. Dale was delivered a parcel.
They tried paper and sound like it.
'Cause famously in sound effects,
often you think of a helicopter,
sounds like (imitates helicopter sounds)
which we used to make using what's called a double ender,
which is a wire with two brass plugs on the end.
- Right.
- It sounds like a helicopter,
'cause what a helicopter actually sounds like
is not like what you think a helicopter's supposed
to sound like.
- No, it's just very, very loud hum.
- It's a loud engine, yeah.
- You can't really hear what you're saying, yeah.
- So anyway, somebody undid their zip as an experiment
and the producer said, what's that?
- That's an amazing sound.
That's perfect parcel opening.
So when the script comes, Mrs. Dale, oh, hello there.
(imitates helicopter sounds)
Oh, what have you got in there?
She said.
(laughing)
- Okay, I'm seeing where the double ender name
came from.
(laughing)
I really hadn't quite realized
that what being a Foley artist entailed,
and I think I want it as a job.
It's so cool if you're working in the films.
Basically, they'll be sent the film
and they'll come into a room and they've got all their props
and often they've collected,
I think all Foley artists collect just like hundreds
and hundreds of different props.
Bring them in, lay them all out.
And they've got a script which tells them vaguely
what sounds to make,
but then they watch the film and live,
they try to imitate what the person's doing.
So you see them sort of jerking around,
clutching at something quickly.
Stomp, stomp, stomp.
They have to grab a shoe, reach for a cloth.
It's amazing, isn't it?
- It is amazing.
And those items, if it makes the perfect sound,
you just want to keep it forever.
And they get passed down from generation to generation.
So I was reading an interview with someone called Alison D. Moore
and her former partner in Foley had retired
and he gave her a copper towel bar
with a koi fish on each end.
And when you twisted it,
it made a screech that sounded exactly like a startled cat.
And he was like, this is my pride and joy.
I take it everywhere I go,
but you can have it now I've retired.
- Wow. - So good.
- The BBC, I wondered, John,
when you were saying that about the Foley sounds,
was that live radio,
the Foley was happening live along with it?
- I did very little actual live radio.
No, you just add the sound effects as you went along.
Well, you were recording live, of course.
And it was a famous, not famous to you,
but to me, I used to do a radio show
called The News Hudlines with Roy Hardy.
It was incredibly quick on the draw.
A bit like a sort of Lee Mack of his day, very fast.
And there was a sketch that involved a fridge.
And in the script,
the studio manager saw SFX door opens.
And that's a standard BBC sound effect
because the rattle of the door knob.
- Yeah, yeah, like that.
- And so, it's a,
Rory said, I'll just look in the fridge.
And there was a,
he said, oh, a wooden fridge.
It's a wonderful moment.
- It is amazing, but it was really,
it was a very strong thing with the BBC for live radio,
particularly comedy shows,
like The Goon Show.
And there was a famous incident where
in the script, Nettie Seagoon,
who was played by Harry Seagoon,
was to be hit by a sock full of custard.
And they tried all these different sounds.
They couldn't get it.
And Spike Milligan got so frustrated during rehearsal
that he took his sock off.
He grabbed an assistant,
sent them to the BBC canteen to fill it up with custard,
which they did, brought it back,
walloped Harry Seagoon over the head with it.
And it still didn't get the sound that they need.
But that story got out.
And the BBC got lots of complaints
because this was in the last year of post-war rationing.
And they said, you are wasting good custard.
- Do they not drink it afterwards out of the cell?
- Well, regardless of what they did.
- No, that is wasteful.
- 'Cause they usually say on those programmes,
"Don't worry, the food was shared amongst the crew
"afterwards." - Yes, yeah.
- Those bizarre sound effects,
I remember I used to briefly please the programme
called The Burgess Wave,
written by David Romick and Andrew Marshall.
And they used to take great pleasure
in writing sound effects for impossible to do.
And I remember one was SFX,
Genghis Khan slices somebody's stomach off.
- Oh, wow. - It was quite a while,
that took to get right. - What did you do for that?
- What did you do?
- Well, I went to the canteen.
I got a fresh stomach.
(all laughing)
It is interesting.
It's one of those unsung things in movies and television
because without those little sounds,
it doesn't have heft at all.
When we did the first episode of Splitting Image,
we decided not to have a laugh track
'cause I don't know why,
but no time, I think.
And it seemed completely boring
'cause we used to make Splitting Image
by recording the voice track first
and then they puppeteer's mime to it.
And of course, they're made of rubber.
So when a puppet touched the desk
and it was a pre-recorded thing, nothing happened.
So the two guys, two sound guys,
absolute geniuses stood up literally all night
doing all that, you know, touching the table,
banging each other's heads, scratching their clothes.
And suddenly it comes alive.
No, it was an amazing thing
'cause actually we owe the whole existence
of Splitting Image to those two guys.
- Yeah.
I was talking about this Foley artist called Alison D. Moore.
I read an interview with her.
It was really interesting.
She said that there are more astronauts on earth
than people working in Foley at the moment.
- What?
- So I reckon that there's about 100 people doing Foley.
And there are more people who've been in space than that.
She said that they can literally change the rating
of a film by the sounds that they put in.
So if there is, for instance, an oral sex scene,
if they make it sound really filthy,
then it can go up from a 15 to an 18.
- But what's the, what's the, is it just like...
- That's normal oral sex, that's how that sounds.
- I think that downgrades it to like a U if you do that.
- It is important to say that the Foley is a specific thing,
which is something that's made on the spot.
Isn't it not like a recording?
- Yeah.
- That doesn't count as a Foley.
- You get lots of sound effects artists.
- But I just wanted to give some people a hint
of things, recordings that could be useful in other contexts.
So for example, the roar of a leopard
sounds like someone roughly sawing wood.
- Okay.
- Which is useful.
- Okay, good to know.
- Bill Bailey said, without the beat in the background,
jazz basically sounds like an armadillo
was let loose on the keyboard.
So if you wanted that sound...
- It's amazing though, because since BBC started
recording their stuff and other massive production studios,
there's these huge Foley archives that now exist.
And a lot of them have been made available to the public.
So the BBC have over 33,000 of its sound effects
that are just on a website you can download
and use as part of whatever you want to use.
It's open to the public.
Hanna-Barbera also is used a lot.
So Hanna-Barbera that made the Flintstones and so on.
Their sounds have been used in so many places
you wouldn't expect multiple Mario Kart
and Mario video games have the sounds
that would have been used in the Flintstones
that are sort of peppered all the way through.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- And they made those sounds by getting a pterodactyl
to put their beak on a record player.
(laughing)
- Yeah, but it's, yeah, it's pretty wild.
And we missed, I think it was the first 10 years
of any kind of recording with BBC radio
until the arrival of a thing called the Blatner phone.
It was only one machine that was recording
all the radio output at the time
that was coming from the BBC.
And it wasn't a great recording necessarily,
but the machine, the spools that would hold the tape
were ginormous and the tape would be traveling
at really high speeds.
So it would be traveling at five feet per second
to record it, which was really dangerous
for anyone who had to monitor the tape
because if it broke off,
it would be like shrapnel shooting out the tape.
And it was like a razor's edge.
You would be cut to pieces if it shot.
- Oh, like a ninja?
- Yeah, yeah.
So it was incredibly dangerous.
- That's a great murder mystery.
That should be a Jonathan Creek episode.
- Yes, that's true, yeah.
And that would happen, it would be more dangerous
because eventually they got two of these machines,
the Blatner phone, which meant that they could change tape
on one while recording on the other.
So that was a seriously dangerous thing.
They used to have to wear heavy gloves
and any time they were doing something
that looked a bit delicate,
they would run to the other side of the room
in case it exploded on them.
- Hang on, presumably when you change the tape,
you stop the, you stop the tape.
- Yeah, yeah, but just, I mean, the think and overheat,
they had incidences basically, where it just got too much.
- It was the most dangerous job in the world
working for the BBC in the '50s.
- It was.
- I'm the '70s.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for a final fact of the show
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that every year,
tens of thousands of people attend Rwanda's
annual gorilla baby naming ceremony.
- Oh, that sounds good. - Isn't it sweet?
It is good.
- Is it sweet?
- It is sweet, yes.
Yeah, yeah, nothing dark to it.
Quita izina, which means to give a name in Nkinyawanda,
which is the language.
And this is so cool.
It's this whole full week of activities devoted to gorillas
and it's all about their conservation and their protection
'cause there's a huge deal in Rwanda.
And the highlight is this naming ceremony
where they've got a huge, really cool looking stage,
which is a wicker sculpture of a gorilla
or a bamboo sculpture of a gorilla the size of a house.
And then a celebrity and all researchers.
- Who's the celebrity?
- Lots of different celebrities.
We'll get to the list.
- Probably some of your mates.
(laughing)
- John Richardson's gotta have a look in naming a gorilla.
- John Keveny goes there often, doesn't he?
- Yeah.
- There are multiple characters who will come up on stage
and then they'll name one of the new baby gorillas
that's been born that year.
And a big picture comes up behind
and they say, I name this gorilla
and they give them sensible.
They don't call them sort of barry.
- Well, quite a lot of the Arsenal footballers go there
'cause Arsenal are sponsored by Rwanda.
- So they are, yeah.
So 'cause the president's a big Arsenal fan.
- He is, yeah.
So in 2018, Alex Scott went.
In 2019, David Louise went.
In 2020, Hector Bellerin and Patrick Obamiang went.
Obamiang named a 14-year-old gorilla Ligitego, meaning goal,
and Bellerin chose Mjugarriro, meaning defender.
So it's like appropriate stuff for them.
So maybe next year they'll be runner-up
or smashed by Paris Saint-Germain.
- Boom.
- So do these poor gorillas have to wait
sometimes nearly a year before they get a name?
- Yes, I suppose they do.
They probably have a holding name.
- They might have their own name in their own language
and they might not care what we call them.
- No, I doubt it.
- That's it, well, no, they couldn't.
I don't know about gorillas,
but did you know that Marma sets
are the only non-human primate that call each other by name?
- Do they?
- Yeah.
And they say, "Hello, Barry."
- And there's always Barry.
- Always Barry.
They all call Barry.
- It's got a point in us, really.
- Of course it may not be their name at all.
It may be just a, all right, Sam.
- It's just a burp.
Idris Elba called, they get big names.
Called Juan Narame, meaning long life.
David Attenborough's obviously named one.
But yeah, it sounds really fun.
And the idea is to protect gorillas.
And the story of protecting gorillas in Rwanda
is an amazing success story, isn't it?
So they-
- Diane Fossey.
- Diane Fossey, yes, who I'm sure we'll talk about.
It's estimated that one mountain gorilla,
and it's mountain gorillas there.
So there are four species and subspecies of gorilla.
But one mountain gorilla can generate $3 million
during its lifetime from tourism.
And that all goes back into conservation.
To protection.
To the extent, and I found this really interesting.
So there are, like I say,
four species and subspecies of gorilla.
There's western lowland,
of which there are between 150 and 300,000.
Remember that.
There's cross river gorillas,
of which there are about 300.
Mountain gorilla,
I think there are about 800 to 1,000.
And grower's gorilla, 6,500.
All are critically endangered,
except one, which is just endangered.
- Right.
- Now, have you memorized all the figures?
- Yeah, the lowland western gorillas, you said.
- There you go.
The western lowland, 150 to 300,000.
Surely they're just endangered.
No, they're critically endangered.
And the mountain gorilla from Rwanda
is the only one that's only endangered,
even though there are only 800,
because their numbers are going up.
- Because they're going up.
But that's, I think that's how they do it, right?
- No, of course it's how they do it.
But I think it's an extraordinary discrepancy
between 300,800, but only one is critically endangered.
- And it's kind of surprising that they're going up,
well, certainly over the last 30 years or so,
'cause they had a big old war in Rwanda.
- Yeah.
- And in actual facts,
there were 16 gorillas killed during that civil war.
But the population still--
- This is a problem now.
Gorillas or guerrillas?
- Yeah, guerrillas or guerrillas.
- I should check that actually,
that I'm not talking about guerrillas.
- What do you call a gorilla with a machine gun?
- I don't know, John.
- Sir.
(laughing)
- But yeah, basically the gorillas moved up
into the mountains away from all the humans
and all the violence.
And so that's why their numbers went way higher.
And also, none of the factions
wanted the bad publicity of killing gorillas.
- Yeah.
- So yeah, they--
- And that is amazing, but mostly the reason,
'cause it is such a success story,
is because Rwanda's run an extraordinary
protection program since then,
which basically means that they--
- How have they stopped the poaching?
Is there sort of security force?
- There's just been an amazing investment
in local communities.
So a lot of the poachers,
'cause people, I always think poachers get a bad rep,
largely they're poaching for survival, right?
That these were people in a country
that were so poor, people were struggling,
and the poachers are now involved in conservation.
So there are a lot of poachers
who do various tourist things now.
And it's just giving them real national pride
in this thing, like this big ceremony,
which means it literally doesn't happen.
- Yeah, because they worked out, as you say,
one gorilla can bring 3 million in an entire lifetime.
So it's more profitable now to be a tourist guide
rather than to kill one and get a one-off payment.
Which, and so that, I mean, it has largely come down
from the stuff I've read to Diane Fosse.
I mean, I know she's the ambassador name,
but she really kind of, she moved there back in the '70s,
plopped herself on the side of the mountain,
when there was virtually no one doing that.
She was given a name,
which was the woman who lives alone in the forest
by all the locals.
- Big ceremony, was it?
(all laughing)
- Natalie Potman Cableog.
- She had to wait a year before they thought of it.
- But yeah, so Diane Fosse, the reason she went out there
was this was off the back of a man called Lewis Leakey,
who we've mentioned before,
one of my favorite people in the world
of paleoanthropology, had wild theories
and also had a lot of discoveries
about ancient versions of Homo sapiens and so on.
- Dan, a few episodes ago, we had to fade you out
when you started going into this kind of thing.
(all laughing)
- Well, he thinks that the reason
that we became the dominant species of planet Earth
is because we were too smelly to eat,
as we were in the wild, he's a brilliant guy.
But he thought that the people who should go out
and study apes should be a single woman
with no scientific training.
He's very much the Picasso of the paleoanthropology world
in that he was a bit dubious with women.
He had a lot of researchers around him
who were, let's say, at his whim.
He was a bit of deviant, but he did amazing things.
- Did you say he was your favorite?
- Do you know what?
We can edit that, right?
(all laughing)
But he picked Diane Fosse.
He thought she'd be perfect.
And he said to her,
"The only thing that you need to have to go out there
is no appendix."
And so she took her appendix out to go.
- Someone else must have taken it out.
- Yeah, a doctor took it out.
And then she got a letter six weeks later from him saying,
by the way, I was joking about the whole appendix thing.
- No. - Yeah.
It was too late.
She already did it by then.
- That's a problem with deadpan humor.
If you don't put the emoji afterwards,
we wouldn't get it.
- She was quite controversial though, Diane Fosse, right?
- Absolutely.
- I read that once she captured,
or her associates captured a poacher,
stripped him of his clothes,
laid him spread eagle on the ground
and lashed his genitals with nettles.
- Yeah, that's how I saw it.
- And she thought basically the way
that you deal with poachers is not like Anna says,
improving society and giving them other ways
of making money.
You should just beat it out of them.
- Yeah.
- I mean, that to be fair is kind of the twist
in her story is that she arrived as a conservationist.
She learned so much about gorillas,
wrote that incredible book.
What's it called?
- Gorillas in the Mist is a movie based on her, right?
- Yeah, based, but that's off her book.
So she wrote a book,
which was a memoir of her time there.
And then when poachers killed a gorilla
that she'd really become close with,
they'd lobbed the gorillas head off.
- Digit, it was called digit.
- That's right.
There was a turning point where she goes
from conservationist really to poacher killer.
And she was furious.
And anyone who was in her way was part of the problem.
So even the anti-poaching league,
she thought, no, you're part of it as well.
And to be fair,
she had a horrific time in her early days there.
She was kidnapped by rebels.
She was sexually assaulted.
She had a lot of bad times there.
- Yeah, she was tough as nails, woman.
I mean, bad childhood tough times there.
Extraordinary person.
But then she did go a little bit,
well, she just went hard line,
didn't she, towards the end? - She did.
- And sort of beat up poachers,
which is quite hardcore.
And I had actually had no idea
that she was murdered, Diane Fossey.
- Yes. - And to research this, but...
- It's just such a wild story.
So Digit was decapitated by the poachers
and his hands cut off to make ashtrays out of.
- And she was horribly mad.
She was found dead in her cabin
and bizarrely blamed on a jealous fellow researcher
in absentia, who I don't think was ever really solved.
I think we assume it was angry poachers.
- Yeah, we still don't know.
There's so many theories out there.
And she's still there though.
She's buried in the gorilla cemetery.
- Next to Digit.
She's buried next to Digit, yes.
- Gorillas though, amazing animals.
- They get high by spinning in circles.
That's a new discovery recently.
And that was like, I really loved this bit of science.
Basically, there was a viral clip that went around
of a gorilla spinning round.
And they thought, oh, that looks fun.
Let's see if anyone else does that.
And then they did more research and found out
that yeah, they do do that.
- Well, if you will withhold drugs from the kids,
they'll find a way, won't they?
They make a, you know how we make a big deal
about lions and tigers roaring?
I think the gorilla roar is the most frightening.
So they do that and then they make the belch sound,
which is the other main kind of vocalization.
And that's a little, sort of like a little burp or a growl,
which says, I'm here, don't worry, I'm your friend.
And so if researchers are working with gorillas,
then they learn to make that sound straight away
to reassure them because you're in the jungle,
you don't have that good visibility.
So it's not as much about facial recognition.
Although the other thing that researchers have to do
is learn to memorize.
And this is something that I think was pioneered
a little bit by Diane Fossey,
but learn to memorize their nose prints.
So that after a few months,
you can spot one 50 yards away and immediately know.
- Well, that makes sense.
- Barry.
- Yeah, that's great.
- Is it that obvious what the prints are?
Or do you have to get really close?
'Cause like fingerprints,
you need to put your fingers in ink, right?
- It's definitely more obvious than that.
It's like wrinkles on a face, on quite a wrinkly face.
- Okay.
I noticed you were looking at me when you said that.
- I was looking past you.
- Do you know that when you arrive into Rwanda,
they go through like any airport security,
there's certain countries you can't bring fruit in and so on.
Do you know what you're not allowed to bring in to Rwanda?
- Drugs.
- Not drugs.
- Oh, you are allowed to bring drugs.
- No, it's just not the answer I'm looking for.
- Okay.
- What's the answer you're looking for?
- Plastic bags.
- If you go to the official tourism website,
that's on there saying you will be stopped
and you can get in serious trouble
if you're trying to smuggle plastic bags into the country.
- 12 months in prison for using plastic bags.
- Wow.
- Is it your joking?
- 100% and the fine of up to $540.
Now that law is really in place for large companies
who are breaking the law.
Like if you or I brought a plastic bag in,
we probably wouldn't get 12 months in prison,
but it is actually on the law books.
That is the punishment.
- Yeah, I remember that happening.
We all thought mad.
Imagine living without plastic bags.
And now we all sort of do.
- We don't, do we?
(all laughing)
- We just pay our 5P and suck it up.
- I think even though we've had all this talk of guerrillas,
the favorite animal in Rwanda is the cow.
They're obsessively into cows.
It's great.
And so there's lots of dances inspired by cows.
So you've got the kind of Rwandan ballet,
which is inspired by cows
where women emulate cows movements.
Maybe they're more graceful in Rwanda.
- Like what does a cow do?
It just stands there for ages
and occasionally eats a bit of grass.
- What I, gentle is what I read and I actually didn't watch it.
So gentle movements.
It's a bit of swaying sometimes.
- Swishing away a fly.
- Yeah.
- It's a tail, it's all in the tail.
- It's very unique.
- All Rwanda women have tails.
Did I not mention that?
- Oh, is that right?
- Yeah.
If you want to wish someone well,
you say may you have a cow or have thousands of cows.
- Same in America, don't have a cow man.
- Yeah.
- Okay, yeah.
- It's like Helena, cowabunga, as the turtle says.
- Yep.
Okay.
There's a lot of crossover.
But they also love milk.
And instead of going to a bar in Kigali,
capital of Rwanda,
you will go to a milk bar very often.
And I think this is since the nineties,
when after the genocide,
there was massive urbanization
and crops were decimated.
A lot of cattle were massacred
and everything changed.
And a lot of people missed that agricultural connection.
And now they all go to milk bars.
- Are they alcoholic milks?
- No.
- You can get that.
- They are not.
- Are they really?
- So they claim.
It might be that they're all getting pissed,
but they're all claiming they're just like
a hot or a cold milk.
- There's also a thing called the Garinka program,
which is the idea that the government
will give every poor family a cow.
And over the years,
they've given over 400,000 cows to different families.
And the idea is that you can use them in your
to fertilize the land.
You can help drink the milk.
If you're not living in the city.
- I was thinking,
you're sitting there in your flat in the city,
third floor of your cow in your land,
and you go, "What the fuck are we gonna do with this?"
(laughing)
- Do you think that the naming ceremony
is based on a sort of human?
Because there are lots of those around the world, right?
- Yeah, it is.
It's big and Rwanda, giving the name,
the name that you give someone determines their life.
- They are born, they have their first cigar,
and then you have a big ceremony where you name them,
and all of the family members come along,
and some people suggest different names,
and then they decide which one they're gonna go with,
and there's a big old party.
- And it's usually Idris Elba,
who it comes down to the decision in the end.
He's a very busy man, but...
- But the ancient Romans had one called
DA's illustrious of purification day.
That was what the naming ceremony was called.
According to Plutarch,
until the baby had a name,
and the umbilical cord fell off,
they were regarded as a plant rather than an animal.
- Really?
- Yes, it was only when the umbilical cord fell off.
- I thought it was like a stalk?
- Yeah, I guess you're rooted to something.
- So this is the thing, I didn't know,
I knew that from somewhere that ancient Roman women
had very small choice of names,
but if you were called Claudius, for example,
you had a daughter, she'd be called Claudia.
You wouldn't have her own name.
And if you had a second daughter,
she would be called Claudia Minor,
and the first one would be called Claudia Major.
If you had a third daughter,
she would just be called Claudius Tertia,
you know, Claudius III until...
- I think Julius Caesar had like four sisters all called Julia.
- Yes, really? - Really?
- Yeah.
- Wow.
In Hungary, there's a Hungarian naming day.
Have you heard of this?
So the idea is that a name is associated
with one day of the year,
and a lot of people will celebrate their name day
rather than actual birthday.
- Oh yeah, I think that happens in a few years.
- I think we've discussed that quite recently,
haven't we? - Often the same day.
- Oh, right.
- It's all like Ghana, where they name kids
after the day of the week.
- Yeah, right.
- So in Akan, for example, Kofi,
as in Kofi Annan means born on Friday.
And Quasi, as in Quasi Quateng means born on Sunday.
- Really?
- And Liz, as in Liz Truss, means born yesterday.
- A bit of three-year-old satire there.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
You can find us all on our various social media accounts.
I'm on Instagram @Tribaland.
James.
- My Instagram is noses.
I think it's James Harkin.
- John, you're on Instagram.
- I'm JohnloidQI.
- Nice.
And anything you want to plug while we're here?
- Well, I really want to say my son, Harry,
who you all know is an amazing band called Waiting for Smith.
And they've got a great new single coming out called
I Got That Smiling For You,
which I think is going to be his smash thing.
Waiting for Smith on Instagram or all the other platforms.
- Nice.
And if you want to get to us as a group, Anna.
- You can email podcast@QI.com
or you can go to Instagram @NoSuchThingAsAFish
or tweet @NoSuchThing.
- Yep.
Or you can go to our website, nosuchthingasafish.com.
You can find all of our previous episodes up there.
There's links to some live shows that we're doing.
There's bits of merch.
There's the gateway to Club Fish,
the membership club where we have bonus material
popping up every fortnight.
It's a really fun place.
Check it out.
Otherwise, just come back here next week
'cause we will be back with another episode
and we will see you then.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)
- Can you do some folio?
I'm just gonna walk over there.
- Yeah.
- That's offensive.
He's not that heavy.
- And I'm back.
I just went to the...
(laughing)
I just went to the bookcase
because staring me in the face
is this book, "The Adoles of London".
- And it's by John Richardson.
Wow.
- Oh my God.
- It's by another John Richardson.
- It's so good, isn't it?
- What a coincidence.
- This guy's amazing.
- He's a polymath.
- How does he get time to do the...
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]