- We run it on QI a few years ago. - Yeah.
- Which was, there's no such thing as a fish.
- It ended up not such thing as a fish.
- No, seriously, it's in the Oxford Dictionary
of Underwater Life.
He says it right there, first paragraph.
No such thing as a fish.
(upbeat music)
Hello and welcome to another episode
of no such thing as a fish,
a weekly QI podcast coming to you
from our offices in Coverns Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber,
and the three other elves joining me today
are James Harkin, Energy Zenski, and Annie Murray.
Once again, we're gathering around the microphone
and we're gonna share with each other
our favorite facts from the last seven days.
So, in no particular order,
we're the best things we found out this week.
(upbeat music)
James, we're gonna start with you, fact number one.
- Okay, my fact this week is,
if the new Godzilla existed,
it would produce 12.9 million gallons of urine a day.
That's more urine than the Exxon Valdez spilled oil.
- How many times does Godzilla go a day?
That's not one bash, is it?
- Well, some animals go all the time,
like voles, I think, just urinate the whole time.
- Really? They're just consistently urinating?
- Well, actually, you're consistently urinating,
but it's, your kidneys trickle out
a milliliter of urine every minute,
but obviously you can store it in your bladder,
but voles, I'm pretty sure they just always let it go.
And birds of prey can sometimes see these tracks of urine,
and that's what helps them find the voles.
- Ah, 'cause they're just constantly living,
leaving a piss trail, basically.
- Yeah, what's weird though, right?
Is that if Godzilla were, if the new Godzilla were real,
he would take the same amount of time to urinate
as the rest of us do, right?
Because hasn't new research shown that all animals
take roughly the same amount of time to wee?
- To wee? - To wee?
21 seconds, I think, on average?
- It's all mammals over a certain size, I think.
So I'm not sure that Godzilla is a mammal.
- Did someone find out that most dogs urinate
in the same direction that they face North,
or they face North West?
- Is that true?
- Well, is it true?
That's a good question.
I think it was dogs defecating,
according to the Earth's magnetic field,
if I remember the study correctly.
I didn't look into it into too much detail to see
how true it is, but yeah, it was definitely claimed.
- There is an article online saying that,
this is the headline, dogs have a butt compass,
which is the most unpleasant phrase I've heard for a long time.
- Yeah, less convenient to carry around than a compass as well.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- But it would be convenient if you were lost with your dog.
- With your dog?
- Absolutely.
If you were, for example, going to the North Pole
and you lost your compass, it's a featureless environment.
You just have to look at the dogs and think,
"But Rover has taken a piss in that direction."
- It's true, and if you had like five or six dogs
and they all started peeing,
but they were all facing nozzle to nozzle,
in a big circle, it means you're exactly in the North Pole.
- Fantastic.
- So we agreed that Godzilla definitely isn't a mammal.
- Originally Godzilla, the initial idea for Godzilla
that it was half gorilla half whale.
And that's where the word Godzilla comes from.
Godzilla is a combination.
And that's where the name, it's the two words
smashed together, gorilla whale.
When they actually made the movie,
they did make it into a reptile dinosaur prehistoric sort of monster.
- Well, one of the guys wanted it to be a giant octopus
called Udaco, which is very close to Okado,
which would have been good.
- Okay, and what was it used in?
Was it used in a Godzilla versus?
- No, it was used to deliver groceries.
(laughing)
- In the 1954 one, which is the original?
- Yeah, the sound of Godzilla roaring was made
by rubbing a leather glove up and down a double base strings.
- Wow.
- Yeah, that's strange.
I really like low-fi solutions to problems.
So in Jurassic Park, the sound was, I think,
tortoises mating.
- Yeah.
- The new Godzilla was massive, isn't it?
Like much bigger than the old Godzilla's.
- Okay, I think that's interesting.
The scaling up that happens over the years.
The bigger and bigger.
- The website where I found how much urine they produce
was deepcnews.com, and it was a postbag I called Dr. M.
I don't know what his real name was.
And he, as well as working out the urine,
he also worked out how much bigger it's gotten
in the last 50 years.
And the 1954 Godzilla was 50 meters tall,
but the new Godzilla is about 150 meters tall.
And his idea, his theory is that the reason
that it's gotten bigger is because skyscrapers
have gotten bigger, and the Godzilla has to be big enough
to crush the skyscrapers.
- That's very interesting.
- Yeah.
- That's adapting.
It's evolution.
It's very fast evolution.
- Well, it could be evolution.
It could be sexual selection.
So the Lady Godzilla's like male Godzilla's
who can crush buildings, and so they have to get bigger.
- So that's suggesting that there is a Lady Godzilla?
- Or that this one isn't a Lady.
I think that in Japanese, they just call it it.
They don't say it's male or further.
- So we've never known if it was a male or female.
- Not to my knowledge.
- I just think there's a general inflation
that goes on with the next film,
you have to have something even bigger.
And it's just run away in a way.
- This guy works it out, that it's getting bigger
on a logarithmic scale.
And he said if they do another one in 2050,
then the Godzilla will be 288.4 meters tall.
- Do you guys know what Godzilla breathes out of his mouth?
- Yeah, doesn't he breathe like nuclear clouds?
- It's atomic breath.
- Atomic breath.
- That's Godzilla.
It's not fire.
I thought it was fire, certainly.
- You think everything is fire.
You think the sun is fire then?
- I don't believe that that is.
- I'd like to back down up.
I also still think the sun is on fire.
- But yeah, wasn't Godzilla initially
a sort of comment on Hiroshima Nagasaki?
That was why it was had all these nuclear content.
- It was.
- It's interesting that the way Godzilla is defeated,
certainly in the last film, is with military weapons.
Whereas the whole point of Godzilla is it's a metaphor
for nuclear bombs, you know, the most devastating weapons
we can come up with.
So it's kind of missing the point if you just attack him
with weapons capable of dealing with it.
- So we should have beaten him with like a peace treaty?
- Yeah, or is it like in the world of the world's way,
the aliens catch the common cold?
- Do you think Godzilla would have been as popular amongst
like 10 to 15 year old boys?
If the second half of the film had been like a potstamp
around the table, peace treaty.
(laughing)
- Oh, just a lot of people tried to sneeze on him.
- Sorry, can you repeat your last amount?
(laughing)
- So what I really like about your fact, James,
which I know you enjoy doing, and I like doing as well,
is the fact that when you get like an original fact
and you work it out and it reminded me of,
when I think you found in one, three, three, nine facts
to make your jaw drop, which is that the Statue of Liberty
wears size 879 shoes.
So I have worked out the shoe size of Godzilla.
- Have you?
- You know, it's the 50 meter Godzilla,
so it's the original.
So he wears UK size 1,680 shoes, which sounds weird,
'cause he's only a little bit taller.
In fact, the 50 meter is smaller than the Statue of Liberty,
but he has bigger feet, so there was a press release
at the time which gave the measurement of his feet.
- Did you say 1,680?
- 1,680.
- So a US size that's 1,679.
(laughing)
- Yep.
- It's a part to get them started out.
- Because the new Godzilla is quite a lot bigger
than the other one, a lot of Japanese super fans
are really upset that the Americans have just made him fat.
- So Godzilla's overweight, that's a problem?
- They're saying like it's fat from the neck downwards
and massive at the bottom.
This is what Godzilla's super fan,
Fumiko Abe, told the AFP at a Tokyo exhibition.
But then they had the premiere, I think,
a couple of weeks ago, and Gareth Edwards,
who we have met, who was--
- Gareth Edwards came, so the director of the latest
Godzilla movie was on museumicuriosity, our radio show.
He told us at the time that he was gonna be doing Godzilla,
but it wasn't announced.
- Oh, did he?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, I don't remember that.
- Very exciting.
- But they asked him at the premiere,
what he thought about these Japanese people
saying that Godzilla had got very fat.
And he said, I just think it's comments like that
that give giant monsters an image complex.
(laughing)
He's such a great combat.
- Yeah.
- Okay, let's move on to fact number two,
and that one's yours, Annette.
- Yeah, this is one of my favorite things I ever found.
It's that the real Long John Silver from Treasure Island
was father to the real Wendy Darling from Peter Pan.
- The real Long John Silver.
- The guy on whom Long John Silver is based,
a guy called William Ernest Henley,
who was a poet and he wrote the poem "Invictus"
by far the most famous thing he did.
- Was that Nelson Mandela's favorite one?
- Yes.
- And Barack Obama quoted it, didn't he?
The last verse of it is funeral.
- Mandela supposedly read it in prison to everyone,
and that got them all kind of, you know,
staying positive.
- It's a fantastic poem.
- So that's his most famous poem, this guy.
- Yes, which just, I don't know if this will ever go in,
but I do really like the last verse, which is,
it matters not how straight to the gate,
how charged with punishments, the scroll,
I am the master of my fate, I am the captain of my soul.
It is a great poem.
- So that was the poem written by the man
who Long John Silver was based on?
- Yeah, that's right.
So he was this like full of life guy, had only one leg,
and Robert Louis Stevenson just thought he was this great guy,
wrote him a letter after writing Treasure Island saying,
"I've got to be honest with you, I based Long John Silver on you
"because I find you, you know, such an incredible chap."
Does anyone read Treasure Island?
- Yes, I have.
- It's extraordinary that we've read it at all,
because for a long time, no one read his books.
Robert Louis Stevenson was seen as just a terrible author.
To the point that when, when in 1973,
they published a 2,000 page Oxford anthology
of English literature, he wasn't mentioned in it at all.
And now he's one of the 26 most translated authors
in the world above Edgar Allan Poe and Oscar Wilde,
but for a long time, no one read him.
- I don't know much about him.
I know he died on Samoa.
- Yes, he's on their postage stamps.
- And he drank a lot of Guinness.
It's the only other thing I know about Robert Louis Stevenson.
- Right, Samoa, he had it shipped out to him.
- Wow, that's a long way to ship out Guinness.
I remember I tried to find the furthest Irish pub
from Dublin, and I reckon it's Waxio Shays in New Zealand.
- So even from there, it's a long way to Samoa.
- Yep, it must be strange to having somebody based on you.
Years ago, I received a guy called Lord Berners,
who was an early 20th century aristocrat and eccentric.
He built one of the last follies in Britain.
You know, those towers that go nowhere and are completely pointless.
He built one of those, and then he put it at the bottom of science
saying members of the public committing suicide off this tower
do so at their own risk.
He was a very, very funny guy.
But he wrote a novel in which he based all of the characters
on his friends, but he also cast it as a lesbian schoolgirl story.
And one of the characters in it, Sitwell, was so angry
that he tried to buy every copy of this book
in circulation to destroy it.
- That's a really good way to get good sales, isn't it?
- Yeah, pretty much.
- Isn't that what you have for Titchcock did
when he released, I think it was Psycho.
He bought up as many copies of the novel Psycho as he possibly could
because he didn't want the ending to be given away.
Was it Psycho?
- Yeah, was Psycho?
- Yeah, you know who Psycho was based on?
- Yes, it's based on the Texas Chainsaw Massacre guy.
- It's based on the same guy as the Texas Chainsaw Massacre.
It's Silence of the Lambs and Psycho
they're all based on the same guy called Ed Geene.
- Oh wow.
- And he was a big famous serial killer in the world.
- So a real gift to, you know,
it's Greenplay writers.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Thank you, Ed.
- But the, if you look at it one way,
it means there are fewer Psychos out there than you think
if they're all based on the same one guy.
- Yeah, yeah, that's true.
Oh, he just had such a variety of fictional type quirks.
- There must be other Psychopaths going,
"Why does he get all the gifts?"
- Yeah.
- I'm doing some great killings.
- And yet, has he won a single Oscar?
- No.
- Yeah, another example of the Academy getting it known.
- Well, Silence of the Lambs won best picture.
- But he did, my point is, was he invited to the ceremony?
- What are you wearing today, Ed?
- Fine, wearing my mother.
(laughing)
- The nipples of all my victims in a belt?
- In a, on a lighter note.
(laughing)
- Yeah, just to take us away from nipple wearing.
When I was looking into Long John Silver,
I found a porn star, here has a similar name.
- When you were looking into Long John Silver.
So his name's Long Dong Silver.
And Long Dong Silver, he's a retired porn star now.
But he was famed, obviously,
for the apparent size of his penis,
which, it turned out that he was using fake penis
during the shoots, which no one really knew about.
He persuaded a makeup artist who did the makeup
for the film "The Elephant Man" to create a prosthetic.
- I wonder if they felt, well, you know,
we've got a trunk, yeah.
(laughing)
Actually, the elephant I didn't have a trunk.
- No, no, no, that would have been the makeup artist going.
I've done the trunk, and they go,
no, he's not physically an elephant man.
What am I going to do with this trunk?
(laughing)
- Do you think I should quickly explain
the Wendy connection?
- Yes, yes.
- So we don't, when he met on his Henry,
was the father to Margaret Henley,
who was one of the girls who Jay and Barry.
So he loved playing with children.
He was always, he loved spending time with children.
And he used to hang out in Kensington Gardens
and entertain the kids and tell them stories.
And Margaret Henley was one of the girls
who used to hang out there with him.
And she was the person who called him Wendy.
Wasn't she?
- Wendy Wendy.
- Wendy Wendy, which is where,
we think he got the name Wendy for Peter Pan.
- Was it right that Wendy was not a name before he came up?
- It was a very popular name at all,
but there are some examples before him.
- The original title of the novel,
which Peter Pan first appeared in,
was going to be the boy who hated mothers.
- It was pretty dark.
- Oh, yeah, it is.
- And Jay and Barry was nicknamed the furry beast
by his friends.
- Yeah.
- He was very, very short and very hersute.
- He also loved to play cricket, right?
- Yeah.
- And this is extraordinary.
His cricket team.
Have you seen his cricket team?
- The Alahackbury.
- Yeah, the people on it.
This was his team.
H.G. Wells, Rudyard Kipling, Arthur Conan Doyle,
PG Woodhouse, Jerome K. Jerome, G.K. Chesterton, A.A. Milne,
and others.
- This is his cricket team and others.
- And there's plenty more very famous.
- Yeah, they're so many.
- But the thing is, they were a terrible team,
and he printed a book of advice for them,
which had little tips.
It was in 1893.
Like, don't practice on an opponent's ground
before the match begins.
This can only give them confidence.
(laughing)
Or, should you hit the ball, run it once,
do not stop to cheer.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, time to move on to fact number three,
and that is, I believe, my facts.
My fact this week is that the tinfoil hats
that conspiracy theorists wear in order to stop the government
from sending messages into their brain
actually does the opposite.
It amplifies the signal.
Almost to the point that if there were a thousand people
in a crowd and they were the one with the tinfoil hat,
that's the only brain that would actually get
the brain messages.
It's like a huge antenna that they're wearing.
- I don't even know that.
- Well, it was a study by a bunch of students in the America
who just wanted to look into the myth, I guess,
because people were doing it.
No one had actually checked it out before.
And obviously, we don't know how to send messages
into people's brains or take them out.
As far as I know, James is shaking your head as if we do.
- We don't, yeah, but they're working on it.
There's been studies done in the last couple of years
where people have thought about a word
and people have been able to work out what word
they were thinking about by measuring their brainwaves.
But they would work if they were made properly, right?
So they are meant to be a Faraday cage
which stops electricity passing through it.
- If it fully covered the head and properly tightly fitted it,
then electromagnetic radiation could not get in.
But as it is, if it's worn loosely or designed,
it's sort of just a skull cap, then it gets in.
But I love the idea that you would make one
that was so good that the government couldn't get in,
but also then you would immediately asphyxiate.
(all laughing)
- You guys know that the Vatican used a Faraday cage
in 2013 to shield the cysteine chapel from its chopping.
So no one could hear who they were electing as Pope
because there was, I think in 2003 was it a Pope
before that was elected.
It was thought there was a leak in Germany.
And so they put a Faraday cage in the Vatican.
- Wow, massive tin foil cardinals.
- Cardinals.
(all laughing)
- That's great.
Have you guys heard of stealthware?
This is a company who make clothes
that make the wearers invisible to infrared surveillance cameras,
particularly those on drones.
So the idea is that you wear these clothes
and drones can't see you and it's supposed to be make you safe.
Say you were being infiltrated by the American government
who were looking at you with drones,
they won't be able to see you anymore.
They make hoodies, they make full length burgers
in this kind of material.
The burger goes for $2,300.
The hoodie is $481.
But unfortunately due to the high cost
and limited availability, so far they've only
sold one item a scarf.
(all laughing)
- I know where we should put all the secrets in my neck.
- It's all of them, but not completely.
- Speaking of hats, useful hats.
The following quote is from radiologist Richard Gerstle's
1950 book How to Survive an Atomic Bomb.
He said, "If you are caught outdoors in a sudden attack,
"a hat will give you at least some protection
"from the heat flash."
(all laughing)
When I say some...
- That's true, you probably could mathematically calculate
how much it gives you.
It's just that it won't...
- It will, by no means save your life under any circumstances.
- This is amazing.
No army at the start of the First World War,
okay, this order's metal helmets.
It took until 1915 and thousands and thousands of deaths
before they said, you know.
The German army had a leather,
just a little leather cap's called a pickle helmet.
Not until 1950, and people start making these helmets.
And we have the image of the helmet from the First World War,
the kind of shallow, again,
innovated for the First World War.
- Francis Galton, who was, I believe,
a relative of Charles Darwin, he invented a hat, didn't he?
Yeah, it was a hat that had an air conditioning device in it,
or a little flap that opened the top,
because it was the idea that if you thought too much
about stuff, your head overheated.
- It doesn't mean my hair is always sinking.
(all laughing)
Weird hats, you mentioned.
When was it dangerous to wear a hat?
Why am I phrasing this like a cute question?
'Cause I reckon that you'll get it changed, wasn't it?
- When was it dangerous?
- In stockpot, you used to be attacked
if you weren't wearing a hat,
because they had the hat industry was quite big there,
and they thought it was unpatriotic to the town,
if you weren't actually attacked.
- Yeah, by verbally or in principle.
- Well, people throw things at you.
- Wow.
- But not as mean as the straw hat riots.
So in the early 20th century, in New York,
past September the 15th,
it was socially unacceptable to wear a straw hat.
It was a summer item.
And if you wore a straw hat,
past September the 15th,
then it was traditional for youths to come along
and knock your hat off your head and trample on it.
And in 1922, it got out of hand.
So the straw hat rioters decided to start
knocking people's hats off their head a bit early,
and I think they approached a bunch of dog workers
who were wearing straw hats on September the 13th,
not the hats off, trampled them, started a fight,
huge fight riot lasted three days,
bunch of people ended up in hospital, disaster.
And in 1924, a guy was murdered for wearing a straw hat
after September the 15th.
So it was a dangerous business actually.
- Three days of fighting.
- Three days of riots, the straw hat riots.
- One last thing on conspiracy theories.
- Okay.
- I like the randomness of them,
because they're often so connected,
but often they also have very strange outputs.
So I found a list of conspiracy theories online,
and this was 16 conspiracy theories
that have been proved to be true.
Some day scientists will use millions
of genetically modified animals in experiments.
Scientists all over the world are creating
bizarre human animal hybrids.
Obama is making government employees
spy on one another and pro-wrestling is fake.
(laughing)
- That's not the seven on this list.
- Should we move on?
- Sorry, sorry, sorry, we were brothers and sisters
before, literally brothers and sisters
in family connections.
The guy who came up with the first ever tin hat
was Julian Huxley, who was the brother
of all the Huxley.
- No!
- Yeah, it was in a short story called The Tissue Culture King,
about a scientist who is lost in a jungle kingdom,
and he offers to culture the king's flesh
so the subjects can worship him in their home.
And then this allows the king to exert telepathic power
over the entire kingdom.
And in that story, he says we used caps of metal foil,
which reduced the effect on ourselves,
but it started as a fiction in a short story.
- Yeah.
- That is great.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, moving on to our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that geese sometimes fly upside down,
to lose height quickly when they're coming into land,
rather than doing a long, slow descent.
They just, it's like a shortcut for them, like a life hack.
- But the best thing is, they flip their body upside down,
but their head and neck stay the right way up.
- So they do a twist, so that it just looks weird.
- It looks really bizarre.
- You see the neck and the head are perfect, you know?
And then they've got this weird upside down body
flapping away beneath them.
- Frankie.
- Yeah, and this is called whiffling.
- So great.
- I know geese, the only animal to do that?
- I think there are a few others which do it.
- The description I read is that it looks like
they're a falling leap, but they're not mine.
- Yeah, there's good footage, which we can put up online
on the podcast page.
Yeah, and there are amazing photos of it
being captured mid-flight, and it looks brilliant.
- Yeah, so I started looking up things about flying upside down.
- Oh, yeah.
- The planes which are flown upside down.
- There was that movie, wasn't there?
- Flight.
- Dental Washington, yeah, that's right.
- The Robert Zermh, heck, I swear.
- I got distracted.
This fact should be a lot better research,
but I got distracted watching a 10 minute clip from flight.
- Was it the bit at the start where he crashes,
he flies upside down?
- Yeah, it was that.
- Did you see the Boeing issued a statement
after the film came out and they said,
the MD80 cannot sustain inverted flight.
The MD80, as with all commercial airliners,
was designed to fly upright, so it was a bit, you know.
- Do you remember that plane that flew under Tower Bridge?
- Oh, yeah. - Remember that?
- No.
- Yeah, you must remember it.
- I remember the Arc de Triomphe one.
- Go on.
- Well, in 1919, someone flew a biplane
through the Arc de Triomphe, and the Arc de Triomphe is big,
but it's not that big.
And it was the wingspan of the plane,
plus a medium meter on either side.
- Wow.
- It's such cool footage, and we can put that up online.
- Yeah, let's put that up.
- Yeah, it's amazing.
- The guy who flew under Tower Bridge,
I was talking about, this guy was called Harker Hunter,
and he flew under Tower Bridge on the 5th of April, 1968.
He did it as a, he flew across the Thames
as a demonstration against Harold Wilson's government,
and he was struck off from the RAF for it, I think.
And weirdly, there was a quote from him
when they asked him about it, and he said,
he was flying down the Thames,
and he said, until this very instant,
I had absolutely no idea that, of course,
Tower Bridge would be there.
(laughing)
- What did he think it was gonna be?
I don't know.
- Just going back to the animals in the air very quickly,
so he's flying upside down.
This is something that I've found out weeks ago,
and I've mentioned it to you guys a bunch before,
but we haven't said it on the podcast.
It's about ladybirds.
There's, I mean, this really surprised me,
that recent research has shown that ladybirds,
who were thought to have only flown at a height of, say,
are shoulders, an average human's shoulder height,
actually have been found flying at the height of 3,600 feet,
and they travel as fast as 37 miles per hour,
and they can go as far as 74 miles in one journey.
- Do you know how they find them?
- What do you mean?
- Well, they originally found this out,
'cause obviously you've got to be at that height to find one,
so they sent up planes with sticky panes and saw what they got.
That was very early, that was by planes.
- When you try to swat a fly, you know how,
you try to swat it, and you're definitely gonna get it.
It looks barely conscious, and then it gets away,
and you don't understand how.
And apparently this is because the moment they see you coming,
they do a somersault rather than just falling
and that speeds up their descent.
So they just drop into a somersault.
You can sort of imagine it,
and I wouldn't be able to explain the physics, maybe you would.
And then they pick up the air
with their wings and fly away.
- That's so cool.
- Little somersault.
- Tennis rocket, that's what you need,
'cause they can avoid most of the strings,
but they can't avoid all of them.
- Good.
- Sorry to bring the helicopter down, but.
- Unlike tennis balls in my experience.
(laughing)
Every time I hit it, I do a little cheer,
but then forget to run.
(laughing)
- And this might seem unrelated, but on geese.
Can we go on geese?
- I would almost say that's completely related.
(laughing)
- Goose grabbing was very popular as a sport,
and 17th century new Amsterdam,
which obviously became New York.
And the way it was used smear the neck of a goose
with soap or something slippery,
and you hang the goose upside down,
and a bunch of competitors ride towards it on horses,
and the aim is to try and rip it's head off.
- Oh, sorry.
- Do you remember we did what used as a goose on cue?
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Remember that, we came up with loads of different things
that you can use geese for.
- Oh, yeah. - 'Cause they were used
as guard dogs in ancient Rome and various different--
- They were used to turn spits in the kitchen,
which was grabbed the handle
and turn it around, slowly in the kitchen.
- That's great.
- Have you heard of the goose crusade?
And I was during the crusades.
There was a group of crusaders slightly mad.
They somehow managed to believe
that a goose was filled with a holy spirit.
And so they worshipped him and used him as a guide
to find their way to Jerusalem.
- Like the compass direction every time he did a little goose poo.
(laughing)
'Cause that should be east.
Wow, I'm still stunned by that cruelty of that.
- Yeah, well, when James mentioned the goose rebellion,
I thought what was it called?
- The goose crusade. - The goose crusade.
- What are they called a goose age?
'Cause that is some kind of disgusting drink.
(laughing)
- God, progress movie.
- Life gives you geese, make goose age.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it for another podcast.
That is all of our facts, thanks so much everyone for listening.
If you wanna get in touch with us about any of the things
that we've said during the course of this show,
you can get us on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @SriberlandAndy.
- @AndrewHunterM.
- James.
- @EdShaped.
- Anna, still fighting against the avalanche of requests
coming through to us on Twitter and Facebook
to get her on there.
- #GetAnnerOnTwitter.
(laughing)
- #BuggerOffAllOfYou.
- So in the meantime, you can get her on @Quikipedia
or you can go to the page that she creates
for each of every single one of these episodes,
which is qi.com/podcast.
And we're gonna have pictures and videos and links
to all the stuff that we've been talking about in this episode.
We're gonna be back again next week with another set of facts,
so we'll talk to you then.
Catch you later.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
(door closing)
[BLANK_AUDIO]