(percussive music)
- Hey everyone, welcome to this week's episode of Fish.
Before we get going, just wanna let you know,
thank you for all your feedback
about last week's ultimate crossover episode.
It was very enjoyable to do.
In fact, so much so, we've decided to do it again.
Except this time, we've decided to crossover completely,
a full crossover, a 360 crossover.
- Done, we messed up again, didn't we?
- We lost an entire episode, somehow.
- So if you were in Bristol a few months ago,
quite a few months ago, you will have seen
an amazing show, guys.
I gotta tell you, this was one of the best shows we ever did.
Unfortunately, it doesn't seem like we recorded it.
- So only you, Bristolians, will have the memory
of that show.
And then this is kind of the lesser version, you say?
- Yeah.
- Oh, it's still worth listening to.
- I would say.
Definitely one for the completest, I'd say.
- Yes.
- Yeah, it's amazing how negative you guys are.
We haven't even recorded it yet.
(all laughing)
- So enjoy this week's episode.
Here we go.
(upbeat music)
Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing
as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber, and I'm sitting here
with Andrew Hunter Murray, James Harkin, and Anna Chazinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days.
And in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, Andy.
- Okay, my fact is, it's about Bristol, actually.
I've just chosen completely at random
out of all the cities I could have chosen.
And I learned it about four months ago,
shortly before we performed in Bristol.
My fact this week is that the first hot air balloon flight
in Bristol was indoors.
And people at home have to imagine
the cheers and laughter of the Bristol crowd
when they first heard that.
- They went nuts when Andy said that.
My God.
- So there's this firm in Bristol called Cameron Balloons,
and it's the world's biggest balloon firm.
Basically, Bristol is the capital of hot air ballooning
pretty much in the world, definitely in the UK.
- Yep.
- And the first flight was in 1784,
and you had to go indoors to see it.
And you had to pay a little amount to see it.
And if you paid more, apparently you could see it filled up
with air.
- Apparently it was a pricing structural way.
- Wait a minute.
So the people who didn't pay much,
they just saw a load of canvas.
- It sounds like that, doesn't it?
I can't quite believe that, that's true.
- Was this new to people at the time?
As in, how long did Balloons exist before this happens?
- That's a great question.
- Really good question.
- So they had the Aztecs.
They had, they made like Balloons
out of animal intestines.
I think we know that.
And I remember reading once that they made Balloon animals
out of those intestines.
(laughing)
But I don't know if that doesn't sound very true, does it?
- So, I mean, how big were the animals back then?
- What do you mean?
- As in, do they make like a full hot air balloon out
of an animal?
- No, no, no, sorry.
So just Balloons in general, I'm saying about the history
of not the history of hot air balloons.
(laughing)
- And the Civil War, they definitely had hot air balloons
'cause Lincoln had a hot air balloon balloon corp.
Corps.
- Cool.
- Corps.
- Just keep throwing guesses at the letters that you see.
(laughing)
- Yeah, he had a balloon corp and they had seven Balloons
and they used to go over and the Confederates actually
tried to build their own Balloons in retaliation
and then they stopped doing them
because people found them really easy to shoot.
It was quite an easy target.
So we know it goes back as far as the Civil War
in America, at least.
- Yeah, they were actually a huge deal
in the 19th century hot air balloon flights.
And I think in 1897 there was an attempt
to reach the North Pole by balloon.
That was three Swedish people who tried to get there.
They disappeared.
No one knew what happened to them.
There were these reports of silk falling from the sky.
And then randomly in 1930, 33 years later,
they were found in this Thor by Whalers just by chance.
They found as the Thor came the bodies of these guys
and they'd crashed after three days
but they'd lived on these ice flows
and they'd eaten polar bears for--
- Wow, that is hard cars, yeah.
- That's amazing.
- I reckon I'd go hungry before I decided to go for
- Oh, look at that.
- It was so sad though, 'cause they were convinced
that they could steer their balloon over the North Pole.
And it was partly funded by Alfred Nobel.
Their attempt, yeah.
And but unfortunately the drag ropes didn't work very well
and in a few minutes they fell off
so they had no way of steering.
So they lost lots of ballast
and they kept on just bumping along the ground
and leaking a bit and then rising a bit.
And it took them 65 hours to land
and they didn't get to the stores in time.
So it was sad.
- The other thing about eating polar bears
is their liver's contained so much vitamin A
that they're poisonous.
- Yeah, that's awful.
If you're diving vitamin A poisoning,
want to survive the hot air balloon crash
onto an ice flow and then pour a polar bear
to death with your bare hands.
- This is quite cool about higher balloons.
So usually you're not allowed to fly in rain
and so it's all weather dependent, isn't it,
if anyone tries to fly.
They can't actually fly in wet weather.
I guess it's just not recommended.
But when you do fly in wet weather,
the rain gets caught in
and actually goes over the people inside the basket
so it makes its way into the...
But because of the flames,
it comes down like a hot shower.
So it's really warm water that drops on them.
- That's nice. - Yeah, that's very cool.
Have you heard of splash and dash?
While we're talking about water and hot air ballooning?
- No.
- Splash and dash is a cool thing you can do
if you have a hot air balloon.
It's what you sink just low enough
to dip your toes into a lake and then climb up again.
- Oh cool.
- It's pretty risky.
- Your toe is below the bottom of the basket.
- Well, there is a trend for ballooning
with no basket these days.
- No way. - You have a sofa.
- You have a sofa.
- What?
- Yeah.
- No way.
- It's not very common.
- It's a trend though.
- It's a trend.
- You're serious people can go up in a sofa,
do they have to be strapped in, right?
- I think it's really recommended that you try something.
- I don't know though,
because I never fall enough myselfer.
- That's true.
- I mean, I don't know if that's true, but you look to me
like the kind of guy who wouldn't.
- They protect the things that are easy to kind of sail.
- That's true, yeah?
- No, if it's swinging in high winds from a balloon
as a thousand feet up,
I don't have belts on my sofa,
so I think mine wouldn't be safe at all.
- Well, I've had belts fitted to all my soapers at home
and just in case,
and they save my life on countless occasions.
Well, speaking of no baskets for a hot air balloon,
have you heard of, they're called smoke hot air balloons?
It was a carnival attraction that used to happen.
So this is during the 1800s,
and there's footage that you can see of this online,
and it's honestly incredible.
This was a daredevil thing.
So what they would do is,
daredevil's would attach themselves by a rope
to an inflating hot air balloon with no baskets,
so simply the balloon.
So the balloon would completely fill up.
They would untether it,
and it would rock it off into the sky,
and these people would just be dragged behind it
on the end of the ropes,
and would fly up after it.
And when they got to a certain height,
they would loosen themselves from the rope,
fall down and parachute back to Earth.
- Very cool. - Well, it's absolutely incredible.
You see them lob up in these people.
They're surrounded by people in the videos,
and they just go fong and disappear off into the air.
- But you have to loosen yourself up before it gets too high,
presumably. - Yeah, I think you obviously know
when it's you've had enough.
- Okay. - Yeah.
- I thought you were going to say they shot the balloon down.
Why?
(laughing)
'Cause I didn't imagine that they had a parachute on
when you were describing it.
So I was thinking how would I get myself out of this one?
- Yeah.
- And I would have, my first choice would have been a gun
instead of a parachute.
(laughing)
- What one item do you want to take up from you?
- I read a brilliant account.
This is actually the source of 1838,
but it was about something that happened in 1785,
and it was when Jean-Pierre Blanchard,
who was one of the first people to go up in a hot air balloon,
went up, he went 6,000 feet up,
and then he dropped from his hot air balloon,
a dog attached to a parachute,
just to kind of see what would happen,
and this whirlwind apparently swept the dog away
above the clouds, so it kind of disappeared,
and Blanchard is in his balloon.
This is what the account says, handed down through the ages.
Blanchard was in his balloon,
and he met the dog in his parachute above the clouds.
- This is rubbish.
- Do you remember that thing with that sauce?
(laughing)
- He got the loop the loop guy.
- Yeah, which is true.
- He fell out of his plane during a loop the loop,
and then fell back into it once it had finished doing the loop.
- Yeah, so he was upside down, he fell down,
he thought he was doomed,
but his plane, which was mid-loop the loop,
met him at the bottom.
- So remember how obviously fells that was?
- Look, your thing sounds similar.
- Dan's defies physics.
Mine, imagine a really small dog,
like a little terrier, with a parachute in high winds.
It could be swept away into the clouds,
and then old Blanchard saw his dog above the clouds,
who barked with joy apparently at seeing his master.
He tried to grab him,
and they both had landed 12 minutes later,
separately after which the dog ran away.
- When you say barked with joy,
do you not mean barked in absolute terror?
- barked in like,
"Why the fuck do you just drop me out of that balloon, mate?"
- He then shits himself with joy.
(laughing)
- Ben Franklin patented a balloon-related thing,
like he painted it everything else.
- He patented a refrigerator that tethered to a balloon,
and it was meant to lift food up into where the air was cool,
and that's how you'd refrigerate your food.
- Why?
- I have heard of that before.
- That is so cool.
- It's inconvenient, though.
- It is.
If you're going for a late-night snack, it's...
- But what you have to do is pull it down.
You just kind of winch it back down.
- Yeah.
- You get your food out,
and then you let it go back up again.
- Again, I was thinking of shooting it down,
I feel like.
- By the anti-thing.
(laughing)
- These eggs are broken again.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Chuzinski.
- My fact this week is that in rage rooms,
where people pay to smash things up,
the things people want to smash up the most are printers.
Yeah, they hate them.
They hate printers.
So, rage rooms are these things
that are kind of popping up all over the place.
Quite a few of them in America and in Canada,
where you pay to go,
and you can either smash up their possessions,
so they provide a bunch of stuff,
or you can bring your own stuff,
and they're becoming increasingly popular.
- Better to do someone else's stuff, right?
- Well, I think it depends.
How much you just like that person.
- If you just like your own stuff a lot.
- Yeah, well, why did you pay it then?
- I know, but let's say you've got a pen
that you really don't like.
- You're not gonna smash up a pen.
- That is the most pussy rage room attendant
I've ever seen.
- What?
- You turning up with one bike.
- You're right.
(laughing)
- I'm now with this guy, baby.
- He keeps leaking.
- I do it really psychologically though.
I put it in a chair and then I shine a light in it's nib.
(laughing)
- I asked you to let a question before I beat it up.
- I'm holding a pen, I'm sorry,
I've got a poor imagination.
- I love at the end of the hour
you come up slightly beat up somehow.
(laughing)
- Just got stuff drawn over the space.
- Pen strolls out nonchalantly out of you.
(laughing)
Hails a cab.
- But no, this is a thing if you go through
the rage room site.
There's a one called Battle Sports in Toronto
that says it goes through 15 printers a week.
The same in New York and the fragment room and Singapore.
They also printers are almost sold after objects.
We need to provide lots of them.
People want to break them up.
- I like this in America in New York.
There's the Reckon Club and the Reckon Club,
it has, you know, you can get packages that you can buy.
So I want it all.
It's a package you can get, which is $149.
You can even buy gift certificates for people.
So, you know, both they presence,
go for an hour in the rage room.
- They should have called it the Reckfast Club.
- Yes, they should have.
Very nice.
- Why didn't they?
- We should start our own.
You and your pen's only.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, so what's nice about this is it's the same,
obviously, like every rage room you go in
and you destroy stuff, but what I particularly like
is when they started, there was a guy who runs it
called Mr. Daily or Dally, D-A-L-Y.
- Dally, he's got Tom Daley, I think, actually.
- Oh, is he, Mr. Tom Daley.
So he, when he was in there and they say
this was an early setback, he was in the room
showing a couple of all the things
that they could do via his laptop, a video.
And then he left the room, but he accidentally left
the laptop in there, he smashed it up.
(all laughing)
Yeah, so he came back in there, the other guy was like,
"Ah!"
And he didn't tell them, 'cause he thought,
"Oh, I don't want to ruin their experience."
But he, as of then, started labeling everything
as, "Don't smash this."
- I went on the Wikipedia for rage rooms,
but I did it about four months ago,
so it might have been changed by now.
But they said that the concept of an anger room
is at least 20, at least 2000 years old.
- Is it?
- Yeah, but that's what Wikipedia says,
and who are we to doubt them?
- What are they saying about this?
- They say it was Queen Kaikei,
who in an old book was said that she was going to,
the palace anger room, and actually it was a sulking chamber
when I looked it up.
That's how it's usually translated.
- Apparently it was like a dark room
where you would lie down and sulk.
- Mm-hmm.
- Yeah, so not really arranged.
- I do like the sound of that though.
- Yeah, yeah, 'cause people rage manifest differently,
doesn't it?
Some people just want to lie down in the dark
and be really pissed off with the world.
Some of us like to smash our exes stuff.
Actually the most,
the most I say that because I think the most common thing
for people who do bring in their own things
are people who've had a breakup
and they bring in all their exes old stuff.
This is what the Toronto play said.
So it's said for $20 extra,
you can bring your own stuff to smash.
And the founder said that by far and away,
the most common thing to do is to bring in your exes stuff.
And he said, "The people often come in
and you'll hear them screaming and shouting in there,
things like, oh, you think you're so good?
Argg, and then you'll hear us smash."
- You think you're always right?
- I think that's pronounced "Arg."
(laughing)
- How do you spell "Arg" then?
Is it without the age?
- I don't think there is a word.
- Who says "Arg"?
- Pirates.
- No, they don't, they go, "Arg."
- Oh yeah.
- Oh, we've not been hearing the end of their sentence.
(laughing)
- One of the first ones that was set up in Dallas in 2011
by a lady called Donna Alexander.
And she just started charging $5 to smash things
that she collected from curbs in the area.
- Herica.
- She just sort of picked it up.
So it was very ad hoc at the beginning.
And then she'd get people knocking on her door,
kind of like a fight club saying,
"Is this where you go to smash stuff up?"
And her insurer had to invent an entirely new category
just for her.
- Oh, very exciting.
- Yeah.
- And what do you mean by just picking stuff up
like as in flight tipping?
- You know when people leave things out,
exactly flight tipping, like leave an old fridge out
or drop a lot of pens that they don't want anymore
for the faulty kind of thing.
- That's really cool.
- Yeah.
- Stuff on printers?
- Oh yeah.
- I was reading about printer jams
and everyone finds them very annoying.
Apart from people who work in printers
who find them really exciting.
I say it's the it's the it's the elemental struggle
between the natural and the mechanical
because paper is made out of trees
and printers are made out of metal and shit and plastic.
- I think the ultimate challenge
is throwing a dog with a parachute
out of a hot air balloon and then catching it again.
- Do you guys know about the first printer ever to go into space?
- No.
- This was a printer that was sent up on the ISS in 1998.
Sorry, this was the first color printer ever to go into space.
(laughing)
So it was sent up in 1998 with a discovery mission
and it was used solely to make Halloween masks.
So it was sent up.
It was kind of a secret thing.
So John Glenn, who was by then a senator,
was on that mission.
But he'd been the third person I think to orbit the Earth
in 1962.
And so he was this big space hero by that point.
And so on that 1998 mission,
the whole crew printed color portraits of him
off this floppy disk and they made these portraits
into Halloween masks.
And then they all went around pretending to be John Glenn
in a nod to his greatness.
- Cool.
I'd print out a full alien costume
and then sell it to take it to myself
and then freak my crew mates out.
- Do you think they'd fall for that?
Because I don't think anyone was floating around
going oh my god it's John Glenn.
Oh my god it's John Glenn, oh my god it's John Glenn.
- That's true.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is one of the first things
that McDonald's founder Ray Crock did
when he bought the baseball team San Diego Padres
was to sign a player called Big Mac.
- Very good.
Did he do it because he was the founder of McDonald's
or was he just a good baseball player?
- Big Mac was a great baseball player.
Willie MacCovie was his real name.
He was a very good player and obviously Ray Crock
who built McDonald's from a very tiny brother operation
of the McDonald brothers into the global success it was.
Had an eye for franchising, for merchandising,
for commercialization.
He saw that by getting Big Mac in
he could do a lot of cross promotion.
So for example, during the first season
they did Big Mac Sundays.
So the idea would be that you could take a ticket stub
and get a free Big Mac after a match
if the Padres had won.
Unfortunately when the promotion started
they lost 11 straight home games.
And so as a result they had to change it to
whether they win or lose you get a free Big Mac.
- Yeah they were terrible weren't they
when he first took over.
- Yeah.
- Was there not a thing about him
shouting at them on the pitch or something like that?
- The first match he went, he was very excited
because the idea of him signing this new player
and the fact that Ray Crock had taken over it.
He got the attendance right up.
They, for their opener, they drew 39,000 people
but they totally sucked in the match.
And as a result he went into the booth
where the commentators were commentating on the match
took over the Tannoy and he said,
"I have good news and bad news."
The good news is that the Dodgers drew 31,000
for their opener and we've drawn 39,000 for ours.
The bad news is that this is the most stupid
baseball playing I have ever seen.
He said that to the players heard the fans
and the fans cheered, they loved it.
They loved that he was being honest.
And then someone ran on the field of Strieker
and he yelled, "Get that Strieker off the field.
"Throw him in jail."
So he was just commenting to the whole stadium
of 39,000 people his thoughts.
It was amazing.
- He was angry.
- Yeah.
Just before we did this show in Bristol,
the night before, or the day before,
I watched the founder for research for this.
I was a really good film about Ray Crock
but I can't remember any of it now.
(laughing)
- Good story.
- I think I remember is that when the brothers
who founded McDonald's, so this is not Ray Crock,
their idea was called the method, I think.
And they worked out the size of their kitchen
and where everything went,
so there was a most efficient possible way
of running a kitchen.
And the way they did it is they went to a tennis court
and they had chalk and they drew all the different
possibilities and they got people,
hired people for very little money
to try out pretending to cook all these burgers,
pretending to do milkshakes,
pretending to do fries until they got the exact one.
And they did this for days and days.
They eventually found the right one
and then that night it rained
and all of their chalk marks got washed away
and they had to do the whole experiment.
- Oh no.
- The whole sort of the design of the kitchen
like the choreography.
That's very cool.
- Oh wow.
- Do you know that Ray Crock was in the same
Ray Cross company in the first world war
driving ambulances as Walt Disney?
- Wow.
- Was it really?
- And they both went on to be very successful
in their own ways, and they both lied about their age
to get in.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- He had a really weird relationship with his wife,
didn't he?
- Did he?
- Joan Crock.
So she, Crock suddenly becomes a funny asser name
when he was actually a Joan.
So I think first of all they were married
when he said he wanted to buy the Padres
and she said is that a monastery?
And then it seems like they must have had some tensions
'cause first of all she launched an alcoholism charity
called Operation Cork, which is Crock,
his surname spelled backwards.
And she used to produce TV dramas
about the impact of alcoholism on families
'cause I think he was an alcoholic.
So she said she raised awareness about that.
But also when he died in 1984 she immediately gave away
the estate and distributed all the money
to all these like some great charities.
And also she gave a million dollars
to the Democratic Party, which is a slap in the face
because Ray Crock was a massive Republican.
He'd given like quarter of a million to Nixon's re-election campaign.
So yeah, she sort of undid his legacy in some ways.
- And she was amazing for the baseball team as well
'cause after he passed away she took over
but she knew virtually nothing about baseball.
But in that first season after she took over
her team made it to the World Series.
- Well it seems like she knew a lot about baseball
on like her husband.
(laughs)
- Well she learned, yeah she learned on the go,
yeah he definitely didn't like it.
He at one point after the Padres had lost 102 games
said I bought the team to have some fun
but it's proving to be about as enjoyable as a wake
your own, that was his public comment about his own team.
- Your guy called Big Mac.
- Yeah.
- I went on the internet and searched
for some other names of baseball players
and I found that there was a guy called Thomas Lewis Fries
and another one called Philip Douglas Koch.
So you can have Big Mac fries and coke with the players.
Some other players, Cannonball, Ticcom, Jolly Dick Shot.
- Lovely.
- His nickname was Ugly so people called him Ugly Dick Shot
and Wonderful Mounds.
- No.
- His name is nice.
- Wonderful, sorry that's a nickname surely.
- His first name was Wonderful,
his second name was Terrific.
- What?
- No.
- Wonderful Terrific.
- Actually Wonderful Mounds.
- Okay.
- I mean it wasn't the surname that I was quibbling with.
(laughs)
- Wonderful Terrific Mounds.
That's a good name, isn't it?
- Yes, it's a lovely.
- Well there's a guy in basketball called Metaworld Peace.
That's his name.
He's playing for China now
and he's changed his name to Panda.
- Okay.
- He just keeps going for the name changes.
- This is an American footballer called Lion King.
- Sir, Lion King, first name Lion.
- Yeah, cool.
- That's so good.
- Did you know chicken nuggets were almost onion nuggets?
They trial the two, not realizing
that people might prefer chicken.
They almost made them onions.
- That might be nice, like an onion bargie.
- I think so.
- Or an onion ring.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- It's like an onion ring, but it's an onion ball.
- Yeah, fine.
- It's like an onion bargie, in fact.
- Yeah, yeah.
(laughs)
Yeah.
There's a point.
Do you know there's a secret rebel McDonald's operating
in India?
- Ah, this is very cool.
- I need to blow in their cover.
- Yeah, well sorry guys.
There was a big kerfuffle between McDonald's global
and the Indian version of McDonald's.
- Do they make chicken bargies?
- I don't know if they do.
I hope they do.
They do do a thing called McSpicy Peneer,
which is very popular, it sells out every day,
but they canceled their franchise agreement
with 150 restaurants.
They said, "Oh, it's not working out for whatever reason."
And the restaurants kept on going, selling the food.
- Right.
- And no one stopped them or intervened.
And they've left up the golden archers and everything,
and they're still trading under the McDonald's name.
Yeah.
- Yeah, the archers aren't always golden.
There are a few exceptions,
one of which is in Sedona in Arizona
and their turquoise, why, get any guesses?
Why?
- 'Cause the yellowness blends into the desert,
so you can't see it.
- Exactly.
- No, it was, it was actually said,
it sort of clashed too much with it.
- Oh, so the opposite.
- Yeah, but yeah.
You're the right kind of line.
So yeah, the government said,
look, that kind of clashes with our desert.
It looks silly, do something else.
Yeah.
- I read that the guy who created the golden archers
was offered a deal very early on in the day
of a cut of it forever on,
or a one off payment, which was a very low sum.
- They always take the very low sum.
- Yeah, they take the low sum.
- They always go in and they say,
well, offer you this very low sum.
- I love you, money for the rest of your life
and they always take it.
- Yeah.
- They never even specify the low sum, do they?
They just say, very low sum, do you want it?
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for a final fact of the show
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that
the yellow-billed ox-pecker bird sleeps in giraffe's armpits.
- Mmm. - It's so cool.
- Nice.
- We've known for a long time
that they kind of hang out on these African animals
like giraffe and water buffalo and stuff like that.
But they've only just found out that they stay there
overnight as well.
And that comes from a multi-year camera trap study
in Tanzania, Serengeti National Park.
And so they're putting the cameras on these animals
in the middle of the night
and they found that the birds stay there.
And it seems that usually they stay there
and they have this symbiotic relationship
where they eat all the little bugs
that live in the giraffe's armpits
and they get the protection of the giraffe.
- Not just the armpits as well.
- Yes. - The legs, it's all the pits.
- The crotch is crotch every one of the pits.
- Okay, so you can get up to seven birds
in a single crotch.
(laughing)
- That was that.
A YouTube video we used to watch
in the first year of uni, I think,
so the birds are one crotch, yeah.
(laughing)
But it's really good, the giraffes are great.
They're great beds because they're off the ground,
meaning you're a bit safer as a bird,
whereas buffalo lie down and they're unstable.
Giraffes stable.
- Wait, except when a giraffe sleeps,
because they've been seen in the wild
to be sleeping while laying down.
And what they do is they bend around
and they use their butt as a pillow.
So they bring their head right around
and rest it on the top of their butt.
- That's nice.
- So I would say the best thing about being a giraffe,
actually, you can do that.
- It must be right.
I mean, we would all kill to do that.
But oxpeckers, they eat the little animals,
but they also eat the host bodily fluids,
including mucus, blood and snot,
and even the goop that you get in your eyes.
- Yeah.
- They also like to live on zebras.
And I read one article, I'll just read a bit of it.
Still in its statue-like pose,
the zebra raised its tail quickly
and held it out behind its body.
The oxpecker immediately scuttled down
onto the hairless black shiny skin
that surrounds the zebra's anal region
and worked this area assiduously.
- Sounds like an extract from six birds one crotch.
(laughing)
- Ooh, I've got a fact about symbiotic
analist relationships.
- Right.
- So there's a kind of leech called plackob,
plackob deloidies, jager skeoldi,
which is a leech, which lives inside hippo anuses.
It spends most of its life, in fact, inside a hippo's bottom.
And they live for about 2.6 years.
So they were covered in the new scientist in 1995
and the headline was, "Leech rides the tunnel of love."
'Cause it's safe from oxpeckers, actually.
It's safer if you go right into the bottom
and they have to swim into a hippo's bottom to have sex.
- Do they swim into it or do they just crawl into it?
- I think when the hippo is-
- Under water?
- Under water, I swear I'm in.
But it has special tools designed
to push open a hippo's sphincter.
- When you say tools, it's part of its body.
- It's part of its body, yeah.
- I think it's a little shovel.
(laughing)
- One really cool symbiotic relationship, I quite like.
Crabbs and urchins.
- Oh yeah. - So I didn't know about this, but-
- I hope we talk about Victorian street children here.
We're not gonna be very disappointed.
- And Jen, it's a lice, I hope.
(laughing)
- Of course.
- Cool, Blimey, Gavna.
So you're crab-proof-harving.
(laughing)
- Spot scratching your crotch, Dodger.
- No, it's neither of those things.
I see urchins and it's just crabs, like normal crabs.
And so urchins travel on the back of crabs,
which is useful for them, as it means they can travel.
So urchins can't really travel very well otherwise.
- See the world?
- Exactly, get out there, take some photos.
- On the gap, yeah.
(laughing)
- Right, some urchin postcards, but it's good for the crab
because they can suddenly use it as a disguise
or a weapon if they need to.
So they can sometimes get the urchin down with their claw
or face something with the urchin
and act like they've got a really awesome spiky back.
- Yeah, wow.
- I've got another one, just while we're on
the symbiotic relationship role, there's an ant,
which is called Campanosa Schmitze, which is a great name.
And it only lives on a single species of pitcher plant.
You know, pitcher plants, they're the ones that consume prey
by, I think they fall into, they drown.
- Yeah.
- So they look like a chum.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Oh wow.
- But the ants swim around in the digestive fluids
of the plant, they consume the nectar of the plant
and they also consume some of the prey that the plant eats,
but the plants which have ants swimming around
in their stomachs, basically, get bigger than those
which don't have them because the ants keep the traps clean
and they hunt mosquito larvae, which would otherwise
soak up more nutrients.
So it's beneficial to, if you're a pitcher plant,
to have ants in your stomach.
And the plants also eat the ants poo.
- Nice, as well as eating the ants.
- They don't eat the ants, the ants survive in there,
the ants are tolerated within the system.
- Yeah, you get some pitcher plants, don't you,
where you get little shrews who sit on the,
on the side of them and then poo into them
just like little toilets.
Yeah, and they eat the nitrogen of those.
- What's the benefit for the shrew,
'cause they don't mind where they poo.
- Just gets a toilet, you know, for dinner.
- Is that enjoyable?
'Cause they--
- Yeah, yes, 'cause it can sit there reading its iPhone.
- Okay, that makes sense.
- It's beneficial, you wouldn't like it
if we took away your toilet from you, Dan.
But if the concept of toilets didn't exist for us,
I would just poo here right now.
- They've now got the concept of toilets,
so they have to go as a pitcher plant.
- They don't, I mean, Dan's also very sick of question here.
What is going on?
- No animal understands the importance
of a good sewerage system except humans.
One earth is a shrew clamping up at the top of the flower
in order to take a shit where I was just doing it all around.
- I think what happens is it eats something from the flower,
maybe some nectar or something,
and that is a laxative, and then that makes it poo.
I believe that's true.
- So it almost can't get out in time.
It's kind of like a zine or something,
and it sort of has to poo in the shower.
- It's like a delicious restaurant,
but with very bad hygiene standards.
But then they use your poo to power the electricity.
- Oh, wow.
- Where is this restaurant?
- I feel a start-up coming on.
- Hey, I've got something on armpits.
In the 19th century in Austria,
there used to be the thing where, at Dancers,
women would carry underneath their armpits
a single slice of apple,
and they would hold it there all night long,
and the idea was at the end of the night,
the girl would approach someone who they'd fancy
to guy if it was a guy that they fancy.
They would go up and they would take the apple out,
and they would present the apple.
- They still do that on Love Island, I think, do they?
(all laughing)
- I think I'm sure.
- So it was sent to the guy, and if the guy eats it,
he's saying, "I'm keen."
- Yeah.
- Wow.
And is there any way for him to say,
"I'm keen without eating the armpit."
- But I think if you're not willing to eat the apple
that's been inside the armpit of your loved one,
you don't love her at all.
- You're not keen enough.
So women's armpits smell of onion,
and men's smell of cheese, apparently.
And this is--
- Well, between us, we can have a delicious bag of crisps.
(all laughing)
- You know those like salt and shake crisps
that you used to get where they don't taste of anything,
but you have to put your own--
- Yeah, absolutely.
- Are you proposing that you scissors someone else's armpit
with one crisp in the middle,
and you're gonna lovely cheese and onion--
- I'm gonna go to an Austrian dance.
(all laughing)
- I think it doesn't cost any more just to buy cheese
and onion rather than just buying cheese
and then wiping it up against a woman's armpit.
- That's true.
- I don't see why you would.
- Those crisps, they used to be the same price
as ready salted crisps,
but you still had to put extra work in.
- That's so weird.
- It was fun.
- Yeah, it was fun.
- But this is about compounds in their armpits,
by the way, this isn't just people sniffing them
and saying, "Oh, that's oniony."
- Okay.
- This is the compound that women's armpits generate
is something called as a thio alcohol,
which when it combines with a bacteria smells like onion,
and then men's sweat has--
- Would you say alcohol?
- Yeah, but don't go licking women's armpits for that.
Again, it's not worth it, I'll buy you a beer.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @tribaland, James.
- @JamesHarkin.
- Andy.
- @AndreyHunterM.
- And Chazinsky.
- You can email podcast@ky.com.
- Yep, that's right, you can go to our group account,
@nosuchthing or our Facebook page.
No such thing as a fish or a website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
Do go there, it's got all of our previous episodes.
It's got links to our upcoming shows.
We are always doing live shows
to check it out if you ever wanna see us.
It has everything from book links.
It's just got it all.
It's where we put our things.
Okay, we'll be back again next week.
See you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)