(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here
with James Harkin, Anna Tyshinski, and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that indigenous Bolivian women
traditionally wear huge, colorful skirts and bowler hats.
(laughing)
And I can't believe I'd never really seen this before.
It's striking, and they all do.
So these are, they tend to be known as Cholitas,
which is basically a term for like the Aymara and the Quechua
and other rural Bolivian women.
- Not Charlie Chaplin, as it sort of sounds like,
the Cholitas.
- It's a, I know you're trying to make a jump
to the Charlie Chaplin bowler hat,
and I appreciate that.
- Yeah, so like his fan club, you know,
all these like Lady Gaga's, I call them monsters.
- Beliebers, yeah.
- Maybe you've blown this wide open,
that is why they do it.
So Cholitas, it used to be a pejorative term I think,
and it was, it comes from the Spanish Cholo for mixed race,
but it's like very much reclaimed by them now.
And if you look them up,
they always wear these stunning kind of white,
like silky waistcoats with a brooch
and these huge dresses with like petticoats underneath.
So like really big Elizabethan style dresses.
And then a bowler hat, which doesn't fit.
- But it does work.
It makes the look awesome.
- Oh, it works in that way.
- Oh yeah.
- And it works in like a, you know,
because bowler hats were originally invented
to stop twigs from hurting your head when they,
so I wondered if...
- It would probably stop a twig from hurting your head.
- It's not functional.
- I'm talking fashion, I was saying it works.
- That works, it does work.
Yes, and we're not quite sure why they do it.
They started doing it the turn of the 20th century.
There's the legend that when British
and Irish railway workers were in Bolivia,
which they worked, the railway building company
was a British company.
There was a big shipment of bowler hats
that was sent for them to wear.
'Cause it was like workers hats and they were too small.
So some clever marketing person flogged them
to the indigenous women.
I think there was a guy called Domingo Solingo,
who did a very good job of popularizing them
and like ran a good PR campaign.
- Try to get men to wear it first
from one of the other stories, versions of the story.
And they were just not interested.
So they're just as a last minute thing when women,
- But then, when he was walking along
with a tray of samples one day, he tripped over
and one of the hats fell onto a woman's head.
And completely by accident, he discovered.
- That's so interesting, 'cause they are, I mean,
they are comically small.
They're not like, you know, just a little bit too small
to go on your head, are they?
- They're not like yamulka, if you're a bit string.
It's like, yeah, just--
- They're clearly too small.
It's what I'm saying. - They sit on top.
They sit on top. - They sit on top.
- So I mean, who were they made for, is my--
- Yes.
- This happened, we have this in the house all the time
where you order something and then a novelty small sized
version comes in the post.
That must be what it was. - What?
- You know, like, we bought a crown
for my son, Will's birthday and it arrived
and it was the size that would fit a Kendall's head
by accident because we just hadn't read the measurements.
We got a washing line. - I'm not telling you the measurements.
- Need to read the measurements.
They clearly didn't hear as well.
- One thing I like about the charita thing
is that they, I didn't really, I mean,
I didn't know anything about this style before
or even this cultural grouping before researching this,
but they weren't allowed to walk freely
in the main square of La Paz,
which is the capital of Bolivia,
or in the wealthy suburbs in this outfit for many years.
And then it's really been brought back on board
to the extent that they're officially a part
of the city's cultural heritage now.
It's called the charita of La Paz.
And also there are charita fashion shows.
There is a charita modeling agency
and I'm sure you guys came across the Fighting Charitas.
- Oh yeah, I did not, I'd like to hear about
the Fighting Charitas. - It's just a wrestling group,
but they're female wrestlers who wrestle in traditional--
- With the hat. - With the hat.
- Do they do like odd job?
- The odd job kill.
Yeah, they do, yeah.
They die by the dozen every man.
Anyway, the Fighting Charitas, they're all right.
- That's the one where they play golf, isn't it?
- Golf. (laughing)
- That's the only Bond film I've seen,
the one where they play golf.
- Did you Google Bond film golf?
- I just Google golf and it came up.
- Right, do you have, you know, there's an app
that can tell you when to go to the toilet at the cinema,
like toilet break.
Do you have an app that just tells you
when golf scenes are in a movie?
- Yeah, yeah. - And you just show up
for that bit?
- I do, I only ever watched Caddy Shack in that Bond film.
(laughing)
- They are a real happy story,
which, you know, we're all on the lookout for these days,
but I think it was basically since Eva Morales
was in charge of Bolivia, right,
who was their first indigenous president,
who came in the early 2000s
and sort of completely rehabilitated their reputations
'cause they had been kind of ostracized
and had all these horrible repressive rules
made against them.
And now they're doing so well
and it's a real great story and they're quite well off.
They've got all these celebrations about their heritage.
They have, I think they have a few indigenous people
in parliament, they're like lawyers and doctors
and yeah, it's quite nice 'cause they have since,
like literally back in the day when the Spanish colonized
and they wanted to distinguish them,
the superior colonists from the indigenous people.
So they said, okay, well, what do people
who were lower class do in Spain?
They wear these big peasant dresses
and so they made them all wear these big peasant dresses.
- What does that come from?
- So yeah, they put them in these,
to just say like you're beneath us
and the charlatans just went, all right,
we're gonna own this.
- It's interesting 'cause like the big dresses
come from the Spanish peasants
and the Bola hats come from British,
you know, up class people.
- Yeah, I see. - They're such a fusion.
- Yes, yeah.
Have you guys ever drunk Coca-Cola?
- No.
(laughs)
- Yes.
- What kind of a question is that?
- You might be right, you might be right that you haven't.
So this launched in April 2010 and Coca-Cola
- What is it, cola, C-O-L-L-A, Coca-Cola.
- Yeah, is a local Coca-Cola basically
that they've just manufactured on their own.
So it has a red label with white writing.
I mean, the packaging is very similar,
but it's sold as a legit product there.
They've not been in trouble.
- And they're all right with this.
Or are we now getting them in trouble
if someone knows that Coca-Cola is listening to cola?
- No, it's becoming a bigger, yeah, yeah.
- 'Cause it's named after the cola people
and the coca nut, which is in it.
- Yeah.
- And they say to Coca-Cola or Brit-Vay-Co,
everyone's Coca-Cola, they say,
"Well, you know, there's nothing you can do about it."
And I'm not sure Coca-Cola are particularly happy about it,
but there's nothing they can do.
- They're definitely not happy about it.
But they can do cool.
And they've got Coca-Leaf extracts in it as well.
So actually it's an illegal drink to be sold over here.
So they're quite regional because it's legal there,
but for us, yeah, it's a drug.
- I think we should legalize,
I mean, we should probably legalize all drugs,
but Coca-Leaves, I definitely think
we should legalize in this country.
- So we can get this cola drink?
- No, because like when I was in the Andes,
it's the best thing.
It just gives you a little bit of a pickup.
- Yeah.
- Oh, it's so useful.
Honestly, when you've got a hangover or you're tired
or anything, just chew a Coca-Leaf
and it just makes you feel so much better.
And it's just a tiny little buzz.
- Have you tried cocaine James?
You'll love it.
(all laughing)
- I think the, I think the Pope has tried the Coca-Leaves.
- I think he visited several years ago and when he went,
I think he said, oh, I'll have some of that.
So.
- Yeah, everywhere.
Like if you go to a hotel,
you know, if you go to a hotel in the UK,
they might have a bowl of Murray Mint.
- Oh, a lovely hotel would have that.
- Yeah, exactly.
Well, all the hotels in Peru and in Bolivia,
they have a bowl of these leaves
and you just pick them up and chew on them.
- It's actually a bowl, it's a bowl of a hat
upside down, isn't it?
Full of those leaves.
- Are you sure it's not just potpourri?
(all laughing)
Because it leaves your breath really,
really nice at the end of it.
- Guys, did you know, not 25 minutes walk
from where we're sitting right now,
is where the first bowl of hats were sold.
- Is that true?
- Invented and sold in St. James's Street.
I mean, it might have been invented in someone's house,
you know, but it was brought to St. James's Street
to lock and co-hatters who've been going
since like basically the 17th century
when they were founded.
And the shop is still there today.
So you can still buy hats from them.
- I think we'll pass there quite a lot, do you?
- Right, so that's where the bowl of hat is from.
- That's very exciting.
- That is exciting, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- We're gonna turn up next week in a bowl of hat
'cause I can see it, of the four of us.
- Just a comically small one, I think.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- No, that's already, it's a nice shop.
I don't think they make a huge deal out of it
on the shop front.
- No, they don't, and their legacy is huge
because they not only sell bowl of hats,
they sell all kinds of hats.
They sold Admiral Lord Nelson,
his, what was it called?
- The Bicorn. - Bicorn, sorry.
- Yeah, the Bicorn that he rode.
- Yeah, Napoleon was the Tricorn.
- You don't wanna go to use them, they get very offended.
- No one with a unicorn hat, which is insane.
(laughing)
- And I think that would've,
that would've made the Battle of Trafalgar really exciting.
- That's got the element of surprise, I think,
in the unicorn hat.
- According to Locke's, it was devised
by a pair of people called Thomas and William Bowler.
Okay, and they, Edward Cook said,
"Can you make this hat for us to Locke's?"
And Locke said, "Well, we'll get our mates,
"Thomas and William Bowler, to make it."
Now, according to the OED,
the Bowler hat gets its name because it's shaped like a bowl,
not because it's named after these guys' bowlers.
So, I don't wanna upset the people at Locke and Co,
'cause I'm sure their story is completely true,
but there is a suggestion that maybe
there's nothing to do with these Thomas and William Bowler
people, and if you do look at the kind of newspaper archives,
there was a thing called a bowl hat
that existed before the Bowler hat,
and you can see loads of examples of people
having their bowl hats stolen and stuff like that.
- So, did the Bowlers exist for the credits?
- It feels like, no, in fact, they definitely existed.
Thomas and William Bowler existed,
and actually, there was another guy called William Bowler
who existed before them, who was a famous hat maker.
So, there were bowlers who were making hats for sure,
but whether these guys invented the Bowler hat
and gave the name to it, I'm not so sure.
- Yeah. - It's tough and really torn.
- I'm not gonna walk past Locke's sharp
in case of odd job hat comes to us, you know, that's.
- Do you know what they have on Bowler hats?
The curl at the edge, which I'd actually never noticed
was a fundamental feature of them.
- What, on the brim?
- Yeah, so there's a brim,
and then it curls very sharply inwards
at a 40-degree angle, a little bit,
and it's a dorset curl, and it's named after Alfred Dorsey,
and this is niche, but he was basically,
I think he was the Byron of France.
He was apparently extremely attractive.
He was the handsomest man of his time,
and he was mates with Byron, in fact,
and he, the other time he might have seen him,
is he's the model for the New Yorker mascot.
You know if he, you know all the New Yorkers,
you've got that bloke who's actually not wearing a bowler hat.
- That's a top hat.
He wore a number of different hats, just literally.
- But that's him, his face is him, is what you're saying.
- His silhouette is him, yeah.
- Alfred Monaco?
- He's got a magnifying glass, I think,
and maybe a monocle.
- I think you're thinking of Monopoly.
- Mr. Monopoly is not exactly anything of that.
- That was actually based on Keats.
- Yeah, apparently, according to--
- Glad we settled that.
- No, Anna, that's a great knowledge about his dorset curls.
- I think let's connect the bowler hat to the New Yorker.
- Sorry, what was the link?
He invented the thing on the rim.
- It was named after him.
- The curl.
- 'Cause he was such a dandy.
- I guess he was a curly, curly dandy.
- Wow.
- That's really cool.
- Well, that's really cool as a strong term, but it's--
- It's probably the one thing I'll remember
from this podcast.
- I know, he'll be so annoyed about that.
- The Susie Dent wrote an amazing book
about how slang is used amongst different tribes of people,
so like taxi drivers and dock workers and stuff like that.
And she mentions in that section
that Hackney taxi cabs, the height of the cab,
was based on the bowler hat height for when you're getting in.
- Yep, sounds a bit dubious, but I think--
- I don't know what you're saying.
I didn't say anything.
All I did was pull a face.
And the listener didn't notice that.
- No, but I think that is a room of that sort of out there,
isn't it?
- I thought Hackney cabs were sort of for top parts,
'cause bowler hats don't really have any height.
They're the same as a head.
- That would only add another centimeter or two
to the height of the cab.
- Absolutely, but maybe a necessary extra centimeter.
It feels like you wouldn't redesign the whole cab.
- You've got quite a long torso, Andy, don't you?
Oh, do you have long legs, actually, the short torso?
- I've got a normal torso.
- Oh, sorry.
- Long, I've got a normal torso, long legs, long neck, short head.
- Okay, and that's why the Murray cab,
it has a lot of legroom, doesn't it?
- A lot of legroom, and then a very low ceiling, yeah.
- Sorry.
(laughing)
You know before we were talking about bicons,
tricons, and unicorns?
- Yeah.
- There is a, what I suppose would be a quadricon.
- No.
- Cool.
- And the quadricon is a very--
- That's too much surprise, Andy, sorry.
- That's awesome.
- The idea of a four-corner tat,
which is not worth that.
- You think that's incredible.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- It's up there with Alfred Dorsay.
- That's the thing I'm going to remember, Anna.
- I suppose the reason it's interesting
is because it is related to this fact,
because it's the traditional hat
of the Tuwanakan people of Bolivia,
and that is like a really old culture,
pre-Columbian culture in Bolivia,
and they had these very intricately designed
four-cornered hats that sort of,
the rich people would wear the intricately designed ones,
and the poor people were really plain ones,
but you'd have like birds' heads,
you would stick on there.
Some of them had wings attached to them.
- That's awesome.
- But that sounds a bit grim.
- Yeah.
- Like a decapitated bird's head.
- Maybe.
- They must have done some kind of,
you know, put pickled it or something.
- It was a different time.
- It's popular back in the day
to put dead birds and things, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- A full bird, yeah.
- Not a decap...
Okay, gotcha.
- Not just chopping the head off and sticking it on.
- The bloodied neck sort of hanging out.
- I think they wiped that away.
- Yeah.
- The birds.
Is that where we get, like wearing a knotted handkerchief
on your head at the beach from this tribe?
- Absolutely not, no.
(laughing)
- That would be quite unusual for this culture
to come back to life having, you know,
gone out before the Spanish came along
and then traveled to 1950s seaside hotels.
(laughing)
- That would be unusual.
- One of the greatest test pilots in America
for wartime planes was a gorilla
wearing a bowler hat, smoking a cigar.
- Okay.
- And what I've done there is tricked you
because actually, because actually it was a man.
(laughing)
- What's your career?
- Oh, no, I do.
- Oh, no, I don't allow you to say that.
This is a guy called Jack Valentine-Willems
and he was one of the greatest test pilot pilots
that were out there.
And he used to take out planes that weren't ready,
that they were, it was advanced technology.
(laughing)
- Why would you do that?
- Well, you know, you got a test pilot,
he's testing.
- No, but it is ready, right?
He's not taking a plane with one wing.
- No, no, but you're, sorry.
As in, we don't know the limits
to which we can push this particular plane.
So he would push it to places to see if it worked.
- He just made it sound like he was sneaking
into the hangar at night.
- Sorry.
- No, these are, they were approved flights.
And what he used to do is a bit of a practical joker
is he used to bring with him a gorilla mask
and he used to bring a polar hat and a cigar.
And he would fly up to other processions of planes
that were flying and he would have that gear on
and he would wave at the other pilots.
And I think from what I've read,
the idea was is that no one would believe anything
about the plane, let alone the pilot.
They came and said, I saw a new plane
and it was being flown by a gorilla
with a cigar and a polar hat.
That sounds a bit pushed for me.
I think actually he was just a practical joker.
But the idea was he was gonna say,
no one would believe that pilot existed.
Therefore, they might not believe the plane existed.
That was being tested either.
- It was interesting that you tried
his practical joke on us, didn't you?
'Cause he was trying to make people
think a gorilla was flying the plane
and you also kind of made us, no, you didn't.
- Believed it.
- Yeah.
- But it was less dangerous in this context
'cause we're just sitting around a table.
Whereas I think making a prank
out of putting off pilots flying actual planes
is very responsible.
Well, they're quite a lot of comical,
a pilot gets so distracted they fly into a mountain.
- Oh, yeah.
- Yeah.
400 deaths were resulted.
A comical flying into the mountain.
(laughing)
- Another death in the army today
and man, was it funny.
We close our show with this white-hearted story.
- I think it was picturing the cartoon version.
(upbeat music)
- Okay.
It is time for fact number two and that is James.
My fact this week is that there are no animals
in the only zoo in Kalamazoo.
(laughing)
- What a sad lot of children there must be in Kalamazoo.
- Yeah.
- Oh, what?
It sounds great.
- Does it?
- Oh, yeah.
- What is there?
- It's the air zoo.
- I see.
- It's the air zoo and the air zoo is a museum
about aeroplanes which has lots of planes
that are named after animals.
- Okay.
'Cause it does sound like the air zoo is what they've called it
'cause all the cages are just full of air.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- It sounds like an air guitar.
- Yeah.
- You're right.
It does sound like that,
but actually it's a really awesome air museum.
- So planes that are named after animals.
So I'm thinking immediately,
I'm thinking the Sopwith Camel.
- It's probably an animal.
- I don't know if there is one of those.
- Okay.
- All I know is that there's a war hawk,
a goonie bird, a wild cat, a bear cat and a hell cat.
- Oh, these are very American animal play names.
- It's very American.
Yeah, Kalamazoo is in the north of United States of America.
- Yeah.
- Michigan.
- In Michigan.
- Yeah.
- The hell cat.
- Yeah, it's a very.
The Sopwith Camel is a very British animal play name.
(laughing)
- Okay.
- Ridiculous.
- A goonie bird sounds quite British as well.
- No, I still think that's a bit of an American.
- Like a goonie bird.
- You gotta see the goonie bird.
- Yeah, you do.
- It could be.
- I was thinking goon show.
Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So yeah, and actually on the war hawk,
sorry you just mentioned that,
the person who runs this museum who's called Sue Parrish,
she was one of the last 20 members
of the women's Air Force service pilots from World War II
who still flew planes and she flew a bright pink war hawk.
- That's great.
- Is she still alive?
- She was still alive when I read an article
a few years, it was from a few years ago,
I couldn't tell whether she died or not.
- I think she's not, yeah.
- Yeah, the article actually I read was from the early 90s,
so she might have died since then.
- She has, so there's an airport,
which is Battle Creek and Kalamazoo Airport.
There's a statue of her.
- Oh, is that?
- I believe it's at the airport.
If it's not the airport, it's someone of the vicinity.
- I didn't see that.
- And you can also see her plane,
which is, as you said, pink.
Kind of cool.
- Do you know why I was pink this airplane?
- Oh, oh, oh, oh.
- Yes, because she only flew it
when it was Red Sky at night,
which happens to light in the evenings,
and it was a cauliflower-ish thing.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Not far off in fairness, just wrong,
but not a million miles from.
- Is it, no, you're right.
- Dan, please, I've got it.
She flew only among flocks of flamingos,
and it was a cauliflower-ish thing.
- We're getting wrong, guy.
- Okay.
- It was because she's a woman,
a women-like pink thing.
No, it wasn't, it wasn't.
- Damn it.
- It was because it was originally flown in Libya,
these planes, and the landscape,
lots of, you know, rocks and sand,
and quite pink sand and stuff like that.
And so it just helped to blend into the landscape.
- Okay, so it's not hot pink?
- No, it's not hot pink.
It's not fluorescent.
It's pink, it is quite pink.
- It's pretty pink.
Yeah, it looks awesome.
And I think that's in the entrance
when you go into the Arab museum,
as opposed to the airport.
- Yeah, and after World War II,
she wanted to become a commercial pilot,
but she got rejected in letters saying,
"With your qualifications, if you were a man,
"we would have hired you."
- Oh, well, that's nice consolation, though, isn't it?
- It's awful, that is.
- It's the highest praise you can give, really.
- Yeah, absolutely.
But yeah, basically I remembered
that there was a place called Kalamazoo,
and I Googled to see if there was a zoo there,
and there isn't, but there is this place.
- I didn't know anything about Kalamazoo
before starting to research it.
Apart from, of course, the Glenn Miller song,
I've Got a Girl in Kalamazoo in 1942.
- Put it on the map, internationally, in a way.
- But it's named as one of those places
which has a funny name, and no one really knows
where it is or if it's real, and it's kind of, you know,
it's lumped in with places like Timbuktu,
which have an interesting--
- I wonder why.
It's like--
- Exactly.
- With your writing songs.
- Exactly, but Kalamazoo, get this.
I'm only getting in with this fact before you guys all do,
'cause I know you'll all have it, too,
was the first place in the world to install dropped curbs.
(laughing)
- Is that a curb where you can get like a buggy down,
you mean, like it goes flat?
- It's as it sounds.
The curb has been dropped so that you can,
yeah, so you can get a buggy down.
- That's quite amazing, isn't it?
- I know.
- Do they have a blue plaque there?
They must have.
- Well, there are lots of claims as to what, you know,
there are other cities which try to steal Kalamazoo's thunder.
They're all, I think, incorrect.
I think this was the first city where you had dropped--
- How deep have you had to dig for this?
This is a full day's work.
- There was this veteran from the second of my walk,
who was Jack Fisher, who was an advocate
for both veterans and disability rights,
and he trialed them.
In America, they're called curb cuts,
and they were first tried out here.
- That's incredible.
- What year were we talking?
- I think it was the late '40s or early '50s,
and there are other places
which tried them in the early '60s.
There was another thing in the '60s,
and I think in America,
there was some disability activists
who hacked away at curbs at night
and laid concrete to smooth their path.
- That makes sense, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
They only did it on a few occasions in a few places,
but when you say he tested it,
what's interesting about it
is it feels it doesn't need testing.
It feels just logical, right?
It just doesn't, what do they think might go wrong?
- Well, I guess it's never been done before,
and he's just pointing out,
"Look, this would make it a lot easier
for lots of people to get around
if you install these things."
So they say, "All right, well, we'll install a few."
And then, obviously, you just see how it works.
- I mean, things that can go wrong
is it allows dickheads like me
to pop your bike up on the pavement
while you're cycling and really upset pedestrians.
He didn't think of that, did he?
- No.
- He didn't think of that, the idiot.
- I don't know.
- Same with my car.
(all laughing)
- Kalamazoo originally was called Bronson,
and it was because a guy called Titus Bronson
was the first white man, basically,
to arrive there and set up a town there.
And then, yeah, he turned it into a place
where the streets were kind of named very obviously
for the thing that they were operating as.
So there was Church Street,
where you'd have three churches on there.
There was the Academy, which had the college on it.
There was Jail Street.
- Jail Street.
- It makes sense, doesn't it?
- Yeah, it makes total sense.
- You know where everything is.
- I think the church one is weird,
'cause I know that, so there's a thing in capitalism,
right, where if you've got a shop
that sells a certain thing, like baby clothes,
then you have lots of shops in the same area,
they cluster, because that works.
- Like the Curry Mile in Manchester
with all the Curry houses. - Exactly.
But churches, you rarely are like,
well, we've got to fit 10 churches into this county.
Shall we just put them all on the same street?
- Yeah, absolutely true.
- It's interesting.
- The story goes that Bronson was in Detroit,
and he walked west into the woods,
and he kept going until he got out of the woods,
and this was where Kalamazoo was.
He walked, it's 140 miles walk
until he got to any kind of clearing.
There's this, we're not quite sure why,
but he definitely left town at one stage.
Now, he might have left town
because they changed the name to Kalamazoo,
or he might have left town
because he stole a cherry tree.
- Yeah.
- He was run out of town.
- I love that, the cherry tree.
- And there's a few different stories,
and it's not clear what's what,
because if you look at contemporary reports,
neither of them is mentioned.
But there is a 1909 headline
from the Detroit Free Press that says,
"Because of the name of the village he founded
"was changed to Kalamazoo, Titus Bronson died
"of a broken heart."
- Ah.
- And so when they changed the name,
apparently it hurt him so much that he died.
- They have gone by a lot of different names.
They used to be called the Celery City.
- What, they grew a lot of celery?
- They grew a lot of celery.
Someone came over and grew celery there.
Actually it was a Scott, I think, called George,
apparently George Celery Taylor, he was known as.
But you know how you never know
if people were actually called that at the time?
- Like the bowlers from earlier.
- Like the bowl?
- No, that definitely was the name.
- Yeah, but that could have been like the trade
that then became the name.
- No, but they didn't name themselves out of the hats.
They were, "I'm saying we don't know."
- "I'm saying we do."
- Ah, okay, well there we go.
- One of the reasons that Kalamazoo is mentioned
in a lot of songs, so you mentioned,
who do you mention before? - Glenn Miller.
- Glenn Miller.
- So Kalamazoo in other songs by Frank Zappa,
Ben Folds, Johnny Cash, The Black Keys,
who I know you like.
I think there's Kalamazoo mentioned in there.
And I think one of the reasons is
'cause Gibson guitars were made in Kalamazoo.
- Yeah.
- And loads of famous people, Chuck Berry,
Eric Clapton, Cheryl Crowe, Bob Dylan,
all people use Gibson guitars.
And really interesting thing about the Gibsons
is the Gibson girls.
Now during World War II,
the Gibson guitar company was still making guitars,
but the thing was they didn't have anyone
to make the guitars, right?
Because all the men had gone to war.
So what they did was they brought in all the local women
to make these guitars, but they denied making them.
And the reason being that they thought that,
one, if we told people we're making guitars during the war,
people would think we're being really frivolous
and we shouldn't be doing this kind of thing.
But secondly, they weren't sure
whether people would buy guitars
if they knew they were made by women.
- Right.
- So they sold them as what they called new old stock.
So they pretended that these were old guitars
that they had in stock and they were selling during the war.
We're not making them during the war,
but actually all these women were doing all the work.
And they also sometimes said
that they were made by seasoned craftsmen
who were too old for war.
- Yeah, right.
- Right.
- Wow.
- I mean, not brilliant, obviously.
Sorry.
- It's good, Mark.
You can appreciate the marketing.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Did the women who were making them
leave any kind of clues as to the fact they,
like, inside, did they write?
- Drop a tampon into the body of the guitar.
(all laughing)
- Use tampons and just rattling around in there.
- Yeah, yeah.
- That was the key to their individual sound, actually.
(all laughing)
- Just a couple more things on Kalamazoo.
Notable person from there.
William Shakespeare.
Junior.
And what I did there was trick you to make you think.
- It was actually a gorilla.
- It's actually a gorilla.
- He's William Shakespeare Junior.
He was an inventor, quite a notable inventor there.
So he was around in the 1800s,
and he invented what's known as the Shakespeare fishing tackle,
which is a really big thing that's still used today.
Do you know it?
- No, I'm just trying to think of the pun.
(all laughing)
- Me too, me too.
Yeah, so yeah, fishing tackle, lots of innovations
of that sort.
He had patents for camera equipment and so on.
- Cast, casting, now.
- Oh yeah.
You can say whatever you want now for the next five minutes.
- Yeah, well I'm trying to debate, it's not working.
- Okay, no, I'll join now.
Anna, you take over.
- Anyway, let's scale.
- God, astonishing, you run through his plays.
There are almost no fish puns.
- It's bad, isn't it?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Amidst some nice brim.
- Very good.
- Nice, there you go.
- There you go.
- Thank God.
- Can we move on?
Is that, is that?
- No.
- I get we're still doing it.
(laughing)
- God, Andy.
- Macro Beth.
- No.
- No, that's nice, that's great.
- That's good, that's good.
- Yeah, we'll take it.
- Yeah.
As you pike it.
- Oh, very nice.
- Lovely, I'll tell you off, you guys all got one.
(laughing)
- All right, if you have one at home,
then why not send it to Andrew Hunter M?
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that some American gravestones
feature recipes.
- Hmm.
- Yummy, yummy.
- I've had to cook the human below it?
- Yes.
(laughing)
- This is a thing that happens sometimes in the States.
The original wording of the fact was,
lots of American gravestones contain recipes
and it was pointed out that they're about 11 so far.
(laughing)
There was a query over whether that's technically lots
or not, which is fair.
But there are people who have made it their hobby
to track down all gravestones which feature recipes
and bake 'em up.
And it's especially big on places like TikTok.
There are lots of grave people on TikTok
and they're nicknamed Tapophiles,
which is people who love graves and cemeteries and--
- Is that what, it's on TikTok?
'Cause I haven't been on TikTok.
I didn't realize it was that.
I thought it was like dancing and stuff.
- It's not all of TikTok.
Yeah, there's a lot, again,
when I say lots of people on TikTok do it,
some people on TikTok do it.
(laughing)
It's more effort than filming it or dance.
But it's not really interesting.
- Well, I like TikTok Tapophiles.
It's a nice elicitation, isn't it, worth becoming one?
- Yeah.
These grave recipes, some of them date back decades
or further than that.
- I just thought TikTok, it's like,
what do you call that thing that reminds you of death?
- The pendulum, the reaper.
- Oh, Memento Mori.
- Memento Mori, isn't it?
So whenever you think about TikTok--
- TikTok.
- Is it very morbid place TikTok?
Is it one big Memento Mori?
- It's just thinking about the number of seconds
you have left.
- Yeah, the number of seconds you spent watching this, crap.
(laughing)
Yeah.
- Wow, so--
- Yeah, so people are doing it on making up the recipes
and then showing them on their TikTok videos, right?
- Yeah, people are going around doing that.
- Any examples?
- Well, there's a lovely Fudge recipe.
There is blueberry pie.
There's yeast cake.
- But it doesn't always work.
Sometimes there was one gravestone
which had a typo in the recipe on it.
- Oh, no.
- I know, and it would have made very runny fudge
if you made it according to that.
But thankfully--
- What was the typo?
I want to know what typo is that makes runny fudge.
- It was too much vanilla.
- Oh, really?
- But it's a tablespoon as opposed to a teaspoon,
I believe was the--
- That's not gonna make it that runny.
Is it just, that's not much difference.
Like it's not like a kilogram versus a gram.
'Cause you don't put much vanilla in a Fudge recipe.
It's just a tiny amount.
- Well, that's why.
Because if you do a tablespoon,
apparently it turns out vapor.
Anyway, they corrected the entire gravestone
off the back of that, which is a relief.
- Why would you, yeah.
Trying to look out why you would do it.
- Do what, put a recipe on?
- Yeah.
- Well, people like to be creative
on their gravestones, right?
It's a really fun thing.
And passing down your great recipe, I think.
- I think that's what it is.
I think it's something that matters to you,
something that's traditional,
something that a recipe you might have inherited
from the generation above you.
I see it.
- People like to pass on recipes
to the next generation, don't they?
And what about a place?
- I guess it's very little you can pass on.
You could pass on like a series of dance moves.
I'm trying to think of something else.
You might pass on to the next generation.
But you're right, recipes are probably it.
- Dance moves.
On your grave is encouraging people to dance on your grave.
- You could have a set of those footprint outlines.
- Like they have in Japan.
I was thinking like, you know those games
that you play in Japan where you can dance.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- What were they like up?
- Well, I was just thinking,
I'd like mine to be kind of like that MOLWAKA game.
So you put a coin into the grave
and then my head pops out from one other side.
You gotta slam it with a hammer.
Then my arm comes out another and then my leg.
- It'd be so annoying if you're one of those people
who wasn't actually dead
and tries to escape from your grave.
But it's been constantly malleted down.
- You guys don't, seriously.
(laughing)
- But I think it's great.
I mean, there are so many gravestones around the world
where people as their sort of like last wish
have said, can you make this happen?
And people do and they're beautiful.
And I'd read a great one.
There was a 99 year old woman who in Mexico,
her dying wish was for her gravestone
to be made according to what she loved most in life.
And so she got it.
It was a 600 pound, five foot tall penis.
Just a giant penis.
- What she loved in life, a five foot penis.
- She loved calling people dicks in life, apparently.
And that's what she asked for.
And I've seen the video of them unveiling it.
It looks like it's got a giant condom over the top of it,
which is then removed.
It's a huge pink penis, like five foot five.
- But unfortunately, if you're in Libya,
you couldn't see it.
(laughing)
- The testicles, apparently,
they really had a lot of problem with
because the ball sack apparently kept just disfiguring
during the melting process of the actual materials,
which was, I believe, plastic.
And so they had to like build the testicles
quite a few times.
And they're big balls when you see it.
So it's sort of standing up.
- Right.
- Anyway, is this, is it a churchyard
or a cemetery surrounded by other?
I can imagine being slightly annoyed
if I had the grave next door.
- Totally, absolutely.
- By that time, it can't be annoyed.
- No, it's true.
- I know you're an easily annoyed person, Andy,
but I reckon that after death,
you're not going to be under there going.
(laughing)
- He will.
- If I can, I will.
That's what it's going to say on his tombstone.
(laughing)
- I'm so with you, though.
If I was a relative of someone who'd been buried next to that,
I would find that so irritating.
- But this is what happens a lot in the UK.
Certainly, so many graves are the traditional,
whether it's slate or, you know,
it's normally, it's grazed stone and it's carved
and it's all down to the individual church
or individual local authority.
And so there's this mad, you know,
if you want something out of the ordinary,
you might get it approved, but you really might not.
Like shape-wise, like a big penis.
- Shape-wise and colour-wise,
and there are rules about what you can and can't carve,
but there's no one authority in the UK
which tells you what you can't get.
- It feels like we shouldn't have that.
And it does feel reasonable to say no penises.
- Yeah.
- I don't know.
- I agree, I agree, definitely.
- Well, on that and gravestones,
there's an amazing cemetery in Paris,
the Peer-Lachaise Cemetery,
and it's got loads of good graves in it.
But one of them's the grave of Victor Noir,
who was a 19th century journalist.
And he wasn't that famous in his lifetime.
I think he was shot by Napoleon Bonaparte's nephew in 1870.
- Wow.
- And loads of people suddenly went to his funeral
because it became this kind of political cause.
But for some reason, we don't know why.
His effigy, so on his gravestone,
there's a big bronze effigy of him lying down.
It has a bulge in his crotch.
- Oh, yeah.
- It's quite tight trousers, lovely big penis bulge.
And what's so rank about it is that it's a bit like,
you know, there's Grave Fry's Bobby and Edinburgh,
a famous dog statue,
and everyone always rubs its nose for luck.
So that's really shiny.
And in the same way, everyone keeps rubbing and mounting
and writhing against this crotch.
So it's incredibly shiny.
And not only that, it's not just the crotch,
but his lips and nose.
- Well, the kiss is lit.
Yeah, the kiss is lit.
- I know, do they do to his nose?
(laughing)
But what?
I mean, that's, cause that's not just rubbing.
They've mounted fully.
- Yeah, yeah.
So it's a fertility thing.
You go and you do that if you want to get pregnant.
- People say that, but it's not.
It's people going for a joke.
Everyone's like, this is 20th century.
This is people going to France and going.
- It's for Instagram, isn't it?
That's great.
There is a sign that says any damage caused by graffiti
or in decent rubbing will be prosecuted.
- Oh.
- It's just there.
- It's all in decent rubbing.
(laughing)
- What's decent rubbing?
Yeah, that's actually a better question, yeah.
- But I always think with these,
they would be the best place for like a zombie apocalypse
to start where there's loads of famous people.
- Oh, that would be great.
- Or like Westminster Abbey.
That's where you want your zombie apocalypse to start,
isn't it?
Where all the famous people are buried.
- I think Jim Morrison is in the one
you were just talking about as well, I believe.
That's really good.
- 'Cause that's a good mix.
Westminster Abbey is all a bit like Royals and Nobles,
isn't it?
But if you went to this one,
you get rock stars, you get authors, you get weirdos.
- The doors to hell have opened.
- Yes, yes, more like that.
- You've redeemed yourself.
Fish gate is forgotten.
(laughing)
- Speaking as we were earlier of people doing
inappropriate things in graveyards.
Do you guys know about the bustuary?
They were sex workers in Rome in the first century AD
and they plied their trade in cemeteries.
- Oh, naughty.
- Yeah, so in the daytime, they were professional mourners.
But in the nighttime, they were sex workers
and they would write on the gravestones
what the prices and stuff like that.
(laughing)
- They used them like phone boxes.
- A little bit, yeah, and people would go
and they had very pale skin and severe expressions
and they were kind of quite gothic
looking in and of themselves.
There was one called Noctina who would sleep on the graves
and cover her eyes with coins
and then they were also prostitutes.
- That feels like she's encouraging
some worrying kinks though.
- I'm afraid that there was some of that.
If you read Marshall, juvenile and catalyst,
all talk about it and apparently there was some of this.
- Bloody hell.
- The fact that they're professional mourners
in the daytime, you know, that's sort of,
and then at night time, basically,
the morning garb comes off and they're saucy.
- And then in the morning, the morning garb goes back on.
- Oh yeah, they had this weird thing in Roman tombs
which were called libation tubes.
Have you heard of this?
- No.
- This is so cool, these are terracotta tubes
that go down into the grave from ground double
and they're deliberately so you can give the dead a drink.
- Yeah, that's so sad.
- You go to mine into them.
- Yeah, it was just a pipeline right down
to the mouth of the dead.
- Was that different to the sausage one?
The sausage pipe?
I don't remember the sausage pipe.
- Yeah, we did talk about that.
- That's rigged such a fake though.
- Yeah.
- Was there a sausage pipe?
- John Bondison wrote about it and buried alive.
- Yeah, there was a, I think the idea was
if you were buried alive, you had a string that you pulled
and it would ring a bell and they would come and get you
and say, "We're coming to get you out,
but here have a sausage until then."
And they would pop a sausage in the sausage pipe
so he had some sustenance while they were.
- A cooked sausage.
- It doesn't say I assume a cooked sausage.
- I must be.
- You don't want to give them food poisoning while they're down.
- Tragic, he died of botulism
while we were getting the spade.
A fast-acting lethal sausage.
- You know, PETA, the animal rights organization,
they did a thing a few years ago.
They bought a tombstone in a cemetery
for one of their colleagues.
It was called Matt Prescott.
But it was, they bought a tombstone in a very specific place.
They bought it right near Colonel Sanders.
- Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And it had a message on it.
It was a little poem that they'd written
for their colleague, Matt.
And it was an acrostic.
And the first letter of every line spelled out the phrase,
KFC tortures birds.
- Wow.
- I know.
- My favorite gravestone is an acrostic.
- Oh.
- It's awesome.
It's for a guy called John Ren, R-E-N-I-E.
Ren or Ren.
And what it says on it is it says here lies John Ren.
But then it says it basically 45,760 times in total
because it's an acrostic that goes 19 squares across
and 15 squares down.
And everywhere you start reading it,
you can make here lies John Ren along this box of it.
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- And the total that you can add it up to is, yeah, 45,000.
So it's like the second line, it reads,
here lies John Ren.
Like that.
- Kind of thing, yeah.
- And then the next one is slightly different.
The next one is slightly different.
So you can read it down diagonally.
- Exactly.
- Like the world's most boring word search.
- Yes.
- But just great.
Such an, it's an amazing thing to look at.
- Oh, the guy who first formulated pi to 35 places
was a German mathematician called Ludolf van Sirlen.
And his gravestone reads 3.14159-265-3589-7932.
- Amazing.
- I don't know why I start if it isn't a recipe for pi.
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show.
And that is my fact.
My fact this week is that doctors used to prepare
their patients for surgery by either getting them
really drunk or smacking them on the head with a mallet
and hoping they didn't kill them.
(laughing)
That's back in the day.
So.
- When are we to which day?
- Back in the day.
- This is in the 1800s.
This was in the top floor
of America's oldest surgical ampy theater as it's known.
This is in the Pennsylvania hospital.
And I guess what's so surprising is how late in the day
this was happening.
This is in the sort of mid 1800s.
- It's not, mid 1800s was when we had,
we, I take a lot of credit,
but we had got like some aether chloroform stuff
was starting to happen.
- And a lot of them weren't fully accepted though.
So this, it definitely was around at this time.
But this hospital was like, not into it.
We'd rather hit you on the head.
- Happened in Britain as well.
There was a guy called Henry Hill Hickman
who used to try suffocation to get his ovations.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so this was a thing.
And, you know, the drunkenness hopefully would see them
through an operation as would such a massive hit
on the head.
- Some of these operations were very quick, weren't they?
They were amputations and stuff.
And they were trying to do them
in the matter of seconds.
- In fact, that seems to be the most effective method
of pain killing up until, you know,
they found ether and stuff was just speed.
And there was, we talked about it.
- The drug.
- QI.
(laughing)
- You love it.
- Just getting incredibly anxious before your friction.
- Yeah, I was, yeah, doing it within a short amount of time.
And we've mentioned Robert Liston on QI,
but his, he was a famous 19th century surgeon
and his catchphrase was, "Time me, gentlemen, time me."
And there's a huge amount of showmanship
to his surgical performances.
- It's a good catchphrase, that.
- It's a good catchphrase.
And it would kind of reassure you.
If you're having your leg cut off,
you want it to be quick.
And he used to brag he could amputate a leg in 25 seconds.
- Wow.
- And his chances of dying,
'cause he gets a lot of stick these days
for being all about the show and that's about the safety.
But you only had a one in six chance of dying,
which was quite good for surgeons then.
And there was one great, the best story about him,
which I'm pretty sure we looked at when we did QI
and is probably not true,
but it was reported that he once was so focused
on doing something incredibly fast
that he's amputating a limb.
And he accidentally at the same time cut through
his associate nurse's finger on the way.
And so both the person whose limb was amputated
and the person whose finger he amputated died
pretty quickly afterwards.
And also someone who was watching died of shock.
And it's always recorded as the only operation
with a 300% mortality rate.
- Yeah, wow, great story.
- It's a strong story.
- Don't check it ever.
That's a comical ending.
Like an airplane going into a mountain.
That's comical surgery.
- That's comedy, you're right.
That's, yeah.
- Just on the sort of reputation of surgery back in the day.
- Yeah.
- And this is a fact actually got sent in to us
from Sarah on Twitter.
So thank you, Sarah.
It was about the operating theater in Aberdeen.
And there used to be above the door
to the operating theater in Aberdeen,
the words, "Prepare to meet thy God."
- Ooh.
- Which is, oh, this is such an uncharable thing to read.
- Wow.
- And it was all about this surgeon
called Alexander Ogston who worked there
and he discovered Staphylococcus,
which is a very big--
- Common bacteria for getting like--
- Infections and abscesses and all of that.
Really dangerous staphylococcus.
And he was so inspired by antiseptic zeal
that he returned and he pulled the sign down
and burned it on one occasion.
- Wow.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It was a very, very religious place
to have your operation.
- I can imagine.
So the one that I was talking about in Pennsylvania,
the surgery itself had a sky roof basically.
So there was a dome at the top and it was glass.
So they would do all the operations in the day
and natural light was what was giving them--
- That's good.
- The light, yeah.
- Lovely.
- But I'm afraid the surgeons will take off their robes
and show you a good time, yeah, yeah.
- They would write their prices on the patient's spleen.
And they did have anesthetics before then,
various types throughout the world.
A Chinese physician called Huatuo,
I'm sure I'm pronouncing that wrong.
Apologies if I am.
But from 140 AD to 208 AD.
This guy, he would use something called mafeisan,
which is cannabis boil pounder.
So he gave it to the patient.
And apparently it was so good,
there was a guy called General Kuanyu
and he was wounded by a poison arrow
and he was sort of given some surgery
to try and bring the arrow out and clean the wound.
And the general played chess while his bone
was being scraped clean.
'Cause his concoction was so good.
- But did he win the game?
(laughing)
- He just kept whacking the pieces
after he was in a selfish pain, no.
- Yeah, we still don't know how they work.
- Yeah, crazy, yeah.
- I find there's so much momentum,
we don't know how or why it works.
It's just, we kept trying and this one stuck.
I mean, it's people speculate that,
this is general anesthetic, so what puts you to sleep.
Speculator that it dissolves some of the fat
in your brain cells, so stops the cells activity.
There's just been a study that found out
that one particular anesthetic
maybe weakens the transmission of signal,
electrical signals between your neurons
in like the higher functioning parts of your brain.
So that's why it will knock you unconscious,
but it won't stop you breathing
'cause the lower functioning parts can still keep going.
But yeah, it's so weird that we don't,
we just accept it works.
But I like, before another anesthetic.
I don't know how my microwave works.
- But someone does.
- Yeah, that's true.
- Sorry, when I say we, I don't just mean
we couldn't be asked to research it.
I mean, even the scientists
can't be asked to find out properly.
But another ancient way of anesthetizing people
was electric rays.
- These, the eels. - Yeah, yeah.
So these were used in ancient Rome.
It was like torpedo fish,
I think we've talked about before,
could give you a real electric shock.
And it was treatment for gout,
or it was if you wanted to numb an area
and you needed to do something to it.
It was recommended that you stand on the shore
and you let your legs be washed by the sea
as various electric rays
wrapped themselves around it
and wait for them to electrify you.
- If you were just stood in the sea,
you would need to bring them to you, right?
They wouldn't just naturally sting you.
- Yeah, how are you attracting them?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Yeah, maybe you drop some food for them.
No, wait, are you the food?
- You are kind of, you can maybe cut your legs
so there's a bit of blood in the water.
- Yeah, nice.
Then awful if the shark comes before the eels.
And then she's holding up to take it.
- Yeah, it's not convenient though.
So they quickly, they would shock you,
you would go numb, they would carry you out, and then.
- And then they can do a treatment on you
like cut off a bunion. - Like cut off your legs.
- Or bunion, all that for a bunion, my God.
Jesus.
You know how in the very first episode of this podcast
we talked about, anyone remember?
- We talked, yeah, President Garfield's.
- President Garfield's Anus.
So I have a related fact to this.
- I think you should quickly explain that
for anyone who can't remember 460 episodes ago.
- So this is the fact that for the last,
was it month of his life?
- Three months, I believe.
- Three months.
President Garfield ate everything through his Anus
and that's because he'd been shot
and he wasn't able to eat through the mouth
and so he was fed through the bump.
So the American president usually hands over power
when...
- Yes, he does.
But in Donald Trump's case...
(laughing)
You're so right, Donald Trump is the outlier here.
- Is he?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, James, that's exactly right.
So, okay, normally when the US president,
always a man so far, has a colonoscopy,
which is a procedure, and you're a bit older,
they put a camera up your bum
and they just check what's going on.
Normally a small camera on a little wire,
not like a big long lens paparazzi camera.
And it's a very common thing.
So Joe Biden did it in 2021,
handed over to Kamala Harris for the,
you know, half an hour, a couple of hours of the anesthetic.
George Bush had it twice
and both times handed over briefly to Dick Cheney.
There was a report a year or so ago
that Donald Trump underwent this procedure,
but he refused to have the anesthetic
because he didn't want to hand over to Mike Pence,
however briefly, the reigns of office.
So he just sort of bear-backed it.
One chance, I thought they had,
"Silence, Donald Trump, for a couple of blissful hours."
That's really interesting.
I've got another thing about putting stuff up the bum,
if you want to hear it.
So this is about the first woman physician
to specialize in anesthesia, who's called Isabella Herb.
And she was the first person to use ethylene
as a general anesthetic.
And there were two main ways
that she'd get you out of the anesthesia state.
One of them was to give you strychnine,
which would apparently help, presumably not that much.
And the other one was the installation
of warm saline solutions to the rectum.
Installation.
So if you were under because of this ethylene,
then she would squirt some salty water up your bum
and it would get you out of the...
Sounds kind of pleasant,
although is that not the thing that makes you wait yourself?
No, that's fingering then.
I think that's putting your hand in a bowl of water,
it does not squirt.
I bet if you put your bum in it, though, something happens.
The interesting thing about ethylene
and a problem that she had was that it does explode quite easily.
And so what she did was, she had her operating theatre
and they had very, very high humidity
because apparently that helped you
'cause there's slightly less oxygen in the air,
so less likely to explode.
But also because it was an early time
of having electric lights and stuff like that,
they grounded everything in the building.
So the table where the person was being operated on.
And in fact, everyone kind of had things attached to them.
Do you remember we talked about this big spike
that people had on their heads?
Yeah, everyone had electrical conductors
to conduct the charge orders.
Basically, everyone was wearing these wires to
and they attached to the pipes around the room,
the water pipes,
so that if there was any kind of spark in there,
instead of setting off the ethylene,
it would go into these grounded things
and then go down into the building.
Isn't that amazing?
That's really cool.
Isn't that so cool as well?
What a great name.
Imagine, you know when you fill in the forms
before you do an operation where you say,
"I understand that I might blah, blah, and blah, blah."
Imagine just that,
"Well, I understand there's a 30% chance I'll explode."
Yeah, yeah, I know what you're thinking about.
Just on doctors sort of beating patients around us,
this mallet people did in the fact.
August Beer was the person who came up
with the first spinal anesthesia.
That was in the 1890s, 1898.
And so that was injecting cocaine into your spinal cord,
was the first spinal anesthesia.
And he wanted to work out
how much you really needed to inject
because if you injected too much, had bad side effects.
And so he thought, "Okay, well, I'm gonna test out on myself."
And so he asked his assistant, also called August,
to inject him.
(laughing)
- Funnily must have heard.
- To August.
I mean, a very non-August time.
And so his assistant injected his spine.
Sadly, his spinal fluid started leaking out
quite drastically and so they had to stop.
So he said, "Do you mind if we swap?"
So the August swapped.
And his assistant said, "Okay, you try it on me."
So August, the assistant, lies there.
And August Beer jabs him with the cocaine
and then tests how high his pain threshold is.
And the account is just incredible.
So he starts by tickling his feet.
Quite pleasant, couldn't feel anything.
And then he jabbed a large blunt needle into his thigh
and then he got a larger blunter needle
and put it in down his femur, apparently.
He then, and he's awake through this process
'cause it's local anaesthetic.
So he's chatting away and having a great time.
He got sharp forceps and crushed his skin up.
He burned a cigar out on him.
He yanked all his pubic hair off.
(laughing)
- That was just for fun, wasn't it?
- Yeah, he'd asked for a wax
and you might as well two birds one stone.
(laughing)
He actually yanked his pubic hair off
and then did the chest hair for comparison.
- Really?
- Just to say, see, it would hurt if, you know,
if you weren't anesthetized.
- Wow, wow, wow.
- Hit his shin with a hammer, squeezed his testicles very hard.
And--
- Squeeze his testicles, oh my God.
- So look how impressive is that?
- I think he compressed his testicles
between two plates, didn't he?
And then just kept squeezing, squeezing, squeezing.
- Did he?
- I'd remember all the media about this, yeah.
- Well, they had a big feast afterwards
so maybe they ate all the testicle plates.
(laughing)
- Oh my God, so afterwards, was it just broken?
- How did you, how did that go for you?
- Oh, it's absolutely fine.
(laughing)
- He was a bit bruised as it wore off.
But he was, they had, they wind and dine and cigar together
and--
- Cigar, I wouldn't let cigars anyone see me after that.
- Some people wake up in the middle
of a general anaesthetic and it sounds awful.
The good thing is you almost always forget afterwards.
So I spoke to someone who carries out anaesthesia
quite regularly and says sometimes patients
get chatty during procedures
and you can just tell them to shut up
and be really rude to them 'cause they won't remember
after the operation, you know?
One patient had been going on and on about their job,
I think at NatWest and how interesting it was
and they just had to say, look, to shut up, please.
- That's so funny because when I last had
general anaesthesia, I thought I'll just have a chat
'cause I've not met an anaesthesia expert before
and I just started chatting to him and then went under
and now I'm realizing that as soon as I went under
he's like, you barry bastard.
(laughing)
- You work up with no pews, right?
Yeah, so normally you don't remember it
but sometimes you do remember it and you can't move
because the drugs are paralyzing you.
That sounds like the worst thing in the world
because you wake up, you know what's going on
and you can't do anything about it.
- And all you can hear is the anesthetist going,
ah, I shagged your mum, yeah.
(laughing)
- Fenella woke up after she had surgery
where she went under general anaesthetic
and she woke up and was quite tired
and they didn't realize that she was awake.
This is post-surgery, they were moving her away
and all she heard was a conversation
about how much the doctors enjoyed no such thing as a fish.
(laughing)
- The worst possible nightmare.
She was like, ah, Christ.
- I would put you back under.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it, that is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland.
Andy.
- @AndrewHunterM.
- James.
- @JamesHarkin.
- And Anna.
- You can email podcast.qi.com.
- Yep, you can go to our group account
which is @NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThingAsAfish.com.
Check out all the previous episodes
from NoSuchThingAsAfish.
They're all up there.
You can also find your way into Club Fish.
There's lots of bonus content up there.
Check it out, it's really awesome.
And otherwise, just come back here
to our free podcast that comes out every week.
We'll be back again next week with another one.
We'll see you then, goodbye.
(upbeat music)