(Theme song plays)
Now, Lo and welcome to another episode of None Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast this week coming to you live from Paris!
(Cheering and applause)
Thank you very much, Marie and James Harkin, and once again we have gathered around the microphones
who are four favorite facts from the last seven days and in a particular order, here we go!
Starting with you, James!
Okay, my fact this week is that North American potcups sometimes fall out of trees and impale themselves of their own spice.
So, they get pushed into them?
Like, so they're ready to get us what impaled beans.
(Laughter)
Do they die?
We all die, aren't they?
(Laughter)
I don't think we're in Paris, I should've realised the philosophy would come early in the morning.
Well, actually, not usually, and the reason that we know about this for a few reasons, but it's kind of a report that came out by a guy called oldest Rose and his colleagues,
and they noticed that quilts have antibiotics on them, and they worked out that the reasons that they have antibiotics on them
is because they do impale themselves quite often, and it means that it will kind of get infected and it won't kill them.
It is weird that they spend so much time up trees, and this is North American microbiome, isn't it?
Yeah, they absolutely lot of climbing trees!
Yeah, actually, a female potcupide is only interested in sex once a year, and she signals that by climbing the tree, urinating and screaming.
(Laughter)
It's sexy.
We all dry up.
(Laughter)
But the males have urination as well in their mating, so the males, they can sometimes make the females receptive to mating, and the way they do that is urinating on them.
And they have a special high velocity urine, which can go six feet.
Wow.
So even if a female is on a completely different branch, the male can spray her and then she will become fertile.
That's incredible.
Yeah, is it true?
I might have this wrong, but is it true?
So there's a fight that happens between two males who are according the one, so the urination thing, as well as being an exciting thing for the mating ritual,
is also in the same way that a dog might pee on a fire hydrant to mark it as its territory.
It's a territory marking thing, I think, as well.
That feels slightly possible.
Yeah, they're not really sure.
They think, yeah, it could be pheromones to attract them, but they do have this massive bite.
So, lots of males can get involved, because they're very solitary porky bites, and they have this very narrow window of fertility, the females.
And so they're on their own, middle of nowhere, there's something like, "Fuck, I'm fertile, so they have to do this whole screaming, weeing thing."
So it just spends urine in the air and hope the male smell it.
So then a bunch of males flock to them, and then they do have this huge bite.
And so it's very normal if you see a male porky by mating, he'll usually be doing it with a bunch of someone else's, some other porky finds quills sticking out of it.
Wow.
Covered in other men's quills.
Yeah, not comfortable.
No.
The female porky minds are pregnant or lactating for 11 months of the year, and they can be pregnant for all of their lives, and they live for 20 to 30 years.
So they basically spend their entire lives pregnant or breastfeeding.
Why under the screaming so much?
Why are they not more porky minds then?
They're just good at hiding from you.
I think they're not quite a lot.
If you're in a narrow group, I think you hear it quite a lot.
So what they have lots of quills, actually they have spines all over their penis as well at the males.
It's covered in what they call horny material.
It's a very common one.
But they've no, you know, the proper for humans is that they can stab us with their quills.
And there was a paper from 1955, which is all about being quilled by porky pines.
And this is our friends at improbable research.
So the guy who did the ignoble awards, which we mentioned before,
there was a paper in 1955 written by Albert R. Schabel, and in it he wrote,
"Many hundreds of quills have penetrated various parts of the author's own body in numbers of one or two to as many as 40 at one time.
On one occasion, 40 were driven into the forehead and the bridge of the nose by one stroke of a porky pint's tail.
They added, "The penetration of porky pint quills into the human body is never a pleasant sensation."
That's last time, speak.
We're thinking of trying it out.
They have really interesting sex organs, don't they?
Porky pines, the males have really interesting sex organs.
So they keep their testes inside them.
They don't let their testes into their scrotal sac for most of the year.
They're just sitting in their stomachs on my, not their stomach, their abdomen.
And then they just plop them down into the scrotal sac once they're going to mate.
And they suck them back up again when they're not mating.
But then they've got, as you said, their penis is fined.
But also, it's usually pointing backwards.
So it's in sort of a sheath that points backwards towards them.
So when they mate with the female, it flips out a pen knife.
Oh, wow.
That's amazing.
Yeah.
No wonder they keep their testes inside.
They'll probably be stabbing themselves otherwise while they're around.
That's probably just, yeah, protection.
There was a politician from Florida called Bobby Bean.
And he wanted to become a senator.
And he ran with the promise that he would make sex with Porcupines legal.
And how did he--
He's now president.
Did he, did he win?
No, he didn't win.
Actually, it wasn't quite as stupid as you might think.
His idea was to, he wants it to erase kind of useless laws that exist.
So it currently is illegal explicitly to have sex with Porcupines in Florida.
And he's like, you know, they have a pen knife spiky penis.
We're probably not going to do that.
And it's spiky on the outside, we probably don't eat this law.
And there was like other things like there was a rule against men wearing strapless gowns
that he wanted to get rid of as well.
So wrappers gowns, yeah.
Well, how's he going to seduce the Porcupines?
And they eat people's toilets sometimes.
What?
Porcupines.
They do.
They genuinely do.
Well, okay.
Let's have some qualification here.
So what they do, they love sodium.
So it's salt, basically.
And they need one of it.
They crave salt all the time.
And some people in the territory still have outdoor wooden toilets.
And a lot of the words, you know, if your aim is poor,
has urine soaked into it, okay?
So urine contains salt.
And, you know, people, there are toilets which have been eaten away at.
By Porcupines.
So they don't eat the porcelain, but they do eat the ceramic wood.
So they eat the hut.
Yeah, they do eat the hut.
Yeah.
So boy scouts, I think on Boy Scout cats, they often say,
"You'll go to the loo and you're surrounded by Porcupines chewing through the hut."
They try that to say to urine.
Oh my gosh.
So you're really frightening.
But the salt love gets them into all sorts of trouble.
So they chew through cars a lot.
So cars are quite salty.
They genuinely do.
No, they don't.
They're coming from a toilet volume.
You'll draw the line at cars.
Very weird.
They actually chew through cars mostly in winter.
Can you guess why?
Salt on the roads.
Did you read that?
Oh, great stuff.
And if you drink, it must be on the toes when you're driving along.
It gets on the toes, flicks up onto the engine.
And then they climb, they'll eat your engine out from the inside.
Wow.
Another thing that Dan, you might be interested in, is getting bones.
What?
What is this case?
Am I in some kind of weird fever dream?
What is on the toilets?
The cars are the yetis.
Yeah, we're just thinking about why we could push it.
There's a theory that's prevalent among people who believe in the Sasquatch,
which is the same as a yeti, right?
In the old style.
Absolutely not.
It's like talking a hedgehog in a pocket, you find the same thing.
It's insulting.
I'm sorry to the Sasquatch and the yeti communities.
So people even have Sasquatch.
People are often say to them, why aren't there any bones?
Why we never find any bones?
Yeah.
And they say, well, it's obviously because they're very salty and pocket finds a big one.
Yes.
Yes, there's something you believe in.
Yeah, that's a true fact that they believe in.
It's true.
And also, they say that in Canada, they don't actually put salt on the roads anymore,
speaking of salt, because big-foot keeps eating it all.
So they think, we're going to start with losing too much salt.
Really?
Yeah, we should probably move on today.
Do you think of what we do?
We just do a couple of different requirements.
Oh, can I just do one more thing on pocket?
Yes.
Just really quickly, because it's that French person.
There was a 19th century French explorer called Jules Gerard,
who reported on a group of people called the Hatchichere,
they were from Algeria.
And all they ever did was smoke Hachiche and kill pocket bites.
I can't hear the smoke Hachiche and kill pocket bites.
And I've just finished my Hachiche.
Yeah.
But now I'm quite sleepy.
And we do need to move on to our next facts.
Just really quickly, because you know that fish can climb trees.
What?
Yeah, fish, coin trees, and loads of different types of fish.
So one of them is the mangrove kidney fish in mangrove forests.
And that exists in like lots of America, Florida and Brazil.
Liz and puddles.
And then the puddles dry up.
At which point they actually climb up the nearest tree.
So it looks like a normal fish climbs its way up a tree.
And then it climbs into a hole in the tree,
then it's an insect made or an actual hole in a tree.
And it just waits it out in the hole until it rains again.
And it can wait in a tree for months.
So sometimes you're just walking off a tree and there's a fish halfway up.
We're hanging out with the urinating poultry pie.
It's very weird in the upper canopy.
OK, it is time for fact number two, and that is Andy.
My fact is that scientists are developing a t-shirt
which tells you when you smell.
This is really cool.
So there is a British microtrip maker,
and the firm is called Arm.
They are working on putting AI devices in clothes, basically.
So the idea is that you will have a microtrip in your armpit,
effectively, in your shirt, and it will inform you on scale of one to five.
How bad your body odor is and whether it may be it's time to have a shower
or change your clothes.
OK.
But if you change your clothes and you've lost the shirt that tells you,
I guess you have to change for another microtrip t-shirt.
Yeah, it's going to be quite an expensive endeavor.
Will the washing the clothes not make the microtrip?
Absolutely.
This is the key problem that they are trying to.
It's making a microtrip which will withstand repeated washing machines.
So you have no choice but to wear that one shirt.
Andy permanently on number five.
Yeah, it's all true.
I'm not saying it's free of problems, or I just don't know.
I do think it's a good idea.
There is a way, actually, to make clothes clean themselves.
So you can put some narrow particles in clothes and then clean themselves.
Scientists are using this to make robotic trousers for old people.
OK, so old people have trouble walking.
And they think if they can make these robotic trousers, it will help them to walk.
OK, nice thing.
Yeah.
Sounds dangerous to me.
I've seen the wrong trousers, but go on.
The thing is, they put these other particles in, which means they don't have to be washed.
So that's good for the electronics, but the problem is all the old people they give them to
said they would just wash them anyway.
OK.
That's the hard thing to get around, isn't it?
Yeah.
And there will be, just while we're on the smart clothes thing.
And there will perhaps one day soon, the underpants that you can use to control your home.
So this is really cool.
So this is not too far away.
Actually, we like turning light stuff and stuff, because I always want to slide in bed.
And I rolled up one of my socks and threw it at the light switch and turned the light side.
So my wife is not nearly as impressed as you guys.
James has been trying to get the story into the podcast for five years.
It's very impressive. I rolled up a sock, and you were on the other side of the room.
It wasn't like it was here.
No, your socks must be real hard.
If only you had microchips in your socks to tell you, please wash me.
So you would be able to get underpants that control your home.
OK, I'm determined to tell you about this.
So it basically just is more putting sensors in clothes.
So you will have sensors which measure your heart rate, your temperature,
your body temperature, or the temperature of your body inside your pants.
The pressure, the hydration.
What do you need that for?
Well, OK, well, here we go.
So you could connect your thermostat in your house.
You could link it up with your body temperature.
And when you're at home, it could notice.
Oh, thanks feeling.
Thanks for passing through a bit hard.
I want to overheat it down a little bit.
And then you could think it's fair that we all have to live in a polarly cold house
because it's done.
It's done.
Very pretty.
You know, you know my machine that follows your home is for you?
Well, there's, it's, it's, it was a kickstyle, though, I think.
It's called a faulty mate.
And I was watching a video.
So it's a massive machine, it's about as big as a person.
It's at the side of the fridge.
So I don't know where you're going to put it.
So next to your fridge?
The fridge?
You don't want to confuse them, though?
No, true.
I'll turn up with the appellate.
No, it's a folder, the pastor.
That's amazing.
You know the movie Armageddon?
Yes.
There's been some research recently done by some scientists
where they did a simulation to see how well that would have worked
if Bruce Willis had actually nuked it like he does in the movie
and it splits apart.
And what they discovered in simulation was that it would break apart
like it does in the movie.
Unfortunately, the gravity is so great that it would just be pulled back together
and there's one solid asteroid and just wipe us out.
That's how the movie should have ended.
And this is a new discovery, isn't it?
Yeah.
Because last year when they ran the simulation, and this really is the top people
that NASA and all these other organizations have, last year when they ran it,
they did save Tokyo from the asteroid by doing a nuclear explosion,
which blew it apart.
But since then, yeah, they've just go, well, they'll just suck themselves back together
and keep coming at us.
So there are also some other weird ways of diverting asteroids.
So I really like the mass driver way, which basically is the idea that you would,
it's quite slow working, so you need to know that the asteroid was going to hit you
in about 100 years' time.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
You've got to pass them a little on to your grandchildren.
But the idea, basically, is that you get onto the servers of the asteroid,
you get some landing objects onto it, and they pick up rocks from the asteroids
and they just throw them at the Earth.
And the motion of that pushes the asteroid away from the Earth.
So it's kind of like, imagine if you're sitting on a swing, I guess,
and you've got a tennis ball.
And then if you throw the tennis ball away, you'll kind of go backwards on the swing, right?
It's the opposite, even when I'm on the reaction balls.
So if enough bits of rock are thrown at the Earth and the asteroid,
it'll sort of slow it down.
But then if too many are thrown at us, then we die anyway from the things you've thrown at us.
Yeah, you have to make sure they're not too big, though, bits of rock.
Yeah.
Wow.
And you need 100 years?
You need 100 years, yes.
I think, previously, Dan said that the warning we would have is about one second.
Look, you've not said that.
It's not true.
Well, we know about loads.
This is a really cool thing.
So NASA, apparently, knows about 795,000 asteroids.
So can I just say, like, for instance, the Chelepins meteor,
we didn't know about that at all until it landed.
So it might be that we have no seconds.
So I was wrong by one second.
But this is the amazing thing.
And the problem is, it's really hard to keep track of them, once you've spotted them.
So scientists have lost more than 900 near-Earth asteroids.
As in, they've spotted ones.
We thought, oh, that's a bit worrying.
And then we don't know what they've gone.
Wow, really?
Yeah, so we saw them once.
And because sometimes it takes 20 hours to confirm that what you're seeing is right.
Sometimes the weather is bad, so you can't see it again from a ground-based observatory.
So you just sort of say, oh, well, there.
See you.
I think it's gross.
Don't come back.
And we're going to have to move on to our final factor.
Some things killed by asteroids might have been the dinosaurs.
Okay.
And again, I didn't really say that since it's very well.
But I think all the points were there.
But there is one guy who doesn't think that.
There's a guy called Professor Brian J. Ford.
And he thinks that the dinosaurs actually died out because of a lack of sex legs.
Sex legs.
Damn, how's your crotch beard getting any hotter?
Well, it is sex legs.
It's exactly what it sounds like.
Go.
So his theory is that because dinosaurs were so big, they wouldn't be able to have sex,
because they would just crush each other.
That's not the only way they could do it is by using the legs to be buoyant.
And then, do you know what I mean?
They can only have sex with legs.
And he says that as the continent's drifted, there were loads of shallow,
there used to be loads of shallow legs and the word shallow legs anymore,
which is true.
And so he thinks because of those lack of shallow legs, all the dinosaurs died out.
Actually, this would mean that all the fossils we find would be crushed dinosaurs
underneath their crushing mate.
Yeah, you're right.
It's just a theory.
It's a great theory.
One thing about asteroid names.
Oh, yeah.
So asteroids, it used to be the near-death objects,
and most of which asteroids had to be named after mythical creatures,
but there have been loads and loads found since that was decided, I think, about 50 years ago.
So, it also used to be that they had to be named after things from mythology,
but they couldn't have creation or underworld themes,
because there was, for other bits of space.
So you have to really do your research into your biological creature.
Anyway, so these rules were kind of loose,
because there are like tens of thousands of them that have names now.
So if you, I was looking at the name of the massive list of asteroid names,
and you have these really grand ones like Palace and Juno and Achilles,
and then you have Bill Smith and Sarah Jenkins,
Donald Anderson, Randy Peterson,
and I was looking for our names in them.
So there are a lot of annas, so there's an anna just anna on her own,
and then they're like, you know, annas.
Oh, that's the one that's going to get us, isn't there?
I'm reading for her.
There's also a James on his own, and a Daniel on his own,
but there is no Andrew and Andy.
Right, thanks a lot.
So, I think the next asteroid name you should claim it.
Oh, we can name a sex lake after you.
Yes.
So I'd like to be remembered.
Time for our final fact on the show, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that until the 1840s,
there was no maximum size for a rugby team.
So, matches were sometimes played with up to 300 players on the pitch at the same time.
So is that an 150 against 150?
No, 29 against what?
He's very good.
We do have an example of it, so the game of rugby was set to have been invented
in a school called rugby, hence where it got the same from, in 1823.
There was a match played in 1839 where rugby school house had 75 players,
so that was their team, and they played a team that was called the rest.
And there was 225 people.
That's amazing.
Do we know who won?
I don't actually know who won, I couldn't find out.
I'm sure it's out there somewhere, but yeah.
And it was obviously, it was a very chaotic game, as you can imagine.
They hadn't really got any rules to begin with, rules slowly kind of.
Actually, it is to be like basically a load of guys in the field,
just trying to get the ball from one end to the other, but with no rules, right?
Yeah.
It's just basically one big scrub.
Strangling and throttling were outlawed in 1862.
That's when I went right off the game.
That's just health and safety gone mad in the end, isn't it?
But this is, yeah, because these go back hundreds of years, don't they?
They're all comes from games which are called folk football.
So there's one that's still played in England in Derbyshire in Ashburn,
where you keep playing until you score a goal or until 10pm,
which ever comes sooner, just knock off.
Because people would die quite often.
And there are lots of records of people dying playing rugby,
partly because people used to carry knives in cheats on their belts.
And so you might just run into someone else's knife by mistake.
That hammer, that's a foul.
But this is the other thing.
The game of rugby is problematic, because it lets people take revenge on each other,
because there are no rules.
So if you've got a village of people basically having a big fight,
you could just say, "Oh, yeah, you ran under my knife."
Where was this? This happened?
This is sort of 14th, 15th centuries.
Right.
So this is the four proper rugby.
Yeah, yeah.
Because there was one corner.
I wonder if this is what you're talking about.
Caltio's Thorikot?
Well, that's a very similar game.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, that, like, what I'm saying, it's a rugby game.
But the idea is to play rugby, but also just kick each other's ass.
Really badly.
Like, you're allowed to punch kick, headbutt, elbow, choking is permitted.
There's no clubs allowed, you know, to soften the punch.
And the amazing thing.
And there would be deaths, and they would just carry on and so on.
But the main thing was, if the game was going a bit too slow,
and they wanted the fans to sort of have a bit more of a fast experience
and get the game done, they'd just let some balls come in.
So they just ran the balls, running around attacking humans.
I mean, it sounds incredible.
Yeah, that's Italy, isn't it?
Caltio, yeah.
This presumably was recently.
They're not going to soften it now.
Yeah.
You're allowed to do everything except kick people in the head.
And who's telling the balls not to do that?
Well, even in rugby, kicking used to be, um, shin kicking specifically,
used to be massively caught in the game.
So this is one of the biggest controversies rugby ever saw,
was when they were drawing out the rules.
It was, like, in the 1870s.
And hacking was really part of rugby, which was basically really,
vigorously kicking someone else's shins.
And somebody wanted to outlaw it.
And somebody will say, "That's going to ruin the game."
It's kind of it.
But it was the case that, like, after a scrubber broken up,
everyone else had let the balls, the other end of the pitch.
You still have apparently, just you have two players left over,
kicking each other in the shin, really hard,
at the other end of the pitch.
So then people used to wear sharpened boots with spikes on them
to really get that shin kick as good as it could be.
Well, yeah.
And then they would wear white trousers to show off the blood.
This was a mark of...
This is the English school system.
It was first, basically.
Although I was ready.
And then rugby moved to France, to other countries.
And in the late 19th century in France, once we did have rules,
but rugby wasn't seen not so much as a team game,
the more of an individual game.
There was still a team, but you were trying to see how well
you could do yourself.
And so it was, like, one athlete against the group.
And you were trying to get around them.
So basically, players were reluctant to get dirty,
reluctant to find themselves on the ground.
And they thought it was less cleverest to get involved in scrubs.
And this only was challenged when France played England in 1906.
And fabled out of the English, was not played by those rules at all.
Actually, one of the objections to getting rid of the shin kicking
was, I read, and I don't know what this means.
And just don't shoot the messenger.
But so this is hacking when it was going to be banned.
And the secretary of Black Heath FC said,
"We can't ban the practice of kicking each other in the shins
because it will do away with all the courage and pluck of the game
and bring over a lot of Frenchmen."
Wow.
You really, really know your audience so well.
So when it took off, they eventually,
I think it was the 1870s going to take.
Whole football club said, "Okay, fine.
We'll stop each other kicking in the shins with sharp and booze."
But you're still allowed to trip up the man who's running.
That was just a nice little innovation.
They thought they were trying.
Nice.
Yeah.
Oh, if you thought the rugby balls could give you as well.
Good thing.
Yeah, but not the way you would think.
Oh, I didn't have a thought in my head.
Nice thing.
Okay, so they hit you in the head so hard that you die.
Brilliant.
That's not the way that you would think.
Good.
Okay, it's not that way.
So rugby balls, the first person to make a uniform oval rugby ball
was a guy called Richard Linden.
And his wife actually was involved in the manufacturing too.
So what it was was you would have a pig's bladder
and you had to blow that up and then surround it in leather.
That's just how you made the ball.
But Linden's wife Rebecca was the one who did the actual blowing up
and she contracted a lung disease and she died from it
because there wasn't an unexpectedly, you know, there was an infected bladder.
And she had had 17 children for him as well by him, you know.
This is a very sad story.
And so that determined him to make a rubber bladder.
It basically prompted the innovation of...
And he also invented the modern pump.
Yes.
Sorry near syringe and he thought, well, I could take that from an ear and plate.
For more than that.
Yeah, for more than that.
But who was looking after all those kids?
Well, he was inventing these silly rugby ball base things.
That's my question.
What I've read about rugby does not relate.
Probably something.
Just a tiny little nugget of how influential this little rugby school in England
has been on global sporting outside of inventing rugby itself.
There was a student there who was from Australia called Thomas Willes.
He went back to Australia and he invented Aussie rules.
Which back in Australia is a huge sport.
It's not gone global.
In fact, they have Australia have an old star Aussie rules team
that they announce every year.
But because no one is good enough to play them, they've never played a match.
So we've got this like super group who just get announced and they meet up.
But that's it.
They should play the rest.
Yes.
That's such a good point.
So rugby is known for having really hard core players playing it, I guess.
So my favourite story is Wayne Shelford.
She was quite famous for being particularly hard core.
He was captain of the All Blacks in the 80s.
He and one of his got fan in.
Or maybe that's him.
I don't know.
It sounded like him based on what I'm about to tell you.
(Laughter)
It's just a banana.
So he has come to the All Blacks.
Very hard core.
In one of his very first games, he was super young.
He had French, he was playing France and a French boot ripped open his scrotum
and let a testicle hang in three.
He also had four teeth knocked out in the same incident.
But he didn't want to leave the pitch.
Anyone else has just been sucked up by important hours.
(Laughter)
Also, that's how the kick that gets your testicles on your team.
And let's go kick top with such force if I put it to your hand.
It's telling these testicles without long.
But he just said that the video quick, so it up, so it up,
so it up, so it up right there and then and he kept on playing.
What?
We're not going to be made.
Yeah?
I'm telling you that he was not unconscious later on.
(Laughter)
We're going to have to wrap up shortly.
I'm going to have to stitch a stitch.
A testicle with podcast back into the scrotum of the microphone box.
I thought that was never going to end.
(Laughter)
Anything else before we wrap up?
I just have my big rugby story,
aside from the testicle ripping, maybe, is the story of the dultristic gladiators.
I don't know if you know this one, so dultristic gladiators were a team in the year 2000
and they were an amateur over 40s, very unfit rugby team,
who just played sort of amateur games for fun.
And then they thought they would make, so they thought they'd go to Romania for kind of a big bruise-up and play some rugby over there.
And they were giving some toys to an orphanage, actually, to be fair.
(Laughter)
Anyway, they were in Romania, and the Romania's got winner.
There was a rugby team there, and they were invited to play a game.
And so they were like more playing game with the local remains in the local park.
And there'd been some sort of mistranslation, and so Romania thought that they were basically a national level team.
(Laughter)
And so when they turned up, they realised it was in their national stadium.
It was being broadcast on television.
(Laughter)
There were thousands of spectators there, and they were playing against the Romanian national team.
They did say, "We did get a bit suspicious when they offered us a training session night before, and we refused to do that, as we do our pre-match. We'll mub in the bar."
(Laughter)
But I think before the match, apparently, the Romanian's were all training,
and the Brits, where they were looking at them and smoking on the sidewalk.
(Laughter)
The Romanian's took pity and only beat them 60/17 out of sympathy in the end.
Okay, that is it that is all of our facts. Thank you.
[Applause]
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]