(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing as a Fish, A Weekly Podcast"
coming to you from the QI offices and covered guarded.
My name is Dad Shriver, and I'm sitting here
with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter-Marie,
and Adich Zinski.
And Adich Zinski, and once again,
we have Gather Grown on my face.
And once again, we have Gather Grown on the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order.
Here we go.
- What even does that have to do with the sound of the microphone?
- Very confusing.
- Starting with my fact, my fact this week
is that the man who popularized the high five
only has four fingers.
(laughing)
And this was a basketball player
called Wiley Brown.
Back in 1978/79 season of basketball,
he and his mate started high fiveing.
And they talk about it really, really interestingly.
Like I read an interview where he said,
"No one was doing it, they all did it low.
"There's all these low fives going on.
"No one did it high."
And then he said, "Then the first time we did it,
"both of us looked at each other and said,
"Did that just happen?"
(laughing)
- He really did to it.
There's a magical moment.
- Can I just ask, when you say four fingers,
you mean on one of his hands?
- Exactly, nine fingers.
- Yes, exactly.
So he had nine fingers in total.
He was missing a thumb.
He lost his thumb when he was four years old
and prosthetic thumb was made,
which meant that he could still become
an amazing sports star
'cause he played basketball and football.
He was a bit sort of carefree about his thumb at times.
He actually went to the finals of a basketball match,
having left his thumb back at the hotel
that he stayed at and they had to rescue it.
- That would be awful if you had to hitchhike hold.
(laughing)
- Well, you could only do it on one side of the road.
- He actually hated his thumb, his prosthetic thumb.
Yeah, he tried not to wear it.
So he played basketball without the thumb for ages
and then one of his coaches said,
"You're really good without that.
"But you'd be even better with it."
And they made him wear one
and it kept on flying off matches
and he said it made him look like a freak
'cause you know, it was someone would bash into his thumb
and it would fly into the crowd.
And so he tried not to wear it
and the coach was adamant.
And so much so that he said if he wasn't wearing his thumb,
he wouldn't let the other teammates pass
to his right hand, which really damaged the game.
So they could only pass to his left hand.
- Oh, so.
- Yeah, he wasn't a fan.
- I should say that I got this fact.
It was sent into us by a guy called Michael Buccino.
He's a listener and again, it's quickly up to say this.
If you wanna see the finest interview ever, ever recorded,
go to YouTube and put in Wiley Brown,
talking about the high five.
It is nine minutes of interview where they ask a question,
which is, "So you invented the high five, how was it?"
He says, "Yeah, it's great."
And then they've got nine minutes more of interview.
- It's too long.
- It's not too long.
- It is.
- I watched it.
- No, 'cause they run out of questions
but he does not run out of answers.
He is so enthusiastic.
And he has a new tale for each time the high five started.
So he did it with Derek Smith, who Wiley Brown says,
"Is the actual creator of the high five?"
Because in all the stories Smith is the one who instigates it.
So for example, another story is that he said he was going up
during practice to Derek Smith to give him a low five,
classic low five, as they always did.
And then he said, "Out of nowhere,
"Smith looked brown in the eye and said, 'No, up high.'"
I mean, that's what I can also do.
- There was another theory about who invented the high five.
- Yeah, it's very controversial, isn't it?
- Yeah, so there's a baseball player called Dusty Baker,
and another called Glenn Burke, and it's claimed that when Baker
was getting back towards the dugout,
Burke offered a raised hand and Baker,
not knowing what to do, smacked it.
Again, very much the same sort of amazing foundation moment.
And then Burke went out and he got a home run
and then on the way back he gave him another high five.
And that was in 1977 that that supposedly happened.
- So that's earlier?
- It's earlier, so that predates.
- Yes.
- Maybe an origin.
- Do you know Glenn Burke, who you were talking about?
- Yeah.
- He's famous because he was pretty much the first
major league baseball player to come out as gay.
And there was a documentary in 2010 called Out,
The Glenn Burke Story, and they said that the Dodgers'
executives offered him $75,000 to get married,
because it would cause such a problem if people found out
he was gay while he was still playing.
- No way.
- And apparently when they said,
"Would you take $75,000 to get married?"
He said, "I guess you mean to a woman?"
It's just quite a good reply.
- That's a great title for a movie, Out.
I guess you mean to a woman?
- Oh, right, no, no.
Out.
- Oh, the actual movie itself.
- Do you think there was any confusion at the start
when people would say, "Hey, how's Glenn?"
And then you go, "Oh, he's out."
And they go, "No, he's not, he's still out."
Just years of playing.
- Yeah, that's good.
And then Dusty Baker, just one fact about him,
he was famous for liking to chew toothpicks.
He said toothpicks are an excellent source of protein,
which he was wrong about.
- No.
- So on high fives, there is a basketball team
called the Phoenix Sons.
- Yes.
- Has he heard of them?
- Yeah.
- Is that like saying, there is a football team
called Manchester United.
- Yes, it is.
- You're on it.
- Anyway, these Phoenix Sons in 2016,
they announced that they were keeping track
of all the high fives that their team passed to each other,
hoping that they would create more camaraderie,
like throughout the season they did this.
And supposedly teams which embrace the most
in terms of the high fives or other celebrations
are more successful.
- Yeah, I think it's surely more likely
that if you're more successful,
you score more points than you high fives each other more.
- Yeah, that's true.
There is a cause and effect thing there.
But I've read articles saying that sports players
who touch each other more are supposedly better
at the spots.
And I'm pretty sure that England cricket team
always touch each other on the bum,
whenever they do something good.
- Yes.
- And I think that kind of comes from that idea.
- Sports, psychologists.
- Most sports do, yeah, there's bum slaps all the time.
- If we want to improve our performance on the podcast,
should we start slapping each other's bum?
- No, I don't think we should.
I think we could just...
(laughing)
- That was a high five by the way, not a bum slap.
- There is a machine that an artist has invented
where you can, it does self high fives.
Have you seen it?
- No.
- It's unbelievably disgusting looking.
- It's the sound that the saddest loneliest machine in the world.
- She's a Turkish-born artist.
I think she lives in America.
Good.
Denise O'Zueger.
Sorry, how does she pronounce her surname?
I don't know, but I don't think it's like that.
(laughing)
I'm so sorry if I can just pronounce it,
which I definitely have.
So she cast her own arm, right?
She made two cast of her arms,
and then one of them is just sticking out of this machine.
And the other one is like rotating very slowly,
like a cabab thing.
(laughing)
And every minute, they come into contact
'cause it's going around in a circle, the moving up,
and it just slowly brushes the fingers of the other arm.
- So that's not really a high f--
That's how you would imagine Michael Gov would high-five.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's really, it's really worth it.
It only does one high-five per minute.
I'm not sure what the point is.
- One high-five per minute.
- But it's hard, it's hard.
That's the point.
- It's not, it's okay.
- The thumbs up that Donald Trump's gradually destroying
for everyone else in the world.
(laughing)
Do you know what the origin of that is?
- Apparently there were little theories.
- In basketball, when someone got hit in the face
by a stray thumb and they held it off and said,
"Who's this?"
(laughing)
- It's a strong theory, but no.
So apparently there's a--
- Yeah, two other things.
- Well, there's quite a strong myth that says
that gladiators, you give the thumbs up for gladiators
if you thought they should live in and the thumbs down.
They should die, but I think that's not true.
I think you just put your thumb out and that meant,
I think we've got no evidence that the thumbs up
meant live and thumbs down meant die.
But, Desmond Morris says that it's from medieval times
where if you were a businessman doing a deal,
then the way you do it is you'd lick your thumb
and then you press it up against someone else's
licked thumb and that was really like,
"Hey, deal is done."
- Wow, that's like blood brothers,
but slightly weirdly more disgusting.
- What it reminds me of is,
do you remember in the last QI meeting,
Anna, when you were trying to show us some pick-up lines
and you tried one on under, you missed this done?
- Two.
- She licked her thumb, wiped it on these clothes
and said, "Let's get you out of these wet clothes."
- Oh, that's, yeah, that's a good one.
- He was smitten.
- The single most erotic moment of my life.
(laughing)
- That's strong.
- You know, couples,
Marion couples used to shake hands at the altar.
- Oh, really?
- So this is a BBC History magazine claims this,
but yeah, in the 17th century you got married
and then you shake hands with the bride.
- So because it's like a contract movie.
- Yeah, exactly.
- The kissing thing, when I got married in January,
the priest told us that, you know, it's not a thing,
you don't need to do it.
It's like, it's just people just started doing it.
It just caught on like the high five
and just people decided to do it.
But it's never been officially a part of the ceremony.
- Yeah, I know.
- You make his the bride is not a line
a part of the ceremony.
- He popularized it, don't.
- I think it was a half-lipped amount.
(laughing)
- Yeah, I don't know.
- It's quite American.
I always think of it as not a--
- What, you made out kiss the bride?
- Yes, in fact, that's what he said to me.
He said that it's something that was seen
in American movies and then everyone thought,
"Oh, there's meant to be that line."
And then we started doing it.
- So when I was looking at stuff about high fives,
I came across an article about a lollipop man.
He's quit because he was high five in the children
as they walked across the road.
And he was told not to do it.
And he was like, "Right, fine, I'm gonna quit."
- Okay.
- So just very quickly, a lollipop man,
'cause I didn't know this until I got to this country,
is someone who stands by a zebra crossing
and allows school children to walk across.
- I had no idea.
- He's holding a large lollipop shaped object
to stop the cars.
- But he doesn't sell lollipops.
- And a zebra crossing is a road crossing
with black and white stripes on it.
- That the Beatles walked over on Abbey Road.
- Yes, but there are thousands and thousands
of zebra crossings.
It's not like Britain has one zebra crossing
and all school children have to cross that
before they go to the school.
- I was surprised I got the space to take that photo
with all the kids. - Anyway, lollipop man.
- So this guy, he was from a Plymouth City Council.
And then I just carried on reading the rest
of the Google searches on pages two and three
that people don't normally go to.
And there was also a lollipop man in Edinburgh
who was told not to high five children.
There was a lollipop lady in the Vale of Glamorgan
who had the same.
There was two lollipop men in Essex that I found.
There was a guy in Weston, Batonshire,
who's left his job because he wasn't allowed
to high five kids.
And there was a guy in Australia, in Bayside, Australia,
who was also left his job because, well, he got told off
because he was high five in children.
So this seems to be a real problem.
- Amazing that it's like a deal breaker for keeping your job.
(laughing)
- No high five?
I'm out of here.
- That is so weird.
- It's weird.
- It's just a thing that seems to be happening
all over the world.
- That's amazing.
I bet no one else has made that connection in the world.
I bet even they have not made that connection.
- It's a lollipop. - I bet they mean.
- The high five club.
- They mean high five each other and that feels like it.
(laughing)
- It's because it's dangerous.
- So the idea is, you're supposed to be concentrating
on the road and not high five in kids as they go across.
And presumably what's happened, I might be completely wrong
about this, but it seems to me like a memo's gone out
to all the different councils and they've all gone
round checking that no one's high five in people.
I don't know if that's right, but it's a real coincidence.
- It doesn't take that much concentration to high five,
does it?
- I thought you could focus on the road as well as also.
- Yeah.
- But if someone was repeatedly high five
in while driving, I would not be so comfortable
as a passenger.
- How would you do that so that you'll hand out the window?
- I guess so, yeah.
- But then you're driving too close to the paper.
(laughing)
- No, you would high five other drivers
coming in the opposite direction.
- Oh, of course.
- What you can't see on the Abbey Road cover
is a crest fall in lollipop van on the other side
taking his P-45 slip with it.
- Yeah.
- I don't ever high five the Beatles again.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two.
And that is Chuzinski.
- Yeah, my fact this week is that when the first American
woman went into space, NASA designed a makeup kit for her.
And this is an interview I was reading this week
with Sally Ride, who was in the first group
of female Americans who went into space.
And yeah, she said that NASA called her in for a meeting
and said, look, we're really worried about this,
but we're sending women out there now.
And we obviously need to design your makeup kit.
So what kind of stuff should we be putting in there?
'Cause we're a bit stuck with that.
- What did she say?
- And she said it was the last thing she wanted
to be thinking about at that time.
- Effectively, this fact is about the sort of slightly
backward, massively backward sexism that happens
to a lot of women to say.
- We don't want people to look like a minger for the aliens,
do you? (laughing)
- So there was this interview with Sally Ride, too.
It was quite sweet saying that when NASA came to her,
they were a bit confused about various things,
like they didn't know how many tampons they would want out
in space, so they suggested a hundred tampons per person
for a week and she was like, you know what I mean?
(laughing)
- What if you need to build a fort?
- Tampon fort, please put your child to do this.
- It's like a pillow fort, but for a mouse.
(laughing)
- But some of them, I read an interview with another
of the women who went up who said that
when they came in and asked them do they want makeup,
what kind of makeup do they want?
They were loud gaffors by some of the women,
but one of them said, look, these pictures taken in space
will follow us around for the rest of our lives.
And I don't want to disappear into the background.
So a couple of them did take these makeup kits up.
- Wow.
- Yeah.
- Well, they sort of specially tested makeup that would adhere
to the skin, even in a microgravity.
- But what doesn't happen with makeup, Andy,
is women don't put makeup on at the start of the day,
and by the end of the day, the gravity's just pulled it down
to the bottom of their faces.
(laughing)
- Paul's is on your feet.
- That's a good point.
- I'm a face-up crotch look at a freepier.
(laughing)
- No, it's extraordinary, though, that they sort of...
- It is weird.
What's also weird is how long NASA took to
and send women into space, given how long
the Soviet Union did not take, so it was 20 years after,
it was an odd way of creating that space.
(laughing)
- They untucked a long time.
- So the Soviet Union sent Valentina Tereshkva up in 1963,
and one NASA official was actually asked what he thought
about this at the time, and he said it made him sit
to his stomach to think of women in space.
- But this is the weird thing about Tereshkva's trip.
She was only allowed to go because she wasn't menstruating.
- Oh, 'cause they were worried about what would happen
with periods, don't they?
- They were just didn't have enough payload
to take 5,000 tampons of that.
(laughing)
- No, all these reports sort of worrying about it,
and so basically all your blood sort of pools
in your torso and in your head, 'cause there's no gravity,
so that is something that on Earth is affected by gravity.
And there was a report in America in 1964, which said,
"It will be hard to match," I'm quoting here,
"a temperamental psychophysiologic human
and the complicated machine, either spacecraft,
both need to be ready at the same time, i.e.,
we think women will be too mad
if they're menstruating to operate a spacecraft."
- Wow.
- And they also worried that the blood from that system
would also float up and cause,
it could cause theoretically a dangerous condition
called peritonitis, which can be fatal,
as they thought, well, what if that happens?
But the reality is that normal blood circulation
is completely different to menstrual blood,
so it was in every risk.
- And actually, women going up in space is very sensible
and a good idea because they can do everything
that the men can do, but they're smaller,
generally speaking.
You just need less power to get women up there.
- Oh, I thought you'd be...
- Every bit counts.
- You don't have to send them as far because they're smaller,
so they'll look the same size even when they're a bit closer.
- That's the whole point.
That's why we send people in space, so they look smaller.
- See what humans would look like
if they were one sent to me to school.
- That's one small step.
No, it's a double step.
It's just a long way away.
- There's another astronaut called Svetlana Savitskaya,
and she went up in 1984.
She didn't mention first women to fly in space twice.
In 1995, she gave an interview,
and she was talking about the sort of sexism
that was going on with being a female astronaut.
When she arrived at the salue seven,
as she came in, there was another astronaut there
who handed her an apron and told her to get to work.
That was her arrival in space, yeah.
- Was that a tongue-in-cheek thing?
- No, no, it was very much...
- It seems like, well, women shouldn't be up here,
so I'm going to say something extremely offensive.
- Oh, so it was a deliberate, like, you shouldn't be here.
- You shouldn't be here, put the apron on,
if you're going to be here and clean up the eye of Shuttle.
- Wow.
- Yeah, they've been deliberately letting dirt build up
on the Shuttle and jeopardising the entire mission
to make this incredibly petty point.
- Where'd he get the apron from?
Who has an apron in space?
- He would have had to smuggle an apron.
We would have had to craft an apron,
probably from vital bits of the spaceship.
- On the ISS, do you know they have to vacuum every day?
- Really?
- Yeah, 'cause they need to keep it clean
and they need to keep it clear of germs and bacteria.
And, yeah, so they have to vacuum every day.
- It's quite ironic the fact that they're bringing
the vacuum into space.
- Oh, yeah.
(all laughing)
- Do they, 'cause the stuff isn't adhering to the ground,
'cause of the absence of gravity in the lab.
So do they just wave a vacuum in the air?
- I think they must do.
- They must do, right?
- That is so easy.
- I guess what happens is it kind of floats around
and then it'll just stick to things.
- Yeah, I think it does, that's complete.
- We mentioned before, you know you get calluses
on your feet, 'cause you're not walking around
on the ground, so your underside of your feet gets soft.
And then the top of your feet,
'cause you're hooking your feet around
railing to things gets very hard.
Those calluses break off.
And then they're just floating around this base station,
bits of your own footskin.
So you have to vacuum those up.
- Turn the wear socks first times.
- You should be wearing space socks.
- I guess so, yeah I guess so.
- But it is cool they have reverse feet in space.
(laughing)
- I do love that.
- Is that what we're saying?
- That's what we're saying.
- If you live in space you have reverse feet.
- Do you know what happened on the,
the Maiden Space Shuttle Columbia Mission in 1981?
The toilet got clogged when they were up in space
and they had to use these tube-shaped bags
which attached to your bottom with a sticky seal
to go to the loo.
It's very unpleasant.
And then as they were re-entering the Earth's atmosphere,
the toilet was broken and the vacuum dried excrement
got into the ventilation system
and then started floating around in the main cabin.
- No.
- Bad times.
- That's, see you really need the vacuum cleaner
then.
- Yeah you do, yeah.
- You suck that up.
- You can't suck up poo in a vacuum cleaner.
- I wouldn't use it again after I'd done it.
- Yeah.
- If it's vacuum dried.
- Okay.
- If it's vacuum dried you can.
Which is why I always vacuum dry.
(laughing)
- With a more like a little bit.
- Just one more thing on the extreme sexism and space theme.
- Yeah.
- Great theme.
- It's such a strong theme, it's just a real laugh a minute.
So in 1971 there's a NASA memo
which is about psychological issues with long space flights.
And so this is in '71 and this is about how men
can suffer in various ways.
And one of the ways that they'll suffer
is that they don't have a direct sexual release
'cause they're up in space, all a bunch of men on their own.
And this NASA memo says,
the question of direct sexual release
on a long duration space mission must be considered.
Practical considerations preclude men taking their wives.
So it is possible that a woman qualified
from a scientific viewpoint might be persuaded
to donate her time and energies
for the sake of improving crew morale.
- No, whoa.
- No.
- Space prostitutes.
- I said, say yeah.
- That sounds like a movie doesn't it?
(laughing)
- Star Wars.
- So they want a star.
- No.
- They weren't suggesting that.
They were suggesting that providing a woman
puts, they talk about sublimation,
which is the idea that men will be sexually relieved
by just being around a woman.
It will improve them around rather than being on their own
'cause it pointed out that masturbation isn't,
is messy and that homosexual behavior
shouldn't be encouraged.
- Pointed out masturbation is messy.
- I would say as long as it's freeze-dried.
(laughing)
- Do you ever go to add these house, you'll notice.
- It's not safe.
(laughing)
- Oh, deary me.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for back number three
and that is James.
- Okay, my fat this week is that the Indian Justice System
has a backlog of 31 million cases.
- Ah.
- 31 million.
- Yeah, that's nuts.
- Oh my goodness.
- So terrifying.
- And if all of the judges,
managed to deal with 100 cases an hour
and didn't take any breaks,
it would take them 35 years to get rid of the backlog
'cause there's hardly any judges.
- But it's like, it's between 13 and 15 judges,
per million people in India.
- And in America it's more than 100.
- Is it?
- Wow.
- And so I saw this in a review of a book
called When Crime Pays, Money and Muscle in Indian Politics
in the Economist magazine a few weeks ago.
And what it was really, it's an article
about how corrupt politicians are in India.
And they said in this article that if you are a politician
with serious charges hanging over you,
you have an 18% chance of winning your race
and that's compared with 6% for someone
who doesn't have any charges against them.
So you're three times more likely to get into parliament
if you have a serious crime against you
than if you have no crime, which is insane.
- Where's the causation correlation linked then?
Do they speculate?
- Yeah, because I can't believe people
are voting people in just on the grounds
of their criminal history.
- Well, the speculation is that getting the Indian states
do things is very difficult because it's just
there's so much bureaucracy.
And sometimes you just have to bang a few heads together
to get things done.
And so people think, well, this criminal knows
how to get things done, specifically crimes.
But if he can do crimes, he can probably
sort out the roads and the railways
and stuff like that as well.
- So is it only the people who've done crimes well
that are getting elected?
- Well, if you do crimes that well,
you tend not to get a prison.
- Well, indeed, they've been caught.
So I would have thought.
- Well, a lot of these people haven't been found guilty
or anything because there's still 31 million--
- Oh yeah, it's two cases.
- Two thirds of all people in prison in India
have not been convicted of anything.
They're waiting for the trial.
- So they still put them in jail though.
- Yeah, there are 400,000 people in India in prison.
Which is actually, I think, a bit lower
than the British proportion.
Because Britain's got about 80,000 people in prison.
So they've got five times as many,
but the population's way higher.
- But yeah, so you might have to wait 10 years
for your case to be brought to court.
And you might be innocent at all times.
- And some people can't afford bail
or some people don't know that bail is available to them.
So they're just sort of left-moldering in jail
for years and years and years.
- Wow.
- And in the lower house in India, the lock sabber,
34% of the MPs have got criminal charges filed against them.
So that's more than the third.
And according to this article,
you can pretty much walk from Mumbai to Kolkata
without stepping foot outside a constituency
whose MP isn't facing a charge.
- Oh my God.
- And that's about 2,000 kilometers.
- Yeah.
- Wasn't there a thing in the American election this year
that you told me about, Anna,
where there was one of the people running
had a warrant out for their arrest?
- Oh yeah, the green candidate.
- That's why they were running.
(laughing)
- Oh, well, for me, you're not going to go as she let her life.
But for Green.
(laughing)
- Yeah, Jill Stein, wasn't it?
- Jill Stein.
- And it was for protesting.
- Yeah, it was for a vandalism
'cause she'd graffitied something
and it was a mental protest.
- It was in a particular state, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- So she just didn't campaign very much there.
- Of course.
- Or really anywhere else.
- Wow.
- So obviously there are people who have to wait a very long time
to get their cases heard.
One example is a guy, an 85 year old man who in 2014
was granted a divorce that he'd filed for 32 years.
(laughing)
- Wow.
You're probably made up by then, haven't you?
- Yeah.
- Well, you'd hope so.
Otherwise, that's a lot of resentment
that's festering for third volume, isn't it?
- Yeah, true.
- Yeah.
In 2018, in the government whips, sprung six MPs
out of prison so that they could vote.
(laughing)
Yeah.
- Oh, if anyone else was with that cool,
the most rebellious thing they do
is not a Bay Jeremy Corbyn.
Imagine if they were springing people out of jail.
- So it was gonna be a really tight vote
and they decided, oh, we're gonna need these six people
so they got them out of prison.
(laughing)
- That's amazing.
Like on a day trip or just altogether out of prison?
- I think they put them back in.
- Oh, yeah.
But that's like during John Major's government in the UK
'cause he had this wafer thin majority, didn't he?
And they kept on having to bring in, you know,
they were MPs who were really seriously ill
to get legislation through,
they were practically bringing in stretchers, you know?
- Oh, sort of pushing them through, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Do we know how they sprung them out of prison?
Was it a great escape style tunnel digging sort of endeavor?
- The tunnel digging, you'd need to know
that the vote's coming up a long time advance.
(laughing)
- Order 12 bulldozers on tax payers expense.
- There's one court case in India
that's been going on since 1878.
(laughing)
I think this was the oldest I could find.
- That's a long divorce, isn't it?
(laughing)
- Great grandchildren are getting divorced.
It's a replot of land that's less than two acres
and it's a fight between a sheer Muslim family
and a Sunni Muslim family.
And one side argues that their graves are on it
and so they need to keep it at the other side argues
that belongs to them, it's beginning on since 1878.
- The election commission of India says
that no person should have to travel more than two kilometers
to cast a vote.
So in the state of Goodgerat, there's a temple caretaker
who lives in a temple in the middle of a forest
who is the only person who votes in his special voting booth.
Okay, so the police come in whenever there's an election,
they have to go through this massive forest
with snakes and lions and stuff like that
and then they put the voting booth in the middle of the forest
and they sit there and they wait for him to come.
And he says in the morning, he has his breakfast
and he has a cup of tea and he works out
who he's gonna vote for.
And then about 11 o'clock he wanders down
and puts his vote in and they can go home.
- That is amazing.
- Is that cool?
- Yeah, that's really cool.
- That's hilarious that they haven't specified a time.
They've just got a seat.
(laughing)
- Turn out very low this year.
- Just one thing we've never talked about actually,
that's another weird thing about the Indian justice system
is the case of Laan Bihari
who set up the Otar Pradesh group of dead people.
- Oh yeah.
- I've never mentioned this,
but this is totally bizarre.
He's this guy who in 1975 wanted to apply for a bank loan
and so he went to try and get proof of identity
from the revenue office and he found out that he was dead
because his uncle had declared him dead
so we could claim the land that he had inherited.
And it turned out this is a massive problem
and he set up his organization,
which is to represent people who have been declared dead
and indeed even though they're alive.
And he eventually in 2004,
he eventually in '99.
(laughing)
- I told you he was dead, I told you and I'm right.
- In 1994, sorry, he finally managed to get himself
declared alive, but his organization,
which is the Otar Pradesh Dead People Association,
has over 20,000 members and by 2004,
they only managed to declare four of them alive.
- Wow.
I remember reading about him where all the times
he tried to prove that he was alive.
So he started doing things like illegal stuff,
like robbing a bank.
They'd be like, "We can't arrest you, you're not alive,
we can't arrest a dead man."
- So do you think he was robbing the bank
and they're like, "Oh, it's a ghost."
(laughing)
- He would just move mugs around.
- Just walk into sayances.
(laughing)
- There was a sorry, on sayances,
there was a legal case in the UK
that had to be redone because it turned out the jury.
This is in 1994, it turned out the jury
had made their decision based on a say-on.
- What?
- Yeah, it was a double murder case
and they had to spend the night in a hotel
because the case was going on a while
and they all got really drunk
and then one of them entered their wine glass turned over
and went, "All right, let's ask a ghost
whether he's guilty or not."
And they did and then they had to redo the case
because that isn't allowed.
- Why would the ghost know?
Like what was the...
(laughing)
- I'm not sure the ghost did, though.
- Who was the ghost?
- They're right up there.
- Just the ghost of the murdered.
- Man.
- Oh.
- Who killed you?
Did he do it?
- Oh, so it's specifically, it wasn't just a ghost.
- Well, it might because ghosts can talk to each other, right?
So the ghost, whoever it was,
could have gotten asked the murder person they thought.
- So the ghost went to each other?
- I'll get back to you.
I'm seeing him next week for a ghost lunch.
I will...
(laughing)
- I don't know who did that one.
- Mrs. Doubtful is that.
- Oh, I'll ask her.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that scientists are building a special bunker
in Antarctica to store bits of glassier from the Alps.
- It's so exciting.
- Yeah, it's amazing.
- It's because glassiers are melting all over the world.
And I didn't notice that this is a job.
There's a job of being a paleoclimatologist.
So like a paleoclimatologist does dinosaurs.
A paleoclimatologist does ancient weather, basically.
And all these glassiers,
they're really old ice,
and it contains lots of data about what was in the atmosphere,
how much of which kind of gas,
what the weather would have been like, what the climate was.
So if they melt, you suddenly are losing
tens of thousands of years of data.
So what kind of weather did they learn?
It's like, oh, it was snowing.
- Yeah, it was snowing before that.
It's snowing before that.
- Cold, cold, cold, still cold.
(laughing)
- They learn about the gases in the atmosphere.
But they have collecting cross sections of ice.
They have these circular drills.
They're like cookie cutters,
and they just bore right down into the ice,
and then they'd bring it up,
slice it into one meter sections, label them,
and they're currently building this massive bunker,
which is going to be in Antarctica.
- Is this, is their research group,
are they the ones called protecting ice memory project?
- Yes.
- Okay, so this is this big international pen.
- Wait a minute.
- Oh, yeah.
(laughing)
- Did they call themselves Pemps?
- I think it's Pem project, I think it's just a...
- I can see why they didn't bother with the project.
(laughing)
- They make a big deal of that space.
With a PIM project.
(laughing)
PIM pause project.
- Yeah, it's unbelievably cool though.
Actually, so these ice cores that they pull out,
just the idea that all of this stuff that's happened
for hundreds of thousands of years
is literally frozen in time, and we can look at it.
- Yeah.
- So find volcanic ash, or find when carbon dioxide
was in the atmosphere, and how much of it.
And that's how they get a lot of climate data,
which I hadn't realized.
So when we say, you know, when you have those graphs,
which show how much CO2 was in the atmosphere,
X number of years ago, very often,
that's because they've studied an ice core
and they found a little bubble of it somewhere beneath.
It's been reserved for hundreds of thousands of years.
It's always bubbles.
- It's always the bubbles, isn't it?
And they just keep the bubbles.
That's true, 'cause it'd be easier to store, wouldn't it?
And the reason it's an endoccticate
is that even if the power fails,
it's still minus 50 degrees outside.
Whereas if you have it somewhere warmer, right?
And the power fails, obviously,
all your precious data melts.
- Do you guys know about Project Ice Worm?
- Project Ice Worm.
I know what Ice Worms are.
- What are Ice Worms?
- They're worms that live in ice.
- All right, yeah, that's amazing, James.
- Wait, is that true?
- That can't be true.
- They have worms that live on glaciers,
but Anna can tell us about her thing,
and then I'll tell you about Ice Worms.
- Yeah, okay, cool.
- Let's compare Ice Worms.
So this is an endoccticate.
This is in Greenland.
But Project Ice Worm was this American plan in the Cold War
to build this massive underground network of tunnels
below the ice in Greenland.
And then that would be, they would be missile launch sites.
So that way, if they went via Greenland,
then they could get easy access to the Soviet Union.
And we actually did this.
So if you go to Greenland, way, way under the ice,
there's this network of tunnels
that they started building that's full of stuff like sewage
and loads of diesel fuel apparently,
some pollutants and radiological waste.
And I think 21 tunnels were dug under the ground in Greenland.
And then they decided it wasn't actually going to work
because it wasn't viable for people to live under
the ice for long periods of time.
They had hospitals, they had a cinema,
they had shops.
- Shops, yeah, yeah.
- What's all this sewage, therefore?
- Yeah, I don't know why all the sewage is there.
Maybe it made you have a funny tummy
if you're living on a freezer.
- Makes it easy to freeze, try.
- Yeah, that's true.
But it's a problem because the ice sheet might melt
on Greenland.
And then you've got all the radioactive sludge,
which is going to.
- No, but bad news, the ice sheet melts,
the seas kind of rise and stuff like that.
Good news, we find a new cinema.
- Yeah.
- Oh, yeah.
- Imagine that day when the ice melt said there's a,
like an, you know, an Odin.
- Yeah, covered in radioactive waste.
And sewage.
- I can imagine it being a hipster destination cinema,
actually.
People look like it's going to be great.
- You have to dig through 12 meters of ice together.
(laughing)
- Okay, okay, I can't wait anymore.
- What's an ice worm?
- Oh, yeah, sorry.
(laughing)
- That's why you've been quiet all this time.
- It took so long, oh my God.
- Well, an ice worm, like I say,
it is just a worm that lives on ice.
They live in glaciers and they eat little bits of pollen
that have been trapped in the glacier.
They're little black things.
So you can see them really easily.
- And do they burrow through the ice
and live when they're under ice?
- Well, sometimes they do.
So if it's warm on the outside,
if it's above, like, say, two degrees,
they'll go into the ice.
Because if they get above five degrees, they melt.
And they literally melt, they turn to liquid, these worms.
It's like an enzyme in their body,
which starts to liquefy the whole body.
So if they go above, like, say, two or three degrees,
they will melt.
And you see them on glaciers, the little black things.
- Wow.
- That's so terrifying thing, then.
For some reason, I feel it's like speed,
where you can't go over a certain amount.
- And they're obsessively watching
that the moment you're at the time.
- Yeah.
- Sometimes glaciers enter this super fast state.
And they go-- - How fast?
- Not very fast.
- So not super fast.
It's, well, they're called them glaciers surges.
And they move at 100 times their normal speed.
- When I read that the fastest that they've ever gone
is 11 miles per year.
- That's pretty fast.
Is it that? - Is it?
- Well, it's about 45 meters per day.
- Sure, it's like southern rail.
- Yeah, exactly, yeah.
But they are moving four times faster than they were
in the '90s, in the summer's speed of glaciers.
- Which is, that's big.
Where they're going?
- Well, they're melting.
- Down hill, down hill, and towards the--
- Oh, okay, right, okay.
- So that's what a glacier is, basically.
It's loads and loads of snow that's fallen over,
loads and loads of years.
And it's just slowly with gravity moving down
as well to see like a river, but it's made of ice.
- So it's on land?
- Yes.
- Okay. - Yeah.
- Otherwise it'd be an iceberg.
- Yes, okay, so that's the difference.
That's what I didn't understand.
- Yeah, and actually, a fox's glacier mint
chose a polar bear standing on an iceberg.
- You're right.
- So as a completely inaccurate mint.
- It should be an iceberg mint.
- Yes.
- Or they need to change their design.
- Either way.
- Until they do one of those two things,
I'm gonna buy one of those mints.
- I mean, to be honest, if we've been really pedantic,
they should show a fox standing on a glacier.
- So they've got it going in a couple of ways.
- It's in a polar bear on iceberg.
What are you guys doing?
(laughing)
- I'm in a bear iceberg mint.
It should be.
- There are towns in the Alps
who are still burying soldiers from the First World War,
thanks to Glacier melt.
- What do you mean by that?
- Well, loads of soldiers were posted
in the Alps during the First World War,
and it was incredibly, obviously,
very cold, extremely harsh conditions to live in,
and they were fighting very fiercely
over almost no territory, basically.
But lots of soldiers froze to death,
got caught in the Glaciers,
they didn't get caught by the Glaciers,
but they...
- Incredibly slow, like that Austin Powers scene,
edging away from the slow moving Glacier.
- Well, no, we've established that they're super fast,
so maybe they weren't ready for the speed of a...
- Okay.
- Of a Glacier, about 11 miles per year.
- 11 miles per year.
(laughing)
- How did these guys get into the army?
- Anyway, they were caught.
- They're now being discovered
as the Glaciers retreat as they melt.
Bodies are being discovered, and they're being buried.
So there was a funeral for two of them
in 2013, and 500 people turned up to pay their respect.
- Were their bodies preserved properly?
Like, 'cause I remember when they found
Mallory on Everest, you know,
a lot of his skin was there.
His body was there, 'cause they...
- Yeah. - You're properly preserved, aren't you?
- I don't know how well preserved they were,
but there is a particular town called Peo
where they do a lot of these barrels,
'cause they're near a lot of the battlefield sites,
and that's where the bodies are being discovered.
- Wow. - Amazing.
- It is kind of a...
If you're looking on the bright side of Clover Warming,
it is good for glacial archaeology, isn't it?
Because these...
Like you say, it's suddenly revealing all this amazing stuff.
So melting glaciers have suddenly revealed
like lots of Roman coins, some Iron Age horses.
There's a glass you call the Meadow Hall Glacier.
- I'm not sure, I don't know.
Like, a couple of coins in a horse
makes up for losing the entire Netherlands.
- No, no, no, no, no.
- What if you want your children to go
into the same line of work as you when there's no more ice?
It's only good in the very short term.
- Well, I think we've established that this view
is a very short term view, isn't it?
That's already about the long term.
I would be concerned about climate change.
(laughing)
As it is, I'm very excited about these Roman coins.
And a forest, so there's a thousand-year-old...
(laughing)
We could always do it more forest,
and there's a thousand-year-old forest
that's been revealed by a melting glacier in Alaska.
- I bet it's a rubbish forest after all the time
on a glacier, it can't be good.
- It's a bit stumpy, but there is indeed.
- A bit depressing, it's a dead squirrels everywhere.
(laughing)
- Yeah, that's strange, isn't it?
'Cause you do want more trees as well.
You want more forests, but you also want more ice,
so which do you choose?
- Oh, it's so easy to choose, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- But the ice, I think we'll keep the ice.
- Okay, yeah.
- Great, 'cause you can go forests elsewhere
where there's no ice, but you can't put ice.
- You can make ice.
- You can't keep it in the Amazon.
(laughing)
If you have a refrigerator, you can.
- You can't turn the hours into a fridge.
- Dad, but you can put a lot of refrigerators
into the Amazon.
- It's not a refrigerator, it's a freezer.
- Why?
(laughing)
- A refrigerator's just gonna slow down the melting.
That's why my ice tray's always full of water.
(laughing)
I'm living.
That's why my pasties are never any good.
- Do you want some ice, or do you think?
- Dribble, dribble, dribble.
(laughing)
- Have a bite, we'll have an ice cream instead.
- Oh no.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter account.
So I'm on @Streiberland, James.
- @XShakes.
- Andy.
- @AndruHunterM.
- And Anna.
- You can email podcast@QI.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account.
It's @QIPodcast, or you can go to our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
We have all of our previous episodes up there.
We'll be back again next week.
See you then, guys.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)