(phone ringing)
(indistinct chatter)
(upbeat music)
- Hi. - Hello.
- Hi, Andy.
- Andy here, joined by my three chums.
- James. - Hey, what's up?
- Anna. - Come on, Anna.
Please stand up, come on.
James, Anna, and Dan are here as well.
And this is Drop as a Line.
- I've got a mouth full of strutwaffle,
otherwise I would have said high as well.
- Yeah. - Oh, yum.
- The standards of professionals--
- You should like banana.
- Do you have any?
- What is this, strutwaffle?
- We're gonna start us again.
Guys, this is-- - Start us again.
- It's too unprofessional. - Yeah.
- Hi. - Hello.
- Oh my God.
- Right. - Anna, would you like
a strutwaffle?
(laughing)
- I get no respect.
Welcome to Drop as a Line, everybody.
This is the bit of the show where we are--
No, James, open your bottle of carbonated water.
- It's Evian.
(laughing)
- Anyone got anything else?
They'd like to get off their chest or out of their bags.
- No, no, no. - Right, okay.
Welcome to Drop as a Line.
This is where we are going through your words.
I'm reading them out to these guys.
These guys will say something funny
and we'll end after about a little while.
That fair summation?
- Yeah, that's excellent.
Why don't we get on with it?
- Yeah, okay.
- Maybe we should start again.
- No, look, we've had some cracking correspondence.
- Great.
- Here is Ian Dunne with an um, actually--
- Hello. - An old friend.
- Great friend of the show.
- Hi, Ian.
- Just a quick note regarding Rutland,
which came up in episode 511.
In it, you, Andy, said that Rutland
was the smallest county in England.
- Oh, he's from T-side, Ian.
Is that-- - Who is he?
- Yeah, is that, you're going to say that's small?
No, it's not small.
- No, he just says, as was mentioned
in the QI episode, England, Rutrow,
a general ignorance question said that the smallest county
was actually the Isle of Wight at High Tide.
- That's right.
- When the tide is out, indeed, Rutland is smaller.
- That's great.
- I know. - That's a good fact.
- And I've also heard from Hattie Hodgson-Krome,
brilliant name on Twitter.
The population of Rutland are crying out
in the latest episode of--
- Just imagine flying over Rutland
in a small aircraft and just hearing the people.
- Absolutely wailing and gnashing of teeth
coming from Rutland.
In the latest episode of No Such Thing, Andy,
you said it had become, I think,
a unitary authority instead of a county.
- Right. - Actually,
it became an independent county again in 1997.
As a primary school there, at the time,
I received a mug to mark the occasion.
I'm sorry, Hattie, and I'm sorry, Ian.
- I would say, of all the things,
having worked at QI for 20 years, more, in fact,
the thing that gets people hot under the collar
more than almost anything else is the 1971
Unitary Authorities Act,
which made all of the counties of England the new counties.
- Well, it's your chat-up line, isn't it?
You ask people in bars what they think about it.
- I just stand on the corner of Cumbria and Northumberland.
- Do you remember a thing where we spoke about people
not being called BJ in the UK?
- Yeah, that was me.
- Yeah, I just said, I feel like Americans are called BJ.
A few people have messaged me saying, "I know an Aussie BJ."
Yeah.
- Well, Chris Blundle-Drois writes.
(laughing)
- Since we amalgamated, hyphenated our names
when we got married, we are now the Blundle-Droisers,
AKA the BJs.
We live in York.
And now our family and friends knows as the BJs,
God help our two-year-old daughter
when she goes to school in the future.
(laughing)
There we go, thank you, Chris.
- I think it's one of the few instances where being BJ
is going to be less embarrassing for her
than being called Blundle-Drois.
- It's a lovely name.
- It is a lovely name.
The word Blundle, I wish meant something
because I'd love to be saying it on a regular basis.
- Blundle-Bus, if they have a car,
they should call it the Blundle-Bus.
- Yes.
- It sounds a bit like Blunder-Bus.
- And what's that?
- It's a large gum.
- Yeah, just a cool word.
- Cool.
- Andrew Morth writes.
- You know the bit where you say something
and then we're funny after it?
- Oh yeah.
- When do we get to that bit?
(laughing)
- We'll keep going until we've got something.
- Okay.
- Andrew Morth writes.
(humming)
(laughing)
- How dare you, Andrew?
- Oh, lovely.
Another Andy M, as he points out.
I recently joined Clubfish to see
if you guys ever mentioned my amazing fact
about the Hoover Dam back in November, 2022.
Brackets?
No.
(laughing)
- Do we have the fact?
- I did look at it, it's fine.
- Can I tell you the fact, okay?
See if it's the same one.
- Oh yeah.
- They used to, if you had a mental illness,
they used to prescribe you to go to the Hoover Dam
and listen to the water going down the Hoover Dam
and that was supposed to make you feel better.
- Love it.
- That is a good fact.
- Was that his fact?
- No, his fact, it was a really good one actually.
It was about the construction of the dam
and it was really tragic.
It was about the first person and the last person to die
and I think the first person was someone like the architect
or the last person was his son.
- Right.
- And it was a great fact, but it was quite sad.
So I thought it might be a bit gloomy for us.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Anyway, I joined, to see if you mentioned my fact,
with every intention of unsubscribing before I had to pay
because I'm cheap and have very little money at the moment.
- That's fair, that's fair.
- However, around a year ago on the Bonus Podcast,
Andy admitted to peeing in the shower,
which was a shocking revelation
from such a private and conservative man.
I have hence committed to peeing for at least one month
for the privilege of hearing you all open up.
- It's the first and last time Andy ever opened up.
- I know, and I closed right back down.
It was such an unpleasant time for me
that I've just, I've never said anything.
No one ever gets anything out of me now.
- There's months of therapy, wasn't it,
after you've missed that?
Which I know you don't want us to say, of course, but.
- Yeah, Jesus.
Here's a fact about Dan's teeth.
- Oh, yeah, so he doesn't have canines.
- Right, and this is from Jessamy Gloor.
- Please.
- This is a brilliant name.
- Stunning name, stunning.
- I know, as an American who lived in Britain,
I noticed that many white British people
have really long canines,
compared to what seems normal in the USA.
So much so that it gets distracting,
wondering if the British person you're talking to
is actually a vampire.
(laughing)
- This is just the thing we said.
- Well, we were talking about canine teeth, and.
- We just noticed that you don't have any.
- Yeah, everyone said, "Look at your mouth,"
and Anna, I think it was you who said, "Dan, where are yours?"
People have since gone through my Instagram,
finding photos of me with a smile, going, "Yeah, you don't."
Like, just pointing out specific photos to me.
- So she says, "Despite having listened to fish for years,
"I still get the names mixed up,
"but when Anna pointed out that Dan had no canines,
"I easily guessed he was the least British of the four."
- Right, I think that's a coincidence.
I like the theory, but we need more data.
- I like it.
- She says, "No clue if it's genetic or environmental,
"but I've never seen an American try to open a bag of crisps
"with their teeth."
(laughing)
- I actually think that that is a thing that Americans
and non-English people find very unusual about the British,
that if you go to a pub, people will go to the bar
buy a pack of crisps, bite it open,
and then just open it and leave it on a table.
- Yeah.
- How are they opening their crisps to share?
- I don't think they share.
- Well, they don't share.
- There was someone on Twitter who was--
- People share.
- No other country shares.
(laughing)
- It honestly was a revelation
when I came here and I saw that happen.
And then as my Aussie mates came over
and other international friends,
I would do it knowing each time
that I was introducing them to something incredible.
- Oh, wow.
- It's funny, it's sort of inoculated
Britain against true socialism.
Like, that's what we do to share.
(laughing)
- That's all we need.
- And we've never had a proper redistributive--
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Anyway, thank you.
- 'Cause we redistribute crisps round and table
in a pub.
- Yeah.
- I actually don't like doing it.
- Don't you?
- Because--
- You don't like sharing.
- Yeah, 'cause I hate sharing for yourself-ish
and very greedy.
But also, I feel like you know this about me
on my favorite thing about crisps.
My favorite thing to do with crisps.
- You lick the bag?
- No.
You've gotta pop the crisp bag.
So as soon as you ruin the crisp bag.
So I just overturn all the crisps onto the table
and then I bang the bag.
- Yeah.
- Bang the bag.
(laughing)
This is that opening up stuff
that this guy wanted us to do.
- Yeah, happy now.
- That's good stuff.
- Simon Graham writes,
this is about when Dan's fact was about the wall
crashing into air to the center.
- Oh yeah.
- Which is such a good fact.
- Yeah, brilliant.
- So in the following discussion,
you all lamented the demise of the lollipop man
in the pit crew, right?
In 2009, this, I love this email.
Formula One introduced hybrid engines
with kinetic energy recovery systems
which harvested energy when you're braking.
- Yeah, it's the same stuff
as you get in electric cars today.
- Right, and they store it in batteries
and then when you're overtaking,
you sort of, you use that.
The technology was a bit unknown
and somewhat unreliable at the time.
During this early period of the KERS,
there was always a pit crew member standing by
with what looks like a shepherd's crook
in case one of the crew was electrocuted.
- Oh, what, they'd pull him off stage
like someone who's terrible comedian?
- That's it, no.
- There was always a crew member
holding one during the pit stops
in case of electrocution.
- Wow.
- He attached a photo showing a pit member
wearing extra heavy rubber gloves.
And yeah, since the technology has moved on,
it has become more reliable and safe
and the shepherd has gone the way of the lollipop man.
- Wow, I wonder if it did ever happen
'cause we'd have it on camera presumably
if it was a F1 kind of thing.
- I don't know, maybe it would have.
- Isn't that lovely?
- It is quite nice, I imagine you being sacked
as a lollipop man and going home
and then you get the phone call going darling,
don't worry, I've got a new gig.
- I've got an upsetting email to read.
It's from Alex Stroh, subject Dan was right.
- I'm upset already.
- We'll cut this, so what's the point?
- And he's quoting from I think a piece,
maybe a Wikipedia, but it's,
"As water monsters, Kappa have been blamed for drownings
and are often said to try and lure people into water."
- I just thought I really thought you meant
the tracksuit trouser brand.
(laughing)
And they would, they'd weigh you down
if you jump in the sea.
Sorry, Kappa, what?
- They lure people into water
and pull them in with their great skill at wrestling.
- This is like a fictional beast with Kappa, right?
- Yeah, mythical beast in Japan, I believe.
- They're sometimes said to take their victims
for the purpose of drinking their blood,
eating their livers, or gaining power
by taking their shirokodama,
a mythical ball said to contain the soul
which is located inside the anus.
- So sorry, Dan was right about something.
- We were, we were--
(laughing)
- This was from before my time.
- No, no, no, we were on stage together.
This was-- - Soho Theatre.
- Yeah, Soho Theatre,
and we were talking about the bong ball.
- Bong ball that Aussies have.
- Was I in this one?
- Yeah, yeah.
- I was asking what the word bong ball meant,
and it was actually a party thrown by a publican
because bong is part of a barrel.
And Dan thought that the bong ball
was a thing found in an anus.
- I was asking if it was the anus soul ball,
which these Japanese mythological creatures would--
- Yeah, you were right.
- Yeah, I'm still not getting the respect
from having an anus. - No, weird, isn't it?
- Well done.
- Never questioned down on cryptozoology.
I can't believe we even did.
- It's mythological, it's mythological stuff.
- Was it, 'cause it's in Japan,
was it believed by the anus,
which is a large group of Japanese people?
- And they're the Ainu.
- Yeah, but we have to be getting trouble every time
we mention them, 'cause James and his sixth uncle
in the eighties tried.
- Dan, can you read out that word?
That one word?
- Manitowak?
- Okay, this is an email from Alex.
"Andy, just wanted to say that Dan pronounced it
completely correctly.
It was like he was from Wisconsin.
I'm as shocked as you are."
(all laughing)
- P.S., if you use this on Drop as a Line,
please make Dan read my last name.
'Cause that's from Alex Tiebsky."
There we go.
- That sounded like it plausibly could be corrected.
- Yeah.
- Quite good actually as well.
- Just so people can play along at home.
- T-I-E-V-S-K-Y.
- Okay.
- I'd have maybe gone with Tiebsky,
but Tiebsky sounds very, very likely.
- Okay, Alex's right in.
Who was correct?
Andy or Dan?
- And did I pronounce the place right again?
- Oh, good.
Maybe Dan, 'cause I don't know what I said.
- It was a sheer chance.
You've gotta, you know, throw one dart right once.
- Yeah.
- Do it randomly.
- Can I give you a piece of correspondence
that someone sent in?
- Yeah.
- This was sent on my Instagram,
no such thing as James Harkin,
by someone called Katie Collinson.
And it was about an episode that I wasn't in.
And she said, "Tell Dan that liquid soap
"is normally full of preservatives
"because it is made with water."
And apparently you were talking about the difference between,
apparently I did listen to the show.
He's very good with Reese James.
Are you talking about the difference between block soap
and liquid soap?
- Yeah.
- And what I found really interesting is,
I think in the show, you guys mentioned that liquid soap
is worse for the environment because it contains water
and you need to ship that around the world.
- I think I said that.
- I think that's true.
But what's really interesting, I think,
is what Katie said, which she worked for Lush, by the way.
She says that the water causes it to go off.
Because you've got water in there,
it can collect bacteria and stuff like that,
whereas solid soap can't do that.
So, solid soap is cleaner than liquid soap.
- Nice.
- You don't think of off water, do you?
You rarely take a sip of water and go, "Oh, that's been--"
- But if bacteria need to live, they need water, don't they?
- Well, there we go.
Glad that we've got more anti-liquid soap propaganda.
- That's brilliant.
Here's one.
This is a bit of a controversial one.
This is a spicy meat.
It's from Ben Lidgate.
I just listened to your most recent Christmas episode,
in which Dan mentions the fact
that Chuck Norris edits out all the fight scenes
from his movies in order to show them to his kids.
And the rest of you all sounded interested and entertained
as if this was new information for you.
However, I am also currently relistening
to all your old episodes.
And I've just listened to episode 29
from the 3rd of October, 2014,
in which Dan mentions this fact.
And episode 30 from the 11th of October, 2014,
in which Dan mentions it again.
And each time, you all sounded at least slightly surprised.
- Well, two things here.
I think Dan did say this is a fact
I've been trying to prove for a long time.
So he did reference that.
And secondly, that's just being polite, isn't it?
It'd be terrible if every time one of you said a fact,
I didn't find it interesting.
I commented, I don't find that interesting.
- Ben says, I'm beginning to suspect
that the hilarious banter that sounds spontaneous each week
is in fact entirely infected.
How much of what we hear is real.
Are all your interactions entirely scripted?
Or is it simply the case that none of you pay attention
to Dan and he can come up with the same fact every week
and none of you would know this?
- Bingo, there we go.
- By the way, I did have a listener write in to me
having tracked down the interview that I was talking about.
And it is the case that he re-edits the movies.
- Sorry, Chuck Norris re-edits movies.
Why would he do that?
- So basically he doesn't want his kids to talk about it.
- I can only fake it three times.
- However, in that specific interview,
he says he takes it from an R-rated movie
to a movie that they can watch.
He doesn't specifically say, takes out all the fight scenes.
- Which is something I feel I definitely read somewhere else.
- So he might take out some beswearing as well.
- Yeah, or the love scenes or whatever that is.
- Here's hoping that you track down the truth
and we'll end up hearing that fact a fifth time.
- We're getting closer.
- Oh yeah. - See?
- Absolutely. - Over a 10 year period,
you keep mentioning it.
- Someone will help.
- Gene Montarastelli writes, with a sport fact actually,
says that he really enjoyed everything to play for, by the way.
- Thank you. - The QI book of sports.
- Oh, thank you, Gene.
Or John, I'm gonna say.
- Gene.
- Okay, or Gene.
Oh, is it G-E-N-E? - Yeah.
- Sorry, I thought it was J-E-A-N.
- No, no, no, I'm sure you know how to pronounce the word
that I've got written in front of me better than I do.
- Hannah, you're distracting from the fact
that we've got a plug chance here.
- Oh, one reader and I don't get it.
- No, we're moving on.
Actually, he hated it.
(laughing)
- No, what was it he enjoyed?
- We talked about-- - Look everything to play for.
- He talked about, you know, we talked about the name change
for the British basketball league.
- Became the BBL.
- Yeah.
- It was originally the BBL, I should say,
which is also Brazilian but left.
- And their logo looks a bit like a bum.
- Yeah.
- And he says, "When you were talking about this,
"there was a discussion of how a large rump
"might be helpful in basketball.
"Basketball Hall, basketball Hall of Famer, Charles Barkley."
(laughing)
- Sorry.
- He doesn't speak to a lad who doesn't know much
about sports.
(laughing)
- I thought you were capable of reading the words
right in front of you.
(laughing)
- Yeah, okay.
- That's a fair cop.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
All right, whatever.
Basketball Hall of Famer, Charles Barkley.
- Yes. - Easy, easy.
Was known for his ample butt.
And--
- Yeah, he used to use it to bounce off people a little bit,
didn't he?
He would like stuff, you know,
if people are running towards him,
he'd move his bum in the way and they'd kind of--
- Exactly that.
He was very effective at using his generous posterior
to move taller players out of the way.
(laughing)
Incredible.
- What was the name?
- Can you smell my ass?
(laughing)
Can you smell my ass?
That's it.
- Oh, brilliant.
Ross McGuire writes,
this is a, what is it called,
when we get something wrong?
- I'm unusual. - I'm actually,
I'm actually is what it is.
This week's episode said that Bethany England
was the first person to play for a country
that shares her name.
I think it was one of you, Dan or Anna, you said that.
- The first person to play for the,
oh yeah, the country that shares her name.
Sorry, yes, that's right.
I did claim that.
- Well, it's not right, Anna.
Because of a man called Steven Ireland.
- Oh, yes. - Played for Ireland.
Six caps and four goals.
- We don't really, when we talk about football,
we are usually thinking about women's football.
So sometimes we don't always
immediately bring the men's game to mind.
- Absolutely.
- I think that's what happened there.
- Yeah, it's very sexist of us and I do apologise.
Yeah.
That's a great question, well done.
- No, it's a brilliant.
- You know what, when we were sat on stage,
I was going through all the countries
trying to think of any other ones.
And I never got to put anything down.
- We were talking about Alan Brazil, weren't we?
- Actually, mostly the Alan Brazil stuff got cut out
because we didn't know that he'd recently died.
- Oh, I'm so dead though.
- I mean, it was sad, but we spoke about him
as if he was still alive.
- Yeah, right.
- Yeah.
- I've got something, I've got a bad one here.
This is a good one, but it's bad for me.
Matt Shaw writes.
- Your novels are shit.
(all laughing)
- James, I've asked you to stay out of the inbox,
it's important that you hear these for the first time, fresh.
- It's rather that than on the Amazon review.
(all laughing)
- Matt Shaw writes.
I'm a sommelier and a wine importer
with a specialization in fortified wine,
and I love the section you did on Sherry,
but I was compelled to write in
as Andy has unfortunately fallen foul
of one of the classic misunderstandings
of the Solera system.
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah, that pyramid.
- Can you just quickly remind us of the Solera system?
- Basically, the thing I said that was wrong
is that you move most of the Sherry
from one barrel to another,
and the new Sherry's at the top of the pyramid,
and the old Sherry's at the bottom of the pyramid,
and you move it down and down and down,
so it all gets mixed up,
and the older Sherry helps
the newer Sherry develop and blah, blah, blah.
He says it's always represented as a pyramid,
because it's a very useful representation,
but the consistent and persistent side effect
is that every single wine student
gets tricked into thinking
these are physical barrels of pyramids,
which they're not.
- So they just move it with cups running to and from?
- Well, it's like eggs in buckets,
he says if there's a fire or an accident,
you will only lose some of it,
whereas if it's in a pyramid, you lose all of it.
And some of the wine storage warehouses
have their own micro climates,
which influence how the wine ages,
so they have to move around between.
- Oh wow. - Anyway,
the wine doesn't physically flow between the barrels,
it's blended in a separate larger tank.
This is a small point,
and an otherwise well-explained and very interesting section,
but given it's one of the most persistent myths,
I have spent a decade battling
the one I felt it was worth being a pedant for.
- That study is well spent, I must say.
- No, I think that's a good, that's a good, you know.
- Yeah, yeah, really good.
- Here's a question.
- All right, cool.
- Michael Cattle writes,
"Hello from 2019, sort of."
- Oh, time traveler.
- "Playful, off to a playful start with Michael."
I've listened to the entirety of The Fisher
for probably five times or so at this point.
- Right.
- Wow, I'm passing through the end of 2019 again,
and James just mentioned that Polina, his wife,
had booked a flight on a parabolic flight
next year. - Oh yeah.
- Did she ever go on that flight?
And if so, what did she think?
I don't recall hearing an update,
and I'm hoping Polina comes up enough
that the question isn't too personal.
- Okay, well, spoiler alert for the guy living in 2019,
by 2020, there weren't many trips to France
to do parabolic flights.
I don't really want to explain exactly why,
'cause it will spoil everything for you.
- But there was enough vomiting going on in 2020
without parabolic flying.
- Unfortunately, we had to cancel it because of COVID.
And then we had a baby, and we will have to take
medical again before we get a chance to do it,
'cause you need to take a medical.
- That was fair enough.
- You're crying, Shane.
- That's a sad ending to that, Aimee, for Michael,
but thank you.
Oh, here's a really good one.
Dave in sale, credit, Manchester.
Firstly, when are you gonna do a new book of the year?
We'll get back to you.
Secondly, and more importantly,
I thought it would bring to draw your attention
to a possibility of a trademark infringement.
In the audio book of Everything to Play for,
the QI Book of Sports by James Harkin and Anterjinsky,
they both sign off the end of the audio book
by just using the word buy.
(laughing)
- I can't believe someone's listened all the way to the end.
- Do we do that?
- I assume this has already been trademarked by you,
hence my worry.
Civil remedies for trademark infringement
include injunctions, damages, or accounted profits.
Criminal penalties are also available, good luck.
- Does Dave from sale say that, for instance,
you might need to actually trademark something
before it could be infringed?
- No, he doesn't say that.
Just as he assumes I've got it.
- Actually, we've trademarked it.
- Stop.
- And now you are infringing on our trademark
every time you say it.
- How you gonna end this up?
(laughing)
- Very abruptly.
Unlike my normal slow language.
(laughing)
- How interesting, I remember us recording it,
but I didn't recall that we'd done the buy thing.
- So what do you do?
You guys at the end just have a kind of like,
well, that's it everyone.
- Yeah, well, we read the book
and then we did a special extra bonus chapter
where we just chatted like a podcast,
but without the two dead weights.
(laughing)
At the end of that, I presume we just said bye.
- I do remember that, it's the only bit I remember is the buy.
- Deeming, I'm so cross, I'm so furious.
All right, well, we'll thrash that out.
Thank you very much for that.
Thank you, Dave.
- Can't believe you spilled the beans.
- One final thing, sorry.
Tom Rist Smith writes,
"I'm in the toilet of a shuffleboard bar called Meen Doses
"in Wellington, New Zealand,
"and they are playing fish,
"but only in the bathroom, not in the bar."
And a friend of mine wrote to me saying,
"I was in a bar the other day,
"and I'm in the toilet of a shuffleboard bar
"called Meen Doses in Wellington, New Zealand,
"and they are playing fish,
"but only in the bathroom, not in the bar."
- Really?
- And a friend of mine wrote to me saying,
"I was in a bar the other day,
"and I'm in the toilet of a shuffleboard bar
"and they are playing fish in the toilet."
- That's so cool.
- In Wellington.
- That's so exciting.
- So is he just spending lots of time in the toilet now?
- I guess.
- He does spend like 55 minutes in the toilet.
And like, what have you been doing in that toilet
for all that time?
Well, Rist is my middle name.
- Anyway, that's cool, isn't it?
- That's pretty exciting.
- We've made it.
And that's probably the furthest toilet we've been played in.
- It won't doubt the toilet.
- That will turn.
- Yeah.
- We should acknowledge it secretly in an upcoming episode.
- Oh, that's great.
- Just something.
Just something to get a mention of shuffleboard.
- We could make a special 15-minute episode,
send it to this bar.
If you want to be a completist,
not just seeing as a fish,
you have to go to this bar toilet to listen to it.
- That's such a good idea.
Let's do that.
Great, let's definitely do that.
- That's gonna be very bad for people's carbon footprint.
Oh, I feel very guilty about encouraging everyone
to flock to the toilet.
- That's true.
A shuffleboard bar called Mean Doses in Wellington.
- Imagine if--
- It's a long way.
- It's a hundred thousand people time now.
- Oh, God, I've got anxiety about how you're gonna end this.
Toodle-oo.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- I think I covered it.
That was fun, wasn't it?
- Nailed it.
- It was great.
- It was a loo, yeah.
- Pip, pip.
No, thanks everybody for listening.
That was really fun.
I hope you enjoyed it.
If you want to say anything,
just email podcast@qi.com.
We love hearing from you with your spin-off stories
and your bonus facts.
We'll be back again next month with another one of these.
See you next time.
Bye.
Yeah.
- Wow, see you for that.
(upbeat music)