(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish,
a weekly podcast coming to you
from four undisclosed locations in the UK.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I am sitting here with James Harkin, Anna Tijinski
and Andrew Hunter Murray.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 1948,
a drive-through fly-through cinema opened in New Jersey
where you could watch movies from the seat of your car
or the seat of your small aircraft.
- That's great.
- Okay, so a couple of things to say
before we get into this.
Number one is that most of the following material
that you're about to hear from me
comes from an amazing book
called The History of Driving Theatres by Kerry Seagrave.
And secondly, this fact would have made a lot more sense
if it had been in its original setting,
which was in a drive-in show
that we were supposed to do this week.
- Yes, yeah, this episode was meant to be
in one very disclosed location
and unfortunately got canceled.
- Sorry about that, everyone.
- Yeah, much apologies. - Not our fault.
- Not our fault, but you're going to get the facts anyway.
- I think we can pretend.
Guys, we can pretend.
We can just all pretend we're in a car.
The people at home won't know.
- Andy, we weren't supposed to be in a car
when we were doing the show.
It was the audience that were in a car.
We were supposed to be on the stage.
- I was going to bring my car to the stage
and then just sit in there.
So this fly-through,
did you have planes and cars next to each other?
- The planes were behind the cars.
- That makes sense,
because if the planes were in front of the cars,
then it's a raw deal if you're sitting in your car, isn't it?
Just looking at the arse of a plane.
- If it's a 747 or something like that,
you don't want to climb in front of you.
But this was organized by a guy called Edward Brown Jr.,
who was a former Navy pilot,
and his drive-in had capacity for 500 cars
and then 25 aeroplanes on the last couple of rows.
And what would happen is you would fly
into a nearby airfield and then you would taxi into the,
not get a taxi, you would drive the plane on its wheels
into the last row of the theater,
and then afterwards a jeep would tow you back
to the airfield and you'd be able to fly off again.
And the charge for the aeroplanes was 25 cents.
- Wow. - That's extraordinary.
I guess this was a bit more in the time
when your average Joe sometimes had a plane.
People sort of did a bit more in the '40s, didn't they?
They did like a small piece together aeroplanes.
I think it was much, much more common.
Like people used to,
you used to have hobbyists who would do sort of trick flights
in and out of sheds and stuff, but still very weird.
Although I read that it sort of caught on,
so it must have had a few people going
because a few more popped up in the subsequent years, right,
in like Alabama and Texas.
- Yeah, some of them opened by the same guy.
So I don't know if that's a huge mark of success.
- You don't open up a second drive-through fly-through
unless your first one was successful.
- Yeah, absolutely, yeah.
- That's true.
But he really, it was quite exciting what he did
because he bought this land and he turned the whole,
so he set up the airport, he set up the drive-through.
He bulldozed everything in the way using a World War I tank
and it also had a sort of gulf range next to it
and an amusement park and playground.
- There was a great article
by someone called Mary Morley Cohen on this.
And I'm just gonna list the extra things
that one particular drive-in had, okay?
It had a playground, pony rides, a dance floor,
shuffleboard and horseshoe pitching tournaments,
cartoon carnivals, midnight spook shows,
baby parades and beautiful child contests,
daredevil car rides, circus acts,
high tower dives, anniversary and birthday celebrations,
fireworks, a picnic and play area,
potato sack races and television.
- That's just extra TV in case you're bored of the film,
I guess.
- That's amazing.
There was one in Memphis where you could get your laundry done
when you went to the drive-in.
So you turn up with your laundry, hand it in
and then they clean it for you.
And as you left, you'd pick it up.
- That's so good.
- It's almost like the films just weren't the main attraction.
And I think someone did an experiment
'cause they thought actually,
are people even coming to see the films?
And so they didn't advertise what film was showing
and the same number of people showed up.
And then they started interviewing people
as they were driving in and said,
"What film are you coming for?"
And most people didn't know what film they were going to see.
They're just kind of coming 'cause it's a thing to do.
But I think the laundry thing was particularly interesting
because that was about how one of the appeals of the drive-ins
was that it appealed to a much broader audience.
And so, for instance, one of the people they advertised to
was mothers, housewives, because you could bring your kids.
So the idea was you didn't have to find a babysitter
to leave them at home, brought your kids along.
They also specifically advertised to disabled people
because you can stay in your car.
You don't have to get up and maneuver into a seat.
And they advertised specifically to obese people
at the start, didn't they?
I think one of the very first adverts
from the guy who invented the drive-in
was a picture of an overweight lady
trying to squeeze into a cinema seat.
And then it said something like,
"Kate doesn't have any problem at the drive-in."
- So she was called Kate Smith,
the lady who was in that image.
And she was a really famous singer
and she was like the South America's version
of Dame Vera Lynn.
So she was really big during the war
and she sang a load of amazing songs
and everyone got really patriotic about her.
And she was also, she sang for the Philadelphia Flyers.
So before the game, before every game,
she would sing "God Bless America."
And whenever she sang, they almost always won.
They had a record of 100 wins and 29 losses
and five ties whenever she sang.
And normally it was more like 50/50.
So all the other teams really hated her
because she was just this amazingly good mascot
for that team.
But yeah, she was super famous Kate Smith.
- I feel terrible.
- I've described her as just an overweight lady
trying to squeeze into her cinema seat.
And she's basically the lovely charm
of the whole United States.
I'm so sorry.
- But so that was the reason, wasn't it,
for the whole invention of the drive-in.
It was 1933, a guy called Richard Hollingshead
was living in New Jersey
and his mother found cinema seats uncomfortable
and he wanted to fix that.
So he thought if she could watch it
from the comfort of her car,
this would be a much better system.
So he rigged up a sort of system
for her to test it out on
and it's so clever, these sort of innovation
that he did in the early days.
Once he had the idea that this could be commercial,
the thought of, okay, how do I deal with it
if it's raining, for example?
So he would have his water hose
and sprinkler systems going off in the background
while he tested different ways.
He thought if cars were gonna be parked behind each other,
how could they see each other?
So he tested out these sort of ramp systems
whereby he could levitate, not levitate.
- Oh no, no, no, he couldn't levitate.
That would be an amazing innovation, wasn't it?
When Guardian love your search.
- That's the helicopter driving your thinking of, Dan.
Just on bringing your kids, this is a really clever thing
and how it was advertised.
Lots of cinemas put the playground for the children
'cause the children might not want to sit and watch the film.
They put the playground under the screen.
So as you were watching the film as a parent,
you could just check in and see your kids
directly beneath the cinema screen.
- That's so good.
- Although actually not everyone was happy about this idea
that you could bring your kids
because in 1947, there was a picket outside one
of the drive-ins by a load of babysitters
who said, "Down with drive-ins, more work for babysitters."
And while you drive in movie theaters, babysitters starve.
And so they were outside saying, "Down with drive-ins."
- Wow. - Because they were losing money.
- That's amazing. - It feels like
they've kind of won now.
It feels like babysitters have remained culturally necessary
in a way that drive-ins kind of haven't.
- That's true. - Yeah.
- Have you ever heard of another babysitter robot?
(all laughing)
- Is that unique?
- They're not very heavily unionized, the babysitters.
(all laughing)
- I think if I was a babysitter,
I would be really angry with recipe box services.
Because when I was a babysitter,
what you'd get is free reign of whatever was in the fridge.
But with those recipe boxes,
you only get exactly what you have to cook.
So there's never any spare food.
So it means babysitters are starving in that case.
- All right, James.
As an outfit that does some of the advertised hello fresh,
I don't know if we need to be putting babysitters off it,
driving a wedge between them.
- Well, these babysitters anyway, in near Seattle,
they picked it for a while,
but then they were bought off with a free movie and a hot dog.
- Wow. (all laughing)
- So cheekily bought.
- I think that's what they were going for.
- It could be.
- I don't think driving movies have ever been popular enough
that they've been putting babysitters out of business
on mass.
I think they just wanted a free film.
- You know, we know what the first movie was
to play the drive-in, which is quite cool.
So this was in 1933.
It's a movie called "Wives Beware".
And it is the story of a man who tires of married life
and he feigns memory loss
so that he can then pursue other women.
That's the whole plot.
So when his wife's like,
"Hey, you slept with that lady."
He goes, "Did I?"
That's weird.
And that was the movie.
And the reason they had that movie,
and this became the thing for drive-throughs,
was this was a movie that played in cinemas for one week
and then it went off cinemas.
And drive-throughs specifically were playing films
that were not in competition with the cinema.
It was the movies that were no longer on screen there.
And actually the popularity of it started dwindling
to more B movies and then erotic movies.
- But I think one of the reasons was as well though, Dan,
is that there was quite a union
between all of the different movie-making studios
and then America smashed it and whenever it was,
the '40s or '50s or something like that.
But before then, basically, if you weren't in on it,
you couldn't get the best movies.
And so all of the theaters really wanted to stop the drive-ins
from getting the best movies
'cause they thought that everyone would go to the drive-ins
instead of going to the theaters, I think.
- Yeah, I think they were more forced into the position,
weren't they?
Because no one would actually sell them the popular release.
And like Anna says, no one really cared what was on, right?
- No, they just went there to snog.
- They just went there to snog.
So there was a real big problem.
It wasn't just the baby sisters who didn't like the drive-ins.
It was also the puritanical people
'cause they were worried about nekkers.
So when the first one opened in Camden,
this first one, Hollingshead's one,
that we were talking about, a writer noted,
"Perhaps it will occur readily enough to the reader
"what fun young America could have
"in a coop under the added stimulation
"of a sophisticated romance."
So that was the first one that came
and they were already saying
that people might be snogging in the cars.
- They were very paranoid, weren't they?
- They were quite paranoid, but I mean, it did happen.
- Oh yeah, a lot of snogging went on.
- Yeah, one of the owners said,
"The only thing that can slow us down
"is an ugly rumour going around
"that the drive-in are perfect for nekkers."
- They did have people go around checking, didn't they?
- Checking for necking.
- They had necker checkers, yeah.
So a lot of them employed policemen
or just members of staff who had to go around
and look in people's windows
'cause they got this reputation as being passion pits.
And the reputation was from people called blue noses,
which I'd never heard before,
but it's a term for sort of prudish church types in America.
And various drive-ins would have rules
about what was allowed,
so one owner of a drive-in specified,
if a man puts his arm around a woman, that's okay,
but if she puts her arm back around him
and then they go into a clinch, that's out.
And then they're removed from the premises.
So that's where the line is.
- There was an actual law against it in 1972 in New Jersey,
which would find the operator $100
if any cars remained on the premises
one hour after the end of the show.
And they said that the reason was
because they didn't want any carbon monoxide deaths,
but actually it was just to stop the neckers.
- If you can't get your necking done within an hour, then, you know.
- I genuinely didn't know what the word "necking" meant,
so I Googled it, and apparently it's a short, plain, concave section
between the capital and the shaft
of a classical Doric-Ortuskin column,
but just in case people were hearing.
- You probably need a third person to be in the car with you
to not be caught out for necking, right?
Because it's hard to see what's going on around you
when you're kissing, and generally,
kissing sort of etiquette means you have to have your eyes closed.
So if you had your eyes open while kissing,
A, you risk being a weirdo, but you are safer, I guess.
- If the other person has their eyes open as well,
then they're a weirdo, so you can usually get away with it
because they have their eyes closed.
- You're right, one person has to have their eyes open at all times
looking for blue noses,
and the other person gets on with removing their neckers.
- Well, no, you need both with eyes open because all you're getting
is you're getting that window only of your position.
- You can have a mini Periscope installed in the car,
and then you can just see all the way around you at all times.
- Oh, that's cool. In which case, you only need one eye open.
- I don't want to be a female in the car with you, Andy,
when you say Periscope up.
(laughing)
The second ever drive-in was built by a man called
Wilson Shankwaila.
It was, wow.
He was from Pennsylvania,
and they tried to stop it by taxing him,
and so they wanted to give him a massive amusement tax,
and he tried to avoid it by advertising it as
free movies parking 50 cents.
So it was like, he advertised it as just a parking lot
that just happens to have free movies happening.
- That's what he did.
- Shankwaila is another activity that was banned.
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the Beatles once rejected
a 50 million pound reunion gig because the Warm-Up Act
was going to be a man wrestling a great white shark.
This is according to Ringo Starr,
who revealed this in an interview recently
in the lead-up to his 80th birthday,
and he was talking about how back in 1975,
they were approached by a incredible character
called Bill Sargent, who wanted to reunite them,
and he had 50 million pounds,
which is roughly 200 million pounds in today's money,
and the idea was for them to do this gig,
and according to the Beatles,
the pitch was that it was going to be a Warm-Up Act
of a man underwater fighting a shark.
Now, I think Ringo's muddled this story a bit.
I don't think that great white shark
was going to be the Warm-Up Act.
However, Bill Sargent--
- No, you put the great white shark on last.
- Of course, there's no way the Beatles
can follow a man fighting a shark.
It's going to be such a letdown for the audience.
Even the Beatles reuniting.
- You've got a man with a shark,
and then some people saying, "I am a walrus."
Come on.
- Octopus' garden.
Now, desperately trying to think of--
they would have needed a yellow submarine
in order to get to the stage.
I can play this all night.
- OK, we can wait.
I'll leave for another one.
[laughter]
Also, I'm not sure he had 50 million dollars,
'cause he was like the father of pay-per-view, wasn't he?
So his idea was that he would put it on,
and then people would pay to watch it,
and then the Beatles would get the money from that one day.
- Oh. - I think so.
- I see. - But he said--
there was an interview with him in 1976,
and he said, "I definitely asked them to do this,
and as far as I know, they're considering it."
But he said that the problem was that Paul McCartney
was about to start a US tour,
a 20-day US tour that was going to be huge for McCartney,
and that it was because he didn't want to bring the Beatles
back together quite yet that it didn't happen.
That was quite a sergeant.
James, I don't know if we read the same thing about Bill Sargent.
I was reading People magazine from 1976.
- Same article. - Nice.
I reckon probably about 15 years,
no one else has read that article,
and then four people read it this week.
[laughter]
The People and People magazine are going to be so excited
by the sudden boost.
Yeah. Do you think the office, there was a ping noise
that went on four times?
[laughter]
But it was so funny, 'cause it reported that this guy,
Bill Sargent, had made and lost a million dollars
seven times over, and he'd also had two heart attacks.
And then it said, "As of now, the Beatles seem more likely
to provide Sargent with coronary number three
than fortune number eight."
Yeah, and actually, the guy who bought the Great Work Shark,
I think, might have caused another coronary,
because that was also supposed to happen
as a pay-per-view thing, and they even made the posters
and everything, but Bill Sargent had a heart attack
before they could do it, and so they...
- Oh, yeah. - Yeah.
I actually found the press release that they issued
to companies around the world about this big fight,
and it's remarkable reading.
It's about six pages long.
It's written in such great, so in the most unusual,
deaf-defying event ever to come to the screen,
Bill Sargent has announced that he will bring a life fight
to the death between a single man
and a giant live man-eating shark
to theater, arena, and coliseum screens
by satellite closed-circuit television.
And it was a guy called Wally Gibbons,
who was a shark expert,
and he was gonna be given a spear,
and that is how he was gonna fight the shark.
And the sharks, three of them,
were gonna be brought five weeks early to Samoa,
where the fight was gonna occur,
so they could acclimatize to the water,
and in the 48 hours leading up to the fight,
they were gonna be starved.
So Wally was gonna have to fight a starving shark,
and he said a lot about, in this press release,
about what he thought his odds were of surviving.
He thought if he could shoot the shark with the speargun
first time and get him, that was gonna bring the odds up,
but he needed to shoot it about five times to kill it.
-But what about the two other sharks? -Yeah.
-They were backup sharks. -They're holding the towel
and the bucket and they're holding it.
Can I ask you, Addy, if you're in the water,
what are you keeping in the bucket?
I don't know.
I don't think it would have defied death.
I think it would have really embraced death.
I have a suspicion that old Wally, the absolute Wally,
would have died within maybe five seconds.
-Ah. -Because I don't think...
-Do you think? -Yeah, I think so, because...
I don't know.
I think that he tried this a few times,
because there was someone called Geoffrey Mann,
who wrote a book later in life about Bill Sargent
trying to get him to fight a shark in Samoa as well,
which you've got to assume is the same kind of setup.
And apparently that was cancelled, according to this guy,
cancelled last minute by Jack Cousteau,
who... I don't know what he was doing, being involved in the event,
but a famed oceanographer, Jack Cousteau,
cancelled this shark fight.
But he was going to have a knife,
which I think is going to be quite similar to a spear.
And in the end, I was looking up how you'd kill a shark
if you faced it.
And stabbing it is the worst possible thing you can do,
according to a guy called William Johnson.
It's not the worst. The worst thing is to climb into its mouth.
Yeah.
He actually does say, when he's giving advice, he says,
"Go for the face and gills, because they're quite sensitive."
So, you know, like punching them in the face.
But do try to keep your hands out of its mouth.
That's always the best thing.
But Wally Gibbons was an interesting guy, wasn't he?
Like, there was a 1952 contest between fishermen and spearmen,
which were people who caught fish with spears.
And he caught more fish than all the 37 fishermen
who were in that competition on his own.
Wow.
He was amazing. And just after World War II,
he swam around the Solomon Islands,
picking up, like, unexploded shells,
and then taking them away so that they wouldn't affect people
in the future. Isn't that amazing, Wally?
That's really cool. Yeah, he was incredible.
There's a biography in this press release where they say
that he has killed more sharks in man-to-fish underwater combat
than any other man in Australia and possibly in the world.
I mean, so, yeah, I find it unlikely that anyone from
anywhere else in Australia would have killed any sharks
in man-to-fish fights.
And it should sign, probably, that.
Yeah, he was known as a man-fish.
That's what they called him.
Merman. We've got a name for a mountain fish.
It's a merman.
Wally Gibbons also had the best collection of seashells
in the whole of Australia.
He had the world's rarest shell.
He owned it, the Gloria Maris,
which is also known as the Glory of the Seacone.
And that shell used to be so rare
that there was once a collector who bought one in an auction
only to immediately destroy it so that he had the only one
because he found this other one that was...
He didn't want two in the world to exist,
so he bought one in the auction when it came up
and he destroyed it, so he had the only one.
That's pretty sick.
Supposedly, that was in 1792.
But then there was only a few of them in the world.
Wally Gibbons had one of them.
And when proper scuba diving got invented, they found...
Oh, yeah, they're just down there.
They were just a bit lower than we could normally go.
So people, you can collect them quite easily now.
You could buy them for not too much.
I think that would be a disappointing
if the shark fight couldn't go ahead.
But he said, "But don't worry, Wally Gibbons
"will be showing you his seashell collection."
Because I was thinking, Anna said that he would die after five minutes.
If you're the Beatles and you're thinking,
"Okay, we're going on in an hour after the fight."
And then after five minutes, they're like,
"Well, sorry, the guy just got eaten,
"so you're going to have to go on early."
I'd be pretty pissed off.
Also, there's a bit of a weird vibe in the audience right now.
(LAUGHTER)
They probably had a back-up, warmer-backed,
which was a therapist to come out on stage
to help everyone deal with the massacre they'd just seen.
Can I just say one weird, interesting thing about Bill Sargent,
the guy who Dan mentioned at the start,
who was organising the shark fights.
So he was an inventor. He invented tons of stuff.
He had, I think, over 400 patents, so gadget patents.
And one thing that I think he invented
is something that we think of as new, which is televised theatre.
So, you know, now you can go and see the National Theatre Live
at your local cinema,
or you could before the theatre stopped happening.
And he invented the precursor to this called
"Electronovision" in the 1960s.
And so, basically, it involved him going in and videotaping plays
and then broadcasting them in cinemas.
And he made loads of money out of it.
And the first one he did was a tape of Richard Burton in Hamlet in 1964.
And he filmed three separate productions,
then edited them together to get the best best of.
Highlights showed in 1,000 cinemas and made him millions of dollars.
Amazing.
Bill Sargent's first job was a radio repairman,
which he had at the age of six.
- Wow. - So he started work at the age of six.
In fairness, it was in the family workshop,
which was attached to his family home.
Unfortunately, a year later, he burnt them both down by accident.
And then later on, when he got a load of money for his movies,
he set up an electronics laboratory in Missouri.
But then he burned that down as well.
So he had kind of had a habit of burning down electronic shops.
That time, when he burned down the second one, James,
apparently it was because he put down, just not really thinking,
he put down a welding torch in the wrong place.
He put it onto a drum of paint thinner or thinner.
So kind of the winch is obviously highly flammable.
According, I guess, to him,
because I don't think there were many other people around,
he was blown 170 feet into the air.
- What's 170 feet? - No.
- That's impossible. - Someone's flying over to the drive-in fare
to go, "What the fuck was that?"
(LAUGHTER)
- 170 feet. - Yep, that's what he says.
Well...
I love him. Love this man so much.
So this thing of a man fighting a shark
was basically an insane, weird, warm-up act.
And so I looked into a few other weird acts,
like kind of vaudeville acts from, you know, the last century.
So have you heard of Haji Ali,
who was also known as the Egyptian enigma?
- Oh? - He was amazing.
OK, so he was a vaudeville performer.
His act was to swallow kerosene,
then he would swallow some water, OK?
Then he would regurgitate the kerosene
and set it on fire, as he did so.
But then he would regurgitate the water to put out the fire
that he had lit from the kerosene.
- So cool. - I think he was also known as the human volcano.
Or something like that.
And then there's just one line about him saying
he would also regurgitate live goldfish and nuts.
(LAUGHTER)
The nuts was actually more impressive than it sounds, wasn't it,
with Haji Ali, because he...
One of his tricks was being able to regurgitate stuff
in the order specified by the audience.
So he'd swallow a bunch of objects and then be like,
"All right, bring up the goldfish now. OK, bring up your braces."
And so he'd swallow, for instance, 50 hazelnuts
and one almond.
And he'd start regurgitating them one by one.
And when an audience member said, "Bring up the almond now, mate,"
he'd call the almond up.
- And within. - It's amazing.
- Apparently. - Oh, my God.
I genuinely think if you gave me a bowl of nuts
and said, "Which one of those is an almond?"
I would struggle.
(LAUGHTER)
Maybe that's what he was relying on.
He just told the audience it was an almond.
(LAUGHTER)
I can say one more Borderville thing related to animals.
And this was an amazing act,
which was a group of women called the Barrison Sisters.
And it seems like their entire act
was to do a little bit of a sexy dance
that gets more and more sexy.
And all the way through, they would ask the audience,
"Would you like to see my pussy?"
And then when eventually, the audience said, "Yes,"
they would lift their skirts and they would all have a cat in their knickers.
(LAUGHTER)
And that was absolutely massive.
They were huge.
They were so famous, these people.
They played Berlin for eight months with this act.
(LAUGHTER)
- They played a... - But is it like the mousetrap, James?
Are they like, "Please don't tell anyone the spoiler when you leave?"
It must be, right? It must be that.
They must have been exactly like that.
And there was a French nobleman who committed suicide
because he loved one of them so much.
And they were so shocking that after the eight months in Berlin,
they were banned from ever re-entering Germany.
I love the fact that they waited eight months to ban them.
It's like, "Okay, now that everyone in Germany
"has had a chance to see you, now you're banned."
Because now that's not appropriate.
The censors went countless times, thousands of times.
Yeah, we're just trying to assess whether or not
it really is offensive enough to ban.
Just like a few more months of seeing them, to be sure.
- Were the cats alive? - Yeah, they were alive.
They were in, like, a little pouch over their crutches.
So the cats had to sit there in between their legs for the full act.
- They must have been sedated. - Yeah.
I don't know whether they regurgitated them somehow or what,
but they were definitely there.
And there was an article about them,
and one guy in New York said,
"It was the most audacious piece of devilry and abandonment
"I ever saw offered to a New York public."
Wow.
I really thought you were going to say that he committed suicide
because he was so disappointed when they lifted up their skirts
at the end, and he didn't see their vaginas.
Yeah.
Just ask only a cat.
It's all been for nothing.
OK, it's time for fact number three, and that is Anna.
My fact this week is that in 1919,
it was ruled that women would be allowed to swim competitively
without wearing stockings on the one condition
that they quickly put on a robe as soon as they got out of the water.
And this was specifically in America.
And I think these are nylon stockings,
because there weren't been any nylon in 1919, would they?
So was it wool or what?
I think they were wool.
I think quite a lot of people had to wear woolen stuff in the water.
That's not going to be conducive to a quick swim, is it?
It's like carrying a sheep while you're swimming.
Yeah.
It's like that, did you guys all do that swimming survival test
when you were younger, where you had to wear pyjamas in the water?
It was like every time a woman swam in the water,
it was like having to do that survival test.
In every Olympics, they had to pick up a brick
from the bottom of the pool, didn't they?
Yeah.
So this was in America, and it was the Amateur Athletics Union,
which had only recently allowed women to take part
in competitive swimming events anyway.
But it was very controversial what women would wear in the water,
and they essentially had to be covered from neck to toe fully.
And this irritated the women,
because they realised that this would put them at a massive disadvantage
in the Olympics, for instance,
when they were competing against other countries like Australia,
who were a bit looser with their regulations,
and they would be weighed down by their massive cotton waterlogs
and head-to-toe outfits while the Aussies were smashing them.
So there was sort of a campaign.
There was this amazing woman called Charlotte Epstein,
who was a court stenographer, actually,
and she'd formed the Women's Swimming Association in 1917.
And she campaigned to have the stocking requirement removed.
And eventually she did this stunt,
where she invited some of the best women in the country,
female swimmers in the country,
to come to a beach in California
and strip down to ordinary swimsuits without stockings.
And they were all arrested.
And she invited the tabloids to see them all be arrested.
And this kind of created this atmosphere of how ridiculous is this?
Women are just being arrested for wearing swimming costumes.
Come on, guys, sort your shit out.
And so they relaxed the rules.
But you did have to very quickly put on a robe as soon as you emerged.
Yeah, the rules were pretty strict, weren't they, back in the day?
Like, in 1921, in New York,
everyone had to wear a two-piece swimming suit, everyone.
And there was a specific law that made it illegal
for any bold men to stare at women.
Yeah, I saw that. What does that mean?
I couldn't find...
I think that was one person on the beach,
like the person who was monitoring that beach,
who thought that bold men were sort of equated with perverts.
And he said, "I'm going to stop bold men from staring at women."
It's so strange.
Maybe there was a specific bold man that they were worried about,
like, Stairy Steve, and they sort of said,
"Well, we can't say Stairy Steve is found from the beach,
"but we will say this."
Yeah, well, weren't hats very popular back then?
So maybe bold means a hatless,
because maybe they were taking their hat down to hide a protrusion below.
Is that how, you know, how they always say in the olden days,
whenever you met a lady, you had to lift your hat?
It wasn't to hide your protrusion, Dan.
The taller the hat, the bigger the brag.
You remember Mr. Darcy always had a very tall top hat.
But that's how you catch them, is that you just say,
"Can you show me your hands, please?"
And if the hat stays where it is on their lap,
then you know that there's a protrusion situation.
In the Olympics, the first time that women swam in the Olympics,
I think, was in 1912.
And the British team had to wear a bra and knickers
while they swam, as well as their swimsuit.
And that's because they had this amazingly awesome silk swimsuit
that would help them to swim really fast.
But it was completely see-through when it got wet.
And so, I mean, it was amazing.
It was so thin, the silk,
that you could take the whole thing and pass it through a wedding ring.
That's how thin the material was.
But it did have that one problem that it was see-through,
so you had to wear underwear as well.
And was it a Superman situation where it's on top of the outfit?
I've seen the pictures and they were on the inside,
but definitely they should have gone the outside, shouldn't they?
Yeah.
I find it really bizarre that women weren't encouraged to swim
until about the 19th century.
So this only really became a situation then or late on then,
because before that, if you were a woman, you just didn't swim.
I thought there's very little evidence of women swimming
before the 17th century.
There is some.
Yeah, I found the description of a standard ladies' bathing costume
in 1687 by someone called Celia Fiennes,
who said it was made of fine yellow canvas,
which made it that when you went in the water,
it filled up with water,
so no one could see the shape of your body.
Crafty.
I'm clever, like a Mr. Blobby costume.
A Mr. Blobby, yeah, because you can never tell how sexy
the person playing Mr. Blobby is, can't you?
They don't need to be sexy on the inside
if they're wearing a Mr. Blobby costume, I'm theirs.
And in the 18th century in the UK, they made laws.
Every town could make its own laws about what you would wear
when you were swimming.
So in the city of Bath,
they made it illegal for men to swim without a waistcoat.
No.
Is that with, would men have to have the sort of the top as well,
or is this bare chest with a waistcoat on?
I think the waistcoat just referred to anything
that would cover your chest, really.
It wasn't like a proper top hat and tails kind of thing.
Yeah.
Did you guys come across Donald Clark in your research?
He was an early, he was very much fighting the tide of history.
He was an opponent to mixed swimming.
He was a counsellor in Tonbridge,
and he said that by making girls look like wet Scotch terriers,
mixed bathing stops more marriages than any other cause
and much unrest in the country
due to the barbarous licence of women's dress.
So he was basically saying women look like such mingers
when they've been in the water that no one will want to marry them.
And he was then, so this is in a sort of furious letter
to the papers or something,
he was then given a job by the Daily Mail
to go around beaches looking for outrageous things
to be angry about.
Some things haven't changed.
That's amazing.
Wow.
That's so good,
because I think the Daily Mail does employ a lot of people
like that still today, doesn't it?
Literally just find something to get angry about.
We need to fill our vages.
Anything.
I was reading about a swimming hero called Gertrude Eddell,
so she was the first woman to swim the English Channel in 1925.
And she was trained by this guy called Jabez Wolff,
who was a bizarre character himself.
I don't know why she chose him to train her,
because he'd tried and failed to swim the Channel 22 times previously.
And despite, apparently, he employed a bagpiper for encouragement,
and that didn't help.
But anyway, she tried and...
If the bagpipers are behind you,
then that will encourage you to swim forward.
You're trying to get as far away from Scotland as you can.
So her first attempt, he, Jabez,
her trainer pulled her out of the water halfway through,
saying that it looked like she was drowning.
And she said she wasn't drowning at all.
She'd just been having a rest face down in the water.
Eventually she did it.
She was the sixth person ever to swim the Channel,
and she was the fastest ever of men and women.
She did it in 14 and a half hours.
So she beat the previous person by two hours.
Did front crawl all the way.
And the first thing, she did it from France to England.
And the first person to meet her on the beach in Kent
when she arrived was an immigration officer
who demanded to see her passport.
Amazing.
He was actually working for the Daily Mail, wasn't he, at the time?
Do you know what she was fed on the way?
I find this so weird.
What she got fed, chicken legs.
I think...
Because if they touched you in the water,
then that sort of, you're out.
Because you've been kind of supported by him.
But her support boat was apparently full of chicken legs,
which, okay, throws someone a chicken leg in the water.
Oranges and chicken soup to sustain her as she went.
And I have no idea how she was fed the soup.
Right. What must happen, right, is,
I don't want to take anything away from her swim,
but they give her a straw to suck the soup.
And actually she's biting onto the straw
while it's attached to the boat,
and she's used it to pull her along.
So she's water skiing there basically.
Basically doing that.
This is a great and niche conspiracy theory
that needs to see more at.
One person who tried to swim the channel before Gertrude
was an Australian called Annette Kellerman,
who was probably the most famous swimmer in the world.
She was the first woman to publicly wear a one-piece swimming costume.
She was arrested on the beach.
She was one of these people who was arrested
for public indecency for wearing like a two-sexier swimming costume.
But it wasn't really very effective,
and she ended up releasing her own line of bathing costumes
and became massively rich because people wanted to look like her
because she was so famous.
She was paid by the Melbourne exhibition hall to swim in,
and it's aquarium.
So people would come and watch her swim.
It was like you were saying about the Bordeville earlier,
and it was like you would just go to watch her swim.
She was like a swimming costume hero, wasn't she?
She was the person who brought us the swimming costume, Annette Kellerman.
We've been pitching about the Daily Mail,
so for some balance, here's some perspective on the Daily Mirror.
She came between Australia and America.
She came to the UK to do some swimming,
and she broke a record for swimming from Dober to Margate,
and she caused this huge stir, and it was all great.
And the Daily Mirror paid her to swim along that coast
every single day for two months.
And they said to her, she was like, every day for two months?
Oh, God. I mean, that sounds like hell.
And they said it's a huge thing for women.
It's going to go down as a great, successful, women kind.
And what they actually meant was,
there's a lady from Australia in a swimsuit,
which we've never seen before here,
and they obviously invited lots of crowds every day
to come and watch her in her swimsuit
and made loads of money selling their papers.
And it was sort of the first page three type things
were these pictures of Annette Kellerman
and people like her in swimsuits.
I've read about her show.
She was called The Diving Venus,
and the show ran on Broadway for four years.
And then she went to Hollywood and she starred
in a film called Daughter of the Gods.
She did loads of films, but this was in 1916.
And the film used 20,000 extras.
It cost a million dollars to make,
which was pretty unusual at the time.
And there were scenes of her swimming nude in it,
I think from quite a distance,
but this led to the formal banning of,
as they were called, nude scenes in films.
And so, yeah, it's thanks to her.
Yeah, she did all her own stunts in that movie,
including a 20-meter dive into the ocean
with her hands and feet tied together
and also being thrown into a pool with six crocodiles.
Wow, it really, it sounds like a promoter Bill Sargent.
He really would have made a lot of money out of that woman.
When she was on Broadway making all her money,
she made $1,250 a week on Broadway.
And when she was doing it, there was a Harvard professor
who said she was a perfect woman
after comparing her measurements to the Venus de Milo.
Now, the Venus de Milo doesn't have any arms.
No.
Useful in swimming, particularly.
OK, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is Andy.
My fact is that the film of Dr. Dolittle
was delayed for days after the giraffe being used
accidentally stepped on its own penis.
So...
How long is a giraffe's penis?
Is it, like, a fifth leg?
Well, is it that before or after you've trodden on it?
That's the question.
They have really long legs.
I just can't work out the mechanics of this, Andy, at all.
It doesn't...
Well, they, I mean, they're like folding deck chairs.
You know, it's very easy to get something
caught in a folding deck chair,
and I think that's the same principle.
You need to stop going on those nudist holidays, Andy.
I can't take many more of those injuries.
I'll tell you that much.
So, to be completely clear,
this is the 1967 "Dr. Dolittle" with Rex Harrison,
not the 2021 with Robert Downey Jr.,
where pretty much all the animals are CGI,
and nobody stepped on anybody's penises.
And this comes from a great book called
"Scenes from a Revolution, the Birth of the New Hollywood,"
which is kind of an in-depth look at five films in particular.
It's by Mark Harris, and one of those films is "Dr. Dolittle,"
and there was a guy working on it called Herbert Ross,
who was the choreographer,
and he wrote to a colleague saying,
"We're postponed for three days, the giraffe stepped on his cock."
And so, it stepped on his cock, though?
Are we misreading that?
Yeah, stepped on Rex Harrison.
Yeah, so that's that.
It was pretty chaotic, wasn't it, that film?
Sounds amazing.
Apparently, it was revealed after it was one giraffe died,
and I don't think we know how, still,
but one of the people who worked on it said one giraffe died.
But, I mean, the general management of animals
sounds like hell.
It had lots of different filming locations,
so it was partly filmed in LA and then in the Caribbean and in the UK.
And because of quarantine laws,
they had to hire separate sets of identical animals
for each place to play the same characters.
And then also, the animals grow so fast
that they had to keep finding replacements, like doppelgangers.
So, I think there was a pig called "Gubgub" in the film,
which had 40 different piglets play at various times.
I mean, it does seem questionable, doesn't it?
A lot of the sort of stuff they did to the animals,
there was a squirrel that they had to sedate
during a scene that they needed him for.
By the sedation method they used was a fountain pen
where they dripped a gin through it to just get it drunk.
But it ended up losing consciousness,
because it was so drunk that they couldn't properly get the scene done.
That doesn't seem very ethical in terms of...
I think that's absolutely fine.
Elizabeth Taylor used to request that kind of thing
before she'd go over it at the camera.
There's a great story where in one scene
that Rex Harrison was doing, he kept...
This is the story that he kept stopping the scene
and the director's going, "What are you doing?"
And he goes, "Well, you keep calling cut."
He's going, "I'm not calling cut, you're definitely calling cut."
And they worked out that it was the parrot that was in the scene
that's going to mimic the word "cut."
No way.
Yeah, and Rex was getting confused.
So, they built a set for the house of Dr. Doolittle.
Whose whole stake is that he can talk to the animals.
So, he lives with a load of animals.
But the whole house, the set had to be built on a slant
because obviously the animals are pooing everywhere
and peeing everywhere.
So, they had lots of people in the crew
just standing around with brooms waiting for when that happened.
All the furniture had to be either plastic or painted
so that it could be hosed down at the end of each day
filming in this set house.
They had to have double the sets
because frequently animals would just kick a hole
in the walls or the furniture.
The trainers got hepatitis from being bitten.
I read one amazing sentence in the link you sent, Andy,
which is, "Unfathomably, the ducks in the pond
"appeared to forget how to swim and started to sink."
You know you're having a bad time.
You think you'd be able to rely on the ducks
to be able to swim.
So funny.
But apparently what had happened was
it was the wrong time of year,
so they'd lost all their waterproof sheen on their feathers.
And at that time of year,
ducks don't normally swim or something.
And so they all just started sinking.
Yeah, I found that amazing.
I didn't know that.
Didn't know that ever happened.
Incredible.
Has anyone seen the movie?
Years ago as a kid, yeah.
Really? Was that any good?
Yeah, I mean as a kid it was one of those
Sunday afternoon movies.
And I do remember loving it,
but I've read a lot of things
that suggest that I'm completely wrong about that.
It has a very low rating.
It got the best-pitched Oscar nomination,
but it's the lowest-rated score on Rotten Tomatoes
ever to get a nomination.
Ooh, what's it rocking on Rotten?
32%.
Rex Harrison, who was the star of it,
was so horrible to everyone
that he was nicknamed Tyrannosaurus Rex,
which is very clever when you think
because it's a film about animals that are talking.
Yes.
He had a good reputation for behaving like that
quite frequently, didn't he, Rex Harrison?
He was grumpy bastard.
Or a character,
depending on which way you want to frame it.
But I should say,
so I'm a huge My Fair Lady fan
and a big Rex Harrison fan in that.
And there's a guy called Will Harrison,
who's his grandson, who listens to the podcast.
So we have inside Rex Harrison info,
apparently on,
if you look at the film poster of Cleopatra,
who was supposed to just have Richard Burton
and Elizabeth Taylor on it as Anthony and Cleopatra.
OK.
But Rex was like, I'm the big star here, guys.
What the hell are you doing?
Get me on the poster.
And so you see just behind them,
Juliet Caesar, Rex Harrison staring
really creepily down at this loving couple.
And he was always doing stuff like that.
There's one particularly famous anecdote
which is that he'd performed in the theater
and there was an autograph hunter waiting outside.
She had her book ready for him to sign.
He came out, she asked for the autograph
and he said, "Sod off."
And what she did was,
she rolled up the program,
she wanted him to sign and she hit him with it.
And the co-star of the play, Stanley Holloway,
later said that it was a rare but welcome case
of the fan hitting the shit.
That's how they viewed him.
You know Christopher Plummer, the actor?
Yes.
He has a sound of music and stuff, I guess.
He was paid $300,000 not to be in "Doctor Do Little."
Really?
Which is such an epic fail by the accountants, I think.
So basically, Harrison temporarily quit the project.
He decided he wasn't completely up for it.
And then so they said,
"Well, who do we get? We need some Hollywood giant."
So they got Christopher Plummer,
signed him up for $300,000.
And then Harrison said,
"Oh, fine, I will do the film then."
So Plummer never filmed a scene,
never said a line of the dialogue,
but still got paid his full fee for it.
It's the dream job.
It was originally written by a woman called Helen Winston.
And they rewrote it.
They just completely rewrote the thing.
Apart from, they used loads of her stuff,
but then didn't tell her she was going to use it.
And so she sued them and she got
3.2 million out of them for that.
Whoa!
And it lost 9 million in the box office.
So a third of that was just due to stealing this woman's work.
So actually, the two people in it
who had their work stolen from them,
Christopher Plummer and this lady,
sounds like they were the real winners here.
So Dr. Dolittle is incredibly loosely based
on a series of stories written by Hugh Lofting
in the 1920s and during the First World War.
And they bear no resemblance.
I don't think the plots,
but any resemblance to the stories he originally wrote,
but they are about a doctor who talks to animals.
And it's quite a sweet story.
So I hadn't realised he wrote them
while he was fighting in the trenches in World War I,
and he was writing letters back to his children.
And he understandably thought,
"I'm not sure I want to tell the kids
about my trenches-based experience."
And so instead, he wrote these brilliant stories
about a guy who talks to animals.
He was a real crusader for animal rights in lots of ways.
And he once beat up three men,
including one who had a knife,
because they were trying to tame some wild horses.
And they were, I think,
not being especially pleasant to the horses.
So, yeah.
Yeah, he was very strong on sympathising with animals.
He was shocked by how horses were treated.
They did have a very bad time in the First World War.
Yeah, it was the way that he saw horses being treated.
And they needed to be looked after by vets.
But he was like,
"Well, they can't really tell us what's wrong with them
because they're horses."
And that was kind of what gave him the idea
of writing "Doctor Do Little."
But we should say that if you have read "Doctor Do Little"
in the last 20 or 30 years,
you're probably reading a massively sanitised version of it,
because the original is extremely racist.
So, in 1968, there was a librarian called Isabelle Sewell,
who wrote an essay about a few different books,
but specifically about "Doctor Do Little,"
who described you lofting as a white, racist, and chauvinist,
guilty of almost every prejudice known to modern white, western man.
And that was in the '60s.
So, yeah, exactly.
And so, basically, from then on,
he just got pretty much cancelled,
and really all his books went out-print for quite a long time
until they got rewritten with a lot of the racist bits taken out.
Yeah, with no resemblance to the originals, basically.
But on the other hand, loved horses.
Yeah, I mean, anti-war and pro-animal, for sure.
Yeah, yeah.
So, I've been looking a bit into talking to animals,
and people are doing serious work on this right now,
and it's really cool.
So, there is a new device,
which is trying to train basically Lassie technology.
So, the idea is that dogs will have a vest,
and if the person needs help,
they can pull a tab to communicate a message, okay?
So, it might be someone's fallen down a well,
but that's probably not going to be it,
because it's only one message on the tab that they can pull.
So, for example, lots of children with autism
find it very helpful and calming to have a dog,
and if they are panicking or upset,
it might be possible to train the dog
to pull the tab on its little vest,
because it can spot the size that its owner is upset,
and then that will read out the dog saying,
"Could you please pet me now?"
And then therefore, the child will pet the dog,
and we'll calm down and that will help.
So, they're trying to see if they can train dogs
to have several different messages,
or if they can train it.
So, either could you pet me now,
or someone's fallen down a well, or whatever it might be.
It's just those two they've coded in on the internet.
Wait, so the dog senses that the child is anxious,
and so then pulls the tab that says, "Can you pet me?"
So, the child signals they're anxious without realizing it,
and then the dog does something to make the child calm down.
Yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, well, you might be anxious,
because the dog's just told you that someone's fallen down a well.
I really wish I hadn't mentioned this well thing.
Complete red herring.
Do you know that...
I was going to do this as a fact in a future week,
but do you know that the traditional way of preparing melon
in France was to put it down a well for four hours?
Melon?
A melon, yeah.
Because before...
What, and it came up perfectly sliced, I'm sure.
Who lived down that well?
A small child who fell there many years ago.
No, they are...
Basically, you wanted your melon to be nice and cold, right?
And they had no refrigeration, but they did have a well,
which was cold at the bottom.
So, they used to traditionally, in France,
they would put their melon in the well a few hours before,
and then bring it up, and it's nice and cold.
So, the dog would, in this case, have a third tab,
which says, "Your melon is ready, sir."
That was in an article written by B Wilson that I read the other day,
which is pretty amazing.
Artificial intelligence might help us to talk to animals,
or to understand what they're thinking.
There is a scientist called Dr. Krista McLennan,
who is working on a way of using AI to tell you what sheep are thinking.
And apparently, it's really hard for farmers to tell what a sheep is thinking,
just by looking at its face.
Because they don't have much expression on their faces.
You often see farmers kneeling down,
just staring deep into a sheep's eyes, don't you?
Going, "Why can't I tell?"
I mean, I believe this.
So, I was reading this article about this AI algorithm
that tells you whether a sheep's happy or not happy.
And there's part of it.
On NBC, they had a quiz where they would show you pictures of sheep,
and you had to guess whether they were happy or sad.
I only got one out of four, and that was a lucky guess,
because I just had three sad sheep in a row,
and I thought the fourth one must be a happy.
That's games for a show.
I did that same quiz.
I got three.
So, I'm a sheep whisperer, basically.
I didn't. It's quite specific, isn't it, though?
It is tricky.
So, the signs of pain or emotional suffering in a sheep are
narrow eyes, tight cheeks.
Oh, hold on. I don't know if I really want to do the test.
Yeah.
Okay.
Don't tell us your facts.
Anna, tell me the symptoms before you do the test,
is what the test is based on.
That's the thing.
They say if it has a nostril shape like a V rather than a U,
then it's either happy or sad.
Even though it told me that, I couldn't do it.
Although, I think handy, because there were only four,
and it was a 50/50 choice each time, then one out of four
and three out of four is within the standard deviation
of what you would expect.
Okay. All I'm hearing is that I won.
I'm going to be the sheep farmer.
Okay. That's it. That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @shrieberland, Andy.
@andrewhunterm.
James.
@jamesharkin.
And Anna.
You can email podcast@qi.com.
Yep. Or you can go to our group account,
which is @nosuchthing, or there's our website,
nosuchthingasafish.com.
We've got all of our previous episodes up there,
as well as links to bits of merchandise.
That's it, guys.
Thanks again for listening to us during these crazy times.
We hope you are well and safe,
and we will be back again with another episode.
Next week, we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)