[MUSIC]
Hey Clubfish members, welcome to your secret bonus bit of content.
We've got a compilation for you today.
This is the best of the outtakes of things that didn't make it to the main show.
It features me, James, Andy, and Anna.
But you've got some bonus voices joining us this week.
We've got Reese Darby, the brilliant Reese, and of course, the excellent Miles Jupp.
You will have heard them on recent episodes.
And this is all the stuff that didn't quite fit into the main episodes.
Oh and quickly before we get into it, just a quick thank you to everyone who came to the Crosswise festival.
We had such a fun gig.
There was an awesome ending to it where we did a quiz with members from the audience.
It was just so much fun.
So thank you everyone who came.
There's some people traveled all the way from America to come see the show.
Hope you enjoyed it.
And if anyone else wants to come and see us do another live show,
we're returning to the London Podcast Festival.
We're going to be there on the 5th and 6th of September.
We've got a couple of great guests lined up to join us on stage.
Go to know such thing as a fish.com.
You'll find the links there.
Come and see us live.
And I believe that there's going to be online streaming as well.
So if you are overseas and you want to watch it,
do check it out and buy your tickets to watch it online as it happens live.
Last thing to mention is if you miss last week's drop us a line,
just to let you know that the price of club fish is going up by 1 pound.
So it is going to be 3 pounds 99 going forward.
Hope that's okay with you all.
We promise that we're going to continue to put out really fun formats.
So don't go anywhere.
And don't go anywhere right now because here we go.
It's the compilation.
The four fishers recent miles on with the outtakes.
- There's a world one connection,
as well as a world two connection in ugly.
Which is really cool actually.
So in world one, there was an understandable fear that the Germans
were going to invade via Essex.
And a plan was drawn up to evacuate the whole of Essex to Oxfordshire.
1.4 million people.
I don't think they told the people of Oxfordshire.
- Yeah, you were, what do you hear? - You didn't mention it.
There's going to be some stuff happening.
Just don't worry about it.
Just keep your door shut.
But they all got these, you know, things from the council saying
this is what to do.
- Councils have really diminished over there.
They're like now they sometimes can't collect glass.
Well, there's the undefonding, isn't it? We don't get the war anymore.
And the information said, when ugly church bells ring incessantly,
that's your sign, get out, goes to Oxfordshire.
And they also, and they were told destroy all alcohol
because if the Germans arrive and they're invading
and they get drunk, that's even worse than a sober invading Nazi.
Which is quite weird.
- Really, that is weird because didn't,
wasn't the battle of fishguard when the French came over?
In the 18th century, the last time Britain was invaded at all.
They arrived, they all got drunk and couldn't do anything.
- Well, I think it's really on the fence.
Yes, will alcohol make the invaders worse or better?
And maybe it depends on whether they're French or German.
- Oh, yeah, maybe.
But anyway, it's really cool because everyone was given
these evacuation routes.
And it meant you had to take all the back roads
because the army would be using the main roads.
So they had these maps and there were arrows all over Essex
painted on walls and trees and lamp posts
and big white arrows showing people the way.
And the only remnant that remains now is in Ugly.
There's a wall which just has now only the little plaque left saying
this is where the big white arrow was saying, "Get out of door."
Imagine arriving as a Nazi going, "Where is everyone?"
And then seeing giant arrows pointing at you towards
where you needed to go.
- We haven't got this through, Winston.
Protesters have some good gear.
Like I was looking at Stanstead protests.
So there was a protest in Stanstead a few years ago
over a bunch of migrants who were being sent away
and that one of those taken in the dead of night
stuck on a charter plane sent back to the country
from which they'd come from a while ago.
Big protest about that.
But the way they did it was they formed a circle around the plane.
So they got bought cutters.
They got into Stanstead Airport.
They formed a circle around the plane
and they locked themselves in this circle
by putting their arms in pipes filled with expanding foam
and attaching their arms to each other.
So I put my arm in one end of the pipe
and he puts his arm in the other.
Where you get it, what does it expand?
- It's almost like you know those Chinese finger traps
that you put your fingers in,
but like a super big version of that.
- Exactly, it's a giant one of those.
- What if I need a piss?
- Well, you can't, you just have to go loose.
You can't hold your willy.
- So sorry, you're in a big circle with your arms in the pipes.
Or our fingers touching.
- If you want to be happy.
- Possibly not.
- I don't think they, I think you don't want them touching
because you could have a wider circumference
if you're not touching.
- What do you mean?
- Oh yeah, true.
- But what if I feel lonely or scared?
- No, I do want to be holding hands with someone.
- They're the sacrifices you make to save these things.
- Someone else can't even help me have a piss
because they've got their arms in the kitchen.
- Well, there's got to be, I've got it.
There's got to be an external agent
who's free to go around helping people have a piss.
- There was one piss helper, yes.
- What do we need to do then is arrest the piss assistant
and then the whole protest falls apart.
- Yeah, they all wet themselves and it's over.
- And that's how all protests tend.
- I need the toilet, let's go.
I've wet myself, we're done for the day.
- How did it end then?
How did they actually un-tube them?
- They're still there.
- I've claimed stuck in the middle.
They tried to prosecute them on.
Some, actually, anti-terrorism charges
before our judge a couple of years ago.
So that's fucking ridiculous.
These guys aren't terrorists.
But they were extracted from the pipes first.
I don't think anyone's still walking around with the pipes.
- Catch their arms.
- If you are writing, oh, you can't, probably.
- If your piss helper is free,
they ask if they can drop us a line.
- Is a stanza to Gatwick that's won the award for best toilet
like multiple years?
- I can't be stanced at.
- No?
- Unless they're talking about the entire app policy
for the toilet.
- Is it, can I ask that?
Is it an individual cubicle or is it a design of toilet?
- No, no, it's the whole toilet.
It's the cleanliness.
It's in the window as you go down into the toilets.
You know, you walked in and go, wow.
- Wait, there's a window as you go down to the toilet.
- Yeah, it's a little cabinet where they keep it.
- It's a viewing, does your toilet have a viewing though?
- It should.
- Can I give you a music recommendation related to this fact?
- Yes, please.
- It's my favorite song I found recently.
So in 1978, for sure, some listeners remember,
there was the big frequency change
where all of the radio stations in the UK,
all the big BBC ones,
hops to a different frequency
because of e-regulations.
And no one had the internet then.
So it was like, how are they going to know
that their station is at a different frequency,
especially given that.
I believe Radio 3 hopped the frequency
that used to be Radio 1.
So you'd tune in hoping for Tony Blackburn
and you'd get, in certain name,
with famous Radio 3 presenter in the 1970s.
- I honestly thought the Tony Blackburn
was currently on Radio 3 with you.
- He might be, he might be.
And the only reason I know it's him is because
one of the things they did to tell people was
Tony Blackburn stayed at Radio 3 for the day to tell people
a bit like if you move house,
you stay at the house that you've just moved out of.
So when your mates come around, you can go,
"I don't live here anymore."
So if you tuned in, he'd be like,
"Hello, it's me, Tony.
I'm not here anymore, though."
- That's not confusing at all.
- Go to the stage.
- Well, they get someone else to say,
Tony doesn't live here anymore.
- If you want him, he's on Radio 1.
- It's just a dedicated guy.
- That's great, that's so good.
- It was also this incredible song
by the King Singers, who are very famous
at the time, Accapella Group from King's College Cambridge.
They released a single to help people remember
all the new frequencies.
And you've got to look at that.
It's beautiful.
It starts, just I'll just give you the first line.
A new international agreement comes into effect.
And many of the frequencies used for the BBC
will be changed at a time.
I think it was unlike that.
- Is that the tune, or are you just riff that?
- It's a bit like that.
It's like, Accapella Church music.
- Wow.
- But it told everyone what frequencies to go to.
- I reckon, because it said at a time,
that was a really weird way of saying it.
But the frequency for Radio 1 was 97 to 99.
So was it that it was a rhyme if that was it?
- They were actually different frequencies at the time.
And so it's, and there wasn't that much rhyming in this.
I must say much like a lot of songs.
- The whole point of putting things in a song
to help you remember, is it make them rhyme?
- There's no way it makes it easier whatsoever.
It's just a string of numbers,
somewhere much require boys.
- There were two.
In fact, the world's only two female fighter pilot aces,
which I think to be an ace,
you sort of had to shoot down five planes
or more vaguely varied.
But one of them was this woman called Lillia Litviak,
who was in one of the other regiments
that were flying for the Soviets in the Second World War.
And there was just an account which she recounted
and people who were in the same regiment as her recounted,
which sounds really fun,
where she was in this dogfight with a German called Irvenmeier.
And he'd shot down 12 planes before.
So he was well up there in ace territory.
And she defeated him really resoundingly.
And then it sounds like there's one of those nice moments
where he came right down, he was okay.
But he was like, who the hell defeats me?
Introduce me to the man who just bested me.
And so they trotted him up.
Yeah, did you read about this?
- No, I'm just excited.
- Yeah, go on.
- So he got shot down, but he landed okay or?
- He landed okay in that way.
People seem to sometimes survive.
And demanded to be taken to the man who shot him down.
- Yeah, I was so presumptuous.
- I know.
- I just think you don't automatically get to meet the person
who shot you down.
- That's not my voice for you.
- You've got to follow themselves.
- Yeah, he was pissed off.
He was introduced to a woman, he said,
"Bugger off, guys, come on.
Where's the real guy?
Stop taking a piss."
- Very funny, okay, yeah.
That happened to Mary Ellis,
who was another of the 88 girls.
She landed a Wellington bomber,
which was a black and huge plane at the time,
at an RAF base.
And the staff said, "Oh great, so where's the pilot?"
And she said, "Oh, I'm the pilot."
And they point blank refused to believe it,
to the extent of searching the plane,
because they thought they were being pranked.
But there's no way this would work.
- And he also does that on just normal domestic flights.
If it's a woman who comes up at the time,
he's like, "Come on, let's get the real one on."
- Ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Dolores Moghrin, she became a pilot after the war.
She wasn't allowed to say, "This is your captain speaking."
- What? - Because people would freak out
and presumably storm the cockpit or whatever.
- Yes.
- Can I just say, "I'm never quite sure on airplanes."
When they say, "This is your captain."
I'm never sure if it's the person who's piloting
and plane speaking, all the head of the steward
and stewardessing staff.
- I think it's the captain. - Yeah, it's the person piloting.
- When they say, "This is the captain speaking,"
generally speaking, it's the captain.
- It's not the stewardess.
- Unless they say, "This is the captain of catering speaking."
You will receive your cups of tea very shortly.
Just texting at the moment to the airport, actually.
- There's going to be a little bit of turbulence
on the trolley this afternoon,
but we're going to get your drinks to you.
- No, who invented Larson Found Officers?
- Is it someone... - It's my famous.
- Is this guy called Conan Doyle?
- Winston Doyle. - It's always Conan Doyle.
- Neither of those two.
But it's someone more famous, in fact,
than either of those two, I would say.
- Thanks to the Winston Churchill. - Genghis Khan.
- Jesus. - John Wayne.
- It was Napoleon Donapat.
- Oh, I forgot. - Oh, wow.
- Sorry, Andy.
- Napoleon won? - Yeah.
- I can't even walk.
You're saying he invented now what?
- Larson Found. - Larson Found.
- Yeah. - It's been so long.
- Part of his thing,
like Napoleon was bringing everything to Paris,
kind of thing, like centralising the whole country.
And as part of that, he set up an office on the Yildesitay
for lost objects, and it still exists.
- Cool. - And they have a cabinet of curiosities
that include several human skulls,
a wooden leg, and two chunks of masonry
from the World Trade Centre.
And can you believe that?
- Well, that's somehow got lost.
- Yeah. - Well, that's the thing with Larson Found.
You don't know how it got there, right?
- How do they know the masonry is from the World Trade Centre?
- There must be clues.
- They've properly analysed that.
Wow.
- I guess so. - That was amazing.
- Yeah. - And the modern system there
was organised by a guy called Louis Lapine,
who was known as the Little Man with a big stick.
And he was a French policeman,
and he was well known for handling the crowds in Paris,
whenever there was riots and stuff.
But he was also famous for accusing
friend of the podcast, a polinear of stealing the Mona Lisa.
Do you remember that story?
- Yeah, and the cast. - And the reason,
I'm sure you're very familiar.
- Yes, this was episode 300.
- He chose what sort of thing.
That was a very good one.
- I enjoyed that. - I think I was driving
from Patnie.
- He had an accident.
- But yeah, he was like really famous
and really well respected.
But when this...
- A big stick.
- They had to respect him, yeah.
But when this Mona Lisa thing happened,
he lost all of his credibility, really.
- The police officer, Lapine.
- They say when you've got with the Mona Lisa,
because it's been stolen quite a few times.
But every time,
it doesn't matter where you're coming from to steal it,
the painting can see you.
- And this is actually a good hint,
the only way to get it without her seeing you
is going from behind.
- And that's the wall.
- Don't take that advice out of context, please.
- Just on like early trends in general,
have you heard about railway madmen?
- This was a... - Oh, was it like spinoff?
- Yeah.
- What was that?
- It was the opening theme.
- This was the thing, when trains were introduced,
and growing, there was railway mania,
which was when everyone was just building trains,
across the UK in particular,
with no thought of whether they needed to be a train, basically.
- No, they got given huge subsidies
for building train tracks and stuff.
- For a while, it was the most profitable thing you could do.
So people were just building mad little railways
everywhere, thousands of miles.
But railway madmen was a different thing.
People were worried at the time of social change,
and you were locked in the compartments.
That was another thing.
So people really freaked out at the prospect of train travel,
making people lose their way.
It's specifically man as well,
and just go bananas and berserk, basically.
- Yeah. - 'Cause of the speed you were going?
'Cause of the speed...
- Also, it enclosed in tunnels a lot.
I think that was a problem.
- There was a lot of...
Yeah, there's a historian called Amy Millen Smith,
and she did a fantastic report on this,
like a thesis about it.
So it was normal men who were completely fine,
but it was partly all the stuff you said, James,
and partly stress and overwork and anxiety of mod...
Like just modern life, the modern condition,
meant that, you know, in 1869, a gentleman suddenly
took off all his clothing and leaned out of the windows
of his carriage, talking nonsense, you know.
And it was just apparently as soon as the train stopped,
or they got off the train, they completely recovered their wits,
and they were fine.
It was literally the act of being on a moving train.
- Now hang on, can I button with...
Is there anything to do with sitting backwards on a train?
- Oh, don't worry. - They looked into that scientific issue whereby
it could drive you mad if you're always facing the wrong way
and going in a certain direction.
- Yeah. - And I hope it's going backwards on a train.
- It feels sick, yeah, yeah. - It's you.
- Yeah, none of you guys. - I love it.
- Well, yeah, I'm not a fan of it.
So I think it could be linked to a bit of madness that might come.
- I prefer it. I prefer seeing backwards on my...
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - I actually prefer it as well,
because if you crash head on to something,
then you have something to stop you from...
- Oh, y'all crash theory.
- Yeah.
- And don't think backwards crash theory. - Yeah, yeah, that's interesting.
- So you think James that they should put all the seats in a car backwards, presumably?
- Well, I think I'm not the only person who thinks that.
- Really? - I mean, that is safer.
- Except the driver seat, presumably.
- Just don't hold the cars reverse everywhere.
- Yeah.
- That's... yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Just lean around. You're arm over the other seat.
You do that classic move.
- Yes, nice, nice. - Yeah.
- Everyone would drive a lot more slowly.
- Yeah. - Just safer.
- Do you guys know a right-handed batter called...
Lassa Rousseau, Talibula, Minerva, Lenny Vé Vaca,
Boulin, Miner, Kula, Cala, Kebalau?
- Yes, of course. - Yeah, I have his shirt,
but it can't be a fortune to get his name on the pack.
Is that... - I don't know him.
- Is it a real name of someone we have heard of?
- No, no, it's not.
It's just the longest crooked, his name ever,
but he's just a pacific ricketer from Fiji.
And he sounds like a great guy.
Larger because of his long name.
His surname means "Returned Alive"
from Nancula Hospital at La Kemba Island in the Lao Group,
which is easier to pronounce if you want to do it that way.
- Last members for the Lao Group, please.
Last members for the Lao Group.
Buses departing shortly.
But yeah, he was great.
He used to...
They played one international game, Fiji,
against New Zealand in the 1940s and '50s when he played.
And they made him serenade them with South Sea songs after the match,
which he did.
A game, lovely man, I know.
- You know that it took 120 years after the invention of the cricket box
to invent the cricket helmet.
- Okay.
- I like to post that show to people's priorities.
- Pretty much. - Why, doesn't it?
- Would you agree with that?
- I'd have thought, yeah, even terms of what you're keen on.
I suppose it...
- You've got a skull.
You don't have a penis skull.
- You don't have a genital exoskeleton.
- Exactly.
- Yeah.
- We're hoping these less than the guys can do something.
- The ball is generally going to be in the lower part of your body.
- Amid ships.
- Yeah.
- Well, it's absolutely about how bouncing the surface as well, isn't it?
These days it's very bouncing because they're protective and stuff.
But if it was opened to the elements at the time,
the bounce could be variable.
It's more lighty to be lower and slower,
so you'd be more lighty to take one.
And the plums than in the noggin.
- Yeah, about 1850s was the Palner's patent-growing protector, as it was called,
before that you'd just stuff a hanky down there to improvise it.
But it was only in the 1970s.
- It was your hanky made out of Kevlar or what?
- Thank you.
- Yeah, yeah.
- But if it isn't very well used, hanky,
I think that can actually...
(laughing)
- It's hard to fold.
- A heavy head cold actually does protect you
in unpredictable ways, yeah.
And if there's any you could ever use the same one as a kind of gumbee hanky,
it's the first crooked helmet at the same time.
(laughing)
- It's so slanky tied and it's gone.
- Would you have a commentate on Cricket?
Well, I hope you'd done it.
- I think I have done online just briefly.
Yeah, it's quite, it's quite awesome responsibility to be perfectly honest.
If you're thinking, the other people can't see it, and I've really got to...
- Yeah.
- You know, like when you say to the drive in the left,
it's like, I can't see my left shoulder.
Can you tell me if there's anything coming down that hill?
(laughing)
It's that sort of pressure, but for hours.
- It's days.
- I mean, these people can be, you know,
they can be sort of several countries where
and I've got to describe what's going on.
I think it's more high pressure work than people imagine.
- Well, I did read a description of what it's like
commentating on something like Test Match Special.
I can't remember who it was who did it.
Well, like one of the famous commentators said,
"Look, this is the apex of human civilization.
"You're sitting observing a nice cricket match happening.
"People are sending in homemade cakes to you,
"which you can then review on there during a lull in play, basically."
- That the whole play is a lull.
- Yeah.
There's a sort of breathing space.
It's not like commentating on tennis or something like that,
which must be, you know.
- Have you a radio commentator for tennis?
That's a horse racing or whatever.
- Exactly.
- You know, your word per minute is just--
- Exactly, yeah, yeah, I've seen them.
- But this is, he was saying, I think it was a he.
You were either having to describe the immediate play,
which like if there's something going on,
you need to explain that really clearly to the listener,
like he was saying, and then during the quieter bits,
you're talking more about the overall shape of the game.
And during the really quiet bits,
he's talking about the grounds and the whole history
of cricket.
And so you've got three different modes
that you can switch between to a depending on what.
- Oh, you've got mode full, which is something
completely unrelated.
Have you guys ever seen the clip of,
it's the Australian commentator and he tells the joke
that it's a Nicknack party work, give the frog a loan.
- Right.
- Look at Daniel, is that a Keith?
- It's a Keith, it's Kerrio Keith.
And he's, and I can't, who he's commentating with,
but there's always a straight man
who's actually commentating on the cricket
and then, you know, someone more joking.
And he's trying to tell this very long joke
and the other commentator is trying to get in the way
and explain what's happening in the cricket.
And then every two minutes he says,
"And there's no run."
(laughter)
- That's where you use your elbow to test the temperature
of bath water, for instance, rather than your fingers aren't
actually very sensitive to people with their hands
and go, "That's okay, but it's not actually..."
- I feel like my hands are sensitive to temperature.
- I thought it was that your elbow is the
bit of you that's most like a baby.
- 'Cause I always wear gloves, I always wear gloves
when it's cold, I don't wear elbow patches.
- Oh, you should do it.
- You lose so much heat through your elbows.
- Yeah, yeah, but you're only, yeah.
- But also you're down the skatepark a lot,
you're called protective equipment.
So they're elbow guards.
You just don't think of them as well.
- Of course.
- What's the sport wear?
It's two villages versus another,
and it doesn't seem to be a limit on another.
And it's basically getting a ball from...
- Yeah.
- Two posts or something like that.
- Something that's getting from one thing.
- Oppies versus the Downies or opposite of the Downers.
And it's just like village football, really.
- But there's no limit on numbers on the Down.
- Well, I think these days the police limit
who can go.
(laughter)
- Yeah.
- I mean, those sort of sports wear
there's a flexibility.
Like how did it go?
La Cross, there's a sort of set length,
or parameters within which the length of a lacrosse pitch
must be, but actually there is no side boundary.
That's entirely based on where you happen to be playing.
- Yeah.
- So you can set off running in wonder,
and you can just keep going until there's an obstacle.
Essentially, that doesn't get out.
- Yeah, yeah, you can do that.
- We used to do that at school.
And I play football in the playground.
You would have one goal,
and you'd have two teams shooting towards the same goal.
And you would just get someone who would get the ball
I'd just run in the complete opposite direction
with the ball so everyone had to chase after them.
- It's quite, 'cause there's no boundaries.
- But that is true in official lacrosse rules.
I think it's just women's lacrosse.
I weirdly, I think men's lacrosse does have boundaries,
but women's lacrosse--
- Men need boundaries.
(laughter)
- It's good indeed.
- Wasn't it something about like the earliest games
of lacrosse had an insane number of people?
- The American lacrosse foundation claims
the earliest games could have over 100,000 players.
- Stop it.
- And try commentating on that.
- Or state of those changing rooms as well.
(laughter)
- But it's like the handshake before the game is going to take--
- But it's a sort of roughly tafty sport in America,
I think, isn't it, LaCrosse?
We might associate LaCrosse with sort of girls'
boarding schools.
- Yeah.
- In America, then it'd be--
- Well, 'cause women's lacrosse and men's lacrosse
are like just different games, aren't they?
- Yeah. - They have different rules, different.
- Yeah, totally different.
- But you wouldn't hear phrases like
roughty tafty in the men's lacrosse that they play in America,
for instance, whereas you might in the female boarding school
across the replay here.
I've never heard roughty tafty before.
- Well, why not exist as a different--
- No, the phrase. - No, the phrase.
- No, the phrase.
- No, no, no.
- Some sort of post-surgery.
(laughter)
- Even if it's a bubble that's a dessert.
- Oh, then animals, golden hamsters can navigate their way home,
even when blindfolded and let it a complicated route
away from their nests.
- Can they? How do they do it?
Do we know?
- No,, I don't think we do know.
- Oh, and it's really mysterious, isn't it?
Because it's, you know, some of these senses are not,
we don't fully understand.
So there's a thing called the,
oh, it's called the Reed Warbler bird.
- Oh, yeah.
- And the scientists wanted to disrupt,
they thought they must be using the Earth's magnetic field.
Okay, so we'll disrupt it.
So they attached small magnets to these birds' foreheads
in an experiment,
and they also blocked their view of the stars.
And, obviously, they couldn't navigate.
(laughter)
I don't really know what that proves.
- The homing pigeons used to use in the war
to work out where sort of various ships were in things.
Because they had their homing instincts.
And they would know that they would fly
at a very particular pace.
And they would know what time they were released.
And so they're there for,
and the angle from which they basically arrived.
They could work out how far away from that distance.
- Really?
- You'd work out the maths backwards.
So they've arrived from over there.
They set off at this time.
So they must have there for,
that's the way they work.
- I usually have a 20-hour.
- But how do they know where they set off from?
- 'Cause they're going to note on them.
- Oh, what time they set off?
- Well, that information must be,
yes, I was going to say that must be radio,
but then presumably the people radioing
and say where they were.
But maybe, maybe there's so many internet.
Maybe everything.
Any radio signal you send can be intercepted.
But I'm not going to tell you where we are,
but it's 7.58 and I'm releasing the pigeon.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And then it's making that what you will.
(laughter)
- Good luck with that, yeah.
- Oh, Keith has gone off on one.
They were genuinely useful.
They were, they were, they were,
they were sort of called up.
People that were sort of looked after pigeons
were suddenly, they would, they were,
they hide him on for them.
- Yeah, suddenly we went from complete weirdo loners
to very sought after people, I'm so sorry.
- Oh my God.
- That's not how I feel about pigeon fancies, really.
- For our audience are in the pigeon loft at the moment.
- I know.
- Yeah, yeah.
- I've got on satire.
You know, tatler, we're all subscribers.
- Of course.
- Yeah.
- That was meant to be satirical.
(laughter)
It was meant to be taking the piss out of you.
- Can you explain what it is?
- Sorry for those of us.
- Sorry.
- We grew up in Bolton.
It's really not your area.
- Right, world of interiors, but about people.
(laughter)
- So yes, tatler for international listeners
and anyone who's more civilized
is basically a magazine for high society.
It's like photographs of people who aren't quite
the royal family, 'cause they probably can't get access
to them, but who are mates with the royal family.
- Right, so.
- Having wedding.
- Is it tatler that's got, sort of on the back page,
there's always like a, it's not a high street honey,
but it's kind of a, it's like an eligible young lady
who is engaged.
I think maybe that's it, is like,
look at this beautiful young woman.
She's just gone engaged.
You can't get together with her.
- Oh, right.
- Is that it?
- Probably about, yeah.
I mean, it doesn't sound like any other magazine would have that.
- Yeah, like Country Life has a sort of,
yeah, it's made like a lady of the month.
- Maybe it's Country Life, I'm not talking about that.
- But yes, it's a sort of that with an RT black and white photo.
- Yes.
- And sometimes I think it's like single-hand looking.
- Really?
- And free available in your area.
- Oh, that kind of thing, isn't it?
- So this is the page three of...
- Except it's page like 128, 'cause of all the adverts
for posh watches.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And it's a monthly publication.
So it doesn't work in the way that's sort of Metro used to have
our eyes saw yesterday on the 802 from Voxelore,
but we're like, I think I saw you back.
Must have been, I must have been up for four months ago.
(laughing)
I think you admired my plowing.
- That's disgusting.
- I was.
- Oh, yeah.
- Rude of me.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, so what about time?
- Oh, yeah, sorry.
It was founded by a guy called Richard Steele
who called himself Isaac Bickerstaff
when he edited "Tatler"
and Isaac Bickerstaff, actually.
You'll remember the name James.
- I do know the name, but why?
- It was because Jonathan Swift, once published in 1708,
so another great, the other great probably satirist
at the time, published the "Almania" predictions of the year,
writing as Isaac Bickerstaff and he predicted the death
of this astrologer and society person called John Partridge.
And he predicted it on April 1st, it was an April 4th joke.
And this poor guy John Partridge,
who was a bit of a butt of jokes,
spent the rest of his life trying to convince people
that he wasn't dead and when this turned up.
And he wrote a letter saying, I'm not dead.
And Jonathan Swift said, well, that's a hoax
'cause he is, you know, seeing the body made.
- Yeah.
- It was an unkind time, a lot of sick burns
being dished out all over the place,
like saying one of the Irish are so hungry,
why don't they just eat their babies,
which was during the famine.
It was incredibly harsh satir.
- Right.
- Imagine that, imagine that,
'cause it sounds bad now, but it doesn't really love the famine.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, no.
- It's actually even worse.
- It's pitch black, exactly.
He's trying to draw attention to the famine.
And, you know, the awful cruelty that has caused it.
But he's, you know,
he's doing those through a reading process.
- These days, there's not enough nuance on Twitter
for people to get that.
I don't think he'd be able to have done it today.
- So there's a foremost satirist of your time
and it's just to be considered an age lord,
but he actually is a brutal guy.
It's nuanced, for heaven's sake.
(laughing)
- One of you try, we're doing down the people.
I want one of you to tweet something
about a group of people eating babies today
and see what happens to you.
- I'm not on Twitter.
So, one of you two will--
- On Twitter, we'll go down and storm these days.
I can show you that in a group of news.
- I could put it in a WhatsApp group.
(laughing)
- Just see.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, the Christmas one's gone quite.
(laughing)
- Just out of the blue.
- Oh, what's Mars up to?
- Oh, what are we thinking this year?
- Another pseudonym, John Barron.
Do you know this one?
- No, Barron.
- How do you know the name Barron?
- Barron. - Barron.
- Or Barron, like, Barron.
- B-A-D-L-R-O-N.
- The Barron Knights.
- She's a famous Barron these days.
- Barron Trump.
- Yes.
So, Donald Trump pseudonym, John Barron.
So, when Forbes were doing the richest people list,
John Barron wrote to them saying,
"Oh, you've got to put Trump in here."
He's a billionaire.
- No.
- Yeah, and he's got a few others.
There's a guy called John Miller,
who once wrote to People Magazine,
who'd said something about Trump saying actually,
Trump is a very compassionate husband.
And lots of beautiful women are always asking to go out with him.
In fact, Madonna called and wanted to go out with him.
That I could tell you.
- But what makes you think that's one of his pseudonyms?
- We, it came out in court later.
- Oh, that's amazing, that's it.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our outtakes.
If you have anything to say about them,
if you want to share any extra juicy bits of detail
that you know about them,
you can message us on podcast@qy.com.
Those emails go through to Andy,
and a lot of those emails then get taken over
to drop us a line where we discuss them.
So send us your favorite facts, send us an anecdote,
send us anything that you think is worth sharing,
and hopefully you can make it onto a drop us a line.
Just a reminder, no such thing as a fish.com.
You got the ticket link for all of our upcoming gigs,
and two in particular, which is the London Podcast Festival,
it's gonna be happening near Kings Cross at Kings Place,
and that is the fifth and sixth of September.
So get your tickets now, and that's it.
We're gonna be back again with another episode
in a fortnight's time.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)