- Hey everyone, before we begin this week's show,
we just have a quick request.
We are doing a live show on the 28th of February.
It's our third birthday party.
And we were hoping that we could ask you
to submit a bunch of questions, interesting thoughts,
ideas, whatever it is you want for us to read out on stage.
- Yeah, make them funny, make them snappy,
make them cool, make them worthy of being aired,
and they will be podcast at qi.com,
email us your questions.
You could even tweet it to us as well
on our @qipodcast account.
Please do before this coming Tuesday.
And if we see it and it's short enough
and funny enough and intelligent enough,
we will read it on stage.
Okay, on with the show.
(blues music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode of No Such Thing
as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covert Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber and I'm sitting here
with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and Anna Chazinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with you, Andy Murray.
- My fact this week is that the smallest football league
in the world consists of two teams
who play each other 22 times every season.
- Where is it?
- It's on the Isles of Silly,
which is just off Cornwall,
which is the southwest tip of Britain
for anyone who's not from Britain listening.
And they're called the Woolpack Wanderers
and the Garrison Gunners.
And they used to be called the Rangers and the Rovers
and then they thought that was a bit boring
so they could make it more interesting.
- And it's weird that they did that
because you can only really call yourself the Gunners
if you've got a historical connection
to like an Arsenal's case and armaments factory
and the Wanderers.
People are called that when they don't have a permanent stadium
which I assume they always have
because there aren't any other teams in this place.
- Yes.
- So their names are lies.
- I mean, they've been playing since World War I, I believe.
- Well, they must be knackered.
(laughing)
They've got, he forgot to match how long the matches are.
Half-time's coming up next year.
No, so maybe there is a connection potentially for the Gunners.
- Well, they're called the Garrison Gunners
so is it not to do with some kind of Garrison?
- Yeah, I'm sure they're the Garrison on the Elves of Cili.
I don't know, I don't have the facts.
- Do you know what I really like?
They play on the same football pitch every time
but they swap for being a home and a way team
so they're changing rooms.
They change to say a way for the way team that way
and then home on the next match.
- But that means they're the exact opposite
of what you would expect a Wanderers team to be then.
- It's true.
- Because not only have they always played on the same pitch
they even play all their away games on the same pitch as well.
(laughing)
- It's very true.
- The Wikipedia on them is unbelievably cautious.
It says, "The league is reportedly the smallest in the world."
I do not believe there's a one team league anywhere in the world.
- You know how they pick the teams?
They pick them by every year, a few weeks before the season,
the captains of the two teams.
They meet up in the pub and they basically, they take turns.
- No. - Yes.
- Oh my god. - Oh my god.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So they try and make it so the teams
are roughly equal in ability.
- I was reading an interview with them though
and they don't seem to even know which team they play for.
One of them was us.
One of them was us whose team he was on and he said,
"Oh, I'm wearing red, which team is that?"
(laughing)
- Just the Isle of Silly for the people overseas
who haven't heard of it, it's incredibly small
and it's population size as of 2001.
That's the last update I've seen that I could find
2,153 people.
So it's a very tiny population
but they've worked out that 32% of the population participate
at least three times a week in 30 minutes more sport,
way greater than any other bit of Britain.
- But then 1% of the population are in one of these football teams
presumably.
- Yeah, that's amazing.
- Yeah, that's really good.
That must be the highest anywhere.
- Highest proportion of football players anywhere.
- Yeah.
- Professionals.
- And also on their teams, I really like this,
there's a huge gap of the age bracket of who plays
where they're majorotively missing 16 to 25 year olds
and the reason is because the schools in the Isle of Silly
only go up to six form.
So when you're 16, you have to go to the mainland
to finish off your schooling.
And so they end up just staying on the mainland
when they come over rather than going back.
- Basically on holiday, there is a kid.
It's so lovely, amazing bird watching.
- Oh really?
- Amazing birds.
- Did you ever see the Silly Bee?
(laughing)
- No.
- Silly Bee is, yeah, it's a kind of bee
that you find on the Silly Islands.
- That's great.
- Is it good even in a Silly Bee?
(laughing)
- It never collects any pollen.
It only collects twiglets and things like that.
It's such a Silly Bee.
- It just collects anecdotes, yeah.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's actually quite endangered,
but they, someone took a photo of one in 2012
because people thought they might have even got extinct.
So that was big news in the Silly Islands.
- You did a really good job of transferring really quickly
from a laughter voice to the very solemn,
it's quite endangered voice.
- Quite endangered.
There's a serious side to the Silly Bee.
(laughing)
- Have you seen the Silly Police Force
is quite famous around the world?
- Oh yeah, sorry, now everything sounds like Silly.
It's that they've only got two officers
and I think they're one thing saying
they're only posted for a certain number of years
so they don't get too close to the local population.
- They are, it's five years.
- Five years, yeah.
- Well, I know, but the last sergeant,
he wrote the thing saying he'd been there for seven years.
So I don't know.
- Maybe no one liked it.
(laughing)
- He had to borrow a child's bike once
to pursue a drunk driver.
- And this is a Silly policeman
you're talking about.
- He's a Silly policeman.
- I think it's a very good policeman,
but one of the other cases that he dealt with was,
and I'm quoting here,
a shed door was forced open at a football club,
but one of the only clues available was a fried egg.
- This is fried egg on the ground next to the shed.
- Is there any resolution to that story?
Do we know the case of the fried egg?
- If there is, I don't have it.
- Sorry.
- And escape chicken.
(laughing)
- No, they don't fry their eggs today.
That's what he says.
(laughing)
- I was reading, so the teams actually do team up as well
to play against the mainland.
There's a team.
- Which is a massively uneven contest to be fair.
(laughing)
- So they play the England football team,
they play, who are they called?
- It's dynamo chuff in hands and hands.
- Yeah, and so they play them together.
And they have a trophy that they use,
the Lioness Cup.
And the Lioness Cup trophy is the smallest trophy in the world.
- In size, you mean?
- Yeah, in size, it's very tiny.
I think it's in the FIFA museum, isn't it?
- They took it for the FIFA museum for a year.
It's six millimeters tall.
- Whoa.
- That's very sweet.
- That's smaller than a silly bee.
(laughing)
- It was made by a carpenter from dynamo truffs and his wife.
I think they're artists.
- So is it made out of wood then?
- I think it's made of wood and metal.
You know, the oldest player in the football league retired
last year at the age of 70.
- 70, but I read the way that they play.
It doesn't sound overly competitive.
In that, there's a journalist who is gonna play
for the sake of writing an article
and he just kept missing every time
and he missed it like 16 times.
But every time he missed it, everyone was really encouraging
and apparently that's the whole thing it's just about.
So this 70 year old guy, I bet he's shit.
But it doesn't matter, 'cause they're really listening
to this podcast.
He didn't really say it.
Looking at an empty six millimeter high spot
on his mantel piece.
I think, no, I've only been better.
(laughing)
It's like a bee.
- Well, all of the haters is 70 play against, you know,
ages, that don't include 16 to 20 pie,
but everything that happens, he might be outplayed for his age.
Maybe not.
- The silly isles signed a piece treaty
with the Netherlands a few years ago to end formally
the 335 years war between the two countries.
- Oh wow.
- Even though no one actually knows
if the 335 years war ever actually happened.
- Whoa.
- So there have been rumors since the 1600s.
The war was declared between the Netherlands
and the silly isles and then other people say
it can't even have been declared,
'cause they're not a nation and no one really knows,
but the sources go back that far.
And eventually, at some point, the silly isles
wrote to the Netherlands and said,
look, can we just acknowledge
that there's never been a war between us?
And the Netherlands said we can't actually verify that.
I think we're probably still at war.
So the silly isles said, okay, well, can we end the war piece?
(laughing)
And so yeah, they visited each other
and they signed a treaty saying we're at peace.
- It was amazing.
The ambassador came over in a helicopter
with a scroll to sign the piece.
- But the admiral who declared war on the silly isles,
the Dutch one was called Trump.
- Oh, I see.
- 10 Trump.
- I know.
So we don't know if he's any relation.
- That's a long helicopter ride, isn't it?
- 300 years.
(laughing)
- We said that the ambassador got there by helicopter.
- It will have been from the mainland UK, yes.
- The mainland UK.
- You have to, yeah.
- No, I was just only thinking, can you go over the channel
and how far can you go on a helicopter?
- You can go over the channel.
- How bad do you think helicopters are?
- Do you think you just threw them
and then they go as far as you can toss it?
- No, they just don't look like they have much fuel.
- They could go about 300 miles,
like just a small helicopter and then the big ones could go.
- How far's that?
- You just asked how far 300 miles is.
- So you know a mile, yeah.
It's 300 of those.
- We can't reduce it further than that.
(laughing)
And the Netherlands is very close.
- You used to always get a helicopter over.
I think they've cancelled it now,
but when I used to go as a kid,
it was the only way that you'd go over
except for the ferry crossing.
- I think they might be gonna bring it back.
- Oh really?
- Either they're gonna bring it back
or just have brought it back.
Or they said they were going to and haven't done it.
(laughing)
- One of those kind of options there.
- Great facts from James Ollion.
(laughing)
- I do have a fact about the longest
and shortest things in the world,
'cause there's about the world's smallest league of football.
- Yep.
- But I'm afraid it's about the world's largest penis.
- Oh God.
- The world's largest penis is only two inches shorter
than the world's smallest man.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- Are they on the same person?
- Yeah, no.
(laughing)
- This is a man called Roberto Esquivel Cabrera
who says his penis is 19 inches long.
- It's not hard to verify that.
- Well, how long is 19 inches?
(laughing)
- You know what I'm saying?
- It's a short helicopter journey.
- I'll say that.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two
and that is Chazinski.
- My fact this week is that in the 1940s in America,
if you wanted to play a recording of a band song
on the radio, the entire band had to be present
in the studio while you played it.
(laughing)
This is about a musician strike in America
between 1941 and 1943 about the fact that recorded music
was being played on the radio.
And so musicians thought they were gonna go out of business
because they were no longer being paid to play live music.
And so they went on strike and one of their demands
was that every time a recording was played
so the musicians didn't lose out.
Every single person involved in making that recording
had to turn up in the studio and then be paid the fee
that they would be paid for.
- That's amazing.
- That's incredible.
Why would they then still just play the recording
and not have the band play?
- Maybe it's more effort to get your studio set up
and get the sound all sorted.
- Yeah, I guess so, yeah.
- If anyone's listening to this podcast,
we will be turning up in your house.
(laughing)
- I've got, I'm gonna have to meet that 70-year-old man.
- I'm gonna have to meet him in the open moment.
- I'm gonna have to meet the long penis, bloke.
(laughing)
- Just speaking of recreations,
that was another thing that was very popular
in the 1940s going back to the 20s
and as late as the '50s, where they would recreate
sport events because it was too hard to get live recording.
So if there was a baseball match that was going on,
while the baseball match was going on,
they would relay the information
about how the game was going back to a studio
and the commentator would commentate
as if it was live match.
- Whoa.
- But he would have a bat that was hanging next
to his microphone, which he would hit anytime there was a hit
and they would have crowd noise played in and so on
and they would commentate live.
- No.
- Yeah.
- It was all a recreation because it was too expensive
to get the lines to mic up an entire stadium.
- Did they have all the sports equipment
hanging in the studio 'cause they must've had to,
depending on what sport they've had to...
(laughing)
- They had the coconuts of the horse racing.
- And one of the sports announcers was Ronald Reagan
in his early days when he was an actor.
- Wow.
- That is so funny.
- That's really funny.
- Amazing.
James, you had a fact about darts, didn't you?
- About darts.
- Yeah, they used to, in the old days,
they used to have darts on the radio
and the way they would do it is you'd get a darts player
and he would throw the darts at a board
and then the guy would say, tell you what he got
and then there'd be silence while you were allowed
to throw your own darts and then you would be like
playing against the guy.
- Oh, it's so cool.
- Whoa.
- It's so good.
- Why don't we do that kind of stuff anymore?
- Well, I think it's because we have play stations.
(laughing)
- It's a very good point.
- Yeah.
- So, you know, old recording studios were really cramped
and also they didn't have very good technology
to do the recording.
So, for example, you had maybe one recording horn, right?
And you had to, which was soaking up all the sound.
And you had to get the band positioned around it
in exactly the right way that when they played,
instruments wouldn't drown each other out.
- Yeah.
- And sorry, and by horn you mean something
that takes in the sound.
You don't mean that.
- Sorry, I don't mean a French horn which gives out the sound.
- Yeah, or a clown car horn as James just brilliantly
did the sound effect for him.
- Or the horn.
- Or being sexually aroused.
- Yeah, no one had an erection in the through me that.
- Okay, can you guarantee that?
- Can you guarantee that?
(laughing)
- So anyway, basically singers had the worst time of all
because they had to move towards the horn
when they were singing quietly.
And when they had a loud bit coming off in the song,
they had to lean away from the recording horn
so that they didn't drown everybody out.
But in experienced soloists got pushed back and forth
on a trolley by an assistant.
(laughing)
- That's amazing.
- Wow.
- How hard is it to lean towards that?
(laughing)
- Probably people who complained about the sound quality
on this podcast are thinking,
you guys could do with doing that.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Yes, we're all on a trolley at the moment.
That's the problem.
(laughing)
- I'll wheelie chairs with Alex Bell
running around because she is in an hour.
(laughing)
So how long did the strike go on?
- Yeah, I'll just talk about the strike a little bit more.
So it went on for two years.
It's the longest ever strike in Hollywood
entertainment industry history.
And some other weird things about it.
So the guy who led it was this guy called Petrillo.
One of the things that Petrillo said
that radio stations would have to do,
one of the demands he made,
and I'm not sure if he ever got around to enforcing it,
was that as soon as any station had played a record,
they had to immediately destroy that record.
(laughing)
- Oh, that's so nice, that's cool.
- But one thing that happened in the end was,
it led to the decline of the big bands.
And then it just became more about the singers
than the bands.
- Yeah.
- So it didn't have the intended effect long-term,
didn't it?
- Not at all, almost the opposite, in fact.
- I find it amazing that this was all going on
from when did you say 1942 to '44?
- Yes.
- During a period of total war around the world.
This was the main thing that was eating a load of people.
- Right, it feels weird, the music is like,
we're going on strike, it's not the time, mate.
- I thought I'd have a look at some of the songs
that were in the charts in the '40s.
So one famous one was 'White Christmas',
which was number one for 11 weeks in 1942.
- Is this American or British?
- This is the Billbar American chart, yeah.
So 'White Christmas' was number one for 11 weeks,
and I was quite surprised, it first got to number one
in October that year.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, that's kind of interesting.
- So all this whining about Christmas starting too early,
actually, it's always done it.
- And in 1941, so a bit before this strike,
there was things like Chattanooga Chuchu as number one,
songs like 'Blue Champagne', my sister and I,
but on October the 4th of 1941, for eight weeks,
the number one song in America was 'Piano Concerto'
number one in 'Be Flat Minor' by Chikovsky.
That was top of the charts.
- Wow, I thought he was around where earlier.
- In 1940s.
- You know.
- But they had to have his body in the studio,
whenever they played it.
- Gossily exhuming.
I should say that I got this fact from a website called Timeline.
It's Timeline.com, and it's such a good website,
and it basically tells you in-depth stories sort of from history,
sort of related to stuff that happens in the news.
But it's brilliant website, and they got this from a podcast
I've just discovered called the Pessamist's Archive,
which is also great, and the idea of this podcast is,
it's about stuff throughout history,
people have been terrified of change,
and they've always said this is going to destroy it.
- Oh, cool.
- And they have loads of examples of that.
So, you know, trains thought buses were going to destroy them.
Horses and carts campaigned against trains,
because they thought trains were going to destroy them,
which they did.
People thought the radio was really damaging for your ears
and for kids.
People thought Walkman should be banned.
It's so, it's really interesting.
Pessamist's Archive is, I would recommend.
- Yeah, I wonder how many bits and new technology
have just been outright accepted as the right way forward.
Like airplanes, they thought would never.
- Yeah, never thought they'd take off.
(laughing)
- Do you know they played music on Apollo 11?
- Really? - Oh, hardly.
Like in the lift, when you were waiting to take off.
- While they were going.
- While they were going, to keep them calm.
- That's amazing.
- Waiting, what, during take off?
- Apparently. - Wow.
- Did they also have buttons like in a lift
and one of them said, "Moon."
(laughing)
- Jupiter.
- Yeah.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the British Library
has a collection of over 60 million newspapers
and none of them can catch fire.
You cannot light any of them on fire.
- Give us a go, I've got a flamethrower.
(laughing)
- Are they kept in water?
- Are they kept in a vacuum?
- Yeah, no, it's, so the British Library,
obviously ginormous archive.
Too big to even fit in one place in London
in St. Pancras where the British Library is.
So they have a warehouse out in a place called Boston Spa,
which is out in the countryside of England.
And in there, they house all of the newspaper archive.
This goes back some three centuries,
and it's a collection of 60 million.
So what they've done in there is that they've reduced
the oxygen level to a lower percentage,
which means it's impossible to light a flame inside
that you cannot light a match.
You cannot make your lighter produce a flame.
Therefore, you are unable to light any of the newspapers
in there.
It's very clever.
- So cool.
- Yeah, you can't actually work in that building
for too long because you go a bit loopy.
Employees don't actually really need to be down there
for long because the whole thing is operated by robots.
- Amazing.
- Amazing department.
But when they do go in, they're only allowed in for so long
because the oxygen level is so low.
- It's the same amount of oxygen as is in a pressurised
air cabin in a narrow plane.
I didn't quite realise how much the oxygen levels
are reduced when an aircraft cabin is pressurised,
but they're reduced by 25% just because of the pressurisation.
And reducing it by 25% ends up with it being the equivalent
of 15% oxygen concentration at sea level,
which is about the same.
And the only reason we don't really notice it
is because you don't really do anything on a plane.
But if you try to run a marathon up and down that corridor,
you'd be in trouble for a number of reasons.
- A marathon is 26 and a bit miles done.
- And how long is that?
- It's a medium length helicopter ride.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, and also it's all in the dark this warehouse
because robots don't need lights.
- I think it's a bit harsh that these robots have to work
in the dark.
- I know they're robots, but just feels like,
you know, give them a light, give them...
- They hate light, they're like vampires.
- How they meant to read in there?
- Maybe it's to stop them from reading.
- That's right, they're going to be doing their job, yeah.
- If you're a member of the British Library
and you request one, the robot goes to the shelf,
it gets down the thing and then it goes to an airlock
and it passes the thing through the airlock
to a human on the other side
so that it preserves the oxygen levels in the room.
How cool is that?
- Yeah, and then in most cases,
they do have a reading room there,
but a lot of it is ordered from the central London library.
So it gets in a van and they just bring it over.
It's bringing these, it's a lot of effort
to read a newspaper.
- It's amazing, yeah.
- Although you can, most of it's digitised, I think.
So the British Library has pet up
with the British newspaper archive,
which I think I can't really mention,
and they're digitising most of their newspapers on that.
And I think you're only allowed to extract something
from this place in Boston Spa
if it's not available digitally.
- Right.
- A way thing about Boston Spa, it's very small place
in New Yorkshire, it's got a Wikipedia page,
very short.
No word is a mention on its Wikipedia page
that it constitutes the entire British Library
newspaper archive.
I think someone needs to add that in.
- The first library in Britain, Manchester Free Library,
which opened in 1852 in Manchester,
and it had 18,000 bucks.
And it was so popular in its first week
that a police officer was assigned to control
the crowd around the borrowing desk.
- Wow.
- And the first librarian was called Edward Edwards.
(all laughing)
- I was reading a thing about so libraries keep shutting down,
and one of the things as well that happens
in a lot of libraries is if a book doesn't get borrowed,
then they get taken off the library shelf.
And what that means is that if the library actually
wants to keep the book, they end up having to buy the book
back to put on their shelf, so it costs them a lot of money.
So there is a library in Orlando
where they found a guy who checked out 2,361 books
in the span of nine months.
And it turned out it was the librarian there
who created a false library card.
And the idea was is that now that he borrowed it,
it was in circulation and you get paid for circulation
as well it brings in funds.
But he got in serious trouble because it's very legal
to fake of being a library borrower.
- That's a shame, 'cause that is a brilliant idea.
- Yeah, he was saying that he was saving money technically
because they would just buy the books back anyway.
So it was just him trying to be a bit cheeky
about keeping the books without it, costing the library
anything, but unfortunately it was seen as illegal.
And he's now in jail for life.
- What?
(all laughing)
- It's no wonder that is totally plausible
about the American justice system.
He was placed on paid suspension.
- Oh, okay.
- It does sound a bit like playing your own songs
on Spotify nonstop.
- Yes, that kind of thing.
- That's a good idea.
- People do it, don't they?
- Do they?
- I mean, there was a band who did that.
- We spoke about on the podcast ages ago,
I think they're called Wolfpack or something like that.
- Good memory.
- Yeah, what they did was they streamed their album
and told everyone to stream it because if it went enough,
so they said when you go to bed,
just stream it over and over, put on repeat
but put it on low volume or no volume.
- Oh, wasn't a silent album, though.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Sorry, so the volume thing was nothing.
Yeah, and they did make a lot of money
which funded their tour,
but they got caught out by Spotify.
- And they're all in prison.
- Yeah, for life.
(all laughing)
- There is an archive called the London Metropolitan Archives
and they have a whole collection of old London records,
sort of parish records and city records and things like that.
But many of them are unbelievably badly burned
from a fire that happened in 1786.
And then why haven't I was after the fire?
They said we should preserve these records just in case.
And now, 200 and something years later,
what that's nearly 240 years later,
they are becoming able to read them.
- How do you mean?
- What they've been doing is they've been preserving
the pages very carefully in boxes
and then they increase the humidity
and they sort of puff them out and then they scan them
and then they can digitally flatten the pages.
- So you kind of unburn them a little bit.
Basically, yeah.
- Hang on, you can unburn something by getting it wet.
- And no, you increase the humidity.
I don't know if that is--
- It is wetness.
- Yeah, okay, good point.
And then, oh yeah, and they use magnets
to hold the page flat while they're scanning it
or as flat as they can.
I mean, it's unbelievably clever,
but basically it's meaning that they can suddenly read
all these things.
- But all that we find out is that Mr. Jones
lived on high-holbin.
- There could be clues in here.
There could be important clues to how we say everything.
- All I'm saying is it's a lot of effort
to just learn the list of names
of people getting married and stuff.
- You love reading long lists of information, James.
This is right up your street.
- But just the vision of keeping these things for 200 years
is amazing.
- Just in case we change our own technology.
- Yeah, read them again.
- I kind of think that's incredibly admirable.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that's great.
- James thinks it's absolutely worthless, but--
- I like it, yeah.
(all laughing)
- I think the money could be spent better elsewhere.
- Yep.
- They'll give you more libraries.
(all laughing)
- And then take thousands of books out of the better time.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that the man who invented
Muldwine also invented an Aphrodisiac sorbet.
- Muldwine.
- Well, yes, he did.
Well, Amanda, both of those things.
(all laughing)
Muldwine is kind of pretty old, pretty ancient,
but Blue Van, which is the German version of it,
has a guy who is often called the inventor of it.
He's called August Joseph Ludwig von Wachibath.
(all laughing)
- Which is a pretty strong name.
And he is the author of the oldest extant recipe.
So in Germany, they call him the father of Muldwine.
And quite recently, some historians found some writings
of his of a recipe for Aphrodisiac sorbet.
- Mmm.
- And the sorbet is made with the delicious whites of two eggs,
the juice of two lemons, two pounds of sugar,
a few grains of ambergris.
- Hold on, it's done writing this down.
(all laughing)
- It's done just to whip it down his pen
and start scrolling notes on his page.
- So done two eggs.
- Two eggs.
- Yeah, two lemons, two pounds of sugar,
some ambergris, and delicious lozenges
from the pharmacy four ounces of.
- Oh, great.
- It's just strepsils.
- But we don't know what's in the lozenges.
That's a problem, you see.
That might be the magic ingredient.
And all we've said is one pound of sugar per egg.
I mean, that's quite a sugary recipe.
- But also it has an incredibly expensive recipe in there
because it's using ambergris in there.
- Yeah, which you start at least slipped in,
like just some sugars and milk, some solid diamond,
and it's gonna be a flower.
- So we've told on it.
- Yeah.
- But if you don't have that,
you can use the glandulous secretions of a musk rat.
- Oh good.
(all laughing)
- Well, we got a lot of that.
No, what I was writing down was he's called
the father of Muldwine.
I was wondering if that he was called that
because that's just way easier to say than his actual name.
(all laughing)
- Oh, Gustjo's if Ludwig Wagner-Vacabar.
What's hard about that?
- Oh, you're right.
I'm afraid.
- He seemed, it's a shame.
A lot of the articles on him online,
there's a lot of results when he put his name in,
but they're all in German.
And I really want to read more about this guy,
but I didn't have time today.
- You didn't have time to learn German.
(all laughing)
- When are you gonna get that done over the weekend?
- Yeah, I'll say.
- Yeah.
He's, as a wild claim, isn't it?
This father of Muldwine because people have been drinking.
He's been up wine and alcoholic drinks
since the dawn of time.
So I think peeps talks about drinking it.
- Right.
- And- - The ancient Greeks as well.
- The ancient Greeks drinking it.
- Even before the time of Samuel Peep.
(all laughing)
- Well, you said dawn of time,
which is, I think, a bit far back.
- So I said, I said from when we've been drinking-
- You said the dawn of time.
- I said the dawn of time.
- Yeah, the dawn of time.
- The dinosaurs actually had a very,
the first thing's made in the Big Bang.
- Yeah.
- It was a hydrogen helium and Muldwine.
- And gloves.
(all laughing)
- Do you know how they used to heat it?
And I think they still do heat it.
- Over a flame?
No. - No.
- Not over a flame.
- Oh, in a microwave.
- Yeah, that's right.
That's why Samuel peeps did it.
- In some dung.
- Oh, peeps things up.
- No, maybe they, maybe some of them did that.
- Cutting open the body of a horse
and putting it in there.
- And pouring it into there
and then you drink it from the orifice.
- By taking the latent heat of the early universe.
(all laughing)
- It's just the Big Bang was a hot time.
It was actually, it was a drink question.
(all laughing)
- It's still a war, we're calling that.
- All Muldwine gets here from comments.
No, well, peeps records how they would get a polka
really, really hot over the fire.
So you'd hold a polka over the fire
and then you'd have a huge vat of beer,
which I often was in those days, or wine.
And then you'd stir it with a hot polka.
So you'd stir it in a barrel of beer with a polka.
- That's really clever.
- Yeah.
- That's cool.
- Does that work?
- Really well, or would work.
- I think it did seem to be.
- Would work, of course.
- So like if I wanted to make a tea,
but I didn't have a...
- If you had a cup, you didn't have a kettle,
but you didn't have a red hot polka.
(all laughing)
- Yeah, would that work?
- I guess.
- Could you get the water boiling hot?
- Yeah, you could, I suppose.
- Yeah, maybe.
- 'Cause you know, you need it quite hot
so you make a really good cup of tea.
- Yeah.
- But I mean, the cup's not that big, is it?
So I imagine the mould wine, that's a pot.
- Yeah, you don't want to damage the cup
that you're making a tea, and either,
and if you're wiggling around a red hot polka net,
you might.
(all laughing)
So the Victorian television of mould wine,
which they called Smoking Bishop.
- That's a thing.
- Yeah, that was a thing.
It was port, it was port fruit and spices,
but they had also Smoking Archbishop,
which was with Claret and Smoking Pope.
And in a Christmas carol,
screwed promises Bob Cratchett, some Smoking Bishop.
- We'll see.
- Yeah.
You could have quite a fun night, if you were a bishop,
with some Smoking Bishop,
and then you could eat some Stinking Bishop, the cheese.
- Yeah.
- Oh yeah.
- If there are any bishops listening,
who want to know how to party.
(all laughing)
- But wait, it wasn't just bishops who were allowed
to drink it, right?
- No, it was everyone who was allowed to drink it.
It was just a name.
- So you don't have to be a bishop who knows how to party.
You can be anyone who knows how to party.
- That's true, yeah.
- Could we do some Aprodisiac stuff?
- Yeah.
- Okay, no, sorry.
- No, what I was going to say is,
they did an experiment with some rats,
where they took out one of the ingredients,
famigree switches, Ambrian.
So it's like a type of compound,
and they gave it to the rats,
and it produced an increase of a no genital
investigatory behavior.
- So let's unpack that a second.
A no genital investigatory.
Okay, got it, yeah, yeah.
So I think all those words are self, you know?
- Self-explanatory, yeah, yeah.
- Really?
- What Friday night is complete without...
(laughing)
- It's awesome, eight over the bishop party.
- Ain't no genital investigatory behavior.
- Absolutely, yeah.
- Only works in rats though, apparently.
- Well, we don't know.
I think we need to do the investigation for humans.
- Oh god, I don't think we need to.
I think other people need to.
- It only works really in male rats as well.
- The female rats aren't that interested.
- Right.
- Ain't no genital eat or otherwise.
- About that kind of thing.
- Hey, I'm just wondering if you're interested in me,
Aino genital eat or otherwise.
(laughing)
- It's a good word, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- You're being really Aino genital about this mark.
(laughing)
- Is it Aino with one end?
- Yeah. - I know, yeah.
- Aino, right, I've never actually seen that.
- You've shown to that before?
- No. - No.
- It's where volcano is made up of two words.
Folk and Aino.
- Right, I don't know that.
- Because people thought it was vulcan, the god.
Here's Aino's.
- Yeah, that's right.
- Shitting fire into the sky.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Gwyneth Poucho sells Afridisiacs.
And this is a way of talking about her website,
which I know this is very low-brow for us
to go into this subject, but it's unbelievable.
Her website called goop.com, which she sells extraordinary
things on there.
- Like what Anna, and for how much?
(laughing)
- And if you're listening this week's episode
of No Stuff Things A Fish, it's brought to you by Goop.
For all your Aino genital leads.
- So for this Aino genital need, you can get sex bark,
which is sex bark.
- Yeah, sex bark.
- Look at what it's worth and it's sex bites.
(laughing)
- Yeah, it's like chocolate, except then you have to add
something called Hushuwo to it, which is sex dust.
And I don't, it doesn't really specify where you get that.
- It sounds to me like she's just taking objects
and putting the word sex in front of them.
- That's the sex cleaner being.
(laughing)
- There's a lot of sex dust on top of the sex piano.
- But she also sells Jade eggs, do you know what these are?
- Are they made out of Jade for the material?
- I believe they are, they claim to be.
They're also called Yoni eggs and they're advertised
on goop.com as once strictly guarded secret
of Chinese concubines and royalty and antiquity.
And they harness the power of energy, crystal healing
and a cagal-like physical practice.
So it's all very scientifically sound.
- And what you do is you put them into your vagina
and you sit there with one in for a while
and it makes you feel better.
- Strange that they didn't call them sex Jade eggs, isn't it?
(laughing)
- 'Cause you hadn't developed that particular marketing twist yet.
- And then you have to pass them again, presumably.
- You pass them out again, yeah, of the same.
- Wow, clocking.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- That's, yeah, wow, that's, yeah, cool.
- That's only you.
- I mean, if it's consenting adults.
- Nothing criminal about it.
- No, no.
- Gailan said that any food which made you flatulence
was an aphrodisiac.
Any warm, moist and windy foods were ones that produced lust.
- And did he do well?
(laughing)
- This is Tinder for a couple of times.
Looking for a guy who,
- Saferon can help you have a sustained erection they found.
- Wow.
- There was a 2009 study in Iran and the 20 male patients
were given Saferon for 10 days
and they showed a statistically significant improvement
in apparently their tip rigidity and tip tumessence
as well as base rigidity and base tumessence.
But no word on the middle.
- I got it.
(laughing)
- So it's a bit like, you know, the slinky dog
and toy story?
(laughing)
- God.
- I was reading about an aphrodisiac.
This is the title of the story.
Can a rare Hawaiian mushroom really give women
a spontaneous orgasm?
And this was a 15 year old study.
- Not by him.
(laughing)
- Sorry.
- Let me start that again.
- May steady continue in the rare mushroom.
(laughing)
- Same personation of a 15 year old.
- Well, I sounded like.
(laughing)
- Well, you had some 41.
Now, when you were 15,
(laughing)
- I mean, the biggest podcast reveal.
Andy's grunge part.
(laughing)
- This is a study that was done in 2001.
And these two medical students published a report
in the International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms.
And they did this study on 36 volunteers,
both male and female.
And they found that this mushroom,
this Hawaiian mushroom, was causing spontaneous orgasm
in a bunch of the women, a part of the study group.
And so, everyone says it's not a big enough study group
in order for that to be a truth.
So it's a very dubious thing.
And the article I was reading saying,
actually no, it can't give you spontaneous orgasm.
What I was wondering though, was if we thought that it did,
I wonder if there's a sort of placebo effect with it.
Therefore, could you placebo an orgasm?
- Well, almost all afridiziax and things
that are sort of an afridiziax trade on the placebo effect.
- And do they?
Oh, okay.
So oysters and the actual evidence for them changing chemicals
in your body to make you more interested in sex is pretty slim.
- Yeah, although they don't claim spontaneous orgasms
to be fair, that's another...
I think when you have an afridiziax,
you also need to have some other sexual stimulation.
You don't just eat ten oysters and stand,
they're going, "Why haven't I orgasm?"
(laughing)
- I don't know, darling, keep trying.
I'm doing the crossword.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course of this podcast.
- Sorry, Mr. Galen, that was...
(laughing)
It's sexual.
- If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said over the course
of this podcast, we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Streiberland.
James. - @Xshaped.
Andy. - @AndreyHunterM.
- And Chazinski.
- You can email podcast.ky.com.
- Yep, or you can go to our group account,
which is @kypodcast or our website.
No such thing as a fish.com.
We'll be back again next week with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)