(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast coming to you
from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber.
I'm sitting here with Anna Tyshinski, Andrew Hunter Murray,
and James Harkin, and once again,
we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days,
and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that the author, George Elliott,
had a massive head.
(laughing)
- That's very similar to another fact
that we've had a few years ago.
- This is sort of a sequel fact.
So for fans of the show,
you might have remembered in episode 265,
we delivered the jaw-breaking news that George Elliott
had a secret.
- Jaw-slapping news.
- Jaw-dropping news.
- Yeah, the jaw-breaking news.
- My facts are really aggressive.
- The FEMA snapping news coming to you.
So what was the news we delivered then?
- So the jaw-dropping news, no breakage,
is that 50 years after she died, for 50 years,
was the fact that she had a massive hand,
but that was a secret,
and the family denied her having it.
Anyway, so this was written in a book,
which was back in the 1840s.
So there was a biography that was put together
of George Elliott by a writer called Matilda Blind,
or Mathilda Blind.
I can't get the exact pronouncement.
- Could be Blinde as well.
- Could be what?
- Could be Blinde.
- It's probably Matilde Blinde.
- Matilde Blinde.
And so Matilde Blinde wrote a biography of her,
and she went round.
- She's South African.
- Matilde Blinde.
(laughing)
- She's a Kiwi.
- Sorry, she wrote an autobiography.
- She wrote a biography.
- Yeah, yeah.
- A biography, and during the research period,
she went to the farm where George Elliott used to live,
and there was a couple there called the Braes,
and it was Mrs. Cara Brae who told everyone
that she had this big hand.
However, when I was reading the book recently,
I also discovered that her husband became obsessed
with George Elliott because he noticed
that she also had a ginormous head.
- Was she just huge?
- Was she a giant?
- No, she wasn't that big,
but I think that's why they were astounded
by the size of her head.
She was taller than average, I think.
- Yeah, but you're not just dragging out
for when you don't have a fact next time,
'cause George Elliott had a massive elbow.
(laughing)
- It's quite possible we will be back
at 100 episodes time with another feature.
So Mrs. Brae wrote of her,
she said she had her head was massive,
her feature is powerful and rugged,
her mouth large but shapely,
the jaw singularly square for a woman,
unbreakable at the sound of a powerful fact, I imagine.
And so Mr. Brae said,
"I need to get your head turned into a cast,
"I need to take you to London,
"and so we can go and we can do phrenology on it
"and see how it's going to ring."
- So phrenology is where you look at the shape
of someone's head and you can tell their personality.
- Exactly, that's right.
It was very popular back in those days
when people started trying to work out
how the brain functioned and maybe certain bits of our brain.
- Well they couldn't do palm reading on her
'cause it'd be like going through Ella
and showing to Tom Perdue.
(laughing)
- It sounds amazing, the report.
So her head was, it was measured by a doctor
called James DeVille and then it was analyzed
by George Coombe who was one of the leaders
of the phrenological movement in the whole country.
So, you know--
- She would have needed a very big Coombe.
- Oh my gosh.
(laughing)
- And when he first saw the cast of her head,
Coombe, 'cause he was doing the analysis,
he was in the lab, I don't think I had a lab.
But anyway, he took the cast for a man's head,
that's how huge it was, 22 and a quarter inches.
- How much bigger are men's heads than women's heads?
- Statistically speaking.
- My head is five centimeters bigger than George Eliot's.
- But that's good, so this is just a bit bigger
than George Eliot's head.
- Yeah, yeah, so if anyone sees me in the pub
and you're like, oh that's James from the podcast,
imagine my head but five centimeters smaller
and that'll be George Eliot's head.
- It's like she's there.
- So this is actually, now your fact has become
kind of an insult to James 'cause what you're saying
is James Harkin has a really massive head.
- Compared to, but then men don't have larger heads
in general than women, I think.
- That's true, except for Andy, apparently.
- I'm just looking at Andy's head.
- Which Anna was saying at the top of the show.
- Yeah, I'm not very comfortable
with this line of inquiry.
Have you ever, if just listening at home,
have you ever seen a matchstick?
- Imagine the head was a bit smaller.
- It actually goes in from the match shaft.
- Australians, you might know them as dick heads,
those matches.
- That's right.
- Yeah, and funnily, at school,
a lot of the kids were Australian matchmen.
No, but so she was analysed by this phrenologist.
So it said that her temperament was nervous lymphatic,
which means active without endurance.
And lo and behold, it turned out that she worked
from 9 a.m. until 1 p.m.
So she was active, but didn't have endurance.
And intellectual and all of this.
- And she visited this guy over the years.
Kume, she didn't just have her head sent to him
via the casting.
She actually was in his presence a few times.
Well, that's what happened.
You would make the cast of the head
and you would send it to phrenologists
who were keen to sort of measure the bumps and so on.
- You just need to be very careful
that you do specify cast before someone soars
off their own head and turns it into a package.
- Okay, here's the thing I don't get.
What about your hair?
So if you've got a huge hair,
that will surely obscure the lumps and bumps on your head.
- But you feel the bumps.
You're not looking for the bumps.
- But this is one of the things that opponents
of phrenology said, you know, this is why it's nonsense.
So Oliver Wendell Holmes.
- Oh yeah.
- Wait, who was he again?
- I think he was a writer and a doctor, I think.
- He was a celeb, Victorian celeb.
- I just double checked 'cause in my head I went,
oh, Sherlock's brother.
And then I realized not a real answer.
- Definitely not, no, no, no.
But he wrote this.
He said, could you tell how much money there is in a safe
by kneading its knobs with your fingers
when a man fumbles about my forehead
and talks about the organs of individuality, size, et cetera.
I trust him as much as I should
if he felt the outside of my strongbox
and told me there was a $5 or a $10 bill
under this or that particular rivet, which is fair.
- Well, yeah.
- So even at the time, people did say--
- It was a long way of saying, this is bullshit.
- Yeah. - Isn't it?
- Yeah.
- Why is it keeping such small value bills in a safe box?
- Jesus, the point, maybe he's on holiday.
- Even back then.
- It's just the 1700s, that's worth a lot.
- See, is it 1800s, isn't it?
- I think so, yeah, yeah, that was his manner.
- The idea was that, you know, you could have,
your eyeballs almost pushed out even.
And this, in fact, was the first, you know,
the first instance of it.
So, phrenology was coined,
the idea of it was coined by Franz Joseph Gaul.
And he said that he came up with the idea,
or he realized it was the truth,
when he noticed that classmates in his class
could memorize these massive long bits of text.
And the ones that could memorize it had quite bulging eyes.
He said they had big salient eyes.
And he said, this must mean that the organ of verbal memory
is sitting right behind your eyes.
And if you're really gonna remember yourself,
it's pushing them out.
So I don't know if your eyes just drop out of your face
entirely if you've got a really good memory.
But then, yeah, he's the father of it, really, wasn't he?
- Yeah.
- The thing I liked about it, though,
is he wasn't this Gaul character.
He wasn't onto the wrong idea, really.
Because all he--
- No, that's all right.
I think-- - I think--
- Wait a sec.
- I think the way that--
- Well, I mean, it was definitely all bullshit.
- Yeah, yeah, absolutely, but, you know,
modern day brain understanding
is that certain bits of the brain
are compartmentalized to certain things,
like music and so on, and emotions,
and right-thinking, left-thinking, and all that.
- He didn't come up with that idea.
So someone else had come up with that idea,
and he thought, oh, well, what if I took that idea
and then made the bump thing a thing?
- Right, I could just see that.
If I was around at that time,
I definitely would have believed it.
It just sounds so obviously.
- Yeah, well, obviously, yeah.
- I think you would have as well.
- Yeah, you would.
- I mean, it's just quite--
- I think I wouldn't.
- It's very hard to put yourself in there.
- My organ of credulousness is tiny, actually.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- Phrenology is basically astrology, isn't it?
Or it was sort of a version of astrology
in that it seemed to tell people things
that were vague enough that they could go,
yeah, that sounds exactly like me.
- Barnum statements.
- It mostly wasn't, the reports you got
from a phrenologist were very rarely.
You're a wanker.
It was always, oh, you've got a nice organ over there,
some organ there, and I don't think,
I don't think they've often said,
"You've got the organ of the killer."
- No, but they told everyone else.
Actually, they did.
- But it was used to suggest that other races were lower.
It was used in a very racist sense.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And people believed it.
Yeah, eugenicists.
- To be honest, it was mostly used
to whatever your belief was.
- Yeah.
- It was used to kind of strengthen that.
So for instance, there was a woman called Mrs. Hamilton.
She was known as, she was from Ayrshire,
and she would go around talking about phrenology.
But she said that because the bumps on a woman's head
were generally the same as the bumps on a man's head,
this proved that women had exactly the same
intellectual capacity as men's.
And she went around saying,
"Yeah, well, you know, this proves feminism."
See, I knew it was bullshit,
but that is the nail in the coffin of phrenology there,
isn't it?
(laughing)
What the hell's the odd about?
Alderman got phrenologized.
John James Alderman, the big bird man,
did all the bird sketches and stuff.
And actually, he was huge.
- He wasn't a bird man.
He was a man who studied birds.
- He's a man who studied birds.
- Easily, yeah.
- The naturalist who was sort of the leading authority
on birds that time,
and his books were beautiful drawings.
And he wrote in his diary,
"I was astounded when I had my reading,
'cause they said that I must be a strong and constant lover.
An affectionate father,
I would have made a great general
that I was extraordinarily generous.
I know all these to be facts,
so I'm amazed that they discovered them."
(laughing)
- I'm amazed at the person who you're paying
to do your phrenology said,
"Oh, it apparently says you're very generous."
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- You guys remember Aaron Burr?
- Oh, Burr and Hamilton.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Of musical fame.
- Vice President of America.
- Well, Aaron Burr was cast.
His head was cast, but after his death.
- Ah, okay.
- And they found that he had lots of secretiveness
and destructiveness.
- Did he die in the duel?
- No.
- No, he lived, he survived the duel
and then ran away, I think.
- Yeah, he died on his deathbed many, many years ago.
(laughing)
- Oh, he died on his deathbed.
- That was such a mistake.
- He should never have gone there.
- He didn't die on the duel.
- When you're in John Lewis,
don't pick the deathbed.
- Hi, I'm looking for a deathbed.
- Yeah, are you sure?
(laughing)
- Some celebrity fans, just quickly?
- Oh, yeah.
- Oh, modern day ones?
- No.
(laughing)
- Not Kim Kardashian or...
- No, Arthur Conan Doyle?
- Yeah, of course.
- I mean, Arthur Conan Doyle, absolutely everything.
- I wish I'd been friends with him.
The pranking you could have got
down Arthur Conan Doyle, that's been epic.
(laughing)
- Queen Victoria as well, and Prince Albert.
They had studies done by George Cuny.
- How do you say, Andy?
When you say some celebrities,
I thank God you're not bucking Celebrity Love Island.
(laughing)
Well, I've got as Queen Victoria and...
- You'd want to see it.
- Dead.
(laughing)
- Was there a deathbed in there?
- Shit, love the deathbed.
Anyway, they appointed him.
- Barack Obama?
- Oh, find someone living for I don't see.
- End that sentence, James.
- Yeah, sorry, he's into...
- No, no, you don't let me finish my sentence.
- Oh, sorry, okay.
- Barack Obama is a subject
of an incredibly weird book
called The Phrenology of Barack Obama.
It's a self-published book.
- No.
- By a guy called Bensa Magos.
And apparently he looked at a mysterious headscar
on Obama's head that the mass media refuses to discuss.
(laughing)
And according to him,
this is evidence that Obama once had a horn
and leads ultimately to the satanic endgame revealed
by the demon horn of Mollock.
- Oh, okay.
- So...
- I can't believe the Guardian isn't reporting on this.
- That's outrageous.
- It feels like he's missed the boat
'cause he just served two terms
and then left office in an orderly fashion.
- What a taste.
- Like, what's Mollock's endgame here?
(laughing)
- Maybe it took a while to find a publisher, who knows?
- Wow.
- I'm definitely buying it, by the way.
(laughing)
- Sounds awesome.
- Yeah, this guy, Coom,
just going back to the casting of True Celebrities.
He did very famous people.
He did Prince Albert's head.
So George Eliot was having her head done
by the guy that did Prince Albert.
He did William Blake as well.
- Ooh.
- Or rather, he studied,
it was someone else who Coom didn't do it.
It was the, there was a different person, wasn't it?
Yeah, James DeVille.
But where are these casts?
Where's George Eliot's head?
- This room, actually, is inside of the cast.
- They used it to the Statue of Liberty.
(laughing)
- Such a good ending for the movie.
- What a movie, for the phrenology movie.
It's like, they never knew where it was.
Whip pan out to New York.
- And then just winks.
- Yes, yes.
Mount Rushmore.
Pour their hands.
- Gives a little thumbs up with his massive hand.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that the chef
who cooked for Lord's Cricketers on match days
for 35 years was once asked to limit their meals
to five courses, and she refused.
(laughing)
So this was a woman called Nancy Doyle,
and she, yeah, she was the tea lady at Lord's
for 35 years, until 1996, I think she retired.
And she liked to make them large, large meals.
So obviously in cricket, you've got meals codified,
and you have to take your lunch break.
It's in the rules.
- It's so amazing that they're actually
in the rules of cricket, it says,
"Unless the umpires and captains together
"agreter alter it, lunch shall be taken at the agreed time."
It's actually in the rules that you have to have lunch.
- And the captains of each team decide
on what time lunch is happening,
how long or-- - And the umpire, yeah.
- I mean, what other sport has a conversation like that
when you're about to flick the coin
for who bats first or whatever, you know?
By the way, what time--
- When are we having lunch?
(laughing)
- What are we having?
Well, we're having a roast today.
(laughing)
- How are we, you guys?
- So Mrs. Doyle.
- Mrs. Doyle, she, well, her typical menu,
it seemed to be, for lunch you'd have soup,
then a starter, then a roast.
(laughing)
Well, you've got to, 'cause you've got to moisten
your palate, I suppose. - Absolutely, yeah.
- Then a starter, then roast meat and potatoes.
And she also served chips and vegetables.
It's quite hard to know.
This was just on an example list
that I think Mike Brealy gave of what she'd serve up.
Chips and vegetables, then a dessert, then a cheese board.
Then you get back onto plate.
But of course, in cricket, every two hours,
'cause although they decide when you have meals,
it's pretty much every two hours is the general rules.
Roughly, for when you eat.
So two hours later, you get back in,
and she's made you a huge cake.
(laughing)
And there you go.
So there was this moment where Mike Brealy said,
in the '70s-- - It's Mike Brealy who was--
- Mike Brealy was the England captain at the time.
He said to her, "Do you know what?
"I don't know if it's good for the game.
"The guys can't stand up after lunch."
And she replied, so she, you know, he was like,
"Could we possibly make the meals a bit lighter?"
And she said, "But in an Irish accent,
"tell you what, Michael, I won't tell you how to feckin' bat
"and you don't tell me how to feckin' cook, okay?"
- Amazing, wow.
- And that was it, and she was apparently terrifying.
Someone called her a small yet volcanic,
so I think he didn't ask again.
- She also couldn't cook.
I mean, it's in the case-- (laughing)
No, it's not one of her whatsoever,
but she said she'd never read a cookbook.
She didn't use weighing scales,
and she didn't follow recipes.
- But that shows having a natural affinity to cooking.
- Her organ of cooking was absolutely massive.
(laughing)
- She's taught by nuns, wasn't she?
Like, she did get taught, yeah.
She just didn't--
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- I think being able to cook without a recipe is--
- No, that is the mark of quality.
I found a bit of a scandal researching this fact.
- Oh yeah, okay.
- I thought tea in cricket was the most English thing.
- Right.
- It's not English, it's Australian.
- No.
- It was introduced by Australia.
It was imported.
Australia started doing this in about the 1880s,
and then a captain called Joe Darling
brought it over--
- T Darling?
- The T Darling in 1899.
But even then, it was brought onto the field.
So, like, they would bring you a cup of tea
where you stood, and there were photos of England players
just standing around with waitresses,
you know, just bringing them a tea trolley, basically.
And it wasn't standard until about 1905
that players went off and had their tea,
so it was an Aussie thing.
- Very cool.
- I don't know about that.
- You were saying about how Nancy can't cook, Andy.
She can't cook curries.
That is one thing.
- She can't cook anything anymore 'cause she is dead.
- Yes, sorry.
- She can't cook curries.
- Death bed bed?
It was a, what kind of death bed?
- It was a death bed thing, yeah.
Another cause of death, death bed.
- No, she couldn't cook curries, I should have said.
Because during tests, when England's playing
people like India, Pakistan, Sri Lanka,
they want to have food which they had at home,
and so they want to have curries,
and she couldn't cook them,
and so she brought her daughter, Jeanette,
and Jeanette, who was a nurse,
was apparently a brilliant curry maker,
so she would come in and make the curries.
- I love that.
- Just get professional cooks, guys.
It's so weird.
- No, no, no.
- Professional cook.
She was a nurse.
- Get a nurse who might have left some really ill people
to die.
- I'm just gonna leave these death beds, I'll be fine.
Curries have been a problem in the past
for English cricketers, so when they do big tours
of India and Pakistan, and in the '70s and '80s,
when curry was less common here,
and people weren't used to eating it,
a lot of the players found it quite difficult,
and Alex Stewart, in fact, who was a player in the '80s,
said that he, basically, before they were doing
a tour of India, him and Jack Russell,
who, well, I hadn't heard of Jack Russell,
but they couldn't hack the Indian food,
and so before they'd fly out to Pakistan,
they said they'd do a trip to Tesco,
and they'd just buy,
Alec would buy 43 chicken breasts,
43 days worth of mashed potatoes,
and 43 days worth of broccoli,
and every day he'd just make himself chicken breasts,
broccoli, mashed potatoes.
- Did he say it'd go into India?
- Yeah. - Quite a hot country.
Are these chicken breasts refrigerated,
or are they just loose in his case?
- That is horrible.
It just went into the separating chicken case.
- Look, I think they probably
had some kind of refrigeration technology.
- I don't know if we ever mentioned this on the podcast,
that when the Beatles went to India
to see the Maharaja, no, not the Maharaja,
the Guru, wasn't it? - The Guru, yeah.
- They went to see their Guru,
who was gonna teach them transcendental meditation
and how to free their minds and all of this.
And Ringo Starr took a suitcase of baked beans.
- Yeah. - Did we say that?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Great, great, great.
- Well, that's 'cause he had digestion problems
from childhood when he was hospitalized
and nearly died in hospital.
- Wow. - Whoa.
- Just getting the facts in.
- Whereas Alex Stewart was just being a bit of a fool,
which in fact, Atherton wrote in his autobiography,
and I feel like this might cause some tension
with your teammate.
So Atherton was in captain work, played with Stewart,
said, "Alex Stewart has a narrow focus on sport and life.
I do wonder," and he said this of his meal choices in India,
"I do wonder whether he'll look back with regret
at some of the missed opportunities
that touring life offers." - Wow.
- But you could say the same about me when we go on tour.
- That's true. - And I'm sure you all three do.
I don't hear you, though, because it's after 9 p.m.
and I'm in bed.
- You do have a lot of courses on your breakfast,
everyone, don't you? - Oh my God, yes you do.
- That's true, but I have brought them all from home
and I've stopped them in the suitcase.
I've just brought 350 waffles.
- I went to a cricket match once
and it was sponsored by Sauri Maltloaf.
- Oh, lovely. - Yeah, delicious.
- And so there was a guy there
and he was handing out free bits of Maltloaf to everyone.
But no one really likes Maltloaf
and everyone likes beer watching like a shirt cricket.
And so everyone just started throwing Maltloaf at him.
- Oh my God.
- And he refused to give any more Maltloaf to anyone
and everyone got really upset
because they wouldn't give him any Maltloaf.
- But how come they only wanted it
to throw at the guy and hang it up?
If he removes himself, the loop closes.
- Well, he did exactly the right thing
as far as I'm concerned.
But the 20,000 people in Old Trafford
did not see it the same way.
- I love Maltloaf.
I'd have been, I'd have been grubbing around
drinking it up with my big net standing near him.
- What is it?
I don't think I've had it.
- It's absolutely delicious.
We're not sponsored this week by Maltloaf,
but I do really, sorry, if you're listening.
It's a kind of fruity bread, basically.
- Yeah, it's very delicious.
- Although I think any beer drinker worth his salt,
if he loves beer that much,
can turn a Maltloaf into a beer.
It's got malt in it, surely.
- You blend that.
- And a cricket match over five days.
Eventually it's gonna ferment.
- Exactly.
Just on a sort of eating and drinking in cricket
and drinking specifically,
there's a guy, a cricket called Gary Sobers,
and I want you to remember that.
- Oh, I see why we're going here.
- That's where the work out
which road you're gonna go down now.
- Almost a sentence person.
- You need up to be, he's my son.
- Yeah, if he married, if he married in double barrel
with Helen up.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
Anyway, Gary Sobers,
he batted his last century while drunk.
- And not even just a bit tipsy.
This sounds like a mad experience.
So he was playing at Lord's.
He played for the West Indies
and he'd been out clubbing until nine in the morning.
(laughing)
And he was batting that day
and he was going straight into bat.
So he got in at nine.
He's completely hammered
and drank, solidly drinking for, you know, 12 hours straight.
He batted amazingly well.
He hit 132, extraordinary.
But then begged to be taken off
'cause he said suddenly he sort of started to sober up.
- He started to come down.
- Solidly up to the name of the come down
and the sobering up and the hangover.
So he was taken off with a stomach complaint
after batting 132.
And then he was brought off,
but felt quite bad about it.
And so ended up being apparently,
according to him, revived
for the couple of large port and brandies.
- Oh my God.
- I didn't know.
- Port and brandy.
I've not heard of that as a drink.
- No.
- It's not like a very old fashioned Jagerbomb basically.
(laughing)
- I think that was what it was.
- Yeah.
- Can you come back onto cricket?
I thought once you got off the--
- That's sick.
- Yeah.
- Oh, okay.
- I didn't know that.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So he returned.
He returned to hit 150, not out,
and then the England retired.
- Wow.
- What if the drinking still goes up?
W.G. Grace, for example.
So he was around in the late 1800s.
His choice of drink during matches
was if he was coming off,
he would drink champagne during the match
all the way through.
And at lunch, he would have whiskey as his choice of drink.
So he was bladded the whole time
that he was playing.
Or, you know, comfortably marry as opposed to drunk.
I wonder if that still happens.
- Of course it doesn't.
And I think this is one of the great tragedies
of all sports, 'cause of course it doesn't,
'cause they've all changed in the last 30 years
so dramatically.
Like anything you watch, tennis, football, cricket.
- None of them are pissed.
(laughing)
- It's ridiculous.
- It's so cold sober and they're eating these crazy diets.
I think there should be a rule that says
no professional sportspeople are allowed to eat anything
outside of what they would normally eat or drink.
And then you just have to play like that,
which is basically how they did it
until the 70s or 80s, isn't it?
- Agassi won quite seminal match in his career
with a giant hangover from the night before.
And he played so well with the hangover
that he did think, am I gonna have to do this
for every match?
- Wow.
- This is so good.
- And it's kind of like, what's the chop?
The same bolt.
Who, at the Beijing Olympics, I think, 2008,
he pretty much only had chicken nuggets.
- Yeah, 'cause I didn't think he trusted
the local cuisine to the rest of the thing.
- He brought them all.
He brought 43 days work and they were pretty off by the end.
- There are two cricketers for India
called Rishabh Pant and Ishan Kisham.
And when they get together, they just eat any old crap.
And apparently their favorite thing is they get a bun,
they put some chocolate ice cream on the bread,
and then they put Nando sauce on top of that,
and then they put a piece of chicken on top of that,
and they eat it, and they reckon if you eat that,
it guarantees you're gonna score runs the next day.
- Right. - Wow.
- Has anyone put it to a scientific testing,
rigorous testing process?
- These are great cricketers, you know?
- Okay, yeah.
- It's two of the best in the world.
- Yeah, Ash, they're doing what you want, Anna.
They're just combining all the unhealthy foods into one meal.
- Like, I'm very hard to please, yeah, yeah.
Get on them.
- But Sri Lankan cricketers have been banned
from eating biscuits this a few years ago, actually.
But they were losing games,
and the government decided to get involved,
and the Sri Lankan government gave them an ultimatum
and said, "Start winning matches,
"or we're gonna get rid of your biscuits."
And they didn't win matches, and they lost their biscuits.
- No.
- And Lassith Malinga, who's a really famous bowler,
he talked about the comments of the sports minister
and said, "What does a monkey know
"about a parrot's nesting hollow?"
- What an amazing burn.
- Is that so? - That's a sick bit of sledging.
- I just love the idea of one of them going into a shop
trying to buy some biscuits,
and the shopkeeper looking under the counter
where the entire squad's photos are up.
- To be honest, if Lassith Malinga is very clear
what he looks like, he's...
- Okay, he's distinctive looking.
- Very distinctive.
There's no way he got a biscuit in the whole country.
(laughing)
- Loaturing outside a shop asking for a 10-year-old,
"What do I mean?
"Couldn't get me some garibaldies, could you please?"
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three,
and that is Andy.
- My fact is that Northern Ireland
contains the world's only upside-down lighthouse.
(laughing)
- How soon was that an architectural cock up?
- Or maybe to scare moles away from the...
- Exactly, a massive mole problem, aquatic moles,
and no, it is so weird, 'cause genuinely,
it's not just a low, it's got a tower,
but the tower is above the light.
- But it's just for anyone who's picturing in their head
a lighthouse that's been flipped upside down.
It's unfortunately not at all like that,
it is in no way that...
- I'm sorry, it is exactly that.
- Andy, explain exactly what it is.
We'll see if it's exactly what Dan thinks it is.
- It's on an island called Rathland,
which is off the coast of Northern Ireland,
and the lighthouse was built into the cliff face
at the island's edge, and they wanted a lighthouse
'cause they wanted to warn shipping about the island,
and its presence, but the problem is,
the island is often covered in fog.
It's covered in fog, so if you were to have the lighthouse
installed on the cliffs at the bottom of the cliffs,
and the light up at the top of the cliffs,
the light would be lost in the fog.
So they built the tower, which is where all the supplies
are kept, and the stalls, and the spare lenses
for the light bulb, and all of this stuff,
but the actual light itself is at the bottom of the cliffs,
and that's the thing that means it can be seen more.
- So it's like they've sliced the top off a lighthouse,
and then put it down in front of the rest of the lighthouse.
- Exactly.
- Or have they put it all in reverse order?
- No, you have to climb down the stairs,
upside down, together, yeah.
- Yeah, so it's sort of a little,
it's sitting in front of the tower,
it's not directly underneath the tower.
- So it's a lighthouse, and the bulb is at the bottom,
not at the top, it's an upside down lighthouse.
- So it's not like in the daytime,
it makes a dark area.
(laughing)
- That's an inside out lighthouse.
- Yeah, that's okay, sorry, yeah.
I always go the next step.
And it's just a very cool thing.
And it was built in about 1912, I think,
so it's 110 years old now.
And also, I read this about Rathland Island,
I can't, I don't know if it's true,
that it's the island where Robert the Bruce went
after a battle, and it's where he saw the useless spider.
- That is true, well, the fact that,
whether that happened or not,
it's definitely said to have happened on Rathland,
said to have happened in a cave
underneath the lighthouse, but not that lighthouse.
(laughing)
- There's an east lighthouse and a west lighthouse,
and the Robert the Bruce one is the other one.
- Okay, okay.
- So the story is, isn't it that he was in a,
yeah, a Scottish guy, he's gone away
from where the battles are, he's sat down,
he's worried, there's a spider there,
the spider keeps trying to make a web,
keeps trying to jump over, keeps failing,
and eventually he makes it and he thinks,
if at first you don't see, try, try again,
and he goes back and gets dashed on the rocks
because of this useless lighthouse,
the lights at the bottom.
They also have fog bells sometimes, lighthouses,
'cause it is a problem, a lot,
that you can't see a lighthouse if it's obscured by fog,
and it sounds like they haven't really cracked it,
so they have bells, which A is a lighthouse keeper,
I suppose, or you had to in the olden days
before everything was automated,
you had to just ring them kind of constantly,
so I think you'd ring them about two rings
every 15 seconds in fog to let ships know
that you were there, and it only traveled about 100 meters,
so I think the light from whitehouses
can travel many, many kilometers, can't it?
Seven, eight, nine, more than that, kilometers,
but it couldn't travel that far,
and you could wind them up the bells,
so you'd wind them up really, really, really far,
and then it could, as it unwound, like a clock,
it could do 10,000 strikes.
- Wow, cool. - That's awesome, man.
- Yeah, the Rathland Island fog signal
can be heard 20 miles away.
- So they've got an audio signal as well?
- Yeah, yeah, they have a fog signal too, yeah, yeah.
It's pretty cool, they're very cool places, lighthouses.
You know the beautiful lighthouse lens that you see,
which looks almost like a chandelier,
it's got loads of cut faces, and sides, and edges,
and it's incredibly complicated,
and it looks, you know, it's not just a big lamp.
That is the creation of a guy called
Augustin Jean Fresnel, who was, by the way,
the one who realized that light is a transverse wave.
Big deal guy. - Or is it, though?
- Oh, okay. - So that's just
a whole separate base. - I don't think
we've got time to get into that, yeah, you're right.
- But basically, the lenses would have been incredibly heavy
if you just made a single lens.
So he created this clever lens, which can be much thinner,
but it has dozens of prisms, and they all focus the light,
so you do get a beam using much less glass.
But the really cool thing about those heavy,
great lenses at the top, is they were created to float.
- Mercury. - And they float,
oh, mercury, they float in this mercury bath,
and it's so cool, 'cause mercury's so dense,
it's 14 times denser than water,
and if you drop a lump of solid steel into mercury,
it will float, and float really high up in it.
And so the whole lighthouse top was just floating
on this gruel. - Seems quite dangerous.
- So dangerous. - Yeah.
- Don't call it a bath, if you're in that house with kids,
they'll try and bath in that as well.
- What do you think the US Coast Guard's only lighthouse keeper
has in common with the English female cricketer
who has the highest ever score in the test match?
- Long arms.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so she could change the light bulb.
- Change the bulb, how many lighthouse keepers does it take?
Yeah, without going upstairs, yeah.
- Obviously as a cricketer, it's good to have long arms,
don't you? - You need long arms, don't you?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - It's not that though.
- I think-- - What are they having?
Okay, what are they having?
Wait, wait, the US only lighthouse keeper on the--
- The US Coast Guard's only lighthouse keeper.
- I would guess you're not gonna guess it.
If it's the answer, I think,
I reckon you're not gonna guess it,
unless you know we're on both of them.
- So this could be one of those long games,
like the other day, what was it the other day we had?
- Oh my god, which artist?
- Bloody stained glass arches game again.
- This is gonna last us way longer than that.
- Red and white. - Red and white.
- She doesn't live in a lighthouse.
- She does live in a lighthouse.
- Red and white. - But she lives in a lighthouse.
- But actually, we don't know that too.
Do you know where she lives?
- Hang on, hang on, I do know this.
Okay, cricketers wear white, don't they?
- Oh, yeah.
- And the ball is red.
Now, what are the typical colors of a lighthouse?
They're red and white.
- Okay, so take that knowledge.
- Yeah.
- And forget about it.
(laughing)
I try to think of something else.
- Okay, the Coast Guard surname is Lighthouse
and her surname is Coast Guard.
- You're so close.
They have very similar surnames.
- Okay.
- Think of something that's white.
Something else that's white.
- You know the answer?
- Yeah.
- Cocaine, they're both called cocaine.
Jessica Cocaine.
- Oh, yeah.
The US Coast Guard's only lighthouse keeper
is called Sally Snowman and the highest score ever
by an English female cricketer in a test match
was by Betty Snowball.
(laughing)
- Oh my God.
So it's not even something they've got in common.
It's just something quite similar.
- We've got the word snow.
(laughing)
- Oh my God.
- I did.
I'd count that.
(laughing)
- That's a real fair question.
- That's a million dollar question.
(laughing)
That's like, who would know that?
- James, what can my phone a friend be, James?
(laughing)
- I'm there going, option B please.
Red and white is the thing that links them.
(laughing)
- She's about to retire Sally Snowman.
- Has she?
- Yeah, last year I think.
- Which one, she, the coast guard?
- The lighthouse keeper.
- Right.
- Yeah, yeah.
- No more walking in the air for her.
(laughing)
'Cause when you're at the top of the lighthouse
it must feel like you're floating in the moonlit sky.
- Yeah, that's good.
I wonder if she blasted that out in times of fog.
You could hear her walking in the air.
- And abducted boys at night, yes.
- And now all that's left in that lighthouse
is a solitary carrot.
(laughing)
- Did you know that I am a member
of the Association of Lighthouse Keepers?
- Are you?
- Did you join it just for this episode?
- I joined it yesterday.
- Yep.
(laughing)
- Really?
- I gotta say.
- ALK.
- You an alcoholic.
- I am.
And it's fun.
- Have you got a posting yet?
Do we have to do a podcast from Lighthouse?
(laughing)
- But you don't have to be a lighthouse keeper to join.
That's the wonderful thing.
- Evidently if you join.
Unless you've also got a job as a lighthouse keeper
just to join.
- Lots of news guys.
No, but it's really good.
Just a quick shout out to them.
It's very reasonable price for a year's membership.
And I think you might get a sticker for your car.
- Anything else you get for it?
- You get their quarterly journal, Lamp.
- Right.
- And I've read a bit of it.
I've read a sample online.
It's really good.
- Is it?
What are they?
Is it largely just the latest in lighthouse news?
- Shining a light on lighthouse news.
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
They don't do expo days or anything like that.
But it's just lots of news from the lighthouse community.
And you know.
- You've been quite cagey about how much it was.
But what is a reasonable price to pay?
- Also, can I ask what is the sticker?
Is it like my other car?
- It's a lifeline.
(all laughing)
- My other headlamp is a Fresnel lens.
- How much was it?
- Well, I don't want to say in flash,
but it was 18 pounds for a year.
- 18 pounds for one choke and we might cut out.
(all laughing)
- They almost certainly will get that.
I know.
- I'm worried that this is going to take over your life
gradually.
And when you quit the podcast in five years,
this is the moment we should have known.
- Wow, you think I'm going to last five more years
on this show?
I've incredibly left it.
(all laughing)
- I'll just have one weird lighthouse.
One of my favorite lighthouses is,
I think basically an unnecessary lighthouse.
It's the lighthouse in Machias Seal Island.
So this is--
- Machias Seal.
- Machias, M-A-C-H-I-A-S.
- Where's that?
- It's a tiny little island just between the U.S.
and Canada, and it's positioning is crucial because--
- It's a land border, most of that, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- U.S. and Canada?
- Famously.
- It's on like, if you sort of continue the border,
basically, it's in the Atlantic Ocean,
a sort of--
- Between Maine and--
- Exactly, between Maine and New Brunswick.
And so it's disputed,
'cause both countries want ownership
of this tiny uninhabited island.
I think because you can claim fishing rights
around a certain circumference of it,
if you do claim it.
So it's been argued over since 1832,
and Canada, to stake its own claim for the last 25 years,
has just kept a lighthouse keeper in a lighthouse
on there, to stamp its identity on the island.
And it's this guy called Ralph Eldridge.
- Same guy?
- It's been the same guy for 25 years, yeah.
It's actually two guys, and they alternate
one month from one month off.
- Okay.
- But they're fun guys.
I read an interview with Ralph a couple of years ago
where the interviewer said, 'cause it's just him,
the interviewer said, "Are you a lonely person, Ralph?"
And he said, "Lone is the wrong word.
"Independent is better.
"Let's say I like me best of all."
And then the interviewer just goes,
"Divorced, Ralph?
"Yes."
(all laughing)
- There was a bit of lighthouse news this year,
so you might be seeing it in Lamp later on.
- Great.
- In your quarters.
- At least six months time.
(all laughing)
- Who, what time was right?
- And that was, there was a film festival
which took place in a lighthouse this year.
- I know.
- It was a Swedish film festival,
the Gotterborg Film Festival.
And 60 movies were played in total at this festival,
and they were played entirely to one human.
- Did they use the light from the lighthouse?
- As a projector.
- Did you have to keep walking around?
(all laughing)
- There were 19 shipwrecks in it.
- The sailors were so entranced,
watching Back to the Future 3.
- That's so cool.
- Yeah.
- Was it a particular kind of film,
as in was there a genre?
- No, no, no.
- There was that film recently with Robert Pattinson.
- Yes.
- The lighthouse.
- And they played two lighthouse keepers who were going mad.
Yeah, yeah.
- No, no, it's a collection of independent film making.
- Okay.
- Yeah, so every kind of genre.
- It sounds like a horror film festival.
You know, we're gonna trap you in the lighthouse
and show you 60 films.
- Well, no, it was a COVID thing that happened.
And so they couldn't put the festival on as they wanted to.
And actually, sorry, I slightly got it wrong.
So it might've already been in a issue of lamp.
This was 2021.
So you might've missed out on the story just.
- I'm sure you can get back issues.
(all laughing)
So yeah, the idea was they were gonna have to go online
and just stream it online for the entire.
- That's literally the opposite of playing it to one person.
That's playing it to everyone with internet access.
- Yeah, but for one thing they wanted to do
was make it special.
And so they did a competition.
12,000 people applied for it.
And this one person, Lisa Enthroth, won it.
And so she got sent by boat to this island.
They took away all of her electronics.
She had just a little iPad.
- It's a Salica horror film.
There was one person on the island
who was checking on her once a day
just to make sure that she was okay.
- The murderer, as he's always known, yes.
- And she was there for a week, watching these 60 films.
- So she had to watch about nine films a day,
which was presumably about 18 hours.
She's under-slapped.
- She hasn't had anything better to do.
- No, it's true.
- Did she have to watch them?
Did she get tested on them afterwards?
- The creepy caretaker of the island
will do a little film quiz after every single one.
- And who played the butler?
What does the cricketer, the better snowball,
have in common?
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that in 2007,
a Japanese arm wrestling arcade machine was recalled
when it broke three players' arms.
(laughing)
Amazing.
- See, I'm amazed it wasn't recalled
after breaking one player's arm.
- Yeah?
- No, they thought, let's let it break a few bodies first.
- No, I think they happened, all the breaks happened
in a short enough time that they couldn't recall it
before they-
- It's an afternoon at the arcade that must have been.
You know, ringing the third ambulance.
Yeah, amazingly.
Actually, we are gonna contact the manufacturers now, yes.
- Possibly three kids who are holding it at the same time
trying to beat the big boss.
- That's a good idea.
- Three snaps.
- They're all in the same trench coat
standing on each other's shoulders.
- I'm afraid you've lost the arm,
but we have replaced it with one of these claw grapples.
(laughing)
- With which you won't be able to grab anything at all.
- Just try and have your breakfast every morning.
You just, you grab the spoon
and then just drop it before it gets to your mouth.
No, so this is a company called Atlas
and the game was called Arm Spirit.
And what they said, this was in an article from the BBC,
is that probably the players got a bit overexcited
and maybe they twisted their arms in a slightly weird way
'cause the game was, it was like a fake arm
and then you would grab hold of the fake arm
and you would play an arm wrestling game against it.
And they were like 10 levels
and it went from the easiest level, which was a French maid.
- Okay.
- Famously weak, there's a lot of lugging to do
when you're a French maid.
Some of those dusters are extremely heavy with all feathers.
- Look at George Eliot, that's where she got her hand from.
Milk and all them cows.
- I don't, French maid is not the same as like a cow maid.
- Milk maid.
(laughing)
- French milk maids don't wear the little lacy outfit.
- They're quite different.
If you go to a summer's elas for a milk-made outfit,
(laughing)
do you mean French maid?
No, no.
(laughing)
- That makes sense.
- Or something like a milk and cow.
- Yeah, yeah.
- After the French maid,
you might fight against a drunken martial arts master,
a Chihuahua dog and the final is against
a professional arm wrestler.
And it gets harder and harder each time.
So in the end--
- That's not the order I would put that in.
You're saying a Chihuahua dog
is better at arm wrestling than a drunken martial arts master.
- Doesn't seem that way, does it?
- How drunken, yeah, yeah.
- If he's unconscious, then possibly.
(laughing)
- I can see though how an arm breakage might happen
based on a video that I watched on YouTube.
There's lots of videos where you can see people playing,
not this game, not Arm Spirit,
but there's another game called Over the Top.
And very similar.
I think it's exactly the same game, basically.
- I think that's--
- Also, sorry, just for legal reasons,
probably not exactly the same.
- Yes, probably.
There's no Chihuahua, for example, over the top.
And so you've got the big bulky hand there,
and I watched a video of a super strong guy
take on the final boss, and he was holding it,
and my god, he was like really going for it.
And someone leans over next to him and says,
"Ah, when I tried to beat the big box,
"I totally cheated, I lent in,
"I got my arms underneath it, I went."
So I can imagine, by manipulation of your body
in weird ways to try and beat it,
a snap might occur when you buckle.
- No, no, I can see that, yeah, yeah.
- Isn't Over the Top as a move, isn't it, in arm wrestling?
- It's where you kind of twist your wrist a little bit.
- Oh, I thought it was where you put your fingers
over the top of their hand.
But they're probably meant to be anyway.
If they're holding your whole hand in their hand,
you're not going to do very well.
(laughing)
- Okay, so can I just check with--
- There are moves, there are proper moves in arm wrestling.
There are sort of, I think,
a couple of dozen different techniques.
As in, if you're watching with an expert of the game,
they'll say, "Ah, he's trying the French defense now,"
or whatever.
(laughing)
- He's wearing a French made outfit.
- What were you going to say, Anna?
- I was just going to establish it was the kids' fault.
That seems to be where we're landing on this.
The company said they were playing it in a weird way.
- Who do we think is likely to sue?
I think it's the question we need to answer.
- I think there was no, as far as I could see,
I couldn't see any later news stories
that explained whether anyone had sued anyone.
- I feel like some parents got some real,
large quantities of cash behind the scenes for that.
- I don't know what that happened on that.
- But I wouldn't like to comment.
But arm breakage does happen in arm wrestling.
- relatively regularly.
Apparently this is according to John Jenk,
who is the Guinness World Records greatest arm wrestler
of all time.
He says that the people who break their arms
tend to be beginners because you get incredibly strong
when you're starting out arm wrestling,
but you haven't actually built up kind of the bone
and tendon resilience.
So you don't know your own strength.
You break your own arm.
He literally, you push so, so, so hard
that your bone just snaps.
And it's really horrible.
There was a match in Cumbria in 2018.
It was like a farmers event.
And there were various kind of fun things,
like a little fairground ride or a little, you know,
shoot the tail of the donkey or whatever.
They do those things and is that what they do?
- Yeah, it's not really.
- Welcome to Anna's Fair.
- Okay, look, this was nothing like my fantasy fair.
This was just a normal fair.
There was an arm wrestling contest.
A 20 year old girl broke her arm incredibly badly.
It sounds like she was resting another girl.
It was in a huge amount of pain.
Her opponent fainted,
which I can really imagine doing,
if you're arm wrestling someone,
you know when you see one of those snappages
that were at a sudden right angle to the arm.
So her opponent fainted and then they interviewed,
I think this was on the BBC,
they interviewed the paramedic, Andrew Dickinson,
who said, this is what happened, the opponent fainted,
but he also added, the rest of the day
was absolutely fantastic.
It ended in a dance where 600 people attended
and we were on site until 1.30 in the morning.
- Is that good paramedicking?
- I guess if you're the onsite paramedic,
if you were summoned to take her to hospital,
it's very bad paramedicking.
- It's not clear.
- They're starting the dance now.
Would you mind if we just kept the engine running
a little bit longer?
So I was, I always wonder,
'cause I'm not actually a professional arm wrestler myself.
- No. - No, no, no.
I'm a member of the association.
(all laughing)
- Look at the magazine.
- Yeah, slam.
- It's impossible to pick it up.
(all laughing)
But I thought that the rule was
that you couldn't hold the table.
- Right. - Okay.
- Actually, in the professional game,
they install pegs in the table for you to hang on to.
- Yeah. - Yes.
- So it's all about the rest of your body as well.
- Do you think? - Yes.
- I can believe it.
- Yeah, I thought it was just about your arm.
- Am I right?
I've got an old memory of you, James,
of you and me hanging out and you saying to me,
"I have an unbeatable technique."
- I do, yeah. - And then we did it
and you almost broke my arm, basically, in my attempt to,
so you know how to not be facing.
- I do, but I have to really,
you know, I have to trick you into position, basically.
- So why was upside down?
- Okay. (all laughing)
- There's a way, basically, if I was to arm wrestle you
and we kept the table on my right-hand side
and your left-hand side,
and we arm wrestled on that table,
then I would be pulling with my arm
and you'd be pushing with your arm
and the pulling muscle is way stronger
than the pushing muscle, so you could beat anyone.
Then it's like a pub trick
where you can win a pint of something, that kind of thing.
- Yes. - But if you got any brains
on you, you insist, surely you do it over a table, right?
- Yeah, but if you're in a bar,
there might be a bar, right? - If you're on the bar.
- You know, that's why it works in a pub.
- Yeah, that's a good point, yeah, yeah.
- Anyway, I have injuries now,
but it means I can't do arm wrestling.
I have something called tenosinivitis
of the first compartment of the wrist.
It's a very common thing that arm wrestlers get.
And yeah, it's like arm wrestlers thumb, it's called.
- Did you get it from arm wrestling?
- No, I got the version,
which is also known as mom's thumb.
I got it from carrying my baby too much.
But you can get the same injury
from carrying a baby in the wrong way
as you can get from arm wrestling in the wrong way.
- It's better than getting the one
they call wankers collar, isn't it?
- So you mentioned John Brzenk, there, Anna.
He's the great arm wrestling champion.
So he is the guy who the main bit of culture
about arm wrestling ever to exist in the world
is based on. - Oh, what's that?
- It's the movie over the top,
which is a Sylvester Stallone film,
which we have briefly mentioned fleetingly
in passing in the past.
Basically, he plays a character called Lincoln Hawke,
whose character's name changes about twice
as the film continues.
It's not a level of attention to detail.
And he has to arm wrestle his way to winning a big prize
and to a relationship with his son.
But it's based on John Brzenk.
And this is the really nice thing.
John Brzenk worked for decades as a mechanic
at Delta Airlines so that he could arm wrestle
because he wanted to travel.
His main expenditure was plane tickets
to arm wrestling competitions.
Whereas if he worked as a mechanic at Delta Airlines,
free transport.
- Does that also mean that if you're in,
let's say the world championships in Reykjavik
or something and you want to go home,
but there's a problem with the plane
and he's in the middle of an arm wrestling championship,
you have to wait.
- Everyone has to wait, yeah.
- If he sees a competitor heading towards the championship,
he can mess up a piece on the plane.
- Oh, that's good.
- What?
- He's just saying through a crash,
just so it doesn't take off.
- Yeah, just throw something small into the end.
Anyway, but God, you wouldn't want to share
an arm rest with him, would you?
- No.
- Yeah, my man.
- Depends which song though.
Depends on the size.
- I think his, both arms are probably strong.
- I was looking at pictures of all arm restes,
desperately hoping to find like one puny,
flaccid little stringy arm and one knee to arm.
- There is a difference though.
There is a difference in size
and it's roughly the difference
between George Eliot's head and James Harkin's head.
- That's the, yeah, five centimeters.
- Yeah, it's a bad, that's interesting.
- 'Cause you get some of them are experts
with just the right hand
and some of them are experts with just the left hand.
And I think the women's champion last year
won both right hand and left hand.
- Wow.
- Forgotten her name.
- So are there people who just never play each other?
- Yeah, of course.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause if you're right handed
and there's a champion who's a left handed,
how are you ever gonna meet them?
- Yeah.
- You can't both sit on the same side of the table.
- Wow.
- What if you're good though at backhand
or arm wrestling as such?
- What do you mean?
- So if I went that way.
- Well, like I told you, it's really hard to pull things
that in that direction compared to pushing
with your other muscles.
- Hang on, you also make sense of Andy's.
- We're sitting next to each other
and I'm pushing this way
and you're pushing this way.
- I don't think we've invented a new spark.
- No, hang on, I think we might have arm pulling.
Isn't that?
You have exactly the same position as arm wrestling
but you have to pull.
- You have to sit next to each other.
- Or you just have to pull.
You have to pull.
So you slam your own arm down.
- I mean, I think we've invented a sport
that's even less excited to watch arm wrestling.
But are you saying they have the right handed
champion trips and they say,
"And now we're gonna have the left handed champion."
- Yeah, it's different categories.
It's like different weights and boxing
but you've just got different arms.
- Is there any other sport that does that?
- Yeah, boxing.
You can only punch with your right hand
and then some people are really gonna only
punch him with their left hand.
- I don't believe you.
- No, that's because I've not done it in a dream.
- Can I just quickly mention with "Over the Top"
this movie and with John Bridgenk,
basically when "Over the Top" was going into production,
they did a thing for part of the promotion
where they actually set up this massive
arm wrestling championship that was called "Over the Top"
once the movie was green lit.
So they went, "Let's actually do this."
And so they did it as this,
both it was a sort of national thing in America
but then they had international qualifying rounds
that would happen in places like Japan
and they had a final in Las Vegas.
And the final, when all of these competitors
from all around the country came together,
that was the footage that makes it into
the final of the film.
And so, yeah, and so you see real arm wrestlers
who were part of this big tournament.
- Well, you would have to have real arm wrestlers,
otherwise you have normal actors.
(laughing)
You would be like fake arms.
- The problem was is that they wanted to use
real arm wrestlers to fight or to do the arm wrestle
with Stallone in the final of the movie
but they were all too big.
It was unrealistic.
- No, I thought they weren't big enough
'cause it's more about technique.
They've got more normal arm lookings
than the huge weightlifting muscles.
- Some of them are massive arms.
- I don't know.
Dave Dean, who was the main arm wrestler at the time,
was Jay Norris and he was,
and they said this is so impractical
that you would win this.
- Like for instance, Garth, all arms, Carlson.
- Well, he does sound like he's got big arms.
(laughing)
Or tiny, the rest of him.
- Such a weird name, isn't it?
All arms.
- He doesn't play, he's got sort of nine arms.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Terry Big Man Barton is another one.
They're all big then.
I've seen videos.
- They're very WD-40 nicknames, aren't they?
They're not, they're no one's called
the smoke screen or the diplomat.
- The next one I could find was Verne,
the one armed bandit, Martel.
And I don't know why you're laughing
'cause he lost his arm in a motorcycle accident.
- Did he?
- Yeah, one of them.
- 'Cause then he was actually one armed?
Oh my goodness.
- One armed bandit actually did have one arm.
- Oh my God.
- But yeah, he started going back into tournaments again
after his accident.
- Right.
- Which, did he lose his good arm?
- No, he lost his less good arm.
- That's incredible though, 'cause you can't hold on
to the peg, doesn't it, so he couldn't use the zoom.
- So he became the best in the world
in the non-able-bodied class,
but he also came fourth
in the regular able-bodied class once.
Which is pretty amazing.
- Yeah.
- Some arcade game stuff.
- You know those penny pushers
where you put like two p.m.
- I love those.
- And there's like some shells.
- Oh yeah, I've spent more money
than I'm comfortable with on those.
I love them.
- Me too.
- Well, they're invented by a company called Comptons
in 1964, and they were so sure
that it was just gonna be a one-year thing
that they didn't even put a patent on it.
They thought this will just be fun for one year.
Everyone will forget about it,
so we're not gonna do that.
And then that's why you get them in all the arcades now
'cause they weren't patented.
- But why do they steal my money so effectively?
- Well, it's really interesting that.
So there's a hole where all the money goes down.
So it seems that when you put two p.m.
it's bound to come out right.
Eventually it'll come out.
So every two p.m. that goes in--
- Should you call one two p.m. out?
- Yeah.
Now the way to make money is to,
for some of those two p.ms to fall into the machine.
But surely you'd notice.
- Yeah.
- You used to be able to notice.
There used to be a big hole in the middle
and you see the two p.ms go down.
And that would be where, obviously, they made the money.
But now they hide the holes.
- Ah!
- So there are holes on the side
that the two p.ms go into.
And so not all of the two p.ms that go in come out.
- What? - And that's how they make
the money.
- That's a swizz.
It's an absolute swizz.
- That genuinely is something that's been blown wide open.
I can't believe that.
So do they have to muffle the noise
of the two p.ms sliding down the holes?
- No, they must do, I guess.
- Because that's a noisy thing.
When you put your two p.ms at the top.
I sometimes resort to just banging in a fiver.
(laughing)
- You're gonna be the fireman into the slush.
- I have to pipe it down with a long pipe cleaner thing.
- Yeah, I think that'll get me a few two p.ms.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland.
Andy.
- @andrewhunterm.
- James.
- @JamesHarken.
- And Anna.
You can leave our podcast at qi.com.
- Yep, where you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThing is at fish.com.
All of our previous episodes are up there.
So do check them out.
And also go and check out the links
to the upcoming tour dates that we're gonna be playing.
In September, it's the final leg of nerd immunity.
It's an awesome night.
We're gonna do a live podcast in the second half
and a whole show that you've never seen before
in the first half.
It's stand up, it's facts, it's everything you want.
Come and see it.
If I sell it, I hope so.
All right, we'll be back again next week
with another episode.
We'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)