(upbeat music)
- Hello and welcome to another episode
of No Such Thing as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Covent Garden.
My name is Dan Schreiber,
I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray,
James Harkin and Anna Tyshinski.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that
in the 1920 Winter Olympics, US skater, Teresa Weld,
was the only woman in the figure skating who performed jumps.
But she was marked down every time she did
because her skirt rose above her knees,
which was considered too scandalous.
- Mm, did she have pants on?
(laughing)
- You can't tell if it's got rises above the knees.
- Depends how long the pants are.
- Yeah, possibly they could be like bloomers.
- Yeah, they did wear pants down to the knees back then.
- So it sounds very sexy, James.
- Oh yeah.
- And clearly it was at the time.
- Yeah, it depends when about she were.
If she wore what she was wearing then,
now in the Winter Olympics,
like just to show behind the curtain,
we're actually recording this
when the Winter Olympics is on.
And you're gonna hear this in the spring, but...
- Sounds like she was showing people
why in the curtain of her dress.
- Yeah?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- Wow.
(laughing)
- Andy's drunk just so everyone knows.
- But yeah, she would have worn a skirt
that was kind of round the ankles at the time
because that's the way that women--
- She wouldn't have worn her skirt around her ankles.
She wouldn't have worn a skirt.
- That does lose you points actually, yeah.
(laughing)
- It was round her ankles,
but also round her calves, and her knees,
and her thighs, and her bum.
- Yes, and that is the normal way
of describing the length skirt.
(laughing)
- And yeah, this is the way that basically
until the 20s and 30s,
women figure skaters would wear long dresses.
- That's amazing.
- And it was only when a very famous skater
called Sonja Haney came along
and she was only 11 when she started to compete.
And 'cause she was a child,
she could get away with wearing like children's clothes.
- Right, sorry, I thought she'd get away
with wearing much sexier stuff.
(laughing)
- Well, she didn't have to wear full adult long dresses,
and she could do these amazing jumps,
and then all of the adult skaters had to wear a short skirt
so that they could keep up with her amazing skills.
- So, what was the skating like
if Theresa Weld was the only person doing jumps?
What were the others doing in their show-off with skating?
- Well, it's called figure skating,
so they were doing figures mostly.
- Like carving out shapes in the ice.
- Yeah, exactly, not so much carving out
so that you could then pull it out and there's a shape there.
- The last person always fell through, didn't they?
Once you connected the lines.
- Yeah, exactly.
So, what you would do is you would do the shapes
of a figure of eight, or at the very start of figure skating,
someone would shout out what figure they wanted you to do,
so they'd shout out, you know, snowman,
and then you'd have to do a shape of a snowman,
and then they'd shout out something else
and you'd have to do that.
- That's really cool.
- But really in the olden days,
figure skating, especially for women,
wasn't about the jumps.
It was about doing something graceful,
doing lots of shapes and stuff like that,
and then when this woman came in, Teresa Weld,
she was the first to do the jumps,
and then before long, everyone was doing jumps,
and now they're doing kick-ass jumps.
- Yeah, and the jumps sort of took over in a way
because in television terms, drawing these circles
into the ice wasn't as televisual for the Olympics,
so it'd usually be 60% or so of the mark
that you would get was for the figures
that you were creating in the ice,
and they just sort of thought that's a bit crap.
- It sounds incredible, the process,
because it was ended about 30 years ago, wasn't it?
They stopped having actual figures,
so I read a bit about that,
and the judging took such a long time,
so there were 41 different figures at the start of it,
which you would have to be able to master,
but the judges would examine the skating three times,
as in they'd examine the shapes on the ice.
They would get down on their stomachs like detectives
to tell if there was a slight variation in the line,
or detectives.
- It was, generally it was only detectives
getting their stomachs in the prime scenes.
- It was like forensics.
- What they used to do,
they would skate the shape of a dead body
with the name of the ice.
- That was figure 37, yeah, yeah.
No, apparently the judging could last up to eight hours,
which sounds, I read an article from the Dutch Beagle,
the German thing,
and it was saying, it was from the '80s,
just before it ended,
and it was like, this is so boring.
- There was a guy called George Anderson
who wrote a skating book in the 1860s,
and he wrote that after the shamrock,
a one foot figure requiring three turns
and two changes of edge,
the acme of female accomplishment has now been reached.
- Wow.
- So he's like, once you've done the shamrock,
there's literally nothing better than that, true?
- Downhill ever since.
All these quintuple spins.
- One of the early guys who sort of turned figure skating
into the sort of art that it is now
was a guy called Jackson Haynes.
He was from New York, born in 1840s,
and he started, he was the person
who kind of turned it into more of a dance.
You know, he was trained in ballet,
and he took popular dances like the waltz,
and he turned that into what you would do on the ice.
And he did this in America, and they hated it there,
so he came over to Europe,
and he started performing it here,
and they loved it here,
and he performed to royalty.
But I've been reading into banned things
that would get you deducted points
or that you're not allowed to do it all.
And one of the things in modern times
is you're not allowed same sex couples
when you do Olympic or even any sort of official skating.
And it turns out that the very first pairing,
which is with Jackson Haynes, was a same sex couple.
- Was it?
- Yeah.
- Well, he was dancing with another guy.
- Yeah, he was dancing with another guy.
It was in Vienna.
It was called Franz Bellasi,
and they were the first ever couple,
and he's held up actually as a result
as a sort of LGBT pioneer.
- Is he, are we sure they weren't doing
the same sex couple just 'cause it was so regressive
that women weren't allowed to do figure skating?
Was it that they were a--
- No, I think--
- Progressive, progressive.
You know, at a certain point in the circle
that they're the same?
That's possible, although he's sort of been embraced
by the community of sort of being progressive.
- Was it the tango that was also like that originally?
- Just really, all male.
- Yeah, there was one dance,
I can't remember whether it was flamenco or tango,
or there was a huge dance craze, which was men only,
that we think of as a mixed-sex dance these days.
- Right.
- It was classically meant to be that.
- Yeah.
- And it was as well that Haynes wasn't,
he was dressed as a bear at the time.
- Oh, was he?
- Yeah, wasn't strictly two men dancing together.
- I think that is still strictly--
(laughing)
- Well, yeah.
I mean, if only strictly was like that.
- Dan, do you watch the Masked Singer
and you go, "Well, obviously it's an actual robot bunny."
I mean, I don't know what they're talking about,
celebrities, this is clearly a big pile of donuts.
- I'm afraid you are disqualified, it's a human only.
- Human only, sorry.
- So women, women skating was a kind of a thing,
or women competing anyway in figure skating.
And it was actually because of the clothes,
these long dresses that they weren't allowed to take part
in the world championships.
So there was basically only men
who entered figure skating contests for ages,
and it just wasn't really, didn't occur to people
that a woman might enter, so they didn't ban it.
And then this amazing skater called Madge Sires
entered in 1902, the world figure skating championships.
And she got silver, and there was lots of reports
saying she should have got gold,
and actually the winner was a guy called Ulrich Salko,
and he offered her his gold medal, 'cause he said,
"I think you were actually the deserving winner,
"you were better than I was."
But anyway, then the judges are like,
"Oh, bummer, we weren't supposed to have women in this,
"what are we gonna do?"
And so they went through all the problems
with having women figure skate,
and they basically said it was things like,
"The problem with it is that a judge might judge a girl
"on how much he's attracted to her,
"rather than how good she is at skating."
- There's definitely a problem with the female skater,
rather than with the judges there.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, get her off the ice.
But the other thing was, 'cause their dresses are so long,
you can't see their feet,
so they could be doing anything under there.
They could be cheating, they could have five feet,
they could have a child under there.
- They could have a child under there.
- Yeah, yeah, like have a snobberbill.
- Yeah, exactly.
- What do you think is like sneaking into a cinema,
where it's sort of sitting on top of a lot of the code?
- Three kids in a code, and they can't let
that kind of thing get through.
And so to be fair to Matt, she did say,
"Well, I'm very happy to wear a shorter skirt."
But then obviously she couldn't do that either,
so it was really rocking a hard place.
- Right, although while we're on men and women skating,
the patron saint of figure skating is a woman.
Saint Lidwina, you heard of her?
- Yeah, no.
- She was a Dutch teenager, 'cause you know
there are lots of canals and things in the Netherlands,
and they are from Friesey,
but there are lots of skating happens on them.
And I think this was in the 13th century.
Anyway, she was skating, she fell, she broke her leg,
and she never recovered.
And as a result, she's the patron saint of figure skating.
- Right.
- I'm not completely sure why.
- When was she around?
- 13th, a long time ago, several hundred years ago.
And it was, it sounds quite stressful.
There aren't, they think she might have had something
that we'd recognize as a modern condition today,
maybe the first ever case of MS,
but also the saintly accounts are so strange and exaggerated.
It's kind of hard to diagnose.
So for example, large pieces of her body fell off,
blood poured from her mouth, ears, and nose.
She shed bones, skin, and part of her intestines,
and her parents kept them in a vase.
And they gave off--
- That's not MS.
(laughing)
- And they gave off an incredible--
- That's the walking dead to what you're describing.
- Her parents kept these bits of her body in a vase
and they gave off a sweet odor,
so they knew she was holy.
- Oh, the odor of sanctity.
- Yeah, exactly, so it's holy.
Anyway, so--
- Wait, is she still alive while this is happening?
- Yeah, yeah.
- What, while her intestines are in the vase?
- I think, from the account I read, yes.
- Well, I was gonna say,
doesn't it sound like she's very good at skating
if she broke her leg?
But to be honest, if she's missing half of her body parts,
it sounds like, well done to her for getting up
in the morning.
- Yeah, yeah.
- She never skated again, anyway.
(laughing)
- Wow.
- That's very funny.
- You still get costume infringements, don't you,
in skating?
I hadn't realized this.
In fact, I knew very little about figure skating,
but you can get points docked
for wearing the wrong stuff now.
Well, you used to be able to,
until I think about less than 20 years ago,
it used to be that women couldn't wear skirts
that came up above the bum or the hips,
so you had to wear a skirt.
- Above the bum?
- Yeah, so sorry, you had to--
- Too sexy, that's so sexy, it's above the bum.
That was just having a bum out, wasn't it?
- Hang on.
- I don't wanna sound like a prude,
but I do think there are some good reasons why.
- I think every now and then,
the phrase, "You're not going out looking like that,
"you're bleeding" is appropriate.
I've misspoken.
They had to wear skirts and they had to be below the bum.
I should have said it like that.
Yeah, so you would be fined--
- So you'd have to cover the bum?
- You had to cover the bum.
You'd have a point docked.
- Well, you don't anymore, you can wear a leotard, can't you?
- Yes.
- Oh, okay, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But your bum is not fully out.
There's no mooning at the Olympics.
- I don't know what the rules are on that,
but I think you have to cover the genitals.
- And you think you might get jumped
as one of those detectives.
(all laughing)
- What a finishing move that would be for your routine.
Lots of jumps, lots of spins,
and a full moon at the end of it.
(all laughing)
- Suck it, guys.
- So on infringements, there was someone
at the 2018 Winter Olympics called Gabriela Papadakis,
whose nipple fell out during her performance, right?
- A Jackson moment.
- When you say fell out.
- It just, it didn't fall off her body like that.
- They said an argument, they fell out,
and-- - It smelled sweet, though.
It had the odor of sanctity.
- The detectives rushed onto the ice to collect it.
- And put it in a jar.
- It came out of her costume.
And it looks, it's like your worst nightmare,
but also you're getting point stocks.
Not only have you exposed yourself in national television,
you also get points deducted.
They still got silver, impressively.
- Have you heard of the job
of the Olympic figure skating poo wrangler?
- Jesus Christ.
- No.
- Is it surely the detective can double up?
(all laughing)
- Take a scoop on.
- What on earth could this be?
Oh, I know, is it about Hanyu, the Japanese guy?
- Yes, it is.
- I do know that, yeah.
- So this is a skater, he's called,
yeah, he's Japanese, he's called Yuzuru Hanyu,
and he's associated with Winnie the Pooh.
As in, he loves Winnie the Pooh,
and his fans, as a result, love Winnie the Pooh too.
And whenever he skates,
they throw Winnie the Pooh stuffed toys onto the ice.
- That sounds like it would ruin your routine.
- They throw hundreds.
It's insane.
And there was a job at the last,
I don't know if it's at every single Olympics,
but basically there has to be someone who skates around,
scooping up the Winnie the Poohs.
- Right.
- And shoving them into a huge golf park.
- I watched Hanyu in this Olympics,
and there was no Winnie the Poohs there.
So maybe because of COVID?
- So, well, Xi Jinping is compared,
Xi Jinping hates being compared to Winnie the Pooh.
- I forgot about that, yes.
- For some reason, for such a powerful guy,
he's pretty thin-skinned about this.
He doesn't like being compared to Winnie the Pooh.
And yeah, and so it wouldn't be a big problem.
Fortunately, foreign spectators have not been allowed
into China for this Olympics.
So no Winnie the Poohs have been chucked on.
- Hanyu's fans are super crazy.
Like, they literally, they're called fan news,
and they go around the world just following.
Like, if they can get tickets anywhere,
they'll go on eBay for thousands of pounds.
Like, he's really, really super famous in Japan, yeah.
- Well, what's weird is,
I've been to a few sporting events recently,
and in most cases these days,
you get checked as you're coming in
to these sort of bigger ones.
You have to, you know, if you go even see gigs
at like the O2, there's a metal detector and so on.
- Right.
- Surely that's the spot to put the Pooh wrangler,
you know, to...
(laughing)
- But I think normally when it's not happening in a state
where the totalitarian head of state
is compared to Winnie the Pooh and hates it.
- I'm not talking about current Beijing,
I'm talking about any other...
- I think they're fine with it, I like that.
- So they're fine with it.
- Yeah, it's fun, yeah.
- I think surely not at an Olympic level,
if you're going for gold, he'd be really annoyed.
Surely they'd hold back then.
- It's not at him on the ice.
- Oh.
- It's onto the ice while he's performing.
- It's after he's finished.
- It's after he's finished, yeah, yeah.
- Okay, 'cause they're really off-putting.
- It's not mid-routine, yeah.
- Okay.
- But it is apparently off-putting for his opponent.
So Nathan Chen, who's the other really amazing
figure skater male, his manager hates it.
His manager thinks it's like psychological warfare
against him.
- He's jealous 'cause he wants a teddy.
That's so sad, 'cause that's from Djokovic's behavior.
- I wonder if he's been trying to push his own thing,
like Trolls or My Little Pony, he's like, "Come on."
(laughing)
- One sad Troll thrown by his manager at this point.
- So the whole thing about the couples doing their dances,
I was reading this article where it sort of says,
obviously the choreography is amazing,
but also what they want is emotion
and they want to feel a routine.
And so a love story tends to be the thing
that you kind of go for.
And so a problem that siblings have is that they obviously,
it's a bit off if you see a brother and sister
kind of doing sort of that.
So they have a really odd position where they have to come up
with slightly kookier routines as a result
because they can't be seen to be like almost kissing
at the end of a routine.
- There was one in this Olympics.
I'm not sure if it was brother and sister.
It probably wasn't, but one of them was in the alien
and the other one was someone being probed.
(laughing)
- It would still be too sexy for brother and sister,
I think.
- You get the Benny Hill music playing.
One of them chasing the other one with a probe
has 10 points for me.
- It's not interesting.
They've never tried the Benny Hill music, to my knowledge.
(laughing)
- Too sexual, that's the problem.
- One of the most famous figure skaters of all time,
Tonya Harding, at least one of the most infamous.
I was reading up on her.
I never saw that movie with Margot Robbie.
- Eitania.
- Eitania, yeah, but what a pretty extraordinary life
that she's led even post her career.
So she got banned as a result of a controversy
where she was implicated in harming another skater.
What was her name?
Nancy Kerrigan.
- Neat capping nose, no, it was a breeze.
- It was her ex-husband hired someone to do it
and what came out through court cases was that
maybe she had an inkling that this was gonna happen,
that they were planning something.
That's got her a lifetime ban, basically.
But post this happening, she released a sex tape.
It was a sort of leaked sex tape,
but then she went to Penthouse, I think it was,
and they were playboy and said,
"You can officially release it for a man of money."
She became a manager for Pro Wrestlers.
She became herself a boxer.
She did boxing.
She started a band called the Golden Blades.
They got booed off stage on their
first gig. - Oh my gosh.
- Yeah, she's worked as a welder, a painter and a metal,
yeah, this is her career.
A painter at a metal fabrication company,
a hardware sales clerk, a deck builder.
She set the automobile racing land speed record.
Tonya's had a fucking life.
- She's desperately trying to erase
the one thing everyone knows about her.
Just trying anything on a Wikipedia
is all these different things,
but they still put that at the time.
- Exactly, but she was an amazing figure skater
and when they made this movie with Margot Robbie,
there's a scene in it where Margot Robbie
has to do a triple axel and Margot Robbie,
who did train to do it, obviously couldn't do it,
but they also couldn't find anyone to do it
because it's so rare that anyone's ever landed that,
that they had to use CGI in the film, yeah.
- She's also amazing at bow and arrow shooting.
- She shoots the show.
- There was a piece about her that interviewed her
and she goes hunting a lot with her husband,
like hunting sort of elephants.
- Other figure skaters.
(all laughing)
- Hunting elk and such like.
And her husband takes a big gun
and she just takes a bow and arrow.
She says because she wants to give the animal
a 50/50 chance to make it interesting and fair,
although the journalist points out also
because felons aren't technically supposed
to possess guns in Washington state.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is Anna.
- My fact this week is that in the early 1900s,
the US government installed telephones
at the top of trees.
- What?
- Be cool.
- Convenient place to make a call.
This--
- A trunk call.
- Good.
- Yeah.
- Is that a thing?
- That's a very old fashioned term
for a very long distance phone call, yeah.
- Oh, okay.
- Would have got a huge laugh in the '70s.
This is, it was the US Forest Service
that started installing them
at like 10th of the century, early 1900s,
and it was for fire lookouts.
So it was in like fire prone states
like your Arizona's or your California's,
and they'd find the tallest tree
on top of the biggest hill in the area,
and then they'd climb to the top,
they'd put a ladder up the tree,
and then a ranger would basically
lop off the top of the tree,
and in its place put a platform there,
and on the platform is just a telephone.
And then a guy's job is to sit at the top of the tree,
and then if he sees a fire,
he makes a phone call and says fire,
and they go and put it out.
It's so cool.
And sometimes, what I didn't get was it says,
sometimes they're worked in pairs,
and so there'd be two of them up the tree,
and one of them spots the fire
and then sends the other one to put it out.
But I don't understand how one single human being,
I imagine they weren't giant forest fires,
yeah, there's a small campfire, I suppose.
- What would you be, you would just,
if it was small enough,
you'd only see a plume of smoke, right?
I think as soon as you see flames,
that one guy's not really gonna appreciate
what's being sent on his own.
- Once the flames are coming out
at the top of the forest.
- Were you allowed to use the telephones for other things,
like calling your mates or stuff?
- No personal phone calls.
They do go through at the end of the month,
it's your phone record.
The bill's very high this month.
We don't remember hearing from you at all, lots of fires.
- They're still there today, some of them, it's amazing.
They get called the freaks of the peaks.
It's one cool nickname they have.
- The trees. - The people are the trees.
- The people, the people, I think.
But there are not many left.
There were 5,000 at most in the '30s,
and now there I think are a few hundred, maybe 500.
- I think it went up, I think it was peak was the '50s,
where there were about 10,000 in the US.
But yeah, I think such a cool job,
such an interesting kind of person who does that job.
- You've got to be very happy with your own company.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Well, I know if there's two of you up there.
- That's a good point.
But in most cases, it's like the lookout,
not the tree situation, but other lookout.
Sounds like it was one person the entire time.
- Yeah, it mostly does seem to be one person.
- Jack Kerouac was one of these guys, wasn't he?
- Was he? - Yeah, he was.
He spent 63 days as a US Forest Service fire lookout
on a place called Desolation Peak.
- Sounds fun.
- Yeah, and he went there thinking that he'll be on his own.
He only has to look out for fires for a while,
so it'll be fine, he can write some stuff.
But in the end, he wrote only one letter to his mother,
some Haiku poetry, and a couple of journal entries
and no novels.
- Well, I was reading one of the lookouts today
who says when new people come to do the job,
apply for the job, they imagine they're gonna do
all this stuff, like write their great novel
and learn an instrument, he says, or you know, they think--
- Oh my God, imagine if you had like two of you
at the top of the thing.
You see a laughing point climbing with the bagpipes.
Oh, here we go.
- You laugh.
There's genuinely a girl who's learning bagpipes
while she does this.
- Really? - I believe she is.
- Is she by herself?
- So true ones.
- Yes. - Okay.
- Yeah. - Oh God.
- But yeah, he says people tend to get nothing done.
You actually go and you end up--
- Oh, I'm sure.
I mean, you'd always think you'd only get stuff done
and you never do.
That's just life.
- I mean, your job is literally doing nothing.
- But it's to look.
You have to be looking for fires, don't you?
You have to be scaring the horizon.
You know, your binoculars, a little room.
- I feel like you can look
and play the bagpipes at the same time.
- Yes, that is one of the things.
- It's kind of sad that there are all these people
by themselves at the top of trees.
It's a 50/50 split.
And yet they obviously can't date each other
because they're all at the top of trees by themselves.
- You know how trees have sex?
They kind of fire.
- They release their seed into the wind.
- Into the wind.
They should try that.
- I'm sure it's been tried.
I'm sure someone's done it.
(laughing)
- It gets pretty dull up there.
- We've had some complaints from tourists
at the bottom of the tree.
(laughing)
- Well, they could do,
they did a sort of semaphore, not a semaphore.
They did a way of communicating
in the very early days before the phones.
What? - It has nothing.
- No, not semaphore, is that all?
- There we go, thank you, yeah, yep.
- Didn't need to happen, did it?
They had these things called heliographs.
So the ones that weren't high-tech enough
to have the telephones in the early 1900s
would just have two mirrors.
And there would be someone,
and they'd be called the flasher,
who would use the mirrors to transmit messages
by bouncing the sun off them.
- Right, isn't that how you start fires?
(laughing)
That's a great point.
- It's a major flaw in the plan.
Yeah, I guess you have to be quite careful.
I guess if you make sure it's a convex mirror, maybe.
- Okay, yeah, interesting.
- But yeah, it would reflect the sunlight
and they could transmit Morse code up to 70 miles.
- So we're saying that this is a technology basic,
it's not a technology,
it's a lack of technology that should be wiped out by now,
but it's still going.
And you would think with drones,
with satellite imagery, with planes,
we wouldn't need this anymore,
but it survived because it's the one thing
that we can still do when there is an electrical storm
and we can't send up drones
and we can't get satellite imaging
through clouding and so on.
So it's a job that hasn't died out
through the modern technological world,
which is pretty cool.
- Yeah, they've done a few studies recently
and found that the human observation is as efficient,
if not more efficient overall than using drones
and stuff like that.
Exactly like Dan says,
they can't be used in all conditions and stuff.
- And also they know,
'cause it's such a personal attachment they have
to the land,
so often they've been there 30 or 40 years,
you'll get a look out. - What?
- They've lived up there,
so they know every centimeter of the land,
so these people can instinctively spot
the tiniest thing wrong.
- But do you think they're like,
there's a fire where,
you know where the co-op used to be?
(all laughing)
Where old Vera used to live?
- Yeah, just down there.
- Yeah, it's that.
A lot of co-ops in the chorus, actually.
- They use something called an Osborne fire finder,
don't they?
An OFF, which is a topographic map.
So you know like those maps when you go to a tourist place
and it shows you where all the things are on the horizon,
it's like this building is this tower of this building,
it's like one of those.
And then there's a few different things
so you can tell exactly where the fire's happening.
And that was invented in 1840 by a guy
called Sir Francis Ronalds.
And he also was one of the first people
to do electrical signalling.
So when he was 28, he put eight miles worth of iron wire
on his mother's lawn in Hammersmith
and managed to send a signal from one end of the eight miles
to the other end of the eight miles.
It was all kind of like folded up.
So he didn't go very far in actual terms.
But he said after that, he said,
"Why add to the torments of pens, ink, paper and posts?
"Let's us all have electrical conversazione offices
"communicating with each other all over the kingdom.
"Give me enough material and I will electrify the world."
- Wow. - So he basically invented email.
- Yeah. - Isn't that amazing?
- I just sort of imagined him at the end of his garden
going like, "Mom, talk into the wire."
And his mom being like, "I can just say to you,
"come in for dinner, talk into the wire, mom.
"I can hear it."
Yeah, you can't even 10 meters away from me.
So funny.
On the Watchman thing, but the non-fire-related Watchman.
- Oh yeah.
- So, Lausanne in Switzerland has its own Watchman
who climbs the bell tower every night and shouts the time.
And that's been going since 1405.
- They can't have put a clock up there or anything.
- Well, they've got, I think they've also--
- In Switzerland.
(laughing)
- You're absolutely right.
In fact, they've definitely got a clock
'cause it's the bell goes and then the watchkeeper
shouts the time and chouts that it's all fine.
- Watch, watcher.
- Yeah, but--
- Shouts that it's all fine.
- Yeah, there's a rubric that you say,
which is, you know, it's 10 o'clock and all is well.
Good night.
- Oh, not like 10 bongs and--
- Yep, it's right again.
(laughing)
- I do think they speak after the bell rings.
In fact, they do.
The bell rings and then they shout
from the foresight of the tower what time it is.
Anyway, for the first time--
- It feels like a redundant job, literally.
- Yeah, that's the son of the owner of the bell
just trying to find a gig for his kid.
- They've just appointed their first ever female watchkeeper
in 2021.
This is after 600 years.
- Huge steps.
- Yeah, it is.
And there was a big protest a couple of years ago
about the fact that no women had been invited
to be watch keepers.
- Not 'cause she got the job.
- No, no, no, no, no, no, right.
- No, a couple of years ago,
a lot of women said, "Look, we want to enter this."
A sweet gig, apparently.
(laughing)
Well, they had a vacancy last year to join the team
and I think 80% of the applications were from women.
- I think what you want is a dinner lady.
They have the loudest voices in the world, don't they?
- Yes, and there was a voice test.
That was part of it.
It was sort of they need to test
that you've got a good pair of lungs to shout the time.
And the job comes with a little lodge
that you can keep warm in, in between bongs, I guess.
And it comes with a felt hat, a lantern,
and a cheese fondue set.
(laughing)
- It's in the lodge, right?
- Pretty Swiss.
- With those perks, I can really understand
why they went for it.
A felt hat.
Just one more thing, actually, on fire towers
that I found so interesting is that this was,
I was reading a piece with a lookout called Levi Brinniger.
And I do want to say they all have really cool names
like that or like Leaf Hogan.
All names that sound like they're a forest lookout.
But Levi Brinniger pointed out
that if there's a lightning storm,
you are in the tallest place up the tallest tree
with an electric phone line that you're supposed to use.
So first of all, they do have a kill switch.
They just have a kill switch to kill the phone lines
if the lightning came too close.
And then if it's really close, they have a stool,
and there are a couple of others who all had this,
a stool where they've just put sort of glasses
on each leg, under the leg, to insulate it from lightning.
So you just go and sit on this one stool
in the middle of the room and wait for the lightning
to pass through.
- I would have thought the power of a lightning bolt
on a tree if it hits it.
- It explodes it.
And it doesn't matter if you've got four tightly glasses
on the bottom of your chair.
- I think, friend of the podcast, Roy Sullivan,
was that his name?
The guy who was struck by lightning seven times.
I think one of the times he was hit by lightning
was when he was up a fire lookout thing.
- Was it?
- Yeah, yeah, wow.
- Didn't put his glasses under the stool.
- No, clearly, yeah.
- And in fact, it wasn't one of the other times
when he was being chased by a bear.
Do you remember?
- Yes, yes, yes.
- He was being chased by a bear then struck by lightning.
He was beating it off with a stick.
- Sorry, he wasn't, let me rephrase that.
He was beating the bear with a stick at the time.
- Well then, I don't blame the bear for chasing him.
- Yeah, yeah.
- He just wanted to do an ice dance with it.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three.
That is Andy.
- My fact is there is a worm,
which can grow multiple bottoms,
which then fires off to have sex without it.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- So this is a newly named worm, very exciting.
There were a couple in the same kind of family
with the same kind of body shape
that were known about already, but this is a new one.
It's called Ramisela's King Ghidorahi,
which is after a thing from Godzilla.
It's one of the other things that is a villain.
I mean, yeah.
- I always thought Godzilla was the villain,
but anyway, we'll come back to that.
- Well, I'm sure we'll come to that.
Basically, this worm is an amazing branching creature.
It lives in sea sponges.
It has one head, and then the back end of it branches,
'cause it lives in a sea sponge.
It branches through all the different tunnels
and crevices and paths of the sponge, right?
And then when it wants to reproduce,
basically the end of each branch of its body,
and there can be dozens or even hundreds of these branches,
the end of each one breaks off, swims up to the surface,
independently releases its eggs or sperm
into the water column where they'll all find each other.
So they fertilize each other and then the bums die,
but the head of the worm living in the sea sponge lives,
lives to breed another day,
and it starts regenerating all of its--
- It's so amazing. - It's a bums.
- It's incredible. - It really is.
- It's just such a weird, weird thing.
- I just feel so sorry for the head.
Don't you think that is the worst?
Because you're spending your whole life as a face
buried in the pitch-black belly of a sponge,
and you're sending off your arses to have sex,
and you never, ever get to do that yourself.
- Mm. - Isn't that so weird?
- Yes.
- You do have a nice sponge to live in.
- Yeah, I guess that's why it comes true.
- That's a sponge bath every day.
(all laughing)
- They can't survive the head part,
can't survive outside the sponge.
As soon as they go outside the sponge, they die.
- Oh, that's a lady of shallot there.
I bet they sometimes want to.
I bet there are a few heads who have gone sod it.
I'm gonna give it a go.
- Yeah. - Let it pop out.
- That's it. - It's so crazy, isn't it,
when you think of evolution, right?
Like, just the fact that this thing had to evolve
to send its anus off to go and have the babies, you know,
while, like, it was like, what do we do?
We can't, my head can't leave this sponge.
(all laughing)
What do I do?
- These things that you call bums as well,
they are kind of, they can be more than bums.
They can have, like, they have very rudimentary brains.
They have very rudimentary eyes.
- Yeah.
- So they're like, not just a bum.
- No, you're absolutely right.
- So they're their own kind of, as it were, consciousness,
even though I know they're not thinking,
but they've got their own--
- Yeah, they have nerves. - Yeah, this is the most
amazing thing.
- And they're called stolons, technically.
So they're reproductive units.
But as James says, they've got eyes,
they've got very primitive brains,
and that helps them to steer and to mate.
- I find this the most extraordinary thing about this,
and almost anything I've ever read in nature,
that these are basically living creatures
that they turn into.
So every single time they let go of a branch,
that they split their organs in half somehow.
So every organ duplicates,
so that branch has its own set of organs
that it then goes off with.
- Extraordinary.
- It's so weird.
- So all of them have guts and nerves,
and every single branch does.
And so when that forks, the organs fork as well.
And some of them have been measured.
So this is the other species,
Ramicillus multicordata,
which is just a very similar creature.
They've been measured with 500 different branches.
- The reason you kind of call them bums
is because when they're sticking out of the sponge,
it's the bum bitch which's sticking out, right?
And the way that they eat is they can't,
well, we're not quite sure,
because no one's ever found any food inside any of them.
- It's insane.
But what we think is that they dissolve,
they kind of soak in the food into their body,
and then there's no stomach or anything like that,
and then they send out the waste through the bums.
And then when they become like the thing that reproduces
and decides to swim off,
then a new little anal opening comes
where they used to live,
and then they grow out again.
- Constantly mooning the world.
- They were found, the first one was found in the 1870s,
and then they didn't find the other two species,
'cause they're three species altogether, this thing,
until about 20 years ago.
And the first one was found on the Challenger Expedition,
which I had never read about,
but is this extraordinary expedition from 18,
maybe we've discussed it before,
but 1872 to 1876, this three and a half year voyage,
which basically started oceanography.
And I didn't realize that before that,
people didn't care about the oceans at all.
It was a big team of people,
and it sounds really dull.
So Darwin had called the oceans
"a tedious waste, a desert of water."
He was like, "There's nothing in here, don't bother with it."
So everyone thought that,
and then they set off on this expedition.
- You think that's because you know how Darwin basically
lived in England, right?
And then he went all the way over to the Galapagos,
all the way over the sea.
Do you reckon people said, "What were you doing on the way,
all were you doing, fuck all?"
He was like, "Oh, it's pointless, I wouldn't do anything."
Anyway, just see, there's nothing in there.
- He forgot to look in it.
- Is it the opposite where he found,
he obviously knew how much was in there,
but he was just trying to put off other scientists.
"No, don't bother looking there, it's just water, mate."
- Yeah, he always went to get to it.
Well, they did look there
and they collected 4,800 new species,
and they found the Marianas Trench on the expedition,
and they started the whole field.
- This guy who we're talking about with all the bums,
the way that he eats by dissolving stuff
that is around him basically is how mushrooms live.
And so I read one place that they said
that it's basically an animal
that has adopted a fungal lifestyle.
So it's living like a fungus lives, but it's an animal.
- Yeah, it does seem like that.
And actually other marine worms
do that kind of dissolving thing, don't they?
There's a worm called the zombie worm,
which feeds off skeletons of mostly whales
by other dead ocean animals at the bottom of the sea.
And that sends acid out onto the bone,
which kind of melts it, well, dissolves it.
And then they just live inside whale bones
for ever and ever.
- It's incredible.
- That is really amazing.
I think I've read that there are some sponges
which have been observed feeding on fossils,
as in fossilized bones of ancient whales.
And it's why the fossil record
is really patchy in some places.
It's just 'cause down there, they've been eaten, yeah.
- I guess, yeah.
I suppose if bones didn't disintegrate,
we would just have-
- Just be needy.
- Well, yeah, if you actually like,
if you looked at the bottom of the ocean,
it should just be bones, right?
At least one layer.
- Is it really?
- Well, they get compressed and compressed over time,
and they form rock layers, basically.
I mean, so if you look at short cliffs,
that's all the skeletons of the plankton stuff.
- That's right.
- So those bones just turn into
what everything else turns into, which is mulch.
- That's true, but I'm talking,
I think I'm just talking short term.
Let's say in like a 50 year period,
there must be a lot of sea creatures that die
that just do a collection of bones,
but they're being eaten by-
- 'Cause these zombie worms,
something like that. - Yeah, exactly.
- Scale worms are another water worm.
- Oh, yeah.
- And some of them have this really cool trick.
So they're a bit like wood lice,
with the wood lice of the sea.
So they have these like hard scales around them,
and that's so if something tries to eat them,
they slough off these scales,
and the scales end up in the thing's mouth,
and they wriggle off.
- Brilliant.
- But then sometimes they have scales
that produce like bioluminescent light,
and so something will try to eat it.
They slough off the scales in the thing's mouth,
and then the thing's mouth is glowing in the dark,
and then that thing gets hunted by its predator.
- So cool.
- And you're off literally in its face.
(laughing)
- That's clever.
- Have you heard of the bobbit worm?
- Oh, yeah.
Is that the massive one?
- It's huge, yeah.
It's like 10 feet long.
It's a iridescent worm.
It buries its body into the ocean,
and it sort of just sits there,
and it sends out these kind of traps,
like five little antennae that just sit there.
And if a fish comes along,
it leaps out, just sort of slithers very quickly,
and with its jaws,
it can snap, because the force is so great,
it can slice a fish in half.
Like it's just like insanely horrible.
But it then brings it back down into a hole,
and they don't fully know what happens next.
Scientists have not any idea really of what happens next,
'cause we haven't been able to study it.
So they don't know if there's a toxin
that goes into the animal,
that if they haven't split into two,
that is still alive,
that just then kills it,
and then they can, you know, ingest it, and so on.
- Well, so sometimes it's still alive,
kind of thing, I don't know how they kill it.
- Yeah, exactly.
Like, sometimes they'll bring something back in
that they've just got a good grip on,
as opposed to having it sliced.
And the thought is, is that the name,
although no one's fully sure,
they think John Wayne Bobbet's wife is the inspiration for.
- I think so.
- Yeah, I think that is known, isn't it?
- I think that wasn't conclusive.
I think it was a sort of nickname given to it,
and they sort of,
well, at least the places I was reading,
saying we're not fully sure,
because it doesn't do anything to your genitals.
It's not like it bites your balls off,
or it's like, no, it doesn't slice it.
- So we should say this is a famous case
of a couple called John Wayne Bobbet,
and his wife, Lorena Bobbet,
and she cut off his--
- Penis. - Yes.
- And threw it out of a car.
- Yeah. - Yes.
- And this isn't what the worm does,
but it does seem like too much.
- There's something a bit,
there's something a bit slicey,
and a bit penise-y involved here,
'cause it's this worm.
- Yes.
- It kind of lives under the sand,
and then jumps out and grabs you,
a bit like the worms in Dune, really, I think.
Or, what's that other one, Tremors,
a bit like Tremors? - Yeah, yeah, yeah, yes.
- It has been compared to the Mongolian Death Worm.
- Yes, yeah.
- And here we are, back on stage territory.
- Doesn't, Dan.
- It hasn't featured in SpongeBob SquarePants yet,
has it, this creature?
No.
- Imagine if, is there an episode of SpongeBob SquarePants
where it has one of these bond-dividing worms in it?
- SpongeBob Gets Worms, yeah.
(all laughing)
- So a little bit on Godzilla, maybe?
- Yes. - Yes.
- He is a Japanese citizen.
(all laughing)
- Date of birth, April of 1954.
Reason for special, he's got special residency.
- You'd have to.
- Yeah, yeah.
For promoting the entertainment of,
and watching over the Kabukicho neighborhood,
and drawing visitors from around the world.
Because I know you've been to Japan, Andy.
Have you seen the giant Godzilla
that's sticking out of one of the buildings?
- I have not, is it Tokyo? - It's really called
next to Shinjuku Station, yeah.
You're just walking down the street,
and you turn around,
and suddenly there's a massive Godzilla
sort of looking over you.
- That's so cool. - Is he watching over?
'Cause I thought that he destroyed buildings.
- Well, he got-- - I mean, yes.
- He doesn't move because he's just a statue.
- No, but the idea of Godzilla,
the idea of a very destructive creature, right?
- I see what you mean, actually.
- I mean, it's complicated. - He could save you
from Mothra, or from whoever this other guy was,
King Ghidorah. - Ghidorah, yeah, yeah.
- It's a complicated relationship,
because basically, at various points,
he's been the goodie and the heel.
And, you know, if he's fighting King Kong, for example,
- What? - He, as he did
in the latest, very bad movie.
- Oh, they're two completely different creatures.
- Well, you haven't seen King Kong
versus Godzilla, have you?
And I gotta say, that's two hours.
I'm never getting back, because it's--
- What's it about? - It's a bad, really.
- It wasn't bad.
I mean, Kong's skull island is magnificent.
- Is it? - Yeah.
- Yeah, you keep telling me that.
- But basically, Godzilla can be a goodie and baddie.
I mean, very, very destructive of property.
- Thank you. - Yes.
- Thank you, back to that.
Okay. - Yeah.
- He can be angered,
but he's never on the side of the humans, right?
Or is he?
- He's not really on any side.
- He's on Godzilla side. - He's on Godzilla side, yeah.
- Does it look like to him?
So, does it love story with him?
No, that's Kong, isn't it?
- "Fade Down Away" in the '33 movie, yeah.
There's always, yeah, that's the--
- Yeah. - That's Kong.
- That's Kong. - That's Kong, yeah.
- Or Brie Larson in Kong's skull island, yeah.
- Sure, okay.
- And actually, they don't really have a relationship
in the same way that Kong and "Fade Down Away" did.
- I would say, when you're on "Mastermind"
and they say, "What's your specialist subject?"
If you do choose Kong and Godzilla,
don't just give a fucking monologue
as soon as he asks his first question,
'cause you're gonna run out of time.
- The thing about Skull Island is, though,
it's a brilliant Vietnam War metaphor,
and the whole mood, it's incredible.
- I started and finished a long time ago, Andrew.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that comedian Lenny Bruce
was arrested so often during his sets
that he would go on stage wearing his coat
just so he was ready to leave with the police immediately.
- Brilliant. - Go on.
- Yeah, so this is a fact that I learned
in a brilliant autobiography
that was written by George Carlin,
who is also one of the greatest stand-ups
that we've ever had.
It's called "Last Words," highly recommend
anyone who's interested in the world of comedy
reading it, and this was on a night in 1962
when Lenny Bruce was playing at a club
called the Gate of Horn, and during the performance,
a police officer stood up in the middle of the crowd
and he basically shut down the show,
and he immediately arrested Bruce,
and he tried to take him to jail.
So, Carlin's bit of this story is that he was upstairs
having a drink with another comic,
and they weren't only just arresting Lenny Bruce,
they were also arresting anyone else that they could
because they wanted to make a real point
about this happening, this gig.
So they IDed everyone who was at the show
to see if there were any minors there
to see if they could arrest them,
if anyone was too young to be there.
They arrested the owner and the bartender
because drinks were being served during the set,
which was not allowed,
and they ended up arresting as well George Carlin,
who was upstairs and refused to give his ID
and started making a joke out of it
because he was quite drunk.
So George Carlin ended up in the van,
the police van, with Lenny Bruce,
and so he was there specifically for this moment.
Lenny told him he would wear his coat while he was on stage
because sometimes the police would just take him out
immediately and he wouldn't be able to get his coat,
and he loved his coat because it was made
from a really nice cashier
and he didn't want to be parted with it.
So that's why he wore it on stage all the time.
- I saw that he went to prison.
They bailed him out, right?
And he was back on stage by something like 1 a.m.
for the second show of the night.
When he was on stage, he did a joke by saying,
"I better keep my coat on 'cause I may have to go out again."
So he kind of made a point of the arrest as well.
- Yeah.
- Do we know how long into the set the policeman waited?
Did he wait for him to do all his favorite jokes
and then stand up or did he just give him 10 seconds?
- You wait until he said something really rude.
- It was, yeah, it was the moment he said something rude.
So Lenny Bruce is, if you haven't heard of him
as the listener of the show, he was a 1960s comedian.
- The listener, we have more than one listener.
(laughing)
- Sorry, I have one listener.
The rest of you have millions.
I've got one dedicated listener.
He was basically, in a way, the first modern
stand-up comedian, and there were a lot of comedians
before him, obviously, and you can say people like
Bob Hope and so on who would go around on stage
telling jokes, but they were very much joke merchants.
They had a team of writers who were writing for them.
Lenny Bruce was the first person to really talk
about his personal life.
He used swear words.
He talked like a real person, basically.
And that's--
- It was like stream of consciousness-y type stuff
rather than just gag, gag, gag, right?
- Yeah, but they were written, it was written material
as well, but he was basically counter-culture America.
He was part of the beat people.
So Jack Kerouac, who was mentioned before,
very much part of that scene, and he opened up
the whole industry of stand-up to this new way of doing it.
What came with that is he spoke about
very controversial topics.
He spoke about religion, which he really didn't like.
He used swear words on stage, which no one was doing
at this time, and so he was constantly being arrested
for these reasons, and he became a sort of martyr
to the whole of the comedy industry, because he--
- Yeah.
- Sorry.
- Well, no, we should say that he was pardoned as well,
which is great news.
So he was convicted of obscenity, but then he was pardoned.
- In this one, right?
- Well, so this is when he was tried in 1964
for obscenity and prosecuted, but the good news is
that he was pardoned, and it was in 2003
that he was pardoned.
- That's right.
- He had been dead for nearly 40 years, but.
There was a petition to cancel it.
So the governor of New York was George Pataki,
who in 2003 granted this posthumous pardon.
The petition was brought by a couple of comedians
I'd never heard of, called Tom Smothers and Dick Smothers,
known as the Smothers Brothers, who themselves were canceled
and properly canceled, 'cause they were very lefty,
and that was obviously also pretty controversial.
- Yeah, so he wasn't found guilty in the event
that Dan was describing.
He was got off there.
His defense compared him to Aristophanes Rabele
and Jonathan Swift in the court case,
and the jury agreed, and they let him off,
and then he was later arrested quite a lot of times
in lots of different places,
but in New York was the big famous one,
which is what you're talking about, he got.
- I think I agree with the judge, right?
I don't know Rabele, come on, you're not that pretentious,
but Aristophanes and Swift, kind of impenetrable,
desperate wannabe satirists, apparently genius,
but actually not that fun to experience.
I would say it's quite a good description of Lenny Bruce.
- Wow. - For me.
- Yeah, yeah, that's fine.
- For me.
- Jonathan Swift is very funny,
and some of the Aristophanes stuff is pretty funny.
- I love the level, Anna, how can you be at a level
where you're pretentious enough to know Aristophanes
and Jonathan Swift, but no,
I'm not pretentious enough to know Rabele, come on.
- Well, you all know that's the line, okay?
You've crossed the line when you know Rabele.
- I mean, he represented himself in court at various points,
so that might've been the point
where he was being compared to Jonathan Swift
and Aristophanes, so he fired his lawyer
halfway through this trial, the 1964 one.
And then the New York law journal
refused to publish the judgment
because it contained offensive words, so.
- Right.
- And then just going back to the original one
that you were talking about, Dan,
I was reading the newspaper articles
from the day and from the day after and stuff,
and he did his second show,
and then he went back to his hotel, the Clifft Hotel,
and then he got kicked out of his hotel
because the hotel owner had heard about him being arrested
and didn't want his like in his hotel,
and so he just got kicked out into the street.
And as a result from then on,
he performed always with a small suitcase on stage.
(laughing)
- He did like a spot of morphine, heroin, yes,
and actually he was ejected from another hotel once
for blocking its toilet with heroin needles.
- Oh.
- Or for blocking its toilet with needles.
- That's one of needles, isn't it?
(laughing)
It's not like toilet roll, it's like.
- I think maybe it only takes a couple of needles
to block a loo, I've never, never tried it,
but there was another time he was, I promise.
(laughing)
- We've been on tour with you,
we know you are a needle toilet blocker.
The number of Premier Inns we've been unceremoniously kicked
out of.
- I'm sorry about that, but I have changed.
He was another thing I do on tour, actually.
He was kicked out of another hotel
for apparently conducting a nocturnal trio of blondes
in an original composition, the chorus of which ran,
please fuck me, Lenny, in three-part harmony.
- Oh, wow, in harmony.
- In harmony.
- Actually, at a Premier In, you wouldn't be allowed
to do that, 'cause they have the good night's sleep policy.
(laughing)
- Or the sign saying, shh, our corridors.
- That's why it's Lenny Henry who's the mascot
and not Lenny Bruce.
- It was a top-up, wasn't it?
(laughing)
- But yeah, he had a big old sexual appetite
and he married a stripper called Honey Harlow.
- Yes.
- But as you say, Anna, like you don't think he's funny
and a lot of people absolutely agree with you.
He has to be looked at as someone who is just the person
who paved the way and who, you know, Richard Pryor,
who is seen by many as the funniest person ever,
says that Lenny Bruce was the funniest person ever.
George Carlin as well, Lenny Bruce was the funniest person
ever.
Modern day comedians like Mark Marron, Lenny Bruce,
funniest person ever.
- Yeah, I respect him a lot.
- Michael McIntyre, you can see the influence so much
in McIntyre's material.
But they did, they did a, on the 50th.
- I like to just say I like Michael McIntyre.
I don't even know why I said that.
It's just the first day that came into my head.
- They're just not similar.
- However much you like either of them,
I don't think Michael McIntyre would claim
that he's taking after Lenny Bruce.
- I'm just saying if Michael McIntyre was beyond
his BBC primetime show, I'm sorry.
(all laughing)
- But he does block a lot of hotel toilets
with heroin needles, that's the McIntyre thing, isn't it?
It's kind of his trademark, yeah.
- But on the 50th anniversary of his death,
they did a screening of one of his recorded stand-up shows
to an audience of fans and just to, you know,
commemorate him, it was 40 minutes of jokes
and hardly anyone laughed according to the article.
And that makes sense, he was a, he was a conscience.
- He's the one that you go, when you're watching him,
you go, ah, you sort of smile and you're like, oh.
- I like Stuart Lee.
- That's certainly a bit of Stuart Lee to him.
(all laughing)
- Is there anyone left?
- Let's just destroy anyone we might work with in the future.
- There was a brilliant article in Playboy
that he, that was quoting him in 1963
and he was talking about when he was going on stage
and the owner decided to introduce him
but was really worried that he was gonna get a bad reaction.
And so the owner said, "Ladies and gentlemen,
the star of our show, Lenny Bruce,
who incidentally is the next GI
and a hell of a good performer, folks.
And he's a great kidder, you know what I mean?
It's just a bunch of silliness.
He doesn't mean what he says.
The kids and the Pope and the Jewish religion, honestly.
It's just a make-believe world, it's fine.
He's a hell of a nice guy, folks.
And he was at a veterans' hospital today
doing a show for the boys.
And here he is, by the way, his mom's out there tonight too.
She hasn't seen him in a couple of years
and she lives here in the town.
Now, it jokes a joke, right, folks?
What the hell?
I wish she'd try and cooperate.
And whoever has been sticking ice picks
in the tires outside, that's not funny.
- Is this real?
That's real?
That's the best intro ever.
- That's really good.
- I feel like he must have written it for the video.
- That's so good.
- His mom, interestingly, was his main inspiration.
And she was really awesome.
And she was this woman called Sally Ma.
And she was a stand-up comedian,
well, before stand-up was a thing, really,
in the '30s and '40s.
And she did impersonations, I think,
was part of her comedy.
Like, she impersonated Humphrey Bogart
and James Cagney and people like that.
And she--
- She introduced him on stage for his first ever show.
- Oh, did she?
- Well, his first big break, he was in a radio show
called Arthur Godfrey's Talent Scouts.
And she was the hype woman for him.
- She was a manager, also, later in her career.
- Yes.
- So she managed, who I did not know
was a stand-up comedian.
But the man who played Mr. Miyagi
from the Karate Kid movies, Pat Morito,
was a stand-up before he became a sort of
more serious actor.
And yeah, she managed him.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- He had a brief act, didn't he?
Walks on, walks off.
- Beautiful.
That is beautiful.
- Lenny Bruce, actually, he only ever performed
once in the UK.
It was in London.
And it was on Greek Street in central London in Soho.
And it was at the Establishment Club,
which was created by Peter Cook of Beyond the Fringe.
And it was, the Establishment was set up basically
because they wanted to try and give acts the opportunity
to try the stuff that was censored.
At this point in the UK, if you were performing,
it was part of a theater show.
And the Lord Chamberlain had veto over every script
that would be performed.
So they'd go through it and say,
"You can't say this and you can't say this."
But in private establishments, you were allowed to do that.
And so Peter Cook set up this place.
And that is how Lenny Bruce came to the UK
for his one and only trip
because he was deported the second time around.
He wasn't allowed in.
And by all accounts, it was quite a bad run of gigs.
He was pretty ill at that point in terms of the drug taking.
This story you mentioned about the women and the syringes
that was in London, where that happened.
And Peter Cook himself, who was a massive fan of his,
went and picked him up from the airport.
And he said that he just met this shambling guy
coming out at the arrivals.
He got into the car
and he was holding a record player,
a sort of miniature tape recorder.
And he insisted on playing his tapes
all the way on the journey back.
And the tapes consisted of nothing but airplane noises
and grunting and farting.
That was it.
And Peter Cook just saw what the hell is going on here.
And yeah, and so he came and he performed in London.
- What was going on?
- He doesn't really know.
Like Peter Cook, just basically what he had
was a junkie in the back of the car.
- I don't know, is that classic junkie behavior,
playing fart noises over a tape player,
which I haven't been invented yet, but.
- But he might've been, like there was,
there's accounts of Lenny Bruce making car stops
'cause he's sort of like a field of flowers
just so he could run and lay in them
and then get back in the car.
And they didn't realize at the time he was doing heroin.
And that was, that was him just.
- It was a field of poppies.
(all laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That's all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we have said
over the course of this podcast,
we can be found on our Twitter accounts.
I'm on @Shrieberland, Andy.
- @AndrewHunterM.
- James. - @JamesHarken.
- And Anna.
- You can email podcast.qi.com.
- Yep, you can go to our group account,
which is @NoSuchThing or our website.
NoSuchThingAsAfish.com.
Check out all of our previous episodes.
We're sure up there.
Check out our merchandise as well,
including the book that we put together for the tour,
which is now selling online.
It's a sort of history of fish
with lots of random fun things.
Check it out. - By the way,
when you say fish, it's us.
It's not like a history of the sea or the ab.
- No, no, no.
I've uploaded my new fish book.
Yeah, turns out there is such a thing.
So yeah, no, do check that out and come back next week.
Listen to us again,
'cause we'll be back with another episode
and we'll see you then.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)
you