Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode of No Such Things a Fish where we are joined by the incredible Beck Hill
Now who is Beck Hill you ask?
No, you don't because you're already a listener to a problem squared
Which is her amazing podcast that she does with mathematician and comedian Matt Parker where they spend her time solving
everybody's problems
You probably also know Beck through her YouTube channel. She's got all sorts of stuff on there
I think notably you might know her for her flip-chat comedy where she miss his lyrics
There's videos about her show make-away take away that she used to do on CITV
There's loads of stuff on there and of course if you're the right age or if you have children of the right age
You will know her from her books. She has a series of book called horror heights
There are three in the series at the moment
The latest is called Dead Ringer and they are of course available in all places where you buy your books
So that's all about Beck. There will be a little thing later on
Towards the end of the show where we might have an object
Which we will sign and give away to one of our listeners if you want to know more about that
You will have to sign up to club fish
We will give more details on how to win that during our next bonus drop as a line which will be out next Tuesday
Anyway, not much more to say. I mean we do have a live show coming up
Which I think the tickets might be all but sold out, but you can get streaming tickets from that
You can go to no six things a fish dot com forward slash pod fest apart from that really this is the end
It's time to say on with the podcast
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish a weekly podcast coming to you from the qi offices in
Hoburn my name is Dan Shriver. I am sitting here with James Harkin Andrew Hunter Murray and Beck Hill and once again
We have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in a particular order here
We go starting with fact number one and that is
Beck in
1927 a paint and was filed for an upper artist designed to scare criminals into confessing their crimes
By creating an optical illusion of a ghost skeleton
How to do it it's pretty cool. Yeah, I mean it the paint was filed and I mean it was granted in 1930
Okay, it expired in 1947 so if anyone wants to make that now
That make call of duty better. Wouldn't it whether trying to get
line of duty
It is yeah, yeah, I just don't work out there as well. I think it would work everywhere pop a glowing skeleton
Sorry, we'll get we'll get messages from the game as it won't work in call of duty
Intensely realistic war experience
Is more a kind of like can you storm Normandy than where were you on the night of the fourth?
More games need interrogation
The Mario interrogation
It's reading about
Show jumping the other day, you know in the Olympics and in the first Olympic show jumping part of it was
Just because we're talking about video games
The horse had to walk along and people would roll barrels towards them and they'd have to jump over the barrels like in
Isn't that cool? That's amazing. Yeah, imagine if that was your job
Sorry, but this was off topic so quickly
Oh, yeah, so it was like it was a light. Do you know what I couldn't find out whether it was a real skeleton or a fake one
But given the date I'm guessing was a real one
But it was a life-size skeleton with red glowing light bulbs in the eyes that would turn on and off to create the effect of blinking
and it was lit from the top and the bottom and
basically the
the suspected
criminal would be put into a
chamber like a room that's completely darkened and then
the interrogator would sit behind this skeleton and
Talk through a megaphone that would sort of come out of the skeletons mouth and the skeleton be
Lit a little bit to create the effect of a ghostly outline
Blowing eyes. Yeah. Yeah, and it's and the effect the idea was the criminal would go into a darkened room to begin with
So this was going on with the police officers
What's happening and then suddenly this curtain would raise and this furious glowing skeleton would be there saying you did it
Didn't you or whatever it would work so well the first time on I presume everyone who was who'd committed a crime and was trying
To cover it up isn't it's a very striking experience to have if you're the one being you know questioned by a skeleton
But I guess the criminal fraternity would would be more
Yeah, we'll be blasé about it after a few years of the skeleton being there. I would know about it
Wouldn't they yeah, they'd have to keep tracking it out and you know, different
There's a detail in this which kind of confused me because this is the 1930s
Which said that as well as having the the megaphone and the glowing eyes it also had a camera in the head
Yes film would you get sound recording as well to record sound as well and it actually included a way of
Recording the sound and the visuals at the same time onto this film. Yeah, that is very early
And we had cinema and stuff like that, so I think this it was a woman who did it wasn't it?
Helen Adelaide Shelby. Yeah
I think she basically took a load of things that have been invented around that time and said oh, we could do this with this
Oh, we could do this with this. Oh flashing lights. Let's do that for the eyes. Yeah
One thing I couldn't find out was her decision to turn it into an interrogation thing
Like that's quite a cool effect if you were like, oh, well, we could create this effect and put it on stage
What like did she just read a Christmas carol and was like, oh, I know what gets people guilty
But that's the thing she's she doesn't come from that background. So it's Helena. Sorry not or Helena
Rather than Helen and she she was a real estate mogul. She was like she's the bed on horses
There's nothing else in the literature about her that suggests that this came from any background in policing or anything like that
And she kind of disappears as well. You don't really
I found that she did die in
1947 right I found in the newspapers when it expired
And I found that her father-in-law Samuel was a famous Civil War veteran
His first foray in the Civil War was down the Mississippi River and the entire platoon was hospitalized because they all drank swamp water
That's all I found out. She had a husband called Edgar. Let's see how the other detail
Yeah, it's all she's remembered for now is is mostly this doesn't think I I found out that Tom Scott the
YouTuber had
recreated this oh this invention in 2020. So they recreated the actual skeleton and everything and did an experiment with three other people
where he left them alone with a cookie and
One of them had to steal the cookie and then he interrogated them and they didn't know what he was doing
So he was just like I'm trying out a new technique
and then he puts them in this room and
the first to
I've scared at first because they're in a dark room and they have no idea what to expect and then when the skin was it appears
They just crack up laughing
You would though wouldn't you I mean I can imagine it being spooky at first, but I'd be far more scared of a dark room
Yeah, so you know the one-way mirror thing. Yeah, there's not actually there's no such thing as a one-way mirror
No, there is it's actually a window
So that's the dullest fact I found at the course of research
It's all about yeah lighting. Yeah, it's a window covered with highly reflective coating
It's not a mirror. What makes the difference between them. Is it just because a mirror has like a
Steel background. I think the mirror has the that yeah, it's like a properly opaque background
Whereas with the one-way window as all the kids will be calling it
Oh
Because the lights are always off only in the room where the the senior cops are watching the questioning happen
But the lights are always dark in that way
Yeah, if you turned on the lights in that room you'd see them the thing is that is you want people to think it's a mirror, right?
That's the whole point. Yeah, if you say we've got our window here
Then they're gonna go. Oh, I thought that was a mirror like you have to call it a mirror in order to keep up
But everyone knows there are people behind there now. Do they yeah
No, the question is you don't know whether there's someone behind there or not
I can't believe they exist actually to the eggs. I've never been arrested. Have you been interrogated?
What did you do? I used to work in market research my first job and
Wait, there was a market research house, which was in Slough, and I was conducting the surveys
How interesting the focus group stuff. Yeah, it was all one-on-one stuff
It was with women between the age of 18 and 39 who had acid reflux and
They had to speak to me for an hour and a half each and I had to ask them all the questions about their
Yeah, and do you watch them through a one-way mirror?
There were there were there were people from I'm not gonna say which pharmaceutical giant for watching them through the window
The mirror whatever and they were in the they were in the next room and after the interview ended
I'd pop next door and I'd say was there anything else you wanted me to ask and they'd say yeah
Can you just ask question 17 again? Okay, so this this woman middle-aged woman with acid reflux. Yeah, I'm talking to you
I'm here. There's a big window there. Yeah, I mean mirror. Yeah, does she is she thinking all the time?
There's someone behind that or was the illusion kept the whole time
Because I reckon they wouldn't have no otherwise. What's the point? I think I saw I thought might have to say there might be people
Oh, did you observing but don't you know don't worry about it. Just talk to me looking to my eyes
Yeah, were you good interviewer or bad interviewer like you get good cop and bad
No, honestly acid reflux is totally normal don't worry about it. You can tell me about it. You're a sick puppy and you're gonna burn
Yeah
I was not a very good interview right and the weird thing was it was just two of us working on the case me and my boss and
After the fourth day of questioning sessions
We came down to breakfast at the sort of like premier room. We was doing whatever and we both had acid reflux
No, and then it turns out there was another
I once once in a focus group with with the with the windows thing
But we knew that they were people because you just know like oh well
Someone's got to watch it's just so you don't get distracted
But we had to play video games and give feedback on on the video games. I think it was little big planet
Yeah, and I said there should be more interrogation
I was wondering
What happens if you confess but the police of you confess to as a Catholic because obviously they can't pass on what
Confessions that but it doesn't really
Like it's a priest cop that's the pitch of the TV series. He's a priest by day
He's a cop by night, you know, but the priest is not allowed to tell anyone what's in confessed, right, right?
Because although when I was at school and I used to go to confession. We had good priests bad priests
The bad priests used to rat on you all the time man. Yeah, also, there's that one-way mirror in the confession
Spooky images in Catholic churches, they do you know
Growing red eyes, but this is the way that so I think in I think they're all
So in confession booths the rule is that the priest can't disclose anything to anyone. That's how I understand
Yeah, but there is some leeway
I think if there's so like if Dan I'm the priest, right Dan comes into the booth and he says
I'm going to kill James in fact number two
So if notice it sings a fish, right? I think I am allowed as the priest
I think some schools of thought say I am allowed to go to the police and say you might want to check on James check
He's all right. Yeah, you might be a threat to him at some point, but I'm not allowed to say Dan is going to kill him
Yeah, yeah, same with psychiatry, right when you admit
You know planning to murder James
It took me a long time to get that out in the sessions
Just kill him
What are you waiting for?
But they're allowed to pass on active threats, aren't they?
It must be able to. There must be vanishingly few cases of people in confession booths or therapy sessions saying like this is the time
Place I'm going to commit the moida
I don't think it happens much. I like that you tried to make it a lighter thing by
This has gone a bit dark. Let's say moida
Music is often used in interrogation tactics. That's a big thing metal music particularly we've heard about that
Oh, and like one time. Oh, yeah, and John Ronson wrote about the fact that like Barney music would be played the Barney the purple dinosaur
I love you you love that song over and over to to make people go insane ever play the blobby Christmas number one
I bet they have I bet they have it's seen as torture
But um one band that gets used a lot as Metallica and Metallica hate it because you know as any musician would have this opinion
It's that music and politics music and in you know interrogation and questionable torture
Shouldn't be mixed. I wouldn't say all musicians think that but well, yeah, I imagine most of them
I think there is a band in the States a Christian rock band that were like you can use our music demon hunters
I think the demon hunter. It's not cool. It's not quite yeah
So Metallica asked for their music not to be used which it wasn't there was an interview with the guy who has claimed that he killed
Summer bin Laden
I don't know if that ever was confirmed the seal six team and he said that Metallica reached out to them and said can you not use our music and
Demon hunter he claimed then got piped up and said you can have our music. It's fine. And here's some patches demon hunter came out and said
Actually, that's not the case. We didn't know what it was being used for. They just said they like playing our music
They made their own patches. So supposedly a demon
They only yeah, military would like to wear lots of different patches like the scouts
You're killing oh summer bin Laden bud
Oh
One of the most feared
Nazi interrogators was a guy called Hans Schaaf in the second one bore and he was not he wasn't a soldier
He was a Polish born. Thank you as a farmer. He lived in South Africa
but he was fluent in English and if you were an
Pilot or air crew and you were caught
You would go to this little town near Frankfurt and you'll be put up in
Reasonably nice digs and they just talked to you for a couple of weeks and Hans Schaaf was the one leading these efforts
And they would present you with this incredible dossier. They'd say here are all your unit members names. Here's your home base
Here's the commander's dog's name
Here's the pub that you guys all drink in when and they just they would present you tiny fragments of information that made you think
They knew absolutely everything
You were likely to talk and give away secrets of you know wish what the weaknesses of your planes or whatever it might be
But the son the incredibly weird things that Hans Schaaf after the Second World War. He went to work at Disneyland
He became a mosaic artist and he did Cinderella's castle at Disney or Disney World. I think in Florida
Yeah, that is do you know what though if I worked in
Nazi interrogation that I want to go off and then work in a magical wonderland
Art like you've heard that. Yeah, that's amazing. Yeah, I just imagine the interview where they want to find a mosaic maker
They're like, well, what did you do in your previous job?
Okay, it is time for fact number two and that is my fact my fact this week is that in real life
The author of Charlotte's web became the foster parent to the spider children. He based Charlotte on
So spider dad spider dad. Yeah, by spider children mean the children of a spider or not
So Eby white author of Charlotte's web who also penned the classic Stuart Little and quite a few
Bigger adult books as well the elements of style and is sex necessary which he wrote with James Thurver
These were huge books back in the day
He loved animals and Charlotte of Charlotte's web is based on a real spider that he'd seen
He'd spotted it one autumn in 1949 and he came back later and the spider was gone and
The sack of the eggs were still sitting in the web and he thought okay
I'm gonna collect that so he took it down and he put it into a box and he goes to New York
And he travels with this and he has it in his office and the eggs survived and and they came out these spiders and started
Crawling over his office and they even had their web shoot up and they saw them flying across the office and he thought this is great
I'm just gonna let them do what they do and so for weeks
They just made home on his desk in his office. It's his flat. I think it was yeah, yeah
Sorry, New York and and it wasn't until his cleaner came along who just went. I'm sorry
I can't clean everything but the spiders that are infesting this room
That actually then they were murdered. What did she not walk around?
I don't know. I guess my cleaner doesn't kill my cat every time she comes around
She could work around the spider. You don't have hundreds of cats the size of a tiny eyelash
I don't know. It feels like she could work around the spiders. Yeah, you'd think so, but she she complained
He said fine. You can you can kill them and don't have a cleaner. Jeez. I don't have a cleaner
That's how you not get your spider children buried
Yeah, yeah, so yeah, but it's quite nice to know that we never knew the fate of Charlotte the spider itself
I believe I would have died exactly the species
Yeah, we only live for a year don't they it's but if it's bound spider. Yeah, it's quite a good bond spider
That's what that was. I think was it? It's got a scientific name. I didn't see
Oh, yeah, but I didn't even know there was a common name of a barn spider. I've heard of the house by the though
So the spiders called Charlotte covac covatica. Yeah, and it's covatica. Maybe the scientific name it is
So Charlotte a covatica and the a is a shortened scientific word
So Rainer's I think right Aranis I might be pronouncing that wrong Uranus
Sorry just to put you a cap of the charlotte's web
So there's a pig and a spider. Yeah, and the spider saves the pigs life by spinning words into the web
Yeah, someone's gonna kill the pig the farm is gonna kill the pig farm is gonna kill big pig right at the beginning of the book
I think and then yeah, and Charlotte and the pig have an unlikely friendship
Hmm, it is weird that as a farmer you would see the words written in the web and think this pig is incredible
So is I actually didn't write down his full first two names eb
Elwin Brooks elwin Brooks. Thank you. Yeah. Yeah, so eb is elwin Brooks
But actually went by the name Andy his whole life
Yeah, and it's a really odd reason he went to Cornell University
And there's a tradition at Cornell
Which is if you happen to have shared the surname of the person who was the co-founder and the first president of Cornell
Who was a guy called Andrew Dixon white then you had to just be called Andy?
Because he was called Andy. So they showed the so they bite and and so he got given that at Cornell and then the rest of his life
That's what it's what his wife called him. It's what his friends. It's what his colleagues
I'm just that still happens at Cornell if you had surname white that you get nicknamed Andy
You know, it was a real pig as well as a real spider
Yeah, so he it's a lot of it's really drawn from life because he he lived in
Maine on a lovely farm and he just as Dan said he connected with nature a lot and he almost preferred his farm to we definitely preferred his farm to city life
but he kept a pig and in 1948 so
three or four years before writing Charlotte's web
He wrote the essay death of a pig which is all about a pig
he'd been planning to slaughter which then got very ill and
The pig had erycepolis, which is a
condition
Erycepolis. Yeah, erycepolis. It's a skin condition Dan Finsley couldn't pronounce a few years ago on this podcast
Yeah, and it's dangerous because it can transfer to people as well
It's a friend of the podcast
And he wrote I discovered that once one has given a pig and enema there is no turning back
The pigs lot and mine were inextricably bound now. Oh
So you had to give the pig a medical enema at one point or another and it really brought them closer together
Sure, I love everything I've read about EBY. I love he just seems such a dork
He would have been perfect. I think on this podcast like here's a here's an example of how dorky he was
So he fell in love with this girl called Catherine sergeant angle who was a fiction editor who worked at the New Yorker
And that's he was a writer for the New Yorker. She was married at the time. Yeah, that's right. Yeah, and they they eloped and
They had uh, you know, they had their marriage and then he said later on I soon realized I'd made no mistake in my choice of wife
I was helping her pack an overnight bag one afternoon when she said put in some tooth twine
I knew then that a girl who called dental floss tooth twine was the girl for me
Oh, that's so sweet
Well, I uh, I quite enjoyed finding out that when someone asked him why he wrote charlotte's web
He said, uh, I haven't told why I wrote the book, but I haven't told you why I sneeze either
and a book is a sneeze
That is his uh, yeah, he doesn't know why inside you and you just have to you have a story inside you and you have to
Share it with the world. Yeah, I guess it leaves your body at 17 miles an hour. Yeah
And if you keep your eyes open when you're right in the book, they will pop out
Did you see that letter that a little girl wrote to him asking him why it was nine years after charlotte's web had come out
And she said when's the next book coming out and he replied I would like to write another book for children
But I spend all my spare time just answering letters. I get from children about the books. I have already written
So it looks like a hopeless situation unless you can start a movement in america called don't write to eb white until he produces another book
That's harsh that isn't it? Yeah
But that is like the that is exactly the sort of reply that I end up start doing on twitter
Like with the reply guys and stuff. I'm like, oh, I'm just running out of patience now
Do you reply to reply guys? I used to really don't don't bother now. No, no, no
No, I've never heard that term. Is that just people who reply no matter what? Well, no, it's it's it's quite a sex-specific thing, isn't it?
Yeah, well, general generally reply guys tend to be due to reply to women to and in my case
Explain our own jokes to us or why they might be better somehow
in addition to something
often incorrect
Have you thought of trying harder?
He had a really interesting process for writing eb white
So he could never listen to music because that would be it would get his attention
Diverted and that and that's I think quite famous for any writer anything with lyrics get that away
But what he did used to do was sit in the bit of his house that had the most traffic in it
So his wife passing through his kids passing through whoever was in the house. Yeah, not like cars and stuff. No, exactly
But like just yeah foot traffic
From his family. I think that's crazy. I agree. I think that's really difficult to concentrate when there's so much happening
Yeah, it's that must be one of the most unusual writing methods
Anyone's any writers ever heard. Yeah
Like Dan Brown hangs upside down or something to write that sounds like a dr. Zeus book
Dan Brown
Yeah, he would do that if he had if he just needed thinking time he would hang upside down
I don't think he physically
Because the pen just wouldn't work after exactly we might have a space pen. Oh, yeah. Yeah on this anti-gravity or a pencil
You know, uh, stew at little. Yeah, man. Oh, yeah. What is it? What is it though? Best friend a mouse, right?
And was they right? I mean wrong. Oh, he's not a mouse. He's not even a mouse. Is he a doormouse?
No, no, he's so he's he's a child. He looks small. He looks like a mouse. What? Oh, right?
Really? It's very weird. No in the book
Yeah, in the book it's described as because he's he's given birth to by his human parents
And they say and the book says he's the size of a mouse
And he he has all the characteristics of a mouse, but he is
He's quite indeterminate as species. So in the book it's not illustrated as it or is it?
I don't know if the original edition was illustrated because in charlotte's web the illustrator wanted to give the spider
human woman facial features terrifying. Yeah, and uh, and they were like, no
She just looked like a spider and so that was just a spider, but in the animated film
She was given a face given. She's got a lady face. Maybe that's why because he hated the movie didn't he?
Yeah, he saw it and I guess like a lot of children's authors like pl travers seeing mary poppins the movie
Hated the way that their work is translated. Um, he hated charlotte's web. Um, that might be the reason
But this kind of makes sense that maybe stewart little wasn't
A mouse because he did have a bit of a bugbear about
When people made animals a bit more human-like rather than like charlotte's web
It was a pig and it was a spider
Whereas he can never understand mickey mouse and donald duck and say why are they driving a car the hell's going on there?
You feel like the mouse a mouse doesn't drive a car because I haven't read this book because his spider quite realistic
like band spider female band spiders will
Stick some like silk out of their bum and then walk around and that's got like pheromones on it
And then the males will follow her around. Oh, there's a whole chapter about this
It's where the spider babies come from brilliant. Yeah, but he did use a lot of technical terms
He explained like the different bits of like that. He was very he researched spiders for ages to get all of the understanding
So when you read it you get an understanding about like, you know, this bit of the leg is called this this bit of the hand
The end
He um, he was incredibly shy as well. He'd be white. He was very he's very anxious guy about not pretty much everything
Um, when he when he worked at the new yorker, he would sometimes go out of the fire escape if someone
He didn't know turned up at the office. Oh, he'd just pop out, you know of the window effectively
Wow, um, he skipped. Well anytime it was someone he didn't know at the office or someone who's coming to talk to him
I think probably someone coming to take office, isn't it? He wouldn't have done everything done. Yeah, you're right
Um, please give me it just sounds like someone who's smoking and try
Yeah, he skipped parties
He skipped his the burial service of his wife of many decades
He skipped the presidential medal of freedom awards ceremony where jfk was trying to give him a medal
The national medal for literature award. He skipped that too. He just did not want to go out
He was shy around women, wasn't he? Was he? Um, yeah, he once said I have too small a heart and too large a pen
And it feels like he forgets we have the bad sense of it
Yeah, he his wife even when he was communicating sort of love notes and stuff
He would still even hide behind an animal persona. I don't think he was a furry. I think he just didn't
Yeah, I don't think anyone thinks
But you thought that
Actually, he wasn't a fairy. He was a human with the characteristics of a fairy
Yeah, um, this is all by the way
It's a guy called michael simms who wrote this amazing biography on him
Who discovered that charlotte was based on a real spider found out this story about the the eggsack and he did an interview on npr
Where I was reading this on and um, he said that when it came to the audiobook the death scene
So spoiler alert charlotte dies in the book
Um, he found it impossible to read the death scene
Out loud and according to the producer it took him 17 takes in order to get it out finally
Uh, he said they would how many takes did your book take that?
I was just crying the whole way through you shouldn't have put the word erycee plus in
But he would go out he would go out for walks would try and get himself together to go back in and do it
And he would say yeah
He's like this is ridiculous a grown man crying over the death of an imaginary insect go back in and then just start crying all over
Not an insect, mate. Yeah
James is in the booth pressing of us and uh, maybe that's who's crying, you know the final light is and then the insect died
It is time for fact number three and that is andy my fact is that one of the world's best dance choreographers is called
Mr. Millipede
Um, I should say this was sent in by a listener
So thank you to Maggie Mortensen who sent it in. Um, yeah, and uh, mr. Millipede. I think he's Benjamin
Yes, and no now james is looking. It's giving me a look millipede. Is it millipede?
It's how he would pronounce it. It's how he would pronounce it, but it's not how I'm pronouncing it
He's not on this podcast. So no, but it's it's millipede. Yeah, it translates into french as a thousand feet, right? Yeah, there we go
Um, I've seen newspaper articles interviewing him who call him the man with a thousand feet
Really? Yeah, that's great. I think because he dances so well. It's almost as if he has a thousand feet
Maybe yeah, I get a lot harder to dance
It would be yeah if two left feet, but you've got like what 500
And this is just a fact about someone with an amusing name in the world of dance. Hmm. Yeah, no one is to have determinism
Yeah, yeah, I went to school with a girl called erin trimmer who became a hairdresser
Nice
Brilliant
Shout out to erin trimmer
So mr. Millipede, uh, is he's quite notable in the world of hollywood. He has choreographed a lot of movies
He's done june the first june movie. He did the choreograph for the um for the giant worm dance. giant millipede
Yeah, the big millipede that comes out
There's a dance in there. I believe I haven't seen the movie myself. Yes. There's there's a dance
There's a cool shifting dance over the sand
We sashay to avoid attracting the attention of the big old worms that live in the desert
Because they feel the vibrations of your feet they sense movement for them and they're incredibly sensitive to it
But if you walk in a particular way then well, they won't spot you. Is it a dance or is it just someone walking?
Well, it's a gate, you know a gate
I'm not seeing june, but I imagined that it was like a bit in the movie where they're like
And now we do the word
Everybody joins in and they're like it's just a step to the left. Yeah, basically it's I'm imagining
Yeah, mr. Millipede comes running out in leotard
It's like a Jane Fonda video. Yeah. Um, but he also did black swan
Which was the ballet movie and it was on that movie that he met his future wife
Natalie Portman. So yeah, mr. Millipede is married to Natalie Portman
Just some hot goss
Great yeah, yeah, they split up though because he's got together with one of the worms from dune
Yeah, um, but no just uh ballet unless anyone's got anything more on on benny mill. Um, mr. Millipede has got a tattoo on his abdomen
Of a bow house symbol, which I think is quite cool. You know the german architecture thing
It's a it's like a profile of a face uh designed by a painter called oska schlemmer
And oska schlemmer is really cool. He was he had five of his artworks in the nazi organized degenerative art exhibition
In munich. Do you know about that? So they piled up a load of art
Well, basically they the nazis decided and hitler especially because he was he thought of himself as an artist
They got a load of like german artworks that showed the greatness of germany and put them all in an amazing museum
And then down the road they got all the stuff that they really hated and said this is all degenerate this, you know
And I mean, which one would you rather see? Yeah
Like it's I would so much tragic but front to yet another hitler watercolor
exactly
But yeah schlemmer had a load of stuff there and then they had loads of rooms
Like a lot of them were quite anti-semitic the names of the rooms and stuff
But um, they had some that was like an insult to german womanhood
And then they'd have a load of paintings that were insulting german women
And then madness becomes method and nature as seen by sick minds. Oh, yeah, these do sound quite like quite cool
Yeah
Very nice. Anyway, that's just a thing about Bauhaus. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um the movie black swan just very quickly while we're still on millipede
There was a lot of controversy about the movie when Natalie Portman won the oscar for it because
Well, there's a lot of scenes which is to do with really intensive amazing ballet dancing
And there was a stunt double Natalie Portman was good at ballet, but she'd only done it for a year
She wasn't at the level that you needed to be in order to pull those moves
Um, but the person who played the stunt double didn't get any of the credit and there was a lot of questions about
Whether or not best actor should be going to someone who is not necessarily
I can see that
And there's a lot of emotional scenes in there and you know, so there's a lot of acting that goes on so it's justified
I feel like it should be a joint thing
Yeah, like if you win best actor for a particular role then anyone else in the film
That had to play whether it's a stunt double or a stand in or something. Yes, they should all get on stage
They share it, but if it's someone doing the back of your head for a day where you were busy shooting a different sequence
But they can come on stage, but they have to show only the back of their head
Zyruska Statue is only the back of the oscar's head
And and they all have to dress in whatever the actor is wearing. They're all wearing the same outfit
So we change it from the nominations being the actor's names to the character name of the movie
Therefore you can have multiple people character is a really good category. I really like that
Yeah, and then, you know, then it's not as problematic when people eventually do something that makes you go. Oh
Oh, I don't like them anymore. Yeah. Oh, I still like that character. Yeah, that's true
Interestingly, last thing on black swan black swan was made by Darren Aronofsky the director
And he also made the wrestler with Mickey Rourke
And initially black swan and the wrestler were meant to be one movie where a ballet dancer fell in love with the wrestler
And that was the initial movie. It was meant to be one
Cinematic universe combination and then you just split it into two movies. That's a brilliant
What I would have loved to watch it would mr. Milipede also choreographed
Yeah, the wrestling was pro ballet is fake
There's a thing called beat deafness. Have you heard of this? No, it's like I've got it. Yeah. Do you think no?
I'm sure you don't it's like tone deafness only
You can't dance. It's quite rare dancing well is subjective. Isn't it really? Yeah, it is
It is I'm more talking about being in rhythm. So they would they'd watch strictly come dancing for example and be like, wow
Why are they not in time to the band? It's that yeah, well, they would just it would be completely alien to them
It would be they wouldn't think they're out of time or they're in time. They would just be like, well, I don't know
What's going on here? He's just moving his arms and there's music playing but I can't put the two together
Right. What if anyone famous has that? Hmm. I mean, I definitely can't keep to time
I found that out by trying to learn the drums
And after many lessons and a very patient teacher realized I just can't keep to time. I always get faster
Always all the time. And I the thing is I love like I love dancing and stuff
I did dance in high school. I saw a video and I am clearly half a beat behind everyone else
Like it's yeah, yeah, I've just had to what kind of dancing was it?
Uh, um, I did uh interpretive because uh, it's a lot harder to prove wrong
Yeah, that's the best there are some dances that it's clear if you're a beat behind if you do the oki-koki and your arms in when everyone else is out
That's really obvious because you'd have to do like group ones as well. And that that that was more like modern dance
Or whatever. Yeah, so that one was one I was always out. Yeah. Yeah
I'd love to see just videos of that where someone doesn't know
Hi. Yeah, so we're actually on knees not shoulders
Didn't you do a bit of dance me? Yeah you where I'm thinking of your school because you went to a very interesting school
Oh, yeah, yeah, we went to a riddle steiner school. We did urythmi, which is a dance invented by riddle steiner
Yeah, so you used to go it was I you know, it's very kind to call it a dance
What it is is you just give it given a pole and you have to walk forwards and backwards just
Moving the pole from vertical to horizontal a metal pole. Yeah, it would be disappointing if you go to see a pole dancer and that's
Damn telling you about the yeti while he walks back and forwards
Um ballet moves. Oh, yeah. Did you know one of the most iconic?
sports logos of all time
Is a ballet move
Yeah, try and guess it. Oh, oh, I think I know. Yeah, there we go. Yeah, Michael Jordan the famous. Can we keep guessing?
Sorry, sorry
Sorry, go for it. Go for it. I was thinking the olympic rings. Yeah, no clothes
clothes
Do you want it one more? No, no
Yeah, so james is actually as I said earlier, correct
The very iconic Michael Jordan looking like he's going for a dunk. So his arms are out
He's got a ball in his hand legs are wide. It's not going for a dunk going for a dunk. Yeah, you go for a dunk. He's dunking
Okay, okay
Give it a few minutes. I've just been for a dunk. Uh, has it bounced off the backboard?
Yeah
Um, that's everyone assumes that that's him dunking. It's not he's in a photo shoot that he was doing with a guy called Peter Moore
Um, he did a ballet leap and that was caught in the photo and they thought that just looked so perfect a stance
For this logo. Did he know it was a ballet leap? Yeah, I believe so. Yeah
I there's not there's not too much information on it
It's just from this guy Peter Moore who pointed out that when the photos were taken that's what was happening
So we know that it was specifically that
Um, so yeah ballet in Michael Jordan land. I think I might be wrong about no
I'm right about this
When my parents used to ask me what I wanted to be when I grow up until I was about seven or eight
I said I wanted to be a ballet dancer. Wow
Ah legend and then I discovered football. Oh, you get to go on my list of
Uh famous people I'm calling you famous famous people who started off as uh,
Ballerinas or I wouldn't say I started off as a ballerina. Um other people on the list
Tupac. Oh, yeah, the rapper Tupac
I did it with him. There you go
Yeah Tupac was um, he he was the mouse king in the school play the nutcracker, but he actually studied interesting fact about the mouse king
Yeah, not a mouse
That's the dimensions of a mouse
Um, also on the list the Daleks from dr. Who bit of a stretch. No, not really they
So Terry nation when he was designing the Daleks he was inspired by the soviet dance troupe
The georgian state ballet when they're performing in london and believe that that would be a perfect like he got looked at and went
Wow, the way they glided he thought a Dalek would be a perfect way of doing that
Um, and so not only was that the inspiration
But the very first people who sat inside the Daleks were dancers to help with the with the movement because they understood how to
Yeah, use their feet
You never see ballet dancers going upstairs
Exactly incapable of going upstairs. I think louis the
Who's the sun king louis the fourth 14th? Yeah, he was into ballet and that's how he got called to sun king
It's named after a character in a in a ballet. I don't know which one. Yeah, he was massive into it
He used to like try and do the dances himself like dinners and stuff. Yeah, yeah
So what were they called because I was reading that ballerina is the word that you would use for a female ballet person
Italian wouldn't it
So what what's the word? We don't have an english word for a male ballerino ballerino
Ballerino, you know ballerino's. Yeah. Yeah ballerino. I thought I'd take us down a different
Laynote looking at ballet today. Um, and this was uh
Quite recent the director of a leading german ballet company had to be investigated by police
Because uh, he smeared a critic's face with feces with dog feces
Because she'd uh said too many bad things about um, his ballets. Yes, this is a terrible story. Yeah, it's a bit
It was a it was a let's just a drive by
Who's a drive?
I'll take some skills, isn't it? Just going for a dunk
Like so very high passion. It was a critic the critic had written a very hostile reviews of the of the this particular ballet
It was a previous show. I think yeah in the dutch mountains
It was called uh, which had been performed earlier
Furious with the review that was given and they were putting on this new performance
What's interesting is I don't think he knew that she was going to be there on that night
It just happened to have the dog poo at his pocket, which makes it more interesting if that's the case
Come on. No, it can't be true. You know, if he always have a dog with him, maybe like well, what's his dog's poo?
So I wonder if maybe he'd happen to have his dog with him at the time. Oh, god
Crikey. Yeah
I won't lie. There's some there's some reviewers who I think probably
Wow
There's the same names will bleep them out. Oh, no, it's a confessional space. You can say what you want
But if if I think there is a risk to them, I will have to what yeah, um
one of the so the big I mean there's a huge
I guess you'd say a sort of soft power thing for lots of I mean lots of very big eastern european ballet companies, especially russian
So the bolshoi ballet is very very very famous russian ballet. This is interesting
Again, it's people who you wouldn't think would were ballerinas, uh, but but were
So have you seen diehard?
Yes. Oh, yes. I yeah, so know about this. Yeah, this is um one of the henchmen in diehard
It's Carl. Okay. The big blonde guy gets shot. No, it's his brother. They get shot. Exactly. Exactly. He won best character in 1980
I can't believe you don't remember this
16 people except at the end
Carl Carl the huge blonde henchman who's extremely tough. He uh, he was a former principal lead dancer in the bolshoi ballet
Okay, uh, well, I because I've been to see a ball show in Moscow and the guys who do it
They're quite slim, but they're strong. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So strong a lot of strength. Yeah. Yeah
And it also takes a lot of strength to defect which is what
Is that what he did? Alexander got enough dead. Yeah, he was on tour in the usa
Big big thing of ballet defections. Nuri is it ish the cuff. Was it the other guy? Rudolph Nuri defected at the airport
He was about to go back to the soviet union
He had his handlers from the kgb with him and he he he fled to the french police who were who were there at the airport
But he didn't do it. Like I don't think he did a cool move
Okay, it is time for our final fact of the show that is james. Okay. My fact this week is that in 1997
Mattel recalled one of its cabbage patch dolls because it's had started eating children
I remember this see. Yeah. Yeah. Oh my god. Yeah, because I was a bit. I was really into cabbage patch kids
And um, and I remember that that was going that particular toy was going to be released in Australia
And then when they got recalled in the states, they never made it to Australia. How interesting I'd never heard of it before
But yeah, I mean it's incredible and when I say eating children it was only bits of children
It was eating. Yeah, I didn't manage a whole one
It was a toy which had a mouth which you could feed food into
And it had a rucksack at the back and then you would feed them a cookie or something
And it would go through the body and then it would mysteriously arrive in the rucksack and and that would be the game
But children started putting their fingers into the mouths or the hair or whatever and there was really no way to stop it
I don't think kids were deliberately putting their hair in them. I think the hair was getting caught
The hair was getting caught. I can imagine them putting their fingers in deliberately
Someone with a one-year-old child that you know that might happen
But anyway, once you put any part of your body into this mouth
You couldn't get it out because these because behind the lips of the doll of these two
These rollers right and they only rolled one way exactly. Yeah. Yeah, and they had um about 100 incidents reported
In this christmas time it started off just a few and then suddenly like more and more and more people started saying
Yeah, my kids are being eaten by this doll and just legally I I did find a claim by Mattel that these are all isolated incidents
But that really raised a question of how many incidents do they have to be
Stop being isolated
Exactly. Yeah, I mean they did sell many many
Probably at least hundreds of thousands up. They sold a lot of them and so it's a very low percentage of children
Who got eaten by these dolls one is too many, isn't it? Yeah, rather feels that way. Yeah
But yeah, cabbage patch kids. They're incredible. With these dolls
There's there's an extraordinary thing that I never appreciated about cabbage patch dolls
Which is basically their handmade to be in each one is very different from like if not even the model
There's obviously different models within the models each one has differences in it because they are basically
They're all supposed to be kind of unique. Yeah, like for instance
I got one. Yes
Oh, it's still in the box. Well, I only bought it yesterday
This is not one that eats children. This is just a normal cabbage patch doll
Wow. Wow. And as you can see mine is called Leona Jade. How you've gone? Is it a ballerina?
Yeah, she has like a little birth certificate and adoption papers and the idea is that they're all unique pretty much and
And that was different as well, wasn't it that you didn't buy it? You didn't buy a doll. You adopted a doll
Exactly. Oh, yeah. Oh, I've got them. I've got the birth certificates and everything. Yeah
Yeah, I had one called Alice who had
Came with hair like products so you could style the hair it came with a little thing of hair spray
So you could do its hair and I wasn't a doll
Kid like I didn't like Barbies or anything like that. I was more into trolls
But but the cabbage patch kid. There was just something
About it. Did you do you know about the cute schema? No schema of cuteness
So there was a study done
By a university in in japan, of course, they would study cuteness
And it was to look at the things that we respond to as humans to decide that something is cute
So the the forehead is normally quite large big eyes
The eyes usually quite low on the forehead
and sort of chunky short
limbs and things and they believe that the reason that cabbage patch dolls became so popular
And became like because they weren't they didn't do anything not like, you know before all of these the original ones didn't
They didn't do anything. They didn't eat children
They think that the reason they went so big is because it violates the cute schema
So
Oh, if you look at a cabbage patch doll, you'll notice that the eyes are actually quite small
quite close together and so there's elements about them that are considered grotesque
But not enough I find I don't I don't I find a bit creepy and that's why because it divides people and people either think they're cute
Or creepy and so people would talk about them because people go. Oh, they're so cute and other people go. No, no
They're really creepy. Yeah, and as we know from just the media today
If you can cause a divide in public opinion people will talk and debate and argue
Yeah, my um, yeah, my wife won't let me take this home. I bought it. I really really doesn't like it
Is this new was it like an ebay? It's brand new. No, I bought it. This was in a shop, right? Yeah. Yeah. So does anyone want one?
I thought what we could give it away to one of our listeners
Should we give it away to someone on club fish? I'm pretty sure I just claimed it, but yeah, no, of course, of course
You should always give away adopted children
It's just be a double adoption. Yeah. Yeah, let's do that. Okay. We'll work out a competition
Um, the thing about the sort of the look of the freakish look and so on that led to one of the great myths about cabbage patch kids
That circulated in the 80s, which I had
Reading this kind of makes me miss being a kid again and falling for these amazing legends. Dan, you still fall for these things
Yeah, that's true. That's true
But um, the the story was the reason they looked like that was because president of america at the time
Ronald Reagan gave a directive to the makers of it to show
What we would look like following the survival of a nuclear holocaust
And to get us used to the idea that we're gonna look quite freakish and it would be normalized by the time it happened
We would sort of accept it as normal humans being like that and that went around for it. Yeah, it's such a great story
But um, it it's you know, obviously not true, but that's really
It's not true
That's so fun. I find everything about them a bit a bit rum. Yeah
Well, did you guys read about the babyland general hospital? Yeah, was this one at some point? Well, actually it's mentioned on this box
it says that um
There was a young boy called Xavier Roberts who discovered a magical cabbage patch
And he built babyland general hospital where his children now live and play until someone takes them home to care for them and love them
Right and that sounds like just a bit of corporate guff. Yeah, actually. It's a real place
So he so he kind of well, we'll get on I'm sure we'll get on with the history of how they were originated
But in 1978, I think he opened up and I think it was a former medical facility
He opened up babyland general hospital and you could go there as a punter and they held live births
At the hospital and there was a write-up on um slate
Okay, every half hour or so an employee dressed as a doctor or nurse gets on the pa and announces there is a code green
That means that mother cabbage is in labor
And it's time to head to the magical crystal tree to watch a baby being born
The birthing process lasts under three minutes. Uh-huh not realistic
Um a nurse in scrubs and latex gloves stands among the cabbages and tells the crowd that mother cabbage has dilated
The full 10 leaves apart
That's such a gag for the parents
Like if you have no idea the parents are going to be like, oh, I see what they're saying
As the crystal well, there are very specific parent gags as the crystals at the base of the tree begin to glow
The nurse gives the cabbage a shot of imagicillin and announces she will be performing an easyotomy
A pieziotomy gag there as opposed to a c-section which stands for cabbage section
The nurse gently spreads the cabbage leaves reaches in her gloved hands and slowly pulls out a naked doll
The kids in the crowd murmur gasp and applaud
People say that's creepy
Oh, I'd love to see that
But it was the whole story was one of the reasons the other reasons they became so popular because it
Rather than just being a doll. It was this whole
You're buying into the need us. Yeah
Like you're actually adopting a thing, you know, the parents would be like, oh, that's a really cute idea and oh
Oh, my my kid could adopt a doll and stuff. And so yeah, and it worked
That's amazing. It really did work because they were absolutely massive when they were when they first went out
When was that going to be in like the 80s early 80s? Yeah, and there was riots when people were trying to get them in shops and
Um, I was reading some newspaper articles from the time
About these riots that were happening in the in the states
Um, the citizens voice newspaper. This was in pennsylvania one pregnant woman bit another patron and knocked his hat off
I think she was just trying to eat a cookie
Another woman was punched in the face by a female shopper
One woman chased a man through a parking lot calling him an sob
The simi valley star from california said one woman was swinging a baseball bat wildly at other women
To get one of these dolls and it wasn't even the last doll in the shop that she was getting
Apparently because all these dolls are slightly different from each other
She'd seen one that she particularly wanted and she just didn't want anyone else to go near them
So she was swinging the baseball bats
And in 2008
Four kids entertainment Inc who at the time on the license for these they released a special edition of the dolls to commemorate the riots
Oh, wow
And did it come with riots? No, it was just like riot gear
They've become slightly different over the years like this is the one that i've got here is a bit more
Finally and a bit more toy-like than the originals the ones that they did to commemorate. They were
Um more close to the originals. Yeah, you can see I mean it's you know
It's since becoming a parent and understanding the christmas rush to get toys
You can understand why movies like jingle all the way are so you know, Arnold Schwarzenegger's most relatable movie
It's that was all about a toy. Have you not seen it a relatable movie? Absolutely. No, I never think of a more than cold in the barbarian
Yeah, yeah, even more than kind of neither more than julia even more than terminator. Yeah
It's more than more than can be gone and call terminator three rise of the machines
No, no
So zavia roberts the person who invented he's mentioned on the side of the box and correct in your
controversial highly controversial
21 year old art student when he first
Notices that there is a german technique king of needle molding and he sees a lady called martha nelson who is
Making these doll babies and he goes oh that looks really interesting
She has adoption papers for the babies. Um, she has original names for the babies
He goes off changes the technique ever so slightly
But it was very much lifted from what this woman was doing and then he kind of went off and ran with it and got all the
Credit for creating this new style of doll. Yeah, because basically she made this doll, right?
She was selling them to him because he owned a gift shop
And then he wanted to up the price. She refused and so refused to give him any more dolls
And so he said well, I'm just going to make them myself then basically that's what happened
And did he want to mass produce them a bit more because he did yeah
And then the official website says that he was into needle molding
And that he learned quilting skills from his mother and all that kind of stuff
It seems very much. It does. You know, yeah
So what we're saying is that the side of the box here where it says that the bunny bees
We're saying they're not involved at all
No, I think one really weird thing about this this doll. I mean, there's a lot of weird things about this doll, but supposedly
There's a guy called zavia
And he runs a hospital that looks after these
Cabbage babies until they're adopted. That's the guy we're talking about zavia
But if you look at any of these things
He's signed all the buttocks showing us the doll's butt. If you look at the bum of the doll
His signature is on the bum. Really? And I think that's kind of a weird thing for someone running a hospital to do to their babies
Well, it's like those surgeons, isn't it?
So, you know, there's surgeons sometimes they get in trouble because there are a few surgeons who've got in trouble for burning
Their initials on a patient's liver, you know, mid-operation and then it turns out you've just, you know
And it's kind of I guess it's a fun joke
But that's effectively what zavia appears to have done on all these ties
Well, maybe sign them with pen and they went off and got it tattooed afterwards
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it could have been their own decision, you're right. In 2020 bringing in trolls, my favorites
There was one, uh, it was called the poppy and sing doll, I think
And basically she had a little button on her tummy that you would press her and she'd be like
"Ray, let's do a song" or something
Um, but she also had a button underneath her so that when she sat down she would say other things
But that happened to be right, right in the crotch, like right, right in the gusset
Um, it was where that button was located and most of the sounds that she made when you pressed that
were gasping
Her going "Oh" and "Weee!"
Yeah, like it's just sound effects
So there was a, um, there was a petition to recall it by a lot of furious parents who said that it would be grooming
Children, yeah, we've got room on this doll for two buttons. Okay, we've got the tummy one great belly button brilliant
Can anyone think of where we should put the other button?
You know the hand
Play-doh had a their play-doh mountain cake
Cake mountain, sorry the play set that came out
Recently for Christmas, but the extruder, you know, it looks like a syringe
That you would put the play-doh in to do the icing on the cake is incredibly phallic like
If I like enough that it definitely wasn't a mistake
Children won't understand but you know
Is there like the equivalent of beat deafness where you're just
Yeah, and sexual in your window blindness. Yeah to bias and arrest of development way
Understand all those innuendos. Yeah
I um, I hosted a make-away takeaway on citv, which obviously went so well. They decided to close the channel and
Um
But uh, that was an arts and craft show. It was really really fun. But the amount of times they had to stop filming because they go, uh
It's looking a bit phallic like anything that you would make
Anything like event because anything you make there's something there's usually a moment where you have to make something that's sort of like sausage
That might be our problem
She's doing it again
Close the channel
Okay, that's it. That is all of our facts. Thank you so much for listening
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things that we have said over the course of this podcast
We can be found on our twitter accounts. I'm on at shriverland james at james harkin andy at andrew hunter m and beck at beck hill
Comedian or be chill comedian if you spell it wrong. I actually know you spell it the same, but you just pronounce it differently
Yeah, uh, or you can go to our group account, which is at no such thing or why not email us on podcast at qi.com
You can also find all of our previous episodes up on our website
No such thing as a fish.com
But why bother listening to our podcast when there's a far superior one out there called the problem squared
By our guest with us today back hill and also one of our very close buddies mathematician matt parker amazing guy
Um beck give us a quick run down of the podcast
Our listeners send us problems and we we solve them matt solves them and I I help
Are they maths problems or personal problems most of the ones that matt answers uh maths ones and the ones that I solve uh
Yeah, usually personal or creative
Like how big a burger can you fit into your mouth? Nice? Cool. And how's it going? It's doing well
It's doing well, but we have set our sights on we're trying to surpass you guys in terms of positive reviews
So we're on uh 2000 five star reviews on spotify at the moment. You guys are on 11 000
So we've set our sights on trying to beat you
We've told people not to then give you less than five stars. Okay. We've just told them to not vote for you at all
Give us five stars. Okay. Cool. That's a backhanded compliment. I've got a problem. I'm going to be writing into your show with beck
All right, we'll do check it out also beck's brilliant kids books horror heights. They're amazing the third one's coming out very very soon
Uh, just come out. Yeah dead dead ringer dead ringer. Check that out as well
And uh come back next week for another episode of the two star reviewed
No such thing as a fish. We'll see you then. Goodbye
Bye
You
(upbeat music)