Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode of no such thing as a fish coming to you live from my editing suite straight to your ears
We are all on holiday this week having a nice relaxing time
Enjoying the great British weather and so what we have for you is one of our
Compilation specials loads of fun bits from the last few months that didn't quite fit into the show
But a really funny really stupid really just does messing around these are always my favorite episodes by the way
I absolutely love them
I genuinely think some of the best bits of fish that we've ever done have been in these conflations
But it's all sorts of bits all sorts of subjects loads and loads of facts loads and loads of fun
We really really hope you enjoy it. We will be back next week with a normal episode with a very special guest
More on that next week, but for now I guess all there is to say is on with the podcast
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish a weekly podcast coming to you from four undisclosed
Locations in the UK. My name is Dan Shriver
I am sitting here with Anna Tyshinski James Harkin and Andrew Hunter Murray and once again
We have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts from the last seven days and in a particular order here
We go starting with you Andy
My fact is that after his death Anton Chekov was brought back to Russia in a refrigerator wait in over fridge awaited well
Well
Bugs Bunny's gonna be doing my thing for me. I had a friend who used to sleep with his eyes open, so
Every now and then we'd be sat in the front room like you know
Playing video games or something or just chatting and then we'd be like oh rich hasn't spoken for a while
He'd be sat there with his eyes open and it turned out he was asleep
Are you sure he wasn't just trying to avoid talking to you
Clever way
He did sometimes talk in his sleep and say shut the fuck up James
We had just in the sort of modern-day theater version of that James and I got a behind-the-scenes tours of the Harry Potter and the
Curse child set which is the play and in the West End in London and
It we were told at the time that it takes about a million pounds a week to run the whole production
There were so many different little bits and pieces that go into putting it on and one of the things that they have is
There's a moment where
Two of the characters need to emerge from a lake and they've built under the stage a massive water tank
So on the payroll for the Curse child are two scuba instructors who go inside with these kid actors
And they have a they have a little mouth breather on and then they come up through the stage
Completely soaking so it's like this body of water, but that's how
Can I just say I was on this tour with Dan and he's talking rubbish. It's all magic
Completely magic and the reason I know that is because when you go backstage you can see all the ones
backstage and they're plugged in to the
Electricity so you know that it's definitely working. I didn't know you needed to charge a wand. They're all Bluetooth
No
Sorry, I don't understand why these children had to be submerged in water before they came on stage
Was it just so they looked wet? No, no, they came up through the floor of the stage
So it was a tank built underneath the stage. So they were coming up
You but why are they in that right?
Plot coming out of a lake. Oh
They're coming out of a lake. Sorry. I missed that bit. Right. Well, that makes sense. I
Actually went to see the play so I should remember that
But I did leave at the interval
It's literally just before the interval. It's the last thing you would have seen
Well, I remember because Anna, you came out saying there's a fucking lake in this one alone a bullshit. Why are they so wet?
Why are they so wet?
I don't understand how they did it. I can't my brain can't fathom
Do you know who is the highest grossing actor of all time?
I got sent this by our friend Justin Gaynor on email yesterday. He asked me if I knew
So the highest grossing actor so what this means is if you're in a movie
They add the entire amount of money that that movie has made to your amount
So it's brilliant who's been in the most very very high-profile movies in history
I think it was the guy who I mentioned a few episodes ago Frank Welker
Scooby-Doo and the Grinch he did the dog in the Grinch think about that the Grinch is big
But it's not the biggest think about the biggest movies of all time
Andy Circus has been in the biggest movies of all time as CGI guy. So what's your what are you naming as biggest movies there?
Avatar Lord of the Rings
think bigger
Bigger than that even
King Kong and Lord of the Rings Star Wars I guess have we heard of this person or is it?
Yeah, you've had a few extra and it's got the best chance to get this I would say but you are my is it someone who plays
Harrison Fredby background II
Yes, yes
Someone in Jackie Chan films. No, no thick. What's the biggest grossing movie of all time? I was Titanic. No
Ben her
It's a new movie with the wind is fair, but I'm talking about actual money's adventures
Okay, and almost all of the top 20 are Marvel films base. Yes, so Robert Downey Jr. Is no
Someone who's been in all of them John Favreau. No
Samuel L. Jackson. He's that he's number two. He's number two, but he's not been in all of them is a Stan Lee Stan Lee
Because he is in a tiny cameo in every single Marvel movie up until he died and the couple after he died as well
And so if you add up all of those amounts, then he is the biggest of all time
And he was in more rats as well Kevin Smith's movie
I'm not sure if he was in Little Doritz, but he might have been
At the moment right now there are 200 spy albatrosses in the world
Which are flying around logging illegal fishing vessels. This is very cool
Fishermen hate albatrosses famously
They do the H and mariner and stuff. So now they have good reason to hate them. They do have good reason. Yeah
The French National Center for Scientific Research
It fitted them with little GPS trackers because it's like there are so many illegal fishing boats out there
But they and they switch off their their unique ID systems to try and take over all by all fishing boats
Have a sort of radio ID system and if you're fishing in illegal waters, then you turn it off
But the the birds cover so much ground
You know, they can see a fishing boat from 20 miles away and they can pick up the the GPS signals that these
boats aren't able to switch off and in the first six months of the trial
They found 353 fishing vessels in that time of which one third had their ID systems switched off
Implying that they were up to no good and fishing in illegal waters. So this could be a this could be a useful
Technique and do they so but they're doing it unwillingly the albatrosses, right?
I think they ever get together and say I hate this bloody, you know monitoring collar. They've put on me
It's a real it's a real albatross around my neck
Very good. They find that very offensive actually Anna
Didn't see for such a long time where you were going with that. I knew I'd have to see it all the way through it was
It's just not quite common parlance enough that you don't have to finish it off
Um, there's only one other thing I know about cheetahs. Um, and it's that this is a really strange thing
It's that um, if you if you have cheetahs in a zoo, you have to be really careful to pick up their poos because
They there's a particular disease which is spread via cheetah feces and normally they have massive ranges
And you know, they never come across their own poos again. Well, obviously that's not the case in a zoo
um, but in the wild
Scientists study them by their poos and but it's a real problem because cheetah families all poo at the same time
So if well, they do say a family that poos together stays together, don't they?
It's really a nightmare. So you've got a cheetah family
You're a scientist observing them and it gives you the dna and you can work out who's fathered whom
Which is really interesting because cheetah females make with lots of different males and then produce a letter
You know, you can have three different cubs in a letter by different three different fathers
So it's useful to know who's fathered whom for your studies
But obviously they spread out and do their mass poo at the same time
You have to photograph all the cheetahs as they poo you have to map the poos
Then you have to assign the right poo to the right cheetah and then you can study them by the dna
I remember growing up in quite a large family and every morning it was a bit of a stress to see
Who could get in for a shower first
Imagine the jeopardy if you all have to poo at the same time
That is oh my god, thank you
If I've just had a vindaloo
And I you know, I've got my seven siblings there and I'm saying I'm absolutely desperate guys. Are you ready yet?
Well, I have to wait sort of seven hours until one of them is managing to crimp one out
It's very stressful
And then do you see that's why sometimes when you're wandering through Africa you see bags hanging on trees, don't you?
Yeah, the cheetah scientists who've left those poo bags there and they always claim they're going to come back and pick them up
You know in recent podcasts and I was mentioning to us how Stephen king is the master of just taking anything
And turning it into a horror story no matter how ridiculous. He just knows how to do it
So have you guys heard of the Stephen king story the mangler?
No, no, and this this was made into a movie
Um, the story is about a police detective investigating a sudden rash of deaths caused by an industrial laundry press
And this is a laundry press that has become possessed by a demon
So the the villain in this actual story is a laundry press itself going around killing people. Yeah
Um, he can go around
Well, actually he's more interesting to me. He's in he's in he's in his is in laundry room
So no, uh, so you're safe if you don't go in the laundry room
Yeah, that's a good strap line for the film
In fact, I suppose you're you're kind of probably safe as long as you don't put yourself into the mango
Right. Yeah, it's not it can't really be able to the mango must have some kind of independent movement where it can attack you
Right. How how's it might it's well, it might know it might lure you in it might be like
Hey, hey come you know, it might it might speak and get you to go to it or something like that
But I see what you're saying james. It's like we're all we're all safe from charles bronson unless we go into his cell
Like that's you're right. Just don't go into his cell. It's a terrifying thought to leave us all with
Well, they were they were very dangerous though mangles
So in a way, this sounds like it was more historical documentary than his classic horror
Um, they were people used to get injured all the time
I was reading a book that was called save women's lives the history of washing machines
Uh, which was written in 2003 about how um, and it went it was a by a guy who runs a museum about washing machines
And he said whenever he showed people around at least one older person would reveal a scar they had for a mangle
At some point so every you know every time he had one woman who was like
Oh, yeah and revealed a huge bald patch on her head from where she was scalped by it
Because they'd be steam powered quite often and then electric of course. So you couldn't stop them
So if you got your hair caught in a mangle, that's your scalp
Then why are all these people who presumably have PTSD from being mangled in a mangle going to a mangle museum?
It's um stock on syndrome, isn't it?
They've fallen in love with their mangler
Wow, you see Stephen King finger on the pulse. There's obviously a huge market for this
I gotta say that honestly like you always tell us how great Stephen King is and then you regale us with some bullshit story
That makes no sense at all
Diane Keaton just a bit of celebrity trivia. Yeah, Diane Keaton wore clothes pegs on her nose to try and make it thinner
Never had any surgery plastic surgery, but in many ways. This is a kind of surgery
She said in an interview that she did it and the only other person I can find who ever did that was meg and little women
Who used to sleep every night with a peg on her nose to make her nose thinner? I don't think it worked for either of them
But she must have got the idea from little women, right? That's but unless she got it from a cartoon
Because that's the only other people I could think could do that. Yeah, which pegs on this when she was a child, Anna
No, no when she was a young woman. Yeah, if you watch Annie Hall again, Andy, you'll see
Diane Keaton has a peg on her nose
Not the new ones. They've CGI'd it out. But yeah the original
Anna, did you read that fact while reading about sylvio saba by any chance?
I didn't actually
Well, he's got a he can teach
Meg
From little women and Diane Keaton
I think I'll do because he has the record for the most clothes pegs on his face at the same time in one minute
Actually, the most clothes pegs added to the face within a minute. All right. Has it a guess?
Uh
Well, I don't think maybe my skin isn't stretchy enough
But I can only imagine being able to get three or four on mine before it gets too stretched out
I'm going to be honest the Guinness World Record is higher
Yeah, but I didn't expect whether you asked me or when I said what I could do I wasn't thinking well, you know
When you say how fast did Usain Bolt run the 100 meters? I don't think well
I could do it in about 15 seconds. So probably about the same if it's a world record holder
It's going to be better than me. It is better. It is five
five
Okay, let's be serious seven
Okay, thanks guys. Um, it's 51 in a minute 51. That's almost one a second
I know and I'm amazed at just the speed of adding them never mind how stretchy his skin is
Yeah, but um, he he has a bit of form because he's one of these guys who has loads and loads of records
So he's also got he's got about 200 records
He's got the record for most underpants pulled on in 30 seconds
Um, you can actually do both of those records at the same time if you had an outdoor clothesline, couldn't you?
I was really about russian dances and russian balls
Um, they had a ball season in russia which lasted from christmas until masslennitsa, which is like pancake day
It was brought in by peter the great
So they were compulsory if you're in high society you had to go to these balls
The only way is if you had a serious illness or you were in mourning you could miss the ball
But otherwise you had to do it
And then you would do all of these dances you would start with the waltz and then you would do a hungarian dance
Then you'd do another dance another dance and then the final one was the mesurka
Which was like a big russian dance where everyone puts their arms around each other, but then you pair off as well
Uh, and of course anyone who's read anica rena will be very familiar with that kind of thing because of course, um
When ana came into the ball and she danced with alexie. That was kind of the big
Sorry, that's a bit of a spoiler. Don't put don't push your luck james mentioned
There used to be cheaters in america
Like not pet cheaters, but um real kind of wild cheaters. Uh, well, they're false cheaters, but they're kind of very similar
And they're called mirror. See mirror synonyx
They were known as but they died out and the only reason we know about them is because they have in
Um north america they have pronghorn
And pronghorn are really really fast and they move in lots of directions and stuff like that
And the only way that they could have evolved to have run and dodge
And kind of jump around is if there had been a predator that was chasing after them
And so they realized that there must be this other thing and so they called it a mirror synonyx
That's bizarre cheetah. Yeah
And do we have evidence that this cheetah cheetah existed?
They haven't quite found the bones or anything yet, but they just have inferred that there must have been a predator
That was faster than these pronghorn otherwise. Why would they evolve to a get so fast?
Does it's fun? I think that's a big inference. It's fun
It's fun going fast. Why do people buy lamborghini's?
Yeah, well there used to be a predator that had even faster cars than us
That used to come after us and that's why we evolved lamborghini's. I didn't know that
Can I quickly tell you one thing? I don't think it'll go anywhere, but um, the first polish language
Encyclopedia, I just read the other day. I was called noe atene
Which meant new Athens and their definition of the word horse is everyone knows what a horse is
[Laughter]
That's it feels like that was the last article they had to write and they just didn't have the will to do it properly anymore
It's such a good thing, but apparently and I don't know any Polish obviously, but um, apparently
Everyone knows what a horse is has become kind of a phrase to mean something that is more obvious than it seems
Like it looks like a really technical thing, but actually it's really simple
So, but you still know encyclopedia entry it became a sort of in-joke in Poland. Exactly. That is so good
There was a um website um movies from men it's called that did a list they went through
350 films and they did a death count compiling the deadliest actor list
And this was a few years ago. So it might have changed. I don't know if the expendable movies have been used in this, but um
So, you know aliens
We've driven to go into all these incel websites
There's a top 10 list and who do you think has more kills? Is it Schwarzenegger or Stallone?
Well, I would have said Schwarzenegger personally
I think so too. There are a couple of unbelievably silly sort of commando films where so I'll say Schwarzenegger too
I know you're not allowed to guess on this because
So it is Schwarzenegger who has as far as I can tell 842 kills
He ranks number four on the list number six on the list. Can we guess?
Yeah, yeah go for it. Okay. We heard of number one. Oh and Stallone, by the way has 786 so
It's um, it's not a huge difference between the two of them. Is it but yeah, who's in at number one with 1296 kills
I would say it's Moff Tarkin in Star Wars who blows up the planet of Alderaan of course, which I'm guessing now has a very much lower
population than previously imagined
Um, okay killing an entire planet. That's good. What about Thanos? Oh, yeah
um
I don't know. I can't imagine who'd get it's a dan. You're someone in a war someone in war films, right?
It can't you can't be including pressing a button on a bomb, right? Otherwise. Yeah, I think this is I think gotta be hand-to-hand
Hand-to-hand almost so I'll give you who's a bunch. I'll give you three and two
Number two is Dolph Lundgren with 919
Two is jet lee with 1076. Is it that guy you like? I know he'll be yeah bruce lee
Bruce lee must be one. He does not appear on the list. Oh someone like someone who played a famous. Oh jackie chan
I mean jackie chan. Yeah. No jackie chan doesn't appear on the list either
Is it someone who pacifists jackie chan likes to keep people alive? Yeah, okay?
Um, is it picochoo from detective?
Yeah, there was a bloodbath at movie. I really regret taking my three-year-old to that
Is it forever? I mean how surprising are we going? Let me give the answer the answer is
Mila Djokovic
The only woman to appear on the list of the top 10 in the man list
With 1290. Oh that's sticking one to the incels, isn't it? Yeah. Yeah, are we talking about evil?
Resident evil yeah, six resident evil films all of which I've seen
Have you they're great. They're so good. You're the one who tallied up the kills for the site
Well, a lot of them are zombies in that those films so but I guess I guess that counts. That's it. I don't know
Yeah, I don't know what criteria movies for men use
Regresses there are a search, do you think?
I had pineapple last night for dinner by sheer coincidence with and the reason I I had it actually with um
Caramel sauce poured on top that we received as a Christmas present from some people that we work with Anna. Are you okay?
Sorry, that just sounds like a meal of last resort is what I'm trying to say
Like we'll use the Christmas caramel sauce and pour it on top of the pineapple
I mean, it does feel like you had a certain amount of food at Christmas two months ago
And you're getting to the really last bits of the Christmas buffet
It definitely has been there for a while. It was the beginning of December
They sent it I because I hate waste, you know and the pineapple was just going off because no one wants to eat a pineapple
Um, that's been sitting in our fruit bowl for two weeks because it gets delivered with the fruit delivery
And this is why you know, there's this thing where um in the 1700s
People didn't eat pineapples because they were so treasured. They just used them for decoration
But I think it's just because there's such an ass to break into you can't be bothered. Yes
They are a bit of a pain
I always I uh, this is not going to go in but I always make um like a green curry and put it inside the pineapple
Right, so you scoop out all the pineapple stuff and then you put the green curry inside
But it is unbelievably difficult to scoop out. It's all right if you slice it up
It's not that hard, but if you're trying to scoop out the inside, it's completely impossible
Do eat the pineapple on the side pineapple goes in the curry as well very nice very nice
And then I save some of it and usually have it with like meats the next day when I use sweet meat
Because like it goes well with gammon and stuff, doesn't it? Hmm. Yeah classic
anyway
Join us join us next week for cooking with harkin
Yeah
That's funny. Um
Who who takes the most uh naps on the planet national in national terms?
Well, I would have thought like the spaniards maybe yes
Spain has such a
Reputation for their siesta's and it's not born out almost 60 never have a siesta
um Spanish working hours are longer and they tend to sleep a bit less than the rest of europe
And do you know whose fault it is? Uh, was it like the nazis they're usually supplied for everything, aren't they?
Yeah, it was it was the nazis
It's the fascists, but it's the spanish fascists presumably
Actually, no, it's the german fascists in cahoots with the spanish fascists. So in 1942
general franco
Fascist yeah changed the country's clocks in spain to match berlin's time zone in solidarity with hitler
And uh, no one ever changed them back and so the spain is on central european time or european central time
Which is the same as warsaw 1200 miles east of there and this is a mad time zone for the country of spain to be in
Um, it's part of the reason that spanish people work. I mean also the weather and so on but um, you know
Spanish people tend not to eat until 9 p.m. They don't go to bed before midnight
There is a whole campaign to get spain back onto gmt
because spain is just
Not in the right time zone for the circadian rhythms of the people who live there. Wow
We would have thought there's a real too strong arguments a it really doesn't work for them in terms of their circadian rhythms and b
It's got a strong association with fascists. I know ditch it guys
Can I say one more thing about um soap detergents seeing as this was about dad's house? Oh, yeah
There is a thing at the moment in, um, europe called the cern axion solar telescope
And it's that cern and they're trying to find these tiny particles called axions
Uh, and axions are particles that are a little bit related to the higgs
Bozan and things like that. They're going to help us explain what dark matter is if we find them
They were named by a guy called frank will check
Uh, and the reason that he called them axions is because that was his favorite soap powder that he used
And he said that it sounded a bit like a subatomic particle, doesn't it an axion kind of sounds like it
But he said if they find them it will clean up a problem with particle physics
Lovely
Nice
He's also got the best interns name ever, you know, who's going to sort this out? Oh frank will check
Do the boons you have sex for pleasure or do they just have it for procreation? I don't know
I don't know pleasure. They seem like fun loving
Criminals well bonobos do yeah
Like kind of an in between i don't know bonobo is nearly a nanogram of baboon. Well, that's why I was thinking actually
Yeah, yeah, I think if any animal is an anagram of another animal
I'm always disappointed when melons and lemons don't taste the same. I think they kind of should
Yeah, absolutely. Yeah
And they've both got boobs and knobs if you sort of break their names down they do yeah, so it's quite sexy
Yeah, well, we've revealed a lot
This is this is why lexicographers and zoologists are very different
It's so nice to leave knowledge out there for the experts
Any baboon expert is listening won't feel threatened by this podcast, I think
Um, I think my favorite thing that I found out about air force one is that there was a room temperature
Button a little dial that was added onto the plane and this was because president johnson when he was vice president
He kept uh arguing with the crew about lowering and raising the temperature of the cabin
He was always too cold or it's too hot
And so they eventually got tired of this and they installed a temperature control in the conference room
But it was fake didn't work at all
And so he could go up and change it on his own never changed anything
But he'd go that's better and sit down and uh think that he'd controlled the weather inside
Yeah, okay. That's what we call gas lighting and this
There was a haunted rocking chair in the 50s. Did anyone read about that?
I read about this devils. No, it was in a blog called strange company, which I can highly recommend
It's an unbelievably good blog
And this was an article from the boltermos son of the april the 29th 1950 about a rocking chair with the mind of its own
and what it was
Is there was a family called the floyd holidays and they had a rocking chair
And it just wouldn't stop rocking all the time and it just had rocked nonstop for 37 days
And it became really really famous and was on tv in america
We'd go on chat shows and these people would go on chat shows and they'd be like, yeah, we've got a rocking chair
That won't stop rocking
And a lot of people kind of went to visit the house
They almost got rid of it because so many people were coming to visit this haunted rocking chair
And and some people said that maybe it was um vibrations from the refrigeration motor that was
Going off right next to it
But when they moved it to another house it carried on rocking as well
And then eventually they took it to be on tv this rocking chair and it had to go through an airport
And some vandals hearing about it ripped it up and kind of looked inside it to see if there was some motors or something like that
And it was insured for a thousand dollars
So um, they the insurance company said well, I would give you a thousand dollars
Or you can have seven hundred dollars and you can keep the chair and that's what they went for but it kind of stopped
continually rocking at that point
Uh, and we don't know why it was rocking all the time
But most people think that perhaps it was you know
The the legs were in a way that they never quite got in
You know, but hang on isn't that a perpetual motion machine? Isn't that the thing we're told can't happen?
Exactly, that's why it's mysterious. That's why it's in the newspapers. I know
I can't believe all the world's scientists all the brilliant minds have not yet figured out this rocking chair
I I imagine probably they they had other things to figure out but
Basically what happened was whenever it started moving
I assume it just took ages to stop and then other things would get it moving again
And it just would carry on rocking for ages. I bet I bet they when people came to see it
They they said right don't go in don't go into the room just yet
Then as soon as anyone went in the chair was rocking, but also grandpa was just shuffling away from it
Right, look there. You've seen it's rocking and no one's sitting at it, right? You better leave come on get out
Get out. You're probably right
Donald trump obsessed with badges apparently. Sorry. I know we all thought we'd never have to talk about him again
And I'm bringing it back
But there was a report near the start of his term that he from within the white house among his staff
Uh, that said he would constantly be asking ryance prebruss who was his chief of staff at the time about badgers
And was interrogating him because ryance was from wisconsin, which is the home of the american badger
I think it's their state animal and he'd say things like do they have personality? Are they boring?
How do they work? Are they mean to people? He was desperate to know about badgers
Wow
There was a badger in the white house wasn't there. I think it was roosevelt had one called josh
I'm going from memory here
I think yeah, right?
Teddy roosevelt. Yeah, because he had almost all animals didn't he collect he was and he had a lot of crazy pets
I think he might have this is again also from memory
But was he in wisconsin and like a little girl said do you want a badger?
And he said yeah, sure and then she went away and ten minutes later came back with a badger
And then he had to keep her or something awkward. Yeah
Maybe trump read about that and thought if teddy gets one I want one
Um, I mentioned it mainly because did you know that um the nickname that scaramucci had for ryance prebus was rancid penis?
It's amazing that scaramucci only lasted 10 days in a job with his back of making friends
Oh, I've got a this isn't a gross butterfly. Actually, it's just a weird sex butterfly thing
Um, which is and it's another american one actually it's in the sierra nevada mountains
There's a butterfly which has been discovered to be a hybrid of two completely separate species of butterfly
which at some point shagged each other
And produced fertile offspring. Oh, that's that's completely counter to the way the tree of life normally works where species split, you know
Yeah, so this is one of a handful of cases of branches merging
Wow, is this the beginning of the end? Is this when we all start contracting back down into one single?
No
So we're all you know
This theory is from about four years ago, which is well that we're all going to evolve back into amoebas
Oh, wow, I forgot and I'd had it before
I'm consistent
If not good that I forget what I've said as soon as I say it
Okay, here's the thing about changing from black and white to color and back again. Yeah, this is mad
And it's kind of I guess so james's fact is about the
Israel removing color
And that was done again in the uk in 1970 by itv who where the staff went on strike
They went on a three month color strike
Where they were objecting over their pay rates and so they just started making shows black and white again
And because these are quite technical shows to be filmed they just refused to work with the color tv equipment
They switched off the color tubes on the cameras. They were working with and for three months itv just had to go back to black and white because the staff were
I know so funny. Yeah
Wow, and then eventually they resolved the strike and they turned they were willing to make color tv shows again
I wonder if they lost a lot of viewers in that time
Don't know if they like you know last year when the archers
Couldn't have covid because it seems to be run by 120 year old persons
So it was just monologues for about six months and I think you know a lot of people said they would leave the show
But their listenership has sustained and recovered. So maybe the same
Great news. Yeah, but it's similar right? Is neither black or white nor color actually the archers obviously
That's what your imagination is like for me. It's just like the tv's turned off
But that is true, isn't it some people is that right that some people imagine things in black and white
I think yeah or dreaming. Yeah dreaming black and white when they grew up with black and white tv, isn't it?
James, you know that condition that you have the a-fantasia. Yeah, where you can't imagine
What is it you can't imagine anything that are not images
Images that are not there. Yeah, I can't imagine. I can't close my eyes and imagine anything
I was thinking the other day it's very weird that it's called a-fantasia because disney's fantasia is one of the most
Extravagant colorful imaginative things. Do you know what the prefix a means?
No
So absolutely not weird at all when you yeah, when you when you really break it down
Hey, there was another musical knife that I found
Which was from switzerland in the early 19th century. It's really gorgeous. It's like an early very basic swiss army knife
Um, but it's got two blades one for fruit and one for flowers. And if you could imagine a tiny swiss army knife
What's the difference between those two things? It's like you've got your fruit knife and you're trying to cut a top off the flower
And you're like this is not working at all. I will tell you I know
What it's for because the fruit one the fruit blade is guilt and that's so the fruit juice won't corrode it when you slice your lemon
Fine. I suppose that does make sense
Exactly. And then the flower one I guess that does there's no problem
But it's got a musical mechanism inside and this is I think it's from about 1800 and it's got a little clockwork
Barrel inside and it plays music and this was on the antique shoulder a few years ago
Sounds incredibly annoying at the dinner table, doesn't it? And it's going to ruin the vibe if you are trying to murder someone
If you have someone in the heart and it starts playing twinkle twinkle
Is that what happens at most of your dinner parties? I know it is. Yeah, we've got a very big seller
There are some industry legends of naming drugs, which I like as well
Arlene tech is very famous in the biz as the woman who named Viagra
That was her huge innovation. Yeah, and she did it by speaking to so Viagra is a brand name not a
Generic name. Yeah
And she did it by asking a group of urologists what it's like
What it feels like for men when you've had erectile dysfunction and then it's cured
And that one of the doctors said imagine a strong stream
And she combined the word vigorous and the word niagra and came up with Viagra. Ah
Yeah, really good. Yeah
The u.s. Can be strict on its rules about like even brand naming, right?
You've got quite the strong rules of brand naming and the us seems to the us rules seem to basically say
You're not allowed to suggest that the medicine works
So there are a few things like there's a hair regrowth treatment called regain
It's called regain in europe and the rest of the world in america
It's called row game because you're not allowed to suggest that it's always going to cause your hair to regrow
I think hair growth stuff is generally
Oh, it's gorgeous. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, absolutely. They're done. Right. There's another one called which is a stop smoking tablet that you take
Which is called champics
And in america is chantix or chantix because champics is a little bit too triumphant. They're like champion
Exactly, and what if we're not a champion? What if you take them and then you're back on 40 a day by the end of the week?
It's misleading
I guess it's a bit like that thing about how digestive biscuits weren't allowed to be called that in america because they don't help your
Digestion is that right? Yeah
It's very literal but the champion thing you should be allowed to call your
Thing like awesome pill even if it's not right like you should just in theory you would have been a quack in the 18th century
Roll up roll up come and see daniel schreiber's pills of mystery
Stick them up your bum. It'll make you flow like diagra
You know the song wap by cardi b. Um, I've read reports about it in the daily telegraph
There was a republican who was going for congress this time called james p brady
Who said that every time you heard the song it made him want to pour holy water into his ears
What's wrong with this song wap? Was it it sounds so wet-ass pussy and it's about um, wow
Yeah, it's it's about holy water right now. It's an extremely feminist song about women taking charge
of their sexuality
That's disgusting james. So that's gonna sound really bad now
And holy water will only make things wetter. What you need is a holy towel
Some holy kitchen roll perhaps
Um, she credits poppie with saving her life who olive oil
Yes, I'm not who we're talking about
Oh down ron dolly parton. No, she credits poppie the dog with saving her life
Oh poppie the dog, of course
You know the second most famous poppie
This was she was in the 1980s where she fell in love with someone
I think didn't have any physical relationship, but she kind of you know, she was married
But it's a long time. She fancied someone else
Was upset when he didn't fancy her and she looked at her revolver and it's weird
She's dolly part such a bubbly cheerful person
But for a moment she looked at the little gun
She keeps in her bedside table for when she gets burgled and she thought about
She thought about killing herself and then she said she heard the little tap tap tap of poppie the dog's feet coming up the stairs
And she took it as a message from god
In fact, she told the Times in an interview. Well, you know god is dog backwards
So I took it as a message from him
dog's god's little
Little pockets of friendship. He sends our way
And it snapped her out of it. Wow. There's one thing
Physically that we don't know about dolly
Which is
What her arms are like
So she always despite wearing spending, you know, 50 years wearing very tight or very revealing costumes in lots of ways
She's always got sleeves
She's got very long sleeves on and there is a there is a conspiracy theory and even saying that I've talked about way too much
There is a slight small tiny subsection of fan belief that she's absolutely covered in crazy tattoos
you know from wrist to shoulder and
Uh, it's possible, but she has she's been asked about it and she's denied
Um, in fact, she she's quite a clever denial where she she only actually denied that she has snake tattoos
So we know her arms are not covered in snake tattoos, but um, they might be there might be all sorts of other tattoos on her
We don't know there are other types of tattoo. Yeah, so many others
I've just googled dolly parton. Yeah images. Yeah, I can see her arms
Her arms are here. She's handy. Come on, for example
She may have got the tattoos after she did the playboy cover recently. She was that's what I'm saying possible
I'm I have to say I've now done what dan's done and maybe it's our different search preferences
But I can't see any naked arms in any of these pictures
All his naked arms. There we go
Put in dolly parton playboy because that's a famous thing that she did and she's asked to do again for her 75th birthday
Which has now happened and I don't think it's happened for her that she's back on the cover
but she was a playboy model and
And yeah her arms
I've just googled dolly parton's arms
Uh, and there are a few definitely a few images relatively recent. All right guys
We don't have to just you know, she there is such a thing as arm makeup. Can I remind you? Yeah tattoos
Yeah, and I don't like us just google image searching my admittedly quite weak fact about dolly parton's arms
I'm amazed by the fact that there's such a thing as arm makeup
Again, please please don't google whether or not arm makeup. So I'm just gonna do that
Is there a such thing as is there a such thing as arm makeup?
We are definitely is they do it for movies, don't they they do it for movies all the time
Yeah, but you wouldn't sell arm makeup in a separate section of the shop to leg makeup
Is leg makeup a thing
I'm not saying leg makeup is a thing. I'm being just in oh no, I'm being
I'm being corrected in real time and dan it feels horrible. I don't know how you
It's not nice. It's long. You get used to it though. You do you eventually learn to love it
300 more episodes of it Andy and you look tough
Here's a fun thing
About sunglasses and tanning. Oh, yeah
There is a theory that if you don't wear sunglasses
You can get a tan even though you're wearing suntan lotion and you you know wearing clothes
so
There's a theory that just exposing your eyes to light
That will help you tan and this is really this is based on an experiment in mice
So I don't think an equivalence has been done on humans as far as I know. Basically, I can tell if a mouse is tanned
Well, you just shave it. I guess you shave it. Yeah, thanks. Sorry. So this was an experiment in 2000
And the scientists involved they they dressed mice in tiny suits of aluminium foil
Adorable middle little mini mouse armour and they gave them holes for the eyes
Okay
So they had your armour mice and then they had normal mice and they exposed both sets of mice to UV light for a year
And then they looked at their skin and it turned out that both sets of mice
Even the ones which had been wearing suits of armour all year
Had similar amounts of melanin in their skin implying that it was the exposure of the eyes
That was the thing which was giving them the melanin
Does that also if you take that in the other direction, if you go sunbathing with your eyes closed, then you won't get a tan
Yeah
People have suggested that no people think and it's it's well because it's online
I think probably off the back of this experiment people think that if you wear sunglasses
Then your body will be tricked into thinking that it's not sunny and so it will not produce melanin and so you'll get burned really badly
And I so and it's weird. No one's properly debunked this yet
But there was a molecular biologist who has asked this who said that it is not your eyes
At least in humans that trigger the hormone response in the pineal gland which make you produce melanin is your skin
So it definitely doesn't happen in humans. I don't in mice clearly different different setup going on
But don't worry wearing sunglasses is not a substitute or a counteraction of sun tan green
I love just jumping back to andy's description quickly of the mice. It's such a fine line, isn't it between
What you would say is animal cruelty in the kind of way you tell a story
A lot of people would be like and for a year they dress them up in tin foil these poor mice
But andy's sort of going it's a they look like cool little knights. They look they had a fun time
You're the kind of guy andy they would hire
For movies just so they can say no animals were hard during the making of this movie
All the animals had a whale of a time in the making of this movie except the whales
It was terribly mistreated
I like this one. I found one drug that's called um anakinra
Which is a balm that you put on your neck if you've just had it knocked off by a train
It's actually for arthritis. Yeah. Oh, it's a real thing. Oh, yeah
You never of course never lived to experience arthritis
I found out a nice term
This is just a bit of drug industry slang and it's when a drug is no more effective than a placebo
And with the term for that is crossing the futility boundary
Because literally the drug is completely pointless. It doesn't do any better than a placebo drug. So yeah
You've crossed the futility boundary. So you can use that in day-to-day life now
Hopefully we're not we can't buy many of these drugs, right? Surely they're not being approved
Uh, oh, I just mean in day-to-day life. You can say in your own activities
I've really crossed the futility boundary on this
Whatever activity
Broaden out like if you're watching a tv series in your three seasons in you're still not enjoying it
Do you think we've crossed the futility boundary of this section of the podcast? I think the podcast in general some years ago
The texas theme reached number six in the uk charts in 1992 and andrew lewis webber was the man behind it
I bought it. I remember. Did you really? Yeah. Yeah, andrew lewis webber
Composed the tune. No, he remixed it didn't he? It's a russian folks on. Yeah. Yeah, is it? It's by nicolai necrosof
You speak russian james. Can you can you give us a little excerpt possibly just because I did it because I did it
off my curly rod
I'll try i'll try so he goes
Nice one
So angeloid webber then took that very well known traditional tune and passed it off as his own sounds very unlike him
Oh, my goodness. Yeah, musical industry. That's just a little just a little slam from having listened to too many
Lloyd Webber soundtracks over the years. Wow
It's also rendering this podcast completely legally unstable
Okay, that's all of our facts apologies for my singing
Um, if you would like to get in contact with me and tell me how terrible my voice is you can get in touch with me
On at james harkin you can get in touch with andy on at andrew hunter m
You can get in touch with dan on at schreiberland and if you want to speak to ana you can email her on
Podcast at qi.com. Of course, there is a group account on twitter
Which is at no such thing and if you'd like to learn anything more about the show get some merchandise
Maybe get some tickets to come and see us live then you can get all that information at no such thing as a fish dot com
Okay, we'll see you next week. Good. Bye
You
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]