(upbeat music)
- Hi everyone, welcome to this week's episode
of No Such Things A Fish, where we were joined by the legend.
The national treasure already, I think,
but definitely future national treasure, Tom Allen.
- That's right, Tom is absolutely fantastic
as you're about to hear.
He's a flanner, he's a man of out town.
Among many other things, you might not think it
'cause he's so dapper, but he's also a gardener.
- You might not think it 'cause he speaks so nicely,
but he's also a podcaster.
(laughing)
- And he has a new podcast out, it's called "Pottering" with Tom Allen,
and he gets a celebrity to his garden,
be it Nish Kumar, be it James A. Castor, be it Natalie Cassidy,
and they talk about gardening.
- It's lovely, and I think they do some gardening as well, actually.
- He probably has some Natalie Cassidy Bagonias,
get some Nish Kumar, Asperd Distras.
- Lovely, can James name a third plunge?
- Absolutely not, but if you want to hear Tom's podcast,
then go to wherever you get your podcast,
it's called "Pottering" with Tom Allen,
and it's absolutely fantastic,
but Andy, we have some more news.
- That's right, the other thing to say is that,
in a week's time, we're gonna be doing the first
ever Club Fish Quiz.
Now, this is for people who've joined Club Fish
at the top tier, the friend of the podcast tier,
we are gonna be doing a quiz globally, I imagine.
We suspect hundreds of thousands may be attending,
and you can be one of them, it's gonna be on Zoom,
or an equivalent streaming platform.
We've all been writing our questions,
we've been showing them to each other,
we've been coming up with silly games,
it's gonna be so much fun.
So mark your diaries or your calendars
for Friday, the 23rd of January, 7pm British time,
but if you're around the world,
we'd love to see you there as well.
- Gonna be so much fun, we can't wait to do it.
But anyway, please enjoy this week's episode
of "No Six Things A Fish" with the incredible Tom Allen,
on with the podcast.
- On with the show.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, and welcome to another episode
of "No Such Thing" as a Fish, a weekly podcast
coming to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here
with James Harkin, Andrew Hunter Murray, and Tom Allen.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones
with our four favorite facts from the last seven days
and in a particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, and that is Tom.
- In September 1945, a small booklet was discovered
in the main offices of the third Reich in Berlin,
or Reich, if you're from southern Germany.
In Berlin, it was a secret list of 2,820 British individuals
who'd be rounded up in the event
of a successful invasion, and Noel Coward found his name
on page 34.
- Oh, okay, why were they going after him?
- Well, firstly, I think anybody in an entertainment
would be annoyed that they had to go so far.
(laughing)
- Mind your own name.
- There's only one thing worse than being on the Nazis,
deathless.
(laughing)
- And that's not being on the, I can't believe
you're quoting Oscar Wilde in a Noel Coward section.
- Oh yeah, we'll get onto that.
- Well, they just kind of crossed over
in a sort of Dalai Lama way, yeah, yeah.
- Is that what was he?
- Very Dalai Lama way.
- Have you ever looked at who died just before you were born?
- No, I never had.
- Oh, that's a funny thing.
- There was one of the popes,
the one that was before John Paul II.
- Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
- So I think it was, yeah, just before I was born,
you died, so I'm not saying anything else,
but I am Catholic, so.
- I think you could still do it as well.
- I can?
- Well, no, I've been excommunicated as we've said,
but.
- But what a comeback story that would be for you.
- Yeah, and actually the Pope.
- I can change the rules if I'm the Pope.
- Yes, yeah. - Exactly.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Let's get back to Noel Coward.
- I know, I like that.
I was suddenly panicking about who died in 1983.
- Yeah, lots.
- Mount Batson, no, that was '70, '70s.
- Yes, Mount Batson was.
- I went straight through.
- I just got to see what this is.
(laughing)
- We should quickly say who Noel Coward is.
Noel Coward, very famous way around.
- Yes, I didn't bother to say that.
I just assumed all your listeners would know who he was.
- Yeah, but you know better than anyone,
'cause you're part of the Noel Coward Society.
- Well, I have been involved.
But I, the, the, Noel Coward, yeah,
usually seen as a playwright and a writer of songs,
particularly Mad Dogs and Englishman.
He was also an actor, musician, and an author as well.
He wrote a novel.
Well, he was wanted by the sinister,
Armstrong, V1, V1, V1, V1, I don't know what,
I don't know what that looked like.
- I was like a music channel in Germany.
- I'm so glad for V1, V1, V1, I'm glad to come.
A department, it was a department that evaluated
intelligence material.
Well, he was a, it turned out a British spy.
And his cover had apparently been blown.
And if the war had gone differently, well,
the man known the world over further song,
"Don't Let's Be Be See to the Germans"
could have ended his days in front of a firing squad.
- Wow. - So, yeah.
And when the list was discovered amongst other people
who the Nazis didn't like for various reasons,
and the author Rebecca West sent him a telegram to say,
"My dear, the people who were to be seen dead with."
- It was very cool. - That's very good.
- This song, interestingly,
got him in a bit of trouble back home, didn't it?
- Yeah. - What was it called again?
It was cool.
- "Don't Let's Be Be See to the Germans."
- Yeah, so came out during World War II.
It was a satire.
It was-- - It was signed by the BBC.
- Exactly, because the satire didn't quite cross
as well as he hoped it would.
They thought that he was actually genuinely saying that.
- I was excited about it, because I think it's the only thing
that Noel Coward has in common with the prodigy
I found there, songs "Smack My Bitch Up,"
which was also banned by the BBC.
- Can you imagine that him reading "Smack My Bitch Up"
Noel Coward in his accent? - "Smack My Bitch Up."
- He'd have-- I think he'd have gustyed up the lyrics a bit.
He'd have made them cleverer.
- But I always wondered how he got away with being a spy,
'cause he was so flamboyant, right?
It seems like as a spy you have to hide away a little bit.
- Well, Radio IV did a dramatized version of what he was like.
I think a lot of it as well was propaganda work
in North America, obviously, the US.
I think to Ghana support for getting on board with the war effort,
which I know wasn't the case at the beginning.
So I think he was seen as sort of a special envoy,
I suppose, as much as anything.
I don't think he was going behind enemy lines.
- No, but I'm-- - Hamburg.
- He'd been recruited even before the war started.
I think there was someone called Sir Robin Vancetart
who was running-- - Sounds German, actually.
- Yes, but he was at the foreign office
and he was recruiting various people
to go about their business in Europe, quite successful people,
and then report back on the national mood,
what people were saying, just kind of sort of soft intelligence,
as it were, not, you know.
You don't need to observe this tank column
and where it's going, this ball bearings factory.
It was just like what you're hearing in social conversations.
And I think Coward was sacked partly
because he was too public in his maneuverings.
And also because everyone looked at him,
and this is after the war started,
and they just thought, we've just got to a load of parties
and man, happening, you're really letting the side down.
And actually, he was doing the war work, like he was doing.
- He was, he was really publicly shamed about it, I think.
- Yeah. - I think the Daily Mail covered about it,
and said like, they said outrage, go it over there,
spit it all this money, public money, go to parties.
- The Daily Mail, who's departed,
that's, he's just before the war.
- Ooh. - Well, it might, yeah, I mean.
- Yeah. - But I should check,
I should check, it was the Daily Mail,
but it's out there and I'm lovely.
- Well, he used to, again, trouble with the daily express.
- Yeah, and actually, this is another war connection.
So he wrote the screenplay and started a movie called,
in which we serve, which was a really good movie,
often got used to get the morale up
and show how the war was going.
And he kind of based the character on your past life.
- No, that's, and yeah.
- So he consulted with him and that was largely part of it.
- Could we say who went back and was it?
- Sorry, yeah. - Yeah, he was,
he was. - Oh, oh, Mountbaton, I think.
- Oh, Mountbaton. - Yeah, Lord Mountbaton, wasn't he?
- Oh, yeah. - Yeah.
- And he was, he was Prince Philip's uncle
by loose connection, I haven't researched it.
- By big, the brother of his mother, or, yeah.
So it's kind of like loosely unpleased to him.
- Is it like one of those uncles,
who's like just friends with your parents?
- I have a feeling if we're, yeah, exactly.
And you were shocked at some point
to find out that wasn't your uncle.
I remember this when I was five.
I found out Uncle Joe wasn't my uncle.
And I was a bit outraged.
- Uncle Joe. - Yeah, I was in a cup of coffee.
- Yeah, so anyway, Mountbaton was part of this thing
with Noel Coward.
And the daily express started ridiculing the production,
saying that how could you have Noel Coward play
a high-ranking general in the army?
- He's a captain.
- A captain, right?
- In the Navy. - He wasn't.
- Yeah, yeah, he didn't come across.
- Apart from that, don't carry on.
- I feel like I'm going quite lost in it.
- Sorry, no, I'm barely tripping it.
Well, I mean, I'm pretty sure he's a captain.
I haven't watched it, bro.
- I haven't seen the movie and you're a part of the sustain.
And you're being absolutely pancake
between Tom's love of Noel Coward
and my love of military rank.
(laughing)
Sorry.
- Just bring a bit of golf into it.
- You absolutely can't.
(laughing)
- Yeah.
- It seems quite out of time to me, Noel Coward.
- I know his name and I know he's part of the plays,
but I do, you mentioned Oscar Wilde
before I do play some as part of that era,
but he was in things like the Italian job.
- Yes.
- He was, you know, in the '60s.
- Yeah.
- That was his, I think, his last acting role.
- Right.
- He was born in 1899.
And he served briefly in the First World War,
which I didn't know.
'Cause again, I think of him as like,
he's wearing his pajamas, maybe dressed in gown.
He's smoking a pipe through a long holder.
He's writing brilliant dialogue.
He's writing plays like Blind Spirit and Haifi, you know.
- Yeah.
- Witt.
- But he served in this company called the,
the Artists Rifles, which--
- Just sounds awful, doesn't it?
I think it was so, yeah, I think it was a place where
maybe I don't want to be unkind.
Maybe slightly less useful fighters were replaced.
And I think he wasn't ever put in any sort of position
where he'd have to do anything to practical.
- Well, he got himself out of it quite fast.
And this was only in, I mean, he was born in 1899.
So I think he was signed up aged 18
or maybe conscripted.
I'm not sure.
He was discharged for Neurosthenia,
which was very much a catchal you've got nerves.
- Sort of tying a piece of string around his finger.
- Why?
- I guess it's sort of stress.
- A stressor situation, definitely.
- It'd be a tick talk about it now.
- But I think part of the reason he got so involved
in World War II as a spy or whatever,
is 'cause he was a bit embarrassed by the fact
that he'd gone into World War I quite young
and then had to leave quite quickly.
- Yeah, his company suffered lots of casualties
in the last two months of the war.
I mean, hundreds, you know?
So I think, and that was after he'd been
invalidated out as it were.
So yeah.
- I love the main thing about him outside of his plays
and his acting and his songs is the gossip.
He was Mr. Annicdote, basically.
He's like the Charles Brandrath of his day.
(laughing)
- Charles will be very happy.
- Charles Brandrath was absolutely in love with that.
(laughing)
Oh my goodness.
What a Christmas breath of joy.
(laughing)
Well, we'll clip this out inside of him.
- Yes.
- And so there's one great war, Annicdote from him,
which is he said, he never forgot the site
of Coco Chanel entering a Paris air raid shelter
followed by a maid who carried a gas mask
on a velvet cushion.
(laughing)
- That's wonderful stories.
- It was a time when people did,
well, I know there was strata of class,
but I think if you did transcend those strata,
you would just end up being at parties with these people.
- Yeah.
- I don't know, maybe it would be the same now,
but I mean, just like--
- Because his mother, I think, had some vague sort of connection
to the aristocracy.
- Oh, is that really?
- Maybe like an uncle or something.
(laughing)
- Yeah, she, like, feel mashable.
Hague was a distant cousin of hers,
and her sister married the nephew of Sir Henry Ponsonby,
who was private secretary to Perquean Victoria.
- Oh.
- So they were kind of like close to high society,
but not quite in there until he became very famous
and really hobnobbed with the--
- Right.
- Yeah, 'cause I don't know what kind of pretty lower middle class
grew up in Southwest London and very suburban reasonably poor.
And his mum was a real stage mum.
- Yes, she was the Mrs. Worthington, I think.
She was the real Mrs. Worthington.
- She pushed it.
- Mrs. Worthington is--
- Oh, is a song, don't put your daughter on the stage, Mrs. Worthington.
It's kind of a song told from the position of a producer,
I think, in an audition, but essentially kind of saying
to this very pushy stage mum.
She's talentless, please stop putting it into the audience.
But Noel Carrot's career happened partly
because of a medium spiritual guidance.
So his mum went to a show at the Coliseum
and an American celebrity medium Anna Eva Fay.
And his mum asked, "Should Noel, young Noel here,
go back to school or should he stay as a child actor?"
And from beneath this big sheet that she was (laughs)
a medium Anna Fay said, "Keep acting."
- Oh, wow.
- Yeah, I didn't know that.
So that was a, I think, I suspect they probably would have kept
him acting, even if the medium had said, "Go back to school!"
And I suspect the ambition was strong.
- Still there.
I haven't seen Blife's spirit, but I think it's a very satirical
about the spiritualism movement.
- Is that right?
Is it sort of parodying it?
- It was a big drive towards it, wasn't it?
The 20s and 30s?
- Yeah.
- Where people would have--
- Yeah, I guess, I mean, that probably makes sense, doesn't it?
But my dad, even remembers his grandmother having her friends
around for like a say-on, which isn't it?
- Like they go into the back room or something, yeah.
And all these women would come in and try and contact with dad.
- Yeah.
- But it was kind of seen as his thing that people do quite
socially.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It was like a book club of its day.
- The book club of its day, exactly.
- His writing was extraordinary, the speed at which he wrote,
because there were so many knoll-coward plays.
There was a story that, in 1935, in the summer of that year
alone, he wrote nine plays.
That's how quick he knocked out a song called "I'll See You Again,"
which Frank Sinatra recorded while he was stuck in a taxi
in a traffic jam.
- It's similar to, I think, Elton John, in the way
that he, apparently, writes his songs in five minutes.
- I really do.
- That's the tangents and tiaras.
It's something about that creativity.
It's something quite useful about actually not allowing
lots of time.
- Yes.
- And he also says the songs slightly come to him.
He doesn't claim to have written.
- Is that Elton John now?
- Yeah.
- Elton John will say that the songs sort of arrived to him.
- After the war, just to go back to his sort of post-war life,
he spent a lot of time with the Navy.
And in fact, during the war as well,
he frequently would just hitch a lift on royal Navy ships.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- He would just...
- So he had to get on that.
- Well, how did he get off?
- He spent a lot of his life as a tax exile
because he was so financially successful
in the first half of his life
that a lot of his life was just moving around
to different low-taxed jurisdictions.
And he once joined a ship in Bermuda called H.M. Dragon
and, or H.M.S. Dragon, maybe.
And the captain said, "What the hell are you doing
on board this ship?"
And Coward replied that he was,
quote, "exhausted overworked on the verge of a nervous breakdown
and to join the ship in order to be nurse back to health
strength and wait it on hand and foot."
And the captain not only gave him a lift to Trinidad,
he gave him loads more lifts later on.
They became friends.
- This was just like...
- Is as well as a naval captain,
you might be quite pleased
that if somebody, which he and famous,
was suddenly on board.
- Oh, yeah, great.
- That's the entertainment.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- And better than the inser or whatever it's called.
- You say he was rich, he was so rich.
He was making £50,000 a year,
the equivalent of which today,
that would be £15 million per year
that he was making in the late 20s.
- In the late 20s and he was really burning through it, though,
so he had a lot of financial problems
and hence moving to tax havens like Jamaica,
where he moved right next door to Ian Fleming.
- Oh, yes.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, I love this spy.
- And there are stories that he turned down the role of Doctor No,
that that was actually offered to him for the first bond.
- He was just called Doctor before they offered it to him.
(laughing)
- Doctor Noel Coward.
- That's the original.
(laughing)
- Okay, it is time for fact number two,
and that is my fact.
My fact this week is that there is a Marvel superhero
called The Gardener,
whose superpower is that he is insanely good at gardening.
- So is it that he can grow things very, very fast?
- No, it's more that he is obsessed with gardening.
(laughing)
- And he is almost an immortal.
- Gardener gets supposed to be good for you
if you're getting older.
- Yeah.
- Like it helps you live longer, doesn't it?
- Exactly.
- Well, yeah, and potentially forever.
- It's your life.
- It's forever.
- You give enough time to it.
So he's part of this group called The Elders of the Universe.
And basically,
the other one is really good at bowls.
(laughing)
- The other one is just really good at being racist.
- Absolutely ruins Christmas, yeah.
- Captain Crossword, come and say it.
(laughing)
- Yeah, okay, these are each of them
with the last survivors of their own race.
And these were races that evolved just after the Big Bang.
And the idea is that they have extended lifespans,
but not because of a mortal,
but because of a single-minded obsession with a hobby.
- That's cool.
- Yeah.
- That can be, I'll back that.
- There you go.
So his hobby was gardening and horticulture.
And the idea is that he would go from planet to planet
and he would spend sort of up to a year,
sort of terraforming it, making it greener guys.
- Yeah, that's sad.
- Yeah, it might come into his own, actually.
- Yeah.
- I'm actually conscious age.
- There you go.
Well, he should be a bigger character
'cause actually in the original--
- I think I should play him.
(laughing)
- In the original stories,
he and the other Elders all had the Infinity Gems,
which is what Thanos collects
as part of the main Avengers storyline
in order to wipe out all of--
- Oh, so he's one of the original holders of one of these?
- Yeah.
And because some reason when it came to the movie adapted,
the gardener didn't quite get--
- Pretty cool.
That's what I'm thinking.
- Oh, right.
- I'm talking about that.
- Yeah, but yeah, I'd love that.
- Yeah.
- I've seen with like a big wide-brimmed hat.
- You know, the sort of thing that old ladies used to have.
- Oh, yes, yeah.
(laughing)
- Loves on--
- Obviously, floral gloves in one of those kneeling pads.
- I've got one.
- They are very useful.
- Yeah, yeah.
- The best ones when you've got a handle at the side
- Push yourself up. - Ooh, yeah, they're good.
- It's like an upside-down cano store, really.
- That's really helpful.
- And then you've got just to have a couple of beats
to be like, "Oh, with my knees."
- Yeah, absolutely.
- They carry on.
- Okay, we're talking to a seasoned gardener here, I'm guessing.
- Well, I's salty, maybe, if it's just about seasoned.
(laughing)
- You do have a garden, though, that you love to--
- I've got-- I've gotten into gardening.
I like to use the past tense of God.
And I've gotten into gardening in the last sort of four years
since having my own place.
For a long time, I lived with my parents
and I didn't have my own space then.
And so now I do, and it's quite nice just to--
- Well, just mess around, really.
I'm proud and obvious with it,
but I find it really interesting.
- So on famous gardeners, who's the most famous gardener
in the UK?
- Alan Titchfash. - Correct.
- What has Alan Titchfash got in common
with Elvis Presley?
- Ooh, okay, both from Memphis, that's obvious.
(laughing)
- Both sex gods.
- Okay, I'll give you that.
It's slightly related to that.
- Poets?
- He writes poetry, Titchfash.
- It's not that.
- Okay. - I've been to jail.
- Well, Elvis had a song about it.
Titchfash was done out for years, wasn't he?
- For years, yeah.
- That's why he has honest tattoos.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- Come as them up for the show of class.
- One for everybody killed in prison.
- It's how he got into gardening was burying the bodies.
(laughing)
- The answer is that the lower halves
have been censored on television.
- Really?
- So Elvis, obviously, when he became big,
they would only show him from the waist up
so that people didn't get too excited.
But Alan Titchfash has been--
- They were censored for the waist out.
(laughing)
- They have censored his trousers
because he was jeans and in North Korea,
they don't like jeans being shown
because it's a symbol of America.
So they show his programs,
but they blur out his trousers.
- Wow.
- But that means he's free to broadcast
when he the post-style.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- So the North Korean that works, he's--
- He's there.
- You have to paint his legs blue.
(laughing)
- I've seen Titchfash do karaoke.
- Have you, in person?
- In person.
- Wow. - I don't mean to clang.
- What did he say?
Something green, green grass.
- It was, or what's the one I killed a man in Reno?
(laughing)
- Gangster's paradise as well.
- Yeah, I don't remember the song, but it was, yeah.
- Wow, that's very cool.
Well, there's other reasons
that Alan Titchfash is a sex god, by the way,
which is that as well as writing over something
like 70 gardening books,
he's written a series of novels.
- Yes, they are.
- Are they seen?
- Are they?
- Yeah, in fact, I don't know if you remember,
but we had Lou Sanders read Morrissey's contribution
to the world of sex scenes.
- Tom, do you mind?
- I've got a little extra here.
- Oh, here we go.
- Well, I think I have met Alan a few times
and he's always very charming, as you'd imagine.
And he did say to me, 'cause I was talking to him
about audio books, and he did say he was very aware
of his more intimate scenes when he had to sit
in a booth, and read them out, to an engineer.
So as an example of what he might have been reading,
there is a little bit here.
She planted moist hot kisses all over his body.
Beads of sweat began to appear on Guy's forehead for it,
as he became more entangled in the lism limbs
of this human bower constrictor.
It's only 15 minutes, their mutual passion heightened
with groans, sighs, and liquid noises.
(laughing)
- Oh, wow, can I just say, when you're describing lens,
why'd go for the one animal that doesn't have any lens?
- Little lism, lism limb.
- I don't know what lism means.
- I've never heard that word before.
- Lism is kind of young and firm and strong, isn't it?
- Is it?
- Oh, sorry.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Rich marshes, too highbrow for us.
We don't know the vocabulary.
- I know, I bet he lism.
- He's a very educated man.
- I like the way it begins with sheep planted kisses.
Like, 'cause obviously he's a gardener.
- Absolutely.
- Oh, every, every.
- Well, he was wonderful.
- So he was runner up in the 1998 Literary Review
Bad Sex Awards.
And you're right, he felt very uncomfortable reading them.
He said, particularly with a sheet of glass between you
and a very large bearded man, twiddling knobs,
as you say the words, he found it uncomfortable.
- I think it's a bit unfair that bad sex thing,
'cause they go for slabs, don't they?
- Yeah.
- There must be loads of like not famous people
who are writing worse.
- Absolutely.
- What?
- To be fair, the winner that year was Sebastian Forks.
- I was gonna say bird song.
It's got lots of that, that's very interesting.
- Bird song's got some very fruity stuff in it.
- So he was very fruity.
- I remember reading that when I was about 17
and thinking, oh gosh, that seems like a lot of effort.
(laughing)
- Can I ask you about a couple of things you might
or might not use in your garden, Tom?
- Oh yeah, absolutely.
- Should we give it a go?
Right.
Do you ever use worm poo tea bags?
No, I think I have heard of this sort of thing.
- So cool.
- Worms are very important, aren't they?
- Worms are vital.
- And obviously they eat soil.
They poo it out.
You know, they help.
- So do I.
- They do their aerate, all sorts of stuff.
You can get tea bags with worm castings, are you worm poo?
Where you literally make a cup of tea out of it
for your plant and it really helps your plant.
- Really?
- Lion urine?
- Well that's the thing, isn't it?
Because people say to keep away foxes or other animals
if you want them out of your garden.
- You need an apex predator.
- You need an apex, you can't.
The people say, oh just go and we in the garden
and then like, no, then you mend to we in the garden.
It's male urine they respond to.
And apparently that's not, that's not going to do it.
Apparently you need to go to the zoo and ask,
yeah, I'm going to get a lion to we into a cup.
(laughing)
- Or you can get the piss off plant.
- Have you heard of that?
- What's that?
- Piss off plant is a plant that's native
to southern in eastern Africa and it is a plant
that supposedly repels dogs and cats from coming near it
because of the aroma that it emits.
So if you had that in your garden,
most likely they would smell it and never come back again.
- I'll get one of it.
- That's pretty good, that's a great idea.
Do you have an ornamental hermit in your garden?
- No, I don't have anything like that.
That was like a sort of a little house,
wasn't it worded a little.
- Well back in the 18th century,
this was a real life human
that you would bring into your garden.
- Yeah.
- They would dress like a druid
and they would just be sat
and they would have a contract to live there
and negotiations for roaches and negotiations
every autumn as the roaches.
- Well look, I'm not gonna do this for another year.
Let's you revise my terms.
- No, yeah, it's been in 1797.
There was a thing written up that said,
the hermit is never to leave the place
or hold conversation with anyone for seven years
during which he is neither to wash himself
or cleanse himself in any way whatsoever.
- Yeah, my agent's got a problem with his clothes
and I'm like, yeah, (laughing)
agent lives a bit further down the garden
and another little folly.
- Yeah.
- Do we know why people did that?
- Well, I think it's a kind of,
it would be like landed gentry would have this person.
You wouldn't have it in your garden in the hackney.
- I think, no, exactly.
I think what it is is,
the hermit is a symbol of a wilder
and ancient way of living
and it's kind of they are reflecting on history
and on humanity and on progress and the countryside
and the wilderness and I think that's why it's cool
to have a hermit 'cause they kind of hark back to that.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- This has been that kind of sentimentality
isn't it around that kind of pastoral?
- Yeah, it all.
- There was one place which had a hermit
which turned out to be a mechanical hermit.
- Genuinely.
- I think it was an 18th century aristocrat.
- Quite clearly it was a hermit.
(laughing)
- It was like a very, very, very crude
model robo hermit that they had in there.
- With that thing.
- Here's another famous gardener.
So this is a king called hermiti
who was in ancient Sumer
and what would happen in ancient Sumer
is you would get people who would tell the future
and if they saw a bad omen,
like maybe the king's gonna die,
you would put someone else on the throne,
400 days and then you take over again.
So this guy, hermiti, decided to put his gardener
on the throne for 100 days 'cause there'd been a bad omen
and then he died after eating some hot porridge
and his gardener then reigned ancient Sumer
for 24 years.
(laughing)
- Just 'cause he didn't blow on it.
- I guess so.
- Oh, the porridge.
- Yeah.
- That's incredible.
- I know.
- I guess wasn't a successor in place
who would not have taken over the throne.
- Well, he's the king now, right?
- Yeah, you're right.
- So what are you gonna do?
- That's so funny.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it is time for fact number three
and that is Andy.
- My fact is, in 1920, the King of Greece died
after trying to break up a fight between a dog and a monkey.
(laughing)
This is the only royal death I've found
which involved a monkey at all, actually.
- Mm-hmm.
- Little end of the fight between a dog and a monkey.
- Okay.
- This was King Alexander of Greece
and he had a dog, he had a German shepherd
and one day he was having a walk in there.
I think the palace grounds and I think a Barbary ape.
- Quite an aggressive, yeah, not a titler of a monkey.
- Oh, no, no, this isn't like Bubbles.
- No, no, no, no, this is proper.
- They're very naughty Barbary apes, I can say.
They all know.
- Yeah, it's naughty.
(laughing)
- They'll kill your dog.
- Slotering your dog in front, yeah.
- All you King.
- They have the man to brawl to them, yes.
And I went up there with a pusher
with my daughter who is very young
and basically, they will just steal everything.
Everything that's not held down, they'll steal it.
- You got it back though.
- No, she still lives there.
(laughing)
- She is the ape queen now.
- That's why I bow to for Brexit.
I don't want it to be Spanish.
(laughing)
- Yeah, so anyway, this ape and this dog were in a fight.
He was trying to separate them,
at which point the apes wife turned up
and sunk fangs into King Alexander's leg.
- Oh no.
- And I think some days later, he died, he'd become ill
and they had swithered over what to do, the doctors and so.
- So he died and this produced huge geopolitical consequences
with Churchill later wrote,
it is perhaps no exaggeration to remark
that a quarter of a million persons died
of this monkey's bite.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Wow.
- Because they've spent the Greek Civil War.
- Well, it all led to a lot of unhappiness and conflict
inside Greece.
They got back the previous King.
Because what had happened to the previous King was very pro German
and his son was pro German, his eldest son.
And so Britain and Russia and probably France
got rid of those guys and brought in this guy
who wasn't expecting to be King.
Like he was just thought he was gonna spend his days gardening
off just having a lot of fun.
- Having a lovely life.
- Yeah, and then suddenly he's King.
And then, you know, okay, well now we've got our puppet
who's in charge, but then he dies
and then they bring the old people back
and it all goes to shit.
- That's basically what happened, yeah.
And then he fought this war against the Turks
which went disastrously wrong, hundreds of thousands of deaths.
The royalists were kicked out.
And then the European Great Powers just started picking
the Greek royal family.
And then eventually things got a bit more democratic.
And the Greeks in 1862 had this vote for a new King,
a kind of national referendum.
And they almost universally, they chose Prince Alfred of England
who I believe was one of Victoria's sons.
- Yes.
- He won 95% of the vote's cast.
He said no, no thank you, I don't want to do it.
- You used the throne of Greece.
- Yeah, but imagine he probably had a nice house
somewhere, wouldn't he?
- I'm sure he's already got a nice, you're right.
- You're right, yeah, that nice.
- Well yeah, was that?
- That was 1862.
- So this is not happening in the 1860s, wasn't it?
- Oh, going on.
- Bucket.
- Was that unification of Germany around then?
- Yes.
- And then formation of Italy.
- Also my house was built.
- Really?
- So some major events.
- Major, major things too.
- So your garden, that was laid out and was created.
- Yeah.
- By Prince Alfred.
- And actually around the corner from me.
And Napoleon III came to live.
- Is that so?
- No, really.
- Wow, so there you go.
- So we've asked to take a huge decade.
- A huge decade.
But basically Alfred was pressured into saying no
'cause Britain, France, and Russia had all to creed.
Nobody's going to accept this throne.
- Nobody wants it, get over it.
- And every candidate said no until they got to Prince
Wilhelm of Denmark of the Blocksburg House
and he had received six votes
from the entire population of Greece.
And he was then chosen to be the king.
- That is unfortunate.
- I know.
- I think he was 18th highest voted person in that list.
- He came 18th.
- Yeah.
- But various people had just written a Russian king, please.
Or whatever.
- Yeah, yeah.
- They just selected, like they just listed it.
So he came almost dead last.
And yet he then was king for 50 years.
- King, like king face was there.
- Who they really wanted.
- Yeah.
- And then he lasted until 1913, he lasted 50 years.
- 1930.
- 1913.
- He was assassinated by either a socialist or a lunatic.
And it's not clear which apparently.
- Not necessarily.
- Not to get political.
(laughing)
- Lots of assassinations happening around that sort of area
whether that time.
- Yes.
- They loved it.
- A vexed, vexed period.
- A vexed period in the south-east of Europe.
- Yeah.
- I found another monkey bite death.
- Oh.
- Did you?
- Didn't expect to find one.
But I tried hard and I got there.
- Do you know the character Grizzly Adams?
- Grizzly Adams.
- So barely.
- He was making a bet.
- No, no.
(laughing)
- So Grizzly Adams in America,
I think he's quite a well-known historical character.
So he was a Californian mountain man.
He was a trainer of Grizzly bears.
And he used to just do acts,
you know, kind of like a Petey Barnum kind of thing.
- So he made pets with quite a few of these bears
that he thought were friendly.
- I can't see this going.
- Yeah.
- Can't see where this is gonna go.
- And he was killed by a monkey.
- That's like, yeah.
- Oh yeah.
So, okay.
Don't take your eyes off the threat of the monkeys.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- So he got attacked by Grizzly in Sierra Nevada.
- Oh, but the monkey was one who set the Grizzly on him.
- No, the monkey comes in later.
So his scalp was dislodged in this attack,
and it left a silver dollar size impression in his skull,
just above his forehead.
Then he had all these other Grizzlies
that he made friends with.
Anyway, he was re-induced several times in the head
and it opened up the wound,
which meant bits of brain tissue where it's exposed.
And then, as he's still going with the bears, stick.
- He's still going with the bear's stick.
- Okay.
- And then Grizzly out of this on tour with a circus,
when a monkey that he was trying to train jumped up
and beat him in the brain.
- Oh god.
- Not in the head in the brain.
- Well, you don't have any nerves in your brain,
so you wouldn't even feel it.
- Yep.
- So anyway.
- You know, it was happening, I think.
- Maybe came from behind.
- It was possible.
- And so he died, October 25th, 1860.
- It was in Grizzly, that.
- 1860.
- It was another big thing.
- How extraordinary does it?
- If you hadn't said it was a monkey,
I wouldn't have seen that coming at all.
- Yeah, I know, right.
It's a real plot twist at the end there.
- It really is.
- Wow, horrifying end.
Here's some people.
William III of England, Alexander III of Scotland,
Prince Alfonso Portugal, Frederick Augustus II of Saxony,
Duke Geoffrey of Brittany is a beller of arrogant,
Leopold VIII of Austria,
Louis IV of France, William the Conqueror,
they all died the same way.
- Monkeys.
- Not monkeys.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- At what point do we start suspecting the monkeys?
- A raptor of the day.
- This is something that does away with lots of royalties.
- And it's very guessable.
- Oh, is it gouged or something?
- Yeah, gouged, but that's a bit of a hog.
- Yeah, is it sort of explosion or some sort of...
- Oh, 'cause William the Conqueror did explode,
but that was out of your stuff.
- He got brother a beast, I think, didn't he?
- Right.
They couldn't bury him straight away.
And so when the monks came to bury him in his concrete tomb,
they sort of shoved him in it.
And then he exploded.
(laughing)
- Wow, and in the conqueror.
- I'm pretty sure, yeah.
- William the Conqueror, yeah.
He definitely exploded in the...
- Conqueror.
- Oh, it wouldn't be Conqueror's stone, sorry.
- Oh, yeah, okay.
- That's a bit of the story you wanted to pick up on.
- The Romans had Conqueror Avenue.
- I know the Romans had Conqueror,
but I wasn't aware that...
- Yeah, it was a brutalist.
- It wasn't a brutalist coffin.
- I just want to go with something really simple.
(laughing)
- Anyway, the answer is falling off a horse.
- Oh!
- That is a big old way that people died in the past.
- Yes.
- Alexander III probably was riding along a high,
treacherous coastal path, having drank a lot of Bodo wine.
- Good thing.
- And just went straight off it.
- Right.
- What fell off the hill?
- It just jumped straight off it, yeah.
You would think the horse would stop,
but the problem is that quite often when these people die,
there's a big sort of something happens afterwards,
like happened with this Greek guy.
So when Alexander III died,
that started the first war of Scottish independence,
essentially.
- Right.
- So you know, it's quite a big deal when these kings die,
even though they're just people.
- At what point is anyone suggesting a helmet
for horse riding?
- Oh.
- I just...
- You don't see that, I mean, apart from knights,
you don't see people with like cycle helmets
in the past, do you?
- Yeah, but knights do have protection.
You just think that I get how many regal deaths
do they have to have before they say,
I think we should say, if you're the king or queen,
you have to wear a helmet on your horse.
- Yeah.
- Well, how about seat belts?
- Horse seat belts?
- Yeah.
- Horse belts.
- Is that safer?
- You're not gonna fall if you're really tied tight.
- If your horse falls over though,
and your seat belt is on.
- I just wonder if there's a five reggae to come along.
(laughing)
- I feel like there might be a reason
why the horse seat belt hasn't been invented.
- Or maybe a styrups is effectively the horse seat belt
'cause it really helps you hold yourself in place
when you're in the styrups.
- Look at you, you've been riding the horse recently.
- I've ridden one half reggae.
- Didn't you?
(laughing)
- You're wearing it as Mr. equestrian.
- All I'm gonna say is that go off any cleft.
So, you know, despite how much borderline you are.
(laughing)
- Yeah, that's true, isn't it?
How do people move this is a very graphic question,
but how do people die when they fall off a horse?
Do they get trampled in the legs?
- I think it's bang on the head.
- Bang on the head.
- 'Cause actually, you're quite,
as someone who's ridden a horse, I would say.
- Well, you would know, that's why I asked.
(laughing)
- You're quite high up.
- Oh, yeah.
- Like, and they do, like, my horse,
at once they saw a lady horse.
- Oh no.
- And so I started galloping towards them.
(laughing)
- And I almost shitted my angle.
- One advantage for a horse ride,
if it mounted the feet on the horse,
and you just have to sit there,
like a horse that you, (laughing)
- That's amazing, you're riding two horses at once.
(laughing)
- You're out of it.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, it's time for our final fact of the show,
and that is James.
- Okay, my fact this week is that one of the most
popular celebrity tailors of the 1950s was,
ironically called Newdy.
(laughing)
- This guy's a character.
- I reckon quite a few people might have heard of him,
but I'd never heard of him before.
He was the first person to spot rhinestones on clothing.
(laughing)
So if you've ever seen one of those rhinestone cowboy suits
that they wore in America in the,
what, this 50, 60, 70s, he will have made it.
So he made suits for L this.
He made them for--
- How in Titchmarsh?
(laughing)
- Elton John, who he mentioned before,
Hike Williams, John Lennon.
This is the who's who of pop music.
- It's everybody, yeah.
- Stackers.
- Liver archie, I imagine.
- Oh, yeah.
- They never too much sure.
- It was sort of everyone.
In fact, I was thinking, 'cause I, you know,
the term rhinestone cowboy.
- Glen Campbell.
That was originally written by a man called Larry Weiss,
and it was, it was in tribute to Newdy.
- Really?
- Yeah, because that was a thing that all of these
country music stars kept asking for.
They were like, Newdy, more rhinestone.
- More rhinestone, when they were asking for those suits
to be tailored.
So that song was put in more of a sentence though.
They just went, "More rhinestone."
"More rhinestone."
- Oh, these sounds, you know, they're like,
"You're not a rhinestone, Newdy."
(laughing)
- That was, it was a guy called Lefty Frizzle,
who was more rhinestone.
But a few more rhinestone, Newdy, put more rhinestone.
- Rhinestones are stones from the Rhine, by the way,
just in case you didn't know what a rhinestone was.
- I never knew what a rhinestone would be about this,
so that is now just a piece of colored glass,
basically, but they were kind of proper rock crystals.
- Apparently, you just get these little
colorful pebbles on the banks of the Rhine,
and people used to put them on stuff as decoration.
- Yeah, at these days, you melt them onto clothes with heat.
- Do you?
- So you have a little, you have a little glue layer,
and then you just heat them up and you just shove them on.
- But yeah, Newdy, he was born Newter Cup Clear Encore
in Kiev in 1902, and he moved to America,
but he was really into his tailoring,
and then when he was processed,
supposedly according to the story,
when he was processed through Ellis Island,
they changed his name to Newdy,
which I'm not sure how often that actually happened,
and usually it was people just changing their name
to sell more American themselves.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- And then he came to America, opened an underwear shop,
selling G-strings and pasties to strippers.
- Very broad range of West Cornwall, wasn't it?
(laughing)
- But they're called pasties.
- They are called pasties.
- They're called your nipples?
- Okay, I just thought, okay, he's going to get hungry,
and they're quite handy,
because that whole meal running through them.
- If you get one hand on the pole,
and then he's hold onto the cross.
- I think the strippers in Bolton do put pasties
on their nipples, but...
(laughing)
- So they're all the more popular for it,
as well as people love pasties.
They love pasties.
- Yeah.
- And he then had surgery when he was in his forties
and lost all of his money,
'cause he had to pay for the surgery in America.
And then he thought, what am I going to do?
I'm going to make suits for celebrities.
And he got in touch with a guy called Text Williams.
Text Williams auctioned off his horse
and used the money to buy New Deal sewing machine,
and they went into business together.
- Well, you wouldn't have gone on with text.
- Yeah.
- Why?
- You both love horses.
(laughing)
- I could have started coming in and Rady's done so many times.
- But yeah, I'd never heard this guy,
and he was pretty big deal.
- Quite the guy.
- Yeah, that early stage when he was selling the pasties
to strippers, he sold also Taylor Mae's G Strings.
- You don't, you don't, you don't them to not fit.
(laughing)
- You're right.
- If you got round your knees.
(laughing)
- Oh, was that happened again?
I was just eating a pastie.
(laughing)
- Oh dear.
- And the name New Deal became sort of synonymous
with these amazing suits,
and actually the New Deal name is still alive,
thanks to his granddaughter.
Jamie Newdy, who seems to have taken his first name
as her surname, no, not quite sure how.
(laughing)
And so now they do still exist,
but they mostly make t-shirts and coffee mugs
with the name Newdy on it.
They don't really make so many clothes anymore.
- His cars were absolutely bananas.
And I only say this because I've seen one of them,
I think in the flesh.
- No.
- In the Nashville Country Music Hall of Fame.
- Oh wow.
- And it's, I didn't know you'd been there.
- I mean, just 15 years ago.
- I thought I'd heard every one of your anecdotes.
- No, no, no, no.
- Why do you keep telling us the same three then?
(laughing)
- I feel like we're getting distracted
from my fourth anecdotes.
(laughing)
- All these facts, anyway.
- Yeah, go on, thank you so much, that way.
- It's an insane car.
It's got 18 pistols distributed around it.
It kind of built into the doors
and things like that, all the inside.
It's got $1,200 silver dollars glued on
the various points all over it.
My memory might be tricking me.
I feel like it's got a bison's horns on the front.
- Oh wow.
- Where you'd have the Mercedes sign or whatever.
It's got one of those.
I mean, it's an absolutely loopy.
- Well, you would plug in your electric vehicle.
- That's right.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
(laughing)
- Yeah, he was very obsessed with fashion
as a lot of celebrities are.
Tom, you are one of the best-addressed comedians.
- Well, that's very generous to say fashion.
I've always liked zooting and tailoring.
I don't know, I think it makes me feel a certain way.
Sort of stand in a certain way.
I guess that's part of what tailoring has always done for people.
But yes, I do like to wear a suit.
- Yeah, I used to wear ties a lot.
And I've stopped in recent years
and I feel less good as a human as a result.
So I think I might get back into it.
- Well, they're a flash of color, really, I suppose.
Or a bit of variation in the...
- Well, you always wore a black one then you don't.
- Just black.
- Yeah.
- With a white shirt.
- Yeah, so I remember those days.
- Yes.
- The Mormon was here.
(laughing)
- It saves time, doesn't it?
- Yeah.
- So you don't have to change your clothes
at the end of the gig.
You can just get out and fly all the way out.
- Pop the old badge on.
(laughing)
- I don't know those books.
- I do, whoa, what's interesting is I read a study recently.
Is apparently when you wear a tie,
it stops your blood flow by 7.5%.
- Really?
- Well, that gets me high, so I like that.
That's what I'm missing.
- That's not an idea.
- To your brain?
- Yeah.
- So you've been operating with constrictor blood flow
to your brain for some years?
- They did MRI scans on 15 men who were wearing ties
and 15 men who weren't.
- I'm actually going with the MRI machine.
(laughing)
- Very smart clothes.
- Should I pop my umbrella in but I haven't?
(laughing)
- Yeah, and that's what they concluded.
So it is letting less, and it will give you headaches
and dizziness and nausea if you wear a tie more.
- Wow.
- Then it won't do me, right?
- Yeah.
- I find now it's evolved into the work where if men
going to work is rather than suits,
it is some skinny chinos, a quarter-zip jumper
with a shirt underneath open neck and then a lanyard
instead of a tie.
- I love it.
- So people don't wear a tie because they're lanyards.
Which I think will evolve maybe one day into something else
or we've all become quite utilitarian, I think,
in our clothing.
I think we all become quite practical.
I think for a long time there was an air of
Camboyance special of men's clothing, which isn't afforded
so much now, I think if you went out, even me wearing a tie,
people were like, "Oh, all right, all right."
Well, I don't know if you're having a wedding today.
- You know, I'm literally just wearing the same things
like my dad might have worn.
You know, but they can't seem like, yeah.
- Oh.
- I was thinking to tight clothes or snug clothes
and clothing innovations, because it's really fun.
If you look in someone like new scientist
for all the clothing inventions, it's all like,
this is the clothing of tomorrow.
And so in 2007, Philips, the electronics people,
they invented auto snug clothing, right?
Which is where it's a clothes with muscle wires woven
through the fabric.
You pick it up to the power and it adjusts
until your trousers are the exact right size for you.
- That's good.
- And then you know exactly what trousers you need
from now on.
- Yeah, I think that's great.
- I think that's useful.
I can imagine it going wrong, well.
- Oh, absolutely, yeah.
Like hundreds of people were electrocuted very bad.
It's very badly scorched during this.
But it's also, we have a tape measure.
We have the technology to find out
what size trousers someone needs.
- It's not like until 2007 people were like,
"Didn't I have like trousers in the size of my house?"
(all laughing)
- The other thing is it's different in different countries,
right? - Yeah.
- So I bought a pair of large underpants in America
and a pair in Japan and I could tell you,
one of those way too big for me and the other one,
I can't even squeeze them too.
- This is why James has his G-string's tailor.
(all laughing)
- Speaking of putting metal inside clothes,
that's what Lame is, I didn't know this.
So Newdy in 1957 made Elvis Presley a $10,000 gold Lame suit.
And Lame is where you get your fabric,
but then you put metallic fibers into it.
- Oh.
- I didn't know what that was.
- Where else is Lame used in the sporting world?
- So gold being woven through.
- Or any metal woven through fabric.
- Not horse-raining.
- Aerodynamics, stuff.
- Nope.
- I've got a wild theory.
- Go on.
- Is it tennis rackets?
- I thought you were gonna get it, but no.
(all laughing)
For me the one?
- No, it's not that, it's used in fencing.
- Oh, of course.
- Because you need to, when someone stabs you with the sword,
they need to connect it.
And so it's the threads inside.
So all fences use Lame suits in the same way that Elvis did.
- That suit of Elvis is amazing.
- Did you see that in your,
- Yes, I was gonna see.
- I don't remember if I saw it because they've,
they've got a pair of the blue suede shoes.
You know, they've got a load of costumes and outfits.
But that is, if you're listening to this
and you wanna know what that gold Lame suit is,
it's on the front cover of an album,
which gets referred to as 50 million Elvis fans
can't be wrong, which is a very, very funny album title.
- Right.
- And it's this mad gold suit.
- Cool.
- It's very loose.
It doesn't fit him at all well by a modern standard.
- But it's, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think I might, I can't remember if I saw it there.
- You know, if there was a lightning storm, wouldn't it?
- Oh, yeah.
- It would have been absolutely, absolutely.
- Absolutely.
- At the road.
- Found a comedy play from the 1805 called The Taylors,
which was shown at Covent Garden.
And it was kind of taken a piss out of young dandies
at the time.
And they were so annoyed with it that they all turned up
and started booing the actors and stuff.
And not only that, they decided to throw,
not rot 'em tomatoes, but scissors and cutting shears.
- Cool.
- At the actors throughout their opening night.
- Oh my God.
- Well, what is it?
- Grizzly Adams is on the stage too.
(laughing)
He has a terrible night.
- Isn't that mad?
- That's crazy.
- Yeah, that is, but how interesting to think of,
a group of people who want to associate with sort of
foppishness and not being particularly agitated.
- Yeah, but young dandies is like, you know,
muds, rockers, that kind of--
- Yeah, but isn't it?
Yeah, I know it's an obvious thing to say,
but one realises that the things we see today
have all happened before.
- Yeah.
- The kind of protests, all those kind of groups
people being, you know, people being outrageous,
you know, dress sense as a protest or as an expression.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- It's interesting.
- I've got a riddle for you guys.
- Oh, give it.
- Okay.
- Carol Spencer was a fashion designer.
She's spent 30 years working for the same client
designing clothes, but her clothes have never been worn
by a human.
(laughing)
- Riddle means.
- It's like a lacy.
- Well, it's something, it wasn't a lacy.
- So it's nice.
- A horse saddle.
- It wasn't a horse related.
- James would have got it a bit like.
- James did it like.
(laughing)
- I think I've got it.
- God, I know my hit rate with the tennis racket.
- Yeah.
- Back and that up.
I think it's a living Madame Tussaud's wax work
and with the fashion changing of the first.
- Like the sauna.
- Yeah, exactly.
- It's so fashion all the time.
- They keep the wax work, but they don't.
- And they change that.
- You're so close.
- Oh.
It's a model of a person, but it's not Madame Tussaud.
- Oh, is it not the, is it Lenin who's kept in the cabinet?
- It's not.
(laughing)
- Lenin's fashion.
- Lenin, yeah.
(laughing)
- Mr. February Revolution, it's Lenin again.
- The fashion show, where they're all kneeled out.
- Sherman Louse, summer, look.
(laughing)
- Isn't the mannequin piece?
- It's not the mannequin piece.
- Right, shall I tell you all?
- Oh, I feel like we are close.
- I'll tell you this one more clue.
- Okay. - A client was only 11 1/2 inches high.
- Oh.
- She's fashionable.
She's got a lot of outfit changed.
- Bobby.
- It's Bobby.
- Oh.
- I don't even get there.
- I'm sorry.
- You're probably itching to tell us.
- No, no, no, no.
- To play the game is a bit longer.
(laughing)
- I'm so sorry for truncating in Brutian.
- No, no, no, no, no, no.
- I'm sure that we've all got homes to go to.
- The other people listening were like,
"It's obviously Bobby."
"Is it Lenin?"
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us
about the things that we've said
over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found online.
I'm on Instagram, on @Streiberland.
James.
- Come find me on Tech Talk.
No such thing as James Harkin.
Andy.
- Instagram @AndruHunterRab.
- Tom, where could we find you?
- My Instagram handle is @TomIndeed.
So do feel free to follow me there.
Or I have just started a visualized podcast.
I don't know if you're familiar with this idea.
And that is available from all podcast providers.
And also on YouTube @TomAllon is the handle.
And it's called "Pottering."
And it's about gardening and being in the garden
with my friends.
- Oh, great.
So you're in the garden.
You've got your guests sitting there
in the distance.
We see a carpet just sort of wandering around.
- Yes, don't acknowledge him.
He's got another six years left.
(laughing)
- Well, yeah, if you want to get to us as a group,
go to podcast@qy.com.
You can send us some facts.
You can send us some extra things
that you want us to know about
that we were talking about.
Whatever you send Andy goes through these emails.
He cherry picks the best of them
and they make their way to our bonus show called Drop Us A Line.
Now this is part of a secret club called Club Fish,
which you can find on Patreon.
If you go to patreon.com/nosuchthingasafish
you can find all the details there.
And you can also send us your most interesting facts
because we have a bonus show that goes out
on this main feed called Little Fish every Monday.
And we will be reading out the best of your facts on that show.
Otherwise, just come back here.
Next week we're gonna be back again
with another wonderful guest.
We'll see you then.
Good bye.
(upbeat music)