Hey club fish members, welcome to your bonus bit of content. We've got an awesome bumper pack compilation for you today
With the big names of the last nine months. You're gonna hear Beck Hill. You're gonna hear Maisie Adam
You're gonna hear Jenny Colgan, David Mitchell, Sophie Juker, Ella Alshamahi
And you won't hear Neil Gaiman, but you'll hear a clip from a show that he's on so technically he's on it because his breathing is
Probably softly in the background. So almost featuring Neil Gaiman as well such a brilliant collection of nerds
We were so excited to have them on but Anna's back now
So this will be the last time for a while that we're gonna have lots of guests on
Except for the fact that Andy's about to go away for a few weeks and so we'll have two more guests on but outside of that
It's gonna be back to the original four, but we've massively enjoyed having all of our guests on
So sit back now and enjoy some of the best bits that didn't make it onto the main show. Here we go
[Music]
In the 1990s Cliff Richard once brought Heath Cliff the Musical to the Hammersmith Apollo
Oh, that's cool. Where Kate Bush was soon to perform. Yeah, imagine that. Heath Cliff the Musical by Cliff Richard
He didn't call it Heath Cliff Richard
Oh
No, he didn't. Come on Cliff, it's there for the takin'
[Laughter]
See and seagrass is really interesting stuff. This is an initial diversion
But basically it's the only I think it's the only flowering plant that grows underwater
You get seaweed which kind of clings to things underwater and drifts about a bit
But seagrass actually has roots that gets nutrients from the roots and it flowers
And it flowers and then the bees have to put on like scooby to go down there
But it's the best nectar and it's worth it
And what's the point of the flowers if they don't because flowers are there to attract pollination aren't they from insects
I think I guess there must be pollination from undersea creatures but with prawns
Could be prawns. It could be prawns. What was that?
No, currents aren't animals, they're spilt. They put them in a bun and they don't even squeal
[Laughter]
The police chiefs in Romania in a city of Timosora sent their officers to ballet classes
In the hope of helping them manage the traffic with more grace
Oh, that's good. It is useful. There's a lot of NFL players who study ballet in their career
Like they weren't from ballet but they get into it because it helps them with movement, with fluidity, with stretch
Yeah, there's quite a few. There's quite a few. There was one guy particularly who was drafted in 2022 for the Bears
That's what he does. He does ballet and that helps to give him
But I wonder how it would help a traffic cop
It was meant to be that there were complaints about how their movements weren't being particularly well sort of clear
If you're staccato, you're in a relationship with the traffic, aren't you? You're moving with it, you're guiding it, it's your partner
Yeah, you've got four partners
People need to understand what directions you're pointing in and if you're not clear with your movements or anything
No, I got it. That makes sense
Weirdly, when you're talking about the NFL players, I've started doing wrestling classes
Oh, cool
Because I want to get better at slapstick in comedy for kids
Nice
So I want to learn how to fall properly
Oh, great. How's it going?
I could fall on a mat
But I haven't, but I'm not at floors yet
Is it like you're supposed to turn as you fall and land on your shoulder or is that something else that I'm thinking of?
Well, it depends what you're doing, but most of the time it's called a bump and you go on your back to do a bump
That's when they land on their back. You're basically landing between your shoulder blades
And the key is you want to keep your hips sort of as high as possible so that your tailbone doesn't get hit
Yeah
What about your head?
Your head, they need incredible neck muscles
So they actually do exercises to strengthen their neck muscles so that when you fall, your neck can support your head and your chin up
So that your head doesn't go back and bounce
A lot of the sound though, interestingly
Because normally if you do that, you don't actually make that much noise
But you know how it's like bang, like when they do it?
The sound comes from their arms
So you put your arms out the same time that you fall and basically slap the floor as loud as you can
And it's genuinely pain, I know people go, oh yeah, but the ring, it's got springs and stuff
It's really not much at all, it's essentially made with car parts and plywood
It is, yeah, it's painful
What's your wrestling name?
I haven't got one yet, but I quite like the idea of Big Heel
Big Heel, love it
I used to wrestle as a kid, I was called Danny the Tugboat Steam Engine
I had a song and everything
When you say you used to do it as a kid, this is, it wasn't professionally already Finn
No, no, we used to do
Danny the Tugboat Steam Engine, doot doot, was the song, yeah
Oh, that's the whole song, is it?
It was kind of a repeat of the Danny the Tugboat Steam Engine
Sorry, is that a thing, Danny the Tugboat Steam Engine?
Yeah, it's my name
No, no, no, but is that an existing thing or is it a...
Yeah, it's my existing wrestling
No, did you take it from, were you inspired by something else or was it just a damn show?
Oh, there's a lot of wrestlers called like the Tugboat and stuff like that, yeah
And I get you like Thomas a lot
I didn't give myself the name, it was given to me
Danny the Tugboat Steam Engine
By somebody who likes Thomas the Tank Engine
Is the idea that you'll, like, you'll have to be pulled off unconscious after the wrestling bout is over?
No, because the Tugboat pulls other people off, don't they?
Like, the Tugboat helps someone to get into the, into the plot
Yeah, exactly, I pulled a lot of men off in my right time as a, as a wrestler
Um, you know the Lumiere Brothers, who we've mentioned a couple of times in this
So they, two of the big pioneers of film, they hired the basement of the Grand Café in Paris
In 1895, right, for a demonstration
And when people arrived in the room, they saw the screen had been set up
And they thought, ah, it's going to be another slideshow
Uh, and George Melios was in the room because he was a pioneer as well
But he, he thought, oh god, it's a projection, eh?
Which kind of stationary images
He said, I've been doing this for ten years
And then the screen started moving
And Melios said, we stared flabbergasted at this site, stupefied and surprised beyond all expression
At the end of the show there was complete chaos
Wow
I just, imagine, I mean, it must have been an amazing moment
Yeah
The first time that was truly demonstrated
And then Lumiere Sr, so the Lumiere Brothers dad, he was involved in the same kind of business, photography and images
He said he was not going to be selling the process
He got immediate offers on the spot, you know, 10,000 francs, 50,000 francs to find out how to do it
And supposedly, I love this, he told Melios, my son's invention is not for sale, it would ruin you
It can be exploited for a short while as a scientific curiosity
Beyond that, it has no commercial future
Wow
I know
Amazing
Yeah
Gotta imagine seeing that being in the room for that
It would have been incredible
Yeah
The greatest thing about Doctor Who is the fan base
It really kind of does have the most extraordinary fan base to the point where the fans have become Doctor Who
Like, that's, it's quite rare
So
How do you mean?
Okay, so David Tennant basically became an actor because he wanted to be Doctor Who
Peter Capaldi obsessed with Doctor Who to the point where the president of the fan club of Doctor Who
When Peter Capaldi was a kid was sending messages to other people going, this Capaldi kid won't leave me alone
He's so annoying
Wow
He's haunting my time as president of, he's demanding, he should be president, he keeps sending in letters
He keeps sending in fan art, he keeps sending in corrections
Capaldi was obsessed and he did go on to become a Doctor Who
And then Tennant, of course, if you know Tennant's life well, you'll know that he is married to the daughter of a previous Doctor Who
Which is Peter Davidson
Is he?
Yeah, so
Who also played his own daughter in the show Doctor Who?
Yes, yeah, so George, George Mothlis is her name and she comes on to Doctor Who playing Doctor Who's daughter during David Tennant's, no, hang on
What?
No, sorry
It's all tiny white stuff, it's a bit confusing
So his wife plays his daughter?
That's how they met, yeah, they met on set
Yeah, he's married to one Doctor and the daughter of another
My favourite social media post of all time is from George Mothlis as she's standing in her lounge room and both David Tennant and her dad, Peter Davidson are trying to change a lightbulb
And the caption is "How many doctors does it take to change a lightbulb?"
Nice
If you've got a sonic screwdriver
You can use it on your research
Jesus, I'm so proud of you, this is great
I read an article with Peter Capaldi from 1974 where they called him Scotland's biggest Doctor Who fan
It's around online, you see it every now and then, don't you?
I have to say when I started writing for the show when I was 13, I entered a competition to meet Doctor Who
When I entered was Tom Baker, so I must have been about 12, and then when I won it was Peter Davidson, which made me less happy, but made my mother quite a lot more happy
So it kind of balanced out
And having worked in Who and met lots of people from Who, everyone my age entered that competition
The amount of people, yeah, absolutely, the amount of people David Tennant entered, lots of the writers entered, the amount of people I met when I go "I won that W. Smith competition"
They're like "Oh no, it was you!"
So I think there is a definite, I think particularly for the people that play the Doctor because it's in every territory in the world
It's one of Britain's biggest exports, it's one of Britain's huge financial exports
And so for the rest of your life, you're going to have to be the Doctor, so you're going to, you cannot
Wait, so you won the competition?
Yes, I did
What are the odds? That's amazing
I'm so very excited about it
Yeah, that's awesome
So yeah, so this picture is me with Peter Davidson and Monsters, and here's a really nice thing that happened
I got an email out the blue from BBC Archives one day saying "We're doing some archive business"
And we believe that you were present for the taping in front of us in like 1983
Can you confirm it? Were you there on this day? And I was, and I was 12
And I'm down in the official BBC archive on the production line
Oh nice, an update
The fans, the fans in Paris, the mantle of running the show
They're always quite clicky butchers, especially if you go back into like the middle ages and stuff
Being a butcher was a really important job obviously in the city
But also you couldn't sell dodgy meat, so there were lots of laws basically for the butchers
For what they could and they couldn't do
I was reading some offences from the 14th century in London
And you could be arrested if you're a butcher for cutting the meat improperly
So too much or too little
Selling measly pork
And measly pork is pork which looks like it's got measles
So it's got a disease on it and it's got little pock marks in it
You weren't allowed to kill any animals on a Sunday
And you weren't allowed to run around the town in a cloak but not a gown
What? Even when you're off shift?
Even at any stage if you're a butcher
You can't wear a cloak? Why? What did a cloak have connotations on?
I couldn't really work out exactly what the reasoning behind that was
But it was definitely against the rules for butchers
But there was this thing basically in London, you had the fishmongers and the butchers
They were very clicky and they wouldn't hang out with each other
It's like western storeys
Exactly like that, exactly like that
And so they would, if you had like let's say the two or three days before Easter
They were the best times when you could sell your food
Yeah
Because you couldn't buy anything over Easter
And they would have special places where the best places to buy your food are
So over the bridges was one and stuff like that
So there was really good places
And they say only the fishmongers are allowed here or only the butchers are allowed here
And whenever they said only the fishmongers are allowed here
The butchers would kick off and they go in and they start smashing up the fishmongers places
But they'd walk up clicking like that
And in 1443 there was a battle of fishmongers versus butchers in London
Of who would get the prime spots on Easter Eve
Lovely
And one fishmonger was very badly wounded
Yeah
But yeah, the fishmongers were usually royalists
The butchers were usually parliamentarians
Really?
Later on
Oh my god, it's like Celtic Rangers
It really is
And like there were three fishmongers who became Lord Mayor of London
And no butchers did and that was a really
That feels sus, doesn't it?
Yeah, exactly
It was like a big deal whether you're on the butcher side or the fishmonger side
Wow
Isn't that amazing?
That is really cool, I had never heard that
I was reading about the clothes that they had to wear
So you know they have this stripey
Oh yes
So
Like Fred Elliott
Literally I was just about to say I was like Fred and Ashley
In Coronation Street
Coronation Street
I'm just moving things back to my home turf now
Right, I don't believe this before I say it to you
Why are butchers apron striped?
I think I got this from a workwear website
Well, can I say are they red and white stripes?
Yeah
No, I think they're blue and white
Oh are they?
I was thinking like it would cover the blood but yeah
Oh yeah, some are blue and white
Sometimes they wear all white to show how clean the place is
Oh that makes sense
Because otherwise they'd be covered in blood
Oh yeah
And that's a really bad sign
So no, these are the blue and white ones
Is it because they're on Man City fans?
That's right
Is it slimming?
It's slimming
The stripe design and I'm just quoting here
The stripe design and number of stripes signify the level of skill of the butcher
A broad stripe means the butcher is master of their trade
Wow
A single stripe means the butcher works without apprenticeship
So it's like getting a new belt and karate, you get a new apron
Yeah
With the status symbol
And I don't think that still is the case
No, I don't think, I've never heard that before
On the karate thing, I heard on another podcast lateral
That the reason that the, it goes from white belts to black belts
It goes like yellow doesn't it
Yeah
And then something else and brown then black
It's supposed to be a snooker
You have to have a red fight between all of the others
And wear a waistcoat
That sounds way better than my version
But what I think it is is it's like they would get dirtier
So the more fights you would have, the more dirty your belts would get
And so it would be, I'm not sure why yellow would be the first one
You'd piss yourself
You'd piss yourself of the fear after you
But eventually your belt would be
Dan's got a brown belt
There's that famous one about what animals do you think you could fight
Where we have mentioned it before
6% of Americans think they could beat a grizzly bear in a fight
Only half of those surveyed thought they could beat a medium-sized dog
That's interesting
I do think I could beat a medium-sized dog
Well, it's hard to
What's a medium-sized dog?
Labrador
Oh, it's just a dog
It's just a dog, yeah
But there were other surveys done about, let's say for example
Sorry, I just say that those people who don't think they could beat them
Maybe they feel I can't bring it in myself to fight a medium-sized dog
I would also say no to that question
I actually just realised what we've implied is that I think I could beat up a Labrador
I actually don't want to do that
Especially not for the blind person
Can I say a couple of things quickly because I was very impressed that
Both Oxygen and Fizzy Drinks came out of Leeds
I thought, what else came out of Leeds?
Mel B
Mel B came out of Leeds
That's our holy trinity
Oxygen, big wee
Scary Spice
Yeah, so yes, absolutely correct
And maybe you'll know all of these actually, Maisie, being from there
Go on
What famous board game came out of Leeds?
Oh, is it?
It's not Cludo, is it?
It is Cludo, yeah
Is it Cludo? I thought that was Cludo
Cludo was invented in Leeds
But it was a game that was bought by the founders there, Wallingtons
And it was a different game, it was originally called Murder
And it was repackaged and it was turned around, named Cludo Popdown
So that was in Leeds, yeah
What famous American building was designed
Was built in Leeds
No, was designed by someone from Leeds
Oh
Yeah, from Pudsy, I should say
Oh, okay, well
It's definitely, it's not the Empire State, I feel like I'd know that
Oh, that's a good one
Is it that one in Chicago?
No, it's built in 1800, completed in 1800
Completed in 1800, that's very old
Yeah
It's really old
What's that old in America?
Well, the White House
What state is it in?
Hang on, hang on, they couldn't have designed a new White House
12 years before the White House was burned down in the war of 1812
But I'm talking about the original White House
Oh, you're saying they built it, and then it got burned down
And then they built another one
I think that's what happened
That is the timeline, isn't it?
You fiction on in Leeds designed the OG White House
I don't know
No
It was Melby
It's not that, but someone from Leeds, from Pudsy, designed the US Capitol building
Oh, really?
Yeah, yeah
Okay
Yeah, Benjamin La Trobe
Is Pudsy the bear?
Yes
From Pudsy
Pudsy, yeah
From Pudsy and Leeds
Oh, really?
Yeah
Oh, Pudsy was not on notable people from Leeds Wikipedia
Wow
Entry needs to get in there
That's why he's called Pudsy
Yeah
Because he's from Pudsy and Leeds
And then just last thing, Grand Theft Auto is from Leeds
One of the biggest franchise video games of all time
Grand Theft Auto
Well, the first edition is Leeds
The first edition
I don't know what kind of set it is
I was going to say, there's some parts of Leeds where it's like being in the game yourself
It's just probably better for the video game aesthetically to look like Miami
Yeah, but the concept was Leeds
It was a Leeds company, Rockstar Leeds, who created it
How interesting
I got two last bungling criminals
One guy called Derek Mosley
He went into a store, not armed with anything but a baseball bat, attempting to rob it
Unfortunately, it was a gun shop
The manager immediately pulled out a gun
and held him there until the police came
And then this one, my favorite one
1996, a store manager in California, robs a store
The store that he's the manager of
He then reports the robbery
and then the police come
The police then ask him to give a detailed description of the criminal
bringing a sketch artist in
And unfortunately, due to incredible lack of imagination
he details his exact face
and they look at it and go, "But that's you!"
and he went, "Oh shit, yeah, I did it!"
I can't think of any face
Just give him a different nose
Think of it, there must be more than one kind of nose
His nose was unlike this
Quickly back to Kate Bush before we finish
She's got a song called "Pie"
where she sings the number "Pie" to 78 decimal places
There's other words as well, it's like the chorus is the numbers
And the problem is she gets the 54th decimal place wrong
No!
Okay, if you're gonna do a song about pie
you've either gotta get it right
or it's gonna be tongue-in-cheek
but don't actually sing it
In fact, she goes to 78 and then she misses out from 78 to 101
Oh god, it gets worse!
Yeah, it's really bad
But more or less on the BBC, they looked at this
and they said, "Actually there's a theory
that if you look at pie, because it goes on forever, the number
every sort of list of numbers will be in there somewhere"
And so they think that even maybe she wasn't reading the first hundred and something
She was just reading a section of pie
From an area that we haven't even got to yet
But does she start by saying "three point"?
Because then that's like...
Yeah, that's a good point
But we actually don't know whether every single string of numbers is in pie or not
That's an unproven bit of maths that people are still trying to work out
Which more or less called the "Catebush Conjecture"
Because if it's true, then she didn't get it wrong after all
That's great, that's really funny
I think you've completely knocked out the theory with the "three point"
It's at the beginning of the song
It's a lot holding on that first verse
She might have been talking about Newcastle winning in the Champions League
They got three points yesterday
Oh yeah, she voted a song about Newcastle's winning in the Champions League
And then immediately goes into reciting patterns
That's classic Bush
Yes, exactly
You know that thing of when people take bagels
When people have a bagel and then it's got poppy seeds on it
And then they fail a drugs test
I think we probably have mentioned that in this podcast before
Because it can make athletes fail tests if they've had poppy seed bagels
Here's a thing that happened a few years ago
In 2013, a hospital took a newborn baby away from its mum
For five days because she'd failed an opiate test
Which was entirely because she'd had a bagel
She just had a bagel and then she'd had a urine test or something while in hospital
And the last thing she'd eaten before giving birth was a poppy seed bagel
Wow, that's amazing
It's awful, I don't think it's amazing Dan, I think it's really bad
No, it's amazing that that package is what I mean
I should start doing that and taking babies away
But that's pretty amazing that that's not on the walls of hospitals saying
Make sure not to have a bagel prior to birth or something like that
No, you're allowed to eat the bagels, it's just that the test shouldn't have found it
I think so
Because I mean, I don't know if you're aware of this because you do have three kids
But they give you a ton of drugs when you're having kids
Yeah, yeah, I took a lot
My wife did natural, but I was absolutely off my head
When you write one of the novels for it, Jenny
Are you allowed to make up any monster or do they sometimes say
No, a monster made of 50 million bees is a silly monster to have
Funnily enough, a monster made of 50 million bees or anything that's very difficult to do on television
Is very good to do in a novel
So one of the last stories I wrote was about a creature that sucked up all the oceans
Because it was impossible to film and the whole thing is done when they're trying to run from boat to boat
So anything that's out and in fact, my first novel from that was again it's set entirely in the water in the Viking seas
Anything that's really hard to shoot, putting the tARDIS on water on screen is a nightmare
So anything that's very difficult to do and big and expensive needs to go in a novel
It's the old, you know, Simpsons crashing 50 helicopters into house
It costs them no more money than someone walking into a room
So you do have to be a bit...
At one point I had Matt Smith diving to save someone from the water
And he removed his trousers and shoes
Oh here we go, here's the wrong comm element
Well no no, he came back and said the doctor never takes his trousers off
So that's our red line
Did you have the doctor take his trousers off?
Well, if you're running to save someone in the water, then take off your shoes and trousers
It's common sense
And so I'd written it without thinking about it, it was just like what do you do?
And you're running into the water and it just came back with the big mic going
No, the doctor does not know if they're crowds or is never
I never knew Andrew
Do you remember the, do we talk about this, the Anthony Horowitz thing?
Because he wrote the J, Anthony Horowitz wrote the Bond books
And he wrote one where Bond is naked
And yeah, we did mention this I think, but he wrote one where Bond is like
He springs out of bed naked because there's a killer or someone at the door or whatever
And the note came back from the estate saying "No, he needs to be wearing formal pyjamas which button to the neck"
And that's so unsexy
It's like a moral beacon for children, I'd have thought, but good
Have you guys heard of mutton Jeff?
It means deaf
Comedy double-act?
Well, like really old comedy double-act from the 40s or 30s
Yeah
It's a pairing that's been used quite a lot
The first instance of it as far as I could find was from Bud Fisher
He did it as two cartoon characters, it was the first ever
He's a cartoonist, Bud Fisher, and he created these two characters, mutton Jeff
Oh, I thought you said mutton Jeff, like "Oh, the guy gets me my lamb down the ride"
It was beefy Bill, Larry the lamb
The dodgy butcher, like "Yeah, I just got this off the back of a trombone"
Where were you last night, mutton Jeff?
Yeah, no, it was the first daily comic strip in the States, supposedly
When historians are trying to pin that down, it always comes up, 1907
And mutton Jeff is what you actually call good cop/bad cop
It's what that dynamic is based on these two characters who were two mismatched tin horns, they were called
And mutton Jeff, it's used everywhere now to sort of describe that dynamic
But yeah, good cop/bad cop is mutton Jeff
Wow
Which doesn't work, good cop/bad cop
Does it not?
No, and they've done experiments of, you know, scientists have carried out experiments to sort of emotionally destabilize the subjects
And then ask them questions
Okay, here's one, there was students being asked to answer questions about their work in an interview setting
Or to lie about a fictional job
And they were interviewed by a neutral interviewer
And then there was someone else in the corner taking notes, a second interviewer
And that second interviewer either looked supportive as they were taking notes or they looked hostile and suspicious
And basically people who were telling the truth gave detailed answers if that second person looked supportive
You know, they gave better answers, more informative
So it became easier to tell who's lying
So you sort of just need good cop/normal cop
Okay, right
Or normal cop/good cop, you know, but there's not much use for
Just a good cop
Probably
But does the bad cop not just make the good cop seem gooder?
No
Well, I think that's the thinking behind it, but actually it just stresses people out and I think makes them more likely to lie
So Byron's thing was, he said a line that was so potently harsh that it sort of became the reason for Keats dying
Which was that he, what did he say, the critics killed him basically
Oh yeah, there was this idea
He got some really crunching bad reviews for a couple of his epic poems, there's one called Endymion
Which, and he got a terrible review and the consensus later was, well, he died of reviews
And he didn't, he died of tuberculosis
Yeah
And the reviews were years before he got the TB as well
Is it possible though to die of reviews?
Because I...
Are you doing it again with this shit?
No, my doctor says it's better to die
But no, so after Keats died, so he dies in Rome, in the arms of his friend, Joseph Severn, who's a painter
And then he, Keats, in his dying days, he says, I don't want my name even to go on my tombstone
So the famous line on his tombstone is, here lies one whose name was writ in water
He knows this very amazing talent, but ephemeral, that he's passed, you know, he's passed out of the world
And it's a little bit, kind of, poor me, but his friends, they did that, they put that
Here lies one whose name was writ in water
They decided, no, we think he deserves a bit more than that, so they added, above it
Wow
Which, I think, removes the power of the beautiful, no more fragrant message that he thought of
It's even worse than that, because if you go and visit Keats's grave, and as you say, he wanted it to be anonymous, you know, when no one's there
The grave right next to him basically says, I'm with Keats
No
It does, because it's his mate, Joseph Severn, who was buried there
That's so funny
Says, to the memory of Joseph Severn, devoted friend and deathbed companion of John Keats
And so everyone now knows that it's right next door
Wow
All the graves in that grave, I was just saying, like Keats, three down
Yes, it's odd, there's a lot of kings getting bits of them buried in a different place, and the Habsburgs were mad for it
I think they had almost like a tradition, I can't remember where, I'm afraid, but like the body in one place and the heart somewhere else
There's a place in Vienna that I started reading about, hearts being buried separately to the rest of the individual
And the hearts, there are 54 Habsburg hearts in one crypt in Vienna
Wow
That's quite romantic
And they've all got their own hearts
Yeah, yeah, I suppose it is, yeah
I'll spend Valentine's Day with you next week
Well actually, he was like quite pedantic, wasn't he?
Was he?
Because he had that book that you mentioned, The Style?
Oh yeah, the Elements of Style
Elements of Style
And if you read that, it's all about how everyone's grammar is terrible
And, you know, for instance, the word "non" is in the singular, so you should say "none of us is ready" rather than "none of us are ready"
Or you should never start a sentence with "however", and you should never turn a noun into a verb, so you shouldn't say "I was hosting a party"
Because that's turning, you know, the host is a noun and you shouldn't turn it into a verb
I absolutely hated the passive voice, so you know, like, you should say "the dog bit the man" and not "the man was bitten by the dog", that's what he thought
Although the first sentence of his book says "this book is intended for use in English courses in which the practice of composition is combined with a study of literature"
Which has got two examples of the passive voice in the first sentence
That's really good
That's such an interesting book because it was originally written by someone else, it was called William Strunk Jr.
And then E.B. White came in and did a revised expanded edition, but he gets as much of the credit of the book, but it's a weird example of a book sort of getting second
He liked it a second edition, almost like adding loads of extra stuff
Yeah, exactly
Well, in his Sex Necessary book that he did with James Thurber, who then went on to become one of the cartoonists for the New Yorker
In 1950, Thurber was supposed to write an introduction to the book's latest edition at that point
And he contributed just a couple of paragraphs, then wrote to White on the side
"If you know anything about sex, let me know"
Do you know what the rainbow bridge is, if I say that phrase?
No, no
Ah, well, that completely...
Oh, should we know it?
Well, the rainbow bridge is an extremely well-known phrase for when your pet dies
Oh
And it's from a kind of poem which is known all over the world about how your dog crosses the rainbow bridge
And it becomes young again, and it's in a lovely place with lots of dogs to play with
And then one day it'll peel off because it can smell you coming
You see, so it's been a source of comfort and joy all over the world, and most people have heard of it
And the woman who wrote it is 82, and she wrote it when she was about 13, and she lives in Inverness
And they found her this year, her name is Edna, and she had written that when she was a teenager
Somebody in her family had passed it on to somebody else
Who'd passed on, and eventually her husband got hold of it when they were married
And he'd given it to someone who went to America, where they published it in the Dear, one of those American columns
Ask Abbey, where it had been read by 100 million Americans, because it was a syndicated column
How was it like just anonymous at the time?
They didn't, they had no idea who it was
And you can even see in the original Ask Abbey, she says "Oh, I don't know who this is from"
And it's just full of letters from Americans in tears and so on
It spread everywhere, and when we had a dog that died, we got a lot of commiserations and said they're at the rainbow bridge
It's the kind of way that you say "I'm sorry that your animal died"
And until about last year, she had no idea
And then it came up and she went up to her attic and she said "Yeah, here it is"
It was the original piece of paper in a book
That's so cool
That's amazing, you should go visit, you're so close to her, you should go meet her
I think it would be, I kind of work quite heavily off getting paid for writing that idea
This is one of the most published poems in the world, and she did not even know
That's incredible
Neanderthals, I think we can say they were a bit like reindeer in one respect
Really, can we?
Yeah, please tell me
They're big noses, which they use to heat up cold air
And reindeer do that
As in they had great big sinuses and chambers and just a warm up freezing cold air
So actually that's highly debated now
Oh man, why don't you have experts on this?
That was the, it's contentious
So some people think it's more about the amount of oxygen they needed to take in
Because loads of them were living in, they were cold adapted
But loads of them were living in Iraq and the Iberian Peninsula
When it wasn't necessarily cold, so it's not straightforward
Because they did have very very shiny noses, didn't they?
Yeah, okay
And there were elves at the time
Actually, I think they were because there were hobbits around on a different continent
Is that the homo, what they call it?
Homo floresiensis
Yeah, apparently in the original paper they were called Sudanthropus florensianus
Which means they thought it meant a man from the Sunda region of Flores
But actually it translated as flowery anus
Wow
Does anyone know what Marxist glue is?
What might that be?
Marxist glue
It sticks to everybody according to their need
No, no, no
It was a good try and what was a very difficult prompt
I don't like this live-reviewing feature we've just enabled
Marxist glue
Is it a special kind of Soviet glue that was used only in Russia?
Actually, no, used in the West by Marxists
Oh, is it for like protests?
Yes, glue is used in protests
Like the suffragettes manacled themselves to things, but other people glue themselves to things
Very less strong glue made from wheat and water
So it's very cheap, not used to glue yourself to something
Do you glue something else to something?
Posters
Be more communist, please
Very cheap
This isn't the idea at all
Pop it up there straight away
You're not giving anything to international capitalism
You're not giving anything to big print
You're just a bit of wheat
Yeah, absolutely
The thing is it just sticks to what?
It's very, very easy and cheap to make
But once you put it on a wall
You really can't get it off unless you really scrape it off
And they used it quite a lot in history
To lose the Trek, for instance
He would put all of his posters up using this stuff
And his posters became really popular and really expensive
And people would pay a lot of money for his posters
For the Moulin Rouge or whatever
And so you would get people who would follow him around Paris
Trying to grab his posters off as soon as he put them on
Because they knew as soon as this Marxist glue had dried
They would not be able to get it off anymore
That's great
It's a bit banksy-ish, isn't it?
Yeah, it is, I guess
That's very cool
Does anyone want a Japanese soft drink?
This is children's beer
It's a soft drink that I've got from Japan
Wow
And you pour, on the front it's got a picture of a beer
And a drunk looking child
And you put it in a glass and you pour water on it
And apparently it looks and tastes like, well it doesn't taste much like beer, I don't think
I'm so up for this, this is amazing
That sounds so good
It's like a normal white powder
Just a normal white powder
It looks very saucy, someone's to walk in right now
It does look saucy
Okay
Does this look like beer or not?
It doesn't look like you're pulling a pint
What an advertising way that would be if you were pulling a pint
It looks more like pig weight
Have you got a mixer?
Should we stir it?
Yeah
We're going to stir it with a ruler
Oh this is very disappointing
Oh come on, if you went to a pub and you got a pint looking like that
You'd send it back
For the listeners, it's looking like...
I would describe its colour as yakult
Yes
It's very...
Hang on
Yeah
There's not much of a head on it
Well that's what that's supposed to happen, I think if you give it a few minutes
Maybe it looks like it's getting darker
Oh it's like a Guinness, you've got to let it rest for a bit
There you go
Wow
It is getting darker
So this is like the old candy cigarettes
Well that's what I was thinking
The alcohol equivalent of that, that's awesome
You could have this, it's like children's beer
And then some children's cigarettes as well
They first ever detention for having candy cigarettes
Did you?
Yes
Yeah, I sat at the back holding it like this
Like a sort of...
How would you describe this pose for the listener?
Like a 1920s sort of...
Yeah, like a Lana Turner
Yes, I was holding it as if it was as long as Cruella de Vil's cigarette
And I've quite understandably got sent out to a detention
I think maybe momentarily she thought it was a real cigarette
Probably if you're at school and there's quite a lot of people are actually smoking cigarettes
Seems a little bit harsh
I was also doing donuts in my car because it was Grand Theft Auto
Oh it's looking more beer right now
That's done, she said that looks like beer
Yeah, definitely it's got the frothy head
It's got the...
It's a light
It's gone from Yakult to...
It's still quite...
It's a bit carling, isn't it?
Yes, I would say
Oh that's very nice
Is that?
It's sort of sweet, it's slightly sherbet-y, refreshing
Maisie, do you want some?
I'm alright
I like that more than I like any actual beer
Yeah, it tastes like cream soda to me
Oh yeah, cool
That's what that tastes like
Delicious
Okay, great
Even the way it clings to the glass is very beer-like, isn't it?
Yeah, they've absolutely nailed it
Except for the taste
Well, we were doubters at first but it's very far away from Yakult now, isn't it?
Yeah
I'm a convert, I like that
Is anyone going to...
No, you can have it, yeah
Yeah
Can I tell you a headline from this spring?
Florida Man uses chat GPT to land plane
Oh no
What?
Really?
This is a passenger called John Williams
It was a Boeing 737, quite a big plane
The plane got into difficult, the pilot got into difficulties rather
Anyway, I got to the end of this article, was staggered by it
and found this little footnote at the end
We thought it would be fun to share a light-hearted article that is not meant to be taken seriously
It was an April Fool
It was published on the first...
And then you look back in the tiny, tiny font they've said published first of April
But imagine being in a plane, the pilot's taken unwell, you Google it, this is on the first page of results
Brilliant, you're like, "Thank God!"
Okay, I'll just get on the chat GPT
And then getting to the end of the article
And then you just say, "How do you fly a plane?"
And it just goes, "A plane?"
It's a plane, it's a transport instrument
Ron Atkinson almost had to land a plane once
Did he?
Yeah, he was in a flight
Well, that's what he did
Oh, Teddy is co-pilot
God, you're worried chat GPT is landing
Imagine Mr Bean coming over the tunnel
So he was flying, I think, with his family
or certainly a small group of people
and the plane's pilot sort of just conked out
and he had to take controls
and he was flying the plane, they were talking to ground control
and fortunately they got the pilot back awake
so he could land it, but potentially
Wow
Rowan would have had to have landed his own plane
God, that would have been a weird awe-haul
Alright, there you have it, there are all of our outtakes
If you want to get in touch with me, Andy, James or any of the guests
Once again, that's Beck Hill, Maisie Adam, Jenny Colgan, David Mitchell
Sophie Duker, LL Shemahi and almost Neil Gaiman
You can find them at multiple places
Be it Twitter, Blue Sky, Threads, Instagram
Most of them have accounts on those places
So check them out, go say hi
and we'll be back again with more Clubfish bonus features
very soon in the near future, okay
See you then everyone, have a good one, goodbye
[Music]
[BLANK_AUDIO]